<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蒲生氏郷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujisato GAMO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujisato GAMO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujisato GAMO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蒲生 氏郷（がもう うじさと）は、戦国時代 (日本)から安土桃山時代にかけての武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Was a military commander in Japan from the Sengoku period (the Warring State period) through to the Azuchi－Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Was a military commander in Japan from the Sengoku period (the Warring State period) through to the Azuchi－Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujisato GAMO was a military commander in Japan from the Sengoku period (warring state period) through to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>Ujisato GAMO補足しました。was小文字にしました。(warring state period)、the削除しました。小文字にしました。ハイフン半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>初め近江国日野城主、次に伊勢国松阪城主、最後に陸奥国黒川城主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first he was lord of Hino Castle in Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province), subsequently lord of Matsuzaka Castle in Ise-no-kuni (Ise Province) and finally lord of Kurokawa Castle in Mutsu-no-kuni (Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first he was lord of Hino Castle in Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province), subsequently lord of Matsuzaka Castle in Ise-no-kuni (Ise Province) and finally lord of Kurokawa Castle in Mutsu-no-kuni (Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first he was lord of Hino Castle in Omi Province, subsequently lord of Matsuzaka Castle in Ise Province and finally lord of Kurokawa Castle in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>～国は、Provinceの表記としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近江国日野城主蒲生賢秀の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Katahide GAMO, the lord of Hino Castle in Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of Katahide GAMO, the lord of Hino Castle in Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Katahide GAMO, the lord of Hino Castle in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>～国は、Provinceの表記としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初名は賦秀（ますひで）または教秀（のりひで）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was initially called &quot;Masuhide&quot; as well as &quot;Norihide&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was initially called &quot;Masuhide&quot; as well as &quot;Norihide&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was initially called &quot;Masuhide&quot; as well as &quot;Norihide.&quot;</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>またキリシタン大名で洗礼名はレオン（或いはレオ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he was a Daimyo (feudal lord) of the Christian faith with the Christian name &quot;Leon&quot; (or possibly &quot;Leo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as a Christian Daimyo (feudal lord), he took the the Christian name &quot;Leon&quot; (or possibly &quot;Leo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as a Christian Daimyo (feudal lord), he took the Christian name &quot;Leon&quot; (or possibly &quot;Leo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>余分なtheを削除しました。”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>子に蒲生秀行 (侍従)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a child Hideyuki GAMO was a &quot;Jiju&quot; (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a child Hideyuki GAMO was a &quot;Jiju&quot; (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a child Hideyuki GAMO was a &quot;Jiju&quot; (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このほか長男蒲生氏俊がいるが、廃嫡したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was another elder son, Ujisato GAMO but he was disinherited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was another elder son, Ujisato GAMO but he was disinherited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was another elder son, Ujisato GAMO but he was disinherited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lifetime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>To match other files</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>幼少時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Childhood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>蒲生氏は奥州藤原氏・藤原秀郷の系統に属する鎌倉時代からの名門であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujisato was a member of the FUJIWARA-no-Hidesato/Oshu-Fujiwara clan who were said to have been a leading family since the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujisato was reputedly a member of the FUJIWARA-no-Hidesato/Oshu-Fujiwara clan who had beena leading family since the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>I think it is the lineage that is in question here, not the status of the clans.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujisato was reputedly a member of the Oshu-Fujiwara clan, FUJIWARA no Hidesato line, who had been a leading family since the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除、スペース補足。ハイフン削除。文の構成を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>近江蒲生郡日野に生まれ、幼名は鶴千代と名付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born at Hino in Omi-Gamo-gun (Omi-Gamo District) and was given the childhood name of &quot;Tsuruchiyo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born at Hino in Omi-Gamo-gun (Omi-Gamo District) and was given the childhood name of &quot;Tsuruchiyo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born at Hino, Gamo District in Omi Province and was given the childhood name of &quot;Tsuruchiyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Hino, Gamo District in Omi Provinceと訂正しました。”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1568年、主家の六角氏が織田信長によって滅ぼされたため、父・賢秀は織田氏に臣従した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of the the lords of the Rokkakushi (six powerful families) being overthrown by Nobunaga ODA in 1568, his father, Katahide, became a vassal of ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the the lords of the Rokkakushi (six powerful families) being overthrown by Nobunaga ODA in 1568, his father, Katahide, became a vassal of ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the lords of the Rokkaku clan being overthrown by Nobunaga ODA in 1568, his father, Katahide, became a vassal of Oda.</e>
<cmt>余分なtheを削除しました。スペース削除。六角氏の表現を訂正しました。Odaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このとき、人質として岐阜市の信長のもとに送られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time he was sent as a hostage to Nobunaga who was in Gifu City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujisato was then sent as a hostage to Nobunaga who was in Gifu City.</e>
<cmt>Timing.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujisato was then sent as a hostage to Nobunaga who was in Gifu City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>織田家臣時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period as an ODA vassal</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period as an ODA vassal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period as an Oda vassal</e>
<cmt>Odaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>信長は氏郷の才を見抜いたとされ、娘の冬姫と結婚させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga overlooked Ujisato&apos;s age and had him marry his eldest daughter Fuyu-hime (Princess Fuyu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga overlooked Ujisato&apos;s age and had him marry his eldest daughter Fuyu-hime (Princess Fuyu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga saw through the ability of Ujisato and had him marry his eldest daughter Fuyu-hime (Princess Fuyu).</e>
<cmt>誤訳のため、saw through the ability of Ujisatoと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>岐阜城で元服して忠三郎賦秀と名乗り（信長の官職である「弾正忠（だんじょうちゅう）」から1字を与えられたとの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He celebrated his coming of age at Gifu Castle and assumed the name &quot;Chuzaburo-Masuhide&quot; a name which borrowed a single kanji character from one of Nobunaga`s official roles (&quot;judge&quot;) according to one story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He celebrated his coming of age at Gifu Castle and assumed the name &quot;Chuzaburo-Masuhide&quot;, a name which, according to one account, borrows a single kanji character from one of Nobunaga&apos;s official roles (&quot;judge&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Type of apostrophe</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He celebrated his coming of age at Gifu Castle and assumed the name &quot;Chuzaburo Masuhide,&quot; a name which, according to one account, borrows a single kanji character from one of Nobunaga&apos;s official roles, &apos;Danjochu&apos; (judge).</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。ハイフン削除。Danjochu,補足しました。”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、本項では一部を除いて氏郷に統一する）、織田氏の一門として手厚く迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to keep consistency the name &quot;Ujisato&quot; is used throughout this topic except in some part). As one household within the ODA family, he was received warmly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(For consistency, the name &quot;Ujisato&quot; is used in all but one part of this description). Now a member of the ODA family, he was received warmly.</e>
<cmt>Missing bracket?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For consistency, the name &quot;Ujisato&quot; is used in all but one part of this description) Now a member of the Oda family, he was received warmly.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除。Odaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>武勇にも優れ、1568年の北畠具教・北畠具房との戦いにて初陣を飾ると、1569年の伊勢国大河内城攻めや1570年の姉川の戦い、1573年の朝倉攻めと小谷城攻め、1574年の伊勢長島攻め、1575年の長篠の戦いなどに従軍して、武功を挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was exceedingly brave, and earned his first battle stripes in engagements against Tomonori KITABATAKE/ Tomofusa KITABATAKE and, campaigned meritoriously in: attacks on Okawachi Castle in Ise Province in 1569, as well as the Battle of Anegawa in 1570, the1573 Asakura attacks and Siege of Odani Castle, 1574 Ise-Nagashima attacks, and 1575 Battle of Nagashino etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was exceedingly brave, earned his first battle stripes in engagements against Tomonori KITABATAKE/ Tomofusa KITABATAKE, and campaigned with success in attacks on Okawachi Castle in Ise Province in 1569, the Battle of Anegawa in 1570, Asakura attacks and Siege of Odani Castle in 1573, the Ise-Nagashima attacks in 1574, and the Battle of Nagashino in 1575 etc.</e>
<cmt>Consistency in writing dates &quot;…in 15XX&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was exceedingly brave, earned his first battle stripes in engagements against Tomonori KITABATAKE and Tomofusa KITABATAKE, and campaigned with success in attacks on Okawachi Castle in Ise Province in 1569, the Battle of Anegawa in 1570, Asakura attacks and Siege of Odani Castle in 1573, the Ise-Nagashima attacks in 1574, and the Battle of Nagashino in 1575 etc.</e>
<cmt>/をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1582年、信長が本能寺の変により横死すると、安土城にいた信長の妻子を保護し、父とともに居城・日野城（中野城）へ走って明智光秀に対して対抗姿勢を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, with Nobunaga meeting a violent death in the Honnoji Incident, he protected Nobunaga`s wife and children in Azuchi Castle and, together with his father retreated to Hino Castle (Nakano Castle) which was the lord`s castle, and made a point of confronting Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, when Nobunaga was killed in the Honnoji Incident, he protected Nobunaga&apos;s wife and children in Azuchi Castle and retreated with his father to Hino Castle (Nakano Castle) where he was the lord, thereby indicating his opposition to Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>Simplified.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, when Nobunaga was killed in the Honnoji Incident, he protected Nobunaga&apos;s wife and children in Azuchi Castle and retreated with his father to Hino Castle (Nakano Castle) where he was the lord, thereby indicating his opposition to Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>光秀は明智光春、武田元明、京極高次らに近江の長浜城 (近江国)、佐和山城、安土城の各城を攻略させ、次に日野攻囲に移る手筈だったが、直前に敗死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuhide captured a number of castles with Mitsuharu AKECHI, Motoaki TAKEDA, Takatsugu KYOGOKU and others: Nagahama Castle at Omi (Omi Province), Sawayama Castle, Azuchi Castle. Subsequently, during the siege of Hino but just prior to a planned transfer he was defeated and killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuhide captured a number of castles with Mitsuharu AKECHI, Motoaki TAKEDA, Takatsugu KYOGOKU and others including Nagahama Castle at Omi (Omi Province), Sawayama Castle and Azuchi Castle, but was defeated and killed just as he was about to lay siege to Hino.</e>
<cmt>Changed back to one sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuhide captured a number of castles with Mitsuharu AKECHI, Motoaki TAKEDA, Takatsugu KYOGOKU and others including Nagahama Castle at Omi (Omi Province), Sawayama Castle and Azuchi Castle, but was defeated and killed just as he was about to lay siege to Hino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>豊臣家臣時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period as a vassal of Toyotomi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period as a vassal of Toyotomi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period as a vassal of Toyotomi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>その後は羽柴秀吉（豊臣秀吉）に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently he served Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently he served Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently he served Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>秀吉は氏郷に伊勢松ヶ島城12万石を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi granted Ujisato the 12,000 koku Ise-Matsugashima Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi granted Ujisato the Ise-Matsugashima Castle which had a yield of 12,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>12,000 koku is a bit awkward as an adjective.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi granted Ujisato the Ise-Matsugashima Castle which had a yield of 12,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>清洲会議で優位に立ち、信長の統一事業を引き継いだ秀吉に従い、天正12年（1584年）の小牧・長久手の戦いや天正13年（1585年）の紀伊国攻め、天正15年（1587年）の九州征伐や1590年の小田原征伐などに従軍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was prominent in the Kiyosu Conference and followed instructions from Hideyoshi who had assumed and was continuing Nobunaga&apos;s unification efforts. He fought in the 1584 Komaki/Nagakute battles, 1585 Kii-no-Kuni (Kii Province) attacks, the Kyushu Campaign of 1587 and the Odawara Campaign of 1590 etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was prominent in the Kiyosu Conference and followed instructions from Hideyoshi who had assumed power and was continuing Nobunaga&apos;s unification efforts. He fought in the Komaki/Nagakute battles of 1584, the Kii-no-Kuni (Kii Province) attacks of 1585, the Kyushu Campaign of 1587 and the Odawara Campaign of 1590 etc.</e>
<cmt>Consistency in writing dates &quot;…of 15XX&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was prominent in the Kiyosu Conference and followed instructions from Hideyoshi who had assumed power and was continuing Nobunaga&apos;s unification efforts; he fought in the Komaki and Nagakute battles of 1584, the Ki no kuni (Ki Province) attacks of 1585, the Kyushu Campaign of 1587 and the Odawara Campaign of 1590 etc.</e>
<cmt>紀伊国→Ki no kuni (Ki Province)一原文一訳文の原則に従って、一文に訂正しました。’を&apos;に訂正しました。/をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その間、天正16年（1588年）には飯高郡矢川庄四五百森（よいほのもり）で新城建築のための縄張りを行い、松坂城を築城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that period, in 1588 at a place called Yoihonomori Yagawasho in Iitaka County, the site for a new castle was pegged out and Matsuzaka Castle was built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, in 1588 he measured up a site for a new castle at Yoihonomori Yagawasho in Iitaka County, and built Matsuzaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>Better in active voice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, in 1588 he measured up a site for a new castle at Yoihonomori Yagawasho in Iitaka County, and built Matsuzaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>松ヶ島の武士や商人を強制的に移住させて城下町を作り上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Merchants and samurai warriors around Matsugashima were forced to shift homes and a castle-township was built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merchants and samurai warriors around Matsugashima were forced to shift homes and a castle town was built.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merchants and samurai warriors around Matsugashima were forced to shift homes and a castle town was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一連の統一事業に関わった功により、天正18年（1590年）の奥州仕置において伊勢より陸奥国会津に移封され42万石（のちの検地・加増により92万石）の大領を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the success of a series of unifying activities, with the Oshu-shioki (persecutions) in 1590 he was granted large amounts of land by transfer: 420,000 koku (a following survey increased this by 920,000 koku) from Ise to Aizu, Mutsu-no-kuni (Aizu, Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the success of a series of unifying activities and the Oshu-shioki (persecutions) in 1590 he was granted land with yield of 420,000 koku a year (and subsequently land with a yield of 920,000 koku) between Ise and Aizu, Mutsu-no-kuni (Aizu, Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>Simplified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the success of a series of unifying activities and the Oshu-shioki (repression of the Oshu District) in 1590 he was granted land with yield of 420,000 koku a year (and subsequently land with a yield of 920,000 koku) between Ise and Aizu, Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>奥州仕置→Oshu-shioki (repression of the Oshu District) Aizu, Mutsu Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>なお、松ヶ島時代（天正13年（1585年）頃）に賦秀から氏郷と名乗りを改めているが、これは当時の実力者だった羽柴&amp;quot秀&amp;quot吉の名乗りの一字を下に置く『賦秀』という名が不遜であろうという気配りからであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, circa 1585 he was told to change his name from Masuhide to Ujisato but, this was considered as arrogance on the part of Hideyoshi HASHIBA, the strongman at that time and aimed at lowering the status of Ujisato`s name by one kanji character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Circa 1585 he was told to change his name back from Masuhide to Ujisato by Hideyoshi HASHIBA, the strongman at that time, who felt disrespected in the first character &quot;hide&quot; of his own name (Hide-yoshi) being the second character in Masu-hide.</e>
<cmt>Clarified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Circa 1585 he was told to change his name back from Masuhide to Ujisato by Hideyoshi HASHIBA, the strongman at that time, who felt disrespected in the first character &quot;hide&quot; of his own name (Hide-yoshi) being the second character in Masu-hide.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>一方、天正15年（1587年）7月には、秀吉から「羽柴」の姓を賜っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in July 1587 Hideyoshi honored him by bestowed him the family name &quot;HASHIBA&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1587 Hideyoshi then honored him by bestowing on him the family name &quot;HASHIBA&quot;.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think 一方 really means &quot;on the other hand&quot; here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1587 Hideyoshi then honored him by bestowing on him the family name &apos;HASHIBA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>会津においては、町の名を黒川から「若松」へと改め、甲州流の縄張りによる城作りを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Aizu, the town of Kurokawa had its name changed to &quot;Wakamatsu&quot; and a castle pegged-out and built in the Koshu style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Aizu, the town of Kurokawa had its name changed to &quot;Wakamatsu&quot; and a castle was measured out built in the Koshu style.</e>
<cmt>I prefer &quot;measured out&quot; to &quot;pegged out&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Aizu, the town of Kurokawa had its name changed to &apos;Wakamatsu&apos; and a castle was measured out built in the Koshu style.</e>
<cmt>”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>なお、「若松」の名は、出身地の日野城（中野城）に近い馬見岡綿向神社（現在の滋賀県蒲生郡日野町 (滋賀県)村井にある神社、蒲生氏の氏神）の参道周辺にあった「若松の杜」に由来し、同じく領土であった松坂の「松」という一文字もこの松に由来すると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the name &quot;Wakamatsu&quot; (literally `young pine`) originates from the Wakamatsu-no-mori (literally `young pine grove`) which was in the vicinity of the approach to Umamiokawatamuki-jinja Shrine (which was the Gamo Clan&apos;s family shrine near present day Murai, Hino-cho, Gamo-gun, Shiga Prefecture) and close to his birthplace, Hinode Castle (Nakano Castle). Similarly, it is this same pine, meant by the kanji character &quot;Matsu&quot; (lit. &quot;pine&quot;) in the name &quot;Matsuzaka&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note that, the name &quot;Wakamatsu&quot; (literally &apos;young pine&apos;) comes from Wakamatsu-no-mori (literally &apos;young pine grove&apos;) which was in the vicinity of the approach to Umamiokawatamuki-jinja Shrine (the Gamo Clan&apos;s family shrine near present day Murai, Hino-cho, Gamo-gun, Shiga Prefecture) and close to Matsuhide&apos;s birthplace, Hinode Castle (Nakano Castle). The &quot;Matsu&quot; of &quot;Matsuzaka&quot; is also the kanji character for pine and is said to have the same roots.</e>
<cmt>Clarification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that, the name &apos;Wakamatsu&apos; (literally &apos;young pine&apos;) comes from &apos;Wakamatsu-no-mori&apos; (literally &apos;young pine grove&apos;) which was in the vicinity of the approach to Umamiokawatamuki-jinja Shrine (the Gamo clan&apos;s family shrine near present day Murai, Hino-cho, Gamo-gun, Shiga Prefecture) and close to Matsuhide&apos;s birthplace, Hinode Castle (Nakano Castle), also the &apos;Matsu&apos; of &apos;Matsuzaka&apos; is also the kanji character for pine and is said to have the same roots.</e>
<cmt>”を&apos;に訂正しました。’を&apos;に訂正しました。clan小文字にしました。一原文一訳文の原則に従って、一文に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>7層の天守閣（現存する5層の復元天守は寛永年間に改築されたものを元にしている）を有するこの城は、氏郷の幼名にちなみ鶴ヶ城と名付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle that was endowed with a 7 storied castle tower (the existing 5 story tower is based on one which was rebuilt in the Kanei era (1624-1644)) and given GAMO`s childhood imaginary name of &quot;Crane Castle&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle had a 7-story tower (the existing 5-story tower is based on one built in the Kanei era (1624-1644)) and was named after Ujisato&apos;s childhood name as &quot;Tsuraga Castle&quot; (literally Crane Castle).</e>
<cmt>Simplified.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle had a 7-story tower (the existing 5-story tower is based on one built in the Kanei era (1624 - 1644)) and was named after Ujisato&apos;s childhood name as &quot;Tsuraga Castle&quot; (literally Crane Castle).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、築城と同時に城下町の開発も実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, development of the castle village coincided with the castle&apos;s construction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A castle town was built at the same time.</e>
<cmt>Simplified.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A castle town was built at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>具体的には、旧領の日野・松阪の商人の招聘、定期市の開設、楽市楽座の導入、手工業の奨励等により、江戸時代の会津藩の発展の礎を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In real terms, merchants of the former domains of Hino and Matsuzaka were welcomed to town, regular scheduled markets were organized, free markets and free guilds were introduced, handicrafts were encouraged etc which lay the foundation for development in the Aizu domain in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merchants of the former domains of Hino and Matsuzaka were welcomed to the town, regular scheduled markets were organized, free markets and free guilds were introduced and handicrafts were encouraged etc, all of which laid the foundations for development in the Aizu domain in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>氏郷 is translated as Ujisato above. 具体的　can be ignored here, I think.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merchants of the former domains of Hino and Matsuzaka were welcomed to the town, regular scheduled markets were organized, free markets and free guilds were introduced and handicrafts were encouraged etc, all of which laid the foundations for development in the Aizu domain in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>以降は、会津の旧領主である伊達政宗と度々対立しながらも、1591年の大崎・葛西一揆（なお、この際秀吉に対し「政宗が一揆を扇動している」との告発を行っている）、九戸政実の乱を制圧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From then on, along with confrontations with the former lord of Aizu, Masamune DATE, and also the Osaki/Kasai Ikki Uprisings in 1591 (at the time Hideyoshi launched a prosecution of &quot;Masamune inciting sedition&quot;) and, suppression of the Masazane KUNOHE Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Ujisato continued fighting agains the former lord of Aizu, Masamune DATE, and suppressed the Osaki/Kasai Ikki Uprisings in 1591 (at this point he notified Hideyoshi, accusing Masasume of being the instigator) and, suppressing the Masazane KUNOHE Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>Corrected bracked section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Ujisato continued fighting against the former lord of Aizu, Masamune DATE, and suppressed the Osaki/Kasai Ikki Uprisings in 1591 (at this point he notified Hideyoshi, accusing Masasume of being the instigator) and, suppressing the Masazane KUNOHE Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>againstスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>翌1592年の文禄・慶長の役では、肥前国名護屋へと出陣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year 1592 during the Imjin War (Japan`s invasion of Korea and China) de departed for the battlefields from Nagoya in Bizen-no-kuni (Bizen Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year (1592) he departed for Nagoya in Bizen-no-kuni (Bizen Province) to take part in the Imjin War (invasion of Korea and China).</e>
<cmt>Simplified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year (1592) he departed for Nagoya in Bizen no kuni (Bizen Province) to take part in the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。ハイフン削除。原文は「肥前国」となっていますが、「備前国」の誤りだと思います。the Bunroku-Keicho Warに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この陣中にて体調を崩し、文禄4年（1595年）2月7日、京都の伏見蒲生屋敷において死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whilst in camp he wrote about a deterioration in his physical condition and, he passed away in 1595 at the GAMO residence in Fushimi, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he fell sick during the campaign and, after returing to Japan, passed away in 1595 at the GAMO residence in Fushimi, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>I think it needs to be added that he returned to Japan.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he fell sick during the campaign and, after returning to Japan, passed away in 1595 at the Gamo residence in Fushimi, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>returningスペル訂正しました。スペース削除。Gamo に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>享年40。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aged 40.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 40.</e>
<cmt>Natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 40.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>蒲生家の家督は家康の娘との縁組を条件に嫡子の秀行が継いだが、家内不穏の動きから宇都宮市に移され12万石に減封された（会津には上杉景勝が入った）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As head of the GAMO household, he was succeeded by a legitimate child from his marriage with Ieyasu&apos;s daughter however, following inappropriate behavior by his wife she moved to Utsunomiya City at a reduced stipend of 120,000 koku (Kagekatsu UESUGI took control of Aizu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujisato was succeeded as the head of the GAMO household by Hideyuki a legitimate child from his marriage with Ieyasu&apos;s daughter, but following inappropriate behavior by Hideyuki&apos;s wife the family had to move to Utsunomiya City at a reduced stipend of 120,000 koku (Kagekatsu UESUGI took control of Aizu).</e>
<cmt>It is not clear from the Japanese what is happening here. Is it Hideyuki&apos;s wife that misbehaved? Did the entire family have to move?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujisato was succeeded as the head of the Gamo household by Hideyuki a legitimate child from his marriage with Ieyasu&apos;s daughter, but following inappropriate behavior by Hideyuki&apos;s wife the family had to move to Utsunomiya City at a reduced stipend of 120,000 koku (Kagekatsu UESUGI took control of Aizu).</e>
<cmt>Gamo に訂正しました。’を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People &amp; Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character &amp; Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>It is Ujisato&apos;s character which is being discussed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character &amp; Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>家臣を大切にし、また茶湯にも興味を示して利休七哲の一人（筆頭）にまで数えられており（千利休の死後、その子息千少庵は氏郷の許で蟄居している）、諸大名からの人望が厚く、風流の利発人と評される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took great care of his vassals and being interested in the tea ceremony, was even counted as one of the Rikyu shichitetsu (Rikyu&apos;s seven sages). After SEN-no-Rikyu`s death, his son (SEN-no-Shoan) was permitted by GAMO to stay in his home. He was very popular with a number of daimyo (feudal lords) considered to be refined and intelligent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took great care of his vassals and was interested in the tea ceremony, numbering among the Rikyu shichitetsu (Rikyu&apos;s seven sages). After SEN-no-Rikyu&apos;s death, he let Rikyu&apos;s son (SEN-no-Shoan) stay in his home. He was very popular with a number of daimyo (feudal lords) and considered to be refined and intelligent.</e>
<cmt>Simplified.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took great care of his vassals and was interested in the tea ceremony, numbering among the Rikyu shichitetsu (Rikyu&apos;s seven sages) (after SEN no Rikyu&apos;s death, he let Rikyu&apos;s son (SEN no Shoan) stay in his home), and he was very popular with a number of daimyo (feudal lords) and considered to be refined and intelligent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の原則に従って、一文に訂正しました。’を&apos;に訂正しました。ハイフン削除、スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また和歌にも秀でており、会津から文禄の役に参陣途上、近江国武佐にて故郷日野を偲んで詠んだ歌「思ひきや人の行方ぞ定めなき我が故郷をよそに見んとは」が有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He excelled at Waka (a form of traditional Japanese poetry) and en-route to the Bunroku Campaign front, at Musa in Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province) he composed a famous traditional Japanese Waka poem recollecting his birthplace: &quot; Memories and people&apos;s thoughts are shaped by their hometown; which I view differently&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He excelled at Waka (a form of traditional Japanese poetry) and en-route to the Bunroku Campaign front, at Musa in Omi-no-kuni (Omi Province) composed a famous traditional Japanese Waka poem recollecting his birthplace: &quot; Memories and people&apos;s thoughts are shaped by their hometown; which I view differently&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Removed second &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He excelled at Waka (a form of traditional Japanese poetry) and en-route to the Bunroku Campaign front, at Musa in Omi no kuni (Omi Province) composed a famous traditional Japanese Waka poem recollecting his birthplace: &apos;Memories and people&apos;s thoughts are shaped by their hometown; which I view differently.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Omi no kuniに訂正しました。スペース削除。”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>またキリシタン大名でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was yet another daimyo of the Christian faith.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also numbered among the Christian Daimyo</e>
<cmt>Corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also numbered among the Christian Daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>武辺談義や怪談など、話好きであったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said he liked ghost stories and talking about military matters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said he liked ghost stories and talking about military matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said he liked ghost stories and talking about military matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>奇癖として有功の家臣に蒲生姓を乱発し、家中に稀少なるべき同名衆を大量生産することがあり、前田利家にたしなめられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had the strange quirk of assigning the GAMO surname to meritorious vassals and, while best to have fewer family members with the same name, he mass produced them, earning the rebuke of Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had the habit of assigning the GAMO surname to meritorious vassals. It was best to have fewer family members with the same name, but he mass produced them, earning the rebuke of Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>Split into 2 sentences.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had the habit of assigning the Gamo surname to meritorious vassals; it was best to have fewer family members with the same name, but he mass produced them, earning the rebuke of Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>Gamo に訂正しました。一原文一訳文の原則に従って、一文に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>蒲生家中に蒲生姓の家臣が多いのはこのことによる（蒲生頼郷・蒲生郷舎など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, within the GAMO family there were many vassals with the surname &quot;GAMO&quot; (Yorisato GAMO/ Satoie GAMO etc)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, within the GAMO household there were many vassals with the surname &quot;GAMO&quot; (Yorisato GAMO/ Satoie GAMO etc)</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;family&quot; to &quot;household&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, within the Gamo household there were many vassals with the surname &quot;Gamo&quot; (Yorisato GAMO/ Satoie GAMO, etc.).</e>
<cmt>Gamo に訂正しました。&quot; &quot;に訂正しました。コンマ、ピリオド補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また、高山右近とも親交があったためにキリシタンとなり、レオンという洗礼名を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, because of his friendship with Ukon TAKAYAMA he became a Christian and took the Christian name &quot;Leon&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, because of his friendship with Ukon TAKAYAMA he became a Christian and took the Christian name &quot;Leon&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, because of his friendship with Ukon TAKAYAMA he became a Christian and took the Christian name &quot;Leon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>ローマにも度々使いを送り、時のローマ教皇から感謝の手紙を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He frequently sent messages to Rome and received a message of thanks from the Pope of the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He frequently sent messages to Rome and received a message of thanks from the Pope of the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He frequently sent messages to Rome and received a message of thanks from the Pope of the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>このほか、台湾に出兵したという逸話もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also anecdotes about him campaigning in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also anecdotes about him campaigning in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also anecdotes about him campaigning in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>松坂時代、日野から多くの商人や職人を引き連れて松坂の街づくりを推進したが、会津転封により完成を見届けることは出来ず、あとに入ってきた服部一忠、古田重勝に引き継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Matsuzaka era, many merchants and trades people were bought along to promote the building of a high-street however, there was a sudden turnaround in Aizu and the project could not be fully completed and, Kazutada HATTORI who came later and, Shigekatsu FURUTA carried on that work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Matsuzaka era, Ujisato brought many merchants and tradespeople from Hino to help build the town, but was transferred out of Aizu before the work was completed and the subsequently assigned Kazutada HATTORI and Shigekatsu FURUTA were lefet to carry on the work.</e>
<cmt>Correction of trans 1</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Matsuzaka era, Ujisato brought many merchants and tradespersons from Hino to help build the town, but was transferred out of Aizu before the work was completed and the subsequently assigned Kazutada HATTORI and Shigekatsu FURUTA were left to carry on the work.</e>
<cmt>tradespersonsスペル訂正しました。leftスペル訂正しました。スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>会津でも日野や松坂から多くの商人や職人を連れ、会津塗などの発展に力を尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Aizu as well as Hino and Matsuzaka many merchants and trades people were bought along, and efforts wer made to develop Aizu lacquer ware and other goods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many merchants and tradespeople were bought to Aizu from Matsuzaka and Hino, and efforts were made to develop Aizu lacquerware and other goods.</e>
<cmt>Correction of trans 1</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many merchants and tradespersons were bought to Aizu from Matsuzaka and Hino, and efforts were made to develop Aizu lacquerware and other goods.</e>
<cmt>tradespersonsスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>なお、三越の創始者である三井高利の三井家は、日野から松阪に移った際呼び寄せられた商家の一つであり、氏郷会津移封の際に誘いを断って松阪に残った家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Takatoshi MITSUI of the MITSUI family, the founder of Mitsukoshi (a venerable department store chain in Japan), is one merchant who was called upon to shift from Hino to Matsuzaka however, however resisted calls by Ujisato&apos;s to shift to Aizu and their family remained in Matsuzakaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatoshi MITSUI of the MITSUI family, the founder of Mitsukoshi (a venerable department store chain in Japan) was one merchant who Ujisato called upon to shift from Hino to Matsuzaka and later to Aizu, but he resisted going to Aizu and his family remained in Matsuzaka.</e>
<cmt>Simplification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatoshi MITSUI of the Mitsui family, the founder of Mitsukoshi (a venerable department store chain in Japan) was one merchant who Ujisato called upon to shift from Hino to Matsuzaka and later to Aizu, but he resisted going to Aizu and his family remained in Matsuzaka.</e>
<cmt>Mitsuiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>ただし、三井家自体は日野出身ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, strictly speaking, the Mitsui family does not hail from Hino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strictly speaking, however, the Mitsui family cannot be said to hail from Hino.</e>
<cmt>Not sure why this sentence is necessary…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strictly speaking, however, the Mitsui family cannot be said to hail from Hino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="49">
<j>『常山紀談』には、陸奥92万石を与えられたとき、氏郷は「たとえ大領であっても、奥羽のような田舎にあっては本望を遂げることなどできぬ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Jozankidan&quot;, at the time he was granted 920,000 koku in Mutsu, Ujisato said &quot;Even if I am given a large amount, in a rural backwater like Okuwa there is no way to accomplish long held ambitions &quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Jozankidan&quot; it is recorded that Ujisato, on being granted land with a yield of 920,000 koku in Mutsu, said &quot;Even with a large estate, in a rural backwater like Okuwa there is no way to achieve my ambitions &quot;.</e>
<cmt>The translation of the quote in trans 1 is rather unnatural. I think this should be rendered in natural English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Jozankidan&quot; it is recorded that Ujisato, on being granted land with a yield of 920,000 koku in Mutsu, said &apos;even with a large estate, in a rural backwater like Ou there is no way to achieve my ambitions.&apos;</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。スペース削除。原文の「」に合わせて”を&apos;に訂正しました。奥羽→Ou　に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>小身であっても、都に近ければこそ天下をうかがうことができるのだ」と激しく嘆いたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Even if the role is humble, the closer one is to the ruling elite better enables calls to be made.&quot; He was said to have loudly lamented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Even if the role was humble, if I were close to the capital, I could visit the court.&quot;, he is said to have loudly lamented.</e>
<cmt>English in quote is unnatural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, &apos;even if the role was humble, if I were close to the capital, I could visit the court,&apos; he is said to have loudly lamented.</e>
<cmt>also補足しました。原文の「」に合わせて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="51">
<j>戦国時代三大美少年のひとり名古屋山三郎を小姓として寵愛したことも、よく知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Warring State period there was a trio of handsome youths, one of whom was a page Sansaburo NAGOYA of whom he was known to be very fond of.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was know to have been very fond of Sansaburo NAGOYA, one of a trio of handsome youths in the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>This sentence is less awkward like this.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was know to have been very fond of Sanzaburo NAGOYA, one of a trio of handsome youths in the Sengoku perod (Warring States period).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。名古屋山三郎→Sanzaburo NAGOYA に訂正しました。ZSengoku period補足、（）補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="52">
<j>奥州転封後に、旧領主の伊達政宗から16歳という若い刺客を送られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returning to the interior of Japan, Masamune DATE the lord of his former fiefdom sent a young, supposedly 16 year old assassin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning to the interior of Japan, Masamune DATE who was the lord of Ujisato&apos;s former fiefdom sent an young assassin reputed to have been 16 years old.</e>
<cmt>It was not clear who &quot;his&quot; refers to. I have assumed that it is &quot;Ujisato&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning to the interior of Japan, Masamune DATE who was the lord of Ujisato&apos;s former fiefdom sent an young assassin reputed to have been 16 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>だが関所で伊達家との通信文が見つかりこの刺客は牢に繋がれたが、「伊達に対する忠義、天晴れなり」と刺客を解放したとの逸話が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is an anecdote remaining about how at a road checkpoint, a message from the DATE family was discovered and the assassin was sent to prison but, being &quot; gushingly full of admiration for DATE&quot;, the assassin was set free.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A message from DATE family was found, so the story goes, when the boy passed through a checkpoint and he was imprisoned, only to be released on account of his &quot;admirable loyalty to DATE&quot;.</e>
<cmt>&quot;gushingly full of admiration&quot; has negative connotations. &quot;admiralble loyalty&quot; is better.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A message from Date family was found, so the story goes, when the boy passed through a checkpoint and he was imprisoned, only to be released on account of his &apos;admirable loyalty to Date.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Dateに訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="54">
<j>織田信長は人質としてやってきた氏郷を見て一目でその実力と才能を見抜き、娘の冬姫を与えることを約束したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that when Nobunaga ODA upon was sent Ujisato as a hostage, he was able to gauge his abilities and genius at a single glance and promised his daughter Princess Fuyu&apos;s hand in marriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when Ujisato came to Nobunaga ODA as a hostage, Nobunaga realized his abilities at a single glance and promised his daughter Princess Fuyu&apos;s hand in marriage.</e>
<cmt>&quot;abilities and genius&quot; is a strange combination.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when Ujisato came to Nobunaga ODA as a hostage, Nobunaga realized his abilities at a single glance and promised his daughter Princess Fuyu&apos;s hand in marriage.</e>
<cmt>’を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>氏郷記では「蒲生が子息目付常ならず、只者にては有るべからず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Ujisato&apos;s diary it described what Nobunaga said; &quot;The GAMO boy is not an ordinary lad and must be had.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Ujisato&apos;s diary records Nobunaga as saying &quot;The GAMO boy is no an ordinary lad and should not be among common people.</e>
<cmt>Nobunaga&apos;s words have been incorrectly translated in trans 1.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Ujisato&apos;s diary records Nobunaga as saying &apos;the Gamo boy is no an ordinary lad and should not be among common people.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて”を&apos;に訂正しました。’を&apos;に訂正しました。Gamo小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>我婿にせん」と述べたという記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Make him one of us&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Make him one of us&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Make him one of us.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>急死に関して</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details of his Sudden Death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details of his Sudden Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details of his Sudden Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>秀吉やその側近・石田三成、あるいは伊達政宗、直江兼続などによる毒殺説もあるが、下記の理由によりほぼ否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Hideyoshi and his close associates: Mitsunari ISHIDA, as well as Masamune DATE, Kanetsugu NAOE etc there were theories about poisoning but according to the following reasons they have been largely repudiated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that Hideyoshi or one of his close associates such as Mitsunari ISHIDA, Masamune DATE, or Kanetsugu NAOE etc poisoned but this has been largely repudiated for the following reasons.</e>
<cmt>The orignal translation is mistaken. It was the poisoning that was by Hideyoshi et al, not the theory!</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that Hideyoshi or one of his close associates such as Mitsunari ISHIDA, Masamune DATE, or Kanetsugu NAOE etc poisoned but this has been largely repudiated for the following reasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>氏郷を診断した医師・曲直瀬玄朔が残したカルテ「医学天正記」には文禄の役の主兵の途中、既に名護屋城で発病し黄疸、目下にも浮腫などの症状が出たと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the clinical notes &quot;Tenshou Era (1573-1592) Medical Chronicle&quot;, written by Gensaku MANASE, the physician who diagnosed Ujisato, there is a record of a military leader en-route to the Bunroku Campaign with late-stage jaundice at Nagoya Castle: showing symptoms of swelling below the eyes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tenshou Era (1573-1592) Medical Chronicle&quot;, the clinical notes of Gensaku MANASE, the physician who saw Ujisato, there is a record of a military leader who fell ill at Nagoya castle en-route to the Bunroku Campaign and had symptoms of jaundice with swelling under the eyes.</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tenshou Era (1573 - 1592) Medical Chronicle,&quot; the clinical notes of Gensaku MANASE, the physician who saw Ujisato, there is a record of a military leader who fell ill at Nagoya castle en-route to the Bunroku Campaign and had symptoms of jaundice with swelling under the eyes.</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>その他の玄朔の診断内容から、氏郷は今でいう直腸癌または膵臓癌だったと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides this, according to Gensaku&apos;s diagnosis notes, it is suspected that Ujisato had what are referred to today as rectal cancer and pancreatic cancer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Gensaku&apos;s notes, it can also be inferred that Ujisato was suffering from what is referred to today as rectal/pancreatic cancer.</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Gensaku&apos;s notes, it can also be inferred that Ujisato was suffering from what is referred to today as rectal/pancreatic cancer.</e>
<cmt>’を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>辞世の句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Funeral Ode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Funeral Ode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Funeral Ode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>限りあれば　吹かねど花は　散るものを　心短き　春の山風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Limits abound but even if the wind blows not, blossoms fall, life is short so blow Spring mountain winds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Limits abound but even if the wind blows not, blossoms fall, life is short so blow Spring mountain winds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Limits abound but even if the wind blows not, blossoms fall, life is short so blow Spring mountain winds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="62">
<j>祇園南海、幸田露伴の著作にこの句の評釈がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a commentary on this poem in books by Nankai GION and Rohan KODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a commentary on this poem in books by Nankai GION and Rohan KODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a commentary on this poem in books by Nankai GION and Rohan KODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>また、山田風太郎は『人間臨終図鑑』の中で、「この句は戦国武将の絶唱としては白眉である」と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in Futaro YAMADA&apos;s &quot;Person`s Deathbed Reference&quot; there is an evaluation to the effect that &quot;this is a fine example of a poem by a military commander of the Warring State period&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in &quot;Person&apos;s Deathbed Reference&quot;, Futaro YAMADA comments &quot;this is a fine example of a poem by a military commander of the Warring State period&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Simplified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in &quot;Person&apos;s Deathbed Reference,&quot; Futaro YAMADA comments &apos;this is a fine example of a poem by a military commander of the Warring State period.&apos;</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave Site</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grave Site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grave Site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>京都市北区 (京都市)の大徳寺黄梅院、福島県会津若松市の興徳院（遺髪）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obai-in Daitoku-ji Temple in Kita-ku, Kyoto City and, Kotoku-ji Temple Aizuwakamatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture (deceased&apos;s hair).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujisato was buried at Obai-in Daitoku-ji Temple in Kita-ku, Kyoto City and, Kotoku-ji Temple Aizuwakamatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture (deceased&apos;s hair).</e>
<cmt>Inserted subject</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujisato was buried at Obai-in Daitoku-ji Temple in Kita-ku, Kyoto City and, Kotoku-ji Temple Aizuwakamatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture (deceased&apos;s hair).</e>
<cmt>’を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>近年、黄梅院にある墓を発掘したところ、刀を抱いた形で埋葬されていたことが判明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years the grave in Obai-in when excavated revealed a buried figure embracing a sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grave in Obai-in was recently excavated, revealing a figure embracing a sword.</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grave in Obai-in was recently excavated, revealing a figure embracing a sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Flamelai(id:34490), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), キヨンネ(id:56097), てら1971(id:131768), T@ka(id:12814), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), Tast(id:29478), でここ(id:9565), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Knua(id:66861), Chobot(id:20846), Shimoxx(id:9332), こぶまき(id:38278), ５１６(id:45205), Chao35(id:34986), Mnd(id:15140), 1687464(id:40784), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 水野白楓(id:22811), Shinyafortune(id:42940), 章奴(id:50198), Kaznov17(id:68122), Gktwofkscnec(id:71290), 小者(id:172526), Kagetudo(id:163875), 樒(id:35770), Rusk(id:9895), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Boca samba(id:137526), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), スタスタ坊主(id:72792), 福太郎(id:132415), NDR(id:5500), けんち(id:5147), せみまる(id:16528), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>