<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳大寺実盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanemori TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanemori TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanemori TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳大寺 実盛（とくだいじ さねもり、応永7年8月5日 (旧暦)（1400年8月24日） - 応永35年4月23日 (旧暦)（1428年6月6日））は、室町時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanemori TOKUDAIJI (August 24, 1400 - June 6, 1428) was a kugyo (to court official) in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanemori TOKUDAIJI (August 24, 1400 - June 6, 1428) was a kugyo (to court official) during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanemori TOKUDAIJI (September 2, 1400 - June 15, 1428) was a kugyo (court noble) during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主に後小松天皇（100代）・称光天皇（101代）の二帝にわたり仕え、官位は正二位大納言まで進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He mainly served two emperors of Emperor Gokomatsu (the 100th emperor) and Emperor Shoko (the 101st emperor,), and advanced up to Dainagon (a major counselor) at the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He mainly served two emperors, Emperor Gokomatsu (the 100th emperor) and Emperor Shoko (the 101st emperor,), and advanced up to Dainagon (major counselor) at the rank of Shonii (Senior 2nd Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He mainly served two emperors, Emperor Gokomatsu (the 100th) and Emperor Shoko (the 101st), and advanced up to Dainagon (chief councilor of state) at the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一 (major counselor)→(chief councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は太政大臣徳大寺公俊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Kintoshi TOKUDAIJI, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Kintoshi TOKUDAIJI, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Kintoshi TOKUDAIJI, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>室は衛門府持明院基親の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was a daughter of Motochika JIMYOIN at Emonfu (the headquarters of the outer palace guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was the daughter of Motochika JIMYOIN at Emonfu (the headquarters of the outer palace guards).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was the daughter of Motochika JIMYOIN at Emonfu (the headquarters of the outer palace guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に右大臣徳大寺公有、教覚（天台座主）、尊任（仁和寺大僧正）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinari TOKUDAIJI, Udaijin (minister of the right), Kyokaku (Tendai-zasu (the head priest of the Tendai sect)), and Sonin (daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) at Ninna-ji Temple) were his sons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinari TOKUDAIJI, Udaijin (minister of the right), Kyokaku (Tendai-zasu - the head priest of the Tendai sect), and Sonin (daisojo - a Buddhist priest of the highest order) at Ninna-ji Temple) were his sons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinari TOKUDAIJI, Udaijin (minister of the right), Kyokaku (Tendai-zasu - the head priest of the Tendai sect), and Sonin (daisojo - a Buddhist priest of the highest order at Ninna-ji Temple) were his sons.</e>
<cmt>)削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>応永11年（1404年）叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ennobled in 1404.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ennobled in 1404.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was conferred to a peerage in 1404.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以降累進して、侍従・近衛府・加賀国・近衛府・播磨国となり、応永21年（1414年）に従三位となり、公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, he continued being promoted, and was awarded Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1414, becoming a kugyo, after assuming a palace staff, a post at Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), a post in Kaga Province and a post at Konoefu, and a post in Harima Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, he continued being promoted, and was awarded Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank) in 1414, becoming a kugyo, after assuming a palace staff, a post at Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), a post in Kaga Province and a post at Konoefu, and a post in Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, he continued being promoted, and was awarded Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1414, becoming a kugyo, after assuming a palace staff, a post at Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), a post in Kaga Province and a post at Konoefu, and a post in Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>中納言をへて、応永28年（1421年）に大納言に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Dainagon (a major counselor) in 1421 after assuming Chunagon (a middle counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Dainagon (a major counselor) in 1421 after assuming Chunagon (a middle counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Dainagon in 1421 after assuming Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語統一 (chief councilor of state)削除（前出のため）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>応永35年（1428年）に踏歌節会をつとめたが、同年に薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1428, he played in a principal role in Toka no sechi-e (Imperial Court ceremonies where many persons danced while singing), but died in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1428, he played in a principal role in Toka no sechi-e (Imperial Court ceremonies where many persons danced while singing), but died in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1428, he played in a principal role in Toka no sechi-e (Imperial Court ceremonies where many persons danced while singing), but died in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>享年29。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 29 years old when he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was twenty-nine years old when he died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 29.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>