<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>北条時益</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokimasu HOJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokimasu HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokimasu HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>北条時益（ほうじょう ときます、？ - 元弘3年/正慶2年5月8日 (旧暦)（1333年6月19日））は、鎌倉幕府最後の六波羅探題（南方）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokimasu HOJO (date of birth unknown, died May 8, 1333 (old lunar calendar) (June 19, 1333)) was the last Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) (Minamikata) (South) of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokimasu HOJO (date of birth unknown, died May 8, 1333 (old lunar calendar) (June 19, 1333)) was the last Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agent in Rokuhara, Kyoto) (Minamikata) (South) of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokimasu HOJO (date of birth unknown, died June 28, 1333) was the last Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agent in Rokuhara, Kyoto) (Minamikata) (South) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>幕府の説明補足旧暦削除June 19→June 28に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北条氏 (政村流)の北条時敦の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of Tokiatsu HOJO, who belonged to the Hojo clan (Masamura school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of Tokiatsu HOJO, who belonged to the Hojo clan (Masamura school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of Tokiatsu HOJO, who belonged to the Hojo clan (Masamura school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>左近将監。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>用語集が間違っているものと思われます。（of が入っていません。）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1330年（元徳2年）、六波羅探題南方となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata in 1330.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata in 1330.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata (Southern Chief of Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto)) in 1330.</e>
<cmt>六波羅探題南方の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1331年（元弘元年）の元弘の変で、六波羅探題北方の北条仲時とともに、挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Genko Rebellion in 1331, he took up arms with Nakatoki HOJO, who was serving as Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata (North).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Genko Rebellion of 1331, he took up arms with Nakatoki HOJO, who was serving as Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata (North).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Genko Incident of 1331, he took up arms with Nakatoki HOJO, who was serving as Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata (Northern Chief of Rokuhara Tandai).</e>
<cmt>六波羅探題北方の定訳Rebellion→Incident</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>笠置山（京都府相楽郡笠置町）に籠城した後醍醐天皇と楠木正成らを攻め、激戦の末に天皇を隠岐島に配流する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They attacked Emperor Godaigo and Masashige KUSUNOKI, who cloistered themselves in Mt. Kasagi (Kasagi Town, Soraku Country, Kyoto Prefecture), and exiled them to Oki no shima Island after a fierce battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They attacked Emperor Godaigo and Masashige KUSUNOKI, who cloistered themselves in Mt. Kasagi (Kasagi Town, Soraku Country, Kyoto Prefecture), and exiled them to Oki no shima Island after a fierce battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They attacked Emperor Godaigo and Masashige KUSUNOKI, who cloistered themselves in Mt. Kasagi (Kasagi Town, Soraku Country, Kyoto Prefecture), and exiled the emperor to Oki no shima Island after a fierce battle.</e>
<cmt>流罪になったのは天皇だけなので訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>1333年（元弘3年/正慶2年）、後醍醐の綸旨を受けて挙兵に応じた足利尊氏（高氏）に六波羅を攻められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1333, Rokuhara was attacked by Takauji ASHIKAGA (the Ko clan), who took up arms at Emperor Godaigo&apos;s command.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1333, Rokuhara was attacked by Takauji ASHIKAGA (the Ko clan), who took up arms at Emperor Godaigo&apos;s command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1333, Rokuhara was attacked by Takauji ASHIKAGA (the Ko clan), who took up arms at Emperor Godaigo&apos;s command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仲時とともに、光厳天皇や花園天皇を伴って東国へ落ち延びようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He tried to escape to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) with Nakatoki, Emperor Kogon and Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He tried to escape to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly, the Kanto region) with Nakatoki, Emperor Kogon, and Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>article, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He tried to escape to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly, the Kanto region) with Nakatoki, Emperor Kogon, and Emperor Hanazono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、道中の近江国（滋賀県）で野伏に襲われて討死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was attacked by a nobushi (unofficial warrior hidden in a forest) in Omi Province (Shiga Prefecture) on his way, and died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, along the way, he was attacked by a nobushi (unofficial warrior hidden in a forest) in Omi Province (Shiga Prefecture), and died in battle.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, along the way, he was attacked by a nobushi (unofficial warrior hidden in a forest) in Omi Province (Shiga Prefecture), and died in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>