<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利尊氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利 尊氏（あしかが たかうじ、1305年-1358年）は、鎌倉時代後期から南北朝時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA (1305-58) was a general from the late Kamakura period to the Northern and Southern Courts period.</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の対訳からNambokucho periodを削除。尊氏は将軍だったので、ここでは武将をgeneralと訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji ASHIKAGA (1305-58) was a general from the late Kamakura period to the Northern and Southern Courts period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA (1305-58) was a general from the late Kamakura period to the Northern and Southern Courts period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>室町幕府の初代征夷大将軍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 1st Seii Taishogun of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 1st Seii Taishogun of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 1st Seii Taishogun of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji was a descendant of the Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>源氏の対訳からMinamoto clanを削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji was a descendant of the Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji was a descendant of the Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>河内源氏の名門足利氏嫡流足利貞氏の嫡男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 1st son of Sadauji ASHIKAGA, who was a descendant in the direct line of the Ashikaga clan, which was the powerful family in Kawachi Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 1st son of Sadauji ASHIKAGA, who was a descendant in the direct line of the Ashikaga clan, which was the powerful family in Kawachi Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 1st son of Sadauji ASHIKAGA, who was a descendant in the direct line of the Ashikaga clan, which was the powerful family in Kawachi Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>初め執権・北条高時から偏諱を受け高氏と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his early years, he was given the name Takauji (高氏) by the regent Takatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>執権の対訳からShikken削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his early years, he was given the name Takauji by the regent Takatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>kanji seem unnecessary here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his early years, he was given the name Takauji by the regent Takatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>元弘3年に後醍醐天皇が伯耆船上山で挙兵した際、鎌倉幕府の有力御家人として幕府軍を率いて上洛したが、丹波篠村八幡宮で反幕府の兵を挙げ、六波羅探題を滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1333 (Genko 3), when the Emperor Go-Daigo had raised an army at Mt. Senjosan in Hoki Province, Takauji, the powerful vassal of the Kamakura shogunate, was sent to Kyoto leading the main armies of the shogunate to put down the rebellion, but he switched his side and gathered an army against the shogunate at Shinomura Hachimangu in Tamba Province to capture Rokuhara Tandai.</e>
<cmt>伯耆の対訳からHoki削除、御家人の対訳をGoke&apos;ninからvassalに変更、丹波の対訳からTamba削除、和暦のみの記述でしたが、西暦も訳文に追加</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1333, when the Emperor Go-Daigo had raised an army at Mt. Senjosan in Hoki Province, Takauji, the powerful vassal of the Kamakura shogunate, was sent to Kyoto leading the main armies of the shogunate to put down the rebellion, but he switched sides and gathered an army against the shogunate at Shinomura Hachimangu in Tamba Province to capture Rokuhara Tandai.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date; his side-&gt;sides</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1333, when the Emperor Go-Daigo had raised an army at Mt. Senjosan in Hoki Province, Takauji, the powerful vassal of the Kamakura shogunate, was sent to Kyoto leading the main armies of the shogunate to put down the rebellion, but he switched sides and gathered an army against the shogunate at Shinomura Hachimangu in Tamba Province to capture Rokuhara Tandai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幕府滅亡の勲功第一とされ、後醍醐天皇の諱・尊治（たかはる）の御一字を賜り、名を尊氏に改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His achievements were evaluated by Emperor Go-Daigo, and he was awarded the letter (尊), which came from the emperor&apos;s real name Takaharu (尊治), so he changed the letter in his name from &quot;高氏&quot; to &quot;尊氏&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His achievements were evaluated by Emperor Go-Daigo, and he was awarded the letter (尊), which came from the emperor&apos;s real name Takaharu (尊治), so he changed the letter in his name from &quot;高氏&quot; to &quot;尊氏&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His achievements were evaluated by Emperor Go-Daigo, and he was awarded the letter (尊), which came from the emperor&apos;s real name Takaharu (尊治), so he changed the letter in his name from &quot;高氏&quot; to &quot;尊氏&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>後醍醐専制による建武の新政が次第に支持を失っていく中、東下して中先代の乱を鎮圧した後、鎌倉に留まり独自の政権を樹立する構えを見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the despotic Kemmu restoration by Emperor Go-Daigo had been losing support, Takauji traveled to the east to suppress the Nakasendai Rebellion, and stayed in Kamakura to try to build his own government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the despotic Kemmu restoration by Emperor Go-Daigo had been losing support, Takauji traveled to the east to suppress the Nakasendai Rebellion, and stayed in Kamakura to try to build his own government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the despotic Kenmu restoration by Emperor Go-Daigo had been losing support, Takauji traveled to the east to suppress the Nakasendai Rebellion, and stayed in Kamakura to try to build his own government.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字をヘボン式に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これにより朝廷との関係が悪化し、上洛して一時は後醍醐を比叡山へ追いやったが、後醍醐勢力の反攻により一旦は九州へ落ち延びる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, the relationship between Takauji and the imperial court came to an impasse, and he returned to Kyoto, driving the Emperor Go-Daigo out to Mt. Hiei. However, the Emperor&apos;s army made a counterattack and Takauji fled to Kyushu temporarily.</e>
<cmt>比叡山の対訳からMount Hiei削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, the relationship between Takauji and the imperial court came to an impasse, and he returned to Kyoto, driving the Emperor Go-Daigo out to Mt. Hiei. However, the Emperor&apos;s army made a counterattack and Takauji fled to Kyushu temporarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, the relationship between Takauji and the imperial court came to an impasse, and he returned to Kyoto, driving the Emperor Go-Daigo out to Mt. Hiei. However, the Emperor&apos;s army made a counterattack and Takauji fled to Kyushu temporarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>九州から再び上洛し、光厳上皇および光明天皇から征夷大将軍に補任され新たな武家政権（＝室町幕府）を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He reentered Kyoto and established a new samurai government called Muromachi Shogunate, being appointed Seii Taishogun by Grand Emperor (Retired Emperor) Kogon and Empror Komyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He reentered Kyoto and established a new samurai government called the Muromachi Shogunate, being appointed Seii Taishogun by Grand Emperor (Retired Emperor) Kogon and Emperor Komyo.</e>
<cmt>inserted “the”; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He reentered Kyoto and established a new samurai government called the Muromachi Shogunate, being appointed Seii Taishogun by Grand Emperor (Retired Emperor) Kogon and Emperor Komyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後醍醐は吉野へ遷り南朝 (日本)を創始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Emperor Go-Daigo moved to Yoshino and set up the Southern Court there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Emperor Go-Daigo moved to Yoshino and set up the Southern Court there.</e>
<cmt>on the other hand-&gt;at the same time</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Emperor Go-Daigo moved to Yoshino and set up the Southern Court there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>幕府を開いた後は弟・足利直義と二頭政治を布いたが、後に直義と対立し観応の擾乱へと発展する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he established Muromachi Shogunate, he and his brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA divided the power between them, but in later years discord between them increased to the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he established the Muromachi Shogunate, he and his brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA divided power between them, but in later years discord between them increased until the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>use of “the”; to-&gt;until</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he established the Muromachi Shogunate, he and his brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA divided power between them, but in later years discord between them increased until the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>直義の死により乱は終息したが、その後も南朝など反幕勢力の平定を継続し、統治の安定に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disturbance subsided by the death of Tadayoshi, but even after that Takauji had to keep fighting against his enemies such as the Southern Court forces to maintain his government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disturbance subsided with the death of Tadayoshi, but even after that Takauji had to keep fighting against his enemies, such as the Southern Court forces, to maintain his government.</e>
<cmt>by-&gt;with; inserted commas for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disturbance subsided with the death of Tadayoshi, but even after that Takauji had to keep fighting against his enemies, such as the Southern Court forces, to maintain his government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>後醍醐が崩御（死去）した後はその菩提を弔うため天竜寺を建立している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Go-Daigo died, Takauji built Tenryu-ji Temple to pray for the dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Go-Daigo died, Takauji built Tenryu-ji Temple to pray for the dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Go-Daigo died, Takauji built Tenryu-ji Temple to pray for the dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>（後醍醐）天皇に叛旗を翻したことから明治以降は逆賊として位置づけられていたが、第二次大戦後は肯定的に再評価されているように、歴史観の変遷によってその人物像が大きく変化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of his rebellion against the emperor, people had branded him as a traitor since Meiji era, but after World War II they began to look at him more positively, which illustrates how much the historical point of view affects the way we look at the people in history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of his rebellion against the emperor, people had branded him as a traitor since the Meiji era, but after World War II they began to look at him more positively, which illustrates how much the historical point of view affects the way we look at the people in history.</e>
<cmt>inserted “the”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of his rebellion against the emperor, people had branded him as a traitor since the Meiji era, but after World War II they began to look at him more positively, which illustrates how much the historical point of view affects the way we look at the people in history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>誕生から鎌倉幕府滅亡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From birth to the fall of Kamakura Shogunate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Birth to the Fall of the Kamakura Shogunate</e>
<cmt>Capitalized words in section heading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Birth to the Fall of the Kamakura Shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>尊氏は嘉元3年(1305年)に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji was born in 1305 (Kagen 3).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji was born in 1305.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji was born in 1305.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>生誕地は、綾部説（漢部とも。京都府綾部市上杉荘）、鎌倉説、足利荘説（栃木県足利市）の3説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are 3 presumptions about his birthplace: Ayabe (Uesugisho in Ayabe City, Kyoto), Kamakura and Ashikagano sho (Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are 3 presumptions about his birthplace: Ayabe (Uesugisho in Ayabe City, Kyoto), Kamakura and Ashikagano sho (Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are 3 presumptions about his birthplace: Ayabe (Uesugisho in Ayabe City, Kyoto), Kamakura and Ashikagano sho (Ashikaga City, Tochigi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『難太平記』は尊氏が出生して産湯につかった際、2羽の山鳩が飛んできて1羽は尊氏の肩にとまり1羽は柄杓にとまったという伝説を伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nan-Taiheiki&quot; says that when Takauji was given his first bath, two turtledoves flew in; one perched on his shoulder, and the other on the dipper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nan-Taiheiki&quot; says that when Takauji was given his first bath, two turtledoves flew in; one perched on his shoulder, and the other on the dipper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nan-Taiheiki&quot; says that when Takauji was given his first bath, two turtledoves flew in; one perched on his shoulder, and the other on the dipper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>幼名は又太郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Matataro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Matataro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Matataro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>元応元年(1319年)10月10日、15歳のとき元服し従五位下治部大輔に補任されるとともに、幕府執権・北条高時の偏諱を賜り高氏と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 10th, 1319 (the first year of Geno), his coming-of-age ceremony called Gempuku was held at age 15, and he was appointed Jibutaifu of the Fifth Rank, Junior Grade, and given the name Takauji by the regent Takatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 10th, 1319, his coming-of-age ceremony (Gempuku) was held at age 15, and he was appointed Jibutaifu of the Fifth Rank, Junior Grade, and given the name Takauji by the regent Takatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date; added parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 10th, 1319, his coming-of-age ceremony (Genpuku) was held at age 15, and he was appointed Jibutaifu of the Fifth Rank, Junior Grade, and given the name Takauji by the regent Takatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字をヘボン式に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>父・貞氏とその正室・釈迦堂（北条顕時の娘）との間に長男・足利高義がいたが、早世したため高氏が家督を相続することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji&apos;s father Sadauji and his official wife Shakado, daughter of Akitoki HOJO, had the first son Takayoshi ASHIKAGA, but he died early and Takauji succeeded to his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji&apos;s father Sadauji and his official wife Shakado, daughter of Akitoki HOJO, had the first son Takayoshi ASHIKAGA, but he died early and Takauji succeeded to his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji&apos;s father Sadauji and his official wife Shakado, daughter of Akitoki HOJO, had the first son Takayoshi ASHIKAGA, but he died early and Takauji succeeded to his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>『難太平記』によれば、尊氏の祖父・足利家時が三代のちに足利氏が天下を取る事を願って自刃したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nan-Taiheiki&quot;, Ietoki ASHIKAGA, Takauji&apos;s grandfather, killed himself with his sword, praying that the Ashikaga clan may rule over the whole country in 3 generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nan-Taiheiki&quot;, Ietoki ASHIKAGA, Takauji&apos;s grandfather, killed himself with his sword, praying that the Ashikaga clan may rule over the whole country in 3 generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nan-Taiheiki&quot;, Ietoki ASHIKAGA, Takauji&apos;s grandfather, killed himself with his sword, praying that the Ashikaga clan may rule over the whole country in 3 generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>元弘元年（1331年）、後醍醐天皇が二度目の倒幕を企図し、笠置で挙兵した（元弘の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1331 (the first year of Genko), Emperor Go-Daigo plotted the overthrow of the shogunate again and raised an army at Kasagi. (Genko Incident)</e>
<cmt>元弘の変の対訳からGenko no Hen削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1331, Emperor Go-Daigo plotted the overthrow of the shogunate again and raised an army at Kasagi (Genko Incident).</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date; moved period outside parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1331, Emperor Go-Daigo plotted the overthrow of the shogunate again and raised an army at Kasagi (Genko Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>鎌倉幕府は有力御家人である高氏に派兵を命じ、高氏は天皇の拠る笠置と楠木正成の拠る下赤坂城の攻撃に参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura shogunate ordered Takauji, who had been a powerful vassal, to help the shogunate, and he joined the battles at Kasasagi where the emperor was based and the Shimoakasaka Castle in which Masashige KUSUNOKI was based.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamakura shogunate ordered Takauji, who had been a powerful vassal, to help the shogunate, and he joined the battles at Kasasagi where the emperor was based and at Shimoakasaka Castle in which Masashige KUSUNOKI was based.</e>
<cmt>use of “the”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamakura shogunate ordered Takauji, who had been a powerful vassal, to help the shogunate, and he joined the battles at Kasagi where the emperor was based and at Shimoakasaka Castle in which Masashige KUSUNOKI was based.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>このとき、父・貞氏が没した直後であり高氏は派兵を辞退するが、幕府は妻子を人質として重ねて派兵を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident had taken place just after his father&apos;s death, so Takauji at first had refused his help to the shogunate, but the Kamakura shognate took his wife and children as hostages to make Takauji follow its order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident had taken place just after his father&apos;s death, so Takauji at first had refused his help to the shogunate, but the Kamakura shogunate took his wife and children as hostages to make Takauji follow its order.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident had taken place just after his father&apos;s death, so Takauji at first had refused his help to the shogunate, but the Kamakura shogunate took his wife and children as hostages to make Takauji follow its order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>『古典太平記』は、これにより高氏が幕府に反感を持つようになったと記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Koten-Taiheiki&quot;, because of this Takauji began to have hostility toward the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Koten-Taiheiki&quot;, because of this Takauji began to harbor hostility toward the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>have-&gt;harbor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Koten-Taiheiki,&quot; because of this Takauji began to harbor hostility toward the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>引用符の内側にカンマを移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>幕府軍の攻撃の結果、天皇をはじめとして倒幕計画に関わった日野俊基・円観などの公家や僧侶が多数、幕府に捕縛され、天皇は翌年隠岐島に流された（元弘の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of the attack against the emperor made by the shogunate, the emperor and his followers such as Toshimoto HINO and Enkan were captured, and the following year Emperor Go-Daigo was exiled to Oki Islands. (Genko Rebellion)</e>
<cmt>元弘の乱の対訳からGenko no Ran/Genko War削除、隠岐島の対訳からOkinoshima削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the attack against the emperor made by the shogunate, the emperor and his followers such as Toshimoto HINO and Enkan were captured, and the following year Emperor Go-Daigo was exiled to Oki Islands (Genko Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>moved period outside parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the attack against the emperor made by the shogunate, the emperor and his followers such as Toshimoto HINO and Enkan were captured, and the following year Emperor Go-Daigo was exiled to Oki Islands (Genko Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>幕府は大覚寺統の後醍醐天皇に代えて持明院統の光厳天皇を擁立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate installed Emepror Kogon of the Jimyo-in line as emperor, instead of Emperor Go-Daigo of the Daikaku-ji line.</e>
<cmt>大覚寺統の対訳からDaikaku-ji-to削除、持明院統の対訳からJimyo-in-to削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate installed Emepror Kogon of the Jimyo-in line as emperor, instead of Emperor Go-Daigo of the Daikaku-ji line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate installed Emperor Kogon of the Jimyo-in line as emperor, instead of Emperor Go-Daigo of the Daikaku-ji line.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>翌元弘3年/正慶2年（1333年）後醍醐天皇は隠岐島を脱出して船上山に篭城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, Emperor Go-Daigo escaped from Oki Islands, and raised an army at Mt. Senjosan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, Emperor Go-Daigo escaped from Oki Islands, and raised an army at Mt. Senjosan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, Emperor Go-Daigo escaped from Oki Islands, and raised an army at Mt. Senjosan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>高氏は再び幕命を受け、西国の討幕勢力を鎮圧するために名越高家とともに上洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji was ordered to reenter Kyoto with Takaie NAGOE to put down the rebellion in the west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji was ordered to reenter Kyoto with Takaie NAGOE to put down the rebellion in the west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji was ordered to reenter Kyoto with Takaie NAGOE to put down the rebellion in the west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>名越高家が赤松則村に討たれたことを機として、後醍醐天皇の綸旨を受けていた高氏は天皇方につくことを決意し、同年4月29日、所領の丹波国篠村八幡宮（京都府亀岡市）で反幕府の兵を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaie was killed by Norimura AKAMATSU, which made Takauji decide to side with the emperor. On April 29th of the same year, he raised an army against the shogunate at Shinomura Hachimangu (present Kameoka City, Kyoto) in Tamba Province.</e>
<cmt>丹波国の対訳からTamba no Kuni削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaie was killed by Norimura AKAMATSU, which made Takauji decide to side with the emperor. On April 29th of the same year, he raised an army against the shogunate at Shinomura Hachimangu (present Kameoka City, Kyoto) in Tamba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaie was killed by Norimura AKAMATSU, which made Takauji decide to side with the emperor. On April 29th of the same year, he raised an army against the shogunate at Shinomura Hachimangu (present Kameoka City, Kyoto) in Tamba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>諸国に多数の軍勢催促状を発し、近江国の佐々木道誉などの御家人を従えて入京し、同年5月7日に六波羅探題を滅亡させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji gathered forces from various provinces, and entered Kyoto followed by vassals such as Doyo SASAKI from Omi Province, and then succeeded in destroying Rokuhara Tandai on May 7th, 1333.</e>
<cmt>近江国の対訳からOmi no Kunii削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji gathered forces from various provinces, and entered Kyoto followed by vassals such as Doyo SASAKI from Omi Province, and then succeeded in destroying Rokuhara Tandai on May 7th, 1333.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji gathered forces from various provinces, and entered Kyoto followed by vassals such as Doyo SASAKI from Omi Province, and then succeeded in destroying Rokuhara Tandai on May 7th, 1333.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>同時期に上野国の御家人である新田義貞も挙兵しており、高氏の嫡子で鎌倉から脱出した千寿王（後の足利義詮）を奉じて鎌倉へ進軍し、幕府を滅亡させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At about the same time, Yoshisada NITTA, vassal of Kozuke Province, also gathered an army, and destroyed the shogunate, taking Takauji&apos;s heir Senjuo (later called Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), who had escaped from Kamakura, with him.</e>
<cmt>上野国の対訳からKozuke no Kuni削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At about the same time, Yoshisada NITTA, vassal of Kozuke Province, also gathered an army, and destroyed the shogunate, taking Takauji&apos;s heir Senjuo (later called Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), who had escaped from Kamakura, with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At about the same time, Yoshisada NITTA, vassal of Kozuke Province, also gathered an army, and destroyed the shogunate, taking Takauji&apos;s heir Senjuo (later called Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), who had escaped from Kamakura, with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この時、高氏の側室の子・竹若丸が混乱の最中に殺されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this fighting, Takauji&apos;s illegitimate son Takewakamaru was killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this fighting, Takewakamaru, the son of Takauji&apos;s concubine, was killed.</e>
<cmt>illegitimate son-&gt;son of [his] concubine (to call a child “illegitimate” conveys a sense of unintended and shameful circumstances that is not associated with 側室)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this fighting, Takewakamaru, the son of Takauji&apos;s concubine, was killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>高氏は鎌倉陥落後に細川和氏・細川頼春・細川師氏の兄弟を派遣して義貞を上洛させ、鎌倉を足利方に掌握させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Kamakura shogunate was crumbled, Takauji ordered Kazuuji HOSOKAWA, Yoriharu HOSOKAWA and Morouji HOSOKAWA to make Yoshisada NITTA return to Kyoto, and let the Ashikaga clan rule Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Kamakura shogunate was crumbled, Takauji ordered Kazuuji HOSOKAWA, Yoriharu HOSOKAWA and Morouji HOSOKAWA to make Yoshisada NITTA return to Kyoto, and let the Ashikaga clan rule Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kamakura shogunate was crumbled, Takauji ordered Kazuuji HOSOKAWA, Yoriharu HOSOKAWA and Morouji HOSOKAWA to make Yoshisada NITTA return to Kyoto, and let the Ashikaga clan rule Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>建武の新政から南北朝動乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Kemmu restoration to the turbulent in the Northen and Southern Courts period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Kemmu Restoration to the Turbulence of the Northern and Southern Courts Period</e>
<cmt>capitalized words in section heading; turbulent-&gt;turbulence; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Kenmu Restoration to the Turbulence of the Northern and Southern Courts Period</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>鎌倉幕府の滅亡後、高氏は後醍醐天皇から勲功第一とされ、鎮守府将軍および従四位下左兵衛督に任ぜられ、またに30箇所の所領を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the fall of the Kamakura shogunate, Emperor Go-Daigo considered Takauji&apos;s work was commendable, and gave him the ranks of Chinjufu Shogun and Sahyoe no kami of the courtly title of the Fourth Rank, Junior Grade, along with 30 plots of land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the fall of the Kamakura shogunate, Emperor Go-Daigo considered Takauji&apos;s work to be commendable, and gave him the ranks of Chinjufu Shogun and Sahyoe no Kami with the courtly title of Fourth Rank, Junior Grade, along with 30 plots of land.</e>
<cmt>use of “the”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the fall of the Kamakura shogunate, Emperor Go-Daigo considered Takauji&apos;s work to be commendable, and gave him the ranks of Chinjufu Shogun and Sahyoe no Kami with the courtly title of Fourth Rank, Junior Grade, along with 30 plots of land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>さらに天皇の諱・尊治から御一字を賜り尊氏と改名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to that, he was given the letter (尊), which came from the emperor&apos;s given name, and changed the letter of his name Takauji (高氏) into Takauji (尊氏).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to that, he was given the letter (尊), which came from the emperor&apos;s given name, and changed the letter of his name Takauji (高氏) into Takauji (尊氏).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to that, he was given the letter (尊), which came from the emperor&apos;s given name, and changed the letter of his name Takauji (高氏) into Takauji (尊氏).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>尊氏は建武政権では政治の中枢からはなれており、足利家の執事職である高師直・高師泰兄弟などを送り込み、弟・足利直義を鎌倉将軍府執権とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Kemmu administration, Takauji left politics and let KO no Moronao, the regent of the Ashikaga clan, and KO no Moroyasu engage in politics, while he made his brother Tadayoshi the regent of the Kamakura Shogunfu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Kemmu administration, Takauji left politics and let KO no Moronao, the regent of the Ashikaga clan, and KO no Moroyasu engage in politics, while he made his brother Tadayoshi the regent of the Kamakura Shogunfu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Kenmu administration, Takauji left politics and let KO no Moronao, the regent of the Ashikaga clan, and KO no Moroyasu engage in politics, while he made his brother Tadayoshi the regent of the Kamakura Shogunfu.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字をヘボン式に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>これには後醍醐天皇が尊氏を敬遠したとする見方と、尊氏自身が政権と距離を置いたとする見方とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two interpretations of such Takauji&apos;s behavior; one is that it was Emperor Go-Daigo who made Takauji leave politics, and the other is that it was Takauji who try to keep away from the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two interpretations of Takauji&apos;s behavior; one is that it was Emperor Go-Daigo who made Takauji leave politics, and the other is that it was Takauji who tried to keep away from the government.</e>
<cmt>deleted “such”; try-&gt;tried</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two interpretations of Takauji&apos;s behavior; one is that it was Emperor Go-Daigo who made Takauji leave politics, and the other is that it was Takauji who tried to keep away from the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、征夷大将軍の宣下を受け、鎌倉に幕府を開く意図があったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here is also a different presumption that Takauji intended to establish the new government in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a different presumption that Takauji intended to establish the new government in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>here-&gt;there</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a different presumption that Takauji intended to establish the new government in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>この状態は「新政に尊氏なし」と言われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This condition was called &quot;Takauji&apos;s absence in the new government&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This condition was called &quot;Takauji&apos;s absence in the new government&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This condition was called &quot;Takauji&apos;s absence in the new government&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>後醍醐天皇が北畠顕家を鎮守府将軍に任じて幼い義良親王（後の後村上天皇）を奉じさせて奥州鎮定に向かわせると、尊氏は直義に幼い成良親王を奉じさせ鎌倉へ下向させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Emperor Go-Daigo appointed Akiie KITABATAKE as Chinjufu Shogun and made him take Prince Noriyoshi (later called Emperor GO-Murakami) to Oshu in order to pacify the place, Takauji made Tadayoshi lead young Prince Narinaga (Nariyoshi) down to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Emperor Go-Daigo appointed Akiie KITABATAKE as Chinjufu Shogun and made him take Prince Noriyoshi (later called Emperor GO-Murakami) to Oshu in order to pacify the place, Takauji made Tadayoshi lead young Prince Narinaga (Nariyoshi) down to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Emperor Go-Daigo appointed Akiie KITABATAKE as Chinjufu Shogun and made him take Prince Noriyoshi (later called Emperor GO-Murakami) to Oshu in order to pacify the place, Takauji made Tadayoshi lead young Prince Narinaga (Nariyoshi) down to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>後醍醐天皇の皇子であり同じく征夷大将軍職を望んでいた護良親王は尊氏と対立し、尊氏暗殺を試みるが尊氏側の警護が厳重で果たせなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s son Prince Morinaga, who also wanted a title of Seii Taishogun, gradually rivaled Takauji, and plotted to assassinate Takauji, but Takauji&apos;s security was so tight that he failed to do it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s son Prince Morinaga, who also coveted the title of Seii Taishogun, gradually came to rival Takauji, and plotted to assassinate him, but Takauji&apos;s security was so tight that he failed to do it.</e>
<cmt>wanted a-&gt;coveted the; rivaled-&gt;came to rival; replaced name with “him”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s son Prince Morinaga, who also coveted the title of Seii Taishogun, gradually came to rival Takauji, and plotted to assassinate him, but Takauji&apos;s security was so tight that he failed to do it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>建武 (日本)元年（1334年）、尊氏は、実子恒良親王を皇太子としたい後醍醐天皇の寵姫阿野廉子と結び、後醍醐天皇とも確執していた護良親王を捕縛し鎌倉の直義のもとに幽閉させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1334, Takauji captured and confined Prince Morinaga, who was in conflict with the emperor too, to Tadayoshi&apos;s place in Kamakura, being conspired with the emperor&apos;s mistress Yasuko (Kadoko) ANO, who wanted to make her son Prince Tsunenaga (Tsuneyoshi) a crown prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1334, Takauji captured and confined Prince Morinaga, who was in conflict with the emperor too, to Tadayoshi&apos;s place in Kamakura, conspiring with the emperor&apos;s mistress Yasuko (Kadoko) ANO, who wanted to make her son Prince Tsunenaga (Tsuneyoshi) a crown prince.</e>
<cmt>being conspired-&gt;conspiring</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1334, Takauji captured and confined Prince Morinaga, who was in conflict with the emperor too, to Tadayoshi&apos;s place in Kamakura, conspiring with the emperor&apos;s mistress Yasuko (Kadoko) ANO, who wanted to make her son Prince Tsunenaga (Tsuneyoshi) a crown prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>建武2年（1335年）に信濃国で、北条高時の遺児北条時行を擁立した北条氏残党の反乱である中先代の乱が起こり、時行軍は鎌倉を一時占拠する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1335, Nakasendai Rebellion was raised in Shinano Province by the survivors of the HOJO clan, taking Tokiyuki HOJO, bereaved son of Takatoki HOJO, with them, and Tokiyuki&apos;s army occupied Kamakura temporarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1335, Nakasendai Rebellion was raised in Shinano Province by the survivors of the HOJO clan, taking Tokiyuki HOJO, bereaved son of Takatoki HOJO, with them, and Tokiyuki&apos;s army occupied Kamakura temporarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1335, Nakasendai Rebellion was raised in Shinano Province by the survivors of the HOJO clan, taking Tokiyuki HOJO, bereaved son of Takatoki HOJO, with them, and Tokiyuki&apos;s army occupied Kamakura temporarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>その際、直義が独断で護良親王を殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the rebellion, Tadayoshi killed Prince Morinaga without permission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the rebellion, Tadayoshi killed Prince Morinaga without permission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the rebellion, Tadayoshi killed Prince Morinaga without permission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>尊氏は後醍醐天皇に征夷大将軍の官を望むが得られず、同年8月2日、勅状を得ないまま鎌倉へ進発し、後醍醐天皇はやむなく征東大将軍の号を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji requested Emperor Go-Daigo to appoint him Seii Taishogun only to be rejected, so he marched to Kamakura without emperor&apos;s permission on August 2nd of the same year, which made Emperor Go-Daigo reluctantly assigned him as Seito Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>征東大将軍は征夷大将軍と同質のものと解されている</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji requested that Emperor Go-Daigo appoint him Seii Taishogun only to be rejected, so he marched to Kamakura without emperor&apos;s permission on August 2nd of the same year, which made Emperor Go-Daigo reluctantly appoint him as Seito Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>assigned-&gt;appoint</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji requested that Emperor Go-Daigo appoint him Seii Taishogun only to be rejected, so he marched to Kamakura without emperor&apos;s permission on August 2nd of the same year, which made Emperor Go-Daigo reluctantly appoint him as Seito Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>尊氏は直義の兵と合流し相模川の戦いで時行を駆逐して、同月19日には鎌倉を回復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi&apos;s army joined by Takauji defeated Tokiyuki HOJO at the Battle of Sagamigawa and retrieved Kamakura on 19th of the same month.</e>
<cmt>相模川の戦い→Battle of Sagami River</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi&apos;s army, joined by Takauji, defeated Tokiyuki HOJO at the Battle of Sagamigawa and regained Kamakura on the 19th of the same month.</e>
<cmt>added commas; retrieved-&gt;regained; added “the”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi&apos;s army, joined by Takauji, defeated Tokiyuki HOJO at the Battle of Sagamigawa and regained Kamakura on the 19th of the same month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>尊氏は従二位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji was given the courtly title of the Second Rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji was given the courtly title of the Second Rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji was given the courtly title of the Second Rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>直義の意向もあって尊氏はそのまま鎌倉に本拠を置き、独自に恩賞を与え始め京都からの上洛の命令を拒み、独自の武家政権創始の動きを見せ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Tadayoshi&apos;s intention, Takauji established a base in Kamakura and began to allot lands to his followers, ignoring the emperor&apos;s command to return to Kyoto, and he tried to establish his own samurai government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Tadayoshi&apos;s approval, Takauji established a base in Kamakura and began to allot lands to his followers, ignoring the emperor&apos;s command to return to Kyoto, and he tried to establish his own samurai government.</e>
<cmt>intention-&gt;approval</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Tadayoshi&apos;s approval, Takauji established a base in Kamakura and began to allot lands to his followers, ignoring the emperor&apos;s command to return to Kyoto, and he tried to establish his own samurai government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>同年11月、尊氏は新田義貞を君側の奸であるとして後醍醐天皇にその討伐を上奏するが、後醍醐天皇は逆に義貞に尊良親王を奉じさせて尊氏討伐を命じ、東海道を鎌倉へ向かわせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, Takauji suggested to the emperor that Yoshisada NITTA was an enemy of the imperial court and should be killed, but on the contrary the emperor ordered Yoshisada to kill Takauji, making Yoshisada take Prince Takanaga (Takayoshi) to Kamakura along Tokaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, Takauji suggested to the emperor that Yoshisada NITTA was an enemy of the imperial court and should be killed, but on the contrary the emperor ordered Yoshisada to kill Takauji, making Yoshisada take Prince Takanaga (Takayoshi) to Kamakura along Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, Takauji suggested to the emperor that Yoshisada NITTA was an enemy of the imperial court and should be killed, but on the contrary the emperor ordered Yoshisada to kill Takauji, making Yoshisada take Prince Takanaga (Takayoshi) to Kamakura along Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>さらに奥州からは北畠顕家も南下を始めており、尊氏は赦免を求めて隠居を宣言するが、直義・高師直などの足利方が三河国など各地で敗れはじめると、尊氏は建武政権に叛旗を翻すことを決意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides that, Akiie KITABATAKE began to go down to Kyoto from Oshu, so Takauji declared his retirement to get a reprieve. However, once the Ashikaga side such as Tadayoshi and Ko no Moronao began to lose at various provinces such as Mikawa, Takauji decided to revolt against the Kemmu government.</e>
<cmt>三河国→Mikawa</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides that, Akiie KITABATAKE began to go down to Kyoto from Oshu, so Takauji declared his retirement to get a reprieve. However, once the Ashikaga side, including Tadayoshi and KO no Moronao, began to lose at various provinces such as Mikawa, Takauji decided to revolt against the Kemmu government.</e>
<cmt>such as-&gt;including</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides that, Akiie KITABATAKE began to go down to Kyoto from Oshu, so Takauji declared his retirement to get a reprieve. However, once the Ashikaga side, including Tadayoshi and KO no Moronao, began to lose at various provinces such as Mikawa, Takauji decided to revolt against the Kenmu government.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字をヘボン式に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>同年12月、尊氏は新田軍を箱根・竹ノ下の戦いで破り、京都へ進軍を始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December of the same year, Takauji defeated Nitta&apos;s army at the Battle of Hakone Take no Shita, and advanced his army up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December of the same year, Takauji defeated Nitta&apos;s army at the Battle of Hakone Take no Shita, and advanced his army up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December of the same year, Takauji defeated Nitta&apos;s army at the Battle of Hakone Take no Shita, and advanced his army up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>この間、尊氏は持明院統の光厳天皇へ連絡を取り、京都進軍の正統性を得る工作をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that time, Takauji secretly made contact with Emperor Kogon of Jimyo-in line to justify his entering Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that time, Takauji secretly made contact with Emperor Kogon of the Jimyo-in line to justify his entering Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>inserted “the”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that time, Takauji secretly made contact with Emperor Kogon of the Jimyo-in line to justify his entering Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>建武3年正月、尊氏は入京を果たし、後醍醐天皇は比叡山へ退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following month, Takauji reached Kyoto, while Emperor GO-Daigo fled to Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following month, Takauji reached Kyoto, while Emperor GO-Daigo fled to Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following month, Takauji reached Kyoto, while Emperor GO-Daigo fled to Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>しかしほどなくして奥州から上洛した北畠顕家と楠木正成・新田義貞の攻勢に会った尊氏は同年2月、京都を放棄して赤松円心の進言を容れて九州に下った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shortly thereafter, Takauji was attacked in Kyoto by the armies of Akiie KITABATAKE, Masashige KUSUNOKI and Yoshisada NITTA from Oshu, and he gave up Kyoto, accepting Enshin AKAMATSU&apos;s advice to leave for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shortly thereafter, Takauji was attacked in Kyoto by the armies of Akiie KITABATAKE, Masashige KUSUNOKI and Yoshisada NITTA from Oshu, and he gave up Kyoto, accepting Enshin AKAMATSU&apos;s advice to leave for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shortly thereafter, Takauji was attacked in Kyoto by the armies of Akiie KITABATAKE, Masashige KUSUNOKI and Yoshisada NITTA from Oshu, and he gave up Kyoto, accepting Enshin AKAMATSU&apos;s advice to leave for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="58">
<j>九州への西下途上、長門国赤間関（山口県下関市）で少弐頼尚に迎えられ、筑前国宗像の宗像大社宮司宗像氏範の支援を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On his way down to Kyushu, Yosinao (Yorihisa) SHONI came to meet him at Akamagaseki, Nagato Province (present Shimonoseki City, Yamaguchi Prefecture), and he was supported by Ujinori MUNAKATA, the chief priest of the Munakata Taisha in Munakata, Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt>長門国の対訳からNagato no Kuni削除、筑前国の対訳からChikuzen no Kuni削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his way down to Kyushu, Yoshinao (Yorihisa) SHONI came to meet him at Akamagaseki, Nagato Province (present Shimonoseki City, Yamaguchi Prefecture), and he was supported by Ujinori MUNAKATA, the chief priest of Munakata Taisha Shrine in Munakata, Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt>spelling; added “shrine”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On his way down to Kyushu, Yoshinao (Yorihisa) SHONI came to meet him at Akamagaseki, Nagato Province (present Shimonoseki City, Yamaguchi Prefecture), and he was supported by Ujinori MUNAKATA, the chief priest of Munakata Taisha Shrine in Munakata, Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>宗像大社参拝後の3月初旬、筑前多々良浜（福岡市東区 (福岡市)）での多々良浜の戦いにおいて後醍醐天皇方の菊池武敏を破り勢力を立て直した尊氏は、京に上る途中で光厳上皇の院宣を獲得し、西国の武士を急速に傘下に集めて再び東上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginng of March, after visiting Munakata Taisha, Takauji defeated Taketoshi KIKUCHI (Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s side) at the Battle of Tatarahama (present Fukuoka City), and on his way up to Kyoto, he got Emperor Kogen&apos;s order and immediately gathered western warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginng of March, after visiting Munakata Taisha, Takauji defeated Taketoshi KIKUCHI (Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s side) at the Battle of Tatarahama (present Fukuoka City), and on his way up to Kyoto, he got Emperor Kogen&apos;s order and immediately gathered western warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning of March, after visiting Munakata Taisha, Takauji defeated Taketoshi KIKUCHI (Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s side) at the Battle of Tatarahama (present Fukuoka City), and on his way up to Kyoto, he got Emperor Kogon&apos;s order and immediately gathered western warriors.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>同年4月25日の湊川の戦いで新田義貞・楠木正成の軍を破り、同年6月、京都を再び制圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He smashed the armies of Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI at the Battle of Minatogawa on April 25th of the same year, and seized Kyoto again in June.</e>
<cmt>湊川の戦いの対訳からBattle of Minato Riverを削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He smashed the armies of Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI at the Battle of Minatogawa on April 25th of the same year, and seized Kyoto again in June.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He smashed the armies of Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI at the Battle of Minatogawa on April 25th of the same year, and seized Kyoto again in June.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="61">
<j>京へ入った尊氏は、比叡山に逃れていた後醍醐天皇の顔を立てる形での和議を申し入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji attempted a reconciliation with Emperor Go-Daigo, who had been at Mt. Hiei, for the emperor&apos;s honor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji attempted a reconciliation with Emperor Go-Daigo, who had been at Mt. Hiei, to svae face for the emperor.</e>
<cmt>changed to “save face”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji attempted a reconciliation with Emperor Go-Daigo, who had been at Mt. Hiei, to save face for the emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>和議に応じた後醍醐天皇は同年11月2日に光厳上皇の弟光明天皇に神器を譲り、その直後の11月7日、尊氏は建武式目十七条を定めて政権の基本方針を示し、新たな武家政権の成立を宣言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Daigo, who had accepted Takauji&apos;s offer, transferred the Imperial Regalia of Japan to Emperor Komyo, a younger brother of Grand Emperor Kogon, and right after that, on November 7th, Takauji declared the opening of a new samurai government, setting the Kemmu Shikimoku in order to show the basic policy of his government to his people,</e>
<cmt>三種の神器の対訳からThree Sacred Treasures of Japan削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Daigo, accepting Takauji&apos;s offer, transferred the Imperial Regalia of Japan to Emperor Komyo, a younger brother of Grand Emperor Kogon, and right after that, on November 7th, Takauji declared the opening of a new samurai government, setting the Kemmu Shikimoku in order to show the basic policy of his government to his people.</e>
<cmt>who had accepted-&gt;accepting; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Go-Daigo, accepting Takauji&apos;s offer, transferred the Imperial Regalia of Japan to Emperor Komyo, a younger brother of Grand Emperor Kogon, and right after that, on November 7th, Takauji declared the opening of a new samurai government, setting the Kenmu Shikimoku in order to show the basic policy of his government to his people.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字をヘボン式に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>一方、後醍醐天皇は同年12月に三種の神器を帯して京都を脱出して吉野（奈良県吉野郡吉野町）へ逃れ、光明に譲った神器は偽であると宣言して吉野朝廷を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Emperor Go-Daigo escaped from Kyoto to Yoshino (present Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture) taking the Imperial Regalia of Japan with him in December, and announced that the transferred regalia were fake, so he established Yohino Imperial Court (=Southern Court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Daigo escaped from Kyoto to Yoshino (present Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture) taking the Imperial Regalia of Japan with him in December, and announced that the transferred regalia were fake, so he established Yohino Imperial Court (=Southern Court).</e>
<cmt>deleted “while”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Go-Daigo escaped from Kyoto to Yoshino (present Yoshino-cho, Yoshino-gun, Nara Prefecture) taking the Imperial Regalia of Japan with him in December, and announced that the transferred regalia were fake, so he established Yoshino Imperial Court (=Southern Court).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>観応の擾乱から晩年まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanno Disturbance to before Takauji&apos;s death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanno Disturbance to The Later Years</e>
<cmt>before takauji&apos;s death-&gt;the later years</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanno Disturbance to The Later Years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>延元3年/暦応元年（1338年）、尊氏は光明天皇から征夷大将軍に任じられ（在職 1338年 - 1358年）、ここに、後に室町幕府と呼ばれることになる武家政権が名実ともに成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1338, Takauji was appointed Seii Taishogun (reigned 1338-58) by Emperor Komyo, which meant that an actual samurai government later called Muromachi Shogunate was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1338, Takauji was appointed Seii Taishogun (reigned 1338-58) by Emperor Komyo, which meant that an actual samurai government later called Muromachi Shogunate was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1338, Takauji was appointed Seii Taishogun (reigned 1338-58) by Emperor Komyo, which meant that an actual samurai government later called Muromachi Shogunate was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>翌年、後醍醐天皇が吉野で死去すると、尊氏は慰霊のために天龍寺造営を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, when Emperor Go-Daigo passed away in Yoshino, Takauji began to found Tenryu-ji temple to pray for the soul of the dead emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, when Emperor Go-Daigo passed away in Yoshino, Takauji began to found Tenryu-ji temple to pray for the soul of the dead emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, when Emperor Go-Daigo passed away in Yoshino, Takauji began to found Tenryu-ji temple to pray for the soul of the dead emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>造営費を支弁するため、元 (王朝)へ天龍寺船が派遣されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to raise the funds to build the temple, a trading vessel called Tenryu-ji-bune was set sail for Yuan Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>元の対訳からYuan削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to raise the funds to build the temple, a trading vessel called Tenryu-ji-bune was set sail for Yuan Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to raise the funds to build the temple, a trading vessel called Tenryu-ji-bune was set sail for Yuan Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="67">
<j>新政権において、尊氏は政務を直義に任せ、自らは武士の棟梁として君臨した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the new government, Takauji gave Tadayoshi a post of administrative leader and he himself became the leader of the house vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the new government, Takauji gave Tadayoshi a post as administrative leader and he himself became the leader of the house vassals.</e>
<cmt>of-&gt;as</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the new government, Takauji gave Tadayoshi a post as administrative leader and he himself became the leader of the house vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>佐藤進一は「室町幕府論」（『岩波講座日本歴史7』、岩波書店、1963）において、この状態を、主従制的支配権を握る尊氏と統治権的支配権を所管する直義との両頭政治であり、鎌倉幕府以来、将軍が有していた権力の二元性が具現したものと評価した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin&apos;ichi Sato called such conditions diarchy by Takauji, who held a military power in the lord-and-vassal relationship, and Tadayoshi, who controlled over the judicial functions of the regime, in his essay &apos;Muromachi Bakufu&apos; in &quot;Iawanami Koza Nihon Rekishi vol.7&quot; (Iawanami Publishing, 1963) and explained that the potentiality of the shogun&apos;s dual power which had continued since Kamakura Shogunate, came to appear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin&apos;ichi Sato called such conditions diarchy by Takauji, who held a military power in the lord-and-vassal relationship, and Tadayoshi, who controlled the judicial functions of the regime, in his essay &apos;Muromachi Bakufu&apos; in &quot;Iawanami Koza Nihon Rekishi vol.7&quot; (Iawanami Publishing, 1963) and explained that the potentiality of the shogun&apos;s dual power which had continued since Kamakura Shogunate, came to appear.</e>
<cmt>deleted “over”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin&apos;ichi Sato called such conditions diarchy by Takauji, who held a military power in the lord-and-vassal relationship, and Tadayoshi, who controlled the judicial functions of the regime, in his essay &apos;Muromachi Bakufu&apos; in &quot;Iawanami Koza Nihon Rekishi vol.7&quot; (Iawanami Publishing, 1963) and explained that the potentiality of the shogun&apos;s dual power which had continued since Kamakura Shogunate, came to appear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>二元化した権力は徐々に幕府内部の対立を呼び起こしていき、高師直らの反直義派と直義派の対立として現れていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dual power gradually led to a conflict between anti-Tadayoshi group represented by Ko no Moronao, and Tadayoshi group in the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dual power gradually led to a conflict between anti-Tadayoshi group represented by KO no Moronao, and the Tadayoshi group in the government.</e>
<cmt>capitalized surname; added “the”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dual power gradually led to a conflict between anti-Tadayoshi group represented by KO no Moronao, and the Tadayoshi group in the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>この対立はついに観応の擾乱と呼ばれる内部抗争に発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This conflict finally raised an internal split called Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This conflict finally raised an internal split called the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>added “the”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This conflict finally raised an internal split called the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>尊氏は当初、中立的立場を取っていたが、師直派に擁立されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first Takauji took a neutral stance on it, but he came to side with Moronao&apos;s group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first Takauji took a neutral stance on it, but he came to side with Moronao&apos;s group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first Takauji took a neutral stance on it, but he came to side with Moronao&apos;s group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>正平 (日本)4年/貞和5年（1349年）、襲撃を受けた直義が逃げ込んだ尊氏邸を師直の兵が包囲し、直義の引退を求める事件が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1349, Moronao demanded Tadayoshi&apos;s retirement from politics, surrounding Takauji&apos;s castle in which Tadayoshi had sheltered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1349, Moronao demanded Tadayoshi&apos;s retirement from politics, surrounding Takauji&apos;s castle in which Tadayoshi had sheltered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1349, Moronao demanded Tadayoshi&apos;s retirement from politics, surrounding Takauji&apos;s castle in which Tadayoshi had sheltered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>直義は出家し政務を退くこととなったが、直義の排除には師直・尊氏の間で了解があり、積極的に意図されていたとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi became a priest and lost his power, but it is said that Moronao and Takauji made a prearrangement to exclude Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi became a priest and lost his power, but it is said that Moronao and Takauji made an arrangement to exclude Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>deleted “pre”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi became a priest and lost his power, but it is said that Moronao and Takauji made an arrangement to exclude Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>尊氏は直義に代わって政務を担当させるため嫡男義詮を鎌倉から呼び戻し、代わりに次男足利基氏を下して鎌倉公方とし、東国統治のための鎌倉府を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Takauji called back his heir Yoshiakira from Kamakura to put him in charge of political affairs instead of Tadayoshi, he sent his second son Motouji ASHIKAGA to Kamakura in return and set the Kamakurafu to rule the eastern provinces, appointing Motouji Kamakura kubo.</e>
<cmt>当時の政治の中心は、土地所有をめぐる争いを裁くことでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Takauji called back his heir Yoshiakira from Kamakura to put him in charge of political affairs instead of Tadayoshi, he sent his second son Motouji ASHIKAGA to Kamakura in return and set the Kamakurafu to rule the eastern provinces, appointing Motouji Kamakura kubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Takauji called back his heir Yoshiakira from Kamakura to put him in charge of political affairs instead of Tadayoshi, he sent his second son Motouji ASHIKAGA to Kamakura in return and set the Kamakurafu to rule the eastern provinces, appointing Motouji Kamakura kubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>直義の引退後、尊氏庶子で直義猶子の足利直冬が九州で直義派として勢力を拡大していたため、正平5年/観応元年（1350年）、尊氏は直冬討伐のために中国地方へ遠征した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tadayoshi&apos;s retreat, Takauji&apos;s illegitimate and also Tadayoshi&apos;s adopted son Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA was enlarging his power as a member of the Tadayoshi&apos;s side in Kyushu, so Takauji made an expedition to Chugoku District to kill Tadafuyu in 1350.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tadayoshi&apos;s retreat, Takauji&apos;s illegitimate son - also Tadayoshi&apos;s adopted son - Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA was enlarging his power as a member of the Tadayoshi faction in Kyushu, so Takauji made an expedition to Chugoku District to kill Tadafuyu in 1350.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tadayoshi&apos;s retreat, Takauji&apos;s illegitimate son - also Tadayoshi&apos;s adopted son - Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA was enlarging his power as a member of the Tadayoshi faction in Kyushu, so Takauji made an expedition to Chugoku District to kill Tadafuyu in 1350.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>すると直義は京都を脱出して南朝方に付き、桃井直常、畠山国清ら一部の譜代の武将たちもこれに従った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Tadayoshi escaped from Kyoto and sided with the Southern Court, followed by a few of the devoted military commanders such as Tadatsune MOMONOI and Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>「武将」は「将軍」と区別するためにmilitary commanderと訳しています</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Tadayoshi escaped from Kyoto and sided with the Southern Court, followed by a few of the devoted military commanders such as Tadatsune MOMONOI and Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Tadayoshi escaped from Kyoto and sided with the Southern Court, followed by a few of the devoted military commanders such as Tadatsune MOMONOI and Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>直義の勢力が強大になると、義詮は劣勢となって京を脱出し、尊氏も直義に摂津国打出浜（兵庫県西宮市）で敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tadayoshi&apos;s army grew stronger, Yoshiakira became powerless and fled from Kyoto. Takauji was also defeated by Tadayoshi&apos;s army at Uchidehama in Settsu Province (present Nishinomiya City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>摂津国→Settsu no Kuni</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tadayoshi&apos;s army grew stronger, Yoshiakira became powerless and fled from Kyoto. Takauji was also defeated by Tadayoshi&apos;s army at Uchidehama in Settsu Province (present Nishinomiya City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tadayoshi&apos;s army grew stronger, Yoshiakira became powerless and fled from Kyoto. Takauji was also defeated by Tadayoshi&apos;s army at Uchidehama in Settsu Province (present Nishinomiya City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>尊氏は高兄弟の出家を条件に直義と和睦し、正平6年/観応2年（1351年）に和議が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji sought reconciliation with Tadayoshi on condition that the KO brothers would become priests, and they came to an agreement in 1351.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji sought reconciliation with Tadayoshi on condition that the KO brothers would become priests, and they came to an agreement in 1351.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji sought reconciliation with Tadayoshi on condition that the KO brothers would become priests, and they came to an agreement in 1351.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>高兄弟は護送中に上杉能憲により謀殺されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The KO brothers were assassinated by Yoshinori UESUGI while they were being transferred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The KO brothers were assassinated by Yoshinori UESUGI while they were under escort.</e>
<cmt>being transferred-&gt;under escort</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The KO brothers were assassinated by Yoshinori UESUGI while they were under escort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="80">
<j>直義は義詮の補佐として政務に復帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi became Yoshiakira&apos;s assistant and got involved in political affairs again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi became Yoshiakira&apos;s assistant and got involved in political affairs again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi became Yoshiakira&apos;s assistant and got involved in political affairs again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>尊氏・義詮は佐々木道誉や赤松則祐の謀反を名目として近江・播磨へ出陣し、実際には直義・直冬追討を企てて南朝方と和睦交渉を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji and Yoshiakira marched to Harima Province on the ostensible purpose to put down the revolt plotted by Doyo SASAKI and Sokuyu (Norisuke) AKAMATSU, but in reality they attempted a reconciliation with the Southern Court, conspiring to kill Tadayoshi and Tadafuyu.</e>
<cmt>播磨の対訳からHarima削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji and Yoshiakira marched to Harima Province on the ostensible purpose to put down the revolt plotted by Doyo SASAKI and Sokuyu (Norisuke) AKAMATSU, but in reality they attempted a reconciliation with the Southern Court, conspiring to kill Tadayoshi and Tadafuyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji and Yoshiakira marched to Harima Province on the ostensible purpose to put down the revolt plotted by Doyo SASAKI and Sokuyu (Norisuke) AKAMATSU, but in reality they attempted a reconciliation with the Southern Court, conspiring to kill Tadayoshi and Tadafuyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>この動きに対して直義は北陸方面へ脱出して鎌倉へ逃げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sensing this conspiracy, Tadayoshi fled to the northern area and reached Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sensing this conspiracy, Tadayoshi fled to the northern area and reached Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sensing this conspiracy, Tadayoshi fled to the northern area and reached Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>尊氏と南朝の和睦は同年10月に成立し、これを正平一統という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October of the same year, Takauji and the Southern Court reconciled, which was called Shohei-itto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October of the same year, Takauji and the Southern Court reconciled, an event that was called Shohei-itto.</e>
<cmt>which-&gt;an event that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October of the same year, Takauji and the Southern Court reconciled, an event that was called Shohei-itto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>平行して尊氏は直義を追って東海道を進み、駿河薩捶山（静岡県静岡市清水区）、相模早川尻（神奈川県小田原市）などでの戦闘で撃ち破り、直義を捕らえて鎌倉に幽閉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Takauji chased Tadayoshi along the Tokaido, and defeated him at the battles of Mt. Satsutamayama in Suruga Province (Present Shimizu Ward, Shimizu City, Shizuoka Prefecture) and Hayakawajiri in Sagami Province (present Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture). Takauji captured Tadayoshi and confined him in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>駿河の対訳からSuruga削除、相模の対訳からSagami削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Takauji chased Tadayoshi along the Tokaido, and defeated him at the battles of Mt. Satsutamayama in Suruga Province (present-day Shimizu Ward, Shimizu City, Shizuoka Prefecture) and Hayakawajiri in Sagami Province (present-day Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture). Takauji captured Tadayoshi and confined him in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>capitalization; present-&gt;present-day</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Takauji chased Tadayoshi along the Tokaido, and defeated him at the battles of Mt. Satsutamayama in Suruga Province (present-day Shimizu Ward, Shimizu City, Shizuoka Prefecture) and Hayakawajiri in Sagami Province (present-day Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture). Takauji captured Tadayoshi and confined him in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>直義は、正平7年/観応3年（1352年）2月に急死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi died suddenly in February, 1352.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi died suddenly in February, 1352.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi died suddenly in February, 1352.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>『太平記』は尊氏による毒殺の疑いを記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Taiheiki&quot; says that Tadayoshi might have been poisoned by Takauji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Taiheiki&quot; says that Tadayoshi might have been poisoned by Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Taiheiki&quot; says that Tadayoshi might have been poisoned by Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="87">
<j>その直後に宗良親王、新田義興・新田義宗、北条時行などの南朝方から襲撃された尊氏は武蔵国へ退却するが、すぐさま反撃し関東の南朝勢力を制圧すると、京都へ戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after Tadayoshi&apos;s death, being attacked by the Southern Court forces represented by Prince Muneyoshi, Yoshioki NITTA, Yoshimune NITTA and Tokiyuki HOJO, Takauji retreated to Musashi Province, but soon returned to Kyoto defeating the Southern forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after Tadayoshi&apos;s death, being attacked by the Southern Court forces represented by Prince Muneyoshi, Yoshioki NITTA, Yoshimune NITTA and Tokiyuki HOJO, Takauji retreated to Musashi Province, but soon returned to Kyoto to defeat the Southern forces.</e>
<cmt>defeating-&gt;to defeat</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after Tadayoshi&apos;s death, being attacked by the Southern Court forces represented by Prince Muneyoshi, Yoshioki NITTA, Yoshimune NITTA and Tokiyuki HOJO, Takauji retreated to Musashi Province, but soon returned to Kyoto to defeat the Southern forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>その後足利直冬が京都へ侵攻するが、結局直冬は九州へ去る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA intruded in Kyoto, but eventually he left for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA intruded in Kyoto, but eventually he left for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA intruded in Kyoto, but eventually he left for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>正平9年/文和3年（1354年）にも京都を南朝に一時奪われるが、翌年奪還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1354, Kyoto was retaken by the Southern Court temporarily, but retaken by Takauji the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1354, Kyoto was retaken by the Southern Court temporarily, but taken back by Takauji the following year.</e>
<cmt>retaken-&gt;taken back (to avoid repetition)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1354, Kyoto was retaken by the Southern Court temporarily, but taken back by Takauji the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>尊氏は自ら直冬討伐を企てるが、正平13年/延文3年4月30日（1358年）、背中に出来た癰（よう、腫物）のため、京都二条万里小路邸にて死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He plotted to kill Tadafuyu, but died of a tumor on his back at the palace of Made&apos;nokoji in Nijo, Kyoto, on April 30th, 1358 (Shohei 13/Enbun 3).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He plotted to kill Tadafuyu, but died of a tumor on his back at the palace of Made&apos;nokoji in Nijo, Kyoto, on April 30th, 1358.</e>
<cmt>deleted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He plotted to kill Tadafuyu, but died of a tumor on his back at the palace of Made&apos;nokoji in Nijo, Kyoto, on April 30th, 1358.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>享年54。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death: 54.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at death: 54.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age at death: 54.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="92">
<j>『梅松論』などによると、尊氏は後醍醐に背いて朝敵となったことを悔やんで一時は出家を宣言したり、合戦で苦戦した際には切腹すると言い出すなどの記述があり、佐藤進一は尊氏を躁鬱病ではないかと推測している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Baishoron&quot;, Takauji regretted having turned against Emperor Go-Daigo, and he was telling temporarily that he would become a priest. He also announced that he would kill himself when he was in hard-fought battles, so Shin&apos;ichi SATO took these descriptions into consideration, and presumed that Takauji might have been a manic depressive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Baishoron&quot;, Takauji regretted having turned against Emperor Go-Daigo, and he for a while he was talking about becoming a priest. In the heat of battle he also talked about killing himself, so Shin&apos;ichi SATO took these descriptions into consideration, and presumed that Takauji might have been a manic depressive.</e>
<cmt>tell/announce-&gt;talk about</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Baishoron,&quot; Takauji regretted having turned against Emperor Go-Daigo, and he for a while he was talking about becoming a priest. In the heat of battle he also talked about killing himself, so Shin&apos;ichi SATO took these descriptions into consideration, and presumed that Takauji might have been a manic depressive.</e>
<cmt>引用符の内側にカンマを移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>個人的に親交のあった夢窓疎石は、尊氏の徳を評価した文章を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji&apos;s close friend Muso Soseki described Takauji as a man of virtue in his writing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji&apos;s close friend Muso Soseki described Takauji as a man of virtue in his writing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji&apos;s close friend Soseki MUSO described Takauji as a man of virtue in his writing.</e>
<cmt>議論の末、僧の名前も通常通り逆順とすることとなったので、夢窓疎石の語順を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>尊氏は傘下の武将たちへの恩賞を惜しむことがなく、そのことが苦境に立たされても常に武将たちの支持が得られた理由だとする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji was willing to allot lands to his military commanders, which is considered one of the reasons why he had constantly been supported by them when he was in difficult situations.</e>
<cmt>「武将」は「将軍」と区別するためにmilitary commanderと訳しています</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji was willing to allot lands to his military commanders, which is considered one of the reasons why he was always supported by them when he was in difficult situations.</e>
<cmt>had constantly been-&gt;was always</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji was willing to allot lands to his military commanders, which is considered one of the reasons why he was always supported by them when he was in difficult situations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>後世の評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluations made by later generations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluations of Later Generations</e>
<cmt>made by-&gt;of; capitalized words in section heading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluations of Later Generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>尊氏を逆賊とする評価は、江戸時代に徳川光圀が創始した水戸学に始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the Mitogaku originated by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA that started to consider Takauji as a traitor in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the Mitogaku originated by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA that started to consider Takauji as a traitor in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the Mitogaku originated by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA that started to consider Takauji as a traitor in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>水戸学は朱子学名分論の影響を強く受けており、皇統の正統性を重視していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitogaku was strongly influenced by Shushigaku Meibunron, and emphasized the validity of the Imperial line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitogaku was strongly influenced by Shushigaku Meibunron, and emphasized the validity of the Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitogaku was strongly influenced by Shushigaku Meibunron, and emphasized the validity of the Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>そのため、正統な天皇（後醍醐天皇）を放逐した尊氏は逆賊として否定的に描かれることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, Takauji, who exiled the authentic emperor (Go-Daigo), was described in a negative way as a traitor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, Takauji, who exiled the authentic emperor (Go-Daigo), was described in a negative way as a traitor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, Takauji, who exiled the authentic emperor (Go-Daigo), was described in a negative way as a traitor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>水戸学に発する尊氏観はその後も継承され、尊王思想が高まった幕末期には尊皇攘夷論者によって等持院の尊氏・義詮・義満3代の木像が梟首される事件も発生している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitogaku&apos;s view of Takauji was inherited by the later generations, and in the late Tokugawa period when Sonno-Joi (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarian) culminated, heads of the wooden statues of Takauji, Yoshiakira and Yoshimitsu (ASHIKAGA) in Toji-in were hanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitogaku&apos;s view of Takauji was inherited by the later generations, and in the late Tokugawa period when Sonno-Joi (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarian) culminated, the heads of wooden statues of Takauji, Yoshiakira and Yoshimitsu (ASHIKAGA) in Toji-in were pilloried.</e>
<cmt>use of &quot;the&quot;; hanged-&gt;pilloried</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitogaku&apos;s view of Takauji was inherited by the later generations, and in the late Tokugawa period when Sonno-Joi (Revere the Emperor, Expel the Barbarian) culminated, the heads of wooden statues of Takauji, Yoshiakira and Yoshimitsu (ASHIKAGA) in Toji-in were pilloried.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="99">
<j>明治時代になると、明治政府の立場から天皇を中心とする国民国家を建設するため、国家主義的な歴史観が構築されていったが、それは大政奉還・王政復古を正当化する歴史観であり、そのため大化の改新・建武の中興・明治維新が最も重要な改革に位置づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji period, the Meiji government sought for establishing the nation-state which set the emperor in the center of the nation. This produced the nationalistic view of history, which justified Taisei Hokan and Osei Fukko, so Taika Reforms, Kemmu no Chuko (=Kemmu restoration) and Meiji Restoration were ranked as the most important restoration.</e>
<cmt>大政奉還の対訳からReturn of Political Rule of the Emperor削除、王政復古の対訳からRestoration of Imperial Rule削除、明治維新の対訳からMeiji Ishin削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji period, the Meiji government sought to establish a nation-state which set the emperor in the center of the nation. This produced a nationalistic view of history, which justified Taisei Hokan and Osei Fukko, and so the Taika Reforms, Kemmu no Chuko (=Kemmu restoration) and Meiji Restoration were ranked as the most important reforms.</e>
<cmt>use of aticles; for establishing-&gt;to establish; changed one &quot;restoration&quot; to &quot;reform&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji period, the Meiji government sought to establish a nation-state which set the emperor in the center of the nation. This produced a nationalistic view of history, which justified Taisei Hokan and Osei Fukko, and so the Taika Reforms, Kenmu no Chuko (=Kenmu restoration) and Meiji Restoration were ranked as the most important reforms.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字をヘボン式に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>明治中期までは近代的歴史学による実証的研究から後醍醐天皇・南朝の正統性はそれほど強調されていなかったが、明治40年代に入り、南北朝正閏論を経て、後醍醐天皇・南朝の正統性が強く主張されていき、それに伴って尊氏に対する否定的な評価が確定することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until mid Meiji period, source-based study of modern historiography did not emphasize the validity of Emperor Go-Daigo (the Southern Court), but at around Meiji 40 when the Nambokucho Seijunron arose, the validity of Emperor Go-Daigo (the Southern Court) came to be stressed, creating a negative evaluation of Takauji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until mid Meiji period, source-based study of modern history did not emphasize the validity of Emperor Go-Daigo (the Southern Court), but at around 1907 40 when the Nambokucho Seijunron arose, the validity of Emperor Go-Daigo came to be stressed, creating a negative evaluation of Takauji.</e>
<cmt>historiography-&gt;history; deleted repetitive parenthetical notation; deleted leading space; converted Japanese date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until mid Meiji period, source-based study of modern history did not emphasize the validity of Emperor Go-Daigo (the Southern Court), but at around 1907 40 when the Nanbokucho Seijunron arose, the validity of Emperor Go-Daigo came to be stressed, creating a negative evaluation of Takauji.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字をヘボン式に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>戦前の国定教科書には「天皇に弓を引いた逆臣」と書かれており、斎藤実内閣の中島久万吉商工大臣が尊氏を礼賛した文章を書いたために辞任する事件も起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to an authorized textbook written before WWII, Takauji was &quot;a traitor who released an arrow against the Emperor&quot;, and Kumakichi NAKAJIMA, a member of the Makoto SAITO Cabinet, was forced to retire because he had praised Takauji in his writing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to an authorized textbook written before WWII, Takauji was &quot;a traitor who released an arrow against the Emperor&quot;, and Kumakichi NAKAJIMA, a member of the Makoto SAITO Cabinet, was forced to retire because he had praised Takauji in his writing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to an authorized textbook written before WWII, Takauji was &quot;a traitor who released an arrow against the Emperor&quot;, and Kumakichi NAKAJIMA, a member of the Makoto SAITO Cabinet, was forced to retire because he had praised Takauji in his writing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="102">
<j>戦後になると、国家主義的な歴史観が大きく後退し実証主義的な歴史研究が進展したことに伴い、尊氏の再評価が進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After WWII, the nationalistic view of history became obsolete, and the source-based study of history made progress, revaluating Takauji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After WWII, the nationalistic view of history became obsolete, and the source-based study of history made progress on reevaluating Takauji.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;on&quot;; revaluating-&gt;reevaluating</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After WWII, the nationalistic view of history became obsolete, and the source-based study of history made progress on reevaluating Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>佐藤進一による主従制的支配者としての尊氏の評価はその一例であり、これは武家政権に関する研究が大きく進展する契機となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sato&apos;s interpretation of Takauji as a ruler in the lord-and-vassal relationship was one example, which afforded an opportunity to develop a study of the samurai government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sato&apos;s interpretation of Takauji as a ruler in the lord-and-vassal relationship was one example, which afforded an opportunity to develop a study of the samurai government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sato&apos;s interpretation of Takauji as a ruler in the lord-and-vassal relationship was one example, which afforded an opportunity to develop a study of the samurai government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>現代の歴史研究において、尊氏を逆賊とする見解は存在せず、むしろ尊氏が逆賊となるまでの経過が歴史研究の一テーマになることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In today&apos;s history study, nobody interprets Takauji as a traitor any more, and the process of Takauji&apos;s becoming a traitor sometimes can be a theme of historical study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In today&apos;s historical study, nobody interprets Takauji as a traitor any more, and the process of Takauji&apos;s becoming a traitor sometimes can be a theme of historical study.</e>
<cmt>history-&gt;historical</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In today&apos;s historical study, nobody interprets Takauji as a traitor any more, and the process of Takauji&apos;s becoming a traitor sometimes can be a theme of historical study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>文化面においても、吉川英治が昭和30年代に書いた『私本太平記』は尊氏を主人公としているが読者に広く受け入れられており、尊氏への評価が戦前のものから大きく変化していることがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shihon Taiheiki&quot; written by Eiji YOSHIKAWA in Showa 30&apos;s had set Takauji as a main character, and accepted by many readers, which suggested that not only the political but also the cultural view of Takauji had shifted very much compared with that before WWII.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shihon Taiheiki&quot; written by Eiji YOSHIKAWA in the late 1950s had Takauji as a main character, and was accepted by many readers, which suggested that not only the political but also the cultural view of Takauji had shifted very much compared with that before WWII.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Showa 30s&quot; to &quot;late 1950s&quot;; deleted &quot;set&quot;; added &quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shihon Taiheiki&quot; written by Eiji YOSHIKAWA in the late 1950s had Takauji as a main character, and was accepted by many readers, which suggested that not only the political but also the cultural view of Takauji had shifted very much compared with that before WWII.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>尊氏の肖像画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A portrait of Takauji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Portrait of Takauji</e>
<cmt>capitalized words in section heading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Portrait of Takauji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>京都国立博物館所蔵の『騎馬武者像』は尊氏の肖像として一般に知られていたが、2代将軍足利義詮の花押が像上部に据えられていることや、騎馬武者の馬具に描かれている輪違の紋が足利氏の家紋ではないこと（高氏の家紋が輪違）などの理由から、足利家執事高師直あるいはその子の高師詮の肖像とする説が有力視されており、現在では尊氏説は否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kibamusha zo (means a portrait of warrior on the horse back)&quot; preserved in the Kyoto National Museum was generally known as a portrait of Takauji, but now considered to be a portrait of Ko no Moronao, the regent of the Ashikaga clan, or that of Ko no Moroakira, son of Moronao. It&apos;s because there&apos;s a decorative signature of the 2nd shogun Yoshiakira on the upper part of the body, and the family crest of the two rings described on the warrior&apos;s harness was not the Ashikaga family&apos;s, but the KO family&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kibamusha zo&quot; (a portrait of warrior on the horse back), preserved in the Kyoto National Museum, was generally known as a portrait of Takauji, but is now considered to be a portrait of KO no Moronao, the regent of the Ashikaga clan, or that of KO no Moroakira, son of Moronao. It&apos;s because there&apos;s a decorative signature of the 2nd shogun Yoshiakira on the upper part of the body, and the family crest of the two rings described on the warrior&apos;s harness was not the Ashikaga family&apos;s, but the KO family&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>moved quotation mark; deleted &quot;means&quot;; added commas; capitalized &quot;KO&quot;; deleted extra space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kibamusha zo&quot; (a portrait of warrior on the horse back), preserved in the Kyoto National Museum, was generally known as a portrait of Takauji, but is now considered to be a portrait of KO no Moronao, the regent of the Ashikaga clan, or that of KO no Moroakira, son of Moronao. It&apos;s because there&apos;s a decorative signature of the 2nd shogun Yoshiakira on the upper part of the body, and the family crest of the two rings described on the warrior&apos;s harness was not the Ashikaga family&apos;s, but the KO family&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="107">
<j>鎌倉時代に藤原隆信が描いたとされる国宝神護寺三像のうち伝平重盛像は、平重盛を描いたものと考えられてきたが、1990年代半ばに美術史家の米倉迪夫や黒田日出男らによって尊氏像であるとの説が提示され、広い支持を集めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Portrait of Taira no Shigemori, one of the Jingo-ji san zo, painted by FUJIWARA no Takanobu in Kamakura period, had been considered a portrait of Shigemori TAIRA, but Michio YONEKURA and Hideo KURODA claimed that it is a portrait of Takauji, and now this interpretation is widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>神護寺三像の対訳からThree portrait paintings in Jingo-ji削除、平重盛像の対訳からTAIRA no Shigemori zo/Portrait painting of TAIRA no Shigemori削除</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Portrait of Taira no Shigemori, one of the Jingo-ji san zo, painted by FUJIWARA no Takanobu in Kamakura period, had been considered a portrait of Shigemori TAIRA, but Michio YONEKURA and Hideo KURODA claimed that it is a portrait of Takauji, and now this interpretation is widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Portrait of Taira no Shigemori, one of the Jingo-ji san zo, painted by FUJIWARA no Takanobu in Kamakura period, had been considered a portrait of Shigemori TAIRA, but Michio YONEKURA and Hideo KURODA claimed that it is a portrait of Takauji, and now this interpretation is widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>等持院所蔵の尊氏木像との比較や、冠をとめる笄（こうがい）が室町初期に流行した形状であることなどが根拠として挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their opinion bases on the comparison of the portrait with the wooden statue of Takauji preserved in Toji-in, and the popular shape of the hairpin called Kogai to hold the hat in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their opinion is based on the comparison of the portrait with the wooden statue of Takauji preserved in Toji-in, and the popular shape of the hatpin, called Kogai, used in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>bases-&gt;is based; hairpin-&gt;hat pin; shorted for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their opinion is based on the comparison of the portrait with the wooden statue of Takauji preserved in Toji-in, and the popular shape of the hatpin, called Kogai, used in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>広島県尾道市の浄土寺にも尊氏を描いたとされる肖像画が所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There&apos;s another portrait of Takauji preserved in Jodo-ji Temple in Onomichi City, Hiroshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There&apos;s another portrait of Takauji preserved in Jodo-ji Temple in Onomichi City, Hiroshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There&apos;s another portrait of Takauji preserved in Jodo-ji Temple in Onomichi City, Hiroshima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="110">
<j>その他、江戸時代に描かれた錦絵に歌川芳虎の「太平記合戦図」（尊氏、兵庫・福海寺に避難する図）、橋本周延の「足利尊氏兵庫合戦図」（尊氏、兵庫・福海寺に避難する図）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to that, there are some ukiyoe pictures in which Takauji was described: &quot;Taiheiki Kassenzu&quot; made by Yoshitora UTAGAWA, &quot;Ashikaga Takauji Hyogo Kassenzu&quot; made by Chikanobu HASHIMOTO. Both paintings are deal with Takauji sheltering in the Jodo-ji Temple in Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to that, there are some ukiyoe pictures of Takauji: &quot;Taiheiki Kassenzu&quot;, by Yoshitora UTAGAWA; and &quot;Ashikaga Takauji Hyogo Kassenzu&quot;, by Chikanobu HASHIMOTO. Both paintings deal with Takauji sheltering in the Jodo-ji Temple in Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation; deleted &quot;made&quot;; deleted &quot;are&quot;; simplified long phrase to &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to that, there are some ukiyoe pictures of Takauji: &quot;Taiheiki Kassenzu,&quot; by Yoshitora UTAGAWA; and &quot;Ashikaga Takauji Hyogo Kassenzu,&quot; by Chikanobu HASHIMOTO. Both paintings deal with Takauji sheltering in the Jodo-ji Temple in Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>引用符の内側にカンマを移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>また、現代になって作られた銅像が足利市鑁阿寺参道と京都府綾部市安国寺町に設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the bronze statues of Takauji were made lately; one is placed on the approach to the Bunna-ji Temple in Ashikaga City, and the other is in Ankokuji Town, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also some bronze statues of Takauji were made recently; one is placed on the approach to the Bunna-ji Temple in Ashikaga City, and the other is in Ankokuji Town, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>the-&gt;some; lately-&gt;recently</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also some bronze statues of Takauji were made recently; one is placed on the approach to the Bunna-ji Temple in Ashikaga City, and the other is in Ankokuji Town, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="112">
<j>父：足利貞氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Father: Sadauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Father: Sadauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Father: Sadauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>母：上杉清子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mother: Kiyoko UESUGI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mother: Kiyoko UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mother: Kiyoko UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>弟：足利直義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">younger brother: Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Younger Brother: Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Younger Brother: Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>足利尊氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>正室：赤橋登子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official wife: Toko AKAHASHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wife: Toko AKAHASHI</e>
<cmt>capitalization; &quot;official&quot; seems unnecessary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wife: Toko AKAHASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>子：足利義詮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>子：娘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: a daughter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: a daughter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: a daughter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>子：聖王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Seio</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Seio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Seio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>子：足利基氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Motouji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Motouji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Motouji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>子：頼子（崇光天皇皇后）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Yoriko (Raishi), or an empress of Emperor Suko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Yoriko (Raishi), empress of Emperor Suko</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;or an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Yoriko (Raishi), empress of Emperor Suko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>子：了清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Ryosei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Ryosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Ryosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>子：娘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: a daughter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: a daughter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: a daughter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>側室：加古基氏（法名：雲光院覚遍、足利一族）の女（『尊卑分脈』・『系図纂要』より）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concubine: a daughter of Motouji KAKO (Buddhist name: Unkoin Kakkuhen, a member of the Ashikaga clan) (according to &quot;Sompi Bummyaku&quot; and &quot;Keizu San&apos;yo)&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concubine: a daughter of Motouji KAKO (Buddhist name: Unkoin Kakkuhen, a member of the Ashikaga clan) (according to &quot;Sompi Bummyaku&quot; and &quot;Keizu San&apos;yo&quot;)</e>
<cmt>deleted extra parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concubine: a daughter of Motouji KAKO (Buddhist name: Unkoin Kakuhen, a member of the Ashikaga clan) (according to &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; and &quot;Keizu San&apos;yo&quot;)</e>
<cmt>スペル修正、ヘボン式に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>子：足利竹若丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Takewakamaru ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Takewakamaru ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Takewakamaru ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>側室（越前局?）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concubine: (Echizen no tsubone?)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concubine: (Echizen no tsubone?)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concubine: (Echizen no tsubone?)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>子：足利直冬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>側室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concubine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concubine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concubine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>子：英仲法俊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child: Eichu Hoshun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child: Eichu Hoshun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child: Eichu Hoshun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>史料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical Materials</e>
<cmt>capitalized word in section heading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>太平記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiheiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiheiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiheiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>梅松論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baishoron</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baishoron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baishoron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>小説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Novels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="132">
<j>太平記（森村誠一）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiheiki written by Seiichi MORIMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiheiki written by Seiichi MORIMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiheiki written by Seiichi MORIMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>私本太平記（吉川英治）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihon Taiheiki written by Eiji YOSHIKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shihon Taiheiki written by Eiji YOSHIKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shihon Taiheiki written by Eiji YOSHIKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>新・太平記（山岡荘八）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin Taiheiki written by Sohachi YAMAOKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin Taiheiki written by Sohachi YAMAOKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin Taiheiki written by Sohachi YAMAOKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>足利尊氏（童門冬二）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashikaga Takauji written by Fuyuji DOMON</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashikaga Takauji written by Fuyuji DOMON</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashikaga Takauji written by Fuyuji DOMON</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>足利尊氏（村上元三）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashikaga Takauji written by Genzo MURAKAMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashikaga Takauji written by Genzo MURAKAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashikaga Takauji written by Genzo MURAKAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>風の群像（杉本苑子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaze no Gunzo written by Sonoko SUGIMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaze no Gunzo written by Sonoko SUGIMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaze no Gunzo written by Sonoko SUGIMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>TVドラマ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TV dramas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TV dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TV dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="138">
<j>太平記 (NHK大河ドラマ)（1991年日本放送協会大河ドラマ、俳優：雨笠利幸/真田広之、主人公）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiheiki (NHK Taiga drama) (Cast: Toshiyuki AMAGASA/ Hiroyuki SANADA, 1991)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiheiki (NHK Taiga drama) (Cast: Toshiyuki AMAGASA/ Hiroyuki SANADA, 1991)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiheiki (NHK Taiga drama) (Cast: Toshiyuki AMAGASA/ Hiroyuki SANADA, 1991)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>北条時宗 (NHK大河ドラマ)（2001年NHK大河ドラマ、俳優：三觜要介）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hojo Tokimune (NHK Taiga drama) (Cast: Yosuke MITSUHASHI, 2001)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hojo Tokimune (NHK Taiga drama) (Cast: Yosuke MITSUHASHI, 2001)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hojo Tokimune (NHK Taiga drama) (Cast: Yosuke MITSUHASHI, 2001)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), ＤＦ．Ｋｉｎｇ(id:48817), March(id:9468), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), OKBot(id:143139), ＋－(id:17104), るがこむ(id:181), でここ(id:9565), Natunohi(id:6550), らりた(id:1327), Dr jimmy(id:111486), 代言人(id:33675), Whiteapple(id:1178), 俊(id:14924), 秀の介(id:490), Knua(id:66861), 5816K(id:102574), Shimoxx(id:9332), FlaBot(id:30804), Rabbit(id:12621), Tosiho(id:73924), ロリ(id:613), Oxhop(id:2551), 浩(id:70121), Carbuncle(id:346), Enthousiasme(id:42600), たね(id:10372), 砂場(id:27896), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Himazin(id:22034), グラタン(id:94405), Escarbot(id:59151), Kagetudo(id:163875), MenasimBot(id:188172), Rusk(id:9895), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 海衛士(id:19229), 伏儀(id:142093), Junger(id:10282), Suisui(id:69), Broad-Sky(id:68334), Tangobot(id:47812), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Yu-ki-na(id:115957), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 味っ子(id:17086), Robert De Smith(id:28533), Johncapistrano(id:969), Sunen(id:10700), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Hage＠＠(id:80202), 怪蘇(id:45514), 葉村史陽(id:15735), Piasu9(id:134995), Tak1701d(id:109054), LERK(id:4460), Kozawa(id:672), Lonicera(id:20638), Izayohi(id:13095), G(id:21), やりたこ(id:113528), Lombroso(id:20212), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Kamitani(id:30757), Yonoemon(id:55450), PrimeN(id:102297), さよなら大好きな人(id:31545), Falcosapiens(id:221), Louperibot(id:128971), きまま(id:183217), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>