<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源義家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshiie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 義家（みなもと の よしいえ）は、平安時代後期の武将で、河内源氏の源頼信の孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiie was the busho (Japanese military commander) in the Heian Period and the grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorinobu of the Kawachi Genji (the Kawachi branch of the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshiie was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Heian Period and the grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorinobu of the Kawachi Genji (the Kawachi branch of the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshiie was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Heian period and the grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorinobu of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。ハイフン補足、説明訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>八幡太郎義家（はちまんたろうよしいえ）という呼び名でも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known by his alias, Hachiman-taro-yoshiie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known by his alias, Hachiman-taro-yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known by his alias, Hachimantaro Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、スペース補足。大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後に武家政権鎌倉幕府を開いた源頼朝、そして室町幕府の足利尊氏の祖先に当たることから後世に英雄視され、様々な逸話が生み出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was the ancestor of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who established the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) headed by bushi (warrior) and Takauji ASHIKAGA who founded the Muromachi bakufu, he was often portrayed as a hero by later generations and many anecdotes were made about him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the ancestor of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who established the Kamakura bakufu (military govenment) and Takauji ASHIKAGA who founded the Muromachi bakufu, he was often portrayed as a hero by later generations and there are many anecdotes about him.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Since he was&quot;→&quot;As&quot;&quot;Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun&quot;→&quot;military government&quot;― less wordy. Maybe Shogunate is OK for &quot;bakufu&quot;&quot;headed by bushi (warrior)&quot; erased&quot;many anecdotes were made&quot;→&quot;there are many anecdotes&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the ancestor of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who established the Kamakura bakufu (military government) and Takauji ASHIKAGA who founded the Muromachi bakufu, he was often portrayed as a hero by later generations and there are many anecdotes about him.</e>
<cmt>governmentスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>比叡山等の強訴の頻発に際し、その鎮圧や白河天皇の行幸の護衛に活躍するが、陸奥国守となったとき、清原氏の内紛に介入して後三年の役を起こし、朝廷に事後承認を求めるが、朝廷は「私戦」として官符を下さなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He actively participated as the guard for the Emperor Shirakawa during his imperial visits, suppressed rebelling Mount Hiei monks, but when he became Mutsu-kokushu (the Lord of Mutsu province), he interfered in the internal conflict of the Kiyohara clan and triggered the Later Three Years&apos; War and sought the official post-war consent from the imperial court but was denied as &quot;a private feud.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as a guard for the Emperor Shirakawa during his imperial visits and suppressed rebelling Mount Hiei monks, but after becoming Mutsu-kokushu (the Lord of Mutsu Province), he interfered in the internal conflict of the Kiyohara clan, triggering the Later Three Years&apos; War which, although he sought official post-war consent, was declared &quot;a private feud&quot; by the court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;actively participated&quot;→&quot;served&quot;&quot;when he became&quot;→&quot;after becoming&quot;&quot;and triggered&quot;→&quot;, triggering&quot;&quot;and sought the&quot;→&quot;although he sought&quot;&quot;denied as&quot;→&quot;declared&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as a guard for the Emperor Shirakawa during his imperial visits and suppressed rebelling Mount Hiei monks, but after becoming Mutsu no kuni no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province), he interfered in the internal conflict of the Kiyohara clan, triggering the Later Three Years&apos; War which, although he sought official post-war consent, was declared &apos;a private feud&apos; by the court.</e>
<cmt>用語集より、陸奥国守→Mutsu no kuni no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province)に統一しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>その後約10年間は閉塞状態であったが、白河天皇の意向で昇殿を許されたが、中御門右大臣・藤原宗忠はその日記『中右記』承徳2年10月23日条に「義家朝臣は天下第一武勇の士なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a blockade condition for the later ten years, but he was allowed to visit the imperial palace by the consent from the Emperor Shirakawa, but U-daijin (the chief of an Imperial Japanese Council of State) and Nakamikado FUJIWARA no Minetada wrote in his diary, &quot;Chuyu-ki&quot; (dated October 23, 1099), &apos;Minamoto Chosin (person who served the imperial court) is the only and best bushi of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>義家朝臣は天下第一武勇の士なり。→ &apos;Minamoto Chosin (person who served the imperial court) is the only and best bushi of the emperor. [http://www.geocities.jp/ktmchi/rekisi/cys_51.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the next ten years he was under house arrest, but he was allowed to visit the imperial palace with Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s consent, although Udaijin (Minister of the Right) NAKIMIKADO, whose real name was FUJIWARA no Munetada, wrote in his diary, &quot;Chuyu-ki&quot; (dated October 23, 1099), &apos;Minamoto Chosin (person who served the imperial court) is the Emperor&apos;s best and bravest bushi.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m not sure if &apos;house arrest&apos; is the right term in this situation but it seems better than the original translation.&quot;Minetada&quot;→&quot;Munetada&quot;I think &apos;Nakamikado&apos; was another name he used, not a title&quot;only and best&quot;→&quot;best and bravest&quot;Capitalized &apos;e&apos; of &quot;emperor&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the next ten years he was under house arrest, but he was allowed to visit the imperial palace with Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s consent, although Udaijin (Minister of the Right) Nakamikado, also as known as FUJIWARA no Munetada, wrote in his diary, &quot;Chuyu-ki&quot; (dated October 23, 1099), &apos;Minamoto no Asomi (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) is the Emperor&apos;s best and bravest bushi.</e>
<cmt>Nakamikado小文字にしました。whose real name wasをalso as known asとしました。朝臣→Asomi (second highest of the eight hereditary titles)、称号です。訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>昇殿をゆるさるるに、世人、甘心せざるの気あるか」と書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are indications that the public does not approve of his visit to the imperial palace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>昇殿をゆるさるるに、世人、甘心せざるの気あるか→However, there are indications that the public does not approve of his visit to the imperial palace.&apos;[http://www.geocities.jp/ktmchi/rekisi/cys_51.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are indications that the public does not approve of his visit to the imperial palace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are indications that the public does not approve of his visit to the Imperial Palace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Imperial Palace大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>その活動時期は摂関政治から院政に移り変わる頃であり、政治経済はもとより社会秩序においても大きな転換の時代にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period when he was active was when the political system was shifting from Sekkan seiji (regency government) to the In-sei (government by a retired emperor) and a giant change was observed within the political economy and stability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active at a time when the political system was shifting from a regency government (Sekkan seiji) to government by a retired emperor (In-sei), resulting in huge political, economic and social changes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The period when he was active was&quot;→&quot;He was active at a time&quot;Swapped Japanese and Englsh definitions around&quot;giant change was observed within the political economy and stability&quot;→&quot;resulting in huge political, economic and social changes&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active at a time when the political system was shifting from a regency government (Sekkan seiji) to government by a retired emperor (In-sei), resulting in huge political, economic and social changes.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このため歴史学者からは、義家は新興武士勢力の象徴ともみなされ、後三年の役の朝廷の扱いも「白河院の陰謀」「摂関家の陰謀」など様々な憶測がされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, historians assumed that Yoshiie represented the new rising bushi class, and the treatment of imperial court on the Later Three Years&apos; War was considered to be the &apos;conspiracy of Shirakawa-in (retired Emperor Shirakawa)&apos; or &apos;the conspiracy of Sekkan-ke (Sekkan families).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, historians believe that, since Yoshiie represented the new rising bushi class, his treatment by the imperial court over the Later Three Years&apos; War was a &apos;conspiracy of Shirakawa-in (retired Emperor Shirakawa)&apos; or a &apos;conspiracy of the Sekkan-ke (the five houses of the Fujiwara clan that usually held the regency).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;assumed&quot;→&quot;believe&quot;Added &quot;, since&quot;&quot;and the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;&quot;on&quot;→&quot;over&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;Added definition of &quot;Sekkan-ke&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, historians believe that, since Yoshiie represented the new rising bushi class, his treatment by the imperial court over the Later Three Years&apos; War was a &apos;conspiracy of Shirakawain (Retired Emperor Shirakawa)&apos; or a &apos;conspiracy of the Sekkan-ke (the five houses of the Fujiwara clan that usually held the regency).&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。ハイフン削除。Retired大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>生前の極位は正四位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His highest official rank before his death was Shoshiinoge (the Lower Fourth Court Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His highest official rank before his death was Shoshiinoge (the Lower Fourth Court Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His highest official rank before his death was Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>用語集より、正四位下→Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出生と没年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Date of Birth and Death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dates of Birth and Death</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;Made &quot;date&quot; plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dates of Birth and Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>生没とも諸説あってはっきりしないが、68歳で死去とする史料が多く、またその没年は、史料としての信頼性が最も高い『中右記』1106年（嘉承1）7月15日条から逆算し、1039年（長暦3）の生まれとする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were various theories on the dates of his birth and death and remain uncertain, but many references pointed out that he died at the age of 68, and it is mostly likely that he was born in 1039 by calculating back from the most reliable &quot;Chuyu-ki&quot; (dated July 15, 1106).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories about the dates of his birth and death and they remain uncertain, but many references point out that he died at the age of 68, and by calculating back from the most reliable &quot;Chuyu-ki&quot; entry, dated July 15, 1106, it is mostly likely that he was born in 1039.</e>
<cmt>&quot;were&quot;→&quot;are&quot;&quot;pointed&quot;→&quot;point&quot;Changed word orderAdded &quot;entry&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories about the dates of his birth and death and they remain uncertain, but many references point out that he died at the age of 68, and by calculating back from the most reliable &quot;Chuyu-ki&quot; entry, dated July 15, 1106, it is mostly likely that he was born in 1039.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>源頼義の長男として、河内源氏の本拠地である河内国石川郡壷井（現大阪府羽曳野市壷井）の香炉峰の館に生まれたという説、鎌倉で生まれたとの説もあるが、いずれも伝承の域を出ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were theories that he was born as the eldest son of MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi in the Koroho-no-yakata (residence) in Tsuboi, Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture or Kamakura, but they remain within the realm of folklores.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are theories that he was the eldest son of MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, born in the Koroho-no-yakata (residence) in Kamakura (present day Tsuboi, Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture), but they remain within the realm of conjecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;were&quot;→&quot;are&quot;Moved &quot;born&quot;Changed word orderAdded &quot;present day&quot; and brackets&quot;folklores&quot;→&quot;conjecture&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are theories that he was the eldest son of MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, born in Koroho residence in Kamakura (present day Tsuboi, Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture), but they remain within the realm of conjecture.</e>
<cmt>香炉峰の館→Koroho residenceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>幼名は不動丸、または源太丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name is Fudomaru or Gentamaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Fudomaru or Gentamaru.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Fudomaru or Gentamaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>七歳の春に、京都郊外の石清水八幡宮で元服したことから八幡太郎と称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went through the genpuku (Coming of Age Ceremony) at Iwashimizu-hachiman-gu Shrine, outside Kyoto, during the spring of his seventh year and named himself Hachiman-taro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went through the genpuku (Coming of Age) Ceremony at Iwashimizu-hachiman-gu Shrine, outside Kyoto, during the spring of his seventh year and took the name Hachiman-taro.</e>
<cmt>Moved closing bracket&quot;named himself&quot;→&quot;took the name&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went through the genpuku (Coming of Age) ceremony at Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine, outside Kyoto, during the spring of his seventh year and took the name Hachimantaro.</e>
<cmt>ceremonny小文字にしました。ハイフン削除、スペース補足、H大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>前九年の役から下野守まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War to Shimotsuke-no-kami (the Lord of Shimotsuke)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War to Shimotsuke-no-kami (the Lord of Shimotsuke)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War to Shimotsuke no kami (the governer of Shimotsuke Province)</e>
<cmt>用語集より、下野守→Shimotsuke no kami (the governer of Shimotsuke Province)としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>鎮守府将軍、陸奥守に任ぜられた父頼義が安倍氏 (奥州)と戦った前九年の役では、1057年（天喜5）11月に数百の死者を出し大敗した黄海の戦いを経験。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Yoriyoshi, who held titles of Chinjufu Shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of North) and Matsu-no-kami (the Lord of Mutsu), experienced a great defeat at the Battle of Kiumi which produced several hundred casualties in November 1057 in the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War against the Abe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1057, during the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War against the Abe clan, his father Yoriyoshi, who held the titles Chinjufu Shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of North) and Matsu-no-kami (the Lord of Mutsu), suffered a huge defeat at the Battle of Kiumi, resulting in several hundred casualties.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&quot;experienced a great&quot;→&quot;suffered a huge defeat&quot;&quot;which produced&quot;→&quot;resulting in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Yoriyoshi, who held the titles Chinjufu Shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of North) and Mutsu no kami (the governer of Mutsu Province), suffered a great defeat at the Battle of Kiumi resulting in several hundred casualties in November 1057 during the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War against the Abe clan.</e>
<cmt>用語集より、陸奥守→Mutsu no kami (the governer of Mutsu Province)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後出羽国の清原氏の応援を得て父頼義はやっと安倍氏を平定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Yoriyoshi finally suppressed the Abe clan with the assistance from the Kiyohara clan of Dewa-no-kuni (Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriyoshi finally defeated the Abe clan with the assistance of the Kiyohara clan of Dewa-no-kuni (Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;His father&quot;&quot;suppressed&quot;→&quot;defeated&quot;&quot;from&quot;→&quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriyoshi finally defeated the Abe clan with the assistance of the Kiyohara clan of Dewa no kuni (Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、『奥州後三年記』（『続群書類従』収録）には清原家衡の乳母の千任に、「なんぢが父頼義、安倍貞任、安倍宗任をうちえずして、名簿 (名札)をさヽげて故清将軍（鎮守府将軍・清原武則）をかたらひたてまつれり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was mentioned in &quot;Oshu-gosannen-ki&quot; (A Chronicle of Later Three Years&apos; War in Oshu) (recorded in &quot;Zoku-Gunsho-Ruiju&quot;) that he was taunted by Sento, the nurse of Iehara KIYOHARA, &apos;Thy father Yoriyoshi could not suppress Sadato ABE and Muneto ABE so he presented myobu (full name and rank presented from the servant to the master to pledge an oath) to the late Shogun Sei (Chinjufu Shogun, KIYOHARA no Takenori) to ally with him.</e>
<cmt>名簿→myobu (full name and rank presented from the servant to the master to serve) [http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/187663/m0u/名簿/], 清将軍→Shogun Sei と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as recorded in the &quot;Zoku-Gunsho-Ruiju,&quot; the &quot;Oshu-gosannen-ki&quot; (A Chronicle of The Later Three Years&apos; War in Oshu) mentioned that Sento, the nurse of Iehara KIYOHARA, taunted Yoshiie saying &apos;Thy father Yoriyoshi could not defeat Sadato ABE and Muneto ABE, so he had to pledge allegience and subservience (myobu) to the late Shogun Sei (the Chinjufu Shogun, or &quot;Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North&quot; KIYOHARA no Takenori) in order to make an alliance.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderDeleted brackets&quot;presented myobu (full name and rank presented from the servant to the master to pledge an oath)&quot;→&quot;had to pledge allegience and subservience (myobu)&quot;Added definition of Chinjufu Shogun&quot;to ally with him&quot;→&quot;in order to make an alliance&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as recorded in the &quot;Zoku-Gunsho-Ruiju,&quot; the &quot;Oshu-gosannen-ki&quot; (A Chronicle of The Later Three Years&apos; War in Oshu) mentioned that Sento, the nurse of Iehara KIYOHARA, taunted Yoshiie saying &apos;Thy father Yoriyoshi could not defeat Sadato ABE and Muneto ABE, so he had to pledge allegiance and subservience (myobu) to the late Shogun Sei (the Chinjufu Shogun, or &quot;Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North&quot; KIYOHARA no Takenori) in order to make an alliance.</e>
<cmt>allegianceスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ひとへにそのちからにてたまたま安倍貞任らをうちえたり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By gaining power from it, he was able to suppress Sadato ABE group just by chance.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only in this way could he defeat them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only in this way could he defeat them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>」といわれて激怒したことが載っているが、「名簿」（みょうぶ）を差しだし、臣下の礼をとったかどうかはともかく、それに近い平身低頭で参戦を頼みこんだことが判る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book mentioned that Yoshiie became furious from hearing such comment, but even if his father presented &apos;myobu&apos; to pledge an allegiance or not, it was obvious that he asked the another to join the war while being close to begging down on his knees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book mentioned that Yoshiie became furious upon hearing this, but whether his father pledged allegiance or not, it was obvious that he had been close to begging down on his knees in order to gain an ally in the war.</e>
<cmt>&quot;from hearing such comment&quot;→&quot;upon hearing this&quot;&quot;even if his father presented &apos;myobu&apos; to pledge an allegiance&quot;→&quot;whether his father pledged allegiance&quot;&quot;asked the another to join the war while being close to begging down on his knees&quot;→&quot;had been close to begging down on his knees in order to gain an ally in the war&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book mentioned that Yoshiie became furious upon hearing this, but whether his father pledged allegiance or not, it was obvious that he had been close to begging down on his knees in order to gain an ally in the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>1063年（康平6）2月25日に義家はその勲功を賞され従五位下出羽国守に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiie was awarded for his meritorious deeds by being assigned as the Jugoi no Ge (the Lower Fifth Court Rank) of the Dewa-kokushu (Lord of Dewa) on February 25, 1063.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiie was awarded for his valor by being assigned to the Jugoi no Ge (the Lower Fifth Court Rank) of the Dewa-kokushu (Lord of Dewa) on February 25, 1063.</e>
<cmt>&quot;meritorious deeds by being assigned as&quot;→&quot;his valor by being assigned to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiie was awarded for his valor by being assigned to the Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) of Dewa no kuni no kami (Governor of Dewa Province) on February 25, 1063.</e>
<cmt>用語集より、従五位下→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)出羽国守→Dewa no kuni no kami (Governor of Dewa Province)としました、</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし出羽国はその清原氏の本拠地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Dewa-no-kuni was the headquarter of the Kiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Dewa-no-kuni was the headquarters of the Kiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Dewa no kuni was the headquarters of the Kiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>清原武則には前九年の役で頭を下げた経緯もあり受領としての任国経営が思うに任せなかったのか、『朝野群載』には、翌年朝廷に越中国守への転任を希望したことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a written record that KIYOHARA no Takenori expressed a wish to the imperial court to change assigned position to the Ecchu-kokushu (the Lord of Ecchu Province) on the following year, perhaps due to having a bad experience in the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War and seemed to badly manage his assigned kuni (province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was recorded that, the following year, KIYOHARA no Takenori expressed a wish to the imperial court to be reassigned to the Ecchu-kokushu (the Lord of Ecchu Province), possibly due to his experiences in the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War and his apparent mismanagement of his assigned province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;There was a written record&quot;→&quot;It was recorded that&quot;Changed word order&quot;seemed to badly manage his assigned kuni (province)&quot;→&quot;his apparent mismanagement of his assigned province&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was recorded that, the following year, KIYOHARA no Takenori expressed a wish to the Imperial Court to be reassigned to the Ecchu no kuni no kami (Governor of Ecchu Province), possibly due to his experiences in the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War and his apparent mismanagement of his assigned province.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court大文字にしました。用語集より、越中国守→Ecchu no kuni no kami (Governor of Ecchu Province)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ただしそれが承認されたかどうかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is unclear if this request was granted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is unclear if this request was granted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is unclear if this request was granted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>尚、この年、義家は在京しており美濃において美濃源氏の祖源国房と合戦している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that year, Yoshiie was in Kyoto and battled with MINAMOTO no Kunifusa, the ancestor of the Mino Genji (the Mino branch of the Minamoto clan) at Mino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that year, Yoshiie was in Kyoto and battled with MINAMOTO no Kunifusa, the ancestor of the Mino Genji (the Mino branch of the Minamoto clan) at Mino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that year, Yoshiie was in Kyoto and battled with MINAMOTO no Kunifusa, the ancestor of the Mino-Genji (Minamoto clan) at Mino.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足、説明訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>1070年（延久2）義家は下野国守となっており、陸奥国で印と国庫の鍵を盗んだ藤原基通 (散位)を捕らえたことが『扶養略記』8月1日条に見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Fuso-Ryakki&quot; entry for August 1 shows that by 1070, Yoshiie had become the Shimotsuke-kokushu (Lord of Ecchu Province) captured FUJIWARA no Motomichi (San-I (having no official title)) who stole the stamp and key to the national vault at Mutsu-no-kuni (Mutsu province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Fuso-Ryakki&quot; entry for August 1 shows that by 1070, Yoshiie had become the Shimotsuke-kokushu (Lord of Ecchu Province) and had arrested FUJIWARA no Motomichi (no official title) for stealing the stamp and key to the national vault in Mutsu-no-kuni (Mutsu province).</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&quot;Ecchu&quot;→&quot;Shimotsuke&quot;&quot;captured&quot;→&quot;and had arrested&quot;&quot;who stole&quot;→&quot;for stealing&quot;&quot;at&quot;→&quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Fuso-Ryakki&quot; entry for August 1 shows that by 1070, Yoshiie had become the Shimotsuke no kami and had arrested FUJIWARA no Motomichi (no official title) for stealing the stamp and key to the national vault in Mutsu no kuni (Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>用語集より、下野守→Shimotsuke no kami (the governer of Shimotsuke Province)としました。前出。陸奥国→Mutsu no kuni (Mutsu Province)と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>当時の陸奥国守は大和源氏の源頼俊で、即位間もない後三条天皇が源頼俊らに北陸奥の征服を命じており、北陸奥の征服自体は成功したが、この藤原基通の件の為か大和源氏源頼俊には恩賞はなく、その後の受領任官も記録には見えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mutsu-kokushu at that time was MINAMOTO no Yoritoshi of the Yamato Genji (the Yamato branch of the Minamoto clan), and the Emperor Gosanjo ordered Minamoto no Yoritoshi group to conquer North Mutsu, which succeeded, but no reward was given to MINAMOTO no Yoritoshi of the Yamato Genji due to FUJIWARA no Motomichi incidence, and was not presented in future records that he received estates or was assigned with a new post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Lord of Mutsu at that time was Yoshiie&apos;s father, MINAMOTO no Yoritoshi of the Yamato Genji (the Yamato branch of the Minamoto clan), and the newly enthroned Emperor Gosanjo ordered him to conquer North Mutsu but even though he succeeded, he received no reward, possibly due to the FUJIWARA no Motomichi incident, and there is no record that he received any land or new postions later..</e>
<cmt>&quot;Mutsu-kokushu&quot;→&quot;The Lord of Mutsu&quot;Added &quot;Yoshiie&apos;s father&quot;Added &quot;newly enthroned&quot;&quot;Minamoto no Yoritoshi group&quot;→&quot;him&quot;&quot;incidence&quot;→&quot;incident&quot;Rewrote last clause</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The governer of Mutsu Province at that time was Yoshiie&apos;s father, MINAMOTO no Yoritoshi of the Yamato-Genji (Minamoto clan), and the newly enthroned Emperor Gosanjo ordered him to conquer North Mutsu but even though he succeeded, he received no reward, possibly due to the FUJIWARA no Motomichi incident, and there is no record that he received any land or new postions later.</e>
<cmt>The governer of Mutsu Province に表現を統一しました。Yamato-Genjiハイフン補足。括弧内説明訂正しました。余分なピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この件に関して野口実氏は義家陰謀説も出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minoru NOGUCHI pointed out the Yoshiie Conspiracy Theory about this incidence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minoru NOGUCHI has put forward the Yoshiie Conspiracy Theory about this incident.</e>
<cmt>&quot;pointed out&quot;→&quot;has put forward&quot;&quot;incidence&quot;→&quot;incident&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minoru NOGUCHI has put forward the Yoshiie Conspiracy Theory about this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>白河帝の爪牙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Souga (Claws and Fangs) of Shirakawa-tei (the Emperor Shirakawa)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Souga (Claws and Fangs) of Emperor Shirakawa</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Shirakawa-tei&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Souga (Claws and Fangs) of Emperor Shirakawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>1079年（承暦3）8月　美濃国で源国房と闘乱を起こした右兵衛尉源重宗（清和源氏満正流４代）を官命により追討。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He subjugated U-hyoenokami, MINAMOTO no Shigemune (the fourth generation of the Mansei line of the Seiwa branch of the Minamoto clan) who caused the feud with MINAMOTO no Kunifusa in Mino-no-kuni, under orders from the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1079, he was ordered by the Imperial Court to hunt down and kill U-hyoenokami, MINAMOTO no Shigemune (the fourth generation of the Mansei line of the Seiwa branch of the Minamoto clan) for causing the feud with MINAMOTO no Kunifusa in Mino-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>Not sure of English for &quot;U-hyoenokami&quot;Added dateChanged word order&quot;subjugated&quot;→&quot;hunt down and kill&quot;&quot;under orders from the imperial court&quot;→&quot;he was ordered by the imperial court&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1079, he was ordered by the Imperial Court to hunt down and kill Uhyoe no jo (officer of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), MINAMOTO no Shigemune (the fourth generation of the Mansei line of the Seiwa branch of the Minamoto clan) for causing the feud with MINAMOTO no Kunifusa in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>用語集より、右兵衛尉→Uhyoe no jo (officer of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards)。Mino-no-kuniをMino Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>1081年（永保1）9月14日に検非違使とともに園城寺の悪僧を追補　（『扶桑略記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He chased and captured the akuso (warrior monk) with the Kebiishi (body of police commissioners in the Heian period) on September 14, 1081 (&quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Fuso-Ryakki,&quot; on September 14, 1081, with the Kebiishi (Imperial police), he chased and captured a warrior monk from Onjo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderAdded &quot;Onjou-ji Temple&quot;Changed definition of &quot;Kebiishi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Fuso-Ryakki,&quot; on September 14, 1081, with the kebiishi (police and judicial chief), he chased and captured a warrior monk from Onjo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語集より、検非違使→kebiishi (a police and judicial chief)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その年の10月14日には白河天皇の石清水八幡宮行幸に際し、その園城寺の悪僧（僧兵）の襲撃を防ぐために、弟・源義綱と二人でそれぞれの郎党を率いてを護衛したが、このとき本官（官職）が無かったため関白・藤原師実の前駆の名目で護衛を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accompanied Emperor Shirakawa during his imperial visit to Iwashimizu-hachiman-gu Shrine, and tried to prevent attacks by akuso of Onjo-ji Temple by guarding with his younger brother, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna by leading their roto (servants to bushi), but since they did not have Honkan (official government post), they guarded the emperor with an excuse of being the front runner for Kanpaku (a chancellor) FUJIWARA no Morozane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 14 the same year, he accompanied Emperor Shirakawa during his imperial visit to Iwashimizu-hachiman-gu Shrine, and in order to prevent attacks by the warrior monks of Onjo-ji Temple, formed an escort with his younger brother, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna, and their retainers but, since they held no official postion, they guarded the Emperor using the excuse of being outriders for Kanpaku (chancellor) FUJIWARA no Morozane.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;On October 14 the same year&quot;&quot;by leading their roto (servants to bushi)&quot;→&quot;and their retainers&quot;&quot;they did not have Honkan (official government post)&quot;→&quot;they held no official postion&quot;&quot;the front runner&quot;→&quot;outriders&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 14 the same year, he accompanied Emperor Shirakawa during his imperial visit to Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine, and in order to prevent attacks by the warrior monks of Onjo-ji Temple, formed an escort with his younger brother, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna, and their retainers but, since they held no official position, they guarded the Emperor using the excuse of being outriders for Kanpaku (chancellor) FUJIWARA no Morozane.</e>
<cmt>Iwashimizu-hachiman-gu をIwashimizu Hachiman-guに訂正、表記統一しました。Shrinenopositionスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>さらに帰りが夜となったので義家は束帯（朝廷での正式な装束）から非常時に戦いやすい布衣（ほい：常服）に着替え、弓箭（きゅうせん）を帯して白河天皇の乗輿の側らで警護にあたり、藤原為房の『為房卿記』には、「布衣の武士、鳳輦（ほうれん）に扈従（こしゅう）す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, since the returning trip was at night, Yoshiie changed from soukutai (traditional formal court dress) to Hoi (traditional everyday clothes), which was easy to fight in the case of emergency, and armed themselves with kyusen (bow and arrow) to guard on the sides of vehicle of Emperor Shirakawa, and FUJIWARA no Tamefusa commented in &quot;Tamefusa-kyo-ki&quot; (A Diary of FUJIWARA no Tamefusa), &apos;bushi in hoi, koshu (attend) to Horen (an imperial carriage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, since the return trip was at night, Yoshiie changed from soukutai (traditional formal court dress) to hoi (everyday clothes), which were easier to fight in case of emergency and, armed with bows and arrows, formed an escort on either side of the Emperor&apos;s palanquin, leading FUJIWARA no Tamefusa to comment in &quot;Tamefusa-kyo-ki&quot; (A Diary of FUJIWARA no Tamefusa), &apos;Plain-clothed warriors attending the imperial carriage.</e>
<cmt>&quot;returning&quot;→&quot;return&quot;Deleted &quot;traditional&quot;&quot;was easy&quot;→&quot;were easier&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;themselves&quot;Deleted &quot;kyusen &quot;and brackets&quot;to guard on the sides of vehicle of Emperor Shirakawa&quot;→&quot;formed an escort on either side of the Emperor&apos;s palanquin&quot;Rewrote quote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, since the return trip was at night, Yoshiie changed from soukutai (traditional formal court dress) to hoi (everyday clothes), which were easier to fight in case of emergency and, armed with bows and arrows, formed an escort on either side of the Emperor&apos;s palanquin, leading FUJIWARA no Tamefusa to comment in &quot;Tamefusa-kyo-ki&quot; (A Diary of FUJIWARA no Tamefusa), &apos;Plain-clothed warriors attending the imperial carriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>未だかつて聞かざる事也」と書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is something unheard of even now.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has never been heard of.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;is something unheard of even now&quot;→&quot;has never been heard of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has never been heard of.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>同年12月 4日の白河天皇の春日社行幸に際しては義家は甲冑をつけ、弓箭を帯した100名の兵を率いて白河天皇を警護する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 4 of the same year, Yoshiie guarded Emperor Shirakawa while wearing Japanese armor and helmet and lead 100 army men with kyusen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 4 of the same year, Yoshiie led 100 men wearing armor and helmets and armed with bows and arrows as a bodyguard during Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s visit to Kasuga Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderAdded &quot;Kasuga Shrina&quot; as in original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 4 of the same year, Yoshiie led 100 men wearing armor and helmets and armed with bows and arrows as a bodyguard during Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s visit to Kasuga-sha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Kasuga-shaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この段階では公卿達の日記『水左記』などにも「近日の例」と書かれるようになり、官職によらず天皇を警護することが普通のことと思われはじめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this time, it was considered to be a norm to guard the emperor disregarding governmental position as mentioned in the diary of kugyo (aristocrats), &quot;Suisa-ki&quot; as an &apos;example of nowadays.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time, it was beginning to be considered the norm to guard the emperor without regard to governmental position, as can be seen in entries such as &apos;an example of nowadays&apos; in the &quot;Suisa-ki&quot; diary of the kugyo (aristocrats).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;beginning to be&quot;&quot;disregarding&quot;→&quot;without regard to&quot;Changed word order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time, it was beginning to be considered the norm to guard the emperor without regard to governmental position, as can be seen in entries such as &apos;an example of nowadays&apos; in the &quot;Suisa-ki&quot; diary of the kugyo (aristocrats).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>のちの「北面の武士」の下地にもなった出来事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This event became the ground for the formation of the later &apos;Hokumen no Bushi (royal guards).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This event became the basis for the formation of the &apos;Hokumen no Bushi (royal guards).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;ground&quot;→&quot;basis&quot;deleted &quot;later&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This event became the basis for the formation of the &apos;Hokumen no bushi&apos; (the Imperial Palace Guards for the north side).</e>
<cmt>用語集より、「北面の武士」→&apos;Hokumen no bushi&apos; (the Imperial Palace Guards for the north side)と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この頃から義家・義綱兄弟は白河帝に近侍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna brothers served their master, Shirakawa-tei, at a close range from this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this time, the brothers, Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna, closely attended the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order.&quot;served their master, Shirakawa-tei, at a close range&quot;→&quot;closely attended the Emperor&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this time, the brothers, Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna, closely attended the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>後三年の役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Later Three Years&apos; War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Later Three Years&apos; War</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Later Three Years&apos; War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>1083年（永保3）に陸奥国守となり、出羽清原氏の内紛に介入して後三年の役がはじまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1083, Yoshiie became the Mutsu-kokushu and involved with the internal conflict of Kiyohara clan in Dewa to trigger the Later Three Years&apos; War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1083, Yoshiie became the Mutsu-kokushu and got involved in the Kiyohara clan&apos;s internal conflict in Dewa, triggering the Later Three Years&apos; War.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;got&quot;&quot;with&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;trigger&quot;→&quot;triggering &quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1083, Yoshiie became the Mutsu no kuni no kami and got involved in the Kiyohara clan&apos;s internal conflict in Dewa, triggering the Later Three Years&apos; War.</e>
<cmt>Mutsu no kuni no kamiと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>ただしこの合戦は朝廷の追討官符による公戦ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this battle was not the official war declared by the imperial court to subjugate the enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this battle was not the official one of subjugation declared by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;war&quot;→&quot;one of subjugation&quot;Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this battle was not the official one of subjugation declared by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>朝廷では1087年（寛治1）7月9日に「奥州合戦停止」の官使の派遣を決定した事実も有る事から、『後二条師通記』にはこの戦争は「義家合戦」と私戦を臭わせる書き方がされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial court declared the &apos;Termination of Oshu Kassen&apos; (the Battle of Oshu) on July 9, 1087, and &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; (A Diary of Gonijo Moromichi) wrote this war as more of a private war, referring to it as &apos;Yoshiie Battle,&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court dispatched the &apos;Termination of the Battle of Oshu&apos; declaration on July 9, 1087, and is described as a private war in &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; (A Diary of Gonijo Moromichi), which also refers to it as &apos;Yoshiie&apos;s Battle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;declared&quot;→&quot;dispatched&quot;Added &quot;declaration&quot;Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court dispatched the &apos;Termination of the Battle of Oshu&apos; declaration on July 9, 1087, and is described as a private war in &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; (A Diary of Gonijo Moromichi), which also refers to it as &apos;Yoshiie&apos;s Battle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>後三年の役において動員した兵は、石井進 (歴史学者)氏のにそって分類すれば、国守軍の「館の者共」、つまり受領国守の私的郎党として動員した近畿から美濃国、そして相模国の武者（大半は側近、または京でのコネクションを思わせる辺境軍事貴族）と、清原氏勢力外の陸奥南部の「国の兵共」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Categorizing in the way of Susumu ISHII (historian), the mobilized soldiers at the Later Three Years&apos; War were Kokushu army (Provincial army), &apos;Yakata no mono tomo&apos; (people of the residential hall) (private army of the provinces granted by the emperor from Mino-no-kuni from Kinki area), Sagami-no-kuni (Segami Province) bushi (most of them were borderline military aristocrats who may have had tight connections to Kyoto), and &apos;Kuni-no-heidomo&apos; (Soldiers of the Province) of southern Mutsu outside the control of the Kiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to historian Susumu ISHII, the armies at the Later Three Years&apos; War were the Kokushu (Daimyo&apos;s) Army, known as the &apos;Yakata no mono tomo&apos; (people of the manor), a private army of bushi (most of whom were borderline military aristocrats from who may have had close connections to Kyoto) from Mino-no-kuni and Sagami-no-kuni Provinces, mobilized as private retainers of the daimyo, and the &apos;Kuni-no-heidomo&apos; (Soldiers of the Province) of southern Mutsu, which was outside the Kiyohara clan&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence, especially definition of 国守軍 but not sure if I&apos;ve got it perfectly.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to historian Susumu ISHII, the armies at the Later Three Years&apos; War were the Kokushu (Daimyo&apos;s) Army, known as the &apos;Yakata no monodomo&apos; (people of the manor), a private army of bushi (most of whom were borderline military aristocrats from who may have had close connections to Kyoto) from Mino and Sagami Provinces, mobilized as private retainers of the daimyo, and the &apos;Kuni-no-heidomo&apos; (Soldiers of the Province) of southern Mutsu, which was outside the Kiyohara clan&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>館の者共→Yakata no monodomoに訂正しました。スペース削除しました。from Mino and Sagami Provincesに訂正しました。Kuni no heidomo、ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>「地方豪族軍」として陸奥国奥六郡の南三郡を中心とした清原清衡の軍と、そもそもの発端の当事者であり、後三年の役では後半に加勢したらしい出羽国の吉彦秀武の軍からなると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were also KIYOHARA no Kiyohira&apos;s &apos;Powerful Local Clan Army&apos; who based themselves in three southern districts of Okuroku-gun (Okuroku district), Segami-no-kuni and the army of KIMIKO no Hidetake from Dewa-no-kuni, who directly caused and participated in the later half of the Later Three Years&apos; War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were also KIYOHARA no Kiyohira&apos;s &apos;Powerful Local Clan Army&apos; based in the three southern districts of Okuroku-gun, Mutsu-no-kuni and the army of KIMIKO no Hidetake from Dewa-no-kuni, who had been involved in the incident from the beginning and participated in the latter half of the Later Three Years&apos; War.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were also KIYOHARA no Kiyohira&apos;s &apos;Powerful Local Clan Army&apos; based in the three southern districts of Okuroku-gun, Mutsu Province and the army of KIMIKO no Hidetake from Dewa Province, who had been involved in the incident from the beginning and participated in the latter half of the Later Three Years&apos; War.</e>
<cmt>Mutsu Province、Dewa Provinceと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>最終局面での主要な作戦が吉彦秀武から出ていること、及び前九年の役の例を勘案すれば、最大兵力は、戦場となった地元出羽国の吉彦秀武の軍、次ぎに当事者清原清衡の軍であり、国守軍は陸奥南部の「国の兵共」を加えたとしても、それほど多かったとは思えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By considering the fact that the main battle operation near the end of the war came from KIMIKO no Hidetake, and seeing Earlier Nine Years&apos; War events, the biggest military forces consisted of KIMIKO no Hidetake army at the local Dewa-no-kuni, where the battle field took place, Kiyohara no Kiyohira army, and Kokushu army, on the other hand, could not have been big even if &apos;Kuni-no-heidomo&apos; of the southern Mutsu was added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the fact that the main action near the end of the war came from KIMIKO no Hidetake, and taking into consideration examples from the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War, the biggest military force was KIMIKO no Hidetake&apos;s army from Dewa-no-kuni, where the battle took place, followed by Kiyohara no Kiyohira&apos;s army, while the Kokushu army, even if the &apos;Kuni-no-heidomo&apos; from southern Mutsu was added, could not have been so big.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the fact that the main action near the end of the war came from KIMIKO no Hidetake, and taking into consideration examples from the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War, the biggest military force was KIMIKO no Hidetake&apos;s army from Dewa Province, where the battle took place, followed by KIYOHARA no Kiyohira&apos;s army, while the government army, even if the &apos;Kuni no heidomo&apos; from southern Mutsu was added, could not have been so big.</e>
<cmt>Dewa Provinceと訂正しました。KIYOHARA大文字にしました。Kokushuをgovernmentとしました。Kuni no heidomo、ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>1087（寛治1）11月に義家は出羽国金沢柵にて清原武衡、清原家衡を破り、12月、それを報告する「国解」の中で「わたくしの力をもって、たまたまうちたいらぐる事をえたり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1087, Yoshiie suppressed KIYOHARA no Takehira and KIYOHARA no Iehara at Kanazawa-saku of Dewa-no-kuni, and it was reported in &apos;Kokuge&apos; (an official report to the government), &apos;I defeated them with my own power by chance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1087, Yoshiie defeated KIYOHARA no Takehira and KIYOHARA no Iehara at Kanazawa fortress in Dewa-no-kuni, and he reported in &apos;Kokuge&apos; (an official report to the government), &apos;Using my own power, I was lucky enough to defeat them.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1087, Yoshiie defeated KIYOHARA no Takehira and KIYOHARA no Iehara at Kanazawa fortress in Dewa Province, and he reported in &apos;Kokuge&apos; (an official report to the government), &apos;Using my own power, I was lucky enough to defeat them.</e>
<cmt>Dewa Provinceと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>早く追討の官符を給わりて」と後付けの追討官符を要請するが、朝廷はこれを下さず、「私戦」としたため恩賞はなく、かつ翌年1088年（寛治2）正月には陸奥守を罷免される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please give me kanpu (official written command from the imperial court) fast,&apos; and sought the official post-war kanpu for subjugating the enemy but was rejected by the imperial court which considered it as a &apos;private war,&apos; and no reward was made and took away Mutsu-no-kami in the following January 1088.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please give me kanpu (official written command from the imperial court) fast,&apos; and sought official post-war consent for defeating the enemy but was rejected by the Court which, because it considered it a &apos;private war,&apos; made no reward and in January the following year, he was removed as Mutsu-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please give me kanpu (official written command from the Imperial Court) fast,&apos; and sought official post-war consent for defeating the enemy but was rejected by the Court which, because it considered it a &apos;private war,&apos; made no reward and in January the following year, he was removed as the governer of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court大文字にしました。The governer of Mutsu Province に表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>何よりも陸奥国の兵（つわもの）を動員しての戦闘であり、義家自身が国解の中で「政事をとどめてひとえにつわもの（兵）をととの」、と述べているように、その間の陸奥国に定められた官物の貢納は滞ったと思われ、その後何年もの間催促されていることが、当時の記録に残る（『中右記』1096年（永長1）12月15日条、1097年（永長2） 2月25日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiie, who lead the tsuwamono (soldiers) of Mutsu-no-kuni to the battle, reported in Kokuge himself, &apos;stopped the politics and organize the tsuwamono,&apos; and refrained from the tax paid to the Mutsu-no-kuni, and was repeatedly pressed by the imperial court for several years hence as recorded in (&quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; dated December 15, 1096 and February 25, 1097).</e>
<cmt>政事をとどめてひとえにつわもの（兵）をととの→stopped the politics and organize the tsuwamono[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiie, who had led the Mutsu soldiers into battle, reported in the Kokuge, &apos;stop the politics and organize the soldiers,&apos; and refrained from paying Mutsu-no-kuni&apos;s tax to the Court, which repeatedly pressed him for several years (&quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; dated December 15, 1096 and February 25, 1097).</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiie, who had led the Mutsu soldiers into battle, reported in the Kokuge, &apos;stop the politics and organize the soldiers,&apos; and refrained from paying Mutsu Province&apos;s tax to the Court, which repeatedly pressed him for several years (&quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; dated December 15, 1096 and February 25, 1097).</e>
<cmt>Mutsu Provinceと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>当時の法制度からは、定められた官物を収めて、受領功過定に合格しなければ、新たな官職に就くことができず、義家は官位もそのままに据え置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The law at that time required the submission of a designated amount of tax to pass the Zuryo-kokka-sadame (criteria to determine if one is eligible for employment) to be assigned to the official government post, and Yoshiie&apos;s rank remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The law at that time required the submission of a designated amount of tax to pass the Zuryo-koka-sadame (criteria to determine if one is eligible for employment) to be assigned to an official government post, and Yoshiie&apos;s rank remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;k&apos;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The law at that time required the submission of a designated amount of tax to pass the Zuryo-koka-sadame (criteria to determine if one is eligible for employment) to be assigned to an official government post, and Yoshiie&apos;s rank remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>弟義綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Younger Brother Yoshitsuna</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Younger Brother Yoshitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Younger Brother Yoshitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>1091年（寛治5）6月　義家の郎党藤原実清と源義綱の郎党藤原則清が、河内国の所領の領有権を争い、義家・義綱兵を構える事件がおき、京を震撼させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1091, FUJIWARA no Sanekiyo of Yoshiie roto and FUJIWARA no Norikiyo of Minamoto Yoshitsuna roto fought over the right of the estate in Kawachi-no-kuni and shook Kyoto by mobilizing Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna armies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1091, Kyoto was shocked when Yoshiie&apos;s retainer, FUJIWARA no Sanekiyo and Minamoto Yoshitsuna&apos;s retainer, FUJIWARA no Norikiyo fought over the rights to the estate in Kawachi-no-kuni and shook Kyoto by mobilizing Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna armies.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&quot;of Yoshiie roto&quot;→&quot;Yoshiie&apos;s retainer&quot;&quot;of Minamoto Yoshitsuna roto&quot;→&quot;Minamoto Yoshitsuna&apos;s retainer&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1091, Kyoto was shocked when Yoshiie&apos;s retainer, FUJIWARA no Sanekiyo and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna&apos;s retainer, FUJIWARA no Norikiyo fought over the rights to the estate in Kawachi Province and shook Kyoto by mobilizing Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna armies.</e>
<cmt>MINAMOTO no、と訂正しました。Kawachi Provinceと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>弟義綱はその年1091年（寛治5）の正月に、藤原師実が節会に参内する際の行列の前駆を努めた他、翌1092年（寛治6）2月には藤原忠実が春日祭使となって奈良に赴く際の警衛、1093年（寛治7）12月には、源俊房の慶賀の参内の際に前駆を努めるなどが公卿の日記に見えるが、義家の方は1104年まで、そうした活動は記録にない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was written in the kugyo diary that younger brother Yoshitsuna acted as the front runner for the procession of FUJIWARA no Morozane during the sandai (a visit to the Imperial Palace) to participate at the party in January 1091 of that year, guarded FUJIWARA no Tadazane going to Nara as the Kasugasai-shi (Kasugasai (festival in Nara Prefecture) ambassador) in February 1092, led the procession of MINAMOTO no Toshifusa during his imperial visit in December 1093, but no such activities were recorded for Yoshiie until 1104.</e>
<cmt>春日祭使→Kasugasai-shi (Kasugasai (festival in Nara Prefecture) ambassaderと判断しました。 [http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/春日祭/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was written in the kugyo diary that Yoshitsuna was the outrider for FUJIWARA no Morozane&apos;s procession visit to the Imperial Palace to participate at a banquet in January 1091; in February 1092 he guarded FUJIWARA no Tadazane on the way to Nara as the Kasugasai-shi (Kasugasai festival ambassador) and led the procession of MINAMOTO no Toshifusa during his imperial visit in December 1093, but no such activities were recorded for Yoshiie until 1104.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was written in the kugyo diary that Yoshitsuna was the outrider for FUJIWARA no Morozane&apos;s procession visit to the Imperial Palace to participate at a banquet in January 1091; in February 1092 he guarded FUJIWARA no Tadazane on the way to Nara as the Kasugasai-shi (Kasugasai festival ambassador) and led the procession of MINAMOTO no Toshifusa during his imperial visit in December 1093, but no such activities were recorded for Yoshiie until 1104.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>1093年（寛治7）10月の除目で、義綱は陸奥守にに就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsuna was inaugurated to Mutsu-no-kami in the Jimoku (biannual inauguration ceremony of the government officials) in October 1093.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsuna was made Mutsu-no-kami at the Jimoku biannual inauguration ceremony of the government officials in October 1093.</e>
<cmt>&quot;inaugurated to&quot;→&quot;made&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;at&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsuna was made Mutsu no kami at the Jimoku biannual inauguration ceremony of the government officials in October 1093.</e>
<cmt>前出にならって、Mutsu no kamiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>翌年の1094年（寛治8）には出羽国守を襲撃した在地の開拓領主・平師妙（もろたえ）を郎党に追捕させ、従四位上に叙されて官位は兄義家と並び、翌年の1095年（嘉保2）正月の除目で、事実上陸奥よりも格の高い美濃国守に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made his roto to chase and captured the TAIRA no Morotae (cultivated the wild land) who attacked the Dewa-kokushi, and was at the same governmental rank level with his older brother when awarded with Ju-shii-jo (Upper Fourth Court Rank), and was inaugurated to Mino-Kokushu (higher quality than Mutsu) in Jimoku of the following January 1095.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1094, his retainers chased and captured TAIRA no Morotae, who had attacked the Dewa-kokushi, and he became the same governmental rank as his older brother when he was awarded the Ju-shii-jo (Upper Fourth Court Rank), and at the Jimokuin in January of the following year, he was made Lord of Mino, a province of higher status than Mutsu.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;He made&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1094, his retainers chased and captured TAIRA no Morotae, who had attacked the governer of Dewa Province, and he became the same governmental rank as his older brother when he was awarded the Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), and at the Jimoku in January of the following year, he was made the governer of Mino, a province of higher status than Mutsu.</e>
<cmt>The governer of Dewa Province に表現を統一しました。用語集より、従四位上→Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)と訂正しました。Jimokuに訂正しました。The governer ofに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>その美濃における延暦寺領荘園との争いで僧侶が死亡したことから、比叡山側は義綱の配流を要求して強訴に及ぶが、関白藤原師通は大和源氏の源頼治と義綱に命じてそれを実力で撃退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since monks died in the battle with the Enryaku-ji Temple which owned the shoen in Mino, the side of Mount Hiei demanded the exile of Yoshitsuna to the top officials, but Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Moromichi ordered MINAMOTO no Yoriharu and Yoshitsuna to drive them away with force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the deaths of some monks in the battle with the Enryaku-ji Temple over its territory in Mino, the side of Mount Hiei petitioned for Yoshitsuna&apos;s exile, but Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Moromichi ordered MINAMOTO no Yoriharu and Yoshitsuna to deal with them with force.</e>
<cmt>Following the deaths of some monks</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the deaths of some monks in the battle with the Enryaku-ji Temple over its territory in Mino, the side of Mount Hiei petitioned for Yoshitsuna&apos;s exile, but Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Moromichi ordered MINAMOTO no Yoriharu and Yoshitsuna to deal with them with force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>このときも比叡山延暦寺・日吉神社側の神人・大衆に死傷者が出、比叡山側は朝廷を呪詛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were casualties observed among monks and masses of the Enryaku-ji Temple and Hiyoshi-jinja Shrine of Mount Hiei that people of Mount Hiei cursed the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the casualties among both monks and lay people at Enryaku-ji Temple and Hiyoshi-jinja Shrine on Mount Hiei, the people of Mount Hiei cursed the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;There were casualties observed among monks and masses of the&quot;→&quot;Due to the casualties among both monks and lay people at&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;on&quot;Deleted &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the casualties among both monks and lay people at Enryaku-ji Temple and Hiyoshi-jinja Shrine on Mount Hiei, the people of Mount Hiei cursed the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>比叡山は天台密教の総本山であり、呪詛の最大の権威であって、朝廷にとっては最大の精神的脅威であったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mount Hiei was the temple authorized in the Esoteric Buddhism of the Tendai Sect and had the greatest power for curses and may have imposed the greatest psychological threat for the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the headquarters of the esoteric Tendai sect, Mount Hiei had the most authority for curses and may have posed the greatest psychological threat to the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>As the headquarters of the esoteric Tendai sect, Mount Hiei had the most authority for</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the headquarters of the esoteric Tendai sect, Mount Hiei had the most authority for curses and may have posed the greatest psychological threat to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>それに追い打ちをかけたのが、その4年後の1099年（承徳3）6月に、当事者の関白藤原師通が38歳で世を去ったことであり、朝廷は比叡山の呪詛の恐怖におののいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial court further developed the fear for the curse made by Mountain Hiei four years later when Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Moromichi died at the age of 38 in June 1099.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial court was further filled with fear of the curse made by Mountain Hiei four years later when Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Moromichi died at the age of 38 in June 1099.</e>
<cmt>wasfilled withof</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court was further filled with fear of the curse made by Mount Hiei four years later when Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Moromichi died at the age of 38 in June 1099.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court大文字にしました。Mount Hiei に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>この件の影響か、このあと義綱が受領に任じられることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Perhaps influenced by this event, Yoshitsuna was not awarded with new estates afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Perhaps influenced by this event, Yoshitsuna was not awarded with new estates afterwards.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Perhaps influenced by this event, Yoshitsuna was not awarded with new estates afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="56">
<j>院昇殿から没まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the visit to the imperial residence of the emperor to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Visit to the Emperor&apos;s Imperial Residence to Death.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Visit to the Emperor&apos;s Imperial Residence to Death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>後三年の役から10年後の1098年（承徳2）に「今日左府候官奏給云々、是前陸奥守義家朝臣依済舊國公事、除目以前被忩（そう）行也（件事依有院御気色也）、左大史廣親候奏」（『中右記』正月23日条）と白河天皇の意向もあり、やっと受領功過定を通って、4月の小除目で正四位下に昇進し、10月には院昇殿を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten years after the Later Three Years&apos; War in 1098, he passed the Zuryo-kokka-sadame with the support from Emperor Shirakawa (&quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; dated January 23) and promoted to Shoshiinoge in Kojimoku (emergency inauguration ceremony done outside of biannual jimoku) in April, and was granted to visit the imperial residence in October.</e>
<cmt>「今日左府候官奏給云々、是前陸奥守義家朝臣依済舊國公事、除目以前被忩（そう）行也（件事依有院御気色也）、左大史廣親候奏」→[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ten years after the Later Three Years&apos; War, in 1098, he passed the Zuryo-kokka-sadame with the support of Emperor Shirakawa (&quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; dated January 23) and promoted to Shoshiinoge in a Kojimoku (extraordinary inauguration ceremony done outside of the biannual jimoku) in April, and was granted permission to visit the imperial residence in October.</e>
<cmt>from ofAdded &quot;a&quot;Added &quot;permission&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ten years after the Later Three Years&apos; War, in 1098, he passed the Zuryo-kokka-sadame with the support of Emperor Shirakawa (&quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; dated January 23) and promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in a Kojimoku (extraordinary inauguration ceremony done outside of the biannual jimoku) in April, and was granted permission to visit the imperial residence in October.</e>
<cmt>用語集より、正四位下→Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし、その白河法皇の強引な引き上げに、当時既に形成されつつあった家格に拘る公卿は反発し、中御門右大臣・藤原宗忠はその日記『中右記』承徳2年10月23日条の裏書きに「義家朝臣は天下第一武勇の士なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, kugyo, who were concerned with the high class family blood formed at that time, opposed to the aggressive promotion made by Emperor Shirakawa, and Nakamikado U-daijin, FUJIWARA no Minetada wrote in his diary, &quot;Chuyu-ki&quot; (dated October 23, 1099), &apos;Minamoto Chosin is the only and best bushi of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>「義家朝臣は天下第一武勇の士なり。→Minamoto Chosin was the only and best bushi of the emperor. [http://www.geocities.jp/ktmchi/rekisi/cys_51.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the kugyo (aristocracy), who were concerned with family status that was already in place, were opposed to the aggressive promotion made by Emperor Shirakawa, and U-daijin NAKAMIKADO, FUJIWARA no Minetada wrote in his diary, &quot;Chuyu-ki&quot; (dated October 23, 1099), &apos;Minamoto Chosin is the Emperor&apos;s best and bravest bushi.</e>
<cmt>withthat was already in place</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the kugyo (aristocracy), who were concerned with family status that was already in place, were opposed to the aggressive promotion made by Emperor Shirakawa, and Udaijin Nakamikado, FUJIWARA no Minetada wrote in his diary, &quot;Chuyu-ki&quot; (dated October 23, 1099), &apos;Minamoto Asomi is the Emperor&apos;s best and bravest bushi.</e>
<cmt>Udaijin、ハイフン削除しました。Nakamikado小文字にしました。ChosinをAsomiに訂正、前出ありです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>昇殿をゆるさるるに、世人甘心せざるの気あるか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are indications that the public does not approve of his visit to the imperial court,</e>
<cmt>昇殿をゆるさるるに、世人、甘心せざるの気あるか→However, there are indications that the public does not approve of his visit to the imperial court[http://www.geocities.jp/ktmchi/rekisi/cys_51.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are indications that the public does not approve of his visit to the imperial court,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are indications that the public does not approve of his visit to the Imperial Court,</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>但し言うなかれ」と書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">but I should not utter it.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">but I should not utter it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">but I should not utter it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="61">
<j>1101年（康和3）7月7日、次男対馬国守源義親が、鎮西に於い太宰大弐大江匡房に告発され、朝廷は義家に義親召還の命を下す（『殿暦』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second son of Yoshiie, MINAMOTO no Yoshichika of Tsushima-kokushu (the Lord of Tsushima Province) was disclosed by OE no Masafusa, Dazai daini, at Chinzei (Kyushu), and the imperial court ordered Yoshiie to bring Yoshichika to the imperial court (&quot;Den-reki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second son of Yoshiie, MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, the Lord of Tsushima Province was indicted by Dazai daini OE no Masafusa, at Chinzei (in Kyushu), and Yoshiie was ordered to bring Yoshichika to the imperial court (&quot;Den-reki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>indictedDeleted &quot;the imperial court&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second son of Yoshiie, MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, the government of Tsushima Province was indicted by Dazai daini OE no Masafusa, at Chinzei (in Kyushu), and Yoshiie was ordered to bring Yoshichika to the Imperial Court (&quot;Den-reki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>The governer ofに訂正しました。Imperial Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかし義家がそのために派遣した郎党の首藤資通（山内首藤氏の祖）は1102年（康和4）2月20日、義親とともに義親召問の官吏を殺害してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sukemichi SUDO (the ancestor of YAMAUCHI-SUDO clan), roto, who was dispatched for that purpose, assassinated the imperial ambassador with Yoshichika on February 20, 1102.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the retainer dispatched by Yoshiie, Sukemichi SUDO (an ancestor of the YAMAUCHI-SUDO clan), assassinated the imperial ambassador with Yoshichika on February 20, 1102.</e>
<cmt>the an</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the retainer dispatched by Yoshiie, Sukemichi SUDO (an ancestor of the Yamauchi-Sudo clan), assassinated the imperial ambassador with Yoshichika on February 20, 1102.</e>
<cmt>Yamauchi-Sudoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>12月28日ついに朝廷は源義親の隠岐国配流を決定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, the imperial court gave the decision to exile MINAMOTO no Yoshichika to Oki-no-kuni (Oki Province) on December 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, the imperial court gave the decision to exile MINAMOTO no Yoshichika to Oki-no-kuni (Oki Province) on December 28.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, the Imperial Court gave the decision to exile MINAMOTO no Yoshichika to Oki Province on December 28.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court大文字にしました。Oki Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="64">
<j>その後『中右記』によると、1104年（長治1）10月30日、義家・義綱はそろって延暦寺の悪僧追捕を行っているが、これが義家の最後の公的な活躍となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna chased and captured akuso from the Mount Hiei on October 30, 1104, but this became the last official activity for Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna chased and captured warrior monks from Mount Hiei on October 30, 1104, but this was Yoshiie&apos;s last official activity.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna chased and captured warrior monks from Mount Hiei on October 30, 1104, but this was Yoshiie&apos;s last official activity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="65">
<j>1106年（嘉承1）には別の子の源義国（足利氏の祖）が、叔父の新羅三郎源義光等と常陸国において合戦し、6月10日、常陸合戦で源義家に実子義国を召し進ぜよとの命が下される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other son, MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni (the ancestor of the Ashikaga clan) battled with his uncle Shinra-Saburo MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu in 1106, and the imperial court ordered MINAMOTO no Yoshiie to follow his son Yoshikuni and join the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His other son, MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni (the ancestor of the Ashikaga clan) battled with his uncle Shinra-Saburo MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu in 1106, and the imperial court ordered MINAMOTO no Yoshiie to follow his son Yoshikuni and join the battle.</e>
<cmt>The his</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His other son, MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni (the ancestor of the Ashikaga clan) battled with his uncle Shinrasaburo MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu in 1106, and the imperial court ordered MINAMOTO no Yoshiie to follow his son Yoshikuni and join the battle.</e>
<cmt>Shinrasaburoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>義国と争っていた源義光、平重幹等にも捕縛命令が出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an arrest warrant issued for MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu and TAIRA no Shigemoto, who was fighting with Yoshikuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an arrest warrant issued for MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu, TAIRA no Shigemoto and others who were fighting Yoshikuni.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;and others&quot;Deleted &quot;with</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an arrest warrant issued for MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu, TAIRA no Shigemoto and others who were fighting Yoshikuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>そうした中で義家は、1106年（嘉承1）7月15日に68歳で没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In midst of this, Yoshiie died at the age of 68 on July 15, 1106.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In midst of this, Yoshiie died at the age of 68 on July 15, 1106.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In midst of this, Yoshiie died at the age of 68 on July 15, 1106.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>その翌日、藤原宗忠はその日記『中右記』に、「武威天下に満つ、誠に是れ大将軍に足る者なり」と追悼する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Minetada mourned on the following day in &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;he was the loyal man who was excellent in military skills and was truly a person who excelled to the level of a great shogun.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Minetada lamented on the following day in the &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;he was the greatest soldier in the country and truly deserved to be called a great shogun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>lamentedthe greatest soldier in the countrytruly deserved to be called</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Minetada lamented on the following day in the &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;he was the greatest soldier in the country and truly deserved to be called a great shogun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="69">
<j>その翌年の1107年（嘉承2）12月19日、隠岐に配流されていた源義親が、出雲国目代を殺害、その周辺諸国に義親に同心する動きも現れたため、白河法皇は隣国因幡国の国守であり院近臣でもあった平正盛に義親の追討を命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 19, 1107, the following year, Minamoto no Yoshichika who was exiled to Oki-no-kuni assassinated the Mokudai (a deputy provincial governor) of Izumo-no-kuni (Izumo Province), and since surrounding provinces showed the sympathy to Yoshichika, Emperor Shirakawa ordered TAIRA no Masamori, the kokushu and In-no-kinshin (government official in close association to the imperial court) of next province, Imba-no-kuni (Imba Province), to execute Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 19, 1107, the following year, MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, who was in exile in Oki-no-kuni, assassinated the Mokudai (deputy provincial governor) of Izumo-no-kuni (Izumo Province), and with surrounding provinces showing sympathy to Yoshichika, Emperor Shirakawa ordered TAIRA no Masamori, the kokushu and In-no-kinshin (government official in close association to the imperial court) of the next province, Imba-no-kuni, to execute Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt>in exile in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 19, 1107, the following year, MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, who was in exile in Oki Province, assassinated the Mokudai (deputy provincial governor) of Izumo Province, and with surrounding provinces showing sympathy to Yoshichika, Emperor Shirakawa ordered TAIRA no Masamori, the governer of province and In no Kinshin (the Retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) of the next province, Inaba Province, to execute Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt>Oki Provinceとしました。スペース削除。Izumo Provinceとしました。the governer of province and In no Kinshin (the Retired Emperor&apos;s courtier)としました。Inaba Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="70">
<j>翌年の1108年（天仁1）1月29日に平正盛は源義親の首級を持って京に凱旋、大々的な凱旋パレードが行われ、平正盛が白河院の爪牙として脚光を浴びる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Masamori returned in triumph to Kyoto on January 29, 1108, the following year, carrying the head of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, and a victory parade was performed in honor, and Masamori came into the spotlight as the Souga of Shirakawa-tei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Masamori returned in triumph to Kyoto on January 29, 1108, carrying the head of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, a victory parade was performed in his honor, and Masamori rose to prominence as the &apos;claws and teeth&apos; of Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>came into the spotlightose to prominence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Masamori returned in triumph to Kyoto on January 29, 1108, carrying the head of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, a victory parade was performed in his honor, and Masamori rose to prominence as the &apos;claws and teeth&apos; of Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>このパレードに対して、藤原宗忠は『中右記』に「故義家朝臣は年来武者の長者として多く無罪の人を殺すと云々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning this parade, FUJIWARA no Minetada wrote in &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;the late Yoshiie Chosin killed many innocent people and others for being the wealthy bushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning this parade, FUJIWARA no Minetada wrote in the &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;the late Yoshiie Chosin killed many innocent people in his time as a warrior.</e>
<cmt>in his time as a warrior</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning this parade, FUJIWARA no Minetada wrote in the &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;the late Yoshiie Asomi killed many innocent people in his time as a warrior.</e>
<cmt>ChosinをAsomiに訂正、前出ありです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>積悪の余り、遂に子孫に及ぶか」と記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The long built up evilness finally proclaimed his descendant.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sins he built up have finally proclaimed his descendant.&apos;</e>
<cmt>The sins he built up have</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sins he built up have finally proclaimed his descendant.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="73">
<j>「白河法皇の陰謀」説とその後の研究</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Conspiracy of Emperor Shirakawa&apos; Theory and the Later Study</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Conspiracy of Emperor Shirakawa&apos; Theory and Later Study</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Conspiracy of Emperor Shirakawa&apos; Theory and Later Study</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>戦後初期の義家観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The view of Yoshiie in early post-World War II period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The view of Yoshiie in the early post-World War II period</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The view of Yoshiie in the early post-World War II period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>戦後初期の歴史学者の中での通説となったものは、石母田正の『中世的世界の形成』をベースに、古代支配階級である貴族や宗教勢力に対して、新たに発生した在地領主層（封建的農奴主階級）が武装したものが「武士」であり、その新興勢力（武士階級）が、古代支配階級である貴族や宗教勢力を排除し、鎌倉幕府という武士階級を中心とした中世世界をもたらしたという歴史観であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The accepted theory and views among historians in early post-World War II period was based on &quot;Chuseiteki sekai no keise&quot; (The formation of the medieval world) by Tadashi ISHIMODA, which stated that &quot;bushi&quot; was the rising armed land lord class (the head of feudal peasant class) people who eliminated the ruling class consisting of old aristocrats and religious forces, and this new power (bushi class) founded the Kamakura bakufu controlled by the bushi class in medieval era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The accepted theory and views among historians in early post-World War II period were based on &quot;Chuseiteki sekai no keise&quot; (The formation of the medieval world) by Tadashi ISHIMODA, which stated that &quot;bushi&quot; were the rising armed land lord class (the head of feudal peasant class), who eliminated the ruling class consisting of old aristocrats and religious forces, and this new power (bushi class) founded and controlled the Kamakura bakufu controlled in medieval era.</e>
<cmt>waswere</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The accepted theory and views among historians in early post-World War II period were based on &quot;Chuseiteki sekai no keise&quot; (The formation of the medieval world) by Tadashi ISHIMODA, which stated that &quot;bushi&quot; were the rising armed land lord class (the head of feudal peasant class), who eliminated the ruling class consisting of old aristocrats and religious forces, and this new power (bushi class) founded and controlled the Kamakura bakufu controlled in medieval era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="76">
<j>当時の学説では「武士」はその在地領主をベースとしたものであり、平将門や藤原秀郷などは学会用語としては「武士」ではなく、その前段階の「兵」（つわもの）といわれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The academic theory at that time stated that &apos;bushi&apos; based themselves in their estates and did not consider TAIRA no Masakado and FUJIWARA no Hidesato as &apos;bushi&apos; but &apos;Tsuwamono (soldier)&apos; according to the academic vocabulary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The academic theory at that time stated that &apos;bushi&apos; based themselves in their estates and did not consider TAIRA no Masakado and FUJIWARA no Hidesato as &apos;bushi (warrior)&apos; but as &apos;tsuwamono (soldier)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(warrior)&quot;Added &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The academic theory at that time stated that &apos;bushi&apos; based themselves in their estates and did not consider TAIRA no Masakado and FUJIWARA no Hidesato as &apos;bushi (warrior)&apos; but as &apos;tsuwamono (soldier).&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>両者の違いを、竹内理三は1965年にこのようにも説明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rizo TAKEUCHI also explained in the following way in 1965 about the differences between the two:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rizo TAKEUCHI explained in the following way in 1965 about the differences between the two:</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;also&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rizo TAKEUCHI explained in the following way in 1965 about the differences between the two:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="78">
<j>「兵と武士の相違を今一度述べれば、兵は所従（従者）を持つが、兵の上に兵は居ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By comparing the discrepancy between tsuwamono and bushi now, tsuwamono has attendants, but no tsuwamono was placed above tsuwamono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To state the difference between tsuwamono and bushi once more, a tsuwamono has attendants below him, but no tsuwamono has another tsuwamono above him.</e>
<cmt>Reworded quote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To state the difference between tsuwamono and bushi once more, a tsuwamono has attendants below him, but no tsuwamono has another tsuwamono above him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>つまり重層的な階級制が無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In another words, there was no multiple layered class system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In another words, there was no multiple layered class system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In another words, there was no multiple layered class system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>彼らはそれぞれ一個の独立した力量で従者を従えたもので、支配の組織をもっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were attended by servants with independent control of power and lacked the system to rule over them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were attended by servants with independent control of power and lacked the system to rule over them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were attended by servants with independent control of power and lacked the system to rule over them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>ところが武士となると、その下に郎党があり、さらにその下に郎党があると言う具合に支配関係は重層的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However with bushi, bushi had roto below, who were served by roto below them, and had multiple layered ruling relationship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However with bushi, they had retainers below them, who were served by retainers below them, and had a multilayered ruling relationship</e>
<cmt>&quot;bushi&quot;→&quot;they&quot;&quot;roto&quot;→&quot;retainers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However with bushi, they had retainers below them, who were served by retainers below them, and had a multilayered ruling relationship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>（『日本の歴史』第6巻「武士の登場」（中央公論社）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Bushi no Tojo&quot; (The Rise of Warriors), &quot;Nihon no Rekishi, Vol. 6&quot; (A History of Japan, Vol. 6) (Chuo Koron sha (currently Chuo Koron Shinsha)).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Bushi no Tojo&quot; (The Rise of Warriors), &quot;Nihon no Rekishi, Vol. 6&quot; (A History of Japan, Vol. 6) (Chuo Koron sha (currently Chuo Koron Shinsha)).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Bushi no Tojo&quot; (The Rise of Warriors), &quot;Nihon no Rekishi, Vol. 6&quot; (A History of Japan, Vol. 6) (Chuo Koron sha (currently Chuo Koron Shinsha)).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="83">
<j>そうした「重層的な階級制」は、ちょうど義家の頃に見られるようになり、その背景には、地方経済社会での大きな変動、在地での有力者は田堵・負名（公田請作経営者）から在地領主（所領経営者）へと変化があったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such &apos;multiple layered class system&apos; began to appear at the time of Yoshiie, and is believed that there was a huge economic shift of the district societies, and residential land&apos;s power holder changed from Tato and Fumyo (farm managers who lease public fields from provincial lords and produced agricultural products) to the residential land lords (estate managers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &apos;multilayered class system&apos; began to appear during Yoshiie&apos;s time, and is believed that there was a huge economic shift in local society, and power in residential land shifted from the &apos;Tato&apos; and &apos;Fumyo&apos; (farm managers who leased public fields from provincial lords and produced agricultural products) to the residential land lords (estate managers).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Such&quot;→&quot;This&quot;&quot;at the time of Yoshiie&quot;→&quot;during Yoshiie&apos;s time&quot;&quot;of the district societies&quot;→&quot;in local society&quot;&quot;changed&quot;→&quot;shifted&quot;Added &apos;d&apos; to &quot;lease&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;multilayered class system&apos; began to appear during Yoshiie&apos;s time, and is believed that there was a huge economic shift in local society, and power in residential land shifted from the &apos;Tato&apos; and &apos;Fumyo&apos; (farm managers who leased public fields from provincial lords and produced agricultural products) to the residential land lords (estate managers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="84">
<j>そうした歴史の大きな流れの中で、新興勢力・武士階級と古代支配階級の最初の衝突（抑圧）を源義家の中に見ようとする傾向が大勢を占めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many had the tendency to try to study Minamoto no Yoshiie as the first clash (suppression) between the new rising bushi and old aristocratic ruling classes in midst of such huge historical transformation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many people were inclined to see in Minamoto no Yoshiie the first clash (oppression) between the new rising warrior class and old aristocratic ruling classes in the context of such huge historical transformation.</e>
<cmt>inclinedwarrior classcontext</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many people were inclined to see in MINAMOTO no Yoshiie the first clash (oppression) between the new rising warrior class and old aristocratic ruling classes in the context of such huge historical transformation.</e>
<cmt>MINAMOTO大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>1966年の安田元久『源義家』（吉川弘文館）もそのような視点から書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Minamoto no Yoshiie&quot; (Yoshikawa Kobukan, 1966) written by Motohisa YASUDA wrote from such perspective.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Minamoto no Yoshiie&quot; (Yoshikawa Kobukan, 1966) by Motohisa YASUDA was written from such perspective.</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;written&quot;&quot;wrote&quot;→&quot;was written&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Minamoto no Yoshiie&quot; (Yoshikawa Kobukan, 1966) by Motohisa YASUDA was written from such perspective.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="86">
<j>その最初の衝突（抑圧）の具体例としてあげられたのが、後三年の役の勝利にも関わらず恩賞が与えられず、冷遇されたこと、そして義家に対する荘園寄進が禁じられたことなどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first example of such clash (suppression) was the fact that Yoshiie did not receive rewards despite his victory in the Later Three Years&apos; War and was treated coldly in addition to being banned from receiving new estates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first example of such a clash (suppression) was the fact that Yoshiie did not receive rewards despite his victory in the Later Three Years&apos; War and was treated coldly in addition to being banned from receiving new estates.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first example of such a clash (suppression) was the fact that Yoshiie did not receive rewards despite his victory in the Later Three Years&apos; War and was treated coldly in addition to being banned from receiving new estates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>更に、義家の死後の河内源氏の内紛の中で孫の源為義が意図的に取り立てられ、いっそう河内源氏の結束が乱された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Yoshiie&apos;s grandson, Minamoto no Tameyoshi, was intentionally appointed during the internal conflict of Kawachi Genji clan after the death of Yoshiie, and this further disturbed the unity within the Kawachi Genji clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Yoshiie&apos;s grandson, Minamoto no Tameyoshi, was intentionally promoted during the internal conflict of the Kawachi Genji clan after the death of Yoshiie, further disturbing the unity within the Kawachi Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>appointedpromotedAdded &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;and this&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Yoshiie&apos;s grandson, MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, was intentionally promoted during the internal conflict of the Kawachi-Genji clan after the death of Yoshiie, further disturbing the unity within the Kawachi-Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>MINAMOTO大文字にしました。ハイフン補足しました。スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>更にその為義も冷遇されて一生受領にはなれなかった、などとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tameyoshi himself was treated coldly as well and was not rewarded with estate during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tameyoshi himself was also treated coldly and was not rewarded with an estate during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as well&quot;→&quot;also&quot;Added &quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tameyoshi himself was also treated coldly and was not rewarded with an estate during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="89">
<j>白河天皇や摂関家など、当時の支配者が義家を危険視したという竹内理三、安田元久の論は、当時の国土のほとんどが荘園となっていたという認識を前提としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rulers at that time, including Emperor Shirakawa and Sekkan-ke, viewed Yoshiie as the dangerous individual based on the fact that most of the country was occupied by shoen as according to the arguments made by Rizo TAKEUCHI and Motohisa YASUDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to arguments made by Rizo TAKEUCHI and Motohisa YASUDA, the rulers at that time, including Emperor Shirakawa and the Sekkan-ke, viewed Yoshiie as a dangerous individual based on the fact that most of the country was divided into shoen (manors).</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderAdded &quot;the&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to arguments made by Rizo TAKEUCHI and Motohisa YASUDA, the rulers at that time, including Emperor Shirakawa and the Sekkan-ke, viewed Yoshiie as a dangerous individual based on the fact that most of the country was divided into shoen (manors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>そうした状況のなかで、義家はその荘園の最上位の所有者層に割り込み、白河法皇や摂関家など、王家・上級貴族の経済基盤を脅かしたというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of such situation, Yoshiie managed to squeeze himself into the highest rank of shoen&apos;s land owners and threatened the financial platform of royal families and high class aristocrats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of such a situation, Yoshiie managed to squeeze himself into the highest rank of shoen&apos;s land owners and threatened the financial platform of royal families and high class aristocrats.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of such a situation, Yoshiie managed to squeeze himself into the highest rank of shoen&apos;s land owners and threatened the financial platform of royal families and high class aristocrats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>例えば竹内理三は1965年『武士の登場』の中で、「諸国の百姓から田畑の寄進をうけて貴族と同じ荘園領家化することは、上皇をふくめての貴族層にとってはたえがたいことであった」と説明されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For an example, Rizo TAKEUCHI explained in &quot;Bushi no Tojo&quot;(1965), &apos;aristocrats including the retired emperor could not stand those who became shoen land lords similar to aristocrats by receiving farms from peasants of many districts.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, as Rizo TAKEUCHI explained in &quot;Bushi no Tojo&quot;(1965), &apos;aristocrats, including the retired emperor, could not stand those who, by receiving farms from peasants of many districts, became shoen landlords on a par with aristocrats.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;an&quot;Added &quot;as&quot;Added commas&quot;similar to&quot;→&quot;on a par with&quot;Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, as Rizo TAKEUCHI explained in &quot;Bushi no Tojo&quot; (1965), &apos;aristocrats, including the retired emperor, could not stand those who, by receiving farms from peasants of many districts, became shoen landlords on a par with aristocrats.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="92">
<j>その後の荘園史の進展</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Later Development of the Historical Study of Shoen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later Developments in the Historical Study of Shoen</e>
<cmt>&quot;The Later Development of&quot;→&quot;Later Developments in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later Developments in the Historical Study of Shoen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>しかしこの論は、1970年代以降の荘園史研究の進展から、3つの点で見直しが必要とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this theory required to be revised in three ways from the post-1970&apos;s development of the historical study of shoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, from the 1970&apos;s, developments in the study of shoen history led to this theory being revised in three ways.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from the 1970&apos;s, developments in the study of shoen history led to this theory being revised in three ways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="94">
<j>そのひとつは、網野善彦の1969年「若狭国における荘園制の形成」や石井進 (歴史学者)の1970年「院政時代」、1978年の「相武の武士団」（『鎌倉武士の実像』に収録）における「太田文」の詳細な研究から、荘園がもっとも盛んに立荘された時期は、12世紀中葉以降の鳥羽天皇・後白河天皇院政期であり、更にその大規模荘園の乱立が完了した13世紀においてさえも、荘園領と国衙領は地方により相違はあるものの、平均すれば6対4とほぼ半々であることが明らかになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One is the fact that manor was mostly founded after mid-12th century during Emperors Toba and Gotoba&apos;s In-sei period and the ratio of shoen and national land remained at the average of six to four ratio or half-and-half at the completion of a large scale mushrooming of manor in 13th century as indicated by the detail study written in &quot;Wakasa no kuni ni okeru shoensei no keisei&quot; (The formation of manor system in Wakasa Province) (1969) proposed by Yoshihiko AMINO, &quot;Insei jidai&quot; (The Period of the Government by a Retired Emperor) (1970) by Susumu ISHII, &quot;Oota Fumi&quot; (The letters of Oota) in &quot;Sobu no bushidan&quot; (The bushi groups in Sobu region) (written in &quot;Kamakura bushi no jitsuzo&quot; (The Real Face of Kamakura Warriors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Firstly, following detailed research that appeared in Yoshihiko AMINO&apos;s &quot;Wakasa no kuni ni okeru shoensei no keisei&quot; (The formation of the manor system in Wakasa Province) (1969), Susumu ISHII&apos;s &quot;Insei jidai&quot; (The Age of Cloistered Emperors) (1970) and &quot;Oota Fumi&quot; (The letters of Oota) in &quot;Sobu no bushidan&quot; (Bushi groups of the Sobu region), which appears in &quot;Kamakura bushi no jitsuzo&quot; (The Real Face of Kamakura Warriors) (1978), it became clear that most manors were established after the mid-12th century, during the reigns of the Cloistered Emperors Toba and Gotoba, and that by the time this large-scale expansion stopped in the 13th century, the ratio of shoen to national land was on average of six to four, or about even.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Firstly, following detailed research that appeared in Yoshihiko AMINO&apos;s &quot;Wakasa no kuni ni okeru shoensei no keisei&quot; (The formation of the manor system in Wakasa Province) (1969), Susumu ISHII&apos;s &quot;Insei jidai&quot; (The Age of Cloistered Emperors) (1970) and &quot;Oota Fumi&quot; (The letters of Oota) in &quot;Sobu no bushidan&quot; (Bushi groups of the Sobu region), which appears in &quot;Kamakura bushi no jitsuzo&quot; (The Real Face of Kamakura Warriors) (1978), it became clear that most manors were established after the mid-12th century, during the reigns of the Cloistered Emperors Toba and Gotoba, and that by the time this large-scale expansion stopped in the 13th century, the ratio of shoen to national land was on average of six to four, or about even.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="95">
<j>石井進 (歴史学者)は1986年4月の「中世の村を歩く－寺院と荘園」（現在『中世の村を歩く』収録）において「摂関時代の成立とともに全国土が荘園となったという従来の説には、とても従えないのである。」と書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Susumu ISHII (historian) wrote in &quot;Chusei no mura o aruku - Jiin no shoen&quot; (A walk to medieval villages- Temples and Shrines) (Currently included within &quot;Chusei no mura o aruku&quot;), &apos;I cannot believe the theory that the entire country became shoen at the same time as the establishment of Sekkan period.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The historian Susumu ISHII wrote in &quot;Chusei no mura o aruku - Jiin no shoen&quot; (A walk in medieval villages- Temples and Manors) (Currently the &quot;Chusei no mura o aruku&quot; compilation), &apos;I cannot believe the theory that the entire country became shoen at the same time as the establishment of the Sekkan (regency) period.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;to&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;Shrines&quot;→&quot;Manors&quot;&quot;included in&quot;→&quot;compilation&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; and definition of &quot;Sekkan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1986, the historian Susumu ISHII wrote in &quot;Chusei no mura o aruku - Jiin no shoen&quot; (A walk in medieval villages - Temples and Manors) (Currently the &quot;Chusei no mura o aruku&quot; compilation), &apos;I cannot believe the theory that the entire country became shoen at the same time as the establishment of the Sekkan (regency) period.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1986年4月を補足しました。スペース削除。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="96">
<j>ふたつめは、「貴族と同じ荘園領家化」（石井進）、「上級貴族達と同じように荘園領主」（安田元久）と、荘園支配の階層の最上位に義家がなっていったとみなしていることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second part is the fact that &quot;Kizoku to Onaji Shoen-ryoke ka&quot; (The formation of Shoen-ryoke (A lord who is donated with &quot;Shoen&quot; estates) same as the aristocrats) by Susumu ISHII and &quot;Jokyu Kizoku-tachi to onajiyouni Shoen-ryoshu (Shoen-ryoke)&quot; (Shoen-ryoshu same as high aristocrats) by Motohisa YASUDA considered Yoshiie as the highest class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Secondly, Susumu ISHII in &quot;Kizoku to Onaji Shoen-ryoke ka&quot; (The formation of Shoen-ryoke (A lord who is donated with &quot;Shoen&quot; estates) same as the aristocrats) and Motohisa YASUDA in &quot;Jokyu Kizoku-tachi to onajiyouni Shoen-ryoshu (Shoen-ryoke)&quot; (Shoen-ryoshu same as high aristocrats) claimed Yoshiie was in the top rank of manor owners.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The second part is the fact that&quot;→&quot;Secondly&quot;&quot;considered Yoshiie as the highest class&quot;→&quot;claimed Yoshiie was in the top rank of manor owners&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Secondly, Susumu ISHII in &quot;Kizoku to Onaji Shoen-ryoke ka&quot; (The formation of Shoen-ryoke (A lord who is donated with &quot;Shoen&quot; estates) same as the aristocrats) and Motohisa YASUDA in &quot;Jokyu Kizoku-tachi to onajiyouni Shoen-ryoshu (Shoen-ryoke)&quot; (Shoen-ryoshu same as high aristocrats) claimed Yoshiie was in the top rank of manor owners.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="97">
<j>荘園支配の階層には荘園領主である「本所や領家」、その代官である「預所」、現地での実質支配者で、多くの場合寄進者である「庄司（下司）」の3段階があるが、その最上位が権門といわれる「上皇をふくめての貴族層」や、大寺院・神社が位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shoen ruling class had the leader, &quot;honjo (a head of shoen lords) and ryoke,&quot; and its substitute, &quot;Azukaridokoro&quot; (a deputy of shoen lord) as the actual local ruler, and in many cases, there were three classes of donating &quot;Shoshi or Geshi (a local keeper)&quot; in many cases, but the top most rank was the &quot;Kenmon&quot; which included &quot;aristocrats including the retired emperor&quot; and those of temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shoen ranks included &quot;honjo (head of shoen lords) and ryoke,&quot; their deputy, &quot;azukaridokoro,&quot; and three classes of &quot;Shoshi or Geshi,&quot; the actual local ruler and in many cases, donor, but the top most rank was the &quot;Kenmon&quot; which included &quot;aristocrats including the retired emperor&quot; and those of temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The shoen ruling class had the leader&quot;→&quot;&quot;and its substitute&quot;→&quot;their deputy&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shoen ranks included &quot;honjo (head of shoen lords) and ryoke,&quot; their deputy, &quot;azukaridokoro,&quot; and three classes of &quot;Shoshi or Geshi,&quot; the actual local ruler and in many cases, donor, but the top most rank was the &quot;Kenmon&quot; which included &quot;aristocrats including the retired emperor&quot; and those of temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="98">
<j>1960年代には、義家がその最上位に、権門を押しのけて、あるいは新たな権門として割り込もうとしたかのとうに捉えられていたが、これはたかだか四位の諸大夫・受領層である義家には考えにくい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was interpreted in 1960s that Yoshiie shoved aside old Kenmon or squeezed in as the new Kenmon, but it was hard to be accepted that way when Yoshiie was at the fourth rank of Shodaifu and as a person who accepted estates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was believed in the 1960s that Yoshiie shoved aside the old Kenmon or forced his way into the position, but this was hard to accept when Yoshiie was a fourth rank Shodaifu and a receiver of estates.</e>
<cmt>forced his way into the positiona fourth rank Shodaifua receiver of estates</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was believed in the 1960s that Yoshiie shoved aside the old Kenmon or forced his way into the position, but this was hard to accept when Yoshiie was a fourth rank Shodaifu and a receiver of estates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="99">
<j>福田豊彦は、1974年の「王朝国家をめぐって」（『東国の兵乱ともののふたち』に収録）と言う論文で、「荘園寄進の対象（本家領家）ではなくて、寄進に当たっての媒介の役割を果たした貴族層（預所など）との接点で考える必要がありそうに思います。」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the paper called &quot;Ochokokka o megutte&quot; (About the Monachic State) (collected in &quot;Togoku no heiran to mononofutachi&quot; (Wars in the Eastern Japan and Warriors)) written by Toyohiko FUKUDA in 1974 stated, &apos;I believe there is a need to think not from the perspective of the honke (the highest shoen class) or ryoke (who was given shoen by the imperial court) but aristocrats (such as Azukaridokoro) who acted as the mediators of donation of estates.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his paper &quot;Ochokokka o megutte&quot; (About the Monachic State) (collected in &quot;Togoku no heiran to mononofutachi&quot; (Wars And Warriors in Eastern Japan)) written in 1974, Toyohiko FUKUDA stated, &apos;I believe there is a need to think not from the perspective of the honke (the highest shoen class) or ryoke (who was given shoen by the imperial court) but aristocrats (such as the Azukaridokoro) who acted as the mediators of donation of estates.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;Altered English name of bookDeleted &quot;called&quot;Swapped date and name aroundAdded &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his paper &quot;Ochokokka o megutte&quot; (About the Monarchic State) (collected in &quot;Togoku no heiran to mononofutachi&quot; (Wars And Warriors in Eastern Japan)) written in 1974, Toyohiko FUKUDA stated, &apos;I believe there is a need to think not from the perspective of the honke (the highest shoen class) or ryoke (who was given shoen by the Imperial Court) but aristocrats (such as the Azukaridokoro) who acted as the mediators of donation of estates.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Monarchicスペル訂正しました。Imperial Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="100">
<j>また田中文英は1997年に書いた論文「河内源氏とその時代」（『院政とその時代』に収録）において、義家が立荘して摂関家に寄進し、自らは預所となってそれを子の左衛門尉義時が受け継いだものかと推測する石川荘が、かなり広い地域の中に散在する数町から小さいものでは数段、つまり数十石から数石ぐらいの田畑の寄せ集めの様相を示していることを紹介している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Fumihide TANAKA introduced in 1997 paper, &quot;Kawachi Genji to sono jidai&quot; (The Kawachi branch of the Minamoto clan and their era) (in &quot;In-sei to sono jidai&quot; (The government by a retired emperor and the era)) that Ishikawa Sou believed to have been inherited by Sa-emon-no-jo Yoshitoki (the son of Yoshii, who established the shoen and donated to Sekkan-ke, and became Azukaridokoro), consisted of several towns and farmlands as big as several to several dozen koku (5.12 U.S. bushels) spread over the wide area.</e>
<cmt>石→ koku (5.12 U.S. bushels)[http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=積&amp;dtype=3&amp;stype=4&amp;dname=2na&amp;pagenum=61&amp;index=01478600]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Fumihide TANAKA in his 1997 paper, &quot;Kawachi Genji to sono jidai&quot; (The Kawachi branch of the Minamoto clan and their era) (in &quot;In-sei to sono jidai&quot; (The government by a retired emperor and the era)) intoduced the idea that Ishikawa Manor, founded by Yoshiie, donated to the Sekkan-ke and believed to have been inherited by his son, Sa-emon-no-jo Yoshitoki, after Yoshiie became Azukaridokoro, consisted of several towns and farmlands as big as several to several dozen koku (5.12 U.S. bushels) spread over a wide area.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderAdded&quot; the idea&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Fumihide TANAKA in his 1997 paper, &quot;Kawachi Genji to sono jidai&quot; (The Kawachi branch of the Minamoto clan and their era) (in &quot;In-sei to sono jidai&quot; (The government by a retired emperor and the era)) introduced the idea that Ishikawa Manor, founded by Yoshiie, donated to the Sekkan-ke and believed to have been inherited by his son, Saemonnojo Yoshitoki, after Yoshiie became Azukaridokoro, consisted of several towns and farmlands as big as several to several dozen koku (5.12 U.S. bushels) spread over a wide area.</e>
<cmt>introducedsスペル訂正しました。ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="101">
<j>1091年（寛治5）6月の義家の郎党と義綱の郎党の河内国の所領の領有権争いは、こうした小さな単位の田畠をめぐって争われたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was believed that the fight between roto of Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna of Kawachi-no-kuni in June 1091 was over the right to small farm lands like these.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was believed that the fight between the retainers of Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna over Kawachi-no-kuni in June 1091 was over the right to small farm lands like these.</e>
<cmt>&quot;roto&quot;→&quot;retainers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was believed that the fight between the retainers of Yoshiie and Yoshitsuna over Kawachi Province in June 1091 was over the right to small farm lands like these.</e>
<cmt>Kawachi Province と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>この傾向は近畿一帯に共通する性格であり、12世紀中頃以降の東国などに見られる大規模寄進系荘園と同一視することは出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This characteristic was commonly observed in Kinki region, and it cannot be considered to be the same as greatly expanding Shoen seen in Eastern Japan after the mid-12th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This characteristic was commonly observed in Kinki region, and it cannot be considered to be the same as greatly expanding Shoen seen in Eastern Japan after the mid-12th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This characteristic was commonly observed in Kinki region, and it cannot be considered to be the same as greatly expanding Shoen seen in Eastern Japan after the mid-12th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="103">
<j>『後二条師通記』と『百錬抄』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; and &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; (the historical document based on the diaries of the aristocrats, written during Kamakura period)).</e>
<cmt>『百錬抄』→&quot;Hyakuren-sho (the historical document based on the diaries of the aristocrats, written during Kamakura period)&quot;[http://www.netlaputa.ne.jp/~kitsch/siryou/kam/sisho/kam-sisho.htm]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; and the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; (an historical document based on the diaries of aristocrats, written during the Kamakura period)).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;deleted &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; and the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; (an historical document based on the diaries of aristocrats, written during the Kamakura period)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>次ぎに、「義家に対して随兵の入京禁止令」「義家への土地の寄進禁止」であるが、これは、1091（寛治5）6月　義家の郎党藤原実清と義綱の郎党藤原則清、河内国の所領の領有権を争いから、源義家・源義綱が兵を構える事態となり、京が騒然としたことに関する当時内大臣・藤原師通の日記『後二条師通記』と、鎌倉時代後期に、それまでの諸日記を編纂した『百錬抄』（ひゃくれんしょう）に見える記事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, there were the &apos;Prohibition Order for Yoshiie to enter his army into Kyoto&apos; and &apos;Prohibition for Yoshiie to accept Land donations,&apos; but these were articles derived from the diaries of Nai-daijin (the Minister of the Center, ranked below U-daijin) FUJIWARA no Moromichi, &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; and the edited collection of diaries, &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; written in the late Kamakura era, concerning Yoshiie&apos;s roto FUJIWARA no Sanekiyo and Yoshitsuna&apos;s roto FUJIWARA no Norikiyo who mobilized the army over the issue of estate right and disturbed Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, there were the &apos;Ban on Yoshiie bringing his army into Kyoto&apos; and the &apos;Ban on Yoshiie accepting land donations,&apos; knowledge of which comes from entries in &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki,&quot; the diaries of Nai-daijin (the Minister of the Center, ranked below U-daijin) FUJIWARA no Moromichi, and the edited collection of diaries, &quot;Hyakuren-sho,&quot; written in the late Kamakura era, concerning events in June 1091, when Kyoto was in uproar over the mobilization of Yoshiie and Yoshitsune&apos;s troops following the territorial dispute between their retainers, FUJIWARA no Sanekiyo and FUJIWARA no Norikiyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Next&quot;→&quot;Finally&quot;- Japanese has &apos;next&apos; but &apos;finally&apos; is better in the context.&quot;Prohibition Order&quot;→&quot;Ban&quot;Reworded final part of sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, there were the &apos;Ban on Yoshiie bringing his army into Kyoto&apos; and the &apos;Ban on Yoshiie accepting land donations,&apos; knowledge of which comes from entries in &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki,&quot; the diaries of Naidaijin (the Minister of the Center, ranked below Udaijin) FUJIWARA no Moromichi, and the edited collection of diaries, &quot;Hyakuren-sho,&quot; written in the late Kamakura era, concerning events in June 1091, when Kyoto was in uproar over the mobilization of Yoshiie and Yoshitsune&apos;s troops following the territorial dispute between their retainers, FUJIWARA no Sanekiyo and FUJIWARA no Norikiyo.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="105">
<j>両史料は片方は一次史料であり、もう片方は約2世紀も後での2次史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of these documents was a primary historical source but another was a secondary historical source written two centuries after the event described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of these documents is a primary historical source but the other is a secondary historical source, written two centuries after the event described.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was&quot;→&quot;is&quot;&quot;another&quot;→&quot;the other&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of these documents is a primary historical source but the other is a secondary historical source, written two centuries after the event described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>「義家に対して随兵の入京禁止令」といわれるものは『百錬抄』の「前陸奥守義家、兵をしたがえて京に入ること…を停止」であるが、同じ事実を『後二条師通記』には「諸国国司隋兵留めらるべきの官符」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prohibition Order for Yoshiie to enter his army into Kyoto&apos; is from &apos;The entrance of former Mutsu-no-kami, Yoshiie, into Kyoto, accompanied by his army… stopped&apos; from &quot;Hyakuren-sho,&quot; but &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; refers to the same event as &apos;Kanpu strong enough to stop the accompanying soldiers of Kokuji (Provincial government official) of each province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>隋兵→随兵→ accompanying soldiersと判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Ban on Yoshiie bringing his army into Kyoto&apos; is from the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; entry &apos;The entrance of the former Mutsu-no-kami, Yoshiie, into Kyoto, accompanied by his army… stopped,&apos; but &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; refers to the same event as &apos;the Kanpu is strong enough to stop the accompanying soldiers of Kokuji (provincial government official) of each province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;Change word orderAdded &quot;the&quot; and &quot;is&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Ban on Yoshiie bringing his army into Kyoto&apos; is from the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; entry &apos;The entrance of the former Mutsu no kami, Yoshiie, into Kyoto, accompanied by his army… stopped,&apos; but &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; refers to the same event as &apos;the Kanpu is strong enough to stop the accompanying soldiers of Kokuji (provincial government official) of each province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Mutsu no kamiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="107">
<j>「諸国国司隋兵留めらるべき」は「義家に対して随兵の入京禁止」とは全く異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strong enough to stop the accompanying soldiers of Kokuji of each province&apos; entirely differed from the &apos;prohibition for Yoshiie to enter his army into Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strong enough to stop the accompanying soldiers of Kokuji of each province&apos; is entirely different from the &apos;prohibition for Yoshiie to enter his army into Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;differed&quot;→&quot;is different&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strong enough to stop the accompanying soldiers of Kokuji of each province&apos; is entirely different from the &apos;prohibition for Yoshiie to enter his army into Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="108">
<j>もうひとつの「義家への土地の寄進禁止」は『百錬抄』には同じ寛治5年6月12日のこととあるが、『後二条師通記』にはその記述は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another &apos;prohibition for Yoshiie to accept Land donations&apos; was mentioned in &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; as June 12, 1091, but &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; lacked such description.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Ban on Yoshiie accepting land donations&apos; was mentioned in the the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; entry for June 12, 1091, but &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; contains no such description.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Another&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; and &quot;entry&quot;&quot;as&quot;→&quot;for&quot;&quot;lacked&quot;→&quot;contains no&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Ban on Yoshiie accepting land donations&apos; was mentioned in the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; entry for June 12, 1091, but &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; contains no such description.</e>
<cmt>余分なthe削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>かわりに翌年の寛治6年5月12日条に義家が構立した荘園が停止されたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, it mentioned about the suspension of Shoen established by Yoshii on May 12, 1092.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, on May 12, 1092, it mentions the suspension of the Shoen established by Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>Moved dateChanged verb to present tense.Deleted &quot;about&quot;added &apos;e&apos; to Yoshii</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, on May 12, 1092, it mentions the suspension of the Shoen established by Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="110">
<j>この件は、安田元久も『百錬抄』には疑いを拭いきれないようで、1974年の『日本の歴史(7) 院政と平家』の中で「もし『百錬抄』にいう措置がとられたのであれば、それは左大臣俊房以下の公卿たちが、関白師実とともにとった処置であって、上皇の意志からでたものではなかったことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even Motohisa YASUDA could not erase the doubt on &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; and noted in &quot;Nihon no Rekishi, Vol. 7, Insei and the Taira Family&quot; (A history of Japan, Vol. 7, The Government by a Retired Emperor and the Taira Family), &apos;if such treatment was made in &quot;Hyakuren-sho,&quot; then it must have been performed by Kanpaku Morozane kugyo below Sa-daijin (the senior chief of an Imperial Japanese Council of State, ranked above U-daijin) Toshifusa, and it becomes in the way that it was not from the will of the retired emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohisa YASUDA could not erase the doubt over the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; and noted in &quot;Nihon no Rekishi, Vol. 7, Insei to Taira &quot; (A history of Japan, Vol. 7, The Cloistered Government and the Taira Family), &apos;if the measures mentioned in &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; were carried out, it must have been by nobles below Sa-daijin (the senior chief of an Imperial Japanese Council of State, ranked above U-daijin) Toshifusa, in collusion with Kanpaku Morozane and did not reflect the will of the emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;on&quot;→&quot;over&quot;erased &quot;and the&quot; and &quot;family&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohisa YASUDA could not erase the doubt over the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; and noted in &quot;Nihon no Rekishi, Vol. 7, Insei to Taira &quot; (A history of Japan, Vol. 7, The Cloistered Government and the Taira family), &apos;if the measures mentioned in &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; were carried out, it must have been by nobles below Sadaijin (the senior chief of an Imperial Japanese Council of State, ranked above Udaijin) Toshifusa, in collusion with Kanpaku Morozane and did not reflect the will of the emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>family小文字にしました。ハイフン削除しました。スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>」と微妙な書きかたをしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote in such a strange way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote subtly.</e>
<cmt>This sentence was mistranslated but I don&apos;t think it&apos;s really necessary in the English seeing as it&apos;s part of the above sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote subtly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="112">
<j>関白藤原師実は『後二条師通記』の藤原師通の父であり、藤原師通はその陣定に内大臣として出席しており、当時の公卿の日記の書き方から『後二条師通記』寛治5年6月12日条はその翌朝に書かれたものと推察できほぼリアルタイムとみなしてよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Morozane was the father of FUJIWARA no Moromichi who wrote &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; and Moromichi attended jin-no-sadame (political debate made during Heian period) as Nai-daijin, and assuming by the way kugyo wrote his diary, &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; (dated June 12, 1091), it was probably written on the following morning and can be considered as real-time event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Morozane was the father of &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; author FUJIWARA no Moromichi, who attended jin-no-sadame (government councils during Heian period) as Nai-daijin and, as the Kugyo nobles usually did, probably wrote the entry dated June 12, 1091 the following morning and, as such, it can be considered accurate.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderChanged definition of &quot;jin-no-sadame&quot;Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Morozane was the father of &quot;Gonijo Moromichi Ki&quot; author FUJIWARA no Moromichi, who attended jin-no-sadame (government councils during Heian period) as Nai-daijin and, as the Kugyo nobles usually did, probably wrote the entry dated June 12, 1091 the following morning and, as such, it can be considered accurate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>もし『百錬抄』にいう措置がとられたのであれば、左大臣が白河法皇に上奏し、院の意向が公卿議定に伝えられた後に関白が介入したことになるが、当時の官奏の手順から不自然感を免れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If such treatment mentioned in &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; was made, Kanpaku must have intervened after the will of Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa (after hearing the report from Sa-daijin) was told to the debating Kugyo, but it seemed unnatural by looking at how the politics proceeded at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the measures mentioned in the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; were carried out, the Kanpaku must have acted after Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa had heard the Sa-daijin&apos;s report and his wishes told to the Kugyo, but this would have been against the protocol of the time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;such treatment&quot;→&quot;the measures&quot;&quot;was made&quot;→&quot;were carried out&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;intervened&quot;→&quot;acted&quot;Changed word orderDeleted &quot;debating&quot;Reworded last clause</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the measures mentioned in the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; were carried out, the Kanpaku must have acted after Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa had heard the Sadaijin&apos;s report and his wishes told to the Kugyo, but this would have been against the protocol of the time.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>もしあったとすればその関白の息子である藤原師通がその変則介入を日記に書かないなどということがあるだろうか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this event was true, then why was it that FUJIWARA no Moromichi, the son of that Kanpaku, did not mention about such irregular procedure in his diary?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this event was true, then why was it that FUJIWARA no Moromichi, the son of that Kanpaku, did not mention such an irregular procedure in his diary?</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;about&quot;Added &quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this event was true, then why was it that FUJIWARA no Moromichi, the son of that Kanpaku, did not mention such an irregular procedure in his diary?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>安田元久の疑いはその点にも及んでいると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohisa YASUDA probably doubted concerning this issue as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohisa YASUDA&apos;s doubts probably stem from this issue.</e>
<cmt>&quot;probably doubted concerning this issue as well&quot;→&quot;&apos;s doubts probably stem from this issue&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohisa YASUDA&apos;s doubts probably stem from this issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="116">
<j>この件に関して、元木泰雄は1994年の『武士の成立』で、約１年を隔てた2件の事柄をまとめて編集してしまった可能性があると指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasuo MOTOKI argued in &quot;Bushi no Seiritsu&quot; (The establishment of Warriors) (1994) that there is a likeliness that they must have edited to condense two events that occurred within the span of a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuo MOTOKI, in &quot;Bushi no Seiritsu&quot; (The establishment of Warriors) (1994), argued that there is a likeliness that the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; was edited to condense two events that occurred within the span of a year.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&quot;they must have&quot;→&quot;&quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; was edited&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasuo MOTOKI, in &quot;Bushi no Seiritsu&quot; (The establishment of Warriors) (1994), argued that there is a likeliness that the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; was edited to condense two events that occurred within the span of a year.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>尚、以下は元木氏の指摘ではないが、『百錬抄』の編者の認識の誤りはこれだけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following was not pointed out by Mr. MOTOKI, but it was not the only one that the editor of &quot;Hyakuren-sho &quot;had misconception of past events.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mr. MOTOKI doesn&apos;t mention it, but this was not the only misconception the editor of the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; had.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The following was not pointed out by&quot;→&quot;doesn&apos;t mention it&quot;&quot;it&quot;→&quot;this&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mr. MOTOKI doesn&apos;t mention it, but this was not the only misconception the editor of the &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; had.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>もう一件は一次史料である複数の公卿の日記と相違している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second part was that &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; differed from the primary historical source of many kugyo diaries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; also differed from the primary historical source of many kugyo diaries.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;second part was that&quot;Added &quot;also&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Hyakuren-sho&quot; also differed from the primary historical source of many kugyo diaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="119">
<j>後三年の役の恩賞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Onsho (reward grants) of the Later Three Years&apos; War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Onsho (rewards) of the Later Three Years&apos; War</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;grants&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Onsho (rewards) of the Later Three Years&apos; War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>尚、後三年の役の勝利にも関わらず恩賞が与えられなかった点に関しては、本来朝廷の命令（官符）無しに合戦を起こすことは当時でも違法行為であり、合戦の途中においても「奥州合戦停止」の官使の派遣を決定したりしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not puzzling that Yoshiie was not rewarded despite facing the victory at the Later Three Years&apos; War since joining the battle without the imperial court consent was illegal at that time, and the ambassador for the &quot;Termination of the Battle at Oshu&quot; was assigned in the midst of the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding Yoshiie&apos;s failure to be rewarded despite victory in the Later Three Years&apos; War, engaging in battle without imperial consent was illegal at that time and an ambassador carrying the &quot;Termination of the Battle at Oshu&quot; order had been dispatched midway through the conflict.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It was not puzzling that&quot;→&quot;Regarding&quot;&quot;was not&quot;→&quot;failure to be&quot;Deleted &quot;facing the&quot;&quot;at&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;joining the&quot;→&quot;engaging in&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot; and &quot;court&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;an&quot;&quot;for&quot;→&quot;carrying&quot;Added &quot;order&quot;&quot;was assigned&quot;→&quot;had been dispatched&quot;&quot;in the midst of the battle&quot;→&quot;midway through the conflict&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding Yoshiie&apos;s failure to be rewarded despite victory in the Later Three Years&apos; War, engaging in battle without imperial consent was illegal at that time and an ambassador carrying the &quot;Termination of the Battle at Oshu&quot; order had been dispatched midway through the conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>従って追討の事後承認を求めたのに対して、これを拒否したのは不思議ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is believable that they rejected the plead for consent for subjugating the enemy after the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is not surprising that Yoshiie&apos;s post-conflict request for approval was rejected.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is not surprising that Yoshiie&apos;s post-conflict request for approval was rejected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="122">
<j>更に当時は「財貨」であるより以前に、朝廷の諸行事の装飾の貴重にして重要な材料であり、ほとんど陸奥からしか手に入らなかった砂金の「不貢金」を起こしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there was an issue of &quot;bu-kokin&quot; (Rejection of gold supply) of gold dust only available from Mutsu but was precious and scarce material applied on decorations used in imperial court ceremonies rather than as the &apos;commodity.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there was the issue of &quot;bu-kokin&quot; (lack of gold supply), with gold dust,which was more an important material for decorations used in imperial court ceremonies rather than a &apos;commodity,&apos; coming mostly only from Mutsu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;an&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Changed word order&quot;precious and scarce&quot;→&quot;important&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there was the issue of &quot;bu-kokin&quot; (lack of gold supply), with gold dust,which was more an important material for decorations used in imperial court ceremonies rather than a &apos;commodity,&apos; coming mostly only from Mutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>これは租税未収以上の、朝廷の諸行事に支障をきたす大問題であり、そのために朝廷の陣定で議題にあがっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This issue was greater than the unpaid tax problem for it hindered imperial court rituals and came up on political debate made in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This issue was greater than the unpaid tax problem for it hindered imperial court rituals and came up in political debate in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;on&quot;→&quot;in&quot;Deleted &quot;made&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This issue was greater than the unpaid tax problem for it hindered imperial court rituals and came up in political debate in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="124">
<j>受領の勤務評定である受領功過定を10年も通らなかったのは当時の制度にそった処置であり、義家だけがそうであった訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that Yoshiie did not pass the zuryo-kokka-sadame, which was a criteria required to receive estate from the imperial court, for ten years was a norm and went according to the policy back then, and not only Yoshiie was faced with that issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that Yoshiie did not pass the zuryo-kokka-sadame, which was required to receive estates from the imperial court, for ten years was a norm and in accordance with policy back then, and Yoshiie was not the only one faced with this problem.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;a criteria&quot;Added &apos;s&apos; to &quot;estate&quot;&quot;went according to&quot;→&quot;in accordance with&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;&quot;back then&quot;→&quot;at the time&quot;Deleted &quot;not only&quot;&quot;that issue&quot;→&quot;this problem&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that Yoshiie did not pass the zuryo-kokka-sadame, which was required to receive estates from the Imperial Court, for ten years was a norm and in accordance with policy back then, and Yoshiie was not the only one faced with this problem.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>白河院が院近臣であった国守を、受領功過定を経ずに同じ国でそのまま重任（他国に転ずるより利益は大きい）させようとしたのを藤原師通が猛反対して諦めさせたことまである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was up to the point where FUJIWARA no Moromichi greatly opposed and made Emperor Shirakawa stop trying to reappoint (more benefit than being reassigned to a different province) Yoshiie to Kokushu that was a minister position close to the emperor without passing the zuryo-kokka-sadame.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It reached the point where FUJIWARA no Moromichi fiercely opposed and finally halted Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s attempts to reappoint Yoshiie to Kokushu, a position close to the emperor, of the same province (of more benefit than reassigning him to a different province) without having passed the zuryo-kokka-sadame.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was up to&quot;→&quot;reachedmade Emperor Shirakawa stop trying&quot;→&quot;finally halted Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s attempts to&quot;Added &quot;of the same province&quot;Changed word orderDeleted &quot;minister&quot;&quot;passing&quot;→&quot;having passed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It reached the point where FUJIWARA no Moromichi fiercely opposed and finally halted Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s attempts to reappoint Yoshiie to the head of provincial governor, a position close to the emperor, of the same province (of more benefit than reassigning him to a different province) without having passed the zuryo-kokka-sadame.</e>
<cmt>head of provincial governorとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="126">
<j>その官物未進の決着に10年がかかるが、それがやっと完済できたのかどうかは記録が無いが、その合格は内大臣藤原宗忠の日記である中右記・承徳2年正月23日条には「件事依有院御気色也」、つまり白河法皇の意向であったことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took ten years to finalize the unpaid tax issue and although there is no written record of such completion, but the passing of zuryo-kokka-sadame was written on January 23, 1098 of the diary of FUJIWARA no Minetada, &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;things went in accordance with the emperor,&apos; indicating the support from the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>「件事依有院御気色也」→&apos;things went in accordance with the emperor&quot;と判断しました[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took ten years to finalize the unpaid tax issue and although there is no written record of its settlement, Yoshiie&apos;s passing of the zuryo-kokka-sadame is mentioned in the January 23, 1098 entry of FUJIWARA no Minetada&apos; diary &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;things went the Emperor&apos;s way,&apos; indicating it was the Emperor&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>&quot;such completion&quot;→&quot;its settlement&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;Yoshiie&apos;s&quot;&quot;was written on&quot;→&quot;is mentioned in the&quot;Added &quot;entry&quot;&quot;in accordance with the emperor&quot;→&quot;the Emperor&apos;s way&quot;&quot;the support from the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa&quot;→&quot;it was the Emperor&apos;s will&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took ten years to finalize the unpaid tax issue and although there is no written record of its settlement, Yoshiie&apos;s passing of the zuryo-kokka-sadame is mentioned in the January 23, 1098 entry of FUJIWARA no Minetada&apos; diary &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;things went the Emperor&apos;s way,&apos; indicating it was the Emperor&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>伝承の世界</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The World of Traditions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The World of Traditions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The World of Traditions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="127">
<j>前九年の役のとき、1057年（天喜5）11月に数百の死者を出し大敗した黄海の戦いで、僅か六騎となって逃れたが、その戦いの中で「将軍の長男義家、驍勇絶倫にして、騎射すること神の如し。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite the Battle of Kiumi of November 1057 during the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War caused several hundred casualties and only six cavalries escaped, Yoshiie within that battle was described as, &apos;the eldest son of shogun, Yoshiie, matchless by being strong and powerful, shot arrows from the back of the horse like gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Kiumi in November 1057 during the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War, in which several hundred men died and only six riders escaped, Yoshiie was described as, &apos;the eldest son of the shogun, Yoshiie, without equal in strength or bravery, shot arrows from the back of the horse like a god.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Despite&quot;→&quot;at&quot;&quot;on&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;caused&quot;→&quot;in which&quot;&quot;cavalries&quot;→&quot;riders&quot;Deleted &quot;within that battle&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;matchless by being strong and powerful&quot;→&quot;without equal in strength or bravery&quot;Made &quot;gods&quot; singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Kiumi in November 1057 during the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War, in which several hundred men died and only six riders escaped, Yoshiie was described as, &apos;the eldest son of the shogun, Yoshiie, without equal in strength or bravery, shot arrows from the back of the horse like a god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>白刀を冒し、重圍を突き、賊の左右 に出でて、大鏃の箭を以て、頻りに賊の師を射る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held the white blade, burst through the tight encirclement, merged right and left of the rebel, and shot frequently to the rebel leader with an arrow with huge arrow head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wielding his white sword, he burst through the tight encirclement, harried the enemy left and right, and repeatedly shot the enemy&apos;s leader with large-headed arrows.</e>
<cmt>&quot;He held the white blade&quot;→&quot;Wielding his white sword&quot;&quot;merged right and left of the rebel&quot;→&quot;harried the enemy left and right&quot;&quot;shot frequently to the rebel leader with an arrow with huge arrow head&quot;→&quot;repeatedly shot the enemy&apos;s leader with large-headed arrows&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wielding his white sword, he burst through the tight encirclement, harried the enemy left and right, and repeatedly shot the enemy&apos;s leader with large-headed arrows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>矢空しく発たず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He did not shoot needlessly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He did not waste a single arrow.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did not waste a single arrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>中たる所必ず斃れぬ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who were shot always fell to the ground.</e>
<cmt>中たる所必ず斃れぬ。→Those who were shot always fell to the ground.と判断しました。[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who were shot always fell to the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who were shot always fell to the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>雷の如く奔り、風の如く飛び、神武命世なり」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ran like a lightening, flew like winds and showed greatest military virtue of that time, similar to gods,&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He ran like the thunder, flew like the wind and showed greatest military virtue of that time, similar to gods,&apos;</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He ran like the thunder, flew like the wind and showed greatest military virtue of that time, similar to gods,&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>と『陸奥話記』にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">as written in &quot;Mutsuwa-ki&quot; (A Chronicle of the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">as written in &quot;Mutsuwa-ki&quot; (A Chronicle of the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">as written in &quot;Mutsuwa-ki&quot; (A Chronicle of the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="133">
<j>同じ『陸奥話記』には、その後、清原武則が「君が弓勢を試さんと欲す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same &quot;Mutsuwa-ki&quot; mentioned afterwards that KIYOHARA no Takenori said, &apos;I would like to see how much you can pull an arrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same &quot;Mutsuwa-ki&quot; mentioned that afterwards, KIYOHARA no Takenori said, &apos;I would like to see how well you can shoot an arrow.</e>
<cmt>&quot;much&quot;→&quot;well&quot;&quot;pull&quot;→&quot;shoot&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same &quot;Mutsuwa-ki&quot; mentioned that afterwards, KIYOHARA no Takenori said, &apos;I would like to see how well you can shoot an arrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>いかに」と問うと、義家は「善し」と。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Could you show it to me?&apos; to which Yoshiie replied, &apos;Certainly.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Could you show me?&apos; to which Yoshiie replied, &apos;Certainly.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;it to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Could you show me?&apos; to which Yoshiie replied, &apos;Certainly.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>そこで武則は「堅き甲（かぶと：と読むが鎧のことか）三領を重ねて、これを樹の枝に懸る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takenori piled three Japanese battle helmets and perched them on top of a tree branch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takenori piled three Japanese battle helmets on top of a tree branch.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takenori piled three Japanese battle helmets on top of a tree branch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>義家は一発にて甲三領を貫かせしむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiie pierced through three helmets with one shot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiie pierced through the three helmets with one shot.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiie pierced through the three helmets with one shot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>」武則は大いに驚いて「これ神明の変化なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takenori was greatly surprised and said, &quot;this must be the god transformed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takenori was greatly surprised and said, &quot;this must be a god transformed.</e>
<cmt>thea</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takenori was greatly surprised and said, &apos;this must be a god transformed.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>あに凡人の堪える所ならんや。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not a normal person can stand this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No normal person can compare.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Not a&quot;→&quot;No&quot;&quot;can stand this&quot;→&quot;compare&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No normal person can compare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>宜しく武士の為に帰伏する所、かくの如し」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an honor that they subjugate themselves under such bushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>宜しく武士の為に帰伏する所、かくの如し」。→It is an honor that they subjugate themselves under such bushi.&quot; と判断しました。[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an honor to surrender to such a bushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;that they subjugate themselves under&quot;→&quot;to surrender to&quot;Added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an honor to surrender to such a bushi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>と語ったという逸話がも残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such anecdote still remains on record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such anecdotes still remain on record.</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;s&apos; to &quot;anecdote&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such anecdotes still remain on record.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="141">
<j>義家が2歳のときに用いた「源太が産衣」という鎧と、生け捕った敵千人の首を髭ごと切ったことから「髭切」と名付けられた刀は、河内源氏嫡子に伝えられる宝となり、後の平治の乱では源頼朝が用いたという逸話が鎌倉時代初期の『平治物語』にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The armor which 2 years old Yoshiie carried, &quot;Genta ga Ubuginu&quot; (the baby clothes of Genta) and the katana (Japanese sword) called &quot;Hige kiri&quot; (beard cutter) that was named for cutting off the head with the beard of several thousand enemies captured alive, became the family treasure passed down the Kawachi Genji clan heir, and there is an anecdote in &quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Heiji) that Yoritomo MINAMOTO used it in Heiji-no-Ran (Heiji Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>源太→Genta [定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The armor which 2-year-old Yoshiie wore, &quot;Genta ga Ubuginu&quot; (the baby clothes of Genta), and the katana (Japanese sword) called &quot;Hige kiri&quot; (beard cutter) that was named for cutting off the bearded heads of a thousand prisoners, became treasures passed down to the Kawachi Genji clan heir, and there is an anecdote in the &quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Heiji) that Yoritomo MINAMOTO used it during the Heiji-no-Ran (Heiji Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the head with the beard of several thousand enemies captured alive&quot;→&quot;the bearded heads of a thousand prisoners&quot;Deleted &quot;the family&quot;Made &quot;treasure&quot; pluralAdded &quot;to&quot; and &quot;the&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;during the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The armor which 2-year-old Yoshiie wore, &apos;Genta ga Ubuginu&apos; (the baby clothes of Genta), and the katana (Japanese sword) called &apos;Hige kiri&apos; (beard cutter) that was named for cutting off the bearded heads of a thousand prisoners, became treasures passed down to the Kawachi-Genji clan heir, and there is an anecdote in the &quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Heiji) that Yoritomo MINAMOTO used it during the Heiji no ran (Heiji Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。ハイフン補足しました。ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>これは源頼朝が源氏の嫡流であると印象づけるための創作といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was probably created to give impression to others that Yoritomo MINAMOTO is from the official line of Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story was probably created to give the impression that Yoritomo MINAMOTO was descended from the official line of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;story&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;deleted &quot;to others&quot;&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was descended&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story was probably created to give the impression that Yoritomo MINAMOTO was descended from the official line of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="143">
<j>鎌倉時代中期の説話集『古今著聞集』には前九年の役の後、捕虜となったのち、家来とした（事実ではないが）安部宗任との話がいくつかあり、射芸に秀で、意味もなく動物を殺そうとしない優しさ、更に射た矢を取ってきたかつての敵・安部宗任に背中を向け、背負った矢入れに入れさせた剛胆さ、更には神通力まで備えた超人的な武士として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The collection of tales, &quot;Kokon chomon shu&quot; (Collected Stories of Ancient and Modern Times) written in the mid-Kamakura period, mentioned several conversation with ABE no Muneto, who was captured after the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War and became the servant (not based on truth), and portrayed Yoshiie as a supernatural warrior who excelled in archery, was kind not to unnecessarily kill animals, and was bold in the way that he turned to his back to his one-time enemy, ABE no Muneto, and let him insert arrows into the arrow holder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection of tales, &quot;Kokon chomon shu&quot; (Collected Stories of Ancient and Modern Times), written in the mid-Kamakura period, mentioned several conversations with ABE no Muneto, who was captured after the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War and became a servant (though this was not true), that portrayed Yoshiie as a supernatural warrior who excelled in archery, was kind to not unnecessarily kill animals, and was bold in the way that he turned to his back to his one-time enemy, ABE no Muneto, and let him insert arrows into the arrow holder.</e>
<cmt>Added commaAdded &apos;s&apos; to conversation&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;&quot;not based on truth&quot;→&quot;though this was not true&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection of tales, &quot;Kokon chomon shu&quot; (Collected Stories of Ancient and Modern Times), written in the mid-Kamakura period, mentioned several conversations with ABE no Muneto, who was captured after the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War and became a servant (though this was not true), that portrayed Yoshiie as a supernatural warrior who excelled in archery, was kind to not unnecessarily kill animals, and was bold in the way that he turned to his back to his one-time enemy, ABE no Muneto, and let him insert arrows into the arrow holder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="144">
<j>しかしその一方では以下のような伝承も残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the following folklore has been told on the other hand,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is also the following contrasting legend.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the following folklore has been told on the other hand&quot;→&quot;there is also the following contrasting legend&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is also the following contrasting legend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="145">
<j>京の義家の屋敷の近所の者が、ある夜に義家が鬼に引きずられて門を出て行く夢を見た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A neighbor of Yoshiie&apos;s Kyoto palace dreamed about Yoshiie being dragged out the gate by an oni (Japanese ogre).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A neighbor of Yoshiie&apos;s Kyoto residence dreamed about Yoshiie being dragged out the gate by an oni (Japanese ogre).</e>
<cmt>&quot;palace&quot;→&quot;residence&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A neighbor of Yoshiie&apos;s Kyoto residence dreamed about Yoshiie being dragged out the gate by an oni (Japanese ogre).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>そこで義家の屋敷を覗うと、屋敷の中では義家が死んだと大騒ぎになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the person visited the palace and saw a confusion within the palace that Yoshiie passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the person visited the residence and saw that it was in a tumult over Yoshiie&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>&quot;palace&quot;→&quot;residence&quot;&quot;a confusion within the palace that&quot;→&quot;that it was in a tumult over&quot;passed away&quot;→&quot;&apos;s death&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the person visited the residence and saw that it was in a tumult over Yoshiie&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>あれは義家が地獄に引きずられていくところだったに違いない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It must have been when Yoshiie was about to be dragged into hell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His dream must have been Yoshiie being dragged into hell.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It&quot;→&quot;His dream&quot;Deleted &quot;when&quot;&quot;was about to be&quot;→&quot;being&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His dream must have been Yoshiie being dragged into hell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="148">
<j>父頼義も殺生の罪人で、本来なら地獄に堕ちるべき人間である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Yoriyoshi was also the cruel criminal, and naturally a person who was supposed to go to hell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Yoriyoshi was also a cruel criminal who, by rights, should have gone to hell.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;&quot;and naturally a person who was supposed to go to hell&quot;→&quot;who, by rights, should have gone to hell&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Yoriyoshi was also a cruel criminal who, by rights, should have gone to hell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>前九年の役で切り落とした首は1万八千、その片耳を取り集めて、乾して皮古二合に入て上洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He collected one ear from each of eighteen thousand heads he beheaded in the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War, dried, and brought it to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>皮古二合→[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He collected one ear from each of the eighteen thousand heads he beheaded in the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War, dried them and brought them to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; and &quot;them&quot;&quot;it&quot;→&quot;them&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He collected one ear from each of the 18,000 heads he beheaded in the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War, dried them and brought them to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>しかし、後年仏門に入って、その耳を堂（京・六条坊門北の耳納堂）の土壇の下に埋めて弔い、自分の殺生を悔いたために最後は成仏できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoriyoshi entered the temple, and buried ears below the platform of (Mino-do, Rokujo-bomon (center street in Kyoto during Heian Period), Kyoto) and gave condolence to the dead and regretted his cruelty that he was able to enter Nirvana upon his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in his later years, Yoriyoshi entered the priesthood, buried the ears below a platform (known as Mino-do on Rokujo-bomon, the main street in Kyoto during Heian Period) and repenting his cruelty, was able to enter Nirvana upon his death.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;in his later years,&quot;&quot;temple&quot;→&quot;priesthood&quot;Deleted &quot;and&quot; and &quot;and gave condolence to the dead&quot;&quot;regretted&quot;→&quot;repenting&quot;deleted &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in his later years, Yoriyoshi entered the priesthood, buried the ears below a platform (known as Mino-do on Rokujo-bomon, the main street in Kyoto during Heian period) and repenting his cruelty, was able to enter Nirvana upon his death.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>しかし義家は罪も無い人を沢山殺して、それを悔いるところも無かったので無限地獄へ堕ちた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshiie killed many innocent people, and did not regret so he went to the infinite hell</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshiie killed many innocent people, and did not regret it so he went to the infinite hell</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;it&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshiie killed many innocent people, and did not regret it so he went to the infinite hell.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>（『古事談』）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Ko-jidan&quot; (Collection of Old Stories)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Ko-jidan&quot; (Collection of Old Stories)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Ko-jidan&quot; (Collection of Old Stories)).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="153">
<j>今様狂いの後白河天皇が編纂した『梁塵秘抄』巻第二にある「鷲の棲む深山には、概ての鳥は棲むものか、同じき源氏と申せども、八幡太郎は恐ろしや」はそのような言い伝えを反映しているものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chapter 2 of Volume 4 of &quot;Ryojinhi-sho&quot; (Song to Make the Dust Dance on the Beams) edited by Imayo-kurui (imayo (Japanese poem or songs during Heian Period) madness) Emperor Goshirakawa reflected on such tale, &apos;Should all birds live on the deep mountain where the eagle lives? Even if it&apos;s the same Minamoto clan, Hachiman-taro is somebody to be feared.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chapter 2 of &quot;Ryojinhi-sho&quot; (Songs to Make the Dust Dance on the Beams) edited by Emperor Goshirakawa, who loved the Imayo style of poems, reflected on such a tale, &apos;Should all birds live on the deep mountain where the eagle lives? Even if it&apos;s the same Minamoto clan, Hachiman-taro is somebody to be feared.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;volume 4&quot;- not in originaladded &apos;s&apos; to &quot;Song&quot;mayo-kurui (imayo &quot;(Japanese poem or songs during Heian Period) madness)&quot;→&quot;who loved the Imayo style of poems,&quot;Added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chapter 2 of &quot;Ryojinhi-sho&quot; (Songs to Make the Dust Dance on the Beams) edited by Emperor Goshirakawa, who loved the Imayo style of poems, reflected on such a tale, &apos;Should all birds live on the deep mountain where the eagle lives? Even if it&apos;s the same Minamoto clan, Hachimantaro is somebody to be feared.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Hachimantaro、ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="154">
<j>それらの伝承は平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけてのものであるが、同時代の藤原宗忠がその日記『中右記』に「故義家朝臣は年来武者の長者として多く無罪の人を殺すと云々。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These folktales were made from the end of Heian period to the early Kamakura period, but FUJIWARA no Minetada wrote in &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;the late Yoshiie Chosin killed many innocent people and etc. for being the wealthy bushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These folktales were made from the end of Heian period to the early Kamakura period and, though FUJIWARA no Minetada&apos;s entry in &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;the late Yoshiie Chosin was a wealthy bushi who killed many innocent people.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;&apos;s entry&quot;&quot;killed many innocent people and etc. for being the wealthy bush&quot;→&quot;was a wealthy bushi who killed many innocent people&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These folktales were made from the end of Heian period to the early Kamakura period and, though FUJIWARA no Minetada&apos;s entry in &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; &apos;the late Yoshiie Chosin was a wealthy bushi who killed many innocent people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>積悪の余り、遂に子孫に及ぶか」と記したことも合わせ考えると、それらの説話も、個々には事実ではあり得ないが、しかし当時の京の人間の義家観として、義家の実像の一面を伝えているようにもとれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The long built up evilness finally proclaimed the descendants,&apos; and other tales may not be true individually, but may have captured one aspect of Yoshiie viewed by Kyoto residents at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sins he built up have finally claimed his descendant,&apos; and other tales may not be true individually, they may have captured one aspect of Yoshiie as viewed by Kyoto residents at that time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The long built up evilness finally proclaimed the descendants&quot;→&quot;The sins he built up have finally claimed his descendant&quot;Added &quot;they&quot; and &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sins he built up have finally claimed his descendant,&apos; and other tales may not be true individually, they may have captured one aspect of Yoshiie as viewed by Kyoto residents at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="156">
<j>後三年の役が私戦とされて恩賞が出なかったため、義家は河内国石川荘の自分の私財を投じて部下の将士に報奨を与え、武家の棟梁としての信望を高めたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He supposedly increased his popularity as a warrior for casting aside his private property to award his generals when he himself was not rewarded for the Late Three Years&apos; War being considered as a private war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there was no reward for the Later Three Years&apos; War due to it being considered a private war, he is said to have awarded his own property to his men, thereby enhancing his popularity as a warrior</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there was no reward for the Later Three Years&apos; War due to it being considered a private war, he is said to have awarded his own property to his men, thereby enhancing his popularity as a warrior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>ただし平安時代末期の『奥州後三年記』にはその記述はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &quot;Oshu-gosannen-ki&quot; written during the end of Heian Period did not record such event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the &quot;Oshu-gosannen-ki,&quot; written at the end of Heian Period, did not record such an event.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; and commas&quot;during&quot;→&quot;at&quot;Added &quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the &quot;Oshu-gosannen-ki,&quot; written at the end of Heian period, did not record such an event.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>後世では、東国における武門の習いは義家が整備したといわれ、その名声は武門の棟梁としての血脈としての評価を一層高めることとなったというのは、主に南北朝時代の末に、義家の子孫である足利幕府の正統性をうたう為に書かれた『源威集』にある「諸家輩、源家将軍ヲ代々仁王ト奉仰ハ此故也」からの派生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later generations claimed that, the way of bushi in Eastern Japan was established by Yoshiie, and increased the reputation as the bloodline of the chief of the bushi perhaps due to &quot;Geni-shu&quot; written to legitimize the Ashikaga shogunate created by the descendant of Yoshiie during the end of the Nanboku period (the period of Northern and Southern Court).</e>
<cmt>諸家輩、源家将軍ヲ代々仁王ト奉仰ハ此故→[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later generations claimed that the Way of the Bushi in Eastern Japan was established by Yoshiie, and that the increased reputation from a blood connection to the chief of the bushi was derived from a phrase in the &quot;Geni-shu,&quot; written to legitimize the Ashikaga shogunate created by the descendants of Yoshiie during the end of the Nanboku (Northern and Southern Court) period.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later generations claimed that the Way of the Bushi in Eastern Japan was established by Yoshiie, and that the increased reputation from a blood connection to the chief of the bushi was derived from a phrase in the &quot;Geni-shu,&quot; written to legitimize the Ashikaga shogunate created by the descendants of Yoshiie during the end of the Nanboku (Northern and Southern Court) period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="159">
<j>足利氏に伝わる伝承としては、「われ七代の孫に生まれ代わりて天下を取るべし」という八幡殿（義家）の置き文が足利家に伝わったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story handed down the Ashikaga clan is the letter written by Hachiman-dono (Lord Hachiman (Yoshiie)), &quot;the son of seven generation after me must conquer entire Japan in place of me.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story handed down through the Ashikaga clan is that a letter written by Hachiman-dono (Lord Hachiman - Yoshiie) stated, &quot;the son of the seventh generation after me must conquer the entire nation in my placee.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;through&quot; and &quot;that&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;Added &quot;stated&quot;, &quot;the&quot;, &quot;th&quot;&quot;entire Japan in place of me&quot;→&quot;the entire nation in my place&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story handed down through the Ashikaga clan is that a letter written by Hachiman-dono (Lord Hachiman - Yoshiie) stated, &quot;the son of the seventh generation after me must conquer the entire nation in my place.&quot;</e>
<cmt>placeスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>義家から七代目にあたる足利家時は、自分の代では達成できないため、三代後の子孫に天下を取らせよと祈願し、願文を残して自害したと『難太平記』にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nan-taihei-ki&quot; mentioned that the Ietoki Ashikaga, who was seventh generation son since Yoshii, could not achieve it during his lifetime, so he wished three generation after him to conquer Japan in a letter and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nan-taihei-ki&quot; mentioned that Ietoki Ashikaga, who was the seventh generation son after Yoshii, could not achieve it during his lifetime, so, in a letter, he wished the third generation after him would conquer Japan and then committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;since&quot;→&quot;after&quot;Changed word orderAdded&quot;the&quot;&quot;to&quot;→&quot;would&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nan-taihei-ki&quot; mentioned that Ietoki ASHIKAGA, who was the seventh generation son after Yoshiie, could not achieve it during his lifetime, so, in a letter, he wished the third generation after him would conquer Japan and then committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>ASHIKAGA大文字にしました。Yoshiieのe補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>足利尊氏が北条氏打倒に立ち上がったのは、家時から三代後の子孫としてそれを見せられたからであり、『難太平記』の著者今川了俊も、自分もそれを見たと記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why Takauji ASHIKAGA rose up to defeat Hojo clan was because he had to prove as the third generation person since Ietoki, and Sadayo IMAGAWA, the author of &quot;Nan-taihei-ki,&quot; claimed that he saw it too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why Takauji ASHIKAGA rose up to defeat the Hojo clan was because he had to prove himsef as the third generation since Ietoki, and Sadayo IMAGAWA, the author of &quot;Nan-taihei-ki,&quot; claimed that he saw it too.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; and &quot;himself&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why Takauji ASHIKAGA rose up to defeat the Hojo clan was because he had to prove himself as the third generation since Ietoki, and Sadayo IMAGAWA, the author of &quot;Nan-taihei-ki,&quot; claimed that he saw it too.</e>
<cmt>himselfスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>しかし、義家の時代に「天下を取る」というような概念は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there was no notion during Yoshiie&apos;s time to conquer Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there was no notion during Yoshiie&apos;s time of conquering Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;to conquer&quot;→&quot;of conquering&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there was no notion during Yoshiie&apos;s time of conquering Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="163">
<j>義家の名声を恐れた白河天皇や、摂関家の陰謀によって、河内源氏は凋落していったとされるのは主に戦後である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The notion that the decline of the Kawachi Minamoto clan was lead by Emperor Shirakawa who feared the popularity of Yoshiie and the conspiracy of Sekkan-ke formed after the World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea that the decline of the Kawachi Minamoto clan was due to Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s fear of Yoshiie&apos;s popularity and the conspiracy of the Sekkan-ke formed after the World War II.</e>
<cmt>&quot;lead by&quot;→&quot;due to&quot;&quot;who feared the popularity of Yoshiie and the conspiracy of&quot;→&quot;&apos;s fear of Yoshiie&apos;s popularity and the conspiracy of the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea that the decline of the Kawachi-Genji was due to Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s fear of Yoshiie&apos;s popularity and the conspiracy of the Sekkan-ke formed after the World War II.</e>
<cmt>Kawachi-Genji、前出にあわせ訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>現在研究者の間では本稿で紹介したような見直しが行われているが、ネット上ではその陰謀説はいまだに非常に根強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present historians are currently making adjustments mentioned in this article, but such conspiracy theory is still widely discussed across internet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present historians are currently making the adjustments mentioned in this article, but such conspiracy theories are still widely discussed across internet.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Made theory plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present historians are currently making the adjustments mentioned in this article, but such conspiracy theories are still widely discussed across internet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="165">
<j>尚、「天下第一武勇の士」と評したのは白河天皇と書いてあるサイトがネット上に散見されるが、前述の通り藤原宗忠の日記『中右記』10月23日条である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are web sites which mention that, &apos;the only and the best bushi of the emperor&apos; was commented by Emperor Shirakawa, but it was actually from the diary of FUJIWARA no Minetada, &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; dated October 23, 1098.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are web sites which mention that, &apos;the Emperor&apos;s best and bravest bushi&apos; was written by Emperor Shirakawa, but it was actually from the diary of FUJIWARA no Minetada, &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; dated October 23, 1098.</e>
<cmt>Changed quote&quot;commented&quot;→&quot;written&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are web sites which mention that, &apos;the Emperor&apos;s best and bravest bushi&apos; was written by Emperor Shirakawa, but it was actually from the diary of FUJIWARA no Minetada, &quot;Chuyu-ki,&quot; dated October 23, 1098.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>和歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="166">
<j>吹く風をなこその関と思へども道もせに散る山桜かな</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuku kaze wo nakosono seki to omoe domo michimoseni chiru yamazakura kana (Since it is called as nakoso no seki (&quot;do not come&quot; seki (checkpoint)), I thought it applied to winds as well, but there are many cherry petals scattered across, enough to block the path.)</e>
<cmt>なこ→do not come [http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/144473/m0u/なこ/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuku kaze wo nakosono seki to omoe domo michimoseni chiru yamazakura kana (Since it is called nakoso no seki (&quot;do not come&quot; checkpoint), I thought it applied to winds as well, but there are many cherry petals scattered across, enough to block the path.)</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;as&quot;, Japanese and brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuku kaze wo nakosono seki to omoe domo michimoseni chiru yamazakura kana (Since it is called nakoso no seki (&quot;do not come&quot; checkpoint), I thought it applied to winds as well, but there are many cherry petals scattered across, enough to block the path.)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>勅撰和歌集の一つである『千載和歌集』に収録されており、「陸奥国にまかりける時、勿来の関にて花の散りければよめる」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was included in &quot;Senzai-wakashu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years), one of the &quot;Chokusen Wakashu&quot; (Collection of waka edited by the order of active and retired emperor), &apos;mutsu-no-kuni ni makarikeru toki, nakoso no seki nite hana no chiri kereba yomeru&apos; (You can understand when you ride to Nakoso checkpoint in Mutsu-no-kuni and kick up scattered flowers).</e>
<cmt>「陸奥国にまかりける時、勿来の関にて花の散りければよめる」→&quot;mutsu-no-kuni ni makarikeru toki, nakoso no seki nite hana no chiri kereba yomeru&apos; (You can understand when you ride to Nakoso checkpoint in Mutsu-no-kuni and kick up scattered)&quot;と判断しました[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Included in &quot;Senzai-wakashu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years), one of the &quot;Chokusen Wakashu&quot; collection of waka compiled for the emperor, &apos;mutsu-no-kuni ni makarikeru toki, nakoso no seki nite hana no chiri kereba yomeru&apos; (You can understand when you ride to Nakoso checkpoint in Mutsu-no-kuni and kick up scattered flowers).</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;it was&quot;&quot;edited by the order of active and retired&quot;→&quot;compiled for the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Included in &quot;Senzai-wakashu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years), one of the &quot;Chokusen Wakashu&quot; collection of waka compiled for the emperor, &apos;mutsu-no-kuni ni makarikeru toki, nakoso no seki nite hana no chiri kereba yomeru&apos; (You can understand when you ride to Nakoso checkpoint in Mutsu Province and kick up scattered flowers).</e>
<cmt>Mutsu Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="168">
<j>落ち行く敵を呼び止めて　“衣のたては綻びにけり”　敵は見返り　”年を経し　糸の乱れの苦しさに”　つけたることのめでたさに、めでてゆるししやさしさよ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Calling to escaping lost enemy, &quot;Clothes are falling apart,&quot; to which the enemy turned around and added, &quot;By accumulating years, strings suffer from disturbance,&quot; which pleased me, and in kindness, forgave him.</e>
<cmt>落ち行く敵を呼び止めて　“衣のたては綻びにけり”　敵は見返り　”年を経し　糸の乱れの苦しさに”　つけたることのめでたさに、めでてゆるししやさしさよ。→Calling to escaping lost enemy, &quot;Clothes are falling apart,&quot; to which the enemy turned around and added, &quot;By accumulating years, strings suffer from disturbance,&quot; which pleased me, and in kindness, forgave him.[http://www.geocities.jp/ktmchi/rekisi/cys_50.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Calling to the fleeing enemy, &quot;Your clothes are falling apart,&quot; to which the enemy turned around and added, &quot;Over the years the threads become entangled and this pains me,&quot; which pleased me, and in kindness, I forgave him.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;your&quot;Changed 2nd quoteAdded &quot;I&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Calling to the fleeing enemy, &quot;Your clothes are falling apart,&quot; to which the enemy turned around and added, &quot;Over the years the threads become entangled and this pains me,&quot; which pleased me, and in kindness, I forgave him.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="169">
<j>戦前の軍国主義華やかりし頃、大正元年・小学校唱歌「八幡太郎」に織り込まれた義家の歌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the song of Yoshiie applied to elementary school song in 1912 before the World War, the time when militarism flourished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was an elementary school song from 1912, when militarism was rife, that incorporates one of Yoshiie&apos;s tanka.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was an elementary school song from 1912, when militarism was rife, that incorporates one of Yoshiie&apos;s tanka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="170">
<j>「敵」とは安倍貞任で、衣川関を捨てて敗走する安倍貞任を追う源義家が、矢を番えながら下の句を歌いかけると、貞任は即座にその上の句を返したので、義家は感じいって「武士の情け」と、矢を放つのを止めたという話。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the tale where Minamoto no Yoshiie chased after the &quot;enemy,&quot; Sadato ABE, who abandoned and escaped from Koromogawa Seki (castle) and called out the lower line while aiming the arrow, to which, Sadato immediately shot back the top line of the song, so Yoshiie didn&apos;t shoot him due to the &quot;sympathy of bushi (warrior).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the tale where Minamoto no Yoshiie chased after the &quot;enemy,&quot; Sadato ABE, who abandoned and escaped from Koromogawa Seki (castle) and called out the lower line while aiming the arrow, to which, Sadato immediately shot back the top line of the song, so Yoshiie didn&apos;t shoot him due to the &quot;sympathy of bushi (warrior).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the tale where Minamoto no Yoshiie chased after the &quot;enemy,&quot; Sadato ABE, who abandoned and escaped from Koromogawa Seki (castle) and called out the lower line while aiming the arrow, to which, Sadato immediately shot back the top line of the song, so Yoshiie didn&apos;t shoot him due to the &quot;sympathy of bushi (warrior).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>中世の説話集『古今著聞集』にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was quoted from the collection of tales from the medieval era, &quot;Kokon chomon shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was quoted in the collection of tales from the medieval era, &quot;Kokon chomon shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;from&quot;→&quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was quoted in the collection of tales from the medieval era, &quot;Kokon chomon shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>ただし江戸時代に水戸光圀が編纂させた『大日本史』の段階から「疑ふらくは、和歌者流好事家の所為に出でしなり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was written in &quot;Dai-Nihon shi (A History of Great Japan)&quot; edited by Mitsukuni MITO in Edo Period, &quot;it was probably created by the Waka lovers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;Dai-Nihon shi (A History of Great Japan)&quot; edited by Mitsukuni MITO in Edo Period, comments that &quot;it was probably created by Waka lovers.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;it was written in&quot; Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &quot;Dai-Nihon shi&quot; (A History of Great Japan) edited by Mitsukuni MITO in Edo period, comments that &quot;it was probably created by Waka lovers.</e>
<cmt>括弧書きを&quot;の外にしました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>故に今、取らず。」とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, I do not accept it.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, I do not accept it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, I do not accept it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="174">
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>鎌倉幕府を開いた源頼朝は、義家のひ孫にあたる源義朝の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo MINAMOTO who established the Kamakura bakufu is the son of Yoshitomo MINAMOTO, who is the great-great-grandson of Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo MINAMOTO, who established the Kamakura bakufu, was the son of Yoshitomo MINAMOTO, who was the great-great-grandson of Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo MINAMOTO, who established the Kamakura bakufu, was the son of Yoshitomo MINAMOTO, who was the great-great-grandson of Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="176">
<j>室町幕府を開いた足利尊氏（源尊氏）は、義家の三男の源義国の次男の足利義康（源義康）の子孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takuji ASHIKAGA (MINAMOTO no Takuji), who established Muromachi bakufu is the descendant of the second son of the third son of Yoshiie, Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA (MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takuji ASHIKAGA (also known as MINAMOTO no Takuji), who established the Muromachi bakufu was the descendant of the second son of Yoshiie&apos;s third son, Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA (also known as MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;also known as&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takuji ASHIKAGA (also known as MINAMOTO no Takuji), who established the Muromachi bakufu was the descendant of the second son of Yoshiie&apos;s third son, Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA (also known as MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="177">
<j>南朝方の新田義貞（源義貞）は、同じく源義国の長男の新田義重（源義重）の子孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshisada NITTA (MINAMOTO no Yoshisada) of Nan-cho (the Southern Dynasty) is the descendant of the eldest son of the same MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu, Yoshishige NITTA (MINAMOTO no Yoshishige).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshisada NITTA (also known as MINAMOTO no Yoshisada) of the Southern Dynasty (Nan-cho) was the descendant of the eldest son of the same MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu, Yoshishige NITTA (also known asMINAMOTO no Yoshishige).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;also known as&quot;&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshisada NITTA (also known as MINAMOTO no Yoshisada) of the Southern Court (Nan-cho) was the descendant of the eldest son of the same MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu, Yoshishige NITTA (also known as MINAMOTO no Yoshishige).</e>
<cmt>DynastyをCourtに訂正しました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="178">
<j>河内源氏氏神の壷井八幡宮の宮司の高木氏は、義家の五男の源義時の子孫という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mr. Takagi, the chief priest of the Shinto Shrine at Tsuboi-hachiman-gu Shrine for the clan deity of Kawachi Minamoto, is the descendant of the fifth child of Yoshiie, MINAMOTO no Yoshitoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mr. Takagi, the chief priest of the Shinto Shrine at Tsuboi-hachiman-gu Shrine for the clan deity of Kawachi Minamoto, is a descendant of the fifth child of Yoshiie, MINAMOTO no Yoshitoki.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mr. Takagi, the chief priest of the Shinto Shrine at Tsuboi Hachiman-gu Shrine for the clan deity of Kawachi-Genji, is a descendant of the fifth child of Yoshiie, MINAMOTO no Yoshitoki.</e>
<cmt>Tsuboi Hachiman-guに訂正しました。Kawachi-Genji、前出にあわせ訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave site</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grave site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grave site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="179">
<j>河内源氏の本拠地だった大阪府羽曳野市壷井に楼門だけが残る源氏の氏寺の通法寺跡近くに、祖父の頼信、父の頼義と供にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located near the Tsuho-ji Temple, where only the gate remains, in Tsuboi, Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture of the headquarter of the Kawachi Genji along with his grandfather Yorinobu and his father Yoriyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave, along with his grandfather Yorinobu&apos;s and his father Yoriyoshi&apos;s, is located near the Tsuho-ji Temple, of which only the gate remains, in Tsuboi, Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture, the headquarters of the Kawachi Genji.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;His grave&quot;Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave, along with his grandfather Yorinobu&apos;s and his father Yoriyoshi&apos;s, is located near the Tsuho-ji Temple, of which only the gate remains, in Tsuboi, Habikino City, Osaka Prefecture, the headquarters of the Kawachi-Genji.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sat666(id:127263), Bakkai(id:7233), Nnh(id:474), Πrate(id:11329), Cprobot(id:97843), Tetsu9(id:14553), 味っ子(id:17086), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Andee(id:20421), Ultratomio(id:1090), 星組背番号10(id:19983), 沢田(id:40580), Robert De Smith(id:28533), でここ(id:9565), １３２人目(id:18687), Typocorrecter(id:170180), 俊(id:14924), 代言人(id:33675), NPD(id:58640), 怪蘇(id:45514), UMBRO(id:100484), Ktmchi(id:113301), Khhy(id:13490), 阿波座行広(id:39667), ととりん(id:31982), DOERAX(id:25212), Law soma(id:45202), 松茸(id:27535), Sat.K(id:3751), 葉月(id:25674), 小者(id:172526), MDR-SK(id:192066), Carkuni(id:79281), 海衛士(id:19229), M.O.Sumeragi(id:55846), Junger(id:10282), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>