<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>廬井鯨</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IOI no Kujira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IOI no Kujira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IOI no Kujira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>廬井 鯨（いおい の くじら、生没年不明）は、日本の飛鳥時代の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IOI no Kujira (廬井 鯨, date of birth and death unknown) is a Japanese who lived in Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IOI no Kujira (date of birth and death unknown) lived during the Asuka period of Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IOI no Kujira (date of birth and death unknown) lived during the Asuka period of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>旧仮名遣いでの読みは「いほゐのくぢら」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It reads &apos;IHOI no Kujira&apos; in old Japanese syllabary characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the old Japanese syllabary characters, it is considered that his name had been pronounced as &apos;Ifowi no Kudira.&apos;</e>
<cmt>飛鳥時代はf,w,dが発音されていたので「Ifowi no Kudira」となります。オリジナル著者がこの文章を入れたのは発音の違いを示したかったためです。「旧仮名遣いでの」という言い方はとても変で、この著者以外には使わないと思いますが、正確に訳すと左のようになります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the old Japanese syllabary characters, it is considered that his name had been pronounced as &apos;Ifowi no Kudira.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>姓（カバネ）は造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) is Miyatsuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His kabane (hereditary title) was Miyatsuko.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) was Miyatsuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>672年の壬申の乱のとき、大友皇子（弘文天皇）側の別将となり、大和の古道で戦って敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Jinshin War in 672, he was an another commander of the troops from OTOMO no Oji (Emperor Kobun) and lost when he fought on Yamato no kodo (the ancient paths in Yamato Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jinshin War of 672, he became Suke-no-Ikusanokimi (assistant commander) of the army of Otomo no Miko (Prince Otomo who has been called Emperor Kobun after the Meiji period); he fought at the old road of Yamato and lost.</e>
<cmt>固有名詞読み間違い、「別将」は「すけのいくさのきみ」、「古道」は固有名詞ではなく、特に重要な言葉でもないので普通に訳します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Jinshin War of 672, he became Suke-no-Ikusanokimi (assistant commander) of the army of Otomo no Miko (Prince Otomo who has been called Emperor Kobun after the Meiji period); he fought at the old road of Yamato and lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>廬井氏（五百井氏）は、近江国栗太郡廬井を本拠とする氏族とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ioi clan (Ionoi clan) had their headquarter in Ioi, Kurita gun, Omi-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ioi clan (written as 廬井氏 or 五百井氏) was a family having their base in Ioi, Kurumoto County, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミス、固有名詞読み間違いがあります。「栗太」は「くるもと」、登録単語は間違いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ioi clan (written as 廬井氏 or 五百井氏) was a family having their base in Ioi, Kurumoto County, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>壬申の乱勃発時に廬井鯨がどのような地位にあったかは不明だが、大友皇子（弘文天皇）の側の将犬養五十君が倭（大和国）の敵軍に向けて南に進んだとき、その別将であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s not sure in which rank IOI no Kujira was when the Jinshin War broke out, however, he was an another commander when INUKAI no Ikimi, a commander of the troops from Otomo no Oji (Emperor Kobun), moved south toward the enemy in Wa (Yamato Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rank of IOI no Kujira at the outbreak of the Jinshin War is unknown, however, he was Suke-no-Ikusanokimi when INUKAI no Ikimi, Ikusanokimi (commander) of the army of Otomo no Miko (Emperor Kobun), advanced south to capture Yamato (Yamato Province) the enemy&apos;s troops had camped.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミス、固有名詞読み間違いがあります。「倭」は「やまと」。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rank of IOI no Kujira at the outbreak of the Jinshin War is unknown, however, he was Suke-no-Ikusanokimi when INUKAI no Ikimi, Ikusanokimi (commander) of the army of Otomo no Miko (Emperor Kobun), advanced south to capture Yamato (Yamato Province) the enemy&apos;s troops had camped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>五十君は、村屋まで進んで陣営を置き、鯨に200の精兵を率いさせ、敵将大伴吹負の本営を衝かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isokimi charged forward to Muraya, set up the camp, and made Kujira lead two hundreds soldiers to attack the headquarters of OTOMO no Fukei, the enemy general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikimi advanced to Muraya and built a camp, and ordered Kujira lead two hundreds selected soldiers to attack the main camp of commander OTOMO no Fukei who was supporting the enemy&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikimi advanced to Muraya and built a camp, and ordered Kujira lead two hundreds selected soldiers to attack the main camp of commander OTOMO no Fukei who was supporting the enemy&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鯨の部隊は少数だったが、そのときは吹負の周りの兵力も少なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though there were not so many soldiers in Kujira&apos;s troop, Fukei didn&apos;t have many neither around him at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Kujira&apos;s troop was not formed of a lot of soldiers, Fukei also didn&apos;t have many soldiers there at that time.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Kujira&apos;s troop was not formed of a lot of soldiers, Fukei also didn&apos;t have many soldiers there at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、鯨の軍の前進は徳麻呂らが射る矢でとどめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kujira&apos;s troop couldn&apos;t go forward because of arrows shot by Tokomaro&apos;s troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Kujira&apos;s troop could not go further because the Fukei&apos;s soldiers including Tokomaro fought back with arrows.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Kujira&apos;s troop could not go further because the Fukei&apos;s soldiers including Tokomaro fought back with arrows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そうするうちに、大和の古道にあった味方の左翼が破れ、そこから三輪高市麻呂と置始菟の敵部隊が転じて来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Over time, their left wing fighting in Yamato no kodo lost, and this caused the attack from enemy troop led by MIWA no Takechimaro and OKISOME no Usagi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the battle, the left wing of the Otomo no Miko&apos;s army (which Kujira had been supporting) was defeated at the old roads of Yamato, and from there, the enemy&apos;s troops led by MIWA no Takechimaro and OKISOME no Usagi came to join the battle at the Fukei&apos;s camp.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the battle, the left wing of the Otomo no Miko&apos;s army (which Kujira had been supporting) was defeated at the old roads of Yamato, and from there, the enemy&apos;s troops led by MIWA no Takechimaro and OKISOME no Usagi came to join the battle at the Fukei&apos;s camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>鯨の部隊は背後に敵をうけて敗走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kujira&apos;s troop took flight due to the enemy behind them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kujira&apos;s troop was attacked by those enemy&apos;s troops from behind, and ran away.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kujira&apos;s troop was attacked by those enemy&apos;s troops from behind, and ran away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>鯨もまた白馬に乗って逃げたが、馬が泥田にはまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kujira also rode away on a white horse, but the horse got stuck in the mud.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kujira also ran away on a white horse, however the horse got stuck in the mud of a field.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kujira also ran away on a white horse, however the horse got stuck in the mud of a field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>吹負はこれを見て、甲斐の勇者に「あの白馬に乗る者は廬井鯨だ。急いで追って射よ」と命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukei saw this and ordered a brave man from Kai Province, &apos;That man on the white horse is IOI no Kujira. Go after him right away and shoot him.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukei saw him and ordered a brave man from Kai Province, &apos;That man on the white horse is IOI no Kujira. Go after him right away and shoot him.&apos;</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukei saw him and ordered a brave man from Kai Province, &apos;That man on the white horse is IOI no Kujira. Go after him right away and shoot him.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>甲斐の勇者が近づくと、鯨は急いで馬に鞭を打った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the brave man came closer, Kujira whipped his horse quickly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the brave man came closer, Kujira whipped his horse quickly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the brave man came closer, Kujira whipped his horse quickly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>馬は泥田から抜け出し、逃げることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The horse got out of the mud and he could ride away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The horse got out of the mud and he could ride away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The horse got out of the mud and he could ride away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後の鯨について知られることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobody knows what happened to Kujira after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There remain no records about Kujira after that.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。「知られることはない」は「記録、書物による情報がない」という意味です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There remain no records about Kujira after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nevylax(id:38464), Kinori(id:443), 水野白楓(id:22811), Ktoetx(id:104437), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>