<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中御門経之</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneyuki NAKAMIKADO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneyuki NAKAMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneyuki NAKAMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中御門 経之（なかみかど つねゆき、文政3年12月17日 (旧暦)(1821年1月20日) - 明治24年(1891年)8月27日）は、幕末期の公卿にして明治期の華族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneyuki NAKAMIKADO (January 20, 1821-August 27, 1891) was Kugyo (the top court officials) in the end of the Edo period and the peerage in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneyuki NAKAMIKADO (January 20, 1821-August 27, 1891) was Kugyo (the top court officials) in the end of the Edo period and a peerage in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneyuki NAKAMIKADO (January 20, 1821-August 27, 1891) was Kugyo (the top court officials) in the end of the Edo period and a peerage in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>坊城俊明の五男として生まれるが、中御門資文の養嗣子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the fifth son of Toshiaki BOJO and became an adoptive heir of Sukefumi NAKAMIKADO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the fifth son of Toshiaki BOJO and became the adoptive heir of Sukefumi NAKAMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the fifth son of Toshiaki BOJO and became the adoptive heir of Sukefumi NAKAMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>麝香間祗候、大納言、留守長官等を歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held positions such as Jako no ma shiko (emperor&apos;s personal attendant in Jako room), Dainagon (Major Counselor) and rusu chokan (a person representing the chief officer during his absence).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held positions such as Jako no ma shiko (emperor&apos;s personal attendant in Jako room), Dainagon (Major Counselor) and rusu chokan (a person representing the chief officer during his absence).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held positions such as Jako no ma shiko (emperor&apos;s personal attendant in Jako room), Dainagon (chief councilor of state) and rusu chokan (a person representing the chief officer during his absence).</e>
<cmt>Dainagon (Major Counselor)→Dainagon (chief councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>位階・勲等・爵位は、従一位・勲一等・侯爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His ranks and orders were Juichii (Junior First Rank), the First Order of Merit and marquis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rank, order and peerage were Juichii (Junior First Rank), the First Order of Merit and marquis respectively.</e>
<cmt>「爵位」を補完、理解しやすいようrespectivelyを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rank, order and peerage were Juichii (Junior First Rank), the First Order of Merit and marquis respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>妻は堀河康親の娘・富子（岩倉具視の実姉）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was Tomiko, a daughter of Yasuchika HORIKAWA (an elder sister of Tomomi IWAKURA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was Tomiko, a daughter of Yasuchika HORIKAWA (an elder sister of Tomomi IWAKURA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was Tomiko, a daughter of Yasuchika HORIKAWA (an elder sister of Tomomi IWAKURA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>安政5年（1858年）に通商条約勅許問題が起こると、88人の反対グループ（廷臣八十八卿）の一人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When an issue on the imperial sanction for the Treaty of commerce began to be discussed in 1858, he was against it as a member of the opposing group of 88 retainers (Teishin hachiju-hachi kyo [88 retainers of Imperial Court]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When an issue on the imperial sanction for the Treaty of commerce arose in 1858, he was against it as a member of the opposing group of 88 retainers (Teishin hachiju-hachi kyo [88 retainers of Imperial Court]).</e>
<cmt>動詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When an issue on the imperial sanction for the Treaty of commerce arose in 1858, he was against it as a member of the opposing group of 88 retainers (Teishin hachiju-hachi kyo [88 retainers of Imperial Court]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>文久3年（1863年）、孝明天皇の石清水八幡宮行幸を共にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863 he followed the Emperor Komei&apos;s gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out) to the Iwashimizuhachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863 he followed the Emperor Komei&apos;s gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out) to Iwashimizuhachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1863 he followed the Emperor Komei&apos;s gyoko (Emperor&apos;s going out) to Iwashimizuhachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかしその後、岩倉具視と手を結んで討幕派公卿の一人となり、慶応2年（1866年）には佐幕派であった関白の二条斉敬と中川宮朝彦親王を弾劾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after that, he became one of the Kugyo of anti-Shogunate group with Totomi IWAKURA and impeached Nariyuki NIJO, the chief adviser to the Emperor, and the Imperial prince Nakagawa no miya Asahiko who were Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun) in 1866.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he became one of the Kugyo of anti-Shogunate group with Tomomi IWAKURA and impeached Nariyuki NIJO, the chief adviser to the Emperor, and Imperial prince Nakagawa no miya Asahiko who were Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun) in 1866.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス訂正、冠詞削除、後列との兼ね合いでHowever削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he became one of the Kugyo of anti-Shogunate group with Tomomi IWAKURA and impeached Nariyuki NIJO, the chief adviser to the Emperor, and Imperial prince Nakagawa no miya Asahiko who were Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun) in 1866.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>ところがこのため、親王を厚く信任していた孝明天皇の怒りを買うこととなり、閉門処分に処せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, for this reason he faced the wrath of the Emperor Komei who deeply relied on the Imperial Prince and was punished with house confinement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, for this reason he faced the wrath of Emperor Komei who deeply relied on the Imperial Prince and was punished with house confinement.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, for this reason he faced the wrath of Emperor Komei who deeply relied on the Imperial Prince and was punished with house confinement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同年末、孝明天皇が崩御し、睦仁親王（後の明治天皇）が践祚された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end of the same year, the Emperor Komei died and the Imperial Prince Mutsuhito (later the Emperor Meiji) ascended to the throne.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end of the same year, Emperor Komei died and Imperial Prince Mutsuhito (later Emperor Meiji) ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除、to削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end of the same year, Emperor Komei died and Imperial Prince Mutsuhito (later Emperor Meiji) ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後に罪を許されて宮中に復帰する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he was forgiven and returned to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he was pardoned and returned to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>動詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he was pardoned and returned to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後は討幕の密勅作成などに参加し、慶応3年（1867年）12月の王政復古 (日本)とともに議定に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he joined the meeting for the secret Imperial command of attacking the shogunate and was assigned to gijo (official post) at the time of the Restoration of Imperial Rule on December 1867.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he joined the meeting for the secret Imperial command of attacking the shogunate and was assigned to gijo (official post) at the time of the Restoration of Imperial Rule in December 1867.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he joined the meeting for the secret Imperial command of attacking the shogunate and was assigned to gijo (official post) at the time of the Restoration of Imperial Rule in December 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>翌・明治元年（1868年）1月、会計事務総督を兼ね、2月に会計事務局督に転じ、閏4月には権中納言となり、ついで会計官出仕、8月に同知事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to the chief of accountancy on January in the following year, 1868, at the same time, transferred to Toku (Captain) of the accounting office on February, Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and Shusshi (supernumerary government official) of finance officer on leap April, and the governor of finance officer on August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to the chief of accountancy in January of the following year, 1868, at the same time, transferred to Toku (Captain) of the accounting office in February, Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and Shusshi (supernumerary government official) of finance office in leap April, and the governor of finance office in August.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更、officeに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned to the chief of accountancy in January of the following year, 1868, at the same time, transferred to Toku (Captain) of the accounting office in February, Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and Shusshi (supernumerary government official) of finance office in leap April, and the governor of finance office in August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>明治2年（1869年）2月、造幣局掛等を歴任し、5月に内廷職知事に任じられ、7月に留守長官に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held positions such as an officer of Mint Bureau on February 1869, was assigned to the governor of Naiteishiki (内廷職) (officials who were in charge of daily lives of the Imperial family) on May, and was transferred to rusu chokan on July.</e>
<cmt>内廷職の読み方、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held positions such as an officer of Mint Bureau in February 1869, was assigned to the governor of Naiteishiki (内廷職) (officials who were in charge of daily lives of the Imperial family) in May, and was transferred to rusu chokan in July.</e>
<cmt>前置詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held positions such as an officer of Mint Bureau in February 1869, was assigned to the governor of Naiteishiki (内廷職) (officials who were in charge of daily lives of the Imperial family) in May, and was transferred to rusu chokan in July.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>9月には維新の功により賞典禄1,500石を永世下賜され、11月に大納言に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September, he was given 1,500 goku (crop yields) as Shotenroku and Eiseiroku (premiums) because of a merit of the Restoration and was assigned to Dainagon on November.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, he was given 1,500 koku (crop yields) as permanent Shotenroku (premium) for a merit of the Restoration and was assigned to Dainagon in November.</e>
<cmt>前置詞変更、「石」の読み方変更、賞典禄と永世禄は同じなので一つに統一、単数化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, he was given 1,500 koku (crop yields) as permanent Shotenroku (premium) for a merit of the Restoration and was assigned to Dainagon in November.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし明治3年（1870年）、病により留守長官を辞し、麝香間祗候を仰せ付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he resigned rusu chokan in 1870 because of disease and was assigned to Jako no ma shiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he resigned rusu chokan in 1870 because of his disease and was assigned to Jako no ma shiko.</e>
<cmt>his追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he resigned rusu chokan in 1870 because of his disease and was assigned to Jako no ma shiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>その後、霞会館創設の計画協議などに当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he joined the discussion to found Kasumi-kaikan (Kasumi Hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he joined the discussion to found Kasumi-kaikan (Kasumi Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he joined the discussion to found Kasumi-kaikan (Kasumi Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>明治24年（1891年）8月、病が重くなったため、特旨をもって従一位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1891, he was conferred to Juichii with a special consideration because he became worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1891, he was conferred Juichii with a special consideration because his disease became worse.</e>
<cmt>to削除、主語変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1891, he was conferred Juichii with a special consideration because his disease became worse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>明治24年（1891年）8月27日に、病気のため薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 27, 1891, he died of disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 27, 1891, he died of disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 27, 1891, he died of disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 生涯一薩摩人(id:75048), Boa(id:20845), Nekomiminarikin(id:199247), Geogie(id:143809), 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Cprobot(id:97843), Point136(id:211299), Nalc(id:139567), シェーラ(id:17988), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>