<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鳥居禅尼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Torii zenni&quot; (the Buddhist nun &quot;Torii&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Torii zenni&quot; (the Buddhist nun &quot;Torii&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torii Zenni</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。括弧説明削除しました。Zenni大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鳥居禅尼（とりいぜんに、生没年不詳）、平安時代末期、鎌倉時代初期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Torii zenni,&quot; whose birth &amp; death year is unknown, was a woman living from the last days of the Heian period to the early Kamakura peroid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Torii zenni,&quot; whose birth &amp; death year is unknown, was a woman living during the last days of the Heian period to the early Kamakura peroid.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torii zenni (the Buddhist nun Torii, year of birth and death unknown) was a woman living during the last days of the Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。括弧説明補足しました。periodスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源為義の娘で、源義朝の異母姉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the daughter of &quot;MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi&quot; &amp; the older half sister of &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the daughter of &quot;MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi&quot; &amp; the older half sister of &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi and the older half sister of MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。&amp;をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>治承・寿永の乱の際に反平氏をよびかける以仁王の令旨を諸国の源氏に伝え歩いた源行家（源義盛）は同母弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had a younger real brother &quot;MINAMOTO no Yukiie&quot; (also called &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoshimori&quot;), who, in Jisho-Juei War, visited on foot the members of the Minamoto clan scattered nationwide, and transmitted the Prince Mochihito&apos;s order to overthrow the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had a younger real brother &quot;MINAMOTO no Yukiie&quot; (also called &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoshimori&quot;), who, in Jisho-Juei War, visited on foot the members of the Minamoto clan scattered nationwide, and transmitted the Prince Mochihito&apos;s order to overthrow the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had a younger real brother MINAMOTO no Yukiie (also called MINAMOTO no Yoshimori), who, in Jisho-Juei War, visited on foot the members of the Minamoto clan scattered nationwide, and transmitted the Prince Mochihito&apos;s order to overthrow the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1140年代に、行範と結ばれ、「たつたはら（立田原）の女房」とよばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1140s,&apos; she got married to &quot;Yukinori&quot; and began to be called &quot;Tatsutahara no nyobo&quot; (the wife of Tatsutahara).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the 1140s,&apos; she was married to &quot;Yukinori&quot; and began to be called &quot;Tatsutahara no nyobo&quot; (the wife of Tatsutahara).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the 1140s, she was married to Yukinori and began to be called Tatsutahara no nyobo (the wife of Tatsutahara).</e>
<cmt>s&apos;の&apos;を削除しました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>行範は、16代熊野別当長範 （1089年 - 1141年） の嫡男で、新宮在庁・社僧として熊野速玉大社の社僧や神官などを束ねていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukinori was the heir of &quot;Naganori&quot; (1089 - 1141) who was the sixteenth &quot;Kumano betto&quot; (the title of the official who administered three shrines in Kumano), and Yukinori led &quot;shaso&quot; (priests attached to a shrine) &amp; &quot;shinkan&quot; (Shinto priests) both in Kumano-Hayatama-taisha Shrine as a responsible person at the site.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　※「新宮」とは「熊野速玉大社・社殿」の別名であり、「新宮在庁・社僧として」とは（京都にあって熊野三山を統括した「熊野三山検校」とは異なり）「熊野速玉大社の現地責任者として」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukinori was the heir of &quot;Naganori&quot; (1089 - 1141) who was the sixteenth &quot;Kumano betto&quot; (the title of the official who administered three shrines in Kumano), and Yukinori led &quot;shaso&quot; (priests attached to a shrine) &amp; &quot;shinkan&quot; (Shinto priests) both in Kumano-Hayatama-taisha Shrine as a responsible person at the site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukinori was the heir of Naganori (1089 - 1141) who was the 16th Kumano betto (the title of the official who administered three shrines in Kumano), and Yukinori led shaso (priests attached to a shrine) and shinkan (Shinto priests) both in Kumanohayatama-taisha Shrine as a responsible person at the site.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。数字に訂正しました。&amp;をandに訂正しました。ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>彼女は1140年代中頃から、範誉、行快（1146年 - 1202年）、範命（1148年 - 1208年）、行遍、行詮、行増らの男子と、数人の女子を次々ともうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around from the middle of 1140s,&apos; Torii zenni successively gave birth to some sons &amp; daughters, and her sons were &quot;Noriyo,&quot; &quot;Gyokai&quot; (1146 - 1202), &quot;Hanmyo&quot; (1148 - 1208), &quot;Gyohen,&quot; &quot;Gyosen,&quot; &quot;Gyozo&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the middle 1140s,&apos; Torii zenni successively gave birth to some sons &amp; daughters, and her sons were &quot;Noriyo,&quot; &quot;Gyokai&quot; (1146 - 1202), &quot;Hanmyo&quot; (1148 - 1208), &quot;Gyohen,&quot; &quot;Gyosen,&quot; &quot;Gyozo&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the middle 1140s, Torii zenni successively gave birth to some sons and daughters, and her sons were Noriyo, Gyokai (1146 - 1202), Hanmyo (1148 - 1208), Gyohen, Gyosen, Gyozo and others.</e>
<cmt>s&apos;の&apos;を削除しました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。&amp;をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>娘の1人は、18代熊野別当湛快（1099年 - 1174年）の次男湛増（21代熊野別当）の妻になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of her daughters became the wife of the twenty-first Kumano betto &quot;Tanzo,&quot; who was the second son of the eighteenth Kumano betto &quot;Tankai&quot; (1099 - 1174).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of her daughters became the wife of the twenty-first Kumano betto &quot;Tanzo,&quot; who was the second son of the eighteenth Kumano betto &quot;Tankai&quot; (1099 - 1174).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of her daughters became the wife of the 21st Kumano betto Tanzo, who was the second son of the 18th Kumano betto Tankai (1099 - 1174).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。21ｓｔと訂正しました。数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>承安 (日本)3年（1173年）、湛快の引退後、夫・行範は19代熊野別当に就任したが、わずか数か月で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1173, her husband Yukinori assumed the nineteenth Kumano betto after Tankai&apos;s retirement, but Yukinori died in just a few months from his assumption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1173, her husband Yukinori assumed the nineteenth Kumano betto after Tankai&apos;s retirement, but Yukinori died just a few months from his assumption.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1173, her husband Yukinori assumed the 19th Kumano betto after Tankai&apos;s retirement, but Yukinori died just a few months from his assumption.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>行範の死後、「たつたはらの女房」はすぐさま剃髪して鳥居禅尼と名乗り、菩提寺の東仙寺に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yukinori&apos;s death, &quot;Tatsutahara no nyobo&quot; immediately tonsured herself, bored the name of Torii zenni and entered Tosen-ji Temple, her family temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yukinori&apos;s death, &quot;Tatsutahara no nyobo&quot; immediately tonsured herself, bore the name of Torii zenni and entered Tosen-ji Temple, her family temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yukinori&apos;s death, Tatsutahara no nyobo immediately tonsured herself, bore the name of Torii zenni and entered Tosen-ji Temple, her family temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ちなみに東仙寺は、旧新宮城付近にあったといわれる寺で、現在鳥居禅尼の祈念仏といわれる阿弥陀如来仏・薬師如来仏などが同寺にまつられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, Tosen-ji Temple is said to have existed near former Shingu-jo Castle, and now, the statues of Amitabha Tathagata, Healing Buddha and others, to which Torii zenni is said to have dedicated her prayer, are enshrined in the temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, Tosen-ji Temple is said to have existed near former Shingu-jo Castle, and now, the statues of Amitabha Tathagata, Healing Buddha and others, to which Torii zenni is said to have dedicated her prayers, are enshrined in the temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, Tosen-ji Temple is said to have existed near former Shingu-jo Castle, and now, the statues of Amitabha Tathagata, Healing Buddha and others, to which Torii zenni is said to have dedicated her prayers, are enshrined in the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そこで行範の菩提を弔いつつ、後家として一家の要の位置を占め、子供たちを育てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torii zenni prayed for Yukinori there, occupied the psition of the pivot in the family as a widow, and raised her children.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torii zenni prayed for Yukinori there, occupying the position of the pivot in the family as a widow, and raised her children.</e>
<cmt>&quot;position of the pivot in the family&quot; doesn’t makes sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torii zenni prayed for Yukinori there, occupying the position of the pivot in the family as a widow, and raised her children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>鳥居禅尼の子には、那智の有力社僧に養子に入り後に那智執行となった範誉を筆頭に、弓の名手として伊勢の海賊から恐れられたと『古今著聞集』に記された行快（後の22代熊野別当）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of her children, the oldest son Noriyo was adopted by an influential shaso in Nachi and later became the most responsible person at the site of Kumano-Nachi-taisha Shrine, and Gyokai (the twenty-second Kumano betto in later days) was feared by pirates in Ise, &quot;Kokin Chomonju&quot; (A Collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) says, as a masterful arrow shooter.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。*「那智執行（なちしぎょう）」とは、熊野那智大社における現地の最高責任者のことです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of her children, the oldest son Noriyo was adopted by an influential shaso in Nachi and later became the most responsible person at the site of Kumano-Nachi-taisha Shrine, and Gyokai (the twenty-second Kumano betto in later days) was feared by pirates in Ise, &quot;Kokin Chomonju&quot; (A Collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) says, as a masterful arrow shooter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of her children, the oldest son Noriyo was adopted by an influential shaso in Nachi and later became the most responsible person at the site of Kumano Nachi-taisha Shrine, and Gyokai (the 21st Kumano betto in later days) was feared by pirates in Ise, &quot;Kokin Chomonju&quot; (A Collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) says, as a masterful arrow shooter.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除しました。スペース補足しました。21stとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>さらには範命（後の23代熊野別当）、『新古今和歌集』の歌人として有名になった行遍、後の権別当の行詮、同じく権別当の行増などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in addition, there existed Hanmyo (later, the twenty-third Kumano betto), Gyohen, who became famous as a maker of Japanese poetry in &quot;Shin Kokin Waka Shu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Poems), and Gyosen &amp; Gyozo, who both became &quot;gon no betto&quot; (the acting chief) of Kumano betto later.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in addition, there existed Hanmyo (later, the twenty-third Kumano betto), Gyohen, who became famous as a maker of Japanese poetry in &quot;Shin Kokin Waka Shu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Poems), and Gyosen &amp; Gyozo, who both became &quot;gon no betto&quot; (the acting chief) of Kumano betto later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in addition, there existed Hanmyo (later, the 23rd Kumano betto), Gyohen, who became famous as a maker of Japanese poetry in &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Poems), and Gyosen and Gyozo, who both became gon no betto (the acting chief) of Kumano betto later.</e>
<cmt>23rdと訂正しました。Wakashuと訂正しました。&amp;をandに訂正しました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>鳥居禅尼は源平の乱後、乱中の数々の功績によって、甥に当たる将軍源頼朝から恩賞を受け、鎌倉幕府の御家人になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Battles between the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan, &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoritomo,&quot; who was the Kamakura shogun &amp; Torii zenni&apos;s nephew, rewarded Torii zenni for her much contribution during the battles, and she became an immediate vassal of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battles between the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan, &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoritomo,&quot; who was the Kamakura shogun &amp; Torii zenni&apos;s nephew, rewarded Torii zenni for her contribution during the battles, and she became an immediate vassal of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battles between the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was the Kamakura shogun and Torii zenni&apos;s nephew, rewarded Torii zenni for her contribution during the battles, and she became an immediate vassal of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。&amp;をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>恩賞の例としては、紀伊国佐野庄および湯橋（1190年）、但馬国多々良岐庄（1194年）などの地頭への任命が挙げられる（『吾妻鏡』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rewards were, for example, her appointment to &quot;Jito&quot; (the estate steward) of Sano-no-sho &amp; Yubashi, both in Kii Province, in 1190, and then to Jito of Tataraki-no-sho in Tajima Province in 1194 (cf. &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; [The Mirror of the East]).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rewards were, for example, her appointment to &quot;Jito&quot; (the estate steward) of Sano-no-sho &amp; Yubashi, both in Kii Province, in 1190, and then to Jito of Tataraki-no-sho in Tajima Province in 1194 (cf. &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; [The Mirror of the East]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rewards were, for example, her appointment to Jito (the estate steward) of Sano no sho and Yubashi, both in Ki Province, in 1190, and then to Jito of Tataraki no sho in Tajima Province in 1194 (cf. &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。&amp;をandに訂正しました。ハイフン削除しました。スペース補足しました。Ki Provinceに訂正しました。[ ]を()に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>承元4年（1210年）、幕府は鳥居禅尼の願いをいれ、これらすべての知行地の地頭職を養子に譲補することを認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1210, at Torii zenni&apos;s request, the Kamakura shogunate permitted her to transfer the position of Jito controlling over her all territory to her adopted child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1210, at Torii zenni&apos;s request, the Kamakura shogunate permitted her to transfer the position of Jito and control over all territory to her adopted child.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1210, at Torii zenni&apos;s request, the Kamakura shogunate permitted her to transfer the position of Jito and control over all territory to her adopted child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>養子の名前はわからないが、行詮の子の行忠か長詮が養子とされたと思われる（『吾妻鏡』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the adopted child is unknown, but supposedly, it was &quot;Yukitada&quot; or &quot;Chosen,&quot; both the sons of Gyosen (cf. &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the adopted child is unknown, but supposedly, it was &quot;Yukitada&quot; or &quot;Chosen,&quot; both the sons of Gyosen (cf. &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the adopted child is unknown, but supposedly, it was Yukitada or Chosen, both the sons of Gyosen (cf. &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>新宮別当家は、こうした鳥居禅尼の働きにより鎌倉将軍家の一族として手厚く遇され、熊野三山内外にその勢力を伸ばしていったものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to these appeals of Torii zenni, &quot;Shingu betto-ke&quot; (the lineage based in Kumano-Hayatama-taisha Shrine assuming Kumano betto for generations) seems to have been treated with the greatest respect as the member of the Kamakura shogunate family, and have expanded their influence inside &amp; outside of &quot;Kumano Sanzan&quot; (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-taisha and Kumano-Nachi-taisha).</e>
<cmt>*「新宮別当家」とは、熊野別当を代々引き継いだ、新宮に本拠を置く家系です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to these appeals of Torii zenni, &quot;Shingu betto-ke&quot; (the lineage based in Kumano-Hayatama-taisha Shrine assuming Kumano betto for generations) seems to have been treated with the greatest respect as the member of the Kamakura shogunate family, and have expanded their influence inside &amp; outside of &quot;Kumano Sanzan&quot; (three major shrines, Kumano-Hongu-taisha, Kumano-Hayatama-taisha and Kumano-Nachi-taisha).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to these appeals of Torii zenni, Shingu betto-ke (the lineage based in Kumano Hayatama-taisha Shrine assuming Kumano betto for generations) seems to have been treated with the greatest respect as the member of the Kamakura shogunate family, and have expanded their influence inside and outside of Kumano Sanzan (three major shrines, Kumano Hongu-taisha, Kumano Hayatama-taisha and Kumano Nachi-taisha).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。ハイフン削除しました。&amp;をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>鳥居禅尼は女性なので別当にこそなれなかったが、熊野三山統轄機構の中枢部にいた夫の行範や義弟の範智（20代熊野別当）、それに娘婿の湛増（21代熊野別当）、さらには子や孫を通じてその影響力を大いに発揮し、1210年頃、かなりの高齢で死去したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Torii zenni could not become Kumano betto because of her gender, she exerted a great influence through her family members occupying the central part of the organization controling Kumano Sanzan, such as her husband Yukinori, her younger brother-in-law &quot;Noritomo&quot; (the twentief Kumano betto), her son-in-law &quot;Tanzo&quot; (the twenty-first Kumano betto) and her sons &amp; grandsons, and she is said to have gone at a considerable old age around 1210.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Torii zenni could not become Kumano betto because of her gender, she exerted a great influence through her family members occupying the central part of the organization controling Kumano Sanzan, such as her husband Yukinori, her younger brother-in-law &quot;Noritomo&quot; (the twentief Kumano betto), her son-in-law &quot;Tanzo&quot; (the twenty-first Kumano betto) and her sons &amp; grandsons, and she is said to have passed away due to considerable old age around 1210.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Torii zenni could not become Kumano betto because of her gender, she exerted a great influence through her family members occupying the central part of the organization controlling Kumano Sanzan, such as her husband Yukinori, her younger brother-in-law Noritomo (the 20th Kumano betto), her son-in-law Tanzo (the 21st Kumano betto) and her sons and grandsons, and she is said to have passed away due to considerable old age around 1210.</e>
<cmt>controllingスペル訂正しました。20th, 21stとしました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。&amp;をandに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), BAKU(id:55205), 小者(id:172526), R28Bot(id:177951), Ikedat76(id:34218), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>