<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平基盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Motomori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Motomori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Motomori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 基盛（たいら の もともり、保延5年（1139年） - 応保2年3月17日 (旧暦)（1162年5月2日））は、平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Motomori is a busho (Japanese military commander) (1139 to May 2, 1162) in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Motomori was a busho (Japanese military commander) (1139 to May 2, 1162) in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Motomori was a busho (Japanese military commander) (1139 - May 9, 1162) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。toをハイフンンに訂正しました。Periodを小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平清盛の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the second son of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は高階基章の娘で、同母兄に平重盛がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is a daughter of Motoaki TAKASHINA, and his uterine brother is TAIRA no Shigemori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Motoaki TAKASHINA, and his maternal half brother was TAIRA no Shigemori.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Motoaki TAKASHINA, and his maternal half brother was TAIRA no Shigemori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名を香王、通称を安芸判官といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name is Kao, and he was unofficially called Aki Hangan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Kao, and he was unofficially called Aki Hangan.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Kao, and he was unofficially called Aki Hangan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>久寿2年（1155年）4月11日に院判官代に補され、翌日兵衛府に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned as inhangandai (Assistant to the Chief of the Administrative Office of the Retired Emperor) on April 11, 1155, and assigned to Hyoe-fu, a governmental office in charge of palace guard, on the following day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned as inhangandai (Assistant to the Chief of the Administrative Office of the Retired Emperor) on April 11, 1155, and assigned to Hyoe-fu, a governmental office in charge of palace guard, on the following day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned as inhangandai (Assistant to the Chief of the Administrative Office of the Retired Emperor) on May 20, 1155, and assigned to Hyoe-fu, a governmental office in charge of palace guard, on the following day.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同年11月には衛門府となり、12月には検非違使の宣旨を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of the same year, he was assigned to Emon-fu, another government office, and then appointed to Kebiishi (Imperial police force) by senji (order letter by the Emperor) in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, he was assigned to Emon-fu, another government office, and then appointed to Kebiishi (Imperial police force) by senji (order letter by the Emperor) in December.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the same year, he was assigned to Emon-fu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards), another government office, and then appointed to kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) by senji (Imperial decreer by the Emperor) in December.</e>
<cmt>衛門府→Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards)検非違使→kebiishi (a police and judicial chief)order letterをImperial Decreeに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱に際しては、父とともに後白河天皇方に参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Hogen War broke out in 1156, he joined the forces of Emperor Goshirakawa together with his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Hogen War broke out in 1156, he joined the forces of Emperor Goshirakawa, together with his father.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Hogen War broke out in 1156, he joined the forces of Emperor Goshirakawa, together with his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>弱冠17歳ながら宇治路の警護に当たり、東山 (京都府)法性寺の辺りで崇徳天皇方に参陣途上の源親治を捕らえるという大功を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was put in charge of guarding Uji-ji Highway at a very young age of 17 and made a great achievement by arresting MINAMOTO no Chikaharu, who was about to join the forces of Emperor Sutoku, near Hossho-ji Temple at Higashiyama, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was put in charge of guarding Uji-ji Highway at the very young age of 17 and made a great achievement by arresting MINAMOTO no Chikaharu, who was about to join the forces of Emperor Sutoku, near Hossho-ji Temple at Higashiyama, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was put in charge of guarding Uji-ji Highway at the very young age of 17 and made a great achievement by arresting MINAMOTO no Chikaharu, who was about to join the forces of Emperor Sutoku, near Hossho-ji Temple at Higashiyama, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>続く平治の乱（1159年）にも出陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also went to the battlefield in the subsequent campaign of the Heiji War in 1159.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also went to the battlefield in the subsequent campaign of the Heiji War in 1159.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also went to the battlefield in the subsequent campaign of the Heiji War in 1159.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>以降平家一門の栄達に伴い、大和国、淡路国、越前国などの諸国司を歴任、正四位下まで昇進するが、応保2年に24歳にして早世した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Taira clan rose to power, Motomori was also assigned as kokushi (local governor) of a few provinces including Yamato, Awaji, and Echizen, finally reached the title of Shoshii-no-ge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), but died young at the age of 24 in 1162.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Taira clan rose to power, Motomori was also assigned as kokushi (local governor) of a few provinces, including Yamato, Awaji, and Echizen, eventually reaching the title of Shoshii-no-ge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), but he died young at the age of 24 in 1162.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Taira clan rose to power, Motomori was also assigned as kokushi (local governor) of a few provinces, including Yamato, Awaji, and Echizen, eventually reaching the title of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), but he died young at the age of 24 in 1162.</e>
<cmt>Shoshii-no-ge、ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>『源平盛衰記』によると、宇治川を騎馬で渡河しようとした際、藤原頼長の怨霊に祟られ溺死したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Genpei Seisuiki, or the History of the Rise and Fall of the Genji and Heike, when Motomori tried to cross the Uji River on horseback, he was haunted by the vengeful spirit of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga and drowned to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Genpei Seisuiki, or the History of the Rise and Fall of the Genji and Heike, when Motomori tried to cross the Uji River on horseback, he was haunted by the vengeful spirit of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga and drowned to death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Genpei Seisuiki,&quot; (the History of the Rise and Fall of the Genji and Heike), when Motomori tried to cross the Uji River on horseback, he was haunted by the vengeful spirit of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga and drowned to death.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足しました。本の内容説明は括弧書きにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>一子平行盛は後に治承・寿永の乱における源氏との戦闘で活躍、一女は藤原季能の室になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His only son TAIRA no Yukimori made a good showing in battles against the Minamoto clan in the Jisho and Joei Rebellion, and his only daughter married into FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His only son TAIRA no Yukimori made a good showing in battles against the Minamoto clan in the Jisho and Joei Rebellion, and his only daughter married into FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His only son TAIRA no Yukimori made a good showing in battles against the Minamoto clan in the Jisho and Joei Rebellion, and his only daughter married into FUJIWARA no Sueyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 味っ子(id:17086), YOSHI438(id:174755), Haruno Akiha(id:107628), ゐ(id:795), 小者(id:172526), 獲加多支鹵大王(id:68289), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>