<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今川氏豊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujitoyo IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujitoyo IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujitoyo IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>今川 氏豊（いまがわ うじとよ 生没年不詳）は戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujitoyo IMAGAWA (date of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujitoyo IMAGAWA (date of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujitoyo IMAGAWA (date of birth and death unknown) was a military commander in the period of warring states.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>駿河国守護今川氏親の末子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Youngest child of Shugo (provincial constable) of Suruga Province, Ujichika IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the youngest child of Shugo (provincial constable) of Suruga Province, Ujichika IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the youngest child of Ujichika IMAGAWA, provincial constable of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>今川義元の弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Younger brother of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Younger brother of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a younger brother of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名は竹王丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Chikuomaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Chikuomaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Chikuomaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>那古野城主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the castellan of Nagoya-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the castellan of Nagoya-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the lord of Nagoya-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>官名は左馬助。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official name of government office was Samanosuke (vice-minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official name of government office was Samanosuke (vice-minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of government office was the vice-minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天文 (元号)5年（1536年）に兄で今川家当主の今川氏輝と同日に死去した今川彦五郎と同一人物とも考えられていたが、最近の研究では別人とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some believed he was the same person as Hikogoro IMAGAWA, who died on the same day as Ujiteru IMAGAWA, an older brother and the head of Imagawa family, but recent studies see him as a different person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some believed he was the same person as Hikogoro IMAGAWA, who died on the same day as Ujiteru IMAGAWA, an older brother and the head of Imagawa family, but recent studies see him as a different person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some believed he was the same person as Hikogoro IMAGAWA, who died on the same day in 1536 as Ujiteru IMAGAWA, an older brother and the head of Imagawa family, but recent studies regard him as a different person.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、氏豊の名は今川氏の良質の文書には現れず、氏親の子ではなく傍流という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the name, Ujitoyo, does not appear in good quality documents of the Imagawa clan, and some say he was not the child of Ujichika, but a was a branch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the name, Ujitoyo, does not appear in good quality documents of the Imagawa clan, and some say he was not the child of Ujichika, but a was in a branch.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the name Ujitoyo does not appear in properly handed-down documents of the Imagawa clan, and some say that he was not the child of Ujichika, but a child from a branch.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>永正12年(1515年)に今川氏親は遠江国で尾張国守護の斯波義達と戦い勝利し、斯波氏の威は衰えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1515, Ujichika IMAGAWA fought and won against Shugo of Owari Province, Yoshitatsu SHIBA, in Totomi Province, and the power of Shiba clan declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1515, Ujichika IMAGAWA fought and won against the Shugo of Owari Province, Yoshitatsu SHIBA, in Totomi Province, and this caused the power of Shiba clan to decline.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1515, Ujichika IMAGAWA fought and won against the governor of Owari Province, Yoshitatsu SHIBA, in Totomi Province, which caused the power of Shiba clan to decline.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>大永年間（1521年 - 1528年）に氏親は那古野氏の領地だった尾張国那古野の地に城を築き（那古野城、後の名古屋城）、氏豊を城主とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1521 to 1528, Ujichika constructed a castle (Nagoya-jo Castle (那古野城), later Nagoya-jo Castle (名古屋城) in Nagoya, Owari Province, which was once a territory of the Nagoya clan, and appointed Ujitoyo as the castellan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1521 to 1528, Ujichika constructed a castle (Nagoya-jo Castle (那古野城), later Nagoya-jo Castle (名古屋城) in Nagoya, Owari Province, which was once the territory of the Nagoya clan, and appointed Ujitoyo as the castellan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1521 to 1528, Ujichika constructed a castle (Nagoya-jo Castle [first written as 那古野城, and later written as 名古屋城]) in Nagoya, Owari Province, which was once the territory of the Nagoya clan, and appointed Ujitoyo as the lord.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>氏豊は斯波義達の娘を娶った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujitoyo married the daughter of Yoshitatsu SHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujitoyo married the daughter of Yoshitatsu SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujitoyo married the daughter of Yoshitatsu SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>那古野氏は明徳 - 応永年間に今川仲秋が尾張守護となったときに尾張国に代官として封じられた今川氏の一族で、氏豊はその養子となったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nagoya clan was a family of the Imagawa clan who were contained in Owari Province as daikan (local governor) when Nakaaki IMAGAWA became Shugo of Owari between Meitoku and Oei eras, and it is believed that Ujitoyo was adopted by them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nagoya clan was a family of the Imagawa clan who were contained in Owari Province as daikan (local governor) when Nakaaki IMAGAWA became Shugo of Owari between Meitoku and Oei eras, and it is believed that Ujitoyo was adopted by them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nagoya clan was a family of the Imagawa clan who were invested with Owari Province as the local governor when Nakaaki IMAGAWA became the military governor of Owari from 1390 to 1427, and it is believed that Ujitoyo was adopted by them.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>享禄5年（1532年）、勝幡城主織田信秀の奇計によって兵を城に侵入され、城を落とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1532, troops invaded their castle in a clever scheme by Shobata-jo Castle castellan, Nobuhide ODA, and the castle was surrendered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1532, troops invaded their castle in a clever scheme by Shobata-jo Castle castellan, Nobuhide ODA, and the castle was surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1532, troops invaded their castle in a clever scheme by Shobata-jo Castle lord, Nobuhide ODA, and the castle was surrendered.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>『名古屋合戦記』によると、氏豊が連歌を非常に好み、そのことに目をつけた信秀が那古野城に催される連歌会に足繁く通い何日も逗留するようになり、氏豊に信用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nagoya Kassen-ki&quot; (Records of battles in Nagaya), Ujitoyo enjoyed renga (linked verse) very much, and Nobuhide, who set his eyes on this, participated frequently in the renga-kai (a gathering of linked verse) held at the Nagoya-jo Castle and sojourned for days, and eventually earned the trust of Ujitoyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Nagoya Kassen-ki (Records of battles in Nagoya), Ujitoyo enjoyed renga (linked verse) very much, and Nobuhide, who set his eyes on this, participated frequently in the renga-kai (a gathering of linked verse) held at Nagoya-jo Castle after sojourning for days. eventually earned the trust of Ujitoyo.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nagoya Kassen-ki&quot; (Records of battles in Nagoya), Ujitoyo enjoyed renga (linked verse) very much, and Nobuhide, who set his eyes on this, participated frequently in the renga-kai (a gathering of linked verse) held at Nagoya-jo Castle by sojourning for days eventually earned the trust of Ujitoyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>信秀が城の本丸に窓を開けるが、氏豊は夏風を楽しむ風流のためだろうと信頼しきっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuhide built a window in the Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of the castle, but Ujitoyo completely trusted him, thinking it was for the splendor of enjoying the summer breeze.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuhide built a window in the Honmaru (the keep of a castle), but Ujitoyo completely trusted him, thinking it was for the splendor of enjoying the summer breeze.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuhide built a window in the keep of a castle, and Ujitoyo completely trusted him, thinking it was for the splendor of enjoying the summer breeze.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ある日、信秀は城内で倒れ「家臣に遺言をしたい」と頼み、同情した氏豊はこれを許し、信秀の家臣が城内に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, when Nobuhide collapsed in the castle and requested to &apos;leave a will for the vassals,&apos; Ujitoyo allowed this in sympathy, and the vassals of Nobuhide entered the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, when Nobuhide collapsed in the castle and requested to &apos;leave a will for the vassals,&apos; Ujitoyo allowed this in sympathy, and the vassals of Nobuhide entered the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, when Nobuhide collapsed in the castle and requested to &apos;leave a will for the vassals,&apos; Ujitoyo allowed the request in sympathy, and the vassals of Nobuhide entered the castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その夜、信秀はにわかに城内に引き入れた手勢を使って城に火を放ち、城の内外から攻め寄せて城を乗っ取ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That night, Nobuhide set fire on the castle with his own forces which he abruptly brought inside the castle, and captured the castle by attacking it from in and out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That night, Nobuhide set fire to the castle with his own forces which he abruptly brought inside the castle, and captured the castle by attacking it from the inside out.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that night, Nobuhide set fire to the castle with his own forces which he abruptly brought inside the castle, and captured the castle by attacking it from the inside.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>氏豊は命乞いをして助けられ、女方の縁を頼って京都に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujitoyo begged for his life and was saved, and fled to Kyoto relying on ties to some women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujitoyo begged for his life and was saved, and fled to Kyoto relying on ties to some women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujitoyo begged for his life and was saved, and fled to Kyoto relying on connections of his wife.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>天文2年（1533年）に尾張国に下向した山科言継と飛鳥井雅綱が勝幡城で織田信秀ら織田家家中に蹴鞠の指導をした際に今川竹王丸（氏豊）も招かれていたと『言継卿記』に記されていることから、那古野城の奪取の時期については天文7年(1538年)年説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it is described in &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) that when Tokitsugu YAMASHINA and Masatsuna ASUKAI taught kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period) at the Shobata-jo Castle to Nobuhide ODA and other Oda family members in 1533, Chikuomaru (Ujitoyo) IMAGAWA was also invited, some say the takeover of Nagoya-jo Castle was in 1538.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it this was described in the Tokitsugu Kyoki (Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) that when Tokitsugu YAMASHINA and Masatsuna ASUKAI taught kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period) at the Shobata-jo Castle to Nobuhide ODA and other Oda family members in 1533, Chikuomaru (Ujitoyo) IMAGAWA was also invited. This has prompted some to say that the takeover of Nagoya-jo Castle was in 1538.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was described in &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) that when Tokitsugu YAMASHINA and Masatsuna ASUKAI taught kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period) at the Shobata-jo Castle to Nobuhide ODA and other Oda family members in 1533, Chikuomaru (Ujitoyo) IMAGAWA was also invited, which has prompted some to say that the takeover of Nagoya-jo Castle was in 1538.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>その後、那古野城は信秀の嫡男織田信長に与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Nagoya-jo Castle was provided to Nobuhide&apos;s legitimate son, Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Nagoya-jo Castle was provided to Nobuhide&apos;s legitimate son, Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Nagoya-jo Castle was handed down to Nobuhide&apos;s legitimate son, Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>那古野城を奪われた後、駿河に帰らず京に逃れた理由は不明で、今川家の家督争いの花倉の乱にも関与していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown why he did not return to Suruga and fled to Kyoto after losing the Nagoya-jo Castle, and he also did not take part in the Hanakura Rebellion, a succession dispute in the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unknown why he did not return to Suruga and fled to Kyoto after losing the Nagoya-jo Castle. It is also a mystery why he did not take part in the Hanakura Rebellion, a succession dispute in the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons why he did not return to Suruga and fled to Kyoto after losing the Nagoya-jo Castle and why he did not take part in the Hanakura War, a succession dispute in the Imagawa family are unknown.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そのため氏親の子ではなかったのではないかという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, some say he was not the child of Ujichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, some say he was not the child of Ujichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, some people doubt that he was not the child of Ujichika.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 味っ子(id:17086), Route54(id:154369), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>