<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>服部持法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiho HATTORI</e>
<cmt>固有名詞は統一用語に従いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiho HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiho HATTORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>服部 持法（はっとり じほう、生没年不明）は、鎌倉時代後期から南北朝時代 (日本)にかけて活躍した伊賀国の武士、悪党。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiho Hattori (服部 持法: dates of birth and death unknown) was a samurai of Iga Province and Akuto (a villain in the medieval times), who was active from the late Kamakura Period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiho Hattori (服部 持法: dates of birth and death unknown) was a samurai from Iga Province and an akuto (a villain of medieval times), who was active from the late Kamakura Period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>「of」→「from」, 「Akuto」→「an akuto」,「in the」→「of」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiho Hattori (dates of birth and death unknown) was a samurai from Iga Province and an akuto (a villain of medieval times), who was active from the late Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>日本語をのぞき、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称は右衛門太郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name is Uemontaro (右衛門太郎)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name is Uemontaro (右衛門太郎)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Uemontaro.</e>
<cmt>過去形にし、日本語をのぞき、ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imina (personal name) is unknown</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (personal name) is unknown</e>
<cmt>「His」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was unknown</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>持法は入道号。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiho is a Nyudo-go (priest title)</e>
<cmt>入道号→定訳不明Nyudo-go (priest title)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiho is a Nyudo-go (priest title)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiho was the name he assumed when he entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また道秀とも号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also has another priest title, Doshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also has another priest title, Doshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">`Doshu` was another religious title that he used.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>服部氏は伊賀国阿拝郡服部郷（現三重県伊賀市）を拠点とする有力御家人であり、阿拝郡・山田郡 (伊賀国)など北伊賀を支配下に置いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hattori clan was a powerful vassal (gokenin) with its bases at Hattori-go, Ae Country, Iga Province (present Iga City, Mie Prefecture), and was dominating the northern part of Iga Province, such as Ae Country and Yamada Country (Iga Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hattori clan were powerful vassals (gokenin) with bases in Hattori-go, Ae Country, Iga Province (present-day Iga City, Mie Prefecture), and dominated the northern part of Iga Province, such as Ae Country and Yamada Country (Iga Province).</e>
<cmt>「was a」→「were」, 「vassal」→「vassals」,「its」削除,「at」→「in」, 「present」→「present-day」,「was dominating」→「dominated」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hattori clan were powerful gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) with bases in Hattori-go, Ae-gun County, Iga Province (present-day Iga City, Mie Prefecture), and dominated the northern part of Iga Province, such as Ae -gun County and Yamada-gun Country (Iga Province).</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>14世紀初頭より、同国名張郡の東大寺領黒田荘で悪党が蜂起した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the beginning of the 14th century, Acto (villains) became active at Kuroda no sho (estate), a territory of Toda-ji Temple in Nabari Country of the same province, and although Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) tried to suppress them upon the request of Todai-ji Temple, it could not put down the insurgency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the beginning of the 14th century, akuto became active in Kuroda no sho estate, a territory of Todai-ji Temple in Nabari Country of the same province, and although the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) tried to suppress them upon the request of Todai-ji Temple, it could not put down the insurgency.</e>
<cmt>「Acto (villains)」→「akuto」, 「(estate)」→「estate」,「at」→「in」, 「Toda-ji」→「Todai-ji」,「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the beginning of the 14th century, villains became active in Kuroda estate which was part of the lands belonging to Todai-ji Temple in Nabari-gun County in Iga Province</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>東大寺の依頼を受けた六波羅探題が鎮圧にあたるも果たせなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the authorities in Rokuhara (Kyoto) tried to suppress the villains (at the request of Todai-ji Temple) the insurgency could not be suppressed..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>六波羅探題は嘉暦2年（1327年）伊賀守護代平常茂と服部持法に覚舜・道願ら悪党の捕縛を命ずる「厳密之沙汰」を下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuhara Tandai issued a &apos;strict order&apos; that commanded Iga shugodai (delegates of shugo), Tsuneshige TAIRA and Jiho HATTORI, to arrest the group of Akuto (villains) including Kakushun and Dogan.</e>
<cmt>「厳密之沙汰」→定訳不明：&apos;strict order&apos; としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rokuhara Tandai issued a &apos;strict order&apos; that commanded the Iga shugodai (delegates of shugo), Tsuneshige TAIRA and Jiho HATTORI, to arrest the group of akuto, which included Kakushun and Dogan.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入x2, 「Akuto」→「akuto」,「(villains)」削除 (it is not necessary to explain every time I think), 「including」→「, which included」,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1327 the authorities in Rokuhara (Kyoto) issued a strict decree that commanded the police commanders in Iga Province (Tsuneshige TAIRA and Jiho HATTORI), to arrest a gang of villains which included Kakushun and Dogan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし悪党から賄賂を受けていた両人は手勢も連れず荘内に入り、むしろ悪党らに饗応されただけで退去し、六波羅へは悪党はすでに逐電済みであると報告しただけに終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since those two had been receiving bribes from Akuto (villains), they went into the estate without their own soldiers and after being entertained by villains, they left the site and tried to close out the case by reporting to Rokuhara that Akuto had already run away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Tsuneshige and Jiro had been receiving bribes from the akuto, they went into the estate without their own soldiers and after being entertained by the villains left the site and reported to Rokuhara that the akuto had already run away.</e>
<cmt>「those two」→「Tsuneshige and Jiro」, 「Akuto (villains)」→「the akuto」, 「the」挿入, 「, they」挿入,「tried to close out the case by reporting」→「reported」, 「Akuto」→「the akuto」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tsuneshige and Jiro had been bribed by the villains and, when the pair went into the estate (unaccompanied by their soldiers) following some entertainment provided by the villains, the pair left the estate and reported to the Rokuhara authorities that the villains had escaped.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>六波羅探題はこの結果に納得せず、同年7月再び両人に悪党の住居破壊および捕縛を命ずる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuhara Tandai was not convinced by the result and in July of the same year the agency once again issued the order to destroy the houses of the villains and arrest them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rokuhara Tandai was not convinced by this outcome and in July of the same year the order was once again issued to destroy the houses of the villains and arrest them.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「the result」→「this outcome」, 「agency once again issued the order」→「the order was once again issued」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rokuhara Tandai was not convinced by this outcome and in July of the same year the order was once again issued to destroy the houses of the villains and arrest them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、持法らは病と称して命令を聞かず、8月になって黒田荘に出向くが、再び逐電済みと報告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Jiho and other did not follow this order with the pretext that they were ill, and in August they visited Kuroda no sho (estate) and reported back that the villains had again run away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Jiho and the others did not follow this order with the pretext that they were ill, but eventually in August they visited Kuroda no sho and reported back that the villains had again run away.</e>
<cmt>「other」→「the others」, 「and」→「but eventually」, 「(estate)」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Jiho and the others did not follow this order (on the pretext they were ill), but they eventually (August) visited the Kuroda estate and reported back that the villains had evaded capture yet again.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>業を煮やした六波羅探題は伊賀国の地頭・御家人を同道させるべしと命令し、ようやく持法らは従ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Rokuhara Tandai, being inpatient, ordered Jiho and his retainers to go there with the jito (estate steward) and gokenin (vassals) of Iga Province, and finally they reluctantly followed the order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Rokuhara Tandai, being impatient, ordered Jiho and his retainers to go there with the jito (estate steward) and gokenin of Iga Province, and finally they reluctantly followed the order.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「inpatient」→「impatient」,「(vassals)」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Rokuhara police commissioner became impatient and ordered Jiho and his retainers to visit the estate in the company of the estate steward) and Iga Province vassals: an order the constables eventually followed..</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>鎌倉幕府滅亡後、南北朝時代 (日本)の動乱が始まると、服部郷高畠村の地から高畠右衛門太郎入道道秀と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the downfall of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), when the revolt in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) arose, he named himself Uemon Taro Nyudo Doshu TAKAHATA after his home village, Takahata-mura (village), Hattori-go (district).</e>
<cmt>高畠右衛門太郎入道道秀→定訳不明： Uemon Taro Nyudo Doshu TAKAHATA としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the downfall of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), when the revolt in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts arose, he named himself Uemon Taro Nyudo Doshu TAKAHATA after his home village, Takahata-mura village, Hattori-go district.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「(Japan)」削除(this is clear by the context), 「(village)」→「village」, 「(district)」→「district」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the downfall of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), when the revolt in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts arose, he named himself Doshu Nyudo Uemontaro TAKAHATA after his home village, Takahata-mura village, Hattori-go district.</e>
<cmt>順序を入れ変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この頃からは完全に悪党に転じ、北伊賀の東大寺領荘園（鞆田荘・玉滝荘・湯船荘など）を浸食し、「当国名誉大悪党張本」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around this time, he turned into a villain and invaded the estates belonging to Todai-ji Temple (Tomoda no sho, Tamataki no sho, Yubune no sho, etc.) and he was called &apos;honorary great Akuto in chief of all the province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「当国名誉大悪党張本」→定訳不明： &apos;honorary great Akuto in chief of all the province&apos; としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since around this time, he became a villain himself and invaded the estates belonging to Todai-ji Temple (including Tomoda no sho, Tamataki no sho and Yubune no sho) and he was called &apos;great and honorable akuto, chief of all the province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「turned into」→「became」, 「himself」挿入, 「including」挿入, 「, etc.」削除, 「honorary great Akuto in」→「great and honorable akuto,」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, TAKAHATA completely turned into a villain himself; invaded the estates in the north part of the Iga Province which belonged to Todai-ji Temple (including Tomoda, Tamataki and Yubune estates) and TAKAHATA himself was called &apos;great and honorable villain, chief of all the province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同国内の国人衆と一揆を結び、南朝 (日本)・北朝 (日本)双方の間にあって、寝返りを繰り返しながら、守護の支配を退けていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In cooperation with Kokujin-shu (small local lords) in the province he provoked riots, changing sides frequently between the Japanese Northern Court and the Southern Court, and gradually put off the control of shugo (the provincial constable).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In cooperation with Kokujin-shu (small local lords) in the province he provoked riots, changing sides frequently between the Japanese Northern Court and the Southern Court, and gradually challenged the control of the shugo (the provincial constable).</e>
<cmt>「put off」→「challenged」, 「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banding together with minor provincial lords, TAKAHATA provoked riots, frequently switched allegiances (from the Japanese Northern Court and the Southern Court), and gradually eroded the control of the provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>室町幕府は守護に仁木義直を任じて支配強化を図ったが、持法は一方で守護支配に抵抗する国人と結びつつ、裏では義直と結託していたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muromachi bakufu tried to strengthen the control, appointing Yoshinao NIKI as shugo, but it is said that Jiho was secretly in collusion with Yoshinao, while working with small local lords who were opposed to the control of shugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi bakufu tried to strengthen its control, appointing Yoshinao NIKI as shugo, but it is said that Jiho was secretly in collusion with Yoshinao, while working with small local lords who were opposed to the control of the shugo.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入x2, 「the」→「its」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu (shogunate) tried to strengthen its control by appointing Yoshinao NIKI as provincial governor however, some say Jiho colluded with Yoshinao behind the scenes while simultaneously conspiring with minor local lords in resistance to the powers of the governor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>幕府は守護を桃井直常に交代させたが、やはり国人一揆を鎮圧することはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although bakufu replaced the then shugo with Tadatsune MOMONOI, it was impossible to suppress the revolt of small local lords (Kokujin ikki or Kokujin revolt).</e>
<cmt>国人一揆→定訳不明：revolt of small local lords (Kokujin ikki or Kokujin revolt)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the bakufu replaced the then shugo with Tadatsune MOMONOI, it was impossible to suppress the revolt of small local lords (Kokujin ikki or Kokujin revolt).</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the bakufu replaced the shugo with Tadatsune MOMONOI, it was impossible to suppress Kokujin ikki (kokujin (local samurai) revolt).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>貞和2年（1346年）征夷大将軍足利尊氏・副将軍足利直義兄弟が夢窓疎石の勧めにより、全国に安国寺利生塔の建立を命じた際には、伊賀国に対し幕府は服部持法と柘植新左衛門に寺領保護と造営成否の注進を命じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1346, when Seii taishogun (literally, &apos;great general who subdues the barbarians&apos;) Takauji ASHIKAGA, and the Vice-shogun and his brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, ordered the construction of Ankoku-ji Temple Risho-to Pagodas all over Japan according to the advise by Muso Soseki (Buddhist monk), the bakufu ordered the government of Iga Province to oblige Jiho HATTORI and Shinzaemon TSUGE to take charge of the protection of temples&apos; estates and the reporting on the progress of the pagodas&apos; construction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1346, when Seii Taishogun (literally, &apos;great general who subdues the barbarians&apos;) Takauji ASHIKAGA, and the Vice-shogun and his brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, ordered the construction of Ankoku-ji Temple Risho-to Pagodas all over Japan according to the advice of Muso Soseki (a Buddhist monk), the bakufu ordered the government of Iga Province to oblige Jiho HATTORI and Shinzaemon TSUGE to take charge of the protection of temples&apos; estates and the reporting on the progress of the pagodas&apos; construction.</e>
<cmt>「taishogun」→「Taishogun」, 「advise by」→「advice of」, 「a」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1346, when Seii Taishogun (literally, &apos;great general who subdues the barbarians&apos;) Takauji ASHIKAGA, and the Vice-shogun and his brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, ordered the construction of Ankoku-ji Temple Risho-to Pagodas all over Japan according to the advice of Muso Soseki (a Buddhist monk), the bakufu ordered the government of Iga Province to oblige Jiho HATTORI and Shinzaemon TSUGE to take charge of the protection of temples&apos; estates and the reporting on the progress of the pagodas&apos; construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後も伊賀は惣国一揆と守護仁木氏が共存する状態が室町時代を通じて維持された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even since then, in Iga Province, the coexistence of the riots affecting the whole province (sokoku ikki) and the control of the Niki clan, as the provincial constable (shugo) had been maintained all through the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>惣国一揆→定訳不明：riots affecting the whole province (sokoku ikki) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this too, conflict between the control of the Niki clan in the form of the provincial constable on the one hand, and riots affecting the whole province (sokoku ikki) was a characteristic of Iga Province that continued throughout the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently as well, (for the duration of Muromachi period) Iga Province was characterized by province-wide unrest that accompanied rule by the Niki clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 トホホ川(id:50502), KurmUmy(id:202680), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>