<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一色義道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimichi ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimichi ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimichi ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一色 義道（いっしき よしみち、 － 天正7年（1579年））は戦国時代 (日本)、安土桃山時代の武将・大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimichi ISSHIKI (- 1579) was a Busho (Japanese military commander)/Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord)in the Sengoku (Warring States) Period in Japan and Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimichi ISSHIKI (- 1579) was a Busho (Japanese military commander) and Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord)in the Sengoku (Warring States) and Azuchi-Momoyama Periods.</e>
<cmt>slash→&quot;and&quot;Deleted &quot;Period in Japan&quot;Made &quot;Period&quot; plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimichi ISSHIKI (date of birth unknown - 1579) was a Busho (Japanese military commander) and Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku (Warring States) period (Japan) and Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>date of birth unknown追加。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>丹後国の大名一色氏の当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Head of the Isshiki Clan and Daimyo of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Head of the Isshiki Clan and Daimyo of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Head of the Isshiki clan and Daimyo of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>clanを小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一色義幸の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Child of Yoshiyuki ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Child of Yoshiyuki ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Child of Yoshiyuki ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一色義定（義俊、満信）の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Father of: Yoshisada ISSHIKI, Yoshitoshi and Mitsunobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Father of: Yoshisada ISSHIKI, Yoshitoshi and Mitsunobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Father of Yoshisada ISSHIKI (also known as Yoshitoshi or Mitsunobu).</e>
<cmt>also known as を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>義通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimichi</e>
<cmt>As this is a kanji related sentence, I&apos;m not sure it&apos;s necessary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name, originally written as Yoshimichi (義道), is sometimes written in different Chinese characters as Yoshimichi (義通).</e>
<cmt>原文wikiを参照し、漢字表記の違いを表現しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>式部大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikibunotaifu (government official of the Ministry of Education)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikibunotaifu (government official of the Ministry of Education)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Served as Shikibu no taifu (government official of the Ministry of Education).</e>
<cmt>Shikibu no taifu とスペースを入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>左京大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakyo-no-daibu (Chief Steward East Kyoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakyo-no-daibu (Chief Steward of East Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also served as Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>官職名の表現及び補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>丹後の一色氏は元々室町幕府の四職の一家であったが、戦国時代 (日本)には没落の一途をたどり、丹後の守護職も隣国の若狭武田家に奪われる有様で、かつての守護家の権威を利用しどうにか実効支配を続ける状態であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Isshiki Clan of Tango Province was originally Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) one family forming part of the Shishiki (Four major feudal lords who worked for Muromachi bakufu) but, collapsed in entirety during the Sengoku (Warring States) Period in Japan, was dispossessed by the Takeda Clan of the neighboring Wakasa Province, and was then left in a situation of trying somehow or other to continue to use its influence as a ruling family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Isshiki Clan of Tango Province was originally one of the four families used by the Muromachi Shogunate for security but collapsed in entirety during the Sengoku (Warring States) Period in Japan, was dispossessed by the Takeda Clan of the neighboring Wakasa Province, and was then left in a situation of trying somehow or other to continue to use its influence as a ruling family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) one family forming part of the Shishiki (Four major feudal lords who worked for Muromachi bakufu)&quot;→&quot;one of the four families used by the Muromachi Shogunate for security&quot;Deleted comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Isshiki clan of Tango Province was originally one of the four families used by the Muromachi Shogunate for security, but it collapsed in entirety during the Sengoku (Warring States) period (Japan), with its position as Shugo (military governor) taken over by the Takeda clan of the neighboring Wakasa Province, and was then left in a situation of trying somehow or other to continue to use its influence as a ruling family of the past.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を修正・追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>1558年、父の隠居により家督を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1558, inherited the role of head of the clan with the retirement of his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1558, he inherited the role of head of the clan with the retirement of his father.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1558, he inherited the role of head of the clan with the retirement of his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>弟の一色義清を吉原城に送り、丹後の奥三郡の統治につとめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Younger brother Yoshikiyo ISSHIKI was sent to Yoshiwara-jo Castle to serve as ruler of Okumizawa County in Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother, Yoshikiyo ISSHIKI, was sent to Yoshiwara-jo Castle to serve as ruler of Okumizawa County in Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;His&quot;, commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother, Yoshikiyo ISSHIKI, was sent to Yoshiwara-jo Castle to serve as ruler of three districts in the backland of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>奥三郡→three districts in the backland of Tango Province　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>1568年、織田信長が上洛すると信長に急速に接近して親交を深め、1575年の越前一向一揆討伐にも参陣して、信長から丹後国一国を安堵された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Nobunaga ODA&apos;s move to Kyoto in 1568, Nobunaga quickly drew closer and the friendship deepened. In 1575 he fought in the Echizen ikko ikki (religious riot) where he secured all of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nobunaga ODA moved to Kyoto in 1568, Yoshimichi developed a close relationship with him and in 1575, after fighting in the Echizen Ikko-ikki religious riots, Nobunaga gave him control of the whole of Tango Province</e>
<cmt>&quot;With&quot;→&quot;When&quot;Deleted &quot;&apos;s&quot;&quot;move&quot;→&quot;moved&quot;&quot;Nobunaga quickly drew closer and the friendship deepened&quot;→&quot;Yoshimichi developed a close relationship with him&quot;&quot;. In&quot;→&quot;and in&quot;Reworded last part - mistranslated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nobunaga ODA moved to Kyoto in 1568, Yoshimichi developed a close relationship with him and in 1575, after fighting in the Echizen Ikko-ikki religious riots, Nobunaga gave him control of the whole of Tango Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、信長が焼き討ちした比叡山の僧侶や追放した将軍・足利義昭を匿ってしまったため、信長の怒りを買って1578年から信長の命を受けた明智光秀と細川幽斎率いる織田軍に攻められることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because he gave shelter to monks of Mount Hie (who had been burnt out by Nobunaga) and exiled Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, he earned the wrath of Nobunaga and from 1578 he was at Nobunaga`s order attacked by Oda forces comprised of Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because he gave shelter to the monks of Mount Hie (who had been burnt out by Nobunaga) and the exiled Shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, he earned the wrath of Nobunaga and from 1578, Nobunaga ordered his forces, comprised of Yusai HOSOKAWA and Mitsuhide AKECHI, to attack him.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;, commas&quot;he was at Nobunaga`s order attacked by Oda forces comprised of Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and Mitsuhide AKECHI&quot;→&quot;Nobunaga ordered his forces, comprised of Yusai HOSOKAWA and Mitsuhide AKECHI, to attack him&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because he gave shelter to the monks of Mount Hiei (who had been burnt out by Nobunaga) and the exiled Shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, he earned the wrath of Nobunaga and from 1578, Nobunaga ordered his forces, comprised of Yusai HOSOKAWA and Mitsuhide AKECHI, to attack him.</e>
<cmt>Hiei としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>一時はこれを撃退したが、翌年に入ると光秀の調略に応じて義道の家臣団が次々と寝返ってしまい、細川軍の猛攻の前に居城の建部山城も落城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He repulsed the attacks for a time but in response to a scheme of Mutsuhide, Yorimichi&apos;s vassals changes sides one after the other and, prior to a fierce attack by Hosokawas&apos;s forces Takebeyama-jo Castle also capitulated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimichi repulsed the attacks for a time but in response to a scheme of Mutsuhide, Yorimichi&apos;s vassals changed sides one after the other and, prior to a fierce attack by Hosokawas&apos;s forces, Takebeyama-jo Castle also capitulated.</e>
<cmt>&quot;He&quot;→&quot;Yoshimichi&quot;&quot;changes&quot;→&quot;changed&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimichi repulsed the attacks for a time but in response to a scheme of Mutsuhide, Yoshimichi&apos;s vassals changed sides one after the other in the following year, and prior to a fierce attack by Hosokawa&apos;s forces, Takebeyama-jo Castle also capitulated.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos;　としました。Yoshimichi、Hosokawa&apos;s と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>但馬国に逃亡を企てて、起死回生を果たすべく中山城（京都府舞鶴市中山）に身を寄せたが、城主の中山幸兵衛は既に細川方に内応しており、行き場を失った義道は自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He contemplated fleeing to Tajima Province and although he was fighting a lost cause he received shelter at Nakayama-jo Castle (Nakayama, Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture) but, Kobee NAKAYAMA the Lord of the castle, had already betrayed him to the Hosokawa side and having no place to go Yoshimichi committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He contemplated fleeing to Tajima Province and although he was fighting a lost cause he received shelter at Nakayama-jo Castle (Nakayama, Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture); however, Kobee NAKAYAMA, the Lord of the castle, had already betrayed him to the Hosokawa side and, having no place to go, Yoshimichi committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>&quot;but,&quot;&quot;; however,&quot;Added commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He contemplated fleeing to Tajima Province and although he was fighting a lost cause he received shelter at Nakayama-jo Castle (Nakayama, Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture); however, Kobee NAKAYAMA, the lord of the castle, had already betrayed him to the Hosokawa side and, having no place to go, Yoshimichi committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>lord 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>勇将として知られた子の義定と異なり、義道は領内に悪政を敷いたため人望に乏しく、そのために国人の離反を防げなかったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Known differently to that of his brave son Yoshisada, Yoshimichi was not so popular due to the spread of misgovernment throughout his domains and for that reason he could not protect himself from the people`s disaffection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike his son, Yoshisada, who was known for his bravery, Yoshimichi was not so popular due to the spread of misgovernment throughout his domains and for that reason he could not protect himself from the people`s disaffection.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Known differently to that of his brave son Yoshisada&quot;→&quot;Unlike his son, Yoshisada, who was known for his bravery&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike his son, Yoshisada, who was known for his bravery, Yoshimichi was not so popular due to the spread of misgovernment throughout his domains and for that reason he could not protect himself from the people&apos;s disaffection.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lombroso(id:20212), 210.(id:9838), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Cprobot(id:97843), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>