<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>板倉勝重</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsushige ITAKURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsushige ITAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsushige ITAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>板倉 勝重（いたくら かつしげ）は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代の大名、京都所司代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsushige ITAKURA was Kyoto Shoshidai (Kyoto Deputy), a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsushige ITAKURA was a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period, and served as the deputy (Shoshidai) of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsushige ITAKURA was a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period, and served as Kyoto Shoshidai (deputy of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>京都所司代→Kyoto Shoshidai (deputy of Kyoto)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は板倉好重、母は本多光重の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Yoshishige ITAKURA, and his mother was a daughter of Mitsushige HONDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Yoshishige ITAKURA, and his mother was a daughter of Mitsushige HONDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Yoshishige ITAKURA, and his mother was a daughter of Mitsushige HONDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に板倉重宗、板倉重昌ら。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons were Shigemune ITAKURA and Shigemasa ITAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons include Shigemune ITAKURA and Shigemasa ITAKURA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons include Shigemune ITAKURA and Shigemasa ITAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>史料では官位を冠した板倉伊賀守の名で多く残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many historical sources with the name Itakura iga no kami, his official rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many historical sources in which his name, Itakura iga no kami, occurs prefixed by his official rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many historical sources in which his name, Itakura Iga no kami (Governor of Iga Province) occurs prefixed by his official rank.</e>
<cmt>伊賀守の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>三河国額田郡小美村（現在の愛知県岡崎市）に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Oimura, Nukata district, Mikawa Province(current Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Oimura, Nukata district, Mikawa Province(present day Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Oimura, Nukata district, Mikawa Province(present day Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幼少時に出家して浄土真宗の永安寺の僧となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was a child, he renounced the world and became a priest of Yoan-ji Temple of Jodo Shinshu (an offshoot of the Jodo Templesect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was a child, he renounced the world and became a Buddhist priest in the Jodo Shinshu sect (an offshoot of the Jodoshu sect), attached to Yoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was a child, he renounced the world and became a Buddhist priest in the Jodo Shinshu sect (an offshoot of the Jodoshu sect), attached to Yoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ところが1561年（永禄4年）に父の好重が善明提の戦いで戦死、さらに家督を継いだ弟の板倉定重も1581年（天正9年）に武田氏軍の籠る遠江国・高天神城攻め（高天神城の戦い）で戦死したために徳川家康の命で家督を相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his father Yoshishige was killed in the battle of Zemmyo tsutsumi in the Eiroku era, and his brother Sadashige ITAKURA, who had taken over as head of the Family, was also killed in the battle of Takatenjin-jo Castle in Totomi Province where the army of the Takeda clan had hidden themselves in 1581, which resulted in Katsushige taking over as head of the Family on Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s orders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his father, Yoshishige, was killed in the battle of Zemmyo tsutsumi in the Eiroku era, and his brother, Sadashige ITAKURA, who had suceeded their father as head of the Family, was also subsequently killed in the fighting at the battle of Takatenjin-jo Castle in Totomi Province, where the army of the Takeda clan had hidden themselves in 1581, which resulted in Katsushige becoming the next head of the Family, under orders from Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his father, Yoshishige, was killed in the battle of Zemmyo tsutsumi in 1561, and his brother, Sadashige ITAKURA, who had succeeded their father as head of the family, was also subsequently killed in 1581 in the fighting at the battle of Takatenjin-jo Castle in Totomi Province, where the army of the Takeda clan had hidden themselves, which resulted in Katsushige becoming the next head of the family, under orders from Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>1561年　を追加しました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>その後は主に施政面に従事し、1586年（天正14年）には家康が浜松城より駿府城へ移った際には駿府町奉行、1590年（天正18年）に家康が関東へ移封されると、武蔵国新座郡・豊島郡で1,000石を給され、関東代官、江戸町奉行となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he was mainly engaged in administrative policy, and in 1586 when Ieyasu moved from Hamamatsu-jo Castle to Sumbu-jo Castle, he became a town magistrate of Sumbu, in 1590 when Ieyasu&apos;s territory was moved to the Kanto region he became governor of Kanto and town magistrate of Edo, given 1,000 koku in Niikura district and Toyoshima district, Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter he was engaged primarily in implementing administrative policy, and in 1586 when Ieyasu moved from Hamamatsu-jo Castle to Sumbu-jo Castle, he became the town magistrate of Sumbu; in 1590, when Ieyasu&apos;s territory was moved to the Kanto region, he became the governor of Kanto and the town magistrate of Edo, receiving fiefs amounting to 1,000 koku in the disctricts of Niikura and Toyoshima, Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter he was engaged primarily in implementing administrative policy, and in 1586 when Ieyasu moved from Hamamatsu-jo Castle to Sunpu-jo Castle, he became the Sunpu machi-bugyo (town magistrate of Sunpu); in 1590, when Ieyasu&apos;s territory was moved to the Kanto region, he became the Kanto daikan (governor of Kanto) and the Edo machi-bugyo (town magistrate of Sunpu), receiving fiefs amounting to 1,000 koku in the districts of Niikura and Toyoshima, Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>駿府町奉行、関東代官、江戸町奉行　の日本語読みを追加しました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>関ヶ原の戦い後の1601年（慶長6年）、三河国3郡に6,600石を与えられるとともに京都町奉行（のち京都所司代）に任命され、京都の治安維持と朝廷の掌握、さらに大坂城の豊臣家の監視に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1601 after the Battle of Sekigaharaduring the Keicho era, he was given 6,600 koku in 3 districts of Mikawa Province, and at the same time he was appointed as town magistrate of Kyoto (Kyoto Shoshidai [Kyoto Deputy] in later years), took control of maintaining security in Kyoto City, grasped Imperial Court, and then monitored the Toyotomi family of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1601, after the Battle of Sekigaharaduring the Keicho era, he was given fiefs amounting to 6,600 koku in 3 districts of Mikawa Province, and at the same time he was appointed as town magistrate of Kyoto (and later the Kyoto Deputy (Shoshidai)); he assumed responsibilty for maintaining security in the city of Kyoto, reporting on developments at the Imperial Court, and monitoring the Toyotomi family of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar, inconsistent title/capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1601, after the Battle of Sekigahara during the Keicho era, he was given fiefs amounting to 6,600 koku in three districts of Mikawa Province, and at the same time he was appointed as the Kyoto machi-bugyo (town magistrate of Kyoto) (and later the Kyoto Shoshidai); he assumed responsibility for maintaining security in the city of Kyoto, reporting on developments at the Imperial Court, and monitoring the Toyotomi family of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>京都町奉行 の日本語読みを追加しました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1603年（慶長8年）、徳川家康が征夷大将軍に就任して江戸幕府を開いた際に従五位下伊賀国守に叙任され、1609年（慶長14年）には近江国・山城国に領地を加増され1万6,600石余を知行、大名に列している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1603 when Ieyasu Tokugawa assumed the title of seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and established the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), he was ordained ju go i ge, (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), director of Iga, and in 1609 he was given more territory in Omi Province and Yamashiro Province with more than 6,600 koku as enfeoffment and was raised to Daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1603, when Ieyasu Tokugawa assumed the title of Seiitaishogun (literally, &quot;Great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and established the Edo bakufu (feudal government headed by a shogun), he was awarded the coutr rank of Ju-go-i-ge, (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), appointed as director of Iga Province, and in 1609 he was given more territory in the provinces of Omi and Yamashiro, whereupon he was rasied in status to Daimyo, with fiefs amounting to more than 6,600 koku.</e>
<cmt>grammar, inconsistent title/capitalization, some unclear portions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1603, when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA assumed the title of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;Great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and established the Edo bakufu (feudal government headed by a shogun), he was awarded the court rank of Jugoinoge, (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), appointed as Iga no kuni no Kami (officer in charge of regional administration in Iga), and in 1609 he was given more territory in the provinces of Omi and Yamashiro, whereupon he was raised in status to Daimyo, with fiefs amounting to more than 16,600 koku.</e>
<cmt>TOKUGAWA　を大文字にしました。スペルを修正しました。数字を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年の猪熊事件では京都所司代として後陽成天皇と家康の意見調整を図って処分を決め、朝廷統制を強化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made a decision as Kyoto Shoshidai [Kyoto Deputy] on the Inokuma incident of the same year, harmonizing views among Emperor Goyozei and Ieyasu, and strengthened the control of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made a decision as the deputy of Kyoto (Shoshidai) on the Inokuma incident that occurred the same year, harmonizing views among Emperor Goyozei and Ieyasu, and strengthened the system of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made a decision as the Kyoto Shoshidai on the Inokuma incident that occurred the same year, harmonizing views among Emperor Goyozei and Ieyasu, and strengthened the control of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>統制→control としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1615年（元和 (日本)元年）の大坂の役の発端となった大坂の役方広寺鐘銘事件では、本多正純らと共に強硬策を上奏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Siege of Osaka-Hokoji shomei incident which triggered the Siege of Osaka in 1615 during the Genna era, he proposed hard-line measures to the Emperor together with Masazumi HONDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Siege of Osaka-Hokoji shomei incident, which triggered the Siege of Osaka in 1615 during the Genna era, along with Masazumi HONDA and other, he proposed hard-line measures against the Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple Bell, which triggered the Siege of Osaka in 1615, along with Masazumi HONDA and others, he proposed hard-line measures against the Court.</e>
<cmt>Incident of Hoko-ji Temple Bell　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大坂の陣後に江戸幕府が禁中並公家諸法度を施行すると、朝廷がその実施を怠りなく行うよう指導と監視に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Edo bakufu implemented Kinchu narabi ni kuge shohatto (Acts Governing the Imperial Court and Nobility) after the sieges of Osaka, he directed and monitored so that the Imperial Court would steadily implement the Acts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Edo bakufu implemented the Acts Governing the Imperial Court and Nobility (Kinchu narabi ni kuge shohatto) following the sieges of Osaka, Katsushige directed and monitored implementation of the ordinances by the Imperial Court to ensure that the laws were not being ignored.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Edo bakufu implemented Kinchu narabi ni kuge shohatto (Acts Governing the Imperial Court and Nobility) following the Siege of Osaka, Katsushige directed and monitored implementation of the ordinances by the Imperial Court to ensure that the laws were not being ignored.</e>
<cmt>「禁中並公家諸法度」を、日本語（英語の補足）の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1620年（元和 (日本)6年）、子の重宗に京都所司代の職を譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1620, he gave up the post of Kyoto Shoshidai (Kyoto Deputy) to his son Shigemune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1620, he resigned from the post of deputy of Kyoto (Shoshidai) and passed it to his son, Shigemune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1620, he resigned from the post of Kyoto Shoshidai and passed it to his son, Shigemune.</e>
<cmt>Kyoto Shoshidai　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1624年（寛永元年）に死去、享年79。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1624 he died at the age of 79.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1624 he died at the age of 79.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1624 he died at the age of 79.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 0null0(id:582), Reggaeman(id:6214), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), Yanahan(id:2437), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 黒砂糖(id:38164), Sketch(id:102), CooZone(id:42589), YAMAARASHI(id:18211), Aboshi(id:9318), Carkuni(id:79281), Yonoemon(id:55450), Kouchiumi(id:19253), Blowback(id:173308), Kanoe(id:17203), こいつぅ(id:2105), トホホ川(id:50502), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>