<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源成雅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Narimasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Narimasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Narimasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 成雅（みなもと の なりまさ、生没年未詳）は、平安時代後期の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Narimasa (dates of birth and death: unknown) was a court noble in the latter Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Narimasa (dates of birth and death: unknown) was a court noble during the latter Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Narimasa (year of birth and death unknown) was a court noble during the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>dates of birth and death: unknownを(year of birth and death unknownに変更しました。latterをlateに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>村上源氏の陸奥守源信雅（右大臣源顕房の子）の四男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth son of Mutsu no Kami (Ggovernor of Mutsu Province) MINAMOTO no Nobumasa (a son of Minister of the Right MINAMOTO no Akifusa), descendent of Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth son of Mutsu no Kami (Ggovernor of Mutsu Province) MINAMOTO no Nobumasa (a son of the Minister of the Right MINAMOTO no Akifusa), descendent of Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth son of Mutsu no Kami (governor of Mutsu Province) MINAMOTO no Nobumasa (a son of the Minister of the Right MINAMOTO no Akifusa), descendent of Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>Ggovernorをgovernorに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は伊予国守藤原国明の女、あるいは「為家朝臣女」とされるが不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The details of his mother is unknown, although it is said that she was the daughter of Iyo no kuni no Kami (governor of Iyo Province) FUJIWARA no Kuniaki or &apos;the daughter of Tameie ASOMI/ ASON.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details of his mother are unknown, although it is said that she was the daughter of Iyo no kuni no Kami (governor of Iyo Province) FUJIWARA no Kuniaki or &apos;the daughter of Tameie ASOMI/ ASON.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details of his mother are unknown, although it is said that she was the daughter of Iyo no kuni no Kami (governor of Iyo Province) FUJIWARA no Kuniaki or &apos;the daughter of Tameie ASOMI/ ASON.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正四位下、左近衛中将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ranked Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was Sakone no chujo (middle captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ranked Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was Sakone no chujo (middle captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was ranked Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was Sakone no chujo (middle captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>姉妹が妻となっていた藤原頼長に近侍し、保元元年(1156年)における保元の乱の際には、頼長とともに崇徳天皇方に参加する（当時成雅は左近権少将の職にあった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He closely served FUJIWARA no Yorinaga, since his elder sister as well as his little sister became Yorinaga&apos;s wives, and when Hogen Disturbance broke out in 1156, he took part in the side of Emperor Sutoku with Yorinaga (at that time, he was in the post of Sakon no gon no shosho).</e>
<cmt>「姉妹が妻」→his elder sister as well as his little sister としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He closely served FUJIWARA no Yorinaga, since his elder sister as well as his little sister became Yorinaga&apos;s wives, and when the Hogen Disturbance broke out in 1156, he took part on the side of Emperor Sutoku with Yorinaga (at that time, he was at the post of Sakon no gon no shosho).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He closely served FUJIWARA no Yorinaga, since his elder sister as well as his little sister became Yorinaga&apos;s wives, and when the Hogen Disturbance broke out in 1156, he took part on the side of Emperor Sutoku with Yorinaga (at that time, he was at the post of Sakon no gon no shosho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>上皇方が後白河天皇方に敗れると、出家（法名は蓮浄）し恭順の意を示すが、赦されず越後国に配流となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Retired Emperor side was defeated by the Emperor Goshirakawa side, he entered the priesthood (his homyo (Buddhist name given to a person who was died or has entered the priesthood) was Renjo) to demonstrate his allegiance, however he was not acquitted and banished to Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Retired Emperor side was defeated by Emperor Goshirakawa, he entered the priesthood (his homyo - a Buddhist name given to a person who died or had entered the priesthood - was Renjo) to demonstrate his allegiance, however, he was not acquitted and was banished to Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Retired Emperor side was defeated by Emperor Goshirakawa, he entered the priesthood (his homyo - a Buddhist name given to a person who died or had entered the priesthood - was Renjo) to demonstrate his allegiance, however, he was not acquitted and was banished to Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>数年を経て応保年間には帰洛が許され、その後かつての敵である後白河院の近習となっていたことが『梁塵秘抄』に見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several years after, he was allowed to return to Kyoto during the Oho era, and according to &quot;Ryojin-hisho&quot; (Songs to make the dust dance on the beams), he later became kinshu (attendant) to Goshirakawa-in (Retired Emperor Goshirakawa), who once was his enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several years after, he was allowed to return to Kyoto during the Oho era, and according to &quot;Ryojin-hisho&quot; (Songs to make the dust dance on the beams), he later became kinshu (attendant) to Goshirakawa-in (Retired Emperor Goshirakawa), who once was his enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several years after, he was allowed to return to Kyoto during the Oho era, and according to &quot;Ryojin-hisho&quot; (Songs to make the dust dance on the beams), he later became kinshu (attendant) to Goshirakawa-in (Retired Emperor Goshirakawa), who once was his enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>僧形となっていたことから、世上、近江中将入道と呼ばれたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he was in the priesthood, he was commonly called Omichujo-Nyudo (monk and middle captain of Omi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he was in the priesthood, he was commonly called Omichujo-Nyudo (monk and middle captain of Omi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he was in the priesthood, he was commonly called Omichujo-Nyudo (monk and middle captain of Omi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>降って安元3年(1177年)には、鹿ケ谷の陰謀に加担したかどで捕らえられ、再度佐渡国に配流となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in 1177, he was arrested on suspicion of being involved in the Shishigatani Plot, and again banished to Sado Island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in 1177, he was arrested on suspicion of being involved in the Shishigatani Plot, and again banished to Sado Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in 1177, he was arrested on suspicion of being involved in the Shishigatani Plot, and again banished to Sado Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>