<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>毛利元春</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoharu MORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoharu MORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoharu MORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>毛利 元春（もうり もとはる、元亨3年（1323年） - ？）は、南北朝時代 (日本)・室町時代における毛利家の当主で、毛利親衡の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoharu MORI (1323 - the year of his death unknown) was the head of the MORI family during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and Muromachi, and a legitimate son of Chikahira MORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoharu MORI (1323 - year of death unknown) was the head of the MORI family who lived during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and Muromachi period, and was the legitimate son of Chikahira MORI.</e>
<cmt>室町時代→Muromachi period[&quot;period&quot;が抜けていたので、補いました]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoharu MORI (1323 - year of death unknown) was the head of the MORI family who lived during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and Muromachi period, and was the legitimate son of Chikahira MORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>子に毛利広房・厚母元房・麻原広内・毛利忠広・長井広世・福原元淵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirofusa MORI, 厚母元房, 麻原広内, Tadahiro MORI, Hiroyo NAGAI, and 福原元淵 were his children.</e>
<cmt>厚母元房、,麻原広内、福原元淵→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Hirofusa MORI, Motomusa ATSUMO, Hironai OBARA, Tadahiro MORI, Hiroyo NAGAI and Motofuchi FUKUBARA.</e>
<cmt>厚母→ATSUMO[山口県にある地名を参照しました]麻原広内→Hironai OBARA[「麻原」はhttp://fukubara.web.infoseek.co.jp/personality/fukubarahirotoshi.htm を参照しましたが、「広内」は仮表記です]福原元淵→Motofuchi FUKUBARA[「福原」は、Wikipedia 「安芸福原氏」の項目を参照しましたが、「元淵」は、仮表記です]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Hirofusa MORI, Motomusa ATSUMO, Hironai OBARA, Tadahiro MORI, Hiroyo NAGAI and Motofuchi FUKUBARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初名は高師泰から一字拝領し「師親（もろちか）」と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was called Morochika, a part of which was borrowed from the name KO no Moroyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was first named &apos;Morochika&apos; written as &apos;師親&apos; in Japanese by receiving one letter &apos;師&apos; from the name KO no Moroyasu written as &apos;高師泰&apos; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>それぞれの漢字を表記しないと、意味が通じなくなるので、漢字表記を追加しました。また、英訳は、用語集及び用語リストのレビュー結果を参照し、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was first named &apos;Morochika&apos; written as &apos;師親&apos; in Japanese by receiving one letter &apos;師&apos; from the name KO no Moroyasu written as &apos;高師泰&apos; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は従五位下、備中守、左近将監、権大丞、右馬頭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official court rank was Jugoinoka (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), and he served as Bicchu no kami (governor of Bicchu Province), Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Taijo (Senior Secretary), and Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After holding the office of Governor of Bicchu and rising to the rank of Jugoinoge (Juior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), he also held the office of Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Taijo (Senior Secretary) and Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>用語リストのレビュー結果を参照し、変更しました。従五位下→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)[読み方を&quot;Jugoinoka&quot;と表記していたので、訂正しました]備中守→Governor of Bicchu[作業指示書一式の&quot;Dos and Don&apos;ts for the Kyoto Project&quot;第3項目、Be careful not to &quot;romanize&quot; Japanese terms unnecessarily、に従い、変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After holding the office of Governor of Bicchu and rising to the rank of Jugoinoge (Juior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), he also held the office of Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Taijo (Senior Secretary) and Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>13歳で元服し、曽祖父・毛利時親の代官として足利尊氏に一貫して従った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having had Genpuku (coming of age) ceremony at the age of 13, he consistently followed Takauji ASHIKAGA as a substitue for Tokichika MORI, his great-grandfater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoharu had Genpuku (coming-of-age ceremony for boys) at the age of 13, and consistently followed Takauji ASHIKAGA on behalf of his great-grandfather, Tokichika MORI.</e>
<cmt>元服→Genpuku (coming-of-age ceremony for boys)[用語集を参照し、変更しました]代官として→on behalf of[&quot;as a substitute for&quot;は、物に対して使う場合が多いので、変更しました]曽祖父→great-grandfather[ミススペルを訂正しました]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoharu had Genpuku (coming-of-age ceremony for boys) at the age of 13, and consistently followed Takauji ASHIKAGA on behalf of his great-grandfather, Tokichika MORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>祖父の毛利貞親、父の毛利親衡は後醍醐天皇の南朝 (日本)に従って越後国南条荘にて活躍し、一家で対立することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, his grandfater Sadachika MORI, and his fatehr Chikahira MORI followed Southern Court (Japan) ruled by Emperor Godaigo, and worked actively in Nanjo-so in Echigo Province, which caused a conflict within the MORI family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since his grandfather, Sadachika MORI, and his father, Chikahira MORI, followed the Southern Court (Japan) ruled by the Emperor Godaigo and played active roles in Nanjo-so in Echigo Province, a conflict arose within the MORI family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;grandfather&quot;と &quot;father&quot; のミススペルを訂正し、不必要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since his grandfather, Sadachika MORI, and his father, Chikahira MORI, followed the Southern Court (Japan) ruled by the Emperor Godaigo and played active roles in Nanjo-so in Echigo Province, a conflict arose within the MORI family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>後見役の曽祖父時親はそうした争乱の最中の1341年（暦応4年）に没し、安芸国吉田荘の支配は元春が引き継ぐことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Tokichika, his greate grandfater and conservator died in the middle of the conflict in 1341, Motoharu took over the control of Yoshida-so in Aki Province,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his great-grandfather, Tokichika, who acted as his conservator, died in the middle of the conflict in 1341, Motoharu succeeded to the control of Yoshida-so in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;great-grandfather&quot;のハイフンを付け、ミススペルを訂正し、文尾のカンマをピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his great-grandfather, Tokichika, who acted as his conservator, died in the middle of the conflict in 1341, Motoharu succeeded to the control of Yoshida-so in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>元春は19歳で家督を相続し「郡山殿」と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoharu succeeded to the reigns of the family at the age of 19, and was called &quot;郡山殿&quot;</e>
<cmt>郡山殿→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After succeeding to the family headship at the age of 19, Motoharu came to be called &apos;Koriyama-dono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>家督→family headship[用語集を参照し、変更しました]「郡山殿」→&apos;Koriyama-dono&apos;[「郡山城」にちなみ、「郡山殿」と呼ばれるようになりました。「～殿」の表記は、用語集を参照しました]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After succeeding to the family headship at the age of 19, Motoharu came to be called &apos;Koriyama-dono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一族を敵に回して勝ち残った元春は、九州探題今川貞世にしたがって、鎮西へ下向し戦いを繰り広げることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoharu, who made an enemy of his family, survived and left the capital to Chinzei (nickname of Kyushu), following Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner) Sadayo IMAGAWA to wage a battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoharu who won a battle with his hostile family headed down to Chinzei (nickname of Kyushu) in attendance on Sadayo IMAGAWA, Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner), and waged battles.</e>
<cmt>一族を敵に回して勝ち残った→survive a battle with his hostile family[「敵対する一族との戦いに勝った」と同じ意味であるので、簡潔な表現としました]～へ下向する→head down to ～[対訳では、&quot;leaving the capital&quot;とありますが、元春は、京から鎮西に向かったのではないので、変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoharu who won a battle with his hostile family headed down to Chinzei (nickname of Kyushu) in attendance on Sadayo IMAGAWA, Kyushu Tandai (local commissioner), and waged battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>一方、敵対関係となった父・親衡は、九州の南朝方勢力、周防の大内弘世などと結んで、九州出陣中の元春の領地へ侵攻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Motoharu&apos;s father Chikahira, with whom he had a hostile relationship, invaded Motoharu&apos;s territory in cooperation with pro-Southern Court forces in Kyushu and Hiroyo Ouchi from Suo Province while he was going to the front in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Motoharu&apos;s father, Chikahira, who got adversarial with Motoharu, cooperated with the Southern Court forces in Kyushu, Hiroyo OUCHI in Suo Province and so on, and invaded Motoharu&apos;s territory during his departure for the front in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>Motoharu&apos;s father と Chikahira の間に、カンマを付けました。南朝方勢力→the South Court forces[用語集を参照し、変更しました]大内弘世→Hiroyo OUCHI[用語集を参照し、&quot;OUCHI&quot;と大文字表記に変更しました]などと→and so on[訳されていなかったので、補いました]九州出陣中→during his departure for the front in Kyushu[対訳・用語集において、「出陣」を&quot;departure for the front&quot;と表記しているので、変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Motoharu&apos;s father, Chikahira, who got adversarial with Motoharu, cooperated with the Southern Court forces in Kyushu, Hiroyo OUCHI in Suo Province and so on, and invaded Motoharu&apos;s territory during his departure for the front in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>1385年に嫡子広房が安芸西条にて戦死するに及び、その子毛利光房に跡を継がせ、その成長まで後見することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his legitimate child Hirofusa was killed in a battle in Saijo, Aki Province, Motoharu made Hirodusa&apos;s son Mitsufusa MORI succeed to Hirofusa&apos;s position, then Motoharu acted as a guardian for Mitusfusa until he grew up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, his legitimate son, Hirofusa, was killed in a battle at Saijo in Aki Province in 1385, and Motoharu had Hirofusa&apos;s son, Mitsufusa MORI, succeed to own position, and acted as guardian until Mitsufusa grew up.</e>
<cmt>「1385年」の訳が抜けていたので、補いました。～に及び→as a result[「結果として～となってしまった」との意味が含まれるので、変更しました]嫡子→legitimate son[対訳の&quot;legitimate child&quot;でも間違いではないのですが、より厳密に表記するため、変更しました]&quot;Hirofusa&apos;s&quot;及び&quot;Mitsufusa&quot;のミススペルを訂正しました。「その子毛利光房に跡を継がせ」は、「広房が戦死したので、光房に元春の跡を継がせた」の意味なので、Hirofusa&apos;s position を own position に変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, his legitimate son, Hirofusa, was killed in a battle at Saijo in Aki Province in 1385, and Motoharu had Hirofusa&apos;s son, Mitsufusa MORI, succeed to own position, and acted as guardian until Mitsufusa grew up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>元春の代あたりから庶子家が派生し、坂氏・有富氏・麻原氏・中馬氏・福原氏などが生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around the age of Motoharu, branch families of the MORI family such as SAKA clan, ARITOMI clan, OBARA clan, CHUMAN clan, and FUKUHARA clan were created by giving birth to children out of wedlock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around the age of Motoharu, derivative families were established by illegitimate children, and the Saka family, Aritomi clan, Obara clan, Chuma clan, Fukubara clan and so on were established.</e>
<cmt>庶子家が派生する→derivative families were established by illegitimate children[用語集を参照し、変更しました]派生する→derive[用語集を参照し、変更しました]各「氏」の名前の表記を対訳・用語集の表記に従い、変更しました。中馬氏→Chuma clan[&quot;CHUMAN&quot;とは読まないので、最後の&quot;N&quot;を削除し、また、表記方法を変更しました]福原氏→Fukubara clan[Wikipediaを参照し、変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around the age of Motoharu, derivative families were established by illegitimate children, and the Saka family, Aritomi clan, Obara clan, Chuma clan, Fukubara clan and so on were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また坂氏からさらに桂氏・光永氏・志道氏などの庶流家が生まれ、戦国大名としての毛利氏を支える一族家臣となっていくのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, more branch families such as KATSURA clan, MITSUNAGA clan, and SHIJI Clan were created from SAKA clan, and became vassals of the MORI clan as a warlord in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, branch families such as the Katsura clan, Mitsunaga clan, Shiji clan and so on were derived from the Saka clan, and became subordinate families supporting the MORI clan as Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>各「氏」の名前の表記を対訳・用語集の表記に従い、変更しました。&quot;and&quot;の後のスペースを一つに減らしました。生まれ→derived[この場合、「派生する」の意味なので、用語集を参照し、変更しました]～など→and so on[訳が抜けていたので、補いました]支える→supporting[訳が抜けていたので、補いました]一族家臣→subordinate families[「家臣となる家々」と解釈し、変更しました]戦国大名→Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period)[用語リストの指示に従い、変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, branch families such as the Katsura clan, Mitsunaga clan, Shiji clan and so on were derived from the Saka clan, and became subordinate families supporting the MORI clan as Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kuma83(id:31177), Kawai(id:5634), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>