<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原忠房</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadafusa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadafusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadafusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 忠房（ふじわら の ただふさ、生年未詳 - 延長 (元号)6年（928年）12月1日 (旧暦)）は、平安時代前期の廷臣、舞楽家、歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadafusa (birth date unknown-January 14, 929) was a retainer of the Imperial Court, bugakuka (a person who performed traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing), and kajin (waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) poet) in early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadafusa (birth date unknown-January 14, 929) was a retainer of the Imperial Court, bugakuka (a person who performed traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing), and kajin (waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) poet) in the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadafusa (year of birth unknown - January 19, 929) was a retainer of the Imperial Court, court music and dance performer and poet in the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>birth date unknown-January 14, 929 をyear of birth unknown - January 19, 929 に修正しました。bugakuka (a person who performed traditional Japanese court music accompanied by dancing) をcourt music and dance performer に修正しました。kajin (waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) poet) をpoet に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原京家の出身で右京大夫藤原興嗣（あるいは興嗣の父藤原広敏）の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came from the Fujiwara Kyo Family (Fujiwara family in Kyoto) and was the son of FUJIWARA no Okitsugu (or FUJIWARA no Hirotoshi, who was the father of Okitsugu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came from the Fujiwara Kyo Family (Fujiwara family in Kyoto) and was the son of FUJIWARA no Okitsugu (or FUJIWARA no Hirotoshi, who was the father of Okitsugu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came from the Fujiwara Kyo Family (Fujiwara family in Kyoto) and was the son of FUJIWARA no Okitsugu (or FUJIWARA no Hirotoshi, who was the father of Okitsugu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>従四位・京職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had the rank of Jushinoi and worked in Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had the rank of Jushinoi and worked in Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the rank of Jushinoi and worked in Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>中古三十六歌仙の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the members of Chuko Sanjurokkasen (thirty-six poets selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the members of Chuko Sanjurokkasen (thirty-six poets selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the medieval 36 Immortal Poets.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に従いmembers of Chuko Sanjurokkasen (thirty-six poets selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane) をmedieval 36 Immortal Poets に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>官歴は右兵衛佐、左少将等を歴任し、大和国国司、従四位上・山城国守、右京大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of his court official positions were, Uhyoe no suke (assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Yamashiro no kuni no kami (Governor of Yamashiro Province) with the Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) rank, and Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of his court official positions was: Uhyoe no suke (assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Yamashiro no kuni no kami (Governor of Yamashiro Province) with the rank of Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), and Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His record of offices and ranks held was: Uhyoe no suke (assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards), Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Yamashiro no kuni no kami (Governor of Yamashiro Province) with the rank of Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), and Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>官歴統一リストの表記に従いThe history of his court official positions をHis record of offices and ranks held に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>一門には雅楽に秀でた者が多く、忠房も琵琶の名手であった父の興嗣よりその才を受け継ぎ、歌舞や管弦の分野において活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were people who excelled in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) among the disciples, and Tadafusa himself was the excellent player of biwa (lute) for he received that talent from his father Okitsugu and was active in the fields of utamai (a performance of singing and dancing) and Kangen (gagaku piece without dance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his disciples there were people who excelled in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), and Tadafusa himself was an excellent player of the biwa (lute), for he received that talent from his father, Okitsugu, and was active in the fields of utamai (a performance of singing and dancing) and Kangen (gagaku piece without dance).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among his family there were people who excelled in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), and Tadafusa himself was an excellent player of the biwa (lute), for he received that talent from his father, Okitsugu, and was active in the fields of utamai (a performance of singing and dancing) and Kangen (gagaku piece without dance).</e>
<cmt>一門disciples を family に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>忠房が作曲し敦実親王が振付を施した胡蝶や延喜楽は、高麗楽の代表的な作品として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kocho (Butterflies) and Engiraku that Tadafusa composed the music as Imperial Prince Atsumi choreographed were famous for the representative works of Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kocho (Butterflies) and Engiraku for which Tadafusa composed the music and which Imperial Prince Atsumi choreographed were famous as representative works of Komagaku music.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kocho (Butterflies) and Engiraku for which Tadafusa composed the music and which Imperial Prince Atsumi choreographed were famous as representative works of Komagaku (Korean Music).</e>
<cmt>Komagaku music をKomagaku (Korean Music) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>また歌人としての名声も高く、に開催された「日本紀竟宴和歌」や、の「宇多法皇春日行幸名所和歌」などに出詠するとともに、同じくの「京極御息所歌合」では判者を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also held a high reputation as the kajin, performed his poetry in &apos;Nihongi kyoen waka&apos; (The World of Nihongo-kyo en-waka) and &apos;Uda hoo kasuga gyoko meisyo waka&apos; (waka of Cloistered Emperor Uda&apos;s visit to famous place), and served as a judge in &apos;Kyogoku no Miyasundokoro utaawase&apos; (poetry contest of KYOGOKU no Miyasundokoro).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also held a high reputation as a kajin, performed his poetry in &apos;Nihongi kyoen waka&apos; (The World of Nihongo-kyo en-waka) and &apos;Uda hoo kasuga gyoko meisyo waka&apos; (waka of Cloistered Emperor Uda&apos;s visit to famous place), and served as a judge in &apos;Kyogoku no Miyasundokoro utaawase&apos; (poetry contest of KYOGOKU no Miyasundokoro).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also held a high reputation as a poet, performed his poetry in &apos;Nihongi Kyoen Waka&apos; (The Poems at the Completion Banquet for the Lectures on &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot;) and &apos;Uda hoo kasuga gyoko meisyo waka&apos; (poems at Cloistered Emperor Uda&apos;s visit to famous place), and served as a judge in &apos;Kyogoku no Miyasundokoro utaawase&apos; (poetry contest of KYOGOKU no Miyasundokoro).</e>
<cmt>kajin を poet に修正しました。&apos;Nihongi kyoen waka&apos; (The World of Nihongo-kyo en-waka) を&apos;Nihongi Kyoen Waka&apos; (The Poems at the Completion Banquet for the Lectures on &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot;) に修正しました。waka of Cloistered Emperor をpoems at Cloistered Emperor に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>中古三十六歌仙の一人として知られ、勅撰和歌集（『古今和歌集』、『後撰和歌集』、『拾遺和歌集』）に17首が入首している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known to be one of the Chuko Sanjurokkasen and had seventeen of his waka poems in Chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) (&quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (the second of the Imperial anthologies of classical Waka poetry), and &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known to be one of the Chuko Sanjurokkasen and had seventeen of his waka poems in Chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) (&quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (the second of the Imperial anthologies of classical Waka poetry), and &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known to be one of the Chuko Sanjurokkasen and had seventeen of his waka poems in Chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) (&quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry), &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (the second of the Imperial anthologies of classical Waka poetry), and &quot;Shui Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Gleanings of Japanese Poems)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), VolkovBot(id:105371), Ks8823(id:130146), 松茸(id:27535), Vynmh3965(id:176195), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), YOSHI438(id:174755), Snap55(id:89773), ぽーるべあー(id:152979), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>