<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一条兼香</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneyoshi ICHIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneyoshi ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneyoshi ICHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一条 兼香（いちじょう かねよし/かねか、元禄5年12月16日 (旧暦)（1693年1月12日）－寛延4年8月2日 (旧暦)（1751年9月21日））は、江戸時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneyoshi ICHIJO (his given name can also be pronounced &quot;Kaneka&quot;)(January 12, 1693 - September 21, 1751) was Kugyo (the top court officials) in the middle of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneyoshi ICHIJO (his given name can also be pronounced &quot;Kaneka&quot;, January 12, 1693 - September 21, 1751) was a Kugyo (top court official) in the mid-Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>ArticleGrammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneyoshi ICHIJO (his given name can also be pronounced &quot;Kaneka,&quot; January 21, 1693 - September 21, 1751) was a Kugyo (top court official) in the mid-Edo period.</e>
<cmt>元禄5年12月16日→変換すると西暦1693年1月21日となるため、表記を修正、カンマの位置を移動、Edo periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>桜町天皇の側近として活躍し、従一位関白左大臣・太政大臣を歴任して14年にわたって朝廷の中枢にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active as a close adviser of Emperor Sakuramachi, held Juichii (Junior First Rank) Kanpaku sadaijin (imperial regent and minister of the left) and Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) positions for fourteen years, and was a center of the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a close adviser of Emperor Sakuramachi, remaining at the center of the court for fourteen years, reaching Juichii (Junior First Rank) and holding the positions of Kanpaku-sadaijin (Regent and Minister of the Left) and Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister of State).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityHyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a close adviser of Emperor Sakuramachi, remaining at the center of the court for fourteen years, reaching Juichii (Junior First Rank) and holding the positions of Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) and Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister of State).</e>
<cmt>Kanpaku Sadaijinとし、補足の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「後円成寺」と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goenjoji&apos; was used as a pseudonym.</e>
<cmt>後円成寺→Goenjoji[正しい読み方が確認できませんでした]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also used the name &apos;Goenjoji&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also used the name &apos;Goenjoji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>摂関家の一つである鷹司家の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Takatsukasa family, one of Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Takatsukasa family, one of the five Sekkan-ke families that provided regents.</e>
<cmt>Changed explanation of &quot;Sekkan-ke&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Takatsukasa family, one of the five Sekkan-ke families that provided regents and advisers to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>「摂関家」→&quot;regents&quot;は「摂政」であり、「関白」も含めた説明となるよう修正しました。(参考: Eudict)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母方の叔母が継室として嫁いでいた一条兼輝に男子がいなかったために、養子として一条家に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by the Ichijo family since his maternal aunt was married into Kaneteru ICHIJO as a second wife but did not have any male child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by the Ichijo family since his maternal aunt, who was married to Kaneteru ICHIJO, did not have any sons.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationRelative pronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by the Ichijo family since his maternal aunt, who was married to Kaneteru ICHIJO, did not have any sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>蔵書家として知られた養父の影響で学問に励み、後に政敵となる近衛家熙からも「当世の才」として高く評価された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was studious by the influence of his adopted father, who was known as a book collector, and was highly praised as &apos;a talent of the period&apos; by Iehiro KONOE, who would later be a political enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influenced by his adoptive father, who was known as a book collector, he studied hard and was highly praised as &apos;a talent of the period&apos; by Iehiro KONOE, who would later be a political enemy.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influenced by his adoptive father, who was known as a book collector, he studied hard and was highly praised as &apos;a talent of the period&apos; by Iehiro KONOE, who would later be a political enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元禄15年（1701年）10歳で元服すると、3年後に従三位権中納言に任ぜられて公卿に加わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) at ten years old in 1701 and joined Kugyo as he was appointed to Jusanmi rank Gonchunagon (Junior Third Rank Provisional Middle Counselor) three years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1701, at the age of ten, he celebrated his coming of age, and three years later joined the Kugyo when he was appointed Jusanmi Gonchunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor with the Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1701, at the age of ten, he celebrated his coming of age, and three years later joined the Kugyo when he was appointed Jusanmi Gon Chunagon (Provisional Vice-Councilor of State with the Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに基づき、Gonchunagon→Gon Chunagonとし、補足修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>宝永2年（1705年）に養父が死去し14歳（数え歳）で一条家を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1705, his adopted father died and succeeded the Ichijo family at fourteen years old (in his fourteenth year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1705, his adoptive father died and he became the head of the Ichijo family at the age of fourteen (in his fourteenth year).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1705, his adoptive father died and he became the head of the Ichijo family at the age of fourteen (in his fourteenth year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当時、近衛基熙・家熙父子が江戸幕府征夷大将軍徳川家宣の外戚である事を背景として 院政を行っていた霊元上皇と対立し、家熙の娘を中御門天皇の女御にするなど朝廷内で絶大な力を振るっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Motohiro KONOE and his son, Iehiro conflicted with the retired Emperor Reigen who administered cloister government in the context of being a maternal relative of Ienobu TOKUGAWA, a seii taishogun (literally, great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), he had Iehiro&apos;s daughter to be a nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of an emperor)), and wielded immense power within the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Motohiro KONOE and his son, Iehiro, were in conflict with retired Emperor Reigen, who headed a cloistered government and was a maternal relative of Shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA, and by having Iehiro&apos;s daughter made a nyogo (emperor&apos;s consort) wielded immense power within the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationRevised for clarity, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Motohiro KONOE and his son, Iehiro, were in conflict with the Retired Emperor Reigen, who headed a cloistered government and was a maternal relative of Ienobu TOKUGAWA, the Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and by having Iehiro&apos;s daughter made a nyogo (emperor&apos;s consort) wielded immense power within the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>retired Emperor Reigen→the Retired Emperor Reigenとし、「江戸幕府征夷大将軍」を訳出するため一部訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これに対して兼香は実兄の鷹司兼熙、父方の従兄弟である九条輔実・二条綱平兄弟（兄弟の父である九条兼晴は兼香の実父・鷹司房輔の実弟）と結んでこれに対抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, Kaneyoshi was against it together with his real brother, Kanehiro TAKATSUKASA, and paternal cousins, Sukezane KUJO and Tsunahira NIJO brothers (Kaneharu KUJO, their father, was Fusasuke TAKATSUKASA&apos;s real brother, Kaneyoshi&apos;s father).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, Kaneyoshi was opposed to this, together with his brother, Kanehiro TAKATSUKASA, and paternal cousins, Sukezane KUJO and Tsunahira NIJO (their father, Kaneharu KUJO, was the brother of Kaneyoshi&apos;s father, Fusasuke TAKATSUKASA).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, Kaneyoshi was opposed to this, together with his brother, Kanehiro TAKATSUKASA, and paternal cousins, Sukezane KUJO and Tsunahira NIJO (their father, Kaneharu KUJO, was the brother of Kaneyoshi&apos;s father, Fusasuke TAKATSUKASA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、享保7年（1722年）に内大臣に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) in 1722.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he was appointed Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 1722.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he was appointed Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) in 1722.</e>
<cmt>Udaijin→Naidaijinに訂正、補足修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>享保13年（1728年）、右大臣であった兼香は皇太子昭仁親王の東宮傅を兼務する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1728, Kaneyoshi as Udaijin, also had an additional post as togu-no-fu (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) for Imperial Prince Teruhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1728, Kaneyoshi as well as being Udaijin, also held the additional post of Togu-no-Fu, in charge of the education of Crown Prince Teruhito.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, wordiness. Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1728, Kaneyoshi as well as being Udaijin (Minister of the Right), also held the additional post of Togu no Fu, in charge of the education of Crown Prince Teruhito.</e>
<cmt>Udaijinの補足追加、統一事項よりTogu-no-Fuのハイフンを消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>博識で有職故実や垂加神道にも精通していた兼香は、衰退した朝廷儀式の再興と組織改革の実現を志していた皇太子から厚い信任を得るようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was knowledgeable and have a thorough knowledge of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) and Suika Shinto (Shinto thoughts advocated by Ansai YAMAZAKI), and gained the confidence from the Prince who had his sights on resuscitating rituals in court and delivering organizational reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extremely knowledgeable and with a thorough knowledge of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) and Suika Shinto (a mix of Shinto and Confucianism), he gained the confidence of the Prince, who had his sights on reviving court rituals and implementing organizational reform.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extremely knowledgeable and with a thorough knowledge of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) and Suika Shinto (a mix of Shinto and Confucianism), he gained the confidence of the Crown Prince, who had his sights on reviving court rituals and implementing organizational reform.</e>
<cmt>Prince→Crown Princeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この間の享保17年（1732年）に従一位に叙せられ、享保20年（1735年）には皇太子が桜町天皇として即位する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, he was appointed to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 1732 and the Prince was enthroned as Emperor Sakuramachi in 1735.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, he was appointed to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 1732 and the Prince was enthroned as Emperor Sakuramachi in 1735.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, he was appointed to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 1732 and the Crown Prince was enthroned as Emperor Sakuramachi in 1735.</e>
<cmt>Prince→Crown Princeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>元文2年8月29日 (旧暦)（1737年9月23日）、父である中御門上皇を失って親政を開始した桜町天皇は左大臣であった兼香を関白に任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 23, 1737, Emperor Sakuramachi, who started the direct Imperial rule after losing his father, the retired Emperor Nakamikado, he appointed Kaneyoshi, who was Sadaijin (minister of the left) at that time, to be Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 23, 1737, Emperor Sakuramachi, who had begun ruling directly after losing his father, retired Emperor Nakamikado, appointed Kaneyoshi, who was Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) at that time, to be Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPronounCapital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 23, 1737, Emperor Sakuramachi, who had begun ruling directly after losing his father, the Retired Emperor Nakamikado, appointed Kaneyoshi, who was Sadaijin at that time, to be Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>retired Emperor Nakamikado→the Retired Emperor Nakamikadoに修正、Sadaijin, Kanpaku→既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>関白となった兼香は東山天皇の時代に一度は復活しながらも財政不足から次の中御門天皇時代には開けなかった大嘗祭復活のための支援を江戸幕府に求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneyoshi, who became Kanpaku, called on the Edo bakufu to assist a revival of Daijo-sai festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor), which could not being held during the period of Emperor Nakamikado after it was revived once during the period of Emperor Higashiyama due to a lack of finance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After becoming Kanpaku, Kaneyoshi asked the Edo Shogunate for assistance in reviving the Daijo-sai festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor), which had drained the finances when it was revived once for Emperor Higashiyama and so was not held for Emperor Nakamikado.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After becoming Kanpaku, Kaneyoshi asked the Edo bakufu for assistance in reviving the Daijo-sai festival (a festival to celebrate the succession of an emperor), which had drained the finances when it was revived once for Emperor Higashiyama and so was not held for Emperor Nakamikado.</e>
<cmt>Edo Shogunate→Edo bakufuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当時の将軍徳川吉宗も朝廷の伝統儀式の復活に賛同を示し、翌年元文3年（1738年）には桜町天皇の大嘗祭が開催される事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogun of the time, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, agreed with the revival of the traditional rituals in court and Daijo-sai festival of Emperor Sakuramachi was held in 1738.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogun at the time, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, agreed with the revival of the traditional rituals in court and Emperor Sakuramachi&apos;s Daijo-sai festival was held in 1738.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionMoved &quot;Emperor Sakuramachi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogun at the time, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, agreed with the revival of the traditional rituals in court and Emperor Sakuramachi&apos;s Daijo-sai festival was held in 1738.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、元文4年（1539年）には吉宗の依頼により、当時和歌に優れた4人の公家（中院通躬・烏丸光栄・三条西公福・冷泉為久）を推挙して吉宗に自作の和歌を提出させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, as a request from Yoshimune in 1539, four kuge (court noble) (Michimi NAKANOIN, Mitsuhide KARASUMARU, Kintomi SANJONISHI, and Tamehisa REIZEI) excellent in waka at that time were recommended and presented their own waka to Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in 1539, at a request by Yoshimune, he recommended four kuge (court nobles), Michimi NAKANOIN, Mitsuhide KARASUMARU, Kintomi SANJONISHI, and Tamehisa REIZEI, who were outstanding waka poets of the period and had them present their waka to Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt>&quot;元文4年&quot; is 1739, not 1539 but as the Japanese has the latter, I left it as is.Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in 1739, at a request by Yoshimune, he recommended four kuge (court nobles), Michimi NAKANOIN, Mitsuhide KARASUMARU, Kintomi SANJONISHI, and Tamehisa REIZEI, who were outstanding waka poets of the period and had them present their waka to Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt>元文4年→変換すると1739年のため、訳文を修正 （原文の1539年は誤りと思われます)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>この元文2・3年は兼香と桜町天皇にとっては重要な意義の持つ年であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These two to three years had an important meaning for Kaneyoshi and Emperor Sakuramachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These two to three years were extremely significant for Kaneyoshi and Emperor Sakuramachi.</e>
<cmt>Revised to make more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These two to three years were extremely significant for Kaneyoshi and Emperor Sakuramachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そもそも兼香の関白就任の直接の要因は、前任の二条吉忠の病死によるものであったが、この年には基熙・家熙と並んで3代にわたって朝廷で優位を保ってきた太政大臣近衛家久も病死、更に翌年には右大臣になったばかりの二条宗熙が父・吉忠の後を追うように病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The direct reason for Kaneyoshi to be appointed to Kanpaku in the first place was the death of the former Kanpaku, Yoshitada NIJO from disease, but Daijo-daijin, Iehisa KONOE, who maintained his priority in the court for 3 generations with Motohiro and Iehiro KONOE, also died of a disease in this year, and Munehiro NIJO, who just became udaijin, died from disease next year as if he followed his father, Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The direct reason for Kaneyoshi&apos;s appointment to Kanpaku in the first place was the death of the former Kanpaku, Yoshitada NIJO, from disease, but Daijo-daijin Iehisa KONOE, who maintained his domination of the court for 3 generations through Motohiro and Iehiro KONOE, also died of a disease the same year, and Munehiro NIJO, who had just become Udaijin, died from disease the following year soon after his father, Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityTense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The direct reason for Kaneyoshi&apos;s appointment to Kanpaku in the first place was the death of the former Kanpaku, Yoshitada NIJO, from disease, but Daijo-daijin Iehisa KONOE, who maintained his domination of the court for three generations through Motohiro and Iehiro KONOE, also died of a disease the same year, and Munehiro NIJO, who had just become Udaijin, died from disease the following year soon after his father, Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>&quot;3&quot;をスペルアウト</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この結果、摂関家（一条家・近衛家・二条家・九条家・鷹司家）の当主は、元文3年（1738年）から寛保3年（1743年）までの5年間に以下の表の様な変動に見舞われることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the head of Sekkan-ke (the Ichijo family, the Konoe family, the Nijo family, the Kujo family, and the Takatsukasa family) had moves as the following list during five years since 1738 to 1743.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, during the five years from 1738 to 1743, the position of head of each of the Sekkan-ke famlies (the Ichijo family, the Konoe family, the Nijo family, the Kujo family, and the Takatsukasa family) was unsettled, as seen in the following list.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - I took the Japanese to mean the heads of each Sekkan-ke family, rather than the overall head, which is what translation 1 implies</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, during the five years from 1738 to 1743, the position of head of each of the Sekkan-ke famlies (the Ichijo family, the Konoe family, the Nijo family, the Kujo family, and the Takatsukasa family) was unsettled, as seen in the following list.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>一条家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ichijo family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ichijo Family</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ichijo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>当主兼香（関白左大臣47歳→同52歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family head, Kaneyoshi (Kanpaku sadaijin (imperial regent and minister of the left) from forty seven years old to fifty two years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family head, Kaneyoshi (Kanpaku sadaijin from forty-seven years old to fifty-two years old)</e>
<cmt>Deleted translation of Kanpaku sadaijin as it appears aboveHyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family head, Kaneyoshi (Kanpaku Sadaijin from forty-seven years old to fifty-two years old)</e>
<cmt>他の表記とあわせ、sadaijin→Sadaijinとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>嫡男道香(左近衛大将17歳→右大臣22歳)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His heir, Michika (Became Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) at seventeen years old and udaijin at twenty two years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heir, Michika (became Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) at the age of seventeen and Udaijin at twenty-two)</e>
<cmt>Revised to make less wordyHyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heir, Michika (became Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) at the age of seventeen and Udaijin at twenty-two)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>近衛家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Konoe family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Konoe Family</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Konoe Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>当主近衛内前（権大納言11歳→内大臣16歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family head, Uchisaki KONOE (Became Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) at eleven years old and naidaijin (Minister of the Center) at sixteen years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family head, Uchisaki KONOE (became Gon Dainagon (provisional Major Counselor) at eleven years old and naidaijin (Minister of the Center) at sixteen years old)</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family head, Uchisaki KONOE (became Gon Dainagon (Provisional Chief Councilor of State) at eleven years old and Naidaijin at sixteen years old)</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagon→Dainagonの統一表記より修正、naidaijin→Naidaijinとし、既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>二条家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nijo family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nijo Family</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nijo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>当主二条宗基（従五位上12歳（翌年元服）→権大納言兼右近衛大将17歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family head, Munemoto NIJO (Became Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) at twelve years old (genpuku next year) and Gon Dainagon and Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) at seventeen years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family head, Munemoto NIJO (became Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) at twelve years old (coming of age ceremony the following year) and Gon Dainagon and Ukone no Daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) at seventeen years old)</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family head, Munemoto NIJO (became Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) at twelve years old (coming of age ceremony the following year) and Gon Dainagon and Ukone no Daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) at seventeen years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>九条家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kujo family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kujo Family</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kujo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>当主九条稙基（権大納言兼右近衛大将14歳→内大臣19歳で死去）⇒寛保3年九条尚実（稙基の叔父である僧堯厳が還俗・正五位下27歳（翌年元服））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family head, Tanemoto KUJO (Gon Dainagon and Ukone no daisho at fourteen years old and died when he was udaijin at nineteen years old)=&gt;Naozane KUJO became the family head in 1743 (Tanemoto&apos;s uncle, a priest Gyogen returned to secular life and became Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) at twenty seven years old (had genpuku next year))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family head, Tanemoto KUJO (Gon Dainagon and Ukone no Daisho at fourteen years old and died when he was Udaijin at nineteen years old); succeded in 1743 by his uncle, Naozane KUJO (a priest by the name of Gyogen, he returned to secular life and became Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) at twenty-seven years old and had his coming of age ceremony the following year)</e>
<cmt>Capital letterRevised for clarity - moved a part of the clause in brackets outside.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family head, Tanemoto KUJO (Gon Dainagon and Ukone no Daisho at fourteen years old and died when he was Naidaijin at nineteen years old); succeded in 1743 by his uncle, Naozane KUJO (a priest by the name of Gyogen, he returned to secular life and became Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) at twenty-seven years old and had his coming of age ceremony the following year)</e>
<cmt>Udaijin→Naidaijinに訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>鷹司家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takatsukasa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takatsukasa Family</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takatsukasa Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>当主鷹司基輝(権大納言12歳→内大臣17歳で死去)⇒寛保3年輔平（閑院宮家より相続・無位無官8歳（2年後元服））</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family head, Mototeru TAKATSUKASA (Became Gon Dainagon at twelve years old and died when he was naidaijin at seventeen years old)=&gt;Sukehira TAKATSUKASA became the family head in 1743 (succeeded from the Kaninnomiya family and was Muimukan (without any rank and post) at eight years old (had genpuku two years later)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family head, Mototeru TAKATSUKASA (became Gon Dainagon at twelve years old and died when he was Naidaijin at seventeen years old); succeded by Sukehira TAKATSUKASA in 1743 (from the Kaninnomiya family and at eight years old (he had his coming of age ceremony two years later) was without any rank or position</e>
<cmt>Capital letterChanged word orderRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family head, Mototeru TAKATSUKASA (became Gon Dainagon at twelve years old and died when he was Naidaijin at seventeen years old); succeded by Sukehira TAKATSUKASA in 1743 (from the Kaninnomiya family and at eight years old (he had his coming of age ceremony two years later) was without any rank or position</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、二条宗基は九条稙基の弟、鷹司基輝は一条兼香の子、同輔平は一旦一条兼香の養子となり、兄・基輝の相続という名目で鷹司家に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Munemoto NIJO was a brother of Tanemoto KUJO, Mototeru TAKATSUKASA was a child of Kaneyoshi ICHIJO, Sukehira TAKATSUKASA was an adopted child of Kaneyoshi ICHIJO once but entered the Takatsukasa family to succeed his brother, Mototeru TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Munemoto NIJO was Tanemoto KUJO&apos;s brother, Mototeru TAKATSUKASA was Kaneyoshi ICHIJO&apos;s son, and Sukehira TAKATSUKASA was at one time adopted by Kaneyoshi ICHIJO but entered the Takatsukasa family to succeed his brother, Mototeru TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Munemoto NIJO was Tanemoto KUJO&apos;s brother, Mototeru TAKATSUKASA was Kaneyoshi ICHIJO&apos;s son, and Sukehira TAKATSUKASA was at one time adopted by Kaneyoshi ICHIJO but entered the Takatsukasa family to succeed his brother, Mototeru TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また、寛保3年（1743年）の内大臣は九条稙基（19歳・死去）→鷹司基輝（17歳・死去）→近衛内前（16歳）に任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, as a naidaijin of 1743, Tanemoto KUJO (at nineteen years old but died)=&gt;Mototeru TAKATSUKASA (at seventeen years old but died)=&gt;Uchisaki KONOE (at sixteen years old) were appointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in 1743, the position of Naidaijin was held by Tanemoto KUJO (at nineteen years old but died), then Mototeru TAKATSUKASA (at seventeen years old but died), followed by Uchisaki KONOE (at sixteen years old).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in 1743, the position of Naidaijin was held by Tanemoto KUJO (at nineteen years old but died), then Mototeru TAKATSUKASA (at seventeen years old but died), followed by Uchisaki KONOE (at sixteen years old).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>この時期、一条家以外の各家では、幼い当主の擁立と死去が相次ぎ、摂関家としての役割を果たせる状況ではなかった（最年長の九条尚実は幼少時から寺院に入っていたため政治経験がない)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, fielding and death of a young family head occurred one after another in each family except the Ichijo family, the situation was not good for Sekkan-ke to fulfill a role (the oldest, Naozane KUJO did not have experience in politics since he entered a temple when he was young).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, the heads of each family, except the Ichijo, all came to power and died young, a situation that made it difficult for the Sekkan-ke to fulfill its role (the oldest, Naozane KUJO, was politically inexperienced, having entered a temple when he was young).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, the heads of each family, except the Ichijo, all came to power and died young, a situation that made it difficult for the Sekkan-ke to fulfill its role (the oldest, Naozane KUJO, was politically inexperienced, having entered a temple when he was young).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、江戸幕府の朝廷統制政策により清華家以下の諸家は政治の最高意思決定の場から実質排除されていたため、兼香と嫡男・道香が左右大臣として政務を取り仕切らなければ、政務が進まないという事態に陥ったのである（なお、道香は元文4年（1739年）に兼香が一時中風によって静養を余儀なくされた際に内覧に任じられている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Kaneyoshi and his heir, Michika got into the situation where they had to take control of government affairs as Sayu-daijin (the Minister of the Left and the Minister of the Right) because the families below the Seiga family was excluded from the political supreme decision-making process due to the Imperial court controls by the Edo bakufu (Also, Michika was appointed to Nairan (a preliminary inspection of official documents submitted from the Great Council of State to the Emperor) when Kaneyoshi was temporarily forced to rest due to paralysis in 1739).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, because the Edo shogunate&apos;s policy for controling the Imperial Court excluded families below the rank of Seigake from the highest political decision-making process, Kaneyoshi and his heir, Michika, as Ministers of the Left and Right, were left in control of, but unable to make progress in, government affairs (in addition, Michika was appointed Nairan (in charge of inspecting documents submitted to the Emperor) when Kaneyoshi was temporarily forced to rest due to paralysis in 1739).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, because the Edo bakufu&apos;s policy for controling the Imperial Court excluded families below the rank of Seigake from the highest political decision-making process, Kaneyoshi and his heir, Michika, as Ministers of the Left and Right, were left in control of, but unable to make progress in, government affairs (in addition, Michika was appointed Nairan (in charge of inspecting documents submitted to the Emperor) when Kaneyoshi was temporarily forced to rest due to paralysis in 1739).</e>
<cmt>Edo shogunate&apos;s→Edo bakufu&apos;sに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>逆にそれは桜町天皇と兼香の進める政策を阻む障害が存在しないという状況でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, it was the situation where there was no obstacles to prevent the policy that Emperor Sakuramachi and Kaneyoshi were promoting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, this situation meant there were no obstacles to prevent the policy that Emperor Sakuramachi and Kaneyoshi were promoting.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, this situation meant there were no obstacles to prevent the policy that Emperor Sakuramachi and Kaneyoshi were promoting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>桜町天皇と一条兼香のコンビは先の大嘗祭復活に続いて、元文5年（1740年）に新嘗祭復活、次いで延享元年（1744年）の甲子改元時における宇佐神宮・香椎宮への奉幣使復活など、廃絶していた朝廷行事の再興を実現する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the combination of Emperor Sakuramachi and Kaneyoshi ICHIJO, they resuscitated Imperial court events that was once abolished, such as Daijo-sai festival first, Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) in 1740, and Hoheishi (an imperial messenger to a Shinto shrine) to Usa-jingu Shrine and Kashii-gu Shrine at the time of Kashi Kaigen (changing the name of the era in the year of Kashi (Kinenoe) in Chinese astrology).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Sakuramachi and Kaneyoshi ICHIJO together revived Imperial court events that had died out, starting with the Daijo-sai festival, followed by the Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) in 1740, and the Hoheishi (imperial messenger) to Usa-jingu Shrine and Kashii-gu Shrine in 1744, the start of the traditional Chinese sixty-year cycle.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Sakuramachi and Kaneyoshi ICHIJO together revived Imperial court events that had died out, starting with the Daijo-sai festival, followed by the Niiname-sai festival (ceremonial offering by the Emperor of newly-harvested rice to the deities) in 1740, and the Hoheishi (imperial messenger) to Usa-jingu Shrine and Kashii-gu Shrine in 1744, the start of the traditional Chinese sixty-year cycle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>またこれと並行して大嘗祭が復活した元文3年頃より、天皇と兼香は朝廷官制の見直しの準備を開始していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In parallel with this, the Emperor and Kaneyoshi had started the preparation to revise the government-regulated organization in court since around 1738 when Daijo-sai festival was revived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In parallel with this, from around 1738, when the Daijo-sai festival was revived, the Emperor and Kaneyoshi had begun preparations to overhaul the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In parallel with this, from around 1738, when the Daijo-sai festival was revived, the Emperor and Kaneyoshi had begun preparations to overhaul the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>この動きは延享3年12月15日_(旧暦)（1747年1月25日）に兼香がこれまで内覧を務めてきた息子・道香に関白を譲って太政大臣に昇進し、半年後に桜町天皇が桃園天皇に譲位して院政を開始すると、早くも兼香の娘・富子の入内が決定（実施は兼香没後の宝暦5年（1755年）11月）され、官制改革の構想も徐々に進めていく事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 25, 1747, Kaneyoshi moved over Kanpaku post to his son, Michika, who has served as Nairan, and was promoted to Daijo-daijin, and when Emperor Sakuramachi was abdicated the throne to Emperor Momozono and started the cloister government six months later, judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) for Kaneyoshi&apos;s daughter, Tomiko, was decided quickly (happened in November, 1755 after Kaneyoshi died), and framework of the government-regulated organization restructuring was gradually progressed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plan to reform the court proceded gradually, beginning on January 25, 1747, with Kaneyoshi passing the position of Kanpaku to his son, Michika, who was serving as Nairan, and being promoted to Daijo-daijin, and when Emperor Sakuramachi abdicated in favor of Emperor Momozono and started a cloistered government six months later, the entry of Kaneyoshi&apos;s daughter, Tomiko, to the court was decided quickly (though it actually happened in November 1755, after Kaneyoshi died).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plan to reform the court proceded gradually, beginning on January 25, 1747, with Kaneyoshi passing the position of Kanpaku to his son, Michika, who was serving as Nairan, and being promoted to Daijo-daijin, and when Emperor Sakuramachi abdicated in favor of Emperor Momozono and started a cloistered government six months later, the entry of Kaneyoshi&apos;s daughter, Tomiko, to the court was decided quickly (though it actually happened in November 1755, after Kaneyoshi died).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="41">
<j>だが、寛延3年4月23日 (旧暦)（1750年5月28日）桜町上皇が31歳の若さで急死すると、兼香の長年の宮廷主導に対する風当たりが一気に強まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the retired Emperor Sakuramachi died suddenly at a young age of thirty one years old on May 28, 1750, Kaneyoshi was criticized all at once against his long time leadership in court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the retired Emperor Sakuramachi died suddenly at a young age of thirty one years old on May 28, 1750, Kaneyoshi came under a hail of criticism for his long-time leadership of the court.</e>
<cmt>Revised last part of sentence for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the Retired Emperor Sakuramachi died suddenly at a young age of thirty one years old on May 28, 1750, Kaneyoshi came under a hail of criticism for his long-time leadership of the court.</e>
<cmt>the Retired Emperor Sakuramachiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その年の9月24日_(旧暦)、故上皇と兼香による本格的な改革案「官位御定」が上皇の遺詔として桃園天皇の摂政である道香によって発表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 24 (in old calendar) in the same year, full scale reform proposal of &apos;Kani Gojyo (official rank order from the Emperor)&apos; by the late retired Emperor and Kaneyoshi was introduced as the retired Emperor&apos;s will by Michika who was Sessho (regent) of Emperor Momozono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 24 (by the lunar calendar) in the same year, Michika, who was Emperor Momozono&apos;s Sessho, or Regent, introduced the full-scale reform &apos;Kani Gojyo (Imperial decision on official ranks)&apos; proposed by the late retired Emperor and Kaneyoshi, in accordance with the retired emperor&apos;s final wishes.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderRevised for clarityI&apos;m not sure but I think &quot;官位御定&quot; should be &quot;kan&apos;i osadame&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 23 in the same year, Michika, who was Emperor Momozono&apos;s Sessho, or Regent, introduced the full-scale reform &apos;Kani Gojyo&apos; (Imperial decision on official ranks) proposed by the late Retired Emperor and Kaneyoshi, in accordance with the Retired Emperor&apos;s final wishes.</e>
<cmt>旧暦表記→新暦に修正、クォーテーションの位置を移動、Retired Emperorとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これは侍従と近衛府における定員の制限、成人前の天皇の猶子門跡の禁止、堂上家以下地下人の諸大夫に至るまで官人の官位昇進に厳しい規定を課した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This imposed the rules limiting the number of jiju (a chamberlain) and the fixed number of Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), prohibiting succession of a temple by an adopted child of an underage Emperor, and promoting an official rank of government officials such as Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo) of jigenin (a lower rank of ancient Japanese nobility) below Tosho-ke (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This limited the number of jiju (Chamberlains) and members of the Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), prohibited adopted children of an underage Emperor from becoming heads of temples, and imposed strict regulations on promoting officials from the jigenin, a low rank of ancient Japanese nobility below the Tosho-ke (relatively high ranking hereditary nobles), who had reached the position of Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo).</e>
<cmt>Article PrepositionRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This limited the number of jiju (Chamberlains) and members of the Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), prohibited adopted children of an underage Emperor from becoming heads of temples, and imposed strict regulations on promoting officials from the jigenin, a low rank of ancient Japanese nobility below the Tosho-ke (relatively high ranking hereditary nobles), who had reached the position of Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>更にこれまで朝廷が手を付けてこなかった諸社の祠官の任官・門跡の諸大夫の官位・門跡寺院や両本願寺などの坊官の呼称を停止する事など形式的に流されがちであった公家官位の仕組みを根本的に改めるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it was the proposal to revise the official rank structure of kuge fundamentally which tended to be influenced formally, such as suspending appointment of Shikan (a Shinto priest) at temples, official rank of Shodaibu of monzeki (successor of a temple), and names for boukan (a priest who served for the Monzeki families) at a monzeki temple (a temple of high rank where members of imperial family and nobility enter the priesthood) and both east and west Hongan-ji Temples, which the imperial court never touched.</e>
<cmt>「両本願寺」を「東西本願寺」と分かりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, by suspending apppointments of Shikan (Shinto priest) at temples, official ranks for Shodaibu of monzeki (successor of a temple), and names for boukan (top priests) at monzeki temples (where priests of noble or imperial lineage lived) and at both Higashi and Nishi Hongan-ji Temples, which until now the Court hadn&apos;t concerned itself with, the reforms proposed changing the fundamental structure of the kuge, which tended to be very formal</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, by suspending apppointments of Shikan (Shinto priest) at temples, official ranks for Shodaibu of monzeki (successor of a temple), and names for bokan (top priests) at monzeki temples (where priests of noble or imperial lineage lived) and at both Higashi and Nishi Hongan-ji Temples, which until now the Court hadn&apos;t concerned itself with, the reforms proposed changing the fundamental structure of the kuge, which tended to be very formal.</e>
<cmt>boukan→bokanに修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="45">
<j>この重大決定が他の摂関家や武家伝奏、更には江戸幕府にも知らせずに上皇と兼香によって決められていた事に内外は騒然とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It created a disturbance in and out since this important decision was made by the retired Emperor and Kaneyoshi without telling other Sekkan-ke, buke tenso (liaison officers between the imperial court and the military government), and Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that the retired Emperor and Kaneyoshi had made this important decision without telling other Sekkan-ke, buke tenso (liaison officers between the imperial court and the shogunate), or the Edo shogunate itself created a disturbance within and outside of the court</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that the Retired Emperor and Kaneyoshi had made this important decision without telling other Sekkan-ke, buke tenso (liaison officers between the imperial court and the bakufu), or the Edo bakufu itself created a disturbance within and outside of the court.</e>
<cmt>the retired Emperor→the Retired Emperor、the Edo shogunate→the Edo bakufu、the shogunate→the bakufu とし、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>特に近衛内前（左大臣・23歳）・二条宗基（右大臣・24歳）・九条尚実（内大臣兼左近衛大将・34歳）の摂関家三当主の憤慨は激しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, three family heads of Sekkan-ke, Uchisaki KONOE (sadaijin, twenty two years old), Munemoto NIJO (udaijin, twenty four years old), Naozane KUJO (naidaijin and Sakone no daisho, thirty four years old) were very furious at it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the heads of three Sekkan-ke families, Uchisaki KONOE (Sadaijin, twenty-two years old), Munemoto NIJO (Udaijin, twenty-four years old), Naozane KUJO (Naidaijin and Sakone-no-daisho, thirty-four years old) were extremely furious.</e>
<cmt>Capital lettersHyphensRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the heads of three Sekkan-ke families, Uchisaki KONOE (Sadaijin, twenty-two years old), Munemoto NIJO (Udaijin, twenty-four years old), Naozane KUJO (Naidaijin and Sakone no daisho, thirty-four years old) were extremely furious.</e>
<cmt>統一事項より、Sakone-no-daishoのハイフン消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>13年にわたって続いた桜町天皇と兼香の宮廷主導が続いている間に幼少であった彼らも成長して朝廷政務への参画を勝ち取ろうと図ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While long term leadership in court by the Emperor Sakuramachi and Kaneyhoshi was continued for thirteen years, they grew up and sought to win the participation to government affairs in court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boys at the start of the thirteen-year leadership of the court by Emperor Sakuramachi and Kaneyoshi, upon reaching adulthood they planned to gain participation in government affairs in court.</e>
<cmt>Revised for claritySpelling of &quot;Kaneyoshi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boys at the start of the thirteen-year leadership of the court by Emperor Sakuramachi and Kaneyoshi, upon reaching adulthood they planned to gain participation in government affairs in court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>彼らは桜町天皇の女御であった二条舎子（青綺門院）や幕府を動かして圧力をかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They put pressure by manipulating Ieko NIJO (Seikimon-in), who was a nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of an emperor)) of Emperor Sakuramachi, and bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They pressured Ieko NIJO (also known as Seikimon-in), a nyogo of Emperor Sakuramachi, and the shogunate to act.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - deleted explanation of &apos;nyogo&apos; as it appears earlier.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They pressured Ieko NIJO (also known as Seikimonin), a nyogo of Emperor Sakuramachi, and the bakufu to act.</e>
<cmt>女性の院号のため、Seikimon-in→Seikimoninに修正、the shogunate→the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="49">
<j>また、幕府との対立を危惧する武家伝奏（広橋兼胤・柳原光綱）も若い道香を説得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, buke tenso (liaison officers between the imperial court and the military government) (Kanetane HIROHASHI and Mitsutsuna YANAGIHARA), who worried about conflict against bakufu, persuaded young Michika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, buke tenso Kanetane HIROHASHI and Mitsutsuna YANAGIHARA, who were worried about conflict against the shogunate, attempted to persuade young Michika.</e>
<cmt>GrammarRevised for clarity - deleted explanation of &apos;buke tenso&apos; as it appears earlier.Changed &quot;persuaded&quot; to &quot;attempted to persuade&quot; to make it fit better with the next sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, buke tenso Kanetane HIROHASHI and Mitsutsuna YANAGIHARA, who were worried about conflict against the bakufu, attempted to persuade young Michika.</e>
<cmt>the shogunate→the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>その結果、12月27日 (旧暦)に道香はその圧力に屈して「官位御定」の事実上の白紙撤回（「官位御定」そのものは認められたものの、最重要項目とされていた諸社の祠官の任官・門跡の諸大夫の官位・坊官の呼称の廃止が撤回されてしまった）に至ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Michika was yielded to the pressure and virtually withdrew &apos;Kani Gojyo&apos; (&apos;Kani Gojyo&apos; itself was accepted, but the most important items, such as suspending appointment of Shikan at temples, official rank of Shodaibu of monzeki, and names for boukan at a monzeki temple and both east and west Hongan-ji Temples recalled).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Michika, yielding to the pressure, virtually withdrew &apos;Kani Gojyo&apos; (&apos;Kani Gojyo&apos; itself was accepted, but the most important items, such as suspending appointments of Shikan at shrines, official ranks for Shodaibu of monzeki, and names for boukan at monzeki temples and both Higashi and Nishi Hongan-ji Temples, were dropped).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, on January 24, 1751, Michika, yielding to the pressure, virtually withdrew &apos;Kani Gojyo&apos; (&apos;Kani Gojyo&apos; itself was accepted, but the most important items, such as suspending appointments of Shikan at shrines, official ranks for Shodaibu of monzeki, and names for boukan at monzeki temples and both Higashi and Nishi Hongan-ji Temples, were dropped).</e>
<cmt>「12月27日 (旧暦)」を訳出 (新暦に変換)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>この決定に衝撃を受けた兼香は翌年には失意のうちに病に倒れてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneyoshi was shocked by this decision and became sick in frustration next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneyoshi was shocked by this decision and became sick in frustration next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneyoshi was shocked by this decision and became sick in frustration next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>太政大臣を辞した兼香には前代の功労者として准三宮が与えられるが、間もなく60歳で病没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After resigning from Daijo-daijin, he was given Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) as person of merit, but he died soon after that at sixty years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After resigning from the position of Daijo-daijin, he was given the honorary rank of Jusangu (usually given to the Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) for distinguished service, but died soon after at the age of sixty.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After resigning from the position of Daijo-daijin, he was given the honorary rank of Jusangu (usually given to the Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) for distinguished service, but died soon after at the age of sixty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="53">
<j>兼香の日記として『兼香公記』及び同別記（文章集『求玉鈔』、官位改革の経緯を綴った『玉藻秘記』他）が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneyoshi left a diary of &quot;Kaneyoshi Koki&quot; and its separate paragraphs (collection of his writing &quot;Kyugyokusa&quot; and &quot;Tamamo Hiki (confidential record)&quot; that wrote how the official rank reform happened).</e>
<cmt>求玉鈔→Kyugyokusa［正しい読み方が確認できませんでした］</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneyoshi&apos;s diary &quot;Kaneyoshi Koki&quot; and its companion volumes (including the collection of his writings &quot;Kyugyokusa&quot; and &quot;Tamamo Hiki (confidential record)&quot; that describe how the official rank reform happened) are still in existence.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneyoshi&apos;s diary &quot;Kaneyoshi Koki&quot; and its companion volumes (including the collection of his writings &quot;Kyugyokusa&quot; (求玉鈔) and &quot;Tamamo Hiki&quot; (confidential record) that describe how the official rank reform happened) are still in existence.</e>
<cmt>読みが不確かのため、&quot;Kyugyokusa&quot; (求玉鈔) とし、Tamamo Hikiのクォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>官位履歴一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;of job grade&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>元禄15年（1701年）　元服　正五位下　右近衛少将　左近衛中将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1701, he had Genpuku, and became Shogoinoge, Ukone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1701, he had his coming-of-age ceremony, and was made Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank), Ukone-no-shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), and Sakone-no-chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;HyphensAdded explanation of &quot;Shogoinoge&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1701: He had his coming-of-age ceremony, and was made Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank), Ukone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ハイフンをとり、Ukone no shosho、Sakone no chujoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>同16年（1702年）　従四位下　正四位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1702, he became Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) and Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1702, he was made Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) and Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1702: He was made Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) and Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>宝永元年（1704年）　従三位　権中納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1704, he became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1704, he was made Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Gon-Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;Hyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1704: He was made Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Gon Chunagonとし、既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>同2年（1705年）　踏歌節会外弁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1705, he became Geben (a kugyo who supervised many matters outside Jomei Gate) at Toka no sechie (Imperial Court Ceremony)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1705, he was the Geben (person in charge of the main gate during important events) at the Toka-no-Sechie Imperial Ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityFull stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1705: He was the Geben (person in charge of the main gate during important events) at the Toka no Sechie Imperial Ceremony.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ハイフンをとり、Toka no Sechie</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>同3年（1706年）　正三位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1706, he became Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1706, he was made Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1706: He was made Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>同5年（1708年）　左近衛中将辞任　権大納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1708, he resigned from Ukone no shosho and became Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1708, he resigned as Ukone-no-Shosho and became Gon-Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>PrepostionHyphens</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1708: He resigned as Sakone no chujo and became Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Ukone-no-Shosho→Sakone no chujoに訂正、Gon Dainagonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>同6年（1709年）　従二位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1709, he became Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1709, he was made Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1709: He was made Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>享保3年（1718年）　左近衛大将兼務</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1718, he had an additional post as Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1718, he was given the additional post as Sakone-no-daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>&quot;had an&quot;→&quot;was given the&quot;Hyphens</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1718: He was given the additional post as Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ハイフンをとりSakone no daishoとし、既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>同4年（1719年）　正二位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1719, he became Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1719, he was made Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1719: He was made Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>同7年（1722年）　内大臣（任5月3日_(旧暦)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1722, he became naidaijin (appointed on May 3 (in old calendar)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1722, he was made Naidaijin (appointed on May 3, lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;Capital letterPunctuation&quot;in old&quot;→&quot;lunar&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1722: He was made Naidaijin (appointed on June 16).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>同8年（1723年）　内大臣辞任　同還任　（※）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1723, he resigned from naidaijin and had reappointment.(*)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1723, he resigned as Naidaijin and then was reappointed.(*)</e>
<cmt>PrepostionCapital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1723: He resigned as Naidaijin and then was reappointed.(*)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>同11年（1726年）　左近衛大将辞任　右大臣（任9月15日_(旧暦)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1726, he resigned from Sakone no daisho and became udaijin (appointed on September 15 (in old calendar)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1726, he resigned as Sakone-no-daisho and was made Udaijin (appointed on September 15, lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>PrepostionHyphens&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;Capital letterPunctuation&quot;in old&quot;→&quot;lunar&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1726: He resigned as Sakone no daisho and was made Udaijin (appointed on October 10).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、ハイフンをとりSakone no daishoとし、旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>同13年（1728年）　東宮傅兼務</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1728, he had an additional post as togu-no-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1728, he was given the additional post of Togu-no-fu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;had an&quot;→&quot;was given the&quot;PrepostionCapital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1728: He was given the additional post of Togu no fu.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Togu no fuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>同17年（1732年）　従一位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1732, he became Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1732, he was made Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>became→&quot;was made&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1732: He was made Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>同20年（1735年）　桜町天皇即位に伴い、東宮傅辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1735, with Emperor Sakuramachi enthronement, he resigned from togu-no-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1735, with Emperor Sakuramachi&apos;s enthronement, he resigned as Togu-no-fu.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;&apos;s&quot;PrepostionCapital etter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1735: With Emperor Sakuramachi&apos;s enthronement, he resigned as Togu no fu.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Togu no fuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>元文2年（1737年）　関白左大臣（関白任8月29日 (旧暦)・左大臣任11月7日 (旧暦)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1737, he became Kanpaku-sadaijin (appointed to Kanpaku on August 28 (in old calendar) and Sadaijin on November 7 (in old calendar)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1737, he was made Kanpaku on August 28 (lunar calendar) and Sadaijin on November 7 (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;PrepostionRevised for brevityPunctuation&quot;in old&quot;→&quot;lunar&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1737: He was made Kanpaku on September 23 and Sadaijin on November 28.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>延享2年（1745年）　左大臣辞任（辞2月13日_(旧暦)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1745, he resigned from sadaijin (resigned on February 13 (in old calendar)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1745, he resigned as Sadaijin on February 13 (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>PrepostionCapital letterPunctuation&quot;in old&quot;→&quot;lunar&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1745: He resigned as Sadaijin on March 15.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>同3年（1746年）　太政大臣（任2月28日_(旧暦)）　関白辞任（辞12月15日_(旧暦)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1746, he became Daijo-daijin (appointed on February 28 (in old calendar)) and resigned from Kanpaku (resigned on December 15 (in old calendar)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1746, he was made Daijo-daijin on February 28 (lunar calendar) and resigned as Kanpaku on December 15 (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>&quot;became&quot;→&quot;was made&quot;Prepostion&quot;in old&quot;→&quot;lunar&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1746: He was made Daijo-daijin on April 18 and resigned as Kanpaku on January 25 in the following year.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>寛延4年（1751年/宝暦元年）　太政大臣辞任（辞7月29日_(旧暦)）　准三宮　死去</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1751, he resigned from Daijo-daijin (resigned on July 29 (in old calendar)), received Jusangu, and died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1751, he resigned as Daijo-daijin (on July 29, lunar calendar), received Jusangu, and died.</e>
<cmt>Prepostion&quot;in old&quot;→&quot;lunar&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1751: He resigned as Daijo-daijin (on September 18), received Jusangu, and died.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>※2月1日_(旧暦)から7日間、櫛笥隆賀・広幡豊忠の2人に内大臣職を譲る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*Reappointed naidaijin post to Takayoshi KUSHIGE and Toyotada HIROHATA during seven days from February 1 (in old calendar)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* For a period of seven days from February 1 (lunar calendar), the position of Naidaijin was assigned to Takayoshi KUSHIGE and Toyotada HIROHATA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity&quot;in old&quot;→&quot;lunar&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* For a period of seven days from March 7 (lunar calendar), the position of Naidaijin was assigned to Takayoshi KUSHIGE and Toyotada HIROHATA.</e>
<cmt>上記にあわせ※→*とし、旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>両者が内大臣を務めた（同4日に櫛笥→広幡）後、2月8日_(旧暦)付で内大臣還任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After both of them served as naidaijin (pass the post from Kushige to Hirohata on February 4) and reappointed naidaijin post on February 8 (in old calendar)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After both of them had served as Naidaijin (the post was passed from Kushige to Hirohata on February 4), Kaneyoshi was reappointed on February 8 (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>TenseRevised for clarity&quot;in old&quot;→&quot;lunar&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After both of them had served as Naidaijin (the post was passed from Kushige to Hirohata on March 10), Kaneyoshi was reappointed on March 14.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pedigree record</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family</e>
<cmt>&quot;Pedigree record&quot;→&quot;Family&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>元関白鷹司房輔の末子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the youngest son of Fusasuke TAKATSUKASA, a former chancellor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the youngest son of Fusasuke TAKATSUKASA, a former chancellor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the youngest son of Fusasuke TAKATSUKASA, a former Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>他の表記に合わせ、chancellor→Kanpakuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>母は参議山科言行の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Tokiyuki YAMASHINA, Sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Sangi (councilor) Tokiyuki YAMASHINA.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Sangi (councilor) Tokiyuki YAMASHINA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>正室は広島藩浅野綱長の娘、継室は岡山藩池田綱政の養女（孫）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Tsunanaga ASANO of Hiroshima Domain, and his second wife was an adopted daughter (grandchild) of Tsunamasa IKEDA of Okayama Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was a daughter of Tsunanaga ASANO of Hiroshima Domain, and his second wife was an adopted daughter (grandchild) of Tsunamasa IKEDA of Okayama Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Tsunanaga ASANO of Hiroshima Domain, and his second wife was an adopted daughter (grandchild) of Tsunamasa IKEDA of Okayama Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>元関白一条兼輝（冬経）の養子となって一条家を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by Kaneteru (also known as Fuyutsune) ICHIJO, a former chancellor, and succeeded the Ichijo family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by Kaneteru (also known as Fuyutsune) ICHIJO, a former chancellor, and became head of the Ichijo family.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by Kaneteru (also known as Fuyutsune) ICHIJO, a former Kanpaku, and became head of the Ichijo family.</e>
<cmt>他の表記に合わせ、chancellor→Kanpakuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 目白梅(id:141468), Pontafon(id:33761), TakuyaMurata(id:156), Cprobot(id:97843), ひろくん(id:79638), 水野白楓(id:22811), UMBRO(id:100484), 伏儀(id:142093), のりまき(id:53470), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>