<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>甲斐の勇者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kai no Yusha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kai no Yusha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kai no Yusha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>甲斐の勇者（かいのゆうしゃ）は、天武天皇元年（672年）に日本で起きた壬申の乱に現れる騎兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kai no Yusha (Brave Man from Kai Province) was a cavalryman fought in the Jinshin War of 672.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kai no Yusha (Brave Man from Kai Province) was a cavalryman fought in the Jinshin War of 672.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kai no Yusha (Brave Man from Kai Province) was a cavalryman fought in the Jinshin War of 672.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名称、生没年不明の一兵士であるが、その性格をめぐって学説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name, year of birth and death are unknown; historians have been studying on his character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name, year of birth and death are unknown; historians have been studying on his character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name, year of birth and death are unknown; historians have been studying on his character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>壬申の乱を起こした天武天皇は、挙兵の決断と同時に吉野宮から東に逃れ、美濃国と伊勢国を固めてから、東山（東山道）と東海（東海道）に兵力動員を命じる使者を派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After raised the army (at the beginning of the Jinshin War), Oama no Miko (Oshiama no Miko or Prince Oama who became Emperor Tenmu following the victory in the war) left Yoshino no Miya (Yoshino Palace) to the east and first controlled Mino Province and Ise Province, then he sent messengers to gather soldiers in Yamanomichi (Tosan-do Road) and in Umitsuji (Tokai-do Road).</e>
<cmt>東山Yamanomichi…岩波文庫『日本書紀』の読みに従います。東海Umitsuji…岩波文庫『日本書紀』の読みに従います。他の『日本書紀』を題材とする記事において、乱の間は「大海人皇子（天武天皇）」という表記で統一されているので、補います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time of raising the army (at the beginning of the Jinshin War), Oama no Miko (Oshiama no Miko or Prince Oama who became Emperor Tenmu following the victory in the war) who set off the Jinshin War left Yoshino no Miya (Yoshino Palace) to the east and first controlled Mino Province and Ise Province, then he sent messengers to gather soldiers in Yamanomichi (Tosan-do Road) and in Umitsuji (Tokai-do Road).</e>
<cmt>原文「壬申の乱を起こした」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time of raising the army (at the beginning of the Jinshin War), Oama no Miko (Oshiama no Miko or Prince Oama who became Emperor Tenmu following the victory in the war) who set off the Jinshin War left Yoshino no Miya (Yoshino Palace) to the east and first controlled Mino Province and Ise Province, then he sent messengers to gather soldiers in Yamanomichi (Tosan-do Road) and in Umitsuji (Tokai-do Road).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>徴兵範囲は記されないが、後の律令制では甲斐国は東海道に属し、『続日本紀』で引用されている大海子の舎人安斗連智徳の日記によれば信濃では徴兵が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The districts which soldiers were selected are unknown; &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) quoted a diary written by Toneri (palace servant) of Oama no Miko, ATO no Muraji Chitoko, according to it, soldiers were gathered in Shinano Province (belonged to Tosan-do Road), therefore, presumably, in Kai Province which belonged to Tokai-do Road by later Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code), soldiers were gathered as well, and Kai no Yusha might have been one of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The districts which soldiers were selected are unknown; as a diary by Toneri (palace servant) of Oama no Miko, ATO no Muraji Chitoko, quoted in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), shows that soldiers were gathered in Shinano Province (belonged to Tosan-do Road), it is presumable that soldiers were gathered also in Kai Province which belonged to Tokai-do Road by later Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) as well.</e>
<cmt>セミコロンより後ろ部分を言い換え、原文に合わせて最後の文を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The districts which soldiers were selected are unknown; as a diary by Toneri (palace servant) of Oama no Miko, ATO no Muraji Chitoko, quoted in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), shows that soldiers were gathered in Shinano Province (belonged to Tosan-do Road), it is presumable that soldiers were gathered also in Kai Province which belonged to Tokai-do Road by later Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>美濃の不破郡に集結した軍勢は、二手に分かれて7月2日に西に向かって進軍を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The troops were gathered first at Fuwa-no-kori County of Mino Province (Tosan-do Road) and were divided in two big army, then they began to march to the west on July 2 (in old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The troops were gathered first at Fuwa County of Mino Province (Tosan-do Road) and were divided in two big army, then they began to march to the west on August 3, 672.</e>
<cmt>原文の「7月2日」を天武天皇元年としてグレゴリオ暦に変更しました。「不破郡」をFuwa Countyに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troops were gathered first at Fuwa County of Mino Province (Tosan-do Road) and were divided in two big army, then they began to march to the west on August 3, 672.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのうちの一つは、伊勢から倭（大和国）に送り込まれ、その地で連戦していた大伴吹負の軍への援兵になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the armies march to Yamato City of Yamato Province via Ise Province, and supported OTOMO no Fukei&apos;s army which had kept fighting at Yamato City and its vicinity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the armies were sent to Yamato City of Yamato Province via Ise Province to support OTOMO no Fukei&apos;s army which had kept fighting at Yamato City and its vicinity.</e>
<cmt>動詞を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the armies were sent to Yamato City of Yamato Province via Ise Province to support OTOMO no Fukei&apos;s army which had kept fighting at Yamato City and its vicinity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>7月、大友皇子（弘文天皇）側の将、犬養五十君は、廬井鯨に200の精兵を与え、大和の古道中つ道に置かれた吹負の本営を急襲させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, a general INUKAI no Ikimi, who was supporting Otomo no Miko (Prince Otomo who has been called Emperor Kobun since the Meiji era), gave IOI no Kujira two hundreds selected soldiers to attack Fukei&apos;s main camp at Naka-tsu-michi Road (Naka-no-michi Road), one of the old roads of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>犬養五十君INUKAI no Ikimi…「いそきみ」ではなく「いきみ」です。廬井鯨IOI no Kujira</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, a general INUKAI no Ikimi, who was supporting Otomo no Miko (Prince Otomo who has been called Emperor Kobun since the Meiji era), gave IOI no Kujira two hundreds selected soldiers to attack Fukei&apos;s main camp at Naka-tsu-michi Road (Naka-no-michi Road), one of the old roads of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>ここでいう「7月」は、旧暦7月2日に進軍した後を指すと思われますので、グレゴリオ暦の8月に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, a general INUKAI no Ikimi, who was supporting Otomo no Miko (Prince Otomo who has been called Emperor Kobun since the Meiji era), gave IOI no Kujira two hundreds selected soldiers to attack Fukei&apos;s main camp at Naka-tsu-michi Road (Naka-no-michi Road), one of the old roads of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>吹負は一時危うくなったが、徳麻呂らの防戦と、三輪高市麻呂・置始菟の部隊の来援で鯨を退けることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukei&apos;s army was forced into a corner for a while, however, supporting soldiers such as Tokomaro guarded them very well and the support armies led by MIWA no Takechimaro and by OKISOME no Usagi arrived to fight back, and at last Kujira&apos;s army retreated.</e>
<cmt>徳麻呂Tokomaro…苗字がなく、ここだけに登場する兵士です。徳はtoko、岩波文庫『日本書紀』の読みに従います。三輪高市麻呂MIWA no Takechimaro置始菟OKISOME no Usagi</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Fukei&apos;s army was forced into a corner for a while, supporting soldiers such as Tokomaro guarded them very well and the support armies led by MIWA no Takechimaro and by OKISOME no Usagi arrived to fight back, and at last Kujira&apos;s army retreated.</e>
<cmt>Althoughを用いて言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Fukei&apos;s army was forced into a corner for a while, supporting soldiers such as Tokomaro guarded them very well and the support armies led by MIWA no Takechimaro and by OKISOME no Usagi arrived to fight back, and at last Kujira&apos;s army retreated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>白馬に乗って逃げる鯨が泥田にはまって動けなくなったのを見た吹負は、甲斐の勇者に「その白馬に乗っている者は、廬井鯨だ。急ぎ追って射よ」と命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way of the retreat, Kujira&apos;s white horse was stuck in mud of a rice field; Fukei saw Kujira struggling and ordered Kai no Yusha, &quot;That man riding on the white horse is IOI no Kujira, go and shoot him!&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the way of the retreat, Kujira&apos;s white horse was stuck in mud of a rice field; Fukei saw Kujira struggling and ordered Kai no Yusha, &quot;That man riding on the white horse is IOI no Kujira, go and shoot him!&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way of the retreat, Kujira&apos;s white horse was stuck in mud of a rice field; Fukei saw Kujira struggling and ordered Kai no Yusha, &quot;That man riding on the white horse is IOI no Kujira, go and shoot him!&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>甲斐の勇者は馳せて追い、鯨に迫った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kai no Yusha rushed on his horse to Kujira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kai no Yusha rushed on his horse to Kujira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kai no Yusha rushed on his horse to Kujira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>鯨は急いで馬に鞭をやり、やっと泥を抜けて逃走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kujira promptly flicked a whip at his horse and managed to get out of the mud to run away for his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kujira promptly flicked a whip at his horse and managed to get out of the mud to run away for his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kujira promptly flicked a whip at his horse and managed to get out of the mud to run away for his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>『日本書紀』は乱の経過を詳しく伝えるが、動員された兵力の性格について語る箇所は少なく、長く歴史学者の間で学説上の争点になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicle of Japan) recorded the details of the war, however, it didn&apos;t record the origin of the soldiers gathered up for the war, therefore, historians have been studying and discussing it for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicle of Japan), which recorded the details of the war, scarcely described the origin of the soldiers gathered up for the war, therefore, historians have been studying and discussing it for a long time.</e>
<cmt>「乱の経過を詳しく伝える」を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicle of Japan), which recorded the details of the war, scarcely described the origin of the soldiers gathered up for the war, therefore, historians have been studying and discussing it for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>甲斐の勇者については、関晃が1957年の論文「甲斐の勇者」において、東海の使者の命をうけて甲斐から派遣された軍に属した兵士と推測した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a paper &quot;Kai no Yusha&quot; written by Akira SEKI in 1957, Kai no Yusha was a soldier of a troop from Kai Province, which was one of the troops formed by the order of the messenger who was sent by Oama no Miko to Umitsuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a thesis &apos;Kai no Yusha&apos; written by Akira SEKI in 1957, Kai no Yusha was a soldier of a troop from Kai Province, which was one of the troops formed under the order delivered by the messenger of Umitsuji.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを原文に合わせて変更しました。「論文」はthesisに変更し、formed以下も前置詞等を変更しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a thesis &apos;Kai no Yusha&apos; written by Akira SEKI in 1957, Kai no Yusha was a soldier of a troop from Kai Province, which was one of the troops formed under the order delivered by the messenger of Umitsuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、騎馬で射ることをよくしたらしいことから、民衆層というより、郡司級の一族に属したのではないかと推測した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And based on the ability of shooting on a horse, it is considered that Kai no Yusha was not from civilian but from Kori no Tsukasa (manager of county).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And based on his ability of shooting on a horse, it is considered that Kai no Yusha did not belong to the common people but district managers.</e>
<cmt>後半を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And based on his ability of shooting on a horse, it is considered that Kai no Yusha did not belong to the common people but district managers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この説は一定の支持を得たが、直木孝次郎は6月26日の使者発遣から7月の合戦までの期間から疑問視し、乱以前からの私的従者としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although many historians were in favor of Seki&apos;s opinion, Kojiro NAOKI suggested another opinion; according to it, Kai no Yusha had served as a personal follower of Fukei since before the war, because it was too short time since the dispatch of the messengers on June 26 until the battles in July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although many historians were in favor of Seki&apos;s opinion, Kojiro NAOKI suggested another opinion; according to it, Kai no Yusha had served as a personal follower of Fukei since before the war, because it was too short time since the dispatch of the messengers on July 29, 672 until the battles in August.</e>
<cmt>原文の「6月26日」「7月」は天武天皇元年と思われますので、グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although many historians were in favor of Seki&apos;s opinion, Kojiro NAOKI suggested another opinion; according to it, Kai no Yusha had served as a personal follower of Fukei since before the war, because it was too short time since the dispatch of the messengers on July 29, 672 until the battles in August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、甲斐には大伴部が存在することから、大伴氏に私的に仕えていた人で、それがたまたま甲斐の出身者だったということではないかという有力な反論があり、実情は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today there is another opinion,; according to it, Kai no Yusha was one of personal followers of the Otomo clan originated from Otomo-be (a group in Otomo, served Yamato Dynasty) in Kai Province; however, the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there is another opinion that Kai no Yusha was one of personal followers of the Otomo clan originated from Otomo-be (a group in Otomo, served Yamato Dynasty) and happened to be from Kai Province, the truth is still unknown.</e>
<cmt>「たまたま」を訳出し、全体を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there is another opinion that Kai no Yusha was one of personal followers of the Otomo clan originated from Otomo-be (a group in Otomo, served Yamato Dynasty) and happened to be from Kai Province, the truth is still unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MIO(id:31681), でここ(id:9565), Kinori(id:443), Ktoetx(id:104437), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>