<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>秦大魚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hata no Ona</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HATA no Ona</e>
<cmt>・姓は大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HATA no Ona</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>秦 大魚（はた の おおな、生没年不詳）は、奈良時代の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hata no Ona (year of birth and death unknown) is a court noble in the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HATA no Ona (year of birth and death unknown) is a court noble in Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>・「奈良時代」の前の冠詞は削除しました。・姓は大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HATA no Ona (year of birth and death unknown) is a court noble in Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>聖武天皇の御世に外従五位下へと叙せられ（天平12年11月21日 (旧暦)）、その後三河国守と下野国守を歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the reign of Emperor Shomu, he was appointed to Ge-jugoinoge (Jugoinoge [Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade] given to persons outside Kyoto) (December 18, 740), and then successively served as Mikawa no kuni no kami (Governor of Mikawa Province) and as Shimotsuke no kuni no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the reign of Emperor Shomu, he was appointed to Ge-jugoinoge (Jugoinoge [Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade] given to persons outside Kyoto) (December 18, 740 or November 21 on the old calendar), and then successively served as Mikawa no kuni no kami (Governor of Mikawa Province) and as Shimotsuke no kuni no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province).</e>
<cmt>・念のため旧暦も併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the reign of Emperor Shomu, he was appointed to Ge-jugoinoge (Jugoinoge [Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade] given to persons outside Kyoto) (December 18, 740 or November 21 on the old calendar), and then successively served as Mikawa no kuni no kami (Governor of Mikawa Province) and as Shimotsuke no kuni no kami (the governor of Shimotsuke Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>万葉集にある壹岐宅麻呂（雪連宅滿）の母は大魚の娘といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mother of Iki no takumari (雪連宅滿) who appeared in Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) is said to be the daughter of Ona.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mother of IKI no takumaro (Yuki no Muraji Yakamaro) who appeared in Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) is said to be the daughter of Ona.</e>
<cmt>・「宅麻呂」のスペルを修正しました。・「雪連宅滿」の読みは「ゆきのむらじやかまろ」としました。・姓（壱岐）は大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mother of IKI no takumaro (Yuki no Muraji Yakamaro) who appeared in Manyoshu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves) is said to be the daughter of Ona.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ともに九州北部地方を本拠地として東へと活動の範囲を広げていき、山城国松尾大社に氏神を祀った秦氏と、これに南接する地に壱岐島の月読神社 (京都市)を祀った伊吉博徳の縁を窺い知るものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship between Hata clan, who was based in the northern Kyusyu region, expanded the scope of activities toward the east, and worshipped ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) in Matsuo-taisha Shrine in Yamashiro no Kuni and IKI no Hakatoko who was also based on the northern Kyusyu and worshipped Tsukiyomi-jinja Shrine (Kyoto City) of Iki island in the place which is adjacent to the south side of Matsuo-taisha Shrine is expressed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between Hata clan, who was based in the northern Kyusyu region, expanded the scope of activities toward the east, and worshipped ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) in Matsuo-taisha Shrine in Yamashiro no Kuni and IKI no Hakatoko who was also based on the northern Kyusyu and worshipped Tsukiyomi-jinja Shrine (Kyoto City) of Iki island in the place which is adjacent to the south side of Matsuo-taisha Shrine is expressed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This demonstrates the relationship between the Hata clan, which was based in northern Kyushu and had expanded the scope of its activities further east and worshipped an ujigami (a guardian god or spirit of a particular place in the Shinto religion) at Matsuo-taisha Shrine in Yamashiro no Kuni, and IKI no Hakatoko, who was also based in northern Kyushu and worshipped at Iki Island&apos;s Tsukiyomi-jinja Shrine (in Kyoto), which is adjacent to the south side of Matsuo-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>続日本紀の記述では、大魚の姓は三河守任官までは前であるが、下野守任官の際は忌寸となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan Continued) describes that the family name of Ona was mae before he was appointed to Mikawa no kuni no kami, and it changed to Imina when he was appointed to Shimotsuke no kuni no kami.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan Continued) describes that the family name of Ona was MAE before he was appointed to Mikawa no kuni no kami, and it changed to IMIKI when he was appointed to Shimotsuke no kuni no kami.</e>
<cmt>・姓の部分は大文字に直しました。・「忌寸」のスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan Continued) describes that the family name of Ona was MAE before he was appointed to Mikawa no kuni no kami, and it changed to IMIKI when he was appointed to Shimotsuke no kuni no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この間に改姓したものと考えられるが、不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that his family name was changed in the intervening period, but it is unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that his family name was changed in the intervening period, but it is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that his family name was changed in the intervening period, but it is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 FCTR3(id:246533), FCTR2(id:213046), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>