<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朝倉孝景 (7代当主)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA (7th family head)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage ASAKURA (7th family head)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA (the seventh head of the family)</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朝倉 孝景（あさくら たかかげ）は室町時代中期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage ASAKURA was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA was a military commander in the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>朝倉氏七代目当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 7th family head of the Asakura clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 7th family head of the Asakura clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the seventh head of the Asakura clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>当初教景（のりかげ）と名乗り、次いで敏景→教景→孝景の順で改名している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He initially used the name Norikage, then changed names to Toshikage, Norikage, and Takakage, in this order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He initially used the name Norikage, then changed names to Toshikage, Norikage, and Takakage, in that order.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He initially used the name Norikage, then changed names to Toshikage, Norikage, and Takakage in the order.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>よって朝倉孝景 (10代当主)と区別するために代表的な名乗りの一つである「朝倉敏景」と表記する事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, in order to distinguish from Takakage ASAKURA (tenth family head), he may be described using one of his representative names, &apos;Toshikage ASAKURA.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, in order to distinguish him from Takakage ASAKURA (tenth family head), he may be described using one of his representative names, &apos;Toshikage ASAKURA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, in order to distinguish him from Takakage ASAKURA (the tenth head of the family), he may be described using one of his representative names &apos;Toshikage ASAKURA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、法名から「英林孝景（えいりんたかかげ）」と呼ばれることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, he is often referred by his homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood), &apos;Eirin Takakage.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he is often referred by his homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood), &apos;Eirin Takakage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he is often referred to by his Buddhist name &apos;Eirin Takakage.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>朝倉氏は元は越前国（福井県）の土豪であったが、南北朝時代 (日本)を経て越前守護斯波氏の重臣となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Asakura clan was originally a powerful local clan in Echizen Province (Fukui Prefecture), who became the senior vassal of the Shiba clan, the military governor of Echizen, through the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Asakura clan was originally a powerful local clan in Echizen Province (Fukui Prefecture), that became the senior vassal of the Shiba clan, the military governor of Echizen, through the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Asakura clan was originally a powerful local clan in Echizen Province (Fukui Prefecture) that became the senior vassal of the military governor of Echizen, the Shiba clan, after the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>長禄2年（1458年）に始まった越前守護斯波義敏と越前守護代甲斐常治の合戦（長禄合戦）で、孝景は守護代側に与し、その主力として活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the battle between the military governor of Echizen, Yoshitoshi SHIBA, and the deputy military governor of Echizen, Jochi KAI, (battle of Choroku), which began in 1458, Takakage took sides with the deputy military governor, and played an active role as his main force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the battle between the military governor of Echizen, Yoshitoshi SHIBA, and the deputy military governor of Echizen, Jochi KAI, (battle of Choroku), that began in 1458, Takakage took sides with the deputy military governor, and played an active role as his main force.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the battle that began in 1458 between the military governor of Echizen, Yoshitoshi SHIBA, and the deputy military governor of Echizen, Jochi KAI, (battle of Choroku), Takakage took the side of the deputy military governor and played an active role as the main force.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>長禄3年（1459年）8月11日 (旧暦)、足羽郡和田荘での合戦で守護側の堀江利真・朝倉将景（孝景の叔父であり、義父）らを敗死させ、守護代方を勝利に導くとともに、その地位を高める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 16, 1459, in the battle in Wada no Sho, Asuwa County, he defeated and killed Toshizane HORIE and Yukikage ASAKURA (uncle and father-in-law of Takakage) on the military governor&apos;s side, led the deputy military governor&apos;s side to victory, and strengthened his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 16, 1459, in the battle in Wada no Sho, Asuwa County, he defeated and killed Toshizane HORIE and Yukikage ASAKURA (uncle and father-in-law of Takakage) on the military governor&apos;s side, led the deputy military governor&apos;s side to victory, and strengthened his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 16, 1459, in the battle in Wada no Sho, Asuwa County, Takakage led the deputy military governor&apos;s side to victory and strengthened his position by defeating and killing Toshizane HORIE and Yukikage ASAKURA (uncle and father-in-law of Takakage) on the military governor&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、和田での合戦の翌12日、甲斐常治が京で亡くなったため、相対的に孝景の影響力が強まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, on the 17th, the day following the battle in Wada, Jochi KAI died in Kyoto, which increased the relative influence of Takakage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, on the 17th, the day following the battle in Wada, Jochi KAI died in Kyoto, which increased the relative influence of Takakage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, on September 17, the day following the battle in Wada, Jochi KAI died in Kyoto, which conversely increased the influence of Takakage.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>長禄合戦の最中、合戦を引き起こした斯波義敏が八代将軍足利義政の忌諱に触れて周防に没落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the battle of Choroku, Yoshitoshi SHIBA, who started the battle, displeased Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the eighth shogun, and fell out of power in Suo province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the battle of Choroku, Yoshitoshi SHIBA, who started the battle, displeased Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the eighth shogun, and fell out of power in Suo province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitoshi SHIBA, who started the battle of Choroku, displeased Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the eighth shogun, during the war and fell out of power in Suo Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その子息松王丸（後の斯波義良）がわずか3歳で守護となっていたものの、孝景は山名宗全と組んで、寛正2年（1461年）9月2日 (旧暦)、足利庶流である渋川義鏡の子息斯波義廉を斯波氏家督とすることに成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son, Matsuomaru (later Yoshisuke SHIBA), was the military governor at age 3, but on October 14, 1461, Takakage worked with Sozen YAMANA and succeeded in assigning Yoshikado SHIBA, the son of Yoshikane SHIBUKAWA, a branch family of Ashikaga, as the family head of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son, Matsuomaru (later Yoshisuke SHIBA), was the military governor at age 3, but on October 14, 1461, Takakage worked with Sozen YAMANA and succeeded in assigning Yoshikado SHIBA, the son of Yoshikane SHIBUKAWA, a branch family of Ashikaga, as the family head of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son, Matsuomaru (later Yoshisuke SHIBA), was the military governor at the age of three, but on October 14, 1461, Takakage worked with Sozen YAMANA and succeeded in assigning Yoshikado SHIBA, the son of Yoshikane SHIBUKAWA from a branch family of Ashikaga, to the family head of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>ところが、幕府政所執事伊勢貞親が、自己の妾と義敏の妾が姉妹であったため、義敏に肩入れしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sadachika ISE, a steward of the Bakufu Mandokoro, was backing up Yoshitoshi, because his mistress was a sister of Yoshitoshi&apos;s mistress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Sadachika ISE, a steward of the Bakufu Mandokoro, was backing up Yoshitoshi, because his mistress was the sister of Yoshitoshi&apos;s mistress.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Sadachika ISE, a steward of the Administrative Board of the shogunate government backed up Yoshitoshi, because his mistress was the sister of Yoshitoshi&apos;s mistress.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その結果、文正元年（1466年）7月24日 (旧暦)、義廉は斯波氏家督を追われ、代わりに斯波義敏が斯波氏惣領に復帰する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, on September 12, 1466, Yoshikane was forced out as the family head of the Shiba clan, and Yoshitoshi SHIBA returned as soryo (heir) of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, on September 12, 1466, Yoshikane was forced out as the family head of the Shiba clan, and Yoshitoshi SHIBA returned as soryo (heir) of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, on September 12, 1466, Yoshikane was forced out from the position of the head of the Shiba clan, and Yoshitoshi SHIBA returned as heir of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これに反発した孝景と宗全らは、文正の政変を起こして伊勢貞親・斯波義敏・赤松政則らを京から追放し、再びが斯波氏惣領となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage and Sozen who objected to this, staged the Bunsho Coup to banish Sadachika ISE, Yoshitoshi SHIBA, Masanori AKAMATSU, etc. from Kyoto, and Yoshikane became the soryo of the Shiba clan again.</e>
<cmt>Webを参考に「再び」の後に「義廉」を補って訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage and Sozen who objected to this, staged the Bunsho Coup to banish Sadachika ISE, Yoshitoshi SHIBA, Masanori AKAMATSU, etc. from Kyoto, and Yoshikane became the soryo of the Shiba clan again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage and Sozen who objected to this, staged the Bunsho Coup to banish Sadachika ISE, Yoshitoshi SHIBA, Masanori AKAMATSU, etc. from Kyoto--Again, Yoshikane became the heir of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>このような斯波氏の内訌に加え、足利将軍家や畠山氏の家督相続問題から、応仁元年（1467年）に応仁の乱が勃発すると、孝景は主家の斯波義廉と協力して西軍として活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such internal discord of the Shiba clan, along with issues involving succession to the position of family heads in the Ashikaga shogunate, Hatakeyama clan, etc., led to the outbreak of the Onin War in 1467, and Takakage played an active role in the West squad in cooperation with the master, Yoshikane SHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such internal discord within the Shiba clan, along with issues involving succession to the position of family heads in the Ashikaga shogunate, Hatakeyama clan, etc., led to the outbreak of the Onin War in 1467, and Takakage played an active role in the Wesern squad in cooperation with the master, Yoshikane SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such internal discord within the Shiba clan, along with issues involving succession to the position of the heads of the Ashikaga shogunate, Hatakeyama clan, etc., led to the outbreak of the Onin War in 1467, and Takakage played an active role in the Western squad in cooperation with the master, Yoshikane SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>伏見稲荷に籠もって西軍を苦しめた足軽大将骨皮道賢を討ち取ったのも孝景である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Takakage who defeated Doken HONEKAWA, a samurai in command of a troop of foot soldiers, who secluded in Fushimi Inari and tormented the West squad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Takakage who defeated Doken HONEKAWA, a samurai in command of the foot troops, who was secluded in Fushimi Inari and who had tormented the Western squad.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also Takakage who defeated Doken HONEKAWA, a samurai in command of the foot troops, who was secluded in Fushimi Inari and had tormented the Western squad.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。不要なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>ところが、孝景は、文明_(日本)3年（1471年）5月、将軍義政及び細川勝元から、守護権限行使の密約をもらって東軍に寝返る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in May (old lunar calendar) 1471, he was offered a secret agreement on authorization to act as regional military governor by Shogun Yoshimasa and Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and changed sides to the East squad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in May (old lunar calendar) 1471, he was offered a secret agreement on authorization to act as regional military governor by Shogun Yoshimasa and Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and changed sides to join the Eastern squad.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in May 1471, he was offered a secret agreement on authorization to act as regional military governor by Shogun Yoshimasa and Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and shifted sides to join the Eastern squad.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>当初は苦戦するも、その後は連勝を重ねて実力で越前一国をほぼ手中に収め（下記「戦歴」参照）、斯波氏に代わり、越前国の守護に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He initially had a tough time, but then made consecutive victories, gaining control of the entire Echizen Province on his own (refer to &apos;Military career&apos; below), and was appointed to military governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He initially had a tough time, but then won consecutive victories, gaining control of the entire Echizen Province on his own (refer to &apos;Military career&apos; below), and was appointed to military governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He initially had a tough time, but then won consecutive victories, gaining control of the entire Echizen Province on his own (refer to &apos;Military career&apos; below), and was appointed to military governor of Echizen Province in the place of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、甲斐常治の嫡子である甲斐敏光や二宮氏らの反撃を受け、一時苦境に立たされる中、文明13年（1481年）、54歳で死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he received counterattacks from Toshimitsu KAI, the legitimate son of Jochi KAI, and the Ninomiya clan, and died in hardship in 1481 at the age of 54.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he came under counterattacks from Toshimitsu KAI, the legitimate son of Jochi KAI, and the Ninomiya clan, and died in hardship in 1481 at the age of 54.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he came under counterattacks from Toshimitsu KAI, who was the legitimate son of Jochi KAI, and the Ninomiya clan, and died in hardship in 1481 at the age of fifty-four.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>嫡男の朝倉氏景 (8代当主)がその跡を継ぎ、孝景の弟である朝倉経景・朝倉景冬・朝倉光玖の助力を得て、越前を統一した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legitimate son, Ujikage ASAKURA (8th family head) succeeded, and with the help of Takakage&apos;s brothers, Tsunekage ASAKURA, Kagefuyu ASAKURA, and Kokyu ASAKURA, he unified Echizen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legitimate son, Ujikage ASAKURA (8th family head) succeeded, and with the help of Takakage&apos;s brothers, Tsunekage ASAKURA, Kagefuyu ASAKURA, and Kokyu ASAKURA, he unified Echizen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legitimate son Ujikage ASAKURA (the eighth head of the family) succeeded him, and with the help of Takakage&apos;s brothers Tsunekage ASAKURA, Kagefuyu ASAKURA, and Kokyu ASAKURA, he unified Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>従来、一乗谷を朝倉氏の本拠としたのはこの孝景であると言われていたが、これは『朝倉始末記』という流布本にのみ記載されているもので、ほかに根拠はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditionally, it has been told that it was Takakage who based the Asakura clan in Ichijodani, but this is described only in a rufu-bon (widely circulated edition) called &quot;Asakura Shimatsuki,&quot; and there are no other basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditionally, it has been told that it was Takakage who based the Asakura clan in Ichijodani, but this is only described in a rufu-bon (widely circulated edition) called &quot;Asakura Shimatsuki,&quot; and there is no other basis for this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditionally, it has been told that it was Takakage who based the Asakura clan in Ichijodani, but this is only described in a widely circulated edition called &quot;Asakura Shimatsuki&quot; (Records on the rise and fall of the Asakura clan) and there is no other basis for this.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>『親元日記』などの史料により、かなり以前から朝倉氏が一乗谷に根拠を持っていたことが判明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on historical materials such as &quot;Chikamoto Nikki&quot; (Chikamoto&apos;s diary), it is clear that the Asakura clan was based in Ichijodani well before this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on historical materials such as &quot;Chikamoto Nikki&quot; (Chikamoto&apos;s diary), it is clear that the Asakura clan was based in Ichijodani well before this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on historical materials such as &quot;Chikamoto Nikki&quot; (Chikamoto&apos;s diary), it is clear that the Asakura clan was based in Ichijodani well before this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="23">
<j>孝景は分国法である「朝倉孝景条々」（朝倉敏景十七箇条）を制定したとされているが、これにも疑義がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage is said to have established the bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain), &apos;Asakura Takakage jojo&apos; (a family precept of Takakage ASAKURA) (The seventeen articles of Toshikage Asakura), but there are doubts about this as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage is said to have established the bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain), &apos;Asakura Takakage jojo&apos; (a family precept of Takakage ASAKURA) (The seventeen articles of Toshikage Asakura), but there are doubts about this as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage is said to have established the law individual sengoku daimyo enforced in their own domain, &apos;Asakura Takakage jojo&apos; (a family precept of Takakage ASAKURA) (the seventeen articles of Toshikage Asakura), but there are doubts about this as well.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>天下一の極悪人、天下悪事始業の張本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Worst villain in the world, the chief villain who starts evil deeds in the world</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Worst villain in the world, the chief villain who commits evil deeds in the world</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Worst villain in the world, who was the chief villain who commits evil deeds in the world</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>朝倉孝景は、公領や公家領・寺社領の押領を多く行ったため、当時の権力層である「寺社」「公家」（寺社本所（じしゃほんじょ）にとってはまさに仇敵だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA, who stripped many public lands, lands of kuge (court noble), and lands of temples and shrines, was the sworn enemy of &apos;temples and shrines&apos; and &apos;kuge&apos; (Jisha honjo), who were in power at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage ASAKURA, who stripped many public lands, lands from kuge (court noble), and of temples and shrines, was the sworn enemy of &apos;temples and shrines&apos; and &apos;kuge&apos; (Jisha honjo), who were in power at the time.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA--who took a lot of public lands, lands of court nobles, and of temples and shrines--was the sworn enemy of &apos;temples and shrines&apos; and &apos;court nobles&apos; who were in power at the time (whose lands were collectively called &apos;Jisha honjo&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>公卿の一人甘露寺親長は、日記の中で孝景のことを「天下悪事始行の張本」と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikanaga KANROJI, one of the Kugyo (the top court officials), criticized Takakage as &apos;the chief villain who starts evil deeds in the world&apos; in his journal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikanaga KANROJI, one of the Kugyo (the top court officials), criticized Takakage as &apos;the chief villain who commits evil deeds in the world&apos; in his journal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikanaga KANROJI, one of the Kugyo (the top court officials), described Takakage as &apos;the chief villain who commits evil deeds in the world&apos; in his journal.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>彼の死を聞いた際には「越前の朝倉孝景が死んだということだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he heard of his death, he went as far as to say, &apos;Takakage ASAKURA of Echizen died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he learned of his death, he went as far as to say, &apos;Takakage ASAKURA of Echizen died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he learned of his death, he went as far as to say, &apos;Takakage ASAKURA of Echizen died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>朝倉孝景は「天下一の極悪人」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA is &apos;the worst villain in the world.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage ASAKURA was &apos;the worst villain in the world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA was &apos;the worst villain in the world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>あのような男が死んだことは「近年まれに見る慶事」である」とまで記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The death of such a man is &apos;one of the most auspicious event in recent years&apos;.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The death of such a man is &apos;one of the most auspicious events in recent years&apos;.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The death of such a man is &apos;one of the most auspicious events in recent years.&apos;</e>
<cmt>不要な&apos;を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、一条兼良も自ら越前国に下って孝景と直談判して家領の足羽御厨の回復を求めたが失敗に終わり、『桃華蘂葉』の中で「言語道断也」と記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Kanera ICHIJO went down to Echizen Province in person for a direct negotiation with Takakage to request the return of his territory, Asuwa no mikuriya, but failed, and wrote &apos;It was outrageous&apos; in &quot;Tokazuiyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Kanera ICHIJO went to Echizen Province in person for a direct negotiations with Takakage to request the return of his territory, Asuwa no mikuriya, but failed, and wrote &apos;It was outrageous&apos; in &quot;Tokazuiyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Kanera ICHIJO, who went to Echizen Province in person for a direct negotiations with Takakage to request the return of his territory &apos;Asuwa no mikuriya&apos; and failed, wrote &apos;It was outrageous&apos; in &quot;Tokazuiyo&quot; (a book on knowledge of court rules, ceremony, decorum and records of the past of the Ichijo family).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>興福寺別当の経覚は、孝景の押領に対抗するため、延暦寺に追われていた親戚の本願寺蓮如を自領の吉崎御坊に匿い、代官の役目を負わせつつ浄土真宗の布教を許した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to fight against Takakage&apos;s stripping of land, Kofuku-ji betto (the head priest of Kofuku-ji Temple), Kyogaku, sheltered his relative, Hongan-ji Rennyo, who was exiled to Enryaku-ji Temple, in his territory, Yoshizaki Gobo, and allowed propagation of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) while assigning him the role of daikan (local governor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to fight against Takakage&apos;s stripping of land, Kofuku-ji betto (the head priest of Kofuku-ji Temple), Kyogaku, sheltered his relative, Hongan-ji Rennyo, who was was exiled to Enryaku-ji Temple, in his territory, Yoshizaki Gobo, and allowed propagation of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) while assigning him the role of daikan (local governor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to fight against Takakage&apos;s stripping of land, Kyogaku, who was the head priest of Kofuku-ji Temple, sheltered his relative Hongan-ji Rennyo, who was exiled to Enryaku-ji Temple, in his territory &apos;Yoshizaki Gobo&apos; and allowed propagation of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism), while assigning him the role of local governor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これが後に朝倉氏歴代を悩ませる一向一揆の温床となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became the breeding ground for an uprising of Ikko sect followers, which later haunted successive generations of the Asakura clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became the breeding ground for an uprising of the Ikko sect followers, which later haunted successive generations of the Asakura clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became the breeding ground for an uprising of the Ikko sect followers, which later haunted successive generations of the Asakura clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>その一方で、孝景は、連歌・和歌などに親しみ、歌僧正徹、連歌師飯尾宗祇などと交流を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Takakage enjoyed renga (linked verse), waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), etc. and was in touch with poet-monk, Shotetsu, renga poet, Sogi IIO, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Takakage enjoyed renga (linked verse), waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), etc. and was in touch with poet-monk, Shotetsu, renga poet, Sogi IIO, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Takakage enjoyed renga (linked verse), waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables), etc. and was in touch with poet-monk, Shotetsu, renga poet, Sogi IIO, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>戦歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Military career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>孝景の主だった戦歴は以下のとおりである（旧暦で記す）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage&apos;s main military career is as follows (listed based on old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>西暦に変換して訳しているため「（旧暦で記す）」に対する訳は不要かもしれません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage&apos;s main military career is as follows (listed based on the old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage&apos;s main military career is shown below.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>【長禄合戦】</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Battle of Choroku]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Battle of Choroku]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Battle of Choroku]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>長禄 2年11月 1日　近江・越前国境、×甲斐敏光・孝景 ─ ○堀江利真</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 15, 1458: The army of Toshimitsu KAI and Takakage was defeated by the army of Toshizane HORIE at the border between Omi Province and Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 15, 1458: The army of Toshimitsu KAI and Takakage was defeated by the army of Toshizane HORIE at the border between Omi Province and Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 15, 1458: The army of Toshimitsu KAI and Takakage was defeated by the army of Toshizane HORIE at the border between Omi Province and Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>長禄 3年 5月13日　越前・金ヶ崎城、○甲斐敏光・孝景 ─ ×斯波義敏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 22, 1459: The army of Yoshitoshi SHIBA was defeated by the army of Toshimitsu KAI and Takakage in Echizen, Kanegasaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 22, 1459: The army of Yoshitoshi SHIBA was defeated by the army of Toshimitsu KAI and Takakage in Echizen, Kanegasaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 22, 1459: The army of Yoshitoshi SHIBA was defeated by the army of Toshimitsu KAI and Takakage in Echizen, Kanegasaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>長禄 3年 8月11日　越前・足羽郡和田、○孝景・堀江庶流 ─ ×堀江利真・朝倉将景ら</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 16, 1459: The army of Toshizane HORIE, Yukikage ASAKURA, etc. was defeated by the army of Takakage and branch family of Horie in Echizen, Wada, Asuwa County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 16, 1459: The army of Toshizane HORIE, Yukikage ASAKURA, etc. was defeated by the army of Takakage and branch family of Horie in Echizen, Wada, Asuwa County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 16, 1459: The army of Toshizane HORIE, Yukikage ASAKURA, etc. was defeated by the army of Takakage and branch family of Horie in Echizen, Wada, Asuwa County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>【応仁の乱─京都】</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Onin War - Kyoto]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Onin War - Kyoto]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Onin War - Kyoto]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>応仁元年 1月21日　京都、○孝景 ─ ×大野持種</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 6, 1467: The army of Mochitane ONO was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 6, 1467: The army of Mochitane ONO was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 6, 1467: The army of Mochitane ONO was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>応仁元年 5月26日　京都、○孝景外 ─ ×京極持清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 6, 1467: The army of Mochikiyo KYOGOKU was defeated by the army of Takakage and others in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 6, 1467: The army of Mochikiyo KYOGOKU was defeated by the army of Takakage and others in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 6, 1467: The army of Mochikiyo KYOGOKU was defeated by the army of Takakage and others in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>応仁元年 6月 8日　京都、○孝景 ─ ×京極持清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 18, 1467: The army of Mochikiyo KYOGOKU was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 18, 1467: The army of Mochikiyo KYOGOKU was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 18, 1467: The army of Mochikiyo KYOGOKU was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>応仁元年 6月11日　京都、○孝景 ─ ×細川成之</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 21, 1467: The army of Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 21, 1467: The army of Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 21, 1467: The army of Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>応仁元年 6月14日　京都・二条、○孝景 ─ ×武田信賢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 24, 1467: The army of Nobukata TAKEDA was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto, Nijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 24, 1467: The army of Nobukata TAKEDA was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto, Nijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 24, 1467: The army of Nobukata TAKEDA was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto, Nijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>応仁 2年 3月21日　京都・山科、○孝景 ─ ×骨皮道賢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 22, 1468: The army of Doken HONEKAWA was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto, Yamashina.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 22, 1468: The army of Doken HONEKAWA was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto, Yamashina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 22, 1468: The army of Doken HONEKAWA was defeated by the army of Takakage in Kyoto, Yamashina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>【応仁の乱─越前】</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Onin War - Echizen]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Onin War - Echizen]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Onin War - Echizen]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>文明 3年 6月10日　越前、○孝景 ─ ×甲斐方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 7, 1471: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 7, 1471: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 7, 1471: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>文明 3年 7月21日　越前・河俣、×孝景 ─ ○甲斐方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 16, 1471: The army of Takakage was defeated by the army of the Kai side in Echizen, Kawamata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 16, 1471: The army of Takakage was defeated by the army of the Kai side in Echizen, Kawamata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 16, 1471: The army of Takakage was defeated by the army of the Kai side in Echizen, Kawamata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>文明 3年 8月24日　越前・鯖江外、○孝景 ─ ×甲斐方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 17, 1471: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Sabae, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 17, 1471: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Sabae, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 17, 1471: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Sabae, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>文明 3年 9月11日　越前・清水谷、△孝景 ─ △池田勘解由左衛門尉（時忠か）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 2, 1471: The army of Ikeda kageyusaemon no jo (Tokitada?) and the army of Takakage fought to a draw in Echizen, Shimizudani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 2, 1471: The army of Ikeda kageyusaemon no jo (Tokitada?) and the army of Takakage fought to a draw in Echizen, Shimizudani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 2, 1471: The battle between the army of Ikeda kageyusaemon no jo (presumably Tokitada) and the army of Takakage ended in a draw in Echizen, Shimizudani.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>文明 4年 8月 6日　越前・府中、○孝景 ─ ×甲斐方（府中守護所落去）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 17, 1472: The army of the Kai side (fall of Fuchu shugosho (provincial administration)) was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Fuchu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 17, 1472: The army of the Kai side (fall of Fuchu shugosho - provincial administration) was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Fuchu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 17, 1472: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Fuchu (fall of Fuchu shugosho - provincial administration).</e>
<cmt>括弧を文末に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>文明 4年 8月 8日　越前・長崎、○孝景 ─ ×甲斐方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 19, 1472: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Nagasaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 19, 1472: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Nagasaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 19, 1472: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Nagasaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>文明 5年 8月 8日　越前・樋山外、○孝景 ─ ×甲斐方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 9, 1473: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Hiyama, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 9, 1473: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Hiyama, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 9, 1473: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Hiyama, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>文明 6年 1月18日　越前・杣山、○孝景 ─ ×甲斐方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 13, 1474: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Somayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 13, 1474: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Somayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 13, 1474: The army of the Kai side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Somayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>文明 7年 2月14日　越前・犬山、○孝景 ─ ×二宮方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 30, 1475: The army of the Ninomiya side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Inuyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 30, 1475: The army of the Ninomiya side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Inuyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 30, 1475: The army of the Ninomiya side was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Inuyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>文明 7年11月 3日　越前・井野、○孝景 ─ ×二宮左近将監・二宮駿河守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 10, 1475: The army of Ninomiya Sakon no shogen, Ninomiya Suruga no kami was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Ino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 10, 1475: The army of Ninomiya Sakon no shogen, Ninomiya Suruga no kami was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Ino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 10, 1475: The army of Ninomiya Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Ninomiya Suruga no kami (the governor of Suruga) was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Ino.</e>
<cmt>役職の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>文明 7年12月 3日　越前・土橋、○孝景 ─ ×二宮方（土橋城落城）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 8, 1476: The army of the Ninomiya side (fall of Dobashi-jo Castle) was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Dobashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 8, 1476: The army of the Ninomiya side (fall of Dobashi-jo Castle) was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Dobashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 10, 1475: The army of Ninomiya Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Ninomiya Suruga no kami (the governor of Suruga) was defeated by the army of Takakage in Echizen, Ino.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Seibuabina(id:37532), 桂鷺淵(id:151322), GAVVA(id:47103), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 砂場(id:27896), 松茸(id:27535), HI(id:72996), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>