<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>千葉常秀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunehide CHIBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunehide CHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunehide CHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>千葉 常秀（ちば つねひで、生没年不詳）とは鎌倉時代前期の御家人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunehide CHIBA (the year of his birth and dead unknown) was gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunehide CHIBA (the year of his birth and dead unknown) was a gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>不定冠詞を追加しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunehide CHIBA (the year of his birth and dead unknown) was a gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) during the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>千葉胤正の子で千葉成胤の弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a child of Tanemasa CHIBA and a brother of Naritane CHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a child of Tanemasa CHIBA and a brother of Naritane CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a child of Tanemasa CHIBA and a brother of Naritane CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は境平氏（さかい へいじ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Heiji SAKAI.</e>
<cmt>Ｗｅｂには、「境平氏」となっており、抜けている「平」を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Heiji SAKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Heiji SAKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「境 常秀」「上総 常秀」と呼ばれる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also referred to as &apos;Tsunehide SAKAI&apos; or &apos;Tsunehide KAZUSA.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also referred to as &apos;Tsunehide SAKAI&apos; or &apos;Tsunehide KAZUSA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also referred to as &apos;Tsunehide SAKAI&apos; or &apos;Tsunehide KAZUSA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に千葉秀胤・千葉時常。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetane CHIBA and Tokitsune CHIBA were his children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had sons, Hidetane CHIBA and Tokitsune CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>訳文は倒置していますがどうでしょうか。統治しない形で（原文の内容で）修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had sons, Hidetane CHIBA and Tokitsune CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>上総千葉氏の祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the founder of the Chiba clan in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the founder of the Chiba clan in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the founder of the Chiba clan in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>通称である「境」は千葉氏の本拠である千葉荘の外れにあった境川（現在の村田川）流域に拠点があったからとされ、後に下総国垣生荘及び上総国玉崎荘などを支配して玉崎荘の大柳館（現在の千葉県睦沢町）を拠点とし、更に千葉荘とは境川対岸の上総国市原郡にも進出することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The home base of the Chiba clan was in Chiba no sho (the private estate of the Chiba clan), in the watershed of the Sakai-gawa River, which was located on the outskirt of Chiba no sho and from which his common name, &apos;Sakai,&apos; was derived, and then he also reigned Habu no sho in Shimousa Province, Tamasaki no sho in Kazusa Province and established his base at Oyanagi no tate (now Mutsuzawa cho, Chiba Prefecture) in Tamasaki no sho, additionally expanding his territory to Ichihara County in Kazusa Province, opposite shore of the Sakai-gawa River from Chiba no sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that his common name, &apos;Sakai&apos; was derived from the fact that the foothold of the Chiba clan was located in the watershed of Sakai-gawa River, which is running through the outskirt of their base territory, Chiba no sho (the private estate of the Chiba clan); later he also reigned Habu no sho in Shimousa Province and Tamasaki no sho in Kazusa Province, and established his foothold at Oyanagi no tate (currently Mutsuzawa-cho, Chiba Prefecture) in Tamasaki no sho; he further expanded his territory to the opposite shore of Sakai-gawa River from Chiba no sho, Ichihara District in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>この文章は本来分割すべきかと思います。「and」によるrun-on sentenceとなっています。「；」により完全に分割する方法を取りました。境川の記述部分についても修正しています。「郡」の訳を「County」から「District」に変更しています。青字は語順変更のみ行ったことを表しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that his common name, &apos;Sakai&apos; was derived from the fact that the foothold of the Chiba clan was located in the watershed of Sakai-gawa River, which is running through the outskirt of their base territory, Chiba no sho (the private estate of the Chiba clan); later he also reigned Habu no sho in Shimousa Province and Tamasaki no sho in Kazusa Province, and established his foothold at Oyanagi no tate (currently Mutsuzawa-cho, Chiba Prefecture) in Tamasaki no sho; he further expanded his territory to the opposite shore of Sakai-gawa River from Chiba no sho, Ichihara District in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>元暦元年（1184年）に、祖父千葉常胤とともに源範頼の治承・寿永の乱軍に参加して周防国・豊後国を転戦、文治5年（1189年）の奥州合戦でも祖父とともに多賀城に入っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1184, he joined the army of MINAMOTO no Noriyori, who fought the Battle of Jisho-Juei, with his grandfather, Tsunetane CHIBA, and moved from Suo Province (now, a part of Yamaguchi Prefecture) to Bungo Province (now Oita Prefecture) to fight, entering the Taga-jo Castle at the Battle of Oshu (now the Tohoku region) with his grandfather in 1189.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1184, he joined the army of MINAMOTO no Noriyori for the Battle of Jisho-Juei, and took part in various battles in Suo Province (now, a part of Yamaguchi Prefecture) and Bungo Province (now Oita Prefecture) with his grandfather, Tsunetane CHIBA, while they again took part in the Battle of Oshu (the area currently in Tohoku region) together by entering Taga-jo Castle in 1189.</e>
<cmt>転戦などの記述が直訳的で冗長でしたので語順訂正や簡略化によってわかりやすいものに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1184, he joined the army of MINAMOTO no Noriyori for the Battle of Jisho-Juei, and took part in various battles in Suo Province (now, a part of Yamaguchi Prefecture) and Bungo Province (now Oita Prefecture) with his grandfather, Tsunetane CHIBA, while they again took part in the Battle of Oshu (the area currently in Tohoku region) together by entering Taga-jo Castle in 1189.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>建久元年（1190年）の源頼朝の上洛に従い、祖父の譲りによって兵衛府に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1190, he accompanied MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who went up to Kyoto, and appointed to Hyoe-fu (Head quarters of the Middle Palace Guard) from his grandfather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo headed to Kyoto in 1190, Tsunehide joined the force, and he was appointed to the new Hyoe-fu (Head quarters of the Middle Palace Guard) after his grandfather Tsunetane returned the position.</e>
<cmt>関係代名詞による分割が冗長化につながっています。関係代名詞を用いない方法で簡略化しました。訳文によると兵衛府に任じたのは祖父である事になってしまいます。原文では祖父がその地位を譲ったため、常秀が新たに兵衛府に任じられたとありますので、そのように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo headed to Kyoto in 1190, Tsunehide joined the force, and he was appointed to the new Hyoe-fu (Head quarters of the Middle Palace Guard) after his grandfather Tsunetane returned the position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>5年後の頼朝上洛にも随行して東大寺の大仏殿落成供養に随行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five years later, he also accompanied Yoritomo, who went up to Kyoto to participate in the inauguration ceremony of rebuilding the Great Buddha Hall of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five years later, Tsunehide accompanied Yoritomo again as he went to Kyoto for participating in the inauguration ceremony of the rebuilt Great Buddha Hall of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「also」の利用が誤訳につながっています。原文では「5年後ーにも随行して」の意味ですが、訳文では「彼も随行して」となってしまっています。修正しました。大仏殿落成供養の訳部分が冗長だったため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five years later, Tsunehide accompanied Yoritomo again as he went to Kyoto for participating in the inauguration ceremony of the rebuilt Great Buddha Hall of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>正治2年（1200年）には、源頼家に供奉して鶴岡八幡宮に参詣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1200, he joined the procession of vassals that accompanied MINAMOTO no Yoriie, who visited to Tsuruoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>供奉→行幸などの行列に加わること＜広辞苑→join the procession of vassals that accompany Yoriie訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1200, he joined the procession of vassals that accompanied MINAMOTO no Yoriie visiting Tsuruoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>関係代名詞による分割が冗長化につながっています。関係代名詞を用いない方法で簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1200, he joined the procession of vassals that accompanied MINAMOTO no Yoriie visiting Tsuruoka Hachiman-gu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>建仁3年（1203年）には大江親広とともに鎌倉中寺社奉行に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1203, he was appointed to Jisha-bugyo (magistrate of temples and shrines) at Kamakura, the shogunal capital, as well as OＥ no Chikahiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1203, he was appointed to Jisha-bugyo (magistrate of temples and shrines) of shogunal capital Kamakura along with OＥ no Chikahiro.</e>
<cmt>コンマによる分割が冗長化につながっています。コンマ利用を避け簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1203, he was appointed to Jisha-bugyo (magistrate of temples and shrines) of shogunal capital Kamakura along with OＥ no Chikahiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>元久2年（1205年）の畠山重忠追討には北条義時に従って後陣に詰めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1205, he followed Yoshitoki HOJO, to hunt down and kill Shigetada HATAKEYAMA, who had taken up arms against the HOJO, serving as rear guard.</e>
<cmt>畠山重忠→who had taken up arms against the HOJOを補足しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1205, Tsunehide took part as the rear guard of the troops of Yoshitoki HOJO, which was organized to hunt down and kill a rebel, Shigetada HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>コンマによって分割されることで、主従の関係が非常にわかりづらくなります。原文により内容を理解している訳者は分割された分節が何に従い、何を意味しているのか正確に分かりますが、このように分割されていると始めてこの内容に接する人間は意味を誤解するか、意味がまったくわからなくなる可能性があります。例えば、「serving as rea guard」は誰の行為かと考えたとき、文の最初にある&quot;代名詞を充てられて弱まった「he」の行為だと瞬時に理解できる人がいるか疑問です。文中、固有名詞がある場合は代名詞より強い印象を持ちますし、文法的にも「〜ing」形はその直前の内容を修飾する分節を形成するものと定義されると思いますので、パッと見た時、「serving〜」の前にある「HOJO」の行為と判断する可能性が高いといえます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1205, Tsunehide took part as the rear guard of the troops of Yoshitoki HOJO, which was organized to hunt down and kill a rebel, Shigetada HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>承久元年（1219年）には源実朝右大臣就任の鶴岡八幡宮拝賀に供奉し、実朝暗殺事件に遭遇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he accompanied MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, who visited to Tsuruoka Hachiman-gu Shrine to show gratitude to god for assumption of udaijin (minister of the right) in 1219, he encountered the assassination of Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1219, Tsunehide encountered the scene of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo being assassinated when he accompanied Sanetomo visiting Tsuruoka Hachiman-gu Shrine to make an address of gratitude to god for the bestowment of udaijin (minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>言い回しのぎこちない部分を多少修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1219, Tsunehide encountered the scene of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo being assassinated when he accompanied Sanetomo visiting Tsuruoka Hachiman-gu Shrine to make an address of gratitude to god for the bestowment of udaijin (minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>嘉禄元年（1225年）には小山朝政とともに従五位下下総守に任じられ、後に上総介に転じて嘉禎元年（1235年）の明王院 (鎌倉市)の供養に際して九条頼経に供奉している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1225, he was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Shimousa no kami (Governor of Shimousa Province) with Tomomasa KOYAMA, and then to Kazusa no Kami, and in 1235, he accompanied Yoritsune KUJO in joining the inauguration ceremony of Myoo-in Temple (in Kamakura City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1225, he was bestowed the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed to Shimousa no kami (Governor of Shimousa Province) along with Tomomasa KOYAMA, while he was later transferred to Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province): he accompanied Yoritsune KUJO in joining the inauguration ceremony of Myoo-in Temple (in Kamakura City).</e>
<cmt>従五位下は「任じられる」ものではないため、「下総守」に任じられた事と同義にまとめることはできないと思います。従五位下には叙せられ、その上で下総守にも任じられたとすべきだと思います。原文で「上総介」のところを訳文では「上総守」としています。また上総介の説明がありませんでしたので加えました。（続く項目で上総介に関する説明がありますが、別の意義についての詳細説明です）原文は内容がわかれる部分で分割すべきと思いますが、訳も分割されていないため、ここでは「；」により内容の異なる部分を分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1225, he was bestowed the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed to Shimousa no kami (Governor of Shimousa Province) along with Tomomasa KOYAMA, while he was later transferred to Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province): he accompanied Yoritsune KUJO in joining the inauguration ceremony of Myoo-in Temple (in Kamakura City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>官位などは宗家を継いだ兄・成胤を越え、更には千葉介（下総介）の上官である下総守、ついで親王任国である上総国衙の最高の地位である上総介の地位を得て宗家をしのぐ地位を獲得するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He surpassed his elder brother, Naritane, who succeeded to the head Chiba family in official rank; he was promoted to Shimousa no kami, higher rank of Chiba no suke (assistant governor of Chiba Province) (also called Shimousa no suke) and at last to Kazusa no suke, the highest rank of Kazusa Kokuga (territories governed by provincial government office), which was Shinno-ningoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He surpassed his elder brother Naritane who succeeded the head of Chiba family, in terms of their official ranks; Tsunehide was promoted to Shimousa no kami, a higher rank to Naritane&apos;s Chiba no suke (assistant governor of Chiba Province, also called Shimousa no suke), while Tsunehide later achieved the position of Kazusa no suke, the highest rank official of Kazusa Kokuga (territories governed by provincial government office) designated as Shinno-ningoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes).</e>
<cmt>訳文では多くの分節がandで接続されておりわかりづらいため、語順の変更や形容詞の追加などで分節や文章をつなぎ、接続詞を減らしています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He surpassed his elder brother Naritane who succeeded the head of Chiba family, in terms of their official ranks; Tsunehide was promoted to Shimousa no kami, a higher rank to Naritane&apos;s Chiba no suke (assistant governor of Chiba Province, also called Shimousa no suke), while Tsunehide later achieved the position of Kazusa no suke, the highest rank official of Kazusa Kokuga (territories governed by provincial government office) designated as Shinno-ningoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>更に『千葉大系図』には上総守護に補任されたと記されており、源頼朝に討たれた上総広常の子孫に代わって上総氏の地位を継承したとする見方もあるが明証はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the &quot;Chiba Taikeizu (Genealogy of the Chiba Family)&quot; records that he was assigned to be Kazusa Shugo (the Governor of Kazusa Province); it is believed that instead of the descendants of the Hirotsune KAZUSA, who was killed by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, he succeeded to the position of the Kazusa clan, but there is no reliable evidence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the record of &quot;Chiba Taikeizu (Genealogy of the Chiba Family)&quot;, Tsunehide was consequently appointed as Kazusa Shugo (the Governor of Kazusa Province); therefore, some suggests the possibility that he succeeded the head position of the Kazusa clan instead of the descendants of Hirotsune KAZUSA, who was killed by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo; but there is no reliable evidence to prove.</e>
<cmt>これも語順修正と、文章の分節・統合の修正です。文章の流れを重視しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the record of &quot;Chiba Taikeizu (Genealogy of the Chiba Family)&quot;, Tsunehide was consequently appointed as Kazusa Shugo (the Governor of Kazusa Province); therefore, some suggests the possibility that he succeeded the head position of the Kazusa clan instead of the descendants of Hirotsune KAZUSA, who was killed by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo; but there is no reliable evidence to prove.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>没年は不詳だが、嘉禎4年（1238年）から仁治2年（1241年）の間と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of his death was known, but it is assumed from 1238 to 1241.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the year of his death is not specified, it is estimated to be around 1238 to 1241.</e>
<cmt>原文で「没年は不詳だが」とあるところ、訳文では「the year of his death was known」となっており誤訳です。修正しました。assumeは推定の意味でも「当然〜だと思う」の意味が強くなります。estimateを用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the year of his death is not specified, it is estimated to be around 1238 to 1241.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>