<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山崎闇斎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ansai YAMAZAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ansai YAMAZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ansai YAMAZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山崎 闇斎（やまざき あんさい、元和 (日本)4年12月9日 (旧暦)（1619年1月24日） - 天和 (日本)2年9月16日 (旧暦)（1682年10月16日））は、江戸前期の儒者・朱子学者・神道家・思想家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ansai YAMAZAKI (January 24, 1619 - October 16, 1682) was a Confucian scholar, neo-Confucian Scholar, Shintoist and thinker in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>江戸前期→the early Edo period (based on ALC)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ansai YAMAZAKI (January 24, 1619 - October 16, 1682) was a Confucian scholar, neo-Confucian scholar, Shintoist and philosopher of the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>While &quot;思想家&quot; and &quot;哲学者&quot; are not quite the same thing, &quot;thinker&quot; seems strange to me without some kind of adjective indicating what kind of thinker he was (e.g. political thinker).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ansai YAMAZAKI (January 24, 1619 - October 16, 1682) was a Confucian scholar, neo-Confucian scholar, Shintoist and philosopher of the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は嘉、字は敬義、通称嘉右衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was known as Uemon KA, his name was KA and his nickname was Moriyoshi.</e>
<cmt>字（あざな）は下のサイトによればあだ名とのことです。http://www.weblio.jp/content/%E3%81%82%E3%81%96%E3%81%AA</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was known as Kaemon YAMAZAKI, his actual name was Ka YAMAZAKI and his nickname was Moriyoshi.</e>
<cmt>The original translation doesn&apos;t seem to reflect the likely meaning of the Japanese.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was known as Kaemon YAMAZAKI, his actual name was Ka YAMAZAKI and his nickname was Moriyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>闇斎は号、霊社号は垂加霊社 (すいか・しでます)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the name Ansai as his go (byname) and Suika (Shidemasu)-Reisha as Reisha-Go.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the name Ansai as Confucian scholar Go (title) and Suika-Shidemasu as Reisha (an architecture where a small shrine to warship ancestors&apos; spirits is placed)-Go.</e>
<cmt>There is too much Japanese in this translation for a native speaker to have any chance of understanding this. I&apos;ve fixed a little of it but it really needs to be re-translated. Certainly the term &quot;reisha-go&quot; needs to be accompanied by an explanation and I&apos;m not sure if &quot;byname&quot; is an appropriate explanation of &quot;go&quot;.(translator note)Reisha is a place or building where &quot;Shoushi&quot; (a small shrine) to warship ancestors&apos; spirits is placed and often near the family grave yard or familiar place.祖先の霊を祀るために墓所や縁故の場所に小祠を設けたものを霊社儒者号を闇斎、神道号を垂加（すいか）と称した。http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/%E5%B1%B1%E5%B4%8E%E9%97%87%E6%96%8E/Idea of &quot;Shoushi&quot; can be obtained from the following: the http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110004654715/</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the name Ansai as Confucian scholar Go (title) and Suika (also called Shidemasu) -Reisha as Reisha-Go (Shintoist title).</e>
<cmt>原文の「すいか・しでます」は、「垂加」の読みが「すいか」「しでます」の2つあるという意味のため、Suika-Shidemasu→Suika (also called Shidemasu) -Reishaとし、後に続く補足を削除、および「霊社号」→「神道号」と解釈し、Reisha-Go (Shintoist title)としました。(参照: http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/%E5%B1%B1%E5%B4%8E%E9%97%87%E6%96%8E/)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Monk&apos;s Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Monk&apos;s Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>京都で浪人 (武士)の子として生まれ、幼くして比叡山に入り、ついで妙心寺に移って僧となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born to a Ronin (Samurai) family in Kyoto, he entered Hieizan mountain at his young age and moved to Myoshin-ji Temple to become a monk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born to a ronin (masterless samurai) family in Kyoto, he left home for Mt. Hiei at a young age to enter the Myoshin-ji Temple and become a monk.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Born to a ronin (masterless samurai) family in Kyoto, he left home for Mt. Hiei at a young age to enter the Myoshin-ji Temple and become a monk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>19歳のころ土佐の吸江寺に移り、湘南宗化の弟子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was about nineteen years old, he moved to Gyuko-ji Temple in Tosa to go apprentice under Soke SHONAN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was around 19 years of age, he moved to Gyuko-ji Temple in Tosa for an apprenticeship under Soke SHONAN.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was around 19 years of age, he moved to Gyuko-ji Temple in Tosa for an apprenticeship under Shonan Soke.</e>
<cmt>Soke SHONAN→Shonan Sokeとしました。(僧侶名)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>土佐南学派の谷時中から朱子学の手ほどきを受け、また野中兼山や小倉三省らとの交わりのなかで、朱子学への傾倒を深め、1642年に還俗して儒者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was having Neo-Confucian training from Jichu TANI in the Tosa-Namgakuha, he grew seriously involved in the Neo-Confucian from socializing with Kenzan NONAKA and Sansei OGURA, and accomplished an exclaustration to become a New-Confucian in 1642.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had Neo-Confucian training from Jichu TANI in the Tosa-Namgakuha. He became seriously involved in Neo-Confucianism from his association with Kenzan NONAKA and Sansei OGURA, and accomplished an exclaustration to become a New-Confucian in 1642.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had Neo-Confucian training from Jichu TANI in the Tosa Nangaku school, and he became seriously involved in Neo-Confucianism from his association with Kenzan NONAKA and Sansei OGURA, and accomplished an exclaustration to become a New-Confucian in 1642.</e>
<cmt>訳文が二文に分かれているため一文になるよう修正、Tosa-Namgakuha→Tosa Nangaku schoolに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>1665年、会津藩主保科正之の賓師に迎えられ、藩政への助言者として活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was invited to work as a Hinshi for the lord of Aizu, Masayuki HOSHINA in 1665 and took an active role to give advice about the ruling in the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was invited to work as a Hinshi for the lord of Aizu, Masayuki HOSHINA in 1665; and, took an active role in giving advice on the ruling of the domain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was invited to work as a Hinshi (guest teacher) for the lord of Aizu, Masayuki HOSHINA in 1665; and, took an active role in giving advice on the ruling of the domain.</e>
<cmt>Hinshiの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>領内の寺院・神社の整理をおこない、神仏習合を排除した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He reorganized temples and shrines in his territory to rule out the syncretization of Shinto and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He reorganized temples and shrines in his territory to rule out the syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He reorganized temples and shrines in his territory to rule out the syncretization of Shinto with Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また吉川惟足の影響で、神道研究にも本格的に取り組むようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influenced by Koretari YOSHIKAWA, he also got to be seriously involved in Shinto research.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influenced by Koretari YOSHIKAWA, he also became seriously involved in Shinto research.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influenced by Koretari YOSHIKAWA, he also became seriously involved in Shinto research.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>彼の提唱した朱子学を、崎門学または闇斎学という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Neo-Confucian advocated by him is called Kimon-gaku or Ansai-gaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Neo-Confucianism he advocated is known as Kimon-gaku or Ansai-gaku.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Neo-Confucianism he advocated is known as Kimon-gaku or Ansai-gaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>従来の神道と儒学を統合して、垂加神道を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He integrated the former Shinto and Neo-Confucian to set up the foundation of the Suika-Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He integrated traditional Shinto with Neo-Confucianism, and laid the foundation for Suika-Shinto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He integrated traditional Shinto with Neo-Confucianism, and laid the foundation for Suika-Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その思想の独自性は、放伐を否定した点にあり、水戸学・国学などとともに、幕末の尊王攘夷思想に大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Distinctive character of his philosophy was to deny Hobatsu (expel outrageous tyrants, etc. from a capital), and this had significant influence on the Sonno-Joi (Revere the Emperor and expel the foreigners) in the end of the Edo Period as well as Mito-gaku and Koku-gaku.</e>
<cmt>放伐の英訳に下を括弧書きで追加しました。Expel outrageous tyrants, etc. from a capital.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distinctive character of his philosophy was the denial of Hobatsu (expel outrageous tyrants, etc. from a capital), and this had significant influence on the Sonno-Joi (Revere the Emperor and expel the foreigners) at the end of the Edo Period, as well as for Mito-gaku and Koku-gaku.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distinctive character of his philosophy was the denial of Hobatsu (expel outrageous tyrants, etc. from a capital), and this had significant influence on the Sonno-Joi (Revere the Emperor and expel the foreigners) at the end of the Edo period, as well as for Mito-gaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) and Koku-gaku (the study of Japanese classical literature).</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更、Mito-gaku、Koku-gakuの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>門人には、佐藤直方・浅見絅斎・三宅尚斎・植田艮背・遊佐木斎・谷秦山・正親町公通・出雲路敬直らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His monjin students were Naokata SATO, Keisai ASAMI, Shosai MIYAKE, Konpai UEDA, Mokusai YUSA, Jinzan TANI, Kinmichi OGIMACHI and Yoshinao IZUMOJI, and the line of Ansai-gaku was called &apos;Kimon-gaku school.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His monjin students were Naokata SATO, Keisai ASAMI, Shosai MIYAKE, Konpai UEDA, Mokusai YUSA, Jinzan TANI, Kinmichi OGIMACHI and Yoshinao IZUMOJI. The line of Ansai-gaku is called the &apos;Kimon-gaku school.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His disciples were Naokata SATO, Keisai ASAMI, Shosai MIYAKE, Konpai UEDA, Mokusai YUSA, Jinzan TANI, Kinmichi OGIMACHI and Yoshinao IZUMOJI.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」monjin students→disciplesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>闇齋学の系統を「崎門学派」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The line of Ansai-gaku is called the &apos;Kimon-gaku school.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>著書一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of books written</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List of books written</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List of Books Written</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>文会筆録</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunkai Hitsuroku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunkai Hitsuroku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunkai Hitsuroku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>倭鑑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato Kagami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato Kagami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato Kagami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>伊勢神宮儀式序</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise-jingu Gishikijo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise-jingu Gishikijo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise-jingu Gishikijo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>闢異</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Byakui</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Byakui</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Byakui</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>垂加文集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suika Bunshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suika Bunshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suika Bunshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>神代巻風葉集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamiyo no Maki Fuyo-Shu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamiyo no Maki Fuyo-Shu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamiyo no Maki Fuyo-Shu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>中臣祓風水草</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakatomi no Harae Fusuiso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakatomi no Harae Fusuiso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakatomi no Harae Fusuiso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>墓所・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Monk&apos;s Grave and Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Monk&apos;s Grave and Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Monk&apos;s Grave and Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>山崎闇斎は、人間の心（心神）は、即ち天神と同源であり同一であるとの思想から、自らの心神を自宅の祠に祀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on his philosophy that human&apos;s spirit (Shinshin) and so-called Tenjin were of the same nature or hypostasis and were identical, Ansai YAMAZAKI was enshrining his Shinshin in Hokora (a small shrine) in his house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His philosophy declared that the human spirit (Shinshin) and Tenjin were of the same source and were identical. Ansai YAMAZAKI enshrined his Shinshin in Hokora (a small shrine) in his house.</e>
<cmt>wording, explanation will be required for the Japanese words in red.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His philosophy declared that the human spirit (Shinshin) and Tenjin (heavenly gods) were of the same source and were identical; Ansai YAMAZAKI enshrined his Shinshin in Hokora (a small shrine) in his house.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため一文になるよう修正、Tenjinの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>社名は、闇斎の霊社号と同じ、垂加霊社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrine&apos;s name was the same as Ansai&apos;s Reisha-Go, Suika-Reisha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shrine&apos;s name was the same as Ansai&apos;s Reisha-Go, Suika-Reisha.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shrine&apos;s name was the same as Ansai&apos;s Reisha-Go, Suika-Reisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>のちに下御霊神社の境内に遷座して、猿田彦神社に合祀され、現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, after his shrine was transferred to the premise of Shimogoryo-jinja Shrine, the shrine got to be enshrined in Sarutahiko-jinja Shrine together and is now existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, after his shrine was transferred to the Shimogoryo-jinja Shrine premises, the shrine was enshrined together in Sarutahiko-jinja Shrine and remains there today.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, after his shrine was transferred to the Shimogoryo-jinja Shrine premises, the shrine was enshrined together in Sarutahiko-jinja Shrine and remains there today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>墓所は、京都左京区黒谷の金戒光明寺にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is at Konkai Komyo-ji Temple in Kurotani, Sakyo-ku, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is at Konkai Komyo-ji Temple in Kurotani, Sakyo-ku, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is at Konkai Komyo-ji Temple in Kurotani, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Sakyo-ku→Sakyo Wardに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 猫定規(id:79367), やりたこ(id:113528), Yonoemon(id:55450), Harunosaiten(id:139340), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Nnh(id:474), Stanislaus(id:1806), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 二八(id:10408), 難民(id:4644), けんち(id:5147), Setomanko(id:3051), Knoy(id:8965), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>