<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊勢貞親</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadachika ISE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadachika ISE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadachika ISE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊勢 貞親（いせ さだちか、1417年（応永24年） - 1473年2月18日（文明 (日本)5年1月21日 (旧暦)））は、室町時代の室町幕府政所執事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadachika ISE (1417 - February 18, 1473, which was January 21 according to the old calendar) was mandokoro shitsuji (head of the chief governing body) within the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadachika ISE (1417 - February 18, 1473, which was January 21 according to the old calendar) was mandokoro shitsuji (head of the chief governing body) within the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadachika ISE (1417 - February 27, 1473) was mandokoro shitsuji (head of the chief governing body) within the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>西暦のみを採用(指示書による）18 -&gt; 27 (グレゴリオ暦に変更)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は伊勢貞国、母は蜷川親俊の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sadakuni ISE and his mother was the daughter of Chikatoshi NINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Sadakuni ISE and his mother was the daughter of Chikatoshi NINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Sadakuni ISE and his mother was the daughter of Chikatoshi NINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>兄弟に伊勢貞藤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadafuji ISE was his brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadafuji ISE was his brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadafuji ISE was his brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に伊勢貞宗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadamune ISE was his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadamune ISE was his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadamune ISE was his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>法号は聴松院悦堂常慶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His hogo (posthumous Buddhist name) was 聴松院悦堂常慶.</e>
<cmt>聴松院悦堂常慶→[読み方不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His hogo (posthumous Buddhist name) was 聴松院悦堂常慶.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">translate name</e>
<cmt>法号の読み方不明です</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1454年（享徳3年）に家督を相続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1454, he inherited the family estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1454, he inherited the family estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1454, he inherited the family estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>8代将軍足利義政の幼少の頃から養育し、1443年には管領の畠山持国の仲介で義政との擬似父子関係を取り結んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadachika raised young Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the future shogun, and through mediation by Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA, then a kanrei (top official post in the Muromachi bakufu), tied spurious father-son relation with Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadachika raised young Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the future shogun, and through mediation by Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA, then a kanrei (top official post in the Muromachi bakufu), formed a spurious father-son relation with Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadachika raised young Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the future 8th shogun, and through mediation by Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA, then kanrei (top official post in the Muromachi bakufu), formed a spurious father-son relation with Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処(原文の文末を修正）8thを補うa kanrei→kanrei</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また分一銭制度の確立などを通じて幕府財政の再建を成功させて信任を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded in restructuring bakufu finances through the establishment of the buichisenseido (tax system developed by the Muromachi bakufu), thereby winning the confidence of the Ashikaga shogunate</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded in restructuring bakufu finances through the establishment of the buichisenseido (tax system developed by the Muromachi bakufu), thereby winning the confidence of the Ashikaga shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded in restructuring bakufu finances through the establishment of the buichisenseido (tax system developed by the Muromachi bakufu), thereby winning the confidence of the Ashikaga shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1460年（寛正5年）に政所執事に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1460, he was appointed mandokoro shitsuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1460, he was appointed mandokoro shitsuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1460, he was appointed mandokoro shitsuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>禅僧の季瓊真蘂らとともに政務に消極的な義政に代わって実権を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In place of passive Yoshimasa, Sadachika and a zen monk, Shinzui KIKEI, held power over the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In place of passive Yoshimasa, Sadachika and a zen monk, Shinzui KIKEI, held power over the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In place of passive Yoshimasa, Sadachika and a zen monk, Shinzui KIKEI, held power over the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>1464年に義政の正室の日野富子が男子（足利義尚）を産むと、貞親は義尚の乳父となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1464, when Yoshimasa&apos;s legal wife, Tomiko HINO, gave birth to a boy (Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA), Sadachika became his menoto (a foster father).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1464, when Yoshimasa&apos;s legal wife, Tomiko HINO, gave birth to a boy (Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA), Sadachika became his menoto (a foster father).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1464, when Yoshimasa&apos;s legal wife, Tomiko HINO, gave birth to a boy (Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA), Sadachika became his menoto (a foster father).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この頃、斯波氏の斯波義敏と斯波義廉の間で行われていた家督争いがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time, there was a fight for the family estate within the Shiba clan between Yoshitoshi and Yoshikado.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, there was a fight for the family estate within the Shiba clan between Yoshitoshi and Yoshikado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, there was a fight for the family estate within the Shiba clan between Yoshitoshi and Yoshikado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>貞親はこれに介入し、1466年（文正元年）には貞親らは義政に進言して斯波家家督を義敏に与えさせるが、山名持豊（宗全）や義敏派であった細川勝元らが義廉支持に回る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadachika intervened and made suggestion to Yoshimasa to award the Shiba estate to Yoshitoshi; however, Mochitoyo YAMANA (Sozen) and Katsumoto HOSOKAWA sided with Yoshikado.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadachika intervened and suggested that Yoshimasa award the Shiba estate to Yoshitoshi; however, Mochitoyo YAMANA (Sozen) and Katsumoto HOSOKAWA sided with Yoshikado.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadachika intervened and suggested that Yoshimasa award the Shiba estate to Yoshitoshi; however, Mochitoyo YAMANA (Sozen) and Katsumoto HOSOKAWA sided with Yoshikado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>義尚誕生後に発生した次期将軍が決定していた義政の弟の足利義視との間で将軍後継問題が発生し、同年には義尚の乳父であった貞親は義視を排斥するために義視謀反の噂を流す謀略を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Yoshihisa was born, it was decided that Yoshimasa&apos;s younger brother Yoshimi ASHIKAGA would be the next shogun; however, with the birth of Yoshimasa&apos;s son, a dispute over who would become the next shogun broke out between Yoshimasa and Yoshimi, and in the same year, Sadachika, Yoshihisa&apos;s foster father, schemed to discredit Yoshimi by starting a rumor that Yoshimi was planning a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Yoshihisa was born, it had been decided that Yoshimasa&apos;s younger brother Yoshimi ASHIKAGA would be the next shogun; however, with the birth of Yoshimasa&apos;s son, a dispute over who would become the next shogun broke out between Yoshimasa and Yoshimi, and in the same year, Sadachika, Yoshihisa&apos;s foster father, schemed to discredit Yoshimi by starting a rumor that Yoshimi was planning a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Yoshihisa was born, it had been decided that Yoshimasa&apos;s younger brother Yoshimi ASHIKAGA would be the next shogun; however, with the birth of Yoshimasa&apos;s son, a dispute over who would become the next shogun broke out between Yoshimasa and Yoshimi, and in the same year, Sadachika, Yoshihisa&apos;s foster father, schemed to discredit Yoshimi by starting a rumor that Yoshimi was planning a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>義視が勝元を頼ると讒訴の罪を問われて近江国（滋賀県）へ逃れ、真蘂や赤松政則ら貞親派が失脚する文正の政変に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimi sought the help of Katsumoto, which resulted in Sadachika being accused of zanso(bringing false charges) and driven out to Omi Province (Shiga Prefecture), an incident leading to the Bucho Political Incident in which Shizui and Masanori AKAMATSU, who had sided with Sadachika, were ousted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimi sought the help of Katsumoto, which resulted in Sadachika being accused of zanso (bringing false charges) and driven out to Omi Province (Shiga Prefecture), an incident leading to the Bucho Political Incident in which Shizui and Masanori AKAMATSU, who had sided with Sadachika, were ousted.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimi sought the help of Katsumoto, which resulted in Sadachika being accused of zanso (bringing false charges) and driven out to Omi Province (Shiga Prefecture), an incident leading to the Bunsho Political Incident in which Shizui and Masanori AKAMATSU, who had sided with Sadachika, were ousted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処Bucho→Bunsho</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>翌1467年（応仁元年）には細川勝元率いる西軍と山名持豊率いる東軍との間で戦端が開かれ応仁の乱に至ると、義政に呼び戻され復帰する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, in 1467, a fight broke out between the east force led by Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and east force led by Mochitoyo YAMANA, which developed into the Onin War, and he was called back by Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, 1467, a fight broke out between the east force led by Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and east force led by Mochitoyo YAMANA, which developed into the Onin War, and he was called back by Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, 1467, a fight broke out between the west force led by Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and east force led by Mochitoyo YAMANA, which developed into the Onin War, and he was called back by Yoshimasa.</e>
<cmt>用語修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1471年に出家して政務を引退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1471, he resigned from his position and joined priesthood.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1471, he resigned from his position and joined priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1471, he resigned from his position and joined priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>1473年に死去、享年57。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1473, at the age of 57.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1473, at the age of 57.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1473, at the age of 57.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>応仁の乱の原因を作った1人とも言われ、『応仁別記』という本には「世の中は 皆歌読に 業平の 伊勢物語 せぬ人ぞなき」という落首が伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to be one of the persons responsible for the Onin War, and in the book entitled &quot;Onin Bekki,&quot; it includes a lampoon &quot;世の中は 皆歌読に 業平の 伊勢物語 せぬ人ぞなき.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「世の中は 皆歌読に 業平の 伊勢物語 せぬ人ぞなき」→「意味解釈が困難なため訳出できませんでした」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to be one of the persons responsible for the Onin War, and the book entitled &quot;Onin Bekki&quot; includes a lampoon &quot;世の中は 皆歌読に 業平の 伊勢物語 せぬ人ぞなき.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to be one of the persons responsible for the Onin War, and the book entitled &quot;Onin Bekki&quot; includes a lampoon &quot;世の中は 皆歌読に 業平の 伊勢物語 せぬ人ぞなき.&quot;</e>
<cmt>和歌の翻訳が困難</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、子の貞宗に対して『伊勢貞親教訓』を残す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadachika left &quot;Ise (修正候補なし) kokum&quot; (&quot;The teachings of Sadachika ISE&quot;) to his son, Sadamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadachika left &quot;Ise (修正候補なし) kokum&quot; (&quot;The teachings of Sadachika ISE&quot;) to his son, Sadamune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadachika left &quot;Ise Sadachika kyokun&quot; (The teachings of Sadachika ISE) to his son, Sadamune.</e>
<cmt>用語修正,punctuation</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ちなみに北条早雲（いわゆる北条早雲）は、貞親の同族備中国伊勢氏の当主で貞親と共に幕政に関与した伊勢盛定の嫡男（一説には盛定の妻は貞親の姉妹であり、貞親と盛時は伯父と甥の関係であるもいう）とされ、貞親の推挙によって足利義視に仕えたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, Moritoki ISE (a.k.a. Soun HOJO) was a family lord of the Ise clan, a clan related to Sadachika, in Bicchu Province, and was the son of Morisada ISE (one theory argues that Morisada&apos;s wife was Sadachika&apos;s sister and the relationship between Sadachika and Moritoki was that of uncle and nephew), who was involved in the shogunate government along with Sadachika and served Yoshimi ASHIKAGA on Sadachika&apos;s recommendation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, Moritoki ISE (a.k.a. Soun HOJO) was a family lord of the Ise clan, a clan related to Sadachika, in Bicchu Province, and was the son of Morisada ISE (one theory argues that Morisada&apos;s wife was Sadachika&apos;s sister and the relationship between Sadachika and Moritoki was that of uncle and nephew), who was involved in the shogunate government along with Sadachika and served Yoshimi ASHIKAGA on Sadachika&apos;s recommendation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, Moritoki ISE (a.k.a. Soun HOJO) was a family lord of the Ise clan, a clan related to Sadachika, in Bicchu Province, and was the son of Morisada ISE (one theory argues that Morisada&apos;s wife was Sadachika&apos;s sister and the relationship between Sadachika and Moritoki was that of uncle and nephew), who was involved in the shogunate government along with Sadachika and served Yoshimi ASHIKAGA on Sadachika&apos;s recommendation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>伊勢貞親教訓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise Sadachika Kyokun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise Sadachika Kyokun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise Sadachika Kyokun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>伊勢貞親教訓（いせさだちかきょうくん）は、室町時代後期に伊勢貞親が嫡男貞宗に対して著した教訓状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise Sadachika Kyokun is the teachings of Sadachika ISE left for Sadamune, at the end of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ise Sadachika Kyokun is the teachings of Sadachika ISE left for Sadamune, at the end of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ise Sadachika Kyokun is the teachings of Sadachika ISE left for Sadamune, at the end of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>全38条の本文及び執筆意図について記した覚書（末文と和歌1首）により構成されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book consists of 38 articles and a memorandum explaining the intent of the work (epilogue and one waka poem).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book consists of 38 articles and a memorandum explaining the intent of the work (epilogue and one waka poem).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book consists of 38 articles and a memorandum explaining the intent of the work (epilogue and one waka poem).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>執筆年代については諸説あるが、貞宗が元服を控えた長禄年間とする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many theories as to when the book was written, but the most dominant theory is that it was written several years before Sadamune&apos;s genpuku (a ceremony to celebrate a young man&apos;s coming of age).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many theories as to when the book was written, but the most dominant theory is that it was written several years before Sadamune&apos;s genpuku (coming of age ceremony).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many theories as to when the book was written, but the most dominant theory is that it was written several years before Sadamune&apos;s genpuku (coming of age ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>伊勢氏が代々武家故実の伝承するとともに足利将軍家の嫡男の養育にあたり、また自身も足利義政の養育に尽した経験から、武家の教育において重要視すべき点を説いて、将来貞宗に期待されるであろう役割に対する自覚を促したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It details the bukekojitsu (manners and rules for the samurai class) of Ise, and the fostering of the Ashikaga shogunate family&apos;s children, focusing on important points in the education of samurai family, that he learned fostering Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, prompting an increased consciousness of Sadamune&apos;s future role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It details the bukekojitsu (manners and rules for the samurai class) of Ise, and the fostering of the Ashikaga shogunate family&apos;s children, focusing on important points in the education of samurai family, that he learned while fostering Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, prompting increased consciousness of Sadamune&apos;s future role.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It details the bukekojitsu (manners and rules for the samurai class) of Ise, and the fostering of the Ashikaga shogunate family&apos;s children, focusing on important points in the education of samurai family, that he learned while fostering Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, prompting increased consciousness of Sadamune&apos;s future role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>貞親自身は『為愚息教訓一札』と命名しているように、彼が説いている事は伊勢氏の当主として必要であると思われた事を記した家訓であり、流布を目的に書かれたものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As suggested by the title Sadachika gave, &quot;為愚息教訓一札&quot;, the book described family precepts required for the head the family estate, and was not written with the intention making it public.</e>
<cmt>『為愚息教訓一札』→[読み方不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As suggested by the title Sadachika gave, &quot;為愚息教訓一札&quot;, the book described family precepts required for the head of the family estate, and was not written with the intention making it public.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">complete translation</e>
<cmt>『為愚息教訓一札』→[読み方不明]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかし、武家、特に大名家の後継者教育にとっては重要視されるべき点について体系的に論じられており、貞親が「“大名教育学”の祖」とされる所以である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book systematically describes important points regarding the education of successors to samurai families, particularly the feudal lord&apos;s family, thereby giving Sadachika the title, &quot;The Forefather of Daimyo Education.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book systematically describes important points regarding the education of successors to samurai families, particularly the feudal lord&apos;s family, thereby giving Sadachika the title, &quot;The Forefather of Daimyo Education.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book systematically describes important points regarding the education of successors to samurai families, particularly the feudal lord&apos;s family, thereby giving Sadachika the title, &quot;The Forefather of Daimyo Education.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>貞親は大きく分けて次の4つの点を重要視している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadachika placed importance on the following four points.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadachika placed importance on the following four points.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadachika placed importance on the following four points.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>神仏にたいする崇敬の念を怠らないこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Do not neglect reverence to God and Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Do not neglect reverence to God and Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Do not neglect reverence to the gods and Buddha.</e>
<cmt>用語修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>政務においてあるいは一族郎党を率いる棟梁として、上下・主従の礼を厳守させること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In government and as a leader of a clan, have the people show respect to their superiors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In government and as a leader of a clan, have the people show respect to their superiors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In government and as a leader of a clan, have the people show respect to their superiors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>同時に従者としての礼を守り、忠義に尽くす者に対しては恩賞を与えるなどの配慮を欠かさないこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Show courtesy to followers and reward those who are loyal and faithful to the lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Show courtesy to followers and reward those who are loyal and faithful to the lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Show courtesy as followers and reward those who are loyal and faithful to the lord.</e>
<cmt>用語修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>武家として身に付けるべき教養として真っ先に「弓馬」を挙げて、日々怠ることがないことを説き、続いて学問の必要性を説く（ただし、「弓馬」ほどは強調しない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai should acquire skill in archery and horsemanship, which should be practiced daily; then comes the importance of academic training (not to be insisted upon as much as archery and horsemanship).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai should acquire skill in archery and horsemanship, which should be practiced daily; then comes the importance of academic training (not to be insisted upon as much as archery and horsemanship).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai should acquire skill in archery and horsemanship, which should be practiced daily; then comes the importance of academic training (not to be insisted upon as much as archery and horsemanship).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>芸能は（良くも悪くも）人目につかない程度で十分としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Art (good or bad) is sufficient at an inconspicuous level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Art (good or bad) is sufficient at an inconspicuous level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Art (good or bad) is sufficient at an inconspicuous level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これに対して犬追物は「越度（＝度を越した）なき」とし、猿楽は「よきほどに可斗」として深入りを戒めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, one should not be too taken up with inuoumono (dog-hunting, a skill involving archery) and sarugaku (the performing arts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, one should not be too taken up with inuoumono (dog-hunting, a skill involving archery) and sarugaku (the performing arts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, one should not be too taken up with inuoumono (dog-hunting, a skill involving archery) and sarugaku (the performing arts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>最後に平生の礼儀を守ることの重要性を説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lastly, Sadachika explains the importance of showing courtesy on a daily basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lastly, Sadachika explains the importance of showing courtesy on a daily basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lastly, Sadachika explains the importance of showing courtesy on a daily basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>特に伊勢氏は政所執事・武家故実宗家であり、日常的な部分より礼儀作法を重んじることは一族郎党に対する棟梁の権威を守り、幕府内部においての地位を保つために重要であることとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Ise clan, in particular, was mandokoro shitsuji and the family set the example for bukekojitsu (manners and rules for the samurai class), therefore showing respect and courtesy was important in maintaining authority as a leader and Ise&apos;s position in the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ise clan, in particular, was mandokoro shitsuji and the family set the example for bukekojitsu (manners and rules for the samurai class); therefore, showing respect and courtesy was important in maintaining authority as a leader and Ise&apos;s position in the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ise clan, in particular, was mandokoro shitsuji and the family set the example for bukekojitsu (manners and rules for the samurai class); therefore, showing respect and courtesy was important in maintaining authority as a leader and Ise&apos;s position in the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>特に来客に対して不愉快にさせないことは、政治的な味方を1人でも多く得る（逆に考えれば敵対者を生み出さない）上でも必要であるとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It states that showing hospitality to visitors will lead to gaining allies (in other words, not creating enemies).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It states that showing hospitality to visitors will lead to gaining allies (in other words, not creating enemies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It states that showing hospitality to visitors will lead to gaining allies (in other words, not creating enemies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>以上の「神仏への崇敬」「公私における主従関係の徹底」「武芸を重視した教養の習得」「日常からの礼儀作法の厳守」という4点は、伊勢氏に限らず武家一般の基本的なあり方について論じている部分が多く、鎌倉幕府の北条重時による『北条重時家訓』と並んで後世に影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above four points: &quot;Reverence to God and Buddha,&quot; &quot;Relationship between leaders and followers in private and public settings,&quot; &quot;Education focusing on the military and cultural arts,&quot; and &quot;Courtesy on a daily basis&quot; are fundamental in education of samurai families in general, not only the Ise clan, and the book greatly influenced later generations along with &quot;Hojo Shigetoki Kakun&quot; (&quot;A family precept by Shigetoki HOJO&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above four points: &quot;Reverence to God and Buddha,&quot; &quot;Relationship between leaders and followers in private and public settings,&quot; &quot;Education focusing on the military and cultural arts,&quot; and &quot;Courtesy on a daily basis&quot; are fundamental in the education of samurai families in general, not only the Ise clan, and the book greatly influenced later generations, along with &quot;Hojo Shigetoki Kakun&quot; (&quot;A family precept by Shigetoki HOJO&quot;).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above four points: &quot;Reverence to God and Buddha,&quot; &quot;Relationship between leaders and followers in private and public settings,&quot; &quot;Education focusing on the military and cultural arts,&quot; and &quot;Courtesy on a daily basis&quot; are fundamental in the education of samurai families in general, not only the Ise clan, and the book greatly influenced later generations, along with &quot;Hojo Shigetoki Kakun&quot; (&quot;A family precept by Shigetoki HOJO&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Carkuni(id:79281), Novo(id:87875), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Shikai shaw(id:14306), Iwaro(id:60082), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 伏儀(id:142093), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>