<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山中幸盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimori YAMANAKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukimori YAMANAKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukimori YAMANAKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山中 幸盛（やまなか ゆきもり）は、戦国時代 (日本)の山陰地方の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimori YAMANAKA was busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period who resided in the San-in district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukimori YAMANAKA was a busho (a military commander) during the Sengoku Period, who resided in the San-in region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukimori YAMANAKA was a busho (a military commander) during the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States), who resided in the San-in region.</e>
<cmt>「戦国時代」→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>出雲国能義郡（現島根県安来市広瀬町）に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Nogi-gun in Izumo Province (Hirose-cho, Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture, as it is known today).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Nogi-gun in Izumo Province (Hirose-cho, Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture, as it is known today).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Nogi-gun in Izumo Province (Hirose-cho, Yasugi City, Shimane Prefecture, as it is known today).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>戦国大名尼子氏の家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a retainer of the Amago clan, which was a Sengoku daimyo clan (&quot;Sengoku daimyo&quot; refers to a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a retainer of the Amago family, which was a Sengoku daimyo (feudal lord) family.</e>
<cmt>家 is family, not clan</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a retainer of the Amago clan, which was a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>the Amago clanとし、「戦国大名」を統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original surname was Minamoto.</e>
<cmt>「本姓は源氏」：「本姓は源」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original surname was Minamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original surname was Minamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家系は宇多源氏の流れを汲む佐々木氏（京極氏）の支流で、尼子氏の一門である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family was a branch of the Sasaki clan (also known as the Kyogoku clan) descended from the Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan) and belonged to the Amago clan.</e>
<cmt>「佐々木氏（京極氏）の支流で、尼子氏の一門である」：史実に照らすと、下記の訳の方がベターと思われます。His family belonged to the Amago clan, which was a branch of the Sasaki clan (also known as the Kyogoku clan) descended from the Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan).</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family was a branch of the Sasaki clan (also known as the Kyogoku clan) which was descended from the Uda-Genji lineage (descendents of Emperor Uda who had been given the surname Minamoto) and belonged to the Amago clan.</e>
<cmt>if 氏 is clan, then the distinction here is not yet clear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family was a branch of the Sasaki clan (also known as the Kyogoku clan) which was descended from the Uda-Genji lineage (descendents of Emperor Uda who had been given the surname Minamoto) and belonged to the Amago clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>実名は幸盛（ゆきもり）、通称鹿介である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With his real name being Yukimori, he was commonly known as Shikanosuke.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though his real name was Yukimori, he usually went by the name Shikanosuke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though his real name was Yukimori, he usually went by the name Shikanosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>講談の類で鹿之助とされたため一般には山中鹿之介（しかのすけ）なる誤った表記で知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above alias was meant to be expressed as &quot;鹿介&quot;, but was expressed as &quot;鹿之助&quot; in stories and the like, which resulted in him being known as Shikanosuke YAMANAKA wrongly expressed as &quot;山中鹿之介&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Shikanosuke was meant to be written with the two characters &quot;鹿介&quot;, but was written by the three characters &quot;鹿之助&quot; in historical tales and the like, which resulted in his becoming known by the written name &quot;山中鹿之介&quot;, using the wrong characters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Shikanosuke was meant to be written with the two characters &quot;鹿介,&quot; but was written by the three characters &quot;鹿之助&quot; in historical tales and the like, which resulted in his becoming known by the written name &quot;山中鹿之介,&quot; using the wrong characters.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを半角に修正、カンマの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幼名は甚次郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Jinjiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Jinjiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Jinjiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「山陰の麒麟児」の異名を取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He earned him the nickname of &apos;Kirinji (an infant prodigy) of San-in&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He earned the nickname &apos;Kirinji (child prodigy) of San-in&apos;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He earned the nickname &apos;Kirinji (child prodigy) of San-in.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを半角に修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lifelong History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lifelong History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>文中の（）の年はユリウス暦、月日は西暦部分を除いて全て和暦、宣明暦の長暦による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the months and dates referred to below (excluding years of grace subsequent thereto) follow the Japanese calendar (in concrete terms, choreki (a document that retroactively specifies ancient dates/months/years according to a certain calendar) based on the Senmyo Calendar (a variation of the lunar calendar that was created in ancient China)) while the years referred to below follow the Julian calendar.</e>
<cmt>「（）の」：翻訳指示により、和暦と西暦の併記はしないので、この部分は訳出不要と判断し、訳出しておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereas the years referred to below follow the Julian calendar, all the months and dates (except when following a year from the Julian calendar) follow the Japanese calendar (more specifically, the choreki (a document that retroactively specifies ancient dates/months/years according to a certain calendar) based on the Senmyo Calendar (a variation of the lunar calendar that was created in ancient China)).</e>
<cmt>somewhat unclear. Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereas the years referred to below follow the Julian calendar, all the months and dates (except when following a year from the Julian calendar) follow the Japanese calendar (more specifically, the choreki (a document that retroactively specifies ancient dates/months/years according to a certain calendar) based on the Senmyo Calendar (a variation of the lunar calendar that was created in ancient China)).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>山中家は尼子氏の庶流にあたり、山中幸久を初代とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamanaka family was a branch of the Amago clan that was founded by Yukihisa YAMANAKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamanaka family was a branch of the Amago clan that was founded by Yukihisa YAMANAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamanaka family was a branch of the Amago clan that was founded by Yukihisa YAMANAKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>幼少から尼子氏に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimori served the Amago clan from his tender years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukimori was in the service of the Amago clan from his youth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukimori was in the service of the Amago clan from his youth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>講談などによると、尼子義久が毛利元就に攻められ、次第に勢力を奪われていく中で、尼子十勇士の一人として活躍したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to stories and the like, he rendered considerable service as one of the ten brave warriors of the Amago clan under circumstances where Yoshihisa AMAGO was attacked by Motonari MORI and gradually lost his power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to historical tales and the like, he served as one of the ten brave warriors of the Amago clan during the strife occurring when Yoshihisa AMAGO was beseiged by Motonari MORI, gradually losing his power.</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to historical tales and the like, he served as one of the Ten Brave Warriors of the Amago Clan during the strife occurring when Yoshihisa AMAGO was beseiged by Motonari MORI, gradually losing his power.</e>
<cmt>ten brave warriors of the Amago clan→Ten Brave Warriors of the Amago Clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>いずれにせよ活動が明らかに知られるのは永禄9年（1566年）に尼子義久が毛利氏に降り、戦国大名尼子氏が滅びて以降のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether the foregoing is true or not, only those, among Yukimori&apos;s activities, which took place after the downfall of the Sengoku daimyo Amago clan resulting from Yoshihisa AMAGO&apos;s surrender to the Mori clan in 1566 have been made clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regardless of whether or not the foregoing is true, the only activities of Yukimori&apos;s that have been made clear to posterity are those which took place after the downfall of the Sengoku daimyo Amago clan as the result of that capitulation of Yoshihisa AMAGO to the Mori clan in 1566.</e>
<cmt>the japanese phrase 明らかに知られるのは is wanting in clarity… should it say something like that can be verified from the historical record</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regardless of whether or not the foregoing is true, the only activities of Yukimori&apos;s that have been made clear to posterity are those which took place after the downfall of the daimyo in the Sengoku period, Amago clan as the result of that capitulation of Yoshihisa AMAGO to the Mori clan in 1566.</e>
<cmt>Yukimori’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正、「戦国大名」を統一リストの表記にするため、the Sengoku daimyo Amago clan→the daimyo in the Sengoku period, Amago clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>尼子氏が衰亡していく中、御家再興のため、鹿介が「願わくば、我に七難八苦を与えたまえ」と三日月に祈った逸話は講談などによりよく知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An anecdote relating that Shikanosuke prayed to the moon for the restoration of the Amago clan saying &quot;I would rather sustain all kinds of troubles than see the clan of my lord going to ruin&quot; has been spread through stories and the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a well known anecdote passed down through tales and the like recounting that when the Amago clan was on the decline, Shikanosuke prayed to the moon for the restoration of their former status, saying, &quot;I would rather sustain all kinds of troubles myself than see the clan of my lord fall into ruin&quot;.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;ve rendered the japanese phrase 御家再興 in terms of the status of the clan, as the context is unclear, maybe it should be to restore them &quot;to power&quot;…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a well known anecdote passed down through tales and the like recounting that when the Amago clan was on the decline, Shikanosuke prayed to the moon for the restoration of their former status, saying, &apos;I would rather sustain all kinds of troubles myself than see the clan of my lord fall into ruin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをシングル・半角に修正、ピリオドの位置を移動コメントに関して左記のように修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>山中鹿介の尼子再興運動は、概ね3回に分けて見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The campaign for the restoration of the Amago clan conducted by Shikanosuke YAMANAKA can be roughly divided into three stages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The campaign to restore the status of the Amago clan conducted by Shikanosuke YAMANAKA can be roughly divided into three stages.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The campaign to restore the status of the Amago clan conducted by Shikanosuke YAMANAKA can be roughly divided into three stages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>第一回尼子再興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First Stage of the Restoration of the Amago Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First Stage of the Restoration of the Amago Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First Stage of the Restoration of the Amago Clan</e>
<cmt>No.23に関連して修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>永禄11年（1568年・24歳） - 元亀2年（1571年8月21日・27歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duration: from 1568 until August 21, 1571 (at the ages of 24 through 27 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Duration: from 1568 until August 21, 1571 (from the age of 24 through 27 years old)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Duration: from 1568 until August 21, 1571 (from the age of 24 through 27 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）、鹿介は尼子氏を再興するために京都で僧籍にあった尼子国久の孫尼子勝久を還俗させて擁立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1568, he caused Katsuhisa AMAGO, Kunihisa AMAGO&apos;s grandson holding the priesthood in Kyoto at that time, to quit the priesthood and helped him to the headship of the Amago clan with the aim of the restoration of the Amago clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1568, he had Katsuhisa AMAGO, a grandson of Kunihisa AMAGO&apos;s who was a Buddhist priest in Kyoto, leave the priesthood so that Shikanosuke could install him as the head of the Amago clan as part of his efforts to restore the Amago clan to its former status.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1568, he had Katsuhisa AMAGO, a grandson of Kunihisa AMAGO&apos;s who was a Buddhist priest in Kyoto, leave the priesthood so that Shikanosuke could install him as the head of the Amago clan as part of his efforts to restore the Amago clan to its former status.</e>
<cmt>AMAGO’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>立原久綱・横道正光・牛尾弾正忠・三刀屋蔵人・遠藤甚九郎ら尼子遺臣団は、山名豊祐の家老垣屋播磨守を頼り、但馬国を経由し奈佐日本之介の手を借りて隠岐に依る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Amago remnant corps (a group of retainers set adrift by the downfall of the Amago clan), including Hisatsuna TACHIHARA, Masamitsu YOKOJI, Ushio Danjo-no-jo (the foregoing &quot;danjo-no-jo&quot; derives from a post named &quot;jo&quot; (referring to a judge) in the &quot;Danjo&quot; (referring to the Ministry of Justice)), Kurodo MITOYA(三刀屋蔵人), and Jinkuro ENDO, relied on KAKIYA Harima-no-kami (the foregoing &quot;Harima-no-kami&quot; refers to the Lord of Harima), who was the chief retainer of Toyosuke YAMANA, to pass through Tajima Province, and then took to a fastness in Oki with the aid of Yamatonosuke NASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amago remnant corps (a group of retainers set adrift by the downfall of the Amago clan), including Hisatsuna TACHIHARA, Masamitsu YOKOJI, Ushio Danjo-no-jo (&quot;danjo-no-jo&quot; derives from a judicial post called, &quot;jo&quot;, the equivalent of a judge, in the &quot;Danjo&quot;, the Ministry of Justice), Kurodo MITOYA(三刀屋蔵人), and Jinkuro ENDO, relied on KAKIYA Harima-no-kami (the foregoing &quot;Harima-no-kami&quot; refers to the Lord of Harima), who was the chief retainer of Toyosuke YAMANA, to make their passage through Tajima Province, and then took refuge in Oki with the aid of Yamatonosuke NASA.</e>
<cmt>grammar, capitalization of &quot;remnant corps</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amago Remnant Corps (a group of retainers set adrift by the downfall of the Amago clan), including Hisatsuna TACHIHARA, Masamitsu YOKOJI, USHIO Danjo no jo (&quot;danjo no jo&quot; derives from a judicial post called, &quot;jo,&quot; the equivalent of a judge, in the &quot;Danjo,&quot; the Ministry of Justice), Kurodo MITOYA (三刀屋蔵人), and Jinkuro ENDO, relied on KAKIYA Harima no kami (the foregoing &quot;Harima no kami&quot; refers to the Governor of Harima Province), who was the chief retainer of Toyosuke YAMANA, to make their passage through Tajima Province, and then took refuge in Oki with the aid of Yamatonosuke NASA.</e>
<cmt>Amago remnant corps→Amago Remnant Corpsとし、クォーテーションを半角に修正、カンマの位置を移動、スペース追加、Ushio Danjo-no-jo→USHIO Danjo no joとし、Harima-no-kamiのハイフン消去、Lord of Harima→Governor of Harima Provinceに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>隠岐の豪族・隠岐為清の協力を得て、永禄12年（1569年）には海浜の出雲忠山を占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1569, the Amago remnant corps occupied Izumo-Chuyama located on the seaside with the cooperation of Tamekiyo OKI, the powerful family in Oki.</e>
<cmt>「隠岐の豪族・隠岐為清」：原文の情報が不足しているため、訳文が不自然です。例えば、&quot;Tamekiyo OKI, the head of the powerful family in Oki&quot;のように、&quot;the powerful family&quot;の前に何らかの語句を追記する必要があると思います。「出雲忠山」：地名として&quot;Izumo-Chuyama&quot;と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1569, the Amago remnant corps occupied Izumo-Chuyama, located on the coast (Sea of Japan), with the cooperation of Tamekiyo OKI, a powerful family in Oki.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1569, the Amago Remnant Corps occupied Chuyama, Izumo Province, located on the coast (Sea of Japan), with the cooperation of Tamekiyo OKI, a powerful family in Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corpsとし、Izumo-Chuyama→Chuyama, Izumo Province、およびOki→Oki Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その後、出雲の尼子遺臣の勢力を吸収し、新山城を攻略してここに本営を設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the Amago remnant corps absorbed the power of the Amago remnants residing in Izumo, and captured Niyama Castle to place its headquarters therein.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amago remnant corps then absorbed the former Amago retainers who were then residing in Izumo, and captured Niyama Castle to use as its headquarters.</e>
<cmt>grammar, time frames, status and naming of Amago remnant corps…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amago Remnant Corps then absorbed the former Amago retainers who were then residing in Izumo, and captured Niyama-jo Castle to use as its headquarters.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corps、Niyama-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>毛利氏の拠点となっていた月山富田城を除き、出雲一国をほぼ手中に収めんとするまでに勢力を伸張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Amago remnant corps extended its power, insomuch that it was about to gain possession of the whole Izumo Province, other than Gassan-Toda Castle, which served as the foothold of the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amago remnant corps extended its power to the extent that it was on the verge of gaining possession of the entirety of Izumo Province, with the exception of Gassan-Toda Castle, which was the base of the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amago Remnant Corps extended its power to the extent that it was on the verge of gaining possession of the entirety of Izumo Province, with the exception of Gassan Toda-jo Castle, which was the base of the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corps、Gassan Toda-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、配下の略奪行為が因幡でも見られる（「因幡民談記」より）など統制維持が乱れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, its followers committed depredations in Inaba and other places (according to &quot;Inaba Mindanki&quot; (a geographical description of Inaba)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, its followers committed depredations, plundering Inaba and other places (according to &quot;Inaba Mindanki&quot; (a geographical description of Inaba)), which, combined with other factors, rendered the Amago remnant corps unable to maintain its control over the area.</e>
<cmt>have rewritten this sentence and the following sentence…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, its followers committed depredations, plundering Inaba and other places (according to &apos;Inaba Mindanki&apos; (a geographical description of Inaba)), which, combined with other factors, rendered the Amago Remnant Corps unable to maintain its control over the area.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをシングル・半角に修正、Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。原文を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後は隠岐為清の離反を招き、布部山の戦いに敗北すると衰勢著しく、元亀2年（1571年）8月には最後の拠点であった新山城が落城する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In combination with other factors, this hindered the Amago remnant corps from maintaining its control; thereafter, the Amago remnant corps incurred Tamekiyo OKI&apos;s estrangement as well as was defeated in the Battle of Fubeyama, which caused the remarkable decline in its power, and in turn resulted in the fall of Niyama Castle, that is, its last foothold, in August 1571.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Tamekiyo OKI defected from the Amago remnant corps, and they suffered defeat in the Battle of Fubeyama, which resulted in a remarkable decline in their power, bringing about the fall of Niyama Castle, their last foothold, in August 1571.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Tamekiyo OKI defected from the Amago Remnant Corps, and they suffered defeat in the Battle of Fubeyama, which resulted in a remarkable decline in their power, bringing about the fall of Niyama-jo Castle, their last foothold, in August 1571.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corps、Niyama-jo Castleとしました。訳文に応じ原文を前行に一部移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この戦いで、鹿介は毛利元就の次男吉川元春に捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this battle, Shikanosuke was captured by Motoharu KIKKAWA, the second son of Motonari MORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this battle, Shikanosuke was captured by Motoharu KIKKAWA, the second son of Motonari MORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this battle, Shikanosuke was captured by Motoharu KIKKAWA, the second son of Motonari MORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ところがこの時、腹痛を装って何度も厠に入り、油断した監視の目を逃れるために厠から糞にまみれながらも脱走したといい、勝久とともに再び京都に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said, however, that Shikanosuke, kept in custody, went to the toilet many times feigning to have a stomachache, and escaped from the toilet with his body covered in feces to elude the vigilance of the guard who got caught off guard; consequently, he fled to Kyoto together with Katsuhisa.</e>
<cmt>「油断した監視の目を逃れるために…..脱走した」：原文の語句に従って、これが「目的」であるように訳出しましたが、原文、訳文共に不自然に感じられます。原文を「油断した監視の目を逃れて…..脱走した」として、下記のように訳出するのが自然だと思います。escaped from the toilet with his body covered in feces eluding the vigilance of the guard who got caught off guard</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said, however, that while in custody, Shikanosuke went to the toilet many times, feigning a stomachache, and escaped through the toilet with his body covered in excrement, eluding the less than vigilant guard, and fleeing to Kyoto together with Katsuhisa.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m assuming that the toilet was a hole leading to a sewer ot the like through which he escaped, but that needs to be clarified in the text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said, however, that while in custody, Shikanosuke went to the toilet many times, feigning a stomachache, and escaped through the toilet with his body covered in excrement, eluding the less than vigilant guard, and fleeing to Kyoto together with Katsuhisa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>第二回尼子再興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second Stage of the Restoration of the Amago Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second Stage of the Restoration of the Amago Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second Stage of the Restoration of the Amago Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>元亀3年（1572年8月・28歳） - 天正4年（1576年5月4日・32歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duration: from August 1572 until May 4, 1576 (at the ages of 28 through 32 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Duration: from August 1572 until May 4, 1576 (from the age of 28 through 32 years old)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Duration: from August 1572 until May 4, 1576 (from the age of 28 through 32 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>京へ戻った鹿介らは、織田信長に謁し、中国攻めの先方となることを誓ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, after returning to Kyoto, Shikanosuke and others had an audience with Nobunaga ODA and swore to lead the vanguard of the attack on the Chugoku district.</e>
<cmt>「先方」：文脈より、「先鋒」の誤植と判断し、「先鋒」としてました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, upon returning to Kyoto, Shikanosuke and company had an audience with Nobunaga ODA, during which they swore an oath to lead the charge in the attack on the Chugoku region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, upon returning to Kyoto, Shikanosuke and company had an audience with Nobunaga ODA, during which they swore an oath to lead the charge in the attack on the Chugoku region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>尼子遺臣団は尼子氏再興の志を秘めて山名氏の軍勢に加わり、山名氏に謀叛して鳥取城に篭った武田高信と闘い、因幡国を転戦、甑山城での戦いにて決定的な勝利を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Amago remnant corps participated in the forces of the Yamana clan with the intention of restoring the Amago clan in their bosoms, fought against Takanobu TAKEDA, who rebelled against the Yamana clan and holed up in Tottori Castle, then fought on successive fronts in Inaba Province, and won a decisive victory in the battle at Koshikiyama Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amago remnant corps joined forces with the Yamana clan, intent on restoring the Amago clan to their former status, and fought against Takanobu TAKEDA, who had rebelled against the Yamana clan and was holed up in Tottori Castle; after that, they fought on successive fronts in Inaba Province, wining a decisive victory in the battle at Koshikiyama Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amago Remnant Corps joined forces with the Yamana clan, intent on restoring the Amago clan to their former status, and fought against Takanobu TAKEDA, who had rebelled against the Yamana clan and was holed up in Tottori-jo Castle; after that, they fought on successive fronts in Inaba Province, wining a decisive victory in the battle at Koshikiyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corps、Tottori-jo Castle、およびKoshikiyama-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>もっとも、その後に武田氏に味方した鳥取城を毛利氏に奪われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, the Amago remnant corps was deprived of Tottori Castle by the Mori clan, which took the side of the Takeda clan thereafter.</e>
<cmt>「その後に武田氏に味方した鳥取城を毛利氏に奪われた」を「その後に武田氏に味方した毛利氏に鳥取城を奪われた」の誤植と想定し、これに対応する訳を記載しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, the Amago remnant corps was deprived of Tottori Castle by the Mori clan, who had subsequently sided with the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, the Amago Remnant Corps was deprived of Tottori-jo Castle by the Mori clan, who had subsequently sided with the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corps、Tottori-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>この頃の山陰は勢力地図が頻繁に変わる時代であったが、その一つの要因は、山名氏が毛利と織田の二大勢力に翻弄されていたことにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, the distribution of power was changed frequently partly because the Yamana clan was trifled with the two major forces, namely, Mori and Oda forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this peroid, the distribution of power shifted frequently, in part due to the fact that the Yamana clan was at the mercy of the two major powers of the Mori clan and the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this peroid, the distribution of power shifted frequently, in part due to the fact that the Yamana clan was at the mercy of the two major powers of the Mori clan and the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>織田氏と気脈を通じていた尼子遺臣団は、当時毛利寄りであった山名氏を離反する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having secret contact with the Oda clan, the Amago remnant corps estranged itself from the Yamana clan, which was on Mori&apos;s side at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through secret communications with the Oda clan, the Amago remnant corps managed to sever its ties with the Yamana clan, which had been siding with the Mori at the time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through secret communications with the Oda clan, the Amago Remnant Corps managed to sever its ties with the Yamana clan, which had been siding with the Mori at the time.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>天正2年（1574年）頃には因幡国の諸城を攻略し、織田方の浦上宗景の助力もあって若桜鬼ヶ城・市場城を確保。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1574, the Amago remnant corps captured castles in Inaba Province, and secured Wakasa-Onigajo Castle and Ichiba Castle with the aid of Munekage URAGMI, who was on Oda&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1574, the Amago remnant corps captured castles in Inaba Province, and secured Wakasa-Onigajo Castle and Ichiba Castle with the aid of Munekage URAGMI, who was on Oda&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1574, the Amago Remnant Corps captured castles in Inaba Province, and secured Wakasa Oniga-jo Castle and Ichiba-jo Castle with the aid of Munekage URAGMI, who was on Oda&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corps、Wakasa Oniga-jo Castle、および CastleIchiba-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>一時的に尼子氏を再興することに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the Amago remnant corps temporarily succeeded in the restoration of the Amago clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amago remnant corps had thereby temporarily succeeded in restoring the Amago clan to its former status.</e>
<cmt>unclear about the status of this &quot;restoration&quot;…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amago Remnant Corps had thereby temporarily succeeded in restoring the Amago clan to its former status.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし、天正3年（1575年）9月には毛利方が私都城を攻略し、古くからの尼子遺臣であった横道兄弟・森脇久仍・牛尾大炊助らが毛利氏に降るという事態が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1575, however, forces that were on Mori&apos;s side captured Kisaichi Castle, which resulted in the Yokoji brothers, Hisayori MORIWAKI, Oinosuke USHIO, and other Amago remnants who had been serving the Amago clan since a long time ago surrendering to the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>「古くからの尼子遺臣」：「古くから尼子氏につかえていた遺臣」と解釈して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1575, however, Mori forces captured Kisaichi Castle, which resulted in the surender of the Yokoji brothers, Hisayori MORIWAKI, Oinosuke USHIO, and other members of the Amago remnant corps who had long been in the service of the Amago clan, to the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1575, however, Mori forces captured Kisaichi-jo Castle, which resulted in the surender of the Yokoji brothers, Hisayori MORIWAKI, Oinosuke USHIO, and other members of the Amago Remnant Corps who had long been in the service of the Amago clan, to the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>Kisaichi-jo Castle、Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、天正4年（1576年）には情勢の変化からか、織田信長は鹿介を庇護しない旨を吉川元春に伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Nobunaga ODA told Motoharu KIKKAWA in 1576 that he would not shelter Shikanosuke, probably because of changes in the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Nobunaga ODA told Motoharu KIKKAWA in 1576 that he would not shelter Shikanosuke, probably because of the changed circumstances.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Nobunaga ODA told Motoharu KIKKAWA in 1576 that he would not shelter Shikanosuke, probably because of the changed circumstances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>重臣と庇護者を同時に失った尼子遺臣団は、居城の若桜鬼ヶ城を支えることができずに丹波方面へ落ち延びることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the Amago remnant corps lost ex-key retainers of the Amago clan and a patron simultaneously, which resulted in the corps becoming unable to hold Wakasa-Onigajo Castle against an enemy force and fleeing toward Tanba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amago remnant corps was thereby simultaneously deprived of prominent retainers of the Amago clan and a patron, which made it impossible for the corps to hold Wakasa-Onigajo Castle, and resulted in the remaining members fleeing toward Tanba.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amago Remnant Corps was thereby simultaneously deprived of prominent retainers of the Amago clan and a patron, which made it impossible for the corps to hold Wakasa Oniga-jo Castle, and resulted in the remaining members fleeing toward Tanba.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corps、Wakasa Oniga-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>織田氏の処置は、本願寺などの諸勢力との闘いが続く中で、毛利氏との軋轢を一時的に軽減するための政治的な目的があったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the Oda clan took the foregoing action for the political purpose of temporarily alleviating friction with the Mori clan under circumstances where conflicts against various forces, such as Honganji, remained underway.</e>
<cmt>「本願寺」：情報の追加を避けるため、単に&quot;Honganji&quot;と訳出しましたが、適宜&quot;the Honganji family&quot;または&quot;the Honganji sect&quot;などとされてはどうでしょうか。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the Oda clan took the foregoing actions with the political objective of temporarily alleviating friction with the Mori clan, under circumstances in which they were engaged in ongoing conflicts on several fronts, such as that of Honganji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the Oda clan took the foregoing actions with the political objective of temporarily alleviating friction with the Mori clan, under circumstances in which they were engaged in ongoing conflicts on several fronts, such as that of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Honganji→Hongan-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この後、尼子遺臣団は再び中国方面軍に編入されることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the Amago remnant corps was incorporated again into the armed forces destined for the Chugoku district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amago remnant corps then rejoined armed forces heading toward the Chugoku district.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amago Remnant Corps then rejoined armed forces heading toward the Chugoku district.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>第三回尼子再興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Third Stage of the Restoration of the Amago Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Third Stage of the Restoration of the Amago Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Third Stage of the Restoration of the Amago Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>天正5年（1577年9月27日・33歳） - 天正6年（1578年・34歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duration: from September 27, 1577 until 1578 (at the ages of 33 through 34 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Duration: from September 27, 1577 until 1578 (from the age of 33 through 34 years old)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Duration: from September 27, 1577 until 1578 (from the age of 33 through 34 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>天正5年（1577年）、信長の命により豊臣秀吉の中国遠征が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1577, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s expedition to the Chugoku district was started pursuant to Nobunaga&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1577, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI embarked on an expedition to the Chugoku region, under orders from Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1577, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI embarked on an expedition to the Chugoku region, under orders from Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その先鋒として播磨国に送り込まれ、上月城に拠って尼子氏の再興を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon thereof, the Amago remnant corps was dispatched into Harima Province as the vanguard, and aimed at the restoration of the Amago clan while holding Kozuki Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Amago remnant corps was thereupon dispatched to Harima Province to spearhead the attack, aiming to hold Kozuki Castleand restore the Amago clan to their former status.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Amago Remnant Corps was thereupon dispatched to Harima Province to spearhead the attack, aiming to hold Kozuki-jo Castle and restore the Amago clan to their former status.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corps、Kozuki-jo Castleとし、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし、翌天正6年（1578年）に毛利軍に攻められた際、織田軍が北の上杉謙信や石山本願寺の攻勢に備えるため播磨から軍を引いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the attack on Kozuki Castle by the Mori force, however, the Oda force withdrew from Harima to prepare for offensives of Kenshin UESUGI, who resided in the northern section of Japan, as well as the Ishiyama Honganji force, which resulted in Kozuki Castle being isolated and subjected to siege by the Mori force fired up with enthusiasm for &apos;beating the Amagos&apos;; consequently, the head and retainers of the Amago clan became unable to hold the castle and surrendered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kozuki Castle was attacked by the Mori forces, however, the Oda forces withdrew from Harima to make preparations to launch offensives against the Kenshin UESUGI, who resided in the north, and against the Ishiyama Honganji force. This caused Kozuki Castle to become isolated, and put under siege by the Mori force, which was eager to &apos;Rout the Amago&apos;; as a result, the leader and retainers of the Amago clan were unable to hold the castle, and surrendered.</e>
<cmt>Split into two sentences. I&apos;ve assumed that &quot;Kenshin UESUGI&quot; is the name of a branch family, not an individual, and have therefore used the definite article.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kozuki-jo Castle was attacked by the Mori forces, however, the Oda forces withdrew from Harima to make preparations to launch offensives against the Kenshin UESUGI, who resided in the north, and against the Ishiyama Hongan-ji force.</e>
<cmt>Kozuki-jo Castleとし、Ishiyama Honganji→Ishiyama Hongan-ji、クォーテーションをシングル・半角に修正一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>そのため、上月城は孤立し、「打倒尼子」の意気に燃える毛利軍の包囲攻撃を喰らい、尼子主従は城を支えきれず降伏した。（上月城の戦い）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This caused Kozuki-jo Castle to become isolated, and put under siege by the Mori force, which was eager to &apos;Rout the Amago&apos;; as a result, the leader and retainers of the Amago clan were unable to hold the castle, and surrendered (The Battle of Kozuki Castle).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>（上月城の戦い）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The Battle of Kozuki Castle)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Battle of Kozuki Castle)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Battle of Kozuki Castle)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>この時、主君の尼子勝久は自害したが、鹿介は自害せず、毛利氏に降った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that point, Katsuhisa AMAGO, the lord, killed himself whereas Shikanosuke did not so but submitted to the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that point, Katsuhisa AMAGO, the head of the Amago clan, committed suicide, whereas Shikanosuke did not commit suicide, but submitted to the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that point, Katsuhisa AMAGO, the head of the Amago clan, committed suicide, whereas Shikanosuke did not commit suicide, but submitted to the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし毛利輝元の下へ護送される途上の備中国合の渡（岡山県高梁市）の阿井の渡しにて謀殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shikanosuke was murdered at Ai-no-watashi (阿井の渡し) ferry located at Ainowatashi (合の渡) in Bicchu Province (Takahashi City in Okayama Prefecture as it is known today) while being taken to Terumoto MORI&apos;s whereabouts under guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, Shikanosuke was murdered at the ferry of Ai (阿井の渡し), located at Ainowatashi (合の渡) in Bicchu Province (Takahashi City in Okayama Prefecture, as it is known today), while being taken to the whereabouts of Terumoto MORI under guard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, Shikanosuke was murdered at the ferry of Ai (阿井の渡し), located at Ainowatashi (合の渡) in Bitchu Province (Takahashi City in Okayama Prefecture, as it is known today), while being taken to the whereabouts of Terumoto MORI under guard.</e>
<cmt>Bicchu→Bitchuに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>通説によれば、鹿介は尚も生き延びて、尼子氏を必ずや再興するという執念を胸中に抱いていたため、これを生かしておくと危険と見た吉川元春が先手を打ち、鹿介は殺害されたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a common view, Shikanosuke was murdered for the following reason: Motoharu KIKKAWA deemed it risky to let Shikanosuke live because Shikanosuke had an obsession with his survival and the restoration of the Amago clan without fail, and forestalled Shikanosuke by murdering him.</e>
<cmt>「執念を胸中に抱いていた」：「胸中に」を逐語的に訳出しなくても、&quot;had an obsession&quot;で十分に表現できると判断し、「胸中に」に対応する訳を省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The commonly held view is that Shikanosuke was murdered by Motoharu KIKKAWA as a preemptive measure because he deemed it too risky to let him live, believing that Shikanosuke was determined to survive and committed to again attempting to restore the Amago clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The commonly held view is that Shikanosuke was murdered by Motoharu KIKKAWA as a preemptive measure because he deemed it too risky to let him live, believing that Shikanosuke was determined to survive and committed to again attempting to restore the Amago clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>鹿介の死を以って尼子氏再興活動は完全に絶たれることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the death of Shikanosuke, activities toward the restoration of the Amago clan were completely discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Shikanosuke, efforts toward restoring the Amago clan to their former status ceased completely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Shikanosuke, efforts toward restoring the Amago clan to their former status ceased completely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>殺害現場である現在の高梁市の高梁川と成羽川との合流点付近の国道313号沿いに墓所はあるが、胴体は観泉寺前住珊牛和尚によって埋葬された胴塚が現在も観泉寺墓地に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tomb of Shikanosuke was constructed at the murder scene, which fronts on Route 313 in the vicinity of the confluence of the Takahashigawa and Nariwagawa rivers in Takahashi City, as known today; however, his severed torso was buried in a burial mound at Kansenji Temple by Sangyu (珊牛), the retired chief priest of that temple, and the burial mound still exists in the graveyard of the temple.</e>
<cmt>「前住」：「前住職」を意味するものと解釈して訳出しました。「和尚」については、「住職]と同じことを意味するので訳出しておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tomb of Shikanosuke was erected at the scene of his murder, which faces Route 313 near the area where the Takahashigawa and Nariwagawa rivers converge in Takahashi City, as it is known today; however, his torso was interred in a burial mound at Kansenji Temple by Sangyu (珊牛), the retired chief priest of that temple, and the burial mound remains even to this day in the graveyard of the temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tomb of Shikanosuke was erected at the scene of his murder, which faces Route 313 near the area where the Takahashi-gawa and Nariwa-gawa Rivers converge in Takahashi City, as it is known today; however, his torso was interred in a burial mound at Kansen-ji Temple by Sangyu (珊牛), the retired chief priest of that temple, and the burial mound remains even to this day in the graveyard of the temple.</e>
<cmt>Takahashigawa and Nariwagawa rivers→Takahashi-gawa and Nariwa-gawa Riversとし、Kansenji Temple→Kansen-ji Templeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>首級は備後国鞆の浦に在していた時の室町幕府15代将軍足利義昭や毛利輝元により実検が行われ、その後地元の人たちが手厚く葬った首塚が現在も残る（鞆の浦・静観寺山門前）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikanosuke&apos;s severed head was identified by Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the then 15th shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), who stayed at Tomonoura in Bingo Province, as well as Terumoto MORI, and then buried in a burial mound located in front of the gate of Seikanji Temple by local residents with all due respect, and the burial mound still exists now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikanosuke&apos;s decapitated head was identified by Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the then 15th shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (feudal government headed by a shogun), who was staying at Tomonoura in Bingo Province, and Terumoto MORI, after which it was interred by the local residents, with all due respect, in a burial mound located in front of the gate of Seikanji Temple, remains in the temple grounds to this day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikanosuke&apos;s decapitated head was identified by Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the then 15th shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), who was staying at Tomonoura in Bingo Province, and Terumoto MORI, after which it was interred by the local residents, with all due respect, in a burial mound located in front of the gate of Seikan-ji Temple, remains in the temple grounds to this day.</e>
<cmt>Shikanosuke’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正、「室町幕府」→統一リストの表記に修正、Seikanji Temple→Seikan-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>評価とその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How Yukimori YAMANAKA was Treated/Evaluated and What Happened after his Death</e>
<cmt>「評価とその後」：後続の記述の内容に基づき、「評価」は「処遇」も意味するものと解釈し、また、「その後」とは山中幸盛の死後の出来事に言及するものと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How Yukimori YAMANAKA was Treated/Evaluated and What Happened after his Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How Yukimori YAMANAKA was Treated/Evaluated and What Happened after his Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>信長公記には、信長が事実上見殺しにしたことを豊臣秀吉が悔やみ、嫡子の織田信忠に対して「信長の名声に傷がついた」と嘆く一節がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shincho Koki&quot; (a biography of Nobunaga ODA) contains a passage referring to the fact that Hideyoshi TOYOYMI regretted that Nobunaga had virtually let Yukimori YAMANAKA go to his death by not giving him help and showed grief to Nobutada ODA, Nobunaga&apos;s eldest son, saying that the way Yukimori died injured Nobunaga&apos;s reputation.</e>
<cmt>「信長の名声に傷がついた」：原文の語句だけを訳出すると、&quot;Nobunaga&apos;s reputation was injured&quot;となりますが、これだけでは話の流れを把握しづらいので、「幸盛の死に様（the way Yukimori died）」が信長の名声を傷つけた」と読み替えて訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shincho Koki&quot; (a biography of Nobunaga ODA) contains a passage referring to the fact that Hideyoshi TOYOYMI regretted that Nobunaga had, in effect, let Yukimori YAMANAKA go to his death by not providing him with aid, and expressed his feelings to Nobutada ODA, Nobunaga&apos;s eldest son, saying that the way Yukimori had died had injured Nobunaga&apos;s reputation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shincho Koki (a biography of Nobunaga ODA) contains a passage referring to the fact that Hideyoshi TOYOYMI regretted that Nobunaga had, in effect, let Yukimori YAMANAKA go to his death by not providing him with aid, and expressed his feelings to Nobutada ODA, Nobunaga&apos;s eldest son, saying that the way Yukimori had died had injured Nobunaga&apos;s reputation.</e>
<cmt>原文表記に合わせ&quot;Shincho Koki&quot;のクォーテーション削除、Nobunaga’s のアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>もっとも、信長の鹿介ら尼子遺臣団に対する措置は最初から冷酷と言っていいほどで、その事績をたどるとほぼ捨て駒として使われていることが窺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The actions that Nobunaga took for Shikanosuke and other members of the Amago remnant corps was indeed almost ruthless from the beginning; it may be gathered, by looking back through Nobunaga&apos;s deeds, that they were substantially used as if they were sacrificed chessmen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can practically be said that Nobunaga&apos;s actions toward Shikanosuke and other members of the Amago remnant corps were ruthless from the beginning; looking back over the results of Nobunaga&apos;s deeds, it may be inferred that they were sacrificed like a piece in a game of chess.</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can practically be said that Nobunaga&apos;s actions toward Shikanosuke and other members of the Amago Remnant Corps were ruthless from the beginning; looking back over the results of Nobunaga&apos;s deeds, it may be inferred that they were sacrificed like a piece in a game of chess.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>それとは対照的に、秀吉は上記のような発言をしていることからしても尼子遺臣団に対してかなり好意的・同情的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast with Nobunaga, Hideyoshi was amicable and sympathetic to the Amago remnant corps, as indicated by his remark to Nobutada ODA referred to the above.</e>
<cmt>「上記のような発言」：この発言は直前のセンテンスではなく、その1つ前のセンテンスにおいて言及されており、そのため、&quot;the above remark&quot;だけでは何を指しているのかを把握するのがやや難しいと感じました。どの発言に言及するものであるかを明確に示すために、&quot;his remark to Nobutada ODA referred to the above&quot;と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to Nobunaga, Hideyoshi was amicable and sympathetic to the Amago remnant corps, as indicated by his remark to Nobutada ODA referred to above.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to Nobunaga, Hideyoshi was amicable and sympathetic to the Amago Remnant Corps, as indicated by his remark to Nobutada ODA referred to above.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>ただし、これは後に織田家の権力を乗っ取った秀吉による、信長の印象操作であるとの見方もできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this can be interpreted as management of impressions of Nobunaga by Hideyoshi, who seized the power of the Oda clan later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this could also be interpreted as an attempt by Hideyoshi to manipulate the image of Nobunaga after he assumed control of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>It is not clear how this type of manipulation of Nobunaga&apos;s image would serve Hideyoshi positively, unless he meant to shame or denigrating Nobunaga and raise himself.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this could also be interpreted as an attempt by Hideyoshi to manipulate the image of Nobunaga after he assumed control of the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>the Oda clan→the Oda familyに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="56">
<j>鹿介の死は尼子再興運動の終幕ではあったが、尼子遺臣団の完全な解体とはならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The death of Shikanosuke resulted in the termination of the campaign for the restoration of the Amago clan but did not lead to the complete dissolution of the Amago remnant corps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The death of Shikanosuke resulted in the termination of the campaign to restore the status of the Amago clan, but did not lead to the complete dissolution of the Amago remnant corps.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The death of Shikanosuke resulted in the termination of the campaign to restore the status of the Amago clan, but did not lead to the complete dissolution of the Amago Remnant Corps.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>上月城陥落時、亀井茲矩率いる部隊は秀吉に従っていたために難を逃れていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the fall of Kozuki Castle, the unit led by Korenori KAMEI, which was obedient to Hideyoshi, escaped danger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the fall of Kozuki Castle, the unit led by Korenori KAMEI, which was obedient to Hideyoshi, escaped danger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the fall of Kozuki-jo Castle, the unit led by Korenori KAMEI, which was obedient to Hideyoshi, escaped danger.</e>
<cmt>Kozuki-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>尼子遺臣団の一部はこの亀井家の家臣団として再編成され近世大名への道を歩み始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some members of the Amago remnant corps was reorganized into the vassalage of the Kamei family headed by the said Korenori KAMEI, and embarked on the road to kinsei (early modern) daimyo.</e>
<cmt>「この亀井家」：「亀井家」という語はここで初めて使用されているので、&quot;the said Kamei family&quot;と訳出することができません。「この亀井茲矩を当主とする亀井家」と読み替えて訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some members of the Amago remnant corps were reorganized into the vassalage of the Kamei family, headed by Korenori KAMEI, and set forth on the path to becoming daimyo in the early modern period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some members of the Amago Remnant Corps were reorganized into the vassalage of the Kamei family, headed by Korenori KAMEI, and set forth on the path to becoming daimyo in the early modern period.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>その後は東軍に属して関ヶ原の戦いでも前衛の部隊として参戦、徳川幕藩体制に組み込まれ、幕末を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, those members of the Amago remnant corps participated in the Battle of Sekigahara as the advance guard of the East squad, and then were incorporated into the Tokugawa shogunate and domain system; thereafter, their status had been succeeded to by their descendants until the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate..</e>
<cmt>原文の主語が不明です。「その後は東軍に属して関ヶ原の戦いでも前衛の部隊として参戦、徳川幕藩体制に組み込まれ、」の部分の主語は前文の「尼子遺臣団の一部」、それ以降の部分の主語は「尼子遺臣団の一部の子孫」と解釈しました。言及されている時代の長さを考えると、そのように解釈するのが妥当と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, those members of the Amago remnant corps fought in the Battle of Sekigahara as the advance guard of the Eastern forces, and were incorporated under the domain system deployed by the Tokugawa shogunate; their descendants maintained this status through to the final days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, those members of the Amago Remnant Corps fought in the Battle of Sekigahara as the advance guard of the Eastern forces, and were incorporated under the domain system deployed by the Tokugawa shogunate; their descendants maintained this status through to the final days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Amago Remnant Corpsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="60">
<j>また、鹿野町の大名となった亀井茲矩の手により、菩提寺として幸盛寺が建立され、その後境内に墓所が建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Koseiji Temple (expressed as &quot;幸盛寺&quot; in kanji) was erected by Korenori KAMEI, who became the lord of Shikano-cho, to retain the family grave of Yukimori YAMANAKA (expressed as &quot;山中幸盛&quot; in kanji); thereafter, his tomb was raised in the precincts of the temple.</e>
<cmt>「鹿野町の大名」：「鹿野町」は、言及されている時代の地名ではなく現在の地名です。そのため、原語に忠実に訳出すると不自然になります（the lord of Shikano-cho)。翻訳指示に従い、一応そのように訳出しました。the lord of the Shikano domain (Shikano-cho, Tottori City, as it is known today)「菩提寺として幸盛寺が建立され」：「山中幸盛の菩提寺として幸盛寺が建立され」として訳出しました。尚、「幸盛寺」の名称が山中幸盛の名前に由来することを示すために、漢字表記を併記しました。不要であれば削除してください。「墓所が建立」：「墓（廟）が建立」と解釈しました。&quot;his tomb was raised&quot;または&quot;his mausoleum was raised&quot;という訳が考えられますが、前者を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Koseiji Temple (written with the characters &quot;幸盛寺&quot;) was established as the family&apos;s temple by Korenori KAMEI, who had become the daimyo of Shikano-cho, to retain the family grave of Yukimori YAMANAKA (written by the characters &quot;山中幸盛&quot;); thereafter, his tomb was erected in the precincts of the temple.</e>
<cmt>The Japanese does not give the details included that the 1st translation includes regarding the grave of Yukimori Yamanaka, though it would appear from the name of the temple to have been erected in his honor.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Kosei-ji Temple (written with the characters &quot;幸盛寺&quot;) was established as the family&apos;s temple by Korenori KAMEI, who had become the daimyo of Shikano, to retain the family grave of Yukimori YAMANAKA (written by the characters &quot;山中幸盛&quot;); thereafter, his tomb was erected in the precincts of the temple.</e>
<cmt>「鹿野町」→ウェブ上で確認したところ「鹿野」のみの表記だったため、内容に沿わない&quot;Shikano-cho&quot;のかわりに&quot;Shikano&quot;と表記しました。Koseiji Temple→Kosei-ji Templeとし、クォーテーションを半角に修正、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="61">
<j>幸盛の行動は忠誠心溢れるもののように感じられるが、尼子氏の嫡流で当主である尼子義久らは毛利氏の監視下にあり、ある面から見れば幸盛の行動は主君の命に関わるものでもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimori&apos;s behavior seems to be full of loyalty; from a different viewpoint, however, his behavior endangered the life of his lord, in that Yoshihisa AMAGO, who was a direct descendant of the Amago family and the head of the family, as well as some of other members of the family was kept under surveillance by the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Yukimori&apos;s behavior can be appreciated to demonstrate ample loyalty, from another point of view, his actions can be seen to have endangered the life of his lord in so far as Yoshihisa AMAGO, who was a direct descendant and head of the Amago family, as well as some of other members of the family, came to be kept under the surveillance of the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Yukimori&apos;s behavior can be appreciated to demonstrate ample loyalty, from another point of view, his actions can be seen to have endangered the life of his lord in so far as Yoshihisa AMAGO, who was a direct descendant and head of the Amago family, as well as some of other members of the family, came to be kept under the surveillance of the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>Yukimori’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>事実尼子三兄弟は20年近くに渡って軟禁状態に置かれるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, the Amago three brothers were under house arrest for nearly 20 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, the three Amago brothers were under house arrest for nearly 20 years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, the three Amago brothers were under house arrest for nearly 20 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>そのことを勘案するならば、幸盛が忠誠を誓ったのは「尼子」の血脈ではなく、あくまで大名家としての「尼子家」であったと言えるかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With consideration given to that fact, it may be true that Yukimori pledged loyalty only to the &apos;Amago family&apos; being a daimyo family, not to the &apos;Amago&apos; lineage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, if that is to be taken into consideration, it can also be said to be true that Yukimori&apos;s pledged of loyalty was only to the &apos;House of Amago&apos; in its capacity as a daimyo family, and not to the &apos;Amago&apos; blood line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, if that is to be taken into consideration, it can also be said to be true that Yukimori&apos;s pledged of loyalty was only to the &apos;House of Amago&apos; in its capacity as a daimyo family, and not to the &apos;Amago&apos; blood line.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="64">
<j>衰亡した主家に忠誠を尽くして戦い続けたことはほぼ史実が裏付けており、その有り様が後人の琴線に触れ、講談などによる潤色の素地となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the light of historical facts, there can be little doubt that Yukimori kept fighting while rendering devoted service to the family of his lord that had suffered a decline and fall.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「ほぼ史実が裏付けており」：原文の意味が不明ですが、「史実に照らせばほぼ間違いない」ということであろうと推察しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In light of the historical facts, there can be little doubt that Yukimori continued fighting, rendering devoted service to the family of his lord, even after it had fallen into ruin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In light of the historical facts, there can be little doubt that Yukimori continued fighting, rendering devoted service to the family of his lord, even after it had fallen into ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>その有り様が後人の琴線に触れ、講談などによる潤色の素地となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such attitude moved the hearts of future generations, which constituted the foundation of embellishment through stories and the like.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「有り様」：辞書の定訳である&quot;situation&quot;や&quot;state&quot;をあてはめてもしっくりしないので、より具体的な用語を使用すべきと判断し、&quot;attitude&quot;を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such attitude moved the hearts of future generations, which constituted the foundation of embellishment through stories and the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such attitude moved the hearts of future generations, which constituted the foundation of embellishment through stories and the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>特に江戸時代には忠義の武将としての側面が描かれ、悲運の英雄としての「山中鹿之助」が作られていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period, in particular, his faithful warlord aspect was depicted, which led to the creation of the image that &apos;Shikanosuke YAMANAKA&apos; was an ill-fated hero.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo Period, in particular, he was depicted as a faithful warlord, which led to the creation of the image of &apos;Shikanosuke YAMANAKA&apos; as an ill-fated hero.</e>
<cmt>not quite sure how to incorporate 「側面」、&quot;with an emphasis on his aspect&quot; maybe/</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, in particular, he was depicted as a faithful warlord, which led to the creation of the image of &apos;Shikanosuke YAMANAKA&apos; as an ill-fated hero.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更、余分なスペース消去、クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>これが世に広く知られ、武士道を精神的な支柱とした明治以降の国民教育の題材として、月に七難八苦を祈った話が教科書に採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This image became widely-spread, and a story of Yukimori&apos;s praying to the moon for sustaining all kinds of troubles in exchange for the restoration of the Amago clan was adopted as a material for national education in and after the Meiji Period where people were psychologically supported by Bushido (the code of the samurai), and became a content of schoolbooks.</e>
<cmt>「月に七難八苦を祈った」：「尼子氏の再興の代わりに」という文言を挿入しないと、混乱を招きかねないのでそのようにしました。一般的には、苦難を祈ることはあり得ないからです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This image became wide spread, and the story of Yukimori praying to the moon in order to take on all kinds of troubles in exchange for the restoration of the Amago clan was adopted in textbooks from the Meiji Period, during which Bushido (the way of the samurai) was used as a source of spiritual support for the people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This image became wide spread, and the story of Yukimori praying to the moon in order to take on all kinds of troubles in exchange for the restoration of the Amago clan was adopted in textbooks from the Meiji period, during which Bushido (the way of the samurai) was used as a source of spiritual support for the people.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="68">
<j>なお、長男山中幸元（鴻池新六）は父の死後、武士を廃して摂津国川辺郡 (兵庫県)伊丹市で酒造業を始めて財をなし、のちに大阪に移住して江戸時代以降の豪商鴻池財閥の始祖となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimoto YAMANAKA (Shinroku KONOIKE), Yukimori&apos;s eldest son, abandoned samurai status after his father&apos;s death to enter into the sake brewing industry in Kawabe-gun in Settsu Province (Itami City in Hyogo Prefecture; as it is known today); thereafter, he moved to Osaka and founded the Konoike zaibatsu, a business tycoon that had been in existence since the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>「摂津国川辺郡 (兵庫県)伊丹市」：「）」の位置が間違っているようです。「伊丹市」の直後に配置されるべきものとして訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukimoto YAMANAKA (Shinroku KONOIKE), Yukimori&apos;s eldest son, abandoned samurai status after his father&apos;s death to enter into the sake brewing industry in Kawabe-gun in Settsu Province (Itami City in Hyogo Prefecture, as it is known today); thereafter, he moved to Osaka and founded the Konoike zaibatsu, and became a successful business magnate from the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukimoto YAMANAKA (Shinroku KONOIKE), Yukimori&apos;s eldest son, abandoned samurai status after his father&apos;s death to enter into the sake brewing industry in Kawabe-gun in Settsu Province (Itami City in Hyogo Prefecture, as it is known today); thereafter, he moved to Osaka and founded the Konoike zaibatsu, and became a successful business magnate from the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを半角に修正、Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>その為か、鴻池家では毛利家への財政支援を行わなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this may be the reason why the Konoike family gave no financial support to the Mori family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this may be the reason why the Konoike family gave no financial support to the Mori family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this may be the reason why the Konoike family gave no financial support to the Mori family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>実像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What Yukimori YAMANAKA was really like?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What Yukimori YAMANAKA was really like?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What Yukimori YAMANAKA was really like?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>勇猛な美男子であったといい、毛利軍で猛将として知られた菊池音八や、有名な品川大膳との闘い、信貴山城攻略での松永久秀の家臣河合将監をいずれも一騎打ちで討ち取ったという逸話が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have been brave and good-looking; there is a well-known anecdote that depicts his slaying each of the following in single combat; Otohachi KIKUCHI (菊池音八), who is famous for having been a strong general of the Mori force; Daizen SHINAGAWA (the fight against this samurai is famous); Shogen KAWAI, a retainer of Hisahide MATSUNAGA (slain at the time of assault on Shigisan Castle)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have been brave and good-looking; there is a well-known anecdote that depicts his slaying each of the following in single combat; Otohachi KIKUCHI (菊池音八), who is famous for having been a strong general of the Mori force; Daizen SHINAGAWA (the fight against this samurai is famous); Shogen KAWAI, a retainer of Hisahide MATSUNAGA (slain at the time of assault on Shigisan Castle)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to have been brave and good-looking; there is a well-known anecdote that depicts his slaying each of the following in single combat; Otohachi KIKUCHI (菊池音八), who is famous for having been a strong general of the Mori force; Daizen SHINAGAWA (the fight against this samurai is famous); Shogen KAWAI, a retainer of Hisahide MATSUNAGA (slain at the time of assault on Shigisan-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>Shigisan-jo Castleとし、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>品川大膳との一騎討ちについては、史料により異同がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether or not Yukimori slew Daizen SHINAGAWA in single combat is supported or not, depending on historical documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical documents provide differing accounts of the single combat between Yukimori and Daizen SHINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical documents provide differing accounts of the single combat between Yukimori and Daizen SHINAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>毛利側の資料『陰徳太平記』では、品川が優勢に勝負を進め幸盛を追い込んだ所を僚友・秋上庵介の助力で勝ったと記され、尼子側の記述『雲陽軍実記』では幸盛が見事に討ち取ったと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Intoku Taiheiki&quot;, a historical document written by an author being on Mori&apos;s side states that Yukimori defeated Shinagawa with the aid of Iorinosuke AKIAGE, Yukimori&apos;s associate, though Shinagawa proceeded with a fight in his favor and drove Yukimori into a corner whereas &quot;Unnyogun Jitsuki&quot; written by an author being on Amago&apos;s side states that Yukimori slew Shinagawa admirably</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Intoku Taiheiki&quot;, a historical document written by an author biased toward the Mori, maintains that Yukimori defeated Shinagawa with the aid of Iorinosuke AKIAGE, though Shinagawa had battled yukimori into a corner and had the advantage; whereas, the &quot;Unnyogun Jitsuki&quot; written by an author biased toward the Amago, maintains that Yukimori slew Shinagawa in a fair combat and in an admirable manner.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Intoku Taiheiki,&quot; a historical document written by an author biased toward the Mori, maintains that Yukimori defeated Shinagawa with the aid of Iorinosuke AKIAGE, though Shinagawa had battled yukimori into a corner and had the advantage; whereas, the &quot;Unyogun Jitsuki&quot; written by an author biased toward the Amago, maintains that Yukimori slew Shinagawa in a fair combat and in an admirable manner.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを半角に修正、カンマの位置を移動、Unnyogun→Unyogunに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>史料によって異同があり事実は不明であるが、参考として史料の成立としては『雲陽軍実記』の方が100年前後古い事だけを付記しておく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With views varying depending on historical documents, whether the foregoing remains to be confirmed; just for reference, it is a fact that &quot;Unnyogun Jitsuki&quot; came into existence approximately 100 years earlier than &quot;Intoku Taiheiki&quot; did.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notwithstanding that the views varying depending on the historical document, it is an established fact that the Unnyogun Jitsuki was written and had been placed on public record approximately 100 years before the appearance of the Intoku Taiheiki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notwithstanding that the views varying depending on the historical document, it is an established fact that the &quot;Unyogun Jitsuki&quot; was written and had been placed on public record approximately 100 years before the appearance of the &quot;Intoku Taiheiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 みなみたけむら(id:10110), Bakkai(id:7233), Reggaeman(id:6214), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), Nate(id:165259), Paraisogo(id:4372), 李小明(id:174463), 謝艾(id:196690), ウィキ夫(id:183418), Greenland4(id:114494), Newport8865(id:71168), 玄史生(id:43670), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Koon16000(id:43615), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), 海衛士(id:19229), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Baffclan(id:499), Ponsaku(id:31417), タチコマ robot(id:143190), Kuma83(id:31177), Safkan(id:423), Kouko0515(id:100370), Miya.m(id:4662), Jmho(id:10472), Autoblinda(id:100335), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>