<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原伊子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Ishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Ishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Ishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原伊子（ふじわら の いし、生没年不詳）は、平安時代末期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Ishi (dates of birth and death unknown) was a woman in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Ishi (dates of birth and death unknown) was a woman at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Ishi (years of birth and death unknown) was a woman at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>datesをyearsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は関白松殿基房。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Motofusa MATSUDONO, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Motofusa MATSUDONO, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Motofusa MATSUDONO, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>木曾源氏の武将源義仲の正室、のち公卿源通親の側室となり道元を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She became the lawful wife of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka who was a busho (Japanese military commander) of Kiso-Genji (the Minamoto clan) and later a concubine of MINAMOTO no Michichika, Kugyo (the top court official), and had Dogen as her baby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She became the lawful wife of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka who was a busho (Japanese military commander) of Kiso-Genji (the Minamoto clan) and later a concubine of MINAMOTO no Michichika, Kugyo (the top court official), and had Dogen as her baby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She became the lawful wife of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka who was a busho (Japanese military commander) of Kiso-Genji (the Minamoto clan) and later a concubine of MINAMOTO no Michichika, Kugyo (the top court official), and had Dogen as her baby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her official court rank was Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her official court rank was Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her official court rank was Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>松殿伊子とも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her name can also be written as &apos;松殿伊子&apos; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her name can also be written as &apos;松殿伊子&apos; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name can also be written as &apos;松殿伊子&apos; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>冬姫とも伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was said to be called Fuyu-hime as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was said to be called Fuyu-hime as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was said to be called Fuyu-hime as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>藤原北家嫡流の一人である藤原基房の娘として誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born as a daughter of FUJIWARA no Motofusa who was one of the direct descendants of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born the daughter of FUJIWARA no Motofusa who was one of the direct descendants of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born as the daughter of FUJIWARA no Motofusa who was one of the direct descendants of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>bornの後にasを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）11月19日、源義仲が後白河法皇の御所法住寺殿を襲撃するというクーデターを決行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 19, 1183, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka went on the coup to attack Hojuji-dono Palace, the imperial palace of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 19, 1183, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka joined the coup to attack Hojuji-dono Palace, the imperial palace of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, 1184, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka joined the coup to attack Hojuji-dono Palace, the imperial palace of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。ピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これにより一時的に独裁権力を獲得した義仲は、後白河院政の体制下で干されていた状態だった松殿家の基房と接近した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka who temporarily gained the dictatorship due to this coup approached Motofusa of the Matsudono family who had been on the outer under Goshirakawa-insei (the government by the retired Emperor Goshirakawa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka, who temporarily gained the dictatorship due to this coup approached Motofusa of the Matsudono family who had been on the outside under Goshirakawa-insei (the government by the retired Emperor Goshirakawa).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka, who temporarily gained the dictatorship due to this coup approached Motofusa of the Matsudono family who had been on the outside under Goshirakawa-insei (the government by the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa).</e>
<cmt>retiredのrを大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>基房は近衛家に関白の座を奪われて以来、失地回復を狙っていたのでこれをチャンスと見て義仲に協力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Motofusa had sought the retribution since he was deprived of the position of Kanpaku by the Konoe family, he considered it to be his chance and cooperated with Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Motofusa had sought etribution since he was deprived of the position of Kanpaku by the Konoe family, he considered it to be his chance and cooperated with Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Motofusa had sought retribution since he was deprived of the position of Kanpaku by the Konoe family, he considered it to be his chance and cooperated with Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>etributionをｒetributionに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>11月21日に義仲は基房の娘伊子を正室とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 21, Yoshinaka had Ishi, the daughter of Motofusa as his lawful wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 21, Yoshinaka married Ishi, the daughter of Motofusa as his lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 12, Yoshinaka married Ishi, the daughter of Motofusa as his lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>時に伊子十七歳という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Ishi was 17 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Ishi was 17 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Ishi was 17 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに同日、義仲は幽閉した後鳥羽天皇を通じて除目を行い、摂政近衛基通を解任して、伊子の弟松殿師家をかわりの摂政とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On that day, Yoshinaka held Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) through the imprisoned Emperor Gotoba to dismiss Sessho (regent) Motomichi KONOE and instead replace with Moroie MATSUDONO, the younger brother of Ishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that day, Yoshinaka held Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) through the imprisoned Emperor Gotoba to dismiss Sessho (regent) Motomichi KONOE and instead replace him with Moroie MATSUDONO, the younger brother of Ishi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that day, Yoshinaka held Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) through the imprisoned Emperor Gotoba to dismiss Sessho (regent) Motomichi KONOE and instead replace him with Moroie MATSUDONO, the younger brother of Ishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>こうして一時的に義仲と松殿家に天下が訪れたが、関東では法皇幽閉を聞きつけた鎌倉源氏がいよいよ挙兵に及ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura-Genji (the Minamoto clan) which had heard of imprisonment of the Cloistered Emperor Gotoba was about to take up arms in Kanto region, while Yoshinaka and the Matsudono family temporarily ruled the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura-Genji (the Minamoto clan) which had heard of imprisonment of Cloistered Emperor Gotoba was about to take up arms in the Kanto region, while Yoshinaka and the Matsudono family temporarily ruled the world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura-Genji (the Minamoto clan) which had heard of imprisonment of Cloistered Emperor Gotoba was about to take up arms in the Kanto region, while Yoshinaka and the Matsudono family temporarily ruled the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>源範頼と源義経の軍が京都へ向かって進軍を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune started to charge forward to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune started their charge forward to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune started their charge forward to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>『源平盛衰記』には、源義経に攻められている最中、義仲が五条内裏で伊子といつまでも別れを惜しんでいたので、越後中太能景（『平家物語』には家光とある）と加賀国住人の津波田三郎が切腹してこれを諌めたとする逸話が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans) described the following story: Yoshinaka remained unwilling to part from Ishi in Gojo Dairi (the Emperor&apos;s residential compound) in the middle of being attacked by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, so 越後中太能景 (referred to Iemitsu in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike)) and Saburo TSUNADA who lived in Kaga Province committed Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) to remonstrate that behavior.</e>
<cmt>読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans) describes the following story: Yoshinaka remained unwilling to part from Ishi in Gojo Dairi (the Emperor&apos;s residential compound) in the middle of being attacked by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, so 越後中太能景 (referred to Iemitsu in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; - The tale of the Heike) and Saburo TSUNADA who lived in Kaga Province committed Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) to remonstrate that behavior.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans) describes the following story: Yoshinaka remained unwilling to part from Ishi in Gojo Dairi (the Emperor&apos;s residential compound) in the middle of being attacked by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, so Kazukage Echigo no chuta (referred to Iemitsu in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; - The tale of the Heike) and Saburo TSUNADA who lived in Kaga Province committed Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) to remonstrate that behavior.</e>
<cmt>越後中太能景をKazukage Echigo no chutaとしておきました（コトバンク）。Yoshikageと読むこともあるようです。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>夫義仲の敗死後は父の山荘で暮らしていたが、再び父基房の権勢復興のための政略結婚に使われ、今度は公卿源通親の側室とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though she lived in the mountain villa owned by her father after her husband Yoshinaka died in action, she was again got married off for political reason to regain reins of power of her father Motofusa and became the concubine of Kugyo (the top court official) MINAMOTO no Michichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though she lived in a mountain villa owned by her father after her husband Yoshinaka died in action, she was again married off for political reasons to regain the reins of power by her father Motofusa and became the concubine of Kugyo (top court official) MINAMOTO no Michichika.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though she lived in a mountain villa owned by her father after her husband Yoshinaka died in action, she was again married off for political reasons to regain the reins of power by her father Motofusa and became the concubine of Kugyo (top court official) MINAMOTO no Michichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この通親は、後白河法皇崩御後に朝廷政治の第一人者となり、「源博陸」と称される程の権勢を誇っていた人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michichika was the person who became the leading figure of Imperial Court government after the death of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and had so much power as to be referred to &apos;Gen hakuroku&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michichika was the person who became the leading figure in the Imperial Court government after the death of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and had so much power he was referred to as &apos;Gen hakuroku&apos;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michichika was the person who became the leading figure in the Imperial Court government after the death of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and had so much power as he was referred to as &apos;Gen hakuroku&apos;.</e>
<cmt>powerの後にasを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>正治2年（1200年）1月2日、宇治木幡山荘において通親との間に道元（曹洞宗開祖）を儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 2, 1200, she had Dogen (the founder of Soto sect) as a baby with Michichika in Uji Kohata villa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 2, 1200, she had Dogen (the founder of Soto sect) as a baby with Michichika in Uji Kohata villa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 26, 1200, she had Dogen (the founder of Soto sect) as a baby with Michichika in Uji Kohata villa.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>のち伊子の弟師家はこの道元を養子に迎えて、松殿家の復興を目指したが、結局それには至らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Moroie, the younger brother of Ishi had Dogen as the adopted child to aim at restoring the Matsudono family, but eventually it did not realized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Moroie, the younger brother of Ishi had Dogen as the adopted child to aim at restoring the Matsudono family, but eventually it was not realized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Moroie, the younger brother of Ishi had Dogen as the adopted child to aim at restoring the Matsudono family, but eventually it was not realized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>2年後に通親とも死別した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michichika died and she became widowed two years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michichika died and she became widowed two years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michichika died and she became widowed two years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>伊子は道元とともに木幡山荘に移り住んだが、5年後の道元8歳の時に病で死去したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishi moved to live in Kohata villa with Dogen, but she died of disease five years later when Dogen was eight years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishi moved to live in Kohata villa with Dogen, but she died of disease five years later when Dogen was eight years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishi moved to live in Kohata villa with Dogen, but she died of disease five years later when Dogen was eight years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>道元が出家を志したのは幼い日に両親と死別することになったためだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why Dogen entered into priesthood was because of the bereavement of his parents in his childhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why Dogen entered into priesthood was because of the bereavement of his parents during his childhood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why Dogen entered into priesthood was because of the bereavement of his parents during his childhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>