<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>北畠顕家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiie KITABATAKE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiie KITABATAKE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiie KITABATAKE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>北畠 顕家（きたばたけ あきいえ、文保2年（1318年） - 延元3年/建武 (日本)5年5月22日 (旧暦)（1338年6月10日））は、南北朝時代 (日本)の公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiie KITABATAKE (1318 - June 10, 1338) was a court noble in the Nanbokucho era (Japan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiie KITABATAKE (1318 - June 10, 1338) was a court noble in the Nanbokucho era (Japan.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiie KITABATAKE (1318 - June 10, 1338) was a court noble during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>This reads a little more naturally, I think.The checker should take care not to leave the full stop inside the parentheses!All of this translation will need to be rechecked to make sure that, unless the grammar requires otherwise, all periods are placed outside of the parentheses.Japan&apos;s Nanbokucho period→the period of the Northern and Southern Courtsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北畠親房の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest son of Chikafusa KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest son of Chikafusa KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Chikafusa KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>Just because the Japanese doesn&apos;t have a subject doesn&apos;t mean the English shouldn&apos;t. As this forms part of a paragraph some effort should be made to make it flow, I think.ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>権中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Supernumerary second-ranked councilor of state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supernumerary second-ranked councilor of state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the position of gon-chunagon (literally, &quot;acting middle ranking councilor&quot;).</e>
<cmt>It would be helpful if the translator could indicate whether their translation of the names of positions, etc., are 仮訳 or not. If they have found an established translation for such terms, it would also help if they could cite the source (e.g. URL).</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>弟に北畠顕信、北畠顕能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brothers were Akinobu KITABATAKE and Akiyoshi KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brothers were Akinobu KITABATAKE and Akiyoshi KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brothers were Akinobu KITABATAKE and Akiyoshi KITABATAKE..</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に北畠顕成（後に村上師清と名乗り、村上水軍の祖となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child was Akinari KITABATAKE (later, identified as Morokiyo MURAKAMI and became a patriarch of Murakami-Suigun navy.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His child was Akinari KITABATAKE (later, he was known as Morokiyo MURAKAMI and he became a patriarch of Murakami-Suigun navy.)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son was Akinari KITABATAKE (who later became known as Morokiyo MURAKAMI and was the founder of the Murakami-Suigun navy).</e>
<cmt>It is more natural to use the word &quot;son&quot; if we know the child in question is male. Also, I don&apos;t think &quot;patriarch of... Navy&quot; is very clear.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>北畠家は村上源氏の庶流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitabatake Family was a branch family of Murakami-Genji (Murakami Gen clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kitabatake Family was a branch family of the Murakami-Genji (Murakami Gen clan.)</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;the&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kitabatake family was a branch family of the Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan.)</e>
<cmt>Family→familyMurakami Gen→Minamoto</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Personal history→Biography</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>父の親房は、後の「三房」の1人として後醍醐天皇に近侍し、1333年（元弘3年/正慶2年）から開始された建武の新政を補佐していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Chikafusa was one of &quot;Sambo (three omniscients with &quot;fusa&quot; (房)&quot; character in their name)&quot; and was serving the Emperor Godaigo as a valet in later years, and provided assistance for the Kemmu-no-shinsei commenced in 1333.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Chikafusa was a &quot;Sambo (one of three omniscients with &quot;fusa&quot; (房)&quot; character in their name)&quot;, served the Emperor Godaigo in later years, and assisted the 1333 Kemmu restoration.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, wording; 建武の新政 is known as the Kemmu Restoration</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Chikafusa was a &apos;Sambo (one of three omniscients with fusa (房) character in their name),&apos; served the Emperor Godaigo in later years, and assisted the 1333 Kenmu restoration.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;　&quot;を削除原文の「」を&quot;から&apos;にコンマを&apos;内に移動Kemmu→kenmu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>顕家はこの年に従三位陸奥守となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiie became Jusammi rank Mutsu-no-kami (chief of Mutsu-no-kami.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiie became Jusammi rank Mutsu-no-kami (chief of Mutsu-no-kami.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiie became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Mutsu no kami.</e>
<cmt>Jusammi rank Mutsu-no-kami (chief of Mutsu-no-kami.)→Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Mutsu no kami</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>翌1334年（建武元年）、後醍醐天皇の皇子である義良親王（のちの後村上天皇）を奉じ、父とともに陸奥国の多賀城（宮城県多賀城市）に下向し、東北地方経営を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, 1334, he went to Tagajo Castle (Tagajo City, Miyagi Prefecture) with his father in obedience to Imperial Prince Norinaga&apos;s order, Godaigo Emperor&apos;s prince (later, Emperor Gomurakami) to be involved in the management of the Tohoku Region.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすいと考えて、Castleを追加しました。多賀城→Tagajo CastleWording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, 1334, in accordance with an order from Imperial Prince Norinaga (the son of Emperor Godaigo; later to be known as Emperor Gomurakami), he went to Tagajo Castle (Tagajo City, Miyagi Prefecture) with his father and began management of the Tohoku Region.</e>
<cmt>wording; made this more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, 1334, in accordance with an order from Imperial Prince Norinaga (the son of Emperor Godaigo; later to be known as Emperor Gomurakami), he went to Tagajo Castle (Tagajo City, Miyagi Prefecture) in Mutsu Province with his father and began management of the Tohoku Region.</e>
<cmt>in Mutsu Province補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同年、従二位に叙任し、1335年（建武2年）鎮守府将軍に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he assumed the Junii rank, and in 1335, was appointed as Shogun of Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he assumed the rank of Junii, and in 1335, he was appointed as Shogun of Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt>verb tense; wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he assumed the Junii (Junior Second Rank), and in 1335, he was appointed as Shogun of Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt>rank of Junii→Junii (Junior Second Rank)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>同年、足利尊氏軍が鎌倉にて建武政権に反旗を翻し、京都へ迫ったため、顕家は12月 (旧暦)、奥州の兵を引き連れ、尊氏軍を追って上京した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s army rebelled against the Kemmu Government in Kamakura in the same year and was approaching Kyoto, Akiie went to Kyoto with Oshu army, running after ASHIKAGA&apos;s army and defeated and expelled the army from Kyo together in cooperation with of Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, while Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s army rebelled against the Kemmu Government in Kamakura and approached Kyoto, Akiie brought the Oshu army to Kyoto in pursuit of ASHIKAGA&apos;s army. They were able to defeat and expell them from Kyo with the help of Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, while Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s army rebelled against the Kenmu Government in Kamakura and approached Kyoto, Akiie brought the Oshu army to Kyoto in pursuit of ASHIKAGA&apos;s army in December (old lunar calender).</e>
<cmt>Kemmu→kenmu一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これを新田義貞、楠木正成とともに破り、京より追い出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were able to defeat and expel them from Kyo with the help of Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処expell→expel</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>翌1336年（建武3年）1月 (旧暦)、再度の入京を目指す尊氏を摂津国で破った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January of the following year, 1336, he defeated Takauji in Settsu-no-kuni who was attempting to go to Kyoto again, resulting in Takauji leaving for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January of the following year, 1336, he defeated Takauji in Settsu-no-kuni, while he was attempting to go to Kyoto again. Takauji later departed for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January of the following year, 1336, he defeated Takauji in Settsu Province, while he was attempting to go to Kyoto again.</e>
<cmt>Settsu-no-kuni→Settsu Province一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>尊氏は九州へと落ち延びる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji later departed for Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>3月 (旧暦)、中納言に任官、蜂起した足利方を掃討するため再び奥州へ戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he assumed a vice councilor of state, and returned to Oshu again to destroy ASIKAGA&apos;s army who rose in revolt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he assumed a vice councilor of state, and returned to Oshu again to destroy ASIKAGA&apos;s army who rose in revolt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he assumed a vice councilor of state, and returned to Oshu again to destroy ASIKAGA&apos;s army who rose in revolt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1337年（延元2年/建武4年）には足利方に多賀城を攻略されるが、この時は顕家は国府を霊山 (福島県)（福島県相馬市および伊達市 (福島県)）に移していたため難を逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1337, Taga Castle was captured by Ashikaga clan, and he ran into no trouble at that time because Akiie had transferred the Kokufu to Ryozen (Fukushima Prefecture) (Soma City and Date City, Fukushima Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1337, Taga Castle was captured by the Ashikaga clan; however, he escaped disaster at that time because Akiie had transferred the Kokufu to Ryozen (Soma City and Date City, Fukushima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1337, Taga Castle was captured by the Ashikaga clan; however, he escaped disaster at that time because Akiie had transferred the Kokufu to Ryozen (Soma City and Date City, Fukushima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>1338年（延元3年/建武5年）5月 (旧暦)、再び西上して足利方と戦い、義良親王を奉じて鎌倉を攻略する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1338, moving west again, he fought a battle with Ashikaga clan, and captured Kamakura in obedience to Imperial Prince Yorinaga&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1338, moving west again, he fought a battle with the Ashikaga clan, and captured Kamakura as ordered by Imperial Prince Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1338, moving west again, he fought a battle with the Ashikaga clan, and captured Kamakura as ordered by Imperial Prince Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>美濃国青野原の戦い（現、岐阜県大垣市）で足利方に勝利したものの、兵力の減少や疲弊により京攻略を諦め伊勢に後退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he won a victory from the Asikaga side in the Battle of Aonogahara in Mino-no-kuni (Ogaki City, Gifu Prefecture), he relinquished the capture of Kyo due to a decrease in and exhaustion of military forces and left for Iga, and later, although he advanced to Iga, he lost battles because the soldiers were exhausted or wounded as a result of battles which they fought one after another from Oshu and couldn&apos;t exert all their strength.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While, he won a victory from the Ashikaga side in the Battle of Aonogahara in Mino-no-kuni (Ogaki City, Gifu Prefecture), he abandoned his Kyo campaign due to dwindling force numbers and sheer exhaustion, and departed for Iga. Later, despite advancing on Iga, he lost battles because his soldiers&apos; strength was sapped and they incurred injuries sustained in the constant battling from Oshu.</e>
<cmt>spelling, wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While, he won a victory from the Ashikaga side in the Battle of Aonogahara in Mino Province (Ogaki City, Gifu Prefecture), he abandoned his Kyo campaign due to dwindling force numbers and sheer exhaustion, and departed for Ise.</e>
<cmt>Mino-no-kuni→Mino ProvinceIga→Ise一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>次いで伊賀に進出したものの、奥州から従軍していた歴戦の将兵は疲労や怪我によって力を出せずに敗退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, despite advancing on Iga, he lost battles because his soldiers&apos; strength was sapped and they incurred injuries sustained in the constant battles with Oshu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処表現スタイル。 - “battling from Oshu.”=&gt;” battles with Oshu.”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そして、再起を期して和泉国堺浦石津で兵を挙げる事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Again, he was to rise up in arms in Sakaiura and Ishizu in Izumi-no-kuni, wishing for resurgence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Again, seeking to revive his campaign he raised an army in Sakaiura and Ishizu in Izumi-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Again, seeking to revive his campaign he raised an army in Sakaiura and Ishizu in Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt>Izumi-no-kuni→Izumo Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、予定していた味方の援軍到着遅延の為に高師直軍との戦いでは劣勢に回り全軍は潰走。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, due to a delay in the expected arrival of reinforcements on the same side, his army was behind in battles against KO no Moronao&apos;s army and ended in debacle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to a delay in the expected arrival of his reinforcements, his army could not match KO no Moronao&apos;s army and they were routed.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to a delay in the expected arrival of his reinforcements, his army could not match KO no Moronao&apos;s army and they were routed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その後、共廻り等二百騎を従えて尚も奮戦したが戦死した（石津の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he still fought battles having two hundred soldiers in tow including attendants, but was killed in battle (the Battle of Ishizu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he still fought battles having two hundred soldiers in tow including attendants, but was killed in battle (the Battle of Ishizu.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he still fought battles having two hundred soldiers, including attendants, but was killed in battle (the Battle of Ishizu.)</e>
<cmt>表現スタイル。 “in tow” は軽いので削除。. =&gt;” two hundred soldiers, including attendants”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>享年21。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">21 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">21 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 21 years old.</e>
<cmt>He was補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>死の前に後醍醐に対して新政の失敗を諌める奏上文（顕家諫奏）を遺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before his death, he wrote the Address (Akiie&apos;s Kanso (Akiie to say advices to the Emperor) to Godaigo to remonstrate that the Kemmu-no-shinsei was a failure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before his death, he wrote an Address (Akiie&apos;s Kanso--Akiie&apos;s advice to the Emperor) to Godaigo to convince him of the failure of the Kemmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Wording; Should be 顕家諫奏→Akiie&apos;s Kanso (Akiie advises Emperor)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before his death, he wrote an Address (Akiie&apos;s Kanso--Akiie&apos;s advice to the Emperor) to Godaigo to convince him of the failure of the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Kemmu→kenmu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>顕家が戦死したとされる堺市西区 (堺市)の石津川沿いには供養塔が建てられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a memorial tower constructed in a place along Ishizu-gawa river in Nishi Ward, Sakai City (Sakai City) where Akiie seemed to be killed in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a memorial tower constructed in a place along the Ishizu-gawa river in Nishi Ward, Sakai City, where Akiie was supposedly killed in battle.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a memorial tower constructed in a place along the Ishizu-gawa river in Nishi Ward, Sakai City, where Akiie was supposedly killed in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>墓は、大阪市阿倍野区の北畠公園内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is in Kitabatake Koen Park in Abeno Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is in Kitabatake Koen Park in Abeno Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is in Kitabatake Koen Park in Abeno Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また阿倍野区にある阿部野神社は北畠顕家を祀っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Abeno-jinja Shrine in Abeno Ward enshrines Akiie KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Abeno-jinja Shrine in Abeno Ward enshrines Akiie KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Abeno-jinja Shrine in Abeno Ward enshrines Akiie KITABATAKE..</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>更に、顕家が陸奥国府を築いた霊山には霊山神社が建てられ、顕家親子らを祀っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Ryozen-jinja Shrine was built in Ryozen where Akiie constructed Mutsu-kokufu and enshrines Akiie and his child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Ryozen-jinja Shrine was built in Ryozen where Akiie constructed Mutsu-kokufu; it is the shrine that enshrines Akiie and his child.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Ryozen-jinja Shrine was built in Ryozen where Akiie constructed Mutsu-kokufu; it enshrines Akiie and his child.</e>
<cmt>“it is the shrine that enshrines”=&gt;”it enshrines ”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>ちなみに、武田信玄よりも先に「風林火山」の旗印を用いたことでも有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, he is famous for having used a flag of Fu-Rin-Ka-Zan (as fast as the wind, as quiet as the forest, as daring as fire, and as immovable as the mountain) earlier than Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, he is also famous for having used the Fu-Rin-Ka-Zan (as fast as the wind, as quiet as the forest, as daring as fire, and as immovable as the mountain) banner prior to Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, he is also famous for having used the Fu-Rin-Ka-Zan (as fast as the wind, as quiet as the forest, as daring as fire, and as immovable as the mountain) banner prior to Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology of Government Posts and Ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* Dates are based on a lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Dates are based on a lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Dates are based on a lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>※→*</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1321年（元応3）、1月5日、従五位下に叙位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1321, assuming the Jugoi-no-ge rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, 1321, assuming the Jugoi-no-ge rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1321, assuming the Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>Jugoi-no-ge rank→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>1322年（元亨2）、1月5日、従五位上に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1322, promoted to the Jugoi-no-jo rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, 1322, promoted to the Jugoi-no-jo rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1322, promoted to the Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>Jugoi-no-jo rank→Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>1324年（元亨4）、4月9日、正五位下に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 9, 1324, promoted to the Shogoi-no-ge rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 9, 1324, promoted to the Shogoi-no-ge rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 9, 1324, promoted to the Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>Shogoi-no-ge rank→Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>1325年（正中 (日本)2）、12月30日、侍従に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 30, 1325, appointed as Palace staff.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 30, 1325, appointed as Palace staff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 30, 1325, appointed as Palace staff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="35">
<j>1326年（正中3）、1月5日、従四位下に昇叙し、侍従如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1326, promoted to the Jushii-no-ge rank with Palace staff position unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, 1326, promoted to the Jushii-no-ge rank with Palace staff position unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1326, promoted to the Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) with Palace staff position unchanged.</e>
<cmt>Jushii-no-ge rank→Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>2月19日、右近衛少将に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 19, promoted to Ukon-e-no-Shosho (lowest general of Ukon-e-fu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 19, promoted to Ukon-e-no-Shosho (lowest general of Ukon-e-fu.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 19, promoted to Ukon e no Shosho (lowest general of Ukon-e-fu).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを）の外にUkon-e-no-Shosho→Ukon e no Shosho</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>1327年（嘉暦2）、3月24日、従四位上に昇叙し、武蔵介を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 24, 1327, promoted to the Jushii-no-jo rank and also assuming Musashi-no-suke (vice governor of Musashi-no-kuni.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 24, 1327, promoted to the Jushii-no-jo rank and also assumed Musashi-no-suke (vice governor of Musashi-no-kuni.)</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 24, 1327, promoted to the Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and also assumed Musashi no suke (vice governor of Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>Jushii-no-jo rank→Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)Musashi-no-kuni→Musashi ProvinceMusashi-no-suke→Musashi no sukeピリオドを）の外に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>右近衛少将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukon-e-no-Shosho remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukon-e-no-Shosho remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukon e no Shosho retained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>Ukon-e-no-Shosho→Ukon e no Shoshoremained→retainedに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="39">
<j>1328年（嘉暦3）、1月5日、正四位下に昇叙し、右近衛少将・武蔵介如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1328, promoted to the Shoshii-no-ge with Ukon-e-no-Shosho and Musashi-no-suke unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, 1328, promoted to the Shoshii-no-ge with Ukon-e-no-Shosho and Musashi-no-suke unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1328, promoted to the Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) with Ukon e no Shosho and Musashi no suke unchanged.</e>
<cmt>Shoshii-no-ge→Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)Ukon-e-no-Shosho→Ukon e no ShoshoMusashi-no-suke→Musashi no suke</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>3月16日、少納言を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 16, also assuming the Shonagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 16, he also assumed the Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 16, he also assumed the Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>4月19日、左近衛少将に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 19, appointed as Sakon-e-no-Shosho (lowest general of Sakon-e-fu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 19, appointed as Sakon-e-no-Shosho (lowest general of Sakon-e-fu.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 19, appointed Sakon-e-no-Shosho (lowest general of Sakon-e-fu.)</e>
<cmt>“as”削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>少納言・武蔵介如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonagon and Musashi-no-suke remained unchanged</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shonagon and Musashi-no-suke remained unchanged</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shonagon and Musashi-no-suke retained unchanged</e>
<cmt>remained→retainedに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>11月9日、中宮（西園寺実兼の娘、後醍醐天皇中宮藤原禧子）権亮を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 19, also assuming Chugu (FUJIWARA no Kishi as the Godaigo Emperor&apos;s Empress, Sanekane SAIONJI&apos;s daughter) gon-no-suke (supernumerary assistance administrator of Chugushiki government office.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 19, he also assumed Chugu (FUJIWARA no Kishi as the Godaigo Emperor&apos;s Empress; Sanekane SAIONJI&apos;s daughter) gon-no-suke (supernumerary assistance administrator of the Chugushiki government office).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 19, he also assumed Chugu (FUJIWARA no Kishi as the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s Empress; Sanekane SAIONJI&apos;s daughter) gon no suke (supernumerary assistance administrator of the Chugushiki government office).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除Godaigo Emperor&apos;s→Emperor　Godaigo&apos;sgon-no-suke→gon no suke</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>少納言を去る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leaving the Shonagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He departed for Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He departed for Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="45">
<j>1330年（元徳2）、4月6日、右中弁に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 6, 1330, appointed as Uchuben (vice minister of Ubenkan-kyoku, Daijokan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 6, 1330, he was appointed as Uchuben (vice minister of Ubenkan-kyoku, Daijokan).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 6, 1330, appointed Uchuben (vice minister of Ubenkan-kyoku, Daijokan).</e>
<cmt>日付統一。 =&gt; “April 6, 1330, appointed Uchuben (vice minister of Ubenkan-kyoku, Daijokan).”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>中宮権亮如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugu-gon-no-suke remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chugu-gon-no-suke remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chugu-gon-no-suke retained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>remained→retainedに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>10月5日、左中弁に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 5, appointed as Sachuben (vice minister of Sabenkan-kyoku, Daijokan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 5, he was appointed as Sachuben (vice minister of Sabenkan-kyoku, Daijokan).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 5, he was appointed as Sachuben (vice minister of Sabenkan-kyoku, Daijokan).</e>
<cmt>日付統一。 October 5, appointed…</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>中宮権亮如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugu-gon-no-suke remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chugu-gon-no-suke remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chugu-gon-no-suke retained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>remained→retainedに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="49">
<j>1331年（元徳3）、1月5日、正四位上に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1331, promoted to the Shoshii-no-jo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, 1331, promoted to the Shoshii-no-jo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1331, promoted to the Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>Shoshii-no-jo→Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>1月13日、参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 13, taking office of councilor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 13, taking office of councilor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 13, taking office of councilor.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。 “January 13, took office of councilor.”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>1月16日、左近衛中将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 16, also assuming Sakonoe-Chujo (lieutenant general of Sakon-e-fu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 16, also assuming Sakonoe-Chujo (lieutenant general of Sakon-e-fu).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 16, also assuming Sakonoe-Chujo (lieutenant general of Sakon-e-fu).</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>11月5日、参議と左近衛中将を辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 5, resigned as councilor and Sakonoe-Chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 5, he resigned as councilor and Sakonoe-Chujo.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 5, he resigned as councilor and Sakonoe-Chujo.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。November 5, resigned…</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>同日、従三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same date, promoted to the Jusammi rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to the Jusammi rank on the same date.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same date, he was promoted to the Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Jusammi rank→Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="54">
<j>1332年（元弘2・正慶元）、12月26日、参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 26, 1332, taking office of councilor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 26, 1332, he assumed the office of councilor.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 26, 1332, he assumed the office of councilor.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>同日、左近衛中将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same date, also assuming Sakonoe-Chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also assumed Sakonoe-Chujo on the same date.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same date, he also assumed Sakonoe-Chujo.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="56">
<j>1333年（元弘3・正慶2）、6月12日、弾正大弼を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 12, 1333, also assuming Danjo-Daihitsu (vice general of Danjodai.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 12, 1333, he also assumed Danjo-Daihitsu (vice general of Danjodai).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 12, 1333, he also assumed Danjo-Daihitsu (vice general of Danjodai).</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>8月5日、陸奥守を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 5, also assuming Mutsu-no-kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 5, he also assumed Mutsu-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 5, he also assumed Mutsu no kami.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>9月10日、弾正大弼を止む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 10, resigned as Danjo-Daihitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 10, he resigned as Danjo-Daihitsu.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 10, he resigned as Danjo-Daihitsu.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>10月10日、正三位に昇叙し、参議・陸奥守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 10, promoted to the Shosammi rank with councilor and Mutsu-no-kami unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 10, he was promoted to the Shosammi rank with his positions as councilor and Mutsu-no-kami remaining unchanged.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 10, he was promoted to the Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) with his positions as councilor and Mutsu no kami retaining unchanged.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。remaining→retainingに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>月日不詳、右近衛中将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date unknown, also assuming Ukon-e-no-Chujo (lieutenant general of Ukon-e-fu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On an unknown date, he also assumed the rank of Ukon-e-no-Chujo (lieutenant general of Ukon-e-fu).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An unknown date, he also assumed the rank of Ukon e no Chujo (lieutenant general of Ukon-e-fu).</e>
<cmt>Ukon-e-no-Chujo→Ukon e no Chujo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="61">
<j>1334年（建武 (日本)元）、12月17日、従二位に昇叙し、参議・右近衛中将・陸奥守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 17, 1334, promoted to the Junii with councilor, Ukon-e-no-Chujo and Mutsu-no-kami unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 17, 1334, he was promoted to the Junii with his status as councilor, Ukon-e-no-Chujo and Mutsu-no-kami remaining unchanged.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 17, 1334, he was promoted to the Junii (Junior Second Rank) with his status as councilor, Ukon e no Chujo and Mutsu no kami retaining unchanged.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。remaining→retainingに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="62">
<j>1335年（建武2）、月日不詳、陸奥権守に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unknown date of 1335, appointed as Mutsu-no-Gonnokami (supernumerary chief of Mutsu-no-kuni.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On an unknown date in 1335, he was appointed as Mutsu-no-Gonnokami (supernumerary chief of Mutsu-no-kuni).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An unknown date in 1335, he was appointed as Mutsu no Gonnokami (supernumerary chief of Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>陸奥守を去る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigned as Mutsu-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned as Mutsu-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>主語を明確に</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned as Mutsu no kami.</e>
<cmt>Mutsu-no-kuni→Mutsu no kami</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>11月12日、鎮守府将軍を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 12, also taking office of the Shogun of Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 12, he also took the office of Shogun of Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 12, he also took the office of Shogun of Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="65">
<j>1336年（建武3・延元元）、2月4日、検非違使別当に補任し、右衛門督を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 4, 1336, promoted to Kebiishi no Betto (chief of statutory office) and also assuming Emon-no-kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 4, 1336, he was promoted to Kebiishi no Betto (chief of statutory office) and also assumed the position of Emon-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 4, 1336, he was promoted to Kebiishi no Betto (chief of statutory office) and also assumed the position of Emon no kami.</e>
<cmt>Emon-no-kami→Emon no kami</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>2月5日、鎮守府大将軍としてあらためて補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 5, appointed as chief of Shoguns of Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 5, he was appointed as chief of the Shoguns of Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 5, he was appointed as chief of the Shoguns of Chinjufu.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>2月26日、陸奥権守を去るか？（同日、義良親王、三品陸奥太守叙任により）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 26, resigned as Mutsu-no-Gonnokami? (On the same day, Imperial Prince Norinaga was appointed as Sambon (third-ranked of Imperial Prince) Mutsu-Taishu (president of Mutsu-no-kuni.) March 2, promoted to supernumerary second-ranked councilor of state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 26, resigned as Mutsu-no-Gonnokami? (On the same day, Imperial Prince Norinaga was appointed as Sambon (third-ranked of Imperial Prince) Mutsu-Taishu (president of Mutsu-no-kuni.) March 2, promoted to supernumerary second-ranked councilor of state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 26, resigned as Mutsu no Gonnokami? (On the same day, Imperial Prince Norinaga was appointed as Sanbon (third-ranked of Imperial Prince) Mutsu-Taishu (president of Province).</e>
<cmt>Mutsu-no-Gonnokami→Mutsu no Gonnokamiスペース削除Sambon→SanbonMutsu-no-kuni→Mutsu Provinceピリオドを）の外に一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>3月2日、権中納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 2, promoted to supernumerary second-ranked councilor of state.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>鎮守府大将軍・検非違使別当・右衛門督如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chief of Shoguns of Chinjufu, Kebiishi no Betto and Emon-no-kami remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His position as Chief of the Shoguns of Chinjufu, Kebiishi no Betto and Emon no kami remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His position as Chief of the Shoguns of Chinjufu, Kebiishi no Betto and Emon no kami retained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>Emon-no-kami→Emon no kamiremained→retainedに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>月日不詳、検非違使別当・右衛門督を辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date unknown, resigned as Kebiishi no Betto and Emon-no-kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On an unknown date he resigned as Kebiishi no Betto and Emon no kami.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An unknown date he resigned as Kebiishi no Betto and Emon no kami.</e>
<cmt>Emon-no-kami→Emon no kami</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>12月、解官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December, dismissed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was dismissed in December.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December, he was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="72">
<j>1338年（暦応元・延元3）、5月22日、薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 22, 1338, died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 22, 1338, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 22, 1338, he died.</e>
<cmt>日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>享年21．</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">21 years old. Buddhist name was Chokoji-Do&apos;on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 21 years old.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 21 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>法名：長興寺道音。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Chokoji-Doon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処Do&apos;on→Doon</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>年月日不詳、贈従一位左大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date unknown, given the Juichii (rank) Sadaijin (minister of the left of Dajokan) after death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On an unknown date he was posthumously given the Juichii (rank) of Sadaijin (minister of the left of Dajokan).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An unknown date he was posthumously given the Juichii (Junior First Rank) of Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>(rank)→(Junior First Rank)of Dajokan補足日付統一。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Deewell(id:22093), Oxhop(id:2551), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), いたる(id:58536), Himazin(id:22034), Seibuabina(id:37532), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 沢田(id:40580), Greenland4(id:114494), 間久部緑郎(id:22345), でここ(id:9565), Kenpei(id:11349), YurikBot(id:18605), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), Yukimura.S(id:2138), Shostakist(id:54214), UMBRO(id:100484), 参謀中佐(id:11557), Kone(id:377), Muyo(id:14948), 難民(id:4644), Red Star Belgrade(id:25968), 小川尚明(id:93076), Junger(id:10282), ５１６(id:45205), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>