<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>松井須磨子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumako MATSUI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumako MATSUI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumako MATSUI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>松井 須磨子（まつい すまこ、1886年3月8日 - 1919年1月5日）は、日本の新劇俳優。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumako MATSUI (March, 8, 1886 - January, 5, 1919) was an actress of the Japanese new-drama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumako MATSUI (March 8, 1886 - January 5, 1919) was an actress of the Japanese shingeki (literally, new play).</e>
<cmt>不要なカンマを削除しました用語登録の訳に修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumako MATSUI (March 8, 1886 - January 5, 1919) was an actress of the Japanese shingeki (literally, new play).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本名、小林正子（こばやしまさこ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her real name was Masako KOBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her real name was Masako KOBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real name was Masako KOBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Profile</e>
<cmt>所有格を省略しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>長野県埴科郡清野村（現・長野市松代町 (長野県)清野）に士族小林藤太（旧松代藩武士）の五女（九人兄妹の末っ子）として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born as the fifth daughter (the youngest of 9 children) of Tota Kobayashi who was a samurai class (a samurai belonged to the former Matsushiro clan) in Kiyono-mura, Haniwa-gun County, Nagano Prefecture (presently known as Kiyono, Matsushiro-cho, Nagano-city (Nagano Prefecture)).</e>
<cmt>藤太-Tota (定訳不明)清野村-Kiyono-mura (定訳不明)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born as the fifth daughter (the youngest of nine children) of Tota KOBAYASHI who was a warrior class (a samurai belonged to the former Matsushiro Domain) in Kiyono-mura Village, Hanishina-gun County, Nagano Prefecture (presently known as Kiyono, Matsushiro-cho, Nagano City [Nagano Prefecture]).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました名字を大文字に修正しました表記方法、記号、スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born as the fifth daughter (the youngest of nine children) of Tota KOBAYASHI who was a warrior class (a samurai belonged to the former Matsushiro Domain) in Kiyono-mura Village, Hanishina-gun County, Nagano Prefecture (presently known as Kiyono, Matsushiro-cho, Nagano City [Nagano Prefecture]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>数え年6歳の時､上田町の長谷川家の養女となり､1900年上田の尋常小学校を卒業する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was adapted by the Hasegawa family in Ueda-cho when she was 6 years old (age by the traditional Japanese system) and graduated from a common elementary school in Ueda in 1900.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was adapted by the Hasegawa family in Ueda-cho when she was six years old (age by the traditional Japanese system) and graduated from a common elementary school in Ueda in 1900.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was adapted by the Hasegawa family in Ueda-cho when she was six years old (age by the traditional Japanese system) and graduated from a common elementary school in Ueda in 1900.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし養父が亡くなったため実家に戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, she returned to her biological paretnts after her foster father passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, she came back to her biological parents&apos; home after the death of her foster father.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, she came back to her biological parents&apos; home after the death of her foster father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>実家に戻った年､実父も亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her biological father also passed away in the same year of her return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her biological father also passed away in the same year she returned.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her biological father also passed away in the same year she returned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>数え年17歳の春に上京する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She moved to Tokyo when she was 17 years old (age by the traditional Japanese system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She moved to Tokyo when she was 17 years old (age by the traditional Japanese system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She moved to Tokyo when she was 17 years old (age by the traditional Japanese system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>1903年親戚の世話で最初の結婚をするが、1年で離婚している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She married with the man who was introduced by her relative in 1903; however, they were divorced within a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However she married a man who was introduced by her relative in 1903, they divorced within a year.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスを修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However she married a man who was introduced by her relative in 1903, they divorced within a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1908年に俳優養成所勤務の前澤誠助と結婚し、1909年、坪内逍遥の文芸協会演劇研究所第1期生となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She re-married with Seisuke MAEZAWA who was working at the Actors&apos; training center in 1908 and became a member of the inaugural class of the drama institute associated with the literary association established by Shoyo TSYBOUCHI in 1909.</e>
<cmt>前澤誠助-Seisuke MAEZAWA (定訳不明)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She remarried Seisuke MAEZAWA who was working for an actors&apos; training institute in 1908 and became a member of the inaugural class of the dramatic workshop of the literature association established by Shoyo TSUBOUCHI in 1909.</e>
<cmt>文法ミス、スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She remarried Seisuke MAEZAWA who was working for an actors&apos; training institute in 1908 and became a member of the inaugural class of the dramatic workshop of the literature association established by Shoyo TSUBOUCHI in 1909.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>演劇にのめり込む余り家事をおろそかにするようになり、前澤は彼女に愛想を尽かして離婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She devoted herself to acting and ofen neglected her household chores; therefore, MAEZAWA was disgusted and devorced her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She devoted herself to acting and often neglected her household chores, therefore, Maezawa was disgusted and divorced her.</e>
<cmt>文法、表記方法、スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She devoted herself to acting and often neglected her household chores, therefore, Maezawa was disgusted and divorced her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>1911年、『人形の家』の主人公ノラを演じて認められ、1913年、島村抱月と芸術座 (劇団)を旗揚げした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was recognized by playing Norah, a main character, in &quot;a Doll&apos;s House&quot; in 1911 and started Geijutsuza (Arts Theatre) with Hougetsu SHIMAMURA in 1913.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was recognized by playing Nora, a main character, in &quot;A Doll&apos;s House&quot; in 1911 and started Geijutsuza (Arts Theatre) with Hougetsu SHIMAMURA in 1913.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was recognized by playing Nora, a main character, in &quot;A Doll&apos;s House&quot; in 1911 and started Geijutsuza (Arts Theatre) with Hougetsu SHIMAMURA in 1913.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そして、『復活（小説)』（レフ・トルストイ原作、島村訳）のカチューシャ役が大当たりし、人気女優となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, her role as Katyusha in the play &quot;Resurrection (a novel)&quot; (by Leo TOLSTOY, translated by SHIMAMURA) was a huge hit and she became a popular actress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, her role as Katyusha in the play &quot;Resurrection (novel)&quot; (written by Lev Tolstoj, translated by Shimamura) made a huge hit and she became a popular actress.</e>
<cmt>文法ミス、スペルミスを修正しました不要なスペースを削除しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, her role as Katyusha in the play &quot;Resurrection (novel)&quot; (written by Lev Tolstoj, translated by Shimamura) made a huge hit and she became a popular actress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>彼女が歌った主題歌『カチューシャの唄（復活唱歌）』（抱月作詞・中山晋平作曲）のレコードも当時2万枚以上を売り上げる大ヒットとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A theme song &quot;Kachusha no uta (Katyusha song) (Resurrection-shoka Song)&quot; (song written by Hogetsu and composed by Shimpei NAKAYAMA) sung by Sumako became a huge hit selling 20,000 records at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theme song &quot;Kachusha no uta (Katyusha song)&quot; (by composer Hougetsu and lyricist Shinpei NAKAYAMA) sung by Sumako became a huge hit and more than 20,000 records ware sold at that time.</e>
<cmt>補足部分を削除しました表現、スペルミスを修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theme song &quot;Kachusha no uta (Katyusha song)&quot; (by composer Hougetsu and lyricist Shinpei NAKAYAMA) sung by Sumako became a huge hit and more than 20,000 records ware sold at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このことから、須磨子は日本初の歌う女優となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Sumako was the first actress who could sing as well as act in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Sumako became the first Japanese actress who could sing.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Sumako became the first Japanese actress who could sing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>だが、1917年に発売したレコード『今度生まれたら』（北原白秋作詞）では、歌詞の中にある「かわい女子（おなご）と寝て暮らそ」の部分が当時の文部省により猥褻扱いされ、日本における発禁レコード第1号ともなってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the record &quot;If I am reborn&quot; (song written by Hakushu KITAHARA) released in 1917 became the first record which was banned because the part &quot;sleep and live with a cute girl&quot; in the song were considered as an obscene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, her record &quot;If I am reborn&quot; (lyrics by Hakushu KITAHARA) released in 1917 became the Japan&apos;s first banned record which was shut down by Ministry of Education at that time because the part &quot;sleep and live with a cute girl&quot; in the lyrics were considered as obscene.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, her record &quot;If I am reborn&quot; (lyrics by Hakushu KITAHARA) released in 1917 became the Japan&apos;s first banned record which was shut down by Ministry of Education at that time because the part &quot;sleep and live with a cute girl&quot; in the lyrics were considered as obscene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>1918年11月5日、スペインかぜで島村が病死すると、2ヶ月後の1919年1月5日、芸術座の道具部屋において自殺（縊死）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two months after SHIMAMURA died of the Spanish Flu on November 5, 1918, she committed suicide (by hanging) in an equipment room on January 5, 1919.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two months after Shimamura died of the Spanish Flu on November 5, 1918, she committed suicide (by hanging) in an equipment room on January 5, 1919.</e>
<cmt>表記方法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two months after Shimamura died of the Spanish Flu on November 5, 1918, she committed suicide (by hanging) in an equipment room on January 5, 1919.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>島村と不倫関係にあった彼女は、島村の墓に一緒に埋葬されることを望んでいたがそれは叶わず、彼女の墓は長野市松代町清野の小林家墓所（生家の裏山）にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her wish was to be buried with SHIMAMURA with whom she had been having an affair; however, she was instead buried at the KOBAYAHI family grave (located on the hill behind her birthplace) in Kiyono, Matsushiro-cho county in Nagano city. city.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although her wish was to be buried together with Shimamura with whom she had been having an affair, she was instead buried in a graveyard of the Kobayashi family (locates on the hill behind her birthplace) in Kiyono, Matsushiro-cho County in Nagano City.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました表記方法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although her wish was to be buried together with Shimamura with whom she had been having an affair, she was instead buried in a graveyard of the Kobayashi family (locates on the hill behind her birthplace) in Kiyono, Matsushiro-cho County in Nagano City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、新宿区弁天町の多聞院には分骨墓がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A portion of her ashes was burried at Tamonin in Benten-cho, Shinjuku Ward.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A portion of her ashes was buried in Tamonin Temple in Benten-cho Country, Shinjuku Ward.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A portion of her ashes was buried in Tamonin Temple in Benten-cho Country, Shinjuku Ward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>著作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary work</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>『牡丹刷毛』（1914年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Botanhake (Peony brush)&quot;(1914)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Botanhake&quot; (Peony brush) (1914)</e>
<cmt>記号の位置を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Botanhake&quot; (Peony brush) (1914)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kumoi(id:79799), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), PANYNJ(id:38638), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Woyzzeck(id:8923), 陽一(id:92099), 暇・カキコ(id:65563), Spiduction66(id:74316), Greenland4(id:114494), Hhst(id:13720), Akaloli(id:141644), 寒漁夫(id:99134), Sjyjd123(id:157028), ゐ(id:795), R28Bot(id:177951), Yas(id:739), Alexbot(id:157199), 絵鞠(id:56670), Klesha(id:203751), Mark-zero(id:48822), Donko(id:55382), Qurren(id:20140), Katsuya(id:21306), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>