<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>祇園女御</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gion no nyogo (Gion consort)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gion no nyogo (Gion consort)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gion no nyogo (Gion consort)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>祇園女御（ぎおんのにょうご　生没年未詳）は白河法皇の晩年の寵妃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gion no nyogo (date of birth and death unknown) was a favorite consort of the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gion no nyogo (date of birth and death unknown) was a favorite consort of the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gion no nyogo (year of birth and death unknown) was a favorite consort of the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa in his later years.</e>
<cmt>date of birth and death unknown をyear of birth and death unknown に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>源仲宗の妻、その子源惟清の妻、宮廷仕えの女房と諸説があるが、氏素性は未詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many opinions regarding her family background such as that she was wife of MINAMOTO no Nakamune, wife of Nakamune&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Korekiyo, or a nyobo (a court lady,) however, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many opinions regarding her family background, such as the opinion that she was the wife of MINAMOTO no Nakamune, the opinion that she was the wife of Nakamune&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Korekiyo, and the opinion that she was a nyobo (a court lady); however, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many opinions regarding her family background, such as the opinion that she was the wife of MINAMOTO no Nakamune, the opinion that she was the wife of Nakamune&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Korekiyo, and the opinion that she was a nyobo (a court lady); however, details are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>女御の宣旨は下されなかったが、居住地にちなんで祇園女御、または白河殿と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although no official permission to entitle as a Nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court, or a consort of an emperor) was given to her, she was called Gion no nyogo or Shirakawa dono after the places where she lived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although she was not given official permission to entitle as a Nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court, or a consort of an emperor), she was called Gion no nyogo or Shirakawa dono after the places where she lived.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although she was not given official permission to entitle as a Nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court, or a consort of an emperor), she was called Gion no nyogo or Shirakawa dono after the places where she lived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>長治2年（1105年）祇園社の南東に堂を建立して、丈六阿弥陀仏を安置し金銀珠玉で飾り立てるなど「天下美麗過差」の様は人々の耳目を驚かせたという（『中右記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1105, it is said that she built a hall at southeast of Gion-sha Shrine, placed Joroku Amidabutsu (Amitabha statue with the height of one jo and six shaku, about 4.85 m), and decorated it with gold, silver and gems and the state of &apos;unsuitably luxurious beauty&apos; which surprised the ears and eyes of the world (.&quot;Chuyuki&quot;, the diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1105, it is said that she built a hall at the southeast of Gion-sha Shrine, placed Joroku Amidabutsu (Amitabha statue with the height of one jo and six shaku, about 4.85 m), and decorated it with gold, silver, and gems and the state of &apos;unsuitably luxurious beauty&apos; which surprised the ears and eyes of the world (.&quot;Chuyuki&quot;, the diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada.)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1105, it is said that she built a hall at the southeast of Gion-sha Shrine, placed Joroku Amidabutsu (Amitabha statue with the height of one jo and six shaku, about 4.85 m), and decorated it with gold, silver, and gems and the state of &apos;unsuitably luxurious beauty&apos; which surprised the ears and eyes of the world (.&quot;Chuyuki&quot;, the diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>身辺には平正盛が早くから仕えていて、天永4年（1113年）10月1日に正盛が建立した六波羅蜜堂で一切経供養を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From early on, TAIRA no Masamori attended on her, and she had a mass service with a &apos;Complete Buddhist Scriptures&apos; on October 1 in 1113 at Rokuharamitsu-do hall which Masamori built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From early on, TAIRA no Masamori attended on her, and she had a mass service with &apos;Complete Buddhist Scriptures&apos; on October 1 in 1113 at Rokuharamitsu-do hall which Masamori built.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From early on, TAIRA no Masamori attended on her, and she had a mass service with Complete Buddhist Scriptures on October 1, 1113 at Rokuharamitsu-do hall which Masamori built.</e>
<cmt>シングルコーテーションを削除しました。October 1 in 1113 をOctober 1, 1113 に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原璋子（崇徳天皇・後白河天皇の生母、藤原璋子）を養女としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She made FUJIWARA no Shoshi (real mother of Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Goshirakawa) as an adopted daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She made FUJIWARA no Shoshi (real mother of Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Goshirakawa) an adopted daughter.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She made Kentaimon-in (FUJIWARA no Shoshi, real mother of Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Goshirakawa) an adopted daughter.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA no Shoshi をKentaimon-in に修正しました（※）。※原文には「藤原璋子」とありますが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「待賢門院」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E7%A5%87%E5%9C%92%E5%A5%B3%E5%BE%A1</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>太上法皇崩御の際は、他の女房らと素服を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time when the Cloistered Retired Emperor demised, she was given white clothes (mourning attire) together with other nyobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time when the Cloistered Retired Emperor demised, she was given white clothes (mourning attire) together with other nyobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time when the Cloistered Retired Emperor demised, she was given white clothes (mourning attire) together with other nyobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>『古事談』には、祇園女御の食事に鮮鳥を差し出すことを平忠盛に命じられた加藤大夫成家が、主人からの処罰を逃れるためにあえて白河天皇の殺生禁断令を破った話が伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past), there is a tradition that Kato dayu Nariie, who was told by TAIRA no Masamori to serve fresh meat of fowl as a meal of Gion no nyogo, Nariie daringly breached the ban on killing animas and fishes imposed by Emperor Shirakawa in order to avoid punishments from his master.</e>
<cmt>用語集では読み不明となっていますが、これに倣っています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past), there is a tradition that Kato dayu Nariie, who was told by TAIRA no Masamori to serve fresh meat of fowl as a meal of Gion no nyogo, Nariie daringly breached the ban on killing animals and fishes imposed by Emperor Shirakawa in order to avoid punishments from his master.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past), there is a tradition that Kato dayu Nariie, who was told by TAIRA no Masamori to serve fresh meat of fowl as a meal of Gion no nyogo, Nariie daringly breached the ban on killing animals and fishes imposed by Emperor Shirakawa in order to avoid punishments from his master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>祇園女御は、妹の子である平清盛を猶子にしたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Gion no nyogo made Kiyomori TAIRA, who was a child of her younger sister, as her adopted son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Gion no nyogo made Kiyomori TAIRA, who was a child of her younger sister, her adopted son.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Gion no nyogo made Kiyomori TAIRA, who was a child of her younger sister, her adopted son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>清盛が通常の尉ではなく兵衛府に任官されたのも、祇園女御の後押しがあったためといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the reason why Kiyomori was not appointed to an ordinary rank of &apos;jo&apos; (Lieutenant) but to a higher rank of a officer of Hyoe-fu (Headquarters of the Middle Palace Guards) was that there was support of Gion no nyogo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the reason why Kiyomori was not appointed to an ordinary rank of &apos;jo&apos; (Lieutenant) but to a higher rank of a officer of Hyoe-fu (Headquarters of the Middle Palace Guards) was that he had the support of Gion no nyogo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the reason why Kiyomori was not appointed to an ordinary rank of &apos;jo&apos; (Lieutenant) but to a higher rank of a officer of Hyoe-fu (Headquarters of the Middle Palace Guards) was that he had the support of Gion no nyogo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>