<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原頼長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yorinaga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yorinaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yorinaga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 頼長（ふじわら の よりなが、保安 (日本)元年（1120年） - 保元元年7月14日 (旧暦)（1156年8月1日））は、平安時代末期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yorinaga (1120 – August 1, 1156) was a court noble at the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yorinaga (1120 – August 1, 1156) was a court noble at the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yorinaga (1120 – August 8, 1156) was a court noble at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原忠実の次男で、母は土佐守藤原盛実の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second son of FUJIWARA no Tadazane and his mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Morizane, the Governor of Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Tadazane and his mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Morizane, the Governor of Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of FUJIWARA no Tadazane and his mother was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Morizane, the Governor of Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正室は権中納言藤原実能の娘・幸子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legal wife was Yukiko, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi, a Gonno-chunagon (Provisional Middle Councilor) at court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legal wife was Yukiko, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi, a Gonno-chunagon (Provisional Middle Councilor) at court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legal wife was Yukiko, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi, a Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) at court.</e>
<cmt>Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>関白・藤原忠通の異母弟で、1125年にその猶子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger half brother was FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, a Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) and in 1125 was adopted by the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger half brother was FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, a Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) who in 1125 was adopted by the family.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger half brother was FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, a Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) who in 1125 was adopted by the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幼名は菖蒲若。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Ayawaka (Lit. Iris Youth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Ayawaka (Lit. Iris Youth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Ayawaka (Lit. Iris Youth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>世に悪左府、宇治左大臣という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Widely known as the Aku-safu (&quot;evil&quot; Minister of the Left) and Uji-sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Widely known as the Aku-safu (&quot;evil&quot; Minister of the Left) and Uji-sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Widely known as the Aku-safu (&quot;evil&quot; Minister of the Left) and Uji-sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lifetime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大治5年（1130年）に元服して従五位に叙せられ、侍従・近衛少将・伊予権守などに任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1130 he was conferred the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) at his coming of age ceremony and, was appointed as: Jiju (chamberlain), Konoe-shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Palace Guards and Iyo-gonno-kami (Senior Provincial Governor of Iyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1130 he was conferred the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) at his coming of age ceremony and was appointed: Jiju (chamberlain), Konoe-shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Palace Guards), and Iyo-gonno-kami (Senior Provincial Governor of Iyo).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1130 he was conferred the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) at his coming of age ceremony and was appointed: Jiju (chamberlain), Konoe no shosho (Minor Captain of the Palace Guards), and Iyo no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Iyo Province).</e>
<cmt>近衛少将→Konoe no shosho (Minor Captain of the Palace Guards)伊予権守→Iyo no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Iyo Province)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同年、右近衛権中将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year he was made Ukonoe-gonno-chujo (Lieutenant General of the Inner Palace Guards, right division).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year he was made Ukonoe-gonno-chujo (Lieutenant General of the Inner Palace Guards, right division).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year he was made Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>右近衛権中将→Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1131年に従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1131 achieved Jusan-i (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1131 achieved Jusan-i (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1131 achieved Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Jusanmiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>翌年参議を経ずに権中納言に昇進して、8歳年上の藤原実能の娘・幸子を娶った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to role of Chunagon (Middle Counselor) without going through the Sangi (royal adviser), and takes Sachiko (eight years his senior) daughter of FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi as his wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to post of Chunagon (Middle Counselor) without going through the post of Sangi (royal adviser), and took Sachiko (eight years his senior) daughter of FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi as his wife.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Promoted to post of Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) without going through the post of Sangi (royal adviser), and took Sachiko (eight years his senior) daughter of FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi as his wife.</e>
<cmt>権中納言 = Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1134年に大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1134 becomes Dainagon (Major Councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1134 became Dainagon (Major Councilor).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1134 became Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>大納言 = Dainagon (chief councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1136年には内大臣、右近衛大将を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1136 takes on the dual roles of: Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) and Ukone-no-taisho (Major Captain of the Right Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1136 took on the dual roles of Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) and Ukone-no-taisho (Major Captain of the Right Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1136 took on the dual roles of Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) and Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>右近衛大将→Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1139年には東宮傅となり左近衛大将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1139 as Sakone-no-taisho (Major Captain of the Left Palace Guards) becomes Togufu (Tutor of the Imperial Prince).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1139, as Sakone-no-taisho (Major Captain of the Left Palace Guards), he became Togufu (Tutor of the Imperial Prince).</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1139, as Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), he became togu no fu (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>東宮傅→togu-no-fu (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince)左近衛大将→Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>頼長は幼時より令名高く、膨大な和漢の書を読み「日本一の大学生、和漢の才に富む」（にっぽんいちのだいがくしょう、わかんのざえにとむ）とその学識の高さを評された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was held in high repute from the time Yorinaga was in the cradle, was extensively read in Japanese and Chinese literature and highly regarded as a scholar &quot;The most advanced student in Japan endowed with the talents in Japanese and Chinese literature&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was held in high repute from the time Yorinaga was in the cradle; he was extensively read in Japanese and Chinese literature and highly regarded as a scholar, &quot;The most advanced student in Japan endowed with the talents in Japanese and Chinese literature&quot;.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was held in high repute from the time Yorinaga was in the cradle; he was extensively read in Japanese and Chinese literature and highly regarded as a scholar, &apos;The most advanced student in Japan endowed with the talents in Japanese and Chinese literature.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかしながら、彼は酷薄で他人に容赦のない性格でもあり「腹黒く、よろずにきわどき人」とも評され、悪左府と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was also seen as possessing an unforgiving and callous nature towards others &quot;A mean and generally dangerous person&quot; and called the Aku-safu (&quot;evil&quot; Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was also seen as possessing an unforgiving and callous nature towards others, &quot;A mean and generally dangerous person&quot; and was called the Aku-safu (&quot;evil&quot; Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was also seen as possessing an unforgiving and callous nature towards others, &apos;A mean and generally dangerous person&apos; and was called the Aku-safu (&quot;evil&quot; Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて”を&apos;に訂正しました。全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、儒学を好み誰しもが認める博識であったが、意外にも文学を不得手としており、「和歌の道に堪えず」と公言して漢詩も得意ではなかったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said everyone was aware of his liking for Confucianism and his extensive knowledge but, he expressed a surprising lack of skill with literature declaring that he &quot;Couldn`t stand traditional Japanese waka poetry&quot; and that Chinese poetry was also not his forte.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that everyone was aware of his liking of Confucianism and his extensive knowledge, but he expressed a surprising lack of skill with literature, declaring that he &quot;Couldn`t stand traditional Japanese waka poetry&quot; and that Chinese poetry was also not his forte.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that everyone was aware of his liking of Confucianism and his extensive knowledge, but he expressed a surprising lack of skill with literature, declaring that he &apos;couldn&apos;t stand traditional Japanese waka poetry&apos; and that Chinese poetry was also not his forte.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>父忠実は温厚な関白の兄忠通を嫌い、才能溢れた弟の頼長を偏愛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Tadazane disliked his elder brother Tadamichi who was a mild-mannered Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) and, favored his extremely gifted younger brother Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Tadazane, disliked his elder brother Tadamichi, who was a mild-mannered Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor), and favored his extremely gifted younger brother Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Tadazane, disliked his elder brother Tadamichi, who was a mild-mannered Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor), and favored his extremely gifted younger brother Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>忠通は頼長の23歳上だったため、頼長はかつて忠通の養子だったこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamichi being 23 years older than Yorinaga meant that at one stage Yorinaga was just like Tadamichi&apos;s adopted son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamichi&apos;s being 23 years older than Yorinaga meant that at one stage Yorinaga was just like Tadamichi&apos;s adopted son.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamichi&apos;s being 23 years older than Yorinaga meant that at one stage Yorinaga was just like Tadamichi&apos;s adopted son.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし1143年、忠通に実子近衛基実が生まれるとその関係に終止符が打たれ、忠通と頼長は出世を競うようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, once Tadamichi&apos;s real son Motozane KONOE was born in 1143, this relationship was bought to a grinding halt with Tadamichi and Yorinaga subsequently competing for advancement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, once Tadamichi&apos;s real son Motozane KONOE was born in 1143, this relationship was bought to a grinding halt with Tadamichi and Yorinaga subsequently competing for advancement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, once Tadamichi&apos;s real son Motozane KONOE was born in 1143, this relationship was bought to a grinding halt with Tadamichi and Yorinaga subsequently competing for advancement.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>1149年、左大臣に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to Sadaijin (Minister of the Left)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoted to Sadaijin (Minister of the Left)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Promoted to Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 1149.</e>
<cmt>in 1149.補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>同年、忠実は忠通の藤氏長者の地位を頼長へとって与える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year Tadazane handed over Tadamichi&apos;s position as head of the Fujiwara Clan to Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year Tadazane handed over Tadamichi&apos;s position as head of the Fujiwara Clan to Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year Tadazane handed over Tadamichi&apos;s position as head of the Fujiwara clan to Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。Clan小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>1150年、頼長は源為義・源頼賢の兵を率いて忠通の別邸を襲って氏長者の印たる朱器台盤を奪い、これらを忠実は摂関家ゆかりの東三条殿ともに頼長に渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1150, Yorinaga took command of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi and MINAMOTO no Yorikata&apos;s troops and attacked Tadamichi&apos;s villa and made off with the head clansman&apos;s seal and family treasures and Tadazane took them to the Sekkan regent family&apos;s Higashi-Sanjodono estate and handed them over to Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1150, Yorinaga took command of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi&apos;s and MINAMOTO no Yorikata&apos;s troops, attacked Tadamichi&apos;s villa, and made off with the head clansman&apos;s seal and family treasures; Tadazane took them to the Sekkan regent family&apos;s Higashi-Sanjodono estate and handed them over to Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1150, Yorinaga took command of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi&apos;s and MINAMOTO no Yorikata&apos;s troops, attacked Tadamichi&apos;s villa, and made off with the head clansman&apos;s seal and family treasures; Tadazane took them to the Sekkan regent family&apos;s Higashi-Sanjodono estate and handed them over to Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、この年には頼長は養女藤原多子を近衛天皇に入内させ外祖父になることを望んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also that year, with hopes of becoming a maternal grandfather, Yorinaga&apos; adopted daughter FUJIWARA no Masaruko was taken as wife by Emperor Konoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also that year, with hopes of becoming a maternal grandfather, Yorinaga gave over his adopted daughter FUJIWARA no Masaruko as the wife of Emperor Konoe.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also that year, with hopes of becoming a maternal grandfather, Yorinaga gave over his adopted daughter FUJIWARA no Masaruko as the wife of Emperor Konoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>1151年、忠実の尽力により頼長は内覧の宣旨を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1151, thanks to Tadazane&apos;s efforts, Yorinaga was proclaimed as Internal Auditor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1151, thanks to Tadazane&apos;s efforts, Yorinaga was proclaimed Internal Auditor.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1151, thanks to Tadazane&apos;s efforts, Yorinaga was proclaimed Internal Auditor.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>更に忠実の長女で忠通の同母姉であった藤原泰子も頼長を可愛がって忠通を疎んじた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Tadazane&apos;s eldest daughter FUJIWARA no Yasuko (who was also Yorimichi&apos;s sister) was fond of Yorinaga but distanced herself from Yorimichi. Yorinaga gave her possession of the Higashi-Sanjodono estate and Sekkan regent family&apos;s Tsuchi-Mikadodono estate sites.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Tadazane&apos;s eldest daughter, FUJIWARA no Yasuko, (who was also Yorimichi&apos;s sister), was fond of Yorinaga but distanced herself from Yorimichi. Yorinaga gave her possession of the Higashi-Sanjodono estate and Sekkan regent family&apos;s Tsuchi-Mikadodono estate sites.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Tadazane&apos;s eldest daughter, FUJIWARA no Yasuko, (who was also Yorimichi&apos;s sister), was fond of Yorinaga but distanced herself from Yorimichi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>頼長は彼女が所有していた東三条殿と並ぶ摂関家の拠点土御門殿を譲られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinaga was given her possession of the Higashi-Sanjodono estate and Sekkan regent family&apos;s Tsuchi-Mikadodono estate sites.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理全角の’を半角にしました。was givenとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>執政の座についた頼長は朝議復興に辣腕を振るい、学術の再興に務め、鳥羽天皇の寵幸を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once in place as administrator, Yorinaga acted shrewdly by reviving the deliberations of the court, applied himself to reviving scholarship, which received the blessings of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once in place as administrator, Yorinaga acted shrewdly by reviving the deliberations of the court and applied himself to reviving scholarship, which received the blessings of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once in place as administrator, Yorinaga acted shrewdly by reviving the deliberations of the court and applied himself to reviving scholarship, which received the blessings of Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかしながら、近衛天皇は頼長をあからさまに嫌っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was obvious that Emperor Konoe disliked Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was obvious that Emperor Konoe disliked Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was obvious that Emperor Konoe disliked Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>またこの年、家人に命じて鳥羽法皇の寵臣である藤原家成の邸宅を破壊させるという行為に及んでおり、これを境に徐々に法皇からの信頼を失っていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also that year, he committed a deed of ordering family members to destroy the residence of FUJIWARA no Ienari who was a favorite retainer of Cloistered Emperor Toba the upshot being from that point onwards he gradually lost the confidence of the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also that year, he committed a deed of ordering family members to destroy the residence of FUJIWARA no Ienari, who was a favorite retainer of Cloistered Emperor Toba, the upshot being from that point onwards he gradually lost the confidence of the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also that year, he committed a deed of ordering family members to destroy the residence of FUJIWARA no Ienari, who was a favorite retainer of Cloistered Emperor Toba, the upshot being from that point onwards he gradually lost the confidence of the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>1155年、近衛天皇が子なく崩御し、忠通と法皇の寵姫藤原得子の推す後白河天皇が即位すると状況は一変する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1155 the childless Emperor Konoe passed away and Tadamichi and the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s favorite concubine FUJIWARA no Nariko supported the ascension of Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s however, once enthroned, circumstances completely changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1155 the childless Emperor Konoe passed away and Tadamichi and the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s favorite concubine FUJIWARA no Nariko supported the ascension of Emperor Goshirakawa; however, once enthroned, circumstances completely changed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1155 the childless Emperor Konoe passed away and Tadamichi and the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s favorite concubine FUJIWARA no Nariko supported the ascension of Emperor Goshirakawa; however, once enthroned, circumstances completely changed.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>近衛天皇崩御のおりに頼長が呪詛したとの噂が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the death of Emperor Konoe, rumors surfaced that Yorinaga was cursed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the death of Emperor Konoe, rumors surfaced that Yorinaga was cursed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the death of Emperor Konoe, rumors surfaced that Yorinaga was cursed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>口寄せによって現れた天皇の霊は「何者かが自分を呪うために愛宕山 (京都市)の天公像の目に釘を打った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a Sharman kuchiyose medium, the Emperor&apos;s ghost had appeared bewailing &quot;Someone cursed me by driving nails into the eyes of the Tenko (celestial fox) statue on Mt Atago (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a Sharman kuchiyose medium, the Emperor&apos;s ghost had appeared bewailing &quot;Someone cursed me by driving nails into the eyes of the Tenko (celestial fox) statue on Mt Atago (Kyoto).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a Sharman kuchiyose medium, the Emperor&apos;s ghost had appeared bewailing &apos;Someone cursed me by driving nails into the eyes of the Tenko (celestial fox) statue on Mt Atago (Kyoto).&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。原文の「」に合せて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>このため、自分は眼病を患い、ついに亡くなるに及んだ」と述べ、調べてみると確かに釘が打ちつけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That&apos;s why I was inflicted with eye disease and in due course died&quot;. Upon checking, it was found that nails had in fact been driven into the statue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;That&apos;s why I was inflicted with eye disease and in due course died.&quot; Upon checking, it was found that nails had in fact been driven into the statue.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That&apos;s why I was inflicted with eye disease and in due course died,&apos; upon checking, it was found that nails had in fact been driven into the statue.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて”を&apos;に訂正しました。全角の’を半角にしました。コンマ補足しました。upon小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>住僧に尋ねてみると「5、6年前の夜中に誰かが打ち付けた」と答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Chief Priest was queried her responded &quot;5 or 6 years ago in the middle of the night, someone drove nails into it&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Chief Priest was queried, she responded, &quot;5 or 6 years ago in the middle of the night, someone drove nails into it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Chief Priest was queried, she responded, &apos;5 or 6 years ago in the middle of the night, someone drove nails into it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>忠通と美福門院が、これは頼長の仕業であると述べ、それを信じた法皇は頼長に対する信を失い、内覧を停止され事実上失脚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamichi and the Bifukumonin Temple said this was the work of Yorinaga. Believing this, the Cloistered Emperor lost all confidence in Yorinaga, ceased private audiences with him and in effect Yorinaga was overthrown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamichi and the Bifukumonin Temple said that this was the work of Yorinaga. Believing this, the Cloistered Emperor lost all confidence in Yorinaga, ceased private audiences with him, and in effect Yorinaga was overthrown.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamichi and the Bifukumonin Temple said that this was the work of Yorinaga. Believing this, the Cloistered Emperor lost all confidence in Yorinaga, ceased private audiences with him, and in effect Yorinaga was overthrown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>更に高陽院も病没して後ろ盾を失った頼長は宇治への蟄居を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Kayanoin also passed away and, having lost a major supporter, Yoshinaga was inevitably kept under house-arrest at Uji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Kayanoin also passed away, and, having lost a major supporter, Yoshinaga was inevitably kept under house-arrest at Uji.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Kayanoin also passed away, and, having lost a major supporter, Yoshinaga was inevitably kept under house-arrest at Uji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>頼長は局面の打開のため、嘗て鳥羽法皇から無理強いで譲位させられて以来失意にあった崇徳天皇に接近する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To break this deadlocked state of affairs, Yorinaga was forced by the Cloistered Emperor Toba to abdicate and afterwards drew closer to a despairing Emperor Sutoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To break this deadlocked state of affairs, Yorinaga was forced by the Cloistered Emperor Toba to abdicate and afterwards he drew closer to a despairing Emperor Sutoku.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To break this deadlocked state of affairs, Yorinaga was forced by the Cloistered Emperor Toba to abdicate and afterwards he drew closer to a despairing Emperor Sutoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>1156年、鳥羽法皇が崩御すると政権奪取を図り、崇徳上皇の御所白河殿に源為義・平忠正・源頼憲らの武士を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1156 with the death of Cloistered Emperor Toba, he planned to usurp political power and, brought together samurai warriors (including Minamoto no Tameyoshi, TAIRA no Masatada and MINAMOTO no Yorinori) at Retired Emperor Sutoku&apos;s Gosho Shirakawadono (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1156, with the death of Cloistered Emperor Toba, he planned to usurp political power and brought together samurai warriors (including Minamoto no Tameyoshi, TAIRA no Masatada and MINAMOTO no Yorinori) at Retired Emperor Sutoku&apos;s Gosho Shirakawadono (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1156, with the death of Cloistered Emperor Toba, he planned to usurp political power and brought together samurai warriors (including Minamoto no Tameyoshi, TAIRA no Masatada and MINAMOTO no Yorinori) at Retired Emperor Sutoku&apos;s Gosho Shirakawadono (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>後白河天皇も源義朝・平清盛らを集め一触即発の緊張が高まり、保元の乱が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa also brought together MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, TAIRA no Kiyomori and others leading to an explosively tense situation and outbreak of the Hogen no ran (Hogen Rebellion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Goshirakawa also brought together MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, TAIRA no Kiyomori, and others, leading to an explosively tense situation and the outbreak of the Hogen no ran (Hogen Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa also brought together MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, TAIRA no Kiyomori, and others, leading to an explosively tense situation and the outbreak of the Hogen no ran (Hogen Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>戦闘は数に勝る天皇方の勝利に終わり、頼長は源重貞の放った矢が眼にあたり重傷を負う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor&apos;s side was superior in a number of battles leading to ultimate victory and, Yorinaga received a serious injury when hit in the eye by an arrow fired by MINAMOTO no Shigesada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor&apos;s side was superior in a number of battles, leading to ultimate victory, and Yorinaga received a serious injury when hit in the eye by an arrow fired by MINAMOTO no Shigesada.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor&apos;s side was superior in a number of battles, leading to ultimate victory, and Yorinaga received a serious injury when hit in the eye by an arrow fired by MINAMOTO no Shigesada.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>逃れて父忠実に対面を望むがこれを拒まれ、失意のうちに舟中で死んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whilst escaping he sought a meeting with his father Tadazane but, this was declined and he died in despair on board a boat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whilst escaping he sought a meeting with his father Tadazane, but this was declined and he died in despair on board a boat.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whilst escaping he sought a meeting with his father Tadazane, but this was declined and he died in despair on board a boat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="43">
<j>頼長の死後、長男藤原兼長・次男藤原師長・三男藤原隆長・四男範長は全て地方へ流罪となり、師長を除く三人はそれぞれの配所にて亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yorinaga&apos;s death, his eldest son FUJIWARA no Kanenaga, second son FUJIWARA no Moronaga, third son FUJIWARA no Takanaga and fourth son Norinaga were all banished to the countryside and with the exception of Moronaga, the other 3 died in their place of exile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yorinaga&apos;s death, his eldest son FUJIWARA no Kanenaga, second son FUJIWARA no Moronaga, third son FUJIWARA no Takanaga, and fourth son Norinaga were all banished to the countryside, and with the exception of Moronaga, they died in their place of exile.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yorinaga&apos;s death, his eldest son FUJIWARA no Kanenaga, second son FUJIWARA no Moronaga, third son FUJIWARA no Takanaga, and fourth son Norinaga were all banished to the countryside, and with the exception of Moronaga, they died in their place of exile.</e>
<cmt>全角の’を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>唯一生き残って都に戻ることが出来た師長は、後に父・頼長でさえ果たせなかった太政大臣にまで昇進するものの、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He alone survived and returned to the Miyako capital (Kyoto) however, having done so Moronaga was afterwards unable to perform as his father having been elevated to the Dajodaijin (Prime Minister) role. Later his lifetime was buffeted by trials and tribulations with shogun Kiyomori banishing him once again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moronaga alone survived and returned to the Miyako capital (Kyoto); however, having done so, he was afterwards unable to perform as his father, having been elevated to the Dajodaijin (Prime Minister) role. Later his lifetime was buffeted by trials and tribulations with shogun Kiyomori banishing him once again.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moronaga alone survived and returned to the Miyako capital (Kyoto); however, having done so, he was afterwards unable to perform as his father, having been elevated to the Daijo daijin (Grand minister of state) role.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理太政大臣→Daijo daijin (Grand minister of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>今度は平清盛によって再度流罪にされるなど波乱の生涯を送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later his lifetime was buffeted by trials and tribulations with shogun Kiyomori banishing him once again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>登場作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Screen Productions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Screen Productions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Screen Productions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>『弓張月』（1955年 監督：丸根賛太郎、演：堀正夫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yumiharizuki&quot;, 1955, Director: Santaro MARUNE, Actor: Masao HORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yumiharizuki&quot;, 1955, Director: Santaro MARUNE, Actor: Masao HORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yumiharizuki&quot;, 1955, Director: Santaro MARUNE, Actor: Masao HORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>『新・平家物語 (映画)』（1955年 監督：溝口健二、演：千田是也）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The New Tale of the Heike&quot; (Movie): 1955, Director: Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Actor: Koreya SENDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The New Tale of the Heike&quot; (Movie): 1955, Director: Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Actor: Koreya SENDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The New Tale of the Heike&quot; (Movie): 1955, Director: Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Actor: Koreya SENDA.</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>『新・平家物語 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1972年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：成田三樹夫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The New Tale of the Heike&quot; (NHK Taiga Drama): 1972 NHK Taiga Drama, Staring: Mikio NARITA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The New Tale of the Heike&quot; (NHK Taiga Drama): 1972 NHK Taiga Drama, Starring: Mikio NARITA.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The New Tale of the Heike&quot; (NHK Taiga Drama): 1972 NHK Taiga Drama, Starring: Mikio NARITA.</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>『平清盛 (TBSドラマ)』（1992年 TBS、演：神山繁）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;TAIRA no Kiyomori&quot; (TBS drama) 1972, TBS, Staring: Shigeru KOYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;TAIRA no Kiyomori&quot; (TBS drama) 1972, TBS, Starring: Shigeru KOYAMA</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;TAIRA no Kiyomori&quot; (TBS drama) 1972, TBS, Starring: Shigeru KOYAMA</e>
<cmt>全角の”を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Lonicera(id:20638), Kawai(id:5634), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Andee(id:20421), Loveheian(id:175268), Anton21(id:158479), 小者(id:172526), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), 玄史生(id:43670), 代言人(id:33675), Point136(id:211299), Avxz(id:123412), 小川尚明(id:93076), Kouko0515(id:100370), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>