<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平時忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitada</e>
<cmt>「平時忠→TAIRA-no-Tokitada」は、これまでのファイルに合わせ、「TAIRA no Tokitada」とハイフンなしで表記します。その他の人名についても同様です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tokitada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 時忠（たいら の ときただ）は、平安時代末期の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitada was a noble who lived during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tokitada was a noble who lived during the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitada was a court noble who lived during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>桓武平氏高棟流、いわゆる堂上家の生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Takamune branch of the Kanmu Taira clan, so-called Dojo family (a Court noble family which has a hereditary right to be admitted to the Court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Takamune branch of the Kanmu Taira clan, a so-called Dojo family (a Court noble family which has a hereditary right to be admitted to the Court).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Takamune branch of Kanmu-Heishi (TAIRA clan), a so-called Dojo family (a Court noble family which has a hereditary right to be admitted to the Court).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は兵部権大輔・平時信。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was TAIRA no Tokinobu, who was Hyobu gon no taifu (an official of the Ministry of Military).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was TAIRA no Tokinobu, who was Hyobu gon no taifu (an official of the Ministry of the Military).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was TAIRA no Tokinobu, who was Hyobu no Gon no Taifu (provisional senior assistant minister of Hyobusho Ministry of Military).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は二条大宮（令子内親王）の半物（はしたもの、下仕えの女房）をしていた女性（氏素性は未詳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a lady who worked as a hashita mono (a lower-ranked court lady) for Empress Dowager Nijo (Imperial Princess Reishi); her family background is not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother worked as a hashita mono (lower-ranked court lady) for Empress Dowager Nijo (Imperial Princess Reishi); her family background is not known.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother worked as a hashita mono (lower-ranked court lady) for Nijo no Omiya (Imperial Princess Reishi); her family background is not known.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>兄弟に平親宗、姉妹に平時子（清盛の室）・平滋子（建春門院）・冷泉局（建春門院女房）・清子（宗盛の室）・坊門殿（重盛の室、維盛母の可能性あり）・藤原親隆の室（権少僧都・全真の母）・帥局（建礼門院女房）、室に藤原領子（むねこ）、子に平時実、平時家、時宗、時定、宣子（後鳥羽天皇の典侍）、源義経の側室、中山忠親の室らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a brother, TAIRA no Chikamune, and sisters TAIRA no Tokiko (Kiyomori&apos;s wife), TAIRA no Shigeko (Kenshunmonin), Reizei no Tsubone (a court lady for Kenshunmonin), Kiyoko (Munemori&apos;s wife), Bomon-dono (Shigemori&apos;s wife; she could be Koremori&apos;s mother), wife of FUJIWARA no Chikataka (mother of Gon shosozu, Zenshin), and Sochi no Tsubone (court lady for Kenreimonin); his wife was FUJIWARA no Muneko; and, he had sons, TAIRA no Tokizane, TAIRA no Tokiie, TAIRA no Tokimune and TAIRA no Tokisada, and daughters, Noriko (later, tenji (a maid of honor of the first rank) to the Emperor Gotoba), MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s concubine and Tadachika NAKAYAMA&apos;s wife..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had one brother, TAIRA no Chikamune, and sisters TAIRA no Tokiko (Kiyomori&apos;s wife), TAIRA no Shigeko (Kenshunmonin), Reizei no Tsubone (a court lady for Kenshunmonin), Kiyoko (Munemori&apos;s wife), Bomon-dono (Shigemori&apos;s wife; she may have been Koremori&apos;s mother), wife of FUJIWARA no Chikataka (mother of Gon shosozu, Zenshin), and Sochi no Tsubone (court lady for Kenreimonin); his wife was FUJIWARA no Muneko; and, he had sons, TAIRA no Tokizane, TAIRA no Tokiie, TAIRA no Tokimune, and TAIRA no Tokisada, and daughters, Noriko (later, tenji (a maid of honor of the first rank) to the Emperor Gotoba), MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s concubine, and Tadachika NAKAYAMA&apos;s wife..</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had one brother, TAIRA no Chikamune, and sisters TAIRA no Tokiko (Kiyomori&apos;s wife), TAIRA no Shigeko (Kenshunmonin), Reizei no Tsubone (a court lady for Kenshunmonin), Kiyoko (Munemori&apos;s wife), Bomon-dono (Shigemori&apos;s wife; she may have been Koremori&apos;s mother), wife of FUJIWARA no Chikataka (mother of gon shosozu (Junior lesser prelate), Zenshin), and Sochi no Tsubone (court lady for Kenreimonin); his wife was FUJIWARA no Muneko; and, he had sons, TAIRA no Tokizane, TAIRA no Tokiie, Tokimune, and Tokisada, and daughters, Noriko (later, tenji (a maid of honor of the first rank) to the Emperor Gotoba), MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s concubine, and Tadachika NAKAYAMA&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドなどを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>平大納言、平関白と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Taira dainagon (Major Counselor Taira) or Taira kanpaku.(Imperial Regent Taira).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Taira dainagon (Major Counselor Taira) or Taira kanpaku.(Imperial Regent Taira).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Taira Dainagon (chief councilor of state) or Taira kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitada&apos;s Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tokitada&apos;s Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>生い立ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Backgrounds</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>時忠の母については『吉記』治承5年（1181年）5月28日条に、二条大宮（令子内親王）に仕えた半物であったことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to Tokitada&apos;s mother, it is recorded in the article for May 28, 1181 in &quot;Kikki&quot; (Tsunefusa YOSHIDA&apos;s diary) that she was a hashita mono who served Empress Dowager Nijo (Imperial Princess Reishi).</e>
<cmt>「『吉記』→&quot;Kikki&quot; (a diary of Tunefusa YOSHIDA)」は、他のファイルの例に合わせ 「”Kikki&quot; (Tsunefusa YOSHIDA&apos;s diary」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to Tokitada&apos;s mother, it is recorded in the article for May 28, 1181 in &quot;Kikki&quot; (Tsunefusa YOSHIDA&apos;s diary) that she was a hashita mono who served Empress Dowager Nijo (Imperial Princess Reishi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to Tokitada&apos;s mother, it is recorded in the article for July 18, 1181 in &quot;Kikki&quot; (Tsunefusa YOSHIDA&apos;s diary) that she was a hashita mono who served Nijo no Omiya (Imperial Princess Reishi).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この女性は時信との間に、時忠・時子・藤原親隆の室を産んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Tokinobu, this lady gave birth to Tokitada, Tokiko and the wife of FUJIWARA no Chikataka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Tokinobu, this lady gave birth to Tokitada, and Tokiko, the wife of FUJIWARA no Chikataka.</e>
<cmt>punctuation(assumed that Tokiko was the wife of FUJIWARA no Chikataka)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Tokinobu, this lady gave birth to Tokitada, Tokiko, and the wife of FUJIWARA no Chikataka.</e>
<cmt>「時子」と「藤原親隆の室」は別人なので、and の後のカンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>やがて時信との関係は疎遠となり、右少弁・藤原顕憲と再婚して法勝寺執行・能円を産む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In course of time their relationship became alienated and she remarried FUJIWARA no Akinori, ushoben (Second Assistant Controller of the Right) and gave birth to Noen, the shugyo (chief priest) of Hossho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「執行→working」は、「執行→shugyo (chief priest)」に訂正しました。「法勝寺→Hosho-ji Temple」は、「Hossho-ji Temple」に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In course of time their relationship became alienated and she remarried FUJIWARA no Akinori, ushoben (Second Assistant Controller of the Right) and gave birth to Noen, the shugyo (chief priest) of Hossho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In course of time their relationship became alienated and she remarried FUJIWARA no Akinori, Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) and gave birth to Noen, the shugyo (chief priest) of Hossho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>顕憲の死後、時忠と時子は母を引き取って孝養を尽くしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Akinori&apos;s death, reportedly, Tokitada and Tokiko took on their mother and attended on her with devotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Akinori&apos;s death, reportedly, Tokitada and Tokiko took on their mother and attended her with devotion.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Akinori&apos;s death, reportedly, Tokitada and Tokiko took on their mother and attended her with devotion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>時忠と時子の年齢については、『兵範記』仁安3年（1168年）2月11日条の清盛出家の記事の中に「相国今年五十一、二品四十三云々」とあるので、時子は大治元年（1126年）生まれとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to ages of Tokitada and Tokiko, an article on Kiyomori&apos;s becoming a priest for February 11,1168 in &quot;Heihanki&quot; (TAIRA no Nobumori&apos;s diary) reads as &quot;this year, the shokoku (prime minister) is 51 years old and the nihon (second ranked) is 43 years old...&quot;, and therefore Tokiko must be born in 1126.</e>
<cmt>「『兵範記』→&quot;Heihanki&quot; (A Diary of TAIRA-no-Nobunori)」は他のファイルの記載例に合わせて「&quot;Heihanki&quot; (TAIRA no Nobunori&apos;s diary)」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to ages of Tokitada and Tokiko, an article on Kiyomori&apos;s becoming a priest for February 11, 1168 in &quot;Heihanki&quot; (TAIRA no Nobumori&apos;s diary) reads, &quot;this year, the shokoku (prime minister) is 51 years old and the nihon (second ranked) is 43 years old...&quot;, and therefore Tokiko must have been born in 1126.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to ages of Tokitada and Tokiko, an article on Kiyomori&apos;s becoming a priest for March 29, 1168 in &quot;Heihanki&quot; (TAIRA no Nobumori&apos;s diary) reads, &apos;this year, the shokoku (prime minister) is 51 years old and the nihon (second ranked) is 43 years old...,&apos; and therefore Tokiko must have been born in 1126.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>記主の平信範は時子の叔父なので信憑性は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the writer, TAIRA no Nobunori was Tokiko&apos;s uncle, reliability of this article is quite high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the writer, TAIRA no Nobunori, was Tokiko&apos;s uncle, the reliability of this article is quite high.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the writer, TAIRA no Nobunori, was Tokiko&apos;s uncle, the reliability of this article is quite high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>時忠は『公卿補任』から逆算すれば、大治5年（1130年）生まれである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Counting backward from &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot; (a personnel directory of the court nobles), Tokitada must be born in 1130.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Counting backward from &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot; (a personnel directory of the court nobles), Tokitada must have been born in 1130.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Counting backward from &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot; (a personnel directory of the court nobles), Tokitada must have been born in 1130.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし『吾妻鏡』文治5年（1189年）3月5日条には、時忠の死去を聞いた頼朝が周囲の者に年齢を尋ねたところ、62歳という返事があったと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the article for March 5, 1189 in &quot;Azuma Kagami (Mirror of East)&quot;, it is recorded that, when Yoritomo heard about Tokitada&apos;s death, he asked people around him about Tokitada&apos;s age, the reply was 62 year old.</e>
<cmt>「『吾妻鏡』→”Azuma-kagami” (Mirror of East)」は、「平通盛」のファイルの「対訳欄」の表記に合わせ「Azuma Kagami (Mirror of East)」と表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the article for March 5, 1189 in &quot;Azuma Kagami (Mirror of East)&quot;, it is recorded that, when Yoritomo heard about Tokitada&apos;s death, he asked people around him about Tokitada&apos;s age, and the reply was 62 year old.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the article for March 30, 1189 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (Mirror of East), it is recorded that, when Yoritomo heard about Tokitada&apos;s death, he asked people around him about Tokitada&apos;s age, and the reply was 62 year old.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これによれば、時忠は大治3年（1128年）生まれとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this reply, Tokitada must be born in 1128.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this reply, Tokitada must have been born in 1128.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this reply, Tokitada must have been born in 1128.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>時忠の生年は確定できないが、いずれにしても時子が年長である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s year of birth cannot be ascertained, but Tokiko is elder to Tokitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada&apos;s year of birth cannot be ascertained, but Tokiko was elder to Tokitada.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s year of birth cannot be ascertained, but Tokiko was elder to Tokitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『保暦間記』にも「平大納言時忠ト申ハ、太政入道ノ北方二位殿ノ弟也」とあり、時忠が時子の弟であることは間違いないと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Horyakukanki&quot; (a history book of the 14th century in Japan), it is written that &quot;Taira no dainagon Tokitada is a younger brother of Niidono (second ranked) who is the wife of the dajonyudo (prime minister who became a priest)&quot; and, therefore, it seems sure that Tokitada was the younger brother of Tokiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Horyakukanki&quot; (a history book of 14th century Japan), it is written that &quot;Taira no dainagon Tokitada is the younger brother of the Niidono (the second ranked wife of the dajonyudo (prime minister who became a priest))&quot; and, therefore, it seems sure that Tokitada was the younger brother of Tokiko.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Horyakukanki&quot; (a history book of 14th century Japan), it is written that &apos;Taira no Dainagon Tokitada is the younger brother of Kita no kata, Niidono (the second ranked), of the dajonyudo (prime minister who became a priest))&apos; and, therefore, it seems sure that Tokitada was the younger brother of Tokiko.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>久安2年（1146年）3月、17歳で非蔵人、翌年正月に六位蔵人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, hi-kurodo (non-kurodo) at the age of 17 years old and in January, next year, he was appointed to a rokui kurodo (kurodo with the Sixth Rank)..</e>
<cmt>対訳欄の記載を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1146, he was appointed hi-kurodo (non-kurodo) at the age of 17 years old and in January, and the next year, he was appointed rokui kurodo (kurodo of the Sixth Rank)..</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1146, he was appointed the position of hikurodo (trainee in the Kurodo-dokoro, or the Imperial Secretariat) at the age of 17 years old and in February the next year, he was appointed the position of rokui kurodo (kurodo (Chamberlain) of the Sixth Rank).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>久安4年（1148年）から翌年にかけて検非違使左衛門少尉となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1148 or the next year, he became a kebiishi saemon shoi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, 1148, he became a kebiishi saemon shoi (police and judicial chief).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During 1148 and the following year, he assumed the position of kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) saemon shojo (junior lieutenant of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>久安5年（1149年）4月に叙爵して、蔵人・検非違使の任を離れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1149, he was ennobled and departed from jobs of the kurodo and kebiishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1149, he was ennobled and resigned from kurodo and kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1149, he was ennobled and resigned from kurodo and kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>時忠の若い頃の官歴には、取り立てて見るべきものはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is nothing important in Tokitada&apos;s official career in his youth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is nothing noterworthy about Tokitada&apos;s official career in his youth.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is nothing noteworthy about Tokitada&apos;s official career in his youth.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>非蔵人から六位蔵人となる階層の人物は、その階層で生涯を終えるのが通例だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was normal for persons who become from hi-kurodo to rokui kurodo to finish his life in such level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was normal for a person of the rank of hi-kurodo to rokui kurodo to finish his life at this level.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was normal for a person of the rank of hikurodo to rokui kurodo to finish his life at this level.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>父の時信が五位止まりで、母の身分も低いことから、時忠も本来ならそれ以上の昇進は望めなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As hits father, Tokinobu stopped at goi (Fifth Rank) and his mother&apos;s status was also low, Tokitada also could not expect promotion to higher rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his father, Tokinobu, had stopped at goi (Fifth Rank) and his mother&apos;s status was also low, Tokitada could not expect promotion to higher rank.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his father, Tokinobu, had stopped at goi (Fifth Rank) and his mother&apos;s status was also low, Tokitada could not expect promotion to higher rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そのため、姉の時子とその夫・清盛の庇護を受けていたと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is inferred that Tokitada was protected by his elder sister, Tokiko, and her husband, Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is inferred that Tokitada was protected by his elder sister, Tokiko, and her husband, Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is inferred that Tokitada was protected by his elder sister, Tokiko, and her husband, Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>仁平4年（1154年）8月8日の鳥羽法皇による新御堂法会・仏像安置の儀式に、時忠は清盛と共に院司として列席している（『兵範記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 8, 1154, Tokitada attended the ceremony of Buddhist religious service for new building for temple and enshrinement of Buddhist image held by Cloistered Emperor Toba, together with Kiyomori as inshi (officials of Imperial Agency) (&quot;Heihanki&quot;),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 8, 1154, Tokitada attended a Buddhist religious service for new building for temple and enshrinement of Buddhist image held by Cloistered Emperor Toba, together with Kiyomori, as inshi (officials of Imperial Agency) (&quot;Heihanki&quot;),</e>
<cmt>punctuation, rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 24, 1154, Tokitada attended a Buddhist religious service for new building for temple and enshrinement of Buddhist image held by Cloistered Emperor Toba, together with Kiyomori, as inshi (officials of Imperial Agency) (&quot;Heihanki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>憲仁擁立と配流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Supporting Norihito and Exile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supporting Norihito and Exile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Supporting Norihito and Exile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>平治の乱が終わり清盛の発言力が著しく高まった永暦元年（1160年）4月、時忠は検非違使右衛門権佐に抜擢された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1160, after the Heiji Disturbance was settled and Kiyomori&apos;s influence had remarkably increased, Tokitada was picked out to kebiishi uemon gon no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1160, after the Heiji Disturbance was settled and Kiyomori&apos;s influence had remarkably increased, Tokitada was picked out for promotion to kebiishi uemon gon no suke.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;promotion to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1160, after the Heiji War was settled and Kiyomori&apos;s influence had remarkably increased, Tokitada was picked out for promotion to kebiishi Uemon Gon no suke (provisional assistant captain of police and judicial chief of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>翌年正月には清盛が検非違使別当に就任して京都の治安維持の責任者となり、時忠は清盛の下で現場の指揮に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, next year, Kiyomori was installed as the kebiishi betto (a chief police and judicial official) and became in charge of maintenance of public order in Kyoto and Tokitada took command in the field under Kiyomori&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January of the next year, Kiyomori was installed as kebiishi betto (chief police and judicial official) and put in charge of maintaining public order in Kyoto, and Tokitada took command in the field under Kiyomori&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February of the next year, Kiyomori was installed as Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) and put in charge of maintaining public order in Kyoto, and Tokitada took command in the field under Kiyomori&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>さらに10月には右少弁も兼任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in October, he also served concurrently as the ushoben (second assistant controller of the right).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in October, he was assigned the additional post of ushoben (second assistant controller of the right).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in October, he was assigned the additional post of Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>高棟流平氏は実務官人の家系だったが、太政官の事務を処理する弁官を輩出していたのは別系統の平時範の子孫であり、時忠の系統は主に院や摂関家の家司として活動していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan of the Takamune branch was a family line to work as officials for practical works, but a large number of benkan who were in charge of office work of the Dajokan (Great Minister of the Council of State) were mainly from another line, offspring of TAIRA no Tokinori and people from the line to which Tokitada belonged worked mainly as keishi (officials of the agency of imperial family, noble, etc.) of In and Sekkannke.</e>
<cmt>家司の説明部分の英訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takamune branch of the Taira clan was a family line to work as officials for practical matters, but a large number of benkan who were in charge of office work of the Dajokan (Great Minister of the Council of State) were mainly from another line, offspring of TAIRA no Tokinori, and people from the line to which Tokitada belonged worked mainly as keishi (officials of the agency of imperial family, noble, etc.) of In and Sekkannke.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Taira clan of the Takamune branch&quot; to Takamune branch of the Taira clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takamune branch of the Taira clan was a family line to work as officials for practical matters, but a large number of benkan who were in charge of office work of the Dajokan (Great Minister of the Council of State) were mainly from another line, offspring of TAIRA no Tokinori, and people from the line to which Tokitada belonged worked mainly as keishi (officials of the agency of imperial family, noble, etc.) of In (retired emperors) and Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>時忠が弁官に任じられた要因としては、清盛の後押しのみならず、時忠本人の実務能力の高さも大きく作用したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the reasons why Tokitada was appointed to a benkan were not only backup by Kiyomori but also Tokitada&apos;s capability for practical works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The supposed reasons for Tokitada&apos;s appointment to benkan were not only backup by Kiyomori but also Tokitada&apos;s capability for practical matters.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The supposed reasons for Tokitada&apos;s appointment to benkan were not only backup by Kiyomori but also Tokitada&apos;s capability for practical matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>平治の乱の後、政治の主導権を巡って後白河上皇と二条天皇が激しく対立する中で、応保元年（1161年）9月3日、妹の滋子が後白河の第七皇子（憲仁、後の高倉天皇）を出産した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Heiji Disturbance, while the retired Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo keenly confronted with each other, on September 3, 1161, his younger sister, Shigeko gave birth to the seventh Imperial Prince (Norihito, later, Emperor Takakura) of Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Heiji Disturbance, while the retired Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo keenly confronted each other, on September 3, 1161, Tokitada&apos;s younger sister, Shigeko, gave birth to the seventh Imperial Prince (Norihito, later, Emperor Takakura) of Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Tokitada&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Heiji War, while the retired Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo keenly confronted each other, on September 30, 1161, Tokitada&apos;s younger sister, Shigeko, gave birth to the seventh Imperial Prince (Norihito, later, Emperor Takakura) of Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その直後の15日、時忠は清盛の弟・平教盛とともに二条により解官された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after that, on September 15, Tokitada was dismissed by Nijo together with TAIRA no Norimori, Kiyomori&apos;s younger brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after that, on September 15, Tokitada was dismissed by Nijo together with TAIRA no Norimori, Kiyomori&apos;s younger brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after that, on October 12, Tokitada was dismissed by Nijo together with TAIRA no Norimori, Kiyomori&apos;s younger brother.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>『愚管抄』によれば「ユユシキ過言」をしたのが原因であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Gukansho&quot;, the cause of this dismissal was &quot;seriously improper statement&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Gukansho&quot;, the cause of this dismissal was &quot;seriously improper statement&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), the cause of this dismissal was &apos;seriously improper statement.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その内容は定かでないが、甥である憲仁の立太子を公言した可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the contents of their statement are not known, there is a strong possibility that they stated about official investiture of their nephew, Norihito, to the Crown Prince..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the contents of their statement are not known, there is a strong possibility that they made a statement about official investiture of their nephew, Norihito, to Crown Prince..</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the contents of their statement are not known, there is a strong possibility that they made a statement about official investiture of their nephew, Norihito, to Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="38">
<j>この頃から時忠は清盛の思惑から外れ、独自の動きを見せるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around this time, Tokitada diverged from Kiyomori&apos;s intention and showed independent movements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around this time, Tokitada diverged from Kiyomori&apos;s intention and showed independent movements.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around this time, Tokitada diverged from Kiyomori&apos;s intention and showed independent movements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>翌年6月、院近臣・源資賢が二条を賀茂社で呪詛したとして解官されるが、時忠も陰謀に関わったとして23日に出雲国に配流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, next year, MINAMOTO no Sukekata, who was an In no kinshin (close aide of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakaka), was dismissed by the reason that he put the Kamo-sha Shrine a curse on Nijo, and Tokitada also was sentenced to exile to Izumo Province by the reason that Tokitada took part in this conspiracy.</e>
<cmt>「出雲国→Izumo-no-kuni (Izumo Province)」は、「平教経」、「平通盛」のファイルの表記に合わせて「出雲国→Ｉｚｕmo Ｐｒｏｖｉｎｃｅ」と表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June the next year, MINAMOTO no Sukekata, who was an In no kinshin (close aide of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakaka), was dismissed for putting a curse on Nijo at Kamo-sha Shrine, and Tokitada was also sentenced to exile in Izumo Province for taking part in this conspiracy.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July the next year, MINAMOTO no Sukekata, who was an In no kinshin (close aide of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa), was dismissed for putting a curse on Nijo at Kamo-sha Shrine, and Tokitada was also sentenced to exile in Izumo Province on August 12 for taking part in this conspiracy.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>教盛が短期間で赦免されたのに対してはるかに重い処罰であり、二条親政派が時忠を強く警戒していたことがうかがわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Norimori was remitted in a short period of time, punishment to Tokitada was very heavy and we can infer that the Nijo shinsei (direct administration by Emperor Nijo) group was strongly cautious about Tokitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Norimori was remitted a short time later, Tokitada&apos;s puinishment was very heavy and we can infer that the Nijo shinsei (direct administration by Emperor Nijo) group was strongly cautious about Tokitada.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Norimori was remitted a short time later, Tokitada&apos;s punishment was very heavy and we can infer that the Nijo shinsei (direct administration by Emperor Nijo) group was strongly cautious about Tokitada.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この事件で清盛は二条支持の立場をとり、時忠に手を差し伸べることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, Kiyomori too showed a stance to support Nijo and he did not help Tokitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, Kiyomori too showed a stance to support Nijo and he did not help Tokitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, Kiyomori too showed a stance to support Nijo and he did not help Tokitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="42">
<j>召還、公卿昇進</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Call-backl and Promotion to Kugyo (Court Noble)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recall and Promotion to Kugyo (Court Noble)</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recall and Promotion to Kugyo (Court Noble)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>永万元年（1165年）7月に二条が崩御すると、時忠は召還される（9月14日）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1165, when Nijo died, Tokitada was called back (September 14).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1165, when Nijo died, Tokitada was called back (September 14).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1165, when Nijo died, Tokitada was called back (October 27).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>翌仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）3月に本位に復すと、4月に左少弁、6月には右中弁・検非違使左衛門権佐・蔵人の三事兼帯となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returning to his original status In March 1166, he was appointed to sashoben (Second Assistant Controller of the Left) and, in June, he was appointed to three posts concurrently, uchuben (First Assistant Controller of the Right), kebiishi saemon gon no kami and kurodo.</e>
<cmt>「右中弁→Ushoben (Second Assistant Controller of the Right)」は、「Ｕｃｈｕｂｅｎ (First Assistant Controller of the Right」の誤りと判断し、そのように訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being restored to his original status In March 1166, he was appointed sashoben (Second Assistant Controller of the Left) and, in June, he was appointed to three posts concurrently, uchuben (First Assistant Controller of the Right), kebiishi saemon gon no kami, and kurodo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being restored to his original status in April 1166, he was appointed Sashoben (Second Assistant Controller of the Left) in May, and, in July, he was appointed to three posts concurrently, Uchuben (First Assistant Controller of the Right), kebiishi, Saemon no gon no suke (provisional assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), and kurodo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>10月10日には、5年前に果たせなかった憲仁親王の立太子が実現する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 10, official investiture of Imperial Prince Norihito to the Crown Prince, which could not be achieved five years ago, was realized...</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 10, the official investiture of Imperial Prince Norihito to the Crown Prince, which could not be achieved five years previously, was realized...</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 11, the official investiture of Imperial Prince Norihito to the Crown Prince, which could not be achieved five years previously, was realized.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>翌月、清盛が内大臣となり、時忠も蔵人頭に補された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next month, Kiyomori was appointed to naidaijjin (Minister of the Center) and Tokitada was appointed to kurodo no to (Head chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next month, Kiyomori was appointed naidaijjin (Minister of the Center) and Tokitada was appointed kurodo no to (Head chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next month, Kiyomori was appointed naidaijin (Minister of the Center) and Tokitada was appointed Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>清盛の大臣就任に不満を抱き、五節の節会に欠席した藤原朝方・実家が解官されたことによる後任人事だったが、非蔵人から始まって蔵人頭になったのは極めて異例のことだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This personal change was appointment as a successor because of dismissal of FUJIWARA no Tomokata and FUJWARA no Saneie who were dissatisfied with the appointment of Kiyomori to daijin (Minister) and did not attend the gosechi no sechie, but it was quite unusual that one started from hi-kurodo became the kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This personnel change was appointment as a successor because of the dismissal of FUJIWARA no Tomokata and FUJWARA no Saneie, who were dissatisfied with the appointment of Kiyomori to daijin (Minister) and did not attend the gosechi no sechie, but it was quite unusual that one who had started from hi-kurodo became the kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This personnel change was appointment as a successor because of the dismissal of FUJIWARA no Tomokata and FUJWARA no Saneie, who were dissatisfied with the appointment of Kiyomori to daijin (Minister) and did not attend the Sechi-e (seasonal court banquets) of Gosechi (annual court ceremony of girls music), but it was quite unusual that one who had started from hikurodo became the Kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>位階も正五位下から従四位下に上昇し、翌年正月に正四位下・右大弁、2月11日には参議・右兵衛督となり公卿への昇進を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank rose from Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and, in January, next year, he rose to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)and appointed to udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) and, on February 11, he was promoted to a sangi (Director of palace affairs) and uhyoe no kami.</e>
<cmt>他の箇所に合わせて官位の英文表記から「Ｃｏｕｒｔ」を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rank rose from Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and, in January the next year, he rose to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)and was appointed udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) and, on February 11, he was promoted to sangi (Director of palace affairs) and uhyoe no kami.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rank rose from Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and, in January the next year, he rose to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was appointed Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) and, on March 11, he was promoted to Sangi (councilor) and Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards) to be a court noble.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="49">
<j>仁安3年（1168年）2月に憲仁親王が践祚（高倉天皇）、3月には滋子が皇太后となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1168, Imperial Prince Norihito became the Emperor (Emperor Takakura) and, in March, Shigeko became the Empress Dowager.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1168, Imperial Prince Norihito became the Emperor (Emperor Takakura) and, in March, Shigeko became the Empress Dowager.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1168, Imperial Prince Norihito ascended to the throne (Emperor Takakura) and, in April, Shigeko became the Empress Dowager.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>滋子の叔父・信範は教盛とともに蔵人頭となり、時忠は従三位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeko&apos;s uncle, Nobunori was appointed to Kurodo no to together with Norimori and Tokitada was ranked at Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeko&apos;s uncle, Nobunori, was appointed Kurodo no to together with Norimori, and Tokitada was given the rank Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)..</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeko&apos;s uncle, Nobunori, was appointed Kurodo no to together with Norimori, and Tokitada was given the rank Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>清盛が出家して政界を表向き引退したこともあって、高倉即位後の政治は後白河が主導権を握った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Partly because Kiyomori became a priest and superficially retired from politics, Goshirakawa took the initiative in politics after Takakura became Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Partly because Kiyomori became a priest and superficially retired from politics, Goshirakawa took the initiative in politics after Takakura became Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Partly because Kiyomori became a priest and superficially retired from politics, Goshirakawa took the initiative in politics after Takakura became Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>時忠も滋子の兄という立場から、後白河の側近として活動することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada, also, from his standpoint as a elder brother of Shigeko, took actions as a brain trust of Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada, also, from his standpoint as the elder brother of Shigeko, took actions as part of Goshirakawa&apos;s brain trust.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada, also, from his standpoint as the elder brother of Shigeko, took actions as part of Goshirakawa&apos;s brain trust.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>7月3日、右衛門督・検非違使別当に就任するが、尉・佐を歴任して別当になったのは時忠が初めてだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 3, Tokitada took office as the uemon no kami (a chief official of the Right Division of the Ministry of the Outer Palace Guards) and kebiishi no betto, but Tokitada was the first person who experienced positions of jo and suke and then became betto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 3, Tokitada took office as uemon no kami (a chief official of the Right Division of the Ministry of the Outer Palace Guards) and kebiishi no betto; Tokitada was the first person who had experienced positions of jo and suke and then became betto.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 14, Tokitada took office as Uemon no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Kebiishi no betto; Tokitada was the first person who had experienced positions of jo (Lieutenant) and suke (assistant) and then became betto (chief officer).</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>8月には権中納言となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, he was promoted to gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, he was promoted to gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, he was promoted to Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>同月、清盛辞任で空席となっていた太政大臣に花山院忠雅が任じられ、時忠は慶賀の儀式に出席している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same month, Tadamasa KAZANIN was appointed to dajodaijin (Chancellor of the Realm) which post was vacant after resignation of Kiyomori, and Tokitada attended the ceremony for celebration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same month, Tadamasa KAZANIN was appointed dajodaijin (Chancellor of the Realm), which post was vacant after the resignation of Kiyomori, and Tokitada attended the ceremony for celebration.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same month, Tadamasa KAZANIN was appointed Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), which post was vacant after the resignation of Kiyomori, and Tokitada attended the ceremony for celebration.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>12月、伊勢神宮の正殿が焼失すると、翌嘉応元年（1169年）正月、復興のための公卿勅使として伊勢に派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the main temple of the Ise-jingu Shrine was burnt down in December 1168, Tokitada was dispatched to Ise as an imperial messenger as noble for reconstruction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the main temple of Ise-jingu Shrine was burnt down in December 1168, Tokitada was dispatched to Ise as an imperial messenger and noble for reconstruction.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the main temple of Ise-jingu Shrine was burnt down in January 1169, Tokitada was dispatched to Ise as an imperial messenger and noble for reconstruction in February the following year.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>4月に滋子が建春門院の院号を宣下されたことにより、女院別当に補される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, when Shigeko was given an official letter by Emperor to confer the ingo ingo (a title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) of &quot;Kenshunmonin&quot;, Tokitada was appointed to the nyoin betto (a chief officer serving to a retired empress)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, when Shigeko was given an official letter by Emperor to confer the ingo ingo (title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) of &quot;Kenshunmonin&quot;, Tokitada was appointed as nyoin betto (a chief officer serving a retired empress)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, when Shigeko was given an official letter by Emperor to confer the ingo (title of respect given to close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparable standing) of Kenshunmonin, Tokitada was appointed as nyoin betto (a chief officer serving a retired empress).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>11月に新帝の八十嶋祭が盛大に執り行われ、時忠も公卿として行列に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, Yasoshima no matsuri Festival for the new Emperor was held on a grand scale and Tokitada joined the parade as a noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, Yasoshima no matsuri Festival for the new Emperor was held on a grand scale and Tokitada joined the parade as a noble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, Yasoshima no matsuri Festival for the new Emperor was held on a grand scale and Tokitada joined the parade as a noble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>後白河院政は平氏一門の協力で磐石なものとなり、政情も安定するかに見えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa Insei (the government by the retired Emperor Goshirakawa) became stable thanks to cooperation by Heishi ichimon (the whole Taira clan) and it seemed that the political conditions would also be stabilized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa Insei (the government by the retired Emperor Goshirakawa) became stable thanks to cooperation by Heishi ichimon (the whole Taira clan) and it seemed that the political conditions would also be stabilized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government by the retired Emperor Goshirakawa became stable thanks to cooperation by the whole Taira clans and it seemed that the political conditions would also be stabilized.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="60">
<j>嘉応の強訴と再度の失脚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Direct Petition of Kao and Downfall for the Second Time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Direct Petition of Kao and Second Downfall</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Direct Petition of Kao and Second Downfall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>ところが12月に突如として延暦寺が院近臣・藤原成親の流罪を要求して強訴を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, however, the Enryaku-ji Temple suddenly presented a direct petition requiring exile of FUJIWARA no Narichika, who was an In no kinshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, however, Enryaku-ji Temple suddenly presented a direct petition demanding the exile of FUJIWARA no Narichika, who was an In no kinshin.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, however, Enryaku-ji Temple suddenly presented a direct petition demanding the exile of FUJIWARA no Narichika, who was an In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier).</e>
<cmt>用語集から補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>成親の知行国である尾張国の目代・政友が延暦寺領美濃国平野荘の神人に乱暴を働いたことが発端だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This trouble occurred because Masatomo, who was the mokudai (a deputy) for Owari Province that was the chigyokoku (fiefdom) of Narichika, used violence against jinnin (low-graded Shinto priest or worker subordinated to a Shinto shrine) of Hiranosho, Mino Province, which was owned by Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「尾張国→Owari-no-kuni (Owari Province)」、「美濃国平野荘→Hirano-sho, Mino-no-kuni (Hirano-sho, Mino Province）は、「平教経」、「平通盛」のファイルの表記に合わせて「尾張国→Ｏｗａｒｉ　Ｐｒｏｖｉｎｃｅ」、「美濃国→Ｍｉｎo Province」と表記しました。「神人→Kaminchu (a shrine maiden)」は、意味が異なると思われるため、「神人→jin-nin (low-graded Shinto priest or worker subordinated to a Shinto shrine)」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This trouble occurred because Masatomo, who was the mokudai (deputy) for Owari Province, the chigyokoku (fiefdom) of Narichika, used violence against a jinnin (low-ranked Shinto priest or worker subordinated to a Shinto shrine) of Hiranosho, Mino Province, which was owned by Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This trouble occurred because Masatomo, who was the mokudai (deputy) for Owari Province, the chigyokoku (fiefdom) of Narichika, used violence against a jinnin (low-ranked Shinto priest or worker subordinated to a Shinto shrine) of Hiranosho Manor, Mino Province, which was owned by Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語集から補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>後白河は同じ天台宗でも園城寺を優遇し、延暦寺に対しては院近臣を国司に任じて荘園の停廃・神人の取り締まりなどの強圧的な政策を行っていたため、院と延暦寺の対立は前々から一触即発の状態にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa had given favorable treatment to Onjo-ji Temple among temples of the Tendai Sect of the Buddhism and, toward Enryaku-ji Temple, he applied coercive policy by appointing In no kinshin to the provincial governors, such as suspension or abolishment of private estates and regulations against jin-nin, and, therefore, the confrontation between the In and Enryaku-ji Temple had been in a condition it can be detonated very easily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa had given favorable treatment to Onjo-ji Temple among temples of the Tendai Sect of Buddhism and, toward Enryaku-ji Temple, he applied coercive policy by appointing In no kinshin to the provincial governors, such as suspension or abolishment of private estates and regulations against jin-nin, and, therefore, potential confrontation between the In and Enryaku-ji Temple had been very likely.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa had given favorable treatment to Onjo-ji Temple among temples of the Tendai Sect of Buddhism and, toward Enryaku-ji Temple, he applied coercive policy by appointing In no kinshin to the provincial governors, such as suspension or abolishment of manor and regulations against jinnin, and, therefore, potential confrontation between the In and Enryaku-ji Temple had been very likely.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="64">
<j>22日、延暦寺の大衆が強訴のため下山、23日には上洛の態勢に入ったとの報を受けた後白河は、院御所に公卿を召集して対応を協議するとともに、検非違使・武士に動員令を下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 22, daishu (group of priests) of Enryaku-ji Temple departed from the temple to make direct petition, and, on December 23, Goshirakawa who got a report that the daishu was ready to come to Kyoto, convened nobles to In no gosho to consult about measures and issued a mobilization order to kebiishi and warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 22, a daishu (group of priests) of Enryaku-ji Temple departed from the temple to make direct petition, and, on December 23, Goshirakawa, who received a report that the daishu was ready to come to Kyoto, convened nobles to In no gosho to consult about measures and issued a mobilization order to kebiishi and warriors.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 17, a daishu (group of priests) of Enryaku-ji Temple departed from the temple to make direct petition, and, on January 18, Goshirakawa, who received a report that the daishu was ready to come to Kyoto, convened nobles to In no gosho (the retired Emperor&apos;s court) to consult about measures and issued a mobilization order to kebiishi and samurai.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集から補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>時忠も検非違使別当として院御所・洛中の警備に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada also guarded the In no gosho and the city of Kyoto as the kebiishi no betto.</e>
<cmt>「院御所→Ingosho (the palace of the retired emperor)」は、「院御所→In-no-gosho (the palace of the retired emperor)」に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As trhe kebiishi no betto, Tokitada also guarded the In no gosho and the city of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Kebiishi no betto, Tokitada also guarded the In no gosho and the city of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>しかし大衆は院御所ではなく、警備の手薄な内裏に乱入して気勢を上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the daishu burst not into the In no gosho but the Imperial Palace for which guard was thinner, and made a great fuss.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the daishu burst not into the In no gosho but into the Imperial Palace, whose guard was thinner, and made a great fuss.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the daishu burst not into the In no gosho but into the Imperial Palace, whose guard was thinner, and made a great fuss.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>この事態に時忠は、要求を聞き入れるならすぐに受諾し、聞き入れないなら武士を派遣して大衆を追い払うべきだと、早急な対策をとることを進言する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the situations, Tokitada advised to make quick response either to accept the requirement immediately if they ever do so, or dispatch warriors to get rid of the daishu if they would not accept requirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the situation, Tokitada advised to make quick response to either accept the requirement immediately if they ever do so, or dispatch warriors to get rid of the daishu if they would not accept the requirement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the situation, Tokitada advised to make quick response to either accept the requirement immediately if they ever do so, or dispatch samurai to get rid of the daishu if they would not accept the requirement.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>公卿議定では神輿が破壊される危険性から派兵に消極的な意見が大勢を占め、官兵を率いる平重盛も夜間の出動に難色を示したため、翌日の議定で成親配流・政友拘禁が決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In kugegijo (a meeting to form decisions by nobles), opinions negative to dispatch of troops occupied majority because there was a risk to destroy the portable shrine, and Shigemori, who should take command of governmental troops expressed disapproval of sending out the troops in the night, and, therefore, next day, exile of Narichika and confinement of Masatomo were decided by the decision by noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In kugegijo (a meeting to form decisions by nobles), opinions against dispatch of troops were in the majority, because there was a risk of destroying the portable shrine, and Shigemori, who should take command of governmental troops, expressed disapproval of sending out the troops in the night, and, therefore, the next day, the nobles decided on the exile of Narichika and confinement of Masatomo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In kugegijo (a meeting to form decisions by nobles), opinions against dispatch of troops were in the majority, because there was a risk of destroying the portable shrine, and Shigemori, who should take command of governmental troops, expressed disapproval of sending out the troops in the night, and, therefore, the next day, the nobles decided on the exile of Narichika and confinement of Masatomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="69">
<j>しかし、わずか4日後の28日に成親が召還され、時忠・信範は「奏事不実（奏上に事実でない点があった）」（『百錬抄』）という理由で解官、時忠は出雲国に、信範は備後国にそれぞれ配流されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 28 only four days later, however, Narichika was recalled and Tokitada and Nobunori were dismissed by reason of &quot;soji-fujitu (A report to the throne included untrue information.)&quot; (&quot;Hyakurensho&quot;) and exile of Tokitada to Izumo Province and Nobunori to Bingo Province was decided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 28 only four days later, however, Narichika was recalled and Tokitada and Nobunori were dismissed by reason of &quot;soji-fujitu (A report to the throne included untrue information.)&quot; (&quot;Hyakurensho&quot;), and the exile of Tokitada to Izumo Province and Nobunori to Bingo Province was decided.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 23 only four days later, however, Narichika was recalled and Tokitada and Nobunori were dismissed by reason of &apos;soji-fujitsu&apos; (A report to the throne included untrue information) (&quot;Hyakurensho&quot; (History book from the Kamakura period)), and the exile of Tokitada to Izumo Province and Nobunori to Bingo Province was decided.</e>
<cmt>用語集から補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>同時に時実・時家（時忠の子）や平信基（信範の子）も解官となり（『兵範記』）、結果として堂上平氏が詰め腹を切らされる形になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Tokizane and Tokiie (Tokitada&apos;s sons) and TAIRA no Nobumoto (Nobunori&apos;s son) were also dismissed (&quot;Heihanki&quot;) and, as a result, Dojo-Heishi (the Taira clan that was hereditarily allowed to the Court) was forced to resign.</e>
<cmt>「堂上平氏→Dojo-Heishi (the Taira clan that was hereditarily allowed to the Court)に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Tokizane and Tokiie (Tokitada&apos;s sons) and TAIRA no Nobumoto (Nobunori&apos;s son) were also dismissed (&quot;Heihanki&quot;) and, as a result, members of Dojo-Heishi (the Taira clan that was hereditarily allowed to the Court) were forced to resign.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Tokizane and Tokiie (Tokitada&apos;s sons) and TAIRA no Nobumoto (Nobunori&apos;s son) were also dismissed (&quot;Heihanki&quot;) and, as a result, members of Dojo Heishi (the Taira clan that was hereditarily allowed to the Court) were forced to resign.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>院と延暦寺の抗争が再燃したことで、翌年正月17日に政情不安を危惧した清盛が上洛、武士が六波羅に集結して緊迫した情勢となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As conflict between the In and Enryaku-ji Tample was reignited, Kiyomori, who was worried about instability of political situation, came to Kyoto on January 17, next year, and samurai gathered in Rokuhara and a very tense situation occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As conflict between the In and Enryaku-ji Temple was reignited, Kiyomori, who was worried about instability of the political situation, came to Kyoto on January 17, the next year, samurai gathered in Rokuhara, and the situation became very tense.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As conflict between the In and Enryaku-ji Temple was reignited, Kiyomori, who was worried about instability of the political situation, came to Kyoto on February 11, the next year, samurai gathered in Rokuhara, and the situation became very tense.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>後白河は清盛の圧力により、2月6日、やむを得ず成親の解官と時忠・信範の召還を決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of pressure by Kiyomori, Goshirakawa was obliged to decide on February 6 to dismiss Narichika and recall Tokitada and Nobunori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of pressure exerted by Kiyomori, on February 6 Goshirakawa was obliged to decide to dismiss Narichika and recall Tokitada and Nobunori.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of pressure exerted by Kiyomori, on March 2 Goshirakawa was obliged to decide to dismiss Narichika and recall Tokitada and Nobunori.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>この事件では、延暦寺への対応を巡って後白河と平氏の間に足並みの乱れが生じ、政権が必ずしも一枚岩でないことが露呈することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this incident, disarray between Goshirakawa and Taira clan occurred with respect to measures against Enryaku-ji Temple, and it was revealed that the government was not necessarily monolithic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this incident, disarray between Goshirakawa and the Taira clan occurred with respect to measures against Enryaku-ji Temple, and it was revealed that the government was not necessarily monolithic.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this incident, disarray between Goshirakawa and the Taira clan occurred with respect to measures against Enryaku-ji Temple, and it was revealed that the government was not necessarily monolithic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>成親が4月に早くも権中納言・右兵衛督・検非違使別当に還任したのに対して、時忠が本位に復したのは12月になってからだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Narichika was reappointed to gon chunagon, uhyoe no kami and kebiishi no betto in April, Tokitada returned to his original position only in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereas Narichika was reappointed gon chunagon, uhyoe no kami, and kebiishi no betto in April, Tokitada returned to his original position only in December.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereas Narichika was reappointed gon chunagon, Uhyoe no kami, and Kebiishi no betto in April, Tokitada returned to his original position only in January 1171.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="75">
<j>建春門院の側近</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Close Aide to Kenshunmonin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Close Aide to Kenshunmonin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Close Aide to Kenshunmonin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>承安 (日本)元年（1171年）正月、高倉天皇の元服の儀式が執り行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1171, the traditional ceremony to mark Emperor Takakura&apos;s coming of age was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1171, the traditional ceremony to mark Emperor Takakura&apos;s coming of age was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1171, the traditional ceremony to mark Emperor Takakura&apos;s coming of age was held.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>後白河と清盛の間に生じた不協和音が解消されたわけではなかったが、政権維持のためには両者の協力が不可欠であり、調整役として建春門院の政治的地位が上昇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although discord generated between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori had not been dispelled, but as cooperation between them was indispensable in order to maintain the regime, political influence of Kenshunmonin as a coordinator increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although discord generated between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori had not been dispelled, cooperation between them was indispensable in order to maintain the regime, and the political influence of Kenshunmonin as a coordinator increased.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although discord generated between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori had not been dispelled, cooperation between them was indispensable in order to maintain the regime, and the political influence of Kenshunmonin as a coordinator increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>母后である建春門院の威光により、堂上平氏も勢力を回復していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to influence of Kenshunmonin as the empress dowager, the Dojo-Heishi also recovered its influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to the influence of Kenshunmonin as the empress dowager, the Dojo-Heishi also recovered its influence.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to the influence of Kenshunmonin as the empress dowager, the Dojo Heishi also recovered its influence.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>時忠は一回目の失脚では清盛に、二回目の失脚では後白河に切り捨てられた苦い経験から、双方に不信感を抱いて距離を置くようになったらしく、政界復帰後は建春門院側近としての活動が顕著となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Tokitada became to keep certain distance from Goshirakawa and Kiyomori due to distrust of both of them based on Tokitada&apos;s bitter experiences of being abandoned by Kiyomori at the time of his first downfall and by Goshirakawa at the time of his second downfall, and, after his return to politics, his activities as a close aide of Kenshunmonin became remarkable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Tokitada came to keep a certain distance from Goshirakawa and Kiyomori due to his distrust of them based on Tokitada&apos;s bitter experiences of being abandoned by Kiyomori at the time of his first downfall and by Goshirakawa at the time of his second downfall, and, after his return to politics, his activities as a close aide of Kenshunmonin became remarkable.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Tokitada came to keep a certain distance from Goshirakawa and Kiyomori due to his distrust of them based on Tokitada&apos;s bitter experiences of being abandoned by Kiyomori at the time of his first downfall and by Goshirakawa at the time of his second downfall, and, after his return to politics, his activities as a close aide of Kenshunmonin became remarkable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>娘の一人は建春門院女房となり内侍と称していた（『吾妻鏡』建久2年（1191年）5月12日条）に見える典侍・平宣子と同一人物の可能性が高い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his daughter became a nyobo (high-ranked court lady) of Kenshunmonin and she was called &quot;naishi (a maid of honor to the Empress)&quot;. (There is every possibility that she was the same person as TAIRA no Noriko, a tenji (a court lady of the first rank) mentioned in the article for May 12, 1191 in &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his daughters became a nyobo (high-ranked court lady) of Kenshunmonin and she was called &quot;naishi (a maid of honor to the Empress)&quot;. (There is every possibility that she was the same person as TAIRA no Noriko, a tenji (a court lady of the first rank) mentioned in the article for May 12, 1191 in &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his daughters became a nyobo (high-ranked court lady) of Kenshunmonin and she was called &apos;naishi&apos; (a maid of honor to the Empress) (There is every possibility that she was the same person as TAIRA no Noriko, a tenji (a court lady of the first rank) mentioned in the article for June 12, 1191 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集から補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>子の時実は建春門院の御給により従五位上に叙せられ、時忠は4月21日に権中納言に還任、5月1日には帯剣を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s son, Tokizane was ranked at Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) given through Kenshunmonin and Tokitada was reappointed to gon chunagon on April 21 and allowed taiken (wearing a sword) on May 1.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada&apos;s son, Tokizane, held the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) given through Kenshunmonin, and Tokitada was reappointed gon chunagon on April 21 and allowed taiken (wearing of a sword) on May 1.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s son, Tokizane, held the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) given through Kenshunmonin, and Tokitada was reappointed Gon Chunagon on May 22 and allowed taiken (wearing of a sword) on June 1.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>前年、宗盛・源資賢が権中納言となったことで中納言9人の例が開かれたばかりだったが、早くも10人の例が始まり九条兼実は「未曾有」のことだと非難している（『玉葉』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last year, as Munemori and MINAMOTO no Sukekata became gon chunagon, the total number of chunagon reached nine for the first time and new case of ten chunagon began, and Kanezane KUJO criticized it as &quot;unparalleled in history.&quot; (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last year, as Munemori and MINAMOTO no Sukekata had become gon chunagon, the total number of chunagon reached nine for the first time and new case for ten chunagon began, and Kanezane KUJO criticized it as &quot;unparalleled in history.&quot; (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot;)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last year, as Munemori and MINAMOTO no Sukekata had become Gon Chunagon, the total number of Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) reached nine for the first time and new case for ten Chunagon began, and Kanezane KUJO criticized it as &apos;unparalleled in history.&apos; (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO)).</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="83">
<j>10月23日、後白河と建春門院は福原に御幸して、清盛の歓待を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 23, Goshirakawa and Kenshunmonin visited Fukuhara and they were cordially entertained by Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 23, Goshirakawa and Kenshunmonin visited Fukuhara and were cordially entertained by Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>omit &quot;they&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 18, Goshirakawa and Kenshunmonin visited Fukuhara and were cordially entertained by Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>時忠は、資賢・成親・重盛・宗盛・花山院兼雅とともに供奉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada followed this imperial visit to Fukuhara together with Sukekata, Narichika, Shigemori, Munemori and Kanemasa KAZANIN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada followed this imperial visit to Fukuhara together with Sukekata, Narichika, Shigemori, Munemori, and Kanemasa KAZANIN.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada followed this imperial visit to Fukuhara together with Sukekata, Narichika, Shigemori, Munemori, and Kanemasa KAZANIN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>この御幸において高倉天皇と清盛の娘・平徳子の婚姻が、正式に合意に達したと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is inferred that marriage of Emperor Takakura and Kiyomori&apos;s daughter, TAIRA no Tokuiko was officially agreed upon during this imperial visit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is inferred that the marriage of Emperor Takakura and Kiyomori&apos;s daughter, TAIRA no Tokuiko, was officially agreed upon during this imperial visit.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is inferred that the marriage of Emperor Takakura and Kiyomori&apos;s daughter, TAIRA no Tokuko, was officially agreed upon during this imperial visit.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>この婚姻の成立には高倉の治世安定を願い、政権の内部分裂を回避しようとする建春門院の意向が大きく作用したと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Kenshunmonin&apos;s wish to stabilization of the era of Takakura and her intention to avoid internal separation of the regime played an important role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Kenshunmonin&apos;s wish for stabilization of the era of Takakura and her intention to avoid internal separation of the regime played an important role.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Kenshunmonin&apos;s wish for stabilization of the era of Takakura and her intention to avoid internal separation of the regime played an important role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>翌承安2年（1172年）2月に徳子は中宮となり、時忠は権大夫に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1172, Tokiko became a chugu (the second consort of an emperor) and Tokitada assumed office as gon no daibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1172, Tokiko became a chugu (the second consort of an emperor) and Tokitada assumed office as gon no daibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1172 the following year, Tokiko became a chugu (the second consort of an emperor) and Tokitada assumed office as Gon no daibu (provisional master).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>承安3年（1173年）10月、時忠が責任者となって造営していた建春門院の御願寺・最勝光院が完成、承安4年（1174年）正月には、建春門院の御給で従二位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1173, Saishoko-in Temple, Kenshumonin&apos;s temple to pray, of which construction Tokitada had been responsible for, was completed and, in January 1174, Tokitada rose to Junii (Junior Second Rank) given through Kenshunmonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1173, Saishoko-in Temple, Kenshumonin&apos;s temple of prayer, whose construction Tokitada had been responsible for, was completed and, in January 1174, Tokitada rose to Junii (Junior Second Rank) given through Kenshunmonin.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1173, Saishoko-in Temple, Kenshunmonin&apos;s temple of prayer, whose construction Tokitada had been responsible for, was completed and, in February 1174, Tokitada rose to Junii (Junior Second Rank) given through Kenshunmonin.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>平氏の栄華をたたえて「一門にあらざらん者はみな人非人なるべし」との発言をしたのはこの時期とされる（『平家物語』巻第一「禿髪」より）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, around this time, Tokitada made a statement &quot;All other than family members of Taira family are not person&quot; praising prosperity of the Taira family. (From &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; Vol. 1 (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; Vol.1), &quot;Kamuro&quot;(&quot;Page-Boy Cut&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, around this time, Tokitada made a statement &quot;Only members of the Taira family are humans,&quot; praising the prosperity of the Taira family. (From &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; Vol. 1 (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; Vol.1), &quot;Kamuro&quot;(&quot;Page-Boy Cut&quot;)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, around this time, Tokitada made a statement &apos;Only members of the Taira family are humans,&apos; praising the prosperity of the Taira family (From &apos;Kamuro&apos; (Page-Boy Cut), Volume 1 of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>ただし時忠の属する堂上平氏は、清盛らの武門平氏からは相対的に独立した位置にいるので、この発言は実務官僚としての堂上平氏の躍進を誇ったものとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Dojo-Heisi to which Tokitada belonged was in a position independent from the Bumon-Heishi (warrior Taira clan) to which Kiyomori belonged, however, this statement can also be understood as a message boasting of rapid progress of the Dojo-Heishi.</e>
<cmt>「武門平氏→Bumon Taira clan (Warrior Taira clan)」は、「武門平氏→bumon-heishi (warrior Taira clan)」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the Dojo-Heisi to which Tokitada belonged was in a position independent from the Bumon-Heishi (warrior Taira clan) to which Kiyomori belonged, this statement can also be understood as a message boasting of the rapid progress of the Dojo-Heishi.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the Dojo Heishi to which Tokitada belonged was in a position independent from the Bumon Heishi (warrior Taira clan) to which Kiyomori belonged, this statement can also be understood as a message boasting of the rapid progress of the Dojo Heishi.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>安元元年（1175年）11月12日には右衛門督となり検非違使別当に返り咲いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 12, 1175, Tokitada became uemon no kami and he was reappointed to the kebiishi no betto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 12, 1175, Tokitada became uemon no kami and was reappointed kebiishi no betto.</e>
<cmt>omitte unnecessary wrods</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 2, 1176, Tokitada became Uemon no kami and was reappointed Kebiishi no betto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="92">
<j>政権の動揺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Turmoil in the Regime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Turmoil in the Regime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Turmoil in the Regime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>安元2年（1176年）3月、後白河の50歳を賀す式典が法住寺殿で盛大に催され、時忠も他の公卿や平氏一門とともに出席する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1176, the ceremony to celebrate Goshirakawa&apos;s age of 50 years old was held on a large scale in Hoju-ji den (Hoju-ji Palace) and Tokitada attended the ceremony together with other nobles and family members of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1176, a large-scale ceremony to celebrate Goshirakawa&apos;s age of 50 years old was held in Hoju-ji den (Hoju-ji Palace); Tokitada attended the ceremony together with other nobles and family members of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1176, a large-scale ceremony to celebrate Goshirakawa&apos;s age of 50 years old was held in Hojuji-dono Palace (Hoju-ji Palace); Tokitada attended the ceremony together with other nobles and family members of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>しかし6月に建春門院が病に倒れ、7月8日に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, however, Kenshunmonin was struck down by an illness and died on July 8.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, however, Kenshunmonin was struck down by an illness, and she died on July 8.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, however, Kenshunmonin was struck down by an illness, and she died on August 21.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>建春門院の死により、今まで隠されていた様々な問題が顕在化することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of Kenshunmonin&apos;s death, various problems hidden so far came up to the surface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of Kenshunmonin&apos;s death, various problems that had been hidden until then came up to the surface.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of Kenshunmonin&apos;s death, various problems that had been hidden until then came up to the surface.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>まず母后の不在により後継者のいない高倉の立場が不安定となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, the position of Takakura, who has no successor, became unstable because of non-existence of the empress dowager.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, the position of Takakura, who had no successor, became unstable because of non-existence of the empress dowager.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, the position of Takakura, who had no successor, became unstable because of non-existence of the empress dowager.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>10月23日、守覚法親王の弟子となっていた後白河の第八皇子（後の道法法親王）が藤原隆房に抱えられて参内、11月2日には親宗が養っていた第九皇子（後の承仁法親王）も時忠が引き連れて参内し『玉葉』）、いずれも高倉の猶子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 23, Goshirakawa&apos;s eighth Imperial Prince (later, the priestly Imperial Prince Doho) who had been a disciple of the priestly Imperial Prince Shukaku visited the Imperial Palace being held in FUJIWARA no Takafusa&apos;s arms, and on November 2, the ninth Imperial Prince (later, the priestly Imperial Prince Shojin) who had been fostered by Chikamune visited the Imperial Palace accompanying Tokitada (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and both of them became yushi of Takakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 23, Goshirakawa&apos;s eighth Imperial Prince (later, the priestly Imperial Prince Doho), who had been a disciple of the priestly Imperial Prince Shukaku, visited the Imperial Palace being held in FUJIWARA no Takafusa&apos;s arms, and on November 2, the ninth Imperial Prince (later, the priestly Imperial Prince Shojin), who had been fostered by Chikamune, visited the Imperial Palace accompanying Tokitada (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot;), and both of them became yushi of Takakura.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 2, Goshirakawa&apos;s eighth Imperial Prince (later, Cloistered Imperial Prince Doho), who had been a disciple of Cloistered Imperial Prince Shukaku, visited the Imperial Palace being held in FUJIWARA no Takafusa&apos;s arms, and on December 11, the ninth Imperial Prince (later, Cloistered Imperial Prince Shojin), who had been fostered by Chikamune, visited the Imperial Palace accompanying Tokitada (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot;), and both of them adopted by Takakura.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>これらの皇子は、高倉に皇子が生まれない場合の控えとして養育されていたと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is inferred that those Imperial Princes were fostered as spares for the case where Takakura could not get any Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is inferred that those Imperial Princes were fostered as spares in the event Takakura could not get any Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is inferred that those Imperial Princes were fostered as spares in the event Takakura could not get any Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="99">
<j>後白河は、成人した高倉が政務を行うようになると自らの発言力が著しく制限されることから、早期の譲位を望んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa desired early abdication by Takakura, because that, if grown-up Takakura would administer affairs of state, Goshirakawa&apos;s influence would be remarkably restricted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa desired early abdication by Takakura, because if grown-up Takakura would administer affairs of state, Goshirakawa&apos;s influence would be remarkably restricted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa desired early abdication by Takakura, because if grown-up Takakura would administer affairs of state, Goshirakawa&apos;s influence would be remarkably restricted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>清盛にすれば、徳子に皇子が生まれる前の譲位は絶対に容認できることではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Kiyomori, such abdication before birth of a Imperial Prince from Tokuko could not be allowed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Kiyomori, such abdication before the birth of a Imperial Prince from Tokuko could not be allowed.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Kiyomori, such abdication before the birth of a Imperial Prince from Tokuko could not be allowed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>当時、院政を行うことができたのは天皇の直系尊属に限定されていたので、時忠らが連れてきた皇子が高倉の猶子となったのは高倉の発言力保持のために必要な措置であり、後白河と清盛の対立を防ぐための妥協策でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, only a lineal ancestor of Emperor was allowed to open a cloister government, and, therefore, it was necessary to make those Imperial Princes brought in by Tokitada, etc. yushi of Takakura in order to maintain influence of Takakura and it was a compromise to avoid conflict between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, only a lineal ancestor of an Emperor was allowed to open a cloister government, and, therefore, those Imperial Princes brought in by Tokitada, etc. must be made yushi of Takakura in order to maintain influence of Takakura; this was a compromise to avoid conflict between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, only a lineal ancestor of an Emperor was allowed to open a cloister government, and, therefore, those Imperial Princes brought in by Tokitada, and so on, must be adopted children of Takakura in order to maintain influence of Takakura; this was a compromise to avoid conflict between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>しかし、これは問題の先延ばしに過ぎず、高倉を擁す平氏と後白河の下に結集する院近臣の対立は避けられないものとなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this worked only as a measure to carry forward the problem, and conflict between the Taira clan supporting Takakura and the In no kinshin gathering around Goshirakawa became unavoidable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this served only to carry forward the problem, and conflict between the Taira clan supporting Takakura and the In no kinshin gathering around Goshirakawa became unavoidable.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this served only to carry forward the problem, and conflict between the Taira clan supporting Takakura and the In no kinshin gathering around Goshirakawa became unavoidable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="103">
<j>安元3年（1177年）4月、延暦寺が加賀守・藤原師高の流罪を要求して強訴を起こす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1177, Enryaku-ji Temple made a direct petition requiring exile of FUJIWARA no Morotaka, who were Kaga no kami (governor of Kaga Province).</e>
<cmt>「加賀守→Kaga-no-kami (the Lord of Kaga Province)」は、「加賀守→Kaga-no-kami (governor of Kaga Province)」と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1177, Enryaku-ji Temple made a direct petition requiring exile of FUJIWARA no Morotaka, who was Kaga no kami (governor of Kaga Province).</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1177, Enryaku-ji Temple made a direct petition requiring exile of FUJIWARA no Morotaka, who was Kaga no kami (governor of Kaga Province).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>師高の父は院近臣・西光であり、後白河は強硬な態度で臨んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morotaka&apos;s father was Saiko, who was a In no kinshin, and Goshirakawa assumed a firm attitude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morotaka&apos;s father was Saiko, who was an In no kinshin, and Goshirakawa assumed a firm attitude.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morotaka&apos;s father was Saiko, who was an In no kinshin, and Goshirakawa assumed a firm attitude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>防御に当たった重盛の家人が神輿を射たことから、事態は悪化の一途をたどる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a Shigemori&apos;s retainer, who was defencing, shot the portable shrine, the situation became worse and worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a retainer of Shigemori, who was defending, shot the portable shrine, the situation became worse and worse.</e>
<cmt>possessive, misspelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a retainer of Shigemori, who was defending, shot the portable shrine, the situation became worse and worse.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>『平家物語』によれば、時忠は事態収拾のために延暦寺に乗り込んで交渉に当たり、激昂する大衆に「衆徒の濫悪をいたすは魔縁の所行なり、明王の制止を加ふるは善逝の加護なり」と紙に書いて渡し、その怒りを鎮めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Tale of the Heike,&quot; Tokitada ventured into Enryaku-ji Temple and negotiated in order to settle the situation, and he delivered to the excited daishu a paper on which he wrote &quot;violence by priests is conduct of a devil to disturb Buddhist training, myoo&apos;s restraint against such violence is protection by zensei&apos;&quot; and succeeded to subside their anger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Tale of the Heike,&quot; Tokitada ventured into Enryaku-ji Temple and negotiated a settlement to the situation, and he delivered to the excited daishu a paper on which he wrote &quot;violence by priests is conduct of a devil to disturb Buddhist training; myoo&apos;s restraint against such violence is protection by zensei,&apos;&quot; and he successfully subsided their anger.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; Tokitada ventured into Enryaku-ji Temple and negotiated a settlement to the situation, and he delivered to the excited daishu a paper on which he wrote &apos;violence by priests is conduct of a devil to disturb Buddhist training; myoo&apos;s restraint against such violence is protection by Zenzei (the well-gone; epithet of Buddha),&apos; and he successfully subsided their anger.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせ、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>この話は他に資料の裏付けがないので、事実かどうか定かでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As this episode has no supporting information from other materials, it is not known whether or not it is true.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this episode has no supporting information from other materials, it is not known whether or not it actually happened.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this episode has no supporting information from other materials, it is not known whether or not it actually happened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>実際には、師高の配流・神輿を射た重盛家人の投獄という延暦寺側の要求を、全面的に受諾することで決着がつけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, this trouble was settled by accepting all requirements by Enryaku-ji Temple, namely exile of Morotaka and imprisonment of Shigemori&apos;s retainer who shot the portable shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, this trouble was settled by accepting all requirements by Enryaku-ji Temple; namely, the exile of Morotaka and imprisonment of Shigemori&apos;s retainer who had shot the portable shrine.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, this trouble was settled by accepting all requirements by Enryaku-ji Temple; namely, the exile of Morotaka and imprisonment of Shigemori&apos;s retainer who had shot the portable shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="109">
<j>その後、後白河は天台座主・明雲の処罰を強行し、院と延暦寺の抗争が再燃する中で鹿ケ谷の陰謀が勃発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Goshirakawa forcibly dismissed the chief priest of the Tendai Sect of the Buddhism, Myoun, and while conflict between the In and Enryaku-ji Temple was reignited, the conspiracy of the Shishigatani occurred.</e>
<cmt>「明雲→Meiun」は、「Ｍｙｏｕｎ」の誤りと判断し、そのように訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Goshirakawa forcibly dismissed Myoun, the chief priest of the Tendai Sect of Buddhism, and while conflict between the In and Enryaku-ji Temple was reignited, the conspiracy of the Shishigatani occurred.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Goshirakawa forcibly dismissed Myoun, Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai Sect), and while conflict between the In and Enryaku-ji Temple was reignited, the Shishigatani plot occurred.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>西光・成親が殺害されたことで手足をもがれた形の後白河は平氏への屈服を余儀なくされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Saiko and Narichika were killed, Goshirakawa was like having lost his armes and legs and obliged to surrender to the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Saiko and Narichika were killed, it was as if Goshirakawa had lost his arms and legs, and he was obliged to surrender to the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Saiko and Narichika were killed, it was as if Goshirakawa had lost his arms and legs, and he was obliged to surrender to the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>清盛にしても高倉に皇子が生まれない段階ではそれ以上の措置を講じることはできず、情勢は膠着状態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kiyomori could not take any measure above before Takakura would get an Imperial Prince, the situation was stagnated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kiyomori could not take any measure before Takakura would get an Imperial Prince, the situation was stagnated.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kiyomori could not take any measure before Takakura would get an Imperial Prince, the situation was stagnated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="112">
<j>安徳の誕生と高倉院政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Antoku&apos;s Birth and Cloister Government by Takakura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Antoku&apos;s Birth and Cloister Government by Takakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Antoku&apos;s Birth and Cloister Government by Takakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>治承2年（1178年）5月24日、時忠は徳子の懐妊が確実なことを高倉に伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 24, 1178, Tokitada informed Takakura that Tokuko&apos;s pregnancy was confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 24, 1178, Tokitada informed Takakura that Tokuko&apos;s pregnancy was confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 18, 1178, Tokitada informed Takakura that Tokuko&apos;s pregnancy was confirmed.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>7月24日に藤原隆季が娘の死により中宮大夫を辞任したことで、26日に大夫に昇格する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 24, as FUJIWARA no Takasue resigned chugudaibu (the Load steward to the second consort of an emperor) because of his daughter&apos;s death, Tokitada was promoted to the daibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 24, as FUJIWARA no Takasue resigned from chugudaibu (Lord steward to the emporer&apos;s second consort) because of his daughter&apos;s death, Tokitada was promoted to daibu.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September, as FUJIWARA no Takasue resigned from Chugu daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s Household because of his daughter&apos;s death, Tokitada was promoted to daibu on September 16.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>11月12日、徳子は皇子（言仁、後の安徳天皇）を出産し、時忠の妻・領子が乳母となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 12, Tokuko gave birth to a Imperial Prince (Tokihito, later, Emperor Antoku) and Tokitada&apos;s wife, Ryoko, became the nursermaid of the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 12, Tokuko gave birth to a Imperial Prince (Tokihito, later, Emperor Antoku) and Tokitada&apos;s wife, Ryoko, became the nursermaid of the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 29, Tokuko gave birth to a Imperial Prince (Tokihito, later, Emperor Antoku) and Tokitada&apos;s wife, Ryoko, became the wet nurse of the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>清盛は皇子を皇太子にすることを後白河に迫り、12月には早くも立太子の儀式が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori urged Goshirakawa to make the Imperial Prince to the Crown Prince and, already in December, the ceremony of instituting the Crown Prince was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori urged Goshirakawa to make the Imperial Prince the Crown Prince and, already in December, the ceremony of instituting the Crown Prince was held.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori urged Goshirakawa to make the Imperial Prince the Crown Prince and, already in January, the ceremony of instituting the Crown Prince was held.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>東宮傅（とうぐうのふ）は左大臣・藤原経宗、春宮坊は大夫・宗盛、権大夫・兼雅、亮・重衡、権亮・維盛という陣容であり、後白河の近臣は排除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The togufu (a person responsible for education of the Crown Prince) was the sadaijin, FUJIWARA no Tsunemun, and in the togubo (agency for the Crwon Prince), the daibu was Munemor, the gon no daibu Kanemasa, the suke Shigehira and the gon no suke Koremori and In no kinshin was excluded.</e>
<cmt>「東宮傅→Togu-den (A chief secretary of the younger brother of an Emperor who is heir apparent)」は、「東宮傅→togufu (a person responsible for education of the Crown Prince)」の誤りと判断し、そのように訂正しました。また、「春宮坊→Shungu-bo (The agency of Imperial Prince)」も、「春宮坊→togubo (the agency for the Crown Prince)」の誤りと判断し、そのように訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The togufu (person responsible for education of the Crown Prince) was the sadaijin, FUJIWARA no Tsunemun, and in the togubo (agency for the Crown Prince), the daibu was Munemor, the gon no daibu Kanemasa, the suke Shigehira, and the gon no suke Koremori; In no kinshin was excluded.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The togu no fu (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) was the sadaijin (minister of the left), FUJIWARA no Tsunemune, and in the Togubo (Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters), the daibu was Munemori, the gon no daibu Kanemasa, the suke Shigehira, and the gon no suke Koremori; In no kinshin was excluded.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="118">
<j>さらに清盛は、摂関家領を奪われたことで平氏に敵愾心を燃やす関白・松殿基房を後白河から切り離して自派に引き入れるために、基房の妻（忠雅の娘）も乳母に迎えようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in order to separate Motofusa MATSUDONO, kanpaku (chief advisor to the emperor) who had been filled with hatred against the Taira clan because he was taken fiefdom of the sekkanke (clan eligible for regents) by the Taira clan, from Goshirakawa and entice him to Kiyomori&apos;s side, Kiyomori tried to include the wife of Motofusa (a daughter of Tadamasa) into nursemaids for the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in order to separate Motofusa MATSUDONO, kanpaku (chief advisor to the emperor) who had been filled with hatred against the Taira clan because they had taken from him fiefdom of the sekkanke (clan eligible for regents), from Goshirakawa and entice him to Kiyomori&apos;s side, Kiyomori tried to include the wife of Motofusa (a daughter of Tadamasa) as a nursemaid for the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in order to separate Motofusa MATSUDONO, kanpaku who had been filled with hatred against the Taira clan because they had taken from him fiefdom of the sekkanke (clan eligible for regents), from Goshirakawa and entice him to Kiyomori&apos;s side, Kiyomori tried to include the wife of Motofusa (a daughter of Tadamasa) as a wet nurse for the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、前出補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>これに対して時忠は、執政の室が乳母になるなど聞いたことがないと主張して強く反対した（『玉葉』12月30日条、基房の妻も2月には安徳乳母となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada opposed to this attempt insisting that he had never heard about any case where the wife of regent became nursemaid (Article for December 30 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;; in Feburary, the wife of Motofusa became a nursemaid of Antoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada opposed this attempt, insisting that he had never heard of any case where the wife of a regent became nursemaid (Article for December 30 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;); nonetheless, in Feburary, the wife of Motofusa became a nursemaid of Antoku.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada opposed this attempt, insisting that he had never heard of any case where the wife of a regent became a wet nurse (Article for February 15 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;; nonetheless, in March, the wife of Motofusa became a wet nurse of Antoku).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。また、「12月30日」は「治承2年12月30日」、「2月」は「治承3年」としてグレゴリオ暦にしました。(以下同様）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>自らの妻が乳母であることから関白の妻を近づけたくなかったためと思われるが、時忠が必ずしも清盛の意向に沿って動いていなかったことを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Tokitada did not want to bring the wife of the kanpaku close to the Crown Prince, since Tokitada&apos;s wife was a nursemaid, and it shows that Tokitada not necessarily acted in accordance with Kiyomori&apos;s intension.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Tokitada did not want to bring the wife of the kanpaku close to the Crown Prince, since Tokitada&apos;s wife was a nursemaid; this shows that Tokitada did not necessarily act in accordance with Kiyomori&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Tokitada did not want to bring the wife of the kanpaku close to the Crown Prince, since Tokitada&apos;s wife was a wet nurse; this shows that Tokitada did not necessarily act in accordance with Kiyomori&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="121">
<j>治承3年（1179年）正月7日、時忠は正二位に叙せられ、19日には史上初めて三回目の検非違使別当に補された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 7, 1179, Tokitada was conferred Shonii (Senior Second Rank), and, on 10, appointed to the kebiishi no betto for the third time, as the first case in the history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 7, 1179, Tokitada was conferred Shonii (Senior Second Rank), and, on January 10, was appointed kebiishi no betto for the third time, which was unprecedented.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 22, 1179, Tokitada was conferred Shonii (Senior Second Rank), and, on March 6, was appointed Kebiishi no betto for the third time, which was unprecedented.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>前任者の忠親は「希代之例也」（『山槐記』）と驚愕し、九条兼実は「物狂之至也、非人臣之所為」（『玉葉』）と激しく非難している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadachika, the predecessor, was surprised and recorded &quot;extremely rare case&quot; (&quot;Sankaiki&quot;) and Kanezane KUJO blamed bitterly saying &quot;It is crazy. It cannot be an act of a subject.&quot;(&quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadachika, his predecessor, was surprised and recorded &quot;extremely rare case&quot; (&quot;Sankaiki&quot;), and Kanezane KUJO was bitter with blame, saying &quot;This is crazy. It cannot be an act of a subject.&quot;(&quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadachika, his predecessor, was surprised and recorded &apos;extremely rare case&apos; (&quot;Sankaiki&quot; (diary by Tadachika NAKAYAMA)), and Kanezane KUJO was bitter with blame, saying &apos;This is crazy. It cannot be an act of a subject.&apos; (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>鹿ケ谷事件で検非違使の惟宗信房・平資行・平康頼が陰謀に加担していたことから、検非違使庁改革のため経験豊富な時忠に白羽の矢が立てられたと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is inferred that Tokitada, whoc had sufficient experiences, was chosen for reformation of the kebiishi no cho, because kebiishi, Nobufusa KOREMUNE, TAIRA no Sukeyuki and TAIRA no Yasuyori took part in the Shishigatani Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is inferred that Tokitada, who had sufficient experience, was chosen for reformation of the kebiishi no cho, because kebiishi, Nobufusa KOREMUNE, TAIRA no Sukeyuki, and TAIRA no Yasuyori took part in the Shishigatani Incident.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is inferred that Tokitada, who had sufficient experience, was chosen for reformation of the Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief), because kebiishi, Nobufusa KOREMUNE, TAIRA no Sukeyuki, and TAIRA no Yasuyori took part in the Shishigatani Incident.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="124">
<j>6月に盛子、7月に重盛が相次いで死去したのを機に、後白河は盛子の荘園・重盛の知行国を没収し、清盛の支援する近衛基通を無視して基房の子・松殿師家を権中納言にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the occasion of Moriko&apos;s death in June and Shigemori&apos;s death in July, Goshirakawa seized Moriko&apos;s private estates and Shigemori&apos;s chigyokoku and, neglecting Motomichi KONOE, whom Kiyomori supported, appointed Moroie MATSUDONO, a son of Motofusa, to a gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Moriko&apos;s death in June and Shigemori&apos;s death in July, Goshirakawa seized Moriko&apos;s private estates and Shigemori&apos;s chigyokoku and, neglecting Motomichi KONOE, whom Kiyomori supported, appointed Moroie MATSUDONO, a son of Motofusa, a gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Moriko&apos;s death in July and Shigemori&apos;s death in August, Goshirakawa seized Moriko&apos;s manor and Shigemori&apos;s chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom) and, neglecting Motomichi KONOE, whom Kiyomori supported, appointed Moroie MATSUDONO, a son of Motofusa, a Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>激怒した清盛は11月14日にクーデターを起こし、反平氏公卿・院近臣の大量解官が断行された（治承三年の政変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori, who got angered by this, carried out a coup d&apos;état on November 14, and mass dismissal of anti-Taira nobles and In no kinshin was conducted (Jisho Sannen no Seihen (the coup in 1179)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori, who was angered by this, carried out a coup d&apos;état on November 14, and mass dismissal of anti-Taira nobles and In no kinshin was conducted (Jisho Sannen no Seihen (the coup of 1179)).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori, who was angered by this, carried out a coup on December 21, and mass dismissal of anti-Taira nobles and In no kinshin was conducted (Coup of the Third Year of Jisho).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>堂上平氏からは親宗・時家・平基親が解官の対象となり、大きな打撃を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Dojo Heishi, Chikamune, Tokiie and TAIRA no Motochika were dismissed and Dojo Heishi was seriously damaged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Dojo Heishi, Chikamune, Tokiie, and TAIRA no Motochika were dismissed, and Dojo Heishi was seriously damaged.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Dojo Heishi, Chikamune, Tokiie, and TAIRA no Motochika were dismissed, and Dojo Heishi was seriously damaged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>建春門院在世中は結束していた堂上平氏も、分裂状態にあったことをうかがわせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We can figure out that Dojo Heishi, that was united when Kenshunmonin was alive, was aslo in disunited condition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We can figure out that Dojo Heishi, which had been united when Kenshunmonin was alive, was also disunited.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We can figure out that Dojo Heishi, which had been united when Kenshunmonin was alive, was also disunited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>時忠の管轄していた検非違使庁からも大江遠業・平資行・藤原信盛が解官となり、欠員補充として藤原景高・忠綱・友実・源光長が新たに任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the kebiishi no cho,that was under Tokitada&apos;s control, OE no Tonari and FUJIWARA no Nobumori were dismissed and FUJIARA no Kagetaka, Tadatsuna, Tomozane, and MINOMOTO no Mitsunaga were newly appointed to fill vacancies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the kebiishi no cho, which was under Tokitada&apos;s control, OE no Tonari and FUJIWARA no Nobumori were dismissed and FUJIARA no Kagetaka, Tadatsuna, Tomozane, and MINOMOTO no Mitsunaga were newly appointed to fill vacancies.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Kebiishicho, which was under Tokitada&apos;s control, OE no Tonari, TAIRA no Sukeyuki, and FUJIWARA no Nobumori were dismissed and FUJIARA no Kagetaka, Tadatsuna, Tomozane, and MINOMOTO no Mitsunaga were newly appointed to fill vacancies.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="129">
<j>後白河は鳥羽殿に幽閉状態となり、高倉が政務をとることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa was confined in the Toba-dono palace and Takakura assumed affairs of state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa was confined in Toba-dono palace and Takakura assumed responsibility for affairs of state.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa was confined in Toba-dono palace and Takakura assumed responsibility for affairs of state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>翌年2月、言仁親王の践祚とともに院庁が設置され、執事別当には藤原隆季が就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, next year, at the same time as Imperial Prince Tokihito became the emperor, the In no cho was established and FUJIWARA no Takasue took office as the shituji betto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February of the next year, as Imperial Prince Tokihito became the emperor, the In no cho was established and FUJIWARA no Takasue took office as the shituji betto.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of the next year, as Imperial Prince Tokihito became the emperor, the In no cho was established and FUJIWARA no Takasue took office as the Shitsuji-betto (chief officer).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>時忠も高倉の伯父・安徳の乳父（めのと）の立場から別当の一員として、政務に未熟な高倉を補佐することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada also assisted Takakura, who was inexperienced in assuming affairs of state, as a member of the betto from the standpoint as Takakura&apos;s uncle and Antoku&apos;s menoto (a tutor of a nobleman&apos;s son).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada also assisted Takakura, who was inexperienced in affairs of state, as a member of the betto from the standpoint of Takakura&apos;s uncle and Antoku&apos;s menoto (tutor of a nobleman&apos;s son).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada also assisted Takakura, who was inexperienced in affairs of state, as a member of the betto from the standpoint of Takakura&apos;s uncle and Antoku&apos;s menoto (a foster father).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>高倉院政が開始されたものの、クーデターで成立した政権であるため平氏の軍事力に支えられている面が大きく、その正統性に疑問があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although cloister government by Takakura was commenced, its legitimacy was doubtful because it was formed as a result of a coup d&apos;état and it was largely supported by military power of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although cloister government by Takakura was commenced, its legitimacy was doubtful, because it was formed as a result of a coup d&apos;état and it was largely supported by the military power of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although cloister government by Takakura was commenced, its legitimacy was doubtful, because it was formed as a result of a coup and it was largely supported by the military power of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>しかも清盛の強い要請により、高倉が譲位後すぐに厳島神社に参詣したことが、延暦寺・園城寺・興福寺など伝統的寺院勢力の危機感を煽ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, according to strong request by Kiyomori, Takakura made pilgrimage to Itsukushima-jinja Shrine soon after his abdication, and it caused to stir up a sense of crisis of traditional temples such as Enryaku-ji Temple, Onjo-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, according to strong request by Kiyomori, Takakura made a pilgrimage to Itsukushima-jinja Shrine soon after his abdication, and this stirred up a sense of crisis on the part of traditional temples such as Enryaku-ji Temple, Onjo-ji Temple, and Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to strong request by Kiyomori, Takakura made a pilgrimage to Itsukushima-jinja Shrine soon after his abdication, and this stirred up a sense of crisis on the part of traditional temples such as Enryaku-ji Temple, Onjo-ji Temple, and Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>不穏な空気が流れる中で、5月に以仁王が挙兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a situation where unsettled condition prevails, Mochihitoo (the Imperial Prince Mochihito) raised an army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the prevailing unsettled conditions, Mochihitoo (the Imperial Prince Mochihito) raised an army.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the prevailing unsettled conditions, Prince Mochihito raised an army in June.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦で補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>支援したのは二条天皇の准母・八条院で、後白河と密接につながる園城寺、関白配流に反発する興福寺も同調したことから、新政権にとって大きな脅威となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachijoin, who was the Emperor Nijo&apos;s junbo (an acting mother for the emperor), supported Mochihito and Onjo-ji Temple that was closely connected to Goshirakawa and Kofuku-ji Temple that was against exile of the kanpaku also kept in step with him, it became a great threat to a new regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachijoin, who was the Emperor Nijo&apos;s junbo (acting mother of the emperor), supported Mochihito, and Onjo-ji Temple, which was closely connected to Goshirakawa, and Kofuku-ji Temple, which was against exile of the kanpaku, also kept in step with him; this became a great threat to a new regime.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachijoin, who was the Emperor Nijo&apos;s junbo (acting mother of the emperor), supported Mochihito, and Onjo-ji Temple, which was closely connected to Goshirakawa, and Kofuku-ji Temple, which was against exile of the kanpaku, also kept in step with him; this became a great threat to a new regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>反乱が鎮圧された後、清盛は突如として福原行幸を強行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the rebellion was suppressed, Kiyomori forcibly carried out the imperial visit to Fukuhare all of a sudden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the rebellion was suppressed, Kiyomori forcibly and suddenly carried out an imperial visit to Fukuhare.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the rebellion was suppressed, Kiyomori forcibly and suddenly carried out an imperial visit to Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="137">
<j>福原行幸と反乱の激化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Visit to Fukuhara and Intensified Rebellions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Visit to Fukuhara and Intensified Rebellion</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Visit to Fukuhara and Intensified Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>6月2日、安徳天皇・高倉上皇・後白河法皇は福原に向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 2, Emperor Antoku, retired Emperor Takakura and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa started toward Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 2, Emperor Antoku, retired Emperor Takakura, and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa started toward Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 3, Emperor Antoku, retired Emperor Takakura, and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa started toward Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>随行したのは平氏一門および親平氏貴族・実務官僚で、時忠も天皇の行幸の列に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were accompanied by the family members of the Taira clan, pro-Tairia nobles and governmental officials responsible for practical works and Tokitada also joined the parade of the imperial visit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were accompanied by the family members of the Taira clan, pro-Tairia nobles, and governmental officials responsible for practical matters, and Tokitada also joined the parade of the imperial visit.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were accompanied by the family members of the Taira clan, pro-Taira nobles, and governmental officials responsible for practical matters, and Tokitada also joined the parade of the imperial visit.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>福原到着後に遷都が議論され、輪田を新都建設地とすることが決まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After arrival in Fukuhara, they discussed about the transfer of the capital and it was decided that Wada would be the candidate for constructing new capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After their arrival in Fukuhara, they discussed transfer of the capital and it was decided that Wada would be the candidate for constructing a new capital.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After their arrival in Fukuhara, they discussed transfer of the capital and it was decided that Wada would be the candidate for constructing a new capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>ところが場所が狭いことから計画は白紙となり、昆陽野（こやの）・印南野（いなみの）が代替地として候補に上がったものの、7月にはどちらの案も立ち消えとなってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the space was too narrow, the plan got back to where it was at the beginning, and Koyano and Inamino were proposed as alternatives, but both plans were came to nothing in July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the space was too narrow, the plan returned to where it was at the beginning, and Koyano and Inamino were proposed as alternatives, but both plans came to nothing in July.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the space was too narrow, the plan returned to where it was at the beginning, and Koyano and Inamino were proposed as alternatives, but both plans came to nothing in July.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>結局、福原を暫定的な皇居とすることに落ち着くが、準備不足と混乱から遷都反対の意見も出始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end, it was settled to make Fukuhara as the temporary imperial palace, but, because of insufiicient preparation and confusion, opinions against the trasfer of the capital started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, it was settled that Fukuhara would be made the temporary imperial palace, but, because of insufiicient preparation and confusion, opinions arose against the transfer of the capital.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, it was settled that Fukuhara would be made the temporary imperial palace, but, because of insufficient preparation and confusion, opinions arose against the transfer of the capital.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>高倉の体調不良もあり、時忠と隆季は清盛に還都を申し入れるが、一蹴されてしまう（『玉葉』8月12日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Takakura was not in good condition physically, Tokitada and Takasue proposed Kiyomori to return the capital to Kyoto, but Kiyomori refused flatly (Article for August 12 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Takakura was not in good condition physically, Tokitada and Takasue proposed that Kiyomori return the capital to Kyoto, but Kiyomori refused flatly (Article for August 12 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;),</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Takakura was not in good condition physically, Tokitada and Takasue proposed that Kiyomori return the capital to Kyoto, but Kiyomori refused flatly (Article for September 10 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「8月12日」は「治承4年8月12日」としてグレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="144">
<j>高倉はやむを得ず内裏造営命令を出し、時忠も遷都反対派を抑える役割を任されたらしく、議定で方角の禁忌が問題になると反対意見を封殺するなど、強引な手法をとっている（『玉葉』8月29日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakura reluctantly issued an order to construct the imperial palace, and Tokitada seems to have assinged to a role to suppress opinion groups who were against the transfer of the capital and took such forcible way as to suppress differing views when the problem of the directional taboo was raised in the meeting (Artilce for August 29 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakura reluctantly issued an order to construct the imperial palace, and Tokitada seems to have been assigned a role to suppress opinion groups who were against the transfer of the capital and took such forcible action as to suppress differing views when the problem of the directional taboo was raised in a meeting (Article for August 29 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakura reluctantly issued an order to construct the imperial palace, and Tokitada seems to have been assigned a role to suppress opinion groups who were against the transfer of the capital and took such forcible action as to suppress differing views when the problem of the directional taboo was raised in a meeting (Article for September 27 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「8月29日」は「治承4年8月29日」としてグレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>時忠は福原に邸宅を持っていなかったので、新たに土地を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Tokitada had no residence in Fukuhara, he was newly provided with land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Tokitada had no residence in Fukuhara, he was newly provided with land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Tokitada had no residence in Fukuhara, he was newly provided with land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>8月25日、娘婿の忠親とともに福原の都市計画図を確認し、10月8日、邸宅の造作について意見交換をしている（『山槐記』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 25, he checked the city planning map of Fukuhara with Tadachika, who was his son-in-law, and exchanged views on fixtures of the residence (Article for the same day in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 25, he checked the city planning map of Fukuhara with Tadachika, who was his son-in-law, and exchanged views on fixtures of the residence (Article for the same day in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 23, he checked the city planning map of Fukuhara with Tadachika, who was his son-in-law, and exchanged views on fixtures of the residence on November 4 (Article for the same day in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、月日を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>内裏や貴族の邸宅も徐々に整備されて遷都も軌道に乗るかと思われたが、8月になってから全国各地で反乱が頻発していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the imperial palace and residences of nobles were gradually prepared and improved, the transfer of the capital seemed to have started along the right line, but, in August, revellions occurred frequently in various places in the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the imperial palace and residences of nobles were gradually prepared and improved, the transfer of the capital seemed to have started along the right lines, but, in August, rebellions occurred frequently in various places in the country.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the imperial palace and residences of nobles were gradually prepared and improved, the transfer of the capital seemed to have started along the right lines, but, in August, rebellions occurred frequently in various places in the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>そして10月21日に富士川の戦いで追討軍が大敗したことにより、還都論が再燃することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 21, as the punitive force was severely defeated in the Battle of Fujigawa, the opinions to return the capital to Kyoto were reignited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 21, as the punitive force was severely defeated in the Battle of Fujigawa, opinions to return the capital to Kyoto were reignited.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 17, as the punitive force was severely defeated in the Battle of Fujigawa, opinions to return the capital to Kyoto were reignited.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="149">
<j>まず宗盛が還都を進言して、清盛と激しい口論に及ぶ（『玉葉』11月5日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, Munemori proposed to return the capital to Kyoto and had violent quarrel with Kiyomori (Article for November 5 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, Munemori proposed to return the capital to Kyoto and had violent quarrel with Kiyomori (Article for November 5 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, Munemori proposed to return the capital to Kyoto and had violent quarrel with Kiyomori (Article for November 30 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;),</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>東海道諸国が反乱軍の手の中に落ちていく状況の中で、11月6日、時忠は美濃を東国に対する防衛線とするため、美濃源氏に宣旨を下して味方につける案を出す（『吉記』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the situation in which Provinces in Tokaido had been falling under control of rebels, Tokitada made a proposal on November 6 to give a senji (a informal Imperial letter) to Minot Genji (the Mino branch of the Minamoto clan) to get them over in order to make Mino Province as the defensive line against eastern Provinces (Article for the same day in &quot;Kikki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the situation where Provinces in Tokaido had been falling under the control of rebels, Tokitada made a proposal on November 6 to give a senji (a informal Imperial letter) to Minot Genji (the Mino branch of the Minamoto clan) to get them over in order to make Mino Province the defensive line against eastern Provinces (Article for the same day in &quot;Kikki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the situation where Provinces in Tokaido had been falling under the control of rebels, Tokitada made a proposal on December 1 to give a senji (a informal Imperial letter) to Mino-Genji (Minamoto clan) to get them over in order to make Mino Province the defensive line against eastern Provinces (Article for the same day in &quot;Kikki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>美濃源氏の源光長は検非違使で、時忠とは上司と部下の関係であり、時忠には美濃源氏を懐柔できるという自信があったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Mitsunaga from Mino Genji was a kebiisi and relationship with Tokitada was as superior and subordinate, and, therefore, Tokitada was confident that he could win Mino Genji over.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Mitsunaga from Mino Genji was a kebiisi and his relationship with Tokitada was that of superior and subordinate, and, therefore, Tokitada was confident that he could win Mino Genji over.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Mitsunaga from Mino-Genji was a kebiishi and his relationship with Tokitada was that of superior and subordinate, and, therefore, Tokitada was confident that he could win Mino-Genji over.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>しかし清盛は時忠の案を無視して、美濃源氏討伐のため私郎従（直属の精鋭部隊）を派遣する（『玉葉』11月12日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kiyomori ignored Tokitada&apos;s proｐosal and despatch his private retainers (elite troops directly belonged to Kiyomori) to subjugate Mino Genji (Article for November 12 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kiyomori ignored Tokitada&apos;s proposal and dispatched his private retainers (elite troops belonging directly to Kiyomori) to subjugate Mino Genji (Article for November 12 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kiyomori ignored Tokitada&apos;s proposal and dispatched his private retainers (elite troops belonging directly to Kiyomori) to subjugate Mino-Genji (Article for December 7 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>この結果、美濃は動乱状態となり戦禍は近江にまで波及する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Mino Province fell into condition of disturbance and the disasters of war spread to Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Mino Province fell into condition of disturbance and the disasters of war spread to Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Mino Province fell into condition of disturbance and the disasters of war spread to Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>延暦寺も「還都をしなければ、山城・近江両国を横領する」と強迫的な態度をとっており（『玉葉』10月20日条）、情勢は予断を許さないものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enryaku-ji Temple also took a coercive attitude telling &quot;If the capital is not returned to Kyoto, we will usurp Yamashiro Province and Omi Province.&quot;(Article for ctover 20 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and situations were such that admitted of no prediction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enryaku-ji Temple also took a coercive attitude, saying &quot;If the capital is not returned to Kyoto, we will usurp Yamashiro Province and Omi Province.&quot;(Article for October 20 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and the situation was unpredictable.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enryaku-ji Temple also took a coercive attitude, saying &apos;If the capital is not returned to Kyoto, we will usurp Yamashiro Province and Omi Province.&apos; (Article for November 16 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and the situation was unpredictable.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="155">
<j>11月12日、清盛は還都に同意するが、時忠は難色を示した（『吉記』同日条、『玉葉』11月16日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 12, Kiyomori agreed to return the capital to Kyoto, but Tokitada showed disapproval (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; and article of November 16 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 12, Kiyomori agreed to return the capital to Kyoto, but Tokitada showed disapproval (Article for the same day in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; and article of November 16 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 7, Kiyomori agreed to return the capital to Kyoto, but Tokitada showed disapproval (Article for the same day in &quot;Kikki&quot; and article of December 11 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>近江では反乱軍との戦闘が激化していて、何らかの対策をとって安全が確保されなければ京都に戻るのは危険と判断したためと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the battle with rebels had been intensified in Omi Province, it is inferred that Tokitada judged that it was dangerous to return to Kyoto unless certain measures were taken and security was ensured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the battle with rebels in Omi Province had intensified, it is inferred that Tokitada judged that it was dangerous to return to Kyoto unless certain measures were taken and security was ensured.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the battle with rebels in Omi Province had intensified, it is inferred that Tokitada judged that it was dangerous to return to Kyoto unless certain measures were taken and security was ensured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>時忠は、高倉の意向を無視する清盛の独裁と強硬路線が事態の悪化に拍車をかけていると分析し、還都後に公卿議定を開いて対応策を打ち出そうと考えていたらしい（『吉記』11月21日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Tokitada analysed that the Kiyomori&apos;s dictatorial attitudes and hard line ignoring Takakura&apos;s intention was accelarating worsening of situations and intended to hold kuge-gijo after the return of the government to the former capital in order to establish countermeasures (Article for November 21in &quot;Kikki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Tokitada reasoned that Kiyomori&apos;s dictatorial attitude and hardline ignoring of Takakura&apos;s intention was accelerating deterioration of the situation, and intended to hold kuge-gijo after the return of the government to the former capital in order to establish countermeasures (Article for November 21in &quot;Kikki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Tokitada reasoned that Kiyomori&apos;s dictatorial attitude and hardline ignoring of Takakura&apos;s intention was accelerating deterioration of the situation, and intended to hold kuge-gijo after the return of the government to the former capital in order to establish countermeasures (Article for December 16 in &quot;Kikki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>11月22日、高倉の命を奉じた時忠は天台座主・明雲を通して、日吉社・延暦寺領荘園に対して還都と引き換えに反乱軍の防御・掃滅に当たることを指示した（『吉記』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 22, following Takakura&apos;s order, Tokitada instructed through the tendaizasu Myoun, private estates owned by Hiyoshi-sha Shrine and Enryaku-ji Temple to defense against and annihilate rebels in exchange with the the return of the government to the former capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 22, following Takakura&apos;s order, Tokitada instructed through the tendaizasu Myoun, private estates owned by Hiyoshi-sha Shrine and Enryaku-ji Temple, to defend against and annihilate rebels in exchange for the return of the government to the former capital.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 17, following Takakura&apos;s order, Tokitada instructed through the Tendai-zasu Myoun, manor owned by Hiyoshi-sha Shrine and Enryaku-ji Temple, to defend against and annihilate rebels in exchange for the return of the government to the former capital.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>延暦寺側との合意成立により、翌23日に還都が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After agreement with Enryaku-ji Temple side was made, the return of the government to the former capital was carried on 23, next day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After an agreement with Enryaku-ji Temple was reached, the return of the government to the former capital was carried out on the 23rd, the next day.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After an agreement with Enryaku-ji Temple was reached, the return of the government to the former capital was carried out on December 18, the next day.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="160">
<j>11月30日、東国逆乱についての公卿議定が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 30, kuge-gijo was held with respect to rebvellion in the eastern areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 30, kuge-gijo was held with respect to rebellion in the eastern areas.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 25, kuge-gijo was held with respect to rebellion in the eastern areas.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>徳大寺実定の「近江の賊徒を平定すれば、美濃以下も帰伏する」という意見が賛同を集め、追討が本格化することになる（『山槐記』同日条』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanetada TOKUDAIJI&apos;s opinion &quot;If rebels in Omi Province are subjugated, rebels in Mino Province, etc. would also surrender.&quot; was accepted by the majority, activity to liquidate the rebels was made in full scale (Article for the same day in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanetada TOKUDAIJI&apos;s opinion, &quot;If rebels in Omi Province are subjugated, rebels in Mino Province, etc. would also surrender,&quot; was accepted by the majority, and full-scale action was taken to liquidate the rebels (Article for the same day in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanetada TOKUDAIJI&apos;s opinion, &apos;If rebels in Omi Province are subjugated, rebels in Mino Province, and so on,. would also surrender,&apos; was accepted by the majority, and full-scale action was taken to liquidate the rebels (Article for the same day in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>12月には反乱対策として、公卿層に対する武力の供出（『玉葉』12月13日条）・諸国からの兵糧米徴収（『山槐記』12月10日条）が相次いで実施されるが、時忠はこれらの政策の立案・実行に深く関与していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, various countermeasures against rebellion, such as delivery of military force by nobles (Article for December 13 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and collection of provisions from various Provinces (Article for December 10 in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;) were taken, and Tokitada was deeply involved in the planning and execution of such policies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, various countermeasures were taken against rebellion, such as delivery of military force by nobles (Article for December 13 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and collection of provisions from various Provinces (Article for December 10 in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;), and Tokitada was deeply involved in the planning and execution of such policies.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between December in 1180 and January in 1181 (December, 1180 in old lunar calendar), various countermeasures were taken against rebellion, such as delivery of military force by nobles (Article for January 7 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and collection of provisions from various Provinces (Article for January 4 in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;), and Tokitada was deeply involved in the planning and execution of such policies.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>これらの措置と平氏軍の反撃により、畿内周辺の反乱はひとまず沈静化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of those measures and counterattack by the troops of the Taira clan, rebellion in and arouond the capital were suppressed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of those measures and counterattack by the troops of the Taira clan, rebellion in and around the capital was suppressed.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of those measures and counterattack by the troops of the Taira clan, rebellion in and around the capital was suppressed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="164">
<j>後白河院政の再開</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reopening Cloister Government by Goshirakawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reopening Cloister Government by Goshirakawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reopening Cloister Government by Goshirakawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>高倉の病状は還都の時にはかなり重くなっていて、翌治承5年（1181年）正月14日、21歳の若さで崩御する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakura&apos;s illness was quite serious at the time of the return of the government to the former capital and he died on January 14, 1181 at the age of 21 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakura&apos;s illness was quite serious at the time of the return of the government to the former capital and he died on January 14, 1181 at the age of 21.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;years old&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakura&apos;s illness was quite serious at the time of the return of the government to the former capital and he died on February 6, 1181 the following year at the age of 21.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>時忠は近臣の一人として素服を賜わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada was give sofuku (white clothes) as a close aide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a close aide, Tokitada was give sofuku (white clothes).</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a close aide, Tokitada was give sofuku (white clothes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>時忠は高倉の権威により政治的地位を築き上げてきたため、その早過ぎる死は大きな痛手だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Tokitada had established his political position based on Takakura&apos;s authority, his too early death was a heavy blow to Tokitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Tokitada had established his political position based on Takakura&apos;s authority, his early death was a heavy blow to Tokitada.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;too&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Tokitada had established his political position based on Takakura&apos;s authority, his early death was a heavy blow to Tokitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>高倉没後の政治体制は幼児の安徳が政務を執ることができない以上、もはや後白河の院政再開しか残されていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to political system after Takakura&apos;s death, as infant Antoku could not assume affairs of state, there was no other way than cloister government by Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to the political system after Takakura&apos;s death, as infant Antoku could not assume affairs of state, there was no alternative to cloister government by Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to the political system after Takakura&apos;s death, as infant Antoku could not assume affairs of state, there was no alternative to cloister government by Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>このような状況の中で時忠は、かつて高松院の所有だった荘園を高倉の遺言と称して強引に中宮・徳子に相続させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such situations, Tokitada forcibly made chugu Tokuko inherit private estates owned by Takamatsu-in with excuse that it was Takakura&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under this situation, Tokitada forcibly caused chugu Tokuko to inherit private estates owned by Takamatsu-in under the excuse that it was Takakura&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under this situation, Tokitada forcibly caused chugu Tokuko to inherit manor owned by Takamatsuin under the excuse that it was Takakura&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>後白河はこの措置に対して、不快感を露わににしたという（『玉葉』治承5年2月4日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reportedly, Goshirakawa openly showed displeasure against that measure (Article for February 4 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reportedly, Goshirakawa openly showed displeasure against that measure (Article for February 4 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reportedly, Goshirakawa openly showed displeasure against that measure (Article for February 26 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="171">
<j>時忠は高倉院庁の別当として実務を取り仕切っていたため、このような措置をとることが可能だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Tokitada had been handling practical works as the betto of the Takakurain no cho, he could take such measure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Tokitada had been handling practical matters as the betto of the Takakurain no cho, he could take such a measure.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Tokitada had been handling practical matters as the betto of the Takakurain no cho (Retired Emperor Takakura&apos;s Office), he could take such a measure.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>時忠の意図は、高倉没後に避けられなくなる後白河の政治力増大を食い止めると同時に、徳子の経済基盤を強化することで間接的に自らの発言力を保持することにあったと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is inferred that Tokitada&apos;s intention was to prevent increase of Goshirakawka&apos;s influence on politics that would become inevitable after Takakura&apos;s death and, at the same time, to indirectly maintain his own influence by consolidating econmical foundation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is inferred that Tokitada&apos;s intention was to prevent an increase in Goshirakawka&apos;s political influence that would become inevitable after Takakura&apos;s death and, at the same time, to indirectly maintain his own influence by consolidating an economic foundation.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is inferred that Tokitada&apos;s intention was to prevent an increase in Goshirakawa&apos;s political influence that would become inevitable after Takakura&apos;s death and, at the same time, to indirectly maintain his own influence by consolidating an economic foundation of Tokuko.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>時忠は中宮大夫であり、同年11月25日に徳子が院号宣下を受けた後も、引き続いて建礼門院別当として徳子を補佐する立場にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada was the chugu no daibu and, after Tokuko received ingo-senge on November 25, 1181, he continued to be in a position to support Tokuko as the Kenreimonin no betto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada was the chugu no daibu and, after Tokuko received ingo-senge on November 25, 1181, he continued to be in a position to support Tokuko as the Kenreimonin no betto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada was the Chugu daibu and, after Tokuko was issued an Imperial letter to permit use of &quot;In&quot; title on January 8, 1182, he continued to be in a position to support Tokuko as the Kenreimonin no Betto (chief officer serving to Kenreimonin).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="174">
<j>清盛も後白河の院政再開をただ手をこまねいて見ていたわけではなく、院近臣の解官・畿内惣官職の設置など矢継ぎ早に対策を講じていたが、閏2月4日に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori did not just look on with folded arms reopening of the cloister government by Goshirakawa, and had been taking various measures in quick succession such as dismissal of the In no kinshin and institution of kinaisokanshiki (officer to keep peace in and around the capital), but he died on the 4th day of the intercalary second month, 1181.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori did not just look on with folded arms at the reopening of the cloister government by Goshirakawa, and had been taking various measures in quick succession, including dismissal of the In no kinshin and institution of kinaisokanshiki (officer to keep peace in and around the capital), but he died on the 4th day of the intercalary second month, 1181.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori did not just look on with folded arms at the reopening of the cloister government by Goshirakawa, and had been taking various measures in quick succession, including dismissal of the In no kinshin and institution of kinai-sokanshiki (officer to keep peace in and around the capital), but he died on March 27, 1181.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>後継者の宗盛は院政再開を認めて後白河に恭順する姿勢を見せる一方で、平氏の存立基盤である軍事・警察権は断固として手放さず、後白河の宥和策を退けて東国追討を続行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s successor, Munemori, showed his stance to obey Goshirakawa by agreeing to reopening cloister government, but, on the other hand, he did not give up definitely military and police authority which was the basis of existence of the Taira clan and continued subjugation of eastern Provinces refusing Goshirakawa&apos;s appeasement policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori&apos;s successor, Munemori, showed his stance to obey Goshirakawa by agreeing to reopening of the cloister government, but, on the other hand, he did not give up definite military and police authority, which was the basis of existence of the Taira clan, and continued subjugation of the eastern Provinces, refusing Goshirakawa&apos;s appeasement policy.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s successor, Munemori, showed his stance to obey Goshirakawa by agreeing to reopening of the cloister government, but, on the other hand, he did not give up definite military and police authority, which was the basis of existence of the Taira clan, and continued subjugation of the eastern Provinces, refusing Goshirakawa&apos;s appeasement policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>このため、後白河と宗盛の間には深い溝が生じることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, a deep rift developed between Goshirakawa and Munemori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, a deep rift developed between Goshirakawa and Munemori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, a deep rift developed between Goshirakawa and Munemori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>後白河と平氏の間にはもともと解消することのできない対立があったが、かつては建春門院が調整役を果たしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a conflict between Goshirakawa and the Taira clan that could not be dissolved, but Kenshunmonin worked as the coordinator in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a conflict between Goshirakawa and the Taira clan that could not be dissolved, but in the past Kenshunmonin has worked as a coordinator.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a conflict between Goshirakawa and the Taira clan that could not be dissolved, but in the past Kenshunmonin has worked as a coordinator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>時忠は国母である徳子に建春門院と同様の役割を期待し、承安年間の政治体制の再現を目指していたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We consider that Tokitada expected Tokuko, who was the empress dowager, to play similar role as that of Kenshunmonin and aimed at the reproduction of the political system during the Shoan era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We consider that Tokitada expected Tokuko, who was the empress dowager, to play a role similar to that of Kenshunmonin, and aimed at revival of the political system during the Shoan era.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We consider that Tokitada expected Tokuko, who was the empress dowager, to play a role similar to that of Kenshunmonin, and aimed at revival of the political system during 1171 and 1174.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="179">
<j>しかし徳子は後白河の養女であり、最初からその立場は弱かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tokuko was Goshirakawa&apos;s adopted daughter and her position was weak from the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tokuko was Goshirakawa&apos;s adopted daughter and her position was weak from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tokuko was Goshirakawa&apos;s adopted daughter and her position was weak from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>また、徳子自身も積極的に自らの意思を示す性格ではなかったため、彼女に建春門院の代わりを求めるのは無理があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, as Tokuko&apos;s character was not to positively show her own will, it was difficult to ask her to funciton like Kenshunmonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, as Tokuko&apos;s character was not to positively show her own will, it was difficult to ask her to function as Kenshunmonin had.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, as Tokuko&apos;s character was not to positively show her own will, it was difficult to ask her to function as Kenshunmonin had.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>さらに周囲の状況も、以前と大きく変化していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the top of this, situations had also been changed drastically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On top of this, the situation had also changed drastically.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On top of this, the situation had also changed drastically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>各地では反乱の火の手が燃え盛り、後白河も院政停止・幽閉を経たことで平氏に不満を通り越して憎しみを抱いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In various places, rebellions were becoming more and more intense and, after experiencing suspension of cloister government and confinement, Goshirakawa had against the Taira clan not only dissatisfaction but even hatread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In various places, rebellions were becoming more and more intense and, after experiencing suspension of cloister government and confinement, Goshirakawa had not only dissatisfaction against the Taira clan but even hatread.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In various places, rebellions were becoming more and more intense and, after experiencing suspension of cloister government and confinement, Goshirakawa had not only dissatisfaction against the Taira clan but even hatred.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>後白河はすでに平氏に見切りをつけて、独自に頼朝と和平交渉を始めていた（『玉葉』養和元年（1181年）8月1日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa had already discarded the Taira clan and independently commenced peace negotiation with Yoritomo (Article for August 1, 1181 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa had already discarded the Taira clan and independently commenced peace negotiation with Yoritomo (Article for August 1, 1181 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa had already discarded the Taira clan and independently commenced peace negotiation with Yoritomo (Article for September 18, 1181 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>時忠は5月に母が死去したことで、服喪のため検非違使別当を辞職する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of his mother&apos;s death, Tokitada resigned as the kebiish no betto for mourning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada resigned as kebiish no betto to mourn his mother&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada resigned as Kebiishi no betto to mourn his mother&apos;s death on June.</e>
<cmt>月を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>時忠の政治的地位はしだいに後退していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s political position was gradually weakened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada&apos;s political position was gradually weakened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s political position was gradually weakened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="186">
<j>4月になると後白河は、安徳を八条の頼盛邸から閑院内裏に遷す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, Goshirakawa transferred Antoku from Yorimori&apos;s residence in Hachijo to Kanin-dairi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, Goshirakawa transferred Antoku from Yorimori&apos;s residence in Hachijo to Kanin-dairi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, Goshirakawa transferred Antoku from Yorimori&apos;s residence in Hachijo to Kanin-dairi Palace.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>また、安徳の准母には清盛の後押しで近衛通子（基実の娘）が選ばれていたが、寿永元年（1182年）8月、後白河は第一皇女・亮子内親王を新たに准母として送り込み皇后とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michiko KONOE (Motozane&apos;s daughter) had been chosen for Antoku&apos;s junbo (title usually used when giving Imperial Princess the title of empress or in-go) by backup from Kiyomori, but, in August 1182, Goshirakawa made the first Imperial Princess, Ryoshi the Empress by sending her as the junbo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michiko KONOE (Motozane&apos;s daughter) had been chosen for Antoku&apos;s junbo (title usually used when giving an Imperial Princess the title of empress or in-go) with backup from Kiyomori, but, in August 1182, Goshirakawa made the first Imperial Princess, Ryoshi, the Empress by sending her as the junbo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michiko KONOE (Motozane&apos;s daughter) had been chosen for Antoku&apos;s junbo (title usually used when giving an Imperial Princess the title of empress or in-go) with backup from Kiyomori, but, in September 1182, Goshirakawa made the first Imperial Princess, Ryoshi, the Empress by sending her as the junbo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>いずれも安徳を平氏の手から引き離す方策であり、後白河の影響力は確実に強まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those were measures to separate Antoku from the Taira clan and Goshirakawa&apos;s influence had been surely increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were measures to separate Antoku from the Taira clan and Goshirakawa&apos;s influence had surely been increased.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were measures to separate Antoku from the Taira clan and Goshirakawa&apos;s influence had surely been increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>ただし九条兼実に代表される貴族層は日和見的態度をとっていたため、後白河も一挙に主導権を握ることはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, nobles represented by Kanezane KUJO took wait-and-see attitude, and, therefore, Goshirakawa could not take initiative at one effort.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, nobles represented by Kanezane KUJO took a wait-and-see attitude, and, therefore, Goshirakawa could not take initiative with a united effort.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, nobles represented by Kanezane KUJO took a wait-and-see attitude, and, therefore, Goshirakawa could not take the lead at once.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>後白河と平氏の関係は一種の均衡状態となり、時が過ぎていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship between Goshirakawa and the Taira clan entered into a kind of balanced condition and time elapsed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As time passed, the relationship between Goshirakawa and the Taira clan entered into a kind of balanced condition.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As time passed, the relationship between Goshirakawa and the Taira clan entered into a kind of balanced condition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="191">
<j>しかし、それはつかの間の平穏だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was only a short-lived quiet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the quiet was short-lived.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the quiet was short-lived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>軍事面において平氏は墨俣川の戦いに勝利した後は、養和の大飢饉の影響もあって戦線を維持するのが精一杯であり、内外に敵を抱えた平氏政権はしだいに疲弊していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to military aspect, after victory in the Battle of Sunomatagawa, it was all the Taira clan could do to maintain the front lines partially because of influence of theYowa Famine, and the Taira regime that had enemies both inside and outside, declined gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the military aspect, after victory in the Battle of Sunomatagawa, it was all the Taira clan could do to maintain the front lines, partially because of influence of the Yowa Famine, and the Taira regime, which had enemies both inside and outside, gradually declined.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the military aspect, after victory in the Battle of Sunomatagawa, it was all the Taira clan could do to maintain the front lines, partially because of influence of the Great Famine of Yowa, and the Taira regime, which had enemies both inside and outside, gradually declined.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）正月、時忠は権大納言となるが政権の崩壊は間近に迫っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1183, Tokitada was promoted to gon dainagon, but the breakdown of the regime impended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1183, Tokitada was promoted to gon dainagon, but the breakdown of the regime impended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1183, Tokitada was promoted to Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state), but the breakdown of the regime impended.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="194">
<j>一門都落ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family&apos;s Fleeing from the Capital</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family&apos;s Flight from the Capital</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family&apos;s Flight from the Capital</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）5月、平氏の北陸追討軍が木曽義仲に撃破されたことで（倶利伽羅峠の戦い）、今まで維持されてきた軍事バランスは完全に崩壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1183, the Taira clan&apos;s punitive force for Hokuriku area was defeated by Yoshinaka KISO (the Battle of Kurikaratoge), the military balance that had been maintained collapsed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1183, the Taira clan&apos;s punitive force for the Hokuriku area was defeated by Yoshinaka KISO (the Battle of Kurikaratoge), and the military balance that had been maintained collapsed.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1183, the Taira clan&apos;s punitive force for the Hokuriku region was defeated by Yoshinaka KISO (the battle of the Kurikara Pass), and the military balance that had been maintained collapsed.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>7月22日、義仲軍は延暦寺にまで到達したため、議定が開かれて対策が協議される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 22, as the troop of Yoshinaka reached the Enryaku-ji Temple, a meeting was held to discuss about countermeasured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 22, as the troop of Yoshinaka reached the Enryaku-ji Temple, a meeting was held to discuss countermeasures.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 18, as the troop of Yoshinaka reached the Enryaku-ji Temple, a meeting was held to discuss countermeasures.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>24日、安徳は院御所・法住寺殿に行幸し、時忠も供奉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 24, Antoku visited In no gosho, Hojujiden, and Tokitada attended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 24, Antoku visited In no gosho, Hojujiden, and Tokitada attended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 20, Antoku visited In no gosho, Hojuji-dono, and Tokitada attended.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>京都防衛を断念した宗盛は、勢力挽回のために後白河・安徳らを引き連れて西国に下向する準備を進めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munemori, who gave up defense of Kyoto, was preparing for going down to the western area taking Goshirakawa, Antoku, etc. along in order to recover force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munemori, who gave up the defense of Kyoto, was preparing to go down to the western area, taking Goshirakawa, Antoku, etc. along in order to recover force.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munemori, who gave up the defense of Kyoto, was preparing to go down to the western area, taking Goshirakawa, Antoku, and so on, along in order to recover force.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>25日未明、平氏の意図を察した後白河は、法住寺殿から比叡山に脱出する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 25, before dawn, Goshirakawa knew the Tara clan&apos;s intention, escaped from Hojujiden to Mount Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 25, aware of the Taira clan&apos;s intention, Goshirakawa escaped from Hojujiden to Mount Hiei before dawn.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 21, aware of the Taira clan&apos;s intention, Goshirakawa escaped from Hojuji-dono to Mt. Hiei before dawn.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>宗盛はやむを得ず、安徳と二宮（高倉の第二皇子・守貞親王、後の後高倉院）だけを連れて都を退去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munemor was obliged to leave the capital taking only Antoku and Ninomiya (Takakura&apos;s second son, Imperial Prince Morisada, later Gotakakurain) along..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munemori was obliged to leave the capital, taking along only Antoku and Ninomiya (Takakura&apos;s second son, Imperial Prince Morisada, later Gotakakurain).</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munemori was obliged to leave the capital, taking along only Antoku and Ninomiya (Takakura&apos;s second son, Imperial Prince Morisada, later Gotakakurain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>時忠は閑院内裏に向かい、内侍所（神鏡）を取り出してから都落ちに同行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada went to Kanin dairi and took out Naishidokoro, or shinkyo (Yata mirror, or sacred mirror), and then, joined the party for the fleeing the capital</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada went to Kanin dairi and took out Naishidokoro, or shinkyo (Yata mirror, or sacred mirror), and then joined the party in its flight from the capital</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada went to Kanin-dairi Palace and took out Naishidokoro (also known as shinkyo (Yata mirror, or sacred mirror), and then joined the party in its flight from the capital of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせ、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>貴族は続々と後白河の下に集結し、親平氏派の筆頭である摂政・基通や一門の頼盛も京都に残留する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobles gathered one after another around Goshirakawa, and Motomichi, kanpaku who was the leader of pro-Taira group and Yorimori, a member of the Taira clan) remained in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobles gathered one after another around Goshirakawa, and Motomichi, a kanpaku who was the leader of the pro-Taira group and Yorimori, a member of the Taira clan, remained in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobles gathered one after another around Goshirakawa, and Motomichi, a Sessho (regent) who was the leader of the pro-Taira group and Yorimori, a member of the Taira clan, remained in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>安徳および平氏に付き従った貴族は、わずかに時忠・時実・信基・藤原尹明に過ぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only nobles who followed Antoku and the Taira clan were Tokitada, Tokizane, Nobumoto and FUJIWARA no Koretada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only nobles who followed Antoku and the Taira clan were Tokitada, Tokizane, Nobumoto, and FUJIWARA no Koretada.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only nobles who followed Antoku and the Taira clan were Tokitada, Tokizane, Nobumoto, and FUJIWARA no Koretada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="204">
<j>27日、後白河は都に戻り、翌日に開かれた議定において平氏追討が決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 27, Goshirakawa returned to Kyoto and, in the meeting held next day, it was decided to track down and dispose of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 27, Goshirakawa returned to Kyoto and, in a meeting held the next day, it was decided to track down and dispose of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 23, Goshirakawa returned to Kyoto and, in a meeting held the next day, it was decided to track down and dispose of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>8月6日に平氏一門は一斉に解官されるが、後白河は安徳の帰京・神器の返還を交渉するため、時忠の解官は見送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 6, family members of the Taira clan were dismissed all together, but Goshirakawa postponed dismissal of Tokitada in order to negotiate for return of Antoku to Kyoto and return of sacred treasures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 6, family members of the Taira clan were dismissed altogether, but Goshirakawa postponed dismissal of Tokitada in order to negotiate for return of Antoku to Kyoto and the return of sacred treasures.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 1, family members of the Taira clan were dismissed altogether, but Goshirakawa postponed dismissal of Tokitada in order to negotiate for return of Antoku to Kyoto and the return of sacred treasures.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>もっとも交渉は不調に終わったらしく、16日には時忠も解官となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the negotiation failed and Tokitada also was dismissed on August 16.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the negotiation failed, and Tokitada was dismissed on August 16.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the negotiation failed, and Tokitada was dismissed on September 11.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>後白河にとって平氏が安徳を連れて逃げていったのは不幸中の幸いであり、平氏の占めていた官職・受領のポストに次々と院近臣を送り込んで政治の主導権を確立すると、8月20日、都に残っていた四宮（高倉の第四皇子・尊成、後鳥羽天皇）を践祚させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A bright spot in a tragedy for Goshirakawa was that the Taira clan fled taking Antoku along, and, after securing political initiative by appointing In no kinshin to official posts and zuryo which had been occupied by the Taira clan, Goshirakawa made Shinomiya (Takakura&apos;s fourth imperial prince, Takashige, later the Emperor Gotoba) become the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A bright spot in the tragedy for Goshirakawa was that the Taira clan fled taking Antoku along, and, after securing political initiative by appointing In no kinshin to official posts and zuryo which had been occupied by the Taira clan, Goshirakawa made Shinomiya (Takakura&apos;s fourth imperial prince, Takashige, later the Emperor Gotoba) the emperor.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A bright spot in the tragedy for Goshirakawa was that the Taira clan fled taking Antoku along, and, after securing political initiative by appointing In no kinshin to official posts and Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors) which had been occupied by the Taira clan, Goshirakawa made Shinomiya (Takakura&apos;s fourth imperial prince, Takashige, later the Emperor Gotoba), who stayed in the capital, the emperor.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>この知らせを聞いた平氏の人々は「三宮、四宮も引き連れていくべきだった」と悔しがるが、時忠は「その場合は、義仲が擁立している以仁王の皇子（北陸宮）が位につくだけのことだ」と冷めた見方をしている（『平家物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing this information, members of the Taira clan regretted &quot;We should have taken Sannomiya and Shinomiya along&quot;, but Tokitada looked at this cooly and said &quot;In that case, the imperial prince of Mochihitoo supported by Yoshinaka (Hokuriku no miya) becomes the emperor, instead.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing this information, members of the Taira clan regretted, &quot;We should have taken Sannomiya and Shinomiya along&quot;, but Tokitada looked at this cooly and said &quot;In that case, the imperial prince of Mochihitoo supported by Yoshinaka (Hokuriku no miya) would have become the emperor instead.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing this information, members of the Taira clan regretted, &apos;We should have taken Sannomiya and Shinomiya along,&apos; but Tokitada looked at this coolly and said &apos;In that case, the imperial prince of Prince Mochihito (Hokuriku no miya) supported by Yoshinaka would have become the emperor instead&apos; (&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;).</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="209">
<j>元暦元年（1184年）2月7日、平氏は一ノ谷の戦いで大敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 7, 1184, the Taira clan suffered the crushing defeat in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>「一ノ谷の戦い→the Battle of Ichinotami」は、他のファイルの例に倣い「the Battle of Ichi-no-tani」と表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 7, 1184, the Taira clan suffered a crushing defeat in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 27, 1184, the Taira clan suffered a crushing defeat in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>この戦いの後、後白河が神器の返還を求めて派遣した御坪の召次・花方という使者に、時忠が「浪方」という焼印を顔面に押して追い返したという逸話が『平家物語』「請文」の段にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot;, Chapter &quot;Ukebumi (reply)&quot;, there is an episode that, after this battle, Tokitada drove back a messenger, Otsubo no Meshitsugi, Hanakata sent by Goshirakawa to require return of sacred treasures after branding &quot;Namikata&quot; on his face.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot;, Chapter &quot;Ukebumi (reply)&quot;, there is an episode that, after this battle, Tokitada drove back a messenger, Otsubo no Meshitsugi, that Hanakata had sent by Goshirakawa to require return of sacred treasures, after branding &quot;Namikata&quot; on his face.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Chapter &apos;Ukebumi&apos; (reply) of &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; there is an episode that, after this battle, Tokitada drove back a messenger, Hanakata of Otsubo no Meshitsugi (person who works in Meshitsugi-dokoro, the department of managing daily affairs of In), had sent by Goshirakawa to require return of sacred treasures, after branding &apos;Namikata&apos; on his face.</e>
<cmt>半角スペースにし、前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>花方については、語り本系には見られるが読み本系の古態とされる延慶本には記されてないこと、院宣の使者としては身分が低すぎることから創作の可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Hanakata is mentioned in books of the katarihon system, it is not mentioned in engyobon, which is believed to be an old form of yomihon system, and his status is too low for In&apos;s messenger, and therefore this episode could be a mere fiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Hanakata is mentioned in books of the katarihon system, this episode is not mentioned in engyobon, which is believed to be an old form of the yomihon system, and his status was too low for In&apos;s messenger; therefore this episode could be mere fiction.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Hanakata is mentioned in narration books, this episode is not mentioned in Enkyohon (books copied in Enkyo era), which is believed to be an old form of the yomihon (literally, reading books, an Edo period woodblock printed novel prevalent from the mid to late Edo period that focused on serious and penetrating studies of human affairs), and his status was too low for In&apos;s messenger; therefore this episode could be mere fiction.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>ただし『山槐記』元暦元年7月6日条に、誰の手によるか不明だが院の使者が平氏によって面に印を着けられたとあり、平氏による苛烈な使者への仕打ちは事実と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article for July 7, 1185 in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;, it is mentioned that In&apos;s messenger was branded on this face by the Taira clan, although it is not mentioned who did this, and therefore, cruel action to In&apos;s messenger by the Taira clan must be a fact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article for July 7, 1185 in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;, it is mentioned that In&apos;s messenger was branded on his face by the Taira clan, although it is not mentioned who did this, and therefore, cruel action to In&apos;s messenger by the Taira clan must be a fact.</e>
<cmt>&quot;this&quot; to &quot;his&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article for August 20, 1184 in &quot;Sankaiki,&quot; it is mentioned that In&apos;s messenger was branded on his face by the Taira clan, although it is not mentioned who did this, and therefore, cruel action to In&apos;s messenger by the Taira clan must be a fact.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>一ノ谷の戦いの敗因には、後白河による虚偽の和平提案・源氏の不意打ちがあったとされ（『吾妻鏡』2月20日条）、平氏の後白河への恨みは激しいものがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that causes of defeat in the Battle of Ichinotani include false proposal for pease by Goshirakawa and surprise attach by the Minamoto clan (Article for February 20 in &quot;Azumakagami&quot;) and therefore, resentment by the Taira clan against Goshirawa was profound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that causes of defeat in the Battle of Ichinotani include a false proposal for peace by Goshirakawa and surprise attack by the Minamoto clan (Article for February 20 in &quot;Azumakagami&quot;) and therefore, the Taira clan&apos;s resentment against Goshirawa was profound.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that causes of defeat in the Battle of Ichinotani include a false proposal for peace by Goshirakawa and surprise attack by the Minamoto clan (Article for April 9 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;) and therefore, the Taira clan&apos;s resentment against Goshirakawa was profound.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>平氏はこの敗戦の打撃からついに立ち直れず、翌元暦2年（1185年）3月24日、壇ノ浦の戦いで壊滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan could not recover the damage from this defet and it was annihilated in the Battle of Dan-no-ura on March 24, 1185.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan could not recover from the damage from this defet and was annihilated in the Battle of Dan-no-ura on March 24, 1185.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan could not recover from the damage from this defeat and was annihilated in the Battle of Dan no ura on May 2, 1185 the following year.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="215">
<j>義経への接近</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Approach to Yoshitsune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Approach to Yoshitsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Approach to Yoshitsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>時忠は壇ノ浦で捕虜となり、4月26日に入洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada was taken prisoner in Dannoura and entered Kyoto on April 26.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada was taken prisoner in Dannoura and entered Kyoto on April 26.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada was taken prisoner in Dan no ura and entered Kyoto on June 3.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>時忠は八尺瓊勾玉八咫鏡を守った功績により減刑を願い（『玉葉』5月3日条）、娘を源義経に嫁がせることで庇護を得ようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada asked for mitigation of punishment by reason of his merits of protecting Yasakani, Magatama, and Yatanokagami (three sacred objects of Yata mirror, a comma-shaped bead, and Yata curved jewels) (Article for May 3 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and tried to obtain protection by making his daughter marry Yshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada asked for mitigation of punishment by reason of his merits of protecting Yasakani, Magatama, and Yatanokagami (three sacred objects: Yata mirror, a comma-shaped bead, and Yata curved jewels) (Article for May 3 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and tried to obtain protection by making his daughter marry Yshitsune.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada asked for mitigation of punishment by reason of his merits of protecting Yasakani no magatama (comma-shaped jewel) and Yata no Kagami (Article for June 9 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and tried to obtain protection by making his daughter marry Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>時忠の娘と義経の婚姻について『平家物語』は機密文書の奪取が狙いだったとするが、義経が承諾した理由は不明確である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot;, it is said that the purpose of the marrige of Tokitada&apos;s daughter with Yoshitune was to rob secret document, but the reason why Yoshitsune agreed is not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot;, it is said that the purpose of the marrige of Tokitada&apos;s daughter with Yoshitune was to steal a secret document, but the reason why Yoshitsune agreed is not clear.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; it is said that the purpose of the marriage of Tokitada&apos;s daughter with Yoshitsune was to steal a secret document, but the reason why Yoshitsune agreed is not clear.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>義経は検非違使として都の治安を担っていたので、長期に渡り検非違使別当を務めて警察権を握っていた時忠の地位を継承しようとしたのではないか、という指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a view that, because Yoshitsune was responsible for public security in Kyoto as a kebiishi, Yoshitsune wanted to inherit the position of Tokitada who worked as the kebiishi no betto and had the police authority for a long time period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a view that, because Yoshitsune was responsible for public security in Kyoto as a kebiishi, Yoshitsune wanted to inherit the position of Tokitada, who had served as the kebiishi no betto and had held police authority for a long period of time</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a view that, because Yoshitsune was responsible for public security in Kyoto as a kebiishi, Yoshitsune wanted to inherit the position of Tokitada, who had served as the Kebiishi no betto and had held police authority for a long period of time</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>5月20日、捕虜となった人々の罪科が決定し、時忠・時実・信基・尹明・良弘・全真・忠快・能円・行命の9名が流罪となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 20, punishment for prisoners was determined and nine persons, Tokitada, Tokizane, Nobumoto, Koretada, Yoshihiro, Zenshin, Chukai, Nouen and Gyomei were sentenced to exile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 20, punishment for prisoners was determined and nine persons were sentenced to exile: Tokitada, Tokizane, Nobumoto, Koretada, Yoshihiro, Zenshin, Chukai, Nouen, and Gyomei.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 26, punishment for prisoners was determined and nine persons were sentenced to exile: Tokitada, Tokizane, Nobumoto, Tadaaki, Yoshihiro, Zenshin, Chukai, Noen, and Gyomei.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>時忠は神鏡を守った功績により死罪一等を減じられたとされるが（『吾妻鏡』5月16日条）、武士ではなく文官であり死刑が予定されていたかは疑問である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is said that punishment against Tokitada was reduced by one rank from death because of his merits to have protected the sacred mirror, it is questionable if the death sentence was really intended because Tokitada was not a warrior but a civillian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is said that punishment against Tokitada was reduced by one rank from death because of his merits of having protected the sacred mirror, it is questionable if the death sentence was really intended, because Tokitada was not a warrior but a civillian.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is said that punishment against Tokitada was reduced by one rank from death because of his merits of having protected the sacred mirror (Article in June 22 for &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;), it is questionable if the death sentence was really intended, because Tokitada was not a samurai but a civilian.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直して補足し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="222">
<j>鎌倉に向かった義経が帰京してから配流が執行される予定だったが、この頃から義経と頼朝の間に不和が発生したらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was planned to execute exile after Yoshitsune who visited Kamakura returns to Kyoro, but it seems that discord between Yoshitsune and Yoritomo was generated around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Execution of exile was planned to take place after Yoshitsune, who visited Kamakura, returned to Kyoro, but it seems that discord between Yoshitsune and Yoritomo was generated around this time.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Execution of exile was planned to take place after Yoshitsune, who visited Kamakura, returned to Kyoto, but it seems that discord between Yoshitsune and Yoritomo was generated around this time.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>『愚管抄』には「関東ガ鎌倉ノタチヘクダリテ、又カヘリ上リナドシテ後、アシキ心出キニケリ」とあり、義経はしだいに鎌倉の統制から外れていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Gukansho&quot;, &quot;After Yoshitsune visited Kamakura and returned to Kyoto, an evil intention came out.&quot; and Yoshitsune gradually deviated from regulation by Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Gukansho&quot;, &quot;After Yoshitsune visited Kamakura and returned to Kyoto, an evil intention came out,&quot; and Yoshitsune gradually deviated from regulation by Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Gukansho,&quot; &apos;After Yoshitsune visited Kamakura in Kanto region and returned to Kyoto, an evil intention came out,&apos; and Yoshitsune gradually deviated from regulation by Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>8月中旬には時忠・時実を除く7名が配地に下るが、時忠・時実は義経の庇護を受けて都に残留していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In mid-August, seven persons excluding Tokitada and Tokizane were transferred to the place of exile, Tokitada and Tokizane remained in Kyoto under protection by Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In mid-August, seven of the nine persons, excluding Tokitada and Tokizane, were transferred to the place of exile; Tokitada and Tokizane remained in Kyoto under the protection of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In mid-September, seven of the nine persons, excluding Tokitada and Tokizane, were transferred to the place of exile; Tokitada and Tokizane remained in Kyoto under the protection of Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>8月中旬は、8月15日が新暦で9月17日となるため、trans1に従いmid-Septemberとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>義経の動きに不信感を抱いた頼朝は、梶原景季を派遣して時忠・時実がいまだに在京していることを咎め、朝廷には配流の速やかな執行を言上した（『吾妻鏡』9月2日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo had distrust for Yoshitsune&apos;s behavior and dispatched Kagesue KAJIWARA to blame stay of Tokitada and Tokizane in Kyoto and proposed the Imperial Court to quickly execute exile (Article for September 2 in &quot;Azumakagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo had distrust for Yoshitsune&apos;s behavior and dispatched Kagesue KAJIWARA to blame Yoshitune for Tokitada and Tokizane remaining in Kyoto, and proposed that the Imperial Court quickly execute exile (Article for September 2 in &quot;Azumakagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo had distrust for Yoshitsune&apos;s behavior and dispatched Kagesue KAJIWARA to blame Yoshitsune for Tokitada and Tokizane remaining in Kyoto, and proposed that the Imperial Court quickly execute exile (Article for October 4 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>9月23日、時忠は情勢の悪化を悟り、配流先の能登国に赴いた（『山槐記』同日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada knew worsening of situation and moved to the destination of exile, Noto Province, on September 23.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada, aware that the situation was worsening, moved to the destination of exile, Noto Province, on September 23.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada, aware that the situation was worsening, moved to the destination of exile, Noto Province, on October 25 (Article for the same day in &quot;Sankaiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>『平家物語』では都を離れる前に建礼門院に別れの挨拶をしているので、ある程度の行動の自由は認められていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot;, he visited Kenreimonin to say farewell before he left the capital and, therefore, it seems that he was allowed to have certain level of freedome of activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot;, he visited Kenreimonin to say farewell before he left the capital and, therefore, it seems that he was allowed a certain level of freedom of activities.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; he visited Kenreimonin to say farewell before he left the capital and, therefore, it seems that he was allowed a certain level of freedom of activities.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="228">
<j>10月13日、義経は後白河に頼朝追討の宣旨を下すことを要請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 13, Yoshitsune asked Goshirakawa to issue a senji to track down and dispose Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 13, Yoshitsune asked Goshirakawa to give a senji to track down and dispose of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>word choice, added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 13, Yoshitsune asked Goshirakawa to give a senji to track down and dispose of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>後白河は躊躇するが左大臣・経宗の意見により、18日、頼朝追討の宣旨を出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa hesitated, but, in accordance with Tsunemune, sadaijin&apos;s opinion, he issued a senji to track down and dispose Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa hesitated, but, in accordance with Tsunemune&apos;s, the sadaijin&apos;s, opinion, he issued a senji to track down and dispose of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa hesitated, but, in accordance with Tsunemune&apos;s, the sadaijin&apos;s, opinion, he issued a senji to track down and dispose of Yoritomo on November 18.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>しかし義経に従う武士は少なく、兵は思い通りに集まらなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were not so many warriors who followed Yoshitsune and he could not collect warriors as he wanted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, not many warriors followed Yoshitsune, and he could not collect warriors as he wished.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, not many samurai followed Yoshitsune, and he could not collect warriors as he wished.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>11月3日、義経は都を退去して再起を図ろうとしたが、あえなく自滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 3, Yoshitsune left the capital intending to recover, but he brought about his own destruction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 3, Yoshitsune left the capital intending to recover, but he brought about his own destruction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 3, Yoshitsune left the capital intending to recover, but he brought about his own destruction.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>時実は義経に同行したが捕らえられ、翌年正月に上総国に配流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokizane went along with Yoshitsune, but he was caught and banished to Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokizane went along with Yoshitsune, but he was caught and banished to Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokizane went along with Yoshitsune, but he was caught and banished to Kazusa Province in February 1185.</e>
<cmt>「翌年正月」は「文治元年1月」としてグレゴリオ暦に直し補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="233">
<j>終焉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finale</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>当時の能登守は基房の寵臣・藤原顕家であり、能登国は基房の知行国だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Noto no kami (the Lord of Noto Province) was FUJIWARA no Akiie who was a favirute retainer of Motofusa and Noto Province was Motofusa&apos;s chigyokoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the Noto no kami (Lord of Noto Province) was FUJIWARA no Akiie, who was a favorite retainer of Motofusa, and Noto Province was Motofusa&apos;s chigyokoku.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the Noto no kami (Lord of Noto Province) was FUJIWARA no Akiie, who was a favorite retainer of Motofusa, and Noto Province was Motofusa&apos;s chigyokoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>基房は反平氏的人物だったが正室は花山院兼雅の姉妹であり、顕家の従兄弟には藤原隆房がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motofusa was anti-Taira and his legal wife was a sister of Kanemasa KAZANIN and FUJIWARA no Takafusa was his cosin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motofusa was anti-Taira; his legal wife was a sister of Kanemasa KAZANIN, and FUJIWARA no Takafusa was his cosin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motofusa was anti-Taira; his legal wife was a sister of Kanemasa KAZANIN, and FUJIWARA no Takafusa was his cousin.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>彼ら親平氏貴族の働きかけにより、時忠は配地では丁寧に遇されていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to influences from those pro-Taira nobles, it seems that Tokitada was treated politely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to influence from those pro-Taira nobles, it seems that Tokitada was treated politely.</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to influence from those pro-Taira nobles, it seems that Tokitada was treated politely there.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>また、都に残された時忠の家族にも特に圧迫が加えられた様子はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is no trace of pressure on Tokitada&apos;s family left in the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there is no trace of pressure on Tokitada&apos;s family left in the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there is no trace of pressure on Tokitada&apos;s family left in the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>時忠の邸宅は一旦は没収されて平家没官領となったが、頼朝は時忠の家族をそのまま居住させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s residense was once forfeited and treated as governmental property forfeited from the Taira clan, but Yoritomo allowed Tokitada&apos;s family to live as it was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada&apos;s residense was once forfeited and treated as governmental property forfeited from the Taira clan, but Yoritomo allowed Tokitada&apos;s family to live as it had.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s residence was once forfeited and treated as governmental property forfeited from the Taira clan, but Yoritomo allowed Tokitada&apos;s family to live as it had.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>娘の宣子は後鳥羽天皇の典侍となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughter, Noriko, became the tenji for the Emperior Gotoba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada&apos;s daughter, Noriko, became the tenji for the Emperior Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s daughter, Noriko, became the tenji for the Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>後の建久6年（1195年）3月に頼朝が上洛した時、時忠邸は若宮供僧の宿坊となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, in March 1195, when Yoritomo visited Kyoto, Tokitada&apos;s residence was used as the guesthouse for wakamiya-gusou.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in March 1195, when Yoritomo visited Kyoto, Tokitada&apos;s residence was used as the guesthouse for wakamiya-gusou.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in April 1195, when Yoritomo visited Kyoto, Tokitada&apos;s residence was used as the guesthouse for priests of Wakamiya Shrine.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。「若宮供僧」は「（鎌倉鶴岡八幡宮の）若宮の僧侶」と訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>領子と帥典侍尼（宣子）が鎌倉の頼朝に愁状を出したところ、頼朝は後鳥羽や吉田経房に配慮したらしく収公を差し止め、時忠の遺族に返還している（『吾妻鏡』建久6年7月19日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneko and Sotsunotennji-ni (Noriko) presented a petition to Yoritomo in Kamakura, Yoritomo suspended seizure paying attention to Gotoba and Tsunefusa YOSHIDA and returned it to Tokitada&apos;s berieved family members (Article for July 19, 1195 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muneko and Sotsunotennji-ni (Noriko) presented a petition to Yoritomo in Kamakura; paying attention to Gotoba and Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, Yoritomo suspended seizure and returned the residence to Tokitada&apos;s bereaved family members (Article for July 19, 1195 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muneko and Sochi no tenji-ni (also known as Noriko) presented a petition to Yoritomo in Kamakura; paying attention to Gotoba and Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, Yoritomo suspended seizure and returned the residence to Tokitada&apos;s bereaved family members (Article for September 1, 1195 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="242">
<j>文治5年（1189年）2月24日、時忠は能登国の配地で生涯を終えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 24, 1189, Tokitada ended his life in the place of exile in Noto Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 24, 1189, Tokitada ended his life in his place of exile in Noto Province.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 19, 1189, Tokitada ended his life in his place of exile in Noto Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>その子孫は時国家と称して代々、格式を誇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posterity had been called Tokikuni ke (Tokikuni family) and enjoyed their social standing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posterity was called Tokikuni ke (Tokikuni family), and they enjoyed their social standing.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posterity was called the Tokikuni family, and they enjoyed their social standing.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>幕末には加賀藩主中納言の前田斉泰も上時国家を訪れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Close to the end of the Tokugawa shogunate, Nariyasu MAEDA, Kaga hanshu (the Load of Kaga Domain) and Chunagon (Middle of Counselor) visited Kami Tokikuni ke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Close to the end of the Tokugawa shogunate, Nariyasu MAEDA, Kaga hanshu (Lord of Kaga Domain) and Chunagon (Middle of Counselor), visited Kami Tokikuni ke.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Close to the end of the Tokugawa shogunate, Nariyasu MAEDA, Lord of Kaga Domain and Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), visited the Kamitokikuni family (branch family of the Tokikuni family).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>墓は石川県珠洲市大谷町則貞の国道249号線傍にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is located by the wayside of the National Road Route 249 in Norisada, Otani-machi, Suzu City, Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada&apos;s grave is located by the wayside of the National Road Route 249 in Norisada, Otani-machi, Suzu City, Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada&apos;s grave is located by the wayside of the National Road Route 249 in Norisada, Otani-machi, Suzu City, Ishikawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>同年5月、奥州藤原氏の追討宣旨を要求する頼朝に、後白河は配流されている時実らの赦免を申し入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1189, while Yoritomo asked for a senji to track down and dispose the Oshu branch of the Fujiwara clan, Goshirakawa proposed pardon of Tokizane and other persons who had been exiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1189, while Yoritomo asked for a senji to track down and dispose of the Oshu branch of the Fujiwara clan, Goshirakawa proposed pardon of Tokizane and other persons who had been exiled.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June the same year, while Yoritomo asked for a senji to track down and dispose of the Oshu Fujiwara clan, Goshirakawa proposed pardon of Tokizane and other persons who had been exiled.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>頼朝はこの要請を受け入れ、時実らは帰京した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo accepted this request and Tokizane and other persons returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo accepted this request, and Tokizane and other persons returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo accepted this request, and Tokizane and other persons returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="248">
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>時忠について、九条兼実は「時忠素狂乱之人也」（『玉葉』安元2年（1176年）7月8日条）、慈円は「サカシキコトノミシテ、タビタビナガサレナンドシタリシ者」（『愚管抄』）と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to Tokitada, Kanezane KUJO criticized as &quot;Tokitada is a crazy person.&quot; (Article for July 8, 1176 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and Jien as &quot;He acted tactfully, and he was exiled repeatedly.&quot; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to Tokitada, Kanezane KUJO criticized, &quot;Tokitada is a crazy person.&quot; (Article for July 8, 1176 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and Jien criticized, &quot;He acted tactfully, and he was exiled repeatedly.&quot; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to Tokitada, Kanezane KUJO criticized, &apos;Tokitada is a crazy person&apos; (Article for August 21, 1176 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;) and Jien criticized, &apos;He acted tactfully, and he was exiled repeatedly&apos; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>ただ、兼実と慈円は成り上がりの院近臣にはしばしば非難の言辞を浴びせているので、これらの記述をそのまま鵜呑みにはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Kanezane and Jien often criticized upstart close aides of the In no kinshin, we cannnot accept those descriptions as they are.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Kanezane and Jien often criticized upstart close aides of the In no kinshin, we cannnot accept those descriptions at face value.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Kanezane and Jien often criticized upstart close aides of the In no kinshin, we cannot accept those descriptions at face value.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>頼朝は時忠の死去を聞いて「智臣の誉あるによりて、先帝の朝、平家在世の時、諸事を補佐す。当時と雖も朝廷の為に惜しむべきか」（『吾妻鏡』文治5年（1189年）3月5日条）と語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoritomo heard about Tokitada&apos;s death, he commented, &quot;As he was a clever vassal, he assisted in various matters in the era of the late emperor and in the Taira era. It is a pity for the imperial palace even today&quot; (Article for March 5, 1189 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoritomo heard about Tokitada&apos;s death, he commented, &quot;As he was a clever vassal, he assisted in various matters in the era of the late emperor and in the Taira era. It is a pity for the imperial palace even today&quot; (Article for March 5, 1189 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoritomo heard about Tokitada&apos;s death, he commented, &apos;As he was a clever vassal, he assisted in various matters in the era of the late emperor and in the Taira era. It is a pity for the imperial palace even today&apos; (Article for March 30, 1189 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="252">
<j>『平家物語』では検非違使別当の宣旨を三度受け、都の治安維持に手腕を発揮したことで「悪別当（峻厳な検非違使別当）」の異名をとったとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot;, it is reported that he received senji to appoint him to kebiishi no betto three times and exercised his ability for maintenance of public security in Kyoto and he got a nickname of &quot;akubetto (strict kebiishi betto).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot;, it is reported that Tokitada received senji to appoint him to kebiishi no betto three times and exercised his ability for maintenance of public security in Kyoto, and he gained the nickname &quot;akubetto (strict kebiishi betto).&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; it is reported that Tokitada received senji to appoint him to Kebiishi no betto three times and exercised his ability for maintenance of public security in Kyoto, and he gained the nickname &apos;aku betto&apos; (strict kebiishi betto).</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>この話は語り本系だけにあり読み本系には存在しないので、実際にそのように呼ばれていたかは不明であるが、『百錬抄』『山槐記』の治承3年（1179年）5月19日条には、強盗12人の右手を切り落としたという記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As this episode exists only in books of the katari-hon system and not in books in the yomi^hon system, it is not sure if Tokitada was actually called so, but in the articles for May 19, 1179, in &quot;Hyakurensho&quot; and &quot;Sankaiki&quot;, it is recorded that he cut off the right hands of 12 robbers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this episode is mentioned only in books of the katari-hon system and not in books in the yomi hon system, it is not certain that Tokitada was actually called so, but in the articles for May 19, 1179, in &quot;Hyakurensho&quot; and &quot;Sankaiki&quot;, it is recorded that he cut off the right hands of 12 robbers.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this episode is mentioned only in books of the narration books and not in books in the yomihon, it is not certain that Tokitada was actually called so, but in the articles for July 2, 1179, in &quot;Hyakurensho&quot; and &quot;Sankaiki,&quot; it is recorded that he cut off the right hands of 12 robbers.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>文官でありながら厳しい処罰を実行できたのは、かつて尉・佐として実際に罪人の追捕や裁判の任務に携わっていた経験によるものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be inferred that the reason why he, as a civillian, could carry out strict punishmentcan was his experiences from bering in service as a jo and suke to arrest offenders and to carry out affairs of trials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be inferred that the reason why he, as a civillian, could carry out strict punishment was his experiences in serving as a jo and suke to arrest offenders and to carry out affairs of trials.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be inferred that the reason why he, as a civilian, could carry out strict punishment was his experiences in serving as a jo and suke to arrest offenders and to carry out affairs of trials.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>このような豪胆で激しい性格の一方で、娘を義経に嫁がせて地位の保全を図るなど、目的のためには手段を選ばない冷徹な資質も持ち合わせていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was of such strong -nerved and had violent temper on one hand, and had coolheadedness to consider the end justifies means such as trying to maintain his position by making his daughter marry Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was of such strong nerve and had a violent temper on one hand, and on the other hand had coolheadedness to consider that the end justifies the means, as shown by, for example, his attempt to maintain his position by making his daughter marry Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was of such strong nerve and had a violent temper on one hand, and on the other hand had coolheadedness to consider that the end justifies the means, as shown by, for example, his attempt to maintain his position by making his daughter marry Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>これは実務官僚の家に生まれ、失脚を乗り越えて政界の荒波をくぐり抜けてきたことで形成されたものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that this was formed through his experiences to be born in the family of official responsible to practical works and survived downfalls and passed difficulties in politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that this was formed through his experiences from being born into a family of officials responsible for practical matters and having survived downfalls and difficulties in politics.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that this was formed through his experiences from being born into a family of officials responsible for practical matters and having survived downfalls and difficulties in politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="257">
<j>時忠は子の時実を実務官僚・吉田経房の娘と結婚させ、有職の公卿・中山忠親に娘を嫁がせるなど、政界に幅広い人脈を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitada had established a wide personal relationships in the political world by making his son, Tokizane, marry the dauther of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, an official in charge of practical works and making his daughter marry Tadachika NAKAYAMA, a noble who was well versed in the ancient court and military practices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitada had established wide personal relationships in the political world by making his son, Tokizane, marry the dauther of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, an official in charge of practical matters and making his daughter marry Tadachika NAKAYAMA, a noble who was well versed in the ancient practices of the court and military.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitada had established wide personal relationships in the political world by making his son, Tokizane, marry the daughter of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, an official in charge of practical matters and making his daughter marry Tadachika NAKAYAMA, a noble who was well versed in the ancient practices of the court and military.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>政治的には高倉の側近である藤原隆季・土御門通親と共同歩調を取ることが多かったが、清盛や後白河とは必ずしも親密とはいえず、時にはその意向に逆らうこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Politically, he often kept common pace with FUJIWARA no Takasue and Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, but we cannot say he was close to Kiyomori or Goshrakawa and sometimes he opposed to their intention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Politically, he often kept common pace with FUJIWARA no Takasue and Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, but we cannot say that he was close to Kiyomori or Goshrakawa, and he sometimes opposed their intentions.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Politically, he often kept common pace with FUJIWARA no Takasue and Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, but we cannot say that he was close to Kiyomori or Goshirakawa, and he sometimes opposed their intentions.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="259">
<j>これは時忠が堂上平氏の出身であり、建春門院と高倉のことを最優先にしていたためと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is inferred that this was because Tokitada was form the Dojo Heishi family and he gave the first priority to Kenshunmonin and Takakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is inferred that this was because Tokitada was from the Dojo Heishi family and he gave first priority to Kenshunmonin and Takakura.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is inferred that this was because Tokitada was from the Dojo Heishi family and he gave first priority to Kenshunmonin and Takakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>非蔵人から権大納言にまで昇進したことを考えると、政治家として稀有の人物であり、その存在意義は大きかったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the fact that he rose from hi-kurodo to gon-dainagon, he was a rare person as a statesman and the significance of his existence was quite large.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from his rise from hi-kurodo to gon-dainagon, he was a rare person as a statesman, and the significance of his existence was quite large.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from his rise from hikurodo to Gon Dainagon, he was a rare person as a statesman, and the significance of his existence was quite large.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="261">
<j>時忠の母について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding Tokitada&apos;s Mother</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding Tokitada&apos;s Mother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding Tokitada&apos;s Mother</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>『公卿補任』の時忠の項に母の記載はなく、弟・親宗の項に「母同時忠卿」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article for Tokitada in &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot;, there is no description about Tokitada&apos;s mother and, in the article for Chikamune, his younger brother, it is written as &quot;mother was same as that for Tokitada.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article for Tokitada in &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot;, there is no description of Tokitada&apos;s mother and, in the article for Chikamune, his younger brother, it is written &quot;mother was same as that for Tokitada.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article for Tokitada in &quot;Kugyo bunin,&quot; there is no description of Tokitada&apos;s mother and, in the article for Chikamune, his younger brother, it is written &apos;mother was same as that for Tokitada.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションなどを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>『尊卑分脈』の時忠の項にも母の記載はなく、親宗の項に「母大膳大夫藤家範女」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in the article for Tokitada in &quot;Sonbi bunmyaku&quot;, there is not description about his mother and, in the article for Chikamun, it is writeen as &quot;mother, daughter of FUJIWARA no Ienori, Daizen no Daibu (a chief officer of the Division of Meals).</e>
<cmt>「母大膳大夫藤家範女」は、「母大膳大夫藤原家範女」の誤りと判断し、そのように訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in the article for Tokitada in &quot;Sonbi bunmyaku&quot;, there is no description of his mother and, in the article for Chikamun, it is written &quot;mother, daughter of FUJIWARA no Ienori, Daizen no Daibu (a chief officer of the Division of Meals)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in the article for Tokitada in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy), there is no description of his mother and, in the article for Chikamune, it is written &apos;mother, daughter of FUJIWARA no Ienori, Daizen no Daibu (a chief officer of the Division of Meals).&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語集から補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>親宗の隣にある時子の項には「母同」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article for Tokiko, that is placed adjacent to the article for Chikamune, it is written as &quot;mother, the same.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article for Tokiko, which is placed adjacent to the article for Chikamune, it is written, &quot;mother, the same.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article for Tokiko, which is placed adjacent to the article for Chikamune, it is written, &apos;mother, the same.&apos;</e>
<cmt>半角スペースにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="265">
<j>『尊卑分脈』の藤原道隆流・藤原家範女の項には「美福門院女房少将局平親宗母」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article for FUJIWARA no Michitaka, dauther of FJIWARA no Ienori, it is written &quot;nyobo (a court lady) for Bifukumonin, shosho no tsubone (the office of minor captain), mother of TAIRA no Chikamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article for FUJIWARA no Michitaka Branch, dauther of FUJIWARA no Ienori, it is written &quot;nyobo (a court lady) for Bifukumonin, shosho no tsubone (the office of minor captain), mother of TAIRA no Chikamune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation, omitted &quot;branch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article for FUJIWARA no Michitaka linage, daughter of FUJIWARA no Ienori in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku,&quot; it is written &apos;nyobo (a court lady) for Bifukumonin, shosho no tsubone (the office of minor captain), mother of TAIRA no Chikamune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>ところが藤原基隆（家範の子）女の項にも、同じく「美福門院女房少将局平親宗母」という記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the article for FUJIWARA no Mototaka (Ienori&apos;sn son) also, a description, nyobo (a court lady) for Bikumonin, shosho no tsubone (the office of minor captain), mother of TAIRA no Chikamune.exists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the article for FUJIWARA no Mototaka (Ienori&apos;s son) also, there exists a description, &quot;nyobo (a court lady) for Bikumonin, shosho no tsubone (the office of minor captain), mother of TAIRA no Chikamune&quot;.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, omitted &quot;branch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the article for daughter of FUJIWARA no Mototaka (Ienori&apos;s son) also, there exists a description, &apos;nyobo for Bifukumonin, shosho no tsubone (the office of minor captain), mother of TAIRA no Chikamune.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="267">
<j>一方、勧修寺流・能円（藤原顕憲の子）の項には、「母官女二条大宮半物大納言時忠并従二位時子同母」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in the article for Kanshu-ji Branch, Noen (FUJIWARA no Akinori&apos;s son), it is written as &quot;Mother, a court lady, a hashita mono for Empress Dowager Nijo, mother of dainagon Tokitada and junii Tokiko.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in the article for Kanshu-ji Branch, Noen (FUJIWARA no Akinori&apos;s son), it is written,&quot;Mother, a court lady, a hashita mono for Empress Dowager Nijo, mother of dainagon Tokitada and junii Tokiko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation, omitted &quot;branch&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in the article for Kanshu-ji linage, Noen (FUJIWARA no Akinori&apos;s son), it is written, &apos;Mother, a court lady, a hashita mono for Empress Dowager Nijo, mother of Dainagon Tokitada and Junii Tokiko.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>このように『公卿補任』『尊卑分脈』の各記事には、混乱と矛盾が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are such confusion and inconsistency in articles of &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot; and &quot;Sonbi bunmyaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such confusion and inconsistency is found in articles of &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot; and &quot;Sonbi bunmyaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such confusion and inconsistency is found in articles of &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot; and &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="269">
<j>まず、親宗の母「美福門院女房少将局」が家範の娘と基隆の娘のどちらであるか、という問題がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all, it is not clear if Chikamune&apos;s mother &quot;nyobo of Bifukumonin, shosho no tsubone&quot;was Ienori&apos;s daughter or Mototaka&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First of all, it is not clear if Chikamune&apos;s mother &quot;nyobo of Bifukumonin, shosho no tsubone&quot; was Ienori&apos;s daughter or Mototaka&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First of all, it is not clear if Chikamune&apos;s mother &apos;nyobo of Bifukumonin, shosho no tsubone&apos; was Ienori&apos;s daughter or Mototaka&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>これについては、家範（1048年生まれ）の娘が美福門院（1117年生まれ）に女房として仕え、親宗（1144年生まれ）を産んだとするのは年代的に合わないため、基隆（1075年生まれ）の娘とするのが妥当と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this point, it seems appropriate to judge that she was Mototaka&apos;s (born in 1075) daughter because it is not logical from chronological point of view that Ienori&apos;s (born in 1048) daughter served as a nyogo for Bifukumonin (born in 1117) and gave birth to Chikamune (born in 1144).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this point, it seems appropriate to judge that she was Mototaka&apos;s (born in 1075) daughter, because it is not logical from a chronological point of view that Ienori&apos;s (born in 1048) daughter served as a nyogo for Bifukumonin (born in 1117) and gave birth to Chikamune (born in 1144).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this point, it seems appropriate to judge that she was Mototaka&apos;s (born in 1075) daughter, because it is not logical from a chronological point of view that Ienori&apos;s (born in 1048) daughter served as a nyobo for Bifukumonin (born in 1117) and gave birth to Chikamune (born in 1144).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="271">
<j>次に、能円の母「官女二条大宮半物」が親宗の母・藤原基隆女と同一人物であるか、という問題がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, there is a problem whether or not Noen&apos;s mother, &quot;a hashita mono to court lady, Nijo omiya&quot; was same as Chikamune&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Mototaka&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, there is a problem of whether or not Noen&apos;s mother, &quot;a hashita mono to court lady, Nijo omiya&quot; was the same as Chikamune&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Mototaka&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, there is a problem of whether or not Noen&apos;s mother, &apos;a hashita mono to court lady, Nijo omiya&apos; was the same as Chikamune&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Mototaka&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>半物は女房と雑仕女の中間の身分と推測されるので、公卿になった基隆の娘が半物であったとは考えにくい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the status of hashita mono is inferred to be between nyobo and zoshime, it seems not proper to consider that a daughter of Mototaka, who became a noble, was a hashita mono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the status of hashita mono is inferred to be between nyobo and zoshime, it seems not proper to consider that a daughter of Mototaka, who became a noble, was a hashita mono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the status of hashita mono is inferred to be between nyobo and Zoshime (lower class maid), it seems not proper to consider that a daughter of Mototaka, who became a noble, was a hashita mono.</e>
<cmt>用語集から補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="273">
<j>また、時忠・時子と親宗の母が同じだとすると、基隆女の項に親宗の名だけが記され、時忠・時子の名が欠けていることが不審といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, if the mother of Tokitada and Tokiko was the same person as Chikamune&apos;s mother, it is not clear why only Chikamune is mentioned in the article for Mototaka and lacks names of Tokitada and Tokiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, if the mother of Tokitada and Tokiko was the same person as Chikamune&apos;s mother, it is not clear why only Chikamune is mentioned in the article for Mototaka and the names Tokitada and Tokiko do not appear.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, if the mother of Tokitada and Tokiko was the same person as Chikamune&apos;s mother, it is not clear why only Chikamune is mentioned in the article for daughter of Mototaka and the names Tokitada and Tokiko do not appear.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="274">
<j>時忠・時子と親宗の年齢差も大きく、母は別人である可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the diffierence between the age of Tokitada and Tokiko and the age of Chikamune, there is a high possiblity that the mohter of Tokitada and Tokiko was different from Chikamune&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the difference in age of Tokitada and Tokiko on one hand and Chikamune on the other, there is a high possiblity that the mother of Tokitada and Tokiko was not Chikamune&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the difference in age of Tokitada and Tokiko on one hand and Chikamune on the other, there is a high possibility that the mother of Tokitada and Tokiko was not Chikamune&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="275">
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of Office and Rank</e>
<cmt>他ファイルに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="276">
<j>久安2年（1146年）（17歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1146 (17 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1146 (17 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1146 (17 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="277">
<j>3月16日 (旧暦)：非蔵人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 16 (lunar calendar): Hi-kurodo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 16 (lunar calendar): Hi-kurodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 5: Hikurodo</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="278">
<j>久安3年（1147年）（18歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1147 (18 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1147 (18 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1147 (18 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="279">
<j>1月7日 (旧暦)：蔵人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 7 (lunar calendar): Kurodo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 7 (lunar calendar): Kurodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 15: Kurodo</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="280">
<j>4月11日 (旧暦)：大学寮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 11 (lunar calendar): Daigaku ryo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 11 (lunar calendar): Daigaku ryo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 19: Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="281">
<j>11月14日 (旧暦)：兵衛府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 14 (lunar calendar): Hyoe-fu (the Ministry of Middle Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 14 (lunar calendar): appointed Hyoe-fu (Ministry of Middle Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 15: Appointed Hyoe-fu (Ministry of Middle Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>12月21日 (旧暦)：衛門府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 21 (lunar calendar): Emon-fu (the Ministry of Outer Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 21 (lunar calendar): appointed Emon-fu (Ministry of Outer Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 21, 1148 (December 21, 1147 in old lunar calendar): Appointed Emon-fu (Ministry of Outer Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直したところ翌年になってしまったため、旧暦も補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="283">
<j>久安4年（1148年）（19歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1148 (19 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1148 (19 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1148 (19 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>1月28日 (旧暦)：検非違使兼帯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 28 (lunar calendar): Kebiishi, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 28 (lunar calendar): Appointed to additional post of Kebiishi</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 26: Appointed to additional post of Kebiishi</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="285">
<j>久安5年（1149年）（20歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1149 (20 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1149 (20 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1149 (20 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="286">
<j>4月1日 (旧暦)：従五位下に叙位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1 (lunar calendar): Conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1 (lunar calendar): Conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 16: Conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="287">
<j>保元2年（1157年）（28歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1157 (28 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1157 (28 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1157 (28 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="288">
<j>9月9日 (旧暦)：兵部省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 9 (lunar calendar): Hyobu sho (Ministry of Military)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 9 (lunar calendar): appointed Hyobu sho (Ministry of Military)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 20: Appointed Hyobu sho (Ministry of Military)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="289">
<j>保元3年（1158年）（29歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1158 (29 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1158 (29 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1158 (29 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="290">
<j>11月26日 (旧暦)：従五位上に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 26 (lunar calendar): Promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 26 (lunar calendar): Promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 25: Promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="291">
<j>兵部権少輔如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyobu gon shoyu, as it was</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained position of hyobu gon shoyu</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Hyobu gonno-shobu(Assistant Minister of the Ministry of War).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="292">
<j>平治元年（1159年）（30歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1159 (30 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1159 (30 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1159 (30 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="293">
<j>閏5月25日：刑部省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">25th day of intercalary fifth month: Gyobu sho (Ministry of Justice)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">25th day of intercalary fifth month: Gyobu sho (Ministry of Justice)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 19: Gyobu sho (Ministry of Justice)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="294">
<j>永暦元年（1160年）（31歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1160 (31 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1160 (31 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1160 (31 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="295">
<j>4月3日 (旧暦)：右衛門権佐。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 3 (lunar calendar): Uemon gon no suke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 3 (lunar calendar): Uemon gon no suke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 17: Uemon Gon no suke</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="296">
<j>検非違使に補任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">appointed to kebiishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">appointed kebiishi</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appointed kebiishi</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="297">
<j>10月3日 (旧暦)：弁官兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 3 (lunar calendar): benkan, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 3 (lunar calendar): benkan, concurrently</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 9: Benkan, concurrently</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="298">
<j>永暦2年のち改元して応保元年（1161年）（32歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1161 (32 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1161 (32 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1161 (32 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="299">
<j>4月1日 (旧暦)：正五位下に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 1 (lunar calendar) : Rose to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1 (lunar calendar) : Rose to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 4: Rose to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="300">
<j>検非違使・右少弁・右衛門権佐如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebiishi, ushoben and uemon gon no suke, as they were</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained positions of kebiishi, ushoben, and uemon gon no suke</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his positions as kebiishi, Ushoben, and Uemon Gon no suke.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="301">
<j>9月15日 (旧暦)：解官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 15 (lunar calendar): Dismissed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 15 (lunar calendar): Dismissed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 12: Dismissed</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="302">
<j>応保2年（1162年）（33歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1162 (33 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1162 (33 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1162 (33 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="303">
<j>6月23日 (旧暦)：出雲国に配流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 23 (lunar calendar): Exiled to Izumo Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 23 (lunar calendar): Exiled to Izumo Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 12: Exiled to Izumo Province</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="304">
<j>永万元年（1165年）（36歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1165 (36 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1165 (36 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1165 (36 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>9月14日 (旧暦)：出雲国より召返</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 14 (lunar calendar): Called back from Izumo Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 14 (lunar calendar): Recalled from Izumo Province)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 27: Recalled from Izumo Province</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="306">
<j>永万2年のち改元して仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）（37歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1166 (37 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1166 (37 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1166 (37 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="307">
<j>3月27日 (旧暦)：正五位下に復位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 27 (lunar calendar): Returned to Shogoinoge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 27 (lunar calendar): Returned to Shogoinoge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 5: Returned to Shogoinoge</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="308">
<j>4月6日 (旧暦)：左少弁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 6 (lunar calendar): Sashoben</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 6 (lunar calendar): Sashoben</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 14: Sashoben</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>6月6日 (旧暦)：右中弁。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 6 (lunar calendar): Uchuben</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 6 (lunar calendar): Uchuben</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 11: Uchuben</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>左衛門権佐を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">saemon gon no suke, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assigned additional post of saemon gon no suke</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assigned additional post of Saemon Gon no suke.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="311">
<j>6月8日 (旧暦)：検非違使兼帯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 8 (lunar calendar): Kebiishi, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 8 (lunar calendar): Kebiishi, concurrently</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 13: Kebiishi, concurrently</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="312">
<j>6月19日 (旧暦)：蔵人兼帯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 19 (lunar calendar): Kurodo, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 19 (lunar calendar): Kurodo, concurrently</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 24: Kurodo, concurrently</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="313">
<j>7月12日 (旧暦)：修理左宮城使兼帯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 12 (lunar calendar): Shuri sa kyujoshi (修理左宮城使), concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 12 (lunar calendar): Assigned additional post of shuri sa kyujoshi</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 16: Assigned additional post of Shuri sagujo shi (Secretary of the left Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="314">
<j>8月27日 (旧暦)：従四位下に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 27 (lunar calendar): Rose to jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 27 (lunar calendar): Rose to jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 30: Rose to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="315">
<j>修理左宮城使・検非違使・右中弁・左衛門権佐如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuri sa kyujoshi (修理左宮城使), kebiishi, uchuben and saemon gon no suke, as they were</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained positions as shuri sa kyujoshi, kebiishi, uchuben, and saemon gon no suke</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his positions as Shuri sagujo shi, kebiishi, Uchuben, and Saemon no gon no suke.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="316">
<j>11月3日 (旧暦)：従四位上に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 3 (lunar calendar): Rose to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 3 (lunar calendar): Rose to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 4: Rose to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="317">
<j>修理左宮城使・検非違使・右中弁・左衛門権佐如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuri sa kyujoshi (修理左宮城使), kebiishi, uchuben and saemon gon no suke, as they were</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained positions as shuri sa kyujoshi, kebiishi, uchuben, and saemon gon no suke</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his positions as Shuri sagujo shi, kebiishi, Uchuben, and Saemon no gon no suke.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="65">
<sen id="318">
<j>11月16日 (旧暦)：蔵人頭に補任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 16 (lunar calendar): Appointed to kurodo no to,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 16 (lunar calendar): Appointed kurodo no to</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 17: Appointed Kurodo no to</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="66">
<sen id="319">
<j>仁安2年（1167年）（38歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1167 (38 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1167 (38 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1167 (38 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="320">
<j>1月5日 (旧暦)：正四位下に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5 (lunar calendar): Rose to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5 (lunar calendar): Rose to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 3: Rose to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="321">
<j>蔵人頭如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurodo no to, as it was</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained position as kurodo no to</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="67">
<sen id="322">
<j>1月30日 (旧暦)：右大弁兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 30 (lunar calendar): Udaiben, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 30 (lunar calendar): Assigned additional post of udaiben</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 28: Assigned additional post of Udaiben</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="323">
<j>2月11日 (旧暦)：参議。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 11 (lunar calendar): Sangi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 11 (lunar calendar): Sangi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 11: Sangi</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="324">
<j>右兵衛督兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uhyoue no kami, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assigned additional post of uhyoue no kami</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assigned additional post of Uhyoe no kami.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="325">
<j>蔵人頭・右大弁両官職止む</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigned as kurodo no to and udaiben</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resigned as kurodo no to and udaiben</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Resigned as Kurodo no to and Udaiben</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="68">
<sen id="326">
<j>仁安3年（1168年）（39歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1168 (39 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1168 (39 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1168 (39 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="327">
<j>1月11日 (旧暦)：能登権守兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 11 (lunar calendar): Noto Province, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 11 (lunar calendar): Assigned additional post as Noto Province</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 28: Assigned additional post as Noto no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Noto Province)</e>
<cmt>ウェブに合わせて原文、訳文を直し、グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="328">
<j>2月17日 (旧暦)：従三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 17 (lunar calendar): Rose to Jusanmi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 17 (lunar calendar): Rose to Jusanmi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 4: Rose to Jusanmi</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="69">
<sen id="329">
<j>7月3日 (旧暦)：検非違使別当（一回目）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 3 (lunar calendar): kebiishi betto (first time)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 3 (lunar calendar): appointed kebiishi betto (first time)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 14: Appointed Kebiishi no betto (first time)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="330">
<j>右衛門督を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uemon no kami, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assigned additional post of uemon no kami</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assigned additional post of Uemon no kami.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="331">
<j>参議如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangi, as it was</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained position as sangi</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Sangi.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="70">
<sen id="332">
<j>8月4日 (旧暦)：正三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 4 (lunar calendar): Rose to Shosanmi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 4 (lunar calendar): Rose to Shosanmi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 14: Rose to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="333">
<j>参議・検非違使別当・右衛門督如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangi, kebiishi betto and uemon no kami, as they were</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained posts as sangi, kebiishi betto, and uemon no kami</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his positions as Sangi, Kebiishi no betto, and Uemon no kami.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="71">
<sen id="334">
<j>8月10日 (旧暦)：中納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 10 (lunar calendar): Chunagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 10 (lunar calendar): Appointed chunagon</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 20: Appointed Chunagon</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="335">
<j>8月12日 (旧暦)：検非違使別当・右衛門督両官職兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 12 (lunar calendar): kebiishi betto and uemon no kami, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 12 (lunar calendar): Assigned additional posts as kebiishi betto and uemon no kami</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 22: Assigned additional posts as Kebiishi no betto and Uemon no kami.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="72">
<sen id="336">
<j>仁安4年のち改元して嘉応元年（1169年）（40歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1169 (40 year old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1169 (40 years old)</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1169 (40 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="337">
<j>12月28日 (旧暦)：解官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 28 (lunar calendar): Dismissed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 28 (lunar calendar): Dismissed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 23, 1170 (December 28, 1169 in old lunar calendar): Dismissed.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直したところ翌年になってしまったため、旧暦も補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="338">
<j>出雲国に配流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exiled to Izumo Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exiled to Izumo Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exiled to Izumo Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="73">
<sen id="339">
<j>嘉応2年（1170年）（41歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1170 (41 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1170 (41 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1170 (41 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="340">
<j>2月6日 (旧暦)：出雲国より召返</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 6 (lunar calendar): Called back from Izumo Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 6 (lunar calendar): Recalled from Izumo Province</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 2: Recalled from Izumo Province</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="341">
<j>12月8日 (旧暦)：正三位に復位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 8 (lunar calendar): Returned to Shosanmi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 8 (lunar calendar): Returned to Shosanmi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 22, 1171 (December 8 in old lunar calendar): Returned to Shosanmi</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直したところ翌年になってしまったため、旧暦も補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="74">
<sen id="342">
<j>嘉応3年のち改元して承安 (日本)元年（1171年）（42歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1171 (42 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1171 (42 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1171 (42 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="343">
<j>4月21日 (旧暦)：権中納言還任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 21 (lunar calendar): Reapointed to gon dainagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 21 (lunar calendar): Reapointed gon dainagon</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 3: Reappointed Gon Chunagon</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にし、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="75">
<sen id="344">
<j>承安2年（1172年）（43歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1172 (43 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1172 (43 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1172 (43 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="345">
<j>2月10日 (旧暦)：中宮権大夫兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 10 (lunar calendar): Chugu gon no daibu, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 10 (lunar calendar): Assigned additional post of chugu gon no daibu</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 13: Assigned additional post of Chugu Gon no daibu (provisional master of the Consort&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="76">
<sen id="346">
<j>承安4年（1174年）（45歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1174 (45 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1174 (45 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1174 (45 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="347">
<j>1月11日 (旧暦)：従二位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Janary 11 (lunar calendar): Rose to Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Janary 11 (lunar calendar): Rose to Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 21: Rose to Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="348">
<j>権中納言・中宮権大夫如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his positions as Gon Chunagon and Chugu Gon no daibu.</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="77">
<sen id="349">
<j>安元元年（1175年）（46歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1175 (46 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1175 (46 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1175 (46 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="350">
<j>11月12日 (旧暦)：検非違使別当（二回目）・右衛門督両官職兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 12 (lunar calendar): kebiishi betto (second time) and uemon no kami, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 12 (lunar calendar): Appointed kebiishi betto (second time) and uemon no kami, concurrently</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 2, 1176 (November 12, 1175 in old lunar calendar): Appointed Kebiishi no betto (second time) and Uemon no kami, concurrently</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直したところ翌年になってしまったため、旧暦も補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="78">
<sen id="351">
<j>安元2年（1176年）（47歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1176 (47 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1176 (47 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1176 (47 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="352">
<j>12月8日 (旧暦)：検非違使別当辞職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 16, 1177 (December 8, 1176 in old lunar calendar): Resigned as Kebiishi no betto.</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="79">
<sen id="353">
<j>安元3年のち改元して治承元年（1177年）（48歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1177 (48 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1177 (48 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1177 (48 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="354">
<j>1月24日 (旧暦)：左衛門督・中宮権大夫両官職兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 24 (lunar calendar): Samon no kami and chugu gon no daibu, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 24 (lunar calendar): Appointed samon no kami and chugu gon no daibu, concurrently</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 3: Appointed Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Chugu Gon no daibu, concurrently</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="355">
<j>右衛門督任替</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Changed to uemon no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reassigned as uemon no kami</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reassigned as Uemon no kami</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="80">
<sen id="356">
<j>治承2年（1178年）（49歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1178 (49 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1178 (49 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1178 (49 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="357">
<j>7月26日 (旧暦)：中宮大夫兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 26 (lunar calendar): Chugu no daibu, concrrently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 26 (lunar calendar): Assigned additional post of chugu no daibu</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 16: Assigned additional post of Chugu daibu</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="358">
<j>中宮権大夫任替</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Changed to chugu go no daibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reassigned as chugu go no daibu</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reassigned as Chugu Gon no daibu</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="81">
<sen id="359">
<j>治承3年（1179年）（50歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1179 (50 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1179 (50 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1179 (50 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="360">
<j>1月7日 (旧暦)：正二位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 7 (lunar calendar): Rose to Shonii (Senior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 7 (lunar calendar): Rose to Shonii (Senior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 22: Rose to Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="361">
<j>権中納言・中宮大夫・左衛門督如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gon chunagon, chugu no daibu and saemon no kami, as they were</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retained posts of gon chunagon, chugu no daibu, and saemon no kami</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his positions as Gon Chunagon, Chugu daibu, and Saemon no kami.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="82">
<sen id="362">
<j>1月19日 (旧暦)：検非違使別当（三回目）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 19 (lunar calendar): kebiishi betto (third time)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 19 (lunar calendar): Appointed kebiishi betto (third time)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 6: Appointed Kebiishi no betto (third time)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="83">
<sen id="363">
<j>治承4年（1180年）（51歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1180 (51 years old),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1180 (51 years old)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1180 (51 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="364">
<j>2月25日 (旧暦)：新院（高倉上皇）別当兼帯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 25 (lunar calendar): Shinin (retired Emperor Takakura) betto, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 25 (lunar calendar): Appointed additional post of betto to Shinin (retired Emperor Takakura)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 29: Appointed additional post of betto of Shinin (retired Emperor Takakura&apos;s office)</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="84">
<sen id="365">
<j>治承5年（1181年）（52歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1181 (52 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1181 (52 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1181 (52 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="366">
<j>11月25日 (旧暦)：中宮大夫辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 25 (lunar calendar): Resigned as chugu no daibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 25 (lunar calendar): Resigned as chugu no daibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 8, 1182 (November 25 in old lunar calendar): Resigned as Chugu daibu.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直したところ翌年になってしまったため、旧暦も補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="367">
<j>建礼門院別当に転任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shifted to Kenreimonin no betto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reassigned as Kenreimonin no betto</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reassigned as Kenreimonin no Betto</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="85">
<sen id="368">
<j>寿永元年（1182年）（53歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1182 (53 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1182 (53 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1182 (53 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="369">
<j>10月3日 (旧暦)：中納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 3 (lunar calendar): Shifted to chunagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 3 (lunar calendar): Reassigned as chunagon</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 7: Reassigned as Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="370">
<j>左衛門督兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saemon no kami, concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assigned additional post of saemon no kami</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assigned additional post of Saemon no kami</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="86">
<sen id="371">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）（54歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1183 (54 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1183 (54 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1183 (54 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="372">
<j>1月22日 (旧暦)：大納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 22 (lunar calendar): Dainagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 22 (lunar calendar): appointed dainagon</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 23: Appointed Dainagon</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="373">
<j>8月16日 (旧暦)：解官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 16 (lunar calendar): Dismissed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 16 (lunar calendar): Dismissed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 11: Dismissed</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="87">
<sen id="374">
<j>伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="375">
<j>山梨県笛吹市石和町市部の鵜飼山遠妙寺の縁起、また石和地域の民話に次のような話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following story is included in the engi () of Ukaizan Onmyo-ji Temple in Ichibe, Ishiwa-cho, Fuefuki City, Yamanashi Prefectureand a folk tale of Isawa region.</e>
<cmt>「石和地域→Sekiwa region」は、「Isawa region」の誤りと判断し、そのように訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following story is included in the engi () of Ukaizan Onmyo-ji Temple in Ichibe, Ishiwa-cho, Fuefuki City, Yamanashi Prefectureand a folk tale of the Isawa region.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following story is included in the engi (writing about the history) of Onmyo-ji Temple on Mt. Ukai in Ichibe, Ishiwa-cho, Fuefuki City, Yamanashi Prefectureand a folk tale of the Isawa region.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="88">
<sen id="376">
<j>『平安末期、殺生を禁じる領主により禁漁となっていた笛吹川で鵜飼をした勘作という老鵜匠が、極刑を言い渡され簀巻きにされて川へ沈められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Heian period, an old cormorant fisherman called Kansaku who fished with cormorants in Fuefuki-gawa River where fishing was prohibited by the Lord who prohibited killing was sentenced to death and rolled up in a bamboo mat and sank in the river.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Heian period, an old cormorant fisherman called Kansaku, who fished with cormorants in Fuefuki-gawa River where fishing was prohibited by the Lord, who prohibited killing, was sentenced to death, rolled up in a bamboo mat, and sank in the river.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;In the late Heian period, an old cormorant fisherman called Kansaku, who fished with cormorants in the Fuefuki-gawa River where fishing was prohibited by the Lord, who prohibited killing, was sentenced to death, rolled up in a bamboo mat, and sank in the river.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="377">
<j>だがその後勘作の亡霊が出るようになり、村人が困り果てていたところ、たまたま通りかかった日蓮と弟子・日朗が供養を申し出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon later, an appalition of Kansaku appeared and village people were were a total loss and Nichiren and Nichiro whe happened to pass by offered a memorial service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon later, an appalition of Kansaku appeared; people of the village were at a total loss, and Nichiren and Nichiro, who happened to pass by, offered a memorial service.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon later, an apparition of Kansaku appeared; people of the village were at a total loss, and Nichiren and his disciple Nichiro, who happened to pass by, offered a memorial service.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="378">
<j>二人が法華経69380字余りを一字一字河原の石に書いて川に流し、供養塔を建てたところ、それ以降勘作の亡霊は出なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both priests wrote over 69,380 characters of Hokekyo (the Lotus Sutra) on the pebbles in the river beach, one character on each pebble and threw them into the river and erected a tower for repose of tehkansaku&apos;s soul and, then, the appalition sopped coming out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two priests wrote over 69,380 characters of Hokekyo (the Lotus Sutra) on the pebbles in the river beach, one character on each pebble, threw them into the river, and erected a tower for repose of Tehkansaku&apos;s soul; subsequently, the appalition stopped coming out.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two priests wrote over 69,380 characters of Hoke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra) on the pebbles in the river beach, one character on each pebble, threw them into the river, and erected a tower for repose of the Kansaku&apos;s soul; subsequently, the apparition stopped coming out.</e>
<cmt>スペルなど変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="379">
<j>この時に日朗がこの地に草庵を結び、それが現在の鵜飼山遠妙寺となった。』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, Nichiro built a thatched cottage and, later, it became Ukaisan Onmyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, Nichiro built a thatched cottage, which later became Ukaisan Onmyo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Nichiro built a thatched cottage, which later became Onmyo-ji Temple on Mt. Ukai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="380">
<j>この話は後に世阿弥により能に脚色され、『鵜飼』の演目で知られているが、当寺および地元ではこの話の鵜匠「勘作」が実は時忠であり、配流先の能登国から逃れてこの地に流れ着き、漁師をしていたという伝説を伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tale was dramatized by Seami into a Noh play and it is know with its title &quot;Ukai (cormorant fishing)&quot; and in this temple and the local society maintained a legend in which the cormorant fisherman &quot;Kansaku&quot; was Tokitada who excaped from the place exile, Noto Province&quot; and drifter to this place and lived as a fisherman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tale was dramatized by Seami into a Noh play and it is known by its title &quot;Ukai (cormorant fishing)&quot;; in this temple and in the local society there is maintained a legend that the cormorant fisherman &quot;Kansaku&quot; was Tokitada who had escaped from his place of exile, Noto Province, came to this place as a drifter, and lived as a fisherman.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tale was dramatized by Zeami into a Noh play and it is known by its title &quot;Ukai&quot; (cormorant fishing); in this temple and in the local society there is maintained a legend that the cormorant fisherman &apos;Kansaku&apos; was Tokitada who had escaped from his place of exile, Noto Province, came to this place as a drifter, and lived as a fisherman.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="89">
<sen id="381">
<j>しかし、上述した通り時忠は能登国で死去しており、現地にれっきとした末裔もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, however, Tokitada died in Noto Province and his descendants still live there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, however, Tokitada died in Noto Province and his descendants still live there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, however, Tokitada died in Noto Province and his descendants still live there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="382">
<j>またこの伝説を容れると数々の無理が生じることから考えても、あくまで郷土に伝わる一伝承、昔話として享受するのが妥当であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furhtermore, judging from the fact that unreasonableness occures if we accept this legend as true story, it is reasonable to take this as a legend or old tale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furhtermore, because it would be unreasonable to accept this legend as a true story, it is reasonable to take this as a legend or old tale.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, because it would be unreasonable to accept this legend as a true story, it is reasonable to take this as a legend or old tale.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="90">
<sen id="383">
<j>なお、なぜ時忠が全く縁もゆかりもない甲斐国の伝説に結びつけられているのかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not know why Tokitada, who had no connection to Kai Province, was connected to the legend of Kai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not know why Tokitada, who had no connection to Kai Province, was connected to the legend of Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known why Tokitada, who had no connection to Kai Province, was connected to the legend of Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="91">
<sen id="384">
<j>登場作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Films and TV Plays in which Tokitada Appeared</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Films and TV Plays in which Tokitada has Appeared</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Films and TV Plays in which Tokitada has Appeared</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="385">
<j>『新・平家物語 (映画)』（1955年 大映、監督：溝口健二、演：林成年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogtatari - a film &quot; (the New Tale of the Taira family) (Produced by Daiei in 1995. Direced by Kenji MIZOGUCHI. Starring Naritoshi HAYASHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shin Heike Monogtatari - a film &quot; (the New Tale of the Taira family) (Produced by Daiei in 1995. Direced by Kenji MIZOGUCHI. Starring Naritoshi HAYASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari&quot; (the New Tale of the Taira family): A film; produced by Daiei in 1955, directed by Kenji MIZOGUCHI, starring Naritoshi HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用して表記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="386">
<j>『源義経 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1966年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：清水一郎 (俳優)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yoshitsune MINAMOTO -The NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama.&quot;(The NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama. Broadcasted in 1996. Starring Ichiro SHIMIZU)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yoshitsune MINAMOTO -NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama.&quot;(NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama. Broadcasted in 1996. Starring Ichiro SHIMIZU)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yoshitsune MINAMOTO&quot;: NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama; broadcasted in 1966, starring Ichiro SHIMIZU (an actor).</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用して表記しました。「NHK大河ドラマ」は重複のため最初のみ訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="387">
<j>『新・平家物語 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1972年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：中村梅雀→山崎努）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike monogatari - The NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama.&quot; (The New Tale of the Taira Family)(The NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama. Broadcasted in 1972. Starring Baijaku NAKAMURA and Tsutomu YAMAZAKI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shin Heike monogatari - NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama.&quot; (New Tale of the Taira Family)(NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama. Broadcasted in 1972. Starring Baijaku NAKAMURA and Tsutomu YAMAZAKI)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike monogatari&quot;: NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama; broadcasted in 1972, starring Baijaku NAKAMURA in first half episode and Tsutomu YAMAZAKI in the latter.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用して表記しました。「NHK大河ドラマ」は重複のため最初のみ訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="388">
<j>『草燃える』（1979年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：森塚敏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kusa moeru&quot; (The NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama. Broadcasted in 1979. Starring Bin MORITSUKA)</e>
<cmt>「森塚敏→Ｔｓｕkaｔｏｓｈｉ　ＭＯＲＩ」は、「Ｂｉｎ　ＭＯＲＩＴＳＵＫＡ」の誤りと判断し、そのように訂正して表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kusa moeru&quot; (NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama. Broadcasted in 1979. Starring Bin MORITSUKA)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kusa Moeru&quot;(The Grass it burns): NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama, broadcasted in 1979, starring Bin MORITSUKA.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用して表記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="389">
<j>『義経 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（2005年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：大橋吾郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yoshitsune - The NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama.&quot;(The NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama. Broadcasted in 2005. Starring Goro OHASHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yoshitsune - NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama.&quot;(NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama. Broadcasted in 2005. Starring Goro OHASHI)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yoshitsune&quot;: NHK&apos;s annual, year-long historical fiction television series drama, broadcasted in 2005, starring Goro OHASHI.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用して表記しました。「NHK大河ドラマ」は重複のため最初のみ訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Lonicera(id:20638), Kawai(id:5634), Cprobot(id:97843), 古聞(id:110289), 三浦大輔(id:93377), Yu-ki-na(id:115957), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), Ef3(id:84901), ＋－(id:17104), Enosi(id:19649), Azusayumi7(id:21082), ゐ(id:795), Pitohui(id:61394), Point136(id:211299), Akimoto(id:6951), MasakiTomasawa(id:17687), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>