<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>赤橋登子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toko AKAHASHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toko AKAHASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toko AKAHASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>赤橋 登子（あかはし とうこ、徳治元年〔1306年〕-貞治4年/正平 (日本)20年5月4日 (旧暦)〔1365年5月25日〕）は、鎌倉時代から南北朝時代 (日本)・室町時代の人物で、室町幕府初代征夷大将軍足利尊氏の正室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toko AKAHASHI (1306 - May 25, 1365 (lunar calendar) lived in Kamakura Period, Nanbokucho Period (the Southern and Northern Court Period) and Muromachi Period and she was the legitimate wife of Takauji ASHIKAGA, who was the first Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toko AKAHASHI (1306 - May 25, 1365 (lunar calendar) lived in the Kamakura Period, Nanbokucho Period (the Southern and Northern Court Period) and Muromachi Period and was the legitimate wife of Takauji ASHIKAGA, who was the first Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toko AKAHASHI (1306 - June 2, 1365) lived in the Kamakura period, the Northern and Southern Courts period and the Muromachi period and was the legitimate wife of Takauji ASHIKAGA, who was the first Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正、(lunar calendar)削除、余分なスペース消去、the Kamakura period, the Northern and Southern Courts period and the Muromachi periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北条久時の娘で、鎌倉幕府最後の執権である北条守時は兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daughter of Hisatoki HOJO and Moritoki HOJO, who was the last Shikke (regent) of the Kamakura bakufu, was her elder brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a daughter of Hisatoki HOJO and Moritoki HOJO, who was the last Shikke (regent) of the Kamakura bakufu, was her elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a daughter of Hisatoki HOJO and Moritoki HOJO, who was the last Shikken (regent) of the Kamakura bakufu, was her elder brother.</e>
<cmt>Shikke→Shikkenに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に、室町幕府二代征夷大将軍足利義詮、鎌倉公方初代公方足利基氏、足利頼子（崇光天皇皇后）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had children, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who was the second Seii Taishogun of the Muromachi bakufu, Motouji ASHIKAGA who was the first Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) and Yoriko ASHIKAGA who was the Empress of the Emperor Suko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had children, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who was the second Seii Taishogun of the Muromachi bakufu, Motouji ASHIKAGA who was the first Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) and Yoriko ASHIKAGA who was the Empress of the Emperor Suko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had children, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who was the second Seii Taishogun of the Muromachi bakufu, Motouji ASHIKAGA who was the first Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) and Yoriko ASHIKAGA who was the Empress of the Emperor Suko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>位階は従二位、従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her rank was Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>原文のままです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her rank was Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her rank was Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>スペースをすべて半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正式な名は平 登子（たいら の なりこ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her formal name was TAIRA no Nariko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her formal name was TAIRA no Nariko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her formal name was TAIRA no Nariko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>北条氏と足利氏との融和策の一環として足利高氏（当時）に嫁ぎ、嫡男千寿王（のちの義詮）を産んだが、北条家への人質として鎌倉に差し出されたり、のちに高氏が鎌倉幕府に反抗したため、結果として兄の守時を含む北条一門が族滅の憂き目にあうなど辛酸をなめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a part of measures to reconcile the relationship between the Hojo clan and Ashikaga clan, she married Takauji ASHIKAGA and gave birth to the heir, Senjuo (later, Yoshiakira) and she went through many hardships that Yoshiakira was sent to Kamakura as a hostage for the Hojo family and that as Takauji later turned against the Kamakura bakufu, as a result, the Hojo family including her elder brother, Moritoki was ruined..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a part of measures to reconcile the relationship between the Hojo clan and Ashikaga clan, she married Takauji ASHIKAGA and gave birth to the heir, Senjuo (later, Yoshiakira) and she went through many hardships that Yoshiakira was sent to Kamakura as a hostage for the Hojo family and that as Takauji later turned against the Kamakura bakufu, as a result, the Hojo family including her elder brother, Moritoki was ruined..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a part of measures to reconcile the relationship between the Hojo clan and Ashikaga clan, she married Takauji ASHIKAGA and gave birth to the heir, Senjuo (later, Yoshiakira) and she went through many hardships that Yoshiakira was sent to Kamakura as a hostage for the Hojo family and that as Takauji later turned against the Kamakura bakufu, as a result, the Hojo family including her elder brother, Moritoki was ruined..</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後も南北朝の戦乱がますます激化し、さらに夫の尊氏の死後に子の義詮と基氏とが対立するなど不幸な境遇は続いたものの、孫の足利義満（後の義満）の成長を見守りながら1365年に没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that also, the disturbance of war between the Southern Court and the Northern Court was intensified and her unhappy situation continued such as confrontation between her sons, Yoshiakira and Motouji after the death of her husband, Takauji, but she watched the growth of her grandson Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA (later, Yoshimitsu) and died in 1365.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that also, the disturbance of war between the Southern Court and the Northern Court intensified and her unhappy situation continued as a confrontation between her sons, Yoshiakira and Motouji evolved after the death of her husband, Takauji, but she watched the growth of her grandson Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA (later, Yoshimitsu) and died in 1365.</e>
<cmt>Flow/grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that also, the disturbance of war between the Southern Court and the Northern Court intensified and her unhappy situation continued as a confrontation between her sons, Yoshiakira and Motouji evolved after the death of her husband, Takauji, but she watched the growth of her grandson Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA (later, Yoshimitsu) and died in 1365.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>尊氏や義詮との家族仲は良好であったらしく、没後は義詮のはからいで尊氏の母上杉清子や尊氏の遺骨が分骨されている寺に彼女の遺骨も分骨された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that her family relationship with Takauji and Yoshiakira was good and, after her death, by YOSHIAKIＲA&apos;s arrangement, a part of her ashes was buried in the temple where a part of ashes of Takauji&apos;s mother, Kiyoko UESUGI, and Takauji had been buried.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that her family relationship with Takauji and Yoshiakira was good and, after her death, by YOSHIAKIＲA&apos;s arrangement, a part of her ashes was buried in the temple where a part of ashes of Takauji&apos;s mother, Kiyoko UESUGI, and Takauji had been buried.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that her family relationship with Takauji and Yoshiakira was good and, after her death, by Yoshiakira&apos;s arrangement, a part of her ashes was buried in the temple where a part of ashes of Takauji&apos;s mother, Kiyoko UESUGI, and Takauji had been buried.</e>
<cmt>ＹＯＳＨＩＡＫＩＲＡ’ｓ　→半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 海衛士(id:19229), Cprobot(id:97843), COCKY(id:19672), UMBRO(id:100484), BitBucket(id:30999), オナガドリ(id:15179), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>