<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>岡田以蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izo OKADA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izo OKADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izo OKADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>岡田 以蔵（おかだ いぞう、天保9年（1838年） - 慶応元年閏5月11日 (旧暦)（1865年6月3日））は、土佐国の郷士で土佐勤王党に加わった幕末四大人斬りの一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izo OKADA (1838 - June 3, 1865) was one of the Bakumatsu Shidai Hitokiri (Four famous assassins of Bakumatsu, end of the Edo Period) who joined the Tosa kinnoto (loyalist clique of Tosa) in his hometown, Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izo OKADA (1838 - June 3, 1865) was one of the Bakumatsu Shidai Hitokiri (Four famous assassins of Bakumatsu, end of the Edo Period) who joined the Tosa kinnoto (loyalist clique of Tosa) in his hometown, Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izo OKADA (1838 - June 3, 1865) was one of the Bakumatsu Shidai Hitokiri (Four famous assassins of Bakumatsu, end of the Edo Period) who joined the Tosa kinnoto (loyalist clique of Tosa) in his hometown, Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「人斬り以蔵」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was referred to as &apos;Hitokiri Izo&apos; (Izo the killer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was referred to as &apos;Hitokiri Izo&apos; (Izo the killer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was referred to as &apos;Hitokiri Izo&apos; (Izo the killer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は宜振（よしふる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina (real name) was Yoshifuru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (real name) was Yoshifuru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (real name) was Yoshifuru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>香美郡岩村に二十石六斗四升五合の郷士岡田義平の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Iwamura, Kami County as the eldest son of Yoshihira OKADA who was a country samurai that earned 20 kokou 6 to 4 sho 5 go in rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Iwamura, Kami County as the eldest son of Yoshihira OKADA, who was a country samurai that earned 20 kokou 6 to 4 sho 5 go in rice.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Iwamura, Kami County as the eldest son of Yoshihira OKADA, who was a country samurai that earned 20 koku 6 to 4 sho 5 go in rice.</e>
<cmt>「kokou」を「koku」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>弟に同じく勤皇党に加わった岡田啓吉がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a younger brother named Keikichi OKADA who also joined the Kinnoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a younger brother named Keikichi OKADA who also joined the Kinnoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a younger brother named Keikichi OKADA who also joined the Kinnoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>嘉永元年（1848年）、土佐沖に現れた外国船に対する海岸防備のために父義平が藩の足軽として徴募され、そのまま城下の七軒町に住むようになり、以蔵自身はこの足軽の身分を継いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1848, his father Yoshihira was enlisted as the domain&apos;s ashigaru (common foot soldier) to guard the seaside against ships from overseas that appeared off the coast of Tosa; he continued to live in Shichiken machi inside the castle town, and Izo himself succeeded the status as ashigaru.</e>
<cmt>七軒町の読み方が不明です。「江の口（江口）七軒町」　（『土佐勤王党始末』（新人物往来社）内の寛文七年高知図　参考）という表記を頼りに、『角川　日本地名大辞典　39　高知県』などを参考に「しけんまち」として記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1848, his father Yoshihira was enlisted as the domain&apos;s ashigaru (common foot soldier) to guard the seaside against ships from overseas that appeared off the coast of Tosa; he continued to live in Shichiken machi inside the castle town, and Izo himself succeeded the status as ashigaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1848, his father Yoshihira was enlisted as the domain&apos;s ashigaru (common foot soldier) to guard the seaside against ships from overseas that appeared off the coast of Tosa; he continued to live in Shichiken machi inside the castle town, and Izo himself succeeded the status as ashigaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>武市瑞山（半平太）に師事し小野派一刀流を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a pupil of Zuizan (Hanpeita) TAKECHI and studied under Onohaittoryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a pupil of Zuizan (Hanpeita) TAKECHI and studied under Onohaittoryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a pupil of Zuizan (Hanpeita) TAKECHI and studied under Onohaittoryu school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>武市の門を叩く前にも、我流ながらかなりの剣術の腕前であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before becoming a pupil of TAKECHI, he was self-taught in swordplay, but was quite skilled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before becoming a pupil of TAKECHI, he was self-taught in swordplay, but was quite skilled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before becoming a pupil of TAKECHI, he was self-taught in swordplay, but was quite skilled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>武市に従い江戸に出て、鏡心明智流を桃井春蔵の道場・士学館で学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following TAKECHI, he went to Edo and studied Kyoshin Meichi ryu at Shigakukan, which was the training hall of Shunzo MOMONOI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following TAKECHI, he went to Edo and studied Kyoshin Meichi ryu at Shigakukan, which was the training hall of Shunzo MOMONOI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following TAKECHI, he went to Edo and studied Kyoshin Meichi ryu at Shigakukan, which was the training hall of Shunzo MOMONOI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>万延元年（1860年）、武市に従って中国、九州で武術修行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1860, he followed TAKECHI and practiced martial arts in the Chugoku district and Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1860, he followed TAKECHI and practiced martial arts in the Chugoku district and the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1860, he followed TAKECHI and practiced martial arts in the Chugoku district and the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その途中、豊後国岡藩にとどまり直指流剣術を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On their way, he stopped at Oka Domain in the Bungo Province, and studied the swordplay of 直指 ryu.</e>
<cmt>直指流の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On their way, he stopped at the Oka Domain in Bungo Province, and studied the swordplay of 直指 ryu.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On their way, he stopped at the Oka Domain in Bungo Province, and studied the swordplay of 直指 ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、武市の結成した土佐勤王党に加盟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, he joined Tosa kinnoto which was organized by TAKECHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, he joined Tosa kinnoto which was organized by TAKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, he joined Tosa kinnoto which was organized by TAKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、なぜか後に名簿から削られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For some reason however, he was later crossed out from the name list.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For some reason however, he was later crossed off from the name list.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For some reason however, he was later crossed off from the name list.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>武市の意向なのか分からないが、暗殺の現場には、武市の指示に従って進んで出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not known whether if it was TAKECHI&apos;s idea or not, but Izo voluntarily went forward to the scene of the assassination following the instruction of TAKECHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not known whether if it was TAKECHI&apos;s idea or not, but Izo voluntarily went forward to the scene of the assassination following the instruction of TAKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known whether if it was TAKECHI&apos;s idea or not, but Izo voluntarily went forward to the scene of the assassination following the instruction of TAKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>武市が、教養の無い以蔵を、ただ単に暗殺の道具として使ったともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that TAKECHI used uneducated Izo merely as an instrument in the assassinations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that TAKECHI used uneducated Izo merely as an instrument in the assassinations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that TAKECHI used uneducated Izo merely as an instrument in the assassinations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>土佐藩下目付けの井上佐一郎をはじめ、同志の本間精一郎や池内大学、森孫六・大川原重蔵・渡辺金三・上田助之丞などの京都町奉行の役人や与力、長野主膳（安政の大獄を指揮した）の愛人 村山加寿江の子多田帯刀などを天誅と称して暗殺（村山加寿江は橋に縛りつけられ生き晒しにされた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting with Saichiro INOUE who was the shita metsuke (low class inspector of foot soldiers) of the Tosa Domain, Izo assassinated in the name of heaven&apos;s punishment, Seiichiro HONMA who was his comrade, Daigaku IKEUCHI, Magoroku MORI, Juzo OGAWARA, Kinzan WATANABE, and Jonosuke UEDA who were government officials and yoriki (police sergeants) that belonged to the Kyoto City Magistrate, Tatewaki TADA who was the son of Kazue MURAYAMA (she was tied to a bridge and made a public display alive), a mistress of Shuzen NAGANO (who commanded Ansei no Taigoku, suppression of extremists by the Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>下目付の読み方が不明です。井上佐一郎（資料によっては、佐一郎の一が「市」という表記も見受けられました。『幕末天誅斬奸録』（新人物往来社））について、「下横目」とする表記もあり、「したよこめ」という送り仮名を参考に、「しためつけ」と致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting with Saichiro INOUE, who was the shita metsuke (low class inspector of foot soldiers) of the Tosa Domain, Izo assassinated, in the name of heaven&apos;s punishment, Seiichiro HONMA who was his comrade, Daigaku IKEUCHI, Magoroku MORI, Juzo OGAWARA, Kinzan WATANABE, and Jonosuke UEDA, who were government officials and yoriki (police sergeants) that belonged to the Kyoto City Magistrate, Tatewaki TADA who was the son of Kazue MURAYAMA (she was tied to a bridge and made a public display alive), a mistress of Shuzen NAGANO (who commanded Ansei no Taigoku, suppression of extremists by the Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting with Saichiro INOUE, who was the shita metsuke (low class inspector of foot soldiers) of the Tosa Domain, Izo assassinated, in the name of heaven&apos;s punishment, Seiichiro HONMA who was his comrade, Daigaku IKEUCHI, Magoroku MORI, Juzo OGAWARA, Kinzan WATANABE, and Jonosuke UEDA, who were government officials and yoriki (police sergeants) that belonged to the Kyoto City Magistrate, Tatewaki TADA who was the son of Kazue MURAYAMA (she was tied to a bridge and made a public display alive), a mistress of Shuzen NAGANO (who commanded Ansei no Taigoku [suppression of extremists by the Shogunate]).</e>
<cmt>[ ]を挿入。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>薩摩国の田中新兵衛と共に「人斬り以蔵」と呼ばれ恐れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Shinbei TANAKA of Satsuma Province, he was referred to as &apos;Hitokiri Izo&apos; and was feared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Shinbei TANAKA of Satsuma Province, he was referred to as &apos;Hitokiri Izo&apos; and was feared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Shinbei TANAKA of Satsuma Province, he was referred to as &apos;Hitokiri Izo&apos; and was feared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>八月十八日の政変後、勤王党は失速。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Coup of August 18, the Kinnoto lost its momentum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Coup of August 18, the Kinnoto lost its momentum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Coup of August 18, the Kinnoto lost its momentum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>武市が土佐に戻ると以蔵は土井鉄蔵と名を変え、一人京都に潜伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When TAKECHI returned to Tosa, Izo changed his name to Tetsuzo DOI, and concealed himself alone in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When TAKECHI returned to Tosa, Izo changed his name to Tetsuzo DOI, and concealed himself alone in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When TAKECHI returned to Tosa, Izo changed his name to Tetsuzo DOI, and concealed himself alone in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし元治元年（1864年）6月頃、幕吏に捕えられ入墨のうえ京洛追放、と同時に土佐藩吏に捕われ国もとへ搬送される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, around June of 1864, he was captured by a shogunate official, and on being tattooed, he was banished from capital Kyoto; at the same time, an official of Tosa Domain captured him, and deported him to his hometown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, around June of 1864, he was captured by a shogunate official, and on being tattooed, he was banished from the capital Kyoto; at the same time, an official of the Tosa Domain captured him, and deported him to his hometown.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, around June of 1864, he was captured by a shogunate official, and on being tattooed, he was banished from the capital Kyoto; at the same time, an official of the Tosa Domain captured him, and deported him to his hometown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>土佐藩では吉田東洋暗殺・京洛における一連の暗殺について土佐勤王党の同志がことごとく捕らえられ、上士格の武市瑞山を除いて厳しい拷問を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tosa Domain, his entire comrades of the Tosa kinnoto were arrested for the assassination of Toyo YOSHIDA and the series of assassinations that took place in capital Kyoto, and with the exception of Zuizan TAKECHI who was a Joshi (superior warrior) rank, they had undergone severe torturing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tosa Domain, all his comrades of the Tosa kinnoto were arrested for the assassination of Toyo YOSHIDA and the series of assassinations that took place in the capital Kyoto, and with the exception of Zuizan TAKECHI, who was a Joshi (superior warrior) rank, they underwent severe torture.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tosa Domain, all his comrades of the Tosa kinnoto were arrested for the assassination of Toyo YOSHIDA and the series of assassinations that took place in the capital Kyoto, and with the exception of Zuizan TAKECHI, who was a Joshi (superior warrior) rank, they underwent severe torture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>以蔵も過酷な拷問に耐えたが、遂に全てを白状し、慶応元年（1865年）5月11日に打ち首、晒し首となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izo endured severe torturing, but he finally made a full confession and was beheaded on May 11 1865, and his head was put on public display.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izo endured severe torture, but he finally made a full confession and was beheaded on May 11 1865, and his head was put on public display.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izo endured severe torture, but he finally made a full confession and was beheaded on May 11 1865, and his head was put on public display.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>辞世の句は「君が為 尽くす心は 水の泡 消えにし後ぞ 澄み渡るべき」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His death haiku read &apos;My mind that served for you came to nothing, and will only clear up after you&apos;ve gone.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His death haiku read &apos;My mind that served for you came to nothing, and will only clear up after you&apos;ve gone.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His death haiku read &apos;My mind that served for you came to nothing, and will only clear up after you&apos;ve gone.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>墓所は高知県高知市薊野駅近郊の山中にある累代墓地。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is the family grave in the mountains near the Azo Station at Kochi City, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is the family grave in the mountains near Azo Station at Kochi City, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is the family grave in the mountains near Azo Station at Kochi City, Kochi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>俗名・岡田宣振として埋葬されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried in his secular name, Yoshifuru OKADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried in his secular name, Yoshifuru OKADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried in his secular name, Yoshifuru OKADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>岡田以蔵の事績については同時代資料も本人の書簡なども乏しいが、その性格・性質についてはいくつかの資料によって伺うことが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Documents from the same period or letters written by Izo himself that tell the achievements of OKADA is scarce, but several documents tells about his personality and disposition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documents from the same period or letters written by Izo himself that tell the achievements of OKADA are scarce, but several documents tell about his personality and disposition.</e>
<cmt>subject-verb agreement</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents from the same period or letters written by Izo himself that tell the achievements of OKADA are scarce, but several documents tell about his personality and disposition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>『土佐偉人伝』（寺石正路）によれば、「性質は剛勇で武技を好み、非常に逞しい体躯を持った巨漢」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Tosa Ijinden&quot; (Lives of Great People of Tosa) (Masamichi TERAISHI), he was &apos;courageous, fond of martial arts, and a giant with extremely robust body.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Tosa Ijinden&quot; (Lives of Great People of Tosa) (Masamichi TERAISHI), he was &apos;courageous, fond of martial arts, and a giant with an extremely robust body.&apos;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Tosa Ijinden&quot; (Lives of Great People of Tosa) (Masamichi TERAISHI), he was &apos;courageous, fond of martial arts, and a giant with an extremely robust body.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>もっとも同書は皇国史観に伴って幕末勤皇志士が持てはやされた大正10年（1921年）に記された本であり、いささか美化された感もあるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It must be added that there was a bit of a sense of glorification, for this book was written in 1921, a time when loyal supporters of the Emperor at the end of Edo Period were extolled owing to the historical view that Japan was peerless as a country under the eternal reign of a ceaseless line of &quot;living-god&quot; emperors.</e>
<cmt>皇国史観の訳は、新和英中辞典(研究社）を参照致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It must be added that there was a bit of a sense of glorification, for this book was written in 1921, a time when loyal supporters of the Emperor at the end of the Edo Period were extolled owing to the historical view that Japan was peerless as a country under the eternal reign of a ceaseless line of &quot;living-god&quot; emperors.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It must be added that there was a bit of a sense of glorification, for this book was written in 1921, a time when loyal supporters of the Emperor at the end of the Edo Period were extolled owing to the historical view that Japan was peerless as a country under the eternal reign of a ceaseless line of &quot;living-god&quot; emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>最近の研究では実際には性格は粗く酒色を好んだとされ、殊に晩年は土佐勤王党の仲間からさえ疎まれていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the recent studies, he was in fact rough, and loved sake and women; especially in his later years, he was treated coldly even from his comrades of the Tosa kinnoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to recent studies, he was in fact rough, and loved sake and women; especially in his later years, he was treated coldly even by his comrades of the Tosa kinnoto.</e>
<cmt>article, preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to recent studies, he was in fact rough, and loved sake and women; especially in his later years, he was treated coldly even by his comrades of the Tosa kinnoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>以蔵が捕縛されたと知った武市半平太は、実家への手紙で「あのような安方（あほう）は早々と死んでくれれば良いのに、おめおめと国許へ戻って来て、親がさぞかし嘆くであろう」と、以蔵に良い感情を持っていなかったことが伺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanpeita TAKECHI who learned of Izo&apos;s arrest wrote in a letter to his home, &apos;it is better for such a fool to die soon, and how his parents would lament over him for returning unashamedly to his hometown,&apos; which indicates his ill feeling towards Izo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanpeita TAKECHI, who learned of Izo&apos;s arrest, wrote in a letter to his home, &apos;it is better for such a fool to die soon, and how his parents would lament over him for returning unashamedly to his hometown,&apos; which indicates his ill feeling towards Izo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanpeita TAKECHI, who learned of Izo&apos;s arrest, wrote in a letter to his home, &apos;it is better for such a fool to die soon, and how his parents would lament over him for returning unashamedly to his hometown,&apos; which indicates his ill feeling towards Izo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>以蔵はまた、家が七軒町にあったことから「七以」と軽蔑的に呼ばれていたことも、田内恵吉（武市の実弟）などの書簡として伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letters which were considered to be written by Keikichi TAUCHI (TAKECHI&apos;s real younger brother) and so on tells that since his house stood in Shichiken machi, Izo was also disdainfully referred to as &apos;七以.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「七以」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Letters which were considered to be written by Keikichi TAUCHI (TAKECHI&apos;s real younger brother) and so on tell that since his house stood in Shichiken machi, Izo was also disdainfully referred to as &apos;七以.&apos;</e>
<cmt>subject-verb agreement</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Letters which were considered to be written by Keikichi TAUCHI (TAKECHI&apos;s real younger brother) and so on tell that since his house stood in Shichiken machi, Izo was also disdainfully referred to as &apos;七以.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>一説によれば、以蔵の捕縛を知った武市は彼の自白によって他の同志が危険に晒されるのを恐れ、自分に心酔した牢役人を通じて以蔵に毒を盛ろうとしたとさえ言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, on learning Izo&apos;s arrest, TAKECHI became afraid that Izo&apos;s confession may put his comrades on line, and that he even tried to poison Izo through a jail keeping government official who was devoted to TAKECHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, on learning of Izo&apos;s arrest, TAKECHI became afraid that Izo&apos;s confession may put his comrades on line, and he even tried to poison Izo through a jail keeping government official who was devoted to TAKECHI.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, on learning of Izo&apos;s arrest, TAKECHI became afraid that Izo&apos;s confession may put his comrades on line, and he even tried to poison Izo through a jail keeping government official who was devoted to TAKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これは小説をはじめ広く知られるエピソードで、それらによればこの際、武市は性根の弱い以蔵が拷問に簡単に屈してしまうと心配したとか、以蔵が軽輩故に他の同士より一層激しく耐え難い拷問に遭うであろうと予想した、また、毒を送られた以蔵はそれを（毒とは知らずに）服んだが死なず拷問に屈して白状したとか、毒を見破って憤りのあまり自白に及んだなどと様々に解釈されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an episode widely known through novels and so on and is interpreted in many ways; and according to these episodes, TAKECHI was anxious that a weak natured Izo may easily give into torture, or that Izo may go under a far more severe torture than his other comrades due to his frivolousness, or Izo who received the poison and drank it (not knowing that it was poison), but did not die and confessed for not being able to withstand the torturing, or he confessed in anger in finding out that it was poison.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an episode widely known through novels and so on that is interpreted in many ways; according to versions of this episode, TAKECHI was anxious that a weak natured Izo may easily give into torture; or that Izo may go under a far more severe torture than his other comrades due to his frivolousness; or that Izo received the poison and drank it (not knowing that it was poison), but did not die and confessed for not being able to withstand the torture; or he confessed in anger in finding out that it was poison.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an episode widely known through novels and so on that is interpreted in many ways; according to versions of this episode, TAKECHI was anxious that a weak natured Izo may easily give into torture; or that Izo may go under a far more severe torture than his other comrades due to his frivolousness; or that Izo received the poison and drank it (not knowing that it was poison), but did not die and confessed for not being able to withstand the torture; or he confessed in anger in finding out that it was poison.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>こうした点が、武市から見た以蔵が「ただの暗殺の道具」に過ぎなかったのではないか、とされる所以である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These show why, through the eyes of TAKECHI, Izo was considered &apos;merely as an instrument for assassination.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These show why, through the eyes of TAKECHI, Izo was considered &apos;merely as an instrument for assassination.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These show why, through the eyes of TAKECHI, Izo was considered &apos;merely as an instrument for assassination.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>以蔵が晩年、武市らから冷遇されていた理由について諸書の記述によれば、他の同志より身分が低く教養が無いことによる差別的感情、彼が手がけた数々の暗殺が露見することにより他の同志に累が及ぶ危機感、彼が自刃してしまえばその露見が防げるにも拘らず彼自身がそれを行わなかったことに対する焦燥感や怒り、さらに“尊王攘夷・倒幕”を旨とする土佐勤王党に属しながら“開国派・幕臣”の勝海舟らの護衛を行うなどした（後述）ことにより“剣術こそ強いが確固たる思想・信念を持たぬ者”として軽蔑されたこと、などが原因ではないかと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to some books, the reason why TAKECHI treated Izo coldly in his later years was due, such as from the discriminative feeling for Izo who had low social standing and no education compared with the other comrades, a sense of danger that exposures of many of the assassinations that Izo took part in may have unfavorable effects to his fellow comrades, and resentment and anxiety toward Izo for not taking his own life although those exposures could be protected if he had committed suicide; furthermore, even if he had been a member of the Tosa kinnoto that aimed for &quot;Sonno Joi (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and overthrowing the Shogunate&quot;, he became a bodyguard to Kaishu KATSU (to be explained later) who was &quot;a member of the open country wing and a vassal of the shogun&quot;; Izo was disdained, for &quot;although skillful in swordplay, he was a man with no resolute ideas and beliefs.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to some books, the reason why TAKECHI treated Izo coldly in his later years was, for example, from the discriminative feeling for Izo who had low social standing and no education compared with the other comrades, a sense of danger that exposure of many of the assassinations that Izo took part in may have unfavorable effects to his fellow comrades, and resentment and anxiety toward Izo for not taking his own life although those exposures could be prevented if he had committed suicide; furthermore, even if he had been a member of the Tosa kinnoto that aimed for &quot;Sonno Joi (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and overthrowing the Shogunate&quot;, he became a bodyguard to Kaishu KATSU (to be explained later) who was &quot;a member of the open country wing and a vassal of the shogun&quot;; Izo was disdained, for &quot;although skillful in swordplay, he was a man with no resolute ideas and beliefs.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to some books, the reason why TAKECHI treated Izo coldly in his later years was, for example, from the discriminative feeling for Izo who had low social standing and no education compared with the other comrades, a sense of danger that exposure of many of the assassinations that Izo took part in may have unfavorable effects to his fellow comrades, and resentment and anxiety toward Izo for not taking his own life although those exposures could be prevented if he had committed suicide; furthermore, even if he had been a member of the Tosa kinnoto that aimed for &quot;Sonno Joi (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and overthrowing the Shogunate&quot;, he became a bodyguard to Kaishu KATSU (to be explained later) who was &quot;a member of the open country wing and a vassal of the shogun&quot;; Izo was disdained, for &quot;although skillful in swordplay, he was a man with no resolute ideas and beliefs.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>後に、岡田以蔵が所有していたとされるピストルが発見され、2006年7月1日より8月31日にかけ、高知県立坂本龍馬記念館の催し『それぞれの幕末‐龍馬・半平太・そして以蔵』にて展覧された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, a pistol which was thought to have belonged to Izo OKADA was found, and from July 1, 2006 to August 31, it was put on display during the event &apos;The end of the Edo period for Ryoma, Hanpeita, and Izo&apos; at the Kochi Prefectural Sakamoto Ryoma Memorial Museum.</e>
<cmt>http://www.ryoma-kinenkan.jp/en/　を参考に致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, a pistol which was thought to have belonged to Izo OKADA was found, and from July 1, 2006 to August 31, it was put on display during the event &apos;The end of the Edo period for Ryoma, Hanpeita, and Izo&apos; at the Kochi Prefectural Sakamoto Ryoma Memorial Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, a pistol which was thought to have belonged to Izo OKADA was found, and from July 1, 2006 to August 31, it was put on display during the event &apos;The end of the Edo period for Ryoma, Hanpeita, and Izo&apos; at the Kochi Prefectural Sakamoto Ryoma Memorial Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>同館の説明によればこれはフランス製で、勝海舟より贈られた物だという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the explanation by this museum, the pistol was made in France, and was a gift from Kaishu KATSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the explanation by this museum, the pistol was made in France, and was a gift from Kaishu KATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the explanation by this museum, the pistol was made in France, and was a gift from Kaishu KATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>ちなみに「ピストル」とは公開の折に称されたものだが、厳密には拳銃である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A &apos;pistol&apos; by the way, was a name applied for the public display, and in the strict sense, it was a handgun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A &apos;pistol&apos; by the way, was a name applied for the public display, and in the strict sense, it was actually a handgun.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;actually&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A &apos;pistol&apos; by the way, was a name applied for the public display, and in the strict sense, it was actually a handgun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>なお、当該短銃は個人所有の物を借用し公開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, this pistol was put on public display by borrowing a personal belonging.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, this pistol was put on public display by borrowing a personal belonging.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, this pistol was put on public display by borrowing a personal belonging.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="40">
<j>また、これとは別に中浜万次郎が護衛を受けた際に自らの短銃を以蔵に託そうとしたが受け取らなかったとの伝承もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from this, it was also transmitted that when Manjiro NAKANOHAMA tried to give his pistol to Izo, Izo had refused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from this, it was also transmitted that when Manjiro NAKANOHAMA tried to give his pistol to Izo, Izo had refused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from this, it was also transmitted that when Manjiro NAKANOHAMA tried to give his pistol to Izo, Izo had refused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>ただ、以蔵がこれら短銃を使用した記録は無く、詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is no record that Izo had used these pistols and the details are not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is no record that Izo had used these pistols and the details are not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is no record that Izo had used these pistols and the details are not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>岡田以蔵が関わったとされる天誅事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenchu Incidents, which Izo OKADA was thought to have involved</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenchu Incidents, in which Izo OKADA was thought to be involved</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenchu Incidents, in which Izo OKADA was thought to be involved</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>井上佐一郎暗殺（文久2年8月2日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination of Saichiro INOUE (August 26, 1862)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assassination of Saichiro INOUE (August 26, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination of Saichiro INOUE (August 26, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>井上佐一郎（いのうえ さいちろう）は土佐藩の下横目（下級警官）で、同年4月8日の吉田東洋暗殺事件を捜査していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saichiro INOUE was a shita yokome who was investigating the case on the assassination of Toyo YOSHIDA that took place on May 6th of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saichiro INOUE was a shita yokome who was investigating the case of the assassination of Toyo YOSHIDA that took place on May 6th of the same year.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saichiro INOUE was a shita yokome who was investigating the case of the assassination of Toyo YOSHIDA that took place on May 6th of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これを危険と見た勤王党では、まず井上を料亭「大与（大與・だいよ）」に呼び出して泥酔させ、心斎橋上にて、以蔵・久松喜代馬・岡本八之助・森田金三郎の4人で、身柄拘束のうえ絞殺、遺体は橋上から道頓堀川へと投げ棄てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinnoto that regarded him dangerous, summoned INOUE at first to a fancy Japanese-style restaurant called &apos;Daiyo (otherwise written as 大與) and intoxicated him; then on the Shinsaibashi bridge with the four men, Izo, Kiyoma HISAMATSU, Hachinosuke OKAMOTO, and Kinzaburo MORITA, restrained and strangulated INOUE, and threw his corpse over the bridge to the Dotonborigawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinnoto, which regarded him dangerous, summoned INOUE at first to a fancy Japanese-style restaurant called &apos;Daiyo (otherwise written as 大與) and intoxicated him; then on the Shinsaibashi bridge, the four men Izo, Kiyoma HISAMATSU, Hachinosuke OKAMOTO, and Kinzaburo MORITA, restrained and strangulated INOUE, and threw his corpse over the bridge into the Dotonborigawa River.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinnoto, which regarded him dangerous, summoned INOUE at first to a fancy Japanese-style restaurant called &apos;Daiyo (otherwise written as 大與) and intoxicated him; then on the Shinsai-bashi Bridge, the four men Izo, Kiyoma HISAMATSU, Hachinosuke OKAMOTO, and Kinzaburo MORITA, restrained and strangulated INOUE, and threw his corpse over the bridge into the Dotonbori-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>「Shinsaibashi bridge」を「 Shinsai-bashi Bridge」に修正しました。「Dotonborigawa River」を「Dotonbori-gawa River」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>この事件の際、井上佐一郎と同行していて難を逃れた同僚の岩崎弥太郎は後の三菱財閥の創始者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yataro IWASAKI, a colleague accompanying Saichiro INOUE on this occasion who had escaped this ordeal, later became the founder of the Mitsubishi Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yataro IWASAKI, a colleague accompanying Saichiro INOUE on this occasion who had escaped this ordeal, later became the founder of the Mitsubishi Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yataro IWASAKI, a colleague accompanying Saichiro INOUE on this occasion who had escaped this ordeal, later became the founder of the Mitsubishi Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>以蔵らが最終的に捕縛された際、この事件についての取調べもあったといい、実行犯の1人である森田金三郎だけが黙秘を貫いたため生き残って戊辰戦争に参戦している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that there was an interrogation when Izo and the others were finally arrested, and only Kinzaburo MORITA who remained silent survived, and took part in the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that there was an interrogation when Izo and the others were finally arrested, and only Kinzaburo MORITA, who remained silent, survived, and took part in the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that there was an interrogation when Izo and the others were finally arrested, and only Kinzaburo MORITA, who remained silent, survived, and took part in the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>森田は後にこれを五十嵐敬之に話し、五十嵐によって『井上佐一郎暗殺一件』なる記録が残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, MORITA had told this story to Takayuki IGARASHI, who left behind a record called &quot;An incident of the assassination of Saichiro INOUE.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, MORITA told this story to Takayuki IGARASHI, who left behind a record called &quot;An incident of the assassination of Saichiro INOUE.&quot;</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, MORITA told this story to Takayuki IGARASHI, who left behind a record called &quot;An incident of the assassination of Saichiro INOUE.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="48">
<j>本間精一郎暗殺（文久2年閏8月20日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination of Seiichiro HOMMA (October 13, 1862)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assassination of Seiichiro HOMMA (October 13, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination of Seiichiro HOMMA (October 13, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="49">
<j>本間精一郎（ほんま せいいちろう）は越後国出身の勤皇の志士の1人であったが、特定の藩に属しない論客であったため、その態度を浮薄と見た各藩の志士から疎まれ始めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiichiro HONMA was one of the supporters of the pro-Imperial from Echigo Province, but since he was a disputant who did not belong to a particular domain, the patriots from each of the domains who thought his attitude frivolous, began to hate him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiichiro HONMA was one of the supporters of the pro-Imperial from Echigo Province, but since he was a disputant who did not belong to a particular domain, patriots from each of the domains, who thought his attitude frivolous, began to hate him.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiichiro HONMA was one of the supporters of the pro-Imperial from Echigo Province, but since he was a disputant who did not belong to a particular domain, patriots from each of the domains, who thought his attitude frivolous, began to hate him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そこへ久邇宮朝彦親王と山内容堂との間で、攘夷督促勅使を巡る争いが持ち上がり、前者を推進する本間と後者を推す勤王党の間で対立が起きたとも、本間が幕府と通じているのではないかと疑われたとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, there was a dispute between Imperial Prince Kuninomiya Asahiko and Yodo YAMAUCHI over the imperial envoy to demand expulsion of foreigners, and when there was a confrontation between HONMA who went forward with Imperial Prince Kuninomiya Asahiko, and Kinnoto that supported YAMAUCHI, HONMA was casted doubt that he was communicating secretly with the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, there was a dispute between Imperial Prince Kuninomiya Asahiko and Yodo YAMAUCHI over the imperial envoy to demand expulsion of foreigners, and when there was a confrontation between HONMA, who went forward with Imperial Prince Kuninomiya Asahiko, and the Kinnoto, who supported YAMAUCHI, HONMA cast doubt that he was communicating secretly with the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, there was a dispute between Imperial Prince Kuninomiya Asahiko and Yodo YAMAUCHI over the imperial envoy to demand expulsion of foreigners, and when there was a confrontation between HONMA, who went forward with Imperial Prince Kuninomiya Asahiko, and the Kinnoto, who supported YAMAUCHI, HONMA cast doubt that he was communicating secretly with the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>『伊藤家文書』によると当日、本間は料亭から酔って退出したところを数人の男に取り囲まれて両腕を押さえつけられ、刀と脇差を取り上げられながらも激しく抵抗して格闘し数名を怯ませたものの、わずかな隙にわき腹を刺され、瀕死のところに止めをさされて斬首された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Documents of the Ito family, &quot;HONMA was surrounded by a couple of men when he came out drunk from a fancy Japanese-style restaurant, and although both of his arms were pinned down and his long and short swords were taken away, he furiously fought against them and made some of them shrunk back; however, in an unguarded moment, he was stabbed at the ribs, and was beheaded when he was on the verge of dieing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Documents of the Ito family, &quot;HONMA was surrounded by a couple of men when he came out drunk from a fancy Japanese-style restaurant, and although both of his arms were pinned down and his long and short swords were taken away, he furiously fought against them and made some of them shrink back; however, in an unguarded moment, he was stabbed in the ribs, and was beheaded when he was on the verge of dying.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Documents of the Ito family, &quot;HONMA was surrounded by a couple of men when he came out drunk from a fancy Japanese-style restaurant, and although both of his arms were pinned down and his long and short swords were taken away, he furiously fought against them and made some of them shrink back; however, in an unguarded moment, he was stabbed in the ribs, and was beheaded when he was on the verge of dying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>但し異説もあり、屋内にいた人物が本間と刺客が刀で打ち合う「炭をぶつけ合うような」音を聞いた、という証言もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was however, a different opinion for there was a testimony by a person inside the house who heard the sound &apos;like throwing coals&apos; when HONMA and the assassins were fighting with swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was however, a different opinion, for there was a testimony by a person inside the house who heard a sound &apos;like throwing coals&apos; when HONMA and the assassins were fighting with swords.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was however, a different opinion, for there was a testimony by a person inside the house who heard a sound &apos;like throwing coals&apos; when HONMA and the assassins were fighting with swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>本間も殺害されたあと、高瀬川 (京都府)へと投げ込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HONMA was also thrown into the Takase-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) after being killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HONMA was also thrown into the Takase-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) after being killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HONMA was also thrown into the Takase-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) after being killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>このときの実行犯は以蔵をはじめ、平井収二郎・島村衛吉・松山深蔵・小畑孫三郎・広瀬健太・田辺豪次郎、そして薩摩の人斬りこと田中新兵衛であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The criminals included Izo, as well as Shujiro HIRAI, Ekichi SHIMAMURA, Shinzo MATSUYAMA, Magozaburo OBATA, Kenta HIROSE, Gojiro TANABE and Shinbei TANAKA, who was known as the Hitokiri of Satsuma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The criminals included Izo, as well as Shujiro HIRAI, Ekichi SHIMAMURA, Shinzo MATSUYAMA, Magozaburo OBATA, Kenta HIROSE, Gojiro TANABE and Shinbei TANAKA, who was known as the Hitokiri of Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The criminals included Izo, as well as Shujiro HIRAI, Ekichi SHIMAMURA, Shinzo MATSUYAMA, Magozaburo OBATA, Kenta HIROSE, Gojiro TANABE and Shinbei TANAKA, who was known as the Hitokiri of Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="55">
<j>宇郷玄蕃頭（文久2年閏8月22日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ugo Genba no Kami (Director of the Bureau of Buddhism and Aliens) (October 15, 1862)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ugo Genba no Kami (Director of the Bureau of Buddhism and Aliens) (October 15, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ugo Genba no Kami (Director of the Bureau of Buddhism and Aliens) (October 15, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="56">
<j>宇郷重国（うごう げんばのかみ）は先の関白九条尚忠の諸太夫であり、安政の大獄の際、島田左近と共に志士弾圧を行い、また和宮降嫁推進にも関わったために攘夷派志士からの遺恨を買っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigekuni UGO (Ugo Genba no kami) was a shodaibu (fourth and fifth rank official) to the former chancellor Hisatada KUJO, and he suppressed the patriots with Sakon SHIMADA during Ansei no Taigoku, and because he was also involved in the set up of Kazunomiya koka (the marriage of Kazunomiya Imperial princess to an ordinary person), he was hated by the patriots of Joi (principle of excluding foreigners) group.</e>
<cmt>「諸太夫」は、「諸大夫」として訳出致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigekuni UGO (Ugo Genba no kami) was a shodaibu (fourth and fifth rank official) to the former chancellor Hisatada KUJO, and he suppressed the patriots with Sakon SHIMADA during Ansei no Taigoku, and because he was also involved in the set up of Kazunomiya koka (the marriage of Imperial princess Kazunomiya to an ordinary person), he was hated by the patriots of Joi (principle of excluding foreigners) group.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigekuni UGO (Ugo Genba no kami) was a shodaibu (fourth and fifth rank official) to the former chancellor Hisatada KUJO, and he suppressed the patriots with Sakon SHIMADA during Ansei no Taigoku, and because he was also involved in the set up of Kazunomiya koka (the marriage of Imperial princess Kazunomiya to an ordinary person), he was hated by the patriots of Joi (principle of excluding foreigners) group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>島田左近暗殺（同年7月21日）以来、身の危険を感じた宇郷は居所を転々としていたが、この日は九条家河原町御殿に潜伏しているのを見つかり、寝所を岡田以蔵・岡本八之助・村田忠三郎及び肥後国の堤松左衛門に急襲された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the assassination of Sakon SHIMADA (August 16 of the same year), UGO who sensed danger, was moving from place to place, but he was found hiding in the Karamachi Palace of the Kujo family, and while sleeping, he was suddenly attacked by Izo OKADA, Hachinosuke OKAMOTO, Chuzaburo MURATA, and Matsuzaemon TSUTSUMI from Higo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the assassination of Sakon SHIMADA (August 16 of the same year), UGO, who sensed danger, was moving from place to place, but he was found hiding in the Karamachi Palace of the Kujo family, and while sleeping, he was suddenly attacked by Izo OKADA, Hachinosuke OKAMOTO, Chuzaburo MURATA, and Matsuzaemon TSUTSUMI from Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the assassination of Sakon SHIMADA (August 16 of the same year), UGO, who sensed danger, was moving from place to place, but he was found hiding in the Kawaramachi Palace of the Kujo family, and while sleeping, he was suddenly attacked by Izo OKADA, Hachinosuke OKAMOTO, Chuzaburo MURATA, and Matsuzaemon TSUTSUMI from Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>「Karamachi」を「Kawaramachi」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>飛び起きて逃げようとしたところを以蔵に斬り倒され、子息も堤によって殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was slain by Izo when he tried to escape by jumping out of bed, and his son was also killed by TSUTSUMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was slain by Izo when he tried to escape by jumping out of bed, and his son was also killed by TSUTSUMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was slain by Izo when he tried to escape by jumping out of bed, and his son was also killed by TSUTSUMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>宇郷の首は加茂川河岸に槍に刺し斬奸状と共に晒された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">UGO&apos;s head was thrusted into a spear, and with a document explaining why he was killed, it was put on public display at the riverbank of the Kamogawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">UGO&apos;s head was thrust into a spear, and with a document explaining why he was killed, it was put on public display on the riverbank of the Kamogawa River.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">UGO&apos;s head was thrust into a spear, and with a document explaining why he was killed, it was put on public display on the riverbank of the Kamo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>「Kamogawa River」を「Kamo-gawa River」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>以上は『官武通記』による記録であるが、実行犯については異説があり、以蔵の加担を疑問視する向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is described above were recorded in &quot;Kanbu Tsuki&quot; (Records on civilian and military men), but there were different opinions regarding the criminals, and Izo&apos;s involvement was being questioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is described above were recorded in &quot;Kanbu Tsuki&quot; (Records on civilian and military men), but there were different opinions regarding the criminals, and Izo&apos;s involvement was being questioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is described above were recorded in &quot;Kanbu Tsuki&quot; (Records on civilian and military men), but there were different opinions regarding the criminals, and Izo&apos;s involvement was being questioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="61">
<j>猿の文吉殺害（文久2年閏8月30日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murder of Mashira no Bunkichi (October 23, 1862)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murder of Mashira no Bunkichi (October 23, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murder of Mashira no Bunkichi (October 23, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="62">
<j>猿の文吉（ましらのぶんきち。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mashira no Bunkichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mashira no Bunkichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mashira no Bunkichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>「目明し文吉」とも）は、安政の大獄時、島田左近の手先として多くの志士を摘発した岡っ引である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Also known as &apos;Bunkichi, the Meakashi (hired thief-taker)] was an okappiki (a hired thief-taker) who, as an agent of Sakon SHIMADA, disclosed many patriots during Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Also known as &apos;Bunkichi, the Meakashi (hired thief-taker)] was an okappiki (a hired thief-taker) who, as an agent of Sakon SHIMADA, disclosed many patriots during Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Also known as &apos;Bunkichi, the Meakashi (hired thief-taker)] was an okappiki (a hired thief-taker) who, as an agent of Sakon SHIMADA, disclosed many patriots during Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>当然、志士たちから深い恨みを買っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naturally, many royalists hated him deeply.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naturally, many royalists hated him deeply.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naturally, many royalists hated him deeply.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>岡田以蔵・清岡治之介・阿部多司馬の3人は三条河原へ連行の上、「斬るのは刀の穢れになる」として細引で絞殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three men, Izo OKADA, Harunosuke KIYOOKA, and Tashima ABE took Bunkichi to Sanjo-gawara Riverside, and strangulated him with a cord, since &apos;it would leave a stain on the sword to cut him.&apos;</e>
<cmt>清岡治之介および阿部多司馬の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three men, Izo OKADA, Harunosuke KIYOOKA, and Tashima ABE, took Bunkichi to Sanjo-gawara Riverside, and strangulated him with a cord, since &apos;cutting him would leave a stain on the sword.&apos;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three men, Izo OKADA, Harunosuke KIYOOKA, and Tashima ABE, took Bunkichi to Sanjo-gawara Riverside, and strangulated him with a cord, since &apos;cutting him would leave a stain on the sword.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>文吉は島田の高利貸しの手伝いもしており、民衆からも嫌われていたため、裸に剥かれ河原の杭に縛り付け、竹の棒を肛門から体内を貫通させて頭まで通され晒された遺体には投石する者もあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunkichi also helped with SHIMADA&apos;s money lending, and since the people also hated him, he was stripped of his clothes and tied to a stake in the riverside; a bamboo stick had been pierced through his body from the anus to the head, and there were those that threw rocks at his corpse which was made a public display.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunkichi also helped with SHIMADA&apos;s money lending, and since the people also hated him, he was stripped of his clothes and tied to a stake at the riverside; a bamboo stick had been pierced through his body from the anus to the head, and there were those that threw rocks at his corpse which was made a public display.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunkichi also helped with SHIMADA&apos;s money lending, and since the people also hated him, he was stripped of his clothes and tied to a stake at the riverside; a bamboo stick had been pierced through his body from the anus to the head, and there were those that threw rocks at his corpse which was made a public display.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>なお、この時高札に「イヌ」と書いたため、ここから「○○の手先」の蔑称としての「○○の犬」という表現が生まれたという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, because &apos;inu&apos; (dog) was written on the notice board on this occasion, it is theorized that the expression &apos;one&apos;s dog&apos; was created as a derogatory term for &apos;one&apos;s tesaki&apos; (one&apos;s agent).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, because &apos;inu&apos; (dog) was written on the notice board on this occasion, it is theorized that the expression &apos;one&apos;s dog&apos; was created as a derogatory term for &apos;one&apos;s tesaki&apos; (one&apos;s agent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, because &apos;inu&apos; (dog) was written on the notice board on this occasion, it is theorized that the expression &apos;one&apos;s dog&apos; was created as a derogatory term for &apos;one&apos;s tesaki&apos; (one&apos;s agent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="68">
<j>四与力殺害（文久2年9月23日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination of the four yoriki (November 14, 1862)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assassination of the four yoriki (November 14, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination of the four yoriki (November 14, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="69">
<j>渡辺金三郎（わたなべ きんざぶろう）・森孫六（もり まごろく）・大河原重蔵（おおがわら じゅうぞう）・上田助之丞（うえだ すけのじょう）の4人はいずれも京都町奉行所与力で、やはり安政の大獄で長野主膳・島田左近らと共に志士摘発を行っており、宇郷や文吉に対する天誅後、標的とされることを避けるために京都から江戸へと転任するところであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of the four men, Kinzaburo WATANABE, Magoroku MORI, Juzo OGAWARA, and Sukenojo UEDA were yoriki of the Kyoto City Magistrate, and they had also exposed patriots with Shuzen NAGANO and Sakon SHIMADA during Ansei no Taigoku; after the heaven&apos;s punishment against Ugo and Bunkichi, they were transferred from Kyoto to Edo in order to avoid being targeted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of the four men, Kinzaburo WATANABE, Magoroku MORI, Juzo OGAWARA, and Sukenojo UEDA, were yoriki of the Kyoto City Magistrate, and they had also exposed patriots with Shuzen NAGANO and Sakon SHIMADA during Ansei no Taigoku; after the heaven&apos;s punishment against Ugo and Bunkichi, they were transferred from Kyoto to Edo in order to avoid being targeted.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of the four men, Kinzaburo WATANABE, Magoroku MORI, Juzo OGAWARA, and Sukenojo UEDA, were yoriki of the Kyoto City Magistrate, and they had also exposed patriots with Shuzen NAGANO and Sakon SHIMADA during Ansei no Taigoku; after the heaven&apos;s punishment against Ugo and Bunkichi, they were transferred from Kyoto to Edo in order to avoid being targeted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>彼らが石部宿まで来た夜、30名を越す浪士の一団が宿場を襲い、人々が騒然とする中、これら与力4名が殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the evening of their arrival to Ishibe-juku (the 51st post station of the Tokaido Road), more than thirty members of roshi made an attack on the posting station, and in the uproar, these four men were murdered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the evening of their arrival to Ishibe-juku (the 51st post station of the Tokaido Road), more than thirty members of roshi made an attack on the posting station, and in the uproar, these four men were murdered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the evening of their arrival to Ishibe-juku (the 51st post station of the Tokaido Road), more than thirty members of roshi made an attack on the posting station, and in the uproar, these four men were murdered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>斬奸状には憂国の志士を多数捕らえ、重罪に処したことに対する天誅であると書かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had said in a note that described their crimes, that this was heaven&apos;s punishment for arresting many patriots and making them a felon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had said in a note that described their crimes, that this was heaven&apos;s punishment for arresting many patriots and making them a felon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had said in a note that described their crimes, that this was heaven&apos;s punishment for arresting many patriots and making them a felon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>この襲撃には土佐・長州・薩摩藩・久留米藩の4藩から複数の志士が参加していたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that many of the patriots from Tosa, Choshu, the Satsuma Domain, and the Kurume Domain took part in this raid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered that many of the patriots from Tosa, Choshu, the Satsuma Domain, and the Kurume Domain took part in this raid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered that many of the patriots from Tosa, Choshu, the Satsuma Domain, and the Kurume Domain took part in this raid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>武市半平太が書き遺した『在京日記』に土佐からの参加者12名が記されているが、以蔵はその中に入っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;A diary while staying in Kyoto&quot; written by Hanpeita TAKECHI, the names of the twelve of those from Tosa who took part were listed, but Izo was not included.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;A diary while staying in Kyoto&quot; written by Hanpeita TAKECHI, the names of the twelve of those from Tosa who took part were listed, but Izo was not included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;A diary while staying in Kyoto&quot; written by Hanpeita TAKECHI, the names of the twelve of those from Tosa who took part were listed, but Izo was not included.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>しかし一般には、この襲撃に以蔵も加わっていたとする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was generally viewed that Izo took part in this raid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was generally viewed that Izo took part in this raid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was generally viewed that Izo took part in this raid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="75">
<j>平野屋寿三郎・煎餅屋半兵衛生き晒し（文久2年10月9日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Living public displays of Saburo HIRANOYA and Hanbei SENBEIYA (November 30, 1862)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Living public displays of Saburo HIRANOYA and Hanbei SENBEIYA (November 30, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Living public displays of Saburo HIRANOYA and Hanbei SENBEIYA (November 30, 1862)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="76">
<j>平野屋寿三郎（ひらのや じゅさぶろう?）・煎餅屋半兵衛（せんべいや はんべえ?）は、共に商人ながらこの年5月の勅使・大原重徳東下の際に士分となり供をしていたが、収賄や横領などを行ったため評判が悪かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although merchants, Jusaburo Hiranoya (?) and Hanbei Senbeiya ?) were raised to a samurai class when Shigetomi OHARA left Kyoto for Edo as an Imperial Envoy on May of the same year (old calendar), and they had attended to him, but had a bad reputation for accepting bribery and embezzlement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although merchants, Jusaburo Hiranoya (?) and Hanbei Senbeiya ?) were raised to a samurai class when Shigetomi OHARA left Kyoto for Edo as an Imperial Envoy in May of the same year (old calendar), and they had attended to him, they had a bad reputation for accepting bribery and embezzlement.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although merchants, Jusaburo HIRANOYA (?) and Hanbei SENBEIYA ?) were raised to a samurai class when Shigetomi OHARA left Kyoto for Edo as an Imperial Envoy in May of the same year (old calendar), and they had attended to him, they had a bad reputation for accepting bribery and embezzlement.</e>
<cmt>「Jusaburo Hiranoya」を「Jusaburo HIRANOYA」に修正しました。「Hanbei Senbeiya」を「Hanbei SENBEIYA」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>それがまた、この月の勅使に随行するというので、朝廷の威信失墜を懸念した長州藩・土佐藩両藩の志士が団結して天誅を加えることとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since such men were appointed to accompany the Imperial envoy of that month, patriots from Choshu and Tosa Domain that became anxious for the loss of prestige in the Imperial Court stood together and decided to provoke heaven&apos;s punishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since such men were appointed to accompany the Imperial envoy that month, patriots from Choshu and Tosa Domains that became anxious for the loss of prestige in the Imperial Court stood together and decided to provoke heaven&apos;s punishment.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since such men were appointed to accompany the Imperial envoy that month, patriots from Choshu and Tosa Domains that became anxious for the loss of prestige in the Imperial Court stood together and decided to provoke heaven&apos;s punishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>土佐からは岡田以蔵・千屋寅之助・五十嵐幾之助らが、長州からは寺島忠三郎らが加わり、手分けして両名を連行して殺害しようとしたが、家族の助命嘆願もあり町人でもあることから殺すことはせず、加茂川河岸の木綿を晒す杭に両名を裸にした上で縛り付け、生き晒しにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izo OKADA, Toranosuke SENYA, and Kinosuke IGARASHI from Tosa, and Chuzaburo TERAJIMA joined from Choshu, and they split up to take both of the men in and kill them, but they did not kill because of the pleas of their family to spare their lives, and because of their class as townsmen; the two men were put on public display alive, by being tied naked on to a stake which was used for exposing cotton on the riverside of Kamogawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izo OKADA, Toranosuke SENYA, and Kinosuke IGARASHI from Tosa, and Chuzaburo TERAJIMA joined from Choshu, and they split up to take both of the men in and kill them, but they did not kill because of the pleas of their family to spare their lives, and because of their class as townsmen; the two men were put on public display alive, by being tied naked on to a stake which was used for exposing cotton on the riverside of Kamogawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izo OKADA, Toranosuke SENYA, and Kinosuke IGARASHI from Tosa, and Chuzaburo TERAJIMA joined from Choshu, and they split up to take both of the men in and kill them, but they did not kill because of the pleas of their family to spare their lives, and because of their class as townsmen; the two men were put on public display alive, by being tied naked on to a stake which was used for exposing cotton on the riverside of Kamo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>「Kamogawa River」を「Kamo-gawa River」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="79">
<j>多田帯刀暗殺（文久2年11月15日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination of Tatewaki TADA (January 4, 1863)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assassination of Tatewaki TADA (January 4, 1863)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination of Tatewaki TADA (January 4, 1863)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="80">
<j>多田帯刀（ただ たてわき）は、長野主膳の妾・村山加寿江（むらやま かずえ、可寿江とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatewaki TADA was a son of Kazue MURAYAMA (otherwise written as &apos;可寿江&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatewaki TADA was a son of Kazue MURAYAMA (otherwise written as &apos;可寿江&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatewaki TADA was a son of Kazue MURAYAMA (otherwise written as &apos;可寿江&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>村山たか、とする資料もある）の子で、鹿苑寺（金閣寺）の寺侍であったが、やはり長野と共に安政の大獄において志士弾圧に加わったとして標的にされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some documents describe her as Taka MURAYAMA), who was a mistress of Shuzen NAGANO, and he was a terazamurai (samurai who performed administrative functions at temples) at Rokuon-ji temple (Kinkaku-ji Temple), but was made a target since he also took part in the suppression of patriots during Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some documents describe her as Taka MURAYAMA), who was a mistress of Shuzen NAGANO, and he was a terazamurai (samurai who performed administrative functions at temples) at Rokuon-ji temple (Kinkaku-ji Temple), but was made a target since he also took part in the suppression of patriots during Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some documents describe her as Taka MURAYAMA), who was a mistress of Shuzen NAGANO, and he was a terazamurai (samurai who performed administrative functions at temples) at Rokuon-ji Temple (Kinkaku-ji Temple), but was made a target since he also took part in the suppression of patriots during Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>「temple」を「Temple」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>14日夜、島原遊郭近くにある加寿江の家を浪士らが襲撃、寝ていた加寿江を引き出して三条大橋の袂に生き晒しにし、翌晩、大家を脅して連れてこさせた多田を蹴上刑場へ連行の上、殺害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the night of the 14th, roshi (masterless samurai) made a raid on Kazue&apos;s house near Shimahara yukaku, and pulled her out of the bed and made her a public display alive at the foot of the Sanjo-ohashi Bridge; on the next evening, they brought TADA who was taken in by a threatened owner to the Keage scaffold, and murdered him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the night of the 14th, roshi (masterless samurai) conducted a raid on Kazue&apos;s house near Shimahara yukaku, and pulled her out of bed and made her a public display alive at the foot of Sanjo-ohashi Bridge; on the next evening, they brought TADA, who was taken in by a threatened owner to the Keage scaffold, and murdered him.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the night of the 14th, roshi (masterless samurai) conducted a raid on Kazue&apos;s house near Shimahara yukaku, and pulled her out of bed and made her a public display alive at the foot of Sanjo-ohashi Bridge; on the next evening, they brought TADA, who was taken in by a threatened owner to the Keage scaffold, and murdered him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>首は粟田口に晒した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His head was on public display at Kuritaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His head was on public display at Kuritaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His head was on public display at Kuritaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>加寿江は、三日三晩生き晒しにされたともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that Kazue was on public display alive for three days and three nights.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that Kazue was on public display alive for three days and three nights.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that Kazue was on public display alive for three days and three nights.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>この襲撃には合計20名が参加し、長州の楢崎八十槌ら、土佐の小畑孫三郎・河野万寿弥・依岡珍麿・千屋寅之助らと共に、以蔵も加わっていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A total of twenty men took part in this raid, and it was considered that Izo participated with Yasozuchi NARASAKI of Choshu, Magozaburo OBATA, Masuya KONO, Uzumaro YORIOKA, and Toranosuke CHIYA from Satsuma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A total of twenty men took part in this raid, and it is believed that Izo participated with Yasozuchi NARASAKI of Choshu, Magozaburo OBATA, Masuya KONO, Uzumaro YORIOKA, and Toranosuke CHIYA from Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A total of twenty men took part in this raid, and it is believed that Izo participated with Yasozuchi NARASAKI of Choshu, Magozaburo OBATA, Masuya KONO, Uzumaro YORIOKA, and Toranosuke CHIYA from Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>このうち、依岡は大正年間まで存命して、この事件を語り遺している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, YORIOKA lived until the Taisho era, and told of this incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, YORIOKA lived until the Taisho era, and told of this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, YORIOKA lived until the Taisho era, and told of this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="87">
<j>池内大学暗殺（文久3年1月22日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigaku IKEUCHI (March 11, 1863)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigaku IKEUCHI (March 11, 1863)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigaku IKEUCHI (March 11, 1863)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="88">
<j>池内大学（いけうち だいがく）は、元々は尊皇攘夷派の町人儒学者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigaku IKEUCHI was formerly a Confucian scholar that belonged to the townsmen class, who was one of the Sonno Joi ha (supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigaku IKEUCHI was formerly a Confucian scholar who belonged to the townsmen class, and was one of the Sonno Joi ha (supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigaku IKEUCHI was formerly a Confucian scholar who belonged to the townsmen class, and was one of the Sonno Joi ha (supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>条約勅許問題や将軍後継問題などで策謀を巡らせたため、安政の大獄において幕府からの厳しい追及を受けたが、観念して自首したために比較的軽い罪になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he devised stratagems for the problems on imperial sanction on treaties and the Shogun&apos;s successor, he was severely interrogated from the bakufu during Ansei no Taigoku, but because he surrendered voluntarily, he was charged relatively light.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he devised stratagems for the problems on imperial sanction on treaties and the Shogun&apos;s successor, he was severely interrogated from the bakufu during Ansei no Taigoku, but because he surrendered voluntarily, the charges against him were relatively light.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he devised stratagems for the problems on imperial sanction on treaties and the Shogun&apos;s successor, he was severely interrogated from the bakufu during Ansei no Taigoku, but because he surrendered voluntarily, the charges against him were relatively light.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>これが尊攘派志士の目に「幕府に寝返った」と映り、狙われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because this had appeared as a &apos;betrayal against the Bakufu&apos; to the eyes of the patriots that belonged to the Sonno Joi ha, he was made a target.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because this had appeared as a &apos;betrayal against the Bakufu&apos; to the eyes of the patriots that belonged to the Sonno Joi ha, he was made a target.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because this had appeared as a &apos;betrayal against the Bakufu&apos; to the eyes of the patriots that belonged to the Sonno Joi ha, he was made a target.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>大学は変名のうえ大阪に潜伏していたが、おりしも大阪に来ていた山内容堂の酒宴に招かれ、その帰りを襲われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigaku changed his name and hid himself in Osaka, but just at that moment, he was invited to a banquet of Yodo YAMAUCHI, and was attacked on his way home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigaku changed his name and hid himself in Osaka, but just at that moment, he was invited to a banquet of Yodo YAMAUCHI, and was attacked on his way home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigaku changed his name and hid himself in Osaka, but just at that moment, he was invited to a banquet of Yodo YAMAUCHI, and was attacked on his way home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>首は難波橋に晒され、耳は脅迫文と共に同月24日に正親町三条実愛・中山忠能の屋敷に投げ込まれ、両公卿の辞職を招くこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His head was put on public display at Naniwa bashi Bridge, and on the 24th of the same month, his ears were thrown inside the house of Sanearu Ogimachi-SANJO and Tadayasu NAKAYAMA with a ransom note, resulting in resignation of both of the court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His head was put on public display at Naniwa bashi Bridge, and on the 24th of the same month, his ears were thrown inside the house of Sanearu Ogimachi-SANJO and Tadayasu NAKAYAMA with a ransom note, resulting in resignation of both of the court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His head was put on public display at Naniwa-bashi Bridge, and on the 24th of the same month, his ears were thrown inside the house of Sanearu Ogimachi-SANJO and Tadayasu NAKAYAMA with a ransom note, resulting in resignation of both of the court nobles.</e>
<cmt>「Naniwa bashi」を「Naniwa-bashi」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>この事件においては以蔵の名前だけが挙げられ、他に数名居たとされる正確な人数や構成は伝わっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only the name of Izo was mentioned for this incident, and the exact numbers and the organization of the others who were considered present at the scene were not transmitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only the name of Izo was mentioned for this incident, and the exact number and the organization of the others who were considered present at the scene were not transmitted.</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only the name of Izo was mentioned for this incident, and the exact number and the organization of the others who were considered present at the scene were not transmitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="94">
<j>暗殺（文久3年1月29日）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination of Hajime KAGAWA (March 18, 1863)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assassination of Hajime KAGAWA (March 18, 1863)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination of Hajime KAGAWA (March 18, 1863)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="95">
<j>賀川肇（かがわ はじめ）は、公家千種有文の家臣で、安政の大獄の折、島田左近らに協力して志士弾圧に加わったことで狙われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hajime KAGAWA was a vassal of a Court noble Arifumi CHIGUSA, and was made a target because he had cooperated with Sakon SHIMADA and others, and joined the suppression of the patriots during Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hajime KAGAWA was a vassal of a Court noble Arifumi CHIGUSA, and was made a target because he had cooperated with Sakon SHIMADA and others, and joined the suppression of the patriots during Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hajime KAGAWA was a vassal of a Court noble Arifumi CHIGUSA, and was made a target because he had cooperated with Sakon SHIMADA and others, and joined the suppression of the patriots during Ansei no Taigoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>浪士が自宅に踏み込んできたとき賀川は二階へと逃げ込み隠れていたが、運悪く帰宅した幼い子どもが浪士たちに捕われ厳しい詰問を受けるのを見て自ら階下へ降りたところを斬首された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the roshi made a raid and stepped into his house, KAGAWA went upstairs and hid himself; but on seeing his young children who unfortunately came home and cruelly questioned by the roshi that had captivated them, he went down stairs on his own will, and was beheaded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the roshi made a raid and stepped into his house, KAGAWA went upstairs and hid himself; but on seeing his young children who unfortunately came home and were cruelly questioned by the roshi that had captivated them, he went downstairs on his own will, and was beheaded.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the roshi made a raid and stepped into his house, KAGAWA went upstairs and hid himself; but on seeing his young children who unfortunately came home and were cruelly questioned by the roshi that had captivated them, he went downstairs on his own will, and was beheaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>この事件については一般に薩摩の田中新兵衛の犯行であるとされるが、以蔵も田中と共に加わっていたとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident was generally thought as the crime of Shinbei TANAKA from Satsuma, but it was conjectured that Izo also joined him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident was generally thought as the crime of Shinbei TANAKA from Satsuma, but it was conjectured that Izo also joined him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident was generally thought as the crime of Shinbei TANAKA from Satsuma, but it was conjectured that Izo also joined him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>また一方では、姫路藩の萩原虎六らによるとする異説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there was a different opinion that it was the crime of Toraroku HAGIWARA from the Himeji Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there was a different opinion that it was the crime of Toraroku HAGIWARA from the Himeji Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there was a different opinion that it was the crime of Toraroku HAGIWARA from the Himeji Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="99">
<j>以上9件について、岡田以蔵が関わったとする説が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izo OKADA is thought to have been involved in the nine incidents described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izo OKADA is thought to have been involved in the nine incidents described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izo OKADA is thought to have been involved in the nine incidents described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>しかしながら研究者の間では、「この全てについて必ずしも関与していないのではないか」とする説も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is a theory among the researchers that consider him as &apos;not necessarily involving in all of the incidents.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is a theory among the researchers that consider him as &apos;not necessarily involved in all of the incidents.&apos;</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is a theory among the researchers that consider him as &apos;not necessarily involved in all of the incidents.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>一方で、「暗殺が横行した文久2年～元治元年の間には未だに誰の手によるものか判らない（斬奸状により、尊王攘夷派であることだけ判っているものもある）暗殺事件も多く、そうした中にも以蔵が関わった事件があるのではないか」との見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is also a viewpoint that states &apos;between 1862 to 1864 when assassinations were rampant, there were many assassinations which even today criminals are not identified (only that they were Sonno joi ha is known from notes describing their crime).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there is also a viewpoint that states &apos;between 1862 to 1864 when assassinations were rampant, there were many assassinations for which even today criminals are not identified (only that they were Sonno joi ha is known from notes describing their crime).&apos;</e>
<cmt>added &quot;for&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there is also a viewpoint that states &apos;between 1862 to 1864 when assassinations were rampant, there were many assassinations for which even today criminals are not identified (only that they were Sonno joi ha is known from notes describing their crime).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>岡田以蔵による要人護衛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izo OKADA as bodyguards for leading figures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izo OKADA as bodyguards for leading figures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izo OKADA as bodyguards for leading figures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="102">
<j>勝海舟（文久三年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU (1863)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaishu KATSU (1863)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU (1863)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="103">
<j>勝海舟の自伝「氷川清話」によると、坂本龍馬の口利きで岡田以蔵が勝海舟の護衛を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Hikawa seiwa&apos; (Quiet talks at the Hikwa mansion), which is an autobiography of Kaishu KATSU, Izo OKADA became Kaishu KATSU&apos;s bodyguard owing to the mediation by Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Hikawa seiwa&apos; (Quiet talks at the Hikwa mansion), which is an autobiography of Kaishu KATSU, Izo OKADA became Kaishu KATSU&apos;s bodyguard owing to the mediation of Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Hikawa seiwa&apos; (Quiet talks at the Hikwa mansion), which is an autobiography of Kaishu KATSU, Izo OKADA became Kaishu KATSU&apos;s bodyguard owing to the mediation of Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>3人の暗殺者が襲ってきたが、以蔵が1人を切り捨て一喝すると残り2人は逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three assassins attacked Kaishu, but when Izo cut one of them down and gave a roar, the remaining two assassins ran away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three assassins attacked Kaishu, but when Izo cut one of them down and gave a roar, the remaining two assassins ran away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three assassins attacked Kaishu, but when Izo cut one of them down and gave a roar, the remaining two assassins ran away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>その際、勝が「君は人を殺すことをたしなんではいけない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On that occasion, KATSU said &quot;You should not be fond of killing people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that occasion, KATSU said &quot;You should not be fond of killing people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that occasion, KATSU said &quot;You should not be fond of killing people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>先日のような挙動は改めたがよからう」と諭したが、以蔵は「先生それでもあの時私が居なかったら、先生の首は既に飛んでしまつて居ませう」と返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such actions taken a few days ago is better to be mended&quot; and tried to persuade him, but Izo said in return &quot;But Mr. Katsu, if it weren&apos;t for me, your head must already have been slain.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such actions taken a few days ago are better to be mended&quot; and tried to persuade him, but Izo said in return &quot;But Mr. Katsu, if it weren&apos;t for me, your head must already have been slain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such actions taken a few days ago are better to be mended&quot; and tried to persuade him, but Izo said in return &quot;But Mr. Katsu, if it weren&apos;t for me, your head must already have been slain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>流石に勝も返す言葉が無かったらしく、「これにはおれも一言もなかったよ」と言っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As might be expected, KATSU seemed to have had no words to say in return, for he said &apos;I had no a single word to this.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As might be expected, KATSU seemed to have had no words to say in return, for he said &apos;I had no a single word to this.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As might be expected, KATSU seemed to have had no words to say in return, for he said &apos;I had no a single word to this.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="108">
<j>ジョン万次郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">John Manjiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">John Manjiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">John Manjiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="109">
<j>中浜家の家伝（『中浜万次郎 -「アメリカ」を初めて伝えた日本人-』（中浜博、2005年））によると、岡田以蔵はジョン万次郎の護衛も行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the family tradition of the Nakahama family [(&quot;Manjiro NAKANOHAMA - A Japanese that told about &apos;America&apos; for the first time&quot; (Hiroshi NAKAHAMA, 2005)], Izo OKADA was also a bodyguard of John Manjiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the family tradition of the Nakahama family [(&quot;Manjiro NAKANOHAMA - A Japanese that told about &apos;America&apos; for the first time&quot; (Hiroshi NAKAHAMA, 2005)], Izo OKADA was also a bodyguard of John Manjiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the family tradition of the Nakahama family [(&quot;Manjiro NAKANOHAMA - A Japanese that told about &apos;America&apos; for the first time&quot; (Hiroshi NAKAHAMA, 2005)], Izo OKADA was also a bodyguard of John Manjiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>勝海舟が自分の護衛をした岡田の腕を見込んで万次郎の護衛につけたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU, who was confident in OKADA&apos;s skill as his own bodyguard, made him become a bodyguard of Manjiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaishu KATSU, who was confident in OKADA&apos;s skill as his own bodyguard, made him become a bodyguard of Manjiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU, who was confident in OKADA&apos;s skill as his own bodyguard, made him become a bodyguard of Manjiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>万次郎が建てた西洋式の墓を参りに行った時、4人の暗殺者が万次郎を襲ったが、以蔵は伏兵が2人隠れていることを察知して、万次郎にむやみに逃げず墓石を背にして動かないように指示し、襲ってきた2人を切り捨てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they went to a western style grave that Manjiro had built, four assassins tried to attack Manjiro, but Izo had sensed the two ambushes that were hiding, and told Manjiro not to escape impulsively but to stay put with his back against the gravestone, and had slain the two attackers down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they went to a western style grave that Manjiro had built, four assassins tried to attack Manjiro, but Izo had sensed the two ambushes that were hiding, and told Manjiro not to escape impulsively but to stay put with his back against the gravestone, and slew the two attackers down.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When they went to a western style grave that Manjiro had built, four assassins tried to attack Manjiro, but Izo had sensed the two ambushes that were hiding, and told Manjiro not to escape impulsively but to stay put with his back against the gravestone, and slew the two attackers down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>残った2人は逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remaining two ambushes made an escape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remaining two attackers made an escape.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remaining two attackers made an escape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), Cprobot(id:97843), ポコ(id:70875), Harupri(id:133581), 土方　誠(id:3651), 認定者(id:99098), ロココ(id:80572), Michael Friedrich(id:44338), Ponta2(id:129030), MioUzaki(id:89034), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), A-Taul(id:41790), 代言人(id:33675), Azucar(id:20348), Loveless(id:129239), Kanoe(id:17203), Point136(id:211299), Morio(id:35464), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Maakun(id:16735), Qurren(id:20140), Bankokuya(id:91191), DumZiBoT(id:230315), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Lemon pie(id:66842), Sushiya(id:110938), MIO(id:31681), Yanahan(id:2437), 政岡幸輔(id:89690), ＫｏＺ(id:48584), よもすがら(id:212112), Cave cattum(id:41235), Clarin(id:60278), Roow(id:14132), Kamitani(id:30757), OJY(id:142519), YurikBot(id:18605), 上田隼人(id:23104), 刀剣(id:138403), Ash(id:15625), Shiolabo(id:225786), おきた(id:18906), Muyo(id:14948), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>