<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>河瀬秀治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideji KAWASE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideji KAWASE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideji KAWASE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>河瀬 秀治（かわせ ひでじ、天保12年12月15日_(旧暦)（1842年1月26日） － 明治40年（1907年））は、日本の武士･宮津藩藩士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideji KAWASE (January 26, 1842 - 1907) was a Japanese samurai and a statesman of the Miyazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideji KAWASE (January 26, 1842 - 1907) was a Japanese samurai and a statesman of the Miyazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideji KAWASE (January 26, 1842 - 1907) was a Japanese samurai and a statesman of the Miyazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明治政府に仕えて小菅県や印旛県などの県令を歴任後に実業家として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he served the Meiji Government as the governor of Kosuge Prefecture, Inba Prefecture and others, he flourished as a businessperson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he served the Meiji Government as the governor of Kosuge Prefecture, Inba Prefecture and others, he flourished as a businessperson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he served the Meiji Government as the governor of Kosuge Prefecture, Inba Prefecture and others, he flourished as a businessperson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称外衛、雅号雲影。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly known as Gaiei, and his Gago (pseudonym) was Unei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly known as Gaiei, and his Gago (pseudonym) was Unei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly known as Gaiei, and his Gago (pseudonym) was Unei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>勲四等。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was Fourth Class of Order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official rank was Fourth Class of Order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official rank was Fourth Class of Order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>藩士・午窪成弘（謙下）の3男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the third son of Narihiro UMAKUBO (謙下), a stateman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the third son of Narihiro UMAKUBO (謙下), a stateman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the third son of Narihiro UMAKUBO (謙下), a stateman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>嘉永元年（1848年）才を見込まれて家老職を務めていた河瀬治休の養子となり、藩主本庄宗秀より一字を与えられて「秀治」と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1848 he was adopted by Haruyoshi KAWASE, who was Karo (chief retainer), as a son because of his talent and identified himself as &apos;Hideji,&apos; given a Chinese character from Munehide HONJO, the lord of domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1848 he was adopted by Haruyoshi KAWASE, who was Karo (chief retainer), as a son because of his talent and identified himself as &apos;Hideji,&apos; and given a Chinese character from Munehide HONJO, the lord of domain.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1848 he was adopted by Haruyoshi KAWASE, who was Karo (chief retainer), as a son because of his talent and identified himself as &apos;Hideji,&apos; and given a Chinese character from Munehide HONJO, the lord of domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>文久2年（1862年）頃から尊王攘夷運動に参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around 1862 he had joined Sonno Joi Movement (the Movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1862 he had joined Sonno Joi Movement (the Movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1862 he had joined Sonno Joi Movement (the Movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ところが、慶応4年（1868年）の鳥羽伏見の戦いで宮津藩は江戸幕府に参加して大敗、西園寺公望を総督とする山陰道鎮撫軍の標的とされてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi of 1868, the Miyazu clan joined the side of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), defeated heavily and became the target of the Sanindo Chinbugun (a military unit formed specially for the campaign in Sanindo) the governor of which was Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi of 1868, the Miyazu clan joined the side of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which was heavily defeated and became the target of Sanindo Chinbugun (a military unit formed specially for the campaign in Sanindo) the governor of which was Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi of 1868, the Miyazu clan joined the side of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which was heavily defeated and became the target of Sanindo Chinbugun (a military unit formed specially for the campaign in Sanindo) the governor of which was Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>河瀬は藩内の議論を纏めて西園寺らと会見して恭順の意を伝達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawase summarized the discussion among the clan and conveyed a message of obedience to Saionji and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawase summarized the discussion among the clan and conveyed a message of obedience to Saionji and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawase summarized the discussion among the clan and conveyed a message of obedience to Saionji and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この対応の早さが幸いし、藩主本庄宗武及びその父である前藩主本庄宗秀（元老中）の罪は不問とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to this quick response, Munetake HONJO, the lord of domain and his father Munehide HONJO, former lord of domain (former roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders)), were not convicted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to this quick response, Munetake HONJO, the lord of domain and his father Munehide HONJO, former lord of domain (former roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders)), were not convicted.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to this quick response, Munetake HONJO, the lord of domain and his father Munehide HONJO, former lord of domain (former roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders)), were not convicted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治2年（1869年）新政府に出仕すると、武蔵知県事に任じられ、翌年に小菅県に改称後には同県権令から県令として職に留まり、外国語学校の開設などを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he attended at the new government in 1869, he was assigned to Musashi-chikenji (governor of Musashi region), and after it was reorganized to Kosuge Prefecture, he was assigned to its governor after working as the vice-governor, and worked for the foundation of a foreign language school and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he attended the new government in 1869, he was assigned to Musashi-chikenji (governor of Musashi region), and after it was reorganized to Kosuge Prefecture, he was assigned to be its governor after working as the vice-governor, and worked to found a foreign language school and so on.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he attended the new government in 1869, he was assigned to Musashi-chikenji (governor of Musashi region), and after it was reorganized to Kosuge Prefecture, he was assigned to be its governor after working as the vice-governor, and worked to found a foreign language school and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>明治4年（1871年）廃藩置県後の府県再編に伴って新設された印旛県の県令に転じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871 he was transferred to the governor of the Inba Prefecture which was newly founded in accordance with the reorganization of prefectures after Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871 he was transferred to the governor of the Inba Prefecture which was newly founded in accordance with the reorganization of prefectures after Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871 he was transferred to the governor of the Inba Prefecture which was newly founded in accordance with the reorganization of prefectures after Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>印旛県では茶の生産拡大や牧場設置のためにホーレス・ケプロンを招聘して指導を受けるなどの政策を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Inba Prefecture, he took policies such as the increase of tea production and the invitation of Horace Capron in order to found a ranch and being taught by him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Inba Prefecture, he took policies such as the increase of tea production and the invitation of Horace Capron in order to found a ranch and was taught by him.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Inba Prefecture, he took policies such as the increase of tea production and the invitation of Horace CAPRON in order to found a ranch and was taught by him.</e>
<cmt>Horace Capron→Horace CAPRONに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>明治6年（1873年）に府県の再編成の方針が固まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1873, the Meiji Government established the policy of reorganization of prefectures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1873, the Meiji Government established the policy to reorganize prefectures.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1873, the Meiji Government established the policy to reorganize prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その結果、河瀬は新設される熊谷県の初代県令就任を前提に合併元となる群馬県と入間県の両県兼務の県令に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Kawase was transferred to the governor of the Gunma and the Iruma Prefectures, premised on becoming the first governor of the Kumagaya Prefecture which would be newly founded including the Gunma and the Iruma Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Kawase was transferred to the governor of Gunma and Iruma Prefectures, premised on becoming the first governor of the Kumagaya Prefecture which would be newly founded including the Gunma and Iruma Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Kawase was transferred to the governor of Gunma and Iruma Prefectures, premised on becoming the first governor of the Kumagaya Prefecture which would be newly founded including the Gunma and Iruma Prefectures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同様に印旛県でも千葉県新設を前提に隣接する木更津県の権令柴原和が印旛県権令を兼ねる事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Inba Prefecture, similarly, Yawara SHIBAHARA, the vice-governor of the Kisarazu Prefecture which was the neighboring prefecture of the Inba prefecture, was assigned to the vice-governor of the Inba Prefecture, premised on the foundation of the Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Inba Prefecture, similarly, Yawara SHIBAHARA, the vice-governor of the Kisarazu Prefecture which was the neighboring prefecture of the Inba prefecture, was assigned to be the vice-governor of Inba Prefecture, premised on the foundation of Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Inba Prefecture, similarly, Yawara SHIBAHARA, the vice-governor of the Kisarazu Prefecture which was the neighboring prefecture of the Inba Prefecture, was assigned to be the vice-governor of Inba Prefecture, premised on the foundation of Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Inba prefecture→Inba Prefectureに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして6月15日、熊谷県が発足して河瀬は初代県令となった（同日に千葉県も発足して柴原がそのまま初代県令となった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on June 15, the Kumagaya Prefecture was established and Kawase was assigned to the first governor (on the same day the Chiba Prefecture was also established and Shibahara was assigned to the first governor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on June 15, the Kumagaya Prefecture was established and Kawase was assigned to be the first governor (on the same day Chiba Prefecture was also established and Shibahara was assigned to be the first governor).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on June 15, the Kumagaya Prefecture was established and Kawase was assigned to be the first governor (on the same day Chiba Prefecture was also established and Shibahara was assigned to be the first governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>熊谷県では、県内にある官営富岡製糸場の成功に乗る形で同様の近代的な製糸工場の設置を進め、前橋市や熊谷市に学校を新設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kunagaya Prefecture, Kawase promoted to build the same modern yarn-making factory as the state-owned Tomioka Seishi-jo (Tomioka Silk Mill) after its success, and founded schools in the Maebashi city and the Kumagaya city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kunagaya Prefecture, Kawase promoted the building of a modern yarn-making factory as a state-owned Tomioka Seishi-jo (Tomioka Silk Mill), and after its success he founded schools in Maebashi city and Kumagaya city.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kumagaya Prefecture, Kawase promoted the building of a modern yarn-making factory as a state-owned Tomioka Seishi-jo (Tomioka Silk Mill), and after its success he founded schools in Maebashi City and Kumagaya City.</e>
<cmt>Kunagaya Prefecture→Kumagaya Prefectureに修正、cityの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>明治7年（1874年）に内務省 (日本)に入省して内務大丞兼勧業寮権頭として、明治10年（1877年）の内国勧業博覧会を成功させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1874, he entered the Ministry of Interior (Japan) and made a success of the National Industrial Exhibition in 1877 as naimu daijo (the third highest post in the Ministry of Interior) and Kangyoryo gon no kami (an officer of the agency for promotion of industry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1874, he entered the Ministry of Interior (Japan) and successfuly achieved the post of naimu daijo (the third highest post in the Ministry of Interor) for the National Industrial Exhibition in 1877 and Kangyoryo gon no kami (an officer of the agency for promotion of industry).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1874, he entered the Ministry of Interior (Japan) and successfuly achieved the post of naimu daijo (the third highest post in the Ministry of Interor) for the National Industrial Exhibition in 1877 and Kangyoryo gon no kami (an officer of the agency for promotion of industry).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後ヨーロッパ視察の経験を生かして渋沢栄一・五代友厚らとともに明治13年（1880年）に日本最初の商工会議所である東京商法会議所を結成、同年佐野常民とともに龍池会を結成して副会頭に就任して美術奨励にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, based on the experience of his visit to Europe, he set up Tokyo Shoho Kaigisho (Tokyo Chamber of Commerce), the first Chamber of Commerce in Japan, with Eiichi SHIBUSAWA and Tomoatsu GODAI in 1880, and also set up Ryuchi-kai (Ryuchi party) with Tsunetami SANO in the same year and promoted arts as the vice-president.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, based on the experience of his visit to Europe, he set up Tokyo Shoho Kaigisho (Tokyo Chamber of Commerce), the first Chamber of Commerce in Japan, with Eiichi SHIBUSAWA and Tomoatsu GODAI in 1880, and also set up Ryuchi-kai (Ryuchi party) with Tsunetami SANO in the same year and promoted the arts as its vice-president.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, based on the experience of his visit to Europe, he set up Tokyo Shoho Kaigisho (Tokyo Chamber of Commerce), the first Chamber of Commerce in Japan, with Eiichi SHIBUSAWA and Tomoatsu GODAI in 1880, and also set up Ryuchi-kai (Ryuchi party) with Tsunetami SANO in the same year and promoted the arts as its vice-president.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、アーネスト・フェノロサを支援して鑑画会設立に尽くす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he made an effort to set up Kanga-kai (a name of the organization) by supporting Ernest Fenollosa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he made an effort to set up Kanga-kai (a name of the organization) by supporting Ernest Fenollosa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he made an effort to set up Kanga-kai (a name of the organization) by supporting Ernest FENOLLOSA.</e>
<cmt>Ernest Fenollosa→Ernest FENOLLOSAに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>明治14年（1881年）に内務省から農商務省に商務局長兼工務局長として移籍するものの、農商務少輔品川弥二郎との対立を機に退官した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1881 he was transferred to the Ministry of agriculture and commerce as the chief of commerce agency and industrial agency from the Ministry of Interior, but resigned triggered by the conflict with Yajiro SHINAGAWA, who was Noshomushoho (Junior Assistant Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1881 he was transferred to the Ministry of agriculture and commerce as a chief of commerce agency and industrial agency from the Ministry of Interior, but resigned after triggering a conflict with Yajiro SHINAGAWA, who was Noshomushoho (Junior Assistant Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1881 he was transferred to the Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce as a chief of commerce agency and industrial agency from the Ministry of Interior, but resigned after triggering a conflict with Yajiro SHINAGAWA, who was Noshomushoho (Junior Assistant Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce).</e>
<cmt>the Ministry of agriculture and commerce→the Ministry of Agriculture and Commerceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>河瀬は龍池会副会頭の職務を続けながら、翌年には横浜正金銀行取締役に就任し、明治18年（1885年）には茶業組合結成に尽力して茶の生産・輸出の拡大事業に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With continuing to work as the vice-president of the Ryuchi-kai, Kawase was assigned to be a director of Yokohama Specie Bank in the following year, and made efforts to set up the association for tea industry and expand the production and the export of tea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While continuing to work as the vice-president of the Ryuchi-kai, Kawase was assigned to be a director of Yokohama Specie Bank the following year, and made efforts to set up the association for tea industry and expand the production and export of tea.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While continuing to work as the vice-president of the Ryuchi-kai, Kawase was assigned to be a director of Yokohama Specie Bank the following year, and made efforts to set up the association for tea industry and expand the production and export of tea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、益田孝とともに「中外商業新報」を創刊している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he began to publish &apos;Chugai shogyo shimpo (Journal/Newspaper)&apos; with Takashi MASUDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he began to publish &apos;Chugai shogyo shimpo (Journal/Newspaper)&apos; with Takashi MASUDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he began to publish &apos;Chugai Shogyo Shinpo&apos; (Journal of Foreign and Domestic Commerce) with Takashi MASUDA.</e>
<cmt>&apos;Chugai Shogyo Shinpo&apos; とし、補足を修正 (参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=DsALRa-r5QoC&amp;pg=PA193&amp;dq=chugai-shogyo-shinpo&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=9#v=onepage&amp;q=chugai-shogyo-shinpo&amp;f=false)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), たね(id:10372), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 陽一(id:92099), Component(id:146478), 無言雀師(id:13124), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>