<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>西河克己</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumi NISHIKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumi NISHIKAWA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumi NISHIKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>西河 克己（にしかわ かつみ、1918年7月1日 -）は、映画監督。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumi NISHIKAWA (July 1, 1918) was the movie director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumi NISHIKAWA (July 1, 1918) was a movie director.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumi NISHIKAWA (July 1, 1918 -) was a movie director.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鳥取県智頭町出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from Chizu-cho Town, Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from Chizu-cho Town, Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from Chizu Town, Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>cho削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>父は東京都庁の公務員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was government worker of City Council of Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was a government worker for the City Council of Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was a government worker for the City Council of Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>大正 7年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1918</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1918</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1918</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>- 鳥取県八頭郡土師村に生まれる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Haji-mura Village, Yazu County, Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Haji-mura Village, Yazu County, Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Haji Village, Yazu County, Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>mura削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大正11年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1922</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1922</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1922</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>- 上京（東京都大森 (大田区)へ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came to Tokyo (Omori, Tokyo Prefecture (Ota Ward))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came to Tokyo (Omori, Tokyo Prefecture (Ota Ward))</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came to Tokyo (Omori, Tokyo Prefecture (Ota Ward))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>昭和11年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1936</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1936</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1936</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>- 高輪中学校・高等学校 卒業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He graduated from Takanawa Junior High School, Takanawa High School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He graduated from Takanawa Junior High School, Takanawa High School.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He graduated from Takanawa Junior High School, Takanawa High School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>昭和14年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1939</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1939</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1939</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>- 日本大学藝術学部 卒業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He graduated from Nohon University, College of Art Department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He graduated from Nohon University, College of Art.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He graduated from Nihon University, College of Art.</e>
<cmt>Nihonに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>昭和14年12月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1939</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">39/12/01</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">39/12/01</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>- 松竹大船撮影所、入社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered to Shochiku Obune studio.</e>
<cmt>大船→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered Shochiku Obune studio.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered Shochiku Obune studio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>昭和15年9月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, 1940</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">40/09/01</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">40/09/01</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>- 出征（東南アジア・中国）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to the front. (of the War) (Southeast Asia, China)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought on the front-lines (Southeast Asia, China)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought on the front-lines (Southeast Asia, China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>昭和21年7月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, 1946</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">46/07/01</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">46/07/01</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>- 復員後、松竹に復職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he was demobilized and sent home from the War, he worked for Shochiku again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was demobilized and sent home from the War, he worked for Shochiku again.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was demobilized and sent home from the War, he worked for Shochiku again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>昭和27年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1952</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1952</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1952</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>- 『伊豆の艶歌師』で初監督</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He directed his first movie of &quot;伊豆の艶歌師.&quot;</e>
<cmt>伊豆の艶歌師→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He directed his first movie, &quot;伊豆の艶歌師.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He directed his first movie, &quot;Izu no Enkashi&quot; (street performer of pop songs in Izu).</e>
<cmt>伊豆の艶歌師→Izu no Enkashi (street performer of pop songs in Izu)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>昭和29年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1954</e>
<cmt>抜け補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>- 日活に移籍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He moved to Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He moved to Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He moved to Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>昭和31年3月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1956</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">56/03/01</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">56/03/01</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>- 結婚（1女あり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He married to his wife. (he had one daughter.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He married his wife (he had one daughter).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He married his wife (he had one daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>昭和44年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1969</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1969</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1969</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>- 日活を退社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned from Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned from Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned from Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>昭和54年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1979</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1979</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1979</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>―日本大学芸術学部講師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a lecturer at Nihon University, College of Art</e>
<cmt>抜け補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>昭和63年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1988</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1988</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1988</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>- 日本大学大学院講師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became professor at Japan University, College of Art Department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a professor at Japan University, College of Art.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a lecturer in graduate course at Nihon University, College of Art.</e>
<cmt>lecturerに訂正しました。in graduate course補足しました。Nihonに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>平成 3年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1991</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1991</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1991</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>- 勲四等瑞宝章受章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received the Order of the Sacred Treasure, Gold Rays with Neck Ribbon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the Order of the Sacred Treasure, Gold Rays with Neck Ribbon.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the Order of the Sacred Treasure, Gold Rays with Neck Ribbon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>西河が生まれたのは鳥取県東部の智頭町土師地区。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishikawa was born in Haji Ward, Chizu-cho Town in eastern part of Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishikawa was born in Haji Ward, Chizu-cho Town in the eastern part of Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishikawa was born in Haji Ward, Chizu Town in the eastern part of Tottori Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>cho削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>父親の就職で一家が東京へ移るまでの4年余りを過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He spent there about four years before his father got job and the family moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He spent about four years there before his father got a job and the family moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He spent about four years there before his father got a job and the family moved to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>小説家志望であったが、次善の途として映画監督を志し、松竹大船撮影所に監督助手として入社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he wanted to become a novelist, he also wished to become movie director as his second choice, so he entered into Shochiku Obune studio as assistant director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he wanted to become a novelist, he also wished to become movie director as his second choice, so he entered Shochiku Obune studio as an assistant director.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he wanted to become a novelist, he also wished to become movie director as his second choice, so he entered Shochiku Obune studio as an assistant director.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>当時は日本映画の第1期黄金時代ともいえる時代だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We can say that it was the first golden age of Japanese movie at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We can say that it was the first golden age of Japanese movies at that time.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We can say that it was the first golden age of Japanese movies at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>大学を卒業したのが日中戦争真っ只中であったため、松竹入社後1年を経ずして召集（結局2度応召した）されて旧満州やビルマへ出征、捕虜収容所生活も経験した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he graduated from the University while it was the middle of the Sino-Japanese war, he was called up (after all he was conscripted twice) to Manchuria and Burma after less than one year he started working for Shochiku, he also experienced to spent his time in prisoner&apos;s camp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he graduated from the University while it was the middle of the Sino-Japanese war, he was called up (after all he was conscripted twice) to Manchuria and Burma after less than one year after he started working for Shochiku, he also spent time in a prisoner camp.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he graduated from the University while it was the middle of the Sino-Japanese War, he was called up (after all he was conscripted twice) to Manchuria and Burma after less than one year after he started working for Shochiku, he also spent time in a prisoner camp.</e>
<cmt>War大文字にしました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>戦後復員して昭和21年復職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made demobilization and started to work for Shochiku again in 1946.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was demobilized and started to work for Shochiku again in 1946.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was demobilized and started to work for Shochiku again in 1946.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>原研吉、渋谷実、中村登らの名匠に師事し、昭和27年助監督待遇のまま『伊豆の艶歌師』（主演佐田啓二）を初監督。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied under famous people such as Kenkichi HARA, Minoru SHIBUYA, Noboru NAKAMURA, and he directed movie, &quot;伊豆の艶歌師&quot; (main actor wasKeiji SADA) for the first time while his position was still assistant director in 1952.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under famous people such as Kenkichi HARA, Minoru SHIBUYA, Noboru NAKAMURA, and he directed the movie, &quot;伊豆の艶歌師&quot; (main actor was Keiji SADA) for the first time while his position was still assistant director in 1952.</e>
<cmt>Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under famous people such as Kenkichi HARA, Minoru SHIBUYA, Noboru NAKAMURA, and he directed the movie, &quot;Izu no Enkashi&quot; (street performer of pop songs in Izu) (main actor was Keiji SADA) for the first time while his position was still assistant director in 1952.</e>
<cmt>伊豆の艶歌師→Izu no Enkashi (street performer of pop songs in Izu)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>2本立て映画の1本、いわゆるシスター映画であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was one of double feature movie, and it was what it was called sister&apos;s movie.</e>
<cmt>シスター映画→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was one part of a double feature movie, a so called sister movie.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was one part of a double feature movie, a so called sister movie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>典型的な「大船映画」を数本撮ったあと、昭和29年日活の映画製作再開と同時に日活と監督契約した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he directed a few typical &apos;Obune movie&apos;, he signed the contract with Nikkatsu as director after Nikkatsu started producing movie again in 1954.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he directed a few typical &apos;Obune movies,&apos; he signed a contract with Nikkatsu as a director after Nikkatsu started producing movies again in 1954.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he directed a few typical &apos;Obune movies,&apos; he signed a contract with Nikkatsu as a director after Nikkatsu started producing movies again in 1954.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>山本有三原作による社会派メロドラマ『生きとし生けるもの』（主演山村聡）を第1作に、日活での初期作としては『東京の人』（主演月丘夢路）、『美しい庵主さん』（主演小林旭）などがあるが、当然のように「大船色」が濃く、「日活っぽい」昭和35年の『俺の故郷は大西部』（主演和田浩治）は西河作品としては逆に異色である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first movie was social soap opera, &quot; Ikitoshi ikeru mono (All living things)&quot; (main actor was So YAMAMURA), which original author was Yuzo YAMAMOTO, he also directed &quot;Tokyo no hito&quot; (a person from Tokyo) (main actress wasYumeji TSUKIOKA) and &quot;美しい庵主さん&quot; (The beautiful master of a hermitage) (main actor was Akira KOBAYASHI) as his first movie of Nikkatsu, it was needless to say that those movies had strong &apos;Obune&apos; taste, the movie such as &apos;俺の故郷は大西部&apos; (my hometown is big old western America) (main actor was Koji WADA) in 1960 which had &apos;Nikkatsu taste&apos; was different movie as Nishikawa&apos;s movie.</e>
<cmt>東京の人, 美しい庵主さん, 俺の故郷は大西部→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first movie was a social soap opera, &quot; Ikitoshi ikeru mono (All living things)&quot; (main actor was So YAMAMURA), whose original author was Yuzo YAMAMOTO, he also directed &quot;Tokyo no hito&quot; (a person from Tokyo) (main actress was Yumeji TSUKIOKA) and &quot;美しい庵主さん&quot; (The beautiful master of a hermitage) (main actor was Akira KOBAYASHI) as his first movie with Nikkatsu, it was needless to say that those movies had a strong &apos;Obune&apos; flavor, movies such as &apos;俺の故郷は大西部&apos; (my hometown is big old western America) (main actor was Koji WADA) in 1960 which had a &apos;Nikkatsu flavor&apos; was a different movie than Nishikawa&apos;s movie.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first movie was a social soap opera, &quot; Ikitoshi ikeru mono (All living things)&quot; (main actor was So YAMAMURA), whose original author was Yuzo YAMAMOTO, he also directed &quot;Tokyo no hito&quot; (a person from Tokyo) (main actress was Yumeji TSUKIOKA) and &quot;Utsukushii Ionushi-san&quot; (The beautiful master of a hermitage) (main actor was Akira KOBAYASHI) as his first movie with Nikkatsu, it was needless to say that those movies had a strong &apos;Obune&apos; flavor, movies such as &quot;Ore no Kokyo wa Daiseibu&quot; (my hometown is big old western America) (main actor was Koji WADA) in 1960 which had a &apos;Nikkatsu flavor&apos; was a different movie than Nishikawa&apos;s movie.</e>
<cmt>美しい庵主さん→Utsukushii Ionushi-san俺の故郷は大西部→Ore no Kokyo wa Daiseibu原文に合せて&apos;を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="42">
<j>60年代に入ると『若い人』（主演石原裕次郎）、『青い山脈』（主演吉永小百合）、『伊豆の踊子』（主演吉永小百合）、『エデンの海』（主演高橋英樹 (俳優)）、『帰郷』（主演吉永小百合）などの作品でその才能を遺憾なく発揮し、日本映画の全盛期を飾った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1960&apos;s, he showed his talent freely in movies such as &quot;Wakai hito&quot; (The young people) (main actor was Yujiro ISHIZAKA), &quot;Aoi sanmyaku&quot; (The Green Mountains) (main actress was Sayuri YOSHINAGA), &quot;Dancing Girl of Izu&quot; (main actress was Sayuri YOSHINAGA), Eden no umi (The Sea of Eden) (main actor was Hideki TAKAHASHI), &quot;Kikyo&quot; (going home) (main actress was Sayuri YOSHINAGA), he played an active role in the golden age of the Japanese movies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1960&apos;s, he showed his talent freely in movies such as &quot;Wakai hito&quot; (The young people) (main actor was Yujiro ISHIZAKA), &quot;Aoi sanmyaku&quot; (The Green Mountains) (main actress was Sayuri YOSHINAGA), &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; (main actress was Sayuri YOSHINAGA), Eden no umi (The Sea of Eden) (main actor was Hideki TAKAHASHI), &quot;Kikyo&quot; (going home) (main actress was Sayuri YOSHINAGA), and he played an active role in the golden age of Japanese movies.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1960&apos;s, he showed his talent freely in movies such as &quot;Wakai hito&quot; (The young people) (main actor was Yujiro ISHIZAKA), &quot;Aoi sanmyaku&quot; (The Green Mountains) (main actress was Sayuri YOSHINAGA), &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; (main actress was Sayuri YOSHINAGA), &quot;Eden no umi&quot; (The Sea of Eden) (main actor was Hideki TAKAHASHI), &quot;Kikyo&quot; (going home) (main actress was Sayuri YOSHINAGA), and he played an active role in the golden age of Japanese movies.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>中でも『伊豆の踊子』と『絶唱』（主演舟木一夫）はいずれもリメイク作品であるが、ともに前作を大きく上回ってヒットし、西河監督の地位を揺るぎのないものにした、まさに代表作といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movies such as &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; or &quot;Zessho&quot; (main actor was Kazuo FUNAKI) of above which were remade, became even more popular than the original ones and established Director Nishikawa&apos;s solid position as movie director, thus these movies can represent Nishikawa&apos;s movies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movies such as &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; or &quot;Zessho&quot; (main actor was Kazuo FUNAKI) from above which were remade, became even more popular than the original ones and established Nishikawa&apos;s solid position as a movie director, thus these movies can represent Nishikawa&apos;s movies.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movies such as &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; or &quot;Zessho&quot; (main actor was Kazuo FUNAKI) from above which were remade, became even more popular than the original ones and established Nishikawa&apos;s solid position as a movie director, thus these movies can represent Nishikawa&apos;s movies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="44">
<j>日活がロマンポルノ路線に転換する以前、昭和44年の『夜の牝 年上の女』（主演野川由美子）を最後にTV界に籍を移すが、昭和49年の『伊豆の踊子_(1974年の映画)』（主演山口百恵）のリメイクで映画界に復帰、山口百恵・三浦友和の共演で『潮騒_(1975年の映画)』（1975）、『絶唱_(1975年の映画)』（1975）、『エデンの海_(1976年の映画)』（1976）のリメイク作品や『どんぐりっ子』（主演森昌子）、『春琴抄_(1976年の映画)』（主演山口百恵）を監督した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Nikkatu changed their style of movie to romantic porno, he changed his career into TV activities after he directed &quot; 夜の牝 年上の女 (main actress was Yumiko NOGAWA) in 1969 as his last movie, however he returned to direct movie again when &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; (movie made in 1974) (main actress was Momoe YAMAGUCHI&quot; in 1974, then he directed movies such as &quot;Shiosai&quot; (movie made in 1975) (1975), acted together with Momoe YAMAGUCHI and Tomokazu MIURA, &quot;Zessho&quot; (movie made in 1975) (1975), the remade movie of &quot;Eden no umi&quot; (movie made in 1976) (1976) or &quot;Dongurikko&quot; (main actress was Masako MORI), &quot;Shunkin Sho.&quot; (movie made in 1976) (main actress was Masako MORI)</e>
<cmt>女夜の牝 年上の女→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Nikkatu changed their style of movie to romantic porno, he changed his career into TV activities after he directed &quot;夜の牝 年上の女 (main actress was Yumiko NOGAWA) in 1969 as his last movie, however he returned to direct movies again when &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; (movie made in 1974) (main actress was Momoe YAMAGUCHI), then he directed movies such as &quot;Shiosai&quot; (movie made in 1975) (1975), acted together with Momoe YAMAGUCHI and Tomokazu MIURA, &quot;Zessho&quot; (movie made in 1975) (1975), the remake of &quot;Eden no umi&quot; (movie made in 1976) (1976) or &quot;Dongurikko&quot; (main actress was Masako MORI), and &quot;Shunkin Sho&quot; (movie made in 1976) (main actress was Masako MORI).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Nikkatu changed their style of movie to romantic porno, he changed his career into TV activities after he directed &quot;Yoru no mesu Toshiue no onna&quot; (a night mare Older woman) (main actress was Yumiko NOGAWA) in 1969 as his last movie, however he returned to direct movies again when &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; (movie made in 1974) (main actress was Momoe YAMAGUCHI), then he directed movies such as &quot;Shiosai&quot; (movie made in 1975) (1975), acted together with Momoe YAMAGUCHI and Tomokazu MIURA, &quot;Zessho&quot; (movie made in 1975) (1975), the remake of &quot;Eden no umi&quot; (movie made in 1976) (1976) or &quot;Dongurikko&quot; (main actress was Masako MORI), and &quot;Shunkin Sho&quot; (movie made in 1976) (main actress was Masako MORI).</e>
<cmt>夜の牝 年上の女→&quot;Yoru no mesu Toshiue no onna&quot; (a night mare Older woman)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし、1983年製作の『スパルタの海』（主演伊東四朗）は、公開直前に、映画の舞台となった戸塚ヨットスクールが戸塚ヨットスクール事件で死亡事故が起こり、クランクアップ後にお蔵入り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However just before &quot;Suparuta no umi&quot; (main actor was Shiro ITO) was about to open to the public, which was made in 1983, someone died in the accident in Totsuka Yacht School in which the story was made, after the movie was made, it was put on the shelf without ever being shown.</e>
<cmt>スパルタの海→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However just before &quot;Suparuta no umi&quot; (main actor was Shiro ITO) was about to open to the public, which was made in 1983, someone died in an accident in Totsuka Yacht School in which the story was made, after the movie was made, it was put on the shelf without ever being shown.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However just before &quot;Suparuta no umi&quot; (main actor was Shiro ITO) was about to open to the public, which was made in 1983, someone died in an accident in Totsuka Yacht School in which the story was made, after the movie was made, it was put on the shelf without ever being shown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>その後、戸塚ヨットスクールを支援する団体が著作権を購入し2005年9月にビデオ、DVDとして発売される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the support group of Totsuka Yacht school bought Copyright Act and the movie was made into video tape and DVD for sale in September 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the support group for the Totsuka Yacht school bought the copyrights and the movie was made into video tape and DVD for sale in September 2005.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the support group for the Totsuka Yacht School bought the copyrights and the movie was made into video tape and DVD for sale in September 2005.</e>
<cmt>School大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>1984年の劇画原作『生徒諸君!』（主演小泉今日子）は動員割れ、1985年の『ばあじんロード』（主演松永麗子）は諸処の事情により、未公開のままになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was not enough audiences in the original comics with a realistic narrative made in 1984, the movie &quot;Seitoshokun&quot; (main actress was Kyoko KOIZUMI), &quot;Virgin road&quot; (main actress was Reiko MATSUNAGA) made in 1985 was not shown to the public due to the various reasons.</e>
<cmt>生徒諸君→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was not enough audiences for the original comics with a realistic narrative made in 1984, the movie &quot;Seitoshokun&quot; (main actress was Kyoko KOIZUMI), &quot;Virgin road&quot; (main actress was Reiko MATSUNAGA) made in 1985 was not shown to the public due to the various reasons.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was not enough audiences for the original comics with a realistic narrative made in 1984, the movie &quot;Seitoshokun&quot; (main actress was Kyoko KOIZUMI), &quot;Virgin road&quot; (main actress was Reiko MATSUNAGA) made in 1985 was not shown to the public due to the various reasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="48">
<j>松竹から日活に移ってプログラムピクチャーを多く監督した1950年代～60年代は、文芸・アクション・青春ドラマ・歌謡映画・メロドラマと多種多様のジャンルの広さで活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He directed many program pictures between 1950&apos;s and 1960&apos;s after he moved from Shochiku to Nikkatsu, he also played active role in the great variety of many genres such as arts, action, seishun drama, Kayo Movies (Hit Song Movies), soap operas.</e>
<cmt>青春ドラマ→定訳不明 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He directed many program pictures between 1950&apos;s and 1960&apos;s after he moved from Shochiku to Nikkatsu, he also played an active role in a great variety of genres such as arts, action, seishun drama, Kayo Movies (Hit Song Movies), and soap operas.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He directed many program pictures between 1950s and 1960s after he moved from Shochiku to Nikkatsu, he also played an active role in a great variety of genres such as arts, action, seishun drama, Kayo Movies (Hit Song Movies), and soap operas.</e>
<cmt>1950s and 1960sに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>TV界に進出した70年代前半を経て東宝映画にて映画界に戻り、ホリプロ（元会長堀威夫氏）に吉永小百合作品を監督した経験から、山口百恵・三浦友和のゴールデンコンビで『伊豆の踊子』をリメイクする事になり、その後、『潮騒』『絶唱』『エデンの海』とリメイク作品の監督をし、その新鮮さと斬新な監督技法は日本映画界の中でも歴史に残る作品であり、代表作にリメイク作品が多いというのも特色である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he played active role in TV in early 70&apos;s and again started producing movies, since he had an experience directing Sayuri YOSHINAGA&apos;s movie at Horipro, Inc. (former chairman was Takao HORI), he had an opportunity to remake &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; having two famous actress and actor, Momoe YAMAGUCHI and Tomokazu MIURA, they were called golden combination, and also directed remake movies of &quot;Shiosai&quot;, &quot;Zessho&quot;, &quot;Eden no umi&quot;, he is well known as making remake movies and has fresh and original technique of directing which his movies remained in the history of Japanese movies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he played an active role in TV in the early 70&apos;s and again started producing movies, since he had experience directing Sayuri YOSHINAGA&apos;s movie at Horipro, Inc. (former chairman was Takao HORI), he had an opportunity to remake &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; having a famous actress and actor, Momoe YAMAGUCHI and Tomokazu MIURA, they were called the golden combination, and also directed remakes of &quot;Shiosai,&quot; &quot;Zessho,&quot; &quot;Eden no umi,&quot; and he is well known for remaking movies and has a fresh and original technique for directing so his movies remain in the history of Japanese movies.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he played an active role in TV in the early 70&apos;s and again started producing movies, since he had experience directing Sayuri YOSHINAGA&apos;s movie at Horipro, Inc. (former chairman was Takao HORI), he had an opportunity to remake &quot;Dancing Girls of Izu&quot; having a famous actress and actor, Momoe YAMAGUCHI and Tomokazu MIURA, they were called the golden combination, and also directed remakes of &quot;Shiosai,&quot; &quot;Zessho,&quot; &quot;Eden no umi,&quot; and he is well known for remaking movies and has a fresh and original technique for directing so his movies remain in the history of Japanese movies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="50">
<j>また、60歳を過ぎてからも森昌子、秋吉久美子、小泉今日子、松永麗子、富田靖子らの主演作を製作し、西河作品のスクリーンに「アイドル」を追いかける観客は2つの世代にわたることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also produced movies acted by Masako MORI, Kumiko AKIYOSHI, Kyoko KOIZUMI, Reiko MATSUNAGA, Yasuko TOMITA after he turned sixty years old, there were two separate generations who fancy &apos;idoles&apos; on the screen of Nishikawa&apos;s movie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also produced movies acted by Masako MORI, Kumiko AKIYOSHI, Kyoko KOIZUMI, Reiko MATSUNAGA, Yasuko TOMITA after he turned sixty years old, there were two separate generations who fancy &apos;idols&apos; on the screen of Nishikawa&apos;s movie.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also produced movies acted by Masako MORI, Kumiko AKIYOSHI, Kyoko KOIZUMI, Reiko MATSUNAGA, Yasuko TOMITA after he turned 60 years old, there were two separate generations who fancy &apos;idols&apos; on the screen of Nishikawa&apos;s movie.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="51">
<j>幼年時代を過ごした故郷への思い入れは深く、西河作品には鳥取県に関連したものが幾つか含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some Nishikawa&apos;s movies related to Tottori Prefecture where he spent his childhood, he has strong memory in his hometown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some Nishikawa&apos;s movies related to Tottori Prefecture where he spent his childhood, he has strong memory in his hometown.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some Nishikawa&apos;s movies related to Tottori Prefecture where he spent his childhood, he has strong memory in his hometown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>『絶唱』は原作は松江市だが、映画では鳥取砂丘と賀露港、そして智頭町が舞台に脚色されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original place where &quot;Zessho&quot; was made was in Matsue City, however in this movie there were some scenes of Tottori Sand Dune, Karo-ko Port, Chizu-cho Town were added to the story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original place where &quot;Zessho&quot; was made was in Matsue City, however in this movie there were some scenes of the Tottori Sand Dune, Karo-ko Port, Chizu-cho Town added to the story.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original place where &quot;Zessho&quot; was made was in Matsue City, however in this movie there were some scenes of the Tottori Sand Dune, Karo Port, Chizu Town added to the story.</e>
<cmt>ko、cho削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>また『悲しき別れの歌』（1965）、『夕笛』（1967）、『残雪』（1968）、『ザ・スパイダースバリ珍道中』（1968）などの作品では智頭好夫の名前で脚本を書いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also wrote script of &quot;Kanashiki wakare no uta&quot; (1965), Yubue (1967), Zansetsu (1968), &quot;ザ・スパイダ-スバリ珍道中&quot; (1968) under the name of Yoshio CHITO.</e>
<cmt>悲しき別れの歌, 夕笛, 残雪, ザ・スパイダースバリ珍道中→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also wrote the script for &quot;Kanashiki wakare no uta&quot; (1965), Yubue (1967), Zansetsu (1968), &quot;ザ・スパイダ-スバリ珍道中&quot; (1968) under the name of Yoshio CHITO.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also wrote the script for &quot;Kanashiki wakare no uta&quot; (1965), &quot;Yubue&quot; (1967), &quot;Zansetsu&quot; (1968), &quot;Spiders no Barito Chindochu&quot; (Funny Tour) (1968) under the name of Yoshio CHITO.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot;を補足しました。ザ・スパイダースバリ珍道中→&quot;Spiders no Barito Chindochu&quot; (Funny Tour) [http://www.citwf.com/film329932.htm]と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Okc(id:17021), 経済準学士(id:22656), Balmung0731(id:99201), ウィキウィ2(id:83093), 松茸(id:27535), Lupinoid(id:68), 663highland(id:18755), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), TANUKI(id:28527), MiraModreno(id:212669), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>