<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大江広元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OE no Hiromoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OE no Hiromoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Hiromoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大江 広元（おおえ の ひろもと、久安4年（1148年） - 嘉禄元年6月10日 (旧暦)（1225年7月16日））は、平安時代末期、鎌倉時代初期の実務官僚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OE no Hiromoto (1148-July 16, 1225) was a governmental official responsible for practical works in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OE no Hiromoto (1148-July 16, 1225) was a governmental official responsible for practical works in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Hiromoto (1148 - July 23, 1225) was a governmental official responsible for practical works from the end of the Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉幕府の政所初代別当（長官）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first Betto (representative, the responsible person) of Mandokoro (Administrative Board) for Kamakura Bakufu (director).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first Betto (representative, the responsible person) of Mandokoro (Administrative Board) for Kamakura Bakufu (director).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first chief officer of Administrative Board for Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>最初は朝廷に仕える下級貴族のいわゆる官人であったが、鎌倉に下って源頼朝の側近官僚となり、鎌倉幕府の創設に貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was originally a so-called government official from lower-ranking nobles (esp. one of low to medium rank) that served the imperial court, and later he went down to Kamakura to be a official as a close adviser for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, contributing to establish Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was originally a so-called government official from lower-ranking nobles (esp. one of low to medium rank) that served the imperial court, and later he went down to Kamakura to be a official as a close adviser for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, contributing to establish Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was originally a government official from lower-ranking nobles that served the Imperial Court, went down to Kamakura to be an official as a close adviser for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and contributed to the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。 Imperial Courtに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>大江は本姓であり苗字ではないため、大江広元は“おおえ の ひろもと”と読むのが正しく、“おおえ ひろもと”ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since OE was a main name not a family name, it should be read as `OE no Hiromoto&apos; not as `OE Hiromoto&apos; to be exact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since OE was a main name not a family name, it should be read as `OE no Hiromoto&apos; not as `OE Hiromoto&apos; to be exact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since OE was a real name and not a family name, it should be read as &apos;OE no Hiromoto&apos; not as &apos;OE Hiromoto&apos; to be exact.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief biography</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>広元は『江氏家譜』では藤原光能の息子で、母の再婚相手である中原広季のもとで養育されたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Koshi kafu&quot; (history of the Oe family), Hiromoto was a son of FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi, and he was said to have been brought up under NAKAHARA no Hirosue who was a remarried husband for his mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Koshi kafu&quot; (history of the Oe family), Hiromoto was a son of FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi, and he was said to have been brought up under NAKAHARA no Hirosue who was a remarried husband for his mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Koshi kafu,&quot; Hiromoto was a son of FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi, and he was said to have been brought up under NAKAHARA no Hirosue who was a remarried husband of his mother.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。コンマの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし『尊卑分脈』「大江氏系図」では大江維光は実父、中原広季は養父とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, OE no Koremitsu was stated as his real father, and NAKAHARA no Hirosue was stated as his adopted father in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) and `family tree of the Oe clan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処文章の分割に伴い文意に影響のない範囲で「で」「は」を変換し若干リライトしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, OE no Koremitsu was stated as his real father, and NAKAHARA no Hirosue was stated as his adopted father in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) and `family tree of the Oe clan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; and &apos;Oe shi keizu,&apos; OE no Koremitsu was stated as being his real father, while NAKAHARA no Hirosue was stated as being his adaptive father.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>逆に『続群書類従』「中原系図」では中原広季は実父、大江維光は養父とされており、はっきりしたことは解らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, NAKAHARA no Hirosue was stated as his real father and OE no Koremitsu was stated as his adopted father in &quot;Zoku-Gunsho-Ruiju&quot; and in `family tree of the Nakahara family&apos; by contraries.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, NAKAHARA no Hirosue was stated as his real father and OE no Koremitsu was stated as his adopted father in &quot;Zoku-Gunsho-Ruiju&quot; and in `family tree of the Nakahara family&apos; by contraries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, in &quot;Zoku-Gunsho-Ruiju&quot; and the &apos;Nakahara keizu,&apos; NAKAHARA no Hirosue was stated as being his real father and OE no Koremitsu was stated as his adaptive father, leaving the truth laregly unclear.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>当初は中原広元（なかはら の ひろもと）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, he was called Nakahara no Hiromoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, he was called Nakahara no Hiromoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called NAKAHARA no Hiromoto, at first.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大江姓に改めたのはかなり遅く1216年（建保4年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was quite late he changed his family name into OE, which was 1216.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed his family name into OE quite late, around 1216.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed his family name to OE much later, around 1216.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>極官は正四位陸奥守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His kyokkan (the most highest rank which one was appointed) was Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His kyokkan (the most highest rank which one was appointed) was Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kyokkan (the highest rank one was appointed) was Senior Fourth Rank, the governor of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>広元の兄・中原親能は源頼朝と親しく、早くに京を離れ頼朝に従っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakahara no Chikayoshi, Hiromoto&apos;s elder brother was close to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and he left Kyoto early to follow Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakahara no Chikayoshi, Hiromoto&apos;s elder brother was close to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and he left Kyoto early to follow Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakahara no Chikayoshi, who was Hiromoto&apos;s elder brother, was close to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and left Kyoto early to follow Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1183年（寿永2年）10月には源義経の軍勢と共に上洛し、翌1184年（元暦元年）正月に再度入京して頼朝代官として万事を奉行し、貴族との交渉に活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came out to Kyoto with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s force in October 1183 and he reentered Kyoto in New year, 1184 to perform various affairs; he was also active as a negotiator with court nobles.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came out to Kyoto with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s force in October 1183 and he reentered Kyoto in New year, 1184 to perform various affairs; he was also active as a negotiator with court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikayoshi went up to Kyoto with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s force in October 1183 and reentered Kyoto on New Years Day, 1184 to perform various affairs as a local governor serving Yoritomo; he was also active as a negotiator with court nobles.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その親能の縁から1184年に広元も頼朝も鎌倉へ下り、政所の前身である公文所別当となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With his relationship to Chikayoshi, Hiromoto also went down to Kamakura, and became a Betto (chief officer) of Kumonjo (administration office) which was the precursor of Mandokoro (Administrative Board).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With his relationship to Chikayoshi, Hiromoto also went down to Kamakura, and became a Betto (chief officer) of Kumonjo (administration office) which was the precursor of Mandokoro (Administrative Board).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With his relationship with Chikayoshi, Hiromoto also went down to Kamakura in 1184, and became a chief officer of administration office which was the precursor of Mandokoro.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>更に頼朝が二品右大将となって政所を開設してからは、その別当として朝廷との交渉その他に実務家として活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What&apos;s more, after Yoritomo established Mandokoro as nihon (the second court rank for Imperial Princes) Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was active as a Betto to negotiate with the imperial court and to handle other affairs as a practician.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What&apos;s more, after Yoritomo established Mandokoro as nihon (the second court rank for Imperial Princes) Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), he was active as a Betto to negotiate with the imperial court and to handle other affairs as a practician.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What&apos;s more, after Yoritomo established Administrative Borad as the second court rank, Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards, he was active as a chief officer to carry out negotiations with the imperial court and to handle other affairs as a practician.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>『吾妻鏡』1185年（文治元年）11月12日条により、頼朝が守護・地頭を設置したのも広元の献策によるとよく言われ、研究者の間でも古くはそう理解されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was commonly believed among scholars in the old days that an establishment of Shugo (provincial constable) and jito (manager and lord of manor) by Yoritom was realized by Hiromoto&apos;s suggested proposal according to the article; November 12, 1185 of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was commonly believed among scholars in the old days that an establishment of Shugo (provincial constable) and jito (manager and lord of manor) by Yoritom was realized by Hiromoto&apos;s suggested proposal according to the article; November 12, 1185 of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to an entry of the Eleventh Month, 12th, 1185 of &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; it was commonly believed among scholars in the old days that the establishment of provincial constable and manager and lord of manor by Yoritomo was realized due to Hiromoto&apos;s proposal.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。コンマの位置を訂正しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし1960年（昭和35年）に石母田正がこの問題を詳細に分析し、これは幕府独自の記録によったものではなく、鎌倉時代の後期の一般的な通説に基づく作文ではないかと指摘する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in 1960, Tadashi ISHIMODA further analyzed this issue, and pointed out that it was a composition written based on the common theory in the latter half of Kamakura period and denied that it was from the record of Bakufu itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in 1960, Tadashi ISHIMODA further analyzed this issue, and pointed out that it was a composition written based on the common theory in the latter half of Kamakura period and denied that it was from the record of Bakufu itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in 1960, Tadashi ISHIMODA further analyzed this issue, and pointed out that it was a composition written based on a theory common in the latter half of the Kamakura period, instead of written based on the bakufu&apos;s records.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そこから盛んな論争が巻き起こり、現在では広元の献策「権門勢家の庄公を論ぜず、兵粮米（段別五升）を宛て課す」は、「諸国平均」ではなく「五畿・山陰・山陽・南海・西海諸国」であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, a feverish controversy occurred, nowadays, it is regarded the Hiromoto&apos;s proposed policy; `imposing tax on rice (5-sho per tan) regardless of private estate or public estate&apos; was not for `all the countries,&apos; but for `Goki (Yamato, Yamashiro, Settsu, Kochi and Izumi Provinces), the Sanin (mountain provinces behind the Sanyo or Inland Sea provinces), the Sanyo (Inland Sea provinces), the Nankai (southern provinces), the Saikai (provinces on the western seacoast).&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処意味不明のため、仮訳で、段別五升→5-sho per tan を採用していますが、定かではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, a feverish controversy occurred, nowadays, it is regarded that Hiromoto&apos;s proposed policy; `imposing tax on rice (5-sho per tan) regardless of private estate or public estate&apos; was not for `all the countries,&apos; but for `Goki (Yamato, Yamashiro, Settsu, Kochi and Izumi Provinces), the Sanin (mountain provinces behind the Sanyo or Inland Sea provinces), the Sanyo (Inland Sea provinces), the Nankai (southern provinces), the Saikai (provinces on the western seacoast).&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That started a feverish controversy, and now it is regarded that Hiromoto&apos;s proposed policy; &apos;imposing tax on rice (five-sho per tan) regardless of private estate or public estate&apos; was not for &apos;all the provinces,&apos; but for &apos;Goki (Yamato, Yamashiro, Settsu, Kochi and Izumi Provinces), the Sanin (mountain provinces behind the Sanyo or Inland Sea provinces), the Sanyo (Inland Sea provinces), the Nankai (southern provinces), and the Saikai (provinces on the western seacoast).&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、「守護」職はこのときではなく、1185年での要求は源義経・源行家の捜索・追捕を名目とした一国単位の「国地頭」と「総追捕使」であって、室町時代にまで繋がる守護職の発端は1190年（建久元年）に頼朝が初めて上京し、後白河法皇や九条兼実らと合意した「諸国守護」を奉行する権限にあるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, post of `shugo&apos; (provincial constable) was not established this time; the establishment of `kuni jito&apos; (the appointment of provincial jito to each province) and `So-tsuibushi&apos; (job title which has rights of government, military affair and police authority) in each country on the purpose of searching and capturing MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and MINAMOTO no Yukiie, which was just nominal, was demanded in 1185, and the origin of shugo which would continue until the Muromachi period was the authority which was agreed between Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, Kanezane KUJO and Yoritomo to enforce &apos;syugo in all the countries&apos; when Yoritomo came out to Kyoto for the first time in 1190.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, the post of `shugo&apos; (provincial constable) was not established this time; the establishment of `kuni jito&apos; (the appointment of provincial jito to each province) and `So-tsuibushi&apos; (job title which has rights of government, military affair and police authority) in each country for the purpose of searching and capturing MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and MINAMOTO no Yukiie, which was just nominal, was demanded in 1185, and the origin of shugo which would continue until the Muromachi period was the authority which was agreed between Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, Kanezane KUJO and Yoritomo to enforce &apos;syugo in all the countries&apos; when Yoritomo came out to Kyoto for the first time in 1190.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, the position of &apos;provincial constable&apos; was not established this time; the establishment of &apos;provincial steward&apos; and &apos;General Constable&apos; in each province for the purpose of searching and capturing MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune and MINAMOTO no Yukiie, which was of nominal priority, ordered in 1185, and the origin of provincial constable which would continue until the Muromachi period lay in the authority which was agreed between Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, Kanezane KUJO and Yoritomo to enforce &apos;provincial constables in all the provinces&apos; when Yoritomo came out to Kyoto for the first time in 1190.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>1199年（正治元年）の頼朝の死後は、北条義時や北条政子と協調して幕政に参与する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoritomo died in 1199, he participated in the administration of shogunate government in collaboration with Yoshitoki HOJO or Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoritomo died in 1199, he participated in the administration of the shogunate government in collaboration with Yoshitoki HOJO or Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo died in 1199; thereafter he participated in the administration of the shogunate government in collaboration with Yoshitoki HOJO and Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>承久の乱のときも、長男大江親広が官軍側につき、親子相克した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Jokyu Disturbance occurred, he conflicted his eldest son, OE no Chikahiro who was on the government army side.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Jokyu Disturbance occurred, he had a conflict with his eldest son, OE no Chikahiro who was on the government army side.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Jokyu Disturbance, he had a conflict with his eldest son, OE no Chikahiro who was on the emperor&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、『吾妻鏡』では広元はあくまで幕府軍の側に立って朝廷との一戦に慎重な御家人を鼓舞、主戦論を唱えた北条政子に協調して幕府軍を勝利に導いた影の功労者のひとりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; Hiromoto was on the bakufu army side, and was regarded one of shadow contributors who led the Bakufu army to the victory in collaboration with Masako HOJO who encouraged reluctant gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods)to fight against the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; Hiromoto was on the bakufu army side, and was regarded a shadow contributor who led the Bakufu army to victory in collaboration with Masako HOJO who encouraged reluctant gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods)to fight against the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; Hiromoto was on the bakufu&apos;s side, and was regarded one of contributors behind the scene who led the bakufu army to victory in collaboration with Masako HOJO, who advocated war and encouraged reluctant direct vassals of the shogun to fight against the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Imperial Courtに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ただしこれも「守護・地頭」の件と同様に、顕彰記事の疑いもあるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it was suspicious as well as the issue of `Shugo and jito&apos; mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However it was suspicious as well as the issue of `Shugo and jito&apos; mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the above-mentioned issue was considered suspicious as the issue of &apos;provincial constable and General Constable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ピリオド位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし広元が和田義盛の乱の際しての軍勢召集や所領訴訟に際して、執権である北条義時とともに広元が「連署」をした文書が存在することや、頼朝が強いつながりを有していなかった土御門通親などの公卿との独自の交流を有するなど、鎌倉幕府における京吏の筆頭であり、重要な地位を占めていたことは確かである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was certain that Hiromoto was the head official of Kamakura Bakufu and was in the critical position; the document with signatures of Yoshitoki HOJO, Shikken (Shogunal regent) and Hiromoto when gathering the force for Yoshimori WADA&apos;s Disturbance and a suit for shoryo (territory) exists, and he had his own interactions with nobles such as Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO whom Yoritomo didn&apos;t have a particular interaction with.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was certain that Hiromoto was the head official of Kamakura Bakufu and was in the critical position; the document with signatures of Yoshitoki HOJO, Shikken (Shogunal regent) and Hiromoto when gathering the force for Yoshimori WADA&apos;s Disturbance and a suit for shoryo (territory) exists, and he had his own interactions with nobles such as Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO whom Yoritomo didn&apos;t have a particular interaction with.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is certain that Hiromoto was the head of the court officials in the Kamakura bakufu and was in a critical position, which are proved by the existence of documents with signatures of Shogunal regent Yoshitoki HOJO, and Hiromoto in gathering forces for Yoshimori WADA&apos;s disturbance and a suit for territory; and Hiromoto&apos;s own interactions with imperial nobles such as Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO whom Yoritomo didn&apos;t have any particular interactions with.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>年譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronological record</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronological record</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronological record</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="24">
<j>久安4（1148年）、京都にて誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto in 1148.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kyoto in 1148.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto in 1148.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>中原氏を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was referred to as the Nakahara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was referred to as the Nakahara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was referred to the Nakahara clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>年月不詳　明経得業生となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Month and year unknown, he became a Myogyo Tokugyosho (Distinguished Scholars of Confucianism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Month and year unknown, he became a Myogyo Tokugyosho (Distinguished Scholars of Confucianism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Month and year unknown, he became a Distinguished Scholars of Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>仁安 (日本)3年（1168年）12月13日、縫殿允に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 13, 1168, he was appointed to Nuidono no jo (Secretary at Bureau of the Wardrobe and Court Ladies).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 13, 1168, he was appointed to Nuidono no jo (Secretary at Bureau of the Wardrobe and Court Ladies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 19, 1169, he was appointed to Secretary at Bureau of the Wardrobe and Court Ladies.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>嘉応2年（1170年）12月5日、権少外記に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 5, 1170, he was transferred to Gon no shogeki (provisional junior secretary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 5, 1170, he was transferred to Gon no shogeki (provisional junior secretary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 19, 1171, he was transferred to provisional junior secretary.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>承安 (日本)元年（1171年）1月18日、少外記に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 18, 1171, he was transferred to Shogeki (Junior Secretary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 18, 1171, he was transferred to Shogeki (Junior Secretary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 3, 1171, he was transferred to Junior Secretary.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>承安3年（1173年）1月5日、従五位下に叙位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 5, 1173, he was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5, 1173, he was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 25, 1173, he was appointed to Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>月日不詳、九条兼実の政務に関与。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Month and date unknown, he was involved in government affairs of Kanezane KUJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Month and date unknown, he was involved in government affairs of Kanezane KUJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Month and date unknown, he was involved in government affairs of Kanezane KUJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）4月9日、従五位上に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 9, 1183, he was appointed to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 9, 1183, he was appointed to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 9, 1183, he was appointed to Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>元暦元年（1184年）、相模国鎌倉に下向。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1184, he left Kyoto for Kamakura, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1184, he left Kyoto for Kamakura, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1184, he left Kyoto for Kamakura, Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>源頼朝の家政機関たる公文所別当に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assumed the post of Betto of Kumonjo which took charge of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s domestic service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He assumed the post of Betto of Kumonjo which took charge of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s domestic service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He assumed the post of chief officer of administration office which took charge of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s domestic service.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="35">
<j>9月17日、因幡守に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 17, he was appointed to Inaba no kami (Governor of Inaba Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 17, he was appointed to Inaba no kami (Governor of Inaba Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 30, he was appointed to Governor of Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>文治元年（1185年）4月3日、正五位下に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 3, 1185, he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 3, 1185, he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 11, 1185, he was promoted to Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>因幡守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He remained as the position of Inaba no kami (Governor of Inaba Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He remained as the position of Inaba no kami (Governor of Inaba Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He remained in the position of Governor of Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="38">
<j>4月27日、源頼朝公卿に列するに伴い、公文所を政所と改め、引き続き別当留任（異説として公文所・政所の両所並存・別当兼務説がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumonjo was changed into Mandokoro and he remained in the position of Betto when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo became a court noble on April 27 (different theories; Kumonjo and Mandokoro coexisted, he assumed the post of Betto in addition to another post).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumonjo was changed into Mandokoro and he remained in the position of Betto when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo became a court noble on April 27 (different theories; Kumonjo and Mandokoro coexisted, he assumed the post of Betto in addition to another post).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Administration office was changed into Administrative Borad and he remained in the position of chief officer when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo became a court noble on June 4 (different theories; administration office and Administrative Borad coexisted, and he assumed the position of chief officer in addition to another position in Administrative Borad).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="39">
<j>6月29日、因幡守辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 29, he resigned as Inaba no kami (Governor of Inaba Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 29, he resigned as Inaba no kami (Governor of Inaba Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 3, he resigned as Inaba no kami.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="40">
<j>建久2年（1191年）4月1日、明法博士兼左衛門大尉に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 1191, he was appointed to Myobo hakase (teacher of the law in the Ritsuryo system) and Saemon no daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 1191, he was appointed to Myobo hakase (teacher of the law in the Ritsuryo system) and Saemon no daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 2, 1191, he was appointed to teacher of the law in the Ritsuryo system and Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>検非違使にも補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to a kebiishi (a police and judicial chief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to a kebiishi (a police and judicial chief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to a police and judicial chief.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="42">
<j>11月5日、明法博士辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 5, he resigned as Myobo hakase (teacher of the law in the Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 5, he resigned as Myobo hakase (teacher of the law in the Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 30, he resigned from Myobo hakase.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="43">
<j>建久3年（1192年）2月21日、検非違使・左衛門大尉両官職辞職辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 21, 1192, he resigned as kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and as Saemon no daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 21, 1192, he resigned as kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and as Saemon no daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 12, 1192, he resigned from police and judicial chief and Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="44">
<j>建久7年（1196年）1月28日、兵庫頭に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 28, 1196, he was appointed to Hyogo no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 28, 1196, he was appointed to Hyogo no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 6, 1196, he was appointed to Head of Hyogo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="45">
<j>正治元年（1199年）12月9日、掃部頭に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 9, 1199, he was appointed to Kamon no kami (Director at the Bureau of Palace Upkeep).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 9, 1199, he was appointed to Kamon no kami (Director at the Bureau of Palace Upkeep).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 4, 1200, he was appointed to Director at the Bureau of Palace Upkeep.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="46">
<j>正治2年（1200年）5月、大膳大夫に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1200, he was transferred to Daizen no daibu (Master of the Palace Table).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1200, he was transferred to Daizen no daibu (Master of the Palace Table).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1200, he was transferred to Master of the Palace Table.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="47">
<j>建仁3年（1203年）、大膳大夫辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1203, he resigned as Daizen no daibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1203, he resigned as Daizen no daibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1203, he resigned from Master of the Palace Table.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="48">
<j>建永元年（1206年）、鎌倉幕府政所別当辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1206, he resigned as Mandokoro Betto (Director of the Administrative Board) of the Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1206, he resigned as Mandokoro Betto (Director of the Administrative Board) of the Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1206, he resigned from Director of the Administrative Board of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="49">
<j>建保元年（1213年）1月5日、従四位上昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 5, 1213, he was promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5, 1213, he was promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 4, 1213, he was promoted to Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="50">
<j>建保2年（1214年）1月5日、正四位下昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 5, 1214, he was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5, 1214, he was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 23, 1214, he was promoted to Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="51">
<j>建保4年（1216年）1月27日、陸奥守に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 27, 1216, he was assigned to Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 27, 1216, he was assigned to Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 23, 1216, he was assigned to the governor of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="52">
<j>閏6月1日、大江の氏に改めるに付き、朝廷認可。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 1, change of his family name into OE was approved by the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 1, change of his family name into OE was approved by the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 24, change of his real name into OE was approved by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。Imperial Courtに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="53">
<j>8月、鎌倉幕府政所別当に復職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August he reassumed the post of Mandokoro Betto (Director of the Administrative Board) of the Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August he reassumed the post of Mandokoro Betto (Director of the Administrative Board) of the Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August he reassumed the post of Director of the Administrative Board of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="54">
<j>建保5年（1217年）11月10日、陸奥守辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 10, 1217, he resigned as Mutsu no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 10, 1217, he resigned as Mutsu no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 17, 1217, he resigned from the governor of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>出家し覚阿を号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a priest and referred himself as Kakua.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a priest and referred to himself as Kakua.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a priest and referred to himself as Kakua.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>（陸奥守の後任は、鎌倉幕府執権北條義時となる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Yoshitoki OJO, Shiken of the Kamakura Bakufu took over his post as Moutsu no Kami)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Yoshitoki OJO, Shiken of the Kamakura Bakufu took over his post as Moutsu no Kami)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Shogunal regent Yoshitoki HOJO of the Kamakura bakufu took over his post as Mutsu no Kami)</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="57">
<j>嘉禄元年（1225年）6月10日、入寂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 10, 1225, he passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 10, 1225, he passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 23, 1225, he died.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>享年78。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 78.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 78.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was seventy-eight years old.</e>
<cmt>左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>末裔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendant</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendant</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>複数にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>長男・大江親広は政所別当・京都守護などの幕府要職を歴任するが、承久の乱で朝廷方に付いて敗走し、出羽国寒河江荘に籠もる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiromoto&apos;s eldest son, OE no Chikahiro successively held the posts of Mandokoro Betto, Kyoto Shugo, etc., and he ran away when the imperial court side which he had supported lost in the Jokyu Disturbance, and stayed in Sagae no so, Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiromoto&apos;s eldest son, OE no Chikahiro successively held the posts of Mandokoro Betto, Kyoto Shugo, etc., and he ran away when the imperial court side which he had supported lost in the Jokyu Disturbance, and stayed in Sagae no so, Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiromoto&apos;s eldest son, OE no Chikahiro successively held the positions of Director of the Administrative Board, provincial constable of Kyoto, etc., but he ran away when he took the Imperial Court side and it was defeated in the Jokyu Disturbance, and stayed in Sagae no so, Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Imperial Courtに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>その子孫は寒河江氏などにつながるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sagae clan was said to be descended from OE no Chikahiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sagae clan was said to be descended from OE no Chikahiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sagae clan was said to be descended from OE no Chikahiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="61">
<j>次男・長井広時は備後守護となり、兄大江親広が承久の乱でその地位を失って以降、大江氏の嫡流として、少なくともその子長井泰秀から評定衆を始め幕府の要職を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiromoto&apos;s second son, Hirotoki NAGAI became a military governor of Bingo, and his descendants, at least from Hirotoi&apos;s son, Yasuhide NAGAI, served critical posts of the Kamakura Bakufu like hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) as a main line of the Oe clan after his elder brother, Chikahiro lost his position in the Jokyu Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiromoto&apos;s second son, Hirotoki NAGAI became a military governor of Bingo, and his descendants, at least from Hirotoi&apos;s son, Yasuhide NAGAI, served critical posts of the Kamakura Bakufu like hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) as a main line of the Oe clan after his elder brother, Chikahiro lost his position in the Jokyu Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiromoto&apos;s second son, Hirotoki NAGAI became a provincial constable of Bingo Province, and his descendants, at least from his son, Yasuhide NAGAI, filled critical posts in the Kamakura bakufu such as a member of Council of State as a direct blood line of the Oe clan after his elder brother, Chikahiro lost his position in the Jokyu Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>広元から五代目の長井宗秀は寄合衆にもなり、『吾妻鏡』の編纂者のひとりと目されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munehide NAGAI, the fifth descendant from Hiromoto became a Yoriaishu (a member of the top decision making organ), and was estimated as one of compilers of &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munehide NAGAI, the fifth descendant from Hiromoto became a Yoriaishu (a member of the top decision making organ), and was estimated as one of compilers of &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munehide NAGAI, the fifth descendant from Hiromoto became a member of the top decision making council, and was estimated as a compiler of &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="63">
<j>三男・宗元の経歴は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiromoto&apos;s third son, Munemoto&apos;s career was unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiromoto&apos;s third son, Munemoto&apos;s career was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiromoto&apos;s third son, Munemoto&apos;s career was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>その子那波政茂は1239年（延応元）に左近将監、1241年（仁治2）に従五位下に叙爵、その後従五位上に進み、1254年（建長6）に引付衆となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashige NAWA,the child of Munemoto became a Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1239, he was conferred a peerage as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1241, and promoting to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade), finally became Hikitsukeshu (Coadjutors of the High Court) in 1254.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashige NAWA,the child of Munemoto became a Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1239, he was conferred a peerage as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1241, and promoting to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade), finally became Hikitsukeshu (Coadjutors of the High Court) in 1254.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashige NAWA, the child of Munemoto became a Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards in 1239, he was conferred a peerage as Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade in 1241, and promoted to Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, before finally becoming Coadjutors of the High Court in 1254.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="65">
<j>四男・毛利季光は16歳の1216年（健保4）に従五位下に叙爵、32歳のとき『吾妻鏡』1233年（天福元）11月3日条に評定衆とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourth son of Hiromoto, Suemitsu MORI was conferred a peerage as Jugoinoge in 1216, and became a hyojoshu at at the age of thirty-two according to the article of November 3, 1233 of &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth son of Hiromoto, Suemitsu MORI was conferred a peerage as Jugoinoge in 1216, and became a hyojoshu at at the age of thirty-two according to the article of November 3, 1233 of &quot;Azuma Kagami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiromoto&apos;s fourth son, Suemitsu MORI was conferred a peerage as Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade at the age of 16 in 1216, and became a member of Council of State at the age of 32 according to the article &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;on November 3, 1233.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>1247年の宝治合戦で三浦泰村に味方して三浦一族とともに源頼朝持仏堂であった法華堂で自害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a Battle of Hoji occurred in 1247, he was on Yasumura MIURA&apos;s side and committed suicide with the Miura family at Hokkedo which was jibutsu-do hall (the nobility&apos;s private Buddha statue hall) for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Battle of Hoji occurred in 1247, he was on Yasumura MIURA&apos;s side and committed suicide with the Miura family at Hokkedo which was the jibutsu-do hall (the nobility&apos;s private Buddha statue hall) for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Battle of Hoji occurred in 1247, Suemitsu was on Yasumura MIURA&apos;s side and committed suicide with the Miura family at Hokke-do which was the private Buddha statue hall for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ハイフン補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>しかしその四男毛利経光は越後に居たため巻き込まれず、所領を安堵された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the fourth son of Suemitsu, Tsunemitsu MORI was not involved in it and inherited the territory as he was in Echigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the fourth son of Suemitsu, Tsunemitsu MORI was not involved in it and inherited the territory as he was in Echigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suemitsu&apos;s fourth son, Tsunemitsu MORI was not involved in the incident as he was in Echigo and inherited the territory.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>経光の二男時親は南条と安芸吉田庄を相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second son of Tsunemitsu, Tokichika inherited Nanjo and Yoshidanosho, Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second son of Tsunemitsu, Tokichika inherited Nanjo and Yoshidanosho, Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemitsu&apos;s second son, Tokichika inherited Nanjo and Yoshidanosho, Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>時親は戦国大名安芸毛利家の始祖となって毛利元就に繋がる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Aki Mori family, daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period which would be descended to Motonari MORI originated from Tokichika.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Aki Mori family, daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period which would be descended to Motonari MORI originated from Tokichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokichika founded the Aki-Mori family, a territorial lord in the Sengoku period, which descended to Motonari MORI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>また越後国の越後北条氏（きたじょうし）も時親の子に始る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Echigo-Kitajo clan, Echigo Province originated from the child of Tokichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Echigo-Kitajo clan, Echigo Province originated from the child of Tokichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Echigo-Kitajo clan in Echigo Province decended from a son of Tokichika.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="71">
<j>五男・海東忠成は1227年に叙爵し従五位下、その後従四位下まで進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiromoto&apos;s fifth son, Tadashige KAITO was conferred a peerage as Jugoinoge in 1217, and later advanced to Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiromoto&apos;s fifth son, Tadashige KAITO was conferred a peerage as Jugoinoge in 1217, and later advanced to Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiromoto&apos;s fifth son, Tadashige KAITO was conferred a peerage as Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade in 1227, and later advanced to Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>1245年に評定衆となったが、宝治合戦における兄への加担を問われ辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a hyojoshu in 1245, but resigned with suspicion of supporting his brother in the Battle of Hoji.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a hyojoshu in 1245, but resigned with suspicion of supporting his brother in the Battle of Hoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a member of Council of state in 1245, but resigned with suspicion of supporting his brother in the Battle of Hoji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="73">
<j>また、三河国の酒井氏、因幡国の因幡毛利氏、出雲国の多胡氏など大江広元を祖とするとものは多数見られるが、真偽のほどは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many clans including the Sakai clan in Mikawa Province, the Inaba-Mori clan in Inaba Province, the Tago clan in Izumo Province seemed to be originated in Hiromoto OE, but it was non liquet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many clans including the Sakai clan in Mikawa Province, the Inaba-Mori clan in Inaba Province, the Tago clan in Izumo Province seemed to be originated in Hiromoto OE, but it was non liquet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many clans including the Sakai clan in Mikawa Province, the Inaba-Mori clan in Inaba Province, the Tago clan in Izumo Province seemed to be originated in Hiromoto OE, although their authenticity remains uncertain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>広島市の地名は、広元の子孫・毛利輝元が1589年（天正17年）広島城築城の鍬入れの時に、毛利氏の祖先である広元から一字を採って命名したといわれている（諸説あり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshima City (広島市) was named taking one character 広 from Hiromoto 広元 which was the ancestor of the Mori clan, When Hiromoto&apos;s descendant, Terumoto MORI performed a ritual of spading the ground of a newly built Hiroshima castle in 1589 (various theories as to this).</e>
<cmt>文意訳出のため、全角文字（漢字）を表記しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshima City (広島市) was named taking one character 広 from Hiromoto 広元 which was the ancestor of the Mori clan, When Hiromoto&apos;s descendant, Terumoto MORI performed a ritual of spading the ground of a newly built Hiroshima castle in 1589 (various theories as to this).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshima City (広島市) was named after taking the character 広 from Hiromoto 広元 who was the ancestor of the Mori clan, when Hiromoto&apos;s descendant, Terumoto MORI performed a ritual of spading the ground of the newly built Hiroshima-jo castle in 1589 (various theories as to this).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 陽一(id:92099), Andee(id:20421), Kamakura(id:472), ほっちゃれ(id:147782), 小者(id:172526), Flanc(id:47280), Masyu(id:31065), 玄史生(id:43670), 代言人(id:33675), Geogie(id:143809), 海衛士(id:19229), Loveless(id:129239), Ktmchi(id:113301), Point136(id:211299), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Yas(id:739), Junger(id:10282), Bankokuya(id:91191), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>