<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高畠長直</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naganao TAKABATAKE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naganao TAKABATAKE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naganao TAKABATAKE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高畠 長直（たかばたけ ながなお、？ - 天文 (元号)18年6月24日 (旧暦)（1549年7月18日））は、戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naganao TAKABATAKE (? - July 18, 1549 (lunar calendar) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naganao TAKABATAKE (? - July 18, 1549 (lunar calendar) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naganao TAKABATAKE (? - July 28, 1549) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived in the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正、(lunar calendar)削除、Sengoku periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>細川氏の家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a subordinate warrior of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a subordinate warrior of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a subordinate warrior of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は甚九郎、後に伊豆守の官途名を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His popular name was Jinkuro and, later, he was given a official name of Izu no Kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His popular name was Jinkuro and, later, he was given a official name of Izu no Kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His popular name was Jinkuro and, later, he was given a official name of Izu no Kami (Governor of Izu Province).</e>
<cmt>Izu no Kamiの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>元は山城国鳥羽の国人の出であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His origin was a kokujin of Toba in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His origin was a kokujin of Toba in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His origin was a kokujin (local samurai) of Toba in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>kokujinの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同国の国人は山城国一揆が、当時の管領であった細川政元と関係を持っていたことで知られるように、戦国時代に入ると同氏の影響を強く受けるようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokujin in that Province went under influence of the Hosokawa clan during the Sengoku Period as known from the fact that Yamashiro no Kuni Ikki (uprising in Yamashiro Province) had certain relation with Masamoto HOSOKAWA who was the Kanrei (shogunal deputy) at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokujin in that Province were under influence of the Hosokawa clan during the Sengoku Period as known from the fact that Yamashiro no Kuni Ikki (uprising in Yamashiro Province) had certain relation with Masamoto HOSOKAWA who was the Kanrei (shogunal deputy) at that time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokujin in that Province were under influence of the Hosokawa clan during the Sengoku period as known from the fact that the uprising in Yamashiro Province had certain relation with Masamoto HOSOKAWA who was the Kanrei (shogunal deputy) at that time.</e>
<cmt>Sengoku periodとし、Yamashiro no Kuni Ikki (uprising in Yamashiro Province)→the uprising in Yamashiro Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>高畠氏は桂川 (淀川水系)流域の高畠荘の有力武士であるとともに土倉や水運関係の仕事などを営んでいたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Takabatake clan was an influential samurai in the Takabatake no sho in the basin of Katsuragawa River (Yodogawa River system) and was engaged in the business of doso (storehouse money broker) and transportation by water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Takabatake clan was an influential samurai in the Takabatake no sho in the basin of Katsuragawa River (Yodogawa River system) and was engaged in the business of doso (storehouse money broker) and transportation by water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Takabatake clan was an influential samurai in the Takabatake no sho in the basin of Katsura-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) and was engaged in the business of doso (storehouse money broker) and transportation by water.</e>
<cmt>Katsura-gawa River、Yodo-gawa Riverとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>細川高国と細川晴元が管領の地位を巡って争った際には、長直は兄である与十郎長信とともに晴元側の一員として参戦し、晴元の勝利後には兄が山城郡代として山城国内の細川領を監督する地位に立ったために、長直も晴元の近臣として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takakuni HOSOKAWA and Harumoto HOSOKAWA fought for the position of Kanrei, Naganao participated in the war together with his elder brother, Yojuro Naganobu as a member of the Harumoto side and, after the victory of Harumoto, he served as a close aide of Harumoto because his brother assumed the position of Yamashiro Gundai (Intendant of a region or administrator of a town) to supervise the territory of Hosokawa family in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Takakuni HOSOKAWA and Harumoto HOSOKAWA fought for the position of Kanrei, Naganao participated in the war together with his elder brother, Yojuro Naganobu as a member of the Harumoto side and, after the victory of Harumoto, he served as a close aide of Harumoto because his brother assumed the position of Yamashiro Gundai (Intendant of a region or administrator of a town) to supervise the territory of Hosokawa family in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Takakuni HOSOKAWA and Harumoto HOSOKAWA fought for the position of Kanrei, Naganao participated in the war together with his elder brother, Yojuro Naganobu as a member of the Harumoto side and, after the victory of Harumoto, he served as a close aide of Harumoto because his brother assumed the position of Yamashiro Gundai (Intendant of a region or administrator of a town) to supervise the territory of Hosokawa family in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>高畠氏はその地域性から公家や寺社勢力とも繋がりを持ち、特に桂川から淀川を経た下流にあたる石山本願寺と密接な関係をもっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From its local situation, the Takabatake clan was connected with court nobles and Buddhism temples and Shinto shrines and, in particular, with Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple located in the downstream of Katsuragawa River and Yodogawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From its local situation, the Takabatake clan was connected with court nobles and Buddhism temples and Shinto shrines and, in particular, with Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple located in the downstream of Katsuragawa River and Yodogawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From its local situation, the Takabatake clan was connected with court nobles and Buddhism temples and Shinto shrines and, in particular, with Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple located in the downstream of Katsura-gawa River and Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Katsura-gawa River、Yodo-gawa Riverとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>特に本願寺門主証如とは親密な関係にあり、証如が庭田重直の娘との間に男子（後の顕如）が生まれた時には、管領・晴元の代理として祝辞を述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, he has a close connection with the chief priest of the Hongan-ji Temple, Shonyo, and, when Shonyo obtained a son (later, Kennyo) by a daughter of Shigenobu NIWATA, he delivered congratulations as an agent of the Kanrei, Harumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, he has a close connection with the chief priest of the Hongan-ji Temple, Shonyo, and, when Shonyo obtained a son (later, Kennyo) by a daughter of Shigenobu NIWATA, he delivered congratulations as an agent of the Kanrei, Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, he has a close connection with the chief priest of the Hongan-ji Temple, Shonyo, and, when Shonyo obtained a son (later, Kennyo) by a daughter of Shigenobu NIWATA, he delivered congratulations as an agent of the Kanrei, Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、三好元長・内藤国貞との戦いにも参戦して戦功を挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he took part in the war between Motonaga MIYOSHI and Kunisada NAITO and made a fine war record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he took part in the war between Motonaga MIYOSHI and Kunisada NAITO and made a fine war record.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he took part in the war between Motonaga MIYOSHI and Kunisada NAITO and made a fine war record.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>木沢長政の死後、同じ頃に死去した兄・長信の後を受けて山城郡代となり、細川氏綱やこれと結ぶ畠山政国らとの戦いに参加する一方、天文15年には晴元に従って後奈良天皇に拝謁している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Nagamasa KIZAWA, he succeeded the position of the Yamashiro Gundai of his elder brother, Naganobu and took part in the war against Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA and Masakuni HATAKEYAMA, who was united with Ujitsuna, on one hand, and had an audience with the Emperor Gonara following Harumoto in 1547, on the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Nagamasa KIZAWA, he succeeded the position of the Yamashiro Gundai of his elder brother, Naganobu and took part in the war against Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA and Masakuni HATAKEYAMA, who was united with Ujitsuna, on one hand, and had an audience with the Emperor Gonara following Harumoto in 1547, on the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Nagamasa KIZAWA, he succeeded the position of the Yamashiro Gundai of his elder brother, Naganobu and took part in the war against Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA and Masakuni HATAKEYAMA, who was united with Ujitsuna, on one hand, and had an audience with the Emperor Gonara following Harumoto in 1547, on the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、晴元の重臣三好長慶の氏綱方への離反をきっかけに状況は一変する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, situation changed drastically triggered by breaking away of Choke MIYOSHI, who was of Harumoto, to the Ujitsuna&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the situation changed drastically, triggered by a breakaway from Choke MIYOSHI, who was of Harumoto, to the Ujitsuna&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the situation changed drastically, triggered by a breakaway from Chokei MIYOSHI, who was of Harumoto, to the Ujitsuna&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>Choke MIYOSHI→Chokei MIYOSHIに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天文18年江口の戦いにおいて、晴元方三好政長の軍に参加した長直は三好長慶の攻撃によって敗死してしまうのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Eguchi in 1549, Naganao, who took part in the troop of Masanaga MIYOSHI in the Harumoto&apos;s side was defeated and killed by the attack of Chokei MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Eguchi in 1549, Naganao, who took part in the troop of Masanaga MIYOSHI in the Harumoto&apos;s side was defeated and killed by the attack of Chokei MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Eguchi in 1549, Naganao, who took part in the troop of Masanaga MIYOSHI in the Harumoto&apos;s side was defeated and killed by the attack of Chokei MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>近年、上杉本洛中洛外図に長直の屋敷が描かれている事が確認されたために、執筆年代との関係で様々な議論を呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, as it was confirmed the Naganao&apos;s compound is portrayed in Uesugibon Rakuchu Rakugai Zu (Scenes in and around the Capital of Kyoto, the Uesugi version), there were various discussion with respect to the time of drawing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, as it was confirmed the Naganao&apos;s compound is portrayed in Uesugibon Rakuchu Rakugai Zu (Scenes in and around the Capital of Kyoto, the Uesugi version), there were various discussions with respect to the time of the drawing.</e>
<cmt>Grammar/flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, as it was confirmed the Naganao&apos;s compound is portrayed in Uesugibon Rakuchu Rakugai Zu (Scenes in and around the Capital of Kyoto, the Uesugi version), there were various discussions with respect to the time of the drawing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BAKU(id:55205), Nevylax(id:38464), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>