<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蘇我蝦夷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SOGA no Emishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SOGA no Emishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SOGA no Emishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蘇我 蝦夷（そが の えみし）は、飛鳥時代に大臣（おおおみ）となり中大兄皇子（後の天智天皇）・藤原鎌足・蘇我倉山田石川麻呂らのいわゆる乙巳の変で自殺した政治家、貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SOGA no Emishi became a minister in the Asuka period, and he was a politician and aristocrat who committed suicide in the so-called Isshi no hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) by Prince Naka no Oe no Oji (later Emperor Tenchi), FUJIWARA no Kamatari, SOGANOKURA-YAMADA no Ishikawamaro, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SOGA no Emishi was an aristocrat and highest officer politician in the Asuka period, who committed suicide in the so-called Isshi no hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) led by Prince Naka no Oe no Oji (later the Emperor Tenchi), FUJIWARA no Kamatari, SOGANOKURA-YAMADA no Ishikawamaro, and others.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SOGA no Emishi was an aristocrat and highest officer politician in the Asuka period, who committed suicide in the so-called Isshi no hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) led by Prince Naka no Oe no Oji (later the Emperor Tenchi), FUJIWARA no Kamatari, SOGANOKURA-YAMADA no Ishikawamaro, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>『日本書紀』では蘇我蝦夷、通称は豊浦大臣（とゆらのおおおみ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), his name was SOGA no Emishi and he was commonly called Minister Toyoura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), his name was SOGA no Emishi and he was commonly called Toyura no oomi.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), his name was SOGA no Emishi and he was commonly called Toyura no oomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『上宮聖徳法王帝説』では「蘇我豊浦毛人」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Jogu Shotoku Hooteisetsu&quot; (Biography of Shotoku Taishi), he was called Soga Toyoura Emishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Jogu Shotoku Hooteisetsu&quot; (Biography of Shotoku Taishi), he was called Soga Toyura no Emishi.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Jogu Shotoku Hooteisetsu&quot; (Biography of Shotoku Taishi), he was called Soga Toyura no Emishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>蝦夷は蝦夷と同じ漢字であるため、これは蔑称であり、毛人が本名との説があるが、「蝦夷」も「毛人」も同じ対象を指すことを考慮していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Emishi had the same Chinese characters as Ezo (Shrimp Barbarian), it was a disparaging name, though there was a theory saying that Emishi was the real name, but it is not considered to indicate that both &quot;Ezo&quot; and &quot;Emishi&quot; are referring to the same object.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Emishi and Ezo (northerners) use the same Chinese characters (蝦夷), some people believe that the name 蝦夷 (Emishi) was a derogatory term and his real name was 毛人 (Emishi), but 蝦夷 and 毛人 do not refer to the same thing.</e>
<cmt>・出典元では「蝦夷も毛人も同じ対象を指す」となっていますが、原文に従いました。・漢字表記なしではこの箇所は説明できないと判断したので、漢字表記を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Emishi and Ezo (northerners) use the same Chinese characters (蝦夷), some people believe that the name 蝦夷 (Emishi) was a derogatory term and his real name was 毛人 (Emishi), but 蝦夷 and 毛人 do not refer to the same thing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「えみし」という名称は小野毛人や佐伯今毛人も使用しておる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &quot;Emishi&quot; was used by ONO no Emishi and SAEKI no Imaemishi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &apos;Emishi&apos; was used by ONO no Emishi and SAEKI no Imaemishi.</e>
<cmt>シングルｺｰテンションに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Emishi&apos; was used by ONO no Emishi and SAEKI no Imaemishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>わざと悪いものを自分の名前につけることで逆に厄払いにしたという説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A theory said, purposely applying bad meanings to one&apos;s name could oppositely drive away evils.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, he dared to adopt a bad name to drive away evil (offset evil).</e>
<cmt>表現の修正 （理解しやすいように括弧で補足しました）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, he dared to adopt a bad name to drive away evil (offset evil).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>当時蝦夷は頑強に大和朝廷に抵抗しており、「強い人間」という印象があるため名前につけたとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also another theory said, Ezo was stubbornly resisting Yamato dynasty at that time that the name was made in order to give an impression of being a &quot;Strong man&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory says that he respected Ezo who were resisting the Yamato dynasty adamantly as strong men and adopted his name after them.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory says that he respected Ezo who were resisting the Yamato dynasty adamantly as strong men and adopted his name after them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また蘇我入鹿と同様に死後中大兄皇子らによってこれまでの名前を資料とともに消され、新たに卑しい名前として勝手に名付けられたという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there was also a theory saying that the name was postmortem like SOGA no Iruka by Princes Naka no Oe no Oji who erased the current name with all the materials and named newly arbitrarily with a lowly name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also possible that Naka no Oe no Oji and others, who erased his real name and his records, gave him a derogatory name instead after his and his son Iruka&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also possible that Naka no Oe no Oji and others, who erased his real name and his records, gave him a derogatory name instead after his and his son Iruka&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>推古天皇末年から皇極天皇の御代にかけて権勢をふるった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end year of Emperor Suiko to the reign of Emperor Kogyoku, he held the reins of power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end year of the Emperor Suiko to the reign of the Emperor Kogyoku, Emishi wielded power.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end year of the Emperor Suiko to the reign of the Emperor Kogyoku, Emishi wielded power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>推古天皇の崩御後、皇位継承者の選定に当たり、推古天皇の遺勅として、田村皇子を舒明天皇として即位させることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Suiko passed away and when selection of the heir to the Imperial Throne was to be carried out, with the order left behind in Emperor Suiko&apos;s will, he succeeded in making Prince Tamura ascend the throne as Emperor Jomei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the selection of the heir to the Imperial Throne following the Emperor Suiko&apos;s demise, he succeeded in enthroning the Prince Tamura as the Emperor Jomei in accordance with the order left behind in the Emperor Suiko&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the selection of the heir to the Imperial Throne following the Emperor Suiko&apos;s demise, he succeeded in enthroning the Prince Tamura as the Emperor Jomei in accordance with the order left behind in the Emperor Suiko&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>有力な皇位継承の候補者としては田村皇子と山背大兄王がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Tamura and Prince Yamashiro no Oe were powerful candidates for Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Prince Tamura and the Prince Yamashiro no oe were the main candidates for the succession to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正。定訳を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Prince Tamura and the Prince Yamashiro no oe were the main candidates for the succession to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>（大兄は皇太子の意味となれるが山背大兄王が皇太子となったという記述は日本書紀にはなく、単なる皇子とする者もいる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Oe meant a person who could become a Crown Prince, but the description that Prince Yamashiro no Oe became a Crown Prince was not found in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; [Chronicles of Japan], so there were Oe who simply became a prince)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Oe can mean a crown prince, but because there is no description that the Prince Yamashiro no oe became a crown prince in Nihonshoki [Chronicles of Japan], some people believe that he was simply a prince)</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Oe can mean a crown prince, but because there is no description that the Prince Yamashiro no oe became a crown prince in Nihonshoki [Chronicles of Japan], some people believe that he was simply a prince)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>が、山背大兄王を推薦した叔父の境部摩理勢を殺害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he murdered his uncle SAKAIBE no Marise who recommended Prince Yamashiro no Oe.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Emishi murdered his uncle SAKAIBE no Marise who recommended Prince Yamashiro no Oe as the Emperor Suiko&apos;s successor</e>
<cmt>意味をより明確にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Emishi murdered his uncle SAKAIBE no Marise who recommended Prince Yamashiro no Oe as the Emperor Suiko&apos;s successor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>『日本書紀』によればこれを蝦夷の専横の一つに数える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), this could be counted as one of the domineering tyrannies of Emishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; counted this incident as one of Emishi&apos;s tyrannies.</e>
<cmt>・表現の修正・日本書記の説明は上で行ったので、ここでは省きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; counted this incident as one of Emishi&apos;s tyrannies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>が、一方で父・馬子の死後、蘇我氏に対する内外の風当たりが強くなる中で、皇族や諸豪族との融和を重視して、蘇我氏との血縁関係のない舒明天皇を即位させたという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on the other hand, there was also a theory saying that, after his father Umako died, while the criticisms to the Soga clan were severe from both inside and outside, he valued the harmony of the imperial family and various powerful clans that he made Emperor Jomei, who did not have blood relationship with the Soga clan, ascend the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on the other hand, one theory says that Emishi, while there was growing criticism of the Soga clan from both inside and outside after his father Umako&apos;s death, enthroned the Emperor Jomei who did not have blood relationship with the Soga clan to value the harmony between the imperial family and various powerful families.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on the other hand, one theory says that Emishi, while there was growing criticism of the Soga clan from both inside and outside after his father Umako&apos;s death, enthroned the Emperor Jomei who did not have blood relationship with the Soga clan to value the harmony between the imperial family and various powerful families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>舒明天皇の崩御後は、皇極天皇を擁立したが、山背大兄王の私民を使役して自らの墓所を作らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Jomei passed away, he supported Emperor Kogyoku to the throne but he employed the private retainers of Prince Yamashiro no Oe to make his own grave yard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Emishi set the Emperor Kyogoku on the throne after the Emperor Jomei&apos;s demise, he employed the Prince Yamashiro no oe&apos;s private retainers to make his own graveyard.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Emishi set the Emperor Kyogoku on the throne after the Emperor Jomei&apos;s demise, he employed the Prince Yamashiro no oe&apos;s private retainers to make his own graveyard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また入鹿に紫冠を授け大臣と擬し、弟を物部大臣と呼び、屋敷を宮上の門（みかど）とよばせるなど自らを大王に擬する行為があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, he made himself feel like a great king with such acts as making Iruka the minister for giving purple cap, calling his younger brother a Monobe minister (low-class staff of the Court whose job was mainly to execute sentences), making his residence be called Gate on Imperial Palace, etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, he behaved like okimi (great king) by giving Iruka the purple cap for oomi (a highest officer in national politics of the Yamato dynasty), calling his younger brother Mononobe no oomi, and naming his residence kyujo no mikada (Gate on Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>・「物部大臣」に関しては、仇敵の物部氏の名前を弟に授けたとのことです。・「宮上の門」は読み方が不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he behaved like okimi (great king) by giving Iruka the purple cap for oomi (a highest officer in national politics of the Yamato dynasty), calling his younger brother Mononobe no oomi, and naming his residence kyujo no mikada (Gate on Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>（冠位十二階最高位大徳の色であるが、代々大臣を務めた蘇我氏当主の冠とする説もある）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(though purple was a color of highest rank Daitoku among the &quot;Twelve grades of cap rank&quot;, there was also legend saying that all the headmaster of the Soga clan who served as the minister from generation to generation had this cap color)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, the purple cap indicated the first grade of &quot;Twelve grades of cap rank&quot;, which cap belonged to heads of the Soga clan who had served as oomi for generations.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, the purple cap indicated the first grade of &quot;Twelve grades of cap rank&quot;, which cap belonged to heads of the Soga clan who had served as oomi for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>蝦夷の子の蘇我入鹿は山背大兄王を襲い、上宮王家一家を自殺に追いこんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emishi&apos;s child SOGA no Iruka attacked Prince Yamashiro no Oe, and drove the whole family of Jogu Oke to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SOGA no Iruka, Emishi&apos;s son, attacked the Prince Yamashiro no Oe, and drove the whole family of Jogu Oke to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SOGA no Iruka, Emishi&apos;s son, attacked the Prince Yamashiro no Oe, and drove the whole family of Jogu Oke to commit suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>日本書紀には、蝦夷が入鹿のこの行為を怒り嘆いたと伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), it was said that Emishi scolded Iruka and grieved for his such act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Nihonshoki, Emishi got angry at and grieved over his such act.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Nihonshoki, Emishi got angry at and grieved over his such act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>皇極天皇4年（645年）に天皇の御前で入鹿が殺されると、一時は蝦夷のもとに与する者が集まったが、翌日、入鹿の屍を前に蝦夷は邸宅に火をかけ「天皇記」・「国記」もろとも自殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In AD 645, when Iruka was killed in emperor&apos;s presence, supporters gathered in temporarily at Emishi&apos;s place, but the next day, Emishi put fire on the corpse of Iruka in front of him in the residence, and committed suicide with &quot;Emperor record&quot; and &quot;National record&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 645, when Iruka was killed in the emperor&apos;s presence, the Soga supporters gathers at Emishi&apos;s place, but the next day, he committed suicide by setting fire to his residence in the face of Iruka&apos;s corpse and Tennoki (a Record of the Emperors) and Kokki (National Record) were destroyed as well.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 645, when Iruka was killed in the emperor&apos;s presence, the Soga supporters gathers at Emishi&apos;s place, but the next day, he committed suicide by setting fire to his residence in the face of Iruka&apos;s corpse and Tennoki (a Record of the Emperors) and Kokki (National Record) were destroyed as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 デーモン博士(id:99293), Izayohi(id:13095), Sunearth(id:189194), Aotake(id:34929), Reggaeman(id:6214), Cprobot(id:97843), MIO(id:31681), らんで(id:58934), ごまふあざ(id:36855), Jimmy1970(id:143461), Frozen-mikan(id:6130), Michey.M(id:906), Pitan(id:171), 代言人(id:33675), Nevylax(id:38464), R28Bot(id:177951), UMBRO(id:100484), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Klesha(id:203751), FlaBot(id:30804), Tatsujin28(id:9300), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>