<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今川義忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>今川 義忠（いまがわ よしただ）は室町時代・戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada IMAGAWA was busho (Japanese military commander) in the Muromachi Period and the Sengoku Period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada IMAGAWA was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Muromachi period and the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>busho→a bushoに修正、Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada IMAGAWA was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Muromachi period and the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>守護大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords).</e>
<cmt>shugo daimyo→a shugo daimyoに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original surname was Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original surname was the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>Genji→the Minamoto clanに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original surname was the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家系は源義国を祖とする足利氏の一門　吉良氏の分家にあたる今川氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Imagawa clan which was a branch family of the Kira clan, a family of the Ashikaga clan which was originated by MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Imagawa clan which was a branch family of the Kira clan, a family of the Ashikaga clan which was originated by MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Imagawa clan which was a branch family of the Kira clan, a family of the Ashikaga clan which was originated by MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>源義国は、清和源氏の一家系　河内源氏の棟梁　鎮守府将軍源義家の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni was the son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie who was Chinju-fu shogun (commander-in-chief of the defence of the north) and the head of the Kawachi-Genji, a family line of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan originated from Emperor Seiwa).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni was the son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie who was Chinju-fu shogun (commander-in-chief of the defence of the north) and the head of the Kawachi-Genji, a family line of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan originated from Emperor Seiwa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni was the son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie who was Chinju-fu shogun (commander-in-chief of the defence of the north) and the head of the Kawachi-Genji, a family line of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan originated from Emperor Seiwa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>義忠は駿河国今川氏6代当主である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada was the sixth family head of the Imagawa clan based in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada was the sixth family head of the Imagawa clan based in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada was the sixth family head of the Imagawa clan based in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>嘉吉3年（1441年）、嘉吉の乱に際して父範忠の名代として1,000騎を率いて尾張国まで出陣している（『今川記』では今川範政とされているが、小和田哲男静岡大学教授によると範政は永享5年（1433年）に没しており、名代は義忠と思われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1441, he went to Owari Province leading 1,000 horse soldiers, to fight in the Kakitsu War as a representative for his father, Noritada (it is written in &quot;Imagawa-ki&quot;, that Norimasa IMAGAWA went to the Kakitsu War, but Tetsuo OWADA, professor at Shizuoka University, maintains that Norimasa died in 1433 and Yoshitada was the one who fought in the war).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1441, he went to Owari Province leading 1,000 horse soldiers, to fight in the Kakitsu War as a representative for his father, Noritada (it is written in the &quot;Imagawa-ki,&quot; that Norimasa IMAGAWA went to the Kakitsu War, but Tetsuo OWADA, a professor at Shizuoka University, maintains that Norimasa died in 1433 and Yoshitada was the one who fought in the war).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を移動、in the &quot;Imagawa-ki&quot;とし、professor→a professorに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1441, he went to Owari Province leading 1,000 horse soldiers, to fight in the Kakitsu War as a representative for his father, Noritada (it is written in the &quot;Imagawa-ki,&quot; that Norimasa IMAGAWA went to the Kakitsu War, but Tetsuo OWADA, a professor at Shizuoka University, maintains that Norimasa died in 1433 and Yoshitada was the one who fought in the war).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>康正2年（1454年）、享徳の乱で室町幕府より今川氏へ関東公方足利成氏討伐が命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kyotoku War, the Muromachi bakufu told the Imagawa clan to suppress Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, Kanto kubo, in 1454.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kyotoku War, the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) told the Imagawa clan to suppress Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, Kanto kubo, in 1454.</e>
<cmt>bakufuの補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kyotoku War, the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) told the Imagawa clan to suppress Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, Kanto kubo, in 1454.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>父範忠の名代として出陣して鎌倉市を攻略して征夷大将軍より感状を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada, again as a representative for his father Noritada, went to war, and attacked Kamakura City successfully enough to receive the letter of commendation from seiitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great unifying leader).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada, again as a representative for his father Noritada, went to war, and attacked Kamakura City successfully enough to receive the letter of commendation from the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「征夷大将軍」→統一リストの表記に修正、theを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada, again as a representative for his father Noritada, went to war, and attacked Kamakura City successfully enough to receive the letter of commendation from the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>寛正2年（1461年）に父範忠の危篤を受けて駿河守護職を継承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1461, he took over the post of Suruga no kami (governor of Suruga Province), when his father Noritada became dangerously ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1461, he took over the post of shugo (provincial constable) of Suruga Province, when his father Noritada became dangerously ill.</e>
<cmt>Suruga no kami (governor of Suruga Province)→Shugo (provincial constable) of Suruga Provinceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1461, he took over the post of shugo (provincial constable) of Suruga Province, when his father Noritada became dangerously ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>家督を継承した義忠は将軍足利義政より堀越公方足利政知への援助を申し受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he inherited the family estate, he started to support Masatomo ASHIKAGA, Horigoe kubo, on the request of Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he inherited the family estate, he started to support Masatomo ASHIKAGA, Horigoe kubo, on the request of Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he inherited the family estate, he started to support Masatomo ASHIKAGA, Horigoe kubo, on the request of Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、寛正6年（1466年）には甲斐国の武田信昌とともに古河公方足利成氏の討伐を命じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada, along with Nobumasa TAKEDA in Kai Province, was told to suppress Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, Koga kubo, in 1466.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada, along with Nobumasa TAKEDA in Kai Province, was told to suppress Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, Koga kubo, in 1466.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada, along with Nobumasa TAKEDA in Kai Province, was told to suppress Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, Koga kubo, in 1466.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>今川氏は本拠の駿河国以外に遠江国の守護を保持していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imagawa clan was appointed as shugo not only at home in Suruga Province but also in Totoumi Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imagawa clan was appointed as shugo not only at home in Suruga Province but also in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imagawa clan was appointed as shugo not only at home in Suruga Province but also in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>だが、応永26年（1419年）以降は遠江国は斯波氏の分国となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 1419, however, Totoumi Province became under control of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After 1419, however, Totomi Province became under control of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 1419, however, Totomi Province became under control of the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、遠江国にあった今川了俊系の分家の所領が今川範将が反乱を起こして討たれた後に、斯波氏の被官の国人に奪われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On top of that, the territory in Totoumi Province which belonged to a branch family of Ryoshun IMAGAWA, was taken by local samurai who was a vassal for the Shiba clan, when Norimasa IMAGAWA was killed for the charge of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On top of that, the territory in Totomi Province which belonged to a branch family of Ryoshun IMAGAWA, was taken by local samurai who was a vassal for the Shiba clan, when Norimasa IMAGAWA was killed for the charge of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On top of that, the territory in Totomi Province which belonged to a branch family of Ryoshun IMAGAWA, was taken by local samurai who was a vassal for the Shiba clan, when Norimasa IMAGAWA was killed for the charge of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして今川氏と斯波氏との対立が深まっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus the confrontation between the Imagawa clan and the Shiba clan became more obvious.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus the confrontation between the Imagawa clan and the Shiba clan became more obvious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus the confrontation between the Imagawa clan and the Shiba clan became more obvious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>応仁元年（1467年）に応仁の乱が起こると、堀越公方足利政知と相談の上で1,000騎を率いて上洛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Onin War happened in 1467, Yoshitada went to Kyoto along with 1,000 horse soldiers, after he consulted Masatomo ASHIKAGA, Horigoe kubo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Onin War happened in 1467, Yoshitada went to Kyoto along with 1,000 horse soldiers, after he consulted Masatomo ASHIKAGA, Horigoe kubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Onin War happened in 1467, Yoshitada went to Kyoto along with 1,000 horse soldiers, after he consulted Masatomo ASHIKAGA, Horigoe kubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>山名宗全は義忠を西軍を引き入れようとするが、将軍警固のために上洛したことを理由に花の御所（東軍が占拠している）へ入り、そのまま東軍へ属した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sozen YAMANA tried to bring Yoshitada into the western camp, but Yoshitada, saying that he intended to guard the Shogun, went to Hana no gosho (residence of Shogun in Kyoto) which was seized by the eastern camp, to be a member of the eastern camp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sozen YAMANA tried to bring Yoshitada into the western camp, but Yoshitada, saying that he intended to guard the Shogun, went to Hana no gosho (residence of Shogun in Kyoto) which was seized by the eastern camp, to be a member of the eastern camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sozen YAMANA tried to bring Yoshitada into the western camp, but Yoshitada, saying that he intended to guard the Shogun, went to Hana no gosho (residence of Shogun in Kyoto) which was seized by the eastern camp, to be a member of the eastern camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>かねてから対立している遠江守護の斯波義廉が西軍であったために東軍に属したようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seemed as if he sided with the eastern camp because his opponent Yoshikado SHIBA, Totoumi no kami (governor of Totoumi Province), sided with the western camp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seemed as if he sided with the eastern camp because his opponent Yoshikado SHIBA, shugo of Totomi Province, sided with the western camp.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi no kami (governor of Totoumi Province)→shugo of Totomi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed as if he sided with the eastern camp because his opponent Yoshikado SHIBA, shugo of Totomi Province, sided with the western camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>この上洛中に伊勢新九郎（北条早雲）の姉（または妹）の北川殿と結婚したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that he got married with Kitagawa-dono the sister of Shinkuro ISE (Soun HOJO) during his stay in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that he got married with Kitagawa-dono, the sister of Shinkuro ISE (Soun HOJO) during his stay in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that he got married with Kitagawa-dono, the sister of Shinkuro ISE (Soun HOJO) during his stay in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>新九郎は長年、素浪人とするのが通説で、その姉妹の北川殿は側室とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a long-held belief, Shinkuro was suronin (master-less samurai) and his sister Kitagawa-dono was considered to be a concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a long-held belief, Shinkuro was a suronin (master-less samurai) and his sister Kitagawa-dono was considered to be a concubine.</e>
<cmt>suronin→a suroninとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a long-held belief, Shinkuro was a suronin (master-less samurai) and his sister Kitagawa-dono was considered to be a concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、近年の研究で新九郎は幕府政所執事の名門伊勢氏の一族で備中伊勢氏の幕臣伊勢盛時であることがほぼ明らかになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the latest research shows that Shinkuro was likely to be Moritoki ISE, Shogun&apos;s vassal from the Ise clan (a family of pedigree serving as stewards of bakufu mandokoro) in Bicchu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the latest research shows that Shinkuro was likely to be Moritoki ISE, Shogun&apos;s vassal from the Ise clan (a family of pedigree serving as stewards of the bakufu mandokoro [the administrative board]) in Bitchu.</e>
<cmt>the bakufu mandokoroとし、mandokoroの補足追加 (用語集参照)、Bicchu→Bitchuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the latest research shows that Shinkuro was likely to be Moritoki ISE, Shogun&apos;s vassal from the Ise clan (a family of pedigree serving as stewards of the bakufu mandokoro [the administrative board]) in Bitchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>上洛中に義忠は政所執事伊勢貞親をしばしば訪ねており、盛時の父伊勢盛定が今川家との申次衆を務めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada frequently visited Sadachika ISE, mandokoro shitsuji (chief of mandokoro [the adiministrative board]) during his stay in Kyoto, and Morisada ISE, Moritoki&apos;s father, was working as a messenger for the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada frequently visited Sadachika ISE, mandokoro shitsuji (chief of mandokoro) during his stay in Kyoto, and Morisada ISE, Moritoki&apos;s father, was working as a messenger for the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>mandokoro→既出のため補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada frequently visited Sadachika ISE, mandokoro shitsuji (chief of mandokoro) during his stay in Kyoto, and Morisada ISE, Moritoki&apos;s father, was working as a messenger for the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その縁で北川殿が義忠に嫁いだと考えられ、正室とするのが妥当である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led to the marriage between Yoshitada and Kitagawa-dono, so it is more reasonable to consider her as Yoshitada&apos;s lawful wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led to the marriage between Yoshitada and Kitagawa-dono, so it is more reasonable to consider that she was Yoshitada&apos;s lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>to consider her as→to consider that she wasとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to the marriage between Yoshitada and Kitagawa-dono, so it is more reasonable to consider that she was Yoshitada&apos;s lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>北川殿との間には文明5年（1473年）に嫡子龍王丸（氏親）が生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1473, their legitimate child, Tatsu-o-maru (Ujichika) was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1473, their legitimate child, Tatsuomaru (Ujichika) was born.</e>
<cmt>Tatsu-o-maru→Tatsuomaruとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1473, their legitimate child, Tatsuomaru (Ujichika) was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>応仁2年（1468年）細川勝元の要請で東海道の斯波義廉の分国を撹乱すべく駿河国へ帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada, on the request of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, went back to Suruga Province to disturb the province occupied by Yoshikado SHIBA of Tokaido, in 1468.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada, on the request of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, went back to Suruga Province to disturb the province occupied by Yoshikado SHIBA of Tokaido, in 1468.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada, on the request of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, went back to Suruga Province to disturb the province occupied by Yoshikado SHIBA of Tokaido, in 1468.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>帰国した義忠は積極的に遠江国への進出を図り、斯波氏や在地の国人と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he actively tried to make a foray into Totoumi Province, fighting the Shiba clan or other local lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he actively tried to make a foray into Totomi Province, fighting the Shiba clan or other local lords.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he actively tried to make a foray into Totomi Province, fighting the Shiba clan or other local lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>文明5年（1473年）、東軍の三河国守護細川成之が美濃国守護代斎藤妙椿から攻撃を受けたため、将軍の命により三河国へ出陣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A member of the eastern camp, Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA, Mikawa no kuni no kami (governor of Mikawa Province) and shugo, was attacked by Myochin SAITO, shugodai (deputy military governor) of Mino Province, in 1473, and Yoshitada was ordered by the Shogun to go to war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A member of the eastern camp, Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA, shugo of Mikawa Province, was attacked by Myochin SAITO, shugodai (deputy military governor) of Mino Province, in 1473, and Yoshitada was ordered by the Shogun to go to Mikawa Province to join battle.</e>
<cmt>Mikawa no kuni no kami (governor of Mikawa Province) and shugo→shugo of Mikawa Provinceとし、「三河国へ」→訳漏れのため訳出、一部訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A member of the eastern camp, Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA, shugo of Mikawa Province, was attacked by Myochin SAITO, shugodai (deputy military governor) of Mino Province, in 1473, and Yoshitada was ordered by the Shogun to go to Mikawa Province to join battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そのために将軍から兵糧用として預けられた所領を巡って同じ東軍の尾張国守護斯波義良（西軍の斯波義廉と対立）及び三河国吉良義真の被官となっていた遠江国の国人巨海氏、狩野氏と対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shogun consigned the territory for army provisions, but this caused a conflict between Yoshitada and other members of the eastern camp, such as Yoshisuke (Yoshinaga) SHIBA, Owari no kuni no kami (governor of Owari Province) (opposed to Yoshikado SHIBA of the western camp) and the Kyokai clan and the Kano clan who were local lords of Totoumi Province and vassals of Yoshizane KIRA from Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>「巨海」の読み方不明。一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shogun consigned the territory for army provisions, but this caused a conflict between Yoshitada and other members of the eastern camp, such as Yoshisuke (Yoshinaga) SHIBA, shugo of Owari Province (opposed to Yoshikado SHIBA of the western camp) and the Komi clan and the Kano clan who were local lords of Totomi Province and vassals of Yoshizane KIRA from Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>Owari no kuni no kami (governor of Owari Province)→shugo of Owari Province、Totoumi→Totomi、the Kyokai clan→the Komi clanに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shogun consigned the territory for army provisions, but this caused a conflict between Yoshitada and other members of the eastern camp, such as Yoshisuke (Yoshinaga) SHIBA, shugo of Owari Province (opposed to Yoshikado SHIBA of the western camp) and the Komi clan and the Kano clan who were local lords of Totomi Province and vassals of Yoshizane KIRA from Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>そして、これらを滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada fought and destroyed them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada fought and destroyed them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada fought and destroyed them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そのため、同じの東軍の斯波義良、細川成之と敵対することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently he had to oppose Yoshisuke (Yoshinaga) SHIBA and Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA, who were both members of the eastern camp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently he had to oppose Yoshisuke (Yoshinaga) SHIBA and Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA, who were both members of the eastern camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently he had to oppose Yoshisuke (Yoshinaga) SHIBA and Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA, who were both members of the eastern camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>文明7年（1475年）東軍は西軍の斯波義廉の重臣甲斐敏光を寝返らせ遠江国の守護代とし、義忠と敵対。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against Yoshitada, the eastern camp made Toshimitsu KAI, the senior vassal of Yoshikado SHIBA (western camp), switch sides and appointed Toshimitsu as shugodai of Totoumi Province in 1475.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Against Yoshitada, the eastern camp made Toshimitsu KAI, the senior vassal of Yoshikado SHIBA (western camp), switch sides and appointed Toshimitsu as shugodai of Totomi Province in 1475.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Against Yoshitada, the eastern camp made Toshimitsu KAI, the senior vassal of Yoshikado SHIBA (western camp), switch sides and appointed Toshimitsu as shugodai of Totomi Province in 1475.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>遠江国の政情は混沌とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Totoumi Province turned politically unstable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Totomi Province turned politically unstable.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Totomi Province turned politically unstable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>義忠は遠江国へ出陣して斯波義良方の国人と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada went to Totoumi Province to fight against the local lords working for Yoshisuke (Yoshinaga) SHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada went to Totomi Province to fight against the local lords working for Yoshisuke (Yoshinaga) SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada went to Totomi Province to fight against the local lords working for Yoshisuke (Yoshinaga) SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>文明8年（1476年）、遠江国の国人、横地秀国と勝間田修理亮が義忠に背き斯波氏に内通して見付城を修復して抵抗の構えを見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1476, the local lords of Totoumi Province, Hidekuni YOKOCHI and 勝間田修理亮 colluded with the Shiba clan and renovated Mitsuke-jo Castle to fight against Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>「横地秀国」「勝間田修理亮」「見付城」の読み方不明。一原文一訳分の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1476, the local lords of Totomi Province, Hidekuni YOKOCHI and Katsumata Shuri no suke (勝間田修理亮) colluded with the Shiba clan and renovated Mitsuke-jo Castle to fight against Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomi、勝間田修理亮→Katsumata Shuri no suke (勝間田修理亮)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1476, the local lords of Totomi Province, Hidekuni YOKOCHI and Katsumata Shuri no suke (勝間田修理亮) colluded with the Shiba clan and renovated Mitsuke-jo Castle to fight against Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>このため、500騎を率いて出陣して横地城と勝間田城の城を囲んで、両人を討った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada led 500 horse soldiers to besiege Yokochi-jo Castle as well as Katsumada-jo Castle, and killed both.</e>
<cmt>「横地城」「勝間田城」の読み方不明。一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada led 500 horse soldiers to besiege Yokochi-jo Castle as well as Katsumata-jo Castle, and killed both.</e>
<cmt>Katsumada-jo→Katsumata-joに修正しました。(参考: http://www5f.biglobe.ne.jp/shingen/joukansizuoka/katumata/katumata.html)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada led 500 horse soldiers to besiege Yokochi-jo Castle as well as Katsumata-jo Castle, and killed both.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その帰途の夜、遠江国小笠郡塩買坂（現在の静岡県菊川市）で横地氏と勝間田氏の残党による一揆に不意を襲われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way back, he was caught in the uprising by the Yokochi and Katsumada clan remnants at 塩買坂, Ogasa County, Totoumi Province (present-day Kikugawa City, Shizuoka Prefecture) at night.</e>
<cmt>「塩買坂」「横地」「勝間田」の読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the way back, he was caught in the uprising by the Yokochi and Katsumata clan remnants at Shiokaizaka, Ogasa County, Totomi Province (present-day Kikugawa City, Shizuoka Prefecture) at night.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomi、the Katsumada clan→the Katsumata clanに修正、塩買坂→Shikaizakaとしました。(参考: http://hata0913.hp.infoseek.co.jp/matunaga-1.htm)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way back, he was caught in the uprising by the Yokochi and Katsumata clan remnants at Shiokaizaka, Ogasa County, Totomi Province (present-day Kikugawa City, Shizuoka Prefecture) at night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>義忠は馬に乗って指揮をとるが、流れ矢に当たって討ち死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada spearheaded on the horse, but was killed by a stray arrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada spearheaded on the horse, but was killed by a stray arrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada spearheaded on the horse, but was killed by a stray arrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="40">
<j>義忠の不慮の死により、僅か6歳の龍王丸が残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His untimely death left Tatsu-o-maru who was only six years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His untimely death left Tatsuomaru who was only six years old.</e>
<cmt>Tatsu-o-maru→Tatsuomaruとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His untimely death left Tatsuomaru who was only six years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この後、今川氏は一族の小鹿範満が家督継承を主張して内紛状態になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norimitsu Oshika from the Imagawa family demanded to take over the family estate of the Imagawa clan, and the internal conflict arose.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norimitsu OSHIKA from the Imagawa family demanded to take over the family estate of the Imagawa clan, and the internal conflict arose.</e>
<cmt>Norimitsu Oshika→Norimitsu OSHIKAに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norimitsu OSHIKA from the Imagawa family demanded to take over the family estate of the Imagawa clan, and the internal conflict arose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>それを調停するために北川殿の兄弟であり幕府申次衆の伊勢盛時が駿河国へ下向している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitagawa-dono&apos;s brother Moritoki ISE, a messenger of the bakufu, went to Suruga Province as a mediator.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitagawa-dono&apos;s brother Moritoki ISE, a messenger of the bakufu, went to Suruga Province as a mediator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitagawa-dono&apos;s brother Moritoki ISE, a messenger of the bakufu, went to Suruga Province as a mediator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>このことが、盛時と今川氏との絆を強め、後の盛時の関東地方進出と後北条氏誕生の契機になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the relationship between Moritoki and the Imagawa clan became closer, which later triggered Moritoki&apos;s foray on Kanto region and the birth of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the relationship between Moritoki and the Imagawa clan became closer, which later triggered Moritoki&apos;s foray into the Kanto region and the birth of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>foray on Kanto region→foray into the Kanto regionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the relationship between Moritoki and the Imagawa clan became closer, which later triggered Moritoki&apos;s foray into the Kanto region and the birth of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Aotake(id:34929), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Extrahitz(id:26245), Yanahan(id:2437), 味っ子(id:17086), Kagetudo(id:163875), でここ(id:9565), Rusk(id:9895), Carkuni(id:79281), 海衛士(id:19229), UMBRO(id:100484), Loveless(id:129239), Suisui(id:69), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>