<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>たまがき</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamagaki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamagaki</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamagaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>たまがき/たまかき（生没年不詳）は、京都教王護国寺領の新見庄（岡山県新見市）の荘官、惣追捕使の福本盛吉の妹とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamagaki (Tamakaki) (Birth and death dates unknown) was the younger sister of Moriyoshi FUKUMOTO, who had the title of shokan (an officer governing shoen (manor)) of the estate of Niiminosho (Niimi City, Okayama Prefecture) of Kyoto Kyoogokoku-ji Temple and Sotsuibushi (government post in charge of police and military roles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamagaki (Tamakaki) (Birth and death dates unknown) was the younger sister of Moriyoshi FUKUMOTO, who had the title of shokan (an officer governing shoen (manor)) of the estate of Niiminosho (Niimi City, Okayama Prefecture) of the Kyoto Kyoogokoku-ji Temple and Sotsuibushi (government post in charge of police and military roles).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamagaki (also known as Tamakaki, year of birth and death unknown) was the younger sister of Moriyoshi FUKUMOTO, who had the title of shokan (an officer governing shoen (manor)) of the estate of Niiminosho (Niimi City, Okayama Prefecture) of the Kyoto Kyoogokoku-ji Temple and Sotsuibushi (government post in charge of police and military roles).</e>
<cmt>(also known as Tamakaki, としました。生没年不詳 year of birth and death unknown 用語統一リストより訂正しました。全角の括弧を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>たまがきに関する直接的な史料は「東寺百合文書」（京都府立総合資料館蔵）の中の「たまかき書状」と「祐清注進状」などに限られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The historical document that dealt directly about Tamagaki was limited to &apos;Tamakaki Letter&apos; and &apos;Yusei Chushin jo&apos; (a letter reporting about annual estate income from Yusei) within &apos;Toji Hyakugomonjo Document&apos; (stored in Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The historical documents that dealt directly with Tamagaki were limited to &apos;Tamakaki Letter&apos; and &apos;Yusei Chushin jo&apos; (a letter reporting about annual estate income from Yusei) within &apos;Toji Hyakugomonjo Document&apos; (stored in Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The historical documents that dealt directly with Tamagaki were limited to &apos;Tamakaki Letter&apos; and &apos;Yusei Chushin jo&apos; (a letter reporting about annual estate income from Yusei) within &apos;Toji Hyakugomonjo Document&apos; (stored in Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives).</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>文献などによると、たまがきは、寛正3年（1462年）、東寺から直務代官として、新見に着任した東寺の僧・祐清の身辺の世話をしていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to references, Tamagaki took care of Yusei, who was the monk of To-ji Temple that was assigned to Niimi, as the direct governor from To-ji Temple in 1462.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to references, Tamagaki took care of Yusei, who was the monk of To-ji Temple that was assigned to Niimi, as the direct governor from To-ji Temple in 1462.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to references, Tamagaki took care of Yusei, who was the monk of To-ji Temple that was assigned to Niimi, as the direct governor from To-ji Temple in 1462.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>祐清は、寛正4年（1463年）7月、年貢未納の名主・豊岡を追放したことを機に、隣接する相国寺領に住む豊岡の親族によって斬殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yusei was beheaded by the relatives of Toyooka that lived in the estate of Sokokuji, as a result of exiling Toyooka, who was responsible for evading tax in August 1463.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yusei was beheaded by the relatives of Toyooka that lived in the estate of Sokokuji, as a result of exiling Toyooka, who was responsible for evading taxes in August 1463.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yusei was beheaded by the relatives of Toyooka that lived in the estate of Sokokuji, as a result of exiling Toyooka, who was responsible for evading taxes in August 1463.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="5">
<j>東寺に向けて祐清の遺品を求めた手紙が「たまかき書状」で、中世農村女性の自筆書状として全国的に珍しい史料といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The letter she wrote asking for the remaining goods of Yusei was &apos;Tamakaki Letter,&apos; and is one of the rare historical manuscript written by a peasant woman during the medieval period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The letter she wrote asking for the remaining goods of Yusei was &apos;Tamakaki Letter,&apos; and is one of the rare historical manuscripts written by a peasant woman during the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The letter she wrote asking for the remaining goods of Yusei was &apos;Tamakaki Letter,&apos; and is one of the rare historical manuscripts written by a peasant woman during the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="6">
<j>新見市西方の福本刑部丞邸跡にたまがきの碑がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a monument for Tamagaki at the site of the residence of Fukumoto gyobu no jo in the western side of Niimi City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a monument for Tamagaki at the site of the residence of Fukumoto gyobu no jo in the western side of Niimi City.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a monument for Tamagaki at the site of the residence of Fukumoto gyobu no jo in the western side of Niimi City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>