<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>嵯峨源氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saga Genji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saga Genji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saga-Genji</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>嵯峨源氏（さがげんじ）は、賜姓源氏の最初で、第52代嵯峨天皇の子孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saga Genji was the first of Shisei Genji, and descendant of Emperor Saga, the 52nd emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saga Genji were the descendants of Emperor Saga, the 52nd emperor, and the first to be given the Genji name.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;&quot;was&quot;→&quot;were&quot;&quot;the first of Shisei Genji&quot;→&quot;the first to be given the Genji name&quot;Changed word orderMade &quot;descendant&quot; plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saga-Genji were the descendants of Emperor Saga, the fufty second emperor, and the first to be given the Genji name.</e>
<cmt>-補足52nd→fifty second</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>嵯峨天皇は多くの皇子皇女に源氏姓を賜り臣籍降下させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Saga gave the surname of Genji to many princes and princesses, thereby demoting them to his liege subjects (shinsekikoka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Saga gave the surname of Genji to many princes and princesses, whereupon they ceased to be members of the imperial family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;thereby demoting them to his liege subjects (shinsekikoka)&quot;→&quot;whereupon they ceased to be members of the imperial family&quot; - &quot;demoting&quot; sounds like they were being punished</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Saga gave the surname of Genji to many princes and princesses, whereupon they ceased to be members of the imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>源融（『源氏物語』の光源氏の実在モデル）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Toru (real-life model of Hikaru GENJI in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Toru (real-life model of Hikaru GENJI in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Toru (real-life model of Hikaru GENJI in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>源氏初代となる源信_(公卿)（みなもとの・まこと）、源常（-ときわ）、源弘（-ひろむ）、源融（-とおる）などで、朝廷の一大勢力をなした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first generation Genji including MINAMOTO no Makoto (court noble), MINAMOTO no Tokiwa, MINAMOTO no Hiromu and MINAMOTO no Toru formed a powerful force in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first generation Genji, including MINAMOTO no Makoto (a court noble), MINAMOTO no Tokiwa, MINAMOTO no Hiromu and MINAMOTO no Toru, formed an influential group at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a powerful force in&quot;→&quot;an influential group at&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first generation Genji, including MINAMOTO no Makoto (a court noble), MINAMOTO no Tokiwa, MINAMOTO no Hiromu and MINAMOTO no Toru, formed an influential group at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>中でも左大臣に上った源融の子孫は嵯峨源氏融流として最も有名で、また源融は、紫式部『源氏物語』の主人公光源氏の実在モデルの一人とされる人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, the descendants of MINAMOTO no Toru, who was promoted to Minister of the Left, became the most well-known as Saga Genji Toru lineage, and MINAMOTO no Toru is considered to be one of the real-life models of Hikaru GENJI, the main character in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Known as the Toru Lineage of Saga Genji, the descendants of MINAMOTO no Toru, who was promoted to Minister of the Left, were the most famous members of the clan, and MINAMOTO no Toru himself is considered to be one of the models for Hikaru GENJI, the main character in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;Among them,&quot; Changed word order and reworded first part of sentenceDeleted &quot;real-life&quot;Added &quot;himself&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;for&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Known as the Toru Lineage of Saga-Genji, the descendants of MINAMOTO no Toru, who was promoted to Minister of the Left, were the most famous members of the clan, and MINAMOTO no Toru himself is considered to be one of the models for Hikaru GENJI, the main character in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; by Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>朝廷において一大勢力を形成した嵯峨源氏も、3代目以降で上級貴族であり続けた例はほとんどなく、中下級の貴族として細々と生きるか、受領として地方に赴任し、その地に土着して武士となり新境地を開くしかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite the fact that Saga Genji formed a powerful force in the Imperial Court, after 3 generations, there were hardly any examples of their continued existence as high-ranking aristocrats, and they had no choice but to make a meager living as mid- or low-ranking aristocrats or take jobs as zuryo in the countryside and become indigenized as warriors to open up a new ways for their existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite having formed a powerful force at the Imperial Court, after 3 generations, hardly any of this line were high-ranking aristocrats, and they had no choice but to make a meager living as mid- or low-ranking aristocrats or to take jobs as provincial administrators, becoming indigenized warriors.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence to make it less wordy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite having formed a powerful force at the Imperial Court, after 3 generations, hardly any of this line were high-ranking aristocrats, and they had no choice but to make a meager living as mid- or low-ranking aristocrats or to take jobs as provincial administrators, becoming indigenized warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>嵯峨源氏は一字名で有名だが、二字名の嵯峨源氏もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saga Genji is well-known for single-character names, but there also Saga Genji members with two-character names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saga Genji are well-known for names using a single Chinese character, but there are also Saga Genji members with two-character names.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;are&quot;&quot;single-character names&quot;→&quot;names using a single Chinese character&quot;Added &quot;are&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saga-Genji are well-known for names using a single Chinese character, but there are also Saga-Genji members with two-character names.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>源是茂と弟の源衆望がそうであり、是茂の実父は源融の子の源昇だが、光孝天皇の養子となったためであり、衆望も光孝天皇の子、源是恒の養子となったために嵯峨源氏特有の一字名ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples include MINAMOTO no Koreshige and his younger brother; Koreshige&apos;s biological father, MINAMOTO no Noboru, was a son of MINAMOTO no Toru, but Koreshige was adopted by Emperor Koko, and the younger brother was also adopted by Emperor Koko&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Koretsune, and therefore, their names do not have the single-character names that are characteristic to Saga Genji.</e>
<cmt>源衆望→[読み方不明]、訳文には名前を使わず「弟」としてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples include MINAMOTO no Koreshige and his younger brother; Koreshige&apos;s father, MINAMOTO no Noboru, was a son of MINAMOTO no Toru, but Koreshige was adopted by Emperor Koko and his younger brother was adopted by Emperor Koko&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Koretsune, and therefore they do not have the single-character names that are characteristic of the Saga Genji.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;biological&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;Deleted comma&quot;their names&quot;→&quot;they&quot;&quot;to&quot;→&quot;of the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples include MINAMOTO no Koreshige and his younger brother; Koreshige&apos;s father, MINAMOTO no Noboru, was a son of MINAMOTO no Toru, but Koreshige was adopted by Emperor Koko and his younger brother was adopted by Emperor Koko&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Koretsune, and therefore they do not have the single-character names that are characteristic of the Saga-Genji.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>系図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancestry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancestry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancestry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>摂津国・渡辺氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Watanabe clan of Settsu Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Watanabe Clan of Settsu Province</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Watanabe Clan of Settsu Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>嵯峨源氏で後世に子孫を伝えたのは、源融の後裔で、地方に土着して武家となった系統（融流嵯峨源氏）であり、その代表が源融のひ孫で武蔵権介として関東に下り、箕田源次と名のり、平良文（村岡五郎）との一騎打ちで知られる源宛（箕田宛、箕田源次）の子の源綱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of MINAMOTO no Toru, the lineage (Toru Lineage of Saga Genji) which became indigenized and became warriors in the countryside, were the ones from Saga Genji who passed on their family line to the later generations, and the representative member was MINAMOTO no Tsuna, who was a son of MINAMOTO no Toru&apos;s great grandson, MINAMOTO no Atsuru (MINAMOTO no Ataru) (MITA no Atsuru, Ataru, MITA no Genji), who descended to Kanto as gonnosuke in Musashi then named himself Mita Genji and became known for the one-on-one duel against TAIRA no Yoshifumi (Goro MURAOKA).</e>
<cmt>武蔵権介とは人名ではなく、役職・官職の職名（武蔵の国での権介）ではなかと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saga Genji name was passed on by the Toru Lineage of Saga Genji, the descendants of MINAMOTO no Toru, who had become provincial warriors, and whose head was MINAMOTO no Tsuna, who was a son of MINAMOTO no Toru&apos;s great grandson, MINAMOTO no Atsuru (or Ataru) (also known as MITA no Atsuru or Ataru, MITA no Genji), who had come to Kanto as the Court&apos;s representative in Musashi Province, taking the name Mita Genji and who became known for his one-on-one duel against TAIRA no Yoshifumi (Goro MURAOKA).</e>
<cmt>Reworded first part of sentence&quot;the representative member&quot;→&quot;whose head&quot;&quot;descended&quot;→&quot;had come&quot;&quot;gonnosuke&quot;→&quot;Court&apos;s representative&quot;Added &quot;Province&quot;&quot;then named himself&quot;→&quot;taking the name&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saga-Genji name was passed on by the Toru Lineage of Saga-Genji, the descendants of MINAMOTO no Toru, who had become provincial warriors, and whose head was MINAMOTO no Tsuna, who was a son of MINAMOTO no Toru&apos;s great grandson, MINAMOTO no Atsuru (or Ataru) (also known as MITA no Atsuru or Ataru, MITA no Genji), who had come to Kanto as the Court&apos;s representative in Musashi Province, taking the name Mita-Genji and who became known for his one-on-one duel against TAIRA no Yoshifumi (Goro MURAOKA).</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>源綱（みなもとの・つな）は、清和源氏の源満仲の娘婿である仁明源氏の源敦の養子となり、母方の里の摂津国渡辺津（現・大阪市中央区 (大阪市)）に住み、同地を本拠地として渡辺綱（渡辺源次）と名のり渡辺氏の祖となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Tsuna was adopted by MINAMOTO no Atsushi of Ninmyo Genji, who was the husband of the daughter of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka of Seiwa Genji, and he lived in his mother&apos;s hometown of Watanabe-no-tsu, Settsu Province (present-day Chuo Ward, Osaka City (Osaka City)), used this place as his base, named himself WATANABE no Tsuna (Watanabe Genji) and became the patriarch of Watanabe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Tsuna was adopted by MINAMOTO no Atsushi of the Ninmyo Genji, who was the husband of the daughter of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka of the Seiwa Genji, settled in his mother&apos;s hometown of Watanabe-no-tsu, Settsu Province (present-day Chuo Ward, Osaka City), and used it as his base, taking the name WATANABE no Tsuna (WATANABE Genji) and later becoming the patriarch of the Watanabe clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and he lived&quot;→&quot;settled&quot;&quot;used this place&quot;→&quot;and used it&quot;&quot;named himself&quot;→&quot;taking the name&quot;&quot;became&quot;→&quot;later becoming&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Tsuna was adopted by MINAMOTO no Atsushi of the Ninmyo-Genji, who was the husband of the daughter of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka of the Seiwa-Genji, settled in his mother&apos;s hometown of Watanabe-no-tsu, Settsu Province (present-day Chuo Ward, Osaka City), and used it as his base, taking the name WATANABE no Tsuna (WATANABE Genji) and later becoming the patriarch of the Watanabe clan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>渡辺綱は、源融ゆずりの美男子と伝わるが、清和源氏嫡流である摂津源氏の源頼光の四天王筆頭とされ、大江山の酒呑童子退治説話などに剛勇の武者として登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that WATANABE no Tsuna was a handsome man just as MINAMOTO no Toru, but he was one of the four loyal retainers of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu of Settsu Genji belonging to the lineage of the heirs of Seiwa Genji; and he appears as a valiant warrior in the legend of subjugating Shuten Doji of Mount Oe-yama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that WATANABE no Tsuna was a handsome man like MINAMOTO no Toru and, as one of the four loyal retainers of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu of the Settsu Genji, who were descended from the Seiwa Genji, he appears as a valiant warrior in the legend of his victory over the demon, Shuten Doji of Mount Oe-yama.</e>
<cmt>&quot;just as&quot;→&quot;like&quot;&quot;but he was&quot;→&quot;and as&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;belonging to the lineage of the heirs of&quot;→&quot;who were descended from the&quot;&quot;subjugating&quot;→&quot;his victory over the demon&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that WATANABE no Tsuna was a handsome man like MINAMOTO no Toru and, as one of the four loyal retainers of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu of the Settsu-Genji, who were descended from the Seiwa-Genji, he appears as a valiant warrior in the legend of his victory over the demon, Shuten Doji of Mount Oe-yama.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>渡辺氏は摂津の渡辺津を本拠地とし、住吉区の浜（大阪湾）で行われる天皇の清めの儀式（八十嶋祭）に従事する天皇警護の滝口武者の一族であるとともに、衛門府、兵衛府など中央の官職を有し、また水軍として瀬戸内海の水軍の棟梁格の武家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Watanabe clan was based in Watanabe-Tsu in Settsu, and while it was a Takiguchi-no-Musha family who served as protectors of the Emperor in the Emperor&apos;s purification ritual (Yasoshima Festival) performed on Sumiyoshi Ward beach (Osaka Bay), the family also held positions in the central government including Emonfu and Hyoefu, and furthermore it was a warrior family of Toryo rank in the navy of Seto Inland Sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Watanabe clan was based in Watanabe-Tsu in Settsu, and as well as being members of the Takiguchi-no-Musha, who served as protectors of the Emperor in the Emperor&apos;s purification ritual (Yasoshima Festival) performed on Sumiyoshi Ward beach (Osaka Bay), the family also held positions in the central government, including the Emonfu and Hyoefu Guards, and was one of the main families in the Seto Inland Sea navy.</e>
<cmt>&quot;while it was a&quot;→&quot;as well as being members of the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; and &quot;Guards&quot;Deleted &quot; furthermore it&quot;&quot;a warrior family of Toryo rank in the navy of Seto Inland Sea&quot;→&quot;one of the main families in the Seto Inland Sea navy&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Watanabe clan was based in Watanabe-Tsu in Settsu, and as well as being members of the Takiguchi-no-Musha, who served as protectors of the Emperor in the Emperor&apos;s purification ritual (Yasoshima Festival) performed on Sumiyoshi Ward beach (Osaka Bay), the family also held positions in the central government, including the Emonfu and Hyoefu Guards, and was one of the main families in the Seto Inland Sea navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>肥前国・松浦氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsuura clan, Hizen Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsuura Clan, Hizen Province</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsuura Clan, Hizen Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>北九州の水軍松浦党の惣領氏として知られる松浦氏もまた渡辺氏から分かれたもので、渡辺綱の子の奈古屋授（源授、渡辺授）の子で、肥前国松浦郡の天皇家直轄の宇野御厨の荘官として九州に下った松浦久（源久、渡辺久）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Matsuura clan, which is known as the leading clan of the naval Matsuura party in Kitakyushu, also branched out from the Watanabe clan, and its patriarch was a son of WATANABE no Tusna&apos;s son, 奈古屋授(源授,渡辺授), Hisashi Matsuura (MINAMOTO no Hisashi, WATANABE no Hisashi), Hisashi MATSUURA (MINAMOTO no HISASHI, WATANABE no HISASHI), who went to Kyushu as a Shokan of Uno-no-Mikuriya in Matsuura County in Hizen Province, which was under direct control of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>奈古屋授等は読み方不明なので原文が訳文に残してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsuura Clan, which was known as the leading clan of the naval Matsuura faction in Kitakyushu, also branched off from the Watanabe clan, and its patriarch was WATANABE no Tusna&apos;s grandson, Hisashi MATSUURA (also known as MINAMOTO no Hisashi, WATANABE no Hisashi), who went to Kyushu as the Lord (Shokan) of Uno-no-Mikuriya in Matsuura County, Hizen Province, which was under the direct control of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;&quot;party&quot;→&quot;faction&quot;&quot;out&quot;→&quot;off&quot;&quot;a son of WATANABE no Tusna&apos;s son&quot;→&quot;WATANABE no Tusna&apos;s grandson&quot;Deleted &quot;奈古屋授（源授、渡辺授)&quot; and &quot;Hisashi MATSUURA (MINAMOTO no HISASHI, WATANABE no HISASHI)&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsuura Clan, which was known as the leading clan of the naval Matsuura faction in Kitakyushu, also branched off from the Watanabe clan, and its patriarch was WATANABE no Tusna&apos;s grandson, Hisashi MATSUURA (also known as MINAMOTO no Hisashi, WATANABE no Hisashi), who went to Kyushu as the Lord (Shokan) of Uno-no-Mikuriya in Matsuura County, Hizen Province, which was under the direct control of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>筑後国・蒲池氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamachi clan, Chikugo Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamachi Clan, Chikugo Province</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamachi Clan, Chikugo Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>渡辺氏以外の融流嵯峨源氏としては、源融の孫の源是茂（源宛の父の源仕の弟）の流れを汲み、肥前国の天皇家直轄荘園の神埼荘（鳥羽院領神埼荘）の荘官として下向した源満末がおり、その孫で筑後国三潴郡の地頭となった蒲池久直（源久直）を祖とする九州柳川市の蒲池氏がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Saga Genji heir families other than the Watanabe clan include the Kamachi clan of Yanagawa City, Kyushu, whose patriarch was Hisanao KAMACHI (MINAMOTO no Hisanao), who became the head of the estate of Mizuma County in Chikugo Province, and who was a grandson of MINAMOTO no Mitsusue, who descended as Shokan of Kanzaki-no-sho (Tobain-ryo Kanzaki-no-sho), which was a manor in Hizen Province under the direct control of the Imperial Family, and who is also related to MINAMOTO no Toru&apos;s grandson, MINAMOTO no Koreshige (younger brother of MINAMOTO no Tsukau, the father of MINAMOTO no Atsuru).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another family desended from the Saga Genji was the Kamachi clan of Yanagawa City, Kyushu, whose patriarch was Hisanao KAMACHI (MINAMOTO no Hisanao), the head of the estate of Mizuma County in Chikugo Province and a grandson of MINAMOTO no Mitsusue, who in turn was related to MINAMOTO no Toru&apos;s grandson, MINAMOTO no Koreshige (the younger brother of MINAMOTO no Atsuru&apos;s father, MINAMOTO no Tsukau) and who was the Lord of Kanzaki-no-sho (Tobain-ryo Kanzaki-no-sho), a manor in Hizen Province under the direct control of the Imperial Family,</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderDeleted &quot;who became&quot; and &quot;who was&quot;&quot;Shokan&quot;→&quot;Lord&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another family descended from the Saga-Genji was the Kamachi clan of Yanagawa City, Kyushu, whose patriarch was Hisanao KAMACHI (MINAMOTO no Hisanao), the head of the estate of Mizuma County in Chikugo Province and a grandson of MINAMOTO no Mitsusue, who in turn was related to MINAMOTO no Toru&apos;s grandson, MINAMOTO no Koreshige (the younger brother of MINAMOTO no Atsuru&apos;s father, MINAMOTO no Tsukau) and who was the Lord of Kanzaki-no-sho (Tobain-ryo Kanzaki-no-sho), a manor in Hizen Province under the direct control of the Imperial Family,</e>
<cmt>スペル-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>蒲池氏は後に松浦氏から源圓を婿養子を迎えて同族化したため渡辺党松浦氏の後裔ともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamachi clan is also considered as a descendant of Matsuura clan of Watanabe lineage because Kamachi clan later adopted MINAMOTO no Tsubura from Matsuura clan as a husband, thereby becoming one family,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamachi clan are also considered descendants of the Watanabe branch of the Matsuura clan because they later adopted MINAMOTO no Tsubura of the Matsuura clan as a husband, thereby becoming one family,</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; before clan namesMade &quot;descendant&quot; plural&quot;Matsuura clan of Watanabe lineage&quot;→&quot;the Watanabe branch of the Matsuura clan&quot;&quot;Kamachi clan&quot;→&quot;they&quot;&quot;from&quot;→&quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamachi clan are also considered descendants of the Watanabe branch of the Matsuura clan because they later adopted MINAMOTO no Tsubura of the Matsuura clan as a husband, thereby becoming one family,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>他に筑後の三池氏や草野氏も嵯峨源氏の子孫説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also theories that say that Miike clan and Kusano clan of Chikugo Province also are descendants of Saga Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also theories that say that the Miike Clan and the Kusano cCan of Chikugo Province are descendants of the Saga Genji.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; before clan namesCapitalized &apos;c&apos;Deleted &quot;also&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also theories that say that the Miike clan and the Kusano clan of Chikugo Province are descendants of the Saga-Genji.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan-補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>常陸国・源護</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Mamoru, Hitachi Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Mamoru, Hitachi Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Mamoru, Hitachi Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>また関東に勢力を張り、平将門の乱においても重要な存在となる常陸大掾の源護とその一族もまた武蔵権介の源宛（箕田宛）と同族の嵯峨源氏であろうとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, MINAMOTO no Mamoru of Hitachi Daijo clan, who expanded his forces in Kanto and who was a key figure in the Rebellion by TAIRA no Masakado, and his kin are also said to be of Saga Genji and of the same lineage as MINAMOTO no Ataru (Ataru TADA), who was a gonnosuke in Musashi.</e>
<cmt>武蔵権介とは人名ではなく、役職・官職の職名（武蔵の国での権介）ではなかと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Mamoru of Hitachi Daijo clan, who expanded his forces in Kanto and who was a key figure in the Rebellion by TAIRA no Masakado, and his kin are also said to be of the Saga Genji and of the same lineage as MINAMOTO no Ataru (Ataru TADA), who was a gonnosuke in Musashi.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Mamoru of Hitachi Daijo clan, who expanded his forces in Kanto and who was a key figure in the Rebellion by TAIRA no Masakado, and his kin are also said to be of the Saga-Genji and of the same lineage as MINAMOTO no Ataru (Ataru TADA), who was a gonnosuke in Musashi.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>凡例　太線は実子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend: The bold lines indicate biological children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend: The bold lines indicate biological children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend: The bold lines indicate biological children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>細線ならびに二重線は養子（苗字無しは臣下に下った源氏・一部苗字無しは僧）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plain lines and double lines indicate adopted children (ones without surnames are the Genji members who became liege subjects, and the ones with partially missing surnames became monks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plain lines and double lines indicate adopted children (ones without surnames are the Genji members who became liege subjects, and the ones with partially missing surnames became monks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plain lines and double lines indicate adopted children (ones without surnames are the Genji members who became liege subjects, and the ones with partially missing surnames became monks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Lonicera(id:20638), Fellow(id:67035), Nnamhcie(id:174568), Equaly(id:89792), 水野白楓(id:22811), NPD(id:58640), Mixtures(id:29234), Safkan(id:423), 唐棣色(id:64681), 沢田(id:40580), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>