<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>四条隆資</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasuke SHIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasuke SHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasuke SHIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>四条 隆資（しじょう たかすけ、正応5年（1292年） - 正平 (日本)7年/観応3年5月10日 (旧暦)（1352年6月22日））は、南北朝時代 (日本)の吉野朝廷に仕えた公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasuke SHIJO (1292-June 22, 1352) was a noble man who served the Yoshino Court in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasuke SHIJO (1292-June 22, 1352) was a noble man who served the Yoshino Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasuke SHIJO (1292 - June 30, 1352) was a noble man who served the Yoshino Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を移動しました。スペース補足しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は四条隆実（その死後に祖父である四条隆顕の養子となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was 四条隆実 (after his father died, he was adopted by his grandfather Takaaki SHIJO.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was 四条隆実 (after his father died, he was adopted by his grandfather Takaaki SHIJO.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Takazane SHIJO (after his father died, he was adopted by his grandfather Takaaki SHIJO).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に四条隆量・四条隆貞・四条隆俊・四条有資・西園寺公永母ら。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Takakazu SHIJO, Takasada SHIJO, Takatoshi SHIJO, Arisuke SHIJO and the mother of Kinnaga SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Takakazu SHIJO, Takasada SHIJO, Takatoshi SHIJO, Arisuke SHIJO and the mother of Kinnaga SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Takakazu SHIJO, Takasada SHIJO, Takatoshi SHIJO, Arisuke SHIJO, and a daughter who mothered Kinnaga SAIONJI, and others.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>従一位大納言（死後、贈左大臣）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was conferred Juichi Dainagon (Junior First Rank chief councilor of state) (Zo Sadaijin (the minister of the left, posthumously conferred) after his death.))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was conferred Juichi Dainagon (Junior First Rank chief councilor of state) (Zo Sadaijin (the minister of the left, posthumously conferred)</e>
<cmt>punctuation, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was conferred upon Juichii (Junior First Rank) Dainagon (chief councilor of state) (posthumously conferred upon the minister of the left.)</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Juichii ()、補足しました。大納言 = Dainagon (chief councilor of state)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>南朝の実務における中心人物であり、最後は後村上天皇を守るために自ら足利氏と戦って戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a key person to deal with actual practice and operations for the Southern Court, and afterward, died in war fighting against the Ashikaga clan by himself to protect Emperor Gomurakami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a key person who dealt with the actual practice and operation for the Southern Court, and afterward, died in war fighting against the Ashikaga clan by himself to protect Emperor Gomurakami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a key person who dealt with the actual practice and operation for the Southern Court; finally, he died in war fighting against the Ashikaga clan by himself to protect Emperor Gomurakami.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>後醍醐天皇の時代に権中納言・検非違使別当に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) in the era of Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) in the era of Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned to Provisional Middle Counselor, Superintendent of the Imperial Police in the era of Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1332年、元弘の乱において天皇方として参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fought the Genko War on the side of the Emperor in 1332.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought the Genko War on the side of the Emperor in 1332.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought in the Genko War on the side of the Emperor in 1332.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、鎌倉幕府軍の猛攻を受けて笠置山 (京都府)は落城して天皇は捕らえられてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a castle in Mt. Kasagi (Kyoto Prefecture) fell because it had fierce attack from the army of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the Emperor was captured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, thecastle on Mt. Kasagi (Kyoto Prefecture) fell because after a fierce attack from the army of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the Emperor was captured.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the castle on Mt. Kasagi (Kyoto Prefecture) fell after a fierce attack from the army of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and the Emperor was captured.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幸い幕府軍の追跡を逃れた隆資は護良親王・楠木正成を頼るが、幕府軍の攻撃にあって敗れて再度紀伊国に落ち延びて出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Takasuke fortunately fled from pursuit by the bakufu army, he relied on Imperial Prince Morinaga and Masashige KUSUNOKI, but he was defeated with the attack of the bakufu army and ran away to Kii Province to enter into priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasuke fortunately fled from pursuit of the bakufu army, he relied on Imperial Prince Morinaga and Masashige KUSUNOKI, but he was defeated in the attack of the bakufu army and ran away to Kii Province to enter into priesthood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasuke fortunately escaped from the pursuit by the bakufu army, he was sheltered by Imperial Prince Morinaga and Masashige KUSUNOKI, but defeated by the attack of the bakufu army, and ran away again to Kii Province to enter into priesthood.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、1333年に鎌倉幕府が滅亡して後醍醐天皇が帰京して建武の新政を始めると隆資も還俗して朝廷に復帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the fall of the Kamakura bakufu In 1333, Emperor Godaigo was back to Kyoto to begin with Kemmu Restoration, and Takasuke quit the priesthood to get back to the Court, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the fall of the Kamakura bakufu In 1333, Emperor Godaigo returned to Kyoto to begin the Kemmu Restoration, and Takasuke quit the priesthood to return to the Court, too.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the fall of the Kamakura bakufu in 1333, Emperor Godaigo returned to Kyoto to begin the Kenmu Restoration, then, Takasuke was secularized and return to the Court, too.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、一度苦境に立つと出家して挽回すると還俗するという隆資の行動に対して仏教を愚弄しているという批判が浴びせられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, he was harshly criticized for making a mock of the Buddhism based on his behaviors like as he faced the predicament, he became a priest and as the difficulty was cleared, he quit the priesthood for Genzoku (return to secular life.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, he was harshly criticized for making a mockery of Buddhism, because when he faced a predicament, he became a priest and as the difficulty passed, he quit the priesthood for Genzoku (return to secular life).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, he was harshly criticized for making a mockery of Buddhism, because when he faced a predicament, he became a priest, and as the difficulty passed, he quit the priesthood to return to secular life.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>二条河原の落書において「還俗」が批判に挙げられたのは隆資の事を念頭に置いたものであるとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that criticizing &apos;Genzoku&apos; (return to secular life) in Nijo Kawara Rakusho (the Lampoon at Nijo river beach) was intended to imply Takasuke&apos;s acts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that criticizing &apos;Genzoku&apos; (return to secular life) in Nijo Kawara Rakusho (the Lampoon at Nijo river beach) was intended to imply Takasuke&apos;s acts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that criticizing &apos;the returning to secular life&apos; in the Lampoon at Nijo river beach was intended to imply Takasuke&apos;s acts.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>1336年、楠木正成を倒した足利尊氏が京都を占領すると、隆資は郊外の男山に籠もって高師直軍を破る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Takauji ASHIKAGA defeated Masashige MASASHIGE and occupied Kyoto in 1336, Takasuke entered into Mt. Otoko located in the outskirts of the city and destroyed the army of KO no Moronao.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Takauji ASHIKAGA defeated Masashige MASASHIGE and occupied Kyoto in 1336, Takasuke entered Mt. Otoko located on the outskirts of the city and destroyed the army of KO no Moronao.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Takauji ASHIKAGA had defeated Masashige KUSUNOKI and occupied Kyoto in 1336, Takasuke entered Mt. Otoko located on the outskirts of the city and destroyed the army of KO no Moronao.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>だが、後醍醐天皇が尊氏によって幽閉されたために再度紀伊国に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Emperor Godaigo was confined by Takauji, he fled down to Kii Province again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Emperor Godaigo was confined by Takauji, he fled down to Kii Province again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Emperor Godaigo was captured and confined by Takauji, he fled to Kii Province again.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>やがて、後醍醐天皇が吉野に入った事を知ると吉野にて天皇と合流する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, as soon as he knew that Emperor Godaigo entered into Yoshino, he joined together with the Emperor in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, as soon as he knew that Emperor Godaigo entered Yoshino, he joined together with the Emperor in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, as soon as he learnt that Emperor Godaigo entered Yoshino, he joined the Emperor in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>1338年に後村上天皇が即位すると、近衛経忠・洞院実世とともに吉野朝廷（南朝）の政務を主導することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the enthronement of Emperor Gomurakami in 1338, he took a lead of attending government affairs for the Yoshino Court (the Southern Court) with Tsunetada KONOE and Saneyo TOIN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the enthronement of Emperor Gomurakami in 1338, he took the lead of attending government affairs for the Yoshino Court (the Southern Court) with Tsunetada KONOE and Saneyo TOIN.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the enthronement of Emperor Gomurakami in 1338, he took the leadership in government affairs at the Yoshino Court (the Southern Court) with Tsunetada KONOE and Saneyo TOIN.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その頃、北陸における戦いで足利氏に敗れて吉野に落ち延びた脇屋義助（新田義貞の弟）に対して後村上天皇が慰労して褒賞を出すことを決めた際に洞院実世が「敗軍の将に恩賞を出すと言うのは富士川の戦いで敗れた平維盛以来である」と反対意見を述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, when Emperor Gomurakami decided to give a special service reward to Yoshisuke WAKIYA (Yoshisada NITTA&apos;s older brother) who lost a war against the Ashikaga clan in Hokuriku and fled down to Yoshino, Saneyo TOIN expressed an objection, saying &apos;It will be the first time to give a special bonus to the head of the defeated army since there has been the case of TAIRA no Koremori who lost the Battle of Fujigawa.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, when Emperor Gomurakami decided to present a special service reward to Yoshisuke WAKIYA (Yoshisada NITTA&apos;s older brother) who lost the war against the Ashikaga clan in Hokuriku and fled down to Yoshino, Saneyo TOIN objected, saying &apos;It will be the first time to give a special bonus to the head of a defeated army since the case of TAIRA no Koremori who lost the Battle of Fujigawa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, when Emperor Gomurakami decided to present a special service reward to Yoshisuke WAKIYA (Yoshisada NITTA&apos;s younger brother) who lost the war against the Ashikaga clan in Hokuriku and fled to Yoshino, Saneyo TOIN objected, saying &apos;It will be the first time to give a special bonus to the head of a defeated army since the case of TAIRA no Koremori who lost the Battle of Fujigawa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>だが、隆資は「義助は遠い北国で孤軍奮戦しながらも十分な支援を受けられなかったから敗れたのであり、その責任は支援を与えなかったここにいる公卿達にもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, Takasuke, with the counterargument that &apos;Yoshisuke lost the battle because he fought alone without sufficient support in the faraway northland, so, the fault also lay with the noble people who are here and had not provided support.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, Takasuke, counterargued that &apos;Yoshisuke lost the battle because he fought alone without sufficient support in the far northland, so, the fault also lay with the noble people who are here and had not provided support.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, Takasuke, replied that &apos;Yoshisuke lost the battle because he fought alone without sufficient support in the far northland, so, the fault also lay with the noble people who are here and had not provided support.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（十分な支援を受けながら戦わずに逃げ帰った）維盛と同一に扱うのはおかしい」と反論して、天皇に忠節を尽くしている武士達を蔑視する公卿達の振る舞いを批判し、天皇の指示通りに褒賞を出させたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is ridiculous to treat him in the same way as Koremori (who fled back before fighting despite the receipt of enough support,)&apos; criticized the noble people for their behaviors looking down samurai warriors who remained faithful for the Emperor, and the reward was given to him as directed by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is ridiculous to treat him the same way as Koremori (who fled back before fighting despite the receipt of enough support,)&apos; criticized the noble people for looking down on the samurai warriors who remained faithful to the Emperor, and while a reward was given to him as directed by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is ridiculous to treat him the same way as Koremori (who fled back before fighting despite the receipt of enough support),&apos; and criticized the noble people for looking down on the samurai warriors who remained faithful to the Emperor, and a reward was given to him as directed by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。不要なコンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>1348年、北畠親房・楠木正行と連携して四条畷の戦いに臨んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fought the Shijonawate War in 1348 in cooperation with Chikafusa KITABATAKE and Masatsura KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought in the Shijonawate War in 1348 in cooperation with Chikafusa KITABATAKE and Masatsura KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought in the Shijonawate War in 1348 in alliance with Chikafusa KITABATAKE and Masatsura KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>公卿ながら武士に対しても公平な隆資の姿勢を慕う武士達の奮戦はあったものの、足利軍の圧倒的な兵力の前に惨敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although warriors fought the battle very hard respecting Takasuke&apos;s attitudes of acting in a fair manner toward the warriors who were originally from noble families, they completely lost the war with the overwhelming number of soldiers of the Ashikaga army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although warriors fought very hard respecting Takasuke&apos;s fair manner toward the warriors who were originally from noble families, they completely lost the war against the overwhelming number of samurai of the Ashikaga army.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although warriors fought very hard respecting Takasuke&apos;s fair manner toward the warriors, who were originally from noble families, they completely defeated by the overwhelming number of samurai of the Ashikaga army.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>だが、後村上天皇は隆資を慰労して従一位・大納言に任じたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Emperor Gomurakami promoted Takasuke to Juichii Dai-nagon (Junior First Rank chief councilor of state) to recognize his work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Emperor Gomurakami promoted Takasuke to Juichii Dai-nagon (Junior First Rank chief councilor of state) to recognize his work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Emperor Gomurakami promoted Takasuke to Juichii (Junior First Rank) Dainagon (chief councilor of state) in recognition of his services.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Juichii ()、補足しました。大納言 = Dainagon (chief councilor of state)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>1351年、足利尊氏とその弟・足利直義との確執が深刻となると、尊氏は一時南朝側に降って直義討伐のために鎌倉に出陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the feuds between Takauji ASHIKAGA and his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA got more deepened in 1351, Takauji left for Kamakura to put down Tadayoshi by taking the side of the Southern Court for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As feuds between Takauji ASHIKAGA and his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA became more severe in 1351, Takauji left for Kamakura to put down Tadayoshi by taking the side of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As feuds between Takauji ASHIKAGA and his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA became more severe in 1351, Takauji left for Kamakura to put down Tadayoshi by temporarily taking the side of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この隙を突いて翌1352年南朝軍は京都を占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of this chance, the Southern Court occupied Kyoto in the following year 1352.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of this chance, the Southern Court occupied Kyoto in the following year 1352.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of this chance, the Southern Court occupied Kyoto in 1352.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>後は、男山の仮御所にいる後村上天皇を京都に迎えるだけとなったが、その年の3月には尊氏の嫡男・足利義詮の反撃によって南朝軍は京都を撤退、更に5月には後村上天皇がいる男山の仮御所が包囲された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All they had to do in the end was to get Emperor Gomurakami back in Kyoto from the temporary imperial house in Mt. Otoko, but the army of the Southern Court withdrew from Kyoto because they had the counterattack of Takauji&apos;s legitimate son Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA in March of the same year, and also in May, the temporary imperial house in Mr. Otoko where Emperor Gomurakami was staying was surrounded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All they had to do in the end was to return Emperor Gomurakami to Kyoto from the temporary imperial house in Mt. Otoko, but the army of the Southern Court withdrew from Kyoto because they were counterattacked by Takauji&apos;s legitimate son Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA in March of the same year, and also in May, the temporary imperial house in Mt. Otoko where Emperor Gomurakami was staying, was surrounded.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All they had to do in the end was to return Emperor Gomurakami to Kyoto from the temporary imperial house in Mt. Otoko, but the army of the Southern Court withdrew from Kyoto because they were counterattacked by Takauji&apos;s legitimate son Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA in March of the same year, and also in May, the temporary imperial house in Mt. Otoko where Emperor Gomurakami was staying was surrounded.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>5月10日、天皇は北畠顕能・名和長重に護られて男山を脱出する途中に足利軍と遭遇、殿を務めた隆資は奮戦空しく討ち死にすることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 10, the Emperor encountered the Ashikaga army when he was getting away from Mt. Otoko with his guards Akiyoshi KITABATAKE and Nagashige NAWA, and though Takasuke who was in the position of a rear guard fought hard against the army, he was killed in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 10, the Emperor encountered the Ashikaga army when he was escaping from Mt. Otoko with his guards Akiyoshi KITABATAKE and Nagashige NAWA, and though Takasuke in the position of rear guard, fought hard against the army, he was killed in battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 10, the Emperor encountered the Ashikaga army when he was escaping from Mt. Otoko with his guards Akiyoshi KITABATAKE and Nagashige NAWA, although Takasuke in the position of rear guard fought hard against the army, he was killed in battle.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>一説には『増鏡』の著者とする説もあるが、少数説に留まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is believed to have authored &quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror,) but this is only supported by a small number of people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to have authored &quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror,) but this is only supported by a small number of people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to have authored &quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror), but this is supported by only a small number of people.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。コンマの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), やりたこ(id:113528), お掃除大好き(id:99320), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Nighthawks(id:36125), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>