<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉備真備</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KIBI no Makibi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KIBI no Makibi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KIBI no Makibi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉備 真備（きび の まきび、持統天皇9年（695年） - 宝亀6年10月2日 (旧暦)（775年11月3日））は、日本の奈良時代の学者、政治家（公卿）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KIBI no Makibi (695 - November 3, 775) was a scholar, a statesman and a Kugyo (a court noble) who lived during the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KIBI no Makibi (695 - November 3, 775) was a scholar, a statesman and a Kugyo (a court noble) who lived during the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KIBI no Makibi (695 - November 3, 775) was a scholar, a statesman and a Kugyo (a court noble) who lived during the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>正二位・勲等・右大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ranked Shonii (Senior Second Rank), and held the office of Udaijin (Minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%8B%B2%E7%AD%89くん‐とう【勲等】「国家、社会に功績のあった者を表彰するために設けられた勲位の等級。最高を大勲位とし、勲一等以下勲八等まで分かれる。」とあり、原文のままですと意味が通りませんので、勲等を省略しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ranked Shonii (Senior Second Rank), and held the office of Udaijin (Minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was ranked Shonii (Senior Second Rank), and held the office of Udaijin (Minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>備中国下道郡（後の岡山県吉備郡真備町、現在の倉敷市真備町）出身の父は右衛士少尉下道圀勝（しもつみちのくにかつ）、母は楊貴氏（八木）氏（大和国（後の奈良県）の豪族）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makibi&apos;s father was SHIMOTSUMICHI no Kunikatsu, Ueji no shojo (Jr. Lieutenant of the Right Guards), in Shimotsumichi District, Bicchu Province (later Mabi Town, Kibi County, Okayama Prefecture, and present-day Mabi Town, Kurashiki City), and his mother was from the local ruling family, the YAGI clan, of Yamato Province (later Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makibi&apos;s father was SHIMOTSUMICHI no Kunikatsu, Ueji no shojo (Jr. Lieutenant of the Right Guards), in Shimotsumichi District, Bicchu Province (later Mabi Town, Kibi County, Okayama Prefecture, and present-day Mabi Town, Kurashiki City), and his mother was from the local ruling family, the YAGI clan, of Yamato Province (later Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makibi&apos;s father was SHIMOTSUMICHI no Kunikatsu, Ueji no shojo (Jr. Lieutenant of the Right Guards), in Shimotsumichi District, Bicchu Province (later Mabi Town, Kibi County, Okayama Prefecture, and present-day Mabi Town, Kurashiki City), and his mother was from the local ruling family, the Yagi clan, of Yamato Province (later Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>「the YAGI clan」を「the Yagi clan」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>下道氏は吉備地方で有力な地方豪族吉備氏の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The SHIMOTSUMICHI clan was a branch of a powerful local ruling family, the KIBI clan, in the Kibi region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SHIMOTSUMICHI clan was a branch of a powerful local ruling family, the KIBI clan, in the Kibi region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shimotsumichi clan was a branch of a powerful local ruling family, the Kibi clan, in the Kibi region.</e>
<cmt>「the SHIMOTSUMICHI clan」を「the Shimotsumichi clan」に修正しました。「the KIBI clan」を「the Kibi clan」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>716年（霊亀2年）、下道真備は22歳のときに遣唐留学生となり、翌年の717年（養老元年）に入唐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makibi SHIMOTSU was appointed as a member of the Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty of China in 716 when he was 22 years old, and visited Tang in the following year, 717.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makibi SHIMOTSU was appointed as a member of the Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty of China in 716 when he was 22 years old, and visited Tang in the following year, 717.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makibi SHIMOTSU was appointed as a member of the Japanese envoy to the Tang Dynasty of China in 716 when he was 22 years old, and visited Tang in the following year, 717.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>帰路では種子島に漂着するが、735年（天平7年）に多くの典籍を携えて帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On his way back to Japan, Makibi drifted to Tanegashima Island once but managed to arrive in Kyoto in 735 with various kinds of books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his way back to Japan, Makibi drifted to Tanegashima Island once but managed to arrive in Kyoto in 735 with various kinds of books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On his way back to Japan, Makibi drifted to Tanegashima Island once but managed to arrive in Kyoto in 735 with various kinds of books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>唐では儒学のほか、天文学や音楽、兵学などを学び、帰朝時には、経書（『唐礼』130巻）、天文暦書（『大衍暦経』1巻、『大衍暦立成』12巻）、日時計（測影鉄尺）、楽器（銅律管、鉄如方響、写律管声12条）、音楽書（『楽書要録』10巻）、弓 (武器)（絃纏漆角弓、馬上飲水漆角弓、露面漆四節角弓各1張）、矢（射甲箭20隻、平射箭10隻）などを献上し、『東漢観記』を持ち来たらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tang, he learned not only Confucianism, but also astronomy, music and military science, and brought back &quot;Tokan Kanki&quot; (historical records of Eastern Han Dynasty) to Japan, and offered to the Imperial Court many other books and materials, including Keisho (Confucianism documents [130 volumes of &quot;Torai&quot;]), an astronomical calendar book (one volume of &quot;Taien Calendar&quot; and 12 volumes of &quot;Daienreki Ryusei&quot;), a sun clock (Sokuei Kaneshaku), music instruments (Dorikkan, 鉄如方響, 写律管声12条), music theory books (ten volumes of &quot;Gakusho Yoroku&quot;), bows (arms) (絃纏漆角弓、馬上飲水漆角弓、露面漆四節角弓各1張) and arrows (20 of Shakosen [square arrow] and 10 of Heishasen [flat arrow]).</e>
<cmt>『東漢観記』: http://home.t02.itscom.net/izn/ea/chi04z.html『東漢観記』、経書（『唐礼』）、天文暦書（『大衍暦経』、『大衍暦立成』）、日時計（測影鉄尺）、楽器（銅律管、鉄如方響、写律管声12条）、音楽書（『楽書要録』10巻）、弓 (武器)（絃纏漆角弓、馬上飲水漆角弓、露面漆四節角弓各1張）、矢（射甲箭20隻、平射箭10隻）：読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tang, he learned not only Confucianism, but also astronomy, music and military science, and brought back &quot;Tokan Kanki&quot; (historical records of Eastern Han Dynasty) to Japan, and offered to the Imperial Court many other books and materials, including Keisho (Confucianism documents [130 volumes of &quot;Torai&quot;]), an astronomical calendar book (one volume of &quot;Taien Calendar&quot; and 12 volumes of &quot;Daienreki Ryusei&quot;), a sun clock (Sokuei Kaneshaku), music instruments (Dorikkan, 鉄如方響, 写律管声12条), music theory books (ten volumes of &quot;Gakusho Yoroku&quot;), bows (arms) (絃纏漆角弓、馬上飲水漆角弓、露面漆四節角弓各1張) and arrows (20 of Shakosen [square arrow] and 10 of Heishasen [flat arrow]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tang, he learned not only Confucianism, but also astronomy, music and military science, and brought back &quot;Tokan Kanki&quot; (historical records of Eastern Han Dynasty) to Japan, and offered to the Imperial Court many other books and materials, including Keisho (Confucianism documents [130 volumes of &quot;Torai&quot;]), an astronomical calendar book (one volume of &quot;Taien Calendar&quot; and 12 volumes of &quot;Daienreki Ryusei&quot;), a sun clock (Sokuei Kaneshaku), music instruments (Dorikkan, 鉄如方響, 写律管声12条), music theory books (ten volumes of &quot;Gakusho Yoroku&quot;), bows (arms) (絃纏漆角弓、馬上飲水漆角弓、露面漆四節角弓各1張) and arrows (20 of Shakosen [square arrow] and 10 of Heishasen [flat arrow]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>帰朝後は聖武天皇や光明皇后の寵愛を得て、737年（天平9年）に従五位に列せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his return, Makibi started to receive a favor of Emperor Shomu and Empress Komyo, and got promoted to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in 737.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his return, Makibi earned the favor of Emperor Shomu and Empress Komyo, and got promoted to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in 737.</e>
<cmt>receive a-&gt;earn the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his return, Makibi earned the favor of Emperor Shomu and Empress Komyo, and got promoted to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in 737.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>738年（天平10年）に橘諸兄が右大臣に任ぜられて政権を握ると、同時に帰国した僧玄ボウとともに重用され、真備は右衛士督の役職を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 738, when TACHIBANA no Moroe was promoted to Udaijin and seized power of the feudal government, Makibi was assigned with an important role along with a priest Genbo who returned from Tang with Makibi, and appointed as Ueji no kami (Guard chief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 738, when TACHIBANA no Moroe was promoted to Udaijin and seized power of the feudal government, Makibi was assigned with an important role along with the priest Genbo who returned from Tang with Makibi, and was appointed Ueji no kami (Guard chief).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 738, when TACHIBANA no Moroe was promoted to Udaijin and seized power of the feudal government, Makibi was assigned with an important role along with the priest Genbo who returned from Tang with Makibi, and was appointed Ueji no kami (Guard chief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>740年には、真備と玄昉を除くのを名目に、大宰府で藤原広嗣が反乱を起こしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 740, FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu raised a rebellion in Dazai-fu (the local government office in the Kyushu region) in an attempt to remove Makibi and Genbo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 740, FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu raised a rebellion in Dazai-fu (the local government office in the Kyushu region) in an attempt to remove Makibi and Genbo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 740, FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu raised a rebellion in Dazai-fu (the local government office in the Kyushu region) in an attempt to remove Makibi and Genbo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>741年に東宮学士として皇太子阿倍内親王（後の孝謙天皇・称徳天皇）に『漢書』や『礼記』を教授した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 741, Makibi taught &quot;Kanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Han Dynasty) and &quot;Raiki&quot; (Book of Rites) to the Imperial Princess Abe (later Empress Koken and Empress Shotoku) as Togugakushi (an educator of the Princess).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 741, Makibi taught &quot;Kanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Han Dynasty) and &quot;Raiki&quot; (Book of Rites) to the Imperial Princess Abe (later Empress Koken and Empress Shotoku) as Togugakushi (an educator of the Princess).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 741, Makibi taught &quot;Kanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Han Dynasty) and &quot;Raiki&quot; (Book of Rites) to the Imperial Princess Abe (later Empress Koken and Empress Shotoku) as Togugakushi (an educator of the Princess).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、743年（天平15年）には従四位下、春宮大夫兼皇太子学士、746年（天平18年）には吉備朝臣の姓を賜り、747年に右京大夫に転じて749年（天平勝宝元年）には従四位上に昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his return, Makibi was on the fast track to promotion; he was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed as Togu no daibu (Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) and also as Kotaishigakushi (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) in 743, given the surname of KIBI-ASON in 746, appointed as Ukyo no Daibu Jyuyoi (Minister of the Kyoto Right Administration Office) in 747, and again promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 749.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his return, Makibi was on the fast track to promotion; he was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed Togu no daibu (Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) and also Kotaishigakushi (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) in 743, given the surname of KIBI-ASON in 746, appointed Ukyo no Daibu Jyuyoi (Minister of the Kyoto Right Administration Office) in 747, and again promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 749.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his return, Makibi was on the fast track to promotion; he was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed Togu no daibu (Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) and also Kotaishigakushi (an official in charge of education of the Crown Prince) in 743, given the surname of KIBI-ASON in 746, appointed Ukyo no Daibu Juyoi (Minister of the Kyoto Right Administration Office) in 747, and again promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 749.</e>
<cmt>「Jyuyoi」を「Juyoi」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>孝謙天皇即位後の750年には、藤原仲麻呂が専権し、真備は、筑前守、肥前守に左遷されたが、751年には遣唐副使となり、752年（天平勝2年）に入唐し阿倍仲麻呂と再会する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 750, after Empress Koken was enthroned, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro started to wield his power and Makibi was relegated to the lower positions of Chikuzen no kami (the governor of the Chikuzen Province) and Hizen no kami (the governor of the Hizen Province), but in 751 Makibi was appointed as the assistant to the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty of China and visited Tang in 752 where Makibi reunited with ABE no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 750, after Empress Koken was enthroned, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro started to wield his power and Makibi was relegated to the lower positions of Chikuzen no kami (the governor of the Chikuzen Province) and Hizen no kami (the governor of the Hizen Province), but in 751 Makibi was appointed the assistant to the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty of China and visited Tang in 752 where Makibi reunited with ABE no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 750, after Empress Koken was enthroned, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro started to wield his power and Makibi was relegated to the lower positions of Chikuzen no kami (the governor of the Chikuzen Province) and Hizen no kami (the governor of the Hizen Province), but in 751 Makibi was appointed the assistant to the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty of China and visited Tang in 752 where Makibi reunited with ABE no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>753年には帰路で屋久島に漂着するが、鑑真を伴って無事に帰国している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Makibi was drifted to Yakushima Island on his way back to Japan, he safely returned to Kyoto with Ganjin (a priest of Tang) in 753.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Makibi drifted to Yakushima Island on his way back to Japan, he safely returned to Kyoto with Ganjin (a priest of Tang) in 753.</e>
<cmt>deleted “was”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Makibi drifted to Yakushima Island on his way back to Japan, he safely returned to Kyoto with Ganjin (a priest of Tang) in 753.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>754年（天平勝宝6年）には大宰少弐に昇任、756年に新羅に対する防衛のため筑前国に怡土城を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 754, Makibi was promoted to Dazai no shoni (Junior Assistant Governor-General) of Dazai-fu (a military base) in Chikuzen Province where he ordered to build Ito Castle to reinforce the national defense against Shila (ancient Korean kingdom) in 756.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/119317/m0u/%E5%A4%A7%E5%AE%B0%E5%BA%9C/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 754, Makibi was promoted to Dazai no shoni (Junior Assistant Governor-General) of Dazai-fu (a military base) in Chikuzen Province where he ordered to build Ito Castle to reinforce the national defense against Shila (ancient Korean kingdom) in 756.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 754, Makibi was promoted to Dazai no shoni (Junior Assistant Governor-General) of Dazai-fu (a military base) in Chikuzen Province where he ordered to build Ito-jo Castle to reinforce the national defense against Shila (ancient Korean kingdom) in 756.</e>
<cmt>「Ito Castle」を「Ito-jo Castle」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>758年には大宰府で唐での安史の乱に備えるよう勅を受け、759年（天平宝字3年）に大宰大弐（大宰府の次官）に昇任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then received an order from the Emperor to prepare the Dazai-fu for the aftermath of the An Shi Rebellion which occurred in Tang, and was again promoted to Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of Dazai-fu) in 759.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then received an order from the Emperor to prepare the Dazai-fu for the aftermath of the An Shi Rebellion which occurred in Tang, and was again promoted to Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of Dazai-fu) in 759.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then received an order from the Emperor to prepare the Dazai-fu for the aftermath of the An Shi Rebellion which occurred in Tang, and was again promoted to Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of Dazai-fu) in 759.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後、暦学が認められ、儀鳳暦に替えて大衍暦が採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the study of calendars was officially viewed as credible, and the Taien reki (Taien calendar) which was brought back from Tang was adopted in place of the Giho reki (an old Chinese calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the study of calendars was officially viewed as credible, and the Taien reki (Taien calendar) which was brought back from Tang was adopted in place of the Giho reki (an old Chinese calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 764, Makibi was appointed as the chief in the Todai-ji Temple construction and returned to Kyoto at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt>「Todaiji-Temple」を「Todai-ji Temple」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>764年（天平宝字8年）には造東大寺長官に任ぜられ、70歳で帰京した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 764, Makibi was appointed as the chief in the Todaiji-Temple construction and returned to Kyoto at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 764, Makibi was appointed as the chief in the Todaiji-Temple construction and returned to Kyoto at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 764, Makibi was appointed as the chief in the Todaiji-Temple construction and returned to Kyoto at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>恵美押勝（藤原仲麻呂）が反乱を起こした際には、従三位に昇叙され、中衛大将として追討軍を指揮して乱鎮圧に功を挙げ（藤原仲麻呂の乱）、765年には勲二等を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When EMI no Oshikatsu (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro) raised a rebellion, Makibi was promoted to Jusani (Junior Third Rank) to head a government army (a punitive force to search and kill a rebel) as Chue no daisho (Major Captain of the imperial guard) and succeeded to crush the rebellion, after which Makibi was conferred &apos;Order of Second Class&apos; in 765.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When EMI no Oshikatsu (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro) raised a rebellion, Makibi was promoted to Jusani (Junior Third Rank) to head a government army (a punitive force to search and kill a rebel) as Chue no daisho (Major Captain of the imperial guard) and succeeded in crushing the rebellion, after which Makibi was conferred &apos;Order of Second Class&apos; in 765.</e>
<cmt>changed infinitive to gerund</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When EMI no Oshikatsu (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro) raised a rebellion, Makibi was promoted to Jusani (Junior Third Rank) to head a government army (a punitive force to search and kill a rebel) as Chue no daisho (Major Captain of the imperial guard) and succeeded in crushing the rebellion, after which Makibi was conferred &apos;Order of Second Class&apos; in 765.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>766年（天平神護2年）、称徳天皇（孝謙天皇の重祚）と法王に就任した弓削道鏡の下で中納言となり、藤原真楯の薨逝で大納言となった後、右大臣に昇進して、左大臣の藤原永手とともに政治を執った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 766, Makibi was appointed as Chunagon (the vice-councilor of state) with the backings of Empress Shotoku (an empress regnant, a second enthronement of Empress Koken) and YUGE no Dokyo (Priest Emperor), and promoted to Dainagon (Major Counselor) upon the death of FUJIWARA no Matate, and Makibi finally assumed the post of Udaijin (Minister of the right) to take the helm of the state in tandem with Sadaijin (Minister of the left), FUJIWARA no Nagate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 766, Makibi was appointed Chunagon (the vice-councilor of state) with the backing of Empress Shotoku (an empress regnant, a second enthronement of Empress Koken) and YUGE no Dokyo (Priest Emperor), and promoted to Dainagon (Major Counselor) upon the death of FUJIWARA no Matate, and Makibi finally assumed the post of Udaijin (Minister of the right) to take the helm of the state in tandem with Sadaijin (Minister of the left), FUJIWARA no Nagate.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 766, Makibi was appointed Chunagon (the vice-councilor of state) with the backing of Empress Shotoku (an empress regnant, a second enthronement of Empress Koken) and YUGE no Dokyo (Priest Emperor), and promoted to Dainagon (Major Counselor) upon the death of FUJIWARA no Matate, and Makibi finally assumed the post of Udaijin (Minister of the right) to take the helm of the state in tandem with Sadaijin (Minister of the left), FUJIWARA no Nagate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これは、地方豪族出身者としては破格の出世であり、学者から立身して大臣にまでなったのも、近世以前では、吉備真備と菅原道真のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was an extraordinary promotion that no one from one local ruling family could easily achieve, and Makibi also became the first scholar-turned minister in pre-modern history except SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was an extraordinary promotion that no one from one local ruling family could easily achieve, and Makibi also became the first scholar-turned minister in pre-modern history except SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was an extraordinary promotion that no one from one local ruling family could easily achieve, and Makibi also became the first scholar-turned minister in pre-modern history except SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>770年（宝亀元年）、称徳天皇が崩じた後には、後継の天皇候補として文室浄三および文室大市を推したが敗れ、「長生の弊、却りて此の恥に合ふ」と嘆息したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 770, after Empress Shotoku died, Makibi backed up FUNYA no Kiyomi and FUNYA no Ochi as candidates to the next Emperor, but his effort bore no fruit and it is believed Makibi later said &apos;I have never imagined to live to see myself humiliated this much&apos;.</e>
<cmt>長生の弊、却りて此の恥に合ふ（長生きしてきてこんな恥をかくとは。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 770, after Empress Shotoku died, Makibi backed FUNYA no Kiyomi and FUNYA no Ochi as candidates to the next Emperor, but his effort bore no fruit and it is believed Makibi later said &apos;I have never imagined to live to see myself humiliated this much&apos;.</e>
<cmt>deleted “up”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 770, after Empress Shotoku died, Makibi backed FUNYA no Kiyomi and FUNYA no Ochi as candidates to the next Emperor, but his effort bore no fruit and it is believed Makibi later said &apos;I have never imagined to live to see myself humiliated this much&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ただし、この即位をめぐる話は『水鏡』など後世の史書や物語にしかみえておらず、『続日本紀』には認められないので、後世の作り話ではないかと疑うひとも多い（瀧浪貞子など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this series of events concerning the enthronement is only described in the history books and historical fictions compiled in later times, such as &quot;Mizu Kagami (The Water Mirror)&quot; but not appear in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued); therefore, many critics (including Sadako TAKINAMI, a historian of ancient Japanese history) doubt the authenticity of the descriptions on the events.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this series of events concerning the enthronement is only described in the history books and historical fictions compiled in later times, such as &quot;Mizu Kagami&quot; (The Water Mirror) but not appear in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued); therefore, many critics (including Sadako TAKINAMI, a historian of ancient Japanese history) doubt the authenticity of the descriptions on the events.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this series of events concerning the enthronement is only described in the history books and historical fictions compiled in later times, such as &quot;Mizu Kagami&quot; (The Water Mirror) but not appear in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued); therefore, many critics (including Sadako TAKINAMI, a historian of ancient Japanese history) doubt the authenticity of the descriptions on the events.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>光仁天皇即位後、真備は老齢を理由に辞職を願い出るが、光仁天皇は兼職の中衛大将のみの解任を許し、右大臣の職は慰留した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Makibi offered his resignation due to aging after the enthronement of Emperor Konin, the Emperor only allowed him to resign from his concurrent post of Chue no daisho (Major Captain of the imperial guard), but retained him as Udaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Makibi offered his resignation due to aging after the enthronement of Emperor Konin, the Emperor only allowed him to resign from his concurrent post of Chue no daisho (Major Captain of the imperial guard), but retained him as Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Makibi offered his resignation due to aging after the enthronement of Emperor Konin, the Emperor only allowed him to resign from his concurrent post of Chue no daisho (Major Captain of the imperial guard), but retained him as Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>771年に再び辞職を願い出て許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 771, he again submitted his resignation, which was accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 771, he again submitted his resignation, which was accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 771, he again submitted his resignation, which was accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>それ以後の生活については何も伝わっておらず、775年（宝亀6年）に薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His later life after resignation was not known, except the fact that he died in 775.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His later life after resignation was not known, except the fact that he died in 775.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His later life after resignation was not known, except the fact that he died in 775.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>亡くなった地や墓所がどこなのかは不明であるが、奈良市内にある奈良教育大学の構内には真備の墓と伝えられる『吉備塚（吉備塚古墳）』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is not known exactly where Makibi died or where his tomb is, there is one tomb called &quot;KIBI zuka&quot; (KIBI zuka tomb) in the precinct of Nara University of Education of Nara City, which is believed to be Makibi&apos;s tomb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is not known exactly where Makibi died or where his tomb is, there is one tomb called &quot;KIBI zuka&quot; (KIBI zuka tomb) in the precinct of Nara University of Education of Nara City, which is believed to be Makibi&apos;s tomb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is not known exactly where Makibi died or where his tomb is, there is one tomb called &quot;KIBI zuka&quot; (KIBI zuka tomb) in the precinct of Nara University of Education of Nara City, which is believed to be Makibi&apos;s tomb.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>職務の傍ら孔子をはじめとする儒教の聖人を祭る朝廷儀礼釈奠の整備にも当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides his own duty, Makibi was responsible for arranging the &quot;Sekiten&quot; hosted by Imperial Court, which honored saints of Confucianism including Koshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides his own duty, Makibi was responsible for arranging the &quot;Sekiten&quot; hosted by Imperial Court, which honored saints of Confucianism including Koshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides his own duty, Makibi was responsible for arranging the &quot;Sekiten&quot; hosted by Imperial Court, which honored saints of Confucianism including Koshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>著書に『私教類聚』『道弱和上纂』『刪定律令』などがあるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Makibi wrote &quot;Shikyo Ruijo&quot;, &quot;Dosen Wajosan&quot; and &quot;Santei Ritsuryo Code&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Makibi wrote &quot;Shikyo Ruijo&quot;, &quot;Dosen Wajosan&quot; and &quot;Santei Ritsuryo Code&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Makibi wrote &quot;Shikyo Ruijo&quot;, &quot;Dosen Wajosan&quot; and &quot;Santei Ritsuryo Code&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>『江談抄』や『吉備大臣入唐絵巻』などによれば、真備は、殺害を企てた唐人によって、鬼が棲むという楼に幽閉されたが、その鬼というのが真備とともに遣唐使として入唐した阿倍仲麻呂の霊（生霊）であったため、難なく救われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the literature such as &quot;Godansho&quot; and &quot;Kibinootodo Nitto Emaki&quot;, Tang men who tried to kill Makibi confined Makibi in a castle where a devil lived, but Makibi could escape from the castle without any difficulty, because the devil turned out to be a wraith of ABE no Nakamaro who visited Tang with Makibi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the literature such as &quot;Godansho&quot; and &quot;Kibinootodo Nitto Emaki&quot;, Tang men who tried to kill Makibi confined Makibi in a castle where a devil lived, but Makibi could escape from the castle without any difficulty, because the devil turned out to be a wraith of ABE no Nakamaro who visited Tang with Makibi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the literature such as &quot;Godansho&quot; and &quot;Kibinootodo Nitto Emaki&quot;, Tang men who tried to kill Makibi confined Makibi in a castle where a devil lived, but Makibi could escape from the castle without any difficulty, because the devil turned out to be a wraith of ABE no Nakamaro who visited Tang with Makibi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、難解な「野馬台詩」の解読や、囲碁の勝負などを課せられたが、これも阿倍仲麻呂の霊の援助により解決した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makibi was also forced to decipher a difficult &apos;Yamatai shi (Poems on Japan)&apos; and to play Igo (a board game of capturing territory), but he managed to succeed in all of the challenges facing him with the help of the wraith of ABE no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makibi was also forced to decipher a difficult &apos;Yamatai shi&apos; (Poems on Japan) and to play Igo (a board game of capturing territory), but he managed to succeed in all of the challenges facing him with the help of the wraith of ABE no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makibi was also forced to decipher a difficult &apos;Yamatai shi&apos; (Poems on Japan) and to play Igo (a board game of capturing territory), but he managed to succeed in all of the challenges facing him with the help of the wraith of ABE no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>唐人は挙句の果てには食事を断って真備を殺そうとするが、真備が双六の道具によって日月を封じたため、驚いた唐人は真備を釈放した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tang men finally tried to kill Makibi by not feeding him, but Makibi hid the sun and the moon with a tool of sugoroku (a Japanese cardboard game), which startled the Tang men so much that they decided to release Makibi.</e>
<cmt>http://douman.fc2web.com/harima1/kibinyutou.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tang men finally tried to kill Makibi by not feeding him, but Makibi hid the sun and the moon with a tool of sugoroku (a Japanese cardboard game), which startled the Tang men so much that they decided to release Makibi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tang men finally tried to kill Makibi by not feeding him, but Makibi hid the sun and the moon with a tool of sugoroku (a Japanese cardboard game), which startled the Tang men so much that they decided to release Makibi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>真備が長期間にわたって唐に留まることになったのは、玄宗 (唐)がその才を惜しんで帰国させなかったためともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another interpretation of the legend that Makibi was kept to stay in Tang for a long period of time because he was so smart that Genso (the sixth Emperor of Tang) did not want him to leave Tang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another interpretation of the legend that Makibi was kept to stay in Tang for a long period of time because he was so smart that Genso (the sixth Emperor of Tang) did not want him to leave Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another interpretation of the legend that Makibi was kept to stay in Tang for a long period of time because he was so smart that Genso (the sixth Emperor of Tang) did not want him to leave Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>真備は、袁晋卿（後の浄村宿禰）という音韻学に長けた少年を連れて帰朝したが、藤原長親によれば、この浄村宿禰という人物は、呉音だった漢字の読み方を漢音に改めようと努め、片仮名を作ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makibi came back with a young man called EN Shinkei (later called, KIYOMURA no Sukune) who mastered phonology, and according to FUJIWARA no Nagazane, KIYOMURA no Sukene tried to change the reading of kanji (Chinese characters) from the Wu reading to the Han reading, which is said to have contributed to the creation of katakana (one of the Japanese syllables).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makibi came back with a young man called EN Shinkei (later called, KIYOMURA no Sukune) who mastered phonology, and according to FUJIWARA no Nagazane, KIYOMURA no Sukene tried to change the reading of kanji (Chinese characters) from the Wu reading to the Han reading, which is said to have contributed to the creation of katakana (one of the Japanese syllables).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makibi came back with a young man called EN Shinkei (later called, KIYOMURA no Sukune) who mastered phonology, and according to FUJIWARA no Nagazane, KIYOMURA no Sukene tried to change the reading of kanji (Chinese characters) from the Wu reading to the Han reading, which is said to have contributed to the creation of katakana (one of the Japanese syllables).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、帰路では当時の日本で神獣とされていた九尾の狐も同船していたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that Kyubi no kitsune (a fox having nine tails), a divine legendary beast in Japan, was on board the ship back to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that Kyubi no kitsune (a fox having nine tails), a divine legendary beast in Japan, was on board the ship back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that Kyubi no kitsune (a fox having nine tails), a divine legendary beast in Japan, was on board the ship back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>中世の兵法書などでは、張良が持っていたという『六韜』の兵法を持ち来たらしたとして、真備を日本の兵法の祖とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the military strategy book of the Medieval Period, Makibi was praised as a founder of the Japanese art of warfare for his achievement to bring back &quot;Rikuto (an ancient Chinese strategy book)&quot; which was possessed by Choryo (a politician and a war strategist in early China).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the military strategy book of the Medieval Period, Makibi was praised as a founder of the Japanese art of warfare for his achievement to bring back &quot;Rikuto&quot; (an ancient Chinese strategy book) which was possessed by Choryo (a politician and a war strategist in early China).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the military strategy book of the Medieval Period, Makibi was praised as a founder of the Japanese art of warfare for his achievement to bring back &quot;Rikuto&quot; (an ancient Chinese strategy book) which was possessed by Choryo (a politician and a war strategist in early China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="37">
<j>また、吉備真備は、陰陽道の聖典『ほき内伝』を唐から持ち帰り、常陸国筑波山麓で阿倍仲麻呂の子孫に伝えようとしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that KIBI no Makibi brought home &quot;Hoki-Naiden&quot;, a scripture of Onmyodo (an occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), from Tang, and tried to hand it down to the descendants of ABE no Nakamaro at the foot of Mt. Tsukuba of Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that KIBI no Makibi brought home &quot;Hoki-Naiden&quot;, a scripture of Onmyodo (an occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), from Tang, and tried to hand it down to the descendants of ABE no Nakamaro at the foot of Mt. Tsukuba of Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that KIBI no Makibi brought home &quot;Hoki-Naiden&quot;, a scripture of Onmyodo (an occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements), from Tang, and tried to hand it down to the descendants of ABE no Nakamaro at the foot of Mt. Tsukuba of Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>金烏は日（太陽）、玉兎は月のことで「陰陽」を表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kinu&quot; (a gold bird with three legs, which is believed to be living in the sun) indicates the sun and &quot;Gyokuto&quot; (a rabbit, which is believed to be living in the moon) means the moon and the two elements comprise &apos;yin-yang&apos;.</e>
<cmt>http://www5e.biglobe.ne.jp/~occultyo/touyou/kintogyokuu.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kinu&quot; (a gold bird with three legs, which is believed to be living in the sun) indicates the sun and &quot;Gyokuto&quot; (a rabbit, which is believed to be living in the moon) means the moon and the two elements comprise &apos;yin-yang&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kinu&quot; (a gold bird with three legs, which is believed to be living in the sun) indicates the sun and &quot;Gyokuto&quot; (a rabbit, which is believed to be living in the moon) means the moon and the two elements comprise &apos;yin-yang&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>安倍晴明は、阿部仲麻呂の一族の子孫とされるが、『金烏玉兎集』は安倍晴明が用いた陰陽道の秘伝書として、鎌倉時代末期か室町時代初期に作られた書とみられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ABE no Seimei is said to have been a descendant of the ABE no Nakamaro family, and &quot;Kinu Gyokuto shu&quot; (aka. Hoki-Naiden), which is believed to be used by ABE no Seimei as a book of secrets of Onmyodo, is said to be compiled in the end of the Kamakura Period or early Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>http://www5e.biglobe.ne.jp/~occultyo/touyou/kintogyokuu.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ABE no Seimei is said to have been a descendant of the ABE no Nakamaro family, and &quot;Kinu Gyokuto shu&quot; (aka. Hoki-Naiden), which is believed to have been used by ABE no Seimei as a book of secrets of Onmyodo, is said to have been compiled in the end of the Kamakura Period or early Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ABE no Seimei is said to have been a descendant of the ABE no Nakamaro family, and &quot;Kinu Gyokuto shu&quot; (aka. Hoki-Naiden), which is believed to have been used by ABE no Seimei as a book of secrets of Onmyodo, is said to have been compiled in the end of the Kamakura Period or early Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>伝説によると、中国の伯道上人という仙人が、文殊菩薩に弟子入りをして悟りを開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one legend, Hakudo shonin, an immortal mountain wizard of China, became a disciple of Monju Bosatsu (Manjusri Bodhisattva associated with wisdom, doctrine and awareness) and reached enlightenment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one legend, Hakudo shonin, an immortal mountain wizard of China, became a disciple of Monju Bosatsu (Manjusri Bodhisattva associated with wisdom, doctrine and awareness) and reached enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one legend, Hakudo shonin, an immortal mountain wizard of China, became a disciple of Monju Bosatsu (Manjusri Bodhisattva associated with wisdom, doctrine and awareness) and reached enlightenment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>このときに文殊菩薩から授けられたという秘伝書『文殊結集仏暦経』を中国に持ち帰ったが、その書が『金烏玉兎集』であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Hakudo shonin was given from Monju Bosatsu a book of secrets called &quot;Monju Ketsuju Butsureki kyo&quot;, and brought it back to China, and &quot;Monju Ketsuju Butsureki kyo&quot; is said to be &quot;Kinu Gyokuto shu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Hakudo shonin was given from Monju Bosatsu a book of secrets called &quot;Monju Ketsuju Butsureki kyo&quot;, and brought it back to China, and &quot;Monju Ketsuju Butsureki kyo&quot; is said to be &quot;Kinu Gyokuto shu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Hakudo shonin was given from Monju Bosatsu a book of secrets called &quot;Monju Ketsuju Butsureki kyo&quot;, and brought it back to China, and &quot;Monju Ketsuju Butsureki kyo&quot; is said to be &quot;Kinu Gyokuto shu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その他、『今昔物語集』では、玄昉を殺害した藤原広嗣の霊を真備が陰陽道の術で鎮めたとし、『刃辛抄』では、陰陽書『刃辛内伝』を持ち来たらしたとして、真備を日本の陰陽道の祖としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past) describes that Makibi used Onmyodo to appease the raging spirit of FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu who killed Genbo, while in &quot;Hoki sho&quot;, Makibi was regarded as a founder of Japanese Onmyodo, as he brought the Onmyo book &quot;Hoki Naiden&quot; to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past) describes that Makibi used Onmyodo to appease the raging spirit of FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu who killed Genbo, while in &quot;Hoki sho&quot;, Makibi was regarded as a founder of Japanese Onmyodo, as he brought the Onmyo book &quot;Hoki Naiden&quot; to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, &quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past) describes that Makibi used Onmyodo to appease the raging spirit of FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu who killed Genbo, while in &quot;Hoki sho&quot;, Makibi was regarded as a founder of Japanese Onmyodo, as he brought the Onmyo book &quot;Hoki Naiden&quot; to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="43">
<j>『宇治拾遺物語』では、他人の夢を盗んで自分のものとし、そのために右大臣まで登ったという説話もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji), Makibi is described as a person who stole an ambitious dream of someone else, and for which, he could move up the promotional ladder to Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>http://www51.tok2.com/home/sendatakayuki/bungei/bungei15.html上記ウェブに、「夢占い師から夢を買った」と書かれています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji), Makibi is described as a person who stole an ambitious dream of someone else, and for which, he could move up the promotional ladder to Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji), Makibi is described as a person who stole an ambitious dream of someone else, and for which, he could move up the promotional ladder to Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>書家として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Calligrapher</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Calligrapher</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Calligrapher</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>在唐中、書は張旭に学び、帰朝後、晋 (王朝)唐の書道を弘めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his stay in Tang, Makibi learned Chinese writing from Chokyoku, and spread the calligraphy which originated in Jin (a dynasty of China) across Japan after his return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his stay in Tang, Makibi learned Chinese writing from Chokyoku, and spread the calligraphy which originated in Jin (a dynasty of China) across Japan after his return.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his stay in Tang, Makibi learned Chinese writing from Chokyoku, and spread the calligraphy which originated in Jin (a dynasty of China) across Japan after his return.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>古筆中に、虫喰切、南部の焼切が現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味不明のため訳出できていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 下道東薗桜(id:70079), Bakkai(id:7233), ととりん(id:31982), Wiki0825(id:34646), ノトス(id:42992), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Hannah(id:15935), 松茸(id:27535), 二八(id:10408), MIO(id:31681), Zerozeros(id:189962), VanishingDuck(id:125995), 味っ子(id:17086), Yanahan(id:2437), Tarach(id:163323), Snap55(id:89773), LiDaobing(id:14511), Silver river(id:920), OSY(id:35563), 赤井彗星(id:18381), VolkovBot(id:105371), Mooko(id:36162), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 代言人(id:33675), UMBRO(id:100484), Wabisabix(id:16770), 匿名内緒(id:266295), 岡部碩道(id:182846), LERK(id:4460), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>