<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>加納鷲雄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Washio KANO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Washio KANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Washio KANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>加納鷲雄（かのう わしお、天保10年11月9日 (旧暦)（1839年12月14日） - 明治35年（1902年）10月27日）は、新選組の隊士、伍長で、のち御陵衛士（高台寺党）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Washio KANO (December 14, 1839 - October 27, 1902) was an officer and corporal of Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party and later, became Goryo-eshi (guardians of Imperial mausoleums) (Kodaiji-to party.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Washio KANO (December 14, 1839 - October 27, 1902) was an officer and corporal of the Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party; he later became Goryo-eshi (guardians of Imperial mausoleums) (Kodaiji-to party).</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Washio KANO (December 14, 1839 - October 27, 1902) was an officer and corporal of the Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party; he later became a member of Goryo-eji (guardians of Imperial mausoleums) party (Kodaiji-to party).</e>
<cmt>御陵衛士は、組織の名前なのでparty をつけました。eshi→eji</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>加納道之助ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Michinosuke KANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as Michinosuke KANO.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as Michinosuke KANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>伊豆国出身で流派は北辰一刀流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from Izu-no-kuni, and Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school was his style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from Izu-no-kuni, and his martial style was Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from Izu Province, and his martial style was Hokushin Itto-ryu kendo school.</e>
<cmt>北辰一刀流→Hokushin Itto-ryu kendo school</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>旧名伊豆太郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His former name was Taro IZU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His was formerly known as Taro IZU.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His was formerly known as Taro IZU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>維新後は加納通広（かのう みちひろ）と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, he identified himself as Michihiro KANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration he identified himself as Michihiro KANO.</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration he identified himself as Michihiro KANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>天保10年（1839年）、伊豆国賀茂郡加納村に高野伴平の長男として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1839, he was born as the 1st son of Bampei TAKANO in Kano-mura, Kamo-gun, Izu-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1839, he was born as the first son of Bampei TAKANO in Kano-mura, Kamo-gun, Izu-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1839, he was born as the first son of Bampei TAKANO in Kano Village, Kamo County, Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>地名表記の変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>若くして江戸に出、深川佐賀町にあった北辰一刀流伊東道場に入門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Edo at a young age to enter Ito Dojo training hall for Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school located in Fukagawa-saga-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to Edo at a young age to enter the Ito Dojo training hall for Hokushin-Ittoryu Kobudo school located in Fukagawa-saga-cho.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to Edo at a young age to enter the Ito kendo training hall for Hokushin Itto-ryu kendo school located in Fukagawa-saga Town.</e>
<cmt>北辰一刀流→Hokushin Itto-ryu kendo school地名表記の変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>塾頭伊東甲子太郎（後の甲子太郎）に師事し、一方で、篠原泰之進と共に窪田治部右衛門の神奈川奉行所勤務に随行し、横浜市外国人居留地の警備の任にもついていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied under Kinetaro ITO (later, Kinetaro) as a school manager, and on other hand, with Tainoshin SHINOHARA, he went to Kanagawa Magistrate&apos;s office where Jibu&apos;uemon KUBOTA was working to be on a security mission for Yokohama City&apos;s Enclave for foreign residents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under Kinetaro ITO (later, Kinetaro) as a school manager, while also working with Tainoshin SHINOHARA at the Kanagawa Magistrate&apos;s office (also where Jibu&apos;uemon KUBOTA worked) on security for Yokohama City&apos;s Enclave for foreign residents.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under Kinetaro ITO (later, Kinetaro), the school manager, while also working with Tainoshin SHINOHARA at the Kanagawa Magistrate&apos;s office (also where Jibu&apos;uemon KUBOTA worked) on security for Yokohama City&apos;s Enclave for foreign residents.</e>
<cmt>原文で、甲子太郎が2度出てくるが、意味不明as a school manager→, the school manager,</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>元治元年（1864年）10月、伊東らと新選組の隊士募集に応じて上洛し、入隊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1864, he went to Kyoto to apply for the recruiting of officers of Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party with ITOH and succeeded in getting the position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1864, he went to Kyoto and successfully applied for the position to recruit officers of the Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party with ITOH and succeeded in getting the position.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1864, he went to Kyoto and applied for the position of members of the Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party with ITO and succeeded in getting the position.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に従い、修正。ITOH→ITO</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌年春の組織再編で伍長となったが、慶応3年（1867年）三月に伊東を盟主として結成された御陵衛士（高台寺党）に参加し、新選組を離脱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a corporal upon an organizational restructuring in spring of the following year, but in March 1867, he left Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party to join Goryo-eshi (Kodaiji-to party) which was organized by ITOH as its leader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a corporal upon an organizational restructuring in spring of the following year; but, in March 1867, he left Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party to join the Goryo-eshi (Kodaiji-to party)--organized by ITOH, its leader.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a corporal upon an organizational restructuring in spring of the following year; but, in April 1867, he left Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party to join the Goryo-eji party (Kodaiji-to party)--organized by ITO, its leader.</e>
<cmt>御陵衛士→the Goryo-eji partyITOH→ITOグレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年11月に伊東が新選組によって暗殺された油小路事件では難を逃れて脱出に成功し、薩摩藩邸に保護される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of the same year, he was successful about escaping troubles in the Abura-no-koji Incident in which ITO was assassinated by Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party, and was sheltered at Satsuma-Hantei (Satsuma domain&apos;s residence maintained by a daimyo in Edo.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, he successfully avoided trouble in the Abura-no-koji Incident, which involved the assassination of ITO by the Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party, and was sheltered at Satsuma-Hantei (Satsuma domain&apos;s residence maintained by a daimyo in Edo).</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the same year, he successfully avoided trouble in the Abura-no-koji Incident, which involved the assassination of ITO by the Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party, and was sheltered at Satsuma-Hantei (Satsuma domain&apos;s residence maintained by a daimyo in Edo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同年12月18日、篠原泰之進ら御陵衛士残党とともに油小路事件の報復として、伏見街道で近藤勇を襲撃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 18 of the same year, he assaulted Isami KONDO on Fushimi-kaido Road together with Tainoshin SHINOHARA and other rump of Goryo-eshi (guardians of Imperial mausoleums) to retaliate against the Abura-no-koji Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 18 of the same year, he assaulted Isami KONDO on Fushimi-kaido Road together with Tainoshin SHINOHARA and the others of the Goryo-eshi (guardians of Imperial mausoleums) to retaliate against him for his involvement in the Abura-no-koji Incident.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 12, 1868, he assaulted Isami KONDO on Fushimi-kaido Road together with Tainoshin SHINOHARA and the others of the Goryo-eji (guardians of Imperial mausoleums) party to retaliate against him for his involvement in the Abura-no-koji Incident.</e>
<cmt>御陵衛士→the Goryo-eji party</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>慶応4年（1868年）正月の鳥羽伏見の戦いから始まる戊辰戦争では、赤報隊を経て薩摩軍に属して戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Boshin War triggered by the Battle of Toba and Fushimi occurred around New Year&apos;s Days of 1868, he fought battles belonging to Sekihotai Army and then Satsuma army. On April 4 of the same year when he was in Itabashi camp, found Isami KONDO who was disguised to attempt to escape from among the soldiers of the Bakufu army who surrendered themselves to the government forces in Shimousa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Boshin War, which began with the Battle of Toba and Fushimi around the New Year&apos;s of 1868, he fought battles along with the Sekihotai Army and then the Satsuma army. On April 4 of the same year when he was in Itabashi camp he discovered Isami KONDO, who was disguised in an attempt to escape from among the soldiers of the Bakufu army who surrendered themselves to the government forces in Shimousa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Boshin War, which began with the Battle of Toba and Fushimi in January 1868, he fought battles along with the Sekihotai Army and then the Satsuma army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処原文を分割。around the New Year&apos;s of→in January</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同年4月4日、板橋在陣中に下総国で官軍に投降した幕軍の者から偽装して逃亡しようとする近藤勇を見つける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 26 of the same year when he was in Itabashi camp he discovered Isami KONDO, who was disguised in an attempt to run away, among the soldiers of the Bakufu army who surrendered themselves to the government forces in Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処原文の内容に合わせて修正。下総国→Shimosa Provinceグレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>坂本龍馬を殺した犯人と最後まで思い込んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became obsessed with the idea that Isami KONDO was an offender who killed Ryoma SAKAMOTO to the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He carried to his grave an obsession with the idea that Isami KONDO was the man who killed Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He carried to his grave an obsession with the idea that Isami KONDO was the man who killed Ryoma SAKAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>明治維新後は開拓使、農商務省 (日本)などで働き、明治35年（1902年）10月に東京府麻布の自宅で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, he worked as a Hokkaido Development Commissioner, at the No-Shomusho (Agriculture and Commerce Department) (Japan), etc. and in October 1902, died in his residence in Azabu, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, he worked as a Hokkaido Development Commissioner, at the No-Shomusho (Agriculture and Commerce Department) (Japan) etc., and in October 1902, died in his residence in Azabu, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, he worked as a Hokkaido Development Commissioner, at the No-Shomusho (Agriculture and Commerce Department) (Japan) etc., and in October 1902, died in his residence in Azabu, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>享年64。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ZassouTori(id:136771), 上田隼人(id:23104), Cprobot(id:97843), 土方　誠(id:3651), Safkan(id:423), Maakun(id:16735), Corwin(id:973), Junger(id:10282), Micchi(id:47881), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>