<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原公成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinnari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kinnari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinnari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 公成（ふじわら の きんなり 長保元年(999年) - 長久4年6月24日 (旧暦)(1043年8月1日)）は、平安時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinnari (999 - August 1, 1043) was a court noble in the Heisan period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kinnari (999 - August 1, 1043) was a court noble in the Heisan period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinnari (999 - August 1, 1043) was a court noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「数字不一致確認済み」Heisan→Heian</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家閑院流の流れをつくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was part of the Kanin lineage (閑院流) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was part of the Kanin lineage (閑院流) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was part of the Kanin lineage of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>漢字削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中納言藤原実成の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Chunagon (Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Sanenari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of Chunagon (Middle Counselor) FUJIWARA no Sanenari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Sanenari.</e>
<cmt>中納言の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は藤原陳政の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Chinsei&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was FUJIWARA no Chinsei&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Chinsei&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従二位、参議、権中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank), and the titles of Sangi (Royal Advisor) and Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank), and the titles of Sangi (Royal Advisor) and Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank), and the titles of Sangi (Royal Advisor) and Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>「数字不一致確認済み」権中納言の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>滋野井別当と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also used a self-given alternative name of Betto SHIGENOI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also used a self-given alternate name of Betto SHIGENOI.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also used a self-given alternate name of Betto SHIGENOI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子に藤原実季、藤原茂子、頼忍らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among his children were FUJIWARA no Sanesue, FUJIWARA no Shigeko, and Yorishinobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his children were FUJIWARA no Sanesue, FUJIWARA no Shigeko, and Yorishinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among his children were FUJIWARA no Sanesue, FUJIWARA no Shigeko, and Yorishinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>幼名は犬君。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Inugimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Inugimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Inugimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幼くして祖父である太政大臣藤原公季の養子となり、その溺愛を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by his grandfather, Grand Minisiter FUJIWARA no Kinsue, at an early age, and was excessively loved by him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by his grandfather, Grand Minisiter FUJIWARA no Kinsue, at an early age, and was excessively loved by him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by his grandfather, Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Kinsue, at an early age, and was excessively loved by him.</e>
<cmt>太政大臣の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>公季は公の行事にあたっても常に公成を同道し、また皇太子敦良親王（後の後朱雀天皇）に対しても痛切に公成の引き立てを懇願したといわれ、その様子は親王から些か滑稽に思われる程だったと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinsue is said to have always had Kinnari accompany him, even to his official events, and entreated Imperial Prince Atsunaga (later Emperor Go-Suzaku) for his favor on his behalf so passionately that the Prince found it rather laughable.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinsue is said to have always had Kinnari accompany him, even to his official events, and entreated Imperial Prince Atsunaga (later Emperor Go-Suzaku) for his favor on his behalf so passionately that the Prince found it rather laughable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinsue is said to have always had Kinnari accompany him, even to his official events, and entreated Crown Prince Atsunaga (later Emperor Gosuzaku) for his favor on his behalf so passionately that the Prince found it rather laughable.</e>
<cmt>Imperial→CrownGo-Suzaku→Gosuzaku左記の訳文に合わせて、原文を一文に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>寛弘8年(1011年)侍従、長和2年(1013年)右少将、寛仁元年(1017年)右中将、同4年(1021年)蔵人頭、治安 (元号)3年(1023年)左中将、万寿3年(1026年)に参議を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as a Chamberlain in 1011, as a Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1013, as a Uchujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1017, as a Kurodo no To (Director of the Sovereign&apos;s Secretaries) in 1021, as a Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1023, and as a Sangi (Royal Advisor) in 1026.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as a Chamberlain in 1011, as a Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1013, as a Uchujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1017, as a Kurodo no To (Director of the Sovereign&apos;s Secretaries) in 1021, as a Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1023, and as a Sangi (Royal Advisor) in 1026.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as a Chamberlain in 1011, as a Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1013, as a Uchujo (Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1017, as a Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1021, as a Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) in 1023, and as a Sangi in 1026.</e>
<cmt>「数字不一致確認済み」蔵人頭の定訳参議、既出のため説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>公成自身の最高位は従二位権中納言であったが、娘の茂子が大納言藤原能信の養女として後三条天皇の妃となり白河天皇を産んだことを契機に、後世において閑院流は大いに繁栄し、大臣を輩出する家柄となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the highest rank Kinnari held was Junii (Junior Second Rank), the fact that his daughter Shigeko, who was adopted by Major Counselor FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu, became Emperor Go-Sanjo&apos;s wife and Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s mother triggered the great prosperity of the Kanin lineage in later years, and his family line came to turn out many ministers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the highest rank Kinnari held was Junii (Junior Second Rank), his daughter Shigeko, who was adopted by Major Counselor FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu, became Emperor Go-Sanjo&apos;s wife and Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s mother triggered the great prosperity of the Kanin lineage in later years, and his family line came to turn out many ministers.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the highest rank Kinnari held was Junii Gon Chunagon, his daughter Shigeko, who was adopted by Dainagon (chief councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu, became Emperor Go-Sanjo&apos;s wife and Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s mother triggered the great prosperity of the Kanin lineage in later years, and his family line came to turn out many ministers.</e>
<cmt>権中納言追記従二位、説明削除大納言の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>小式部内侍と恋愛関係にあった時期があり、間に一子頼忍を儲けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a period of time he was in love with KOSHIKIBU no Naishi, and had a daughter Yorishinobu with her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a period of time he was in love with KOSHIKIBU no Naishi, and had a daughter Yorishinobu with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a period of time he was in love with Koshikibu no Naishi, and had a daughter Yorishinobu with her.</e>
<cmt>KOSHIKIBU→Koshikibu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), BAKU(id:55205), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>