<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本居宣長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga MOTOORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本居 宣長（もとおり のりなが、1730年6月21日(享保15年5月7日 (旧暦)) - 1801年11月5日(享和元年9月29日 (旧暦))）は、江戸時代日本の国学者・文献学者・医師である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI (June 21, 1730 - November 5, 1801) was a scholar of Japanese classical culture/ literature as well as a physician in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga MOTOORI (June 21, 1730 - November 5, 1801) was a scholar of Japanese classical culture and literature, as well as a physician, in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI (June 21, 1730 - November 5, 1801) was a scholar of Japanese classical culture and literature, as well as a physician, in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は栄貞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child name was Yoshisada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Yoshisada.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Yoshisada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は瞬庵、春庵（しゅんあん）、鈴屋大人（すずのやのうし）と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Shunan and Suzunoya no Ushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his common names were Shunan and Suzunoya no Ushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his nicknames were Shunan and Suzunoya no Ushi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>当時、既に解読不能に陥っていた『古事記』の解読に成功し、『古事記伝』を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded in deciphering &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The records of Ancient Matters), which was then undecipherable, and wrote &quot;Kojikiden&quot; (Commentaries on Kojiki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded in deciphering &quot;Kojiki (Records of Ancient Matters),&quot; which was then undecipherable, and wrote &quot;Kojikiden (Commentaries on Kojiki).&quot;</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded in deciphering Records of Ancient Matters &quot;Kojiki&quot;, which was then undecipherable, and wrote Commentaries on Kojiki &quot;Kojikiden&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>紀州徳川家に「玉くしげ別本」の中で寛刑主義をすすめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his book &quot;Tamakushige Beppon&quot;, he recommended Kishu Tokugawa family to adopt the policy of lenient punishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his book &quot;Tamakushige Beppon,&quot; he recommended that the Kishu Tokugawa family adopt the policy of lenient punishment.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his book &quot;Tamakushige Beppon&quot;, he recommended that the Kishu Tokugawa family adopt the policy of lenient punishment.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>本居宣長は1730年6月伊勢国松坂（現在の三重県松阪市）の木綿商である小津家の次男として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI was born in June 1730 as the second son of Ozu family which was a cotton merchant in Matsuzaka, Ise Province (Matsuzaka City, Mie Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga MOTOORI was born in June 1730 as the second son of the Ozu family, who were cotton merchants in Matsuzaka, Ise Province (Matsuzaka City, Mie Province).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga MOTOORI was born in June 1730 as the second son of the Ozu family, who were cotton merchants in Matsuzaka, Ise Province (present Matsuzaka City, Mie Province).</e>
<cmt>現在の、を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幼名は富之助。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child name was Tominosuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Tominosuke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Tominosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>16歳の時(1748年)江戸に商売の勉強の為に叔父の店で働くが、本を読めぬ生活を嫌い帰郷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to his uncle&apos;s store in Edo when he was 16 years old (1748) for the purpose of studying commerce, but he returned to his birth place because he didn&apos;t like the life in which he couldn&apos;t read books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to his uncle&apos;s store in Edo when he was 16 years old (1748) for the purpose of studying commerce, but he returned to his birthplace because he didn&apos;t like the life in which he couldn&apos;t read books.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to his uncle&apos;s store in Edo when he was 16 years old (1748) for the purpose of studying commerce, but he returned to his birthplace because he did not have any time to do reading and hated such life.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当時の江戸までの道中の地図資料のいい加減なところから、「山川海島悉く図する」資料集の『大日本天下四海画図』を起筆した（宝暦1年(1752)12月上旬に書写作業完了）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he found the then available root maps to Edo were sloppy, he compiled the collection of material named &quot; Dainihon tenka shikai gazu&quot; (a map of Japan) (he completed its transcription in early December), which, according to him, &quot;covered all mountains, rivers, seas and islands&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he found that the available root maps to Edo were sloppy, he compiled the collection of materials called &quot;Dainihon tenka shikai gazu&quot; (a map of Japan) (he completed its transcription in early December), which, he stated, &quot;covered all the mountains, rivers, seas and islands.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he found that the available root maps to Edo were sloppy, he compiled a collection of materials called &quot;Dainihon tenka shikai gazu&quot; (he completed its transcription in January, 1752), which, he stated, &apos;covered all the mountains, rivers, seas and islands.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。early December→January（グレゴリオ歴）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その意図について、「城下船津名所遺跡其方角を改め在所を分明にし道中の行程駅をみさいに是を記す」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He mentioned about his intention for the above as &quot;to amend and clarify the location of castle towns, port towns, famous places and historic sites and to show the roots and post stations in detail&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He described his intention in the above as being &quot;to amend and clarify the location of castle towns, port towns, famous places and historical sites, and to show the routes and post stations in detail.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He described his intention in the above as being &apos;to amend and clarify the location of castle towns, port towns, famous places and historical sites, and to show routes and post stations in detail.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>また1748年に江戸より帰郷後、京都へ初めて神社参詣の為に上る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1748, after returned from Edo, he went to Kyoto for the first time in order to worship shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1748, once he had returned from Edo, he went to Kyoto for the first time in order to worship at shrines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1748, once he had returned from Edo, he went to Kyoto to worship at shrines which was his first trip to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この時の見聞を元に、自分用の資料として「都考抜書（とこうばっしょ）」を延享3年(1746年)より起筆（宝暦元年（1751年）ころまで書き継がれた）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the information obtained at that time, he started to write &quot;Toko Bassho&quot; in 1746 as his own material (he continued to write until around 1751).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the information then obtained, he started writing &quot;Toko Bassho&quot; in 1746 as an original work (he continued the writing until about 1751).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the information then obtained, he started writing &quot;Toko Bassho&quot; in 1746 as an original work (he continued the writing until about 1751).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>兄が死んだ後、その小津家を継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He suceeded the Ozu family after his elder brother&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded the Ozu family upon the death of his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded the Ozu family upon the death of his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そして、22歳になったとき、医学の修行のため京都へ遊学した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was 22 years old, he went to Kyoto in order to study medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was 22 years old, he went to Kyoto in order to study medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was 22 years old, he went to Kyoto in order to study medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>京では医学を堀元厚・武川幸順に学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, he learned medicine from Genko HORI and Kojun TAKEKAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, he studied medicine under Genko HORI and Kojun TAKEKAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, he studied medicine under Genko HORI and Kojun TAKEKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、儒学を朱子学者の堀景山に師事し、寄宿して漢学や国学などを学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also studied Sinology and Japanese classical culture under Keizan HORI, a Neo-Confucian scholar, while lodging at his house.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also studied Sinology and Japanese classical culture under Keizan HORI, a Neo-Confucian scholar, while lodging at his house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied Confucianism under Keizan HORI, a Neo-Confucian scholar, and also studied Sinology and Japanese classical culture while lodging at his house.</e>
<cmt>儒学を、を補足し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この頃から日本固有の古典学に身を入れるようになり、荻生徂徠や契沖に影響を受け、国学の道に入ることを志す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around that time, he started to devote himself in the study of Japanese indigenous culture/literature and, affected by Sorai OGYU and Keichu, set on his mind to become a scholar of the study of Japanese classical culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At about that time, he began to devote himself to the study of Japanese indigenous culture and literature; moreover, influenced by Sorai OGYU and Keichu, he decided that he would become a scholar of Japanese classical culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this period, he began to devote himself to the study of the classics of Japanese indigenous culture and literature; moreover, influenced by Sorai OGYU and Keichu, he decided that he would become a scholar of Japanese ancient culture and literature.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その京都での生活に感化され、王朝文化の憧れを強めていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the influence of the life in Kyoto, his longing for the cultures of the dynasty age increasingly intensified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the influence of the life in Kyoto, his longing for the cultures of the dynastic age became more intense.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the influence of that life in Kyoto, he longered for the cultures of the dynastic age more intensely.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>松坂に帰った宣長は医師を開業し、そのかたわら『源氏物語』の講義や『日本書紀』の研究に励んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returned to Matsuzaka, he started to practice as a doctor while lecturing &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (Tale of Genji) and studying &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon returning to Matsuzaka, he started to practice as a doctor while lecturing on &quot;Genji Monogatari (Tale of Genji)&quot; and studying &quot;Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he returned to Matsuzaka, he started to practice medicine while lecturing on Tale of Genji &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot;and studying Chronicles of Japan &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>27歳の時、『先代旧事本紀』と『古事記』を書店で購入し、賀茂真淵の書に出会って国学の研究に入ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was 27 years old, he bought &quot;Sendai Kyujihongi&quot; (Ancient Japanese History) and &quot;Kojiki&quot;, read Kamo no Mabuch&apos;s book and started to study Japanese classical culture in earnest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was 27 years old, he bought &quot;Sendai Kyujihongi (Ancient Japanese History)&quot; and &quot;Kojiki,&quot; read Kamo no Mabuchi&apos;s book, and started studying Japanese classical culture in earnest.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was 27 years old, he bought &quot;Sendai Kyujihongi&quot; and &quot;Kojiki&quot;, read KAMO no Mabuchi&apos;s book, and started studying Japanese classical culture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>1763年（宝暦13年）5月25日(旧暦)、宣長は、松阪を来訪した真淵に初見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On may 25, 1763 (lunar calendar), he met Mabuchi, who visited Matsuzaka, for the first time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On may 25, 1763 (lunar calendar), he met Mabuchi, who was visiting Matsuzaka, for the first time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 5, 1763, he met Mabuchi, who was visiting Matsuzaka, for the first time.</e>
<cmt>西暦に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そして、かねてから志していた古事記の注釈について、指導を願うのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking this opportunity, he asked for Mabuchi&apos;s instruction about the commentaries of Kojiki which he had set on his mind to study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking this opportunity, he asked for Mabuchi&apos;s instruction regarding the commentaries of Kojiki, which he had decided to study.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking this opportunity, he asked for Mabuchi&apos;s instruction regarding the commentaries of Kojiki, which he had decided to study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>真淵は、万葉仮名に慣れるため、『万葉集』の注釈から始めた方が良いという旨の教授をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mabuchi instructed him to begin with the commentaries on &quot;Manyo-shu&quot; (Collection of Ten Thousands Leaves) in order to become familiar with Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in Manyo-shu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mabuchi instructed him to begin with the commentaries on &quot;Manyo-shu (Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves)&quot; in order to become familiar with Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in Manyo-shu).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mabuchi instructed him to begin with the commentaries on the oldest existing collection of Japanese poetry &quot;Manyoshu&quot; in order to become familiar with a form of syllabary used in the Manyoshu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>以後、真淵に触発されて『古事記』の本格的な研究に進むことを決意した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prompted by Mabuchi, he made up his mind to study Kojiki in earnest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prompted by Mabuchi, he made up his mind to study Kojiki in earnest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prompted by Mabuchi, he made up his mind to study &quot;Kojiki&quot; earnestly.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この真淵との出会いは、宣長の図随筆集『玉勝間』に収められている「おのが物まなびの有りしより」と「あがたゐのうしの御さとし言」という文章に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above encounter with Mabuchi was described in his essays &quot;The history of my studying&quot; and &quot;The instruction of my mentor&quot;, which were compiled in &quot;Tamakatsuma&quot; (collection of essays).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above encounter with Mabuchi was described in his essays &quot;The History of My Study&quot; and &quot;The Instructions of My Mentor,&quot; which were compiled in &quot;Tamakatsuma&quot; (a collection of essays).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above encounter with Mabuchi was described in his essays &apos;The History of My Study&apos; and &apos;The Instructions of My Mentor,&apos; which were compiled in a collection of essays &quot;Tamakatsuma&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この二つの文章から再構成された宣長と真淵との出会いは、「松阪の一夜」として戦前期の『小学国語読本』に掲載された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scene of Norinaga&apos;s encounter with Mabuchi which was reconstructed based on these two essays was named &quot;A night in Matsuzaka&quot; and appeared in the &quot;textbook for elementary school children&quot; used in the pre-war era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scene of Norinaga&apos;s encounter with Mabuchi, which was reconstructed based on these two essays, was called &quot;A Night in Matsuzaka&quot; and appeared in the &quot;textbook for elementary school children&quot; used in the pre-war era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Norinaga&apos;s encounter with Mabuchi, which was reconstructed based on these two essays, was called &apos;A Night in Matsuzaka&apos; and appeared in the Elementary School Japanese Reader &quot;Shogaku kokugo tokuhon&quot; used in the pre-war era.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>遺言に自分の墓のデザインを示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He designated by his will the design of his grave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He designated the design of his grave in his will.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He designated the design of his grave in his will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>昭和34年に松阪市内を見渡す小高い山（生前の宣長が好んだ場所とされる）へ移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave was removed in 1959 to a small hill from where we can glance over Matsuzaka City (a place Norinaga liked).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave was removed in 1959 to a small hill from where we can glance over Matsuzaka City (a place Norinaga liked).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave was moved in 1959 to a small hill from which Matsuzaka City, a place Norinaga liked, can be seen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>さらに平成11年には遺言のデザインに沿った「本居宣長奥津墓（城）」が建造された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, &quot;Norinaga MOTOORI Okutsu Grave (castle)&quot; was constructed in 1999 in accordance with the design designated by his will.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, &quot;Norinaga MOTOORI Okutsu Grave (castle)&quot; was constructed in 1999 in accordance with the design designated by his will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, &apos;Norinaga MOTOORI Grave&apos; was constructed in 1999 in accordance with the design designated in his will.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>思想</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Philosophy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Philosophy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Philosophy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>宣長の代表作には、約35年を費やして執筆された『古事記』註釈の集大成『古事記伝』や、『源氏物語』の注解『源氏物語玉の小櫛』、『玉勝間』などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most important work of Norinaga are &quot;Kojikiden&quot;, a book compiling commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; for which he spent about 35 years to write, &quot;Genji Monogatari Tama no Ogushi&quot;, commentaries on Genji Monogatari, and &quot;Tamakatsuma&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga&apos;s most important works are &quot;Kojikiden,&quot; a book compiling commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; that took him approximately 35 years to write; &quot;Genji Monogatari Tama no Ogushi,&quot; commentaries on Genji Monogatari; and &quot;Tamakatsuma.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga&apos;s most important works are &quot;Kojikiden,&quot; a book compiling commentaries on &quot;Kojiki&quot; that took approximately 35 years to write; &quot;Genji Monogatari Tama no Ogushi,&quot; commentaries on Genji Monogatari; and &quot;Tamakatsuma.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>日本固有の情緒「もののあはれ」が文学の本質であると提唱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He advocated that the substance of literature should be Japanese indigenous feelings of &quot;Mono no Aware&quot; (sensitivity to things).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He advocated that the substance of literature should be the Japanese indigenous feelings of &quot;Mono no Aware&quot; (sensitivity to things).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He advocated that the substance of literature should be the Japanese inherent feelings of &apos;Mono no Aware&apos;, sensitivity to things.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>大昔から脈々と伝わる自然情緒や精神を第一義とし、外来的な孔子の教え（「漢意」）を自然に背く考えであると非難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He emphasized natural feelings and spirit that had been inherited from the ancient times and criticized the imported teachings of Confucius (karagokoro (Chinese mindedness)) as the teachings that were contrary to nature.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He emphasized the natural feelings and spirit that had been inherited from the ancient times, and criticized the imported teachings of Confucius (karagokoro (Chinese-mindedness)) as teachings that were contrary to nature.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He emphasized the natural feelings and spirit that had been inherited from ancient times, and criticized the imported teachings of Confucius, i.e., Chinese-mindedness called &apos;karagokoro&apos;, as teachings that were contrary to nature.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>したがって、中華文明や思想を尊重する荻生徂徠を批判した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, he criticized Sorai OGYU who respected Chinese culture and philosophy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, he criticized Sorai OGYU, who respected Chinese culture and philosophy.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, he criticized Sorai OGYU, who respected Chinese culture and philosophy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、徂徠の学問の方法論である古文辞学からは多大な影響を受けていることも指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is also pointed out that he was greatly affected by Komonji-gaku (study of ancient words), Sorai&apos;s methodology of study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is also pointed out that he was greatly affected by Komonji-gaku (study of ancient words), Sorai&apos;s methodology of study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, it is also pointed out that he was greatly affected by Sorai&apos;s methodology of study, the study of ancient words.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>『古事記伝』の画期は、当時の人々に衝撃的に受け入れられ、やがて国学の源流を形成してゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kojikiden&quot; made an impact on people at the time and eventually became the origin of the study of the Japanese classical culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kojikiden&quot; had an impact on people of the age, and eventually it became the origin of the study of Japanese classical culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Epoch-making &quot;Kojikiden&quot; had an impact on people in those days, and eventually became the origin of the study of Japanese classical culture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>師・賀茂真淵との関係では「後によき考への出できたらんには、必ずしも師の説にたがふとて、なはばかりそ」と言い、師の教えを仰ぎながらも良いと適ったことは遠慮なく主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he asked Mabuchi&apos;s instruction, he insisted, without hesitation, what he believed to be right even against his mentor, saying &quot;If I have a good thought later, I will not necessarily follow my mentor&apos;s view&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he asked for Mabuchi&apos;s instruction, he insisted, without hesitation, that what he believed was right, even against his mentor, saying, &quot;If I have a good thought later, I won&apos;t necessarily follow my mentor&apos;s view.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he asked for Mabuchi&apos;s instruction, he insisted, without hesitation, that what he believed was right, even against his mentor, saying, &quot;If I have a good thought later, I would dare to state that even if that thought conflicts with my mentor&apos;s view.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>門下生として服部中庸・石塚龍麿・夏目甕麿（みかまろ）・長瀬真幸（まさき）・高林方朗（みちあきら）・小国重年・竹村尚規・横井千秋・代官の村田七右衛門(橋彦)春門父子・神主の坂倉茂樹・一見直樹・倉田実樹・白子昌平・植松有信・肥後の国、山鹿の天目一神社神官・帆足長秋・帆足京(みさと)父子・飛騨高山の田中大秀・本居春庭（宣長の実子）・本居大平（宣長の養子）などが在籍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had many disciples including Nakatsune HATTORI, Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA, Mikamaro NATSUME, Masaki NAGASE, Michiakira TAKABAYASHI, Shigetoshi OGUNI, Naonori TAKEMURA, Chiaki YOKOI, a local governor Shichiemon (Hashihiko) MURATA and his son Harukado Murata, a shrine priest Shigeki SAKAKURA, Naoki HITOMI, Saneki KURATA, Masahira SHIROKO, Arinobu UMATSU, a shrine priest of Tenmokuichi-jinja Shrine in Higo Province Choshu HOASHI and his son Misato HOASHI, Ohide TANAKA of Hida Province, Haruniwa MOTOORI (Norinaga&apos;s son) and Ohira MOTOORI (Norinaga&apos;s adopted son).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had many disciples, including Nakatsune HATTORI; Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA; Mikamaro NATSUME; Masaki NAGASE; Michiakira TAKABAYASHI; Shigetoshi OGUNI; Naonori TAKEMURA; Chiaki YOKOI; a local governor Shichiemon (Hashihiko) MURATA and his son Harukado Murata; a shrine priest Shigeki SAKAKURA; Naoki HITOMI; Saneki KURATA; Masahira SHIROKO; Arinobu UMATSU; a shrine priest of Tenmokuichi-jinja Shrine in Higo Province, Choshu HOASHI and his son Misato HOASHI; Ohide TANAKA of Hida Province; Haruniwa MOTOORI (Norinaga&apos;s son); and Ohira MOTOORI (Norinaga&apos;s adopted son).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had many disciples, including Nakatsune HATTORI; Tatsumaro ISHIZUKA; Mikamaro NATSUME; Masaki NAGASE; Michiakira TAKABAYASHI; Shigetoshi OGUNI; Naonori TAKEMURA; Chiaki YOKOI; a local governor Shichiemon (Hashihiko) MURATA and his son Harukado; a shrine priest Shigeki SAKAKURA; Naoki HITOMI; Saneki KURATA; Masahira SHIROKO; Arinobu UEMATSU; a shrine priest of Tenmokuichi-jinja Shrine in Yamaga of Higo Province, Choshu HOASHI and his son Misato HOASHI; Ohide TANAKA of Hida Takayama; Haruniwa MOTOORI (Norinaga&apos;s son); and Ohira MOTOORI (Norinaga&apos;s adopted son).</e>
<cmt>Yamaga他を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>また、宣長は法学においても特記される提言を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga also made a remarkable proposal concerning law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga also made a remarkable proposal concerning law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga also made a noteworthy proposal concerning law.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>紀州徳川家に贈られた「玉くしげ別本」の中で以下のように述べて、死刑の緩和を提言している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his book &quot;Tamakushige Beppon&quot;, which was given to Kishu Tokugawa family, he recommended to commute death penalty by saying as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his book &quot;Tamakushige Beppon,&quot; which was given to the Kishu Tokugawa family, he recommended that the death penalty be commuted, stating as follows:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his book &apos;Tamakushige Beppon,&apos; which was given to the Kishu Tokugawa family, he recommended that the death penalty be commuted, stating as follows:</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>「定りは宜しくても、其法を守るとして、却て軽々しく人をころす事あり、よくよく慎むべし。たとひ少々法にはづるる事ありとも、ともかく情実をよく勘へて軽むる方は難なかるべし。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Even though the law requires, you should refrain from killing a person without much thought on the pretext of complying with the law. Even when someone offends the law, it doesn&apos;t matter to commute a penalty by taking the circumstances into consideration.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Even though the law requires, you should refrain from killing a person without much thought, on the pretext of complying with the law; even when someone offends the law, it doesn&apos;t matter to commute a penalty by taking the circumstances into consideration.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though the law requires, you must refrain from killing a person thoughtlessly, on the pretext of complying with the law; even when someone offends the law, it doesn&apos;t matter to commute a penalty by taking the circumstances into consideration.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>他の記事に用語を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>家業を手伝うも商人には向かないと、母に相談して医業を学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he initially helped a family business, he later appealed his mother that he was not suitable for a merchant and studied medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he had initially assisted in a family business, he later appealed to his mother that he wasn&apos;t suitable for life as a merchant and instead studied medicine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Norinaga had initially assisted in the family business, he later appealed to his mother that he would not be suitable for life as a merchant and instead studied medicine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>地元・松坂では医師として40年以上にわたって活動していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He practiced as a doctor for more than 40 years in his birthplace Matsuzaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He practiced as a doctor for more than 40 years in his birthplace of Matsuzaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He practiced as a doctor for more than 40 years in his homeland of Matsuzaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また、寛政4年紀州藩に仕官し御針医格十人扶持となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the fourth year of Kansei era, he also became the medical officer of Kishu Domain and was entitled to Juninbuchi (the equivalent of an annual ten-man rice stipend).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the fourth year of the Kansei era, he also became the medical officer of the Kishu domain and was entitled to Juninbuchi (the equivalent of an annual ten-man rice stipend).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1792, he also became the medical officer of the Kishu domain and was entitled to the equivalent of an annual ten-man rice stipend.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>亡くなる10日前まで患者の治療にあたってきたことが記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is recorded that he treated patients until 10 days before his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is recorded that he treated patients until ten days before his death.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is recorded that he treated patients until ten days before his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また意外な一面として、小児科医としても著名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To our surprise, he was also well-known as a pediatrician.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surprisingly, he was also well-known as a pediatrician.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was norteworthy that he was also well-known as a pediatrician.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>乳児の病気の原因は母親にあるとして、付き添いの母親を必要以上に診察した逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The episode has been passed down that he examined mothers who were attending children beyond necessity as he believed that the cause of children&apos;s disease lay in mothers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The anecdote has been passed down that he examined mothers who were attending children beyond necessity, since he believed the cause of children&apos;s disease lay in mothers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The anecdote said that he, beyond necessity, examined mothers who were attending children, since he believed the cause of children&apos;s illness lay in mothers.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="48">
<j>鈴コレクターで、駅鈴のレプリカなど珍しいものを多く所有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a collector of bells and owned many rare ones such as the replica of station bell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An avid collector of bells, he owned many rare ones such as a replica of a station bell.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an avid collector of bells, he owned many rare things like a replica of a station bell.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>また、自宅に「鈴屋」という屋号もつけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He named his house &quot;Suzuya&quot; (bell house).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called his house &quot;Suzuya (bell house).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called his house &apos;Bell House&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="50">
<j>書物の貸し借りや読み方にこだわりがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was particular about borrowing and lending of books as well as the way of reading books.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was particular about the borrowing and lending of books as well as the manner of reading books.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was particular about the borrowing and lending of books as well as the manner of reading books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>借りた本を傷めるな、借りたらすぐ読んで早く返せ、けれど良い本は多くの人に読んで貰いたい、などの考えを記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, he wrote his thoughts as &quot;Don&apos;t damage a borrowed book. When you borrowed a book, read it immediately and return fast. However, I hope good books are read by many people.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that regard, he wrote, &quot;Don&apos;t damage a borrowed book; when you borrowed a book, read it immediately and return it promptly; however, I hope good books will be read by many people.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this regard, he wrote, &apos;Don&apos;t damage a borrowed book; when you borrowed a book, read it immediately and return it promptly; however, I hope good books will be read by many people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="52">
<j>宣長の生涯にわたる恋愛生活は、大野晋によりあきらかになった面が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norinaga&apos;s love affairs throughout his life were mostly disclosed by Susumu Ono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norinaga&apos;s love affairs throughout his life were mostly disclosed by Susumu Ono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norinaga&apos;s love affairs throughout his life were mostly disclosed by Susumu ONO.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TT(id:46431), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), HASIDATE(id:181052), E-190(id:74680), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Nnh(id:474), Mait(id:73947), Cprobot(id:97843), No&apos;o(id:36385), Charon(id:9162), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Mishika(id:276), Greenland4(id:114494), 矢刺幹人(id:10639), Kurz(id:1601), でここ(id:9565), Yelm(id:33836), Dr jimmy(id:111486), PPP(id:22924), 玄史生(id:43670), UMBRO(id:100484), Loveless(id:129239), 捕澤(id:23785), Mnd(id:15140), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Izayohi(id:13095), 目白梅(id:141468), Openup(id:211756), Stanislaus(id:1806), Woyzzeck(id:8923), 水野白楓(id:22811), Himazin(id:22034), T34-76(id:229352), Kaznov17(id:68122), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 松岡 一二三(id:226458), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Unamu(id:14627), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), Dodon(id:187283), Nekosuki600(id:21263), トホホ川(id:50502), 岡部碩道(id:182846), Uryah(id:17871), Ha～Ha(id:36403), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>