<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>良岑清風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YOSHIMINE no Kiyokaze</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YOSHIMINE no Kiyokaze</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YOSHIMINE no Kiyokaze</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>良岑 清風（よしみね の きよかぜ、生年不詳 - 863年5月10日（貞観 (日本)5年4月15日 (旧暦)））は、平安時代の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YOSHIMINE no Kiyokaze (year of birth unknown-May 10, 863) was a Court noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YOSHIMINE no Kiyokaze (year of birth unknown-May 10, 863) was a Court noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YOSHIMINE no Kiyokaze (year of birth unknown-May 10, 863) was a Court noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>カバネは朝臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) was &apos;Asomi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His kabane (hereditary title) was &apos;Asomi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) was &apos;Asomi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>桓武天皇の皇子である良岑安世の第三子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo, Imperial Prince of Emperor Kammu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo, the Imperial Prince of Emperor Kammu.</e>
<cmt>the Imperial Princeです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo, the Imperial Prince of Emperor Kammu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄弟に遍照などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hensho numbered among his brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hensho was his brother.</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hensho was his brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>良岑清風は桓武天皇の孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YOSHIMINE no Kiyokaze was a grandson of Emperor Kammu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YOSHIMINE no Kiyokaze was the grandson of Emperor Kammu.</e>
<cmt>the grandsonの方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YOSHIMINE no Kiyokaze was the grandson of Emperor Kammu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>父は桓武天皇の皇子で大納言贈従二位であった良岑安世である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo, who was Imperial Prince of Emperor Kammu and Dainagon (Chief Councilor of State) of Junii (Junior Second Rank), posthumously conferred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo, who was the Imperial Prince of Emperor Kammu and was the Dainagon (Chief Councilor of State) posthumously conferred Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was YOSHIMINE no Yasuyo, who was the Imperial Prince of Emperor Kammu and was the Dainagon (Chief Councilor of State) posthumously conferred Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>承和 (日本)初年に内舎人に任ぜられ、同5年に下野国掾となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to udoneri (Ministerial equerry) in 834 and to Shimotuke no kuni no jo (an official of Shimotsuke Province) in May of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Udoneri (Ministerial equerry) in 834 and to Shimotuke no kuni no jo (an official of Shimotsuke Province) in May of the same year.</e>
<cmt>appointed to Udoneriの方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Udoneri (Ministerial equerry) in 834 and to Shimotuke no kuni no jo (an official of Shimotsuke Province) in May of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後内匠少允や伊勢国大掾を経て嘉祥2年1月に従五位下に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After working as Takumi no shojo and Ise no kuni no daijo (Senior Secretary of Ise Province), he was created Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in January 849.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After working as the Takumi no shojo (an official at Takumiryo [the Bureau of Skilled Artsans]) and as the Ise no kuni no daijo (Senior Secretary of Ise Province), he was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in January 849.</e>
<cmt>内匠少允は説明を加えた方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After working as the Takumi no shojo (an official at Takumiryo [the Bureau of Skilled Artsans]) and as the Ise no kuni no daijo (Senior Secretary of Ise Province), he was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in January 849.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>公卿となった後も加賀国介、左馬助、左近衛少将、美濃国介、播磨国権介などを歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After becoming kugyo (high-rank Court noble), he held the following posts in a row: Kaga no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Kaga Province), Samanosuke (vice-minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses), Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Mino no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Mino Province), and Harima no kuni no gon no suke (Acting Assistant Governor of Harima Province).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After becoming a kugyo (high-rank Court noble), he served as the Kaga no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Kaga Province), the Samanosuke (vice-minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses), the Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), the Mino no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Mino Province), and the Harima no kuni no gon no suke (Acting Assistant Governor of Harima Province).</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため修正しました。スペースが２つ入っている箇所があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After becoming a kugyo (high-rank Court noble), he served as the Kaga no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Kaga Province), the Samanosuke (vice-minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses), the Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), the Mino no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Mino Province), and the Harima no kuni no gon no suke (Acting Assistant Governor of Harima Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>天安 (日本)元年、母の喪に服するため職位を解かれるが、その後再任されて正五位下に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 857 he was discharged from the official post to mourn his mother&apos;s death but reappointed later and created Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 857, he was discharged from the official post to mourn his mother&apos;s death but was reappointed later and was conferred Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>be動詞が抜けている箇所があります。conferredの方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 857, he was discharged from the official post to mourn his mother&apos;s death but was reappointed later and was conferred Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>貞観2年、美濃守となり従四位下を授かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 860, he was assigned to Mino no kami (Governor of Mino Province) and created Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 860, he was appointed to Mino no kami (Governor of Mino Province) and was conferred Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>appointed、conferredの方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 860, he was appointed to Mino no kami (Governor of Mino Province) and was conferred Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>2年後には美作国守、その翌年には近江国権守へと転任したが、赴任先で間もなく没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred to Mimasaka no kuni no kami (Governor of Mimasaka Province) two years later and to Konoe no kuni no gon no kami (Acting Governor of Konoe Province) in the following year, but he passed away in the appointed province soon afterwards.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was transferred to Mimasaka Province as the Mimasaka no kuni no kami (Governor of Mimasaka Province) two years later, and was again transferred to Konoe Province as the Konoe no kuni no gon no kami (Acting Governor of Konoe Province) in the following year, but passed away soon afterwards.</e>
<cmt>文を自然にするため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was transferred to Mimasaka Province as the Mimasaka no kuni no kami (Governor of Mimasaka Province) two years later, and was again transferred to Konoe Province as the Konoe no kuni no gon no kami (Acting Governor of Konoe Province) in the following year, but passed away soon afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), FCTR2(id:213046), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>