<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中村宗哲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotetsu NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotetsu NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotetsu NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中村 宗哲（なかむら そうてつ）は、千家十職の塗師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotetsu NAKAMURA is a japanner of Senke Jisshoku (the ten designated artisan families who supply their goods to the three Sen Tee Families).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotetsu NAKAMURA was a japanner (one who works in Japanese lacquer) of the Senke Jisshoku (the ten designated artisan families who supply their goods to the three Sen Tea Families).</e>
<cmt>“japanner” needs explanation; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotetsu NAKAMURA was a nurishi (a maker of lacquer ware and handiworks) of the Senke Jisshoku (the ten designated artisan families who supply their goods to the three Sen Tea Families).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中村家は、400年近く続く塗師の家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nakamuras is a japanner family that has continued for nearly 400 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nakamuras are a japanner family that has continued for nearly 400 years.</e>
<cmt>is-&gt;are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nakamuras are a nurishi family that has continued for nearly 400 years.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>当初は蒔絵を施した家具などの製作（「通例塗師」といわれる）も行っていたが、明治時代以降は茶道具の塗師（「型物塗師」といわれる）専業となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family originally produced furniture decorated with makie gold or silver lacquer, but concentrated on lacquering of tea utensils after the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family originally produced furniture decorated with gold or silver lacquer, but concentrated on the lacquering of tea utensils after the Meiji Era.</e>
<cmt>removed “makie”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family originally produced furniture decorated with gold or silver lacquer (Tsure nurishi), but concentrated on the lacquering of tea utensils after the Meiji Era (Katamono nurishi).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>千宗旦の次男、一翁宗守（1593年～1675年）は、中村宗哲家の初代八兵衛（1617年～1695年、当時の八兵衛は吉岡姓）の娘婿となり、吉岡甚右衛門を名乗り塗師を営んでいたが、宗守が父・宗旦から官休庵（武者小路千家）を譲り受けた際に吉岡家を出て千家に復する時、家業を八兵衛に譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soshu ICHIO (1593 - 1675), second son of Sotan SEN, married a daughter of Hachibei, the founder of the Nakamura family (1617 - 1695) (although Hachibei&apos;s surname was Yoshioka at that time), changed his name to Jinuemon YOSHIOKA, operated as a japanner, but when Soshu took over the Kankyu-an Tearoom (Mushakoji-Senke) from his father Sotan, Soshu left the Yoshioka family and returned to the House of Sen after he relinquished the profession to Hachibei.</e>
<cmt>官休庵（武者小路千家）→不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soshu ICHIO (1593 - 1675), second son of Sotan SEN, married a daughter of Hachibei, the founder of the Nakamura family (1617 - 1695) (although Hachibei&apos;s surname was Yoshioka at that time), changed his name to Jinuemon YOSHIOKA, and worked as a japanner, but when Soshu took over the Kankyu-an Tearoom (Mushakoji-Senke) from his father Sotan, Soshu left the Yoshioka family and returned to the House of Sen after he relinquished the profession to Hachibei.</e>
<cmt>removed double-byte space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soshu ICHIO (1593 - 1675), second son of SEN no Sotan, married a daughter of Hachibei, the founder of the Nakamura family (1617 - 1695) (although Hachibei&apos;s surname was Yoshioka at that time), changed his name to Jinuemon YOSHIOKA, and worked as a nurishi, but when Soshu took over the Kankyu-an Tearoom (Mushakoji-Senke) from his father Sotan, Soshu left the Yoshioka family and returned to the House of Sen after he relinquished the profession to Hachibei.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>現在、当代十三代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotetsu is the 13th head of the Nakamura family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotetsu is the 13th head of the Nakamura family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotetsu is the 13th head of the Nakamura family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>2006年（平成18年）に十二代中村宗哲の次女が十三代宗哲を襲名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2006, the second daughter of the 12th Sotetsu NAKAMURA succeeded the name of Sotetsu to become the 13th Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2006, the second daughter of the 12th Sotetsu NAKAMURA succeeded the name of Sotetsu to become the 13th Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2006, the second daughter of the 12th Sotetsu NAKAMURA succeeded the name of Sotetsu to become the 13th Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中村家歴代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the Nakamura Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the Nakamura Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the Nakamura Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>初代宗哲（1617年～1695年、通称：八兵衛 号：公弼・方寸庵・塗翁・勇山・杯斎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Sotetsu (1617 - 1695) - unofficial name: Hachibei; pen name: Kohitsu, Hosunan, Too, Michioki, Isayama, Yuzan, Saishu.</e>
<cmt>号の「塗翁」と「勇山」は音読みと訓読みの二通りとも使っていたかどうか不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Sotetsu (1617 - 1695) - unofficial name: Hachibei; pen name: Kohitsu, Hosunan, Too, Michioki, Isayama, Yuzan, Saishu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Sotetsu (1617 - 1695) - unofficial name: Hachibei; go (pen name): Kohitsu, Hosunan, Too, Michioki, Isayama, Yuzan, Saishu.</e>
<cmt>pen name→go(pen name)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>藤村庸軒、灰屋紹益らと親交を結ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was on friendly terms with Yoken FUJIMURA and Shoeki HAIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was on friendly terms with Yoken FUJIMURA and Shoeki HAIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was on friendly terms with Yoken FUJIMURA and Shoeki HAIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>代表作に江岑好・独楽香合、庸軒好・凡鳥棗など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Koshinko, Komanurikoawase, Yokenko, and Bonchonatsume.</e>
<cmt>代表作の名前ですが、「固有名詞」なのか「普通名詞」なのか、不明です。またすべてが「作品（漆器等）」の名前なのかどうか、判断がつきません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Koshinko, Komanurikoawase, Yokenko, and Bonchonatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Koshinko, Komanurikoawase, Yokenko, and Bonchonatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>二代宗哲（1671年～1706年、通称：八兵衛 号：汲斎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2nd Sotetsu (1671 - 1706) - unofficial name: Hachibei; a pen name: Kyusai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2nd Sotetsu (1671 - 1706) - unofficial name: Hachibei; pen name: Kyusai.</e>
<cmt>removed article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2nd Sotetsu (1671 - 1706) - unofficial name: Hachibei; go: Kyusai.</e>
<cmt>pen name→go</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>代表作に乱菊中棗など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Rangikuchunatsume.</e>
<cmt>「棗」は、「ナツメの形をしているからナツメと呼ばれるようになった茶葉の容器」だそうです。となると「棗」は普通名詞とみなせないわけではないのですが。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Rangikuchunatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Rangikuchunatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>三代宗哲（1699年～1776年、通称：八兵衛 幼名：鍋千代 号：方寸庵・漆翁・漆桶・勇斎・公弼・紹朴・芹生）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3rd Sotetsu (1699 - 1776) - unofficial name: Hachibei; childhood name: Nabechiyo; pen name: Hojoan, Too, Michioki, Shittsu, Yusai, Kohitsu, Shoboku, and Seryo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3rd Sotetsu (1699 - 1776) - unofficial name: Hachibei; childhood name: Nabechiyo; pen name: Hojoan, Too, Michioki, Shittsu, Yusai, Kohitsu, Shoboku, and Seryo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3rd Sotetsu (1699 - 1776) - unofficial name: Hachibei; childhood name: Nabechiyo; go: Hojoan, Too, Michioki, Shittsu, Yusai, Kohitsu, Shoboku, and Seryo</e>
<cmt>pen name→go</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>幼少で両親に死別したが、表千家6代・覚々斎、7代・如心斎らに引き立てられ、若年にして「七事式」制定に参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his parents died when he was a small child, he was supported by the 6th Omote Senke head Kakukasai and the 7th head Joshinsai and was allowed to be a member of the people who established the Shichiji shiki (seven training exercises) despite his youth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his parents died when he was a small child, he was supported by the 6th Omote Senke head, Kakukasai, and the 7th head, Joshinsai, and was allowed to be a member of the group that established the Shichiji shiki (seven training exercises), in spite of his youth.</e>
<cmt>added commas, despite-&gt;in spite of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his parents died when he was a small child, he was supported by the 6th Omotesenke (the house of Omotesen) head, Kakukakusai, and the 7th head, Joshinsai, and was allowed to be a member of the group that established the Shichiji shiki (literally, &quot;seven exercises&quot;; the staff came up with seven exercises of the tea ceremony as a pedagogical device), in spite of his youth.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>俳人であり、与謝蕪村、几菫、堀内仙鶴らと親交を結ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a haiku poet and formed a friendship with YOSA no Buson, Kito and Senkaku HORIUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a haiku poet and formed friendships with YOSA no Buson, Kito and Senkaku HORIUCHI.</e>
<cmt>friendships</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a haiku poet and formed friendships with YOSA no Buson, Kito and Senkaku HORIUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>代表作に覚々斎好・ブリブリ香合、少庵好・彭祖棗など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Kakukakusaiko (or Kakukakusaigonom), Buriburikoawase, Shoanko (or Shoangonomi) and Hoso natsume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Kakukakusaiko (or Kakukakusaigonom), Buriburikoawase, Shoanko (or Shoangonomi) and Hoso natsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Kakukakusaiko (or Kakukakusaigonom), Buriburikoawase, Shoanko (or Shoangonomi) and Hoso natsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>四代宗哲（1726年～1791年、通称：為安・八郎兵衛 号：深斎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4th Sotetsu (1726 - 1791) - unofficial name: Tameyasu and Hachibei; pen name: Shinsai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4th Sotetsu (1726 - 1791) - unofficial name: Tameyasu and Hachibei; pen name: Shinsai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4th Sotetsu (1726 - 1791) - unofficial name: Tameyasu and Hachibei; go: Shinsai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="17">
<j>三代婿養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He married a daughter of the third Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He married a daughter of the third Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He married a daughter of the third Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>安永3年、従六位下主殿少属兼左生火官人に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1774, he was granted Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned to Shosoku (Junior Officer) of Shudenryo (office in charge of the care and maintenance of all the palace buildings) and Saseikakannin.</e>
<cmt>左生火官人はわかりません。読み方も。「生火」は「いけび」と読むそうですが、確信はもてません。[http://www2.diary.ne.jp/i_log.cgi?user=173842&amp;log=200601&amp;start=1]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1774, he was granted Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned to Shosoku (Junior Officer) of Shudenryo (office in charge of the care and maintenance of all the palace buildings) and Saseikakannin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1774, he was granted Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned to Shosoku (Junior Officer) of Shudenryo (office in charge of the care and maintenance of all the palace buildings) and Saseikakannin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>署名には「豊田八郎兵衛」を使用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He used &quot;Hachirobei TOMITA&quot; for his signature name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He used &quot;Hachirobei TOMITA&quot; for his signature name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He used &quot;Hachirobei TOMITA&quot; for his signature name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>後桜町天皇の大礼御用品の御用も司る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also served Empress Go-Sakuramachi as a designated purveyor for imperial ceremonies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also served Empress Go-Sakuramachi as a designated vendor for imperial ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>purveyor-&gt;vendor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also served Empress Go-Sakuramachi as a designated vendor for imperial ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="21">
<j>代表作に三斎好・野風茶器など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Sansaiko and Yafuchaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Sansaiko and Yafuchaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Sansaiko and Yafuchaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="22">
<j>五代宗哲（1764年～1811年、通称：守一・八兵衛 号：豹斎・漆畝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5th Sotetsu (1764 - 1811) - unofficial name: Morikazu and Hachibei; pen name: Hyosai and Shitsuho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5th Sotetsu (1764 - 1811) - unofficial name: Morikazu and Hachibei; pen name: Hyosai and Shitsuho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5th Sotetsu (1764 - 1811) - unofficial name: Morikazu and Hachibei; go: Hyosai and Shitsuho</e>
<cmt>pen name→go</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="23">
<j>四代婿養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the husband of a daughter of the 4th Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the husband of a daughter of the 4th Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the husband of a daughter of the 4th Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>天明3年、従六位下主殿寮補左生火官兼式部大録に任じられ、御所御用達となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1783, he was appointed as an assistant to Shudenryo (office in charge of the care and maintenance of all the palace buildings), Saseikakannin and Shikibu no daisakan (senior alternate adjudicator) with a court rank Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) and became a designated purveyor of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1783, he was appointed to be an assistant to Shudenryo (office in charge of the care and maintenance of all the palace buildings), Saseikakannin and Shikibu no daisakan (senior alternate adjudicator) with a court rank Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) and became a designated vendor to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>purveyor-&gt;vendor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1783, he was appointed to be an assistant to Shudenryo (office in charge of the care and maintenance of all the palace buildings), Saseikakannin and Shikibu no daisakan (senior alternate adjudicator) with a court rank Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) and became a designated vendor to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>天明8年に「天明の大火」に遭い家を焼失するが、歴代の寸法帳などは持ち出しに成功。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1788 when the Great Fire of Tenmei occurred, his houses were burned down, but he successfully brought books with work dimensions and other data handed down for generations out of the burning house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1788 when the Great Fire of Tenmei occurred, his house burned down, but he was able to rescue books with designs and other data handed down for generations out of the burning house.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1788 when the Great Fire of Tenmei occurred, his house burned down, but he was able to rescue books with designs and other data handed down for generations out of the burning house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>三代未亡人からの聞き書きにより、家伝を作成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He compiled a family history out of the information he got from the wife of the late 3rd Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He compiled a family history out of the information he got from the wife of the late 3rd Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He compiled a family history out of the information he got from the wife of the late 3rd Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>俳人であり、三宅嘯山の弟子であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a haiku poet and one of the disciples of Shozan MIYAKE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a haiku poet and one of the disciples of Shozan MIYAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a haiku poet and one of the disciples of Shozan MIYAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="28">
<j>代表作に認得斎好・蔦蒔絵中棗など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Nintoku Saiko and Tsutamakie Chunatsume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Nintoku Saiko and Tsutamakie Chunatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Nintoku Saiko and Tsutamakie Chunatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="29">
<j>六代宗哲（1792年～1839年、幼名：昌之助 通称：八兵衛・為一・八郎兵衛 号：楪斎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">6th Sotetsu (1792 - 1839) - childhood name: Shonosuke; unofficial name: Hachibei, Tameichi and Hachirobei; pen name: Yuzurihasai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">6th Sotetsu (1792 - 1839) - childhood name: Shonosuke; unofficial name: Hachibei, Tameichi and Hachirobei; pen name: Yuzurihasai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">6th Sotetsu (1792 - 1839) - childhood name: Shonosuke; unofficial name: Hachibei, Tameichi and Hachirobei; go: Yuzurihasai</e>
<cmt>pen name→go</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="30">
<j>五代の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eldest son of the 5th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eldest son of the 5th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eldest son of the 5th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1811年に家督相続するも、1815年に弟に家督を譲り、自らは御所御用達と通例の塗師職（大名向け漆器制作）を営業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he succeeded his family business in 1811, he yielded his position to his younger brother in 1815 and started his own business of lacquering as one of the purveyors to the Imperial Court and as an ordinary japanner for daimyo lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he took over the family business in 1811, he yielded his position to his younger brother in 1815 and started his own business of lacquering as one of the vendors to the Imperial Court and as an ordinary japanner for daimyo lords.</e>
<cmt>succeed-&gt;take over, purveyor-&gt;vendor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he took over the family business in 1811, he yielded his position to his younger brother in 1815 and started his own business of lacquering as one of the vendors to the Imperial Court and as an ordinary nurishi for daimyo lords.</e>
<cmt>japanner→nurishi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="32">
<j>代表作に認得斎好・祇園攘疫棗・群亀棗・宝船棗など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Nintoku Saiko, Gionjoekinatsume, Gunkinatsume, and Hosennatsume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Nintoku Saiko, Gionjoekinatsume, Gunkinatsume, and Hosennatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Nintoku Saiko, Gionjoekinatsume, Gunkinatsume, and Hosennatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="33">
<j>七代宗哲（1798年～1846年、幼名：槌六 通称：八郎兵衛・八兵衛 号：得玄・獏斎・黒牡丹）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">7th Sotetsu (1798 - 1846) - childhood name: Tsuiroku; unofficial name: Hachirobei and Hachibei; pen name: Tokugen, Bakusai, and Kurobotan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">7th Sotetsu (1798 - 1846) - childhood name: Tsuiroku; unofficial name: Hachirobei and Hachibei; pen name: Tokugen, Bakusai, and Kurobotan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">7th Sotetsu (1798 - 1846) - childhood name: Tsuiroku; unofficial name: Hachirobei and Hachibei; go: Tokugen, Bakusai, and Kurobotan</e>
<cmt>pen name→go</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="34">
<j>五代次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of the 5th Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of the 5th Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of the 5th Sotetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>兄から家督を譲られ、形物塗師職人（茶道具漆器制作）となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was yielded the head of the family by his brother and became a katamono lacquering artisan (producer of tea utensil japan ware).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was made head of the family by his brother and became a katamono lacquer artisan (producer of lacquer ware tea utensils).</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was made head of the family by his brother and became a Katamono nurishi (producer of lacquer ware tea utensils).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="36">
<j>代表作に名取川硯箱・夕顔台子皆具（浄雪・七代浄益・旦入 合作）など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Natorigawa writing box and Yugaodaisukaigu (Josetsu, Nanadaijoeki, Tannyu and Gassaku).</e>
<cmt>「合作」は joint work だと思いますが、「旦入」とのつながりが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Natorigawa writing box and Yugaodaisukaigu (Josetsu, Nanadaijoeki, and Tannyu Gassaku).</e>
<cmt>moved “and”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Natorigawa writing box and Yugaodaisukaigu (jointly produced by Josetsu, Nanadaijoeki, and Tannyu).</e>
<cmt>浄雪・七代浄益・旦入と共同製作という意味だと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="37">
<j>八代宗哲（1828年～1884年、幼名：丑之助 通称：八郎兵衛・忠一 号：至斎・聴雨・蜂老）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">8th Sotetsu (1828 - 1884) - childhood name: Ushinosuke; unofficial name: Hachirobei and Tadakazu; pen name: Shisai, Chou and Yoro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">8th Sotetsu (1828 - 1884) - childhood name: Ushinosuke; unofficial name: Hachirobei and Tadakazu; pen name: Shisai, Chou and Yoro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">8th Sotetsu (1828 - 1884) - childhood name: Ushinosuke; unofficial name: Hachirobei and Tadakazu; go: Shisai, Chou and Yoro.</e>
<cmt>pen name→go</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="38">
<j>七代長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eldest son of the 7th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eldest son of the 7th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eldest son of the 7th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>京都御所御造営や和宮御降嫁花嫁道具、徳川家茂御上洛道具など多数の御用を司る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the designated purveyor for the Imperial Court, he dealt with plenty of materials and goods including those for the construction work of the Kyoto Imperial Palace, the wedding of Prince Kazunomiya for her marriage with the Tokugawa shogun and for the visit of Iemochi TOKUGAWA to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the designated vendor for the Imperial Court, he dealt with plenty of materials and goods including those for the construction work of the Kyoto Imperial Palace, the wedding of Princess Kazunomiya with the Tokugawa shogun and for the visit of Iemochi TOKUGAWA to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>prince-&gt;princess</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the designated vendor for the Imperial Court, he dealt with plenty of materials and goods including those for the construction work of the Kyoto Imperial Palace, the wedding of Princess Kazunomiya with the Tokugawa shogun and for the visit of Iemochi TOKUGAWA to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>明治維新後は京都博覧会会社に勤務。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, he worked for Kyoto Exhibition Company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, he worked for Kyoto Exhibition Company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, he worked for Kyoto Exhibition Company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>1876年にフィラデルフィアで開催された米国百年祭大博覧会に出品・銅賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1876, he placed his work at the Centennial Exhibition in Philadelphia, USA, and won the bronze medal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1876, he displayed his work at the Centennial Exhibition in Philadelphia, USA, and won the bronze medal.</e>
<cmt>placed-&gt;displayed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1876, he displayed his work at the Centennial Exhibition in Philadelphia, USA, and won the bronze medal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="42">
<j>代表作に碌々斎好・既望棗、玄々斎好・曙棗など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Rokurokusaiko, Kibonatsume, Gengensaiko, and Akebononatsume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Rokurokusaiko, Kibonatsume, Gengensaiko, and Akebononatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Rokurokusaiko, Kibonatsume, Gengensaiko, and Akebononatsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="43">
<j>九代宗哲（1856年～1911年、旧姓：松崎喜三郎 号：義生・英斎・一畝・雲水）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">9th Sotetsu (1856 - 1911) - unofficial name: Kizaburo MATSUZAKI; pen name: Gisho, Eisai, Ippo, and Unsui.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">9th Sotetsu (1856 - 1911) - unofficial name: Kizaburo MATSUZAKI; pen name: Gisho, Eisai, Ippo, and Unsui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">9th Sotetsu (1856 - 1911) - original name: Kizaburo MATSUZAKI; go: Gisho, Eisai, Ippo, and Unsui.</e>
<cmt>unofficial name→original namepen name→go</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="44">
<j>八代婿養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Husband of a daughter of the 8th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Husband of a daughter of the 8th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Husband of a daughter of the 8th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>元々は師範学校卒業後、小学校訓導を務めていた教師出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was originally a school teacher for a public elementary school he started working after graduation from a teacher&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was originally a teacher at a public elementary school, where he started working after graduation from a teacher&apos;s college.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was originally a teacher at a public elementary school, where he started working after graduation from a teacher&apos;s college.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>茶道衰退期の中、京都市立芸術大学に勤務するなど家業の維持に苦心する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amid a decline of tea ceremony, he tried very hard to maintain his family business by taking various measures including employment by Kyoto City University of Arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amid a decline of tea ceremony, he tried very hard to maintain his family business by taking various measures including employment by Kyoto City University of Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amid a decline of tea ceremony, he tried very hard to maintain his family business by taking various measures including employment by Kyoto City University of Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="47">
<j>代表作に玄々斎好・溢梅雪吹大小・溜ミル貝雪吹溜松木下張棗・粒菊蒔絵溜雪吹・黒絵玉書詰平棗、惺斎好・鱗鶴大棗・松摺漆丸卓など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Rokurokusaiko, Itsubaifubukidaisho, Tamirugaifubukiryumatsukinoshitabarinatsume, Ryuomakieryufubuki, Kuroetamashotumehiranatsume, Kakusaiko, Kakusaigonomi, Urokozuruonatsume, and Matussuriurushimarutaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Rokurokusaiko, Itsubaifubukidaisho, Tamirugaifubukiryumatsukinoshitabarinatsume, Ryuomakieryufubuki, Kuroetamashotumehiranatsume, Kakusaiko, Kakusaigonomi, Urokozuruonatsume, and Matussuriurushimarutaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Rokurokusaiko, Itsubaifubukidaisho, Tamirugaifubukiryumatsukinoshitabarinatsume, Ryuomakieryufubuki, Kuroetamashotumehiranatsume, Kakusaiko, Kakusaigonomi, Urokozuruonatsume, and Matussuriurushimarutaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="48">
<j>中村哲太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsutaro NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsutaro NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsutaro NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="49">
<j>九代宗哲と十代尼宗哲の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eldest son of the 9th Sotetsu and the 10th Nisotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eldest son of the 9th Sotetsu and the 10th Nisotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eldest son of the 9th Sotetsu and the 10th Nisotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>父の死後に家督相続、「中村宗哲」として茶道具製作を行うが、その後廃業（廃業は家業を厭っていたからとも、病弱で家業の維持に自信がもてなかったためとも言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father died and he succeeded his father&apos;s title, he started producing tea utensils as &quot;Sotetsu NAKAMURA&quot; but later he retired from business (it is believed that he quit his business because he didn&apos;t like the family business or was not confident in maintaining his family business because of his poor health).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his father died and he succeeded his father&apos;s title, he started producing tea utensils as &quot;Sotetsu NAKAMURA&quot; but later he retired from business (it is believed that he quit his business because he didn&apos;t like the family business or was not confident in maintaining his family business because of his poor health).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father died and he succeeded his father&apos;s title, he started producing tea utensils as &quot;Sotetsu NAKAMURA&quot; but later he retired from business (it is believed that he quit his business because he didn&apos;t like the family business or was not confident in maintaining his family business because of his poor health).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>昭和初年度に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1926.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1926.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1926.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="52">
<j>十代尼宗哲（1862年～1926年、名：真 八代宗哲四女）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10th Nisotetsu (1862 - 1926) - name: Shin; fourth daughter of the 8th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">10th Nisotetsu (1862 - 1926) - name: Shin; fourth daughter of the 8th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">10th Nisotetsu (1862 - 1926) - name: Shin; fourth daughter of the 8th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="53">
<j>九代夫人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wife of the 9th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wife of the 9th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wife of the 9th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>岸田湘煙の女塾に入塾、自由民権運動の影響を受けて成長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She joined a workshop of Shoen KISHIDA and grew under the influence of liberal and democratic rights movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She joined the workshop of Shoen KISHIDA and grew under the influence of liberal and democratic rights movements.</e>
<cmt>a-&gt;the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She joined the workshop of Shoen KISHIDA and grew under the influence of liberal and democratic rights movements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>後、府立女紅場一期生として入学、和裁を勉強する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, she entered a municipal Nyokoba School for women as a member of the inaugural class and learned Japanese dressmaking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, she entered a municipal Nyokoba School for women as a member of the inaugural class and learned Japanese dressmaking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, she entered a municipal Nyokoba School for women as a member of the inaugural class and learned Japanese dressmaking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>結婚後は自宅で和裁塾を開いて家計を助ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After marriage, she opened her own private Japanese dressmaking school to support the household budget.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After marriage, she opened her own private Japanese dressmaking school to support the household budget.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After marriage, she opened her own private Japanese dressmaking school to support the household budget.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>夫の死、長男の廃業に伴い、表千家12代惺斎の命により家督預かりとなり、多数の道具を製作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of her husband, upon retirement of her eldest son, she was ordered by the 12th Kakusai of Omote Senke Family to temporarily succeed her family business and produced many utensils.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of her husband, upon retirement of her eldest son, she was ordered by the 12th Kakusai of Omote Senke Family to temporarily succeed her family business and produced many utensils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of her husband, upon retirement of her eldest son, she was ordered by the 12th Kakusai of Omote Senke Family to temporarily succeed her family business and produced many utensils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="58">
<j>代表作に惺斎好・笹蒔絵硯箱・雛用柳桜茶具（合作）・雛用懐石家具・近江八景棗など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her representative works include Kakusaiko, Sasamakie writing box, Hinayo Ryuo tea utensils (joint work), Hinayo kaiseki furniture, and Omihakkei natsume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her representative works include Kakusaiko, Sasamakie writing box, Hinayo Ryuo tea utensils (joint work), Hinayo kaiseki furniture, and Omihakkei natsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her representative works include Kakusaiko, Sasamakie writing box, Hinayo Ryuo tea utensils (joint work), Hinayo kaiseki furniture, and Omihakkei natsume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="59">
<j>十一代宗哲（1899年～1993年、名：忠蔵 号：元斎・叩城・九土）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">11th Sotetsu (1899 - 1993) - name: Tadakura; pen name: Gensai, Kojo and Kyushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">11th Sotetsu (1899 - 1993) - name: Tadakura; pen name: Gensai, Kojo and Kyushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">11th Sotetsu (1899 - 1993) - name: Tadakura; go: Gensai, Kojo and Kyushi</e>
<cmt>pen name→go</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="60">
<j>九代次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second son of the 9th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second son of the 9th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second son of the 9th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>戦中戦後の多難な時期に多数の名作を製作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He produced various masterpieces during the hard days during and after WW2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He produced various masterpieces during the hard days during and after WW2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He produced various masterpieces during the hard days during and after World War II.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>京都府文化功労者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded by Kyoto Prefecture as the Person of Cultural Merits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was named a Person of Cultural Merits by Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was named a Person of Cultural Merits by Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>昭和60年、十二代に跡を譲り隠居。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1985, he yielded his title to the 12th Sotetsu and retired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1985, he yielded his title to the 12th Sotetsu and retired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1985, he yielded his title to the 12th Sotetsu and retired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="64">
<j>代表作に惺斎好・唐崎松中棗・醍醐枝垂桜大棗、即中斎好・四季 誰が袖蒔絵茶器など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His representative works include Kakusaiko, Karasakimatsunaka natsume, Daigoedadarezakura onatsume, Sokuchusaiko, Shiki, and Daregasodemakie tea utensils.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His representative works include Kakusaiko, Karasakimatsunaka natsume, Daigoedadarezakura onatsume, Sokuchusaiko, Shiki, and Daregasodemakie tea utensils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His representative works include Kakusaiko, Karasakimatsunaka natsume, Daigoedadarezakura onatsume, Sokuchusaiko, Shiki, and Daregasodemakie tea utensils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="65">
<j>十二代宗哲（1932年～2005年、名：弘子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">12th Sotetsu (1932 - 2005) - name: Hiroko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">12th Sotetsu (1932 - 2005) - name: Hiroko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">12th Sotetsu (1932 - 2005) - name: Hiroko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="66">
<j>十一代長女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eldest daughter of the 11th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eldest daughter of the 11th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eldest daughter of the 11th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>兄たちが家職を継がなかったため、家職継承者に指名される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since her elder brothers didn&apos;t succeeded the family business, she was appointed as a successor to the family business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since her elder brothers didn&apos;t enter the family business, she was appointed successor.</e>
<cmt>succeed-&gt;enter, deleted some repetition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since her elder brothers didn&apos;t enter the family business, she was appointed successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>昭和30年京都市立芸術大学工芸科卒。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graduated from Kyoto City University of Arts in 1955.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graduated from Kyoto City University of Arts in 1955.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graduated from Kyoto City University of Arts, Department of Crafts in 1955.</e>
<cmt>Department of Craftsを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>昭和61年に千家への出仕を許され、女性として初めて正式に千家十職当主として認められた人物となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1986, she was allowed to serve the Senke Family and became the first woman who was officially recognized as the head of a Senke Jisshoku Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1986, she was allowed to serve the Senke Family and became the first woman who was officially recognized as the head of a Senke Jisshoku Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1986, she was allowed to serve the Senke Family and became the first woman who was officially recognized as the head of a Senke Jisshoku Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>茶道具以外にも多数の漆器を製作し、工芸家としての評価も高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She produced many pieces of japan ware in addition to tea utensils and won a high reputation as an industrial artist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She produced many pieces of lacquer ware in addition to tea utensils and won a high reputation as an industrial artist.</e>
<cmt>japan-&gt;lacquer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She produced many pieces of lacquer ware in addition to tea utensils and won a high reputation as an industrial artist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>心筋梗塞により急逝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She suddenly died of heart attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died suddenly of a heart attack.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died suddenly of a heart attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>実娘3人も漆工芸家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her three daughters are also japan ware artists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her three daughters are also Japanese lacquer ware artists.</e>
<cmt>added “lacquer”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her three daughters are also Japanese lacquer ware artists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="73">
<j>代表作に而妙斎好・吉祥松溜雪吹・春野旅箪笥など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her representative works include Jinyosaiko, Kichijomatsudamarifubuki, and Harunotabitansu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her representative works include Jinyosaiko, Kichijomatsudamarifubuki, and Harunotabitansu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her representative works include Jinyosaiko, Kichijomatsudamarifubuki, and Harunotabitansu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="74">
<j>十三代宗哲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">13th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">13th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">13th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="75">
<j>十二代次女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second daughter of the 12th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second daughter of the 12th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second daughter of the 12th Sotetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), こぶまき(id:38278), Takranke(id:23355), 草薙(id:23262), Yamayuri(id:157243), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>