<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原登任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Narito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Narito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Narito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原登任（ふじわら の なりとう、987年（永延元年） - 没年不詳）は、平安時代の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Narito (987 – date of death unknown) is a noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Narito (987 – date of death unknown) was a noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>past tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Narito (987 – date of death unknown) was a noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原南家真作流、藤原師長(南家)の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is a son of FUJIWARA no Moronaga (Southern House) of the Matanari clique of the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of FUJIWARA no Moronaga (Southern House) of the Matanari branch of the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>past tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of FUJIWARA no Moronaga (Southern House) of the Matanari branch of the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原長宗、藤原長明らの父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons include FUJIWARA no Nagamune and FUJIWARA no Nagaaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons included FUJIWARA no Nagamune and FUJIWARA no Nagaaki.</e>
<cmt>past tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons included FUJIWARA no Nagamune and FUJIWARA no Nagaaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>主殿頭、出雲守などを歴任後，永承5年（1050年）、陸奥守として下向。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having successively held posts such as Tonomo no kami (the director of the Imperial Palace Keeper&apos;s Bureau) and Izumo no kami (the governor of Izumo Province), he left the capital as Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province) in 1050.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After occupying posts such as Tonomo no kami (the director of the Imperial Palace Keeper&apos;s Bureau) and Izumo no kami (the governor of Izumo Province), he left the capital to become the Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province) in 1050.</e>
<cmt>&quot;having successively held&quot; is a bit of an awkward phrase. I think it is better put as &quot;after occupying..&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After occupying posts such as Tonomo no kami (the director of the Imperial Palace Keeper&apos;s Bureau) and Izumo no kami (the governor of Izumo Province), he left the capital to become the Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province) in 1050.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>翌年の永承6年（1051年）、安倍氏 (奥州)が衣川の柵を越え勢力圏を拡大しようとしたため、陸奥守だった登任は、秋田城介平重成らと安倍氏を討伐しようするが、逆に鬼切部で大敗を喫し更迭された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year in 1051, since the Abe clan (Oshu Province) tried to expand his region of authority beyond Koromogawa River, Narito, who was the Mutsu no kami, tried to subjugate the Abe clan with others such as TAIRA no Shigenari, Akitajo no suke (provincial governor of Akita-jo Castle in Dewa Province); on the contraries, however, he suffers a crushing loss in Onikiribe (a geographical name) and was dismissed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year of 1051, the Abe clan (Oshu Province) tried to expand their region of authority beyond Koromogawa River; Narito, the Mutsu no kami, joined forces with TAIRA no Shigenari, Akitajo no suke (provincial governor of Akita-jo Castle in Dewa Province) and others in an attempt to control them, but suffered a crushing loss in Onikiribe (a place) and was replaced.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year of 1051, the Abe clan (Oshu Province) tried to expand their region of authority beyond the Koromo-gawa River; Narito, the Mutsu no kami (Governor of Mutsu Province), joined forces with TAIRA no Shigenari, Akitajo no suke (provincial governor of Akita-jo Castle in Dewa Province) and others in an attempt to control them, but suffered a crushing loss in Onikiribe and was replaced.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「前九年の役」の発端となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became the outset of the &quot;Zen Kunen no Eki&quot; (Former Nine Years&apos; Campaign).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the beginning of the &quot;Zen Kunen no Eki&quot; (Early Nine-Years Campaign).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the beginning of the &quot;Zen Kunen no Eki&quot; (Early Nine-Years Campaign).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>当時の状況は後任の源頼義による上奏文に、「東夷蜂起シ郡県ヲ領シ以ッテ夷地トナシ、人民ヲ駆使シ蛮虜トナシ六カ郡中、国務ニ従ガワズ、皇威ヲ忘ルルガ如シ」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation at that time is described in a report to the throne as: &quot;Toi hokishi gunkenwo ryoshimotte ichitonashi, jinminwo kushishi banryotonashi mukagunchu, kokumuni shitagawazu, koiwo wasururugagotoshi&quot;(People in six districts in the East of Kyoto revolted like barbarians, stating that they own the territories and acting against the order of the throne) by MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, Narito&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation at that time was described in a report to the throne as &quot;People in six districts in the East of Kyoto revolted like barbarians, stating that they own the territories and acting against the order of the throne&quot;, by MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, Narito&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>I think it is meaningless to include the whole of the Japanese phrase in romaji here. Surely, the translation on its own is OK.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation at that time was described in a report to the throne as &apos;People in six districts in the East of Kyoto revolted like barbarians, stating that they own the territories and acting against the order of the throne,&apos; by MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, Narito&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Mandm(id:45549), 代言人(id:33675), Law soma(id:45202), Tetsu9(id:14553), Shimoxx(id:9332), Point136(id:211299), PRiMENON(id:14071), Zippin(id:9885), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>