<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源多</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Masaru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Masaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Masaru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 多（みなもと の まさる、天長8年（831年） - 仁和4年10月17日 (旧暦)（888年11月24日））は平安時代前期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Masaru (831 - Nov. 24, 888) was a court noble in the early part of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Masaru (831 - Nov. 24, 888) was a court noble who lived in the early part of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>noble in the early part of the Heian Period → noble who lived in the early part of the Heian Period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Masaru (831 - November 24, 888) was a court noble who lived in the early part of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Nov.→November</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は仁明天皇。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Emperor Ninmyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Emperor Ninmyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Emperor Ninmyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は未詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>彼は、一般に仁明天皇第一源氏とされていて、彼の兄弟たちで源氏姓を賜り臣籍降下した者たちを仁明源氏と称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally he is believed to be the first of the Minamoto clan created by Emperor Ninmyo, and those including him and his brothers who were granted the name of MINAMOTO and left the Imperial family members to come down to the status of Imperial vassals were called Ninmyo-Genji.</e>
<cmt>臣籍降下を逐語的に説明しました。参考サイト（クロアチアのもの）の説明では、（of members of the Imperial family) becoming subjects of the state では説明不足だと思いましたので。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, he is believed to be the first of the Minamoto clan that was created by Emperor Ninmyo, and those, including him and his brothers, who were granted the name of MINAMOTO and split from the Imperial family and became vassals were called Ninmyo-Genji.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, he is believed to be the first of the Minamoto clan that was created by Emperor Ninmyo, and those, including him and his brothers, who were granted the name of MINAMOTO and split from the Imperial family and became vassals were called Ninmyo-Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>承和 (日本)2年（835年）源朝臣の姓を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 835, he was granted the asomi (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) of MINAMOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 835, he was granted the title of Asomi (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) of the MINAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>added “title of”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 835, he was granted the title of Asomi (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) of the MINAMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>嘉祥2年（849年）正月には無位から従四位下に直叙され、翌年の嘉祥3年正月に阿波国守に任ぜられたが、同年4月に父仁明天皇とともに出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was granted the title Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) from no title in 849, assigned to the director of Awa Province in 850 and entered the priesthood in April of the same year together with his father Emperor Ninmyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received his first title, Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), in 849, was assigned to be the director of Awa Province in 850, and entered the priesthood in April of the same year together with his father Emperor Ninmyo.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received his first title, Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), in 849, was assigned to be the Awa no kuni no kami (Governor of Awa Province) in January of 850, and entered the priesthood in April of the same year together with his father Emperor Ninmyo.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一January ofを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし間もなく還俗したらしく、仁寿2年（852年）正月に阿波守に再任され、次いで宮内卿に転じて美作国守・備中国守を兼任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it seemed he soon left the priesthood, was reassigned to the director of Awa in 852, and then was appointed as Kunai-kyo (the Chief Administrator of the Imperial Household) and served also as the director of Bicchu and Mimasaka Provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it seems he soon left the priesthood, was reassigned to the directorship of Awa in 852, and then was appointed Kunai-kyo (the Chief Administrator of the Imperial Household) and served also as the director of Bicchu and Mimasaka Provinces.</e>
<cmt>director-&gt;directorship</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it seems he soon left the priesthood, was reassigned to the Awa no kuni no kami in 852, and then was appointed Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) and served also as the Mimasaka no kuni no kami and Bicchu no kuni no kami.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>斉衡元年（854年）8月28日、24歳の若さで参議に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 28, 854, he was appointed as sangi at the age of 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 28, 854, he was appointed councilor at the age of 24.</e>
<cmt>sangi-&gt;councilor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 28, 854, he was appointed Sangi (councilor) at the age of 24.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後左兵衛督・左衛門督を歴任して貞観 (日本)8年（866年）従三位となり、貞観12年中納言に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then served as Sahyoe no Kami (Director of the Left Imperial Guard), Saemon no Toku (Director of the Left Palace Guard), was granted Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 866, and promoted to Chunagon in 870.</e>
<cmt>ネット検索も注意が必要ですね。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then served as Sahyoe no Kami (Director of the Left Imperial Guard), Saemon no Toku (Director of the Left Palace Guard), was granted Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 866, and promoted to Chunagon in 870.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then served as Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards), Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), was granted Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 866, and promoted to Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) in 870.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この間、参議として信濃国・伊勢国・備前国・近江国の守を兼任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period, he also serve as the director of provinces Shinano, Ise, Bizen and Ohmi in the capacity of sangi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, he also serve as the director of Shinano, Ise, Bizen and Ohmi provinces in his capacity as Councilor.</e>
<cmt>sangi-&gt;councilor, changed word order for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, he also served as the Shinano, Ise, Bizen and Ohmi no kuni no kami in his capacity as Sangi.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一時制(serve -&gt; served)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>貞観14年大納言になり、更に貞観17年正三位に進んで按察使・左近大将を兼ね、元慶3年（879年）従二位、元慶6年（882年）右大臣に任命され、その年職封半減を上表して許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Dainagon in ８７２, was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and served as Azechi (Supervisor of Provincial Directors) and Sakonoe no taisho (Western Commander) in 875, was promoted to Junii in 879, appointed as Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 882, and requested return of the half of his salary and granted in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Dainagon in 872, was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and served as Azechi (Supervisor of Provincial Directors) and Sakonoe no taisho (Western Commander) in 875, was promoted to Junii in 879, appointed to Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 882, and in that same year was granted a request to have his salary halved.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Dainagon (chief councilor of state) in 872, was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and served as Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) and Sakon no daisho (Western Commander) in 875, was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 879, appointed to Udaijin (Minister of the Right) in 882, and in that same year was granted a request to have his shokuho (fiefs) halved.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一職封は官職に応じて与えられた領地などを指すようです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>大納言昇進後の陽成天皇・光孝天皇治世下においては上席の左大臣源融らを凌ぐ権勢を持ち、上卿として多くの官符を奉勅宣布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he was promoted to Dainagon, he maintained the political power greater than his seniors including Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) MINAMOTO no Toru under the reign of Emperor Yozei and Emperor Koko and issued many kanpu (orders from the Dajokan to the agencies under its jurisdiction) under the name of Imperial orders in the capacity of the leading official.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was promoted to Dainagon, he held political power greater than his seniors, including Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) MINAMOTO no Toru under the reign of Emperor Yozei and Emperor Koko and issued many kanpu (orders from the Dajokan to the agencies under its jurisdiction) as Imperial orders in his capacity of chief official.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was promoted to Dainagon (chief councilor of state), he held political power greater than his seniors, including Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) MINAMOTO no Toru under the reign of Emperor Yozei and Emperor Koko and issued many kanpu (official documents from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) as Imperial orders in his capacity of chief official.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>仁和3年（887年）正二位に叙位されたが、仁和4年10月17日に58歳で薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 887, but died at the age of 58 on October 17, 888.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 887, but died at the age of 58 on October 17, 888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 887, but died at the age of 58 on October 17, 888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>最終官位は正二位右大臣権左近衛大将だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His final court rank was Shonii Udaijin gon Sakonoe no taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His final court rank was Shonii Udaijin gon Sakonoe no taisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His final court rank was Shonii Udaijin gon Sakone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>死後従一位を追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was presented posthumously Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously given the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously given the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>仁和年中、深紅色の衣服の着用が禁じられていたにも関わらず、右大臣の多は深紅の襖子（あおし）を着用し、検非違使の小野道風に裂き取られたことがあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the era of Ninna when he was Udaijin, he wore an aoshi in crimson although wearing clothes in crimson was prohibited, and his clothes were ripped off by ONO no Michikaze, who was then assigned to Kebiishi (Imperial police force).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the era of Ninna, when he was Udaijin, he wore a red aoshi, even though wearing red clothes was prohibited, and ONO no Michikaze, who was then assigned to Kebiishi (Imperial police force), ripped off his clothes.</e>
<cmt>crimson-&gt;red, edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the era of Ninna, when he was Udaijin, he wore a red aoshi, even though wearing red clothes was prohibited, and ONO no Michikaze, who was then assigned to kebiishi (officialswith judicial and police powers), ripped off his clothes.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 平惣衛門(id:99387), YOSHI438(id:174755), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>