<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原保則</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasunori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yasunori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasunori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 保則（ふじわら の やすのり、天長2年（825年） - 寛平7年4月21日 (旧暦)（895年5月23日））は平安時代初期の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasunori (825-May 23, 895) was the aristocrat of the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yasunori (825-May 23, 895) was an aristocrat of the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasunori (825-May 23, 895) was an aristocrat of the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>大文字を小文字に表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原南家の出自で藤原貞雄の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He born to the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan and was the child of FUJIWARA no Sadao.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He born to the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan and was the child of FUJIWARA no Sadao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born to the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan and was the child of FUJIWARA no Sadao.</e>
<cmt>was を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は安倍弟富の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of ABE no Ototomi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of ABE no Ototomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of ABE no Ototomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>地方官として善政で治績をあげ良吏として知られ良二千石とうたわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made high achievements as the local official with good government, and was known as the good official and praised as the Ryo Nisenseki (competent local official).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He achieved high status as a local official that governed well, and was known as a good official, and praised as the Ryo Nisenseki (competent local official).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He achieved high status as a local official that governed well, and was known as a good official, and praised as the Ryo Nisenseki (competent local official).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>延長 (日本)8年（930年）の清涼殿落雷事件で落命した権大納言藤原清貫は嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kiyotsura, who had the title of Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor) and died from the lightening incident of Seiryoden (Emperor&apos;s private residence), was his legal son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kiyotsura, who possessed the title of Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor) and died from a lightening incident at Seiryoden (Emperor&apos;s private residence), was his legal son.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kiyotsura, who possessed the title of Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor) and died from a lightening incident at Seiryoden (Emperor&apos;s private residence) in 930, was his legal son.</e>
<cmt>年号を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>子は他に弁官藤原万緒がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had another child, FUJIWARA no Mao, who had the title of Benkan (Oversight Department, Division of the Daijokan responsible for controlling central and provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>藤原万緒→FUJIWARA no Mao[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had another child, FUJIWARA no Mao, who held the title of Benkan (Oversight Department, Division of the Daijokan responsible for controlling central and provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had another child, FUJIWARA no Mao, who held the title of Benkan (Oversight Department, Division of the Daijokan responsible for controlling central and provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>斉衡2年（855年）治部省少丞に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to be the Jibusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Civil Administration) in 855.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to be the Jibusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Civil Administration) in 855.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned to be the Jibusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Civil Administration) in 855.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、民部省少丞、兵部省少丞、式部省少丞を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He successively held various posts of Minbusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Popular Affairs), Hyobusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of War), Shikibusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He successively held various posts of Minbusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Popular Affairs), Hyobusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of War), Shikibusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He successively held various posts of Minbusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Popular Affairs), Hyobusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of War), Shikibusho shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>貞観_(日本)2年（860年）大丞正六位上にあった保則は判官となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori, who held the title of Taijo (Senior Secretary) with the rank of Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade), became Jo (office manager) in 860.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori, who held the title of Taijo (Senior Secretary) with the rank of Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade), became Jo (office manager) in 860.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori, who held the title of Taijo (Senior Secretary) with the rank of Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade), became Jo (office manager) in 860.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>貞観8年（866年）保則は従五位下に進み備中国国司に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori was promoted to the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and was assigned to be the Kokushi (Provincial Governor) of Bitchu no kuni (Bitchu Province) in 866.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori was promoted to the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and was assigned to be the Kokushi (Provincial Governor) of Bitchu no kuni (Bitchu Province) in 866.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori was promoted to the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and was assigned to be the Kokushi (Provincial Governor) of Bitchu no kuni (Bitchu Province) in 866.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>飢饉と悪政によって疲弊が甚だしかった備中国に赴任した保則は貧者を救い、勧農を大いにする善政を施して立て直した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori, who was reassigned to Bitchu Province severely damaged from the famine and misgovernment, saved the poor and rebuilt the government with wise government that greatly encouraged farming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori, who was reassigned to Bitchu Province, which was severely damaged from famine and misgovernment, saved the poor and rebuilt the government with through adroit administration that greatly encouraged farming.</e>
<cmt>Edited for grammar and flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori, who was reassigned to Bitchu Province, which was severely damaged from famine and misgovernment, saved the poor and rebuilt the government with through adroit administration that greatly encouraged farming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、備中守、備前国権守を歴任して、その治績を大いにうたわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He successively held various posts of Bitchu no kami (Governor of Bitchu Province) and Bizen no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Bizen Province) and was greatly admired for his achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He successively held various posts of Bitchu no kami (Governor of Bitchu Province) and Bizen no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Bizen Province) and was greatly admired for his achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He successively held various posts of Bitchu no kami (Governor of Bitchu Province) and Bizen no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Bizen Province) and was greatly admired for his achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>保則が備前国にあったとき、他国から入った盗賊が保則の善政を聞いて恥じ入り自首した話が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a story told, when Yasunori was at Bitchu Province, the gang of robbers who came from the different province heard about the good government of Yasunori, and was so ashamed that they turned themselves in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a story told, when Yasunori was at Bitchu Province, a gang of robbers who came from a different province heard about Yasunori&apos;s administration, and were so ashamed that they turned themselves in.</e>
<cmt>Edited for grammar and flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a story told, when Yasunori was at Bitchu Province, a gang of robbers who came from a different province heard about Yasunori&apos;s administration, and were so ashamed that they turned themselves in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>保則が任を終えて京都へ還るとき、人々が道を遮り泣いて別れを惜しんだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yasunori finished his term and was about to return to Kyoto, people walked across the street, cried and mourned for his departure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yasunori finished his term and was about to return to Kyoto, people walked across the street, cried and mourned his passing..</e>
<cmt>Edited for grammar and flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yasunori finished his term and was about to return to Kyoto, people walked across the street, cried and mourned his passing.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>貞観18年（876年）保則は京に還り、右衛門権佐・検非違使となり都の治安に手腕を発揮し、民部大輔となり従五位上に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori returned to Kyoto in 876 and became Uemon Gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Kebiishi (Office of Police and Judicial Chief) where he showed his great skills for the safety of the capital, became Minbu Taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs) and progressed to the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori returned to Kyoto in 876 and became Uemon Gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Kebiishi (Office of Police and Judicial Chief) where he used his great skills to ensure the safety of the capital, and became Minbu Taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs) and progressed to the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori returned to Kyoto in 876 and became Uemon Gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Kebiishi (Office of Police and Judicial Chief) where he used his great skills to ensure the safety of the capital, and became Minbu Taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs) and progressed to the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>元慶元年（877年）頃には弁官に任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to be Benkan in around 877.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to be Benkan in around 877.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned to be Benkan in around 877.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>元慶2年（878年）従五位上に進み、出羽国権守となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to the rank of Jugoinojo and became the Dewa no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Dewa Province) in 878.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to the rank of Jugoinojo and became the Dewa no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Dewa Province) in 878.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to the rank of Jugoinojo and became the Dewa no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Dewa Province) in 878.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>当時、出羽国では夷俘が反乱を起こして官軍が大敗する事件が起きていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Ifu (old slang for Ainu, the indigenous people in Japan) was revolting in Dewa no kuni and the imperial army was being greatly defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Ifu (old slang for Ainu, the indigenous people in Japan) was revolting in Dewa no kuni and the imperial army was greatly defeated.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Ifu (old slang for Ainu, the indigenous people in Japan) was revolting in Dewa no kuni and the imperial army was greatly defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>保則は地方官としての手腕を期待されて出羽国の受領に任じられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori was assigned to the Zuryo (provincial officials) of Dewa no kuni with high expectation of his skill as the local officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori was assigned to Zuryo (provincial officials) of Dewa no kuni with high expectation of his skill as a local officer.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori was assigned to Zuryo (provincial officials) of Dewa no kuni with high expectation of his skill as a local officer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>出羽国へ着任した保則は兵を配して軍事的措置を講じる一方で、それまでの苛政を改めて政府の備蓄米を民に供して夷俘の懐柔を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori, who was assigned to Dewa no kuni, distributed the army to lecture the military treatment while he restored the damaged government, and handed out the stored rice to people in an attempt to conciliate with Zuryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori, who was assigned to Dewa no kuni, distributed the army, while lecturing on military placement as he restored the damaged government, and handed out stored rice to people in an attempt to conciliate with Zuryo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori, who was assigned to Dewa no kuni, distributed the army, while lecturing on military placement as he restored the damaged government, and handed out stored rice to people in an attempt to conciliate with Ifu.</e>
<cmt>「夷俘」を Zuryo から Ifu に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>保則の善政を聞いて反乱を起こしていた夷俘が次々に投降を願い出、保則はこれを許した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rebelling Zuryo heard the wise government of Yasunori and consecutively demanded to surrender themselves and Yasunori accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rebelling Zuryo heard of the wise government under Yasunori and consecutively demanded their surrender which Yasunori accepted.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rebelling Ifu heard of the wise government under Yasunori and consecutively demanded their surrender which Yasunori accepted.</e>
<cmt>「夷俘」を Zuryo から Ifu に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>追討を命じる朝廷に対して保則は寛政により夷俘を鎮撫することこそ上策であると意見し、朝廷はこれを容れ反乱は武力を用いることなく終息した（元慶の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori commented that the better method was to quell the Zuryo by lenient policy rather than to suppress like the demands of the imperial government, and the imperial government accepted that the revolution ended without the use of military force (Gangyo Rebellion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori commented that the better method was to quell the Zuryo by leniecy rather than suppression, like which was carried out under the imperial government, and the imperial government accepted that the revolution ended without the use of military force (Gangyo Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori commented that the better method was to quell the Ifu by leniency rather than suppression, like which was carried out under the imperial government, and the imperial government accepted that the revolution ended without the use of military force (Gangyo War).</e>
<cmt>「夷俘」を Zuryo から Ifu に修正。スペルを訂正。War に用語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>元慶6年（882年）讃岐国権守だった保則は従四位下に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasunori, who was the Sanuki no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Sanuki Province) was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 882.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasunori, who was the Sanuki no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Sanuki Province) was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 882.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasunori, who was the Sanuki no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Sanuki Province) was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 882.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>仁和3年（887年）伊予国守に任じられたが辞退し、大宰大弐に任じられ、従四位上に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to be the Iyo no kuni no kami (Governor of Iyo Province) but refrained and was assigned to be the Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu Offices) and gained the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 887.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to be the Iyo no kuni no kami (Governor of Iyo Province) but declined the position and was assigned to be the Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu Offices) and gained the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 887.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 887, he was assigned to be the Iyo no kuni no kami (Governor of Iyo Province) but declined the position and was assigned to be the Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu Offices) and gained the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>年号の位置を修正。「従四位上」をJushiinogeからJushiinojoに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>宇多天皇は保則の力量を高く評価し、寛平3年（891年）左大弁、次いで参議、近江国権守、民部卿に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Uda highly valued the skill of Yasunori and assigned him to be the Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left) in 891, Sangi (Royal Advisor), Omi no kuni Gon no Kami (Provisional Governor of Omi Province), and Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Uda highly valued the skill of Yasunori and assigned him to be the Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left) in 891, Sangi (Royal Advisor), Omi no kuni Gon no Kami (Provisional Governor of Omi Province), and Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Uda highly valued the skill of Yasunori and assigned him to be the Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left) in 891, Sangi (Royal Advisor), Omi no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Omi Province), and Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>大文字から小文字へ表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>寛平7年（895年）死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed away in 895.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away in 895.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away in 895.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>死の間際に比叡山に入り、そこで念仏を唱えながら亡くなったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Mount Hiei just before he death and supposedly died while chanting Nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered Mount Hiei just before he death and supposedly died while chanting Nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered Mount Hiei just before he death and supposedly died while chanting Nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>三善清行はその功績を称えて『藤原保則伝』を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyoyuki (Kiyotsura) MIYOSHI wrote &quot;FUJIWARA no Yasunori den&quot; (Bibliography of FUJIWARA no Yasunori) in honor of his high achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyoyuki (Kiyotsura) MIYOSHI wrote &quot;FUJIWARA no Yasunori den&quot; (Bibliography of FUJIWARA no Yasunori) in honor of his high achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyoyuki (Kiyotsura) MIYOSHI wrote &quot;FUJIWARA no Yasunori den&quot; (Bibliography of FUJIWARA no Yasunori) in honor of his high achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Papamaruchan22(id:71152), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), 味っ子(id:17086), Point136(id:211299), YOSHI438(id:174755), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>