<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原通憲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michinori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michinori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michinori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 通憲（ふじわら の みちのり、嘉祥元年（1106年）？ - 平治元年12月13日 (旧暦)（1160年1月23日））は、平安時代末期の貴族・学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michinori (1106 - January 23, 1160 (December 13, 1159 by the old calendar)) was an aristocrat and scholar living at the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michinori (1106 - January 23, 1160 (December 13, 1159 by the old calendar)) was an aristocrat and scholar living at the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michinori (1106 - January 23, 1160) was a noble and scholar living at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>period と小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>出家後の戒名である信西（しんぜい）の方が有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is better known by his posthumous Buddhist name Shinzei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is better known by his posthumous Buddhist name Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is better known by his posthumous Buddhist name Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>藤原南家出身とされ、蔵人藤原実兼の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinori is said be from the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan, and the son of FUJIWARA no Sanekane, the keeper of imperial archives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinori is said be from the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan, and the son of FUJIWARA no Sanekane, the keeper of imperial archives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinori is said be from the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan, and the son of FUJIWARA no Sanekane, who held the tile of Kurodo (he keeper of imperial archives).</e>
<cmt>kurodo を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>生母は源有家女説と源有房女説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is some debate about whether his mother was MINAMOTO no Ariei or MINAMOTO no Arifusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is some debate about whether his mother was MINAMOTO no Ariei or MINAMOTO no Arifusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is some debate about whether his mother was the daughter of MINAMOTO no Ariei or the daughter of MINAMOTO no Arifusa.</e>
<cmt>daughter of を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ただし、一時高階経敏の養子となり高階氏を名乗るが、鳥羽上皇の院政期に復姓した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinori was temporarily adopted by TAKESHINA no Tsunetoshi and used the Takashina name; however, he returned to the Fujiwara family when the government of retired Emperor Toba was reinstated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinori was temporarily adopted by TAKESHINA no Tsunetoshi and used the Takashina name; however, he returned to the Fujiwara family when the government of retired Emperor Toba was reinstated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinori was temporarily adopted by TAKASHINA no Tsunetoshi and used the Takashina name; however, he returned to the Fujiwara family when the government of Retired Emperor Toba was reinstated.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>妻は高階重仲の息女、後に、後白河天皇の乳母の藤原朝子（紀伊局）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first wife was the daughter of TAKASHINA no Shigenaka and he later married FUJIWARA no Asako (Kii no Tsubone) who was nanny to Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first wife was the daughter of TAKASHINA no Shigenaka, and he later married FUJIWARA no Asako (Kii no Tsubone), who was nanny to Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first wife was the daughter of TAKASHINA no Shigenaka, and he later married FUJIWARA no Asako (Kii no Tsubone), who was a wet nurse to Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>乳母→wet nurse としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>子として高階氏との間に藤原俊憲・藤原貞憲・藤原是憲の3人が紀伊局との間には藤原成範がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had three children with Takashina&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Toshinori, Sadanori and Korenori, and a son, Shigenori, with Kii no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had three children with Takashina&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Toshinori, Sadanori, and Korenori, and a son, Shigenori, with Kii no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had three children with Takashina&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Toshinori, Sadanori, and Korenori, and a son, Shigenori, with Kii no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>通憲の家系は曽祖父藤原実範以来代々学者の家系として知られ、祖父の藤原季綱は大学頭であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinori came from a line of scholars that started with his great-grandfather, FUJIWARA no Sanenori, and his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Suetsuna, who was head of a university.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinori came from a line of scholars that started with his great-grandfather, FUJIWARA no Sanenori, and his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Suetsuna, who was head of a university.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinori came from a line of scholars that started with his great-grandfather, FUJIWARA no Sanenori, and his grandfather, FUJIWARA no Suetsuna, who was head of Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education).</e>
<cmt>大学頭→Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ところが、天永3年（1112年）に父が蔵人所で急死したため、幼少であった通憲は縁戚であった高階経敏の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1112, his father died suddenly in the Chamberlain&apos;s Office; and being a young boy, he was adopted by TAKASHINA no Tsunetoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1112, his father died suddenly in the Chamberlain&apos;s Office; and being a young boy, he was adopted by TAKASHINA no Tsunetoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1112, his father died suddenly in the Kurodo dokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office); being a young boy, he was adopted by TAKASHINA no Tsunetoshi, one of his relatives.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、藤原璋子（待賢門院）に仕えて天治2年（1125年）に従五位下に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he served FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Empress Dowager Taiken) and in 1125, he was awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he served FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Empress Dowager Taiken) and in 1125, he was awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he served FUJIWARA no Shoshi (Empress Dowager Taiken) and in 1125, he was awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、待賢門院の推挙で鳥羽上皇に仕えた通憲は学問にも励み、当世無双の宏才博覧と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A recommendation from the Empress Dowager Taiken placed Michinori in the service of Emperor Toba, in which he studied hard and became famous as a person of intelligence and extensive knowledge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A recommendation from the Empress Dowager Taiken placed Michinori in the service of Emperor Toba, under whom he studied hard and became famous as a person of intelligence and extensive knowledge.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A recommendation from the Empress Dowager Taiken placed Michinori in the service of Retired Emperor Toba, under whom he studied hard and became famous as a person of intelligence and extensive knowledge.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後日向国国司に任命され、「本朝世紀」、「法曹類林」の編纂も行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was then appointed governor of Hyuga Province, and published &quot;Honchoseiki&quot; and &quot;Hosoruirin.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was then appointed governor of Hyuga Province, and published &quot;Honchoseiki&quot; and &quot;Hosoruirin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was then appointed governor of Hyuga Province, and published &apos;Honcho seiki&apos; (Chronicle of Imperial Reigns)&apos; and &apos;Hosoruirin&apos; (law book established in the late Heian period).</e>
<cmt>書籍の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>彼の願いは曽祖父・祖父の後を継いで大学寮の役職に就いて学問の家系としての家名の再興にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His desire was to follow in the footsteps of his great-grandfather and grandfather by becoming an official of a university dorm and bringing the reputation of scholar back to his family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His desire was to follow in the footsteps of his great-grandfather and grandfather by becoming an official of a university dormitory and bringing a scholarly reputation back to his family.</e>
<cmt>rwording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His desire was to follow in the footsteps of his great-grandfather and grandfather by serving at Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) and bringing a scholarly reputation back to his family.</e>
<cmt>大学寮→Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが、世襲化が進んだ当時の公家社会の仕組みでは、高階氏の戸籍に入ってしまった通憲には、その時点で実範・季綱を世襲する資格を剥奪されており、大学寮の官職には就けなくなってしまっていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in an age when nepotistic succession was common among the nobility, Michinori, who joined the Takashina family, was stripped of his right to succeed Sanenori and Setsuna, and could not be appointed an official to a university dormitory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in an age when nepotistic succession was common among the nobility, Michinori, who joined the Takashina family, was stripped of his right to succeed Sanenori and Setsuna, and could not be appointed an official to a university dormitory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in an age when nepotistic succession was common among the nobility, Michinori, who joined the Takashina family, was stripped of his right to succeed Sanenori and Suetsuna, and could not be appointed an official of Daigaku-ryo.</e>
<cmt>Daigaku-ryo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これに失望した通憲は無力感から出家を考えるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disappointed with his fate, he considered joining the priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disappointed with his fate, he considered joining the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disappointed with his fate, he considered joining the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>鳥羽上皇はこれを宥めようとして康治2年（1143年）に正五位下を与え、翌天養元年（1144年）には藤原姓への復姓を許して少納言に任命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trying to persuade him to reconsider, Emperor Toba awarded him the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1143, and in 1144, approved his return to the Fujiwara family and appointed him as Shonagon (Lower Councillor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an attempt to persuade him to reconsider, Emperor Toba awarded him the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1143, and in 1144, approved his return to the Fujiwara family and appointed him Shonagon (Lower Councillor).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an attempt to persuade him to reconsider, Emperor Toba awarded him the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1143, and in 1144, approved his return to the Fujiwara family and appointed him Shonagon (lesser councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>少納言→Shonagon (lesser councilor of state)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>更に息子・俊憲に文章博士・大学頭に就任するために必要な資格を得る試験である対策の受験を認める宣旨を与えたが、通憲の意思は固く、同年7月22日_(旧暦)に出家して信西と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he issued a proclamation authorizing Michinori&apos;s son, Toshinori, to take the examination for the certification required for appointment as Professor of Letters and head of the university; however Michinori&apos;s decision was firm and he joined the priesthood on July 22 (by the old calendarr) and took the name Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he issued a proclamation authorizing Michinori&apos;s son, Toshinori, to take the examination for the certification required for appointment as Professor of Letters and head of the university; however Michinori&apos;s decision was firm and he joined the priesthood on July 22 (by the old calendar), taking the name Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>spelling, rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he issued a proclamation authorizing Michinori&apos;s son, Toshinori, to take the examination for the certification required for appointment as Monjo hakase (professor of literature) and Daigaku no kami; however Michinori&apos;s decision was firm and he joined the priesthood on August 29, 1144, taking the name Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。文章博士→Monju hakase を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>その後も鳥羽法皇に仕えた信西は、後白河天皇の乳母（紀伊局）の夫であることから、後白河の即位を実現させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he served the Cloistered Emperor Toba, and being the husband of Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s nanny, made efforts for Goshirakawa&apos;s returned to power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he served the Cloistered Emperor Toba, and being the husband of Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s nanny, made efforts for Goshirakawa&apos;s return to power.</e>
<cmt>&quot;returned&quot; to &quot;return&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he served the Cloistered Emperor Toba, and being the husband of Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s wet nurse, made efforts for Goshirakawa&apos;s return to power.</e>
<cmt>乳母→wet nurse としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>平清盛ら武士の起用も進め、1156年7月鳥羽上皇が亡くなるとその葬儀の準備を行い、続いて保元の乱が起こると、源義朝の献策を積極採用して、夜襲作戦を採用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also recruited samurai, such as TAIRA no Kiyomori, and after arranging for memorial services for retired Emperor Toba when he passed away in July 1156, he fought in the Hogen Disturbance, actively adopting MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo&apos;s plan for a night raid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also recruited samurai, including TAIRA no Kiyomori, and after arranging for memorial services for retired Emperor Toba when he passed away in July 1156, he fought in the Hogen Disturbance, actively adopting MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo&apos;s plan for a night raid.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also recruited samurai, including TAIRA no Kiyomori, and after arranging for memorial services for Retired Emperor Toba when he passed away in July 1156, he fought in the Hogen War, actively adopting MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo&apos;s plan for a night raid.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>結果、後白河天皇・信西・清盛側が勝利を収める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa, Shinzei, and Kiyomori achieved victory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Goshirakawa, Shinzei, and Kiyomori achieved victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa, Shinzei, and Kiyomori achieved victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>死刑制度を復活させて、源為義らを処断した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The death penalty was resumed and MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi was executed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The death penalty was resumed and MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi was executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The death penalty was resumed and MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi was executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、摂関家の弱体化と天皇親政を進め、新制七カ条を定め、記録荘園券契所を再興して荘園の整理を行うなど、絶大な権力を振るう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He moved forward to weaken the line of regents and advisers, and the emperor&apos;s rule, and he exerted power to establish Shinsei Nana Kajo and restore Kirokushoenkenkeisho (Research office of manor) to a reorganized manor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinori moved forward to weaken the line of regents and advisers, and the emperor&apos;s rule, and he exerted power to establish Shinsei Nana Kajo and restore Kirokushoenkenkeisho (Research office of manor) to a reorganized manor.</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinori moved forward to weaken the power of Sekkan-ke (families of regents and advisers) and to promoted the direct rule by the emperor; he exerted power to establish Shinsei Nana Kajo (newly established seven rules) and restore Kirokushoenkenkeisho (Research office of manor) to a reorganized manor.</e>
<cmt>新制七カ条　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、大内裏の再建や相撲節会の復活なども信西の手腕によるところが大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The restoration of the Daidairi (The Heian Palace) and the revival of Sumai no Sechie (an annual event of the period) were possible because of Shinzei&apos;s outstanding abilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The restoration of Daidairi (The Heian Palace) and the revival of Sumai no Sechie (an annual event of the period) were made possible by Shinzei&apos;s outstanding abilities.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The restoration of Daidairi (The Heian Palace) and the revival of Sumai no Sechie (an annual event of the period) were made possible by Shinzei&apos;s outstanding abilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その後、二条天皇が即位し、後白河院政が始まると、藤原信頼や源義朝らの反対勢力が結集し、1159年平清盛が熊野詣に出かけた留守にクーデター（平治の乱）が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, when Emperor Nijo was enthroned, and the Goshirakawa government took power, the opposing powers, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and MINAOTO no Yoshitomo, collected their forces and staged a coup (the Heiji Revolt) in 1159 while TAIRA no Kiyomori was visiting Kumano Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, when Emperor Nijo was enthroned and the Goshirakawa government took power, the opposing powers, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and MINAOTO no Yoshitomo, collected their forces and staged a coup (the Heiji Revolt) in 1159 while TAIRA no Kiyomori was visiting Kumano Shrine.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, when Emperor Nijo was enthroned and the government of Retired Emperor Goshirakawa took power, the opposing powers, FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, collected their forces and staged a coup (the Heiji War) in 1159 while TAIRA no Kiyomori was visiting Kumano Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor Goshirakawa としました。Heiji War としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>信西は義朝・信頼の軍勢に追われ、伊賀国の山中で源光保に捕らえられて首をはねられた（クーデターそのものは清盛によって鎮圧され、後の平氏政権の基礎が固まった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzei was pursued by Yoshitomo and Nobuyori&apos;s army, captured in the mountains of Iga Province by MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and beheaded (The coup was put down by Kiyomori, and the foundation for Taira government to come in later years was established).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzei was pursued by Yoshitomo and Nobuyori&apos;s army, captured in the mountains of Iga Province by MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and beheaded (The coup was put down by Kiyomori, and the foundation for Taira government to come in later years was established).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzei was pursued by Yoshitomo and Nobuyori&apos;s army, captured in the mountains of Iga Province by MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and beheaded (The coup was put down by Kiyomori, and the foundation for Taira government to come in later years was established).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>学問に優れ、藤原頼長と並ぶ当代屈指の碩学として知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzei was a learned individual, known as one of the top scholars of the period, an equal of FUJIWARA no Yorigana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzei was a learned individual, known as one of the top scholars of the period, an equal of FUJIWARA no Yorigana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzei was a learned individual, known as one of the top scholars of the period, an equal of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>Yorinaga　と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>『今鏡』でもその才能を絶賛する一方で、陰陽道の家の出でもないのに天文学に通じたがために災いを受けたのだと評されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His outstanding intellect was highly praised in &quot;Imakagami (a collection of historical stories)&quot;; on the other hand, he is said to have brought disaster by studying astronomy even though he was not from the family of Onmyoudou, way of Yin and Yang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His outstanding intellect was highly praised in &quot;Imakagami (a collection of historical stories)&quot;; on the other hand, he is said to have brought disaster by studying astronomy even though he was not from the family of Onmyoudou, the way of Yin and Yang.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His outstanding intellect was highly praised in &quot;Imakagami&quot; (a collection of historical stories); on the other hand, he is said to have brought disaster by studying astronomy even though he was not from the family of Onmyodo, the way of Yin and Yang.</e>
<cmt>陰陽道→Onmyodo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>登場作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Film and drama about Michinori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Film and drama about Michinori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works in which he makes an appearance</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>『弓張月』（1955年 監督：丸根賛太郎、演：百々木直）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yumiharizuki (Half/quarter moon)&apos; (1955, Director: Santaro MARUNE, Michinori played by: Nao MOMOKI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yumiharizuki (Half/quarter moon)&apos; (1955, Director: Santaro MARUNE, Michinori played by: Nao MOMOKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yumiharizuki (Half/quarter moon)&quot; (1955, Director: Santaro MARUNE, portrayed by Nao MOMOKI)</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと合わせ、portrayed by としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>『新・平家物語 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1972年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：小沢栄太郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shin Heike Monogatari (NHK Period Drama)&apos; (1972: NHK Period Drama, Michinori played by Eitaro OZAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shin Heike Monogatari (NHK Period Drama)&apos; (1972: NHK Period Drama, Michinori played by Eitaro OZAWA)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shin Heike Monogatari (NHK Taiga drama series)&quot; (1972: NHK Taiga drama series, portrayed by Eitaro OZAWA)</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと合わせ、portrayed by としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>『平清盛 (TBSドラマ)』（1992年 TBS、演：原口剛）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Kiyomori (TBS Drama)&apos; (1992: Michinori played by Takeshi HARAGUCHI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Kiyomori (TBS Drama)&apos; (1992: Michinori played by Takeshi HARAGUCHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Kiyomori (TBS Drama)&quot; (1992: portrayed by Takeshi HARAGUCHI)</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと合わせ、portrayed by としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Resto1578(id:168692), てら1971(id:131768), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), 水野白楓(id:22811), Andee(id:20421), BAKU(id:55205), 彩華1226(id:64711), YurikBot(id:18605), 代言人(id:33675), Nevylax(id:38464), Point136(id:211299), Ponsaku(id:31417), 川端恵(id:59176), 小太刀(id:18154), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>