<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小野妹子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ONO no Imoko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ONO no Imoko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ONO no Imoko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小野 妹子（おの の いもこ、男性、生没年不詳）は、飛鳥時代の政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ONO no Imoko (male, dates of birth and death unknown) was a politician who lived during the Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ONO no Imoko (male, dates of birth and death unknown) was a politician who lived during the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ONO no Imoko (male, dates of birth and death unknown) was a politician who lived during the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>姓は臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His last name was Omi.</e>
<cmt>臣：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His last name was Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His &apos;kabane&apos;(the title of a chieftain of a clan) was Omi.</e>
<cmt>用語修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に小野毛人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his sons was ONO no Emishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his sons was ONO no Emishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his sons was ONO no Emishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>『日本書紀』によると大唐に派遣され、大禮（冠位十二階の位）蘇因高と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Imoko was deployed to Great Tang of China, where he was called &apos;Soinko&apos; of Ore (one of the twelve grades of cap rank).</e>
<cmt>http://www.weblio.jp/content/%E5%A4%A7%E7%A6%AE</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; Imoko was deployed to Great Tang of China, where he was called &apos;Soinko&apos; of Ore (one of the 12 grades of cap rank).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; Imoko was deployed to Great Tang of China, where he was called &apos;Soinko&apos; of Tairei (one of &quot;the twelve grades of cap rank&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Taireiと読むべきだと思います表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本の通説では『隋書』が記録する「」の文言で知られる国書を携えた使者は小野妹子とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly viewed in Japan that the envoy who carried an official letter to the Sui Dynasty and who is referred to as &apos;the Imperial Prince of the sun-rising country&apos; in &quot;Suishu (the Book of the Sui Dynasty)&quot; was ONO no Imoko.</e>
<cmt>原文では、「」に文字が入っていませんでしたので、「日出処天子」と訳では入れています。http://eow.alc.co.jp/%e5%9b%bd%e6%9b%b8/UTF-8/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A common perception in Japan is that the envoy who carried an official letter to the Sui Dynasty and is referred to as &apos;the Imperial Prince of the land of the rising sun&apos; in &quot;Suishu (the Book of the Sui Dynasty)&quot; was ONO no Imoko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A common perception in Japan is that the envoy who carried an official letter to the Sui Dynasty was ONO no Imoko; the letter is known to include the wording of &quot;the Imperial Prince of the land of the rising sun according to Suishu (the Book of the Sui Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>原文に抜け（「」内）があります。翻訳者の方のいうとおり、｢日出処天子」という言葉を補った場合も、transの訳では、小野妹子が天子ということになってしまうため、修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「妹子」であるが 男性である（当時は「子」が男女問わずに用いられた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his name was &apos;Imoko (妹子)&apos;, he was a man (in this period of time, &apos;ko (子) was used for both male and female names).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his name was &apos;Imoko (妹子),&apos; he was a man (during that period of time, &apos;ko (子) was used for both male and female names).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his name was &apos;Imoko (妹子),&apos; he was a man (during that period of time, &apos;ko (子) was used for both male and female names).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>近江国滋賀郡小野村（大津市）の豪族小野氏の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imoko was born into the ONO clan, a local ruling family, in Ono Village, Shiga County, Omi Province (present-day Otsu City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imoko was born into the ONO clan, a local ruling family, in Ono Village, Shiga County, Omi Province (the present-day Otsu City).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imoko was born into the ONO clan, a local ruling family, in Ono Village, Shiga County, Omi Province (the present-day Otsu City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>『日本書紀』（巻第二十二）によれば、推古天皇15年(607年)、鞍作福利らと大唐に渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Volume 22), Imoko was sent to Great Tang of China with KURATSUKURI no Fukuri in 607.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Volume 22 of &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; Imoko was sent to Great Tang of China with KURATSUKURI no Fukuri in 607.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Volume 22 of &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; Imoko was sent to Great Tang of China with KURATSUKURI no Fukuri in 607.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>推古天皇16年(608年)に裴世清を伴って帰国、ただし煬帝の返書は帰路に百済において紛失した（紛失に関しては諸説あり、とても見せることが出来る内容ではなかったからであるとする説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 608, Imoko returned with HAI Seisei (an envoy of the Sui Dynasty) without a reply letter from Emperor Yodai of Tang, as Imoko lost it in Kudara (Paekche in early Korea) on his way back (there are many theories on the loss of the letter; one theory says that the letter had such a horrible content that Imoko couldn&apos;t show it to the Emperor of Japan).</e>
<cmt>「裴世清」：念のため日本語読みで訳しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 608, Imoko returned with HAI Seisei (an envoy of the Sui Dynasty) without a reply letter from Emperor Yodai of Tang, as Imoko had lost it in Kudara (Paekche in early Korea) on his way back (there are many theories regarding the loss of the letter, one of which asserts that the letter had such a horrible content that Imoko couldn&apos;t show it to the Emperor of Japan).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 608, Imoko returned with HAI Seisei (an envoy of the Sui Dynasty) without a reply letter from Emperor Yodai of Sui, as Imoko had lost it in Kudara (Paekche in early Korea) on his way back (there are many theories regarding the loss of the letter, one of which asserts that the letter had such a horrible content that Imoko couldn&apos;t show it to the Emperor of Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処、原文を修正しました。煬帝は隋の第二大皇帝</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一時は流刑に処されるが、恩赦されて大徳に昇進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Imoko was sent into exile for the loss, he was granted amnesty soon after and promoted to Daitoku (the first grade of &quot;Twelve grades of cap rank&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Imoko was sent into exile for the loss, he was granted amnesty soon after and promoted to Daitoku (the first grade of &quot;12 grades of cap rank&quot;).</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Imoko was sent into exile for the loss, he was granted amnesty soon after and promoted to Daitoku (the first grade of &quot;the twelve grades of cap rank&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>翌年には返書と裴世清の帰国のため、高向玄理、南淵請安、旻らと再び派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, Imoko was again sent to the Sui Dynasty along with TAKAMUKO no Kuromaro, MINABUCHI no Shoan and Min in order to bring another official letter and to accompany HAI Seisei back to the Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, Imoko was again sent to the Sui Dynasty along with TAKAMUKO no Kuromaro, MINABUCHI no Shoan and Min in order to bring another official letter and accompany HAI Seisei back to the dynasty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, Imoko was again sent to the Sui Dynasty along with TAKAMUKO no Kuromaro, MINABUCHI no Shoan and Min in order to bring another official letter and accompany HAI Seisei back to the dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>『隋書』「卷八十一 列傳第四十六 東夷 俀國」には、大業三年（607年）、隋の皇帝煬帝（ようだい）が激怒したことで有名な 「」との文言がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Suishu (Volume 81, Chapter 46, Eastern Barbarians, Wakoku [Japan]), there was a sentence famous for enraging Emperor Odai of the Sui in 607; &apos;this letter is from the Imperial Prince of the sun-rising country to the emperor of the sun-sinking country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>列傳：意味不明です。「日出處天子致書日沒處天子無恙云云」カッコ内追加。最後の四文字は、「お元気でしょうか？」という意味のようですが（下記参照）、有名ではないので訳は省いています。http://suikodo.sblo.jp/article/21825215.html訳文は下記です。http://eow.alc.co.jp/%e8%81%96%e5%be%b3%e5%a4%aa%e5%ad%90/UTF-8/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Suishu (Volume 81, Chapter 46, Eastern Barbarians, Wakoku [Japan]), there was a sentence famous for enraging Emperor Odai of the Sui in 607, stating, &apos;this letter is from the Imperial Prince of the land of the rising sun to the emperor of the land of the setting sun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Suishu (Volume 81, Retsuden [a series of biographies] Chapter 46, Eastern Barbarians, Wakoku [Japan]), there was a sentence famous for enraging Emperor Yodai of the Sui in 607, stating, &apos;this letter is from the Imperial Prince of the land of the rising sun to the emperor of the land of the setting sun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「列伝」の訳を追加しました。スペルミス原文の｢｣内が抜けています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『隋書』には国書を持参した者の名前の記載はなく、ただ使者とあるのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Suishu&quot; does not refer to the name of Imoko, but the man who brought the official letter to the Sui Dynasty is merely mentioned as an envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Suishu&quot; does not refer to the name of Imoko, but instead the man who brought the official letter to the Sui Dynasty is merely mentioned as an envoy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Suishu&quot; does not refer to the name of Imoko, but instead the man who brought the official letter to the Sui Dynasty is merely mentioned as an envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>小野妹子は「華道の祖」とされることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ONO no Imoko is sometimes regarded as a &apos;founder of Kado flower arrangement&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ONO no Imoko is sometimes regarded as the &apos;founder of Kado flower arrangement.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ONO no Imoko is sometimes regarded as the &apos;founder of Kado flower arrangement.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>小野妹子墓は大阪府南河内郡太子町 (大阪府)科長神社（しながじんじゃ）南側の小高い丘の上にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tomb of ONO no Imoko lies on the hill of the southern area of Shinaga-jinja Shrine in Taishi-cho, Minamikawachi County, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tomb of ONO no Imoko lies on the hill of the southern area of Shinaga-jinja Shrine in Taishi-cho, Minamikawachi County, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tomb of ONO no Imoko lies on the hill of the southern area of Shinaga-jinja Shrine in Taishi-cho, Minamikawachi County, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>小野妹子公園（滋賀県大津市小野）そばの唐臼山古墳（からうすやまこふん）を小野妹子の墓とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another theory that Imoko is buried in the Karausuyama-kofun burial mound which is located close to the ONO-no-Imoko park (Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another theory that Imoko is buried in the Karausuyama-kofun burial mound, which is located close to ONO-no-Imoko Park in Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another theory that Imoko is buried in the Karausuyama-kofun burial mound, which is located close to ONO-no-Imoko Park in Ono, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>地名(小野）を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>唐臼山古墳南方の古墳は妹子の父の墓である可能性が指摘されており、大津市教育委員会による事前調査が行われたものの破壊され現存しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been pointed out that another mound in the south of the Karausuyama-kofun burial mound belongs to Imoko&apos;s father and a preliminary survey was conducted by the Otsu City Board of Education, but the mound was found destroyed beyond repair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been pointed out that another mound to the south of the Karausuyama-kofun burial mound belongs to Imoko&apos;s father, and a preliminary survey was conducted by the Otsu City Board of Education, but the mound was found to have been destroyed beyond repair.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been pointed out that another mound to the south of the Karausuyama-kofun burial mound belongs to Imoko&apos;s father, and a preliminary survey was conducted by the Otsu City Board of Education, but the mound was found to have been destroyed beyond repair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>よくある誤解</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misunderstanding</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misunderstanding</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misunderstanding</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>古代の日本の人名の最後に「～子（あるいは古）」と付ける表現は男性名についても珍しいものではなかったが、現代の日本では「～子」は女性名の最後に付ける文字の定番となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although naming a child, regardless of sex, a name ending with &apos;ko (子) or (古)&apos; was not unusual in ancient Japan, it is only common for female names in modern Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although naming a child, regardless of sex, a name ending with &apos;ko (子) or (古)&apos; was not unusual in ancient Japan, today it is only common for female names.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although naming a child, regardless of sex, a name ending with &apos;ko (子) or (古)&apos; was not unusual in ancient Japan, today it is only common for female names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このため、現代において小野妹子を女性であると勘違いする日本人が意外と多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there are unexpectedly many Japanese who believe ONO no Imoko was a woman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, surprisingly many Japanese believe ONO no Imoko was a woman.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, surprisingly many Japanese believe ONO no Imoko was a woman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、「妹」という字が使われているのも誤解を助長する原因と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the kanji &apos;妹&apos; (which means &apos;a younger sister&apos;) can also encourage the misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the kanji &apos;妹&apos; (which means &apos;a younger sister&apos;) can also encourage the misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the kanji &apos;妹&apos; (which means &apos;a younger sister&apos;) can also encourage the misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>例えば、タレントの井上聡（次長課長）が「世界三大美人に入っている日本人は？」という問いに「小野妹子」と答えたことがあった（本当の正解は小野小町。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Satoshi INOUE, half of the comedy duo (Jicho-Kacho), answered &apos;ONO no Imoko&apos;, when asked &apos;who is a Japanese woman chosen for the world&apos;s three the most beautiful women?&apos; (a correct answer was &apos;ONO no Komachi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Satoshi INOUE, half of the comedy duo Jicho-Kacho, answered &apos;ONO no Imoko&apos; when asked &apos;who is a Japanese woman chosen as being among the world&apos;s three most beautiful women?&apos; (the correct answer was &apos;ONO no Komachi).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Satoshi INOUE, half of the comedy duo Jicho-Kacho, answered &apos;ONO no Imoko&apos; when asked &apos;who is a Japanese woman chosen as being among the world&apos;s three most beautiful women?&apos; (the correct answer was &apos;ONO no Komachi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ちなみに、小町は妹子の末裔とされている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Komachi is believed to have been the descendant of Imoko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Komachi is believed to have been a descendant of Imoko.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Komachi is believed to have been a descendant of Imoko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ただしこれは、お笑い芸人である井上が、わざとボケとして発言しただけで本当に女性だと思っていたかどうかは怪しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is doubtful that Inoue truly believed that Imoko was a woman, because he as a comedian could purposely fool people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is doubtful that Inoue truly believed Imoko was a woman, because he as a comedian could intentionally fool people.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is doubtful that Inoue truly believed Imoko was a woman, because he as a comedian could intentionally fool people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、この誤解を利用した東京瓦斯のコマーシャルメッセージにおいて、ギャグ的設定で「女性の妹子」として酒井若菜が出演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, one commercial of Tokyo Gas Company, Limited used this misunderstanding, and an actress, Wakana SAKAI, appeared as a &apos;female Imoko&apos; as a joke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, one commercial for the Tokyo Gas Company, Limited, used this misunderstanding, and as a joke the actress Wakana SAKAI appeared as a &apos;female Imoko&apos; as a joke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, one commercial for the Tokyo Gas Company, Limited, used this misunderstanding, and as a joke the actress Wakana SAKAI appeared as a &apos;female Imoko&apos; as a joke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>誤解をさらに広めてしまうのを防ぐ配慮としてか、共演の妻夫木聡に「小野妹子って男じゃ......」「（本当は男性なのに、女性であると）歴史を曲げるなよ......」とツッコませている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order not to mislead viewers, a co-actor, Satoshi TSUMABUKI, says &apos;ONO no Imoko was a man. Don&apos;t distort the historical fact&apos; in the commercial.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order not to mislead viewers, a co-actor, Satoshi TSUMABUKI, says &apos;ONO no Imoko was a man; don&apos;t distort the historical fact&apos; in the commercial.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order not to mislead viewers, a co-actor, Satoshi TSUMABUKI, says &apos;ONO no Imoko was a man; don&apos;t distort the historical fact&apos; in the commercial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>CM開始当初には無かったが、当該CMの冒頭に、字幕で「※実際には男性です」なる注釈も併せて表示していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company also posted the caption saying &apos;Actually, he was a man&apos; at the beginning of the commercial (although the first version of the commercial did not have such footnote).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company also employed a caption that read, &apos;Actually, he was a man&apos; at the beginning of the commercial (although the first version of the commercial did not have such a caption).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company also employed a caption that read, &apos;Actually, he was a man&apos; at the beginning of the commercial (although the first version of the commercial did not have such a caption).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>ただし、男性名に&quot;妹&quot;の字を使ったのかは、今も誰も明確な答をだしてはいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, no one could have answered to a question that whether or not it was common for a male to use &quot;妹&quot; in his name in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, no one could have answered the question as to whether or not it was common in ancient Japan for a male to use &quot;妹&quot; in his name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, no one could have answered the question as to whether or not it was common in ancient Japan for a male to use &quot;妹&quot; in his name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>そもそも「妹」とは、かつては「いも」と読み、男性からみた同腹の女性の他、恋人や妻などの親しい女性全般を指す言葉であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, &quot;妹&quot; was pronounced &apos;Imo&apos; and referred to women at large including sisters, lovers and wives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, &quot;妹&quot; was pronounced &apos;Imo&apos; and referred to women at large, including sisters, lovers and wives.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, &quot;妹&quot; was pronounced &apos;Imo&apos; and referred to women of close relationships at large, including sisters, lovers and wives.</e>
<cmt>｢親しい」の意味を追加しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TT(id:46431), Straysheep(id:42448), Death Valley 69(id:90824), Nnh(id:474), のーさん(id:258153), Jhnexco(id:191199), 黄金もち(id:102311), Mizumura(id:126435), Lupinoid(id:68), Sutou(id:32), Andee(id:20421), Mishika(id:276), ひろっきー(id:87284), 蓮田駅(id:47050), 代言人(id:33675), 海獺(id:153448), 怪蘇(id:45514), 堀内(id:66111), Loveless(id:129239), 5816K(id:102574), Cinemableu(id:245042), Volfgang(id:98768), KASAGI(id:24405), Kurokirishima(id:177343), デーモン博士(id:99293), Izayohi(id:13095), YOSHI0505(id:107383), 9PgUp(id:24726), 葉月(id:25674), JunK(id:14563), KENPEI(id:11349), ごまふあざ(id:36855), Carkuni(id:79281), トホホ川(id:50502), SVS(id:18615), 木村正人(id:120764), Junger(id:10282), Riden(id:27573), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>