<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>磯田多佳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taka ISODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taka ISODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taka ISODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>磯田多佳（いそだ・たか　本名たか　1879年 - 1945年）は、祇園甲部の芸妓で京都市東山区祇園新橋に営業していたお茶屋『大友（だいとも）』の女将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taka ISODA (her real name was Taka, from 1879 to 1945) was Geisya in Gion Kobu, and she was Okami (mistress) of &quot;Daitomo&quot;, a tea shop which was operated in Gion-Shinbashi, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taka ISODA (her real name was Taka, from 1879 to 1945) was Geisya in Gion Kobu, and she was Okami (mistress) of &quot;Daitomo&quot;, a tea shop which operated in Gion-Shinbashi, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taka ISODA (her real name was Taka, 1879 - 1945) was Geisha in Gion Kobu, and she was Okami (mistress) of &quot;Daitomo,&quot; a tea shop which operated in Gion-Shinbashi, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>from 1879 to 1945を他の表記と合わせて、1879 - 1945としました。Geisyaの表記を、Geishaに訂正しました。コンマ位置訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>多佳は6歳で井上八千代に入門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taka became a disciple of Yachiyo INOUE at the age of six.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taka became a disciple of Yachiyo INOUE at the age of six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taka became a disciple of Yachiyo INOUE at the age of six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そこで芸を磨き、10代で芸妓となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Se brushed up her entertainment skill in INOUE&apos;s place, and became Geisya in her 10&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Se honed her entertainment skill in INOUE&apos;s place, and became Geisya in her teens.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Se honed her entertainment skill in Inoue&apos;s place, and became Geisha in her teens.</e>
<cmt>Inoue小文字に訂正しました。Geisyaの表記を、Geishaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>23歳で母の家業を継ぎ、夏目漱石をはじめ谷崎潤一郎、吉井勇など多くの文学者との交流し、『文学芸妓』と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She took over her mother&apos;s business at the age of 23, and interacted with many literature scholars including Soseki NATSUME, Junichiro TANIZAKI, Isamu YOSHII; that was why she came to be called as &quot;Literature geisya.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She took over her mother&apos;s business at the age of 23, and interacted with many literature scholars including Soseki NATSUME, Junichiro TANIZAKI, Isamu YOSHII; which was why she came to be called the &quot;Literature geisha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She took over her mother&apos;s business at the age of 23, and interacted with many literature scholars including Soseki NATSUME, Junichiro TANIZAKI, Isamu YOSHII; which was why she came to be called the &quot;Literature geisha.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>当時白川の両岸には数軒の御茶屋が立ち並び、その中に『大友』が含まれていて吉井勇の歌にも書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both banks of Shira-kawa River were lined with some tea shops including &quot;Otomo&quot;, which was written in Isamu YOSHII&apos;s poem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both banks of Shira-kawa River were lined with tea shops including &quot;Otomo&quot;, which was written in Isamu YOSHII&apos;s poem.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both banks of Shira-kawa River were lined with tea shops including &quot;Otomo,&quot; which was written in Isamu YOSHII&apos;s poem.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、戦局が悪化し多くのお茶屋が廃業を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the war became worse, many tea shops were forced to be closed.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the war became worse, many tea shops were forced to be closed.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the war became worse, many tea shops were forced to be closed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>空襲に伴う災害を防ぐため疎開が行われ、多佳が守っていたお茶屋が撤去され、彼女は悲しみにくれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evacuation was carried out to minimize disasters caused by air attacks, and she was grieved when her tea shop which she had been protecting was cleared.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evacuation was carried out to minimize disasters caused by air attacks, and she grieved when her tea shop, that she had been protecting, was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evacuation was carried out to minimize disasters caused by air attacks, and she grieved when her tea shop, that she had been protecting, was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1945年にその生涯を閉じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She closed her life in 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She passed away in 1945.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She passed away in 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BAKU(id:55205), 今紫(id:9521), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>