<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>北条重時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetoki HOJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetoki HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetoki HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>北条 重時（ほうじょう しげとき）は、鎌倉時代前期の北条氏の一門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetoki HOJO was the family of the Hojo clan in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetoki HOJO was a member of the family of the Hojo clan in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetoki HOJO was a member of the family of the Hojo clan in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉幕府執権北条義時の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of Yoshitoki HOJO, the regent of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of Yoshitoki HOJO, the regent of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of Yoshitoki HOJO, the regent of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は正室の姫の前。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Yoshitoki&apos;s lawful wife, Himenomae.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため、「正室」の前に「義時の」を付け加えて訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Yoshitoki&apos;s lawful wife, Hime no Mae.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Yoshitoki&apos;s lawful wife, Hime no Mae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉幕府連署。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was rensho (assistant to regents) of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a rensho (assistant to regents) of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a rensho (assistant to regents) of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>承久元年（1219年）に22歳で小侍所別当就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to kozamurai dokoro betto (chief administrator of an office of officers to guard Shogun in attendance) at the age of twenty two in 1219.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to kozamurai dokoro betto (chief administrator of an office of officers to guard Shogun in attendance) at the age of 22 in 1219.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to kozamurai dokoro betto (chief administrator of an office of officers to guard Shogun in attendance) at the age of 22 in 1219.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>寛喜2年（1230年）3月、病となった甥の北条時氏の後任を受けて鎌倉から上洛し、京都六波羅探題北方に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to the capital to take over the position of his nephew Tokiuji HOJO, who became ill in April, 1230 and was appointed to Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata (Northern Chief of Rokuhara Tandai) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to the capital from Kamakura to take over the position of his nephew Tokiuji HOJO, who became ill in April, 1230 and was appointed to Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata (Northern Chief of Rokuhara Tandai) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「鎌倉から」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to the capital from Kamakura to take over the position of his nephew Tokiuji HOJO, who became ill in April, 1230 and was appointed to Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata (Northern Chief of Rokuhara Tandai) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以降17年間六波羅の最高責任者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He kept the position of chief executive for Rokuhara for the next seventeen years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He kept the position of chief executive for Rokuhara for the next 17 years.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He kept the position of chief executive for Rokuhara for the next 17 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>仁治（1242年）の幕府による後嵯峨天皇擁立の際には、重時の同母妹を妻としていた土御門定通と連携して工作が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of enthronement of Emperor Gosaga by the bakufu in 1242, he had deception together with Sadamichi TSUCHIMIKADO, who had Shigetoki&apos;s younger paternal half-sister as his wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of enthronement of Emperor Gosaga by the bakufu in 1242, he had deception together with Sadamichi TSUCHIMIKADO, who had Shigetoki&apos;s younger maternal half-sister as his wife.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of enthronement of Emperor Gosaga by the bakufu in 1242, he had deception together with Sadamichi TSUCHIMIKADO, who had Shigetoki&apos;s younger maternal half-sister as his wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同年に兄の3代執権北条泰時が重病となると、六波羅探題南方の従兄弟北条時盛と共に急ぎ鎌倉へ下った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his elder brother Yasutoki HOJO, the third regent became severely ill in the same year, he immediately went down to Kamakura together with his cousin Tokimori HOJO, who was in Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata (Rokuhara Tandai South).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his older brother Yasutoki HOJO, the third regent became severely ill in the same year, he immediately went down to Kamakura together with his cousin Tokimori HOJO, who was in Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata (Rokuhara Tandai South).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his older brother Yasutoki HOJO, the third regent became severely ill in the same year, he immediately went down to Kamakura together with his cousin Tokimori HOJO, who was in Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata (Rokuhara Tandai South).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>泰時が没すると重時は六波羅に帰任したが、時盛は鎌倉に留まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yasutoki&apos;s death, Shigetoki returned to Rokuhara, but Tokimori stayed in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yasutoki&apos;s death, Shigetoki returned to Rokuhara, but Tokimori stayed in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yasutoki&apos;s death, Shigetoki returned to Rokuhara, but Tokimori stayed in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、探題は重時のみとなり、最後の5年間は重時単独で任に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Shigetoki was the only one at Tandai and served alone during the last five years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Shigetoki was the only one at Tandai and served alone during the last five years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Shigetoki was the only one at Tandai and served alone during the last five years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>寛元4年（1246年）、宮騒動により前将軍藤原頼経が京へ強制送還される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1246, former Shogun FUJIWARA no Yoritsune was deported to the capital due to Miya-sodo (ailed attempt at rebellion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1246, former Shogun FUJIWARA no Yoritsune was deported to the capital Kyoto due to Miya-sodo (failed attempt at rebellion).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1246, former Shogun FUJIWARA no Yoritsune was deported to the capital Kyoto due to Miya-sodo (failed attempt at rebellion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この年の8月、重時は後嵯峨上皇院司葉室定嗣を六波羅に呼び、5代執権となった北条時頼からの書状として、事件に関与した九条道家父子の更迭を後嵯峨上皇に奏上するよう要請し、幕府と上皇の仲介を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, 1246, Shigetoki called Sadatsugu HAMURO, Inshi (official of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) of the Retired Emperor Gosaga to Rokuhara and requested to report the recall of Michiie KUJO and his son, who were involved in the incident, to the Retired Emperor Gosaga as the letter from Tokiyori HOJO who became the fifth regent and acted as the intermediate between the bakufu and the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of the same year, Shigetoki mediated between the bakufu and the Retired Emperor by calling Sadatsugu HAMURO, an Inshi (official of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) of the Retired Emperor Gosaga, to Rokuhara and telling him that the letter from Tokiyori HOJO, who became the fifth regent, requested the Retired Emperor Gosaga to replace Michiie KUJO and his son, who were involved in the incident.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September of the same year, Shigetoki mediated between the bakufu and the Retired Emperor by calling Sadatsugu HAMURO, an Inshi (official of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) of the Retired Emperor Gosaga, to Rokuhara and telling him that the letter from Tokiyori HOJO, who became the fifth regent, requested the Retired Emperor Gosaga to replace Michiie KUJO and his son, who were involved in the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>宝治元年（1247年）に執権時頼と外戚の安達氏らが三浦氏を滅ぼした宝治合戦後、50歳の重時は時頼の要請により鎌倉へ戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1247, after Battle of Hoji that the regent Tokiyori and his maternal relative Adachi clan destroyed the Miura clan, Shigetoki returned to Kamakura at the age of fifty as Tokiyori requested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1247, after Battle of Hoji that the regent Tokiyori and his maternal relative Adachi clan destroyed the Miura clan, Shigetoki returned to Kamakura at the age of 50 as Tokiyori requested.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1247, after Battle of Hoji that the regent Tokiyori and his maternal relative Adachi clan destroyed the Miura clan, Shigetoki returned to Kamakura at the age of 50 as Tokiyori requested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>叔父北条時房死後に空席となっていた連署に就任し、時頼を補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to rensho that was vacant seat after his uncle Tokifusa HOJO&apos;s death and supported Tokiyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to rensho that was vacant after his uncle Tokifusa HOJO&apos;s death and supported Tokiyori.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to rensho that was vacant after his uncle Tokifusa HOJO&apos;s death and supported Tokiyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>六波羅探題北方は子の北条長時が就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child Nagatoki HOJO was appointed to Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His child Nagatoki HOJO was appointed to Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His child Nagatoki HOJO was appointed to Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>重時の娘は時頼の妻となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetoki&apos;s daughter became Tokiyori&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetoki&apos;s daughter became Tokiyori&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetoki&apos;s daughter became Tokiyori&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>康元元年（1256年）に出家し、引退後は極楽寺に隠居した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered the priesthood in 1256 and stayed at Gokuraku-ji Temple after the retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered the priesthood in 1256 and stayed at Gokuraku-ji Temple after the retirement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the priesthood in 1256 and stayed at Gokuraku-ji Temple after the retirement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>連署は弟の北条政村が就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brother Masamura HOJO was appointed to rensho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother Masamura HOJO was appointed to rensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother Masamura HOJO was appointed to rensho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>同年執権時頼が病で出家した為、6代執権には子の長時が就任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the regent Tokiyori entered the priesthood in 1256 due to the illness, his child Nagatoki was appointed to the sixth regent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the regent Tokiyori entered the priesthood in the same year due to the illness, his child Nagatoki was appointed to the sixth regent.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the regent Tokiyori entered the priesthood in the same year due to the illness, his child Nagatoki was appointed to the sixth regent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>弘長元年（1261年）に死去、享年64。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of sixty four in 1261.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 64 in 1261.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 64 in 1261.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>政治姿勢は浄土宗の影響もあり撫民を基礎としたものであり、当時の幕政に明確な統治をもたらしたとする評価がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His political position was based on bumin (policies for the people&apos;s livelihood) under the influence of Jodo Sect, so it was appraised that it brought the shogunate government clear governance at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His political position was based on bumin (policies for the people&apos;s livelihood) under the influence of Jodoshu sect, so it was appraised that it brought the shogunate government clear governance at that time.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His political position was based on bumin (policies for the people&apos;s livelihood) under the influence of Jodoshu sect, so it was appraised that it brought the shogunate government clear governance at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>和歌などの文化的活動も行い、『千載和歌集』にも歌が収録されており、藤原定家とも親交があったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also worked on cultural activities such as waka, and his poems were collected in &quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Japanese Poems of a Thousand Years), and he was said to have a friendship with FUJIWARA no Sadaie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also worked on cultural activities such as waka (traditional Japanese poems), and his poems were collected in &quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Japanese Poems of a Thousand Years), and he was said to have a friendship with FUJIWARA no Sadaie.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also worked on cultural activities such as waka (traditional Japanese poems), and his poems were collected in &quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Japanese Poems of a Thousand Years), and he was said to have a friendship with FUJIWARA no Sadaie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>著作に家訓として残した『極楽寺殿御消息』、『北条重時家訓』などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His literary works were &quot;Gokurakuji-dono Goshosoku&quot;(Letter of Gokurakuji--dono Palace) and &quot;Hojo shigetoki kakun&quot; (&quot;A family precept by Shigetoki HOJO&quot;) as precept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His literary works were &quot;Gokurakuji-dono Goshosoku&quot;(Letter of Gokurakuji-dono Palace) and &quot;Hojo Shigetoki kakun&quot; (A family precept by Shigetoki HOJO) as family precepts.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His literary works were &quot;Gokurakuji-dono Goshosoku&quot;(Letter of Gokurakuji-dono Palace) and &quot;Hojo Shigetoki kakun&quot; (A family precept by Shigetoki HOJO) as family precepts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>※日付は旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>日付はグレゴリオ暦に変換したため、「日付は旧暦」のコメントは訳出しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date according to old lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date according to old lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>承久元年（1219年）7月、幕府小侍所別当に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to bakufu kozamurai dokoro betto in August, 1219.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to bakufu kozamurai dokoro betto in July, 1219.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to bakufu kozamurai dokoro betto in July, 1219.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>承久2年（1220年）12月15日、修理権亮に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Shuri gon no suke (Provisional assistant master in the Office of Palace Repairs) on January 17, 1221.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Shuri gon no suke (Provisional assistant master in the Office of Palace Repairs) on December 15, 1220.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Shuri gon no suke (Provisional assistant master in the Office of Palace Repairs) on December 15, 1220.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>貞応2年（1223年）4月10日、従五位下に叙し、駿河守に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and transferred to Suruga no kami (the governor of Suruga Province) on May 18, 1223.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and transferred to Suruga no kami (Governor of Suruga Province) on April 10, 1223.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and transferred to Suruga no kami (Governor of Suruga Province) on April 10, 1223.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>寛喜2年（1230年）3月11日、小侍所別当から六波羅探題北方に異動。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred to Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata from Kozamurai dokoro betto on May 2, 1230.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was transferred to Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata from Kozamurai dokoro betto on March 11, 1230.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was transferred to Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata from Kozamurai dokoro betto on March 11, 1230.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>嘉禎2年（1236年）11月22日、従五位上に昇叙し、駿河守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and remained in the position of Suruga no kami on December 28, 1236.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and retained his position as Suruga no kami on November 22, 1236.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and retained his position as Suruga no kami on November 22, 1236.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>嘉禎3年（1237年）11月19日、相模守に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred to Sagami no kami (governor of Sagami Province) on December 14, 1237.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was transferred to Sagami no kami (Governor of Sagami Province) on November 19, 1237.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was transferred to Sagami no kami (Governor of Sagami Province) on November 19, 1237.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>暦仁元年（1238年）7月20日、正五位下に昇叙し、相模守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and remained in the position of Sagami no kami on September 7, 1238.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained his position as Sagami no kami on July 20, 1239.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。年号はグレゴリオ暦に直し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained his position as Sagami no kami on July 20, 1239.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>寛元元年（1244年）閏7月24日、従四位下に昇叙し、相模守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) and remained the position of Sagami no kami on September 16, 1243.</e>
<cmt>http://maechan.net/kanreki/で確認したところ、寛元元年閏7月24日は西暦1243年9月16日（グレゴリオ暦）でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained his position as Sagami no kami on Leap July 24, 1244.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。年号はグレゴリオ暦に直し、スペルなど表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained his position as Sagami no kami on Leap July 24, 1244.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>寛元2年（1245年）6月22日、従四位上に昇叙し、相模守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and remained the position of Sagami no kami on August 4, 1244.</e>
<cmt>http://maechan.net/kanreki/で確認したところ、寛元2年6月22日は西暦1244年8月4日（グレゴリオ暦）でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and retained his position as Sagami no kami on June 22, 1244.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。年号はグレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and retained his position as Sagami no kami on June 22, 1244.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="35">
<j>宝治元年（1247年）7月27日、六波羅探題北方から幕府連署に異動。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred to bakufu rensho from Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata on September 5, 1247.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was transferred to bakufu rensho from Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata on July 27, 1247.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was transferred to bakufu rensho from Rokuhara Tandai Kitakata on July 27, 1247.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="36">
<j>建長元年（1249年）6月14日、陸奥守に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was reassigned to Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province) on August 1, 1249.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was transferred to Mutsu no kami (Governor of Mutsu Province) on June 14, 1249.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was transferred to Mutsu no kami (Governor of Mutsu Province) on June 14, 1249.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="37">
<j>康元元年（1256年）3月11日、連署を辞し、出家する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned rensho and entered the priesthood on April 14, 1256.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned rensho and entered the priesthood on March 11, 1256.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned rensho and entered the priesthood on March 11, 1256.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>法号：極楽寺観覚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hogo (a Buddhist name): Gokurakuji Kangaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hogo (a Buddhist name): Gokurakuji Kangaku.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hogo (a Buddhist name): Gokurakuji Kangaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="39">
<j>弘長元年（1261年）11月23日、卒去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on December 23, 1261.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on November 23, 1261.</e>
<cmt>前出により旧暦にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on November 23, 1261.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Mnd(id:15140), Mps(id:215518), やりたこ(id:113528), Ajita(id:34451), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), ちちぶ(id:184715), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), でここ(id:9565), Masyu(id:31065), Mymelo(id:122034), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), いけ2(id:94729), 海衛士(id:19229), こよみ(id:184337), IP WATCHER(id:184313), Ktmchi(id:113301), のりまき(id:53470), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>