<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長田景致</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagemune OSADA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagemune OSADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagemune OSADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長田景致（おさだ かげむね、生年未詳 - 建久元年（1190年））は平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagemune OSADA (birthday is unknown -1190) was a busho at the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagemune OSADA (year of birth unknown -1190) was a busho who lived during the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせて、「生年不詳」の訳を変更しました。表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagemune OSADA (year of birth unknown -1190) was a busho who lived during the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>長田忠致の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A child of Tadamune OSADA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of Tadamune OSADA</e>
<cmt>主語と述語を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of Tadamune OSADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>父、忠致の源義朝暗殺計画に加担し、実行の際には義朝の第一の郎従であり、自分の義兄弟でもある鎌田政清を斬っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated in the plan led by his father, Tadamune, to assassinate MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo; moreover, he also killed Masakiyo, KAMATA, Yoshitomo&apos;s closest Vassal and Kagemune&apos;s Gikyodai (relathionship associated with each other as brother), during assassination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in the plan led by his father, Tadamune, to assassinate MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo; moreover, he also killed Masakiyo KAMATA, Yoshitomo&apos;s closest Vassal and Kagemune&apos;s Gikyodai (relationship associated with each other as brother), during the assassination.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。不要なコンマを削除しました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in the plan led by his father, Tadamune, to assassinate MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo; moreover, he also killed Masakiyo KAMATA, Yoshitomo&apos;s closest Vassal and Kagemune&apos;s Gikyodai (relationship associated with each other as brother), during the assassination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>平治物語においては、これ以外の場面でも常に父と一対で登場し、息の合った行動を見せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He always appeared together with his father in &quot;Tale of Heiji,&quot; beside this scene and they worked well together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He always appeared together with his father in &quot;Tale of Heiji,&quot; beside the scene of assassination and they worked well together.</e>
<cmt>一部の表現と冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He always appeared together with his father in &quot;Tale of Heiji,&quot; beside the scene of assassination and they worked well together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>その最期もまた父と同時であり、義朝の子源頼朝の命で処刑されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that both Kagemune and Tadamune were also executed together by the direction of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, a child of Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that both Kagemune and Tadamune were also executed together by the order of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, a child of Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>適切な語句に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that both Kagemune and Tadamune were also executed together by the order of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, a child of Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>また、彼の子孫は三河国へ逃れて永井と名乗ったとも、甲斐国へ逃げて今でも家名を保っているとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it is also said that his descendants escaped to Mikawa province and named themselves as NAGAI, or escaped to Kai province and retained the family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it is also said that his descendants escaped to Mikawa Province and named themselves as NAGAI, or escaped to Kai Province and retained the family name.</e>
<cmt>該当箇所の小文字を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it is also said that his descendants escaped to Mikawa Province and named themselves as NAGAI, or escaped to Kai Province and retained the family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BAKU(id:55205), Goki(id:7107), 代言人(id:33675), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>