<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原定信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sadanobu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sadanobu</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sadanobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原定信（ふじわら の さだのぶ、寛治2年（1088年） - 保元元年1月18日 (旧暦)（1156年2月10日））は、平安時代後期の書家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sadanobu (1088 - February 10, 1156) was a calligrapher in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sadanobu (1088 - February 10, 1156) was a calligrapher during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sadanobu (1088 - February 17, 1156) was a calligrapher during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原定実の長男で、世尊寺家第5世となり、能書家として重んじられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Sadazane, became the fifth generation of the Sesonji family, and was respected as a noshoka (master of calligraphy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Sadazane, and the fifth generation of the Sesonji family, and was a respected noshoka (master of calligraphy).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of FUJIWARA no Sadazane, and the fifth generation of the Sesonji family, and was a respected noshoka (master of calligraphy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>官位は従四位下、宮内権大輔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in Kudai gon taifu ((Provisional Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Imperial Household)</e>
<cmt>原文には (宮内省) とありますが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「宮内権大輔」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official rank was Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in Kudai gon taifu (Provisional Senior Assistant of the Minister of the Ministry of Imperial Household).</e>
<cmt>correct punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official rank was Jushiinoje (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in Kudai gon taifu (Provisional Senior Assistant of the Minister of the Ministry of Imperial Household).</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたためウェブに合わせて原文・訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大嘗会屏風の筆者となり、多くの墨跡を今日に伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a writer of folding screens used during the Daijoe, or court banquets held during the first harvest festival and many of his work remains to this date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadanobu became a calligraphy artist of folding screens used during the Daijoe (court banquets held during the first harvest festival), and many of his works remain to this date.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadanobu became a calligraphy artist of folding screens used during the Daijoe (court banquets held during the first harvest festival), and many of his works remain to this date.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大治 (日本)4年（1129年）からは23年間をかけて、一切経5048巻を独力で書写したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is reported to have spent 23 years from 1129 to write 5048 volumes of complete Buddhist scriptures all by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is reported to have spent 23 years starting from 1129 to write all 5048 volumes of the complete Buddhist scriptures by himself.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is reported to have spent 23 years starting from 1129 to write all 5048 volumes of the complete Buddhist scriptures by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>鑑識にも長じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had excellent judgment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also was an excellent appraiser.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also was an excellent appraiser.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>保延6年（1140年）10月22日、小野道風書の『屏風土代』と藤原行成書の『白楽天詩巻（高松宮家本）』を入手し、『屏風土代』は延長 (元号)6年（928年）11月、道風35歳の書であること、『白楽天詩巻』は寛仁2年8月21日、行成47歳の書であることを鑑定し、それぞれの奥書きに記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 10, 1140, he obtained &quot;Byobudodai&quot; written by ONO no Tofu and &quot;Hakurakutenshikan (TAKAMATSU no MIYA ke bon (TAKAMATSU no MIYA family version))&quot; written by FUJIWARA no Yukinari, appraised that &quot;Byobudodai&quot; was written by Tofu between December 928 and January 929 (November 928 in old lunar calender), when he was 35, and &quot;Hakurakiutenshikan&quot; was written by Yukinari on October 8, 1018, when he was 47, and noted on their respective Okugaki (postscript).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処用語集では「高松宮家本」は&quot;TAKAMATU no MIYA ke bon&quot; となっていますが、ヘボン式に改め、説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 10, 1140, he obtained &quot;Byobudodai&quot; written by ONO no Tofu and &quot;Hakurakutenshikan (TAKAMATSU no MIYA ke bon (TAKAMATSU no MIYA family version))&quot; written by FUJIWARA no Yukinari, and managed to uncover that &quot;Byobudodai&quot; was written by Tofu between December 928 and January 929 (November 928 in the lunar calender) when he was 35, and that &quot;Hakurakiutenshikan&quot; was written by Yukinari on October 8, 1018 when he was 47, and noted these findings in their respective postscripts.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 10, 1140, he obtained &quot;Byobu Dodai&quot; (the draft for a (Han) poem to be written on a screen) written by ONO no Tofu and &quot;Hakurakuten Shikan&quot; (Poetry Anthology of Bai Juyi) (TAKAMATSU no MIYA ke bon (TAKAMATSU no MIYA family version)) written by FUJIWARA no Yukinari, and managed to uncover that &quot;Byobu Dodai&quot; was written by Tofu at the age of 35, in December 928, and that &quot;Hakurakuten Shikan&quot; was written by Yukinari at the age of 47, on October 8, 1018, and noted these findings in their respective postscripts.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>墨跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bokuseki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bokuseki</e>
<cmt>translation?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bokuseki (ink trace)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>定信和漢朗詠集切</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadanobu Wakanroeishu Kire</e>
<cmt>「切」の読み方不明ですが、「古筆切」 (Kohitsugire、古い書の断片）から推測して&quot;Kire&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadanobu Wakanroeishu Kire</e>
<cmt>no translation given</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadanobu Wakan Roeishu gire (fragmentary leaves of Wakan Roeishu (Japanese and Chinese poems to sing), FUJIWARA no Sadanobu&apos;s handwriting)</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>近来、石川家の秘庫から出たもので、その奥書きに「同日未刻染筆申時終切定信」の自署があるので、定信の真跡と決定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was found recently from the 秘庫 of the ISHIKAWA family and determined to be Shinseki (original handwriting) of Sadanobu because there was an autograph &quot;同日未刻染筆申時終切定信&quot; in okugaki.</e>
<cmt>「同日未刻染筆申時終切定信」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was found recently from the secret vaults of the ISHIKAWA family, and was determined to be the original handwriting of Sadanobu because of his autograph of &quot;同日未刻染筆申時終切定信&quot; in the postscript.</e>
<cmt>translation of 同日未刻染筆申時終切定信?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was found recently from the secret vaults of the Ishikawa family, and was determined to be the original handwriting of Sadanobu because of his autograph of &apos;Sadanobu started writing this from one o&apos;clock to three and finished from three to five on the same day&apos; (同日未刻染筆申時終切定信) in the postscript.</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>詩句と和歌を大きく散らし書きにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Poetic lines and waka (traditional Japanese poems of thirty-one syllables) were written in bold chirashigaki (to write in a random manner).</e>
<cmt>「散らし書き」は「色紙・短冊などに歌の文句を、行を整えずとびとびに、また草仮名や平仮名をまぜ、濃く薄く、細く太くなどさまざまに散らして書くこと。」(http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/127972/m0u/%E3%81%A1%E3%82%89/) とありますので、左のように説明をつけました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Poetic verses and waka (traditional Japanese poems of thirty-one syllables) were written largely in a random manner.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Poetic verses and waka (traditional Japanese poems of thirty-one syllables) were written largely in a manner of Chirashi-gaki (writing unevenly with both long and short lines, both wide and narrow line space and both large and small letters).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>書風は雄健高雅で、連綿も自然で、筆端には才気が溢れており、円熟した晩年の書道と推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His calligraphic style was strong and healthy but elegant with natural continuous (flowing) lines and brilliantbrush strokes, so it is thought to be mature calligraphy in his late years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His calligraphic style is strong and full of energy, but elegant with naturally continuous, flowing lines and displays brilliance in his brush strokes, so it is believed to be written during his late years when his calligraphy was perfected.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His calligraphic style is strong and full of energy, but elegant with naturally continuous, flowing lines and displays brilliance in his brush strokes, so it is believed to be written during his late years when his calligraphy was perfected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>金澤萬葉集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanazawa manyoshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanazawa manyoshu</e>
<cmt>translation?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanazawa Manyoshu (Collection of Ten-Thousand Leaves, FUJIWARA no Sadanobu&apos;s handwriting)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>西本願寺本三十六人家集のうち貫之集下（石山切として分割された）と順集</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsurayukishuge (divided as Ishiyamagire) and &quot;順集&quot; in Nishi-Honganji-bon Sanju-rokunin-kashu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsurayukishuge (divided as Ishiyamagire) and &quot;順集&quot; in Nishi-Honganji-bon Sanju-rokunin-kashu</e>
<cmt>the original translator is really not providing a translation here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsurayukishu no ge (Ki no Tsurayuki &apos;s Anthology, volume 2) (divided as Ishiyama gire (Fragment of Tsurayukishu no ge or Ise shu (The Diary of Lady Ise)) and Shitagoshu (MINAMOTO no Shitago&apos;s Poetry Book) among Nishi-Honganji-bon Sanju-rokunin-kashu (The Nishi Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s Collection of 36 Anthologies)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>兼輔集切</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanesukeshugire</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanesukeshugire</e>
<cmt>translation?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanesuke shu gire (Fragment of FUJIWARA no Kanesuke&apos;s collection)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>戊辰切（朗詠集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boshin-gire (Collection of poems to sing)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boshin-gire (Collection of poems to sing)</e>
<cmt>translation?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boshin gire (Fragment of the Boshin Edition of Wakan Roei Shu (Japanese and Chinese Poems to Sing))</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>糟色紙（順集断片）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">糟色紙(順集断片)</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">糟色紙(順集断片)</e>
<cmt>reading? translation?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasujikishi (Shitagoshu danpen) (Fragment of Shitagoshu (MINAMOTO no Shitago&apos;s Poetry Book)</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>久能寺経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunojikyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunojikyo</e>
<cmt>translation?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunojikyo (the Kuno-ji Temple Sutra)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And so on.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 岡部碩道(id:182846), ReijiYamashina(id:29567), 伏儀(id:142093), Snap55(id:89773), 瑞雲(id:27410), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>