<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>渡辺競</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kio WATANABE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kio WATANABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kio WATANABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>渡辺 競（わたなべ きおう / きそう、生年不詳 - 治承4年（1180年））は、平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kio (or Kiso) WATANABE (Date of birth unknown - 1180) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kio (or Kiso) WATANABE (year of birth unknown - 1180) was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Date&quot; to &quot;year&quot; to match the word list; changed &quot;in&quot; to &quot;during&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kio (also pronounced as Kiso) WATANABE (year of birth unknown - 1180) was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>嵯峨源氏渡辺党の出身で、右馬允渡辺昇の子、あるいは渡辺省の子と伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was descended from Saga-Genji (Minamoto clan) Watanabe Party, and that he was a son of either Umanosuke 渡辺昇 or Habuku WATANABE..</e>
<cmt>読み方が不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was allegedly a descendant of the Saga-Genji (Minamoto clan) Watanabe Party, and was a son of either Umanosuke 渡辺昇 or Habuku WATANABE..</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was allegedly a descendant of the Saga-Genji (Minamoto clan) Watanabe Party, and was a son of either Umanosuke 渡辺昇 or Habuku WATANABE.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子息に鶴田馴（なつく）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son was Natsuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son was Natsuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son was Natsuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は源三、滝口と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His pseudonyms were Genzo and Takiguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pseudonyms were Genzo and Takiguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pseudonyms were Genzo and Takiguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>父祖以来摂津源氏の郎党である渡辺党の一員として、源頼政の忠実な配下として行動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a member of Watanabe party that had been retainers of Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan) since his forefathers, he acted as a faithful vassal of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a member of the Watanabe party, who had been retainers of the Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan) for generations, Kio acted as a faithful vassal to MINAMOTO no Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;since his forefathers&quot; to &quot;for generations&quot;; added comma after &quot;party&quot;; changed &quot;he&quot; to &quot;Kio&quot;; changed &quot;of&quot; to &quot;to&quot; before &quot;MINAMOTO&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a member of the Watanabe party, who had been retainers of the Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan) for generations, Kio acted as a faithful vassal to MINAMOTO no Yorimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そして、保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱などにおいて頼政に従い出陣したことが見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it appears that he departed for the front, following Yorimasa, in wars including Hogen Disturbance in 1156.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kio apparently departed for the front, following Yorimasa into battles, including the Hogen Disturbance in 1156.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kio apparently departed for the front, following Yorimasa into battles, including the Hogen Disturbance in 1156.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>治承4年の以仁王の挙兵にあたっては、当初偽って敵方の平宗盛に投降し、その愛馬『何両』を奪って頼政の元に参陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Rising of Prince Mochihito of 1180, he pretended to surrender to TAIRA no Munemori in the beginning and then he robbed his horse &apos;Nanryo,&apos; joining Yorimasa&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Prince Mochihito raised an army in 1180, Kio first feigned a surrender to TAIRA no Munemori, stole his horse &apos;Nanryo,&apos; and rejoined Yorimasa&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;pretended&quot; to &quot;feigned&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Prince Mochihito raised an army in 1180, Kio first feigned a surrender to TAIRA no Munemori, stole his horse &apos;Nanryo,&apos; and rejoined Yorimasa&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その際、先立って頼政の嫡男源仲綱が愛馬のことで宗盛に辱めを受けていたことの報復として、馬のたてがみと尾の毛をそり、尻に「昔は何両、今は平宗盛入道」の焼印をして突き返し、宗盛を激怒せしめたという逸話が知られる（『平家物語』四・競）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to an anecdote, he enraged Munemori at that time by returning the horse after shaving its mane and tail and branding &apos;formerly Nanryo, now TAIRA no Munemori Nyudo&apos; on its rear in retaliation for having insulted MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna, the legitimate son of Yorimasa over his horse (&quot;Heike monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike), Chapter 4, Kio)..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an anecdote from the &quot;Heike monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heiki) (chapter four, Kio), Kio enraged Munemori by returning the horse after shaving its mane and tail and branding &quot;formerly Nanryo, now TAIRA no Munemori Nyudo&quot; on its rear. This was in retaliation for Munemori having insulted MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna, the legitimate son of Yorimasa, over his horse.</e>
<cmt>changed into two sentences as it was just too long as one; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an anecdote from the &quot;Heike monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heiki) (chapter four, Kio), Kio enraged Munemori by returning the horse after shaving its mane and tail and branding &quot;formerly Nanryo, now TAIRA no Munemori Nyudo&quot; on its rear; this was in retaliation for Munemori having insulted MINAMOTO no Nakatsuna, the legitimate son of Yorimasa, over his horse.</e>
<cmt>rear. This was→rear; this wasセミコロンで一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>必ず競を生け捕りにせよとの宗盛の指令にも関わらず、宇治平等院において奮戦の末に自害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Munemori ordered his army to capture Kio alive, Kio killed himself after fighting bravely in Uji Byodoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Munemori ordered his army to capture Kio alive, Kio killed himself after fighting bravely in Uji Byodoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Munemori ordered his army to capture Kio alive, Kio killed himself after fighting bravely in Uji Byodoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>その人物像については、『源平盛衰記』14・「三位入道入寺事」に、「弓矢取りては並敵もなく、心も剛に謀もいみじかりけるが、而も王城第一の美男なり」と描写されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and Taira clans) (Volume 14) and &quot;Sanmi nyudo 入寺事 &quot; portrayed him to be &quot;an unparalleled archer with a strong mind and extraordinary tactics, and in addition, the best-looking man in the castle.&quot;</e>
<cmt>読み方が不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and Taira clans) (Volume 14) and &quot;Sanmi nyudo 入寺事 &quot; portrays Kio as &quot;an unparalleled archer with a strong mind and extraordinary tactics, in addition to being the best-looking man in the castle.&quot;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and Taira clans) (Volume 14) and &quot;Sanmi nyudo 入寺事 &quot; portrays Kio as &apos;an unparalleled archer with a strong mind and extraordinary tactics, in addition to being the best-looking man in the castle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TTTNIS(id:169490), Andee(id:20421), Tkt058(id:211491), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>