<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>政井みね</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mine MASAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mine MASAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mine MASAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>政井 みね（まさい みね、1888年2月3日 - 1909年11月20日）は、日本の労働者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mine MASAI (February 3, 1888 - November 20, 1909) was a Japanese worker.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mine MASAI (February 3, 1888 - November 20, 1909) was a Japanese worker.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mine MASAI (February 3, 1888 - November 20, 1909) was a Japanese worker.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本近代化を陰で支えた労働者の一人であり、かつて野麦峠を越えた女工哀史を語る際に欠かせない人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was one of the anonymous workers who contributed to the modernization of Japan, and the essential person to tell sad stories of factory girls who once went over the Nomugi Pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was one of the anonymous workers who contributed to the modernization of Japan, and the essential person to tell sad stories of factory girls who once went over the Nomugi Pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was one of the anonymous workers who contributed to the modernization of Japan, and the essential person to tell sad stories of factory girls who once went over the Nomugi Pass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>政井みねは岐阜県吉城郡河合村 (岐阜県)（現飛騨市河合町角川）の農村部に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mine MASAI was born in an agricultural community area of Kawai Village, Yoshiki District in Gifu Prefecture (Tsunogawa, Kawai-cho, Hida City, Gif Prefecture, as of now).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mine MASAI was born in a farming community of Kawai Village, Yoshiki County, Gifu Prefecture (present Tsunogawa, Kawai-cho, Hida City, Gifu Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mine MASAI was born in a farming community of Kawai Village, Yoshiki County, Gifu Prefecture (present Tsunogawa, Kawai-cho, Hida City, Gifu Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>当時はまだ貧しい農村部では、出稼ぎに出る事で食費を浮かし家計を助けるという「口べらし（口減らし）」が一般に行われており、みねも家庭の生活費を助けるために信州の岡谷市へ出稼ぎに出る事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, it was still common in poor agricultural community areas to work away from home to &quot;reduce the mouths to feed&quot; in order to help a household to reduce cost of food, and thus Mine was sent to Okaya City in Shinshu to help her family to reduce their cost of living.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, it was still common in poor farming community to let members go out to town and work for reducing the mouths to feed (it had been called &apos;Kuchi-berashi&apos;), and Mine was also sent to Okaya City in Shinshu to help her family.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, it was still common in poor farming community to let members go out to town and work for reducing the mouths to feed (it had been called &apos;Kuchi-berashi&apos;), and Mine was also sent to Okaya City in Shinshu to help her family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>明治政府による富国強兵のもと、外貨獲得のために日本の近代化を支えたものは水の豊富な長野県諏訪地域における製糸業であり、みねを始め多くの女性労働者が家族との別れを惜しみつつ野麦峠を越え出稼ぎに出る，当時はそんな時代だったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military) policy of the Meiji Government, the silk-reeling industry in Suwa area, Nagano Prefecture, where richly endowed with water, supported modernization of Japan to earn foreign currency, and many female workers like Mine reluctantly left their family home and went over the Nomugi Pass for work - that was a life in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the policy of governments of the Meiji period &apos;Fukoku Kyohei&apos; (fortifying the country, strengthening the military), the filature in Suwa area of Nagano Prefecture where richly endowed with water supported modernization of Japan to earn foreign currency, and many female workers like Mine reluctantly left their family home and went over the Nomugi Pass for work, that was quite usual in those days.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the policy of governments of the Meiji period &apos;Fukoku Kyohei&apos; (fortifying the country, strengthening the military), the filature in Suwa area of Nagano Prefecture where richly endowed with water supported modernization of Japan to earn foreign currency, and many female workers like Mine reluctantly left their family home and went over the Nomugi Pass for work, that was quite usual in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>みねが100人以上の工女とともに信州・岡谷に向かったのは14歳になった1903年2月、交通の難所として名高い野麦峠の中でも最も過酷な条件となる頃である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">14 year-old Mine departed to Okaya in Shinshu with more than 100 female workers in February, 1903, and it was the time when the weather condition becomes worst to cross the Nomugi Pass, which was famous as a dangerous spot for transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">14 year-old Mine departed to Okaya in Shinshu with more than 100 female workers in February, 1903, and it was the time when the weather condition became worst to cross the Nomugi Pass which was famous as a dangerous spot for transportation.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">14 year-old Mine departed to Okaya in Shinshu with more than 100 female workers in February, 1903, and it was the time when the weather condition became worst to cross the Nomugi Pass which was famous as a dangerous spot for transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>残雪は氷の刃と化し、少女たちの足を容赦なく切り裂いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remaining snow brutally cut the feet of the girls like a knife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remaining snow brutally cut the feet of the girls like a knife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remaining snow brutally cut the feet of the girls like a knife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「野麦の雪は赤く染まった」と言われる所以である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why it is said, &quot;the snow of Nomugi was dyed in red&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was why it was said &quot;the snow of Nomugi was dyed in red.&quot;</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was why it was said &quot;the snow of Nomugi was dyed in red.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、足を踏み外して谷に滑落する者、峠の宿（お助け茶屋）に入りきらずに吹雪のなか外で夜を明かす者もいたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them took a misstep and fell into valley, and some could not find a space in a shelter teahouse at the Pass (Otasuke-chaya) and had to spend a night outside in snowstorm.</e>
<cmt>お助け茶屋: Otasuke-chaya (定訳はないようです)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of them took a misstep and fell into the valley, and some could not find a space in the lodging on the pass (called &apos;Otasuke-jaya&apos; literally, saving teahouse) and had to spend a night outside in a snowstorm.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of them took a misstep and fell into the valley, and some could not find a space in the lodging on the pass (called &apos;Otasuke-jaya&apos; literally, saving teahouse) and had to spend a night outside in a snowstorm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>製糸工場、山一林組で働く事となったみねを待っていたものは、現在とは比較にならないほど劣悪な環境下での労働であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mine was assigned to work for a silk mill, Yamaichi-Hayashi Gumi, where she faced the harsh working condition that was nothing to compare to the modern days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mine was assigned to a filature, Yamaichibayashi-gumi, where she faced a harsh condition to work that is not remotely comparable to the condition of today.</e>
<cmt>「山一」と略されますが、本来「やまいちばやし」と続けて読むようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mine was assigned to a filature, Yamaichibayashi-gumi, where she faced a harsh condition to work that is not remotely comparable to the condition of today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>15時間にも及ぶ長時間労働に加え蒸し暑さや悪臭などが漂う工場での労働は生半可なものではなく、工女の逃亡を防ぐため工場に鉄製の桟が張られているという監獄にも近い状態であったが、みねを含め多くの少女たちは自分の賃金で実家を助けるため、また工場が休みとなる正月に両親と再会できることを信じ、歯を食いしばって耐えたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to a long working hours of over 15 hours, humidity and foul odor of the factory made working there even more difficult, and also the factory was surrounded by iron fences to prevent the female workers from escaping like a jail; however, a lot of girls including Mine endured with gritted teeth in order to help their family with their wages, believing they would see their parents again when the factory would be closed for the new year holiday.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to a long working hours of over 15 hours, humidity and foul odor of the factory made working there even more difficult, and also the factory was surrounded by iron fences to prevent the female workers from escaping like a jail; however, a lot of girls including Mine endured with gritted teeth in order to help their family with their wages, believing they would see their parents again when the factory would be closed for the new year holiday.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to a long working hours of over 15 hours, humidity and foul odor of the factory made working there even more difficult, and also the factory was surrounded by iron fences to prevent the female workers from escaping like a jail; however, a lot of girls including Mine endured with gritted teeth in order to help their family with their wages, believing they would see their parents again when the factory would be closed for the new year holiday.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>（その結果、当時の生糸の輸出は日本の総輸出量の3分の1にもなった）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(As a result, the export of raw silk thread made up one third of the total amount of export of Japan at that time.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(As a result, the export of raw silk thread made up one third of the total amount of export of Japan at that time.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(As a result, the export of raw silk thread made up one third of the total amount of export of Japan at that time.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>時は経ち、工女の模範となって年収が百円を超えた（通称、百円工女）みねに突然訪れた病気、それは重度の腹膜炎であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Time passed and Mine became an exemplar of the factory and her annual income reached more than 100 yen (these workers were called &quot;100 yen female worker&quot;), however she suffered a sudden illness of severe peritonitis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Time passed and Mine became an exemplar of the factory and her annual income reached more than 100 yen (these workers were called &quot;100 yen female worker&quot;), however she suffered a sudden illness of severe peritonitis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Time passed and Mine became an exemplar of the factory and her annual income reached more than 100 yen (these workers were called &quot;100 yen female worker&quot;), however she suffered a sudden illness of severe peritonitis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>知らせを受け、みねを引き取りに来た兄・辰次郎は松本市で入院する事を勧めたが、自らの死を既に悟ったのであろうか、みねは故郷の飛騨へ帰りたいと兄の提案を拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receiving the news, Mine&apos;s elder brother Tasujiro came to pick her up and suggested her to stay in a hospital in Matsumoto City, however, Mine probably knew her death was close and refused her brother&apos;s proposal and decided to go back to her hometown, Hida.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Receiving the news, Mine&apos;s elder brother Tasujiro came to pick her up and suggested her to stay in a hospital in Matsumoto City, however, Mine probably knew her death was close and refused her brother&apos;s proposal and decided to go back to her hometown, Hida.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Receiving the news, Mine&apos;s elder brother Tasujiro came to pick her up and suggested her to stay in a hospital in Matsumoto City, however, Mine probably knew her death was close and refused her brother&apos;s proposal and decided to go back to her hometown, Hida.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>やむなく辰次郎はみねを背中に背負い、飛騨へ向かう事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unwillingly Tatsujiro carried Mine on his back and headed to Hida.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unwillingly Tatsujiro carried Mine on his back and headed to Hida.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unwillingly Tatsujiro carried Mine on his back and headed to Hida.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>帰路の途中、多くの人命を奪った野麦峠の茶屋に辿り着くと、みねは喜びながら「あぁ、飛騨が見える」と言い残し、息を引き取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On their way to Hida, when they arrived to the teahouse where many workers lost their lives, Mine was pleased and said &quot;Oh, I can see Hida&quot;, then breathed her last breath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On their way to Hida, when they arrived to the teahouse on the Nomugi Pass where many workers lost their lives, Mine was pleased and said &quot;Oh, I can see Hida,&quot; then breathed her last breath.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On their way to Hida, when they arrived to the teahouse on the Nomugi Pass where many workers lost their lives, Mine was pleased and said &quot;Oh, I can see Hida,&quot; then breathed her last breath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1909年11月20日午後2時、弱冠20歳での死であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died at 2pm on November 20, 1909, at the age of mere 20.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died at 2pm on November 20, 1909, at the age of mere 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died at 2pm on November 20, 1909, at the age of mere 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>この史実は山本茂実の小説、「あゝ野麦峠」で有名になったもので、野麦峠にある慰霊碑や飛騨市河合町角川の専勝寺にある墓には、死後100年近く経った現在でもその死を悼んで訪れる人がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This historical fact was made famous in the novel &quot;Ah, Nomugi Toge&quot; (Oh, the Nomugi Pass) by Shigemi YAMAMOTO, and after 100 years of Mine&apos;s death still many people visit the memorial in the Nomugi Pass and her grave in Sensho-ji temple in Tsunogawa, Kawai-cho, Hida City to commemorate her death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This historical fact became famous by described in the novel &quot;Ah, Nomugi Toge&quot; (Oh, the Nomugi Pass) by Shigemi YAMAMOTO, and today, a hundred years after Mine&apos;s death, still many people visit the memorial in the Nomugi Pass and her grave in Sensho-ji temple in Tsunogawa, Kawai-cho, Hida City to commemorate her death.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This historical fact became famous by described in the novel &quot;Ah, Nomugi Toge&quot; (Oh, the Nomugi Pass) by Shigemi YAMAMOTO, and today, a hundred years after Mine&apos;s death, still many people visit the memorial in the Nomugi Pass and her grave in Sensho-ji temple in Tsunogawa, Kawai-cho, Hida City to commemorate her death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 下総大納言(id:43461), Damedame(id:49335), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), ECLIPSE(id:39342), Im224(id:57113), Yas(id:739), 諸星団(id:72202), Greenland4(id:114494), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>