<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源義親</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshichika</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshichika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshichika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 義親（みなもと の よしちか）は、平安時代後期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshichika was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshichika was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshichika was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源義家の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>源為義の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the father of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>河内源氏三代目棟梁源義家の嫡男だったが、対馬受領に任じられたとき九州で略奪を働き、官吏を殺害したため、隠岐国へ流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although He was the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, third heir of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), he committed looting and killing of government official in Kyushu when he was assigned zuryo (custodial governor) in Tsushima, then he was exiled to Oki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, the third heir of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), he committed looting and killing of a government official in Kyushu when he was assigned zuryo (custodial governor) in Tsushima, then he was exiled to Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>He→he、government official →a government officialに修正、the third heirとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, the third heir of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), he committed looting and killing of a government official in Kyushu when he was assigned zuryo (custodial governor) in Tsushima, then he was exiled to Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>だが、出雲国へ渡って再び官吏を殺して官物を奪ったために、平正盛の追討を受けて誅殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However later he went to Izumo Province and killed government official again and stole kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes), so he was hunted down and killed by TAIRA no Masamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, later he went to Izumo Province and killed a government official again and stole kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes), so he was hunted down and killed by TAIRA no Masamori.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加、government official →a government officialに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, later he went to Izumo Province and killed a government official again and stole kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes), so he was hunted down and killed by TAIRA no Masamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>剛勇の義親が簡単に討たれたことを人々は疑い、その後に幾度も義親を名乗る者が現われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Yoshichika, known as a strong man was killed easily, people doubted the death and a person who called himself Yoshichika appeared one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Yoshichika, known as a strong man was killed easily, people doubted the death and a person who called himself Yoshichika appeared one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Yoshichika, known as a strong man was killed easily, people doubted the death and a person who called himself Yoshichika appeared one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>前九年の役、後三年の役で活躍し「天下第一の武勇の士」と尊崇を集めた父義家譲りのつわものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He contributed at Zen kunen no eki (the Early Nine Years&apos; War) and Gosannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War), he was a strong man like his father, who was called &quot;The best heroic samurai in the world&quot;, then he was called Aku-Tushima no kami Yoshichika, in this case, &quot;Aku&quot; means strongness like MINAMOTO no Yoshihira&apos;s name, &quot;Akugenta&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a strong man like his father, Yoshiie who was called &quot;The best heroic samurai in the world,&quot; having contributed at the Zen Kunen no Eki (the Early Nine Years&apos; War) and the Go Sannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」「義家」→訳漏れのため訳出、「前九年の役、後三年の役」で活躍したのは義親でなく父義家のため、内容に沿うよう訳文を修正、the Zen Kunen no Eki、the Go Sannen no Ekiとし、カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a strong man like his father, Yoshiie who was called &quot;The best heroic samurai in the world,&quot; having contributed at the Zen Kunen no Eki (the Early Nine Years&apos; War) and the Go Sannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>後の源義平の悪源太の、強いという意味での悪と同じく、悪対馬守義親と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Aku-Tsushima no kami Yoshichika; in this case, &quot;Aku&quot; means strongness like MINAMOTO no Yoshihira&apos;s name, &quot;Akugenta.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」Aku-Tushima→Aku-Tsushimaとし、カンマ→セミコロンに変更、ピリオドの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Aku-Tsushima no kami Yoshichika; in this case, &quot;Aku&quot; means strongness like MINAMOTO no Yoshihira&apos;s name, &quot;Akugenta.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>兄の源義宗が早世したため、義家の嫡男となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because his brother, MINAMOTO no Yoshimune died when he was young, Yoshichika became a legitimate son of Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because his older brother, MINAMOTO no Yoshimune died when he was young, Yoshichika became a legitimate son of Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>brother→older brotherとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his older brother, MINAMOTO no Yoshimune died when he was young, Yoshichika became a legitimate son of Yoshiie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>従五位下に叙せられ左兵衛尉、ついで対馬守に任じられるが、九州を横行して、人民を殺害し略奪を働いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned sahyoe no jo and later Tsushima no kami but he conducted looting and killing citizen around Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned Sahyoe no jo (third-ranked officer of Sahyoe-fu, the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards) and later Governor of Tsushima Province but he conducted looting and killing a citizen around the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>Sahyoe no joとし、補足を追加 (用語集参照)、Tsushima no kami→Governor of Tsushima Province、a citizen、the Kyushu regionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and assigned Sahyoe no jo (third-ranked officer of Sahyoe-fu, the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards) and later Governor of Tsushima Province but he conducted looting and killing a citizen around the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>康和3年（1101年）に大宰大弐大江匡房から訴えがあったため、朝廷で追討が議される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1101, OE no Masafusa, Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of the Dazai-fu) sued Yoshichika and tracking down and killing of Yoshichika was discussed at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1101, OE no Masafusa, Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of the Dazai-fu) sued Yoshichika and tracking down and killing of Yoshichika was discussed at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1101, OE no Masafusa, Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of the Dazai-fu) sued Yoshichika and tracking down and killing of Yoshichika was discussed at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>父の義家は郎党藤原資道を遣わして召喚を試みるが、資道は義親に従ってしまい官吏を殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiie, the father sent a retainer FUJIWARA no Sukemichi to call back Yoshichika, but Sukemichi followed Yoshichika and killed government official.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiie, the father sent a retainer FUJIWARA no Sukemichi to call back Yoshichika, but Sukemichi followed Yoshichika and killed a government official.</e>
<cmt>a government officialとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiie, the father sent a retainer FUJIWARA no Sukemichi to call back Yoshichika, but Sukemichi followed Yoshichika and killed a government official.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>翌同4年（1102年）、朝廷は義親を隠岐国へ配流とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year (1102), Imperial Court decided to exile Yoshichika to Oki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year (1102), Imperial Court decided to exile Yoshichika to Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year (1102), Imperial Court decided to exile Yoshichika to Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>だが、義親は配所には赴かず、出雲国に渡って目代を殺害し、官物を奪取した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Yoshichika didn&apos;t go to the place to stay, then he went to Izimo Province, killed mokudai (deputy) and took kanmotsu by force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshichika did not go to the place to stay, then he went to Izumo Province, killed a mokudai (deputy) and took kanmotsu by force.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加、didn&apos;t→did not、Izimo Province→Izumo Provinceに修正、a mokudaliとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshichika did not go to the place to stay, then he went to Izumo Province, killed a mokudai (deputy) and took kanmotsu by force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このため、いよいよ義家が自ら追討へ赴かねばならない状況になったが、嘉承元年（1106年）に義家は死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore Yoshiie had to go to hunt down and kill Yoshichika, but Yoshiie past away in 1106.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Yoshiie had to go to hunt down and kill Yoshichika, but Yoshiie passed away in 1106.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加、passedのスペルミス修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Yoshiie had to go to hunt down and kill Yoshichika, but Yoshiie passed away in 1106.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>嘉承2年（1107年）12月、朝廷は平正盛を追討使に任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1107, Imperial Court ordered TAIRA no Masamori to hunt down and kill Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1108, Imperial Court ordered TAIRA no Masamori to hunt down and kill Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt>「12月」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。(新暦に変換して訳出)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1108, Imperial Court ordered TAIRA no Masamori to hunt down and kill Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>翌同3年（1108年）正月には、はやくも正盛は義親を誅したと報告。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the new year of the next year (1108), Masamori reported that he killed Yoshichika already.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1108, Masamori reported that he killed Yoshichika already.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1108, Masamori reported that he killed Yoshichika already.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>正盛は京へ凱旋し、朝廷より恩賞が授けられ、義親は梟首とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamori went back to Kyoto and was awarded Onsho (reward grants) and Yoshichika&apos;s served head was exposed in public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamori went back to Kyoto and was awarded Onsho (reward grants) and Yoshichika&apos;s severed head was exposed in public.</e>
<cmt>served head→severed headに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamori went back to Kyoto and was awarded Onsho (reward grants) and Yoshichika&apos;s severed head was exposed in public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（源義親の乱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Rebellion by MINAMOTO no Yoshichika)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The War of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika)</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、The War of MINAMOTO no Yoshichikaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The War of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>河内源氏の衰退</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fall of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fall of Kawachi-Genji</e>
<cmt>Kawachi-Genji→既出のため補足削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fall of Kawachi-Genji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>義家が威名を上げた河内源氏では内紛が続き、義親の乱の翌天元2年（1109年）、家督を継いだ源義忠が暗殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshichika developed a reputation as Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) but there were series of internal conflicts among Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), in the next year of rebellion by MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, MINAMOTO no Yoshitada, the heir of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) was assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshichika developed a reputation as Kawachi-Genji but there were series of internal conflicts among Kawachi-Genji; in the next year of the War of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, 1109, MINAMOTO no Yoshitada, the heir of Kawachi-Genji was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>「天元2年（1109年）」→訳漏れのため訳出、Kawachi-Genji→既出のため補足削除、カンマ→セミコロンに変更、rebellion by MINAMOTO no Yoshichika→the War of MINAMOTO no Yoshichikaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshichika developed a reputation as Kawachi-Genji but there were series of internal conflicts among Kawachi-Genji; in the next year of the War of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, 1109, MINAMOTO no Yoshitada, the heir of Kawachi-Genji was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その嫌疑を受けた源義綱（義家の弟）が為義（義親の子）の追討を受け、一族は滅ぼされ、義綱は佐渡国へ流罪となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna (a brother of Yoshiie) was accused of assassination and hunted by Tameyoshi (Yoshichika&apos;s son), Yoshitsuna&apos;s family was destroyed and Yoshitsuna was exiled to Sado Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna (a younger brother of Yoshiie) was accused of assassination and hunted by Tameyoshi (Yoshichika&apos;s son); Yoshitsuna&apos;s family was destroyed and Yoshitsuna was exiled to Sado Province.</e>
<cmt>brother→younger brotherとし、カンマ→セミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna (a younger brother of Yoshiie) was accused of assassination and hunted by Tameyoshi (Yoshichika&apos;s son); Yoshitsuna&apos;s family was destroyed and Yoshitsuna was exiled to Sado Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>為義が家督を継ぐが源氏は凋落し、伊勢平氏が台頭する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tameyoshi succeeded the heir but Minamoto clan lost traction and Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) gained power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tameyoshi succeeded the heir but the Minamoto clan lost traction and Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) gained power.</e>
<cmt>the Minamoro clanとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tameyoshi succeeded to the family headship but the Minamoto clan lost traction and Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) gained power.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>追討後に現れた「義親」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshichika who appeared after his death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshichika who appeared after his death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshichika who appeared after his death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、剛勇で知られた義親が、それまでさしたる武功のなかった正盛に簡単に討たれたことは当時から疑問視されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People didn&apos;t believe Yoshichika&apos;s death because he was know as a strong man and not seemed be to killed by Masamori, who didn&apos;t have much military exploits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People did not believe Yoshichika&apos;s death because he was known as a strong man and did not seem to be killed by Masamori, who had no significant military exploits.</e>
<cmt>didn&apos;t→did not、was know→was known、not seemed be to killed→did not seem to be killed、didn&apos;t have much military exploits→had no significant military exploitsに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People did not believe Yoshichika&apos;s death because he was known as a strong man and did not seem to be killed by Masamori, who had no significant military exploits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>義親生存の噂が流れ、義親と名のる人物が乱の20年以上後まで幾度となく現われており、それらは捕えられたり、殺されたりしたと、当時の公家の日記に記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was rumor that Yoshichika was still alive and there were many people who called themselves Yoshichika even after 20 years from his death, according to diaries of Kuge (court nobles), they were arrested or killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a rumor that Yoshichika was still alive and there were many people who called themselves Yoshichika even after 20 years from his death; according to diaries of Kuge (court nobles), they were arrested or killed.</e>
<cmt>rumor→a rumorとし、カンマ→セミコロンに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a rumor that Yoshichika was still alive and there were many people who called themselves Yoshichika even after 20 years from his death; according to diaries of Kuge (court nobles), they were arrested or killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>平家物語冒頭の「傲れる者も久しからず」の例として挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story about Yoshichika was referred to as an example of the saying &quot;傲れる者も久しからず&quot;at the beginning of Tale of the Heike.</e>
<cmt>「傲れる者も久しからず」の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story about Yoshichika was referred to as an example of the saying &quot;Pride goes before a fall&quot; (傲れる者も久しからず) at the beginning of the Tale of the Heike.</e>
<cmt>&quot;傲れる者も久しからず&quot;→&quot;Pride goes before a fall&quot; (傲れる者も久しからず)とし、the Tale of the Heikeとしました。(参考: http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E9%A9%95%E3%82%8B&amp;dtype=3&amp;dname=2na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=00532800)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story about Yoshichika was referred to as an example of the saying &quot;Pride goes before a fall&quot; (傲れる者も久しからず) at the beginning of the Tale of the Heike.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>義親追討の背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The background of tracking down and killing order of Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The background of tracking down and killing order of Yoshichika</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The background of tracking down and killing order of Yoshichika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>清和源氏研究の奥富敬之によれば、当時は既に白河天皇の院政期に入っており、院と対立する摂関家の武力として仕えていた清和源氏の中の河内源氏は、白河法皇の陰謀により勢力を削がれ、衰退してゆく（「白河院政の黒い手」『清和源氏の全家系』第二巻、新人物往来社）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Takayuki OKUTOMI, specialized in study of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), at the time of Yoshichika, it was already insei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor) led by the Emperor Shirakawa and Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), which was served as military power of Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers to the Emperor) lost their power because of hidden strategy by the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa (&apos;Black hand of Shirakawa insei&apos; &quot;All family lines of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan)&quot; the second band, Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha Co., Ltd.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Takayuki OKUTOMI, specialized in study of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), at the time of Yoshichika, it was already the insei period (during the period of the government by the Retired Emperor) led by the Emperor Shirakawa, and Kawachi-Genji, which was a branch line of Seiwa-Genji and served as military power of Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers to the Emperor) who were against the Emperor Shirakawa lost their power because of hidden strategy by the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa (&apos;Black Hand of the Shirakawa Insei&apos; &quot;All Family Lines of Seiwa-Genji&quot; the second band, Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha Co., Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>「院と対立する」「清和源氏の中の」→訳漏れのため訳出、the insei period、the Retired Emperorとし、カンマの位置を移動、既出のためKawachi-Genjiの補足削除、&apos;Black Hand of the Shirakawa Insei&apos; &quot;All Family Lines of Seiwa-Genji&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Takayuki OKUTOMI, specialized in study of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), at the time of Yoshichika, it was already the insei period (during the period of the government by the Retired Emperor) led by the Emperor Shirakawa, and Kawachi-Genji, which was a branch line of Seiwa-Genji and served as military power of Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers to the Emperor) who were against the Emperor Shirakawa lost their power because of hidden strategy by the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa (&apos;Black Hand of the Shirakawa Insei&apos; &quot;All Family Lines of Seiwa-Genji&quot; the second band, Shin-Jinbutsuoraisha Co., Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>義親の父・源義家に対しては後三年の役を私闘と見なして恩賞を与えず、義家が所有していた荘園を没収したうえ、新たに義家への土地の寄進も禁じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, Yoshichika&apos;s father, Gosannen no Eki was considered as a strife resulting from a personal grudge and Yoshiie was not awarded, furthermore, Yoshiie&apos;s private estates was confiscated and new donation of land to Yoshiie was banned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, Yoshichika&apos;s father, the Go Sannen no Eki was considered a strife resulting from a personal grudge and Yoshiie was not awarded, furthermore, Yoshiie&apos;s private estates was confiscated and new donation of land to Yoshiie was banned.</e>
<cmt>the Go Sannen no Ekiとし、considered as a strife→considered a strifeに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, Yoshichika&apos;s father, the Go Sannen no Eki was considered a strife resulting from a personal grudge and Yoshiie was not awarded, furthermore, Yoshiie&apos;s private estates was confiscated and new donation of land to Yoshiie was banned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>（以上の説は安田元久の説であり、近年疑問視されている。源義家の項を参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The above explanation by Motohisa YASUDA is called in question recent years. Please refer to the article of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The above explanation by Motohisa YASUDA is called in question recent years. Please refer to the article of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The above explanation by Motohisa YASUDA is called in question recent years. Please refer to the article of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>そのため義親が対馬守に任じられたのも、都に近い河内国を本拠地とし、東国を傘下にした河内源氏を、勝手の異なる西国の国司とすることで失敗を期待したものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the reason of Yoshichika&apos;s assignment as Tushima no kami was to push Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) whose home ground was in Kawachi Province and had power in Togoku (eastern country, eastern provinces, Kanto provinces) into Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)) and expect their failure because they were not aware of Saigoku region but became Kokushi (provincial governor) there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the reason of Yoshichika&apos;s assignment as Governor of Tsushima Province was to push Kawachi-Genji whose home ground was in Kawachi Province and who had power in Togoku (eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) into Saigoku (western part of Japan [esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki]) as Kokushi (provincial governor) and to expect their failure because they were not aware of Saigoku region.</e>
<cmt>Tushima no kami→Governor of Tsushima Provinceとし、Kawachi-Genjiの補足を削除、had power→who had power、expect→to expectに修正、Togoku、Saigokuの補足を修正、一部訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the reason for Yoshichika&apos;s assignment as Governor of Tsushima Province was to push Kawachi-Genji whose home ground was in Kawachi Province and who had power in Togoku (eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) into Saigoku (western part of Japan [esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki]) as Kokushi (provincial governor) and to expect their failure because they were not familiar with the Saigoku region.</e>
<cmt>aware of -&gt; familiar with</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>特に義親を朝廷に告発した大江匡房が白河院の近臣であったことなどからも、院の謀略が伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because OE no Masafusa, who sued Yoshichika was a trusted vassal of the retired Emperor Shirakawa, this seems to be a deceptive ploy by the retired Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because OE no Masafusa, who sued Yoshichika was a trusted vassal of the Retired Emperor Shirakawa, this seems to have been a deceptive ploy by the Retired Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>the Retired Emperor Shirakawaとし、seems to be→seems to have beenに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because OE no Masafusa, who sued Yoshichika was a trusted vassal of the Retired Emperor Shirakawa, this seems to have been a deceptive ploy by the Retired Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>子供</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Children</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>長男　源義信　對馬太郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first son MINAMOTO no Yoshinobu 對馬太郎</e>
<cmt>對馬太郎: 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first son MINAMOTO no Yoshinobu, Tsushima no Taro.</e>
<cmt>對馬太郎→Tsushima no Taroとし、カンマ・ピリオド追加しました。(参考: http://katohjuk-web.hp.infoseek.co.jp/aduma35a-01.htm)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first son MINAMOTO no Yoshinobu, Tsushima no Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>従四位下左兵衛佐。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Sahyoe no suke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Sahyoe no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>Sahyo no sukeの補足追加 (用語集参照)、ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Sahyoe no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>次男　源義俊　對馬次郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second son MINAMOTO no Yoshitoshi</e>
<cmt>對馬次郎: 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second son MINAMOTO no Yoshitoshi, Tsushima no Jiro.</e>
<cmt>對馬次郎→訳漏れのため訳出、カンマ・ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second son MINAMOTO no Yoshitoshi, Tsushima no Jiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>右馬允。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umanosuke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uma no jo (Secretary of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>Umanosuke→Uma no joに修正、補足追加、ピリオド追加しました。(参照: http://www.albany.edu/eas/205/rank%20chart.htm)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uma no jo (Secretary of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>三男　源義泰　對馬三郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third son MINAMOTO no Yoshi 對馬三郎</e>
<cmt>對馬三郎: 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third son MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu, Tsushima no Saburo.</e>
<cmt>Yoshi→Yoshiyasu、對馬三郎→Tsushima no Saburoに修正、スペース修正、カンマ・ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third son MINAMOTO no Yoshiyasu, Tsushima no Saburo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>民部丞、伊予介。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minbu no jo, Iyo no suke (assistant governor of Iyo Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minbu no jo (Secretary of Ministry of Popular Affairs), Iyo no suke (Assistant Governor of Iyo Province).</e>
<cmt>Minbu no joの補足追加 (参照: http://www.albany.edu/eas/205/rank%20chart.htm)、assistant governor→Assistant Governorとし、ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minbu no jo (Secretary of Ministry of Popular Affairs), Iyo no suke (Assistant Governor of Iyo Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="37">
<j>四男　源義行　對馬四郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The forth son MINAMOTO no Yoshiyuki 對馬四郎</e>
<cmt>對馬四郎: 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth son MINAMOTO no Yoshiyuki, Tsushima no Shiro.</e>
<cmt>fourthのスペルミス修正、對馬四郎→Tsushima no Shiroとし、カンマ・ピリオド追加、スペース修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth son MINAMOTO no Yoshiyuki, Tsushima no Shiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>兵庫允、伊予介。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyogo no jo, Iyo no suke (assistant governor of Iyo Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyogo no jo (officer of the Bureau of Military Storehouses), Iyo no suke.</e>
<cmt>Hyogo no joの補足追加、Iyo no suke→既出のため補足削除、スペース修正、ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyogo no jo (officer of the Bureau of Military Storehouses), Iyo no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="39">
<j>五男　源為義　六条判官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fifth son MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi Rokujo-no-Hangan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifth son MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, Rokujo no Hangan.</e>
<cmt>カンマ・ピリオド追加、Rokujo no Hanganのハイフン消去しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifth son MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, Rokujo no Hangan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>左衛門大尉、検非違使。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saemon no daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), kebiishi (officials with judicial and police powers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saemon no daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), Kebiishi (officials with judicial and police powers).</e>
<cmt>kebiishi→Kebiishiとし、ピリオド追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saemon no daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), Kebiishi (officials with judicial and police powers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="41">
<j>六男　源宗清　従五位下伊勢守、兵庫允。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixth son MINAMOTO no Munekiyo Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Ise no kami (Governor of Ise Province), Hyogo no jo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixth son MINAMOTO no Munekiyo, Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Governor of Ise Province, Hyogo no jo.</e>
<cmt>カンマ・ピリオド追加、Governor of Ise Provinceとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixth son MINAMOTO no Munekiyo, Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Governor of Ise Province, Hyogo no jo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="42">
<j>源氏を継いだ為義は、他の兄弟とは不仲であったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tameyoshi succeeded heir of Minamoto clan but he didn&apos;t get along with other brothers and the brothers didn&apos;t joined the Hogen War, the Heiji War and raising an army by Minamoto clan, they lived in Kyoto and spend their life as bureaucracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tameyoshi succeeded heir of the Minamoto clan but he did not get along with other brothers.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」the Minamoto clan、didn&apos;t→did notとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tameyoshi succeeded to the Minamoto clan but he did not get along with his other brothers.</e>
<cmt>edited for natural English.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>他の兄弟は保元の乱、平治の乱をはじめ、その後の源氏の挙兵にも一切参加せずに、都にあって官僚の道を歩んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The brothers did not join the Hogen War, the Heiji War and raising an army by the Minamoto clan, and they lived in Kyoto and spent their lives as bureaucrats.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」the Minamoto clanとし、and追加、didn&apos;t joined→did not join、spend→spent、their life→their lives、bureaucracy→bureaucratsに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The brothers did not join the Hogen War, the Heiji War and raising an army by the Minamoto clan, and they lived in Kyoto and spent their lives as bureaucrats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>地方の長官になっても為義与党としての行動をとらなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshichika was assigned as governor of a province, he didn&apos;t cooperated Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they were assigned as governor of a province, they did not cooperate with Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Yoshichika→they、he→they、didn&apos;t cooperated→did not cooperate with、Yoshitomo→Tameyoshiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they were assigned as governor of a province, they did not cooperate with Tameyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また、為義が低い地位で地方の長官にもなれなかった時期にも、他の兄弟は高位につき、長男の源義信は従四位下まで登っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Period, in that Tameyoshi couldn&apos;t even be a provincial governor, his brothers were awarded higher position and the first son, MINAMOTO no Yoshinobu got Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period, in that Tameyoshi could not even be a provincial governor, his brothers were awarded higher position and the first son, MINAMOTO no Yoshinobu got the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>Period→period、couldn&apos;t→could no、tgot Jushiinoge→got the rank of Jushiinogeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period, in that Tameyoshi could not even be a provincial governor, his brothers were awarded higher position and the first son, MINAMOTO no Yoshinobu got the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), １３２人目(id:18687), 代言人(id:33675), 味っ子(id:17086), 葉月(id:25674), Junger(id:10282), 諸星団(id:72202), Hkato(id:78953), 小者(id:172526), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>