<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>楠木正成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashige KUSUNOKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashige KUSUNOKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashige KUSUNOKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>万里小路藤房の妹・滋子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeko, a younger sister of Fujifusa MADENOKOJI</e>
<cmt>「万里小路藤房の妹・滋子」としての「滋子」の読み方は確認できませんが、用語登録に登録されている読み方を当てております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeko, a younger sister of Fujifusa MADENOKOJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeko, a younger sister of Fujifusa MADENOKOJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>楠木 正成（くすのき まさしげ）は、鎌倉時代末期から南北朝時代 (日本)にかけての河内の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashige KUSUNOKI was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived in Kawachi Province from the end of the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashige KUSUNOKI was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived in Kawachi Province from the end of the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashige KUSUNOKI was a military commander who lived in Kawachi Province from the end of the Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>鎌倉幕府からは（悪党）とよばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called &quot;Akuto&quot; (rebel) by Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called &quot;Akuto&quot; (rebel) by Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called &quot;rebel&quot; by the Kamakura Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>建武の新政の立役者として足利尊氏らと共に活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated actively as a leading figure in the Kenmu Restoration with Takauji ASHIKAGA and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated actively as a leading figure in the Kenmu Restoration with Takauji ASHIKAGA and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated actively as a leading figure in the Kenmu Restoration with Takauji ASHIKAGA and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>恩賞方・武者所・記録所寄人・雑訴決断所奉行、和泉守護。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served not only as yoriudo (a dependent, frequently one who served a noble house or proprietor) at Onshokata (office to do desk works of Onsho award), Mushadokoro (place where Samurai of guard of the Imperial Palace is staffed) and Kirokujo (Land Record Office), but also as Zasso-Ketsudansho bugyo (magistrate of agency of Kenmu Government to file lawsuits) and Izumi Shugo (military governor of Izumi).</e>
<cmt>恩賞方・武者所・記録所寄人: 「恩賞方」「武者所」「記録所」は執務場所を示すため、「恩賞方、武者所および記録所で寄人(を務めた)」 と解釈されますので、その意味で訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served not only as yoriudo (a dependent, frequently one who served a noble house or proprietor) at Onshokata (office to do desk works of Onsho award), Mushadokoro (place where Samurai of guard of the Imperial Palace is staffed) and Kirokujo (Land Record Office), but also as Zasso-Ketsudansho bugyo (magistrate of agency of Kenmu Government to file lawsuits) and Izumi Shugo (military governor of Izumi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served not only as a clerk at the office of Rewards, the warriors&apos; office, and the land record office, but also as the magistrate of agency of Kenmu Government to file lawsuits and the military governor of Izumi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>贈正一位（1880年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zo shoichii (Senior First Rank, posthumously conferred) (1880).</e>
<cmt>登録された用語の通りに記載しておりますが、「He was posthumously awarded the rank of Shoichii (Senior First Rank) in 1880」のほうが分かりやすいのではないかと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zo shoichii (Senior First Rank, posthumously conferred) (1880).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously awarded the rank of Senior First Rank in 1880.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>尊氏反抗後新政の軍事主体の主力の一方になり、最後まで勤王をつらぬく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the betrayal of Takauji, Masashige played a major role in the military of the Restoration and gave his loyalty to the Emperor till the last.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the betrayal of Takauji, Masashige played a major role in the military of the Restoration and gave his loyalty to the Emperor till the last.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the betrayal of Takauji, Masashige played a major role in the military of the Restoration and gave his loyalty to the Emperor until his death.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>足利尊氏の軍と戦い湊川で自害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fought against the army of Takauji ASHIKAGA and committed suicide in Minatogawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought against the army of Takauji ASHIKAGA and committed suicide in Minatogawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought against the army of Takauji ASHIKAGA and committed suicide in Minatogawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>明治以降「大楠公」と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has been called &quot;Dai-Nanko&quot; (the Elder Lord of Kusunoki) since the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>大楠公: 用語登録では「Dai-Nanko」のみの表記ですが、Translator Guidelinesの指示により、説明が必要なため、カッコ内に説明を加えております(ただしこれは定訳ではありません)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He has been called &quot;Dai-Nanko&quot; (the Elder Lord of Kusunoki) since the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He has been called the Elder Lord of Kusunok &apos;Dai-Nanko&apos; after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>父は系図により楠木正遠あるいは正玄、正澄、正康、俊親などと伝え、はっきりしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his father is supposed to have been Masatoo, Masaharu, Masazumi, Masayasu or Toshichika KUSUNOKI, depending on various genealogical charts, it is not certain who his father was.</e>
<cmt>正康: 用語登録では「Seiko(読み方不明)」とされていますが、楠木家で名前に「正」が付く人物の名前は「まさ…」と読むため、「まさやす」のほうが確率が高いと思われますので、こちらを採用しております / 俊親: 読み方が確認できませんので、最も一般的と思われる読み方を当てております(用語登録でも「Toshichika(読み方不明)」とされています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his father is supposed to have been Masatoo, Masaharu, Masazumi, Masayasu or Toshichika KUSUNOKI, depending on various genealogical charts, it is not certain who his father was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his father is said to have been Masatoo, Masaharu, Masazumi, Masayasu or Toshichika KUSUNOKI, depending on various genealogical charts, it is not certain who his father was.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>楠木氏の出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the Kusunoki clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the Kusunoki clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the Kusunoki clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>楠木氏は、伊予国の伊予橘氏（越智氏）の橘遠保の末裔という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kusunoki clan is said to be descendants of TACHIBANA no Toyasu of the Iyotachibana clan (Ochi clan) in Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kusunoki clan is said to be descended from TACHIBANA no Toyasu of the Iyotachibana clan (Ochi clan) in Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kusunoki clan is said to be descended from TACHIBANA no Toyasu of the Iyotachibana clan (Ochi clan) in Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、正成以前の系図は諸家で一致せず、後世の創作と見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But a genealogical chart before Masashige of one family of the clan varies from those of the other families, so the charts were likely created by later generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But a genealogical chart before Masashige of one family of the clan varies from those of the other families, so the charts were likely created by later generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a genealogical chart before Masashige of one family of the clan varies from those of the other families, however, the charts were likely to be created in later generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>河内国には楠木姓の由来となるような地名はなく、北条氏得宗家被官の一族で、得宗領の河内へ移ってきたとする説、武蔵国（関東地方）の出身であるとする説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there is no geographical name deriving from the family name &quot;Kusunoki&quot; in Kawachi Province, some insist that the clan had served as low-level bureaucrat of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan and moved later to Kawachi, which was a territory of the Tokuso family of the Hojo clan, but others have different opinions such as one that the clan originally comes from Musashi Province (Kanto region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there is no geographical name derived from the family name &quot;Kusunoki&quot; in Kawachi Province, some insist that the clan served as low-level bureaucrat of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan and moved later to Kawachi, which was a territory of the Tokuso family of the Hojo clan, but others have different opinions such as one that the clan originally comes from Musashi Province (Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there is no geographical name derived from the family name &quot;Kusunoki&quot; in Kawachi Province, some insist that the clan served as low-level official of the Tokuso family of the Hojo clan and moved later to Kawachi (a territory of the Tokuso family of the Hojo clan), but others have different opinions, including one that states that that the clan originally came from Musashi Province (Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、秦氏の系統の説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand some suggest that it derives from the Hata clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand some suggest that it was derived from the Hata clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, some suggest that it was derived from the Hata clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>昭和37年（1962年）に三重県上野市の旧家から『上嶋家文書』（江戸時代末期の写本）が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kamijima-ke bunsho&quot; (Documents of the Kamijima family), which was a manuscript in the end of Edo period, was found in an old family in Ueno City, Mie Prefecture, in 1962.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kamijima-ke bunsho&quot; (Documents of the Kamijima family), which was a manuscript in the end of Edo period, was found in an old family in Ueno City, Mie Prefecture, in 1962.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents of the Kamijima family &quot;Kamijima-ke bunsho&quot;(a manuscript in the end of the Edo period) was found in the old family in Ueno City, Mie Prefecture, in 1962.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>河内国石川郡赤坂村（現大阪府南河内郡千早赤阪村）の出生とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he was born in Akasaka Village, Ishikawa District, Kawachi Province (present-day Chihaya-Akasaka-mura, Minamikawachi-gun, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that he was born in Akasaka Village, Ishikawa District, Kawachi Province (present-day Chihaya-Akasaka-mura, Minamikawachi-gun, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Masashige was born in Akasaka Village, Ishikawa District, Kawachi Province (present-day Chihaya-Akasaka-mura, Minamikawachi-gun, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>生年に関しての確実な史料は存在せず、正成の前半生はほとんど不明で、日本史上きわめて有名でありながら出自がこれほど謎に包まれた人物はほかにいないといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there is no historical material proving his birth date and the first half of his life is almost unknown, it is said that there is no one else whose origin is so mysterious as that of Masashige, although he is highly famous in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there is no historical material proving his birth date and the first half of his life is almost unknown, it is said that there is no one else whose origin is so mysterious as that of Masashige, although he is highly famous in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there is no historical material proving his birth date and the first half of his life is mostly unknown, there is no one else whose origin is so mysterious as that of Masashige, although he is highly well-known in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>様々な歴史家による懸命な研究努力にも拘らず、正成が確かな実像として捉えられるのは、元弘元年の挙兵から建武3年の湊川での自刃までのわずか6年ほどに過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite exhausting efforts by several historians, a real image of Masashige can be drawn only for the time of six years from raising an army in 1331 to committing suicide in Minatogawa in 1336.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite exhaustive efforts by several historians, a real image of Masashige could only be drawn during a period of six years from raising an army in 1331 to committing suicide in Minatogawa in 1336.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite exhaustive efforts by several historians, a true picture of Masashige could only be seen in a period of six years from raising an army in 1331 to committing suicide in Minatogawa in 1336.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>元弘元年（1331年）臨川寺領和若松荘「悪党楠木兵衛尉」として史料に名を残しており、鎌倉幕府の御家人帳にない河内を中心に付近一帯の水銀などの流通ルートで活動する「悪党」とよばれる豪族であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because his name was recorded in a historical material in 1331 as &quot;Hyoenojo KUSUNOKI of Akuto&quot;at wa-wakamatsu-sho in the territory of Rinsen-ji Temple, he is considered to have been a member of a powerful clan that was called &quot;Akuto&quot; and worked in distribution of quicksilver and others in the area around Kawachi, which was not registered in Gokenin cho (register of lower-ranking vassal in the Kamakura and Edo periods) by Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>和若松荘: 「天竜寺文書」という史料には「和泉国若松荘」と記載されているため(http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=B-pBRw52qKAC&amp;pg=PA99&amp;lpg=PA99&amp;dq=%22%E5%A4%A9%E7%AB%9C%E5%AF%BA%E6%96%87%E6%9B%B8%22+%22%E8%8B%A5%E6%9D%BE%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=jv1l5ODEXR&amp;sig=VZ5ow7vxS3JiQb11nXc0mB-xhr8&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=Kv7eStT-GoaUkAXl2fkX&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CAwQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=%22%E5%A4%A9%E7%AB%9C%E5%AF%BA%E6%96%87%E6%9B%B8%22%20%22%E8%8B%A5%E6%9D%BE%22&amp;f=false)、正しくは「和泉国若松荘」または「和泉若松荘(いずみわかまつしょう)」と推測されますが、Webでも「和若松荘」となっているため、原文通りに「わ・わかまつしょう」と記載しております。用語登録とは異なり、「臨川寺領」はローマ字表記ではなく、「臨川寺の領」と訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because his name was recorded in a historical material in 1331 as &quot;Hyoenojo KUSUNOKI of Akuto&quot;at wa-wakamatsu-sho in the territory of Rinsen-ji Temple, he is considered to have been a member of a powerful clan that was called &quot;Akuto&quot; and worked in distribution of quicksilver and others in the area around Kawachi, which was not registered in Gokenin cho (register of lower-ranking vassal in the Kamakura and Edo periods) by Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his name was recorded in historical materials in 1331 as &apos;Hyoenojo KUSUNOKI of Akuto&apos; at wa-wakamatsu-sho in the territory of Rinsen-ji Temple, he is considered to have been a member of a powerful clan that was called &apos;Akuto&apos; and worked in distribution of quicksilver and others in the area around Kawachi, which was not registered in the record of lower-ranking vassal of the Kamakura shogunate &apos;Gokenin cho&apos; by Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、この時既に官職を帯びていることから、これ以前に朝廷に仕え、後醍醐天皇もしくはその周囲の人物達と接触を持っていたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he already had a government post at that time, it is believed that he had served the Imperial Court and had kept contact with Emperor Godaigo or his acquaintances before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he already had a government post at that time, it is believed that he had served the Imperial Court and had kept contact with Emperor Godaigo or his acquaintances before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he already had a government post at that time, it is believed that he had served the Imperial Court and had kept contact with Emperor Godaigo or his acquaintances before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>この年に後醍醐天皇の挙兵を聞くと下赤坂城にて挙兵し、湯浅定仏と戦う（赤坂城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he heard of raising an army of Emperor Godaigo that year, he also raised an army at Shimoakasaka-jo Castle to fight against Jobutsu YUASA (Battle of Akasaka-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he heard of raising an army of Emperor Godaigo that year, he also raised an army at Shimoakasaka-jo Castle to fight against Jobutsu YUASA (Battle of Akasaka-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he heard of raising an army of Emperor Godaigo that year, he also raised an army at Shimoakasaka-jo Castle to fight against Jobutsu YUASA (Battle of Akasakajo Castle).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後醍醐と正成を結びつけたのは、伊賀兼光、あるいは真言宗の僧である文観と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the person who introduced Masashige to Emperor Godaigo was Kanemitsu IGA or Monkan, a monk of the Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the person who introduced Masashige to Emperor Godaigo was Kanemitsu IGA or Monkan, a monk of the Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the person who introduced Masashige to Emperor Godaigo was Kanemitsu IGA or Monkan, a monk of the Shingon Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>後醍醐が隠岐島に流罪となっている間にも、大和国（奈良県）の吉野などで戦った護良親王とともに、河内国の上赤坂城や金剛山 (金剛山地)中腹に築いた山城、千早城に籠城してゲリラ戦法や糞尿攻撃などを駆使して幕府の大軍を相手に奮戦する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Emperor Godaigo was exiled to Oki no shima Island, Masashige and Imperial Prince Morinaga, who fought with him in Yoshino in Yamato Province (present-day Nara Prefecture) and other places, held Kamiakasaka-jo Castle in Kawachi Province and Chihaya-jo Castle, which was a yamajiro (a castle built on a mountain to take advantage of the mountain&apos;s topography) built in the middle of Mt. Kongo (Kongo mountainous district), using guerrilla tactics, excrement attack and others, to fight against a huge army of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>護良親王: 「もりよし」と読む場合もあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Emperor Godaigo was exiled to Oki no shima Island, Masashige and Imperial Prince Morinaga, who fought with him in Yoshino in Yamato Province (present-day Nara Prefecture) and other places, held Kamiakasaka-jo Castle in Kawachi Province and Chihaya-jo Castle, which was a yamajiro (a castle built on a mountain to take advantage of the mountain&apos;s topography) built in the middle of Mt. Kongo (Kongo mountainous district), using guerrilla tactics, excrement attack and others, to fight against a huge army of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Emperor Godaigo was exiled to Okinoshima Island, Masashige and Imperial Prince Morinaga, who fought with him in Yoshino in Yamato Province (present-day Nara Prefecture) and other places, held Kamiakasaka-jo Castle in Kawachi Province and Chihaya-jo Castle, which was a a castle built on a mountain to take advantage of the mountain&apos;s topography, built in the middle of Mt. Kongo (Kongo mountainous district), using guerrilla tactics, excrement attack and others, to fight against a huge army of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>元弘3年 / 正慶2年（1333年）、正成らの活躍に触発されて各地に倒幕の機運が広がり、足利尊氏や新田義貞、赤松円心らが挙兵して鎌倉幕府は滅びた（元弘の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the success of Masashige and others increased opportunities to overthrow the Shogunate in various regions in 1333, Takauji ASHIKAGA, Yoshisada NITTA, Enshin AKAMATSU and others raised an army to defeat the Kamakura bakufu (Genko War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the success of Masashige and others increased opportunities to overthrow the Shogunate in various regions in 1333, Takauji ASHIKAGA, Yoshisada NITTA, Enshin AKAMATSU and others raised an army to defeat the Kamakura bakufu (Genko War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the success of Masashige and others increased opportunities to overthrow the Shogunate in various regions in 1333, warriors including Takauji ASHIKAGA, Yoshisada NITTA, and Enshin AKAMATSU raised an army to defeat the Kamakura bakufu (Genko War).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>後醍醐天皇が京へ凱旋する際、兵庫まで出迎え、同道警護についた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Godaigo returned in triumph to Kyoto, Masashige greeted him in Hyogo to accompany him as a bodyguard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Godaigo returned in triumph to Kyoto, Masashige greeted him in Hyogo to accompany him as a bodyguard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Godaigo returned in triumph to Kyoto, Masashige greeted him in Hyogo to accompany him as a bodyguard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>後醍醐天皇の建武の新政が始まると、正成は記録所寄人、雑訴決断所奉行人、河内・和泉国の守護となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Kenmu Restoration started, Masashige served not only as yoriudo at Kirokujo, but also as Zasso-Ketsudansho bugyonin (secretaries of agency of Kenmu Government to file lawsuits) and Shugo of Kawachi and Izumi Provinces.</e>
<cmt>記録所寄人: 既出箇所(9列目)の訳に合わせておりますので、用語登録の訳語とは異なります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kenmu Restoration started, Masashige served not only as yoriudo at Kirokujo, but also as Zasso-Ketsudansho bugyonin (secretaries of agency of Kenmu Government to file lawsuits) and Shugo of Kawachi and Izumi Provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Godaigo&apos;s Kenmu Restoration started, Masashige served not only as yoriudo at Kirokujo, but also as secretary at Zasso-Ketsudansho and Shugo of Kawachi and Izumi Provinces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>建武の新政においては正成は後醍醐天皇の絶大な信任を受け、結城親光、名和長年、千種忠顕をあわせて「三木一草」と併称され、「朝恩に誇った」とされる（太平記の記述）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Masashige won the deep confidence of Emperor Godaigo in the Kenmu Restoration, it is said that the group of Masashige, Chikamitsu YUKI, Nagatoshi NAWA and Tadaaki CHIGUSA was called &quot;Sanboku-Isso&quot; (literally, &quot;three trees and one grass&quot;, because their names or nominal designations have to do with tree or grass), which refers to four meritorious retainers of the Southern Court, so they were &quot;proud of imperial blessing&quot; (this is a description from &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace)).</e>
<cmt>三木一草: Guidelinesの指示により、カッコ内に説明を加えていますが、これは定訳ではありません。尚、「三木一草」として登録されている用語では「Tadaki CHIGUSA」となっていますが、正しくは「ちぐさただあき」ですので、本文では「Tadaaki」と修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Masashige won the deep confidence of Emperor Godaigo in the Kenmu Restoration, it is said that the group of Masashige, Chikamitsu YUKI, Nagatoshi NAWA and Tadaaki CHIGUSA was called &quot;Sanboku-Isso&quot; (literally, &quot;three trees and one grass&quot;, because their names or nominal designations have to do with tree or grass), which refers to four meritorious retainers of the Southern Court, so they were &quot;proud of imperial blessing&quot; (this is a description from &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Masashige won the deep confidence of Emperor Godaigo in the Kenmu Restoration and the group of Chikamitsu YUKI, Nagatoshi NAWA and Tadaaki CHIGUSA were called &apos;Sanboku-Isso&apos;, it is said that they were &apos;proud of imperial blessing&apos; (a description from The Record of the Great Peace &quot;Taiheiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>建武 (日本)元年（1334年）冬、正成が北条氏残党を討つために京を離れた直後、護良親王が謀反の嫌疑で捕縛され、足利尊氏に引き渡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after Masashige had left Kyoto in winter 1334 to defeat the remnants of the Hojo clan, Imperial Prince Morinaga was captured on suspicion of rebellion to be turned over to Takauji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after Masashige had left Kyoto in winter 1334 to defeat the remnants of the Hojo clan, Imperial Prince Morinaga was captured on suspicion of rebellion to be turned over to Takauji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after Masashige had left Kyoto in winter 1334 to defeat the remnants of the Hojo clan, Imperial Prince Morinaga was captured on suspicion of rebellion to be turned over to Takauji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その直後、正成は建武政権の役職の多くを辞職したと見られることから、正成は護良親王の有力与力であったと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Masashige likely gave up several posts of the Kenmu Government shortly after the capture of Imperial Prince Morinaga, he is considered to have been an important yoriki (literally, &quot;strength that is offered&quot;) (a samurai who served warrior-commanders of higher rank) of the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>与力: ここでは、登録されている「a police sergeant」ではなく、参考サイト(http://books.google.com/books?id=DY0XiflmVIAC&amp;pg=PA89&amp;lpg=PA89&amp;dq=imperial+ranks+japan+court&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=87K36orH2v&amp;sig=IFNDpfnIj9qMbfIhYp8s8jhE_JI&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=r7_nSoibCNeIkQWK57jMBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CA0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22yoriki%22&amp;f=false)の177P、178P等に記されている意味で用いられていると思われるため、その説明を引用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Masashige likely gave up several posts of the Kenmu Government shortly after the capture of Imperial Prince Morinaga, he is considered to have been an important yoriki (literally, &quot;strength that is offered&quot;) (a samurai who served warrior-commanders of higher rank) of the Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Masashige likely gave up several posts of the Kenmu Government shortly after the capture of Imperial Prince Morinaga, he is considered to have been an important samurai who served warrior-commanders of higher rank &apos;yoriki&apos; of the Imperial Prince</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>建武2年（1335年）の中先代の乱を討伐に向かった尊氏がそのまま新政に離反し、尊氏追討の命を受けた義貞が箱根・竹ノ下の戦いに敗北して足利軍が京へ迫るが、北畠顕家らと連絡して足利方を京より駆逐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Takauji went to put down the Nakasendai War in 1335, did not come back and seceded from the Kenmu Government, Yoshisada was ordered to hunt down and kill him, which resulted in the defeat of Yoshisada in the Battle of Hakone Take no Shita, so the Ashikaga side approached to Kyoto, but Masashige contacted Akiie KITABATAKE and others to expel the Ashikaga side from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Takauji went to put down the Nakasendai War in 1335, did not come back and seceded from the Kenmu Government, Yoshisada was ordered to hunt down and kill him, which resulted in the defeat of Yoshisada in the Battle of Hakone Take no Shita, so the Ashikaga side approached to Kyoto, but Masashige contacted Akiie KITABATAKE and others to expel the Ashikaga side from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Takauji went to win the Nakasendai War in 1335 and seceded from the Kenmu Government, Yoshisada was ordered to track down and kill Takauji, which resulted in the defeat of Yoshisada in the Battle of Hakone Take no Shita, so the Ashikaga side approached to Kyoto, but Masashige contacted Akiie KITABATAKE and others to expel the Ashikaga side from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>延元元年 / 建武3年（1336年）、足利方が九州で軍勢を整えて再び京都へ迫ると、正成は後醍醐天皇に新田義貞を切り捨てて尊氏と和睦するよう進言するが容認されず、次善の策として、一旦天皇の京都からの撤退を進言するがこれも却下される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Ashikaga&apos;s troops established themselves in Kyushu and approached to Kyoto again in 1336, Masashige suggested to Emperor Godaigo abandoning Yoshisada NITTA to make peace with Takauji, but the Emperor did not accept his suggestion, so Masashige advised him to take the second best way, that is, a temporary withdrawal from Kyoto, but it was also rejected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Ashikaga&apos;s troops established themselves in Kyushu and approached Kyoto again in 1336, Masashige suggested to Emperor Godaigo abandoning Yoshisada NITTA to make peace with Takauji, but the Emperor did not accept his suggestion, so Masashige advised him to take the second best way, that is, a temporary withdrawal from Kyoto, but it was also rejected.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Ashikaga&apos;s troops established themselves in Kyushu and approached Kyoto again in 1336, Masashige suggested to Emperor Godaigo that the emperor should abandon Yoshisada NITTA to make peace with Takauji, but the Emperor did not accept his opinion, then Masashige advised him to take the second best policy, that is, a temporary withdrawal from Kyoto, which was also rejected.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>絶望的な状況下で義貞の麾下での出陣を命じられ、湊川の戦い（兵庫県神戸市）で足利直義の軍と戦い敗れて、弟の楠木正季と刺し違えたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he was ordered to depart for the front under Yoshisada&apos;s command in hopeless circumstances, he fought against the army of Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA in the Battle of Minatogawa (present-day Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture) to be defeated, so he and his younger brother Masasue KUSUNOKI are said to have stabbed each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ordered to depart for the front under Yoshisada&apos;s command due to the hopeless circumstance, he fought against the army of Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA in the Battle of Minatogawa (present-day Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture) to be defeated, so he and his younger brother Masasue KUSUNOKI are said to have stabbed each other.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was ordered to depart for the front under Yoshisada&apos;s command due to the hopeless circumstance, he fought against the army of Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA in the Battle of Minatogawa (present-day Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture) to be defeated, so he is said to have stabbed each other with his younger brother Masasue KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>法名は霊光寺大圓義龍卍堂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) is Reikojidaiengiryumanjido.</e>
<cmt>霊光寺大圓義龍卍堂: 読み方が不明ですので、最も一般的と思われる読み方をローマ字で表記しております。「Reikojidaiingiryumanjido(読み方不明)」と登録されていますが、「圓」は「えん」ですので、そのように訂正しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (a Buddhist name given to a person who has died or has entered the priesthood) is Reikojidaiengiryumanjido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous buddhist name is Reikojidaiengiryumanjido.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="34">
<j>正成の息子である小楠公こと楠木正行を筆頭に、楠木正時、楠木正儀らも正成と同じく南朝方について戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only Masashige&apos;s son, Masatsura KUSUNOKI, also known as Sho-Nanko (the Younger Lord of Kusunoki), but also Masatoki KUSUNOKI, Masanori KUSUNOKI and others took the side of the Southern Court as well as Masashige to fight against the enemy.</e>
<cmt>小楠公: 用語登録では「Shonanko」とされていますが、「Dai-Nanko」の表記との整合性と、他に「楠公(Nanko)」という単語も出てくることから、「Sho-Nanko」の表記のほうが分かりやすいと思われるため、「Sho-Nanko」と表記しています。また、Guidelinesの指示による説明をカッコ内に入れていますが、これは定訳ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only Masashige&apos;s son, Masatsura KUSUNOKI, also known as Sho-Nanko (the Younger Lord of Kusunoki), but also Masatoki KUSUNOKI, Masanori KUSUNOKI and others took the side of the Southern Court as well as Masashige to fight against the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only Masashige&apos;s son, Masatsura KUSUNOKI, also known as the Younger Lord of Kusunoki &apos;Sho-Nanko&apos;, but also Masatoki KUSUNOKI and Masanori KUSUNOKI took the side of the Southern Court as well as Masashige to fight against the enemy.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="35">
<j>正成の妻・久子は、夫・正成、長男・正行らの死後、戦乱の中、河内（甘南備村）を離れ、美濃国伊自良村長滝釜ヶ谷奥の院に隠棲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period of war Masashige&apos;s wife, Hisako, left Kawachi (Kannabi Village) after death of her husband Masashige, her eldest son Masatsura and other family members to live in seclusion in Okunoin, Nagataki kamagatani, Ijira-mura, Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the warring period, Masashige&apos;s wife, Hisako, left Kawachi (Kannabi Village) after death of her husband Masashige, her eldest son Masatsura and other family members to live in seclusion in Okunoin, Nagataki kamagatani, Ijira-mura, Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the warring period, Masashige&apos;s wife, Hisako, left Kawachi (Kannabi Village) after the death of her husband Masashige, her eldest son Masatsura and other family members to live in seclusion in Okunoin, Nagataki kamagatani, Ijira-mura, Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>奥の院には、それを祀る甘南備神社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Kannabi-jinja Shrine deifying the clan at Okunoin.</e>
<cmt>「それ」が何を指すのか特定不能です(Webの原文通りなので、用語抜け等ではありません)。文脈からは、前文の「久子」を指すと思われますが、人物に「それ」という単語を用いるのは不自然であり、また、125列目に「久子は戦後、湊川神社に合祀された」との記述があり、甘南備神社に祀られているのは久子ではないと判断されるため、「一族(楠木家)」の意味で訳してあります。ただし、117列目に、この神社には「楠木家の遠祖と称える橘諸兄の父、美努王（みぬのおおきみ）」が祀られているという記述があるため、この文自体が不正確だと判断されます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is Kannabi-jinja Shrine deifying the clan at Okunoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannabi-jinja Shrine deifying the clan is at Okunoin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>地域の尊信を得て、河内乃国甘南備の字名、長滝、平井、掛、松尾等々を与える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hisako had gained the trust of the people in the area, she named some places there after the place names such as Nagataki, Hirai, Kake or Matsuo in Kannabi in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hisako had gained the trust of the people in the area, she named some places there after place names such as Nagataki, Hirai, Kake or Matsuo in Kannabi in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hisako had gained the trust of the people in the area, she named the places after Nagataki, Hirai, Kake, Matsuo and so force in Kannabi in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その墓は伊自良湖の登り口、長滝七社神社境内横にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her grave is adjacent to the precincts of Nagataki Nana-sha-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>長滝七社神社: 用語登録では「Nagataki Nana-sha Shrine」となっていますが、仕様指示書によれば「Nagataki Nana-sha-jinja Shrine」とすべきですので、仕様指示書に合わせております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is adjacent to the precincts of Nagataki Nana-sha-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is adjacent to the precincts of Nagataki Nana-sha-jinja Shrine, at the foot of Ijira-ko Lake.</e>
<cmt>at the foot of Ijira-ko Lake補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>後世の処遇と影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluation of Masashige by later generations and his influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluation of Masashige by later generations and his influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluation of Masashige by later generations and his influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>南朝寄りの古典『太平記』では正成の事跡は強調して書かれているが、足利氏寄りの史書である『梅松論』でさえも同情的な書き方をされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The achievements of Masashige were described with emphasis in the pro-Southern-Court classic &quot;Taiheiki&quot;, but even in the pro-Ashikaga history book &quot;Baishoron&quot; (Historical tale compiled in 1349) he was described with some sympathy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The achievements of Masashige were described with emphasis in the pro-Southern-Court classic &quot;Taiheiki&quot;, but even in the pro-Ashikaga history book &quot;Baishoron&quot; (Historical tale compiled in 1349) he was described with some sympathy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The achievements of Masashige were emphasized in the description contained in the pro-Southern-Court classic &quot;Taiheiki,&quot; but in the pro-Ashikaga history book &quot;Baishoron&quot; (Historical tale compiled in 1349) he was described sympathetically.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>理由は、戦死した正成の首（頭部）を尊氏が「むなしくなっても家族はさぞや会いたかろう」と丁寧に遺族へ返還しているなど、尊氏自身が清廉な彼に一目置いていたためであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason was that Takauji acknowledged his clean personality and handed back the head of the fallen Masashige to his family in a polite way, saying that they must want to see him, although they might feel hollowed out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason was that Takauji acknowledged his clean personality and handed back the head of the fallen Masashige to his family in a polite way, saying that they must want to see him, although they might feel hollowed out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason was that Takauji acknowledged Masashige&apos;s integrity and handed back the head of the fallen Masashige to his family in a polite way, saying that they must want to see him, although they might feel sad.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>今日でいうゲリラ戦的戦法を得意とした正成の戦法は、江戸時代に楠木流の軍学として流行し、正成の末裔と称した楠木正辰（楠木不伝）の弟子だった由井正雪も南木流軍学を講じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his tactics that excelled at present-day guerrilla warfare became prevalent as military science of Kusunoki-ryu style in the Edo period, Shosetsu YUI, a disciple of Masatatsu KUSUNOKI (Fuden KUSUNOKI), who claimed descent from Masashige, also taught the military science of Nagi-ryu style (military science proposed by Masatatsu KUSUNOKI).</e>
<cmt>「楠木流」: 定訳が不明ですので、登録されている「南木流」の訳語に合わせ、「Kusunoki-ryu style」と訳しております)。/ 南木流: 用語登録には「Nagi-ryu style」とだけ記載されていますが、説明が必要なため、カッコ内に説明を補足しています(この説明は定訳ではありません)。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his tactics that excelled at present-day guerrilla warfare became prevalent as military science of Kusunoki-ryu style in the Edo period, Shosetsu YUI, a disciple of Masatatsu KUSUNOKI (Fuden KUSUNOKI), who claimed descent from Masashige, also taught the military science of Nagi-ryu style (military science proposed by Masatatsu KUSUNOKI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his tactics that excelled at present-day guerrilla warfare became prevalent as military science of Kusunoki-ryu style in the Edo period, Shosetsu YUI, a disciple of Masatatsu KUSUNOKI (Fuden KUSUNOKI), who claimed descent from Masashige, also taught the military science of Nagi-ryu style.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>佩刀であったと伝承される小竜景光（東京国立博物館蔵）は、山田浅右衛門の手を経て、明治天皇の佩刀となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koryu Kagemitsu, a sword made by a sword craftsman Kagemitsu, which had been handed on to later generations as his carrying sword (a property of Tokyo National Museum), passed into the possession of Emperor Meiji as his carrying sword through Asaemon YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>小竜景光: 用語登録では「Kagemitsu KORYU」となっていますが、これは人名ではなく、刀の名称ですので、「Koryu Kagemitsu」と表記しています。その後の説明(a sword made by…)は定訳ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koryu Kagemitsu, a sword made by a sword craftsman Kagemitsu, which had been handed on to later generations as his carrying sword (a property of Tokyo National Museum), passed into the possession of Emperor Meiji as his carrying sword through Asaemon YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koryu Kagemitsu, a sword made by a sword craftsman Kagemitsu, which had been handed on to later generations as his carrying sword (a property of Tokyo National Museum), passed into the possession of Emperor Meiji as his carrying sword through Asaemon YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>明治天皇は大本営が広島に移った時も携えていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji is said to have carried the sword, even when the Imperial headquarters were relocated to Hiroshima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji is said to have carried the sword, even when the Imperial headquarters were relocated to Hiroshima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji is said to have carried the sword, even when the Imperial headquarters were relocated to Hiroshima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="44">
<j>また、明治政府は南朝功臣の子孫にも爵位を授けるため、正成の子孫を探したが、楠木氏末裔を自称する氏族は数多く全国各地に存在したが、学術的根拠の認められる直系子孫は国家権力を以てしても確認することが出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Government looked for descendants of Masashige to confer descendants of the meritorious retainer of the Southern Court the dignity of a peerage, but it was not possible even for the state power to identify his direct descendants based on scientific evidence, although many clans throughout the nation claimed descent from the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>南朝功臣: 「meritorious retainer of Southern Dynasty」と登録されていますが、用語統一リストの南北朝に関する指示に合わせ、左記のように修正しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Government looked for descendants of Masashige to confer descendants of the meritorious retainer of the Southern Court the dignity of a peerage, but it was not possible even for the state power to identify his direct descendants based on scientific evidence, although many clans throughout the nation claimed descent from the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Government looked for descendants of Masashige to confer descendants of the meritorious retainer of the Southern Court the dignity of a peerage, but it was not possible even for the state power to identify his direct descendants based on scientific evidence, although many clans throughout the nation claimed descent from the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>このため、新田氏、菊池氏、名和氏の子孫等は男爵に叙せられたが、楠木氏からは華族に加えられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason none of the Kusunoki clan was raised to the peerage, while descendants of the Nitta, Kikuchi and Nawa clans were baronized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason none of the Kusunoki clan was raised to the peerage, while descendants of the Nitta, Kikuchi and Nawa clans were baronized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason none of the Kusunoki clan were raised to the peerage, while descendants of the Nitta, Kikuchi and Nawa clans were baronized.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>しかし、大楠公600年祭（昭和10年）時には学術的根拠ある楠木氏の子孫が確認され、湊川神社内に楠木同族会が組織されて現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But descendants of the Kusunoki clan were identified based on scientific evidence at the Dai-Nanko 600 years anniversary in 1935, so the Kusunoki family council has been organized at Minatogawa-jinja Shrine and continues to exist to this day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But descendants of the Kusunoki clan were identified based on scientific evidence at the Dai-Nanko 600 years anniversary in 1935, so the Kusunoki family council has been organized at Minatogawa-jinja Shrine and continues to exist to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But descendants of the Kusunoki clan were identified based on scientific evidence at the Dai-Nanko 600th anniversary in 1935, so the Kusunoki family council has been organized at Minatogawa-jinja Shrine and continues to exist.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>死後の楠木正成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashige KUSUNOKI after death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashige KUSUNOKI after death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashige KUSUNOKI after death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>永禄2年（1559年）、正成の子孫と称した楠木正虎が献金により朝敵の赦免を嘆願し、正親町天皇の勅免を受けて朝敵でなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Masatora KUSUNOKI, who claimed descent from Masashige, petitioned with a donation to pardon Masashige for the specification as an enemy of the court, he was pardoned by order of Emperor Ogimachi to be released from the specification.</e>
<cmt>勅免(勅命による赦免): 定訳が不明ですので、「be pardoned by order of ～」と訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Masatora KUSUNOKI, who claimed to be a descendent of Masashige, petitioned with a donation to pardon Masashige for the specification as an enemy of the court, he was pardoned by order of Emperor Ogimachi to be released from the specification.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Masatora KUSUNOKI, who claimed to be a descendent of Masashige, petitioned through a donation that Masashige be pardoned from being named an enemy of the court, he was pardoned by order of Emperor Ogimachi in 1559.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>また江戸時代には水戸学の尊王思想の史家によって、忠臣として見直された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period he was revaluated as a loyal subject by imperialistic historians of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain).</e>
<cmt>尊王思想の史家: 定訳が不明ですので、「imperialistic historian」と訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period he was revaluated as a loyal subject by imperialistic historians of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period he was revaluated as a loyal subject by imperialistic historians of Mitogaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>江戸時代後期には尊皇家によって頻繁に祭祀されるようになり、その動きはやがてのちの湊川神社の創建に結実し、他方で靖国神社などの招魂社成立に大きな影響を与えることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter half of Edo period he was often enshrined by advocates of reverence for the Emperor, which led to the foundation of Minatogawa-jinja Shrine, and on the other hand it made a major impact on foundation of Shokon-sha Shrine such as Yasukuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>尊皇家: 定訳が不明ですので「advocate of reverence for the Emperor」(文中では複数形)と訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of Edo period he was often enshrined by advocates of reverence for the Emperor, which led to the foundation of Minatogawa-jinja Shrine, and on the other hand it made a major impact on foundation of Shokon-sha Shrine such as Yasukuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the Edo period he was often enshrined by advocates of reverence for the Emperor, which led to the foundation of Minatogawa-jinja Shrine, and also, it made a major impact on foundation of Shokon-sha Shrine such as Yasukuni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>明治になり南北朝正閏論を経て南朝が正統であるとされると大楠公と呼ばれ、講談などでは『三国志演義』の諸葛亮の天才軍師的イメージを重ねて語られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Southern Court had been legitimated through the Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument on legitimacy of either Northern or Southern Court) in the Meiji period, he was called Dai-Nanko and was described in kodan storytelling and others as a person with a similar image of a genius strategist Zhuge Liang of &quot;Romance of the Three Kingdoms&quot;.</e>
<cmt>南北朝正閏論: 「Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument on legitimacy of either Northern or Southern Dynasty)」が登録されていますが、用語統一リストの指示に合わせて、左記のように修正しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Southern Court had been legitimated through the Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument on legitimacy of either Northern or Southern Court) in the Meiji period, he was called Dai-Nanko and was described in kodan storytelling and others as a person with a similar image of a genius strategist Zhuge Liang of &quot;Romance of the Three Kingdoms&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Southern Court had been legitimatized through the argument on legitimacy of either Northern or Southern Court in the Meiji period, he was called Dai-Nanko and was compared in &apos;kodan&apos; storytelling and other sources to the genius strategist Zhuge Liang of &quot;Romance of the Three Kingdoms.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>また、皇国史観の下、戦死を覚悟で大義の為に逍遥と戦場に赴く姿が「忠臣の鑑」、「日本人の鑑」として讃えられ、修身教育でも祀られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kokoku Shikan (emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto) he was praised as &quot;an exemplary loyal subject&quot; or &quot;a true Japanese&quot; who went off to war with a heavy gait, being prepared to die for his cause, so that he was worshiped also in Shushin education (moral training education).</e>
<cmt>「逍遥」は「気ままにぶらぶら歩くこと」を意味しますが、ここでは文脈と合わないため、真意が不明です。絶望的な状況なのに戦場に行かざるを得ないため、「目標に向かって急ぐのではなく、重い足取りで(進む)」という意味と推測し、「with a heavy gait」としました。ただし、「自分の気持ちを押し殺して」と解釈すれば、「holding back his true feelings」等の挿入句が考えられます(個人的には後者が良いと思いますが、「新たな情報の追加」に当たる可能性があるため、表記しておりません)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kokoku Shikan (emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto) he was praised as &quot;an exemplary loyal subject&quot; or &quot;a true Japanese&quot; who went off to war with a heavy gait, being prepared to die for his cause, so that he was worshiped also in Shushin education (moral training education).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto, he was praised as &apos;an exemplary loyal subject&apos; or &apos;a true Japanese&apos; who went off to war with a heavy gait, being prepared to die for his cause, so that he was worshiped also in the moral training education.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>戦後は価値観の転換と歴史学における中世史の研究が進むと悪党としての性格が強調されるようになり、吉川英治は『私本太平記』の中で戦前までのイメージとは異なる正成像を描いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As values were changed and the study of medieval history in the historical science progressed after the war, his character as an Akuto was emphasized, so that Eiji YOSHIKAWA drew a different image of Masashige from that of prewar times in his book &quot;Shihon Taihei ki&quot; (A Private Book of War History).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As values were changed and the study of medieval history in the historical science progressed after the war, his character as an Akuto was emphasized, so that Eiji YOSHIKAWA drew a different image of Masashige from that of prewar times in his book &quot;Shihon Taihei ki&quot; (A Private Book of War History).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As values were changed and the study of medieval history in a historical science progressed after the war, his character as a rebel was emphasized, such that Eiji YOSHIKAWA drew a different image of Masashige from that of prewar times in his book &quot;Shihon Taihei ki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>軍歌「桜井の決別」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Military song &quot;Sakurai no Ketsubetsu&quot; (Parting at Sakurai)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military song &quot;Sakurai no Ketsubetsu&quot; (Parting at Sakurai)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military song &apos;Sakurai no Ketsubetsu&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>楠木正成と息子正行との決別を歌った歌で、1899年（明治32年）6月に発表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a song about the parting of Masashige and his son Masatsura, and it was published in June 1899.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a song about the parting of Masashige and his son Masatsura, and it was published in June 1899.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a song about the parting of Masashige and his son Masatsura, and it was published in June 1899.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>作詞落合直文、作曲奥山朝恭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lyrics were written by Naobumi OCHIAI and the music was composed by Tomoyasu OKUYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lyrics were written by Naobumi OCHIAI and the music was composed by Tomoyasu OKUYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lyrics were written by Naobumi OCHIAI and the music was composed by Tomoyasu OKUYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>国学者で第一高等学校 (旧制)教授だった落合は、学校生徒行軍歌「湊川」の第一篇に「桜井決別」として発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OCHIAI, a scholar of Japanese classical literature and a professor of Daiichi High School (the first old-education-system high school), published the lyrics with a title of &quot;Sakurai Ketsubetsu&quot; (parting at Sakurai) for the first chapter of the marching song for school students with a title of &quot;Minatogawa&quot;.</e>
<cmt>学校生徒行軍歌: 定訳が不明ですので、「marching song for school students」と訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OCHIAI, a scholar of Japanese classical literature and a professor of Daiichi High School (the first old-education-system high school), published the lyrics with a title of &quot;Sakurai Ketsubetsu&quot; (parting at Sakurai) for the first chapter of the marching song for school students with a title of &quot;Minatogawa&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OCHIAI, a scholar of Japanese classical literature and a professor of Daiichi High School (the first old-education-system high school), published the lyrics with a title of &apos;Sakurai Ketsubetsu&apos; (parting at Sakurai) for the first chapter of the marching song for students with a title of &apos;Minatogawa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>作曲の奥山朝恭は岡山師範学校の教師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The composer, Tomoyasu OKUYAMA, was a teacher of Okayama Normal School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The composer, Tomoyasu OKUYAMA, was a teacher of Okayama Normal School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The composer, Tomoyasu OKUYAMA, was a teacher of Okayama normal school.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>墓所・霊廟・史跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graveyard/mausoleum/historic sites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graveyard/mausoleum/historic sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graveyard/mausoleum/historic sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>大楠公首塚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dai-Nanko Kubi-zuka (burial mound for heads)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dai-Nanko Kubi-zuka (burial mound for heads)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Burial Mound for Head &quot;Dai-Nanko Kubi-zuka&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>大阪府河内長野市にある高野山真言宗の寺院、観心寺の境内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located in the precincts of Kanshin-ji Temple of Koyasan Shingon Sect in Kawachinagano City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located in the precincts of Kanshin-ji Temple of Koyasan Shingon Sect in Kawachinagano City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mound is located in the precincts of Kanshin-ji Temple of Koyasan Shingon Sect in Kawachinagano City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>湊川の戦いの後、足利尊氏の命によって送り届けられた楠木正成の首級が葬られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The severed head of Masashige delivered by order of Takauji ASHIKAGA after the Battle of Minatogawa is entombed there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The severed head of Masashige delivered by order of Takauji ASHIKAGA after the Battle of Minatogawa is entombed there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The severed head of Masashige delivered by order of Takauji ASHIKAGA after the Battle of Minatogawa is entombed there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>観心寺塔中院は、正成の曾祖父楠木成氏が再建したと伝えられる、楠木家代々の菩提寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tacchu-in of Kanshin-ji Temple, which is said to have been reconstructed by Masashige&apos;s great-grandfather, Shigeuji KUSUNOKI, is an ancestral temple of the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tacchu-in of Kanshin-ji Temple, which is said to have been reconstructed by Masashige&apos;s great-grandfather, Shigeuji KUSUNOKI, is an ancestral temple of the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tacchu-in of Kanshin-ji Temple, which is said to have been reconstructed by Masashige&apos;s great-grandfather, Shigeuji KUSUNOKI, is an ancestral temple of the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="61">
<j>南木神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagi-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagi-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagijinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="62">
<j>大阪府南河内郡千早赤阪村に鎮座する建水分神社の摂社で、祭神は楠木正成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a sessha (auxiliary shrine (dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine)) of Takemikumari-jinja Shrine in Chihayaakasaka-mura, Minamikawachi District, Osaka Prefecture, and the enshrined deity of Nagi-jinja Shrine is Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a sessha (auxiliary shrine (dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine)) of Takemikumari-jinja Shrine in Chihayaakasaka-mura, Minamikawachi District, Osaka Prefecture, and the enshrined deity of Nagi-jinja Shrine is Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a sessha (auxiliary shrine (dedicated to a deity close-related to that of a main shrine)) of Takemikumari-jinja Shrine in Chihayaakasaka-mura, Minamikawachi District, Osaka Prefecture, and the enshrined deity of Nagijinja Shrine is Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>本社の建水分神社は楠木家の氏神とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the private deity of the Kusunoki clan is enshrined in the main shrine, Takemikumari-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the private deity of the Kusunoki clan is enshrined in the main shrine, Takemikumari-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the private deity of the Kusunoki clan is enshrined in the main shrine, Takemikumari-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>1337年（延元2年 / 建武4年）に後醍醐天皇により自ら彫刻の正成像が祀られたのが起源であり、後に後村上天皇より「南木（なぎ）明神」の神号を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originates from the fact that a statue of Masashige carved by Emperor Godaigo himself was enshrined there, and later Emperor Gomurakami gave the shingo (literally, &quot;shrine name,&quot; which is the title given to a Shinto shrine) of &quot;Nagi Myojin&quot; (the deity of Nagi-jinja Shrine) to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>南木明神: 「Nagi Myojin (the deity of Nagi-ji Shrine)」と登録されていますが、正しくは「Nagi-jinja Shrine」と思われるため、本文では修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originates from the fact that a statue of Masashige carved by Emperor Godaigo himself was enshrined there, and later Emperor Gomurakami gave the shingo (literally, &quot;shrine name,&quot; which is the title given to a Shinto shrine) of &quot;Nagi Myojin&quot; (the deity of Nagi-jinja Shrine) to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This originates from the fact that a statue of Masashige carved by Emperor Godaigo himself was enshrined there in 1337, and later, Emperor Gomurakami gave the shrine the name &apos;the deity of Nagijinja Shrine&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>楠木正成を祀る最古の神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the oldest shrine deifying Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the oldest shrine deifying Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the oldest shrine deifying Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="66">
<j>長滝七社神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagataki Nana-sha-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagataki Nana-sha-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagataki Nana-shajinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="67">
<j>岐阜県山県市長滝にある七社神社横に、八王寺宮と刻まれた楠公夫人久子の墓がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grave of Hisako, the wife of Nanko (Masashige KUSUNOKI), is adjacent to the Nana-sha-jinja Shrine in Nagataki, Yamagata City, Gifu Prefecture, and the characters of &quot;Hachioji-gu Shrine&quot; (literally Eight, King, Temple, Shrine (or Palace)) are engraved on it.</e>
<cmt>八王寺宮: 登録された用語通りに表記していますが、「墓には『…Shrine(神社)』と刻まれている」という英文は、奇妙に響くのではないかと思われます(この場合は、この後のカッコに説明を入れていますので、「Shrine」を削除し、「Hachioji-gu」としたほうが良いかと存じます)。また、この名称の意味は不明ですが、カッコ内に漢字の説明を入れています(これは定訳ではありません。また、「宮」は「神社」のほかに「宮殿」等の意味もあるので、カッコ内に補足しています)。 / 楠公: 英文では、この用語が「大楠公」と同じ意味で用いられていることが分からないため、カッコ内に説明として「楠木正成」の名を入れています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grave of Hisako, the wife of Nanko (Masashige KUSUNOKI), is adjacent to the Nana-sha-jinja Shrine in Nagataki, Yamagata City, Gifu Prefecture, and the characters of &quot;Hachioji-gu Shrine&quot; (literally Eight, King, Temple, Shrine (or Palace)) are engraved on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grave of Hisako, the wife of Nanko (Masashige KUSUNOKI), is adjacent to the Nana-shajinja Shrine in Nagataki, Yamagata City, Gifu Prefecture, and the characters of &quot;Hachioji-gu Shrine&quot; (literally Eight, King, Temple, Shrine (or Palace)) are engraved on it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>楠妣庵観音寺（大阪府富田林市（旧甘南備村）にある臨済宗妙心寺派の寺院で、楠木家の香華寺）も楠公夫人の墓とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it is also said that the wife of Nanko was entombed at Nampian Kanon-ji Temple of Myoshin-ji Temple school of the Rinzai sect in Tondabayashi City, Osaka Prefecture (former Kannabi Village), which is an ancestral temple of the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>香華寺: 用語登録には「Koge-ji Temple」と登録されていますが、「goo辞書」によれば、「香華院(香華寺)」は「菩提寺」を指す(http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/63089/m0u/%E9%A6%99%E8%8F%AF%E9%99%A2/)ので、「菩提寺(an ancestral temple)」として訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it is also said that the wife of Nanko was entombed at Nampian Kanon-ji Temple of Myoshin-ji Temple school of the Rinzai sect in Tondabayashi City, Osaka Prefecture (former Kannabi Village), which is an ancestral temple of the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it is also said that the wife of Nanko was entombed at Nanpian Kanon-ji Temple of Myoshin-ji Temple school of the Rinzai sect in Tondabayashi City, Osaka Prefecture (former Kannabi Village), which is an ancestral temple of the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="69">
<j>正平 (日本)3年 / 貞和4年（1348年）に楠木正行・楠木正時が四條畷の戦いで戦死した後、正成の妻が草庵を建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Masatsura KUSUNOKI and Masatoki KUSUNOKI had fallen in the Battle of Shijonawate in 1348, the wife of Masashige made a thatched hut.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Masatsura KUSUNOKI and Masatoki KUSUNOKI had fallen in the Battle of Shijonawate in 1348, the wife of Masashige made a thatched hut.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Masatsura and Masatoki KUSUNOKI had fallen in the Battle of Shijonawate in 1348, the wife of Masashige made a thatched hut.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>敗鏡尼と称して、楠木一族郎党の菩提を弔った後、戦乱の中、この地を離れ、美濃乃国伊自良村長滝釜ヶ谷奥の院に隠棲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After she had called herself Haikyoni (literally, &quot;the defeated nun of mirror&quot;) and had prayed to Buddha for the happiness of the dead members of the Kusunoki clan, she left the place in the period of war to live in seclusion in Okunoin, Nagataki kamagatani, Ijira-mura, Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>敗鏡尼: Guidelinesの指示により、カッコ内に説明を加えていますが、これは定訳ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After she had called herself Haikyoni (literally, &quot;the defeated nun of mirror&quot;) and had prayed to Buddha for the happiness of the dead members of the Kusunoki clan, she left the place in the period of war to live in seclusion in Okunoin, Nagataki kamagatani, Ijira-mura, Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After she had called herself Haikyoni (literally, &quot;the defeated nun of mirror&quot;) and had prayed to Buddha for the happiness of the dead members of the Kusunoki clan, she left there in the period of war to live in seclusion in Okunoin, Nagataki kamagatani, Ijira-mura, Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>地域の尊志を得て、久子（旧姓・南江）の生地甘南備村の字名、長滝、平井、掛、松尾等を伊自良に与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hisako (her birth name was Mimamie) had gained the trust of the people in the area, she named some places in Ijira after the place names such as Nagataki, Hirai, Kake or Matsuo of her birthplace Kannabi Village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hisako (her birth name was Mimamie) had gained the trust of the people in the area, she named some places in Ijira after the place names such as Nagataki, Hirai, Kake or Matsuo of her birthplace Kannabi Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hisako (her birth name was Minamie) had gained the trust of the people in the area, she named some places in Ijira after Nagataki, Hirai, Kake or Matsuo of her birthplace Kannabi Village.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>奥の院にある甘南備神社は、楠木家の遠祖と称える橘諸兄の父、美努王（みぬのおおきみ）を祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kannabi-jinja Shrine in Okunoin deifies Minu no Okimi, the father of TACHIBANA no Moroe, who is believed to be the forefather of the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kannabi-jinja Shrine in Okunoin deifies Minu no Okimi, the father of TACHIBANA no Moroe, who is believed to be the forefather of the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kannabi-jinja Shrine in Okunoin deifies Minu no Okimi, the father of TACHIBANA no Moroe, who is believed to be the forefather of the Kusunoki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>甘南備村の口碑には、楠木正成夫人久子は、観音像を念持仏にして、行脚に出たが、終わるところ知らずとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to legend of Kannabi Village, Hisako, the wife of Masashige KUSUNOKI, went on a pilgrimage with a Kannon-zo (statue of the Kannon) as nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person), but she did not know when to stop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to legend of Kannabi Village, Hisako, the wife of Masashige KUSUNOKI, went on a pilgrimage with a Kannon-zo (statue of the Kannon) as nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person), but she did not know when to stop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a legend of Kannabi Village, Hisako, the wife of Masashige KUSUNOKI, went on a pilgrimage with a statue of the Kannon as a small portab;e statue of Buddha, but she did not know when to stop.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>墓は、伊自良湖の登り口、長滝七社神社境内西にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her grave is on the west side of the precincts of Nagataki Nana-sha-jinja Shrine at the foot of Ijira-ko Lake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is on the west side of the precincts of Nagataki Nana-sha-jinja Shrine at the foot of Ijira-ko Lake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is on the west side of the precincts of Nagataki Nana-shajinja Shrine at the foot of Ijira-ko Lake.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>楠公夫人がこの地に訪れた最大の理由は、新田義貞亡き後、その弟の脇屋義助が大将となり、北陸で破れ、美濃の南朝一派と共に、最後の根尾城の戦いでも破れ、根尾川の下流、本巣地区の北朝の根城を避け、一緒に戦った伊自良次郎左衛門の家臣と共に、伊自良に流れ、吉野に帰ったその経路に従ったものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main reason for her visit there appears that she followed the track of Yoshisuke WAKIYA, who was a younger brother of Yoshisada NITTA, became a commander after death of his brother, was defeated in Hokuriku region, lost also the last battle, i. e., the Battle of Neo-jo Castle, with a pro-Southern-Court group of Mino, avoided the headquarters of the Northern Court in Motosu District in lower reach of Neo-gawa River, fled to Ijira with the vassals of Jirozaemon IJIRA, who fought with him, and finally went back to Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main reason for her visit there appears that she followed the track of Yoshisuke WAKIYA, who was a younger brother of Yoshisada NITTA, became a commander after death of his brother, was defeated in Hokuriku region, lost also the last battle, i. e., the Battle of Neo-jo Castle, with a pro-Southern-Court group of Mino, avoided the headquarters of the Northern Court in Motosu District in lower reach of Neo-gawa River, fled to Ijira with the vassals of Jirozaemon IJIRA, who fought with him, and finally went back to Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main reason for her visit there appears that she followed the track of Yoshisuke WAKIYA, who was a younger brother of Yoshisada NITTA, succeeded to the commander after death of his brother, got defeated in Hokuriku region, also got defeated in the last battle, i. e., the Battle of Neo-jo Castle, with a pro-Southern-Court group of Mino, avoided the headquarters of the Northern Court in Motosu District in lower reach of Neo-gawa River, fled to Ijira with the vassals of Jirozaemon IJIRA, who fought with him, and finally went back to Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="76">
<j>湊川神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minatogawa-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minatogawa-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minatogawajinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="77">
<j>楠木正成（大楠公）の神霊を主祭神とし、子息の楠木正行（小楠公）および湊川の戦いで斃れた一族十六柱と菊池武吉の神霊を配祀。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shusaijin (main enshrined deities) of the shrine is Masashige KUSUNOKI (Dai-Nanko), while the divine spirits of his son Masatsura KUSUNOKI (Sho-Nanko), sixteen clan members and Takeyoshi KIKUCHI who fell in the Battle of Minatogawa are enshrined as associated deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shusaijin (main enshrined deities) of the shrine is Masashige KUSUNOKI (Dai-Nanko), while the divine spirits of his son Masatsura KUSUNOKI (Sho-Nanko), sixteen clan members and Takeyoshi KIKUCHI who fell in the Battle of Minatogawa are enshrined as associated deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main enshrined deities of the shrine is Masashige KUSUNOKI (Dai-Nanko), while the divine spirits of his son Masatsura KUSUNOKI (Sho-Nanko), sixteen clan members and Takeyoshi KIKUCHI who fell in the Battle of Minatogawa are enshrined as associated deity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>戦後になって大楠公夫人久子の神霊も合祀された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The divine spirit of Hisako, the wife of Dai-Nanko, was also enshrined together after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The divine spirit of Hisako, the wife of Dai-Nanko, was also enshrined together after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The divine spirit of Hisako, the wife of Dai-Nanko, was also enshrined with them after the war.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>神社として創建されたのは比較的新しく、明治5年（1872年）のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was founded as a shrine relatively recently, i. e., in 1872.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was founded as a shrine relatively recently, i. e., in 1872.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was founded as a shrine in 1872, i.e., relatively recently.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>神社創建以前から存在した墓所には、徳川光圀によって墓碑「嗚呼忠臣楠子之墓」が建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gravestone &quot;A Chushin Nanshi no haka&quot; (Ah tomb of loyal subject Nanshi) was erected by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA at the graveyard that had existed before the foundation of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>嗚呼忠臣楠子之墓: 用語登録には「A Shushin Nanshi no haka (以下略)」とありますが、「忠臣」は「Chushin」ですので、そのように訂正しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gravestone &quot;A Chushin Nanshi no haka&quot; (Ah tomb of loyal subject Nanshi) was erected by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA at the graveyard that had existed before the foundation of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gravestone &quot;A tomb of loyal subject Nanshi&quot; was erected by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA at the graveyard that had existed before the foundation of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>湊川の戦いで楠木正成が一族郎党と共に自害したとされる戦没地（異説あり）と、墓所の両方を境内地に含んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The precincts of the shrine contain not only the graveyard but also the place where he is said to have committed suicide with his family members in the Battle of Minatogawa (some disagree with this opinion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The precincts of the shrine contain not only the graveyard but also the place where he is said to have committed suicide with his family members in the Battle of Minatogawa (some disagree with this opinion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The precincts of the shrine contain not only the graveyard but also the place where he is said to have committed suicide with his family members in the Battle of Minatogawa (some disagree with this opinion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="82">
<j>茨木城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ibaraki-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ibaraki-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ibarakijo Castle</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="83">
<j>大阪府茨木市に築城した城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a castle built in Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a castle built in Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was a castle built in Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>現在は廃城となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle is deserted today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle is deserted today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is deserted today.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="85">
<j>奉建塔（楠公六百年記念塔）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoken-to Tower (Nanko 600 years anniversary tower)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoken-to Tower (Nanko 600 years anniversary tower)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoken-to Tower (Nanko 600th anniversary tower)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="86">
<j>没後600年を記念して、昭和15年（1940年）に全国の児童学生や教職員等の募金により浄心寺塞（上赤坂城支塞）跡に建てられた記念塔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tower was built in 1940 at the former site of the fort of Joshin-ji Temple (auxiliary fort of Kamiakasaka-jo Castle) by donations from pupils, students, teachers and others throughout the country to mark the 600th anniversary of his death.</e>
<cmt>支塞: 定義と定訳は確認できませんでしたが、「塞」は「とりで」を意味するので、ここでは「(「支」という漢字が示唆する意味の)副次的な、補助的なとりで、要塞」等を意味すると推測し、その意味で「auxiliary fort」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tower was built in 1940 at the former site of the fort of Joshin-ji Temple (auxiliary fort of Kamiakasaka-jo Castle) by donations from pupils, students, teachers and others throughout the country to mark the 600th anniversary of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tower was built in 1940 at the former site of the fort of Joshinji Temple (auxiliary fort of Kamiakasakajo Castle) by donations from pupils, students, teachers and others throughout the country to mark the 600th anniversary of his death.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>正成討死の年齢43歳に因み、高さはおよそ43尺（約13ｍ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The height of the tower was set at forty three shaku (approximately thirteen meters), because he died in battle at the age of forty three.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The height of the tower was set at forty three shaku (approximately thirteen meters), because he died in battle at the age of forty three.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The height of the tower was set at approximately thirteen meters, because he died in battle at the age of forty three.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>塔には家紋の菊水紋、旗印の「非理法権天」の文字が刻まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest, Kikusui-mon (pattern of floating flowers on a stream) and the characters of the emblem on flag &quot;Hirihokenten&quot; (literally Wrong, Right, Law, Power, Heaven) are engraved on the tower.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest, Kikusui-mon (pattern of floating flowers on a stream) and the characters of the emblem on flag &quot;Hirihokenten&quot; (literally Wrong, Right, Law, Power, Heaven) are engraved on the tower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest, Kikusui-mon (pattern of floating flowers on a stream) and the characters of emblem on the flag &quot;Wrong, Right, Law, Power, Heaven&quot; are engraved on the tower.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>（但し、旗印は史実ではなく伝承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(However, the emblem on flag is not based on historical facts, but on a tradition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(However, the emblem on flag is not based on historical facts, but on a tradition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The emblem on the flag is not based on historical facts, but on a tradition.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>非理法権天の記事を参照）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the article about &quot;Hirihokenten.&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the article about &quot;Hirihokenten.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the article about &quot;Wrong, Right, Law, Power, Heaven&quot;.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="91">
<j>楠公産湯の井戸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nanko ubuyu no ido (water well for Nanko&apos;s first bath)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nanko ubuyu no ido (water well for Nanko&apos;s first bath)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nanko ubuyu no ido (well for Nanko&apos;s first bath)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="92">
<j>生誕の地から徒歩数分のところに「楠公産湯の井戸」とされる井戸がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nanko ubuyu no ido&quot;, which is said to be a water well for Nanko&apos;s first bath, is a few minutes walk away from his birthplace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nanko ubuyu no ido&quot;, which is said to be a water well for Nanko&apos;s first bath, is a few minutes walk away from his birthplace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nanko ubuyu no ido,&quot; which is said to be a water well for Nanko&apos;s first bath, is a few minutes walk away from his birthplace.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田英(id:85936), 0null0(id:582), Cprobot(id:97843), Lupinoid(id:68), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Lkhiutsz(id:209331), Synthebot(id:123032), でここ(id:9565), Kenpei(id:11349), 代言人(id:33675), Shimoxx(id:9332), FlaBot(id:30804), Kouko0515(id:100370), Sago(id:16363), M-sho-gun(id:88956), ロリ(id:613), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Stanislaus(id:1806), 垂耳犬(id:202697), Himazin(id:22034), Seibuabina(id:37532), SUMAKO(id:206516), Kagetudo(id:163875), Rusk(id:9895), Xqbot(id:273540), Amler(id:101250), Kusunoki Masahiro(id:196646), Alexbot(id:157199), けんち(id:5147), Junger(id:10282), Riden(id:27573), Suisui(id:69), Hatabon(id:146971), FREEZA(id:68069), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Yu-ki-na(id:115957), 沢田(id:40580), Sgi1962(id:80778), Maeda(id:2461), Johncapistrano(id:969), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Goki(id:7107), 堀内(id:66111), 怪蘇(id:45514), UMBRO(id:100484), 有吉俊憲(id:16923), 越中掾(id:149423), VSA-itama(id:25395), Kentin(id:6768), Izayohi(id:13095), Juqipedia(id:188816), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Auf(id:633), 水野白楓(id:22811), Race(id:131322), カニサボテン(id:174710), Cave cattum(id:41235), Hisano13(id:168017), Heathrow(id:192652), 高槻(id:98635), Carkuni(id:79281), しがさく(id:295245), Tanuki Z(id:612), Yonoemon(id:55450), VolkovBot(id:105371), きゅうり(id:2182), 663highland(id:18755), Ponsaku(id:31417), こいつぅ(id:2105), Louperibot(id:128971), HHHKKK IBA(id:161861), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), Kawachian(id:10991), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>