<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三条実万</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanetsumu SANJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanetsumu SANJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanetsumu SANJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三条 実万（さんじょう さねつむ、享和2年2月15日 (旧暦)（1802年3月18日） - 安政6年10月6日 (旧暦)（1859年10月31日））は、幕末の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanetsumu SANJO (March 18, 1802 -October 31, 1859) was a Kugyo (high court noble), who lived during the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanetsumu SANJO (March 18, 1802 -October 31, 1859) was a Kugyo (high court noble) in the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>end of the Edo Periodは特定の期間を表す語句とは言えないので前置詞はinの方が自然です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanetsumu SANJO (March 18, 1802 -October 31, 1859) was a Kugyo (high court noble) in the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は三条公修。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Kinosa SANJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Kinosa SANJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Kinosa SANJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正室は山内豊策の娘・眉寿姫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was the daughter of Toyokazu YAMAUCHI, Bijuhime (眉寿姫).</e>
<cmt>眉寿姫→正式な読み方が不明です：Bijuhime (眉寿姫)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was a daughter of Toyokazu YAMAUCHI, Bijuhime (眉寿姫).</e>
<cmt>「娘」は一人とは限りません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Toyokazu YAMAUCHI, Bijuhime (眉寿姫).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に三条公睦、三条実美、河鰭実文、数姫（山内豊惇婚約者）、峯（細川韶邦正室）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were Kinmutsu SANJO, Sanetomi SANJO, Sanefumi KAWABATA, Kazuhime (数姫) (Toyoatsu YAMAUCHI&apos;s fiancee) and Mine (Yoshikuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s lawful wife).</e>
<cmt>数姫→正式な読み方が不明です：Kazuhime (数姫)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were Kinmutsu SANJO, Sanetomi SANJO, Sanefumi KAWABATA, Kazuhime (数姫) (Toyoatsu YAMAUCHI&apos;s fiancee) and Mine (Yoshikuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s lawful wife).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Kinmutsu SANJO, Sanetomi SANJO, Sanefumi KAWABATA, Kazuhime (数姫) (Toyoatsu YAMAUCHI&apos;s fiancee) and Mine (Yoshikuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s lawful wife).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1824年（文政7年）に大納言に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 18214, he was appointed Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1824, he was appointed Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>数字表記のミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1824, he was appointed Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1848年（嘉永元年）には武家伝奏となり、たびたび江戸に下って対米政策について江戸幕府と交渉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1848, he became 武家伝奏Buke tenso (an court officer in charge of handling the samurai families&apos; requests to the Imperial Court, which was the post held by Kugyo), and he went down again to Edo (present Tokyo) to negotiate with the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) on the 対米政策policy toward the United States.</e>
<cmt>武家伝奏→定訳不明：Buke tenso (a court officer in charge of handling the samurai families&apos; requests to the Imperial Court, which was the post held by Kugyo)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1848, he became buke tenso (liaison officers between the imperial court and the military government), and frequently went down again to Edo to negotiate with the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) on the policy toward the United States.</e>
<cmt>「武家伝奏」の訳語は用語集を参照しました。「たびたび」の訳漏れを修正しました。不要な日本語表現を除去しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1848, he became buke tenso (liaison officers between the imperial court and the military government), and frequently went down again to Edo to negotiate with the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) on the policy toward the United States.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1857年（安政4年）内大臣となるが、1859年（安政5年）には日米修好通商条約への勅許を巡り関白九条尚忠と対立して、3月7日には左大臣近衛忠煕とともに参内停止を命じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1857, he was appointed as the minister of the center, however in 1859 he had a conflict with Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) Hisatada KUJO over the Imperial consent on The Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan, and on April 30, 1858 (表記の変更), together with Minister of the Left Tadahiro KONOE, he was ordered to refrain from a visit to the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>内大臣→minister of the centerとしました。なお、「大臣」の表記は肩書き意外は小文字表記にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1857, he was appointed as the minister of the center, but in 1859 he had a conflict with Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) Hisatada KUJO over the Imperial consent on the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan, and on April 30, 1858, together with the Minister of the Left Tadahiro KONOE, he was ordered to refrain from entering the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>howeverは副詞なので文と文を接続する用法はありません。「左大臣」に冠詞をつけました。「参内」の訳語を分かりやすくなるよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1857, he was appointed as the minister of the center, but in 1859 he had a conflict with Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) Hisatada KUJO over the Imperial consent on the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan, and on April 30, 1858, together with the Minister of the Left Tadahiro KONOE, he was ordered to refrain from entering the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これに激怒した孝明天皇によって2日後に右大臣鷹司輔煕と権大納言二条斉敬を勅使として近衛・三条両邸に派遣して両名に参内の勅命を下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Komei, who was enraged at this sanction, sent Minister of the Right Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA and Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor) Nariyuki NIJO to the residences of the Konoe family and the Sanjo family, respectively, as Imperial envoys, and gave them the imperial order of sandai (a visit to the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>右大臣→Minister of the Rightと、肩書きなので語頭を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Komei, who was enraged at this sanction, sent the Minister of the Right Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA and Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor) Nariyuki NIJO to the residences of the Konoe family and the Sanjo family respectively, as Imperial envoys, and gave KONOE and SANJO the imperial order of sandai (a visit to the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>「右大臣」に冠詞をつけました。「両名」が誰を指すのか明確にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Komei, who was enraged at this sanction, sent the Minister of the Right Sukehiro TAKATSUKASA and Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor) Nariyuki NIJO to the residences of the Konoe family and the Sanjo family respectively, as Imperial envoys, and gave KONOE and SANJO the imperial order of sandai (a visit to the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これは長年朝廷の全権を握っていた摂関家が勅使となり、政治的に非力であった清華家出身の三条を出仕させるという公家社会始まって以来の出来事として衝撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This news shocked the people as an unprecedented event in the court noble society, because the head of one of Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor; line of regents and advisers), which had been gripping the absolute power in the Imperial Court for many years, was sent as Imperial envoys to call up the head of Sanjo family, descended from the Seiga family (ranked second in the court noble families), which had no political influence until then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This news shocked the people as an unprecedented event in the court noble society, because the head of one of Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor; line of regents and advisers), which had gripped the absolute power in the Imperial Court for many years, was sent as Imperial envoys to call up SANJO, descended from the Seiga family (ranked second in the court noble families), which had no political influence until then.</e>
<cmt>「三条家」ではなく「三条」です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This news shocked the people as an unprecedented event in the court noble society, because the head of one of Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor; line of regents and advisers), which had gripped the absolute power in the Imperial Court for many years, was sent as Imperial envoys to call up SANJO, descended from the Seiga family (ranked second in the court noble families), which had no political influence until then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1859年（安政6年）の安政の大獄で謹慎の処分を受け、出家して澹空と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1859, after he was punished to house arrest for the involvement in Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate), he entered into priesthood and named himself Tanku (澹空).</e>
<cmt>澹空→正式な読み方が不明です：Tanku (澹空)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1859, after he was placed on probation during Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate), he entered into priesthood and named himself Tanku (澹空).</e>
<cmt>「謹慎」ではなく「自宅軟禁」に近い訳語になっていたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1859, after he was placed on probation during Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate), he entered into priesthood and named himself Tanku (澹空).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年に薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1862年（文久2年）に右大臣が、1899年（明治32年）に正一位が追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He 追贈されたwas posthumously raised to the minister of the right in 1862, and to 正一位Shoichii (Senior First Rank) in 1899.</e>
<cmt>追贈された→be posthumously raised としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously promoted to the minister of the right in 1862, and granted Shoichii (Senior First Rank) in 1899.</e>
<cmt>不要な日本語表現を除去しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously promoted to the minister of the right in 1862, and granted Shoichii (Senior First Rank) in 1899.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 まさふゆ(id:232040), Point136(id:211299), YOSHI438(id:174755), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>