<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>島津歳久</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshihisa SHIMAZU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshihisa SHIMAZU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshihisa SHIMAZU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>島津歳久（しまづとしひさ、天文 (元号)6年（1537年） - 天正20年7月18日 (旧暦)（1592年8月25日））は島津貴久の三男で、島津義久、島津義弘の弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshihisa SHIMAZU (1537- August 25, 1592) was the third son of Takahisa SHIMAZU, and is the younger brother of Yoshihiro SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshihisa SHIMAZU (1537- August 25, 1592) was the third son of Takahisa SHIMAZU, and is the younger brother of Yoshihiro SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshihisa SHIMAZU (1537- August 25, 1592) was the third son of Takahisa SHIMAZU, and is the younger brother of Yoshihisa SHIMAZU and Yoshihiro SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>Yoshihisa SHIMAZUの挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>戦国大名としての島津氏の中興の祖・島津忠良の孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the Chuko no So (the founder of a renaissance) of the Shimazu clan, warring lords, and Tadayoshi SHIMAZU&apos;s grandson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the grandson of Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, Chuko no So (the founder of a renaissance) warlord of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the grandson of Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, Chuko no So (the founder of a renaissance) warlord of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>左衛門督を名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He called himself &apos;Saemon no kami.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called himself &apos;Saemon no kami.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself &apos;Saemon no kami.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日置家の祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the forefather of the Hioki family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the forefather of the Hioki family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the forefather of the Hioki family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>OK (erased space)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>OK (erased space)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>祖父の忠良から「始終の利害を察するの智計並びなく」という評価をされていて、稀代の「智将」といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his grandfather described him as &apos;the cleverest man at inferring the whole interest in holoscopic view,&apos; he was known as a rare &apos;resourceful general.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his grandfather described him as &apos;the cleverest man at inferring the whole interest in holoscopic view,&apos; he was known as a rare &apos;resourceful general.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his grandfather described him as &apos;the cleverest man at inferring the whole interest in holoscopic view,&apos; he was known as a rare &apos;resourceful general.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>主に兄義久の傍らで、作戦参謀として活躍をしており、島津軍団の方針を左右する立場にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was in the key position to determine the policies of Shimazu&apos;s army as a general officer responsible for war strategies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was in a key position to determine the policies of Shimazu&apos;s army as a general officer responsible for war strategies.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was in a key position to determine the policies of Shimazu&apos;s army as a general officer responsible for war strategies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また初陣での奮戦から、兄義弘・弟家久と並び島津家の多くの合戦に参加し、横川城攻め(横川崩れ)、大口市堂ヶ崎における義弘救出戦、大隅国小浜城 (大隅国)攻め、伊東氏攻め、耳川の戦い、第二次水俣城攻め、豊後国入りでの義弘が指揮した肥後口側の軍勢の副将などが主な功績として挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known as a warrior who participated in many wars from the first battle with his older brother Yoshihiro and younger brother Iehisa; the Siege of Yokokawa-jo castle attack (called Yokokawa-jo seme or Yokokawa kuzure), Yoshihiro&apos;s rescue mission, the Siege of Obama-jo castle in the Osumi Province, the Siege of Ito clan, the Battle of the Mimikawa, the Siege of the second Minamata-jo castle, and vice-shogun in the war force of the Higoguchi side led by Yoshihiro in the Bungo Province the are the well known contributions he made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known as a warrior who participated in many wars from his first battle with his older brother Yoshihiro and younger brother Iehisa, followed by well-known contributions he made to the Siege of Yokokawa-jo castle attack (called Yokokawa-jo seme or Yokokawa kuzure), Yoshihiro&apos;s rescue mission, the Siege of Obama-jo castle in the Osumi Province, the Siege of Ito clan, the Battle of the Mimikawa, the Siege of the second Minamata-jo castle, and vice-shogun in the war force of the Higoguchi side led by Yoshihiro in the Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also known as a warrior who participated in many wars from his first battle with his older brother Yoshihiro and younger brother Iehisa, followed by well-known contributions he made to the Siege of Yokokawa-jo castle attack (called Yokokawa-jo seme or Yokokawa kuzure), Yoshihiro&apos;s rescue mission, the Siege of Obama-jo castle in the Osumi Province, the Siege of Ito clan, the Battle of the Mimikawa, the Siege of the second Minamata-jo castle, and vice-shogun in the war force of the Higoguchi side led by Yoshihiro in the Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>政治面においても、鹿児島を中心とする防衛戦の要となる地で治世の実りを上げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also contributed in the government of the area during the defensive war in the Kagoshima region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also contributed to the government of the area during the defensive war in the Kagoshima region.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also contributed to the government of the area during the defensive war in the Kagoshima region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>このように歳久の島津家中での役割は非常に大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As such, Toshihisa&apos;s made a big contribution in the Shimazu family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As such, Toshihisa made a big contribution to the Shimazu family.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As such, Toshihisa made a big contribution to the Shimazu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>秀吉による九州征伐においては、降伏を主張する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He claimed that the army for the Kyushu Conquest should surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He insisted that the army for the Kyushu Conquest should surrender.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He insisted that the army for the Kyushu Conquest should surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>兄義久が泰平寺 (薩摩川内市)にて降伏後は、一転して自身の所領祁答院町にて抵抗、秀吉軍を巧みに険相な路へと引き込み、関白である秀吉の駕籠に矢を六本射掛け天下人の肝を冷やさせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his older brother Yoshihisa surrendered at the Taihei-ji Temple, he continued to resist in his shoryo (territory), kedoin-cho, and cleverly enticed the Hideyoshi army into a rough and dangerous street, then and surprised tenkabito (person becoming the ruler of the country) by shooting six arrows at the palanquin of Hideyoshi, kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the older brother Toshihisa surrendered at Taihei-ji Temple, he continued to resist in his shoryo (territory), Kedoin-cho, and cleverly enticed the Hideyoshi army into a rough and dangerous street, then surprised the tenkabito (person becoming the ruler of the country) by shooting six arrows at the palanquin of Hideyoshi, the kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the older brother Yoshihisa surrendered at Taihei-ji Temple, he continued to resist in his shoryo (territory), Kedoin-cho, and cleverly enticed the Hideyoshi army into a rough and dangerous street, then surprised the tenkabito (person becoming the ruler of the country) by shooting six arrows at the palanquin of Hideyoshi, the kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Toshihisa→Yoshihisa</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、梅北一揆に伴い、この祁答院での件が再燃、秀吉による島津家への歳久追討令を受け、竜ヶ水にて責任をとり切腹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, at the time of Unekita-ikki, the incident at the Taihei-ji Temple was raised as an issue; this led Hideyoshi to issue an order to track down and kill Toshihisa that made him commit suicide by disembowelment (seppuku) at Ryugamizu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, at the time of Unekita-ikki, the incident at Taihei-ji Temple was raised as an issue; this led Hideyoshi to issue an order to track down and kill Toshihisa which made him commit suicide by disembowelment (seppuku) at Ryugamizu.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, at the time of Unekita-ikki, the incident at Taihei-ji Temple was raised as an issue; this led Hideyoshi to issue an order to track down and kill Toshihisa which made him commit suicide by disembowelment (seppuku) at Ryugamizu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>九州征伐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyushu Conquest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyushu Conquest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyushu Conquest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>豊臣秀吉の九州征伐の際、家中が抗戦へ傾く中で秀吉を「農民から体一つで身を興したからには只者ではない」と評価して、四兄弟中ただ一人上方との和平を唱えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the Kyushu Conquest of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI when the all the clan members were getting prepared to fight back in the war, he was the only one among his four brothers who claimed for the reconciliation referring to Hideyoshi as &apos;an unordinary person who established this status born from a farming family&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Kyushu Conquest of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, when the all the clan members were getting prepared to fight back in the war, he was the only one among his four brothers who insisted on reconciliation, referring to Hideyoshi as &apos;an extraordinary person who rose to this status born from a farming family&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Kyushu Conquest of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, when the all the clan members were getting prepared to fight back in the war, he was the only one among his four brothers who insisted on reconciliation, referring to Hideyoshi as &apos;an extraordinary person who rose to this status born from a farming family&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし評議の場で和睦案は一蹴され、島津氏は秀吉と戦うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his proposal of reconciliation was ignored at their meeting, and the Shimazu clan decided to fight against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his proposal for reconciliation was ignored at their meeting, and the Shimazu clan decided to fight against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his proposal for reconciliation was ignored at their meeting, and the Shimazu clan decided to fight against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>義久・義弘の二兄が秀吉に降伏した後も最後まで徹底的に抵抗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the war with Hideyoshi, even after his brothers Yoshihisa and Yoshihiro, surrendered to Hideyoshi, he throughly resisted in the war until the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the war with Hideyoshi, even after his brothers Yoshihisa and Yoshihiro surrendered to Hideyoshi, he put up a strong resistance in the war until the end.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the war with Hideyoshi, even after his brothers Yoshihisa and Yoshihiro surrendered to Hideyoshi, he put up a strong resistance in the war until the end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>秀吉が川内の泰平寺 (薩摩川内市)から大口市に陣を移す途中に位置する歳久の祁答院町領の西端の山崎にて、家来を使いにやり、巧みに秀吉軍を険相な路に案内し、秀吉の駕籠に矢を六本射かけさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hideyoshi moved from the Taihei-ji Temple in Kawauchi (Kawauchi city in Satsuma) to Okuchi city, Toshihisa sent his servants at the west edge of his shoryo (territory), kedoin-cho, and cleverly enticed the Hideyoshi army into a rough and dangerous street and attempted to shoot six arrows at the palanquin of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hideyoshi moved from Taihei-ji Temple in Kawauchi (Kawauchi city in Satsuma) to Okuchi city, Toshihisa sent his servants to the western edge of his shoryo (territory), Kedoin-cho, and cleverly enticed the Hideyoshi army into a rough and dangerous street and attempted to shoot six arrows at the palanquin of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hideyoshi moved from Taihei-ji Temple in Sendai (Satsumasendai city) to Okuchi city, Toshihisa sent his servants to the western edge of his shoryo (territory), Kedoin-cho, and cleverly enticed the Hideyoshi army into a rough and dangerous street and attempted to shoot six arrows at the palanquin of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Kawauchi→Sendai</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>矢を射かけたのは歳久の家来の本田五郎左衛門であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was actually Toshihisa&apos;s retainer Gorozaemon who got hit with Toshihisa&apos;s arrows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was actually Toshihisa&apos;s retainer Gorozaemon who was struck by Toshihisa&apos;s arrows.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was actually Toshihisa&apos;s retainer Gorozaemon who shot arrows.</e>
<cmt>「矢を射かける」の訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>予め襲撃に備えた秀吉の駕籠は空駕籠にしていた為、秀吉は難を逃れたが、全国を見渡しても、関白となった後の秀吉に対してここまで徹底した反骨を見せた者はいないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshihisa&apos;s attempt to shoot Hideyoshi failed as as Hideyoshi&apos;s palanquin was empty, being prepared for the attacks; however, it is said no one else than him behaved completely rebellious towards Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshihisa&apos;s attempt to shoot Hideyoshi failed as Hideyoshi&apos;s palanquin was empty, being prepared for the attacks; however, it is said that no one else but him exhibited rebellious behavior against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshihisa&apos;s attempt to shoot Hideyoshi failed as Hideyoshi&apos;s palanquin was empty, being prepared for the attacks; however, it is said that no one else but him exhibited rebellious behavior against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この征伐前後における彼の矛盾した秀吉への対応には、秀吉の九州征伐で婿養子・島津忠隣を失ったことからの怨恨説、今征伐における秀吉の島津家への不興を一身に背負おうとした説など複数あるが、定説はなく歳久の後年を語る最大の謎である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several theories that have tried to explain his contradictory attitudes toward Hideyoshi: from the grudge he started growing due to the loss of his adopted son, Tadachika SHIMAZU, and from the reason he tried to shoulder all the displeasure that the Shimazu family received, etc, however, none of them is an established theory and this has been the biggest mysteries of Toshihisa in the later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several theories which have tried to explain his contradictory attitudes toward Hideyoshi: from the grudge he started to develop due to the loss of his adopted son, Tadachika SHIMAZU, and from the reasoning that he tried to shoulder all the displeasure that the Shimazu family received, etc, however, there is no proven theory and this contradiction has come to be one of the biggest mysteries about Toshihisa in later years.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several theories which have tried to explain his contradictory attitudes toward Hideyoshi: from the grudge he started to develop due to the loss of his adopted son, Tadachika SHIMAZU, and from the reasoning that he tried to shoulder all the displeasure that the Shimazu family received, etc, however, there is no proven theory and this contradiction has come to be one of the biggest mysteries about Toshihisa in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ちなみに総領である義久は、歳久を代表とする反秀吉派の家臣達を戦後処理における上方との有利な講和条件引き出し(薩摩、大隅、日向三カ国の所領安堵)に利用した節がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa, the eldest child, seems to have used the vassals who were against Hideyoshi and Toshihisa to obtain advantageous conditions of peace (Shoryo Ando, act of providing authorization for land ownership and guaranteeing feudal tenure, of the three provinces, Satsuma, Osumi and Hyuga) with Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa, the eldest child, seems to have used the vassals who were against Hideyoshi and Toshihisa to obtain advantageous conditions of peace (Shoryo Ando, act of providing authorization for land ownership and guaranteeing feudal tenure, of the three provinces, Satsuma, Osumi and Hyuga) with Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa, the eldest child, seems to have used the vassals who were against Hideyoshi and Toshihisa to obtain advantageous conditions of peace (Shoryo Ando, act of providing authorization for land ownership and guaranteeing feudal tenure, of the three provinces, Satsuma, Osumi and Hyuga) with Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>秀吉の征討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Subjugation of Hideyoshi</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Subjugation of Hideyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>1592年、秀吉の始めた朝鮮出兵（文禄・慶長の役）も病気を理由に出陣しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He did not participate in Japan&apos;s invasion to Korea (the Bunroku-Keicho War) in 1592 for the reason of ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He did not participate in Japan&apos;s invasion of Korea (the Bunroku-Keicho War) in 1592 due to illness.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did not participate in Japan&apos;s invasion of Korea (the Bunroku-Keicho War) in 1592 due to illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし上記のように反抗的な態度を取り続けたことと、同年に島津氏の家臣・梅北国兼が秀吉に対して反乱（梅北一揆）を起こしたとき、その反乱軍に歳久の家臣が多く参加したことなどから秀吉の怒りを買うことになり、兄・義久の追討を受けて自殺しようとしたが、追手が立ちはだかっていたため、竜ヶ水に上陸した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because he continued to be rebellious against Hideyoshi and also because many of his vassals participated in the rebel against Hideyoshi (Unekita-ikki) started by a vassal of the Shimazu clan, Kunikane UMEKITA, Hideyoshi became angry with Toshihisa, and this led Toshihisa to attempt suicide, however, he landed Ryugamizu as the army of his older brother, Yoshihisa, came surrounding him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because he continued to be rebellious against Hideyoshi and also because many of his vassals participated in the uprising against Hideyoshi (Unekita-ikki) started by a vassal of the Shimazu clan, Kunikane UMEKITA, Hideyoshi became angry with Toshihisa, and this led Toshihisa to attempt suicide, however, he landed in Ryugamizu as the army of his older brother, Yoshihisa, came surrounding him.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because he continued to be rebellious against Hideyoshi and also because many of his vassals participated in the uprising against Hideyoshi (Unekita-ikki) started by a vassal of the Shimazu clan, Kunikane UMEKITA, Hideyoshi became angry with Toshihisa, and this led Toshihisa to attempt suicide, however, he landed in Ryugamizu as the army of his older brother, Yoshihisa, came surrounding him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>自害しようしたものの、体が不自由なため、上手く自害できず、また追手も太守の実弟ということで手が出せずいたところで「早う近づきて首を取れ」と歳久が言い暫くの後、原田甚次が首を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he tried to commit suicide, he could not do so due to his physical handicap; in addition to it, the army could not kill him right away, since it was led by his own brother, however, Jinji HARADA finally killed Toshihisa following Toshihisa&apos;s remark, &quot;Come here quickly and cut off my head.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原田甚次は読み方が分かりませんでした。Jinji HARADAとしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he tried to commit suicide, he could not do so due to his physical handicap; in addition, the army could not kill him right away, since it was led by his own brother, however, Jinji HARADA finally killed Toshihisa following Toshihisa&apos;s remark, &quot;Come here quickly and cut off my head.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he tried to commit suicide, he could not do so due to his physical handicap; in addition, the army could not kill him right away, since it was led by his own brother, however, Jinji HARADA finally killed Toshihisa following Toshihisa&apos;s remark, &quot;Come here quickly and cut off my head.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>享年56。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 56 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 56 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 56 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>亡骸を調べると義久に宛てた遺書と辞世の句が見つかり、そこには「私は病に侵され、太閤殿下の前に出ることが出来なかったのであって、何らやましいところはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A will written for Yoshihisa and a death haiku were found from Toshihisa&apos;s corpse; the will said &apos;since I know I was ill and could not serve for Imperial Highness Taiko (retired imperial regent), I have nothing to hide to make me suffer from the sense of guilt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A will written for Yoshihisa and a death haiku were found by Toshihisa&apos;s corpse; the will said &apos;since I know I was ill and could not serve the Imperial Highness Taiko (retired imperial regent), I have nothing to hide which would make me suffer from a sense of guilt.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A will written for Yoshihisa and a death haiku were found by Toshihisa&apos;s corpse; the will said &apos;since I know I was ill and could not serve the Imperial Highness Taiko (retired imperial regent), I have nothing to hide which would make me suffer from a sense of guilt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし謀反を疑われた以上、島津家安泰のために切腹しようと思う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since I was suspected of being rebellious against the Imperial Highness, I have decided I will commit suicide by disembowelment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since I was suspected of being rebellious against the Imperial Highness, I have decided I will commit suicide by disembowelment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since I was suspected of being rebellious against the Imperial Highness, I have decided I will commit suicide by disembowelment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>家臣たちは承服しがたいらしいので武士の本分を貫くべくやむをえず交戦するが、これは兄に対して弓を引こうというものではない」という主旨の文がしたためられていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the vassals do not seem to belive me, I have no choice than to fight with them as the Bushi&apos;s duty, however, this does not mean I want to have a rebel against my older brother.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the vassals do not seem to believe me, I have no choice other than to fight them as the Bushi&apos;s duty, however, this does not mean I want to rebel against my older brother.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording. Should &quot;Bushi&quot; should be translated as warrior?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the vassals do not seem to believe me, I have no choice other than to fight them as the Bushi&apos;s duty, however, this does not mean I want to rebel against my older brother.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>辞世の句は「晴蓑めが 玉のありかを 人問わば いざ白雲の 上と答へよ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The death haiku said &apos;&apos;.</e>
<cmt>辞世の句は意味が分かりにくかったため、訳せませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The death haiku said &apos;&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Haiku needs to be translated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The death haiku said &apos;晴蓑めが 玉のありかを 人問わば いざ白雲の 上と答へよ.&apos;</e>
<cmt>辞世の句は、意味不明のため訳出せず</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>死後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After death</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>首級は京都・一条戻橋に晒された後京都浄福寺に、遺体は帖佐の総禅寺に、それぞれ葬られ、霊は島津氏歴代の菩提寺・福昌寺 (鹿児島市)にて供養された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The severed head was stored in the Jofuku-ji Temple of Kyoto after being exposed at the Ichijo Modori-bashi Bridge in Kyoto and the dead body was placed in the Chosa of the Sozen-ji Temple; kuyo (a memorial service for the dead) was given at the Bodai-ji Temple and Fukusho-ji Temple in Kagoshima city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The severed head was stored in Jofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto after being exposed at Ichijo Modori-bashi Bridge in Kyoto, and the dead body was placed in the Chosa of the Sozen-ji Temple; a kuyo (memorial service for the dead) was given at Bodai-ji Temple and Fukusho-ji Temple in Kagoshima city.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The severed head was stored in Jofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto after being exposed at Ichijo Modori-bashi Bridge in Kyoto, and the dead body was placed in the Chosa of the Sozen-ji Temple; a kuyo (memorial service for the dead) was given at the family temple, Fukusho-ji Temple in Kagoshima city.</e>
<cmt>「菩提寺」の訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また秀吉の没後、歳久最後の地に心岳寺を建立し霊を祭った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, after the death of Hideyoshi, the Shingaku-ji Temple was built to enshrine his soul at the place where Toshihisa died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, after the death of Hideyoshi, Shingaku-ji Temple was built to enshrine his soul at the place where Toshihisa died.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, after the death of Hideyoshi, Shingaku-ji Temple was built to enshrine his soul at the place where Toshihisa died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>現在の平松神社はこの心岳寺の跡地に立てられたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present day Hiramatsu-jinja Shrine was built on the site of this shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present day Hiramatsu-jinja Shrine was built on the site of this shrine.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present day Hiramatsu-jinja Shrine was built on the site of this shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>毎年旧暦7月18日にはその遺徳を偲んで「心岳寺詣り」が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each year, on July 18 of Japan&apos;s old lunisolar calendar, &apos;Shingaku-ji Temple visit&apos; is held to remember his illustrious memory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each year, on July 18 of Japan&apos;s old lunisolar calendar, the &apos;Shingaku-ji Temple visit&apos; is held to commemorate his illustrious history.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each year, on July 18 of Japan&apos;s old lunisolar calendar, the &apos;Shingaku-ji Temple visit&apos; is held to commemorate his illustrious history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>また、自害の折刀を握ることが出来ず、傍らの石を持って自害せんとして苦痛を味わったとも伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he could not hold the sword and suffered from anguish when he tried to use the stone beside him to kill himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he could not hold a sword and suffered from anguish when he tried to use the stone beside him to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he could not hold a sword and suffered from anguish when he tried to use the stone beside him to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この際に「女性もお産の時に苦しい思いをするであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that at this time, he said &apos;Women go throught the same pain at the child birth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that at this time, he said &apos;Women go through the same pain in child birth.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that at this time, he said &apos;Women go through the same pain in child birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>自分の死後はそういった女性の苦しみを救ってやろう」と言ったともされており、平松神社には「戦の神」として以外に「安産の神」としても信仰されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death, I wish to save women from these sufferings&apos;; by this anecdote, he is also worshipped as the &apos;god for a smooth delivery&apos; not just as the &apos;god of war.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After death, I wish to save women from these sufferings&apos;; because of this anecdote, he is also worshipped as a &apos;god for a smooth delivery,&apos; not just as a &apos;god of war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After death, I wish to save women from these sufferings&apos;; because of this anecdote, he is also worshipped as a &apos;god for a smooth delivery,&apos; not just as a &apos;god of war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>旧薩摩藩内ではその生き様が郷中教育とも相まって、兄義弘を凌ぐほどの崇拝を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the former Satsuma Province, his way of life told in the Goju (education for the samurai in the Satsuma Province) received great respect that Toshihisa was worshipped even more than his older brother Yoshihiro did.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the former Satsuma Province, his way of life as it was taught in the Goju (education for the samurai in Satsuma Province) received such great respect that Toshihisa was worshipped even more than his older brother Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Is &quot;worshipped&quot; the best word choice? It has a very strong meaning in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the former Satsuma Province, his way of life as it was taught in the Goju (education for the samurai in Satsuma Province) received such great respect that Toshihisa was worshipped even more than his older brother Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>安政の大獄にて追い詰められた西郷隆盛が、小舟の上で同乗していた僧月照に歳久の故事を語り、心岳寺の方角へと手を合わせ水中に身を投じたエピソードも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another anecdote that when Takamori SAIGO was in a predicament at the Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate), he told the story of Toshihisa to the priest Gessho, joined his hands in prayer towards the direction of Shingaku-ji Temple and plunged himself into the water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another anecdote which relates that when Takamori SAIGO was in a predicament at the Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate), he told the story of Toshihisa to the priest Gessho, joined his hands in prayer in the direction of Shingaku-ji Temple and plunged himself into the water.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another anecdote which relates that when Takamori SAIGO was in a predicament at the Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate), he told the story of Toshihisa to the priest Gessho, joined his hands in prayer in the direction of Shingaku-ji Temple and plunged himself into the water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="38">
<j>歳久没後、忠隣の嫡男・島津常久が跡を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death, a legitimate son of Tadachika, Tsunehisa SHIMAZU inherited the position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his death, a legitimate son of Tadachika, Tsunehisa SHIMAZU, inherited his position.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death, a legitimate son of Tadachika, Tsunehisa SHIMAZU, inherited his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Archivist(id:52904), Cprobot(id:97843), Kahusi(id:1523), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Paranoid android(id:9248), こぶまき(id:38278), Point136(id:211299), Blue-flame(id:173983), けんち(id:5147), 00114455pp(id:200694), 「あなたには関係ない」(id:49400), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>