<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近衛篤麿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsumaro KONOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsumaro KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsumaro KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>近衞 篤麿（このえ あつまろ、文久3年6月26日 (旧暦)（1863年8月10日） - 明治37年（1904年）1月1日）は、明治後期の華族・政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsumaro KONOE 1863-1904 was a peerage and statesman in the late of Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsumaro KONOE 1863-1904 was a peer and statesman in the late Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsumaro KONOE 1863-1904 was a peer and statesman in the late Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>号は霞山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He called himself Kasumiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called himself Kasumiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Kasumiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近衛家は五摂家筆頭の家柄で、公爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Konoe family was the head of Gosekke and the rank was Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Konoe family was the head of Gosekke and the rank was Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Konoe family was the head of Gosekke and the rank was Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>第7代学習院院長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seventh president of the Gakushuin School Corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seventh president of the Gakushuin School Corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seventh president of the Gakushuin School Corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>本姓は藤原氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real surname was FUJIWARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real surname was FUJIWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real surname was FUJIWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生い立ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Backgrounds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>1863年（文久3年）6月26日、左大臣・近衛忠房と島津斉彬娘（実は養女）・貞姫の長男として京都に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 26, 1863, he was born in Kyoto as the first son of Tadafusa KONOE, Sadaijin (minister of the left) and Sada-hime (Princess Sada) who was a daughter of Nariakira SHIMAZU (actually, she was an adopted daughter).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 26, 1863, he was born in Kyoto as the first son of Tadafusa KONOE, Sadaijin (minister of the left) and Sada-hime (Princess Sada) who was a daughter of Nariakira SHIMAZU (actually, she was an adopted daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 26, 1863, he was born in Kyoto as the first son of Tadafusa KONOE, Sadaijin (minister of the left) and Sada-hime (Princess Sada) who was a daughter of Nariakira SHIMAZU (actually, she was an adopted daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし父忠房が1873年（明治6年）に家督を継がないまま35歳の若さで病没したために、祖父近衛忠煕の養子という形で家督を相続した（文献によって、忠煕六男と記しているものもある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because his father, Tadafusa died of illness at the age of 35 year old without taking over as head of the family, Atsumaro took over as the head of the family as an adopted child of his grand father, Tadahiro KONOE (according to some historical sources, Atsumaro was the sixth son of Tadahiro).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because his father, Tadafusa died of illness at the age of 35 years old without taking over as head of the family, Atsumaro took over as the head of the family as an adopted child of his grand father, Tadahiro KONOE (according to some historical sources, Atsumaro was the sixth son of Tadahiro).</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his father, Tadafusa died of illness at the age of 35 years old without taking over as head of the family, Atsumaro took over as the head of the family as an adopted child of his grand father, Tadahiro KONOE (according to some historical sources, Atsumaro was the sixth son of Tadahiro).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1879年（明治12年）大学予備門に入学したが、病を得て退学を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1879 he entered a preparatory school of university, but he had to left the school because he got a disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1879 he entered a preparatory school of university, but he had to leave the school because he got a disease.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1879 he entered a preparatory school of university, but he had to leave the school because he got a disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>以後は、和漢に加え、英語を独学する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, besides Chinese and Japanese classics he learned English on his own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, besides Chinese and Japanese classics he learned English on his own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, besides Chinese and Japanese classics he learned English on his own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1884年（明治16年）、華族令の制定に伴い公爵に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1884, due to the Peerage Law he was ordained as Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1884, due to the Peerage Law he was ordained as Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1884, due to the Peerage Law he was ordained as Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1885年（明治18年）にドイツ・フランスの両国に相次いで渡り、ボン大学・ライプツィヒ大学に学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1885, he went to Germany and France and studied at Bonn University and Leipzig University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1885, he went to Germany and France and studied at Bonn University and Leipzig University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1885, he went to Germany and France and studied at Bonn University and Leipzig University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1890年（明治23年）に帰国し貴族院 (日本)となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1890, he returned to Japan and became Kizokuin (the House of Peers in Japan).</e>
<cmt>※原文&quot;貴族院&quot;の後が抜けています。Wikipediaでは「1980年（明治23年）に帰国し貴族院議員となる。」と記述されています。訳出する場合は下記を&quot;became&quot;の後に付け加えます。追加：&quot;a member of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1890, he returned to Japan and became Kizokuin (the House of Peers in Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1890, he returned to Japan and became Kizokuin (the House of Peers in Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1895年（明治28年）には学校法人学習院院長となり、華族の子弟の教育に力を注いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1895, he became president of the Gakushuin School Corporation and put his effort into education for younger people from Peerage family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1895, he became president of the Gakushuin School Corporation and put his effort into education for younger people from Peerage families.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1895, he became president of the Gakushuin School Corporation and put his effort into education for younger people from Peerage families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>ノブレス・オブリージェを自覚する</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became aware of noble obligation (Noblesse Oblige).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became aware of noble obligation (Noblesse Oblige).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became aware of noble obligation (Noblesse Oblige).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>近衛篤麿の人となりは剛腹で、自らの地位と身分を深く自覚していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a big-hearted person and deeply aware of responsibility for his social status and rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a big-hearted person and deeply aware of responsibility for his social status and rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a big-hearted person and deeply aware of responsibility for his social status and rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ヨーロッパの貴族社会を参考に、近代日本においても、自分を含めた華族が社会的に優位な地位にあるものとして、政治的・社会的に「皇室の藩屏」としてその役割を果たすことを強く考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Referring to noble society in Europe, he believed the peerage including him should play role as hanpei (guarding wall of the imperial family), because the peerage were on the high ground in society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Referring to noble society in Europe, he believed the peerage including him should play a role as hanpei (guarding wall of the imperial family), because the peerage were on the high ground in society.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Referring to noble society in Europe, he believed the peerage including him should play a role as hanpei (guarding wall of the imperial family), because the peerage were on the high ground in society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そこで学習院の院長として、学習院の教育機関としての組織を整備し、財政を確立することに尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore as president of the Gakushuin School Corporation, he devote himself to adjust institution of the Gakushuin School Corporation as educational institution and secure a source of revenue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore as president of the Gakushuin School Corporation, he devoted himself to adjust the institution of the Gakushuin School Corporation as an educational institution and secure a source of revenue.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore as president of the Gakushuin School Corporation, he devoted himself to adjust the institution of the Gakushuin School Corporation as an educational institution and secure a source of revenue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、学習院で学んだ華族の子弟の進路として、日本を支える外交官や陸海軍人になることを考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He considered that the young people from the peerage family should be diplomat or enter the navy after their graduation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He considered that the young people from the peerage family should be diplomats or enter the navy after their graduation.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He considered that the young people from the peerage family should be diplomats or enter the navy after their graduation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>このような社会の先達としての貴族主義から、転じて彼の政治姿勢は、藩閥に対して批判的であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he espouse aristocratism and thought nobles should lead society, it is said he had a critical attitude to domain clique.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he espoused aristocratism and thought nobles should lead society, it is said he had a critical attitude to domain cliques.</e>
<cmt>mofified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he espoused aristocratism and thought nobles should lead society, it is said he had a critical attitude to domain cliques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>貴族院の公爵議員として、そして1892年（明治25年）から1904年（明治37年）まで貴族院議長として歴代の藩閥政府には常に批判的であり、第1次松方内閣の選挙干渉などを厳しく批判した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1892 to 1904, he kept a critical attitude to the government dominated by domain clique as a prince-councilor and President of Kizokuin (the House of Peers), he strongly criticized election interference by the first Matsukata cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1892 to 1904, he kept a critical attitude to the government dominated by domain cliques as a prince-councilor and President of Kizokuin (the House of Peers), he strongly criticized election interference by the first Matsukata cabinet.</e>
<cmt>mofified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1892 to 1904, he kept a critical attitude to the government dominated by domain cliques as a prince-councilor and President of Kizokuin (the House of Peers), he strongly criticized election interference by the first Matsukata cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>他方で政党に対しても批判を加えることを忘れず、政党が猟官主義に走る単なる「徒党」と化していることを嘆いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he criticized other political parties, because political parties acted on spoils system and became mere cliques.</e>
<cmt>猟官主義は&quot;spoils system&quot;と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he criticized other political parties, because political parties acted on the spoils system and became mere cliques.</e>
<cmt>mofified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he criticized other political parties, because political parties acted on the spoils system and became mere cliques.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>アジア主義の盟主として活躍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Activities as a leader of Asianisum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Activities as a leader of Asianism</e>
<cmt>mofified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Activities as a leader of Asianism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>近衛篤麿の外交政策は、中国（当時は清）を重視したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About his diplomatic strategy, Atsumaro KONOE weighted heavily on China (Qing at that time).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About his diplomatic strategy, Atsumaro KONOE weighed heavily on China (Qing at that time).</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About his diplomatic strategy, Atsumaro KONOE weighed heavily on China (Qing at that time).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>特に日清戦争後に積極的に中国をめぐる国際問題に関わっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, he actively got involved in international issues related to China after the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, he actively got involved in international issues related to China after the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, he actively got involved in international issues related to China after the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>1891年（明治24年）に東邦協会の副会頭に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1891, he became the vice-president of Tohokyokai (a study group of studies on foreign countries).</e>
<cmt>東邦教会はTohokyokai (東邦協会について（右記Webサイト、上から3番目の記事）：http://www.pref.kanagawa.jp/osirase/02/0219/publication/tayori/tayori14/tayori14.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1891, he became the vice-president of Tohokyokai (a study group of studies on foreign countries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1891, he became the vice-president of Tohokyokai (a study group of studies on foreign countries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>日清戦争後、西欧列強が中国分割の動きを激しくしていく中で危機感を抱く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sino-Japanese War, he felt a sense of danger about strenuous movement of powerful countries in Western Europe to split up China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Sino-Japanese War, he felt a sense of danger about the strenuous movement of powerful countries in Western Europe to split up China.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Sino-Japanese War, he felt a sense of danger about the strenuous movement of powerful countries in Western Europe to split up China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1898年（明治31年）に同文会を設立したが、同文会は、犬養毅の東亜会と合併して東亜同文会となり近衛篤麿は同会の会長に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1898, he formed Dobunkai (an association to study about issues related to China), then Dobunkai and Toakai which was formed by Tsuyoshi INUKAI merged and became Toadobunkai(an association of Pan-Asianism) and Atsumaro Konoe became the president.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1898, he formed Dobunkai (an association to study about issues related to China), then Dobunkai and Toakai which was formed by Tsuyoshi INUKAI merged and became Toadobunkai(an association of Pan-Asianism) and Atsumaro Konoe became the president.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1898, he formed Dobunkai (an association to study about issues related to China), then Dobunkai and Toakai which was formed by Tsuyoshi INUKAI merged and became Toadobunkai (an association of Pan-Asianism) and Atsumaro KONOE became the president.</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加しました。「Atsumaro Konoe」を「Atsumaro KONOE」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>かくて、民間諸団体を糾合し国家主義、アジア主義大同団結運動を目論んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He aimed to bring private association together and unite for a common purpose under the Nationalism and Asianism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He aimed to bring private association together and unite for a common purpose under the Nationalism and Asianism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He aimed to bring private association together and unite for a common purpose under the Nationalism and Asianism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>東亜同文会はアジア主義的色彩の強い立場に立脚し、中国・朝鮮の保護と日本の権益保護のため、外務省・軍部と密接に提携しながら、1900年（明治33年）に南京同文書院（後の東亜同文書院、その後身愛知大学）を設立するなど対中政治・文化活動の推進を図っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toadobunkai stood on the ground strongly influenced by Asianisum, and closely cooperated with the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the military to protect China, Korea and interests of Japan, then led cultural and political activities related to China including establishment of Nankindobunsyoin (a school in Nanjing, later became Toadobunsyoin and then Aichi University).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toadobunkai stood on the ground strongly influenced by Asianism, and closely cooperated with the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the military to protect China, Korea and interests of Japan, then led cultural and political activities related to China including establishment of Nankindobunsyoin (a school in Nanjing, later became Toadobunsyoin and then Aichi University).</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toadobunkai stood on the ground strongly influenced by Asianism, and closely cooperated with the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the military to protect China, Korea and interests of Japan, then led cultural and political activities related to China including establishment of Nankindobunshoin (a school in Nanjing, later became Toadobunshoin and then Aichi University).</e>
<cmt>「Nankindobunsyoin」を「Nankindobunshoin」に修正しました。「Toadobunsyoin」を「Toadobunshoin」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、清朝内で強い権力を持つ地方長官の劉坤一（両江総督）や張之洞（湖広総督）などにも独自に接近、日清の連携をもちかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On his own accord he approached to provincial governors, Kunyi LIU (Viceroy of Liangjiang) and Zhidong ZHANG (Viceroy of Huguang) who had strong power in Qing dynasty, to propose cooperation between Japan and Ching.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his own accord he approached provincial governors, Kunyi LIU (Viceroy of Liangjiang) and Zhidong ZHANG (Viceroy of Huguang) who had strong power in the Qing dynasty, to propose cooperation between Japan and Ching.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On his own accord he approached provincial governors, Kunyi LIU (Viceroy of Liangjiang) and Zhidong ZHANG (Viceroy of Huguang) who had strong power in the Qing dynasty, to propose cooperation between Japan and Ching.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>そうした中1900年（明治33年）6月、中国の華北や満州（現在の中国東北部）を中心に義和団事変が勃発、これに乗じたロシア帝国が満州を占領下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the circumstances, in June 1900, Boxer Uprising (the Righteous Harmony Society Movement) were staged centered in North China and Manchuria (present-day it is north east of China) and the Russian Empire occupied Manchuria.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the circumstances, in June 1900, Boxer Uprising (the Righteous Harmony Society Movement) were staged centered in North China and Manchuria (present-day north east China) and the Russian Empire occupied Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the circumstances, in June 1900, Boxer Uprising (the Righteous Harmony Society Movement) were staged centered in North China and Manchuria (present-day north east China) and the Russian Empire occupied Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>これに強い危機感を抱いた近衛は政府元老の伊藤博文や山縣有朋らにロシアに対して強硬な姿勢を取るよう持ちかけたが一蹴された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KONOE strongly felt a sense of danger about the incident and proposed to take a hard-line stance against Russia and consulted with Hirobumi ITO, former Genro (elder statesman) and Aritomo YAMAGATA but they didn&apos;t accept his opinion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONOE strongly felt a sense of danger about the incident and proposed to take a hard-line stance against Russia and consulted with Hirobumi ITO, former Genro (elder statesman) and Aritomo YAMAGATA but they didn&apos;t accept his opinion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KONOE strongly felt a sense of danger about the incident and proposed to take a hard-line stance against Russia and consulted with Hirobumi ITO, former Genro (elder statesman) and Aritomo YAMAGATA but they didn&apos;t accept his opinion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>そこで近衛は犬養・陸羯南・頭山満・中江兆民ら同志を糾合して同年9月に国民同盟会を結成し、日本政府に対する批判をますます強めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then KONOE brought INUKAI, Katunan KUGA, Mitsuru TOYAMA and Chomin NAKAE together, formed Kokumin-domeikai (People&apos;s Alliance) and stepped up his criticism of the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then KONOE brought INUKAI, Katunan KUGA, Mitsuru TOYAMA and Chomin NAKAE together, formed Kokumin-domeikai (People&apos;s Alliance) and stepped up his criticism of the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then KONOE brought INUKAI, Katunan KUGA, Mitsuru TOYAMA and Chomin NAKAE together, formed Kokumin-domeikai (People&apos;s Alliance) and stepped up his criticism of the Japanese government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>さらに長岡護美に書簡を託し、満州を列国に開放することで領土の保全を図るよう、劉坤一や張之洞に働きかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore he gave letters to Moriyoshi NAGAOKA and proposed to Kunyi LIU and Zhidong ZHANG to open Manchuria to the powerful countries in order to defend the territorial integrity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore he gave letters to Moriyoshi NAGAOKA and proposed to Kunyi LIU and Zhidong ZHANG to open Manchuria to the powerful countries in order to defend territorial integrity.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore he gave letters to Moriyoshi NAGAOKA and proposed to Kunyi LIU and Zhidong ZHANG to open Manchuria to the powerful countries in order to defend territorial integrity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>張が特にこれに大きく触発され、劉とともにこの近衛の案（根津一などがゴーストライターとして考えられるが）を清朝の中央に上奏し、採用を求めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ZHANG was impressed by the idea and he and LIU proposed the idea from KONOE (Hajime NEZU could have been the ghost-writer of this idea) to the central government of the Qing dynasty and asked them to adopt the idea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ZHANG was impressed by the idea and he and LIU proposed the idea from KONOE (Hajime NEZU could have been the ghost-writer of this idea) to the central government of the Qing dynasty and asked them to adopt the idea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ZHANG was impressed by the idea and he and LIU proposed the idea from KONOE (Hajime NEZU could have been the ghost-writer of this idea) to the central government of the Qing dynasty and asked them to adopt the idea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この時は却下されたものの、満州開放案はその後袁世凱も採用し、日露戦争後にはむしろ権益独占を図る日本に対する障害となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The proposal was rejected at that time, but later the idea to open Manchuria was adopted by Shikai YUAN and became hamper for Japanese government, which wanted to monopolize interests in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The proposal was rejected at that time, but later the idea to open Manchuria was adopted by Shikai YUAN and became a hindrance to the Japanese government, which wanted to monopolize interests in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The proposal was rejected at that time, but later the idea to open Manchuria was adopted by Shikai YUAN and became a hindrance to the Japanese government, which wanted to monopolize interests in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また、1903年（明治36年）には対露同志会を結成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1903, he formed a Tairo-doshikai (a group, which insisted hard-line position against Russia).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1903, he formed a Tairo-doshikai (a group which insisted on a hard-line position against Russia).</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1903, he formed a Tairo-doshikai (a group which insisted on a hard-line position against Russia).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>貴族院議長を辞任、枢密顧問官に任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned president of Kizokuin and was assigned privy councilor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned as president of Kizokuin and was assigned privy councilor.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned as president of Kizokuin and was assigned privy councilor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし、将来を嘱望されていた矢先、1904年（明治37年）1月1日に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his future success was expected, he died in January 1, 1904.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his future success was expected, he died in January 1, 1904.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his future success was expected, he died in January 1, 1904.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>享年42（満40歳没）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at the age of 42 (40 years after his birth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Died at the age of 42 (40 years after his birth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 42 (40 years after his birth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>中国に渡航したさいに感染した伝染病が原因であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cause of his death was infectious disease with which he was infected during his trip in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cause of his death was infectious disease with which he was infected during his trip in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cause of his death was infectious disease with which he was infected during his trip in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>近衛家の菩提寺である大徳寺（京都市北区）に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hi was gathered to Daitoku-ji Temple (present-day Kita Ward, Kyoto City), which is the family temple of the Konoe Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hi was gathered to Daitoku-ji Temple (present-day Kita Ward, Kyoto City), which is the family temple of the Konoe Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was gathered to Daitoku-ji Temple (present-day Kita Ward, Kyoto City), which is the family temple of the Konoe Family.</e>
<cmt>「Hi」を「He」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>死後、多額の借財があり、篤麿存命中に近衛家に出入りしていた者が手のひらを返すような態度に変わったため、長男近衛文麿は人間不信の念を強くしたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left a large amount of borrowed property, so people who frequently came to visit the family changed their attitude after Atsumaro&apos;s death, the first son, Fumimaro KONOE was led to deep trust problem about human beings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left a large amount of borrowed property, so people who frequently came to visit the family changed their attitude after Atsumaro&apos;s death, and the first son, Fumimaro KONOE had a deep trust problem for human beings.</e>
<cmt>modified</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left a large amount of borrowed property, so people who frequently came to visit the family changed their attitude after Atsumaro&apos;s death, and the first son, Fumimaro KONOE had a deep trust problem for human beings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>家族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>前妻：衍（さわ。前田慶寧五女。明治2年-明治24年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His former wife: Sawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His former wife: Sawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His former wife: Sawa (the fifth daughter of Yoshiyasu MAEDA, 1869-1891)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が分かれていたのでまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>長男：近衛文麿（貴族院議長、内閣総理大臣）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first son: Fumimaro KONOE (served as a president of Kizokuin, the Prime minister)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first son: Fumimaro KONOE (served as a president of Kizokuin, the Prime minister)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first son: Fumimaro KONOE (served as a president of Kizokuin, the Prime minister)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>後妻：貞（もと。前田慶寧六女。明治4年-昭和20年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second wife was Moto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second wife was Moto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second wife: Moto (the sixth daughter of Yoshiyasu MAEDA, 1871-1945)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が分かれていたのでまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>長女：武子（公爵大山柏妻）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first daughter:Takeko (wife of Kashiwa OYAMA, Prince)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first daughter:Takeko (wife of Kashiwa OYAMA, Prince)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first daughter:Takeko (wife of Kashiwa OYAMA, Prince)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>次男：近衛秀麿（音楽家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second son:Hidemaro KONOE (a musician)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second son:Hidemaro KONOE (a musician)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second son:Hidemaro KONOE (a musician)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>三男：近衛直麿（雅楽研究者）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third son:Naomaro KONOE (a researcher of Gagaku (Japanese traditional music and dance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third son:Naomaro KONOE (a researcher of Gagaku (Japanese traditional music and dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third son:Naomaro KONOE (a researcher of Gagaku (Japanese traditional music and dance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="48">
<j>四男：水谷川忠麿（→水谷川家を継ぐ、春日大社宮司）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The forth son:Tadamaro MIYAGAWA (he succeeded the Mizutanigawa family and became Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) of Kasuga-Taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth son:Tadamaro MIYAGAWA (he succeeded the Mizutanigawa family and became Guji (chief of those who serve a shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) of Kasuga-Taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>modificed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth son:Tadamaro MIYAGAWA (he succeeded the Mizutanigawa family and became Guji (chief of those who serve a shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) of Kasuga-taisha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>「Taisha」を「taisha」に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>著作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His literary work</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His literary work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His literary work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>近衛篤麿 著・近衛篤麿日記刊行会 編『近衛篤麿日記』第1~5巻・別巻 （鹿島出版会、1968~69年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Written by Atsumaro KONOE, edited by association for publication of Atsumaro KONOE&apos;s diaries &quot;Atsumaro KONOE Diary&quot; the first to fifth band (published by Kashima publication association, 1968～1969).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Written by Atsumaro KONOE, edited by association for publication of Atsumaro KONOE&apos;s diaries &quot;Atsumaro KONOE Diary&quot; the first to fifth band (published by Kashima publication association, 1968～1969).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Written by Atsumaro KONOE, edited by association for publication of Atsumaro KONOE&apos;s diaries &quot;Atsumaro KONOE Diary&quot; the first to fifth band (published by Kashima publication association, 1968～1969).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Straysheep(id:42448), Wiki0825(id:34646), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Tom-spring(id:42457), Mintleaf(id:2216), Rename1014b(id:53199), شيوعية(id:206578), Aboshi(id:9318), Kaba(id:17904), 玄史生(id:43670), 代言人(id:33675), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), 総督(id:124846), Muro Bot(id:217619), Loveless(id:129239), こぶまき(id:38278), Aloha-vodka(id:22493), Kouko0515(id:100370), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>