<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近衛家熙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iehiro KONOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iehiro KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iehiro KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>近衛 家熙（このえ いえひろ、寛文7年6月4日 (旧暦)（1667年7月24日） - 元文元年10月3日 (旧暦)（1736年11月5日））は、江戸時代前、中期の公家、摂政関白。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iehiro KONOE () was a court noble lived in early to mid Edo Period, and assumed the position of Sessho (regent) and Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iehiro KONOE (June 4, 1667 - October 3, 1736) was a court noble, who lived in early to mid Edo Period, and assumed the position of Sessho (regent) and Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Added datesAdded &quot;, who&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iehiro KONOE (July 24, 1667 - November 5, 1736) was a court noble, who lived in early to mid Edo period, and assumed the position of Sessho (regent) and Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は近衛基熙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Motohiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Motohiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Motohiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は後水尾天皇の皇女・常子内親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Imperial Princess Tsuneko, a daughter of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Imperial Princess Tsuneko, a daughter of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Imperial Princess Tsuneko, a daughter of Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正室は霊元天皇の皇女・憲子内親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His seishitsu (one&apos;s legal wife) was Imperial Princess Noriko, a daughter of Emperor Reigen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was Imperial Princess Noriko, a daughter of Emperor Reigen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;seishitsu (one&apos;s legal wife)&quot;→&quot;wife&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was Imperial Princess Noriko, a daughter of Emperor Reigen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に近衛家久、中御門天皇の女御近衛尚子、尾張藩主徳川継友の室安己君、徳川家宣の養女となる政姫 (徳川家)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had children: Iehisa KONOE; Hisako KONOE, a nyogo (high ranking lady serving at court) of Emperor Nakamikado; Akogimi, a shitsu (wife) of Tsugutomo TOKUGAWA who was the lord of Owari domain; and Masahime who became an adopted daughter of Ienobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had children were Iehisa KONOE; Hisako KONOE, a nyogo (high ranking lady serving at court) of Emperor Nakamikado; Akogimi, a wife of Tsugutomo TOKUGAWA, who was the lord of Owari domain; and Masahime, who became an adopted daughter of Ienobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>colon→were&quot;shitsu (wife)&quot;→&quot;wife&quot;Added commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were Iehisa KONOE; Hisako KONOE, a nyogo (high ranking lady serving at court) of Emperor Nakamikado; Akogimi, a wife of Tsugutomo TOKUGAWA, who was the lord of Owari domain; and Masahime, who became an adopted daughter of Ienobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>His children としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>寛文7年（1667年）6月4日に京都で誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born on June 4, 1667 in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on June 4, 1667 in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on July 24, 1667 in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幼名を増君と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Masugimi.</e>
<cmt>増君→Masugimi[読み方不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Masugimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Masugimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>延宝元年（1673年）11月に元服し、従五位上に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went through genpuku (a ceremony to celebrate a young man&apos;s coming of age) in November, 1673 and was given the rank of Jugoijo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1673, he had his coming of age ceremony and was given the rank of Jugoijo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>&quot;He went through genpuku (a ceremony to celebrate a young man&apos;s coming of age) in November, 1673&quot;→&quot;In November 1673, he had his coming of age ceremony&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1673, he had his coming of age ceremony and was given the rank of Jugoijo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同時に昇殿を許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he was permitted shoden (go up on Seiryoden).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he was permitted access to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;shoden (go up on Seiryoden)&quot;→&quot;access to the Imperial Court&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he was permitted access to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>延宝4年（1676年）1月に従三位に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1676, he was promoted to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1676, he was promoted to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1676, he was promoted to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>貞享3年（1686年）3月、20歳で内大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Marchi 1686, he assumed the position of Naidaijin (managerial position who support Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Marchi 1686, he assumed the position of Naidaijin (Minister of the Center).</e>
<cmt>&quot;managerial position who support Emperor&quot;→&quot;Minister of the Center&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1686, he assumed the position of Naidaijin (Minister of the Center).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>元禄6年（1693年）8月に右大臣、宝永元年（1704年）1月に左大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1693, he assumed the position of Udaijin (minister of the right), then Sadaijin (minister of the left) in January 1704.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1693, he assumed the position of Udaijin (Minister of the Right), then Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in January 1704.</e>
<cmt>Capitalised &apos;m&apos;, &apos;r&apos;, &apos;m&apos;, &apos;l&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1693, he assumed the position of Udaijin (Minister of the Right), then Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in February 1704.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>宝永4年（1707年）11月関白に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1707, he assumed the position of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1707, he assumed the position of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1707, he assumed the position of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>宝永6年（1709年）に中御門天皇の摂政となり、更に翌年の宝永7年（1710年）に太政大臣に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1709, he became a Sessho of Emperor Nakamikado, then appointed as Daijodaijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1709, he became a Sessho of Emperor Nakamikado, then was appointed Daijodaijin (Grand Minister of State).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;was&quot;Deleted &quot;as&quot;Capitalised &apos;g&apos;, &apos;m&apos;, &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1709, he became a Sessho of Emperor Nakamikado, then was appointed Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister of State).</e>
<cmt>Daijo-daijin　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>正徳 (日本)元年（1711年）7月太政大臣辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned from Daijodaijin in July 1711.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned as Daijodaijin in July 1711.</e>
<cmt>&quot;from&quot;→&quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned as Daijo-daijin in August 1711.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>正徳2年（1712年）8月摂政辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1712, he was resigned from Sessho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1712, he resigned as Sessho.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;was&quot;&quot;from&quot;→&quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1712, he resigned as Sessho.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>享保10年（1725年）准三后の宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1725, he was named Jusango (title given to novels and Imperial families) by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>「宣下」を天皇から身分を与えられるという意味で訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1725, he was named Jusango (title given to nobels and members of the Imperial family) by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Spelling of &quot;nobels&quot;Added &quot;members of the&quot;Made &quot;families&quot; singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1725, he was named Jusango (title given to nobles and members of the Imperial family) by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同年12月24日に落飾し、豫樂院（よらくいん、現代では、予楽の字で表記されるが、『豫樂』と表記するのが正しい）と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 24 in the same year, he performed rakusyoku (cut hair to become a priest) and changed his name to Yorakuin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 24 in the same year, he took the tonsure and changed his name to Yorakuin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;performed rakusyoku (cut hair to become a priest)&quot;→&quot;took the tonsure&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 26, 1726 (December 24, 1725 in old lunar calendar), he took the tonsure and changed his name to Yorakuin.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>書道は、はじめ加茂流を学び、更に近衛家や他に伝わる空海・小野道風らの書に学び独自の境地を切り開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for art of calligraphy, he learned the Kamo school (style) at first, then he learned from the calligraphy of Kukai and ONO no Michikaze handed down in the Konoe family and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied the Kamo style of calligraphy and, after learning the styles of Kukai and ONO no Michikaze, which had been passed down in the Konoe and other families, he went on to develop his own style.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied the Kamo style of calligraphy and, after learning the styles of Kukai and ONO no Michikaze, which had been passed down in the Konoe and other families, he went on to develop his own style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>絵画は水墨画を好んで描き佳作と評される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for painting, he liked ink painting and was highly evaluated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He enjoyed &apos;suibokuga&apos; ink and wash painting and his works are highly regarded.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He enjoyed &apos;suibokuga&apos; ink and wash painting and his works are highly regarded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>茶道は慈胤法親王を師とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for tea ceremony, he became a disciple of</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He taught tea ceremony to Imperial Prince Jiin</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He taught tea ceremony to Cloistered Imperial Prince Jiin.</e>
<cmt>慈胤法親王→ Cloistered Imperial Prince Jiin　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>有職故実にも堪能で、礼典儀礼を研究し、『唐六典』の校勘を長年継続して、致仕後の享保9年（1724年）に20年の歳月をかけて完成させ、家熙没後刊行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was proficient in yusokukojitsu (ancient rules of Imperial court and military commander). also studied ordinance for ceremonies and continued kokan (revision) of &quot;Torikuten&quot;, then completed it in 1724 after chishi (retire a government post), which was published after the death of Iehiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was well-versed in the ancient rules and practices of the Imperial Court and the military, studied ceremonial rituals and etiquette and spent many years revising the &quot;Torikuten&quot;, completing it in 1724 after retiring from the government, though it was not published until after his death.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was well-versed in the ancient rules and practices of the Imperial Court and the military, studied ceremonial rituals and etiquette and spent as many as 20 years revising the &quot;Torikuten,&quot; completing it in 1724 after retiring from the government, although it was not published until after his death.</e>
<cmt>20年　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、公家茶道に通じた茶人であり、『槐記』に見られるように、自ら茶事をおこない、侘び茶人との交流でも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he was a chajin (master of ceremonial tea) familiar with the tea ceremony of court noble, in &quot;Kaiki&quot;, it is described that he held a tea ceremony voluntarilyand known for the interaction with chajin of wabi (the beauty to be found in spareness and simplicity).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also a master of the courtly tea ceremony and the &quot;Kaiki&quot; records that he performed the ceremony himself and was known for his interaction with &apos;wabi&apos; tea masters.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also a master of the courtly tea ceremony and the &quot;Kaiki&quot; records that he performed the ceremony himself and was known for his interaction with &apos;wabi&apos; tea masters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>なお、家煕の人となりや博学多才ぶり、高い見識のほどについては、侍医（専門は現代で言う小児科）で、茶人であった山科道安（やましなどうあん）がその言行を日録風に記した『槐記』11巻により、如実に知ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 11th volume of &quot;Kaiki&quot; written by Doan YAMASHINA, a jii (a doctor for the Emperor and the Imperial family) (specialized in present-day pediatrics) and chajin, Iehiro&apos;s sayings and doings are described like diary and we can clearly see his personality, varied attainments and considerable insight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 11th volume of &quot;Kaiki&quot;. written by Doan YAMASHINA, a court physician (specializing in what is today known as pediatrics) and master of the tea ceremony, Iehiro&apos;s sayings and doings are described like a diary and we can clearly see his personality, varied attainments and considerable insight.</e>
<cmt>Added comma&quot;jii&quot;→&quot;court physician&quot;Deleted &quot;(a doctor for the Emperor and the Imperial family)&quot;&quot;specialized in present-day pediatrics&quot;→&quot;specializing in what is today known as pediatrics&quot;&quot;chajin&quot;→&quot;master of the tea ceremony&quot;&quot;varied attainments&quot;→&quot;expansive knowledge&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 11th volume of &quot;Kaiki&quot;. written by Doan YAMASHINA, a court physician (specializing in what is today known as pediatrics) and master of the tea ceremony, Iehiro&apos;s sayings and doings are described like a diary and we can clearly see his personality, varied attainments and considerable insight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>元文元年（1736年）10月3日薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on October 3, 1736.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on October 3, 1736.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on November 5, 1736.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>享年70。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 70.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His was 70 years old.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;age at death&quot;Added &quot;years old&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 70 years old.</e>
<cmt>His→He</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>京都市北区 (京都市)の京都大徳寺に葬られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried in Daitoku-ji Temple in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried in Daitoku-ji Temple in Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried in Daitoku-ji Temple in Kita Ward (Kyoto City), Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>(Kyoto City)　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TakuyaMurata(id:156), Woyzzeck(id:8923), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Lupinoid(id:68), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Ponsaku(id:31417), 伏儀(id:142093), けんち(id:5147), ５１６(id:45205), Sorrysorry(id:102591), Kzhr(id:131), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>