<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土御門泰福</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutomi TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutomi TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutomi TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>土御門 泰福（つちみかど やすとみ、明暦元年6月20日 (旧暦)（1655年7月23日）－享保2年6月17日 (旧暦)（1717年7月25日））は、江戸時代前期の公卿（非参議）・陰陽家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutomi TSUCHIMIKADO (July 23rd, 1655 ~ July 25th, 1717) was Kugyo (court noble of a class and not a councilor) and onmyoka of the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutomi TSUCHIMIKADO (July 23rd, 1655 ~ July 25th, 1717) was Kugyo (court noble of a class and not a councilor) and onmyoka during the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutomi TSUCHIMIKADO (July 23, 1655-July 25, 1717) was Kugyo (a court noble, non-Councilor) and Inyoka (the Yin and Yang school of philosophy) during the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正。日付表記を修正。「公卿（非参議）、陰陽家」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>土御門泰広の子でその弟土御門隆俊の養嗣子とされているが、実父を隆俊あるいは土御門泰重（泰広・隆俊の父）とする異説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to be a son of Yasuhiro TSUCHIMIKADO and became a son-in-law of Yasuhiro&apos;s younger brother, however, there is a heresy that his real father is Takatoshi or Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO (father of Yasuhiro and Takatoshi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to be the son of Yasuhiro TSUCHIMIKADO and became a son-in-law of Yasuhiro&apos;s younger brother, however, there is here say that his real father was Takatoshi or Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO (father of Yasuhiro and Takatoshi).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to be the son of Yasuhiro TSUCHIMIKADO and became a son-in-law of Yasuhiro&apos;s younger brother, Takatoshi TSUCHIMIKADO, however, there is here say that his real father was Takatoshi or Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO (father of Yasuhiro and Takatoshi).</e>
<cmt>「(その弟)土御門隆俊」を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に土御門泰誠・土御門泰連・土御門泰邦ら。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has sons of Yasumasa TSUCHIMIKADO, Yasutsura TSUCHIMIKADO and Yasukuni TSUCHIMIKADO, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons are Yasumasa TSUCHIMIKADO, Yasutsura TSUCHIMIKADO and Yasukuni TSUCHIMIKADO, and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons are Yasumasa TSUCHIMIKADO, Yasutsura TSUCHIMIKADO and Yasukuni TSUCHIMIKADO, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一般には土御門神道の祖として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is generally known as the originator of the Tsuchimikado Shinto (Shinto of Tsuchimikado school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is generally known as the originator of the Tsuchimikado Shinto (Shinto of Tsuchimikado school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is generally known as the originator of the Tsuchimikado Shinto (Shinto of Tsuchimikado school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>泰広・隆俊の死により泰重の後継者となり、寛文元年（1661年）の泰重の死によりその家督を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a successor of Yasushige due to the death of Yasuhiro and Takatoshi and succeeded the reign of the family by the death of Yasushige in 1661.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a successor of Yasushige due to the death of Yasuhiro and Takatoshi and succeeded the reign of the family by the death of Yasushige in 1661.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a successor of Yasushige due to the death of Yasuhiro and Takatoshi and succeeded the reign of the family by the death of Yasushige in 1661.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>土御門家_(安倍氏)は、代々陰陽頭を務めていたが、江戸時代初期に土御門泰重がその座を幸徳井家に譲渡、その後その陰陽師支配の権限を巡る争いから陰陽頭の返上を求める泰重とこれを拒む幸徳井家側との対立が長く続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tsuchimikado family (the Abe clan) served as Onmyoji no kami (the head of onmyoji) for generations, however, the post was transferred by Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO to the Kotokui family in the early Edo period, and after that, the conflicts over the authenticity of the control of the Onmyoji long lasted between Yasushige who was requiring the return of the post of the head and the Kotokui family who was rejecting the return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tsuchimikado family (the Abe clan) served as Onmyoji no kami (the head of onmyoji) for generations, however, the post was transferred by Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO to the Kotokui family in the early Edo period, and after that, the conflicts over the authenticity of the control of the Onmyoji long lasted between Yasushige who was requiring tyo return the post of the head and the Kotokui family, but who was rejected the return.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tsuchimikado family (the Abe clan) served as Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Bureau of Divination) for generations, however, the post was transferred by Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO to the Kotokui family at the beginning of Edo period, and after that, the conflicts over the authenticity of the control of the Onmyoji long lasted between Yasushige who was requiring to return the post of Director and the Kotokui family, but who was rejected the return.</e>
<cmt>「陰陽頭」「江戸時代初期」を修正。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>泰福が元服して正六位下蔵人兼近衛府に任じられた寛文10年（1670年）にも泰福と幸徳井友傳の間で陰陽頭を巡る相論が発生するも、天和_(日本)2年（1682年）に友傳が35歳で急死、相論の仲裁にあたっていた江戸幕府は友傳の子は幼くて職務が行えないと裁定したため、当時従五位上兵部少輔であった泰福が陰陽頭に就任、継いで翌年には諸国の陰陽師を支配・免許の権限が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1670 when Yasutomi passed the genpuku ceremony and was designated as Shorokuinoge (Senior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade), Kuraudo (keeper of imperial archives) and Konoefu, the disputes occurred again with Tomohiro KOTOKUI regarding Onmyoji no kami, however, Tomohiro died suddenly at the age of 35, and the Edo bakufu shogunate which arbitrated the conflicts handed down the ruling that the son of Tomohiro was too young to execute the post, thus Yasutomi who was at Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and Hyobushoyu accede the post, and in the next year, he was authorized to control and license the Onmyoji of the whole country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1670 when Yasutomi passed the genpuku ceremony and was designated as Shorokuinoge (Senior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade), Kuraudo (keeper of imperial archives) and Konoefu, the disputes occurred again with Tomohiro KOTOKUI regarding Onmyoji no kami, however, Tomohiro died suddenly at the age of 35, and the Edo bakufu shogunate which arbitrated the conflicts handed down the ruling that the son of Tomohiro was too young to execute the post, thus Yasutomi who was at Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and Hyobushoyu acceded the post, and in the next year, he was authorized to control and license the Onmyoji of the whole country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1670 when Yasutomi passed the genpuku ceremony and was designated as Shorokuinoge Kurodo (Senior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade, Chamberlain) and Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards), the disputes occurred again with Tomohiro KOTOKUI regarding Onmyoji no kami, however, Tomohiro died suddenly at the age of 35 in 1682, and the Edo bakufu shogunate which arbitrated the conflicts handed down the ruling that the son of Tomohiro was too young to execute the post, thus Yasutomi who was at Jugoinojo Hyobu-shoyu (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, junior assistant minister of the Hyobusho Ministry of Military) acceded the post, and in the next year, he was authorized to control and license the Onmyoji of the whole country.</e>
<cmt>「正六位下蔵人兼近衛府、従五位上兵部少輔」を修正。年号を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後春宮少進に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he was positioned to Togushojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was positioned to the Togushojo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was positioned to the Togu-shoshin (an official of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters).</e>
<cmt>「春宮少進」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>貞享元年（1684年）の改暦に際しては大統暦の実施を主張するも、後には山崎闇斎のもとで同門であった渋川晴海の貞享暦が優れていることを認めてこれを実施するように上奏し、元禄2年（1699年）には幸徳井家に圧力をかけて土御門家を陰陽道宗家として仰ぐ事を約束させ、同家を支配下に置いたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the Revision of the Calendar in 1684, though he once asserted to adopt the Daito calendar, later he admitted that the Jokyo calendar of Harumi SHIBUKAWA who was a scholar belonging to the same school as Yasutomi of Ansai YAMAZAKI was superior and reported the fact to the emperor to perform, and in 1699, he put pressure upon the Kotokui family and had them promised to be respectful to the Tsuchimikado family as the originator of Onmyodo and controlled the Kotokui family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Revision of the Calendar in 1684, though he once asserted to adopt the Daito calendar, later he admitted that the Jokyo calendar of Harumi SHIBUKAWA who was a scholar belonging to the same school as Yasutomi of Ansai YAMAZAKI was superior and reported the fact to the emperor to perform, and in 1699, he put pressure upon the Kotokui family and had them promised to be respectful to the Tsuchimikado family as the originator of Onmyodo and controlled the Kotokui family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the kaireki (changing of calendar) in 1684, though he once asserted to adopt the Daito calendar, later he admitted that the Jokyo reki (Jokyo calendar) of Harumi SHIBUKAWA who was a scholar belonging to the same school as Yasutomi of Ansai YAMAZAKI was superior and reported the fact to the emperor to perform, and in 1689, he put pressure upon the Kotokui family and had them promised to be respectful to the Tsuchimikado family as the originator of Onmyodo and controlled the Kotokui family.</e>
<cmt>「改暦、貞享暦」を修正。年号を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この功績によって元禄11年（1708年）に従三位に昇り、正徳 (日本)4年（1714年）に従二位にまで昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this achievement, he was appointed to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1708 and promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 1714.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this achievement, he was appointed to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1708 and promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 1714.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this achievement, he was appointed to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1698 and promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 1714.</e>
<cmt>年号を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>また、山崎闇斎から垂加神道を学び、前述の晴海や一条冬経・野宮定縁らと結ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he studied Suika Shinto under Ansai YAMAZAKI and made ties with aforementioned Harumi, Fuyutsune ICHIJO and Sadayori NOMIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he studied Suika Shinto under Ansai YAMAZAKI and made ties with aforementioned Harumi, Fuyutsune ICHIJO and Sadayori NOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he studied Suika Shinto under Ansai YAMAZAKI and made ties with aforementioned Harumi, Fuyutsune ICHIJO and Sadayori NOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、その影響を受けて陰陽道と神道を組み合わせた独自の神道理論（土御門神道）を打ち立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, he was Influenced by them and established a new and unique Shinto theory (Tsuchimikado Shinto) by combining Onmyodo and Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, he was Influenced by them and established a new and unique Shinto theory (Tsuchimikado Shinto) by combining Onmyodo and Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, he was influenced by them and established a new and unique Shinto theory (Tsuchimikado Shinto) by combining Onmyodo and Shinto.</e>
<cmt>Influenced を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>だが、一方で改暦の実質上の中心であった渋川晴海が江戸幕府に召されて天文方に入ったために改暦の中心が江戸に移る結果を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Harumi SHIBUKAWA who was virtually the head of calendar revision work was nominated by the Edo bakufu and to become a Tenmonkata (astronomer appointed by bakufu), the center of the calendar revision work had been moved to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Harumi SHIBUKAWA who was virtually the head of calendar revision work was nominated by the Edo bakufu and to become a Tenmonkata (astronomer appointed by the bakufu), the center of the calendar revision work had been moved to Edo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Harumi SHIBUKAWA who was virtually the head of kaireki work was nominated by the Edo bakufu and to become a Tenmonkata (astronomer appointed by the bakufu), the center of kaireki work had been moved to Edo.</e>
<cmt>「改暦」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>63歳で死去して、墓所は京都真如堂にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 63 whose grave is at Shin nyo do in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 63 and his grave is at Shin nyo do in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 63 and his grave is at Shinnyo-do Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>「真如堂」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>