<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>柳原資明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukeakira YANAGIWARA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukeakira YANAGIWARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukeakira YANAGIWARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>柳原 資明（やなぎわら すけあきら、永仁5年（1297年） - 文和2年/正平 (日本)8年（1353年）7月27日 (旧暦)）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の公卿で、柳原家の祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukeakira YANAGIWARA (1297 – July 27, 1353) was a court noble in the Southern and Northern Dynasties Period (Japan) and the founder of the Yanagiwara family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukeakira YANAGIWARA (1297 – July 27, 1353) was a court noble in the Southern and Northern Dynasties Period (Japan) and the founder of the Yanagiwara family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukeakira YANAGIWARA (1297 – September 3, 1353) was a court noble in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts and the founder of the Yanagiwara family.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正、南北朝時代 (日本)→統一表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>正二位大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Dainagon (Major Counselor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Dainagon (Major Counselor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>Dainagon→統一表記に修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後伏見天皇の院庁執権であった権大納言日野俊光の4男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth son of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) Toshimitsu HINO, who was the regent for the In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) of Emperor Gofushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth son of Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) Toshimitsu HINO, who was the regent for the In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) of Emperor Gofushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth son of Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) Toshimitsu HINO, who was the regent for the In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) of Emperor Gofushimi.</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagon→統一事項に基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「柳原殿」と称される邸宅に住んでいたため、「柳原」を家名とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took the family name &quot;Yanagiwara&quot; because he lived in a house called the &quot;Yanaiwara-dono&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took the family name &quot;Yanagiwara&quot; because he lived in a house called the &quot;Yanaiwara-dono&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took the family name &apos;Yanagiwara&apos; because he lived in a house called the &apos;Yanaiwara-dono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>“Yanagiwara”→&apos;Yanagiwara&apos;、“Yanaiwara-dono”→&apos;Yanagiwara-dono&apos;に修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>正安3年に従五位下に叙任され、文保元年21歳で花園天皇の蔵人に任じられて以後は、専ら持明院統系の天皇・太上天皇に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1301, and in after being appointed as kurodo (Chamberlain) to Emperor Hanazono in 1317 at the age of 21, he worked exclusively for the Jimyo-in line (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) Emperors and Daijotenno (retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1301, and after being appointed as kurodo (Chamberlain) to Emperor Hanazono in 1317 at the age of 21, he worked exclusively for the Jimyo-in line (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) Emperors and Daijotenno (retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1301, and after being appointed as kurodo (Chamberlain) to Emperor Hanazono in 1317 at the age of 21, he worked exclusively for the Jimyo-in line (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) Emperors and Daijotenno (retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後に弁官・左大弁・参議を歴任後、光厳天皇のもとで正三位中納言にまで上るが、鎌倉幕府滅亡後、復位した後醍醐天皇によって昇進人事を無効とされると、建武の新政に激しく反発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being Benkan (Oversight Department: division of the daijokan responsible for controlling central and provincial governmental offices), Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left), and Sangi (Royal Advisor), he climbed to the position of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Chunagon (Middle Counselor) under Emperor Kogon, but after the decline of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), promotional job assignments were made invalid by the reinstated Emperor Godaigo and therefore he became a strong opponent of the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being Benkan (Oversight Department: division of the daijokan responsible for controlling central and provincial governmental offices), Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left), and Sangi (Royal Advisor), he climbed to the position of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Chunagon (Middle Counselor) under Emperor Kogon, but after the decline of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), promotional job assignments were made invalid by the reinstated Emperor Godaigo and therefore he became a strong opponent of the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being Benkan (Oversight Department: division of the daijokan responsible for controlling central and provincial governmental offices), Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left), and Sangi (Royal Advisor), he climbed to the position of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) under Emperor Kogon, but after the decline of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), promotional job assignments were made invalid by the reinstated Emperor Godaigo and therefore he became a strong opponent of the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Chunagon→統一表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>足利尊氏によって光明天皇が擁立されると、改めて権中納言に任じられて、以後北朝 (日本)の有能な実務官僚として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Komyo ascended the throne under Takauji ASHIKAGA, he was reinstated as Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) and later played an active role as a skilled administrative bureaucrat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Komyo ascended the throne under Takauji ASHIKAGA, he was reinstated as Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) and later played an active role as a skilled administrative bureaucrat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Komyo ascended the throne under Takauji ASHIKAGA, he was reinstated as Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state) and later played an active role as a skilled administrative bureaucrat of the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>Gon Chunagon→統一表記に修正、「北朝 (日本)の」を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>建武 (日本)4年（延元3年）、権大納言に上った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1337, he was promoted as Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1337, he was promoted as Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1337, he was promoted as Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagon→既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>貞和2年（正平元年）、一旦は引退したものの2年後には光明上皇の、さらに観応の擾乱後には崇光天皇の院別当を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retired in 1346, but 2 years later he became In no betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) for retired Emperor Komyo, and after the Kanno Disturbance, for Emperor Suko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retired in 1346, but 2 years later he became In no betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) for retired Emperor Komyo, and after the Kanno Disturbance, for Emperor Suko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retired in 1346, but two years later he became In no betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) for the Retired Emperor Komyo, and after the Kanno Disturbance, for Emperor Suko.</e>
<cmt>&quot;2&quot;をスペルアウト、the Retired Emperor Komyoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>文和2年死去、死因は赤痢であると伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1353 and his cause of death is said to be dysentery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1353 and his cause of death was said to have been caused by dysentery.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1353 and his cause of death was said to have been caused by dysentery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 無言雀師(id:13124), MIsogi(id:20599), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>