<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>二階堂行政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimasa NIKAIDO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukimasa NIKAIDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukimasa NIKAIDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二階堂 行政（にかいどう ゆきまさ、生没年不詳）は、鎌倉幕府の政所令・後に別当、十三人の合議制の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimasa NIKAIDO (year of birth and death unknown) held the office of Mandokoro-rei (later called Mandokoro Betto [administrator of a Buddhist temple]), a member of the １3-person parliament during the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>政所令：http://hamuzo001.web.infoseek.co.jp/kamareki.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukimasa NIKAIDO (year of birth and death unknown) held the office of Mandokoro-rei (later called Mandokoro Betto [administrator of a Buddhist temple]), a member of the １3-person parliament during the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukimasa NIKAIDO (year of birth and death unknown) held the office of Mandokoro-rei (later called Mandokoro Betto [administrator of a Buddhist temple]), a member of the １3-person parliament during the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>代々政所執事を務めた二階堂氏の祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the founder of the NIKAIDO clan which had succeeded to the post of Mandokoro (the chief of Mandokoro, the Administrative Board) for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the founder of the NIKAIDO clan which had succeeded to the post of Mandokoro (the chief of Mandokoro, the Administrative Board) for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the founder of the NIKAIDO clan which had succeeded to the post of Mandokoro (the chief of Mandokoro, the Administrative Board) for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後に鎌倉二階堂に屋敷を構えたことから二階堂の姓を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he later took up his residence in Nikaido, Kamakura, his clan was named NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he later took up his residence in Nikaido, Kamakura, his clan was named NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he later took up his residence in Nikaido, Kamakura, his clan was named NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>家系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>家系は藤原南家藤原乙麻呂流で父は藤原行遠、母は源頼朝の外祖父熱田大宮司藤原季範の妹であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With his family line starting with FUJIWARA no Otomaro; his father was 行遠 FUJIWARA and his mother was the younger sister of Yoritomo MINAMOTO&apos;s maternal grandfather, FUJIWARA no Suenori who held the office of Atsuta daiguji (the highest priest serving at Atsuta Shrine in Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>藤原行遠: 読み方不明です。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With his family line starting with FUJIWARA no Otomaro; his father was FUJIWARA no Yukito and his mother was the younger sister of Yoritomo MINAMOTO&apos;s maternal grandfather, FUJIWARA no Suenori who held the office of Atsuta daiguji (the highest priest serving at Atsuta Shrine in Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>「藤原行遠」　→　「ふじわらのゆきとお」　→　『FUJIWARA no Yukito』と、訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With his family line starting with FUJIWARA no Otomaro; his father was FUJIWARA no Yukito and his mother was the younger sister of Yoritomo MINAMOTO&apos;s maternal grandfather, FUJIWARA no Suenori who held the office of Atsuta daiguji (the highest priest serving at Atsuta Shrine in Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>行政はその関係から頼朝に登用されたと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered Yukimasa was employed by Yoritomo through this maternal connection.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered Yukimasa was employed by Yoritomo through this maternal connection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered Yukimasa was employed by Yoritomo through this maternal connection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>「尊卑分脈・二階堂系図」によれば維遠、維行が駿河守、維頼が遠江権守で代々従五位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Sonpi Bunmyaku&apos; (a text that records the lineages of the aristocracy) and &apos;Family Tree of the NIKAIDO clan&apos;, the NIKAIDO family had been ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) for generations; 維遠 and 維行 served as Suruga no kami (the governor of Suruga Province) and 維頼 worked as Totoumi gon no kami (the governor of Totoumi Province).</e>
<cmt>維遠、維行、維頼：読み方不明です。遠江権守：定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Sonpi Bunmyaku&apos; (a text that records the lineages of the aristocracy) and &apos;Family Tree of the NIKAIDO clan&apos;, the NIKAIDO family had been ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) for generations; Koreto and Koreyuki served as Suruga no kami (the governor of Suruga Province) and Koreyori worked as Totoumi gon no kami (the governor of Totoumi Province).</e>
<cmt>「維遠」→「これとお」→『Koreto』、「維行」→「これゆき」→『Koreyuki』、「維頼」→「これより」→『Koreyori』と、訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Sonpi Bunmyaku&apos; (a text that records the lineages of the aristocracy) and &apos;Family Tree of the NIKAIDO clan&apos;, the NIKAIDO family had been ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) for generations; Koreto and Koreyuki served as Suruga no kami (the governor of Suruga Province) and Koreyori worked as Totoumi gon no kami (the governor of Totoumi Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「続群書類従・工藤二階堂系図」では維遠、維行、維頼、行遠の4代が遠江守に任官したことになっているが、いずれも二階堂氏として家を興した後に作成された系図であろうことから割り引いて考える必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the records of &apos;Zoku Gunshoruiju&apos; (The Collection of Historical Sources, second series) and &apos;Family Tree of the KUDONIKAIDO clan&apos; show that four generations of the NIKAIDO family from 維遠, 維行, 維頼 to 行遠 served as Totoumi no kami (the governor of Totoumi Province), both records were created after the establishment of the NIKAIDO clan and therefore, there is a possibility that these descriptions might be fabricated in some parts.</e>
<cmt>「割り引いて考える必要がある」：曖昧な記述のため、訳出では文章を変えています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the records of &apos;Zoku Gunshoruiju&apos; (The Collection of Historical Sources, second series) and &apos;Family Tree of the KUDONIKAIDO clan&apos; show that four generations of the NIKAIDO family from Koreto, Koreyuki, Koreyori to Yukito served as Totoumi no kami (the governor of Totoumi Province), both records could be created after the establishment of the NIKAIDO clan therefore these descriptions might be fabricated in some parts.</e>
<cmt>・「維遠」→「これとお」→『Koreto』、「維行」→「これゆき」→『Koreyuki』、「維頼」→「これより」→『Koreyori』、「行遠」→「ゆきとお」→『Yukito』に、訳出しました。・「were created」　→　『could be created』・「and therefore, there is a possibility that these descriptions might be fabricated in some parts.」 →　『therefore these descriptions might be fabricated in some parts.』に変更修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the records of &apos;Zoku Gunshoruiju&apos; (The Collection of Historical Sources, second series) and &apos;Family Tree of the KUDONIKAIDO clan&apos; show that four generations of the NIKAIDO family from Koreto, Koreyuki, Koreyori to Yukito served as Totoumi no kami (the governor of Totoumi Province), both records could be created after the establishment of the NIKAIDO clan therefore these descriptions might be fabricated in some parts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ただし父は藤原行遠は保延年間（1135～1141年）に遠江国司を殺害して尾張に流配されており、そのときに熱田大宮司藤原季範の妹との間に行政が生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it is recorded that his father, 行遠 FUJIWARA, was deported to Owari in Hoen Era (1135 - 1141) for his killing of the provincial governor of Totoumi Province, and Yukimasa was born to the younger sister of FUJIWARA no Suenori, the Atsuta daiguji in Owari Province, during that period.</e>
<cmt>行遠：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And it is recorded that his father, FUJIWARA no Yukito, was deported to Owari in the Hoen Era (1135 - 1141) for his killing of the provincial governor of Totoumi Province, and Yukimasa was born to the younger sister of FUJIWARA no Suenori, the Atsuta daiguji in Owari Province, during that period.</e>
<cmt>・「行遠 FUJIWARA」→『FUJIWARA no Yukito』に、訳出しました。・「Hoen Era」　→　『the Hoen Era』に、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And it is recorded that his father, FUJIWARA no Yukito, was deported to Owari in the Hoen Era (1135 - 1141) for his killing of the provincial governor of Totoumi Province, and Yukimasa was born to the younger sister of FUJIWARA no Suenori, the Atsuta daiguji in Owari Province, during that period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>藤原季範の父は「尊卑分脈」によれば三河に住みながら尾張目代を務めており、当時の受領国司の子弟が、在地に勢力を張るという図式に当てはめれば、行政の祖父らは遠江・駿河などに留住してある程度の勢力を持っていたのかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, given that the father of FUJIWARA no Suenori assumed the post of Mokudai (a deputy provincial governor) of Owari Province while continuing living in Mikawa (according to &apos;Sonpi Bunmyaku&apos;) and that it was common in this period of time that children of a provincial governor had a big influence on their ruling areas, it is possible the grandfather wielded a certain amount of power in Totoumi and Suruga without leaving these areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, given that the father of FUJIWARA no Suenori assumed the post of Mokudai (a deputy provincial governor) of Owari Province while continuing living in Mikawa (according to &apos;Sonpi Bunmyaku&apos;) and that it was common in this period of time that children of a provincial governor had a big influence on their ruling areas, it is possible the grandfather wielded a certain amount of power in Totoumi and Suruga without leaving these areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, given that the father of FUJIWARA no Suenori assumed the post of Mokudai (a deputy provincial governor) of Owari Province while continuing living in Mikawa (according to &apos;Sonpi Bunmyaku&apos;) and that it was common in this period of time that children of a provincial governor had a big influence on their ruling areas, it is possible the grandfather wielded a certain amount of power in Totoumi and Suruga without leaving these areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉での経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career in Kamakura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career in Kamakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career in Kamakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>行政の『吾妻鏡』での初見は1184年（元暦元年）8月24日条であり、新造の公文所棟上げの奉行として三善康信とともに登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Yukinari first appeared with MIYOSHI no Yasunobu in the article of August 24 in 1184 of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East; a chronicle of the early history of the Kamakura bakufu [Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun]) as a muneage bugyo (ridgepole-raising shogunate administrator) of a newly-built Kumonjo (an administration office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Yukinari first appeared in Article August 24 of 1184 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East; a chronicle of the early history of the Kamakura bakufu [Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun]) as a muneage bugyo (ridgepole-raising shogunate administrator) of a newly-built Kumonjo (an administration office) along with MIYOSHI no Yasunobu.</e>
<cmt>・「with MIYOSHI no Yasunobu」　→　『along with MIYOSHI no Yasunobu』に修正し、文末に移動しました。・「the article of August 24 in 1184 of」　→　『Article August 24 of 1184 in』に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Yukinari first appeared in Article August 24 of 1184 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East; a chronicle of the early history of the Kamakura bakufu [Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun]) as a muneage bugyo (ridgepole-raising shogunate administrator) of a newly-built Kumonjo (an administration office) along with MIYOSHI no Yasunobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>おそらくはこの少し前に鎌倉に下向し、頼朝に仕えたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he left for Kamakura to serve Yoritomo a little while before that date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that he left for Kamakura to serve Yoritomo a little while before that date.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that he left for Kamakura to serve Yoritomo a little while before that date.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同年10月6日条の新造公文所の吉書始では、別当大江広元（当時は中原）の元に寄人として列席している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kissho-hajime (the ceremony announcing the start of new official works) of a newly-built Kumonjo in October 6, 1184, he joined the ceremony as a yoriudo (an officer for Kumonjo) under the bettor, OE no Hiromoto (then called, NAKAHARA no Hiromoto).</e>
<cmt>http://dspace.lib.kanazawa-u.ac.jp/dspace/bitstream/2297/19760/1/AN00044830-52-1-1.pdfhttp://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/200522/m0u/%E5%AF%84%E4%BA%BA/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kissho-hajime (the ceremony announcing the start of new official works) of a newly-built Kumonjo in October 6, 1184, he participated in the ceremony as a yoriudo (an officer for Kumonjo) under the bettor, OE no Hiromoto (then called, NAKAHARA no Hiromoto).</e>
<cmt>「joined」　→　『participated in』に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kissho-hajime (the ceremony announcing the start of new official works) of a newly-built Kumonjo in October 6, 1184, he participated in the ceremony as a yoriudo (an officer for Kumonjo) under the bettor, OE no Hiromoto (then called, NAKAHARA no Hiromoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>1189年（文治5年）の奥州合戦では、『吾妻鏡』9月7日条の藤原泰衡の郎従由利八郎を生虜った件での相論を奉行し、また、その翌日の9月8日条には、朝廷への奥州合戦の次第を報告するにあたってそれを行政が書いたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the article of September 7, 1189 from &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, Yukimasa was in charge of settling a dispute of an incident related to Hachiro YURI (a retainer of FUJIWARA no Yasuhira) who was captured in September 7 during the Battle of Oshu of 1189, and also the article of September 8 says that he compiled a report on the Battle of Oshu to be delivered to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Article September 7 of 1189 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, Yukimasa was in charge of settling a dispute of an incident related to Hachiro YURI (a retainer of FUJIWARA no Yasuhira) who was captured in September 7 during the Battle of Oshu of 1189, and also Article September 8 says that he compiled a report on the Battle of Oshu to be delivered to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>・「the article of September 7, 1189 from &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;」　→　『Article September 7 of 1189 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;』に変更しました。・「the article of September 8」　→　『Article September 8』に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Article September 7 of 1189 in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, Yukimasa was in charge of settling a dispute of an incident related to Hachiro YURI (a retainer of FUJIWARA no Yasuhira) who was captured in September 7 during the Battle of Oshu of 1189, and also Article September 8 says that he compiled a report on the Battle of Oshu to be delivered to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>五味文彦はこの奥州合戦の軍奉行は行政であったのだろうとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumihiko GOMI speculates that Yukinari was a military commissioner in the Battle of Oshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fumihiko GOMI speculated that Yukinari was a military commissioner in the Battle of Oshu.</e>
<cmt>・「speculates」　→　『speculated』に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fumihiko GOMI speculated that Yukinari was a military commissioner in the Battle of Oshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>その翌年の1190年（建久元年）9月15日条の源頼朝の上洛では路次の事、貢金、その他全体の雑事を沙汰する諸事奉行人の筆頭に行政の名が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article of September 15, 1190 which describes the MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s visit to Kyoto, Yukinari was listed as the head of bugyonin (magistrates) who oversaw various matters including routes to take, money and other miscellaneous things.</e>
<cmt>貢金：意味不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Article September 15 of 1190 which describes the MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s visit to Kyoto, Yukinari was listed as the head of bugyonin (magistrates) who supervised various matters including routes to take, money and other miscellaneous things.</e>
<cmt>・「the article of September 15, 1190」　→　『Article September 15 of 1190』に変更しました。・「oversaw」 →　『supervised』に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Article September 15 of 1190 which describes the MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s visit to Kyoto, Yukinari was listed as the head of bugyonin (magistrates) who supervised various matters including routes to take, money and other miscellaneous things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その他、この時期『吾妻鏡』に見える沙汰等に行政の名が多く見られ、『吾妻鏡』1191年（建久2年）1月15日条に政所では別当・大江広元に次ぐ政所令として「主計の允藤原朝臣行政」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he was frequently named as Sata (an officer in charge of enforcing a lord&apos;s order) in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, and in the article of January 15, 1191, he was referred to as &apos;the accountant, FUJIWARA no Asomi Yukinari&apos;, which position was ranked second to Betto, OE no Hiromoto.</e>
<cmt>「政所令として」：省略しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he was frequently named as Sata (an officer in charge of enforcing a lord&apos;s order) in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, and in Article January 15 of 1191, he was referred to as &apos;the accountant, FUJIWARA no Asomi Yukinari&apos;, which position was ranked second to Betto, OE no Hiromoto.</e>
<cmt>「the article of January 15, 1191」　→　『Article January 15 of 1191』に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he was frequently named as Sata (an officer in charge of enforcing a lord&apos;s order) in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, and in Article January 15 of 1191, he was referred to as &apos;the accountant, FUJIWARA no Asomi Yukinari&apos;, which position was ranked second to Betto, OE no Hiromoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後の1193年（建久4年）、五位に叙され民部大夫と呼ばれるようになり、同年政所別当が複数制になった時に別当に昇格した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1193, he was conferred Goi (Fifth Rank) and called Minbu no Taifu, and promoted to Betto when Mandokoro bettor employed a multiple-Betto system the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1193, he was conferred Goi (Fifth Rank) and called Minbu no Taifu, and promoted to Betto when Mandokoro bettor employed a multiple-Betto system the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1193, he was conferred Goi (Fifth Rank) and called Minbu no Taifu, and promoted to Betto when Mandokoro bettor employed a multiple-Betto system the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>1199年（正治元年）4月12日条には頼朝の跡を継いだ源頼家が直に諸訴論に関与することを停止し、13人の重臣が合議して決定することになったとあるが、その中に民部大夫行政の名も入っており、大江広元、三善康信と並んで初期鎌倉政権を支えた実務官僚であったことが解る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the article of April 12, 1199 when MINAMOTO no Yoriie who succeeded Yoritomo decided to stop the direct involvement in lawsuits, and 13 senior vassals became in charge of settling a matter through discussion, Minbu no Taifu Yukinari was listed among the vassals along with OE no Hiromoto and MIYOSHI no Yasunobu, indicating that Yukimasa was one of the governmental bureaucrats responsible for practical work to support the early stage of the Kamakura Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Article April 12 of 1199 which MINAMOTO no Yoriie who succeeded Yoritomo decided to stop the direct involvement in lawsuits, and 13 senior vassals became in charge of settling a matter through discussion, Minbu no Taifu Yukinari was listed among the vassals along with OE no Hiromoto and MIYOSHI no Yasunobu, indicating that Yukimasa was one of the governmental bureaucrats responsible for practical work to support the early stage of the Kamakura Government.</e>
<cmt>・「the article of April 12, 1199 when」　→　『Article April 12 of 1199 which』に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Article April 12 of 1199 which MINAMOTO no Yoriie who succeeded Yoritomo decided to stop the direct involvement in lawsuits, and 13 senior vassals became in charge of settling a matter through discussion, Minbu no Taifu Yukinari was listed among the vassals along with OE no Hiromoto and MIYOSHI no Yasunobu, indicating that Yukimasa was one of the governmental bureaucrats responsible for practical work to support the early stage of the Kamakura Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>その子孫は二階堂を名乗り、二階堂行光系が政所執事をほぼ世襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendants used the surname of NIKAIDO and the direct descendants of Yukimitsu NIKAIDO assumed the post of Mandokoro for generations almost exclusively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants used the surname of NIKAIDO and the direct descendants of Yukimitsu NIKAIDO assumed the post of Mandokoro for generations almost exclusively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants used the surname of NIKAIDO and the direct descendants of Yukimitsu NIKAIDO assumed the post of Mandokoro for generations almost exclusively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>またもう一人の子二階堂行村は1213年 （建暦3）和田合戦における5月4日条においてに「山城判官行村奉行たり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another child, Yukimura NIKAIDO, served as a military commissioner and compiled a record of the Battle of WADA and a list of rewards given to soldiers, as shown in the article of May 4, 1213 written during the Battle of Wada.</e>
<cmt>原文が複雑で訳文に従って、修正できませんでしたの。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another child, Yukimura NIKAIDO, served as a military commissioner and compiled a record of the Battle of WADA and a list of rewards given to soldiers, as shown in the Article May 4 of 1213 written during the Battle of Wada.</e>
<cmt>「the article of May 4, 1213」　→　『the Article May 4 of 1213』に変更しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another child, Yukimura NIKAIDO, served as a military commissioner and compiled a record of the Battle of WADA and a list of rewards given to soldiers, as shown in the Article May 4 of 1213 written during the Battle of Wada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>行親・忠家これを相副う」とあり、軍奉行として合戦記・論功行彰を取り纏めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article describes that he was &apos;a judge of Yamashiro Province. Yukichika and Tadaie supported him.&apos;</e>
<cmt>行親：読み方不明です。（Yukichikaとしました）相副う：意味不明のため訳出があいまいです。原文が複雑で訳文に従って、修正できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The article describes that &apos;he was a judge of Yamashiro Province and Yukichika and Tadaie supported him.&apos;</e>
<cmt>・「he was &apos;a judge」　→　『&apos;he was a judge』に変更しました。・二文を一文にしました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The article describes that &apos;he was a judge of Yamashiro Province and Yukichika and Tadaie supported him.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この家は代々検非違使を世襲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This family had succeeded to the post of Kebiishi (officials with judicial and police powers) for generations by heredity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This family had succeeded to the post of Kebiishi (officials with judicial and police powers) for generations by heredity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This family had succeeded to the post of Kebiishi (officials with judicial and police powers) for generations by heredity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>二階堂行政、二階堂行光、二階堂行村の筆録は『吾妻鏡』の編纂において、かなり利用されていると見られており、吾妻鏡　1204年（元久元）9月15日条、1213年 （健保元）12月19日条などには二階堂行光を顕彰する記事も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that many records written by Yukimasa NIKAIDO, Yukimitsu NIKAIDO and Yukimura NIKAIDO were used in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, and some of its articles, such as ones of September 15, 1204 and December 19, 1213, honor Yukimitsu NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that many records written by Yukimasa NIKAIDO, Yukimitsu NIKAIDO and Yukimura NIKAIDO were used in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, and some of its descriptions, such as ones in the Article September 15 of 1204 and December 19 of 1213, honor Yukimitsu NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>・「its articles」　→　『descriptions』に変更しました。・「such as ones of September 15, 1204 and December 19, 1213」　→　『such as ones in the Article September 15 of 1204 and December 19 of 1213,』に変更修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that many records written by Yukimasa NIKAIDO, Yukimitsu NIKAIDO and Yukimura NIKAIDO were used in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, and some of its descriptions, such as ones in the Article September 15 of 1204 and December 19 of 1213, honor Yukimitsu NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Raad(id:4918), 水野白楓(id:22811), Ktmchi(id:113301), 味っ子(id:17086), Shimoxx(id:9332), Andee(id:20421), BAKU(id:55205), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>