<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源頼家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoriie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoriie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoriie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 頼家（みなもと の よりいえ）は、鎌倉幕府第2代征夷大将軍（鎌倉殿）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoriie was the second Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoriie was the second Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura)).</e>
<cmt>fixed &quot;Seii Taishogun&quot; to match the word list;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoriie was the second Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉幕府を開いた源頼朝の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who founded Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who had founded Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;had&quot; before &quot;founded&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who had founded Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は北条政子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>父頼朝の急死により18歳で家督を相続し、鎌倉幕府の第2代鎌倉殿、征夷大将軍となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded the head of the family at the age of eighteen because of his father&apos;s sudden death, and became the second Kamakura-dono and Seitaishogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie succeeded the head of the family at the age of eighteen due to his father&apos;s sudden death, and became the second Kamakura-dono and Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>Seitaishogun→Seii Taishogun; changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot; since this is a new paragraph</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie succeeded the head of the family at the age of eighteen due to his father&apos;s sudden death, and became the second Kamakura-dono and Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>若年の頼家による従来の習慣を無視した独裁的判断が御家人たちの反発を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dictatorial overtone of young Yoriie who ignored conventional customs led to the objections of gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dictatorial overtone of young Yoriie, who ignored conventional customs, led to the objections of the gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate throughout the Kamakura, Muromachi and Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>added commas; fixed content in parenthesis to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dictatorial overtone of young Yoriie, who ignored conventional customs, led to the objections of the gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate throughout the Kamakura, Muromachi and Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>疎外された母方の北条氏を中心として十三人の合議制がしかれ、頼家の独断は抑えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Yoriie was alienated by his mother and the Hojo clan, his maternal family, held a council system of thirteen members which suppressed his dictator.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Yoriie was alienated by his maternal family, the Hojo clan, and they held a council system with thirteen members to suppress his dictatorship.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Yoriie was alienated by his maternal family, the Hojo clan, and they held a council system with thirteen members to suppress his dictatorship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>その後頼家の後ろ盾である比企氏と、弟の源実朝を担ぐ北条氏との対立が起こり、北条氏一派の攻撃により比企氏は滅亡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, a conflict between the Hiki clan who was a backing of Yoriie and the Hojo clan which supported his brother MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was created, and the Hiki clan was subverted by attacks of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, there was a conflict between the Hiki clan, who backed Yoriie, with the Hojo clan, who supported his brother MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, and the Hiki clan was subverted by attacks from the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, there was a conflict between the Hiki clan, who backed Yoriie, with the Hojo clan, who supported his brother MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, and the Hiki clan was subverted by attacks from the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>頼家は将軍職を剥奪され、伊豆国修禅寺に幽閉されたのち、北条氏の手により暗殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie was deprived the shogunate and was killed by the Hojo clan after a confinement at the Shuzen-ji Temple in the Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie was deprived of the shogunate and was killed by the Hojo clan after being confined in the Shuzen-ji Temple in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie was deprived of the shogunate and was killed by the Hojo clan after being confined in the Shuzen-ji Temple in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>頼家追放により、北条氏が鎌倉幕府の実権を握る事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo clan became to have a real power of the Kamakura bakufu by an exile of Yoriie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan came to have the real power of the Kamakura bakufu with the exile of Yoriie.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;by&quot; to &quot;with&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo clan came to have the real power of the Kamakura bakufu with the exile of Yoriie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>源氏の御曹司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An Onzoshi (son of a distinguished family) of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie was an Onzoshi (son of a distinguished family) of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Yoriie&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie was an Onzoshi (son of a distinguished family) of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>寿永元年（1182年）8月12日、源頼朝の嫡男として鎌倉比企ヶ谷の比企能員の屋敷で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 18, 1182, he was born as the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo at the residence of Yoshikazu HIKI in Hikigayatsu, Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 18, 1182, Yoriie was born as the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo at the residence of Yoshikazu HIKI in Hikigayatsu, Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;he&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 18, 1182, Yoriie was born as the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo at the residence of Yoshikazu HIKI in Hikigayatsu, Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>幼名は万寿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Manju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Manju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Manju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>母は正室の北条政子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Masako HOJO, the legitimate wife of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother, Masako HOJO, was the legitimate wife of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>added a comma and rearranged the sentence to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother, Masako HOJO, was the legitimate wife of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>頼朝36歳、鎌倉入り3年目に待望の源氏の御曹司として、周囲の祝福を一身に受けての誕生であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Yoritomo was thirty-six years old.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoritomo was thirty-six years old, three years after moving to Kamakura, Yoriie was born as the long-awaited Onzoshi of the Minamoto clan and his birth received a tremendous celebration by the people.</e>
<cmt>待望 - long-awaited; combined with the sentence below to reduce sentence fragmentation; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoritomo was thirty-six years old, three years after moving to Kamakura, Yoriie was born as the long-awaited Onzoshi of the Minamoto clan and his birth received a tremendous celebration by the people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>政子が頼家を妊娠した際、頼朝は安産祈祷のため鶴岡八幡宮若宮大路の整備を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masako became pregnant of Yoriie, Yoritomo had Wakamiya-oji Street around Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine repaired.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masako became pregnant with Yoriie, Yoritomo had Wakamiya-oji Street around Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine repaired.</e>
<cmt>of→with;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masako became pregnant with Yoriie, Yoritomo had Wakamiya-oji Street around Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine repaired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>有力御家人たちが土や石を運んで段葛を作り、頼朝が自ら監督を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major gokenin had dankazura (a road which is one step higher than other areas) built by soil and stones, and Yoritomo himself directed the construction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influential gokenin had a dankazura (a road which is one step higher than other areas) built by soil and stones with Yoritomo himself directing the construction.</e>
<cmt>directed→directing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influential gokenin had a dankazura (a road which is one step higher than other areas) built by soil and stones with Yoritomo himself directing the construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>頼家の乳母父には頼朝の乳母であった比企尼の養子である比企能員が選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikazu HIKI, an adopted son of Hikinoama who was menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) of Yoritomo, was selected for Yoriie&apos;s menoto-fu (generally a husband of menoto), and the second daughter of Hikinoama (a wife of Shigeyori KAWAGOE) was selected for his menoto at the time of the ceremony of first breast-feeding.</e>
<cmt>「乳母父」の読み方不明です。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikazu HIKI, the adopted son of Hikinoama, who had acted as Yoritomo&apos;s menoto (a wet-nurse for a highborn baby), was selected as Yoriie&apos;s menoto-fu (generally the husband of a menoto). Hikinoama&apos;s second daughter (the wife of Shigeyori KAWAGOE) was chosen as menoto for Yoriie during the ceremony of first breast-feeding.</e>
<cmt>The sentence is so confusing I had to split it into two to make it comprehensible</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikazu HIKI, the adopted son of Hikinoama, who had acted as Yoritomo&apos;s menoto (a wet-nurse for a highborn baby), was selected as Yoriie&apos;s menoto-fu (generally the husband of a menoto).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」Yoritomo’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>乳母には最初の乳付の儀式に比企尼の次女（河越重頼室）が呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikinoama&apos;s second daughter (the wife of Shigeyori KAWAGOE) was chosen as menoto for Yoriie during the ceremony of first breast-feeding.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>（乳母には）梶原景時の妻の他、比企尼の三女（平賀義信室）、能員の妻など、主に比企氏の一族から選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His menoto were selected mainly from the Hiki clan such as the wife of Kagetoki KAJIWARA, the third daughter of Hikinoama (a wife of Yoshinobu HIRAGA) and Yoshikazu&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie&apos;s menoto were mainly selected from the Hiki clan, such as the wife of Kagetoki KAJIWARA, the third daughter of Hikinoama (the wife of Yoshinobu HIRAGA) and Yoshikazu&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;he&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie&apos;s menoto were mainly selected from the Hiki clan, such as the wife of Kagetoki KAJIWARA, the third daughter of Hikinoama (the wife of Yoshinobu HIRAGA) and Yoshikazu&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>建久4年（1193年）5月、富士山の裾野で行われた巻狩りで、12歳の頼家が初めて鹿を射ると、頼朝は喜んで政子に報告の使いを送り、武士の子なら当たり前の事であるとたしなめられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoriie shoot a deer for the first time at the age of twelve in Makigari (Hunting session) at the foot of Mt.Fuji on June 1193, Yoritomo was delighted and sent a messenger to Masako and was reproved as &apos;it is natural for a son of samurai.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of 1193 when Yoriie shot a deer for the first time at the age of twelve during Makigari (a hunt where the hunting area is surrounded on four sides by hunters) at the foot of Mt.Fuji, Yoritomo was delighted and sent a messenger to Masako reproving that &apos;it is natural for the son of samurai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>shoot→shot; 巻狩り definition found at &lt;http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~jwb/cgi-bin/wwwjdic.cgi?1F&gt;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of 1193 when Yoriie shot a deer for the first time at the age of twelve during Makigari (a hunt where the hunting area is surrounded on four sides by hunters) at the foot of Mt.Fuji, Yoritomo was delighted and sent a messenger to Masako reproving that &apos;it is natural for the son of samurai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この巻狩りで曾我兄弟の仇討ちが起こり、叔父の源範頼が頼朝に謀反の疑いを受けて流罪となったのち誅殺されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this Makigari, there happened the revenge of Soga brothers and their uncle MINAMOTO no Noriyori was killed by a crime of a rebellion by Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Soga brothers had their revenge at this makigari when their uncle, MINAMOTO no Noriyori, was suspected of treason, and after being exiled Yoritomo had him executed as a criminal.</e>
<cmt>I could not understand translation 1 so I did the translation on my own and restructured the sentence. What this sentence is referring to still not clear to me since the &quot;Soga brothers&quot; are mentioned no where else in the article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this makigari, the Soga brothers&apos; revenge took place and their uncle, MINAMOTO no Noriyori, was suspected of treason, and after being exiled Yoritomo had him executed as a criminal.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容が明確になるよう一部訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>建久6年（1195年）2月、頼朝は政子と頼家・大姫を伴って上洛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 1195, Yoritomo went up to Kyoto with Masako, Yoriie and Ohime (the eldest daughter of Yoritomo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March of 1195, Yoritomo went up to Kyoto with Masako, Yoriie and Ohime (the eldest daughter of Yoritomo).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;On&quot; to &quot;in&quot; and added &quot;of&quot; before &quot;1195&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of 1195, Yoritomo went up to Kyoto with Masako, Yoriie and Ohime (the eldest daughter of Yoritomo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>頼家は6月3日と24日に参内し、都で頼朝の後継者としての披露が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie made sandai (a visit to the Imperial Palace) on July 18 and August 8, and was introduced as a heir of Yoritomo at the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie made sandai (a visit to the Imperial Palace) on July 18 and August 8, and was introduced as the heir of Yoritomo at the capital.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;a&quot; to &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie made sandai (a visit to the Imperial Palace) on July 18 and August 8, and was introduced as the heir of Yoritomo at the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>建久8年（1197年）、16歳で従五位近衛府に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1197 he was conferred Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards) at the age of sixteen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1197 he was conferred the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and given the post of Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards) at the age of sixteen.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more grammatically</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1197 he was conferred the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and given the post of Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards) at the age of sixteen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>生まれながらの『鎌倉殿』である頼家は、古今に例を見ないほど武芸の達人として成長した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie, who had been &quot;Kamakura-dono&quot; since he was born, became such an excellent master of military art as never seen before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie, who had been &quot;Kamakura-dono&quot; since he was born, grew up to be an excellent master of military arts, the likes of which had never been seen before.</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;such&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie, who had been &quot;Kamakura-dono&quot; since he was born, grew up to be an excellent master of military arts, the likes of which had never been seen before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>第2代将軍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second Shogun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second Shogun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Second Shogun</e>
<cmt>secondの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>建久10年（1199年）1月、父頼朝が急死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 1199, his father Yoritomo died suddenly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 1199, Yoriie&apos;s father Yoritomo suddenly died.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 1199, Yoriie&apos;s father Yoritomo suddenly died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>頼家は18歳で家督を相続し、建仁2年（1202年）に征夷大将軍宣下される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie succeeded the head of the family at the age of eighteen, and was received an imperial proclamation of Seitaishogun in 1202.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie succeeded the head of the family at the age of eighteen, and in 1202 received the imperial proclamation of Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>moved placement of the year; changed &quot;Seii Taishogun&quot; to match the word list; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie succeeded the head of the family at the age of eighteen, and in 1202 received the imperial proclamation of Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>しかし頼家は側近や乳母一族である比企氏を重用し従来の習慣を無視した独裁的判断が目立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoriie emphasized his close advisers and the Hiki clan, the family of menoto, and tended to show a dictatorial attitude which ignored conventional customs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoriie appointed his close advisers from the Hiki clan and the menoto families, and tended to show a dictatorial attitude, ignoring conventional customs.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoriie appointed his close advisers from the Hiki clan and the menoto families, and tended to show a dictatorial attitude, ignoring conventional customs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>疎外された母方の北条氏を中心とした有力御家人は将軍の権力確立を阻むべく十三人の合議制をしき、頼家の独断は抑えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major gokenin including the Hojo clan who was his maternal family and alienated him, held a council system of thirteen members which suppressed the dictator of Yoriie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influential gokenin, includiing the Hojo clan made up of Yoriie&apos;s maternal family, alienated Yoriie and held a council system with thirteen members to suppress his dictatorship.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influential gokenin, includiing the Hojo clan made up of Yoriie&apos;s maternal family, alienated Yoriie and held a council system with thirteen members to suppress his dictatorship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>反発した頼家は小笠原長経、比企宗朝、比企時員、中野能成以下若い近習5人を指名して、彼らでなければ自分への目通りを許さず、またこれに手向かってはならないという命令を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie was opposed to this, appointed the young five kinju (attendant) including Nagatsune OGASAWARA, Munetomo HIKI, Tokikazu HIKI and Yoshinari NAKANO, and forbade to meet other people except them and ordered not to be opposed to them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie, who opposed the council, appointed five young kinju (attendants), including Nagatsune OGASAWARA, Munetomo HIKI, Tokikazu HIKI and Yoshinari NAKANO, and made it forbidden for anyone to have audience with him except for his kinju, and ordered them to never oppose him.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie, who opposed the council, appointed five young kinju (attendants), including Nagatsune OGASAWARA, Munetomo HIKI, Tokikazu HIKI and Yoshinari NAKANO, and made it forbidden for anyone to have audience with him except for his kinju, and ordered them to never oppose him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>頼朝が死去して数ヶ月後の秋、頼朝の代から側近として重用されていた侍所長官の梶原景時が、頼家の弟である源実朝を将軍に立てようとする陰謀があると頼家に報告する（『玉葉』正治2年正月2日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the autumn of a few month after the death of Yoritomo, Kagetoki KAJIWARA who was the head of Samurai-dokoro (the Board of Retainers) and had been given an important post since the era of Yoritomo, told Yoriie that there was a conspiracy to put up MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, Yoriie&apos;s brother, as Shogun (in the section of twenty-six January, 1200 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the autumn a few months after the death of Yoritomo, Kagetoki KAJIWARA, head of the Samurai-dokoro (the Board of Retainers) who had held an important post since the era of Yoritomo, informed Yoriie of a conspiracy to put up Yoriie&apos;s brother, MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, as Shogun (from the section on the twenty-sixth of January, 1200 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO)).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the autumn a few months after the death of Yoritomo, Kagetoki KAJIWARA, head of the Samurai-dokoro (the Board of Retainers) who had held an important post since the era of Yoritomo, informed Yoriie of a conspiracy to put up Yoriie&apos;s younger brother, MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, as Shogun (from the section on the second of January, 1200 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (The Diary of Kanezane KUJO)).</e>
<cmt>brother→younger brotherとし、&quot;Diary of&quot;→&quot;The Diary of&quot;に修正twenty-sixth→second(日記の日付通りに変更しました）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし景時に反発する御家人たちにより、御家人66名による景時糾弾の連署が頼家に提出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the countersignature of sixty-six gokenin to condemn Kagetoki was submitted to Yoriie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, countersignatures of sixty-six gokenin were submitted to Yoriie to condemn Kagetoki.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, countersignatures of sixty-six gokenin were submitted to Yoriie to condemn Kagetoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>頼家に弁明を求められた景時は、何の抗弁もせず所領に下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagetoki was requested to explain by Yoriie but went back to his land without no excuse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoriie requested that Kagetoki explain himself, Kagetoki went back to his land without an excuse.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoriie requested that Kagetoki explain himself, Kagetoki went back to his land without an excuse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>謹慎ののち、鎌倉へ戻った景時は政務への復帰を頼家に願ったが、頼家は景時を救う事が出来ず、景時は鎌倉追放を申し渡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagetoki who went back to Kamakura after the house arrest, asked Yoriie to have him come back to an official position, but Yoriie could not help him and Kagetoki was ordered to exile from Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagetoki returned to Kamakura after the house arrest and asked Yoriie to let him come back to an official position, but Yoriie was unable to help and Kagetoki was ordered to exile from Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagetoki returned to Kamakura after the house arrest and asked Yoriie to let him come back to an official position, but Yoriie was unable to help and Kagetoki was ordered to exile from Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>正治2年（1200年）1月20日、失意の景時は一族を率いて京都へ上る道中で在地の御家人達から襲撃を受け、一族もろとも滅亡した（『吾妻鏡』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 13, 1200, broken-hearted Kagetoki was attacked by local gokenin on the way to Kyoto with his family and all of the family was defeated (&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 13, 1200, broken-hearted Kagetoki was attacked by local gokenin on the way to Kyoto and his entire family was killed (&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)).</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 13, 1200, broken-hearted Kagetoki was attacked by local gokenin on the way to Kyoto and his entire family was killed (&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>京都の人々は景時を死なせた事は頼家の大失策であると評した（梶原景時の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People in Kyoto reputed that it was a big mistake of Yoriie to have Kagetoki killed (the Kagetoki Kajiwara Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people of Kyoto criticized Yoriie that it was a serious error to have Kagetoki killed (The Kagetoki Kajiwara Incident).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people of Kyoto criticized Yoriie that it was a serious error to have Kagetoki killed (The Kagetoki Kajiwara Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>景時滅亡の3年後、建仁3年（1203年）5月、頼家は実朝の乳母・阿波局 (北条時政の娘)の夫で頼朝の弟である阿野全成を謀反人の咎で逮捕、殺害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 1203 which was three years after the death of Kagetoki, Yoriie arrested and killed Zenjo ANO who was the husband of Awa no tsubone (Sanetomo&apos;s menoto and a daughter of Tokimasa HOJO) and a brother of Yoritomo, for the crime of rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three years after the death of Kagetoki on June 1203, Yoriie arrested and killed the husband of Awa no tsubone (Sanetomo&apos;s menoto and a daughter of Tokimasa HOJO), Zenjo ANO and a brother of Yoritomo for treason.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;for the crime of rebellion&quot; to &quot;for treason&quot;; added comma; rearranged sentence to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three years after the death of Kagetoki on June 1203, Yoriie arrested and killed Zenjo ANO, who was the husband of Awa no tsubone (Sanetomo&apos;s menoto and a daughter of Tokimasa HOJO) and was a brother of Yoritomo, for treason.</e>
<cmt>「阿野全成」→「阿波局の夫」かつ「頼朝の弟」であるという原文の内容に沿うよう訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>さらに阿波局を逮捕しようとしたが、北条政子が引き渡しを拒否する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he tried to arrest Awa no tsubone, but Masako HOJO rejected to taking-over her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie also tried to arrest Awa no tsubone, but Masako HOJO refused to hand her over.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;In addition&quot; to &quot;also&quot; and placed later in the sentence; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie also tried to arrest Awa no tsubone, but Masako HOJO refused to hand her over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>将軍追放</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banishment of Shogun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banishment of the Shogun</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; to make this more grammatical</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banishment of the Shogun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>7月半ば過ぎから頼家は急病にかかり、8月末に危篤状態に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, Yoriie suffered sudden illness and fell critically ill in the middle of October.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, Yoriie suffered a sudden illness and fell critically ill in the middle of October.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;sudden&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, Yoriie suffered a sudden illness and fell critically ill in the middle of October.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>まだ頼家が存命しているにも関わらず、鎌倉から「9月1日に頼家が病死したので、実朝が後を継いだ」との報告が9月7日早朝に都に届き、実朝の征夷大将軍任命が要請された事が、藤原定家の日記『明月記』の他、複数の京都側の記録で確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some records in Kyoto including &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon) written by FUJIWARA no Teika that a report that &apos;Since Yoriie died of disease on October 14, Sanetomo succeeded Shogun&apos; was delivered in the early morning of October 20 and an appointment of Sanetomo to Seitaishogun was requested, although Yoriie was still living.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some records in Kyoto, including &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon) by FUJIWARA no Teika, that describe the report, &quot;Since Yoriie died of disease on October 14, Sanetomo succeeded the position of Shogun,&quot; that was delivered in the early morning of October 20th and an appointment of Sanetomo to Seii Taishogun was requested even though Yoriie was still alive.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some records in Kyoto, including &quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon) by FUJIWARA no Teika, that describe the report, &apos;Since Yoriie died of disease on October 14, Sanetomo succeeded the position of Shogun,&apos; that was delivered in the early morning of October 20th and an appointment of Sanetomo to Seii Taishogun was requested even though Yoriie was still alive.</e>
<cmt>一部シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>使者が鎌倉を発った前後と思われる9月2日、鎌倉では頼家の乳母父で長男源一幡の外祖父である比企能員が北条時政によって謀殺され、比企一族は滅ぼされた（比企能員の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 15, which was around the day when a messenger left Kamakura to Kyoto, Yoshikazu HIKI who was menoto-fu of Yoriie and maternal grandfather of MINAMOTO no Ichiman, Yoriie&apos;s first son, was murdered by Tokimasa HOJO in Kamakura and the Hiki family was subverted (the Conspiracy of Yoshikazu HIKI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 15, which was around the day when a messenger left Kamakura to Kyoto, Yoshikazu HIKI as the menoto-fu of Yoriie and maternal grandfather of MINAMOTO no Ichiman, Yoriie&apos;s first son, was murdered by Tokimasa HOJO in Kamakura, subverting the Hiki family (the Conspiracy of Yoshikazu HIKI).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 15, which was around the day when a messenger left Kamakura to Kyoto, Yoshikazu HIKI as the menoto-fu of Yoriie and maternal grandfather of MINAMOTO no Ichiman, Yoriie&apos;s first son, was murdered by Tokimasa HOJO in Kamakura, subverting the Hiki family (the Conspiracy of Yoshikazu HIKI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>一人残った頼家は多少病状が回復して事件を知り激怒、時政討伐を命じるが従うものはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie who recovered a little and knew the conspiracy got angry and ordered to kill Tokimasa, but nobody obeyed him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie, who had somewhat recovered, learned of the conspiracy and angrily ordered Tokimasa to be killed but nobody obeyed.</e>
<cmt>fixed graammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie, who had somewhat recovered, learned of the conspiracy and angrily ordered Tokimasa to be killed but nobody obeyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>9月7日鎌倉殿の地位を追われ、実朝がこれに代わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 20, Yoriie was exiled from the position of Kamakura-dono, and Sanetomo succeeded it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 20, Sanetomo succeeded the position of Kamakura-dono when Yoriie became exiled.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 20, Sanetomo succeeded the position of Kamakura-dono when Yoriie became exiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これによって時政は幕府の実権を握る事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For these processes Tokimasa took the helm of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was how Tokimasa took the helm of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>eliminated content in parenthesis since it is already described above; changed &quot;For these processes&quot; to &quot;This was how&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was how Tokimasa took the helm of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>『吾妻鏡』によると、「頼家が重病のため、あとは6歳の長男一幡が継ぎ、日本国総守護と関東28ヶ国の総地頭となり、12歳の源実朝には関西38ヶ国の総地頭を譲ると発表された。しかし実朝に譲られる事に不満を抱いた能員が、実朝と北条氏討伐を企てた」（8月27日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; there are descriptions that &apos;it was announced that since Yoriie was seriously ill, his first son Ichiman who was six years old hired and became So-shugo (master of provincial constables) of Japan and So-jito (manager and lord of manor) of the twenty-eight provinces in Kanto region and MINAMOTO no Sanetomo who was twelve years old became So-jito of the thirty-eight provinces in Kansai region. However, Yoshikazu was against the succession by Sanetomo and planned to kill Sanetomo and the Hojo clan&apos; (in the section of October 10).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; the situation is described as, &quot;It was announced that since Yoriie was seriously ill, his first son Ichiman, who was six years old, was hired and became the So-shugo (Master of Provincial constables) of Japan and So-jito (manager and lord of a manor) of the twenty-eight provinces in the Kanto region, while MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, who was twelve years old, became So-jito of the thirty-eight provinces in the Kansai region. However, Yoshikazu was against Sanetomo&apos;s succession and planned to kill him along with the Hojo clan&quot; (Azuma Kagami on the section under August 27th (October 10th of the current calendar)).</e>
<cmt>I have noticed that many articles do pay attention to calendar differences, but in this case, it occurs to me that it is better to keep the original dates since they are written records; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; the situation is described as, &apos;It was announced that since Yoriie was seriously ill, his first son Ichiman, who was six years old, was hired and became the So-shugo (Master of Provincial constables) of Japan and So-jito (manager and lord of a manor) of the twenty-eight provinces in the Kanto region, while MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, who was twelve years old, became So-jito of the thirty-eight provinces in the Kansai region. However, Yoshikazu was against Sanetomo&apos;s succession and planned to kill him along with the Hojo clan&apos; (Azuma Kagami on the section under August 27th (October 10th of the current calendar)).</e>
<cmt>一部シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>「病床の頼家と能員による北条氏討伐の密議を障子の影で立ち聞きしていた政子が時政に報告し、先手を打った時政は自邸に能員を呼び出して殺害、一幡の屋敷を攻め、比企一族を滅ぼし一幡も焼死した」（9月2日条）としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masako eavesdropped on the conversation to subvert the Hojo clan between sick Yoriie and Yoshikazu and told Tokimasa about it. Tokimasa called Yoshikazu to his residence and killed him in order to preempt it. He attacked the residence of Ichiman and subverted the Hiki clan, and Ichiman was also burned to death&apos; (on the section October 15).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Masako, who eavesdropped through a shoji on the secret conference of the Hojo clan to subjugate Yoriie on his sickbed and Yoshikazu, informed Tokimasa of the plot. Tokimasa called Yoshikazu to his residence and killed him in order to preempt the plan. Then he attacked the residence of Ichiman, destroying the relatives of the Hiki clan and Ichiman was also burned to death&quot; (Azuma Kagami on the section under September 2nd (October 15 of the current calendar)).</e>
<cmt>I could not make clear sense of translation one, so I made my own; added original date and put current date in parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masako, who eavesdropped through a shoji on the secret conference of the Hojo clan to subjugate Yoriie on his sickbed and Yoshikazu, informed Tokimasa of the plot. Tokimasa called Yoshikazu to his residence and killed him in order to preempt the plan. Then he attacked the residence of Ichiman, destroying the relatives of the Hiki clan and Ichiman was also burned to death&apos; (Azuma Kagami on the section under September 2nd (October 15 of the current calendar)).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="46">
<j>京都側の記録である『愚管抄』によれば、頼家は病が重くなったので自分から出家し、あとは全て子の一幡に譲ろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool) which was a record of the Kyoto side, Yoriie hoped to become a priest and passed over all to his son Ichiman because of a serious disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), which was a record of the Kyoto side,Yoriie had hoped to become a priest and pass everything onto his son Ichiman because of a serious disease.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), which was a record of the Kyoto side, Yoriie had hoped to become a priest and pass everything onto his son Ichiman because of a serious disease.</e>
<cmt>スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>これでは比企能員の全盛時代になると恐れた北条時政が能員を呼び出して謀殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokimasa HOJO was afraid of this because Yoshikazu HIKI would have a real power, so that he called Yoshikazu to his residence and killed him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokimasa HOJO was afraid of this because it would give Yoshikazu HIKI real power, so he called Yoshikazu to his residence and killed him.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokimasa HOJO was afraid of this because it would give Yoshikazu HIKI real power, so he called Yoshikazu to his residence and killed him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>病床の頼家を御所から大江広元の屋敷に移してしまい、同時に一幡を殺そうと軍勢を差し向けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokimasa sent troops in order to move Yoriie who was ill in bed from the palace to the residence of OE no Hiromoto, and tried to kill Ichiman.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokimasa sent troops to move a bedridden Yoriie from the palace to the residence of OE no Hiromoto and attempted to kill Ichiman.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokimasa sent troops to move a bedridden Yoriie from the palace to the residence of OE no Hiromoto and attempted to kill Ichiman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>一幡はようやく母が抱いて逃げ延びたが、残る一族は皆討たれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ichiman could escape with his mother, the rest Hiki family was all killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ichiman was able to escape with his mother, the rest of the Hiki family was killed.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ichiman was able to escape with his mother, the rest of the Hiki family was killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>やがて回復した頼家はこれを聞いて激怒、太刀を手に立ち上がったが、政子がこれを押さえ付け、修禅寺に押し込めてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie, who recovered soon, got angry to hear that, and stood up with a sword, but Masako stopped him and confined him to the Shuzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie recovered soon after, and upon hearing this news he picked up his sword and stood up, but was stopped by Masako and confined to the Shuzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie recovered soon after, and upon hearing this news he picked up his sword and stood up, but was stopped by Masako and confined to the Shuzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>11月になって一幡は捕らえられ、北条氏の郎党に刺し殺されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December, Ichiman was arrested and killed by a roto (retainer) of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, Ichiman was arrested and killed by a roto (retainer) of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>On→In</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Ichiman was arrested and killed by a roto (retainer) of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of Yoriie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Death of Yoriie</e>
<cmt>&quot;The end&quot; here is not very specific, so I changed this to &quot;The Death&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Death of Yoriie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>頼家は伊豆国に護送され、翌年の元久元年（1204年）7月18日、北条氏の手兵によって殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie was sent to the Izu Province and was killed on August 21 in the next year, 1204, by the soldiers under the Hojo clan&apos;s command.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie was sent to the Izu Province, and in the following year of 1204 on August 21st, he was killed by soldiers under the command of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie was sent to the Izu Province, and in the following year of 1204 on August 21st, he was killed by soldiers under the command of the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>享年23（満21歳没）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was twenty-three years old in the age by the traditional Japanese system (actually, twenty-one years old).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the traditional Japanese calendar system, he was twenty-three years old (twenty-one years old by today&apos;s calendar).</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the traditional Japanese calendar system, he was twenty-three years old (twenty-one years old by today&apos;s calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>『吾妻鏡』はその死について、ただ飛脚から頼家死去の報があった事を短く記すのみである（7月19日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; only described shortly that there was a report by an express messenger about the death of Yoriie (in the section of August 22).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; only gave a short description of a report by an express messenger about the death of Yoriie (in the section of August 22).</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; only gave a short description of a report by an express messenger about the death of Yoriie (in the section of July 19).</e>
<cmt>August 22→July 19（日記の日付に戻しました）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>殺害当日の日付の『愚管抄』によると、入浴中を襲撃され、激しく抵抗した頼家の首に紐を巻き付け、急所を押さえてようやく刺し殺したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool) &apos;s description on the date of killing, Yoriie was attacked while he was taking a bath and fought hardly, but was stabbed to death after being rolled a rope on the neck and vital point attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a description in the &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), Yoriie was attacked while taking a bath and fought back furiously, but he was stabbed to death after a rope was wound around his neck and the assailants attacked his vitals.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a description in the &quot;Gukansho,&quot; Yoriie was attacked while taking a bath and fought back furiously, but he was stabbed to death after a rope was wound around his neck and the assailants attacked his vitals.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Gukansho&quot;→既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="56">
<j>幽閉先の修禅寺では近隣の子供達と付近の山々を遊びまわったりして子供の面倒見は良かったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he loved children so much as he played with neighborhood kids around the mountains near the Shuzen-ji Temple where he was confined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie allegedly loved children so much that he played with the neighborhood kids living in the mountains near Shuzen-ji Temple where he was confined.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;he&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot; since this is a new paragraph; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie allegedly loved children so much that he played with the neighborhood kids living in the mountains near Shuzen-ji Temple where he was confined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>現代でも愛童将軍地蔵というものが当地には残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remains Aido shogun Jizo (loving child Jizo) there still now.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, there is still an Aido Shogun Jizo (a Jizo statue that means &quot;child-loving&quot; Shogun) in the area.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, there is still an Aido Shogun Jizo (a Jizo statue that means &quot;child-loving&quot; Shogun) in the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reputation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reputation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reputation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>鎌倉幕府北条氏編纂である『吾妻鏡』における頼家像は、遊興にふけり家来の愛妾を寝取る暗君として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The image of Yoriie in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; which was edited by the Hojo clan who had a real power of Kamakura bakufu was described as a foolish ruler who pursued pleasures and engaged in adultery with a favorite concubine of his retainer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image of Yoriie in &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; edited by the Hojo clan who held the real power of Kamakura bakufu, describes him as a foolish ruler who pursued pleasures and engaged in adultery with his favorite concubine.</e>
<cmt>&quot;engaged in adultery with his favorite concubine&quot; seems sufficient for &quot;家来の愛妾を寝取る&quot; so I deleted the awkward ending: &quot;of his retainer&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image of Yoriie in &quot;Azuma Kagami,&quot; edited by the Hojo clan who held the real power of Kamakura bakufu, describes him as a foolish ruler who pursued pleasures and engaged in adultery with his retainer&apos;s favorite concubine.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味に沿うよう、his favorite concubine→his retainer&apos;s favorite concubineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>比企氏滅亡と頼家追放に関する吾妻鏡の記述は、京都側の史料とは明らかな相違がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descriptions of Azuma Kagami on the ruin of the Hiki clan and an exile of Yoriie were clearly different from those in the historical materials written by the side of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descriptions within the &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; on the ruin of the Hiki clan and exile of Yoriie are clearly different from those in historical materials written by the Kyoto side.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descriptions within the Azuma Kagami on the ruin of the Hiki clan and exile of Yoriie are clearly different from those in historical materials written by the Kyoto side.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ、クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>頼家をことさら貶める記述は北条氏による政治的作為と考えられ、そのまま鵜呑みには出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be thought that the descriptions to soil Yoriie intentionally were politically produced by the Hojo clan, so that those can not be understood literally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible to conclude that the descriptions were intentionally produced by the Hojo clan as a political move to soil Yoriie&apos;s image, meaning that they cannot be taken literally.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible to conclude that the descriptions were intentionally produced by the Hojo clan as a political move to soil Yoriie&apos;s image, meaning that they cannot be taken literally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>頼家近習であった中原能成は、比企氏滅亡直後に北条時政から与えられた「比企能員の非法のため、所領を奪い取られたそうだが、とくに特別待遇を与える」という文書が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remains a record that Yoshinari NAKAHARA, Yoriie&apos;s kinju, was &apos;given a special treatment because he had been deprived the land by an enormity of Yoshikazu HIKI&apos; which was given by Tokimasa HOJO soon after the ruin of the Hiki clan, but in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; Yoshinari was described as being deprived the land and exiled because of an implication in Yoriie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a remaining record that describes how Yoshinari NAKAHARA, one of Yoriie&apos;s kinju, was &apos;given special treatment because he had been deprived of land by being cheated by Yoshikazu HIKI&apos; which was written by Tokimasa HOJO soon after the ruin of the Hiki clan. In the &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; however, it is described that Yoshinari&apos;s land was confiscated and he was exiled because of an implication made by Yoriie.</e>
<cmt>According to the sanseido dictionary, &quot;非法&quot; = 法に外れること I used &quot;cheated&quot; for this; changed into two sentences; made some adjustments to the second sentence for better clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a remaining record that describes how Yoshinari NAKAHARA, one of Yoriie&apos;s kinju, was &apos;given special treatment because he had been deprived of land by being cheated by Yoshikazu HIKI&apos; which was written by Tokimasa HOJO soon after the ruin of the Hiki clan.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかし、『吾妻鏡』では能成は頼家に連座して所領を没収され、遠流とされた事になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; however, it is described that Yoshinari&apos;s land was confiscated and he was exiled because of an implication made by Yoriie.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>この能成と深い関係のあった時政の子・北条時房も頼家の蹴鞠の相手となっており、頼家の周辺には北条氏による監視の目があったと見られる（『吾妻鏡吾妻鏡の曲筆と顕彰』も参照の事）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokifusa HOJO, a son of Tokimasa, who had a strong relationship with this Yoshinari was a partner of Yoriie in playing kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period, which shows that Yoriie was watched by the Hojo clan (see also the section of &apos;the contortion and award&apos; of Azuma Kagami in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokifusa HOJO, a son of Tokimasa who had a strong relationship with Yoshinari, was Yoriie&apos;s partner in playing kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period, which shows that Yoriie was watched by the Hojo clan (see also the section of &apos;the contortion and award&apos; of Azuma Kagami in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokifusa HOJO, a son of Tokimasa who had a strong relationship with Yoshinari, was Yoriie&apos;s partner in playing kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period), which shows that Yoriie was watched by the Hojo clan (see also the section of &quot;the contortion and award of Azuma Kagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>カッコの不足分を追加、「吾妻鏡の曲筆と顕彰」の表記を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>頼朝死去の前後、大姫 (源頼朝の娘)入内運動の失敗により朝廷の反幕府派が攻勢を強めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the period of Yoritomo&apos;s death, the failure of the judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) campaign of Ohime (a daughter of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo) strengthened the power of anti-bakufu group in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the period of Yoritomo&apos;s death, the power of the anti-bakufu group in the Imperial Court was strengthened by the failure of the judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) campaign of Ohime (a daughter of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo).</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more understandably</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the period of Yoritomo&apos;s death, the power of the anti-bakufu group in the Imperial Court was strengthened by the failure of the judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) campaign of Ohime (a daughter of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>十三人の合議制がしかれたのは、頼家が頼朝の跡を継いでわずか3ヶ月後であり、頼家の政治能力の欠如によるものとは考えにくい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was only three months after the succession of the position of Yoritomo by Yoriie when the council system by thirteen members was introduced, and consequently, it is difficult to think that it was caused by the lack of a political ability of Yoriie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been only three months after Yoriie had succeeded Yoritomo&apos;s position as Shogun when the council system of thirteen members was introduced, therefore making it improbable that it was formed due to a lack of Yoriie&apos;s abilities.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been only three months after Yoriie had succeeded Yoritomo&apos;s position as Shogun when the council system of thirteen members was introduced, therefore making it improbable that it was formed due to a lack of Yoriie&apos;s abilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>頼家排斥は北条氏の陰謀のみではなく、幕府成立の起動力となった東国武士達の、将軍独裁への鬱積した不満が背景にあったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the expulsion of Yoriie was caused by a pent-up discontent of the samurai in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) which had contributed to the establishment of bakufu against the dictator of Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expulsion of Yoriie was not just a conspiracy, but was apparently caused by pent-up discontent within the samurai in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) which contributed to the circumstances of the bakufu acting against the Shogunal dictator.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expulsion of Yoriie was not just a conspiracy, but was apparently caused by pent-up discontent within the samurai in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) which contributed to the circumstances of the bakufu acting against the Shogunal dictator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>頼家はほとんど個性を示さないまま歴史から消え去り、鎌倉幕府は御家人達による血みどろの権力闘争が続く事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriie disappeared from the history without showing almost any of his character, and gokenin in Kamakura bakufu continued to engage in a bloody power struggle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie disappeared from history showing nearly none of his character, and the gokenin in Kamakura bakufu continued to engage in a bloody power struggle.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie disappeared from history showing nearly none of his character, and the gokenin in Kamakura bakufu continued to engage in a bloody power struggle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie&apos;s Grave</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Yoriie&apos;s&quot; for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie&apos;s Grave</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>頼家の墓がある伊豆市の修善寺温泉街では、毎年7月に頼家公祭りが行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the hot spring resort near the Shuzen-ji Temple in the Izu City where there is a grave of Yoriie, Yoriie Festival has been held on every July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grave of Yoriie is located at a hot spring resort near the Shuzen-ji Temple in the Izu City where the Yoriie Festival is held every July.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grave of Yoriie is located at a hot spring resort near the Shuzen-ji Temple in the Izu City where the Yoriie Festival is held every July.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official court ranks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official Court Ranks</e>
<cmt>changed wording and capitalized for the section</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of Offices and Ranks Held</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following dates are based on the old calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following dates are based on the old Japanese calendar.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot; to make this sentence more grammatical; added &quot;Japanese&quot; for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date according to old lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>建久8年（1197年）12月15日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 15, 1197</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 15th, 1197</e>
<cmt>15→15th</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 15, 1197</e>
<cmt>15th→15</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>従五位に叙し、近衛府に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was conferred to Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and an official of Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie is conferred the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed as an official of Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; fixed grammar; fixed to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie is conferred the rank of Jugoi and appointed as an official of Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>Jugoi、Konoefu→既出のため、補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>建久9年（1198年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1198</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1198</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;In&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1198</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>1月13日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 13</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 13th</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 13</e>
<cmt>13th→13</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>- 讃岐国を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also assigned to the governor of the Sanuki Province as an additional post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie is assigned to the governorship of the Sanuki Province as an additional post.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; changed to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie is assigned to the governorship of the Sanuki Province as an additional post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>11月21日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 21</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 21st</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 21</e>
<cmt>21st→21</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>正五位に昇叙し、右近衛権少将・讃岐権介如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) and was assigned to Ukone no Gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), remaining in the position of Sanuki no Gon no suke (provisional vice governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie is promoted to Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) and assigned to Ukone no Gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), while remaining in the position of Sanuki no Gon no suke (provisional vice governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; fixed grammar; changed tense to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie is promoted to Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) and assigned to Ukone no Gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), while retaining his position as Sanuki no Gon no suke (provisional vice governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>「如元」→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>建久10年（1199年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1199</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1199</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;In&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1199</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>1月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>- 家督相続。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded the head of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie succeeds the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; changed to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie succeeds the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>1月20日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 20</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 20th</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 20</e>
<cmt>20th→20</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>- 近衛府に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred to Konoefu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is transferred to Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is transferred to Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="77">
<j>正治2年（1200年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1200</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1200</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;In&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1200</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>1月5日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 5</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5th</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;On&quot; since it felt unnecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5</e>
<cmt>5th→5</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>- 従四位に昇叙し、左近衛中将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank), remaining in the rank of Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie is promoted to the rank of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank), remaining in his post of Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; changed tense to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie is promoted to the rank of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank), retaining his position as Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>「如元」→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>1月8日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 8</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 8th</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 8</e>
<cmt>8th→8</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>- 禁色を許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was permitted to use kinjiki (literally, &quot;forbidden colors,&quot; seven colors traditionally reserved for the imperial family and nobility).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie is permitted to use kinjiki (literally, &quot;forbidden colors,&quot; seven colors tradionally reserved for the imperial family and nobility).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie is permitted to use kinjiki (literally, &quot;forbidden colors,&quot; seven colors tradionally reserved for the imperial family and nobility).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>10月26日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 26</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 26th</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 26</e>
<cmt>26th→26</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>- 衛門府に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred to Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is transferred to Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>changed tense to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is transferred to Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>建仁2年（1202年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1202</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1202</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;In&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1202</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>1月23日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 23</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 23rd</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 23</e>
<cmt>23rd→23</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>- 正三位に昇叙し、左衛門督如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), remaining in the position of Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie is promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), remaining in his post of Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Shosanmi&quot; for consistency with the word list; changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; changed tense to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie is promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), retaining his position as Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>「如元」→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>7月22日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 22</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 22nd</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 22</e>
<cmt>22nd→22</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>- 従二位に昇叙し、征夷大将軍宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) and was given the title of Seitaishogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie is promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) and given the title of Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; changed &quot;Seitaishogun&quot; to &quot;Seii Taishogun&quot; to match the word list; changed tense to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie is promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) and given the title of Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>左衛門督如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He remained in the position of Saemon no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He keeps his position of Saemon no kami.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally; changed tense to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retains his position as Saemon no kami.</e>
<cmt>「如元」→統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="85">
<j>建仁3年（1203年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1203</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1203</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;In&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1203</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>1月23日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 23</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 23rd</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 23</e>
<cmt>23rd→23</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>- 正二位に昇叙し、左衛門督如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank), remaining in the position of Saemon no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie is promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank), retaining his position of Saemon no kami.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; fixed to grammar; changed tense to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie is promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank), retaining his position as Saemon no kami.</e>
<cmt>of→asに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>9月7日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 7</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 7th</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 7</e>
<cmt>7th→7</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>- 出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie becomes a priest.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&quot;; changed tense to read like a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie becomes a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="88">
<j>元久元年（1204年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1204</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1204</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;In&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1204</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>7月18日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 18</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 18th</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;On&quot; since it felt unecessary as part of a timeline</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 18</e>
<cmt>18th→18</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie dies at the age of twenty-three, according to the traditional Japanese calendar (by the current calendar, he died at the age of twenty-one).</e>
<cmt>combined with the sentence below to reduce sentence fragmentation; used &quot;Yoriie&quot; instead of &quot;He&quot;; added details for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie dies.</e>
<cmt>一文にまとめて訳されていますが、原文は二文のため、訳文も二文に分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>享年23（満21歳没）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was twenty-three years old in the age by the traditional Japanese system (actually, twenty-one years old).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was twenty-three years old in the age by the traditional Japanese system (actually, twenty-one years old).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was twenty-three years old, according to the traditional Japanese calendar (by the current calendar, he died at the age of twenty-one).</e>
<cmt>at the age of twenty-three→He was twenty-three years oldとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>戒名：法華院殿金吾大禅閤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist names) was 法華院殿金吾大禅閤.</e>
<cmt>法華院殿金吾大禅閤</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie&apos;s Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name) is 法華院殿金吾大禅閤.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;His&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&apos;s&quot;; changed &quot;was&quot; to &quot;is&quot;; made &quot;names&quot; singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie&apos;s Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist name) is 法華院殿金吾大禅閤.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>墓所：静岡県伊豆市修善寺の修禅寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is located in the Shuzen-ji Temple at Shuzenji, Izu City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriie&apos;s grave is located in the Shuzen-ji Temple at Shuzenji, Izu City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;His&quot; to &quot;Yoriie&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriie&apos;s grave is located in the Shuzen-ji Temple at Shuzenji, Izu City, Shizuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Haguii(id:1313), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), Ideal(id:236), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 味っ子(id:17086), Greenland4(id:114494), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Kenpei(id:11349), 俊(id:14924), 代言人(id:33675), 怪蘇(id:45514), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), 十月之交(id:586), Chobot(id:20846), Loveless(id:129239), FlaBot(id:30804), Kouko0515(id:100370), Kzhr(id:131), 金沢文鎮(id:10856), Izayohi(id:13095), Carbuncle(id:346), たね(id:10372), 水野白楓(id:22811), Complex01(id:10454), Nallimbot(id:230812), ちちぶ(id:184715), Gokenin(id:215093), 前図書頭(id:134750), 小者(id:172526), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ゐ(id:795), 海衛士(id:19229), Hkato(id:78953), Zippin(id:9885), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>