<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高砂太夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasago tayu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tayu TAKASAGO</e>
<cmt>I went with the standard convention for names, even though this seems to be a pseudonym</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasago tayu</e>
<cmt>通常の姓名の読みとは違うので、この語順に戻しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高砂太夫（たかさご たゆう）は、京都市下京区出身の元嶋原太夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasago tayu is a former Shimabara tayu (a high ranking courtesan of Shimabara district in Kyoto) who is from Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tayu TAKASAGO is a former Shimabara tayu (a high ranking courtesan of the Shimabara district in Kyoto) from Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>deleted “who is”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasago tayu is a former Shimabara tayu (a high ranking courtesan of the Shimabara district in Kyoto) from Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>通常の姓名の読みとは違うので、この語順に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本名、櫛田一栄（くしだ かづえ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her autonym is Kazue KUSHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her real name is Kazue KUSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>antonym-&gt;real name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real name is Kazue KUSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical trail</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>this sounds better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>地元で生まれ育った稀少な太夫である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a rare tayu who was born and brought up locally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is one of the rare Tayu who are born and raised in the local area.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is one of the rare Tayu who are born and raised in the local area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>実家が結髪師で客として来る太夫、芸妓、その髪を結う母を見て育ち、幼少の頃から舞踊、茶道など習い、20代で屋形（置屋）『菊春楼』の太夫となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her family home was engaged in hairdoing for Japanese coiffure and she grew looking tayu and geigi, who visited her home as customers, as well as her mother putting up their hair and learned dancing and sado (Japanese tea ceremony) from very early age and became a tayu of yakata (okiya (geisha dwelling)) &quot;Kikuharuro [菊春楼 読み不明].</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her family business was Japanese style hairdressing, and while growing up she saw Tayu and Geigi, who visited her home as customers, watched her mother doing their hair, learned dancing and tea ceremony from an early age, and became the Tayu for a Yakata (also Okiya, a geisha residence) called Kikuharuro.</e>
<cmt>Edited for clarity and flow. Also, I think some of the Japanese terms might need further explanation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her family business was Japanese style hairdressing, and while growing up she saw Tayu and Geigi (geisha), who visited her home as customers, watched her mother doing their hair, learned dancing and tea ceremony from an early age, and became the Tayu for a Yakata (also Okiya, a geisha residence) called Kikuharuro.</e>
<cmt>芸妓の補足をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>座敷をはじめ、京都市北区 (京都市)鷹峯・常照寺 (京都市)で毎年4月第三日曜に行われる吉野太夫花供養などの行事に参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She worked in zashiki (banquets in which guests are attended by geisha) and took part in Yoshinodayu Hanakuyo (memorial flower festival for Yoshinodayu) held on the third Sunday in April every year in the Josho-ji Temple in Takagamine in Kita Ward in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She worked at banquets attended by geisha, and took part in the Yoshinodayu memorial flower festival held on the third Sunday in April every year at Josho-ji Temple in Takagamine, Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity and brevity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She worked at banquets attended by geisha, and took part in the Yoshinodayu memorial flower festival held on the third Sunday in April every year at Josho-ji Temple in Takagamine, Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>現在は引退し、屋形兼小物屋を開き観光客に嶋原の歴史や太夫について説明をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, she has retired as tayu and opened a yakata/haberdashery shop and gives presentation on history of Shimabara and tayu.</e>
<cmt>「(太夫としては）引退」の意味と解し、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, she has retired as a Tayu and opened a Yakata/store, and gives presentation on the history of Shimabara and Tayu.</e>
<cmt>edited for flow. “haberdashery” was out of place here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, she has retired as a Tayu and opened a Yakata/store, and gives presentation on the history of Shimabara and Tayu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>2007年秋TBS系にて放映のテレビドラマ「輪違屋糸里」に「太夫指導」で参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Autumn 2007, she took part in as &quot;instructor with respect to tayu&quot; in TV drama, &quot;Wachigaiya Itosato,&quot; broadcast by TBS networks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Autumn 2007, she appeared as a Tayu instructor in a TV show called &quot;Wachigaiya Itosato&quot;, broadcast on the TBS network.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity and flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Autumn 2007, she appeared as a Tayu instructor in a TV drama called &quot;Wachigaiya Itosato,&quot; broadcast on the TBS network.</e>
<cmt>TV show→TV drama/ピリオドの位置</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 与左衛門(id:159462), びーろんぐ(id:131462), 今紫(id:9521), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>