<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原領子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Muneko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Muneko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Muneko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 領子（ふじわら の むねこ、生没年不詳）は、平安時代末期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Muneko (dates of birth and death unknown) was a woman during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Muneko (dates of birth and death unknown) was a woman during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Muneko (dates of birth and death unknown) was a woman during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>建春門院民部卿局（けんしゅんもんいんみんぶきょうのつぼね）、洞院局（とうのいんのつぼね）の名を有する女房（高級女官）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a high court woman official, who was known as Kenshunmonin Minbukyo no tsubone (Woman Director of the Popular Affairs Office) or Tonoin no tsubone (Woman Official).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a high court woman official, who was known as Kenshunmonin Minbukyo no tsubone (Woman Director of the Popular Affairs Office) or Tonoin no tsubone (Woman Official).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a high court woman official, who was known as Kenshunmonin Minbukyo no tsubone (Woman Director of the Popular Affairs Office) or Tonoin no tsubone (Woman Official).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大納言藤原顕時の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a Dainagon (Chief Councillor of State) FUJIWARA no Akitoki&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a Dainagon (Chief Councillor of State) FUJIWARA no Akitoki&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a Chief Councillor of State and FUJIWARA no Akitoki&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は不詳だが、平忠盛女と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother is unknown but is believed to have been TAIRA no Tadamori&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother is unknown, but is believed to have been TAIRA no Tadamori&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother is unknown, but is believed to have been TAIRA no Tadamori&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。訳を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>平時忠の継室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneko was TAIRA no Tokitada&apos;s second wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muneko was TAIRA no Tokitada&apos;s second wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muneko was TAIRA no Tokitada&apos;s second wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>兄弟に藤原行隆らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yukitaka was her brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yukitaka was her brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yukitaka was her brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>初め平滋子（時忠の妹・後白河天皇女御）の女房となり、民部卿（建春門院民部卿局）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She started her official career as a high ranking maid serving TAIRA no Shigeko (Tokitada&apos;s younger sister and Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s court lady) and was called the Woman Director of the Popular Affairs Office (Kenshunmonin Minbukyo no tsubone)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She started her official career as a high ranking maid serving TAIRA no Shigeko (Tokitada&apos;s younger sister and Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s court lady) and was called the Woman Director of the Popular Affairs Office (Kenshunmonin Minbukyo no tsubone)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She started her official career as a high court official serving TAIRA no Shigeko (Tokitada&apos;s younger sister and Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s court lady) and was called Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs) (Kenshunmonin Minbukyo no tsubone).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>平時忠と出会ったのはこのときと考えらる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is believed to have met TAIRA no Tokitada for the first time when starting her official career.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is believed to have met TAIRA no Tokitada for the first time when starting her official career.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is believed to have met TAIRA no Tokitada for the first time when starting her official career.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、時忠の後妻となって平時宗・平宣子らの母となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She subsequently became Tokitada&apos;s second wife and gave birth to TAIRA no Tokimune and TAIRA no Nobuko, among others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She subsequently became Tokitada&apos;s second wife and gave birth to TAIRA no Tokimune and TAIRA no Nobuko, among others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She subsequently became Tokitada&apos;s second wife and gave birth to TAIRA no Tokimune and TAIRA no Nobuko, and several other children.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、平徳子（高倉天皇中宮）の女房となって洞院局と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She later became a high ranking maid serving TAIRA no Tokuko (Empress of Emperor Takakura), calling herself Tonoin no tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She later became a high ranking maid serving TAIRA no Tokuko (Empress of Emperor Takakura), calling herself Tonoin no tsubone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She later became a court official serving TAIRA no Tokuko (Empress of Emperor Takakura), calling herself Tonoin no tsubone.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>治承2年（1178年）に徳子が言仁親王（のちの安徳天皇）を出産したのに伴いその乳母となり、候名を帥局（そちのつぼね）と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tokuko gave birth to Imperial Prince Tokihito (later Emperor Antoku) in 1178, Muneko served the prince as his nursing mother, renaming herself Sochi no tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tokuko gave birth to Imperial Prince Tokihito (later Emperor Antoku) in 1178, Muneko served the prince as his nursing mother, renaming herself Sochi no tsubone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tokuko gave birth to Imperial Prince Tokihito (later Emperor Antoku) in 1178, Muneko served the prince as his wet nurse, renaming herself Sochi no tsubone.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>治承3年（1179年）11月に起こった平清盛のクーデター（治承三年の政変）で解官・流罪に処された官人の一人に平時家（時忠の先妻の子）もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokiie (Tokitada&apos;s first wife&apos;s son) was among the court officials who were discharged from their official positions and exiled to remote islands after TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s coup d&apos;etat (Coup of the Third Year of Jisho) in November 1179.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tokiie (Tokitada&apos;s first wife&apos;s son) was among the court officials who were discharged from their official positions and exiled to remote islands after TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s coup d&apos;etat (Coup of the Third Year of Jisho) in November 1179.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokiie (Tokitada&apos;s first wife&apos;s son) was among the court officials who were discharged from their official positions and exiled to remote islands after TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s coup d&apos;etat (Coup of the Third Year of Jisho) in December 1179.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それは領子が継子時家を陥れるために讒言したからだという噂が流れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rumor had it that Muneko deliberately slandered Tokiie, who was her stepchild, in order to plunge him into a difficult situation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rumor has it that Muneko deliberately slandered Tokiie, who was her stepchild, in order to plunge him into a difficult situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rumor has it that Muneko deliberately slandered Tokiie, who was her stepchild, in order to put him into a difficult situation.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>その後、治承4年3月に典侍に任ぜられ、帥典侍・帥佐（そちのすけ）と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneko was appointed as an imperial secretary in March (traditional Japanese calendar month) 1179 and was given the title Sochi no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muneko was appointed as an imperial secretary in March (traditional Japanese calendar month) 1179 and was given the title Sochi no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was appointed as Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) in April 1179 and was given the title of Sochi no tenji then Sochi no suke.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同年5月に従五位上に叙され、その後従三位まで昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May (traditional Japanese calendar month) of the same year, she was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and was eventually promoted to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May (traditional Japanese calendar month) of the same year, she was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) and was eventually promoted to the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of the same year, she was awarded Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade and was eventually promoted to the rank of Junior Third Grade.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>養和元年（1181年）、高倉上皇の崩御に伴い出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1181, she became a Buddhist priest after the death of Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1181, she became a Buddhist priest after the death of Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1181, she became a Buddhist priest after the death of Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）の平家都落ちに夫とともに随伴し、壇ノ浦の戦いで源氏方の捕虜になって文治元年（1185年）4月に帰京した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1183, she fled from Kyoto along with her husband, was captured by Minamoto soldiers in the Battle of Dannoura, and returned to Kyoto in April (traditional Japanese calendar month) 1185.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1183, she fled from Kyoto along with her husband, was captured by Minamoto samurai in the Battle of Dannoura, and returned to Kyoto in April (traditional Japanese calendar month) 1185.</e>
<cmt>terminology</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1183, she fled from Kyoto along with her husband, was captured by Minamoto&apos;s samurai in the Battle of Dannoura, and returned to Kyoto in May, 1185.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後の消息は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her later life is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her later life is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her life after that is unknown.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), Izayohi(id:13095), Oxhop(id:2551), MPD(id:17443), 味っ子(id:17086), Point136(id:211299), YOSHI438(id:174755), Andee(id:20421), Sketch(id:102), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>