<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>庄家長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaga SHO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaga SHO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienaga SHO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>庄 家長（しょう いえなが、生没年未詳）は、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期の武蔵国児玉党（現在の埼玉県本庄市栗崎出身）の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaga SHO was busho (a Japanese military commander) from Kodama party of Musashi Province (present Kurisaki, Honjo City, Saitama Prefecture) between the end of the Heian period and the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaga SHO was a busho (a Japanese military commander) from Kodama party of Musashi Province (present Kurisaki, Honjo City, Saitama Prefecture) between the end of the Heian period and the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>武将を他のファイルに合わせて可算扱いに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienaga SHO was a busho (a Japanese military commander) from Kodama party of Musashi Province (present Kurisaki, Honjo City, Saitama Prefecture) between the end of the Heian period and the beginning of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称を太郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Taro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Taro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>栗崎館2代館主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second owner of Kurisaki Yakata (mansion of the head family of the Sho clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second owner of Kurisaki Yakata (mansion of the head family of the Sho clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second owner of Kurisaki Yakata (mansion of the head family of the Sho clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に備中国（現在の岡山県）の武将となり、猿掛城 (備中国)初代城主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he became busho of Bicchu Province (present Okayama Prefecture) as well as the first lord of Sarukake-jo Castle in the province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he became a busho of Bicchu Province (present Okayama Prefecture) as well as the first lord of Sarukake-jo Castle in the province.</e>
<cmt>武将を他のファイルに合わせて可算扱いに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he became a busho of Bicchu Province (present Okayama Prefecture) as well as the first lord of Sarukake-jo Castle in the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>庄太郎家長は、武蔵国児玉郡大寄郷栗崎村（現在の大字栗崎）の地に館を築いたとされる武将庄家弘の子とされ、彼の活躍は、『吾妻鏡』や『源平盛衰記』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is considered a son of busho, Iehiro SHO, who was thought to have built his own mansion in Kurisaki Villege, Oyose-go, Kodama-gun, Musashi Province, and Ienaga&apos;s heroic stories can be seen in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) and Genpei Seisuiki (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans).</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is considered a son of busho, Iehiro SHO, who was thought to have built his own mansion in Kurisaki Village, Oyose-go, Kodama-gun, Musashi Province, and Ienaga&apos;s heroic stories can be seen in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) and Genpei Seisuiki (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans).</e>
<cmt>villageのスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is considered a son of busho, Iehiro SHO, who was thought to have built his own mansion in Kurisaki Village, Oyose-go, Kodama-gun, Musashi Province, and Ienaga&apos;s heroic stories can be seen in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East) and Genpei Seisuiki (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（庄弘高とは年代的から見て兄弟であると考えられ、研究者の間では、弘高が家弘の次男であると考えられている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Ienaga is chronologically thought to have been brothers with Hirotaka SHO and researchers assume that Hirotaka was the second son of Iehiro.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Ienaga is chronologically thought to have been brothers with Hirotaka SHO and researchers assume that Hirotaka was the second son of Iehiro.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Ienaga is chronologically thought to have been brothers with Hirotaka SHO and researchers assume that Hirotaka was the second son of Iehiro.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>児玉党の本宗家4代目である家弘の嫡子に生まれ、児玉党本宗家5代目を継いだ武将である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaga was born as a legitimate son of Iehiro, who was the 4th lord of the head family of Kodama party, and became a military commander as the 5th lord of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaga was born as a legitimate son of Iehiro, who was the fourth lord of the head family of the Kodama party, and became a military commander as the fifth lord of the family.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienaga was born as a legitimate son of Iehiro, who was the fourth lord of the head family of the Kodama party, and became a military commander as the fifth lord of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>児玉党の上州への勢力拡大</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kodama party&apos;s expansion to Joshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kodama party&apos;s expansion to Joshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kodama party&apos;s expansion to Joshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『玉葉』の安元元年（1175年）11月14日条に、伊勢神宮より上野国緑野郡高山御厨に対する児玉庄の濫行が訴え出され、朝廷では児玉庄にその実否を問い合わせている、との旨の記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the article dated November 14, 1175 of &apos;&apos;Gyokuyo (Diary of Kanezane KUJO), Ise Jingu Shrine complained that the Kodama party&apos;s violent conduct against Takayama mikuriya (manors of Imperial family and powerful shrines) in Midono County, Kozuke Province; therefore, Imperial Court were investigating the allegation of the party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the article dated November 14, 1175 of &apos;&apos;Gyokuyo (Diary of Kanezane KUJO), Ise Jingu Shrine complained the Kodama party&apos;s violent conduct against Takayama mikuriya (manors of Imperial family and powerful shrines) in Midono County, Kozuke Province; therefore, the Imperial Court were investigating the allegations of the party.</e>
<cmt>thatを削除しました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the article dated November 14, 1175 of &apos;&apos;Gyokuyo (Diary of Kanezane KUJO), Ise Jingu Shrine complained the Kodama party&apos;s violent conduct against Takayama mikuriya (manors of Imperial family and powerful shrines) in Midono County, Kozuke Province; therefore, the Imperial Court were investigating the allegations of the party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>児玉庄と高山御厨は、神流川を境界にして隣接していたので両者の間で紛争が生じたものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kodama no sho and Takayama mikuriya were neighboring regions bordering Kanna-gawa River, the conflict might have been brought about between them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kodama no sho and Takayama mikuriya were neighboring regions bordering Kanna-gawa River, the conflict might have been brought about because of this.</e>
<cmt>between them→because of thisに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kodama no sho and Takayama mikuriya were neighboring regions bordering Kanna-gawa River, the conflict might have been brought about because of this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この時、児玉党の党首は庄太郎家長であったと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the leader of the Kodama party is thought to have been Ienaga Taro SHO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the leader of the Kodama party is thought to have been Ienaga Taro SHO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the leader of the Kodama party is thought to have been Ienaga Taro SHO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『武蔵七党系図』には、阿佐美実高（弘方の子息の1人で家長の甥）の所領中に、「上野国高山御庄」とある為、朝廷の問い合わせにかかわらず高山御厨がやがて児玉党によって略奪された事が分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;family tree of the seven groups of samurai warriors in Musashi Province,&quot; there is a mention that &apos;Takayama misho of Kozuke Province&apos; was in the shoryo (territory) of Sanetaka ASAMI (one of the sons of Hirokata or Ienaga&apos;s nephew); the description indicates that Takayama mikuriya was sacked by the Kodama party later despite of interrogation of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>・「御庄」の定訳が確認できませんでしたが、ネット検索で読み方は「みしょう」とするようなので、trans1ではそのようにしました。・「弘方」は、ここでは初出なので調べたところ、ウィキペディアで庄弘方（しょうひろかた）であるようです。http://wpedia.goo.ne.jp/wiki/%E5%BA%84%E5%BC%98%E6%96%B9</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;family tree of the seven groups of samurai warriors in Musashi Province,&quot; there is a mention that &apos;Takayama misho of Kozuke Province&apos; was in the shoryo (territory) of Sanetaka ASAMI (one of the sons of Hirokata or Ienaga&apos;s nephew); the description indicates that Takayama mikuriya was sacked by the Kodama party later despite the inquiry of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>interrogation →inquiryに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;family tree of the seven groups of samurai warriors in Musashi Province,&quot; there is a mention that &apos;Takayama misho of Kozuke Province&apos; was in the shoryo (territory) of Sanetaka ASAMI (one of the sons of Hirokata or Ienaga&apos;s nephew); the description indicates that Takayama mikuriya was sacked by the Kodama party later despite the inquiry of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>12世紀末の時点で児玉党が武蔵国国境を越え、その勢力を上野国南部にまで広げていた事が分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It suggests that the Kodama party spread its power over the border of Musashi Province into the southern part of Kozuke Province at the end of the 12th Century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It suggests that the Kodama party spread its power over the border of Musashi Province into the southern part of Kozuke Province at the end of the twelfth Century.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It suggests that the Kodama party spread its power over the border of Musashi Province into the southern part of Kozuke Province at the end of the twelfth Century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>一ノ谷の戦いにおける武功とその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Military exploits of the Battle of Ichinotani and the subsequent years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military exploits of the Battle of Ichinotani and the subsequent years</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military exploits of the Battle of Ichinotani and the subsequent years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>寿永3年（1184年）2月5日、源氏の両将が摂津国に至り、大手軍の大将軍は源範頼となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 5, 1184, two Shoguns of Minamoto clan arrived in Settsu Province and MINAMOTO no Noriyori became Daishogun (command in chief) of Ote army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 18, 1184, two Shoguns of the Minamoto clan arrived in Settsu Province and MINAMOTO no Noriyori became Daishogun (command in chief) of the Ote army.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変更しました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 18, 1184, two Shoguns of the Minamoto clan arrived in Settsu Province and MINAMOTO no Noriyori became Daishogun (command in chief) of the Ote army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>児玉党本宗家の子息である庄氏一族はこれに従い、2月7日、一ノ谷の戦いに参戦する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The SHO family, which consisted of sons of the head family of the Kodama party, followed the Shogun and on February 7, they joined the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SHO family, which consisted of sons of the head family of the Kodama party, followed the Shogun and on March 20, they joined the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SHO family, which consisted of sons of the head family of the Kodama party, followed the Shogun and on March 20, they joined the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>家長は、平朝昌を討ち取り、敗走した生田森の副将軍三位中将平重衡を須磨区海岸で梶原景季（あるいはその父景時）と共に捕える功績を上げるが、長男である庄頼家が戦死し、家督を継ぐべき直系が絶える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaga defeated 平朝昌, and working with Kagesue KAJIWARA (or his father Kagetoki), he captured the beaten vice-shogun or Sanmi no chujo (Junior Third Rank) of Ikuta no mori, TAIRA no Shigehira, however, his oldest son Yoriie SHO was killed in the battle and Ienaga lost the direct line taking over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>・「平朝昌」の定訳が確認できませんでしたので、原文のまま記載しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaga defeated 平朝昌, and working with Kagesue KAJIWARA (or his father Kagetoki), he captured the beaten vice-shogun or Sanmi no chujo (Junior Third Rank) of Ikuta no mori, TAIRA no Shigehira, however, his oldest son Yoriie SHO was killed in the battle and Ienaga lost the direct line taking over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienaga defeated TAIRA no Tomomasa, and working with Kagesue KAJIWARA (or his father Kagetoki), he captured the beaten vice-shogun or Sanmi no chujo (Junior Third Rank) of Ikuta no mori, TAIRA no Shigehira, however, his oldest son Yoriie SHO was killed in the battle and Ienaga lost the direct line taking over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>・「平朝昌」の定訳が確認できませんでしたが、「ともまさ」と推測しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そこで頼家の弟である庄家次を養子にむかえるが、結局、そのまた弟の本庄時家が児玉の庄氏を継ぐ事となる（家次の一族は、その後、備中庄氏となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, he adopted Ietsugu SHO, Yoriie&apos;s younger brother, but eventually, the successor of the SHO family became Tokiie HONJO, who was Ietsugu&apos;s younger brother (Later, Ietsugu&apos;s family became Bicchu-Sho clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of that, he adopted Ietsugu SHO, Yoriie&apos;s younger brother, but eventually, the successor of the SHO family became Tokiie HONJO, who was Ietsugu&apos;s younger brother (Later, Ietsugu&apos;s family became Bicchu-Sho clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of that, he adopted Ietsugu SHO, Yoriie&apos;s younger brother, but eventually, the successor of the SHO family became Tokiie HONJO, who was Ietsugu&apos;s younger brother (Later, Ietsugu&apos;s family became Bicchu-Sho clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そして、児玉庄氏を頼家に代わって継いだ時家が本庄氏を名乗る事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Tokiie, who replaced Yoriie to take over the Kodama Sho clan, took the name, the Honjo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Tokiie, who replaced Yoriie to take over the Kodama Sho clan, took the name, the Honjo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Tokiie, who replaced Yoriie to take over the Kodama Sho clan, took the name, the Honjo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>家長は武功をあげた恩賞として備中国草壁荘の地頭職を与えられている（この事がきっかけとなって、本庄氏が生じたと考えられる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaga got the position of Jitoshiki (manager and lord of manor) in Kusakabe no sho (manor), Bicchu Province as a reward for his military exploits and this is thought to have led to forming the Honjo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaga got the position of Jitoshiki (manager and lord of manor) in Kusakabe no sho (manor), Bicchu Province as a reward for his military exploits and this is thought to have led to forming the Honjo clan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienaga got the position of Jitoshiki (manager and lord of manor) in Kusakabe no sho (manor), Bicchu Province as a reward for his military exploits and this is thought to have led to forming the Honjo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>『平家物語』では、重衡生け捕りは庄高家であるとしているが、『源平盛衰記』及び岡山県の『荘家文書』には家長であると記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; says that it was Takaie SHO who captured Shigehira alive while &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans) and &quot;Shokemonjo&quot; of Okayama Prefecture shows that it was Ienaga.</e>
<cmt>・「荘家文書」の定訳が確認できませんでしたが、下記サイトによれば「しょうけもんじょ」と読むようです。http://www.city.nerima.tokyo.jp/annai/rekishiwoshiru/rekishibunkazai/bunkazai/bunkazaishosai/b0401.html1（ただ、上記サイトはここで扱われている人物の関連文書ではないようです。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; says that it was Takaie SHO who captured Shigehira alive while &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans) and &quot;Shokemonjo&quot; of Okayama Prefecture shows that it was Ienaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; says that it was Takaie SHO who captured Shigehira alive while &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the Minamoto and the Taira clans) and &quot;Shokemonjo&quot; of Okayama Prefecture shows that it was Ienaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、『吾妻鏡』では重衡を捕らえたのは「家国」であると書かれているが、他に家国という人物の所見が見られないため、『源平盛衰記』の記述などから家長の誤記と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; says that it was &apos;Iekuni&apos; who captured Shigehira, however, there is no other description of a man named Iekuni in the document; therefore, the name is probably a writing error of Ienaga gathered from the description of &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; and other historical materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; says that it was &apos;Iekuni&apos; who captured Shigehira, however, there is no other description of a man named Iekuni in the document; therefore, the name is probably a misspelling of the name Ienaga gathered from the description of &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; and other historical materials.</e>
<cmt>writing error of→misspelling of the nameに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; says that it was &apos;Iekuni&apos; who captured Shigehira, however, there is no other description of a man named Iekuni in the document; therefore, the name is probably a misspelling of the name Ienaga gathered from the description of &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; and other historical materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>研究者の間では、重衡の生け捕りを行なったのは家長であると有力視されているが、これは武功に見合うだけの恩賞を与えられている為である（その他の方も参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many researchers think that it was Ienaga who captured Shigehira alive; this is because he was granted rewards that matched his military exploits (Refer to Others also).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many researchers think that it was Ienaga who captured Shigehira alive; this is because he was granted rewards that matched his military exploits (Refer to Others also).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many researchers think that it was Ienaga who captured Shigehira alive; this is because he was granted rewards that matched his military exploits (Refer to Others also).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>丹党との確執と和平</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feud with Tan party and the peace</e>
<cmt>・「丹党」はウィキペディアに読み方が載っていたのでそれを参考にしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E4%B8%B9%E5%85%9A</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feud with Tan party and the peace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feud with Tan party and the peace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>『吾妻鏡』によると、建久4年（1193年）2月9日、武蔵国の丹党（南西部に位置する）と児玉党（北西部に位置する）の両武士団の間で確執が生じ、合戦が生じる直前にまで及んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, on February 9, 1193, the feud arose in Musashi Province between Tan party (in the southwest) and the Kodama party (in the northwest) and their relationship worsened to the blink of a battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, on March 13, 1193, the feud arose in Musashi Province between the Tan party (in the southwest) and the Kodama party (in the northwest) and their relationship worsened to the brink of a battle.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変更しました。冠詞を追加しました。brinkのスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, on March 13, 1193, the feud arose in Musashi Province between the Tan party (in the southwest) and the Kodama party (in the northwest) and their relationship worsened to the brink of a battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>それを聞いて駆けつけた畠山重忠の仲裁によって、18日には和平をして両党は退いたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hearing the feud, Shigetada HATAKEYAMA came to the province for arbitration; then on 18, he succeeded in the settlement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing of the feud, Shigetada HATAKEYAMA came to the province for arbitration; then on 22, he succeeded in the settlement.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変更しました。Hearing ofのofを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing of the feud, Shigetada HATAKEYAMA came to the province for arbitration; then on 22, he succeeded in the settlement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>約10日間の緊張状態が続いていた事になり、もしそのまま開戦していたのなら、武蔵国の武士団勢力分布図に大きく影響を及ぼす事になったと考えられる（この時、児玉党を率いていたのは、家長か、あるいはその子息と考えられる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that the strained relationship between the parties continued for about 10 days; if their bad mood hadn&apos;t changed and they had started a battle, it would have greatly influenced on the power balance of the local samurai groups. (at that time, it is thought to have been Ienaga or his son who led the Kodama party.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that the strained relationship between the parties continued for about ten days; if their bad mood hadn&apos;t changed and they had started a battle, it would have greatly influenced on the power balance of the local samurai groups (at that time, it is thought to have been Ienaga or his son who led the Kodama party.)</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that the strained relationship between the parties continued for about ten days; if their bad mood hadn&apos;t changed and they had started a battle, it would have greatly influenced on the power balance of the local samurai groups (at that time, it is thought to have been Ienaga or his son who led the Kodama party.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>後世（15世紀初め）の話となるが、上杉禅秀の乱の際には、丹党と児玉党の両武士団は上杉氏憲（入道して禅秀）に味方し、共に敗れて所領を召し上げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, at the beginning of the 15th Century, War of Zenshu UESUGI happened and both the Tan party and the Kodama party sided with Ujinori UESUGI (another name of Zenshu before becoming a monk); eventually, both parties were beaten and lost their territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, at the beginning of the fifteenth Century, War of Zenshu UESUGI happened and both the Tan party and the Kodama party sided with Ujinori UESUGI (another name of Zenshu before becoming a monk); eventually, both parties were beaten and lost their territories.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, at the beginning of the fifteenth Century, War of Zenshu UESUGI happened and both the Tan party and the Kodama party sided with Ujinori UESUGI (another name of Zenshu before becoming a monk); eventually, both parties were beaten and lost their territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>応永25年（1418年）、本庄左衛門（入道して西号、本庄元朝か元翁と見られる）が阿久原村を押領するも、鎌倉公方足利持氏が元の領主に返還するようにと命じている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1418, Saemon HONJO (seems to have changed his name into 西号, 本庄元朝, or Genno after becoming a monk) seized Aguhara Villege, however, Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, Kamakura Kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) ordered him to return the land to the previous lord.</e>
<cmt>・「西号」、「本庄元朝」を確認できませんでした。一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1418, Saemon HONJO (seems to have changed his name into 西号, 本庄元朝, or Genno after becoming a monk) seized Aguhara Village, however, Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, Kamakura Kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) ordered him to return the land to the previous lord.</e>
<cmt>villageのスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1418, Saemon HONJO (seems to have changed his name into 西号, 本庄元朝, or Genno after becoming a monk) seized Aguhara Village, however, Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, Kamakura Kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) ordered him to return the land to the previous lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>（阿久原は平安時代後期では児玉党の本拠地であり、本庄氏にとっては先祖発祥地であり、それを奪われた事は耐え難かったものとみられる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(the Aguhara Villege used to home to the Kodama party and the HONJO clan originated in the villege; therefore, they must have been unbearably disappointed when they were deprived of their land.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(the Aguhara Village used to be home to the Kodama party and the HONJO clan originated in the village; therefore, they must have been unbearably disappointed when they were deprived of their land.)</e>
<cmt>villageのスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(the Aguhara Village used to be home to the Kodama party and the HONJO clan originated in the village; therefore, they must have been unbearably disappointed when they were deprived of their land.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>家紋の歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of family crest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of family crest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of family crest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>治承・寿永の乱（源平合戦）の時、児玉党（武蔵七党中最大の武士団）は軍旗に「唐団扇」を描いたが、これはのちに「軍配団扇紋」となる（『源平盛衰記』に児玉党の軍旗について記述がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of Jisho-Juei War (the Genpei War), the Kodama party, which was the biggest samurai group in Musashi-shichito Parties, showed &apos;Touchiwa&apos; on their battle flag and later, this became known as &apos;Gunbaidanuchiwa-mon&apos; (There is a description of the Kodama party&apos;s battle flag in &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of Jisho-Juei War (the Genpei War), the Kodama party, which was the biggest samurai group in Musashi-shichito Parties, showed &apos;Touchiwa&apos; on their battle flag and later, this became known as &apos;Gunbaidanuchiwa-mon&apos; (There is a description of the Kodama party&apos;s battle flag in &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of Jisho-Juei War (the Genpei War), the Kodama party, which was the biggest samurai group in Musashi-shichito Parties, showed &apos;Touchiwa&apos; on their battle flag and later, this became known as &apos;Gunbaidanuchiwa-mon&apos; (There is a description of the Kodama party&apos;s battle flag in &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>すなわち、武家家紋としては最古級の歴史を持つものである（文献史料上においては）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That means that it has the oldest history as a crest of the samurai family (in terms of bibliographic consideration).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That means that it has the oldest history as a crest of the samurai family (in terms of bibliographic consideration).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That means that it has the oldest history as a crest of the samurai family (in terms of bibliographic consideration).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この軍配団扇紋の団扇模様は分家（土地）によって異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each branch family had different pattern of the Gunbaidanuchiwa-mon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each branch family had different pattern of the Gunbaidanuchiwa-mon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each branch family had different pattern of the Gunbaidanuchiwa-mon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>武家家紋は敵味方の識別や家示が目的とされるが、生じた当初は、大きな武士団をまとめ、結束力を高める為に生じたと考えられる（領地を分家に与え、分家は土地名を名乗り、そして家紋もアレンジする）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai used family crests to identify themselves on the battlefields; at first, they were created to bring big samurai groups together and strengthen the local solidarity (As branch samurai families were given their own land, they took the name of their places and added modifications to the original design of their family crest to identify themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai used family crests to identify themselves on the battlefields; at first, they were created to bring big samurai groups together and strengthen the local solidarity (As branch samurai families were given their own land, they took the name of their places and added modifications to the original design of their family crest to identify themselves.)</e>
<cmt>かっこを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai used family crests to identify themselves on the battlefields; at first, they were created to bring big samurai groups together and strengthen the local solidarity (As branch samurai families were given their own land, they took the name of their places and added modifications to the original design of their family crest to identify themselves.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="36">
<j>一族の構成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>兄弟は、弟が4人いて、庄弘高、庄忠家、庄高家、庄弘方。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaga SHO had four brothers: Hirotaka, Tadaie, Takaie, and Hirokata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaga SHO had four brothers: Hirotaka, Tadaie, Takaie, and Hirokata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienaga SHO had four brothers: Hirotaka, Tadaie, Takaie, and Hirokata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>それぞれ、宇治川の戦いや粟津の戦い、一ノ谷の戦い、奥州合戦や承久の乱など、各戦において武功を上げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of the brothers delivered great performance at war such as the battle of Uji-gawa River, Battle of Awazu, the Battle of Ichinotani, the battle of Oshu, and Jokyu War. (Some traditions say that Takaie once sided with MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of the brothers delivered great performance at war such as the battle of Uji-gawa River, Battle of Awazu, the Battle of Ichinotani, the battle of Oshu, and Jokyu War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of the brothers delivered great performance at war such as the battle of Uji-gawa River, Battle of Awazu, the Battle of Ichinotani, the battle of Oshu, and Jokyu War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>（伝承によっては、高家は初め源義仲方だったともされる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Some traditions say that Takaie once sided with MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Some traditions say that Takaie once sided with MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>家長には、頼家（依家）、家綱（改め定綱）、家次、時家、時長の5人の子息がいる（上述の様に、頼家は一ノ谷の戦いで戦死、家次は備中国へ行き土着、時家は本庄氏を名乗り、在地に残る）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaga had five sons: Yoriie, Ietsuna (later changed into Sadatsuna), Ietsugu, Tokiie, and Tokinaga. (As described above, Yoriie was killed in the Battle of Ichinotani; Ietsugu left and settled down in Bicchu Province; and Tokiie took the name of HONJO and remained.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaga had five sons: Yoriie, Ietsuna (later changed into Sadatsuna), Ietsugu, Tokiie, and Tokinaga (As described above, Yoriie was killed in the Battle of Ichinotani; Ietsugu left and settled down in Bicchu Province; and Tokiie took the name of HONJO and remained.)</e>
<cmt>途中のピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienaga had five sons: Yoriie, Ietsuna (later changed into Sadatsuna), Ietsugu, Tokiie, and Tokinaga (As described above, Yoriie was killed in the Battle of Ichinotani; Ietsugu left and settled down in Bicchu Province; and Tokiie took the name of HONJO and remained.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="41">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>『吾妻鏡』には、寿永3年（1184年）2月7日、明石において、重衡が梶原景時（景季の父）と家国（家長）に生け捕られたと記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; says that on February 7, 1184, Shigehira was captured alive in Akashi by Kagetoki KAJIWARA (father of Kagesue KAJIWARA) and Iekuni (Ienaga).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; says that on March 20, 1184, Shigehira was captured alive in Akashi by Kagetoki KAJIWARA (father of Kagesue KAJIWARA) and Iekuni (Ienaga).</e>
<cmt>新暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; says that on March 20, 1184, Shigehira was captured alive in Akashi by Kagetoki KAJIWARA (father of Kagesue KAJIWARA) and Iekuni (Ienaga).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>人名の誤記や混同が多い資料である事を考えると、景季を景時と誤記した可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering that this material has lots of writing errors and mix-ups of names, there is the possibility of mistake Kagesue for Kagetoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering that this material has lots of writing errors and mix-ups of names, there is the possibility of Kagesue being mistaken for Kagetoki.</e>
<cmt>最後の部分を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering that this material has lots of writing errors and mix-ups of names, there is the possibility of Kagesue being mistaken for Kagetoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また、別の伝承では、三郎忠家が重衡を生け捕ったとあり、重衡を捕えた武士の名は諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another tradition delivers that Suburo Tadaie captured Shigehira alive; in this way, there are various theories as to the samurai who caught Shigehira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another tradition delivers that Suburo Tadaie captured Shigehira alive; in this way, there are various theories as to the samurai who caught Shigehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another tradition delivers that Suburo Tadaie captured Shigehira alive; in this way, there are various theories as to the samurai who caught Shigehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし、梶原氏と庄氏の手柄であると言う点に変わりはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Still, the fact remains that it was the achievement of the KAJIWARA clan and the SHO clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Still, the fact remains that it was the achievement of the KAJIWARA clan and the SHO clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Still, the fact remains that it was the achievement of the KAJIWARA clan and the SHO clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="46">
<j>『吾妻鏡』によると、樋口兼光は、「武蔵国児玉の輩（ともがら）と親昵（しんぢつ）たるの間」とあり、親しい関係だった事が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;reported Kanemitsu HIGUCHI as &quot;a person who had close relationship with members of the Kodama clan in Musashi Province&quot;.</e>
<cmt>・「武蔵国児玉の輩（ともがら）と親昵（しんぢつ）たるの間」の部分は、「児玉党とは親しい間柄だった」と解釈して訳しました。そのため後述の「親しい関係だった事が記されている。」の部分は同じ内容のため省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;reported Kanemitsu HIGUCHI as &quot;a person who had a close relationship with members of the Kodama clan in Musashi Province&quot;.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;reported Kanemitsu HIGUCHI as &quot;a person who had a close relationship with members of the Kodama clan in Musashi Province&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>党の誰を指すのかは不明だが、次の項には家長が出てくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is not clear who was close to Kanemitsu HIGUCHI in the clan, there is the mention of Ienaga in the following item:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is not clear who was close to Kanemitsu HIGUCHI in the clan, there is the mention of Ienaga in the following section.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is not clear who was close to Kanemitsu HIGUCHI in the clan, there is the mention of Ienaga in the following section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="48">
<j>建久元年（1190年）11月7日、源頼朝の上洛に際し、先陣随将の13番として庄太郎の名があり（後陣随兵28番目にもなぜか庄太郎の名がある）、建久6年（1195年）3月10日、将軍頼朝公東大寺供養にも、御随兵として庄太郎の名が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 7, 1190, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo went to the capital Kyoto, Taro SHO was the 13th in the leading unit following the commander (strangely, Taro also came into the document as 28th in the following unit with armed force) and then, on March 10, 1195, there is the name of Taro SHO as a member of the army following shogun at the time of the memorial service of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Todai-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>・「先陣随将」、「後陣随兵」の定訳がなかったのですが、それぞれ「将軍につく先陣隊」、「兵を従えた後陣隊」と解釈しました。・「御随兵」の定訳が確認できなかったのですが、「将軍に従う兵の一人」として解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 5, 1190, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo went to the capital Kyoto, Taro SHO was the thirteenth in the leading unit following the commander (strangely, the name Taro also appears in the document as twenty-eighth in the following unit with armed force) and then, on April 21, 1195, Taro SHO was a member of the army following shogun at the time of the memorial service of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Todai-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>新暦に変更しました。文章の構成を変更しました。数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 5, 1190, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo went to the capital Kyoto, Taro SHO was the thirteenth in the leading unit following the commander (strangely, the name Taro also appears in the document as twenty-eighth in the following unit with armed force) and then, on April 21, 1195, Taro SHO was a member of the army following shogun at the time of the memorial service of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Todai-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="49">
<j>家長の没した場所、及び、墓所は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not known exactly where Ienaga died or his grave is.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not known exactly where Ienaga died or his grave is.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known exactly where Ienaga died or his grave is.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>武蔵国で亡くなったのか、備中国で亡くなったのかも分からず、そうした伝承がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it remains even unclear that he died in Musashi Province or in Bicchu Province; there is no report of his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it remains even unclear that he died in Musashi Province or in Bicchu Province; there is no report of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it remains even unclear that he died in Musashi Province or in Bicchu Province; there is no report of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし、13世紀初めに庄氏の菩提寺である宥庄寺（後の宥勝寺）が建立した事から遺骨は武蔵に戻ったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is assumed that his cremains were returned to Musashi from the fact that the family temple of the SHO clan, Yusho-ji Temple was built at the beginning of the 13th Century. (Before the temple established, his cremains might have been placed in the KODAMA clan&apos;s temple, Saiko-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>・「宥庄寺」、「宥勝寺」の定訳は確認できなかったのですが、ネット検索から読み方は「ゆうしょうじ」と読むようです。http://www.ecity.ne.jp/syousai/main2.asp?P_SNO=D0002425一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is assumed that his cremains were returned to Musashi from the fact that the family temple of the SHO clan, Yusho-ji Temple, was built at the beginning of the thirteenth Century.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is assumed that his cremains were returned to Musashi from the fact that the family temple of the SHO clan, Yusho-ji Temple, was built at the beginning of the thirteenth Century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>（建立するまでは児玉氏の菩提寺である西光寺に納められた可能性もあるが）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Before the temple was established, his cremains might have been placed in the KODAMA clan&apos;s temple, Saiko-ji Temple.)</e>
<cmt>wasを追加しました。かっこを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Before the temple was established, his cremains might have been placed in the KODAMA clan&apos;s temple, Saiko-ji Temple.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="53">
<j>建久元年の際には、庄太郎の後ろに四方田三郎（庄弘高）の名が見られ、後陣随兵31番には庄四郎（高家）の名が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1190, the name of Saburo SHIHODEN (Hirotaka SHO) can be found behind Taro SHO while the name of Shiro SHO (Takaie) also came into the document as 31st in the following unit with armed force.</e>
<cmt>・「四方田三郎」の定訳が確認できなかったのですが、ウィキペディアより「しほうでんさぶろう」と読むと思われます。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%9B%9B%E6%96%B9%E7%94%B0%E6%B0%8F</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1190, the name of Saburo SHIHODEN (Hirotaka SHO) can be found behind Taro SHO while the name of Shiro SHO (Takaie) can be found in the document as thirty-first in the following unit with armed force.</e>
<cmt>came into→can be foundに変更しました。数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1190, the name of Saburo SHIHODEN (Hirotaka SHO) can be found behind Taro SHO while the name of Shiro SHO (Takaie) can be found in the document as thirty-first in the following unit with armed force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>建久6年の東大寺供養の際にも、やはり庄太郎の後ろには四方田三郎の名が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Saburo SHIHODEN also followed Taro SHO at the time of the memorial service in Todai-ji Temple in 1195.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Saburo SHIHODEN also followed Taro SHO at the time of the memorial service in Todai-ji Temple in 1195.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Saburo SHIHODEN also followed Taro SHO at the time of the memorial service in Todai-ji Temple in 1195.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>この事から考えても家長が弘高の兄であり、四方田三郎ではなく、本来は四方田二郎弘高と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this, Ienaga was an older brother of Hirotaka, who is thought to have been Jiro Hirotaka SHIHODEN instead of Saburo SHIHODEN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this, Ienaga was an older brother of Hirotaka, who is thought to have been Jiro Hirotaka SHIHODEN instead of Saburo SHIHODEN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this, Ienaga was an older brother of Hirotaka, who is thought to have been Jiro Hirotaka SHIHODEN instead of Saburo SHIHODEN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>詳しい事は庄弘高の方を参照してもらいたいが、諸々の研究結果から岡山県の『荘家文書』の伝えには誤りが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, please refer to the item of Hirotaka SHO; however, various studies reveal that there are some mistakes in &quot;Shokemonjo&quot; of Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>・「荘家文書」の定訳が確認できませんでしたが、「しょうけもんじょ」と読むようです。http://www.city.nerima.tokyo.jp/annai/rekishiwoshiru/rekishibunkazai/bunkazai/bunkazaishosai/b0401.html1（ただ、上記サイトはここで扱われている人物の関連文書ではないようです。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, please refer to the item of Hirotaka SHO; however, various studies have revealed that there are some mistakes in &quot;Shokemonjo&quot; of Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>reveal→have revealedに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, please refer to the item of Hirotaka SHO; however, various studies have revealed that there are some mistakes in &quot;Shokemonjo&quot; of Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ちちぶ(id:184715), Hajimari(id:205606), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>