<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>卜部兼方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanekata URABE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanekata URABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanekata URABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>卜部兼方（うらべかねかた、生没年不詳）は、鎌倉時代中後期の神祇をつかさどる官人、神道家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanekata URABE (year of birth and year of death not known) was a kanjin (government official (esp. one of low to medium rank)) in charge of matters relating to Shintoism (in other words, Shintoist), who lived in the middle and late Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanekata URABE (year of birth and year of death not known) was a kanjin (government official (esp. one of low to medium rank)) in charge of matters relating to Shintoism (in other words, Shintoist), who lived in the middle and late Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanekata URABE (year of birth and year of death not known) was a kanjin (government official (esp. one of low to medium rank)) in charge of matters relating to Shintoism (in other words, Shintoist), who lived in the middle and late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Kamakura periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>神祇官にして平野神社社務。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a jingikan (official in charge of matters relating to Shintoism and worked for clerical work at the Hirano-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a jingikan (official in charge of matters relating to Shintoism and carried out clerical work at the Hirano-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a jingikan (official in charge of matters relating to Shintoism) and carried out clerical work at the Hirano-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>カッコの片方を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>名は懐賢とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Kaiken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Kaiken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Kaiken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>訓は「やすかた」とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese pronunciation is &quot;Yasukata.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese pronunciation is &quot;Yasukata.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese pronunciation is &apos;Yasukata.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父は神祇権大副卜部兼文。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Kanebumi URABE, who was Jingi Gon no Taifu, (Provisional Senior Assistant Director of Divinities).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Kanebumi URABE, who was Jingi Gon no Taifu, (Provisional Senior Assistant Director of Divinities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Kanebumi URABE, who was Jingi Gon no Taifu (Provisional Senior Assistant Director of Divinities).</e>
<cmt>余分なカンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>父兼文ら平野社系卜部氏に代々伝わる家説と奈良時代以降の数々の『日本書紀』注釈を基に『釈日本紀』を著し、後に吉田神道に大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Shaku Nihongi (annotated text of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;) based on views inherited by the family which had been handed down from generation to generation in the Urabe family (Hiranosha branch) including his father Kanebumi and various annotated editions of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; since Nara Period and gave a great influence to Yoshida Shintoism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote &quot;Shaku Nihongi (annotated text of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;) based on views inherited by the family which had been handed down from generation to generation in the Urabe family (Hiranosha branch) including his father Kanebumi and various annotated editions of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; since Nara Period and gave a great influence to Yoshida Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; based on views inherited by the family which had been handed down from generation to generation in the Urabe family (Hirano-sha branch) including his father Kanebumi and various annotated editions of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) since Nara period and gave a great influence to Yoshida Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの片方を追加、文中で説明されているため&quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot;の補足削除、&quot;Nihonshoki&quot;の補足追加、Hirano-sha branch、Nara periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>卜部氏は古代の祭祀貴族の一つで、占い卜（ぼく）（ぼくせん）による吉凶判断を業としていた氏族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Urabe clan was one of saishikizoku (nobles in charge of religious rites) in the old time and had been engaged in making judgment on fortune by divining.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Urabe clan was one of saishikizoku (nobles in charge of religious rites) in the old time and had been engaged in making judgment on fortune by divining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Urabe clan was one of saishikizoku (nobles in charge of religious rites) in the old time and had been engaged in making judgment on fortune by divining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大中臣氏とともに代々神祇官を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family inherited jingikan (an official in charge of matters relating to Shintoism) from generation to generation together with the Onakatomi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family inherited jingikan (an official in charge of matters relating to Shintoism) from generation to generation together with the Onakatomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family inherited jingikan from generation to generation together with the Onakatomi clan.</e>
<cmt>jingikan→既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>平安時代中期には平野社系と吉田神社系の二流に分かれ、兼方の平野社系は卜部氏始祖卜部平麻呂が平野社領となっていることから本来なら宗家の立場である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of the Heian Period, the Urabe family was divided into two branches, one was the Hiranosha branch and the other was Yoshida-jinja branch, and the Hiranosha branch to which Kanekata belonged was originally the head family because the founder of the Urabe clan, Hiramaro URABE&apos;s fief head been owned by the Hiranosha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>原文を二つに分割しました。(この文章の後半の意味が不明です。Wikipediaの記事も同様です。訳文のように解釈しました。)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of the Heian Period, the Urabe family was divided into two branches, one was the Hiranosha branch and the other was Yoshida-jinja branch, and the Hiranosha branch to which Kanekata belonged was originally the head family because the founder of the Urabe clan, Hiramaro URABE&apos;s fief head been owned by the Hiranosha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of the Heian period, the Urabe family was divided into two branches, one was the Hirano-sha branch and the other was Yoshida-jinja branch, and the Hirano-sha branch to which Kanekata belonged was originally the head family because the founder of the Urabe clan, Hiramaro URABE&apos;s fief head been owned by the Hirano-sha Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Heian period、Hirano-sha branch、Hirano-sha Shrineとし、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、吉田神社が藤原氏の氏神であることもあり勢力は二分され、氏長者も二流が交替で受け継ぎ、それぞれ家学として日本書紀等の古典の研究をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, partly because the Yoshida-jinja Shrine was the ujigami (guardian deity) of the Fujiwara clan, the power of two branches were equal and the position of uji no choja (clan head) was inherited by both branches in turns and both branches respectively studied old books such as Nihonshoki as the kagaku (study by the family).</e>
<cmt>原文を二つに分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, partly because the Yoshida-jinja Shrine was the ujigami (guardian deity) of the Fujiwara clan, the power of two branches were equal and the position of uji no choja (clan head) was inherited by both branches in turns and both branches respectively studied old books such as Nihonshoki as the kagaku (study by the family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, partly because the Yoshida-jinja Shrine was the ujigami (guardian deity) of the Fujiwara clan, the power of two branches were equal and the position of uji no choja (clan head) was inherited by both branches in turns and both branches respectively studied old books such as Nihonshoki as the kagaku (study by the family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>室町時代に入り、吉田社系が公卿を出したこともあり盛んになると、平野社系は衰え、兼方の8代孫卜部兼緒の代で絶えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Muromachi Period, the Yoshida branch flourished partly because one of family member became a noble, while the Hiranosha branch declined and ended with Kaneo URABE, who was the descent of Kanekata after eight generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Muromachi Period, the Yoshida branch flourished partly because one of the family member&apos;s became a noble, while the Hiranosha branch declined and ended with Kaneo URABE, who descended from Kanekata after eight generations.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Muromachi period, the Yoshida-sha branch flourished partly because one of the family member&apos;s became a noble, while the Hirano-sha branch declined and ended with Kaneo URABE, who descended from Kanekata after eight generations.</e>
<cmt>Muromachi period、Yoshida-sha branch、Hirano-sha branchに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>平野社系は、吉田社系から吉田兼永が養子に入り継承し、その子孫が藤井充行の代以降藤井家を称し堂上家となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hiranosha branch was inherited by Kanenaga YOSHIDA, who was adopted from the Yoshida-sha branch and his descendent called themselves the Fujii clan up from Ategai FUJII and became a toshoke (family admitted to imperial court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hiranosha branch was inherited by Kanenaga YOSHIDA, who was adopted from the Yoshida-sha branch and his descendent called themselves the Fujii clan up from Ategai FUJII and became a toshoke (family admitted to imperial court).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hirano-sha branch was inherited by Kanenaga YOSHIDA, who was adopted from the Yoshida-sha branch and his descendent called themselves the Fujii clan up from Ategai FUJII and became a toshoke (family admitted to imperial court).</e>
<cmt>Hirano-sha Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>『釈日本紀』との関係を示す兼方の書写になる弘安9年（1286年）の奥書のある『日本書紀』神代巻二巻の卜部家本が、文化庁に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Urabe copies of two volumes of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; for the legendary age having an okugaki (inscription usually preceding the colophone)(in 1286 transcribed by Kanekata, that shows the relation with &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; are possessed by the Agency for Cultural Affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Urabe copies of two volumes of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; for the legendary age having an okugaki (inscription usually preceding the colophone)(in 1286 transcribed by Kanekata, that shows the relation with &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; are possessed by the Agency for Cultural Affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Urabe copies of two volumes of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; for the legendary age having an okugaki (inscription usually preceding the colophone) (in 1286 transcribed by Kanekata, that shows the relation with &quot;Shaku Nihongi&quot; are possessed by the Agency for Cultural Affairs.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 橄欖岩(id:24996), Rimota(id:65657), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>