<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原小忌古曾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kogikoso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kogikoso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kogikoso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原小忌古曾（ふじわら の こぎこそ、生没年不詳）または藤原古木古曾は、平安時代の女性貴族で藤原相通の妻にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kogikoso (dates of birth and death unknown), written as &quot;藤原古木古曾&quot; or &quot;藤原古木古曾,&quot; was a female noble in the Heian period who was a wife of FUJIWARA no Sukemichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kogikoso (dates of birth and death unknown), written as &quot;藤原古木古曾&quot; or &quot;藤原古木古曾,&quot; was a noble female during the Heian period who was the wife of FUJIWARA no Sukemichi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kogikoso (year of birth and death unknown), written as &quot;藤原古木古曾&quot; or &quot;藤原古木古曾,&quot; was a noble female during the Heian period who was the wife of FUJIWARA no Sukemichi.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>夫と同様にせん子女王と何らかの争いをしたためか、長元4年（1031年）壱岐国に流罪となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like her husband, probably because she had some sort of fight against Princess Senshi, she was banished to the Iki province in 1031.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like her husband, probably because she had some sort of fight with Princess Senshi, was banished to the Iki province in 1031.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like her husband, probably because she had some sort of fight with Princess Senshi, was banished to the Iki Province in 1031.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その後の消息は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no information about her life thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no further information about her life thereafter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no further information about her life thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>