<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>北条時輔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokisuke HOJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokisuke HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokisuke HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>北条 時輔（ほうじょう ときすけ）は、鎌倉幕府第5代執権・北条時頼の長男（庶子）で、鎌倉時代中期の六波羅探題南方である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokisuke HOJO was the eldest son (illegitimate child) of Tokiyori HOJO, the fifth regent of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and served in Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata (Rokuhara Tandai South) in the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokisuke HOJO was the eldest son (illegitimate child) of Tokiyori HOJO, the fifth regent of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and served in Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata (Rokuhara Tandai South) in the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokisuke HOJO was the eldest son (illegitimate child) of Tokiyori HOJO, the fifth regent of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and served in Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata (Rokuhara Tandai South) in the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>異母弟に第8代執権・北条時宗らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger paternal half-brother was Tokimune HOJO, the eighth regent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger paternal brothers were Tokimune HOJO, the eighth regent, and so on.</e>
<cmt>異母弟が複数人いることを表現</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger paternal brothers were Tokimune HOJO, the eighth regent, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>烏帽子親は足利頼氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eboshioya (a person who put on an eboshi in the case of genpuku ceremony) was Yoriuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His eboshioya (a person who puts an eboshi on a young man&apos;s head in the case of genpuku ceremony) was Yoriuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>a person who put --&gt;a person who puts</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His eboshioya (a person who puts an eboshi on a young man&apos;s head in the case of genpuku ceremony) was Yoriuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>征夷大将軍宗尊親王の側近として将軍御所に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served in Shogun&apos;s palace as the close adviser of Imperial Prince Munetaka, seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served in Shogun&apos;s palace as a close adviser of Imperial Prince Munetaka of seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>the close adviser を a close adviserに変更。Imperial Prince Munetaka, seii taishogun を Imperial Prince Munetaka of seii taishogun に記述を変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served in Shogun&apos;s palace as a close adviser of Imperial Prince Munetaka of seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>側室の子である為、父・時頼から序列三位として正室の子である弟の時宗や宗政よりも格下に置かれて厳しく冷遇された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was the child of a concubine, his rank was put under his brothers Tokimune and Munemasa, who were the children of the lawful wife, as the third ranking by his father Tokiyori and strictly treated unkindly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he was a child of a concubine, his rank was put under his brothers Tokimune and Munemasa, who were the children of the lawful wife, as the third ranking by his father Tokiyori, and treated strictly and unkindly.</e>
<cmt>the childを a child に変更、strictly treated unkindly を treated strictly and unkindly に変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he was a child of a concubine, his rank was put under his brothers Tokimune and Munemasa, who were the children of the lawful wife, as the third ranking by his father Tokiyori, and treated strictly and unkindly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>文永元年（1264年）六波羅探題に命じられて京都に出向する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was transferred temporarily to Kyoto by the order of Rokuhara Tandai in 1264.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as Rokuhara Tandai and went to Kyoto in 1264.</e>
<cmt>「六波羅探題に命じられて」を「六波羅探題に任命されて」と解釈して訳を見直し。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Rokuhara Tandai and went to Kyoto in 1264.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このとき、六波羅探題南方は佐介流北条時盛以来22年ぶりに復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata was revived since Tokimori HOJO of Sasuke School 22 years ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata was reestablished for the first time in 22 years since the time of Tokimori HOJO.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata was reestablished for the first time in 22 years since the time of Tokimori HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>庶長子であることから鎌倉より遠ざけられたとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that he was kept away from Kamakura as he was the illegitimate child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that he was kept away from Kamakura as he was the illegitimate child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that he was kept away from Kamakura as he was the illegitimate child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、歴任した役職については、他の北条一門と比べてそれほど見劣りするものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, his various posts were not seemed pale by comparing with others in the Hojo family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the posts which he held do not pale so much in comparison to those of other members in the Hojo family.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the posts which he held do not pale so much in comparison to those of other members in the Hojo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このことから、一門内部での地位はそれほど低くなかった可能性はある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, it was possible that his rank within the family was not so low.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, probably, his rank might not be so low in the Hojo family.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, probably, his rank might not be so low in the Hojo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>いずれにしろ、時宗からすれば扱いの難しい存在であったものと察せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Either way, it could be sensed that he was considered as a difficult person for Tokimune to handle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Either way, it could be sensed that he was considered as a difficult person for Tokimune to handle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Either way, it could be sensed that he was considered as a difficult person for Tokimune to handle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>文永5年（1268年）に時宗が執権に就任した際には反得宗派の1人として不満を示し、元 (王朝)からの国書が届いた際にも返答に関して幕府と対立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tokimune was appointed to the regent in 1268, he indicated his frustration as one of anti-Tokuso school and opposed to the bakufu regarding the correspondence when he received the sovereign&apos;s message from Yuan (Dynasty).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tokimune was appointed to the regent in 1268, he indicated his frustration as a member of anti-Tokuso school fraction and opposed to the bakufu regarding the content of the answer to correspondence from Yuan (Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tokimune was appointed to the regent in 1268, he indicated his frustration as a member of anti-Tokuso school fraction and opposed to the bakufu regarding the content of the answer to correspondence from Yuan (Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>文永9年（1272年）、北条時宗失脚計画が露見して北条時章・北条教時兄弟が二月騒動で討たれると時輔も追討対象となり、時宗の命を受けた六波羅探題北条義宗によって攻められて戦死したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the downfall attempt of Tokimune HOJO was exposed, and the brothers of Tokiaki HOJO and Noritoki HOJO were attacked in Nigatsu-sodo (February rebellion), Tokisuke became the target of hunting down and killed by Yoshimune HOJO in Rokuhara Tandai ordered by Tokimune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a conspiracy to to overthrow Tokimune HOJO was detected and brothers of Tokiaki HOJO and Noritoki HOJO were killed in Nigatsu-sodo (February rebellion), Tokisuke became the target of hunting down; and it is said that he was killed by Yoshimune HOJO of Rokuhara Tandai based on the order of Tokimune in 1272.</e>
<cmt>1292年を追記するなど、表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a conspiracy to to overthrow Tokimune HOJO was detected and brothers of Tokiaki HOJO and Noritoki HOJO were killed in Nigatsu-sodo (February rebellion), Tokisuke became the target of hunting down; and it is said that he was killed by Yoshimune HOJO of Rokuhara Tandai based on the order of Tokimune in 1272.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これが事実ならば、享年25。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this was the fact, he died at the age of 25.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this was the fact, he died at the age of 25.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this was the fact, he died at the age of 25.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただし、京都にいた時輔がこの計画に関わっていたかどうかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was not certain whether Tokisuke, who was in Kyoto, was involved in this project or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is not certain whether Tokisuke, who was in Kyoto, was involved in the conspiracy or not.</e>
<cmt>was not certainを is not certainに、 this project をthe conspiracyに変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is not certain whether Tokisuke, who was in Kyoto, was involved in the conspiracy or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>その一方で、京都を脱出して吉野へ逃れたという生存説も当時から存在しており（彼の逃亡・生存を裏付けるかのように、弘安7年（1284年）に時輔父子を捕縛するよう命ずる関東御教書が発給されている）、真相は未だにはっきりしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there was a theory since then that he was alive by leaving Kyoto for Yoshino (kanto migyosho (An official message from Kanto) was issued to order to capture Tokisuke and his son in 1284 as if it confirmed his escape and survival), but the truth is still not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there has been a theory since then that he managed to leave Kyoto for Yoshino to be alive (kanto migyosho (an official message from Kanto) was issued to order to capture Tokisuke and his sons in 1284 as if it confirmed his escape and survival); but the truth is still not clear.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there has been a theory since then that he managed to leave Kyoto for Yoshino to be alive (kanto migyosho (an official message from Kanto) was issued to order to capture Tokisuke and his sons in 1284 as if it confirmed his escape and survival); but the truth is still not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>子供は父の死後（もしくは消息途絶後）も諸国を流浪していたとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children seemed to be wandering various districts after his father&apos;s death (or after he was missing).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children seemed to be wandering various districts after his father&apos;s death (or after he went missing).</e>
<cmt>after he was missing ---&gt; after he went missing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children seemed to be wandering various districts after his father&apos;s death (or after he went missing).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>時宗の死から6年後の正応3年（1290年）11月に次男とされる人物が三浦頼盛と謀反を共謀したとして六波羅探題に捕縛され、拷問を受けて斬首された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 1290, six years after Tokimune&apos;s death, the person who was identified as the second son was captured in Rokuhara Tandai as he was said to be conspired a rebellion with Yorimori MIURA and was tortured to death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1290, six years after Tokimune&apos;s death, a man identified as the second son was captured by Rokuhara Tandai; he was allegedly accused of plotting a rebellion with Yorimori MIURA and was tortured to death.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1290, six years after Tokimune&apos;s death, a man identified as the second son was captured by Rokuhara Tandai; he was allegedly accused of plotting a rebellion with Yorimori MIURA and was tortured to death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>名は伝えられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was not told.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was not told.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was not told.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>長男については消息不明のままである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eldest son is still missing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There has been no description about his eldest son since he got missing.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There has been no description about his eldest son since he got missing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、2001年に放送された日本放送協会大河ドラマ『北条時宗 (NHK大河ドラマ)』では、吉野へ逃れた後さらに高麗へ渡り、モンゴル帝国軍の九州攻撃作戦の立案に関与したというストーリーが描かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in &quot;Tokimune HOJO (NHK Historical drama)&quot; of Japan Broadcasting Corporation Historical drama broadcasted in 2001, the story was depicted that he went across to Goryeo after escaping to Yoshino and involved in planning of tactics to attack Kyushu by the Mongolian Empire Army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in a Japan Broadcasting Corporation Historical drama &quot;Tokimune HOJO (NHK Historical drama)&quot; broadcasted in 2001, the story depicted that he went across to Goryeo after escaping to Yoshino and got involved in making a plan to attack Kyushu by the Mongolian Empire Army.</e>
<cmt>「日本放送協会」と「ＮＨＫ」は同じ組織なので「日本放送協会大河ドラマ」と「NHK大河ドラマ」は重複しています。しかし、原文通りに両方を訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in a Japan Broadcasting Corporation Historical drama &quot;Tokimune HOJO (NHK Historical drama)&quot; broadcasted in 2001, the story depicted that he went across to Goryeo after escaping to Yoshino and got involved in making a plan to attack Kyushu by the Mongolian Empire Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、これは前述の逃亡・生存説を大幅にデフォルメした創作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this was fiction that was largely deformed his previously mentioned escape and survival theory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this is fiction in which his escape and survival theory previously mentioned is deformed quite a lot.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this is fiction in which his escape and survival theory previously mentioned is deformed quite a lot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>官職および位階等の履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of his government posts and Ikai (Court rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of his government posts and Ikai (Court rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of his government posts and Ikai (Court rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="23">
<j>1256年（建長8年）8月11日、元服。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) on September 8, 1256.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) on September 8, 1256.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age) on September 8, 1256.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>時利と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He used the name Tokitoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called himself Tokitoshi.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Tokitoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>1264年（文永元年）10月、幕府の六波羅探題南方に赴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata of the bakufu in October 1264.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata of the bakufu in October 1264.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned to Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata of the bakufu in October 1264.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>没年月日まで在任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served there until he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served there until he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served there until he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>1265年（文永2年）4月11日、従五位下に叙し、式部少丞に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and Shikibu shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Ceremonial) on May 5, 1265.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was conferred on him and he was appointed to Shikibu shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Ceremonial) on May 5, 1265.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was conferred on him and he was appointed to Shikibu shojo (Junior Secretary of the Ministry of Ceremonial) on May 5, 1265.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>（これにより式部大夫とも式部大夫丞とも称される。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(With that, he was also called Shikibu no taifu or Shikibu no taifujo.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(With that, he was also called Shikibu no taifu (式部大夫) or Shikibu no taifujo (式部大夫丞).)</e>
<cmt>次に続く文との関係で漢字の名前も記述</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(With that, he was also called Shikibu no taifu (式部大夫) or Shikibu no taifujo (式部大夫丞).)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>（よって、古文書の中には式部大輔の表記があるが明らかに過誤）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Therefore, there was a description of Shikibu no taifu in ancient documents but it was clearly an error.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Therefore, although some ancient documents have a description of 式部大輔 (Shikibu no taifu), the description in Kanji is clearly a mistake.)</e>
<cmt>漢字表記を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Therefore, although some ancient documents have a description of 式部大輔 (Shikibu no taifu), the description in Kanji is clearly a mistake.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), やりたこ(id:113528), 帝皇(id:112059), Cprobot(id:97843), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 味っ子(id:17086), 前図書頭(id:134750), 小者(id:172526), Easyman(id:86871), Call Tenderas(id:169753), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Revolução dos Cravos(id:220107), UMBRO(id:100484), 怪蘇(id:45514), Kanoe(id:17203), Junger(id:10282), Gigabyte(id:68875), Bankokuya(id:91191), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>