<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>島井宗室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soshitsu SHIMAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soshitsu SHIMAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soshitsu SHIMAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>島井(嶋井) 宗室（しまい そうしつ、天文 (元号)8年（1539年）- 元和 (日本)元年8月24日 (旧暦)（1615年10月16日））は、戦国時代 (日本)、安土桃山時代から江戸時代の博多の商人、茶道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soshitsu SHIMAI (1539 - October 16, 1615) was a Hakata merchant and chajin (master of the tea ceremony) who lived in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan), from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「茶道」はリンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると「茶人」となっていましたので、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soshitsu SHIMAI (1539 - October 16, 1615) was a Hakata merchant and chajin (master of the tea ceremony) of the Sengoku period (period of warring states), who lived from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「who lived in」→「of」, 「(Japan)」削除(clear from the context),「who lived」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soshitsu SHIMAI (1539 - October 16, 1615) was a merchant in Hakata and a master of the tea ceremony who lived from the period of warring states, Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は茂勝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was Shigekatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was Shigekatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was Shigekatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>号は虚白軒。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known under the name of Kyohakuken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known under the name of Kyohakuken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known by the name of Kyohakuken.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>千利休とも親交が深かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was on close terms with SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was on close terms with SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was on good terms with SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>当時の博多では多くの豪商が犇めいていたが、特に宗室・神屋宗湛・大賀宗九は「博多の三傑」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hakata at that time, there were many wealthy merchants; in particular, Soshitsu, Sotan KAMIYA, and Soku OGA were collectively called &quot;three contributors in Hakata.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hakata at that time, there were many wealthy merchants; in particular, Soshitsu, Sotan KAMIYA, and Soku OGA were collectively called &quot;the three great men of Hakata.&quot;</e>
<cmt>三傑 is a little problematic. Could I suggest 「three contributors」→「the three great men」?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hakata at that time, there were many wealthy merchants; in particular, Soshitsu, Sotan KAMIYA, and Soku OGA who were collectively called &apos;the three great men in Hakata.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、宗室と宗湛は秀吉取立て商人であり、大賀宗九は黒田氏取立て商人というわけで、歴史学というジャンルでは、両者の性格は全く違う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Soshitsu and Sotan were the merchants under the patronage of Hideyoshi, Soku OGA was the merchant under the patronage of the Kuroda clan: the natures of the two types of merchants are completely different in historical science.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Soshitsu and Sotan were merchants under the patronage of Hideyoshi, Soku OGA was a merchant under the patronage of the Kuroda clan: the natures of the two types of merchants appear completely different through the lens of history.</e>
<cmt>「the」削除, 「the」→「a」,「are」→「appear」, 「in historical science」→「through the lens of history」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Soshitsu and Sotan were merchants under the patronage of Hideyoshi, Soku OGA was a merchant under the patronage of the Kuroda clan: the natures of the two types of merchants appear completely different through the history.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>島井家の系図には、藤原北家の血筋をひき、代々藤氏を名乗ったが、次郎右衛門茂久の代に、島井姓に改めたと書いてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the family tree of the Shimai family, the family was descended from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and the descendants identified themselves Toji (the Fujiwara clan) for generations; they changed their family name to Shimai in the generation of Jiro Uemon Shigehisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the family tree of the Shimai family, the family was descended from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and the descendants identified themselves as Toji (the Fujiwara clan) for generations; they changed their family name to Shimai in the generation of Jiro Uemon Shigehisa.</e>
<cmt>「as」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the family tree of the Shimai family, the family was descended from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and the descendants declared themselves Toji (the Fujiwara clan) for generations; however, they changed their family name to Shimai in the generation of Jiro Uemon Shigehisa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>対馬の宗氏の家臣である島井氏の一族と言う説もあるが定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is one theory that Soshitsu was from the family of the Shimai clan that was a vassal of the So clan in Tsushima; however, this theory has not been confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is one theory that Soshitsu was from the family of the Shimai clan, vassals of the So clan in Tsushima; however, this theory has not been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>「that was a vassal」→「, vassals」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is one theory that Soshitsu was from the family of the Shimai clan, the vassal of the So clan in Tsushima; however, this theory has not been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>神谷宗湛とは親族関係にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He and Sotan KAMIYA were the relatives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He and Sotan KAMIYA were relatives.</e>
<cmt>「the」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotan KAMIYA was his relative.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>当時の名物茶器は国一つと交換できるレベルの価値だったが、その中でも「初花」「新田」「楢柴」は天下の三大名器と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, a special chaki (tea utensils) was so valuable that one could exchange chaki with a nation; in particular, &quot;Hatsuhana,&quot; &quot;Nitta,&quot; and &quot;Narashiba&quot; were called the three most special chaki in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, special chaki (tea utensils) were so valuable that it was said one could exchange a single chaki for a whole realm; in particular, &quot;Hatsuhana,&quot; &quot;Nitta,&quot; and &quot;Narashiba&quot; were called the three most special chaki in the world.</e>
<cmt>「a」削除, 「was」→「were」, 「it was said」挿入,「chaki with a nation」→「a single chaki for a whole realm」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, special tea bowls were so valuable that it was said one could exchange a single tea bowl for a whole province; in particular, &apos;Hatsuhana,&apos; &apos;Nitta,&apos; and &apos;Narashiba&apos; were called the three most special tea bowls in the world.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>宗室はそのうちの一つである楢柴を持つほどの豪商だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soshitsu was such a wealthy merchant that he owned one of the above chaki, &quot;Narashiba&quot;</e>
<cmt>My translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soshitsu was such a wealthy merchant that he owned one of the above tea bowls, &apos;Narashiba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>博多で酒屋や金融業を営むかたわら、明や李氏朝鮮とも日朝貿易を行なって巨万の富を築き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While running a sake shop and banking business in Hakata, he engaged himself in the Japan-Korea Trade with Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea, thereby acquiring enormous wealth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While running both a sake shop and banking business in Hakata, he engaged himself in the Japan-Korea Trade with Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea, thereby acquiring enormous wealth.</e>
<cmt>「both」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While running both a sake shop and banking business in Hakata, he engaged in the Japan-Korea Trade with Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea, thereby acquiring enormous wealth.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>天正元年（1573年）には、当時の博多の領有者大友義鎮との取引きを開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1573, he started transactions with Yoshishige OTOMO who possessed the domain in Hakata at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1573, he started dealing with Yoshishige OTOMO who possessed the domain in Hakata at that time.</e>
<cmt>「transactions」→「dealing」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1573, he started dealing with Yoshishige OTOMO, who possessed the domain in Hakata at that time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同じ頃、堺の茶人兼豪商である千宗易や天王寺屋道叱らと懇意になり、数奇者として、朝鮮貿易業者として交歓しあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he became friendly with Soeki SEN, who was a chajin and wealthy merchant in Sakai, and Doshitsu TENNOJIYA and associated with one another as sukisha (tea masters) and Japan-Korea traders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he became friendly with Soeki SEN, who was a chajin and wealthy merchant in Sakai, and Doshitsu TENNOJIYA, and they associated as sukisha (tea masters) and Japan-Korea traders.</e>
<cmt>「,」挿入,「they」挿入,「with one another」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he became friendly with Soeki SEN and Doshitsu TENNOJIYA, who were masters of tea ceremony and wealthy merchants in Sakai, and they associated with each other as tea masters and Japan-Korea traders.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>大友氏や、対馬の宗氏らの軍資金を調達する代わりに、大友宗麟から様々な特権を得て豪商としての地位を確立してゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On behalf of the Otomo clan and the So clan in Tsushima, he supplied the sinews of war, thereby obtaining various privileges from Sorin OTOMO to establish his position as a wealthy merchant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On behalf of the Otomo clan and the So clan in Tsushima, he supplied war funds, thereby obtaining various privileges from Sorin OTOMO to establish his position as a wealthy merchant.</e>
<cmt>「the sinews of war」→「war funds」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In exchange for supplying war funds for the Otomo clan and the So clan in Tsushima, he obtained various privileges from Sorin OTOMO to establish his position as a wealthy merchant.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>耳川の戦いで大友氏が没落し、代わって島津氏が台頭してくると、大友氏寄りの宗室は自身の特権が島津氏に奪われることを危惧して当時の天下人・織田信長に謁見して、その保護を得ようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Otomo clan was defeated in the Battle of Mimi-kawa and then the Shimazu clan gained power, Soshitsu, close to the Otomo clan, became afraid that his privileges would be taken away by the Shimazu clan, so he met Nobunaga ODA, the then tenkabito (person becoming the ruler of the country), to gain protection from him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Otomo clan was defeated in the Battle of Mimi-kawa and the Shimazu clan gained power, Soshitsu, close to the Otomo clan, became afraid that his privileges would be taken away by the Shimazu clan, so he met Nobunaga ODA, the then tenkabito (person becoming the ruler of the country), to gain protection from him.</e>
<cmt>「then」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Otomo clan was defeated in the Battle of Mimi-kawa and the Shimazu clan gained power, Soshitsu who was close to the Otomo clan became afraid that his privileges would be taken away by the Shimazu clan so that he met the then ruler of the country Nobunaga ODA to gain protection from him.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この際に楢柴を信長に譲ることを条件にしたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, at the same time, he offered handing over Narashiba to Nobunaga in exchange for protection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, at the same time, he offered to hand over Narashiba to Nobunaga in exchange for protection.</e>
<cmt>「handing」→「to hand」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, at this occasion, he offered to hand over the tea bowl &apos;Narashiba&apos; to Nobunaga in exchange for protection.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>信長は諸外国との貿易を前提に宗室を保護しようとしたが、天正10年（1582年）の本能寺の変で死去したため、この目論見は露と消えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga tried to protect Soshitsu on the condition of having trade with foreign countries, but Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident in 1582 only to thwart Soshitsu&apos;s plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga tried to protect Soshitsu on the condition of having trade with foreign countries, but Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident in 1582 only to thwart Soshitsu&apos;s plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga tried to protect Soshitsu on the condition of having trade with foreign countries, but as Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident in 1582, Soshitsu&apos;s plan was cancelled.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>逸話として、本能寺の変の際に宗室は弘法大師空海直筆の『千字文』を持ち出したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote that Soshitsu took out &quot;Senjimon&quot; (the Thousand Character Classic), Kobo-Daishi Kukai&apos;s autograph, from Honno-ji Temple in the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote that Soshitsu took &quot;Senjimon&quot; (the Thousand Character Classic), Kobo-Daishi Kukai&apos;s autograph, from Honno-ji Temple in the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>「out」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an episode that Soshitsu took &quot;Senjimon&quot; (the Thousand Character Classic), Kobo-Daishi Kukai&apos;s autograph, from Honno-ji Temple in the Honnoji Incident.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>『千文字』は現在では博多の東長寺に収められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Senjimon&quot; is now housed in Tocho-ji Temple in Hakata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Senjimon&quot; is now housed in Tocho-ji Temple in Hakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Senjimon&quot; is now housed in Tocho-ji Temple in Hakata.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>信長の死後に台頭した豊臣秀吉の保護を得て、畿内から博多、さらには対馬にいたる交通路を築き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soshitsu gained protection from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who gained power after Nobunaga&apos;s death, and built transportation lines that extended from the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) to Hakata and further to Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soshitsu gained protection from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who gained power after Nobunaga&apos;s death, and built transportation lines that extended from the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) to Hakata and further to Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soshitsu gained protection from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who gained power after Nobunaga&apos;s death, and established transportation lines extending from the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) to Hakata and further to Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これによって南蛮・朝鮮などの貿易品の取引を行ない、栄華を極めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, he traded products with nanban (Southeast Asian countries), Korea etc., being at the height of his prosperity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, he traded products with nanban (Southeast Asian countries) and Korea among others, and was at the height of his prosperity.</e>
<cmt>「Accordingly」→「Following this」, 「, Korea etc.」→「and Korea among others」,「being」→「and was」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, he traded products with the Southeast Asian countries and Korea among others, and reached his highest prosperity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>秀吉の九州征伐にも協力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he helped Hideyoshi for the Kyushu Conquest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he helped Hideyoshi during the Kyushu Conquest.</e>
<cmt>「for」→「during」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he helped Hideyoshi during the Kyushu Conquest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>天下統一後、秀吉が朝鮮出兵(文禄・慶長の役)を企むと、大切な通商国と戦争するという利害からこれに強硬に反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the unification of the country, Hideyoshi attempted to dispatch troops to Korea (the Bunroku-Keicho War); however, Soshitsu strongly argued that Japan should not battle against Korea as Korea was an important trading nation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the unification of the country, Hideyoshi attempted to dispatch troops to Korea (the Bunroku-Keicho War); however, Soshitsu strongly argued that Japan should not battle against Korea as Korea was an important trading nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the unification of the country, Hideyoshi attempted to dispatch troops to Korea (the Bunroku-Keicho War); however, Soshitsu strongly opposed that Japan should not battle against Korea which was an important trading partner.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>宗義智と協力して渡朝し、朝鮮国王と戦争回避を図る折衝を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He cooperated with Yoshitoshi SO and visited the Kingdom of Korea to have negotiation for avoiding wars.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He cooperated with Yoshitoshi SO and visited the Kingdom of Korea for negotiations to avoid war.</e>
<cmt>「to have negotiation for avoiding war」→「for negotiations to avoid war」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He cooperated with Yoshitoshi SO and visited the King of Korea for negotiations to avoid war.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかしこれは空回りに終わったうえ、秀吉の派兵後も撤兵を強硬に主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his attempt was unsuccessful; additionally, he strongly insisted on the withdrawal even after Hideyoshi&apos;s troop dispatch.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his attempt was unsuccessful; additionally, he strongly insisted on the withdrawal even after Hideyoshi&apos;s troop dispatch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his attempt was unsuccessful; additionally, he strongly insisted on the withdrawal even after the Hideyoshi&apos;s troop dispatch.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そのため、遂に秀吉の怒りを買って蟄居を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, he incurred Hideyoshi&apos;s anger and thus was ordered to be confined in his house.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, he incurred Hideyoshi&apos;s anger and thus was ordered to be confined to his house.</e>
<cmt>「in」→「to」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, he incurred Hideyoshi&apos;s anger and thus, was ordered to be confined to his house.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>後に許された後は、五奉行の石田三成と協力して日本軍の後方兵站役を務める一方で、明との和平の裏工作を行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he was forgiven later, he cooperated with Mitsunari ISHIDA, who was Gobugyo (five major magistrates), and served as military logistics support of the Japanese army, while he arranged peace with Ming behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was forgiven later, he cooperated with Mitsunari ISHIDA, who was a Gobugyo (one of the five major magistrates), and served as military logistics support of the Japanese army, while he arranged peace with Ming officials behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt>「a」挿入,「one of the」挿入,「officials」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was forgiven later, he cooperated with Mitsunari ISHIDA, who was one of the five major magistrates, and served as military logistics support of the Japanese army, while he arranged peace with Ming officials behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="29">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）の関ヶ原の戦い後、博多が黒田氏の支配下に入ると、宗室は黒田長政の福岡城築城などに協力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600 when Hakata became under control of the Kuroda clan, Soshitsu cooperated with Nagamasa KURODA to build Fukuoka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600 when Hakata came under the control of the Kuroda clan, Soshitsu cooperated with Nagamasa KURODA to build Fukuoka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>「became」→「came」, 「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hakata came under the control of the Kuroda clan after the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, Soshitsu cooperated with Nagamasa KURODA to build Fukuoka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>元和元年（1615年）8月24日、77歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 77 on August 24, 1615.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 77 on August 24, 1615.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 77 on October 16, 1615.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>墓地は崇福寺瑞雲庵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is at Zuiun-an of the Sofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is at Zuiun-an of the Sofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His graveyard is at Zuiun-an of the Sofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>死の直前、養嗣子の島井信吉に対して17ヶ条の訓戒を送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Right before he died, he sent the Seventeen Injunctions to his adopted heir Shinkichi SHIMAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before he died, he sent the Seventeen Injunctions to his adopted heir Shinkichi SHIMAI.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before he died, he sent the Seventeen Injunctions to his adopted heir Shinkichi SHIMAI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="33">
<j>著作に『島井宗室日記』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the author of &quot;Shimai Soshitsu nikki&quot; (diary of Soshitsu SHIMAI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the author of &quot;Shimai Soshitsu nikki&quot; (diary of Soshitsu SHIMAI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the author of &quot;Shimai Soshitsu nikki&quot; (diary of Soshitsu SHIMAI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>肖像画は福岡市立博物館所蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His portrait is housed in Fukuoka City Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His portrait is housed in Fukuoka City Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His portrait is housed in the Fukuoka City Museum.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="35">
<j>福岡高速道路呉服町出入口近くに島井宗室屋敷跡の石碑がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a stone monument of the site of the residence of Soshitsu SHIMAI near the exit of Gofukumachi Interchange of the Fukuoka Urban Expressway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a stone monument at the site of the residence of Soshitsu SHIMAI near the exit of Gofukumachi Interchange on the Fukuoka Urban Expressway.</e>
<cmt>「of」→「at」, 「of」→「on」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a stone monument at the site of the residence of Soshitsu SHIMAI near the exit of Gofukumachi Interchange on the Fukuoka Urban Expressway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), でここ(id:9565), Yonoemon(id:55450), Pontafon(id:33761), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Nitobe inazou(id:203211), Cprobot(id:97843), Point136(id:211299), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Chocoyoshi(id:170796), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>