<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>那須与一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NASU no Yoichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NASU no Yoichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NASU no Yoichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>那須与一（なすの よいち、嘉応元年（1169年）？ - 没年不詳）は、平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NASU no Yoichi (1169 - date of death unknown) was a warlord at the end of the Heian era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NASU no Yoichi (1169 - date of death unknown) was a warlord at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NASU no Yoichi (1169 - date of death unknown) was a warlord at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>系図上は那須氏二代当主と伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was the second family head of Nasu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was the second family head of the Nasu clan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was the second family head of the Nasu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は那須資隆（太郎）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Suketaka (Taro) NASU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Suketaka (Taro) NASU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Suketaka (Taro) NASU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>妻は新田義重の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was a daughter of Yoshishige NITTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was a daughter of Yoshishige NITTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was a daughter of Yoshishige NITTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>一般的には本名は「那須宗隆」（平家物語では宗高）と紹介されることも多いが、これは初名であり、当主に就任後は父と同名の資隆と名乗ったと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, his real name is often introduced as &apos;Munetaka NASU&apos; (Munetaka in Heike Monogatari (The Tales of the Heike,)) which is his first name, and since accession to the family head, it is said that he was identifying himself as the same name Suketaka as his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, his real name is introduced as &apos;Munetaka NASU&apos; (Munetaka in Heike Monogatari (The Tales of the Heike)), which is his first name, but it is said that since his accession to the position of family head he identified himself with his father&apos;s name, Suketaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, his real name is introduced as &apos;Munetaka NASU&apos; (Munetaka in Heike Monogatari (The Tales of the Heike)), which is his first name, but it is said that since his accession to the position of family head he identified himself with his father&apos;s name, Suketaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>（この項目での呼称は｢与一｣で統一する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Name in this section will be unified as &apos;Yoichi&apos;.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The name in this section will be unified as &apos;Yoichi.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The name in this section will be unified as &apos;Yoichi.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>｢与一｣とは</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Yoichi&apos; is</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Yoichi&apos; is</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Yoichi&apos; is</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>与一は十あまる一、つまり十一男をしめす通称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoichi, which means ten plus one, is an alias representing the eleventh man.</e>
<cmt>11番目の息子と理解して、十一男→the eleventh man</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoichi, which means ten plus one, is an alias representing the eleventh man.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoichi, which means ten plus one, is an alias representing the eleventh son.</e>
<cmt>the elventh man→the elventh son (11番目の息子）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、与一を称した同時代人としては佐奈田義忠、浅利義遠がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, persons called as Yoichi in the same era were Yoshitada SANADA and Yorito ASARI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, during the same period Yoshitada SANADA and Yorito ASARI were also referred to as &quot;Yoichi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, during the same period Yoshitada SANADA and Yorito ASARI were also referred to as &quot;Yoichi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>彼らと那須与一を合わせて｢源氏の三与一｣と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of them and Yoichi NASU altogether are called as &apos;Three Yoichi of Genji.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collectively, they are called the &apos;three Yoichi of Genji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collectively, they are called the &apos;three Yoichi of Genji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Personal History</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストによる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>吾妻鏡など、同時代の史料には那須与一の名は見えないため、与一の事跡は軍記物語である平家物語や源平盛衰記に伝えるところが大きい（そのため、学問的には与一の実在すら立証できていない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name Yoichi NASU is not seen in Azuma-kagammi (history book) and other historical materials in the same era, and Yoichi&apos;s performance is heavily relied on the descriptions written in Heike Monogatari and Gempei-Josuiki as military epic (therefore, existence of Yoichi has not been proven academically.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Yoichi NASU is not seen in Azuma-kagammi (history book) and other historical materials of the period, so the assessment of Yoichi&apos;s performance relies heavily on the descriptions written in Heike Monogatari and Gempei-Josuiki as military epics (therefore, the existence of Yoichi has not been proved academically).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name NASU no Yoichi is not seen in Azuma Kagami (history book) and other historical materials of the period, so the assessment of Yoichi&apos;s performance relies heavily on the descriptions written in Heike Monogatari and Gempei-Josuiki as military epics (therefore, the existence of Yoichi has not been proved academically).</e>
<cmt>Yoichi NASU→NASU no YoichiAzuma-kagammi→Azuma Kagami</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>平家物語の記述から逆算すると、1169年（あるいは1166年、1168年）頃に誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Counting backward based on the descriptions of Heike Monogatari, he was born in around 1169 (or 1166, 1168.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Counting backward based on the descriptions of Heike Monogatari, he was born in or around 1169 (or 1166 or 1168).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Counting backward based on the descriptions of Heike Monogatari, he was born in or around 1169 (or 1166 or 1168).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>誕生地は当時の那須氏の居城神田城（現在の栃木県那須郡那珂川町 (栃木県)）と推測されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His place of birth is often assumed to be Kanda Castle (located in Nakagawamachi, Nasu-gun, Tochigi Prefecture (Tochigi Prefecture)) as a Kyojo Castle (where the loard usually lived) for Nasu clan in those days.</e>
<cmt>後続の文章から考えて、より適切と思ったので、居城の英訳の一部（where 以下）を括弧書きした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His place of birth is often assumed to be Kanda Castle (located in Nakagawamachi, Nasu-gun, Tochigi Prefecture (the present-day Tochigi Prefecture)) as a kyojo (castle where the lord usually lived) for the Nasu clan in those days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His place of birth is often assumed to be Kanda Castle (located in Nakagawa-machi, Nasu County, Tochigi Prefecture (the present-day Tochigi Prefecture)) as a kyojo (castle where the lord usually lived) for the Nasu clan in those days.</e>
<cmt>地名表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>治承・寿永の乱において、源頼朝方に加わり源義経に従軍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Jisho-Juei-no-ran War (turmoil of the Jisho-Juei,) he was on MINAMOTO no Yoritomo side and fighted with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Jisho-Juei-no-ran War (turmoil of the Jisho-Juei,) he was on the side of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and fought along with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Jisho-Juei-no-ran War (turmoil of the Jisho-Juei,) he was on the side of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and fought along with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>元暦2年（1185年）の屋島の戦いでは、平氏方の軍船に掲げられた扇子の的を射落とすなど功績を挙げ、源頼朝より丹波国・信濃国など五カ国に荘園を賜った（丹後国五賀荘・若狭国東宮荘・武蔵国太田荘・信濃国角豆荘・備中国後月郡荏原荘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Yashima in 1185, he achieved a great performance such that he dropped a folding fan as an aim hoisted onto the Taira clan&apos;s gunsen (battleship) by arrow, and was rewarded with manors in five kuni including Tamba-no-kuni and Shinano-no-kuni from MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (Goka-no-sho manor in Tamba-no-kuni, Togu-no-sho manor in Wakasa-no-kuni, Ota-no-sho manor in Musashi-no-kuni, Sasage-no-sho manor in Shinano-no-kuni and Ebara-no-sho, Shitsuki-gun in Bichu-no-kuni.)</e>
<cmt>軍船→gunsen (battleship)適切な英訳が見つからなかったので、上のようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Yashima in 1185, his achievement was so great that, with a single arrow, he dropped a folding fan as an aim hoisted onto the Taira clan&apos;s gunsen (battleship); consequently, he was rewarded with manors in five kuni, including Tamba-no-kuni and Shinano-no-kuni from MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (Goka-no-sho manor in Tamba-no-kuni, Togu-no-sho manor in Wakasa-no-kuni, Ota-no-sho manor in Musashi-no-kuni, Sasage-no-sho manor in Shinano-no-kuni and Ebara-no-sho, Shitsuki-gun in Bichu-no-kuni.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Yashima in 1185, his achievement was so great that, with a single arrow, he dropped a folding fan as an aim hoisted onto the Taira clan&apos;s gunsen (battleship); consequently, he was rewarded with manors in five Provinces, including Tanba Province and Shinano Province from MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (Goka-no-sho manor in Tanba Province, Togu-no-sho manor in Wakasa Province, Ota-no-sho manor in Musashi Province, Sasage-no-sho manor in Shinano Province and Ebara-no-sho manor in Shitsuki County in Bichu Province)</e>
<cmt>kuni→ProvinceTamba→Tanbagun→County</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、十郎為隆を除く九人の兄達が、皆平氏に味方し、為隆ものちに罪を得たため、与一が十一男ながら那須氏の家督を継ぐ事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, since his nine older brothers excluding Juro-Tametaka supported the Taira clan and also, Tametaka was punished later, Yoichi took over the Nasu clan&apos;s family estate though he was the eleventh man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, since his nine older brothers (excluding Juro-Tametaka) supported the Taira clan, and because Tametaka was punished later, Yoichi took over the Nasu clan&apos;s family estate, though he was the eleventh man.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, since his nine older brothers (excluding Juro-Tametaka) supported the Taira clan, and because Tametaka was punished later, Yoichi took over the Nasu clan&apos;s family estate, though he was the eleventh son.</e>
<cmt>the elventh man→the eleventh son</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>与一は信濃など各地に逃亡していた兄達を赦免し領土を分け与え、下野国における那須氏発展の基礎を築いたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the tradition, Yoichi pardoned his older brothers who were on the run in Shinano and other areas and spared out land to them, and constructed a foundation for the development of the Nasu clan in shimotsuke-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to legend, Yoichi pardoned his older brothers who were on the run in Shinano and other areas and allotted land to them, whereupon he constructed a foundation for the development of the Nasu clan in shimotsuke-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to legend, Yoichi pardoned his older brothers who were on the run in Shinano and other areas and allotted land to them, and he constructed a foundation for the development of the Nasu clan in Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>whereuponを使うと、原文の意味からずれるため、andに戻しました。Shimotsuke-no-kuni→Shimotsuke Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、某年、山城国伏見において死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a certain year, he died in Fushimi, Yamashiro-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>ここで、”しかし”は不自然なので英訳しなかった。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in Fushimi, Yamashiro-no-kuni, but the exact year isn&apos;t known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in Fushimi in Yamashiro Province, but the exact year is not known.</e>
<cmt>Yamashiro-no-kuni→Yamashiro Provinceisn&apos;t→is not</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>法名は即成院殿禅海宗悟大居士（又は即成院殿月山洞明大居士）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Sokujo-inden Zenkai-Sogo Daikoji (or Sokujo-inden Gassan-Domyo Daikoji.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Buddhist name was Sokujo-inden Zenkai-Sogo Daikoji (or Sokujo-inden Gassan-Domyo Daikoji).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Sokujo-inden Zenkai-Sogo Daikoji (or Sokujo-inden Gassan-Domyo Daikoji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、「寛政重修諸家譜」では文治5年（1189年）8月8日死去、「続群書類従」では建久元年（1190年）10月死去とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, his date of death is August 8, 1189 in Kansei-Choshu-Shokafu, and October 1190 in Zoku-Gunshoruiju (Japanese history book.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, his date of death is given as August 8, 1189 in Kansei-Choshu-Shokafu, but it&apos;s given as October 1190 in Zoku-Gunshoruiju (Japanese history book).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, his date of death is given as August 8, 1189 in Kansei-Choshu-Shokafu, but it&apos;s given as October 1190 in Zoku-Gunshoruiju (Japanese history book).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>家督は兄の那須資之が継承したが、まもなく鎌倉幕府の有力御家人宇都宮朝綱の実子（異説もある）である那須頼資が資之の養子となり家督を継ぎ、その頼資の子が、建久4年（1193年）に源頼朝の那須巻狩の際にホスト役を務めた（『吾妻鏡』による）那須光資である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after Sukeyuki NASU, his older brother took over the family estate, Yorisuke NASU, a blood child (also, heresy exists) of Tomotsuna UTSUNOMIYA serving as a key lower-ranking vassal for the Kamakura Shogunate was adopted as Sukeyuki&apos;s son to take over the family estate, and Yorisuke&apos;s child was Mitsusuke NASU, who played a role to host Ｙｏｒｉｔomo MINAMOTO in the Nasu Makigari (hunting technique) in 1193 (according to &quot;Azuma Kagami (Japanese classics)&quot;.)</e>
<cmt>”吾妻鏡”の定訳が見つからなかった。Azuma Mirror, Azuma Kagami等のうち、Azuma Kagamiを採用した。”古典”→Japanese classicsを追加した。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after his older brother, Sukeyuki NASU, took over the family estate, Yorisuke NASU, a blood child (though hearsay exists) of Tomotsuna UTSUNOMIYA, who served as a key lower-ranking vassal for the Kamakura shogunate, was adopted as Sukeyuki&apos;s son in order to take over the family estate; but Yorisuke&apos;s child was Mitsusuke NASU, who had played the role of hosting Ｙｏｒｉｔomo MINAMOTO in the Nasu Makigari (hunting technique) in 1193 (according to &quot;Azuma Kagami (Japanese Classics)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after his older brother, Sukeyuki NASU, took over the family estate, Yorisuke NASU, a blood child (though hearsay exists) of Tomotsuna UTSUNOMIYA, who served as a key lower-ranking vassal for the Kamakura shogunate, was adopted as Sukeyuki&apos;s son in order to take over the family estate; and Yorisuke&apos;s child was Mitsusuke NASU, who had played the role of hosting Ｙｏｒｉｔomo MINAMOTO in the Nasu Makigari (hunting technique) in 1193 (according to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (history book)).</e>
<cmt>butでは原文と意味がずれるので、and に戻しました。吾妻鏡は、Azuma Kagami (history book)　で既出なので、そちらに統一。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>異説・伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heresy/legend</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearsay and Legend</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearsay and Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>幼いころから弓の腕が達者で、居並ぶ兄達の前でその腕前を示し父を驚嘆させたという地元の伝承がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had been an expert archer since his childhood, and there is a local legend that his father was amazed at his technique demonstrated in front of all older brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had been an expert archer since his childhood, and there is a local legend that his father was amazed at the technique he demonstrated in front of all the older brothers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had been an expert archer since his childhood, and there is a local legend that his father was amazed at the technique he demonstrated in front of all the older brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、治承4年（1180年）、那須岳で弓の稽古をしていた時、那須温泉神社に必勝祈願に来た源義経に出会い、父・資隆が兄の千本為隆と与一を源氏方に従軍させる約束を交わしたという伝説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another legend that when practicing archery in Nasu-dake (Mt. Nasudake) in 1180, they met Yoshitsune MINAMOTO visiting Nasu Onsen-jinja Shrine to pray for definite victory, and Yoichi&apos;s father, Yorisuke exchanged a promise that he would let Yoichi and his older brother, Tametaka SEMBON to fight for the Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>点で区切られた3つの文の主語があいまいだ。きっと、家族で稽古中であったと思われる。明記されていないので、左記のように英訳した。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another legend that when practicing archery at Nasu-dake (Mt. Nasudake) in 1180, they met Yoshitsune MINAMOTO, who was visiting Nasu Onsen-jinja Shrine to pray for certain victory, and Yoichi&apos;s father Yorisuke exchanged a promise that he would let Yoichi and his older brother Tametaka SEMBON fight for the Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another legend that when practicing archery at Nasu-dake (Mt. Nasudake) in 1180, they met MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, who was visiting Nasu Onsen-jinja Shrine to pray for certain victory, and Yoichi&apos;s father Suketaka exchanged a promise that he would let Yoichi and his older brother Tametaka SENBON fight for the Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>Yoshitsune MINAMOTO→MINAMOTO no YoshitsuneYorisuke→SuketakaSEMBON→SENBON</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その他与一が開基とする寺社がいくつか存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there are some temples and shrines the founders of which are said to be Yoichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there are some temples and shrines about which it is said that Yoichi was a founder.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there are some temples and shrines about which it is said that Yoichi was a founder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>平家物語に記される、扇の的を射抜く話が非常に有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story about Yoichi&apos;s shooting a folding fan as an aim which is described in the Heike-Monogatari is very well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story about Yoichi&apos;s shooting a folding fan as a target, as described in the Heike-Monogatari, is very well known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story about Yoichi&apos;s shooting a folding fan as a target, as described in Heike Monogatari, is very well known.</e>
<cmt>平家物語→Heike Monogatari</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>子孫についてはいないとされているが、歴史学者の那須義定などが主張する異説（越後那須氏）もあり、梶原氏といさかいをおこしたため家督を捨てて出奔し、越後国の五十嵐家に身を寄せ、結婚して一男一女をもうけ（息子は越後那須氏の祖となる）たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They say that Yoichi had no offspring, but, there is a heresy (Echigo-Nasu clan) claimed by Yoshisada NASU, a historian, according to which, after Yoichi gave up the family estate and left home due to conflicts with the Kajiwara clan, he stayed with the Igarashi Family in the Echigo-no-kuni, got married and had a son (becoming ancestor of the Echigo-Nasu clan) and a daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Yoichi had no offspring, but there is hearsay (Echigo-Nasu clan) claimed by the historian Yoshisada NASU, according to which, after Yoichi gave up the family estate and left home due to conflicts with the Kajiwara clan, he stayed with the Igarashi Family in Echigo-no-kuni, got married and had a son (thus establishing himself as an ancestor of the Echigo-Nasu clan) and a daughter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Yoichi had no offspring, but there is hearsay (the Echigo-Nasu clan) claimed by the historian Yoshisada NASU, according to which, after Yoichi gave up the family estate and left home due to conflicts with the Kajiwara clan, he stayed with the Igarashi family in Echigo Province, got married and had a son (thus establishing himself as an ancestor of the Echigo-Nasu clan) and a daughter.</e>
<cmt>Echigo-Nasu clan→the Echigo-Nasu clanthe Igarashi Family→the Igarashi familyEchigo-no-kuni→Echigo Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その他、常陸国、出羽国、阿波国にも与一の末裔と称する一族が存在したという伝承、寺伝がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there are legends or temple histories telling clans called Yoichi&apos;s descendants lived in Hitachi-no-kuni, Dewa-no-kuni and Awa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>寺伝→temple historyhttp://www.tobunken.go.jp/~bijutsu/publications/bijutukenkyu/375_Tsuda.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there are legends or temple histories stating that clans referred to as Yoichi&apos;s descendants lived in Hitachi-no-kuni, Dewa-no-kuni and Awa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there are legends or temple histories stating that clans referred to as Yoichi&apos;s descendants lived in Hitachi Province, Dewa Province and Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>no-kuni→Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>また、没年についても、1189年（又は1190年）に没したとするのは頼朝の粛清を免れるための偽装、出家した理由はハンセン病にかかり顔が変わってしまったため、とする伝承もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another legend that his death in 1189 (or 1190) was disguised to escape Yoritomo&apos;s purge and that the reason for his becoming a priest was that his complexion changed from suffering Hansen&apos;s disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another legend that his death in 1189 (or 1190) was disguised to facilitate his escape from Yoritomo&apos;s purge, and that the reason for his becoming a priest was that his complexion had changed due to Hansen&apos;s disease.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another legend that his death in 1189 (or 1190) was disguised to facilitate his escape from Yoritomo&apos;s purge, and that the reason for his becoming a priest was that his complexion had changed due to Hansen&apos;s disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、那須義定によると頼朝の死後に赦免されて那須に戻った後に出家して浄土宗に帰依し、源平合戦の死者を弔う旅を30年余り続けた後、貞永元年（1232年）に中風のため摂津国で没したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, according to Yoshisada NASU, Yoich was pardoned and returned to Nasu after Yoritomo&apos;s death, became a priest to enter the Jodo-shu sect and died from paralysis in 1232 in the Settsu-no-kuni after his journey of about thirty years mourning dead persons in the Gempei-Kassen Battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, according to Yoshisada NASU, Yoichi was pardoned and returned to Nasu after Yoritomo&apos;s death, became a priest in order to enter the Jodo-shu sect and died from paralysis in 1232 in the Settsu-no-kuni, after a journey of about 30 years mourning those who had died in the Battle of Gempei-Kassen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, according to Yoshisada NASU, Yoichi was pardoned and returned to Nasu after Yoritomo&apos;s death, became a priest in order to enter the Jodo-shu sect and died from paralysis in 1232 in Settsu Province, after a journey of about 30 years mourning those who had died in the Battle of Gempei-Kassen.</e>
<cmt>no-kuni→Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grave</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grave</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>墓所は、京都府京都市の即成院であるが、兄の那須資之が功照院という寺を建立し、分骨を埋葬したといい、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoichi&apos;s grave is Sokujoin in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, but it is said that Sukeyuki NASU, his older brother constructed a temple named Koshoin (功照院) and conducted Bunkotsu (to bury one&apos;s bone more than two places) there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoichi&apos;s grave is Sokujoin in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, but it is said that Sukeyuki NASU, his older brother, constructed a temple called Koshoin (功照院) and there conducted Bunkotsu (to bury one&apos;s bones in more than two places).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoichi&apos;s grave is in Sokujo-in Temple in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, but it is said that Sukeyuki NASU, his older brother, constructed a temple called Kosho-in (功照院) and there conducted Bunkotsu (to bury one&apos;s bones in more than two places).</e>
<cmt>Yoichi&apos;s grave is Sokujoin→Yoichi&apos;s grave in in Sokujo-in TempleKoshoin→Kosho-in</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>永正11年（1514年）に、一度は廃寺になったものの、天正18年（1590年）、那須資景が那須氏の菩提寺玄性寺（栃木県大田原市）として再建し、那須氏では、こちらを本墓としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1514, Sukekage NASU revived Koshoin which had become ruined as their family temple, Gensho-ji Temple (Otawara City, Tochigi Prefecture), and the Nasu clan regards the temple as their main grave.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1514, Sukekage NASU revived Koshoin (the family temple, which had become a ruin) Gensho-ji Temple (Otawara City, Tochigi Prefecture), and the Nasu clan regards the temple as its main gravesite.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1514, Sukekage NASU revived Koshoin (the family temple, which had become a ruin) as Gensho-ji Temple (Otawara City, Tochigi Prefecture), and the Nasu clan regards the temple as its main gravesite.</e>
<cmt>意味が通るよう、 as を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>また、兵庫県神戸市須磨区には、那須興一宗高公御墓所という与市の墓とされるものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in Suma Ward, Kobe City along the coast of Prefecture, there also is one considered as Yoichi&apos;s tomb with the description of Grave of NASU no Yoichi Munetaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in Suma Ward, Kobe City along the coast of Prefecture, there also is one considered to be Yoichi&apos;s tomb; it bears the description, &quot;Grave of NASU no Yoichi Munetaka.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in Suma Ward, Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture, there also is one considered to be Yoichi&apos;s tomb; it bears the description, &quot;Grave of NASU no Yoichi Munetaka.&quot;</e>
<cmt>兵庫県神戸市須磨区→Suma Ward, Kobe City, Hyogo Prefecture</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この墓にお参りすると、年老いても下の世話にならないとする言い伝えがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a lore that people visiting this tomb would not need to rely on shimo no sewa (helping out someone who can&apos;t control the movements of their bodily wastes) when they get older.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a legend that people visiting this tomb would not need to rely on shimo no sewa (helping out the one who can&apos;t control the movements of his or her bodily wastes) in the years of advanced age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a legend that people visiting this tomb would not need to rely on shimo no sewa (helping out the one who can&apos;t control the movements of his or her bodily wastes) in the years of advanced age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また近くには与市が信仰したとされる北向八幡神社と、地元の人々が与市を祀った那須神社がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the vicinity, there are Kitamuki-Hachiman-jinja Shrine for which Yoichi has been believed to have living faith and Nasu-jinja Shrine at which Yoichi has been worshipped by local people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the vicinity, there are Kitamuki-Hachiman-jinja Shrine, for which Yoichi has been believed to have living faith, and Nasu-jinja Shrine, where Yoichi has been worshiped by local people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the vicinity, there are Kitamuki-Hachiman-jinja Shrine, for which Yoichi has been believed to have living faith, and Nasu-jinja Shrine, where Yoichi has been worshiped by local people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>米沢市中央5丁目の西蓮寺の北西隣の虚空蔵菩薩堂の前には、那須与市の名を刻む三重の、高さ高さ約4.2メートルの石塔がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In front of the statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva standing northwest of Sairen-ji Temple in 5 Chome, Chuo, Yonezawa City, there is a three-storied stone pagoda of 4.2 meter high with his name Yoichi NASU imprinted on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In front of the statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva, which stands northwest of Sairen-ji Temple in 5 Chome, Chuo, Yonezawa City, there is a three-story stone pagoda 4.2 meters tall with the name &quot;Yoichi NASU&quot; imprinted on it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In front of the statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva, which stands northwest of Sairen-ji Temple in 5 Chome, Chuo, Yonezawa City, there is a three-story stone pagoda 4.2 meters tall with the name &quot;NASU no Yoichi&quot; imprinted on it.</e>
<cmt>Yoichi NASU→NASU no Yoichi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これは那須与市の供養塔とされ、塔には「那須与市宗隆公」「千坂対馬守景親公」と刻まれており、裏には「享保四年孟夏十三日建立」と建立日が刻まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is deemed as Yoichi NASU&apos;s memorial tower, on which &apos;NASU no Yoichi Munetaka-ko&apos; and &apos;Chizaka (Chisaka) Tsushima-no-kami Kagechika-ko&apos; are imprinted, and on the other side of which &apos;Built on 13th April, 1719&apos; was imprinted for its date of construction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is deemed to be Yoichi NASU&apos;s memorial tower, on which &apos;NASU no Yoichi Munetaka-ko&apos; and &apos;Chizaka (Chisaka) Tsushima-no-kami Kagechika-ko&apos; are imprinted, and on the other side of which &apos;Completed April 13, 1719&apos; was imprinted as its date of construction.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is deemed to be NASU no Yoichi&apos;s memorial tower, on which &apos;NASU no Yoichi Munetaka-ko&apos; and &apos;Chizaka (Chisaka) Tsushima-no-kami Kagechika-ko&apos; are imprinted, and on the other side of which &apos;Completed April 13, 1719&apos; was imprinted as its date of construction.</e>
<cmt>Yoichi NASU→NASU no Yoichi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>千坂景親は上杉謙信の重臣だが、千坂氏は那須氏とは婚族関係にあり、与一の守本尊（虚空蔵菩薩像）が伝わっていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagechika CHIZAKA (CHISAKA) was one of main retainers of Kenshin UESUGI, but it is said that the guardian deity (statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) for Yoichi was introduced to the CHIZAKA (CHISAKA) clan with a marital relationship with the NASU clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagechika CHIZAKA (CHISAKA) was one of the main retainers of Kenshin UESUGI, but it is said that the guardian deity (statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) for Yoichi was introduced to the CHIZAKA (CHISAKA) clan through a marital relationship with the NASU clan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagechika CHIZAKA (CHISAKA) was one of the main retainers of Kenshin UESUGI, but it is said that the guardian deity (statue of Akasagarbha Bodhisattva) for Yoichi was introduced to the CHIZAKA (CHISAKA) clan through a marital relationship with the NASU clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="37">
<j>また扇の的を射た功名で全国に得た荘園のうち1つの備中荏原庄（現在の岡山県井原市西江原）の山中にも与市の五輪供養塔が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there is Yoichi&apos;s Gorin-Kuyoto (memorial tower with Gorin) in the mountains of Bichu-Ebara-no-sho manor (now, Nishi-ebara, Ibara City, Okayama Prefecture), one of the manors Yoichi received around the country for rewards appreciating his performance of shooting an aim, folding fan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there is Yoichi&apos;s Gorin-Kuyoto (memorial tower with Gorin) in the mountains of Bichu-Ebara-no-sho manor (the present-day Nishi-ebara, Ibara City, Okayama Prefecture), one of the manors Yoichi received around the country for rewards appreciating his feat of shooting a folding fan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there is Yoichi&apos;s Gorin-Kuyoto (memorial tower with Gorin) in the mountains of Bichu-Ebara-no-sho manor (the present-day Nishi-ebara, Ibara City, Okayama Prefecture), one of the manors Yoichi received around the country for rewards appreciating his feat of shooting a folding fan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また備中荏原の菩提寺として開基した永祥寺の境内には、屋島での合戦時に破り捨てた片袖を祭った袖神神社や、那須一族の居城とされる小菅城址や創建した神社も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in the grounds of Eisho-ji Temple which was founded in Bichu-Ebara as their family temple, there are Sodegami-jinja Shrine (袖神神社) worshipping the sleeve torn off while fighting the Battle of Yashima and the site of Kosuge Castle considered as NASU clan&apos;s headquarters as well as constructed temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in the grounds of Eisho-ji Temple which was founded in Bichu-Ebara as their family temple, there are Sodegami-jinja Shrine (袖神神社) dedicated to a sleeve that was torn off while fighting the Battle of Yashima, and the site of Kosuge Castle, which is considered the NASU clan&apos;s headquarters, as well as various temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in the grounds of Eisho-ji Temple which was founded in Bichu-Ebara as their family temple, there are Sodegami-jinja Shrine (袖神神社) dedicated to a sleeve that was torn off while fighting the Battle of Yashima, and the site of Kosuge Castle, which is considered the NASU clan&apos;s headquarters, as well as other shrines they founded.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に合うように、最後の部分を書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>後世への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence on future generations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence on Future Generations</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence on Future Generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>那須氏の当主の通称は一部の例外を除いて代々｢那須太郎｣であったが（那須資隆、那須光資等）、江戸時代以降、那須資景など那須氏の歴代当主は通称として｢那須与一｣を称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aliases of the NASU clan&apos;s family heads had been &apos;NASU no Taro&apos; from generation to generation with certain exceptions (Suketaka NASU and Mitsusuke NASU), but since the Edo era, the Nasu clan&apos;s successive family heads including Sukekage NASU were using &apos;Yoichi NASU&apos; as their alias.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The alias of the NASU clan&apos;s family head had been &apos;NASU no Taro&apos; from generation to generation with certain exceptions (Suketaka NASU and Mitsusuke NASU), but since the Edo period the Nasu clan&apos;s successive family heads, including Sukekage NASU, used &apos;Yoichi NASU&apos; as the alias.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The alias of the NASU clan&apos;s family head had been &apos;NASU no Taro&apos; from generation to generation with certain exceptions (Suketaka NASU and Mitsusuke NASU), but since the Edo period the Nasu clan&apos;s successive family heads, including Sukekage NASU, used &apos; NASU no Yoichi&apos; as the alias.</e>
<cmt>Yoichi NASU→NASU no Yoichi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>現代の日本において、各種の二次創作物やフィクションに登場する｢那須与一｣は、この与一をモデルにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern years of Japan, &apos;Yoichi NASU&apos; appearing in various side creations or fictions have been modeled on this Yoichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern years of Japan, &apos;Yoichi NASU&apos; appearing in various side creations or fictional works have been modeled on this Yoichi.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern years of Japan, &apos;NASU no Yoichi&apos; appearing in various side creations or fictional works have been modeled on this Yoichi.</e>
<cmt>Yoichi NASU→NASU no Yoichi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>那須氏に関係する、または与一と関係があったとする伝承が存在する神社仏閣などでは、与一にちなんだ祭りが行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temples and shrines with legends that they had relations with or were related to Yoichi hold festivals related to Yoichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temples and shrines whose legends state that they had relations with or were related to Yoichi hold festivals associated with Yoichi.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temples and shrines whose legends state that they had relations with or were related to Yoichi hold festivals associated with Yoichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), CRX(id:45108), KMT(id:1772), Carbuncle(id:346), Kussy(id:3128), 松茸(id:27535), Lupinoid(id:68), Yanahan(id:2437), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Charon(id:9162), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), Terrykyo(id:92403), Kafuka1964(id:105407), Jugger90(id:17088), きたし(id:81414), Nnn(id:26535), Hotneko(id:38627), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), NPD(id:58640), Arara(id:66298), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Louperibot(id:128971), Toki-ho(id:10691), 三日月(id:19540), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>