<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原朝方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tomokata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tomokata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tomokata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 朝方（ふじわら の ともかた、久寿2年（1155年） - 建仁元年2月16日 (旧暦)（1201年3月22日））は、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tomokata (1155 - May 29, 1201) was a Kugyo (the top court officials) in the period from the end of the Kamakura period though the beginning of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>暦変換ツールでは訳文のようになりました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tomokata (1155 - May 29, 1201) was a Kugyo (top court official) in the period from the end of the Kamakura period though the beginning of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tomokata (1155 - March 29, 1201) was a Kugyo (top court official) from the late Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>月を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鳥羽法皇・後白河法皇二代に渡って仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served to 2 generations of Cloistered Emperors, Cloistered Emperor Toba and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served two generations of the Cloistered Emperors, Cloistered Emperor Toba and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served two generations of the Cloistered Emperors, Cloistered Emperor Toba and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は藤原北家勧修寺家庶流の藤原朝隆（権中納言）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father FUJIWARA no Tomotaka (Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)) was a member of branch family of the Kajuji family of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father FUJIWARA no Tomotaka (Gon Chunagon - a provisional vice-councilor of state) was a member of the branch family of the Kajuji family of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, FUJIWARA no Tomotaka (Gon Chunagon [provisional vice-councilor of state]), was a member of the branch family of the Kajuji family of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は「夜の大納言」と称されて権勢を誇った葉室顕隆（中納言）の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was daughter of HAMURO no Akitaka (Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)), who was called &apos;Dainagon (chief councilor of state) at night,&apos; fully using his power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of HAMURO no Akitaka (Chunagon - vice-councilor of state), who was called &apos;Dainagon (chief councilor of state) at night,&apos; fully using his power.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of HAMURO no Akitaka (Chunagon [vice-councilor of state]), who was called &apos;Dainagon (chief councilor of state) at night,&apos; fully using his power.</e>
<cmt>括弧を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>三条大納言・堤大納言と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Sanjo Dainagon and Tsutsumi Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Sanjo Dainagon and Tsutsumi Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Sanjo Dainagon and Tsutsumi Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>永治元年（1141年）11月、鳥羽院庁の判官代から六位蔵人に任ぜられて、栄治2年（1142年）に従五位下に叙任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In between December 1141 - January 1142 (November 1141 in old lunar calendar), he was appointed as Rokui no Kurodo (Chamberlain of Sixth Rank) by hogandai (an administrative official of the Retired-Emperor&apos;s Office) of Toba-incho (the retired Emperor Toba&apos;s Office), and was conferred as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In between December 1141 - January 1142 (November 1141 in old lunar calendar), he was appointed Rokui no Kurodo (Chamberlain of Sixth Rank) by hogandai (an administrative official of the Retired-Emperor&apos;s Office) of Toba-incho (the retired Emperor Toba&apos;s Office), and was conferred as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In between December 1141 - January 1142, he was appointed Rokui no Kurodo (Chamberlain of Sixth Rank) by hogandai (an administrative official of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) of Toba-incho (the Retired Emperor Toba&apos;s Office), and was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>一部表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以降、淡路国守・近江国守・弁官などを歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he served as the Governor of Awaji Province, the Governor of Omi Province, Benkan (officials of the Dajokan), and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he served as the Governor of Awaji Province, and Governor of Omi Province, Benkan (officials of the Dajokan), and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he served as the Awaji no kuni no kami (Governor of Awaji Province), Oe no kuni no kami (Governor of Oe Province), Benkan (officials of the Dajokan), and so on.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鳥羽院別当をつとめていたことで後白河法皇の信任を得て、後白河院庁でも別当に任じられ、法皇最大の側近の一人（院近臣）として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gained trust of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa since he was serving as betto (chief officer) in Toba-in, and after being appointed as betto in Goshirakawa-incho, also, he made success as one of the biggest aide of the Cloistered Emperor (In no Kinshin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gained the trust of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa since he was serving as betto (chief officer) in Toba-in, and after being appointed as betto in Goshirakawa-incho, also, he made success as one of the biggest aides of the Cloistered Emperor (In no Kinshin).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gained the trust of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa since he was serving as betto (chief officer) in Toba-in (cloister government by the Retired Emperor Toba), and after being appointed as betto in Goshirakawa-incho (the retired Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s Office), also, he made success as one of the biggest aides of the Cloistered Emperor (In no Kinshin).</e>
<cmt>補足を追加しました（鳥羽院、後白河院庁）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>永万2年（1166年）に蔵人頭兼右大弁に就任、さらに安元元年（1175年）11月、参議に就任し、公卿に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) and Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) in 1166, was further appointed as Sangi (councillor) in between December 1175 - January 1176 (November 1175 in old lunar calendar), and became to be counted as one of Kugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) and Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) in 1166, was further appointed as Sangi (councillor) in between December 1175 - January 1176 (November 1175 on the old lunar calendar), and was counted as one of the Kugyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) and Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) in 1166, was further appointed as Sangi (councilor) in between December 1175 - January 1176, and was counted as one of the Kugyo.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>安元3年（1177年）10月に権中納言となり、寿永2年（1183年）4月からは正式な中納言に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In between October - November 1177 (October 1177 in old lunar calendar), he was appointed as Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), and from May 1183, he was officially appointed as Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In between October - November 1177 (October 1177 on the old lunar calendar), he was appointed Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), and from May 1183, he was officially appointed Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In between October - November 1177, he was appointed Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), and from May 1183, he was officially appointed Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳(旧暦部分）を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>11月に源義仲が後白河法皇に対するクーデターを起こし、義仲からの圧力で一時的に解官されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In between December 1183 - January 1184 (November 1183 in old lunar calendar), MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka made coups against Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and Tomokata was temporarily removed from the post by Yoshinaka&apos;s pressures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In between December 1183 - January 1184, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka made coups against Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and Tomokata was temporarily removed from the post because of pressure from Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In between December 1183 - January 1184, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka made coups against Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and Tomokata was temporarily removed from the post because of pressure from Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、無論法皇の信任を失っての解官ではないので、義仲が直後に鎌倉軍に征討された後はすぐに復権している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, of course, since the removal was not caused from the loss of trust of the Cloistered Emperor, he was immediately re-appointed to the post right after Yoshinaka was destroyed by the Kamakura army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, of course, since the removal was not caused from the loss of trust of the Cloistered Emperor, he was immediately re-appointed to the post right after Yoshinaka was destroyed by the Kamakura army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, of course, since the removal was not caused from the loss of trust of the Cloistered Emperor, he was immediately re-appointed to the post right after Yoshinaka was destroyed by the Kamakura army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>文治2年（1186年)12月、陸奥国出羽国按察使に任じられ、文治4年（1188年）10月、権大納言に昇進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In between January - February 1187 (December 1186 in old lunar calendar), he was appointed as Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) of Mutsu Province and Dewa Province, and in between October - November 1188 (October 1188 in old lunar calendar), his position was raised to Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In between January - February 1187 (December 1186 in old lunar calendar), he was appointed as Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) of Mutsu Province and Dewa Province, and in between October - November 1188 (October 1188 in old lunar calendar), his position was raised to Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In between January - February 1187, he was appointed as Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) of Mutsu Province and Dewa Province, and in between October - November 1188, his position was raised to Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳(旧暦部分）を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし源義経に同意したとされて鎌倉の源頼朝の圧力でまたしても一時的に解官される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was suspected by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo that he agreed with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, and by Yoritomo&apos;s pressures, he again was removed from the position temporarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was suspected by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo of agreeing with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, and because of pressure from Yoritomo, he again was temporarily removed from the position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was suspected by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo of agreeing with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, and because of pressure from Yoritomo, he again was temporarily removed from the position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>後白河法皇の庇護でまもなく復官したが、やがて病に倒れて建仁元年（1201年）2月15日に出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He soon regained the position with the protection of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, but before long, he got ill and became as a priest on March 28, 1201.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He soon regained his position with the protection of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, but before long, he fell ill and became as a priest on March 28, 1201.</e>
<cmt>grammr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He soon regained his position with the protection of Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, but before long, he fell ill and became a priest on March 28, 1201.</e>
<cmt>became a priest としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>翌16日には薨去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on the next day, March 29, 1201.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on the next day, March 29, 1201.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on the next day, March 29, 1201.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>享年67。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 67.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 67.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 67.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>能書家としても知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known for being noshoka (master of calligraphy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known for being noshoka (master of calligraphy).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known for being noshoka (master of calligraphy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dr jimmy(id:111486), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>