<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>列堂義仙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gisen RETSUDO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retsudo Gisen</e>
<cmt>僧侶名で「列堂」という名字にあたる部分が名字かどうか判別がつかないため、語順を変えずにRetsudo Gisen と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retsudo Gisen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>列堂義仙（れつどうぎせん、寛永12年（1635年） - 元禄15年7月24日 (旧暦)（1702年8月17日））は、江戸時代の臨済宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gisen RETSUDO (1635 - August 17, 1702; July 24 in old lunar calendar) was a priest of the Rinzai Sect of Buddhism in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retsudo Gisen (1635-August 17, 1702) was a priest of the Rinzai sect in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Gisen RETSUDO を Retsudo Gisen に修正しました。; July 24 in old lunar calendar を削除しました。Sect を sect に修正しました。Of Buddhism を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retsudo Gisen (1635-August 17, 1702) was a priest of the Rinzai sect in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大和国柳生藩初代藩主柳生宗矩（但馬守）の子で、柳生家菩提寺の芳徳寺の第一世住持となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Munenori YAGYU (Tajima no kami), the first lord of Yagyu Domain in Yamato Province, and he became the first chief priest of Hotoku-ji Temple, the temple of the Yagyu family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Munenori YAGYU (Tajima no kami [the governor of Tajima Province]), the first lord of Yagyu Domain in Yamato Province, and he became the first chief priest of Hotoku-ji Temple, the temple of the Yagyu family.</e>
<cmt>Tajima no kami に [the governor of Tajima Province] を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Munenori YAGYU (Tajima no kami [the governor of Tajima Province]), the first lord of Yagyu Domain in Yamato Province, and he became the first chief priest of Hotoku-ji Temple, the temple of the Yagyu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>義仙は柳生宗矩が側室との間に儲けた子で、幼名を六丸といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gisen was a child Munenori YAGYU had with a concubine, and his childhood name was Rokumaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gisen was a child of Munenori YAGYU and his concubine, and his childhood name was Rokumaru.</e>
<cmt>Munenori YAGYU had with a concubine をof Munenori YAGYU and his concubine に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gisen was a child of Munenori YAGYU and his concubine, and his childhood name was Rokumaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>12歳のとき父を亡くすが、その前後に父の意志により京都の大徳寺で出家、天祐紹果に入門して僧となり名を義仙と改め、列堂和尚と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he lost his father at the age of 12, he entered into priesthood in Daitoku-ji Temple in Kyoto by his father&apos;s will around that time, then became a disciple of Tenyu Joka and a priest, changed his name to Gisen, and called himself Retsudo Osho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he lost his father at the age of 12, he entered priesthood in Daitoku-ji Temple in Kyoto by his father&apos;s will around that time, then became a disciple of Tenyu Joka and a priest, changed his name to Gisen, and called himself &quot;Retsudo Osho (High Priest Retsudo).&quot;</e>
<cmt>While を When に修正しました。entered into の into を削除しました。Retsudo Osho にダブルコーテーションを追記しました。Retsudo Osho に (High Priest Retsudo) を追記しました。出典：http://www.google.com/search?hl=ja&amp;tbo=1&amp;tbs=bks%3A1&amp;q=osho+high+priest&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=&amp;aql=&amp;oq=&amp;gs_rfai=</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he lost his father at the age of 12, he entered priesthood in Daitoku-ji Temple in Kyoto by his father&apos;s will around that time, then became a disciple of Tenyu Joka and a priest, changed his name to Gisen, and called himself &quot;Retsudo Osho (High Priest Retsudo).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>さらに宗矩が亡父柳生宗厳（石舟斎）を弔うため沢庵宗彭を招いて柳生（現在の奈良市柳生下町）に建立した菩提寺の芳徳寺の住持に定められ、芳徳寺に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he was appointed to be the chief priest of the family temple, Hotoku-ji Temple, which had been built by Munenori to hold a memorial service for his deceased father, Muneyoshi YAGYU (Sekishusai) by engaging Soho TAKUAN in Yagyu (Yagyushimo-cho, Nara City, as of now), and he moved to Hotoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he moved to his family temple, Hotoku-ji Temple as the chief priest, which had been built by Munenori to hold a memorial service for his deceased father, Muneyoshi YAGYU (Sekishusai) by engaging Soho TAKUAN in Yagyu (present Yagyushimo-cho, Nara City).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he moved to his family temple, Hotoku-ji Temple as the chief priest, which had been built by Munenori to hold a memorial service for his deceased father, Muneyoshi YAGYU (Sekishusai) by engaging Soho TAKUAN in Yagyu (present Yagyushimo-cho, Nara City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、宗矩の遺志に基づく徳川家光の内意によって、宗矩の遺領1万2500石のうち200石が芳徳寺に寺領として分与された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA&apos;s intention based on Munenori&apos;s last wish, 200 koku from Munenori&apos;s property inheritance 12500 koku were distributed to Hotoku-ji Temple as jiryo (temple estate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA&apos;s intention based on Munenori&apos;s last wish, 200 koku from Munenori&apos;s property inheritance 12500 koku were distributed to Hotoku-ji Temple as jiryo (temple estate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA&apos;s intention based on Munenori&apos;s last wish, 200 koku from Munenori&apos;s property inheritance 12500 koku were distributed to Hotoku-ji Temple as jiryo (temple estate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>1646年に父・宗矩が亡くなって間もなく、1650年には父の遺領の大半を相続していた長兄の柳生三厳（十兵衛）が若くして没し、次兄の柳生宗冬が代わって柳生家を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not long after the death of his father, Munenori in 1646, his eldest brother, Mitsutoshi YAGYU (Jubei) who had inherited most of their father&apos;s property inheritance died young in 1650, and the second elder brother, Munefuyu YAGYU succeeded to the Yagyu family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after his father Munenori died in 1646, his oldest brother Mitsutoshi YAGYU (Jubei) who had inherited most of their father&apos;s property died young in 1650, and the second older brother Munefuyu YAGYU succeeded to the Yagyu family.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after his father Munenori died in 1646, his oldest brother Mitsutoshi YAGYU (Jubei) who had inherited most of their father&apos;s property died young in 1650, and the second older brother Munefuyu YAGYU succeeded to the Yagyu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、宗冬も義仙と比べると22年と大きく年齢の離れた兄で、気性の激しかった義仙は宗冬と不仲であったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But compared to Gisen, Munefuyu was also a 22 years older brother, and it has been said that violent tempered Gisen did not get along well with Munefuyu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But compared to Gisen, Munefuyu was also a 22 years older brother, and it has been said that violent tempered Gisen did not get along well with Munefuyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But compared to Gisen, Munefuyu was also a 22 years older brother, and it has been said that violent tempered Gisen did not get along well with Munefuyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>義仙は僧職に収まりきれない奔放な気性であったらしく、長く柳生を出奔して芳徳寺を留守にしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gisen seems to have had too wild a disposition to fit into priesthood entirely that he had run away from Yagyu and been absent from Hotoku-ji Temple for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gisen seems to have had too fierce temper to fit into priesthood entirely that he had run away from Yagyu and been absent from Hotoku-ji Temple for a long time.</e>
<cmt>wild a disposition を fierce temper に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gisen seems to have had too fierce temper to fit into priesthood entirely that he had run away from Yagyu and been absent from Hotoku-ji Temple for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これに激怒した兄の宗冬が、義仙を追放して代わりの者を住持に立てるよう指示した遺言状が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remains a will of his elder brother, Munefuyu in which he was so enraged at it that he directed Gisen to be banished and another person to be designated to the chief priest instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There remains a will of his older brother Munefuyu who got enraged at Gisen&apos;s absence, directing to banish Gisen and have someone replace him as the chief priest.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There remains a will of his older brother Munefuyu who got enraged at Gisen&apos;s absence, directing to banish Gisen and have someone replace him as the chief priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、義仙が実際に追放されたかどうかは定かではなく、現在も芳徳寺では列堂和尚（義仙）を第一世住持に数えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it is not certain whether Gisen was actually banished or not, and Retsudo Osho (Gisen) is listed as the first chief priest at Hotoku-ji Temple even now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it is not certain whether Gisen was actually banished or not, and Retsudo Osho (Gisen) has been listed as the first chief priest at Hotoku-ji Temple till now.</e>
<cmt>is listed even now を has been listed till now に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it is not certain whether Gisen was actually banished or not, and Retsudo Osho (Gisen) has been listed as the first chief priest at Hotoku-ji Temple till now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>のちには大徳寺の住持に就任したこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he also took the position as the chief priest of Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he also took the position as the chief priest of Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he also took the position as the chief priest of Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>列堂義仙は柳生宗矩の末子で柳生家の菩提寺の開基であることから歴史に名を残したが、歴史学などの学術的視点からの研究はあまり行われておらず、その事歴については十分に分かっていない部分も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gisen RETSUDO&apos;s name has been left in history for the reasons that he was the last son of Munenori YAGYU and the founder of the temple of the Yagyu family, but few studies from academic points of view like history and others have been made, and there are many parts in his history and legends which are not fully known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retsudo Gisen left his name in the history since he was the last son of Munenori YAGYU and the founder of his family temple, but few studies from academic points of view such as historical science and so on have been made, and there are many parts in his history and legends which are not fully known.</e>
<cmt>前半部を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retsudo Gisen left his name in the history since he was the last son of Munenori YAGYU and the founder of his family temple, but few studies from academic points of view such as historical science and so on have been made, and there are many parts in his history and legends which are not fully known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>フィクションの中の列堂義仙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gisen RETSUDO in fictions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retsudo Gisen in fictions</e>
<cmt>Gisen RETSUDO を Retsudo Gisen に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retsudo Gisen in fictions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>小池一夫が時代劇作品の『子連れ狼』で「柳生烈堂」という名で悪役に設定したため、現在ではそのイメージが強くなり、実像が虚像と入り混じってしまっている感もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Kazuo KOIKE set up a role of villain named &apos;Retsudo YAGYU&apos; in his work of period drama, &apos;Kozure-Okami (Lone Wolf and Cub)&apos;, this image has become predominant and it seems that his real person and fictitious images have been mixed up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Kazuo KOIKE set up a role of villain named &apos;Retsudo YAGYU&apos; in his work of period drama, &quot;Kozure Okami&quot; (Lone Wolf and Cub), this image has become predominant and it seems that his real person and fictitious images have been mixed up.</e>
<cmt>Kozure-Okami (Lone Wolf and Cub)&apos; を&quot;Kozure Okami&quot; (Lone Wolf and Cub) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Kazuo KOIKE set up a role of villain named &apos;Retsudo YAGYU&apos; in his work of period drama, &quot;Kozure Okami&quot; (Lone Wolf and Cub), this image has become predominant and it seems that his real person and fictitious images have been mixed up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>隆慶一郎の『吉原御免状』とその続編『かくれさと苦界行』においては「柳生義仙」として登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Keiichiro RYU&apos;s &quot;Yoshihara gomenjo (historical play by Keiichiro Ryu)&quot; and its sequel, &quot;Kakuresato kugaiko (historical play by Keiichiro Ryu)&quot;, he makes appearance as &apos;Gisen YAGYU&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Keiichiro RYU&apos;s novels, &quot;Yoshiwara Gomenjo&quot; and its sequel &quot;Kakuresato Kugaiko,&quot; he makes appearance as &apos;Gisen YAGYU&apos;.</e>
<cmt>In Keiichiro RYU&apos;s &quot;Yoshihara gomenjo (historical play by Keiichiro Ryu)&quot; and its sequel, &quot;Kakuresato kugaiko (historical play by Keiichiro Ryu)&quot; をIn Keiichiro RYU&apos;s novels, &quot;Yoshiwara Gomenjo&quot; and its sequel &quot;Kakuresato Kugaiko,&quot; に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Keiichiro RYU&apos;s novels, &quot;Yoshiwara Gomenjo&quot; and its sequel &quot;Kakuresato Kugaiko,&quot; he makes appearance as &apos;Gisen YAGYU&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>当初は柳生の裏を統べる最強の悪役の役回りで登場、主人公・松永誠一郎との闘いを経て『かくれさと苦界行』の後半にはその役回りは大きく変化してゆくが、惜しくも作者の急逝によりシリーズ全体としては未完に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, he appears as the strongest role of a villain who controls the backstage of YAGYU, then after going through the fights with the hero, Seiichiro MATSUNAGA, in the latter half of &quot;Kakuresato kugaiko&quot;, the character of his role changes greatly, but regretfully due to the author&apos;s sudden death, the series as a whole ended unfinished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, he appears as the strongest villain who controls the backstage of YAGYU, then after going through the fights with the hero, Seiichiro MATSUNAGA, in the latter half of &quot;Kakuresato Kugaiko,&quot; the character of his role changes greatly; however, regretfully, the author&apos;s sudden death left the series as a whole incomplete.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, he appears as the strongest villain who controls the backstage of YAGYU, then after going through the fights with the hero, Seiichiro MATSUNAGA, in the latter half of &quot;Kakuresato Kugaiko,&quot; the character of his role changes greatly; however, regretfully, the author&apos;s sudden death left the series as a whole incomplete.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、火坂雅志の小説では英雄・豪傑として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in Masashi HISAKA&apos;s novel, he is depicted as a hero, a daring man.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in Masashi HISAKA&apos;s novel, he is depicted as a hero and a daring man.</e>
<cmt>, を and に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in Masashi HISAKA&apos;s novel, he is depicted as a hero and a daring man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ＤＦ．Ｋｉｎｇ(id:48817), Safkan(id:423), Nopira(id:29335), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), 果心居士(id:248111), Tmonzenet(id:92869), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>