<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小沢重政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemasa OZAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemasa OZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemasa OZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小沢 重政（おざわ しげまさ、生年不詳 - 元久2年（1205年）6月23日 (旧暦)）は鎌倉時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemasa OZAWA (year of birth unknown - July 18, 1205) was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemasa OZAWA (year of birth unknown - July 18, 1205) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemasa OZAWA (year of birth unknown - July 18, 1205) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉幕府の御家人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Gokenin (Shogunal retainer) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Gokenin (direct vassal) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Given that bakufu is described as meaning &quot;Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun&quot;, it makes more sense to define &quot;gokenin&quot; as just &quot;direct vassal&quot; here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Gokenin (direct vassal) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>秩父氏の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family came from the Chichibu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family was part of the Chichibu clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family was part of the Chichibu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>小沢城城主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was lord of the Ozawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was lord of Ozawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the lord of Ozawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>lord→the lordにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父は鎌倉幕府の重臣・稲毛重成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Shigenari INAGE, was a senior vassal of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Shigenari INAGE, was a senior vassal of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Shigenari INAGE, was a senior vassal of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は北条時政の娘で、北条政子の実の妹といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Tokimasa HOJO who is said to have been a real younger sister of Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Tokimasa HOJO, who is said to have been a younger sister of Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>I realize the Japanese says &quot;実の妹&quot;, but there is no need to say this in English as anyone reading &quot;she was the younger sister of…&quot; will automatically assume this means they were related by blood. Using &quot;real younger sister&quot; makes it sound as if some people have imaginary sisters...</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Tokimasa HOJO, who is said to have been a younger sister of Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>通称は二郎、小太郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Jiro or Kotaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly known as Jiro or Kotaro.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly known as Jiro or Kotaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>小沢小太郎の名で知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known as Kotaro OZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as Kotaro OZAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as Kotaro OZAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>小沢城に入り、小沢小太郎と名乗ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have entered the Ozawa-jo Castle and called himself Kotaro OZAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he called himself Kotaro OZAWA after entering Ozawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>多少わかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he called himself Kotaro OZAWA after entering Ozawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>（小沢城は、父の稲毛重成が築城したという。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his father, Shigenari INAGE, built the Ozawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(His father, Shigenari INAGE is believed to have built Ozawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>括弧がぬけていました。上のセルとバランスをとり変更を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(His father, Shigenari INAGE is believed to have built Ozawa-jo Castle.)</e>
<cmt>()をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>(だが、重政が築城したという説もあり、さらに重政が城主か定かではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is another view that Shigemasa built the castle and, moreover, it is unknown whether he was actually lord of the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, another theory suggests that Shigemasa built the castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。2文にわけました。&quot;view&quot;は少々意味合いが軽いと考え，書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, another theory suggests that Shigemasa built the castle.)</e>
<cmt>()をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>建仁元年（1201年）1月12日 (旧暦)の幕府の的初め儀に、叔父の榛谷重朝とともに一番射手となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the first archer, along with his uncle, Shigetomo HANGAYA, at the first archery ceremony of the year hosted by the bakufu on February 23, 1201.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the first archer along with his uncle, Shigetomo HANGAYA at the first archery ceremony of the year hosted by the bakufu on February 23, 1201.</e>
<cmt>コンマ2コを省きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the first archer along with his uncle, Shigetomo HANGAYA at the first archery ceremony of the year hosted by the bakufu on February 23, 1201.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>元久2年（1205年）6月23日 (旧暦)、北条義時に謀反の疑いをかけられた畠山重忠が二俣川の合戦で、討死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada HATAKEYAMA, who was accused of being in a rebellion by Yoshitoki HOJO, died in the Battle of Futamatagawa on July 18, 1205.</e>
<cmt>二俣川の合戦は、the Battle of Futamatagawaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada HATAKEYAMA, who was suspected of rebellion by Yoshitoki HOJO, died in the Battle of Futamatagawa on July 18, 1205.</e>
<cmt>「謀反の疑いをかけられた」のニュアンスをだすため書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada HATAKEYAMA, who was suspected of rebellion by Yoshitoki HOJO, died in the Battle of Futamatagawa on July 18, 1205.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>その翌日、三浦義村は経師谷（きょうじがやつ）入口で、榛谷重朝と嫡男の秩父重季と次男の秩父秀重を騙して殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following day, Shigetomo HANGAYA, along with his legitimate son, Shigeki CHICHIBU, and his second son, Hideshige CHICHIBU, were deceived into being killed by Yoshimura MIURA at the entrance to Kyojigayatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following day, Yoshimura MIURA deceived Shigetomo HANGAYA, his eldest legitimate son Shigeki CHICHIBU and his second son Hideshige CHICHIBU to kill altogether at the entrance to Kyojigayatsu.</e>
<cmt>文が複雑なので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following day, Yoshimura MIURA deceived Shigetomo HANGAYA, his eldest legitimate son Shigeki CHICHIBU and his second son Hideshige CHICHIBU to kill altogether at the entrance to Kyojigayatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後大河戸氏に父の重成が殺され、子の小沢重政は宇佐美氏に殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, Shigenari, Shigemasa OZAWA&apos;s father, was killed by the Okodo clan and Shigemasa OZAWA was killed by the Usami clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Shigemasa&apos;s father Shigenari was killed by the Okodo clan, while Shigemasa OZAWA was killed by the Usami clan.</e>
<cmt>After a whileは時間的に短すぎると考え，書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Shigemasa&apos;s father Shigenari was killed by the Okodo clan, while Shigemasa OZAWA was killed by the Usami clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>元久2年（1205年）11月3日 (旧暦)、小沢重政の娘綾小路師三位季息女（当時2歳）は乳母夫小沢信重に伴われて鎌倉に下向し北条政子に会う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 21, 1205, Shigemasa OZAWA&apos;s daughter, Ayanokoji Sanmi Morosue Sokujyo (literally, &quot;Daughter of Ayanokoji Sanmi Morosue,&quot; two years old at the time), was accompanied by her nursing father, Nobushige OZAWA, to go down to Kamakura to see Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>綾小路三位師季息女の定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accompanied by her nursing father, Nobushige OZAWA, Shigemasa OZAWA&apos;s daughter, Ayanokoji Sanmi Morosue Sokujyo (literally, &quot;Daughter of Ayanokoji Sanmi Morosue,&quot; two years old at the time) visited Kamakura to see Masako HOJO on December 21, 1205.</e>
<cmt>全体がわかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accompanied by her nursing father, Nobushige OZAWA, Shigemasa OZAWA&apos;s daughter, Ayanokoji Sanmi Morosue Sokujyo (literally, &quot;Daughter of Ayanokoji Sanmi Morosue,&quot; two years old at the time) visited Kamakura to see Masako HOJO on December 21, 1205.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>政子は実妹の孫娘の哀れさに涙し、猶子とした（猶子とは仮の親子関係を結んだ子の総称である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masako was moved to tears commiserating the misfortune of a granddaughter of her sister by blood, and decided to adopt her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masako, who was moved to tears with the pitiful plight of the granddaughter of her younger sister, decided to adopt her.</e>
<cmt>commiserating の使い方に問題があるので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masako, who was moved to tears with the pitiful plight of the granddaughter of her younger sister, decided to adopt her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>政子は孫娘に稲毛重成の遺領小沢郷（稲城市矢野口周辺）を与えたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masako is said to have given her adopted granddaughter Ozawa-kyo (around present-day Yanokuchi, Inagi City), which was a property inheritance of Shigenari INAGE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Masako gave the adopted granddaughter Ozawa-kyo (around present Yanokuchi, Inagi City), which had been a property inheritance of Shigenari INAGE.</e>
<cmt>時制を考慮し，書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Masako gave the adopted granddaughter Ozawa-kyo (around present Yanokuchi, Inagi City), which had been a property inheritance of Shigenari INAGE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>その子孫については『地誌編輯取調簿』によれば、以下のように記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some descriptions about their descendants in the &quot;Chishi Hensyu Torishirabebo&quot; (Local history of Inage City) as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。『地誌編輯取調簿』の定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a description related to their descendants in the &quot;Chishi Hensyu Torishirabebo&quot; (Local history of Inage City) as follows:</e>
<cmt>引用されている記述は次のセルの一文なので単数としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a description related to their descendants in the &quot;Chishi Hensyu Torishirabebo&quot; (Local history of Inage City) as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>｢往古事蹟不詳、鎌倉府ノ頃稲毛三郎重成之ヲ領、後重成ノ族小沢左近将監信重之ヲ給シ、応安ノ頃小沢左エ門尉国高之ヲ領ス」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet details of historical events in the remote past are not known, Shigenari Saburo INAGE governed the area during the Kamakura period, sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the left division of inner palace guards) Nobushige OZAWA later owned the area, and Saemon 尉国高 OZAWA owned the area during the Oei era.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。尉国高の読み不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet the details in the remote past are uncertain, Shigenari Saburo INAGE governed the area during the Kamakura period, which was later given to Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the left division of inner palace guards) Nobushige OZAWA, and then Saemon 尉国高 OZAWA governed the area during the Oei era.</e>
<cmt>領スと給シの違いをだしました。&quot;details&quot; に冠詞を，historical eventsとthe remote pastは意味上重複するのでhistorical eventsを省きました。Sakon no shogenは単語調査ファイルで確認し大文字としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet the details in the remote past are uncertain, Shigenari Saburo INAGE governed the area during the Kamakura period, which was later given to Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the left division of inner palace guards) Nobushige OZAWA, and then Saemon 尉国高 OZAWA governed the area during the Oei era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>