<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山路彰常</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akitsune YAMAJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitsune YAMAJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akitsune YAMAJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山路 彰常（やまじ あきつね、？－明治14年（1881年）9月24日）は、幕末期の天文学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akitsune YAMAJI (date of birth unknown - September 24, 1881) was an astronomer in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitsune YAMAJI (date of birth unknown - September 24, 1881) was an astronomer in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akitsune YAMAJI (date of birth unknown - September 24, 1881) was an astronomer in the late Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸幕府最後の天文方である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the last Tenmonkata (officer in charge of astronomy) in the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the last Tenmonkata (officer in charge of astronomy) of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>in the Edo bakufu --&gt; of the Edo bakufu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the last Tenmonkata (officer in charge of astronomy) of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>山路諧孝の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a legitimate son of Yukitaka YAMAJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a legitimate son of Yukitaka YAMAJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a legitimate son of Yukitaka YAMAJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称・金之丞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly known as Kinnojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly known as Kinnojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly known as Kinnojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>天保5年（1834年）に天文方見習となり、父や渋川景佑による天保暦改暦に参加した。改暦後もその暦書である『新法暦書』の暦理撰述を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1834, he became an apprentice of Tenmonkata and joined a calendar amendment project for the Tenpo reki (Tenpo calendar) coordinated by his father and Kagesuke SHIBUKAWA, after which he also compiled the almanac of &quot;Shinpo Rekisho&quot; as the Rekisho (expository books about the calendar).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1834, he became an apprentice of Tenmonkata and joined a calendar amendment project for the Tenpo reki (Tenpo calendar) coordinated by his father and Kagesuke SHIBUKAWA, after which he also compiled the almanac of &quot;Shinpo Rekisho&quot; as Rekisho (expository books about the calendar).</e>
<cmt>as the Rekisho --&gt; as Rekisho</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1834, he became an apprentice of Tenmonkata and joined a calendar amendment project for the Tenpo reki (Tenpo calendar) coordinated by his father and Kagesuke SHIBUKAWA, after which he also compiled the almanac of &quot;Shinpo Rekisho&quot; as Rekisho (expository books about the calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その功績によって弘化3年（1846年）に異例の親子2代の天文方任命が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resulting from this achievement, an exceptional Tenmonkata nomination for the 2 generations, the Yamaji father and son, occured in 1846.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resulting from this achievement, an exceptional Tenmonkata nomination for the two generations, the Yamaji father and son, occured in 1846.</e>
<cmt>2 --&gt; two</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Resulting from this achievement, an exceptional Tenmonkata nomination for the two generations, the Yamaji father and son, occured in 1846.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、天保9年（1838年）には渋川敬直とともに江戸参府中のオランダ商館長ヨハネス・エルデウィン・ニーマンと会談し、モリソン号事件の真相を江戸幕府老中水野忠邦に報告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in 1838, he had a conference with the curator of the Dutch trading house, Johannes Erdewin Niemann, who did Sanpu (obligation to live in Edo) together with Kagesuke SHIBUKAWA, and informed on the veracity of the Morrison Incident to Tadakuni MIZUNO, who was in the post of roju (member of the Shogun&apos;s council of elders) in the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　参府=「Sanpu (obligation to lord to live in Edo)」定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in 1838, he had a meeting with the curator of Dutch trading house, Johannes Erdewin Niemann in Sanpu (obligation to lord to live in Edo), together with Kagesuke SHIBUKAWA, and reported the veracity of the Morrison Incident to Tadakuni MIZUNO, who was in the post of roju (member of the Shogun&apos;s council of elders) in the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in 1838, he had a meeting with the curator of Dutch trading house, Johannes Erdewin Niemann in Sanpu (obligation to lord to live in Edo), together with Kagesuke SHIBUKAWA, and reported the veracity of the Morrison Incident to Tadakuni MIZUNO, who was in the post of roju (member of the Shogun&apos;s council of elders) in the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>安政3年（1856年）から蕃書調所が天文方から分離するまで蛮書和解御用を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as a Bansho-wage Goyo (Government Office for Translation of Barbarian Books) from 1856 to when Bansho Shirabesho separated from Tenmonkata.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as a Bansho-wage Goyo (Government Office for Translation of Barbarian Books) from 1856 until Bansho Shirabesho was separated from Tenmonkata.</e>
<cmt>to when Bansho Shirabesho separated from Tenmonkata --&gt; until Bansho Shirabesho was separated from Tenmonkata</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as a Bansho-wage Goyo (Government Office for Translation of Barbarian Books) from 1856 until Bansho Shirabesho was separated from Tenmonkata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後も翻訳の業務に携わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, as well, he was involved in translation work.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he was involved in translation work.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he was involved in translation work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>マシュー・ペリーが江戸幕府に贈った電信機に関する調査や父とともに命じられた航海暦の編纂では父に代わって主導し、万延元年（1860年）には柴田収蔵とともに『万国全図』編纂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On behalf of his father, he led projects on a piece of research about telegraphic instruments which Matthew (Calbraith) PERRY gave to the Edo bakufu and a compilation of the nautical almanac which he and his father were ordered to complete.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On behalf of his father, he led a research project on the telegraph instruments which Matthew (Calbraith) PERRY had given to the Edo bakufu and also led a project to compile a nautical almanac which he and his father were ordered to complete; further in 1860, he compiled &quot;Bankoku Zenzu&quot; (map of the world) together with Shuzo SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れあり。「万延元年（1860年）には柴田収蔵とともに『万国全図』編纂した」の訳を追加。その他表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On behalf of his father, he led a research project on the telegraph instruments which Matthew (Calbraith) PERRY had given to the Edo bakufu and also led a project to compile a nautical almanac which he and his father were ordered to complete; further in 1860, he compiled &quot;Bankoku Zenzu&quot; (map of the world) together with Shuzo SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>文久元年（1861年）の父の没後に家督を継承し、明治2年（1869年）の天文方廃止までその職にあるが、天文方の地位低下に伴って活動が縮小していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father&apos;s death in 1861, he inherited the leadership of his family, and he continued the work until the abolition of Tenmonkata but the amount of activity was decreasing with the decline of the status of Tenmonkata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his father&apos;s death in 1861, he inherited the family estate, and continued the work until the abolition of Tenmonkata while the amount of his activity kept decreasing with the decline of the status of Tenmonkata.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father&apos;s death in 1861, he inherited the family estate, and continued the work until the abolition of Tenmonkata while the amount of his activity kept decreasing with the decline of the status of Tenmonkata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>戊辰戦争では天文方見習であった嫡男山路彰善（一郎）が彰義隊に参加して行方不明となる（後に箱館戦争で捕らえられる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legitimate son, Akiyoshi (Ichiro) YAMADA, who was an apprentice of Tenmonkata at the Boshin War, joined Shogitai (an elite corps of the Shogunate) and went missing in action (he was later captured in the Hakodate War).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legitimate son, Akiyoshi (Ichiro) YAMAJI, who was an apprentice of Tenmonkata, joined Shogitai (an elite corps of the Shogunate) at the Boshin War and went missing in action (he was later captured in the Hakodate War).</e>
<cmt>YAMADAをYAMAJIに変更、その他表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legitimate son, Akiyoshi (Ichiro) YAMAJI, who was an apprentice of Tenmonkata, joined Shogitai (an elite corps of the Shogunate) at the Boshin War and went missing in action (he was later captured in the Hakodate War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天文方廃止後の明治2年（1869年）春に嫡孫の山路彌吉（彰善の長男）を連れて無禄にて静岡市に移り住み、程なく（遅くとも明治5年（1872年）以前に）彌吉に家督を譲り、隠居生活を送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the abolition of Tenmonkata, in Spring 1869, he took Yakichi YAMAJI, who was his legitimate grandchild and moved to Shizuoka City, where he knew nobody, and soon after that (no later than 1872), he ceded the reins of the family to Yakichi and lived there in retirement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the abolition of Tenmonkata, in Spring 1869, with his legitimate grandchild Yakichi YAMAJI (oldest son of Akiyoshi), he moved to Shizuoka City with no salary; soon after that (no later than 1872), he handed over the family estate to Yakichi and lived there in retirement.</e>
<cmt>「（彰善の長男）」の訳を追加、「無禄」の訳をwith no salaryに変更、その他表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the abolition of Tenmonkata, in Spring 1869, with his legitimate grandchild Yakichi YAMAJI (oldest son of Akiyoshi), he moved to Shizuoka City with no salary; soon after that (no later than 1872), he handed over the family estate to Yakichi and lived there in retirement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>明治5年（1872年）、彰常は彰善が戊辰戦争で捕らえられて津山藩に預けられていることを知った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1872, Akitsune heard that Akiyoshi had been taken into custody at the Tsuyama Domain because of his participation in the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1872, Akitsune heard that Akiyoshi had been taken into custody at the Tsuyama Domain because of his participation in the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1872, Akitsune heard that Akiyoshi had been taken into custody at the Tsuyama Domain because of his participation in the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そして赦免を得て彰善を津山から連れ戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akitsune got Akiyoshi pardoned and took him from Tsuyama.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitsune managed to obtain remission for Akiyoshi to take him back from Tsuyama.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akitsune managed to obtain remission for Akiyoshi to take him back from Tsuyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>山路愛山（彌吉）は回想録『命耶罪耶』の中で子供の頃（静岡時代）に彰常より、これからは「商人の道」を学ぶように諭された時に武士の子としての誇りから「卑しむべき商人たらんよりは寧ろ自殺するこそよけれ」と叫んだことを記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time when Akitsune explained to Aizan (Yakichi) YAMAJI that he should learn &apos;the way of a merchant&apos; in the days ahead, Aizan noted in his reminiscence, titled &quot;Meikatsumika&quot;, that when he was a little younger (during the time when he was in Shizuoka), his pride as the son of a Samurai caused him to yell out, &apos;It is better to kill myself than to become a humble merchant.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizan (Yakichi) YAMAJI wrote the following story in his commentaries entitled &quot;Meikatsumika&quot;: when Akitsune tried to convince Aizan in his childhood (in Shizuoka) that he should learn &quot;the way of merchant&quot; from that time on, Aizan spoke out proudly as a son of samurai family that he would rather kill himself than become a humble merchant.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizan (Yakichi) YAMAJI wrote the following story in his commentaries entitled &quot;Meikatsumika&quot;: when Akitsune tried to convince Aizan in his childhood (in Shizuoka) that he should learn &quot;the way of merchant&quot; from that time on, Aizan spoke out proudly as a son of samurai family that he would rather kill himself than become a humble merchant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>後にジャーナリスト・歴史家として大成した愛山はこの時の祖父の言が、孫の将来を憂慮した言葉であったと気づいて悔やみ、家に山路徳風・諧孝、そして彰常の3代の肖像画を掲げて子弟に祖父らの業績を鑑にする様に諭したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizan, who later achieved great success as a journalist and historian, realized that what his grandfather had said was due to his anxiety for his grandson and agonized over his own attitude, so he displayed portraits of three generations, Yoshitsugu, Yukitaka and Akitsune YAMAJI, and admonished younger people that they should see their acheivement as a model to be followed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizan, who later achieved great success as a journalist and historian, realized that what his grandfather had said was due to his anxiety for his grandson and agonized over his own attitude, so he displayed portraits of three generations, Yoshitsugu, Yukitaka and Akitsune YAMAJI, and admonished younger people that they should see their acheivement as a model to be followed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizan, who later achieved great success as a journalist and historian, realized that what his grandfather had said was due to his anxiety for his grandson and agonized over his own attitude, so he displayed portraits of three generations, Yoshitsugu, Yukitaka and Akitsune YAMAJI, and admonished younger people that they should see their acheivement as a model to be followed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>