<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大内惟義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreyoshi OUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koreyoshi OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koreyoshi OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大内 惟義（おおうち これよし）は、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけての武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreyoshi OUCHI was a busho (Japanese military commander), who lived from the late Heian Period to the early Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koreyoshi OUCHI was a busho (Japanese military commander), who lived from the late Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koreyoshi OUCHI was a busho (Japanese military commander), who lived from the late Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉幕府の御家人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>源氏一門の重鎮であった平賀義信の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of Yoshinobu HIRAGA, an important figure of the Minamoto clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of Yoshinobu HIRAGA, an important figure of the Minamoto clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of Yoshinobu HIRAGA, an important figure of the Minamoto clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>源義光の曾孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the great-grandson of MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the great-grandson of MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the great-grandson of MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>惟義が伊賀国に赴任した時期に大内姓を称したが、後に戦国大名となる周防国の大内氏とは関係がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Koreyoshi was assigned to Iga Province, he used the family name &apos;Ouchi,&apos; however, he is nothing to do with the Ouchi clan in Suo Province, which later grew up to be a Daimyo (feudal lord) at the Sengoku period (the period of warring state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Koreyoshi was assigned to Iga Province, he called himself as &apos;Ouchi&apos; for the family name, however, he was nothing to do with the Ouchi clan in Suo Province, which later grew up to be a daimyo (feudal lord) at the Sengoku Period (the Period of Warring State).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Koreyoshi was assigned to Iga Province, he called himself as &apos;Ouchi&apos; for the family name, however, he was nothing to do with the Ouchi clan in Suo Province, which later grew up to be a daimyo (feudal lord) at the Sengoku Period (the Period of Warring State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>治承・寿永内乱期の活躍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outstanding achievements during the Jisho-Juei Civil War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outstanding achievements during the Jisho-Juei Civil War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outstanding achievements during the Jisho-Juei Civil War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>治承4年（1180年）8月の源頼朝の挙兵に対し、源氏の一門として早くから従って戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo took up arms in August/September 1189, he fallowed Yoritomo&apos;s forces and went into battle as a member of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo took up arms in August 1180, he fallowed MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s forces and went into battle as a member of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>年号を変え、原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo took up arms in August 1180, he fallowed MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s forces and went into battle as a member of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元暦元年（1184年）2月の一ノ谷の戦いにおいても、源義経に従軍して戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Battle of Ichinotani in March 1184, he also went to the front with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s army and participated in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Battle of Ichinotani in March 1184, he also went to the front with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s army and participated in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Battle of Ichinotani in March 1184, he also went to the front with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s army and participated in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その功績により伊賀国守護（惣追捕使）に補任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For his outstanding achievement at this time, he was appointed as Shugo (provincial military governor) of Iga Province) (Sotsuibushi (government post in charge of police and military roles)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For his outstanding achievement at this time, he was appointed as Shugo (provincial military governor) of Iga Province) (Sotsuibushi [government post in charge of police and military roles]).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For his outstanding achievement at this time, he was appointed as Shugo (provincial military governor) of Iga Province) (Sotsuibushi [government post in charge of police and military roles]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>平清盛ら伊勢平氏の権力基盤の一部であった伊賀を抑える役割を期待されての人事と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This assignment was probably made with the expectation that he would be able to control the Iga clan, which was an element of power basis of the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) including TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This assignment was probably made with the expectation that he would be able to control the Iga clan, which was an element of power basis of the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) including TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This assignment was probably made with the expectation that he would be able to control the Iga clan, which was an element of power basis of the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) including TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同国大内荘（九条家領の荘園）の地頭職を兼ねたともいわれ、このころから「大内冠者」と記されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also said to be in charge of Jito (manager and state steward) at Ouchi-sho manor (medieval manor belonging to the Kujo family) in Ise Province, and around since then, he had been described as &apos;Ouchi Kaja&apos; (Gentleman Ouchi)</e>
<cmt>大内冠者→定訳不明：&apos;Ouchi Kaja&apos; (Gentleman Ouchi)と（）内仮訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also said to be in charge of Jito (manager and state steward) at Ouchi no sho manor (medieval manor belonging to the Kujo family) in Iga Province, and around since then, he had been described as &apos;Ouchi Kaja&apos; (literally, Young man of Ouchi).</e>
<cmt>「同国」を「伊賀国」と変更し、「冠者」の用語補足を変えました。http://tangorin.com/words/kaja</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also said to be in charge of Jito (manager and state steward) at Ouchi no sho manor (medieval manor belonging to the Kujo family) in Iga Province, and around since then, he had been described as &apos;Ouchi Kaja&apos; (literally, Young man of Ouchi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>同年、隣国・伊勢国に潜伏していた志田義広が捕らえられた際には、惟義の家人が援軍として協力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year (1184), when MINAMOTO no Yoshihiro (Saburo-Senjo SHIDA) was captured, Koreyoshi&apos;s family cooperated as support forces.</e>
<cmt>志田三郎先生→Saburo-Senjo SHIDAと表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, when Yoshihiro SHIDA who was hiding in the Ise Province, the neighboring province, was captured, Koreyoshi&apos;s family cooperated as support forces.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「隣国・伊勢国に潜伏していた」を補足しました。原文には (源義広 (志田三郎先生)) とありましたが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「志田義広」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出し、原文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, when Yoshihiro SHIDA who was hiding in the Ise Province, the neighboring province, was captured, Koreyoshi&apos;s family cooperated as support forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>6月から7月にかけて同国で三日平氏の乱 (平安時代)が起こり、平信兼率いる平家の残党に襲われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period of July and September, 1184, the Mikka Heishi no ran (Three days rebellion of the Taira clan) (Heian Period) broke out in Ise Province, and he was attacked by the remnants of the defeated Taira clan lead by TAIRA no Nobukane.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of July and August, the Mikka Heishi War (literally, Three days rebellion of the Taira clan) (Heian Period) broke out in Ise Province, and he was attacked by the remnants of the defeated Taira clan led by TAIRA no Nobukane.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。また1204年の「三日平氏の乱」と表現を区別しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of July and August, the Mikka Heishi War (literally, Three days rebellion of the Taira clan) (Heian Period) broke out in Ise Province, and he was attacked by the remnants of the defeated Taira clan led by TAIRA no Nobukane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>多くの家人を失い、いったん国外へ逃亡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lost many of his family members, and he had to seek refuge out of the province for a while.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lost many of his family members, and he had to seek refuge out of the province for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lost many of his family members, and he had to seek refuge out of the province for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>鎌倉からは山内首藤経俊（平家方からの寝返り）や加藤景員（伊勢出身）・加藤光員らとともに平家の余党を討伐を命じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kamakura government issued the order to subjugate the remnants of the Taira clan, to him as well as Tsuneyoshi YAMAUCHISUDO (a double-cross from the Taira clan), Kagekazu KATO (of Ise Province), and Mitsukazu KATO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamakura bakufu issued the order to subjugate the remnants of the Taira clan, to him as well as Tsuneyoshi YAMAUCHISUDO (a double-cross from the Taira clan), Kagekazu KATO (of Ise Province), and Mitsukazu KATO, and others.</e>
<cmt>用語を変え、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamakura bakufu issued the order to subjugate the remnants of the Taira clan, to him as well as Tsuneyoshi YAMAUCHISUDO (a double-cross from the Taira clan), Kagekazu KATO (of Ise Province), and Mitsukazu KATO, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>が、その指令が届く前に90余人の残党を討って鎮圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, before the order reached him, he had already suppressed the enemy, killed than 90 remnants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, before the order reached him, he had already suppressed the enemy, killed than 90 remnants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, before the order reached him, he had already suppressed the enemy, killed than 90 remnants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>惟義は乱の鎮圧に対する恩賞を頼朝に求めたが、狼藉を鎮めるのは守護の務めであり、家人を殺害されたのは汝の落ち度であるので恩賞を求めるのは道理に叛くとして却下されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreyoshi requested MINAMOTO no Yoritomo a reward for this meritorious suppression, however, Yoritomo rejected request by saying that suppressing the violence was a Shugo (provincial military governor)&apos;s duty, and Koeryoshi&apos;s family members were killed due to his own fault, therefore, it was irrational that Koreyoshi would ask for a reward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koreyoshi requested Yoritomo a reward for this meritorious suppression, however, Yoritomo rejected request by saying that suppressing the violence was a Shugo&apos;s duty, and Koreyoshi&apos;s family members were killed due to his own fault, therefore, it was irrational that Koreyoshi would ask for a reward.</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除し、原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koreyoshi requested Yoritomo a reward for this meritorious suppression, however, Yoritomo rejected request by saying that suppressing the violence was a Shugo&apos;s duty, and Koreyoshi&apos;s family members were killed due to his own fault, therefore, it was irrational that Koreyoshi would ask for a reward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>頼朝側近として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Yoritomo&apos;s close adviser</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Yoritomo&apos;s close adviser</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Yoritomo&apos;s close adviser</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>父の平賀義信とともに頼朝から源氏門葉の側近武将として信頼される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He and his father Yoshinobu HIRAGA gained Yoritomo&apos;s confidence as close advisers, who came from the same Genji blood line.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He and his father Yoshinobu HIRAGA gained Yoritomo&apos;s confidence as close advisers, who came from the same Minamoto clan&apos;s blood line.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He and his father Yoshinobu HIRAGA gained Yoritomo&apos;s confidence as close advisers, who came from the same Minamoto clan&apos;s blood line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>文治元年（1185年）9月に勝長寿院で頼朝の父源義朝の供養が行われた際、義信と惟義、源頼隆の3名のみが遺骨への近侍を許されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1185, when the memorial service of Yoritomo&apos;s father, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, was held at Shochoju-in Temple, only three persons, Yoshinobu, and Koreyoshi and MINAMOTO no Yoritaka, were allowed to come closer to Yoshitomo&apos;s remains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1185, when the memorial service of Yoritomo&apos;s father, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, was held at Shochoju-in Temple, only three persons, Yoshinobu, Koreyoshi and MINAMOTO no Yoritaka, were allowed to come closer to Yoshitomo&apos;s remains.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1185, when the memorial service of Yoritomo&apos;s father, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, was held at Shochoju-in Temple, only three persons, Yoshinobu, Koreyoshi and MINAMOTO no Yoritaka, were allowed to come closer to Yoshitomo&apos;s remains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>元暦2年（1185年）6月に多田行綱から没収した摂津国多田荘および荘内の在地武士である多田院御家人の支配を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1185, he was ordered to manage the Tada-no-sho manor in Settsu Province, which was expropriated from Yukitsuna TADA, and control a unit of local samurais called Tadanoin gokenin (vassals of Tadano-in Shrine).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1185, he was ordered to manage the Tada no sho manor in Settsu Province, which was expropriated from Yukitsuna TADA, and control a unit of local samurai warriors called Tadanoin gokenin (vassals of Tadano-in Shrine).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1185, he was ordered to manage the Tada no sho manor in Settsu Province, which was expropriated from Yukitsuna TADA, and control a unit of local samurai warriors called Tadanoin gokenin (vassals of Tadano-in Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、同年の除目で頼朝に従う源氏一門が受領に任命された際、相模国守に補任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he was appointed Sagami no kuni no Kami (Governor of Sagami Province) at the Jimoku (ceremony to appoint officials) of the same year (1185), while other fellows of the Minamoto clan, who were also in Yoritomo&apos;s service, were appointed Zuryo (Career provincial official).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。受領→定訳不明：Zuryo (Career provincial official)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he was appointed Sagami no kuni no Kami (Governor of Sagami Province) at the Jimoku (ceremony to appoint officials) of the same year, while other fellows of the Minamoto clan, who were also in Yoritomo&apos;s service, were appointed Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors).</e>
<cmt>「受領」は用語集に合わせ修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he was appointed Sagami no kuni no Kami (Governor of Sagami Province) at the Jimoku (ceremony to appoint officials) of the same year, while other fellows of the Minamoto clan, who were also in Yoritomo&apos;s service, were appointed Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>翌々年には美濃国守に転じ、文治5年（1189年）の奥州合戦にも従軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two years later, he was reappointed to Mino no kuni no Kami (Governor of Mino Province) and in 1189 he went with the army to the front during the Battle of Oshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two years later, he was reappointed to Mino no kuni no Kami (Governor of Mino Province) and in 1189 he went with the army to the front during the Battle of Oshu.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two years later, he was reappointed to Mino no kuni no Kami (Governor of Mino Province) and in 1189 he went with the army to the front during the Battle of Oshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>翌建久元年の頼朝上洛および同6年（1195年）の再上洛にも随行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year, in 1190, he traveled in attendance on Yoritomo who went to Kyoto, and in 1195, he accompanied Yoritomo to Kyoto again..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, in 1190, he traveled in attendance on Yoritomo who went to Kyoto, and in 1195, he accompanied Yoritomo to Kyoto again.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, in 1190, he traveled in attendance on Yoritomo who went to Kyoto, and in 1195, he accompanied Yoritomo to Kyoto again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>建久6年には父の義信に代わって武蔵守に任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1195, he was appointed Musashi no kuni no Kami (Governor of Musashi Province), after his father Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1195, he was appointed Musashi no Kami (Governor of Musashi Province), after his father Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>用語を原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1195, he was appointed Musashi no Kami (Governor of Musashi Province), after his father Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉・京への両属</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dual belongingness to Kamakura and Kyoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dual belongingness to Kamakura and Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dual belongingness to Kamakura and Kyoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>頼朝の死後は、平安京に赴き、後鳥羽天皇に近侍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoritomo&apos;s death, he went up to Heiankyo (ancient capital in current Kyoto) and served Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoritomo&apos;s death, he went up to Heian-kyo (ancient capital in current Kyoto) and served Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoritomo&apos;s death, he went up to Heian-kyo (ancient capital in current Kyoto) and served Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>在京の鎌倉幕府代理人的な立場になって鎌倉と京の連絡役を務めたと思われるが、いっぽうで後鳥羽近臣として朝廷との接触を深めていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed that he worked as a liaison between Kamakura and Kyoto playing a role of the agent in Kyoto for Kamakura bakufu (Shogunate), however, his contact with the Imperial Court as a close retainer of Retired Emperor Gotoba was gradually getting more intimate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is presumed that he worked as a liaison between Kamakura and Kyoto playing a role of the agent in Kyoto for Kamakura bakufu, however, his contact with the Imperial Court as a close retainer of Retired Emperor Gotoba was gradually getting more intimate.</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is presumed that he worked as a liaison between Kamakura and Kyoto playing a role of the agent in Kyoto for Kamakura bakufu, however, his contact with the Imperial Court as a close retainer of Retired Emperor Gotoba was gradually getting more intimate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>幕府からは、伊勢・伊賀・越前国・美濃・丹波国・摂津国という近畿6ヶ国の守護を任命されているいっぽうで、朝廷からは駿河国守にも任ぜられていることからも、その両属的な性格がうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His status of dual belongingness can be guess from the fact that while he was holding the position of Shugo (the provincial military governor) appointed by the bakufu (Shogunate), in six provinces in Kinki Region, Ise, Iga, Echizen, Mino, Tanba, and Settsu, he was also appointed Suruga no kuni no Kami (Governor of Suruga Province) by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His status of dual belongingness can be guess from the fact that while he was holding the position of Shugo appointed by the bakufu in six provinces in Kinki Region, such as Ise, Iga, Echizen, Mino, Tanba, and Settsu, he was also appointed Suruga no kuni no Kami (Governor of Suruga Province) by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His status of dual belongingness can be guess from the fact that while he was holding the position of Shugo appointed by the bakufu in six provinces in Kinki Region, such as Ise, Iga, Echizen, Mino, Tanba, and Settsu, he was also appointed Suruga no kuni no Kami (Governor of Suruga Province) by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この時期、北条氏が専権を振るい出し、後鳥羽朝廷との対立が尖鋭化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period, the Hojo clan began to enjoy an autocratic rule, and the growing conflict with the Imperial Court lead by Emperor Gotoba was becoming more and more visible.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, the Hojo clan began to enjoy an autocratic rule, and the growing conflict with the Imperial Court led by Retired Emperor Gotoba was becoming more and more visible.</e>
<cmt>「後鳥羽」は「後鳥羽院」と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, the Hojo clan began to enjoy an autocratic rule, and the growing conflict with the Imperial Court led by Retired Emperor Gotoba was becoming more and more visible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>が、子息の大内惟信の後の行動（後述）から推測すれば、この時期すでに惟義は、心情的には朝廷方へ荷担する意図があった可能性も高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the behaviors that his son Korenobu OUCHI took later, it is highly probable that by that time, Koreyoshi had already made up a mind to join the Imperial Court side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging from the behaviors that his son Korenobu OUCHI took later, it is highly probable that by that time, Koreyoshi had already made up a mind to join the Imperial Court side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging from the behaviors that his son Korenobu OUCHI took later, it is highly probable that by that time, Koreyoshi had already made up a mind to join the Imperial Court side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>建保7年（1219年、のち承久に改元）正月27日、3代征夷大将軍源実朝が、右大臣拝賀のため、鶴岡八幡宮へ御参した際（この日、実朝は暗殺される）の『吾妻鏡』の記事中に「修理権大夫惟義朝臣」の名が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Azuma Kagami &quot;(The Mirror of the East), there is an article touching on February 20, 1219, when the third Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) MINAMOTO no Sanetomo visited Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine in order to congratulate the assumption of Udaijin (the Minister of the Right) (on this day, Sanetomo was assassinated), and in this article Koreyoshi&apos;s name appeared as &apos;Shuri gon no daibu (Provisional master in the Office of Palace Repairs) Tadayoshi no Asomi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Azuma Kagami &quot;(The Mirror of the East), there is an article touching on February 20, 1219, when the third Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) MINAMOTO no Sanetomo visited Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine in order to congratulate the assumption of Udaijin (the Minister of the Right) (on this day, Sanetomo was assassinated), and in this article Koreyoshi&apos;s name appeared as &apos;Shuri gon no daibu Tadayoshi no Asomi&apos; (Tadayoshi of Asomi [second highest of the eight hereditary titles], Provisional master in the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>用語補足を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Azuma Kagami &quot;(The Mirror of the East), there is an article touching on February 20, 1219, when the third Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) MINAMOTO no Sanetomo visited Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine in order to congratulate the assumption of Udaijin (the Minister of the Right) (on this day, Sanetomo was assassinated), and in this article Koreyoshi&apos;s name appeared as &apos;Shuri gon no daibu Tadayoshi no Asomi&apos; (Tadayoshi of Asomi [second highest of the eight hereditary titles], Provisional master in the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>だが、これ以降史料上の消息は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since then, no descriptions referring to him can be found in any historical materials.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since then, no descriptions referring to him can be found in any historical materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since then, no descriptions referring to him can be found in any historical materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>おそらくこの年もしくは翌年に死去したものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is probable that he died this year or the next year</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is probable that he died this year or the next year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is probable that he died this year or the next year</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>承久3年（1221年）、承久の乱が勃発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 12221, the Jokyu War broke out</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1221, the Jokyu War broke out.</e>
<cmt>年号など修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1221, the Jokyu War broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>後鳥羽院ら京方の挙兵に対し、惟義の死後に近畿6国守護職を受け継いでいた子の惟信は、後鳥羽院の下へはせ参じ、京方として鎌倉幕府軍と戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against the Retired Emperor Gotoba and kyogata (the supporters of Imperial Court) that raised an army, Koreyoshi&apos;s son Korenobu, who succeeded to the positions of Shugo in six provinces after his father&apos;s death, hastened to Retired Emperor Gotoba and joined the army of kyogata to fight against the forces of Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Against the Retired Emperor Gotoba and kyogata (the supporters of the Imperial Court) that raised an army, Koreyoshi&apos;s son Korenobu, who succeeded to the positions of Shugo in six provinces after his father&apos;s death, hastened to Retired Emperor Gotoba and joined the army of kyogata to fight against the forces of Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Against the Retired Emperor Gotoba and kyogata (the supporters of the Imperial Court) that raised an army, Koreyoshi&apos;s son Korenobu, who succeeded to the positions of Shugo in six provinces after his father&apos;s death, hastened to Retired Emperor Gotoba and joined the army of kyogata to fight against the forces of Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、あえなく敗戦して消息を絶ち、ここに源氏御門葉平賀・大内氏は滅亡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Korenobu easily lost the battle and since then, his fate remained unknown, and hereto, the Hiraga-Ouchi clan of the Genji (Minamoto clan) blood line definitively perished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he easily lost the battle and since then, his fate remained unknown, and hereto, the Hiraga and Ouchi clans of the Genji (Minamoto clan) blood line definitively perished.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he easily lost the battle and since then, his fate remained unknown, and hereto, the Hiraga and Ouchi clans of the Genji (Minamoto clan) blood line definitively perished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>後鳥羽院が惟義を尊重した理由の一つに来るべき討幕の日のために歴戦の武将である惟義を味方に付けておきたいという思惑があったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the reason why Retired Emperor Gotoba gave Koreyoshi a preferential treatment might have been that the retired emperor wanted to win the experienced busho (Japanese military commander) Koreyoshi over to his side, thinking of the day in which he would overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the reason why Retired Emperor Gotoba gave Koreyoshi a preferential treatment might have been that the retired emperor wanted to win the experienced busho (Japanese military commander) Koreyoshi over to his side, thinking of the day in which he would overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the reason why Retired Emperor Gotoba gave Koreyoshi a preferential treatment might have been that the retired emperor wanted to win the experienced busho (Japanese military commander) Koreyoshi over to his side, thinking of the day in which he would overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>もし、承久の乱で若年の惟信ではなく惟義が朝廷軍を率いていたならば、戦況はまた違ったものになっていた可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If it had not been young Korenobu but Koreyoshi who led the Imperial forces in the Jokyu War, the war situation could have been different</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If it had not been young Korenobu but Koreyoshi who led the Imperial forces in the Jokyu War, the war situation could have been different.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If it had not been young Korenobu but Koreyoshi who led the Imperial forces in the Jokyu War, the war situation could have been different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), カイの迷宮(id:72682), 海衛士(id:19229), 水野白楓(id:22811), ちちぶ(id:184715), 味っ子(id:17086), トホホ川(id:50502), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>