<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原俊憲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshinori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Toshinori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshinori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 俊憲（ふじわら の としのり、保安 (元号)3年（1122年）- 仁安 (日本)2年（1167年））は平安時代後期の廷臣、学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshinori (1122-1167) was a retainer of Imperial Court and scholar in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Toshinori (1122-1167) was a scholar and retainer of the Imperial Court in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshinori (1122-1167) was a scholar and retainer of the Imperial Court in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>信西こと藤原通憲の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eldest son of Shinzei or FUJIWARA no Michinori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of the monk Shinzei, whose rreal name was FUJIWARA no Michinori.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of the monk Shinzei, whose real name was FUJIWARA no Michinori.</e>
<cmt>realのスペルミス修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は高階重仲の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of TAKASHINA no Shigenaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of TAKASHINA no Shigenaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of TAKASHINA no Shigenaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>参議藤原顕業の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by Sangi (councilor) FUJIWARA no Akinari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by Sangi (councilor) FUJIWARA no Akinari.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by Sangi (councilor) FUJIWARA no Akinari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正四位下、参議。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and Sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Sangi with the rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Sangi with the rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>若年より実父信西譲りの才智をもって登用され、大学権助、東宮学士などを経て、保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱の後の除目で右少弁に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was, early in life, appointed to the government positions due to his talent and intelligence inherited from his natural father, Shinzei, and after served as Daigaku no gon no suke, Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics of the Crown Prince) and so on, appointed as Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) at the time of Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) following the Hogen Disturbance in 1156.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the talent and intelligence that he had inherited from his father, Shinzei, he was given government positions while still young, serving as Daigaku no Gon no Suke (Provisional Assistant Director of the Bureau of Education) and Togu Gakushi (Teacher of the Classics to the Crown Prince) amongst others and, following the Hogen Disturbance in 1156, he was appointed Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the talent and intelligence that he had inherited from his father, Shinzei, he was given government positions while still young, serving as Daigaku no Gon no Suke (Provisional Assistant Director of the Bureau of Education) and Togu Gakushi (Teacher of the Classics to the Crown Prince) amongst others and, following the Hogen War in 1156, he was appointed Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right).</e>
<cmt>統一事項より、Hogen Disturbance→Hogen Warに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以後、父の権勢をも背景として要職を歴任し、左少弁蔵人、左衛門権佐、東宮学士を兼帯した際には「希代」のことと評された（『兵範記』・保元2年（1157年）10月23日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, backed by his father&apos;s power, he successively filled various important posts and when he concurrently held the posts of Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left) Kurodo (Chamberlain) (&quot;Heihanki&quot; (diary of TAIRA no Nobunori) December 3, 1157 Section).</e>
<cmt>「保元2年10月23日」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1157年12月3日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, backed by his father&apos;s power, he successively held various important posts and when he concurrently held the posts of Sashoben (Minor Controller of the Left), Kurodo (Chamberlain), Saemon no Gon no Suke (Provivsional Assistant Captain of the Left Division of the Outer Palace Guards) and Togu Gakushi, TAIRA no Nobunori wrote in the December 3, 1157 entry of his diary &quot;Heihanki&quot;, that Toshinori was &apos;one of a kind&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, backed by his father&apos;s power, he successively held various important posts and when he concurrently held the posts of Sashoben (Minor Controller of the Left), Kurodo (Chamberlain), Saemon no Gon no Suke (Provivsional Assistant Captain of the Left Division of the Outer Palace Guards) and Togu Gakushi, TAIRA no Nobunori wrote in the December 3, 1157 entry of his diary &quot;Heihanki,&quot; that Toshinori was &apos;one of a kind.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマ、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>平治元年（1159年）に参議に至るが、同年平治の乱が勃発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Sangi in 1159 and in the same year, the Heiji Disturbance broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Sangi in 1159 and in the same year, the Heiji Rebellion broke out.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Disturbance&quot;→&quot;Rebellion&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Sangi in 1159 and in the same year, the Heiji War broke out.</e>
<cmt>統一事項より、Heiji Rebellion→Heiji Warに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>父信西は殺害され、さらに戦後、戦乱を招いた責任によりその子息は悉く流罪に処せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Shinzei was killed, and further after the Disturbance, Shinzei&apos;s sons were all banished being made to take responsibility for the Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Shinzei, was killed and then after the rebellion, Shinzei&apos;s sons were made to take responsibility and banished.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Shinzei, was killed and then after the war, Shinzei&apos;s sons were made to take responsibility and banished.</e>
<cmt>rebellion→warに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>俊憲も解官の上越後国（後に阿波国に変更）に配流となり、これを契機に出家して法名を真寂と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshinori was also deprived of his positions and exiled to Echigo province (changed to Awa Province later), and taking that opportunity, he became a priest and called himself Shinjaku, his Homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshinori was relieved of his positions and exiled to Echigo Province (and later to Awa Province), and taking that opportunity, he became a priest and took the name Shinjaku.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshinori was relieved of his positions and exiled to Echigo Province (and later to Awa Province), and taking that opportunity, he became a priest and took the name Shinjaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>翌永暦 (日本)元年（1160年）には召還されるが、その後は表舞台に立つことなく、仁安2年に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was recalled in the following year, 1160, but afterward, he never went mainstream and died in 1167.</e>
<cmt>「仁安2年」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1167年」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was recalled the following year, 1160, but he never again held any prominent posts and died in 1167.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was recalled the following year, 1160, but he never again held any prominent posts and died in 1167.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>『愚管抄』や『古事談』『続古事談』にその文才を物語る逸話があり、また『玉葉』元暦元年（1184年）7月9日条にも、かつて俊憲が「後白河院のもとでは戦乱が止まないであろう」と予言していたことが「聖人格言」として紹介されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gukansho &quot; (Jottings of a Fool), &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past) and &quot;Zoku kojidan&quot; contained anecdotes about his talent for writing and the August 23, 1184 section of &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of FUJIWARA no Kanezane) introduced, as a &apos; proverb of wise man,&apos; a prediction he had made saying that &apos;War will not cease as far as the retired emperor Goshirakawa holds power.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「元暦元年7月9日」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦1184年8月23日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gukansho &quot; (Jottings of a Fool), &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past) and &quot;Zoku kojidan&quot;(Talks of the Past, continued) contained anecdotes about his talent for writing and the August 23, 1184 entry in FUJIWARA no Kanezane&apos;s diary &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; refers to Toshinori&apos;s prediction that &apos;war will not cease as long as retired Emperor Goshirakawa holds power&apos; as a &apos; proverb of a wise man&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), &quot;Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past) and &quot;Zoku Kojidan&quot; (Talks of the Past, continued) contained anecdotes about his talent for writing and the August 23, 1184 entry in FUJIWARA no Kanezane&apos;s diary &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; refers to Toshinori&apos;s prediction that &apos;war will not cease as long as the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa holds power&apos; as a &apos;proverb of a wise man.&apos;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース消去、カッコの前のスペース追加、&quot;Zoku Kojidan&quot;とし、retired Emperor Goshirakawa→the Retired Emperor Goshirakawaに修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>著書として『新任弁官抄』『貫首秘抄』があり、また歌人としても『千載和歌集』『新勅撰和歌集』にもその作が入選している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote books &quot;新任弁官抄&quot; and &quot;Kanjyuhisho,&quot; while, as a poet, his waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) were selected for &quot;Senzai (waka) shu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years) and &quot;Shin chokusen wakashu&quot; (New Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His literary works include &quot;Shinnin Benkan-sho&quot; and &quot;Kanjyuhisho,&quot; and his waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) were selected for &quot;Senzai wakashu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years) and &quot;Shin chokusen wakashu&quot; (New Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His literary works include &quot;Shinnin Benkan-sho&quot; and &quot;Kanjuhisho,&quot; and his waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) were selected for &quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot; (Collection of a Thousand Years) and &quot;Shin Chokusen Wakashu&quot; (New Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>Kanjyuhisho→Kanjuhishoに修正、&quot;Senzai Wakashu&quot;&quot;Shin Chokusen Wakashu&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>