<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>河井寛次郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjiro KAWAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjiro KAWAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjiro KAWAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>河井 寛次郎（かわい かんじろう、1890年(明治23年)8月24日 - 1966年(昭和41年)11月18日）は、日本の陶芸家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjiro KAWAI (August 24, 1890 - November 18, 1966) was a ceramic artist in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjiro KAWAI (August 24, 1890 - November 18, 1966) was a ceramic artist in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjiro KAWAI (August 24, 1890 - November 18, 1966) was a ceramic artist in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>陶芸のほか、彫刻、デザイン、書道、詩、詞、随筆などの分野でも優れた作品を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He produced excellent work in the areas such as sculpture, design, calligraphy, poetry, prose poetry (詞), and essay in addition to ceramics.</e>
<cmt>詞→prose poetry[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He produced excellent work in the areas such as sculpture, design, calligraphy, poetry, prose poetry (詞), and essays, in addition to ceramics.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He produced excellent work in the areas such as sculpture, design, calligraphy, poetry, prose poetry (詞), and essays, in addition to ceramics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>学校での研究</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Research in schools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research in schools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research in schools</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>当時の島根県安来町（現在の安来市）の大工の家に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjiro was born as a son of a carpenter in Yasugi-cho, Shimane Prefecture at that time (present-day Yasugi City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjiro was born as a son of a carpenter in Yasugi-cho, Shimane Prefecture (present-day Yasugi City).</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjiro was born as a son of a carpenter in Yasugi-cho, Shimane Prefecture (present-day Yasugi City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>松江中学（現島根県立松江北高等学校）を経て、1910年、東京高等工業学校（現東京工業大学）窯業へ入学する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1910, he entered the department of ceramic engineering at Tokyo Higher Technical School (present-day Tokyo Institute of Technology) after graduating from Matsue Junior High School (present-day Matsue Kita Senior High School of Shimane Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1910, he entered the department of ceramic engineering at Tokyo Higher Technical School (present-day Tokyo Institute of Technology) after graduating from Matsue Junior High School (present-day Matsue Kita Senior High School of Shimane Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1910, he entered the department of ceramic engineering at Tokyo Higher Technical School (present-day Tokyo Institute of Technology) after graduating from Matsue Junior High School (present-day Matsue Kita Senior High School of Shimane Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>寛次郎には師と仰ぐ者がなく、師弟関係を重んじる陶工の世界にあって、学校という教育機関にて指導を受けた新しい世代の陶工となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not having anyone to regard as his master in the world of potters where the master-student relationship was highly valued, Kanjiro became a potter of the new generation who learned pottery in the educational institution called school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not having anyone to regard as his master in the world of potters where the master-student relationship was highly valued, Kanjiro became a potter of the new generation who learned pottery in an educational institution called a school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not having anyone to regard as his master in the world of potters where the master-student relationship was highly valued, Kanjiro became a potter of the new generation who learned pottery in an educational institution called a school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>東京高等工業学校では、陶芸家の板谷波山の指導を受けたほか、窯業の科学的研究を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received instruction from the potter, Hazan ITAYA, and conducted scientific studies of ceramic engineering at Tokyo Higher Technical School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received instruction from the potter, Hazan ITAYA, and conducted scientific studies on ceramic engineering at Tokyo Higher Technical School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received instruction from the potter, Hazan ITAYA, and conducted scientific studies on ceramic engineering at Tokyo Higher Technical School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>東京高等工業学校卒業後は、京都市立陶芸試験場に入所し、東京高等工業学校の後輩でもある濱田庄司とともに1万種以上の釉薬の研究や、中国陶磁など過去の陶磁の模倣や研究も行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjiro joined the Kyoto Ceramic Research Center (京都市立陶芸試験場) after graduating from Tokyo Higher Technical School, and along with Shoji HAMADA, his junior at the school, he studied more than 10,000 types of glazes, reproduce and study ceramics in the past such as Chinese ceramics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjiro joined the Kyoto Ceramic Research Center (京都市立陶芸試験場) after graduating from Tokyo Higher Technical School, and along with Shoji HAMADA, his junior at the school, he studied more than 10,000 types of glazes, reproduced and studied ceramics from the past, such as Chinese ceramics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjiro joined the Kyoto Ceramic Research Center (京都市立陶芸試験場) after graduating from Tokyo Higher Technical School, and along with Shoji HAMADA, his junior at the school, he studied more than 10,000 types of glazes, reproduced and studied ceramics from the past, such as Chinese ceramics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1920年、五代清水六兵衛の技術的顧問を務めていた縁で京都・五条坂にあった彼の窯を譲り受け、「鐘渓窯」と名づけ自らの作品制作を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Serving as technical adviser to Rokube KIYOMIZU the Fifth, Kanjiro in 1920 obtained Rokube&apos;s kiln in Gojozaka, Kyoto, named it &apos;Shokei yo&apos; (Shokei kiln), and began to create his own work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Serving as technical adviser to Rokube KIYOMIZU the Fifth, Kanjiro, in 1920, obtained Rokube&apos;s kiln in Gojozaka, Kyoto, named it &apos;Shokei yo&apos; (Shokei kiln), and began to create his own work.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Serving as technical adviser to Rokube KIYOMIZU the Fifth, Kanjiro, in 1920, obtained Rokube&apos;s kiln in Gojozaka, Kyoto, named it &apos;Shokei yo&apos; (Shokei kiln), and began to create his own work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同年、京都の宮大工の娘・つねと結婚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he married a daughter of a temple and shrine carpenter in Kyoto, Tsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he married the daughter of a temple and shrine carpenter in Kyoto, Tsune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he married the daughter of a temple and shrine carpenter in Kyoto, Tsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>華麗な作風からの転換</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shift from elegant style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A shift from elegant style</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shift from elegant style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>1921年、「創作陶磁展覧会」を東京と大阪の高島屋で開催した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1921, Kanjiro held the &apos;Creative Ceramics Exhibition&apos; (創作陶磁展覧会) at the Takashimaya department stores in Tokyo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1921, Kanjiro held the &apos;Creative Ceramics Exhibition&apos; (創作陶磁展覧会) at the Takashimaya department stores in Tokyo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1921, Kanjiro held the &apos;Creative Ceramics Exhibition&apos; (創作陶磁展覧会) at the Takashimaya department stores in Tokyo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このとき東京高島屋の宣伝部長であった川勝堅一と知り合い、生涯にわたり親交をもつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he met the PR manager of Takashimaya Tokyo, Kenichi KAWAKATSU, with whom he formed a lifelong friendship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, he met the PR manager of Takashimaya Tokyo, Kenichi KAWAKATSU, with whom he formed a lifelong friendship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, he met the PR manager of Takashimaya Tokyo, Kenichi KAWAKATSU, with whom he formed a lifelong friendship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>高島屋での陶磁展では、中国・朝鮮の陶磁の名作に倣い、科学的研究の成果を取り入れた超絶技巧の華やかな作品を発表、新人にして名人と一躍注目を浴びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the ceramics exhibitions at the Takashimaya department stores, Kanjiro introduced sophisticated, elegant works which he modeled from great ceramics in China and Korea and incorporated the results of his scientific studies into, and suddenly received public attention as a master potter even though he was a newcomer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the ceramics exhibitions at the Takashimaya department stores, Kanjiro introduced sophisticated, elegant works that he modeled after the great ceramics from China and Korea and applied the results of his scientific studies to, and suddenly received public attention as a master potter even though he was a newcomer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the ceramics exhibitions at the Takashimaya department stores, Kanjiro introduced sophisticated, elegant works that he modeled after the great ceramics from China and Korea and applied the results of his scientific studies to, and suddenly received public attention as a master potter even though he was a newcomer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかしやがて世評に反し、自身の制作に悩むようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he eventually became concerned about his works against the reputation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he eventually became concerned about the reputation of his works.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrary to the reputation, however, he eventually became concerned about his works.</e>
<cmt>「世評に反し」の部分を明確になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>創作陶磁展覧会と同時期に柳宗悦の集めた李氏朝鮮の陶磁展「朝鮮民族美術展」を展観し、無名の陶工の作り出す簡素で美しい作品に感銘を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time as the Creative Ceramics Exhibition, Kanjiro held the Korean Folk Art Exhibition, a ceramics exhibition displaying the ceramics of the Joseon Dynasty collected by Muneyoshi YANAGI, and was deeply impressed by the simple yet beautiful works of unknown potters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time at the Creative Ceramics Exhibition, Kanjiro held the Korean Folk Art Exhibition, displaying the ceramics from the Joseon Dynasty collected by Muneyoshi YANAGI, and was deeply impressed by the simple yet beautiful works of unknown potters.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time at the Creative Ceramics Exhibition, Kanjiro held &apos;the Korean Folk Art Exhibition&apos;, displaying the ceramics from the Joseon Dynasty collected by Muneyoshi YANAGI, and was deeply impressed by the simple yet beautiful works of unknown potters.</e>
<cmt>「&apos;」を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>“自分の作品は衣装であり化粧であり、中身の体はどうしたのか、心がけはどうしたのか”と、自らの作品制作を中断する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjiro stopped producing his own works, saying to himself, &quot;My works are like costumes and makeup, but what has happened to the body inside and the spirit?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjiro stopped producing his own works, saying to himself, &quot;My works are like costumes and makeup, but what has happened to the body inside and the spirit?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjiro stopped producing his own works, saying to himself, &quot;My works are like costumes and makeup, but what has happened to the body inside and the spirit?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1924年、イギリスから帰国した濱田庄司に現地で収集した雑器・スリップウェアを見せられ、濱田から柳を紹介されその民芸理論に深く共感し、日用の実用的な陶器制作を新たな目標とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1924, he deeply sympathized with Yanagi&apos;s folk theory and set a goal of creating useful ceramics for daily use when Shoji HAMADA returned home from England, showed him the various containers and slipware he collected there, and introduced Yanagi to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1924, he deeply sympathized with Yanagi&apos;s folk theory and set the goal of creating useful ceramics for daily use when Shoji HAMADA returned home from England, showed him the various containers and slipware he collected there, and introduced Yanagi to him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1924, he deeply sympathized with Yanagi&apos;s folk theory and set the goal of creating useful ceramics for daily use when Shoji HAMADA returned home from England, showed him the various containers and slipware he collected there, and introduced Yanagi to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>民芸運動、日用の美へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mingei (folk crafts) movement and towards beauty of daily use</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mingei (folk crafts) movement towards the beauty of daily use</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mingei (folk crafts) movement towards the beauty of daily use</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>1926年、柳、濱田とともに日本民芸美術館設立趣意書を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1926, Kanjiro together with Yanagi and Hamada made public the prospectus for the Japan Folk Crafts Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1926, Kanjiro together with Yanagi and Hamada made public the prospectus for the Japan Folk Crafts Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1926, Kanjiro together with Yanagi and Hamada made public the prospectus for the Japan Folk Crafts Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>古い日用品を発掘しその制作のための技術を復活させ、無名職人による日用の美を世に広め、新しい日用品を制作し普及しようとした「民芸運動」にかかわるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He joined the &apos;Mingei movement,&apos; which aimed to discover old daily necessities and recover the skills to produce them, to promote the beauty of daily use produced by unknown artisans, and to produce and spread new daily necessities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined the &apos;Mingei movement,&apos; which aimed to discover old daily necessities and recover the skills to produce them, to promote the beauty of ceramics for daily use produced by unknown artisans, and to produce and spread new daily ceramic necessities.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He joined the &apos;Mingei movement,&apos; which aimed to discover old daily necessities and recover the skills to produce them, to promote the beauty of ceramics for daily use produced by unknown artisans, and to produce and spread new daily ceramic necessities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>富本憲吉、黒田辰秋、バーナード・リーチらとも合流し、1929年に長い沈黙を破って開いた高島屋の個展では、古典から日用の器へと路線を変更した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenkichi TOMIMOTO, Tatsuaki KURODA, and Bernard Leach also joined the movement, and at his exhibition at the Takashimaya department store held in 1929 after a long period of silence, Kanjiro shifted his focus from classic to daily ware.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenkichi TOMIMOTO, Tatsuaki KURODA, and Bernard Leach also joined the movement, and at his exhibition at the Takashimaya department store was held in 1929 after a long period of silence, Kanjiro shifted his focus from classic to daily ware.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenkichi TOMIMOTO, Tatsuaki KURODA, and Bernard Leach also joined the movement, and at his exhibition at the Takashimaya department store was held in 1929 after a long period of silence, Kanjiro shifted his focus from classic to daily ware.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>寛次郎は各地を訪れ、手仕事の制作現場や、日本や朝鮮やイギリスの器から受けた影響をもとに、実用的で簡素な造形に釉薬の技術を生かし、美しい発色の器を次々と生み出して再び注目を浴びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He visited various places, and influenced by the sites of handicraft production and the ceramics of Japan, Korea and England, he produced a series of ceramics with beautiful coloration made from glaze technology while adopting simple, practical designs, and thus he came to receive public attention again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He visited various places, and influenced by the sites of handicraft production and the ceramics of Japan, Korea, and England, he produced a series of ceramics with beautiful coloration made from glaze technology while adopting simple, practical designs, and thus he received public attention again.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He visited various places, influenced by the sites of handicraft production and the ceramics of Japan, Korea, and England, he produced a series of ceramics with beautiful coloration made from glaze technology while adopting simple, practical designs, and thus he received public attention again.</e>
<cmt>「and」を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この時期以降、寛次郎は作家としての銘を作品に入れないようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, Kanjiro stopped inscribing his name as an artist on his works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Kanjiro stopped inscribing his name as an artist on his works.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Kanjiro stopped inscribing his name as an artist on his works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>室戸台風で五条坂の自宅が損壊したことを契機に、故郷の民家の形をもとに、登り窯の形に対応するかのような構造をした新しい自宅兼仕事場を自ら設計し、大工である実家とも協力して1937年に完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Muroto typhoon destroyed his house in Gojozaka, Kanjiro, modeling the shape of houses in his hometown, designed his new house with an office with the structure to match the shape of the climbing kiln and completed the construction of the house with the help of the carpenters of his parent&apos;s family in 1937.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Muroto typhoon destroyed his house in Gojozaka, Kanjiro, modeling the shape of houses in his hometown, designed his new house to include an office with the structure to match the shape of a climbing kiln and completed the construction of the house with the help of the carpenters from his parent&apos;s family in 1937.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Muroto typhoon destroyed his house in Gojozaka, Kanjiro designed his new house with a studio by modeling the shape of houses in his hometown with the structure to match the shape of a climbing kiln and completed the construction of the house with the help of the carpenters from his parent&apos;s family in 1937.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この自宅兼仕事場が現在の河井寛次郎記念館になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This house with an office currently remains as the Kawai Kanjiro Memorial Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This house with the office currently remains as the Kawai Kanjiro Memorial Museum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This house with the office currently remains as the Kawai Kanjiro Memorial Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>同じ年、川勝堅一の計らいで「鉄辰砂草花図壷」がパリ万国博覧会 (1937年)でグランプリを受賞する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, his &apos;flower design vase with iron and cinnabar glaze&apos; (鉄辰砂草花図壷) won the grand prize at the Paris World Exposition through Kenichi KAWAKATSU&apos;s arrangement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, his &apos;flower design vase with iron and cinnabar glaze&apos; (鉄辰砂草花図壷) won the grand prize at the Paris World Exposition through Kenichi KAWAKATSU&apos;s arrangement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, his &apos;flower design vase with iron and cinnabar glaze&apos; (鉄辰砂草花図壷) won the grand prize at the Paris World Exposition (1937) through Kenichi KAWAKATSU&apos;s special arrangement.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>より奔放な作風へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Towards more freewheeling style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Towards a more freewheeling style</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Towards a more freewheeling style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>第二次世界大戦後、世界の民族芸術に関心を深めた寛次朗は木彫の制作も開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After World War II, Kanjiro, who had developed an interest in folk art in the world, began to produce works in wood carving.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War II, Kanjiro, who had developed an interest in folk art in the world, began to produce works in wood carving.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War II, Kanjiro, who had developed an interest in folk art in the world, began to produce works in wood carving.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>陶の造形も日用の器から簡素ながら奔放な造形へと変化を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also managed to change his ceramic design for pots for daily use to simple yet freewheeling styles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also managed to change his ceramic design for pots for daily use to simple yet freewheeling styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His style of ceramic design also changed from pots for daily use to simple yet abstract designs.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>材料の入手が困難であった戦時中より詩、詞の創作を始め、1947年には寛次郎の詞「火の誓い」を棟方志功の板画で制作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started to write poems and prose poetry during World War II when materials were difficult to obtain, and created his prose poetry &apos;Hi no chikai&apos; (literally, fire oath) on the woodcut by Shiko MUNAKATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started to write poems and prose poetry during World War II when materials were difficult to obtain, and created his prose poetry &apos;Hi no chikai&apos; (literally, fire oath) on a woodcut by Shiko MUNAKATA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started to write poems and prose poetry during World War II when materials were difficult to obtain, and created his prose poetry &apos;Hi no chikai&apos; (literally, fire oath) on a woodcut by Shiko MUNAKATA in 1947.</e>
<cmt>「in 1947」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>随筆「いのちの窓」を陶土に刻んだ陶板を完成させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjiro completed the production of the ceramic panel inscribed with his essay &apos;Inochi no mado&apos; (literally, window of life) on the pot clay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjiro completed the production of a ceramic panel inscribed with his essay &apos;Inochi no mado&apos; (literally, window of life) on the pot clay.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjiro completed the production of a ceramic panel inscribed with his essay &apos;Inochi no mado&apos; (literally, window of life) on the pot clay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>老境にいたり深い思慮を重ねた文章を多数残した時期だったが、壷や皿などの陶の作品は、荒々しい素地で用途にとらわれない自在な形状に、アクション・ペインティングのように釉薬を刷毛で打ちつけるような作品を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the time he wrote a large number of reflective essays in his old age, but, for ceramic works such as pots and plates, he produced them as if they had been produced in the method of action painting by slamming graze with brush on the rough surface of the flexible shapes free of use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a time when he wrote a large number of reflective essays during his old age, but, for ceramic works such as pots and plates, he produced them as if they had been created with a method of action painting by slamming the glaze with a brush against the rough surface of flexible shapes.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a time when he wrote a large number of reflective essays during his old age, but, for ceramic works such as pots and plates, he produced them as if they had been created with a method of action painting by slamming the glaze with a brush against the rough surface of flexible shapes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>またあらゆる釉薬や造形を試し、その創作意欲が生涯枯れることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, he tested all kinds of glazes and designs, never losing his creative drive until his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, he tested all kinds of glazes and designs, never losing his creative drive until his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he tested all kinds of glazes and designs, never losing his creative drive until his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>1955年文化勲章を辞退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjiro declined the Order of Culture in 1955.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjiro declined the Order of Culture in 1955.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjiro declined the Order of Culture in 1955.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>人間国宝、日本芸術院会員などへの推挙もあったが、同様に辞退している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although recommended for Living National Treasure and a member of the Japan Art Academy, he declined them as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although recommended as a Living National Treasure and a member of the Japan Art Academy, he declined them as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although recommended as a Living National Treasure and a member of the Japan Art Academy, he declined them as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>1957年には川勝堅一の計らいで「白地草花絵扁壷」が、ミラノ・トリエンナーレ国際工芸展グランプリを受賞するも、無位無冠の陶工とし晩年まで創作活動を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1957, his &apos;flower design flat vase with white glaze&apos; (白地草花絵扁壷) won the grand prize at the Milan Triennale International Industrial Art Exhibition through Kenichi KAWAKATSU&apos;s arrangement, but Kanjiro continued to work as a potter of no rank or prize until his later years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1957, his &apos;flower design flat vase with white glaze&apos; (白地草花絵扁壷) won the grand prize at the Milan Triennale International Industrial Art Exhibition arranged by Kenichi KAWAKATSU, but Kanjiro continued to work as a potter without rank or prize until his later years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1957, his &apos;flower design flat vase with white glaze&apos; (白地草花絵扁壷) won the grand prize at the Milan Triennale International Industrial Art Exhibition arranged by Kenichi KAWAKATSU, but Kanjiro continued to work as a potter without rank or prize until his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1966年に76歳で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1966, he died at the age of seventy-six.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1966, he died at the age of seventy-six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1966, he died at the age of seventy-six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Alecs.bot(id:194707), 新茶(id:157775), 浩(id:70121), 0null0(id:582), Reggaeman(id:6214), Cprobot(id:97843), ウィキウィ2(id:83093), D.h(id:79056), 663highland(id:18755), Point136(id:211299), Myuko(id:173704), Nopira(id:29335), Lucasart(id:106311), Orangepage(id:166660), Uraios(id:72687), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>