<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>佐久間左馬太</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samata SAKUMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samata SAKUMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samata SAKUMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>佐久間 左馬太（さくま さまた、天保15年10月10日 (旧暦)（1844年11月19日） - 大正4年（1915年）8月5日）は、日本の大日本帝国陸軍軍人、華族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samata SAKUMA (November 19, 1844 - August 5, 1915) was a military man in the Imperial Japanese Army and a peer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samata SAKUMA (November 19, 1844 - August 5, 1915) was a military man of the Imperial Japanese Army and a peer.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samata SAKUMA (November 19, 1844 - August 5, 1915) was a military man of the Imperial Japanese Army and a peer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>台湾総督・東京衛戍総督・近衛師団長等を歴任し、階級は陸軍大将正二位勲一等伯爵に昇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having served as Taiwan Governor, Tokyo Eiju Governor, Konoe (Imperial Guards) Shidan (Corps) and so on, he was raised to Army General Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Kunto (medals for merit) Earl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having held prominent positions such as Taiwan sotoku (governor-general of Taiwan), Tokyo Eiju sotoku (governor-general of Tokyo garrison) and Konoe shidancho (division commander of the Imperial Guards), Samata was raised to Army General, Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Grand Cordon of the Order, and Count.</e>
<cmt>原文の脱字を対応ウェブサイトに準じて修正しました。用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having held prominent positions such as Taiwan sotoku (governor-general of Taiwan), Tokyo Eiju sotoku (governor-general of Tokyo garrison) and Konoe shidancho (division commander of the Imperial Guards), Samata was raised to Army General, Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Grand Cordon of the Order, and Count.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>長州藩士佐久間竹之允を父に持つ左馬太は大村益次郎の元で西洋兵学を学び、慶応2年（1866年）第二次長州征伐の時には長州軍の大隊長として従軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samata, whose father was Takenojo SAKUMA, a feudal retainer of Choshu, learned Western military science under Masujiro OMURA and participated in the First Conquest of Choshu (1866) as a Daitai-cho (head of corps).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samata, whose father was Takenojo SAKUMA, a feudal retainer of Choshu Domain, learned Western military science under Masujiro OMURA and participated in the Second Conquest of Choshu in 1866, as a daitaicho (Chief) of the Choshu army.</e>
<cmt>原文の誤字を修正しました。なお、竹之允の読みが確定出来ません。一応「たけのすけ」とも読めますが、ここでは「たけのじょう」で訳出してあります。表現・用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samata, whose father was Takenojo SAKUMA, a feudal retainer of Choshu Domain, learned Western military science under Masujiro OMURA and participated in the Second Conquest of Choshu in 1866, as a daitaicho (Chief) of the Choshu army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>戊辰戦争を経て陸軍軍人となり、明治5年（1872年）陸軍大尉・西海鎮台付に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After fighting in the Boshin War, he joined the army and was appointed Army Lieutenant/Saikai Chindai-tsuki in 1872.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After fighting in the Boshin War, Samata joined the army and was appointed Army Captain stationed at Saikai Chindai (garrison) in 1872.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After fighting in the Boshin War, Samata joined the army and was appointed Army Captain stationed at Saikai Chindai (garrison) in 1872.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>明治7年（1874年）2月佐賀の乱平定後、熊本鎮台参謀長に就任し台湾出兵に従軍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 1874 after the subdual of the Saga War, having assumed the position of Kumamoto Chindai Army Sanbocho (Assistant Chief of Staff), he participated in an expeditionary force to Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, 1874, after the subdual of Saga War (Saga Rebellion), Samata assumed the position of Kumamoto Chindai (garrison) Sanbocho (Assistant Chief of Staff) and participated in the Taiwan expedition.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, 1874, after the subdual of Saga War (Saga Rebellion), Samata assumed the position of Kumamoto Chindai (garrison) Sanbocho (Assistant Chief of Staff) and participated in the Taiwan expedition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明治10年（1877年）の西南戦争には歩兵第6連隊長として参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Seinan War in 1877 he acted as the Sixth Hohei (foot soldiers) Regiment Chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Seinan War (Satsuma Rebellion) in 1877, Samata acted as Chief of the Sixth Infantry Regiment.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Seinan War (Satsuma Rebellion) in 1877, Samata acted as Chief of the Sixth Infantry Regiment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明治14年（1881年）2月、陸軍少将・仙台鎮台司令官に進み、明治18年（1885年）5月には歩兵第10旅団長、明治19年（1886年）陸軍中将に進み翌年男爵に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 1881 he was raised to Army Major General/Sendai Chindai Army Brigade Commander, to the Tenth Hohei Brigade Commander in May, 1885, to Army Lieutenant General in 1886 and was bestowed baronage the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, 1881, he was raised to Army Major General and Commander at Sendai Chindai, to the Tenth Infantry Brigade Commander in May 1885, and to Army Lieutenant General in 1886, and was bestowed with the Baronage the next year.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, 1881, he was raised to Army Major General and Commander at Sendai Chindai, to the Tenth Infantry Brigade Commander in May 1885, and to Army Lieutenant General in 1886, and was bestowed with the Baronage the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>明治27年（1894年）の日清戦争では第2師団長として出征し威海衛の攻略に当った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sino-Japanese War in 1894, he participated in the war as the Second Division (Japanese Army) and engaged in capturing Ikai City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in the Sino-Japanese War in 1894, as Division Commander of the Second Infantry Division and was engaged in capturing Weihai Garrison.</e>
<cmt>原文のリンク先表示を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in the Sino-Japanese War in 1894, as Division Commander of the Second Infantry Division and was engaged in capturing Weihai Garrison.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>戦後の明治28年（1895年）5月占領地総督に就任し、同年勲一等旭日大綬章を受章し子爵に陞爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, 1895 after the war, he assumed the position of Governor of the occupied territory, received Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun in the same year and was awarded viscountcy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1895, after the war, he assumed the position of General-governor of the occupied territory, received Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun in the same year and was raised to Viscount.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1895, after the war, he assumed the position of General-governor of the occupied territory, received Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun in the same year and was raised to Viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>近衛師団長・中部都督を経て明治31年（1898年）陸軍大将に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having served as the Imperial Guard Chief/Chubu Commander, he assumed the position of Army General in 1898.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having served as Konoe shidancho and Chubu totoku (Governor-general of the Chubu region), he was appointed Army General in 1898.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having served as Konoe shidancho and Chubu totoku (Governor-general of the Chubu region), he was appointed Army General in 1898.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一時休職したものの明治37年（1904年）東京衛戍総督、明治39年（1906年）4月には台湾総督に就任し勲一等旭日桐花大綬章を受章、明治40年（1907年）伯爵に陞爵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he took temporal leave of absence from work, he assumed the position of Taiwan Governor in April, 1906, received Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower and was raised to Earl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite taking a temporary leave of absence from work, he served as the Tokyo Eiju sotoku in 1904, and the Taiwan sotoku and received Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower in April 1906, and was raised to Count in 1907.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ箇所を加筆し、用語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite taking a temporary leave of absence from work, he served as the Tokyo Eiju sotoku in 1904, and the Taiwan sotoku and received Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower in April 1906, and was raised to Count in 1907.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大正4年（1915年）5月に退役、同年8月5日逝去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retired in May, 1915 and passed away on August 5 in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retired in May 1915, and passed away on August 5 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retired in May 1915, and passed away on August 5 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>後を佐久間俊一が継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunichi SAKUMA succeeded him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunichi SAKUMA succeeded him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunichi SAKUMA succeeded him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Horlicks(id:62133), 下総大納言(id:43461), 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Yas(id:739), Clarin(id:60278), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>