<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三浦胤義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyoshi MIURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyoshi MIURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi MIURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三浦　胤義（みうら　たねよし、生年不詳-承久3年（1221年）6月15日）は、鎌倉時代の武士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyoshi MIURA (date of birth unknown - June 15, 1221) was a smurai in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyoshi MIURA (date of birth unknown - June 15, 1221) was a smurai during the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi MIURA (date of birth unknown - July 13, 1221) was a samurai during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>period を小文字にしました。Samurai と修正しました。グレゴリオ暦としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三浦義澄の末子（9男）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Was born the youngest child (the ninth son) of Yoshizumi MIURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Was born the youngest child (the ninth son) of Yoshizumi MIURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the youngest child (the ninth son) of Yoshizumi MIURA.</e>
<cmt>he was としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>生母は伊東祐親の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biological mother was the daughter of Sukechika ITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His biological mother was the daughter of Sukechika ITO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His biological mother was the daughter of Sukechika ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄は三浦友澄・三浦義村ら。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brothers included Tomozumi MIURA and Yoshimura MIURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brothers included Tomozumi MIURA and Yoshimura MIURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brothers included Tomozumi MIURA and Yoshimura MIURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>妻は昌寛の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyoshi&apos;s wife was the daughter of Shokan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyoshi&apos;s wife was the daughter of Shokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi&apos;s wife was the daughter of Shokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>官職は左衛門少尉、右衛門尉、検非違使。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Job grades included Saemon no shoi (a government post), Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and kebiishi (a police and judicial chief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Job grades included Saemon no shoi (a government post), Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and kebiishi (a police and judicial chief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His positions included Saemon no shoi (a government post), Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and kebiishi (a police and judicial chief).</e>
<cmt>his positionsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>九郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had another name, Kuro.</e>
<cmt>追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>平判官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiwa Hangan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiwa Hangan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also known as Taira hangan.</e>
<cmt>追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>子は三浦胤連、三浦兼義ら多数。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyoshi had many children including Tanetsura MIURA and Kaneyoshi MIURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyoshi had many children including Tanetsura MIURA and Kaneyoshi MIURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi had many children including Tanetsura MIURA and Kaneyoshi MIURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>有力御家人の三浦氏一族で、元久2年（1205年）の畠山重忠の乱、牧氏事件に兄の義村とともに出陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyoshi&apos;s family was the Miura Clan, the powerful gokenin and, he departed for the front with his older brother Yoshimura during the Shigetada HATAKEYAMA Rebellion and the Makishi Incident in 1205.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyoshi&apos;s family was the Miura Clan, the powerful gokenin and, he departed for the front with his older brother Yoshimura during the Shigetada HATAKEYAMA Rebellion and the Makishi Incident in 1205.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi&apos;s family was the Miura clan, the powerful gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods), and he departed for the front with his older brother Yoshimura during the Shigetada HATAKEYAMA Rebellion and the Makishi Incident in 1205.</e>
<cmt>御家人の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>建暦3年（1213年）の和田合戦で功を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Distinguished himself in military service during the Battle of Wada in 1213.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Distinguished himself in military service during the Battle of Wada in 1213.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He distinguished himself in military service during the Battle of Wada in 1213.</e>
<cmt>he を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>建保6年（1218年）6月の源実朝の左大将拝賀には参列しており、その後に京に上って検非違使判官に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Attended the ceremony in which MINAMOTO no Sanetomo made greetings in return for the conferment of Sadaisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and subsequently went to Kyoto, receiving an appointment as kebiishi no jo (a police and judicial chief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attended the ceremony in which MINAMOTO no Sanetomo made greetings in return for the conferment of Sadaisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and subsequently went to Kyoto, receiving an appointment as kebiishi no jo (a police and judicial chief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attended the ceremony in which MINAMOTO no Sanetomo made greetings in return for the conferment of Sadaisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) in July, 1218, and subsequently went to Kyoto, receiving an appointment as kebiishi no jo (a police and judicial chief).</e>
<cmt>he を追加しました。グレゴリオ暦　1218年7月　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>在京していたところ後鳥羽上皇の近臣の藤原秀康に説得されて倒幕計画に参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While in Kyoto, participated in the anti-shogunate scheme, persuaded by FUJIWARA no Hideyasu, the trusted vassal of the retired Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While in Kyoto, participated in the anti-shogunate scheme, persuaded by FUJIWARA no Hideyasu, the trusted vassal of the retired Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While in Kyoto, he participated in the anti-shogunate scheme, persuaded by FUJIWARA no Hideyasu, the trusted vassal of the Retired Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>兄の義村は日本国総追捕使に任じられるなら必ず味方すると確約した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His older brother Yoshimura gave his word to be on the side of the retired emperor if he would be appointed to Nihon koku (Japan) So-tsuibushi (job title which has rights of government military affairs and police authority).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His older brother Yoshimura gave his word to be on the side of the retired emperor if he would be appointed to Nihon koku (Japan) So-tsuibushi (job title which has rights of government military affairs and police authority).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His older brother Yoshimura gave his word to be on the side of the retired emperor if he would be appointed to Nihon koku (Japan) So-tsuibushi (job title which has rights of government military affairs and police authority).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>胤義の妻は二代征夷大将軍源頼家の愛妾で男子を生んだ女性であり、頼家の死後に胤義の妻となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The woman, once a favorite concubine of the second shogun MINAMOTO no Yoriie bearing his son, became Taneyoshi&apos;s wife after the death of Yoriie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The woman, once a favorite concubine of the second shogun MINAMOTO no Yoriie bearing his son, became Taneyoshi&apos;s wife after the death of Yoriie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The woman, once a favorite concubine of the second shogun MINAMOTO no Yoriie bearing his son, became Taneyoshi&apos;s wife after the death of Yoriie.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>実朝の横死後に仏門に入っていた妻と頼家の子の禅暁の将軍擁立を望んだが、執権北条氏の画策で将軍後継者には摂関家から三寅が迎えられ、その上に禅暁も殺されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyoshi wanted to install Zengyo, the biological child between his wife, who had become a priestess following the violent death of Sanetomo, and Yoriie, as Shogun but Mitora from Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisors) was brought in to succeed the post of Shogun by the scheming Regent Hojo family and Zengyo was murdered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyoshi wanted to install Zengyo, the biological child between his wife, who had become a priestess following the violent death of Sanetomo, and Yoriie, as Shogun but Mitora from Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisors) was brought in to succeed the post of Shogun by the scheming Regent Hojo family and Zengyo was murdered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi wanted to install Zengyo, the biological child between his wife, who had become a priestess following the violent death of Sanetomo, and Yoriie, as Shogun but Mitora from Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) was brought in to succeed the post of Shogun by the scheming Hojo clan which held the position of Shikken (shogunal regent); furthermore, Zengyo was murdered.</e>
<cmt>摂関家、執権　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>『承久記』によれば、先夫（頼家）と子を北条氏によって殺されて嘆き悲しむ妻を憐れに思い、鎌倉に謀叛を起こそうと京に上ったと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Jokyuki (A Chronicle of the Jokyu War), feeling compassionate for the wife grieving over the murder of her former husband (Yoriie) and child by the Hojo clan, Nariyuki went to Kyoto with a plan to rebel against the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Jokyuki (A Chronicle of the Jokyu War), feeling compassionate for the wife grieving over the murder of her former husband (Yoriie) and child by the Hojo clan, Nariyuki went to Kyoto with a plan to rebel against the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Jokyuki &quot; (A Chronicle of the Jokyu War), feeling compassionate for the wife grieving over the murder of her former husband (Yoriie) and child by the Hojo clan, Taneyoshi went to Kyoto with a plan to rebel against the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Nariyuki→Taneyoshi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>承久3年（1221年）5月に後鳥羽上皇が挙兵すると軍議で「朝敵となった以上、北条義時に味方する者は千人もいまい」と楽観論を述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1221, when the retired Emperor Gotoba raised an army, during the council of war, Taneyoshi optimistically stated, &quot;Now that he has become an enemy of the court, not even thousand people will support Yoshitoki HOJO.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1221, when the retired Emperor Gotoba raised an army, during the council of war, Taneyoshi optimistically stated, &quot;Now that he has become an enemy of the court, not even thousand people will support Yoshitoki HOJO.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1221, when the Retired Emperor Gotoba raised an army, during the council of war, Taneyoshi optimistically stated, &apos;Now that he has become an enemy of the court, not even thousand people will support Yoshitoki HOJO.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>鎌倉の義村に密書を送るが、義村は使者を追い返して密書を幕府に届けてしまい、京方の目算は崩れてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nariyuki sent a secret message to Yoshimura in Kamakura but Yoshimura turned the messenger away but delivered that message to the shogunate whereby expectations of the Kyoto side fell short.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nariyuki sent a secret message to Yoshimura in Kamakura, but Yoshimura turned the messenger away, but delivered that message to the shogunate whereby expectations of the Kyoto side fell short.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi sent a secret message to Yoshimura in Kamakura, but Yoshimura turned the messenger away, but delivered that message to the shogunate whereby expectations of the Kyoto side fell short.</e>
<cmt>Nariyuki→Taneyoshi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>『吾妻鏡』によると、北条政子が御家人を説得する演説をした際に秀康と胤義の名を逆臣として挙げており、鎌倉幕府からは京方の中心人物と見られていたようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Azuma Kagami, during the speech Masako HOJO gave to persuade gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate during the Kamakura, Muromachi and Edo periods), she named Hideyasu and Taneyoshi as gyakushin (rebellious subjects) and it seems that the Kamakura Shogunate viewed them as the central figures in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Azuma Kagami, during the speech Masako HOJO gave to persuade gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate during the Kamakura, Muromachi and Edo periods), she named Hideyasu and Taneyoshi as gyakushin (rebellious subjects) and it seems that the Kamakura Shogunate viewed them as the central figures in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), during the speech Masako HOJO gave to persuade gokenin, she named Hideyasu and Taneyoshi as gyakushin (rebellious subjects) and it seems that the Kamakura Shogunate viewed them as the central figures in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>吾妻鏡　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>6月に京方の大将軍として美濃国と宇治川で幕府軍と戦うが敗北。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, Taneyoshi in the capacity of Daishogun (Commander in Chief) of the Kyoto army fought the Shogunate army in Mino Province and in the Battle of Uji-gawa River but was defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, Taneyoshi in the capacity of Daishogun (Commander in Chief) of the Kyoto army fought the Shogunate army in Mino Province and in the Battle of Uji-gawa River, but was defeated.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, Taneyoshi in the capacity of Daishogun (Commander in Chief) of the Kyoto army fought the Shogunate army in Mino Province and in the Battle of Uji-gawa River, but was defeated.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>院の御所で最後の一戦を図るが、御所の門を閉じられ追い返されてしまい、逆に乱を引き起こした謀臣として逮捕の院宣を出されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyoshi attempted to put up one last fight at the palace of the retired Emperor but was turned away with the palace gate being closed and, instead, an inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) was issued to arrest the tactician Taneyoshi who set off a war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyoshi attempted to put up one last fight at the palace of the retired Emperor, but was turned away with the palace gate being closed and, instead, an inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) was issued to arrest the tactician Taneyoshi who set off a war.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi attempted to put up one last fight at the palace of the Retired Emperor, but was turned away with the palace gate being closed and, instead, an inzen (a decree from the Retired Emperor) was issued to arrest the tactician Taneyoshi who set off a war.</e>
<cmt>Retired としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>残った京方武士と東寺に立て篭もるが、義村の軍勢に攻められ、胤義は子息の胤連、兼義とともに奮戦して西山木嶋（京都市右京区太秦）で自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyoshi and the remaining samurai of the Kyoto side barricaded themselves in To-ji Temple but, being under attack by Yoshimura&apos;s army, after fighting bravely along with his sons Tanetsura and Keneyoshi, Taneyoshi killed himself in Nishiyama Kijima (Uzumasa, Ukyo-ku, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>「西山木嶋」は文脈から判断して地名のようですが、読み方を確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyoshi and the remaining samurai of the Kyoto side barricaded themselves in To-ji Temple, but being under attack by Yoshimura&apos;s army, after fighting bravely along with his sons Tanetsura and Keneyoshi, Taneyoshi killed himself in Nishiyama Kijima (Uzumasa, Ukyo-ku, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi and the remaining samurai of the Kyoto side barricaded themselves in To-ji Temple, but being under attack by Yoshimura&apos;s army, after fighting bravely along with his sons Tanetsura and Keneyoshi, Taneyoshi killed himself in Nishiyama Kijima (Uzumasa, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>Ukyo Wardとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>東国に残していた幼い子たちも処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taneyoshi&apos;s young children who remained in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region) were executed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taneyoshi&apos;s young children who remained in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region) were executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taneyoshi&apos;s young children who remained in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region) were also executed.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Boca samba(id:137526), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>