<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平田職忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada HIRATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada HIRATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototada HIRATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平田 職忠（ひらた もとただ、天正8年（1580年）－万治3年6月16日 (旧暦)（1660年7月23日））は、安土桃山時代・江戸時代初期の地下家官人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada HIRATA (1580-July 23, 1660) was a Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace) government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) from the Azuchi-Momoyama Period through until the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada HIRATA (1580-July 23, 1660) was a government official from a Jige-ke (courtiers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters) family from the Azuchi-Momoyama Period through the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototada HIRATA (1580-July 23, 1660) was a government official from a Jige-ke (courtiers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters) family from the Azuchi-Momoyama period through the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Azuchi-Momoyama Period をAzuchi-Momoyama period に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>蔵人所出納。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was kurodo dokoro (Board of Archivists) suito (local shoen official below the gesu and kumon in rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked in the Kurodo-dokoro (Board of Archivists) as a shutsuno (a low-ranking official in responsible for receiving and sending goods).</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - not sure of the pronunciation of &quot;出納&quot;. Though usually すいとう, for this meaning Wikipedia has &quot;すいのう&quot; and my 旺文社古語辞典 has &quot;しゅつのう&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked in the Kurodo-dokoro (Board of Archivists) as a shutsuno (a low-ranking official in responsible for receiving and sending goods).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>深尾職久の子、母は多忠宗の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a child of Motohisa HIRATA, and his mother was a daughter of OTA no Tadamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Motohisa HIRATA, and his mother was a daughter of OTA no Tadamune.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Motohisa HIRATA, and his mother was a daughter of OTA no Tadamune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>平田職清の養嗣子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the adopted child of Motokiyo HIRATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by Motokiyo HIRATA.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by Motokiyo HIRATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正室は河越宗也の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of 河越宗也.</e>
<cmt>河越宗也→読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was a daughter of Munenari KAWAKOSHI.</e>
<cmt>*Changed kanji to romaji but no idea if it&apos;s right</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Munenari KAWAKOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>号は萃庵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His penname was 萃庵.</e>
<cmt>萃庵→読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His penname was Suian.</e>
<cmt>*Changed kanji to romaji but no idea if it&apos;s right</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pen name was Suian.</e>
<cmt>penname をpen name に修正しました。出典：http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/penname?view=uk</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>Background をCareer に修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>平田家庶流の出身で宗家の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the branch family of the Hirata family, and was adopted by Soke (the head family or house).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally from an illegitimate branch of the Hirata family, he was adopted into the head family.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally from an illegitimate branch of the Hirata family, he was adopted into the head family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天正14年9月26日 (旧暦)（1586年11月7日）に従五位下左近衛将監に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 7, 1586, he was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Sakone no shogen (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 7, 1586, he was appointed Sakone no shogen (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) with the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 7, 1586, he was appointed Sakone no shogen (Lieutenant of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) with the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後に豊後国国司に転じて左衛門大尉を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he turned to Bungo no kuni Kokushi (the governor of Bungo Province), and assumed the additional post as Saemon no daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was transferred to the position of Kokushi (Governor) of Bungo Province, and assumed the additional post of Saemon no Daijo (Senior Lieutenant of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was transferred to the position of Kokushi (Governor) of Bungo Province, and assumed the additional post of Saemon no Daijo (Senior Lieutenant of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>舟橋秀賢に有職故実を学び、官職として知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) from Hidekata FUNAHASHI, and was known as `the reviver of government post research.&apos;</e>
<cmt>官職→定訳不明ですが→government post research と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned yusoku kojitsu (ancient court and military ceremony and etiquette) from Hidekata FUNAHASHI, and was known as `the government post&apos;.</e>
<cmt>*Revised to match original - I don&apos;t know if it was mistyped but although the translator has translated the sentence that appears on the Wikipedia page, that&apos;s not the sentence that&apos;s in cell B16</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned yusoku kojitsu (ancient court and military ceremony and etiquette) from Hidekata FUNAHASHI, and was known as the government post.</e>
<cmt>シングルコーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後陽成上皇にも有職故実を伝授して、慶長13年（1608年）には『職源鈔』の校訂・刊行を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He taught the Retired Emperor Goyozei Yusoku kojitsu, and revised and published &quot;Shokugensho&quot; (history of government services) in 1608.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He taught yusoku kojitsu to Retired Emperor Goyozei, and revised and, in 1608, published &quot;Shokugensho&quot; (History of Government Services).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He taught yusoku kojitsu to Retired Emperor Goyozei, and revised and, in 1608, published &quot;Shokugensho&quot; (History of Government Services).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>慶長20年（元和 (日本)元年）4月7日 (旧暦)（1615年5月4日）には、北面武士の資格で院昇殿が許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 4, 1615, he was admitted Inshoden (be admitted to the retired emperor&apos;s palace) as Hokumen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the north side).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 4, 1615, as a member of the Hokumen no Bushi (the retired emperor&apos;s houshold guards), he was given clearance to be admitted to the retired emperor&apos;s palace.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 4, 1615, as a member of the Hokumen no Bushi (the retired emperor&apos;s household guards), he was given clearance to be admitted to the retired emperor&apos;s palace.</e>
<cmt>houshold をhousehold に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、息子晃海が師の天海とともに徳川家康に仕えたことから江戸幕府の評価も高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his son, Kokai served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA with Kokai&apos;s teacher, Tenkai, his assessment by Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was good.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Mototada&apos;s son, Kokai, together with his teacher, Tenkai, served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Mototada was held in high esteem by the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Mototada&apos;s son, Kokai, together with his teacher, Tenkai, served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Mototada was held in high esteem by the.</e>
<cmt>Edo shogunate をEdo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>慶長年間以後蔵人方地下官人を統率する催官人の地位に挙げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Keicho era (during 1596-1615), he was installed in the position as an official organizing Kurodogata Jigekanjin (officials who served as Kyokumu and Kanmu that were central bodies of low-class officials in the medieval Imperial Palace, and their subordinate Rokuinogekishi).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, after the Keicho era (1596-1615), he was given responsibility for organizing the Kurodogata Jigekanjin (low-ranking government officials).</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - as the translator split the sentence, I presume the two sentences must be connected and so added &quot;As a result&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, after the Keicho era (1596-1615), he was given responsibility for organizing the Kurodogata Jigekanjin (low-ranking government officials).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>更に元和6年12月9日 (旧暦)（1621年1月31日）には大蔵大輔に任ぜられ、翌年正月には従四位上に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 31, 1621, he was appointed to Okura no taifu (a senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury), and was appointed to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) on New year&apos;s days in the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 31, 1621, he was appointed Okura no Taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Treasury) and was promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) the follwing New Year.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 1, 1621, he was appointed Okura no Taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of the Treasury) and was promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) the following New Year.</e>
<cmt>January 31, 1621をJanuary 1, 1621 に修正しました。follwing をfollowing に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>更に寛永元年（1624年）には正四位下、寛永5年2月8日 (旧暦)（1628年3月13日）には正四位上に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1624, she was appointed to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and on March 13, 1628, was appointed to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1624 and to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade) on March 13, 1628.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1624 and to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade) on March 13, 1628.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>寛永11年（1634年）には出納が官務の権限を侵しているとして壬生孝亮から訴えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1634, he was sued by Takasuke MIBU in that suito (local shoen official below the gesu and kumon in rank) impinged the authority of kanmu (official position).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1634, he was sued by Takasuke MIBU, who claimed that the shutsuno was impinging the authority of the higher-ranked kanmu.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - not sure of the pronunciation of &quot;出納&quot;. Though usually すいとう, for this meaning Wikipedia has &quot;すいのう&quot; and my 旺文社古語辞典 has &quot;しゅつのう&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1634, he was sued by Takasuke MIBU, who claimed that the shutsuno was impinging the authority of the higher-ranked kanmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>職忠は江戸幕府の意向を得ていることを理由にこれをかわし、引き続き出納による蔵人方官人支配が認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototada warded it claiming that control by suito was approved by Edo bakufu, and controlling Kurodogata government officials by suito remained to be approved.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototada successfully defended the charge by claiming that control by the shutsuno was approved by the shogunate, and from then on management of Kurodogata government officials was carried out by the shutsuno.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - not sure of the pronunciation of &quot;出納&quot;. Though usually すいとう, for this meaning Wikipedia has &quot;すいのう&quot; and my 旺文社古語辞典 has &quot;しゅつのう&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototada successfully defended the charge by claiming that control by the shutsuno was approved by the Edo bakufu, and from then on management of Kurodogata government officials was carried out by the shutsuno.</e>
<cmt>ｂｙ ｃｌａｉｍｉｎg を半角文字にしました。shogunate を Edo bakufu に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>寛永13年（1636年）に致仕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1636, he retired governmental posts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retired in 1636.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retired in 1636.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>著作は多く、『魚魯愚鈔』（洞院公賢の著作とは別著）・『官職便覧』・『童訓略頌』などがある他、徳川家康以下3代の将軍宣下に関する記録（将軍宣下記）も作成している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His literally works were many, including; &quot;Gyorogusho&quot; (different from the work of Kinkata TOIN), &quot;Kanshikibinran,&quot; 童訓略頌, and created records about the appointment to Shogun in three generations after Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (record of appointment to Shogun).</e>
<cmt>『魚魯愚鈔』 ・『官職便覧』→定訳不明のためスペルアウト、『童訓略頌』→読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His produced many literary works, including &quot;Gyorogusho&quot; (different from Kinkata TOIN&apos;s work of the same name), &quot;Kanshikibinran&quot;, &quot;Dokunryakusho&quot;, and also created records (&quot;Shogunsenge-ki&quot;) about the appointment to Shogun of three of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s successors.</e>
<cmt>*Changed kanji to romaji but no idea if it&apos;s right</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His produced many literary works, including &quot;Gyorogusho&quot; (different from Kinkata TOIN&apos;s work of the same name), &quot;Kanshikibinran&quot;, &quot;Dokunryakusho&quot;, and also created records (&quot;Shogunsenge-ki&quot;) about the appointment to Shogun of three of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s successors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>81歳で死去、墓所は浄福寺 (京都市)にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of eighty one, and his tomb was in Jofuku-ji temple (Kyoto city).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of eighty-one; his tomb is in Jofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 81; his tomb is in Jofuku-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>eighty-one を 81 に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>