<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三条公教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiminori SANJYO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiminori SANJYO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiminori SANJO</e>
<cmt>SANJOスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三条公教（さんじょうきみのり（「きんのり」とも）、康和5年（1103年）-永暦元年7月9日 (旧暦)（1160年8月12日））は、平安時代後期の公卿で藤原北家閑院家流三条家当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiminori SANJYO (Sometimes called &quot;Kinnori&quot;) (1103-Aug. 12, 1160) was a court noble in the late Heian Period and the head of the Fujiwara Hokke Kanin-karyu Sanjyo family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiminori SANJYO (Sometimes called &quot;Kinnori&quot;) (1103-Aug. 12, 1160) was a court noble in the late Heian Period and the head of the Fujiwara Hokke Kanin-karyu Sanjyo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiminori SANJO (Sometimes called &apos;Kinnori&apos;) (1103 - August 19, 1160) was a court noble in the late Heian period and the head of the Sanjo family, Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>SANJOスペル訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて “を&apos;に訂正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。スペース補足しました。period小文字にしました。藤原北家閑院家流三条家→the Sanjo family, Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は太政大臣三条実行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was the Dajyodaijin Saneyuki SANJYO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was the Dajyodaijin Saneyuki SANJYO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was the Daijodaijin (Grand minister of state) Saneyuki SANJYO.</e>
<cmt>太政大臣→Daijodaijin (Grand minister of state)訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>鳥羽天皇・後白河天皇両院政下で活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active under the cloister governments of Emperors Toba and Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active under the cloister governments of Emperors Toba and Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active under the cloister governments of Retired Emperors Toba and Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Retired補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>母方の祖父藤原顕季の引き立てで13歳で鳥羽天皇の侍従となった公教は、天皇が寵愛する従兄弟の美福門院（顕季の孫娘）との関係を利用して31歳の若さで公卿に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His maternal grandfather FUJIWARA no Akisue recommended him to Emperor Gotoba as a chamberlain when he was 13, and used the relationship with his cousin Bihukumon-in (Akisue&apos;s granddaughter), who was the Emperor&apos;s favorite, to become a court noble at the young age of 31.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His maternal grandfather FUJIWARA no Akisue recommended him to Emperor Gotoba as a chamberlain when he was 13, and used the relationship with his cousin Bihukumon-in (Akisue&apos;s granddaughter), who was the Emperor&apos;s favorite, to become a court noble at the young age of 31.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His maternal grandfather FUJIWARA no Akisue recommended him to Emperor Gotoba as a Jiju (chamberlain) when he was 13, and used the relationship with his cousin Bihukumonin (Akisue&apos;s granddaughter), who was the Emperor&apos;s favorite, to become a court noble at the young age of 31.</e>
<cmt>Jiju補足しました。説明を括弧書きにしました。ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>退位して院政を始めた鳥羽法皇も公教の質実で勤勉な態度を高く評価して院庁の執事別当として裁判・行政の中枢を任せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Gotoba abdicated and started his cloister government, Kiminori&apos;s loyal and studious manner was highly evaluated and he was given the central command of the court and government was the shichiji beto of the cloister government office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Gotoba abdicated and started his cloister government, Kiminori&apos;s loyal and studious manner was highly evaluated and he was given the central command of the court and government was the shichiji beto of the cloister government office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Gotoba abdicated and started his cloister government, Kiminori&apos;s loyal and studious manner was highly evaluated and he was given the central command of the court and government was the Shituji betto (chief officer) of the cloister government office.</e>
<cmt>執事別当→Shituji betto （chief officer)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>1155年、美福門院所生の近衛天皇が急死すると、権大納言であった公教は鳥羽法皇・関白藤原忠通らごく数人と秘密裏に会議を開いて後白河天皇の即位を決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1155, when Bifukumon-in&apos;s son, Emperor Kokonoe died suddenly, Kiminori, who was gondainagon at the time, held a small secret meeting with Emperor Toba, Kanpaku FUJIWARA Tadamichi and decided on the ascension of Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1155, when Bifukumon-in&apos;s son, Emperor Kokonoe died suddenly, Kiminori, who was gondainagon at the time, held a small secret meeting with Emperor Toba, Kanpaku FUJIWARA Tadamichi and decided on the ascension of Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1155, when Bifukumon-in&apos;s son, Emperor Konoe died suddenly, Kiminori, who was Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) at the time, held a small secret meeting with the Cloistered Emperor Toba, Kanpaku (chancellor) FUJIWARA no Tadamichi and decided on the ascension of Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>近衛天皇、Emperor Konoeと訂正しました。権大納言、Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor)としました。the Cloistered補足しました。(chancellor)説明補足しました。no 補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>翌年鳥羽法皇の崩御直後に保元の乱が起こると、公教は忠通・藤原信西とともに後白河天皇の傍に近侍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year, when the Hogen Disturbance occurred immediately after the death of Emperor Toba, Kiminori stayed close with Emperor Goshirakawa together with Tadamichi and Shinzei FUJIWARA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, when the Hogen Disturbance occurred immediately after the death of Emperor Toba, Kiminori stayed close with Emperor Goshirakawa together with Tadamichi and Shinzei FUJIWARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, when the Hogen Disturbance occurred immediately after the death of the Cloistered Emperor Toba, Kiminori stayed close with Emperor Goshirakawa together with Tadamichi and FUJIWARA no Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>the Cloistered補足しました。FUJIWARA no Shinzeiに訂正しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>乱で天皇方が勝利すると、延期されていた鳥羽法皇の葬儀を執り行い、また信西の勧める記録所復興に賛同してその長官に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Emperor&apos;s side won, he organized the postponed funeral of Emperor Toba and became the head of the kirokusho(record office) that was resurrected by recommendation of Shinzei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Emperor&apos;s side won, he organized the postponed funeral of Emperor Toba and became the head of the kirokusho(record office) that was resurrected by recommendation of Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Emperor&apos;s side won, he organized the postponed funeral of the Cloistered Emperor Toba and became the head of Kirokujo (Land Record Office) that was resurrected by recommendation of Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>the Cloistered補足しました。記録所→Kirokujo (Land Record Office)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これらの功績が評価されて1157年に内大臣（前年からの左大将を兼務）に就任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This act was avaluated and he was appointed naidaijin (also held sadaisho from the previous year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This act was evaluated and he was appointed naidaijin (also held sadaisho from the previous year).</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This act was evaluated and he was appointed Naidaijin (minister) (also held Sadaisho (Major Captain the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) from the previous year) in 1157.</e>
<cmt>in 1157補足しました。内大臣→Naidaijin (minister)左大将→Sadaisho (Major Captain the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、その3年後に父である実行よりも先に急逝してしまうのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, three years later, he died suddenly before his father Saneyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, three years later, he died suddenly before his father Saneyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, three years later, he died suddenly before his father Saneyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ちなみに娘は忠通の息子松殿基房（後の摂政関白）に嫁ぎ、次男滋野井実国は滋野井家、三男姉小路公宣は姉小路家を起こしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughter married Tadatumichi&apos;&apos;s son, Motofusa MATSUDONO (later regent kanpaku) and his second son Sanekuni SHIGENOI started the Shigenoi family, and his third son, Anekoji Nobu?? started the Anekoji family.</e>
<cmt>姉小路公宣 の読みがわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughter married Tadatumichi&apos;&apos;s son, Motofusa MATSUDONO (later regent kanpaku) and his second son Sanekuni SHIGENOI started the Shigenoi family, and his third son, Anekoji Nobu?? started the Anekoji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughter married Tadatumichi&apos;s son, Motofusa MATSUDONO (later regent kanpaku) and his second son Sanekuni SHIGENOI started the Shigenoi family, and his third son, Kinyoshi ANEGAKOJI started the Anegakoji (Anekoji) family.</e>
<cmt>余分な&apos;を削除しました。姉小路公宣→Kinyoshi ANEGAKOJI [http://www.jlogos.com/webtoktai/index.html?jid=10795205]Anegakoji (Anekoji)複数の読みがあるため、併記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>