<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>水野忠之</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayuki MIZUNO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayuki MIZUNO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayuki MIZUNO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>水野 忠之（みずの ただゆき）は、江戸時代中期の譜代大名で、江戸幕府老中。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayuki MIZUNO was fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) in the mid-Edo period and roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders) of Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayuki MIZUNO was a fudai daimyo (a daimyo as a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) in the mid-Edo period as well as a roju (member of the shogun&apos;s council of elders) of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayuki MIZUNO was a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family in the mid-Edo period as well as a member of the shogun&apos;s council of elders of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>三河国岡崎藩第4代藩主(5万石、後6万石)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the forth lord of Okazaki domain in Mikawa Province (50,000 koku (approximately 9 million liters of crop yield), later 60,000 koku (approximately 10.8 million liters of crop yield)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth lord of the Okazaki domain in Mikawa Province (50,000 koku (approximately 9 million liters of crop yield), later 60,000 koku (approximately 10.8 million liters of crop yield)).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth lord of the Okazaki Domain in Mikawa Province (worth 50,000 koku of rice a year, later 60,000 koku).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Domain大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>忠元系水野家5代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fifth generation of Mizuno family of Tadamoto group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fifth generation of the Mizuno family in the Tadamoto group.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fifth head of the Mizuno family in the Tadamoto line.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>寛文9年（1669年）6月7日午前6時頃に水野家江戸屋敷で誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Edo residence of Mizuno family at about six o&apos;clock in the morning on July 4, 1669.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in the Edo residence of Mizuno family at about six o&apos;clock in the morning on July 4, 1669.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in the Edo residence of Mizuno family about six o&apos;clock in the morning on July 4, 1669.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>三河国岡崎藩主水野忠春（5万石）の四男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the forth son of Tadaharu MIZUNO, the lord of Okazaki domain in Mikawa Province (50,000 koku (approximately 9 million liters of crop yield)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth son of Tadaharu MIZUNO, the lord of the Okazaki domain in Mikawa Province (50,000 koku (approximately 9 million liters of crop yield)).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth son of Tadaharu MIZUNO, who was the lord of the Okazaki Domain in Mikawa Province (50,000 koku).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Domain大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>延宝2年（1674年）7月9日に親族の旗本水野忠近（2300石）の養子となって家督を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by the family member, hatamoto (a direct vassal of the shogun), Tadachika MIZUNO (2,300 koku(approximately 414 thousand liters of crop yield)), on August 10, 1674 and took over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>「忠近」の正しい読み方を確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by a family member, the hatamoto (a direct vassal of the shogun) Tadachika MIZUNO (2,300 koku(approximately 414,000 liters of crop yield)), on August 10, 1674 and took over as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by his relative Tadachika MIZUNO (received a stipend of 2,300 koku), a direct vassal of the shogun, on August 10, 1674, and took over as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。relativeスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元禄10年（1697年）2月には御使番に列し、布衣（六位相当になったことを意味する）の着用を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was raised to Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) in February, 1697 and allowed to wear hoi (clothing for kuge)(it meant that he became equivalent to Rokui (Sixth Rank)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to the status of Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) in February 1697 and was allowed to wear hoi (clothing for kuge) (which meant that he was equivalent to Rokui (Sixth Rank)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to the status of a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield called &apos;Otsukaiban&apos; in February 1697, and allowed to wear the clothing for kuge, which meant that he was equivalent to Sixth Rank.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>元禄11年(1698年)4月19日には日光目付、さらに9月25日には日光普請奉行となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers) in Nikko on May 28, 1698 and Fushin bugyo (shogunate administrator of activities by a community, such as cleaning or fixing stone wall) in Nikko on October 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers) in Nikko on May 28, 1698, and on October 28 he became Fushin bugyo (shogunate administrator of activities by a community, such as cleaning or fixing stone walls) in Nikko.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the inspector of foot soldiers in Nikko on May 28, 1698, and on October 28, he became the shogunate administrator of activities by a community in Nikko.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>元禄12年（1699年）1月11日、実兄である岡崎藩主水野忠盈の養子となって、9月27日に家督相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by his own brother, Tadamitsu MIZUNO, the lord of Okazaki domain on February 10, 1699 and took over as head of the family on October 19.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by his own brother, Tadamitsu MIZUNO, the lord of the Okazaki domain, on February 10, 1699 and on October 19 he took over as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by his elder brother Tadamitsu MIZUNO, the lord of the Okazaki Domain, on February 10, 1699 and on October 19 he took over from Tadamitsu as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Domain大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>10月18日には従五位下・大監物に叙任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Daikenmotsu (duty) on December 8.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Daikenmotsu (duty) on December 8.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Jushiinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), the Daikenmotsu (Senior Inspector) on December 8.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Jugoinoge、括弧、Daikenmotsu補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>元禄14年（1701年）3月14日に赤穂藩主浅野長矩が高家・吉良義央に刃傷沙汰に及んだときには、赤穂藩の鉄砲洲屋敷へ赴いて騒動の取り静めにあたっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Naganori ASANO, the lord of Ako domain had an affair involving bloodshed against Yoshinaka KIRA, koke (privileged family under Tokugawa Shogunate) on April 21, 1701, he went to the residence of Ako domain in Teppozu to settle the commotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Naganori ASANO, the lord of the Ako domain, had an affair involving bloodshed against Yoshinaka KIRA, a koke (privileged family under the Tokugawa shogunate), on April 21, 1701, he went to the residence of the Ako domain in Teppozu to settle the commotion.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Naganori ASANO, the lord of the Ako Domain, had an affair involving bloodshed against Yoshinaka KIRA, a privileged family under the Tokugawa shogunate, on April 21, 1701, he went to the residence of the Ako Domain in Teppozu to settle the commotion.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Domain大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>また翌年12月15日、赤穂義士47士が吉良の首をあげて幕府に出頭した後には、そのうち9名のお預かりを命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in January 31, 1703, after forty seven Ako gishi (loyal retainer) were surrendered to the bakufu with Kira&apos;s head, he was ordered to have nine of them in the custody.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in January 31, 1703, after 47 Ako gishi (loyal retainers) surrendered to the bakufu with Kira as the head, he was ordered to take nine of them into custody.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, on January 31, 1703, after forty-seven Ako loyal retainers surrendered to the bakufu with Kira&apos;s head, he was ordered to take nine of them into custody.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>間十次郎・奥田貞右衛門・矢頭右衛門七・村松三太夫・間瀬孫九郎・茅野和助・横川勘平・三村次郎左衛門・神崎与五郎を三田中屋敷へ預かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had Jujiro HAZAMA, Sadaemon OKUDA, Emoshichi YATO, Sandayu MURAMATSU, Magokuro MASE, Wasuke KAYANO, Kanpei YOKOKAWA, Jirozaemon MINOMURA, and Yogoro KANZAKI in the custody of the second city residence in Sanda.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had Jujiro HAZAMA, Sadaemon OKUDA, Emoshichi YATO, Sandayu MURAMATSU, Magokuro MASE, Wasuke KAYANO, Kanpei YOKOKAWA, Jirozaemon MINOMURA and Yogoro KANZAKI in the custody at the second city residence in Sanda.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had Jujiro HAZAMA, Sadaemon OKUDA, Emoshichi YATO, Sandayu MURAMATSU, Magokuro MASE, Wasuke KAYANO, Kanpei YOKOKAWA, Jirozaemon MINOMURA and Yogoro KANZAKI in custody at the second city residence in Mita.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>大石良雄をあずかった細川綱利（熊本藩主54万石）に倣って水野も義士達をよくもてなした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizuno treated the gishi well in the style of Tsunatoshi HOSOKAWA (the lord of Kumamoto domain, 540,000 koku (approximately 97.2 million liters of crop yield)) who had Yoshio OISHI in the custody,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizuno treated the gishi well in the style of Tsunatoshi HOSOKAWA (the lord of Kumamoto domain, 540,000 koku (approximately 97.2 million liters of crop yield)), who had held Yoshio OISHI in custody.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizuno treated the royal retainers well in the style of Tsunatoshi HOSOKAWA (the lord of Kumamoto Domain, 540,000 koku), who had held Yoshio OISHI in custody.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Domain大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし細川は義士達が細川邸に入った後、すぐさま自ら出てきて大石達と会見したのに対して、水野は幕府をはばかってか、21日になってようやく義士達と会見している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, while Hosokawa met Oishi and other gishi right after they came to Hosokawa residence, Mizuno met the gishi on January 18 at last, perhaps to avoid attention from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, while Hosokawa met Oishi and other gishi right after they came to the Hosokawa residence, Mizuno met the gishi on January 18 at last, perhaps so as not to draw the attention of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, while Hosokawa met Oishi and other royal retainers right after they came to the Hosokawa residence, Mizuno met the royal retainers on February 6 at last, perhaps so as not to draw the attention of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>決して水野家の義士達へのもてなしが細川家に劣ったわけではないが、水野は細川と比べるとやや熱狂ぶりが少なく、比較的冷静な人物だったのかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It did not mean that hospitality to the gishi by Mizuno family was inferior to that of Hosokawa family, but Mizuno&apos;s enthusiasm was little lower than Hosokawa&apos;s, so Mizuno was perhaps relatively calm person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This didn&apos;t mean that hospitality to the gishi by the Mizuno family was inferior to that of the Hosokawa family, but Mizuno was slightly less enthusiastic than Hosokawa, by which one can assume that Mizuno was a relatively calm person.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This didn&apos;t mean that hospitality to the royal retainers by the Mizuno family was inferior to that of the Hosokawa family, but Mizuno was slightly less enthusiastic than Hosokawa, by which one can assume that Mizuno was a relatively calm person.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>もちろん会見では水野も義士達に賞賛の言葉を送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course Mizuno also sent words of the praise to the gishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course, Mizuno also sent words of praise to the gishi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course, Mizuno also sent praise to the royal retainers at the meeting.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また江戸の庶民からも称賛されたようで、「細川の　水の（水野）流れは清けれど　ただ大海（毛利甲斐守）の沖（松平隠岐守）ぞ濁れる」との狂歌が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he was praised by the common people in Edo, and kyoka (comic waka) remained as &apos;In Hosokawa, flow of water (pronounce as mizuno in Japanese) is clear but offing (Matsudaira Oki no kami (Matsudaira, Governor of Oki Province)) of the ocean (Mori Kai no kami (Mori, Governor of Kai Province)) is cloudy.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also praised by the common people in Edo, and kyoka (comic waka) remained as &apos;In Hosokawa, flow of water (pronounced as mizuno in Japanese) is clear but often (Matsudaira Oki no kami (Matsudaira, the governor of Oki Province)) of the ocean (Mori Kai no kami (Mori, the governor of Kai Province)) is cloudy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also praised by the common people in Edo, and comic waka poem remained as &apos;In Hosokawa, the flow of water (pronounced as mizuno in Japanese) is clear but often (Matsudaira Oki no kami (Matsudaira, the governor of Oki Province)) of the ocean (Mori Kai no kami (Mori, the governor of Kai Province)) is cloudy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これは細川家と水野家が浪士たちを厚遇し、毛利家と松平家が冷遇したことを表したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It described Hosokawa and Mizuno families treated the roshi (masterless samurai) very well, but Mori and Matsudaira families did not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It implied that the Hosokawa and Mizuno families treated the roshi (masterless samurai) very well but the Mori and Matsudaira families did not.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It implied that the Hosokawa and Mizuno families treated the masterless samurai very well but the Mori and Matsudaira families did not.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後、2月4日に幕命に従って9士を切腹させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he had those nine gishi Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) in accordance with the bakufu on March 20, 1703.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, on March 20, 1703, he had those nine gishi commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) in accordance with the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, on March 20, 1703, MIZUNO made those nine gishi commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) in accordance with the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>宝永2年（1705年）1月1日に奏者番に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to sojaban (an official in charge of the ceremonies) on January 25, 1705.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Sojaban (an official in charge of ceremonies) on January 25, 1705.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to an official in charge of ceremonies on January 25, 1705.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに正徳 (日本)元年（1711年）12月23日には若年寄に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in Edo bakufu) on January 30, 1712.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in the Edo bakufu) on January 30, 1712.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Junior Councillor on January 30, 1712.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>正徳4年（1714年）9月6日に京都所司代に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Kyoto shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy) on October 14, 1714.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Kyoto shoshidai (Kyoto deputy) on October 14, 1714.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Kyoto deputy on October 14, 1714.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>このときに従四位下侍従和泉守に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade), jiju (a chamberlain) of Izumi no kami (Governor of Izumi Province) on this occasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that occasion he was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), as a jiju (a chamberlain) of Izumi no kami (the governor of Izumi Province).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that occasion, he was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), as a chamberlain, the governor of Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)に訂正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>享保2年（1717年）9月27日に財政をあずかる勝手掛老中となり、将軍徳川吉宗の享保の改革を支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became roju of kattegakari (director of finance) who held finance on October 31, 1717 and supported Kyoho no kaikaku (Kyoho reform) by Shogun Yoshimune TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a roju of kattegakari (director of finance) on October 31, 1717 and supported Kyoho no kaikaku (the Kyoho reform) by Shogun Yoshimune TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a member of shogun&apos;s council of elders of director of finance on October 31, 1717, and supported the Kyoho reform by Shogun Yoshimune TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>享保10年（1725年）には1万石を加増された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10,000 koku (approximately 1.8 million liters of crop yield) were added in 1725.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1725, 10,000 koku (approximately 1.8 million liters of crop yield) were added.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1725, 10,000 koku was added.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>享保15年（1730年）6月12日に老中を辞し、7月6日に隠居した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned from roju on July 26, 1730 and retired on August 19.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned from roju on July 26, 1730 and retired on August 19.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned from the member of shogun&apos;s council of elders on July 26, 1730, and retired on August 19.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="28">
<j>隠居後は落髪して祥岳と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the retirement, he was tonsured and entered the priesthood and called himself Shogaku.</e>
<cmt>「祥岳」の正しい読み方を確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his retirement, he was tonsured and entered the priesthood, whereupon he called himself Shogaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his retirement, he was tonsured and entered the priesthood, and took the Buddhist name Shogaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>享保16年（1731年）3月18日に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on April 24, 1731.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on April 24, 1731.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on April 24, 1731.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>享年63。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of sixty three.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 63.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 63.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>生前の遺命に基づいて、牛込宝泉寺にて荼毘し、24日遺骨は下総国山川万松寺へ送られてここに葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on his will in his lifetime, he was cremated in Ushigome Hosen-ji Temple, and his cremains were sent to Bansho-ji Temple in Yamakawa of Shimosa Province and buried there on April 30, 1731.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the will he had left, he was cremated in Ushigome Hosen-ji Temple; his remains were sent to Bansho-ji Temple in Yamakawa of Shimosa Province and buried there on April 30, 1731.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the will he had left, he was cremated in the Ushigome Hosen-ji Temple; his remains were sent to Bansho-ji Temple in Yamakawa of Shimosa Province and buried there on April 30, 1731.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>法名は、高隆院殿祥嶽元貴居士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Koryu Inden Shogaku Genki Koji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Koryu Inden Shogaku Genki Koji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Koryu Inden Shogaku Genki Koji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), ゐ(id:795), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Point136(id:211299), Seibuabina(id:37532), Auxgllot(id:110551), Tribot(id:186681), ASAMA501(id:91947), シェーラ(id:17988), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>