<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>依田勉三</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Benzo YODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Benzo YODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Benzo YODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>依田 勉三（よだ べんぞう、嘉永6年5月15日 (旧暦)（1853年6月21日） - 大正14年（1925年）12月12日）は日本の北海道開拓者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Benzo YODA (June 21, 1853 - December 12, 1925) was a Japanese settler into Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Benzo YODA (June 21, 1853 - December 12, 1925) was a Japanese Hokkaido pioneer.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Benzo YODA (June 21, 1853 - December 12, 1925) was a Japanese Hokkaido pioneer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北海道開墾を目的として結成された「晩成社」を率い帯広市を開拓した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He reclaimed Obihiro City leading &apos;Banseisya&apos; that was formed for the purpose of cultivation of Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He reclaimed land to build Obihiro City as the leader of a group of pioneers named &apos;Banseisha&apos; that was formed for the purpose of developing Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>用語・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He reclaimed land to build Obihiro City as the leader of a group of pioneers named &apos;Banseisha&apos; that was formed for the purpose of developing Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>開墾に関わる業績から緑綬褒章を受章している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded a Medal with Green Ribbon for his achievements regarding cultivation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded a Medal with a Green Ribbon for his achievements regarding reclamation work.</e>
<cmt>用語・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded a Medal with a Green Ribbon for his achievements regarding reclamation work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生立ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Backgrounds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Backgrounds</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Backgrounds</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>依田家は甲斐国武田氏の流れを汲む伊豆国那賀郡大沢村（現：賀茂郡 (静岡県）松崎町）の豪農で、勉三は善右衛門の三男として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yoda Family, descended from the Takeda clan in Kai Province, was a wealthy farmer in Osawa-onsen Hot Spring (Shizuoka Prefecture) (present Matsuzaki-cho, Kamo-gun County 〔Shizuoka Prefecture〕), Naga-gun County (Shizuoka Prefecture), Izu Province, and Benzo was born as the third-born son of Zenemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yoda Family, descended from the Takeda clan of Kai Province, was a wealthy farmer&apos;s family in Osawa-mura Village, Naka-gun County, Izu Province (present-day Matsuzaki-cho, Kamo-gun County, Shizuoka Prefecture), and Benzo was born as the third-born son of Zenemon.</e>
<cmt>原文のリンク先表示を修正のうえ一部再訳出しました。誤訳・表現・形式を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yoda Family, descended from the Takeda clan of Kai Province, was a wealthy farmer&apos;s family in Osawa-mura Village, Naka-gun County, Izu Province (present-day Matsuzaki-cho, Kamo-gun County, Shizuoka Prefecture), and Benzo was born as the third-born son of Zenemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>尤も次男が夭逝したため戸籍上は次男となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the second son passed away young, he was recorded as the second-born son in family register.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the second son passed away young, he was recorded as the second-born son in the family register.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を補足しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the second son passed away young, he was recorded as the second-born son in the family register.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幼名を久良之助といい、土屋三余・西郷頼母から漢籍を教わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Kuranosuke, and he learned Chinese classic books from Sanyo TSUCHIYA and Tanomo SAIGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Kuranosuke, who learned about Chinese classic books from Sanyo TSUCHIYA and Tanomo SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。なお、西郷頼母は対応wikiサイト上には「保科酔月」とありますが、酔月は号であり正しくは「保科頼母」である事、また、久良之助が教わっていた時期にどちらを名乗っていたか確証がとれませんでしたので、原文通りのまま残しております。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Kuranosuke, who learned about Chinese classic books from Sanyo TSUCHIYA and Tanomo SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>12歳で母が、後を追うように14歳のときに父が逝去し兄の依田佐二平が後を継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At his age of 12, his mother passed away, followed by his father at 14, so his elder brother, Sajibei YODA, succeeded the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lost his mother at the age of 12 and his father at the age of 14, and therefore, his elder brother, Sajibei YODA, succeeded the family head.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lost his mother at the age of 12 and his father at the age of 14, and therefore, his elder brother, Sajibei YODA, succeeded the family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>兄とともに伊豆の松崎町にある土屋三余の私塾「三余塾」に学び、19歳の時に上京しスコットランド出身の宣教師・医師ヒュー・ワデル（1840-1901）の英学塾に学び後に開拓の同志となる鈴木銃太郎・渡辺勝と知り合う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned at a private school called &apos;Sanyo juku&apos; managed by Sanyo TSUCHIYA in Matsuzaki-cho, Izu Province, along with his brother, then went up to Tokyo at 19 to learn at an English school managed by Hugh WADDELL (1840-1901), a mossionary and doctor from Scotland, where he met Jutaro SUZUKI and Masaru WATANABE who became his comrades of reclamation.</e>
<cmt>「WADDELL」については一般的な綴りを使いました。正式なスペルは不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned at a private school &apos;Sanyo juku&apos; managed by Sanyo TSUCHIYA in Matsuzaki-cho, Izu, along with his older brother, then went to Tokyo at the age of 19 to learn at Eigaku juku (a private school of English language and literature) managed by Hugh WADDELL (1840-1901) who was a missionary and doctor from Scotland, at which school he met Jutaro SUZUKI and Masaru WATANABE, who were to become his fellow pioneers.</e>
<cmt>表現・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned at a private school &apos;Sanyo juku&apos; managed by Sanyo TSUCHIYA in Matsuzaki-cho, Izu, along with his older brother, then went to Tokyo at the age of 19 to learn at Eigaku juku (a private school of English language and literature) managed by Hugh WADDELL (1840-1901) who was a missionary and doctor from Scotland, at which school he met Jutaro SUZUKI and Masaru WATANABE, who were to become his fellow pioneers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後慶應義塾に進むが胃病と脚気のため2年在学の後中退し郷里に帰る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he went on to Keio Gijuku, but due to stomach disorder and beriberi, he left the school before graduation and went back to his hometown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he went on to Keio Gijuku, but due to stomach disorder and beriberi, he left school before graduation and went back to his hometown.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he went on to Keio Gijuku, but due to stomach disorder and beriberi, he left school before graduation and went back to his hometown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治12年（1879年）に兄・佐二平が提唱した洋学校に渡辺勝を招き教頭とし1月15日に私立豆陽学校として開校した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1879, he invited Masaru WATANABE to the Yogakko (School of Western Studies) advocated by his brother Sajibei in order to put him as a vice-principal, then opened the school under the name of Shiritsu Toyo Gakko (Toyo Private School) on January 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1879, he invited Masaru WATANABE for the position of vice principal of a Yogakko (School of Western Studies) advocated by his older brother Sajibei, then opened the school under the name of Shiritsu Toyo Gakko (Toyo Private School) on January 15.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1879, he invited Masaru WATANABE for the position of vice principal of a Yogakko (School of Western Studies) advocated by his older brother Sajibei, then opened the school under the name of Shiritsu Toyo Gakko (Toyo Private School) on January 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この学校は後に郡立中学豆陽学校と名称を変更した後昭和24年（1949年）4月に静岡県立下田北高等学校となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This school later changed the name to Gunritsu Chugaku Toyo Gakko (County Secondary School of Toyo), then changed again to Shizuoka Prefectural Shimoda-kita High School in April 1949.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This school later was renamed to Gunritsu Chugaku Toyo Gakko (Toyo Kamo-County Secondary School), and renamed again to Shizuoka Prefectural Shimoda-kita High School in April 1949.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This school later was renamed to Gunritsu Chugaku Toyo Gakko (Toyo Kamo-County Secondary School), and renamed again to Shizuoka Prefectural Shimoda-kita High School in April 1949.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同校の同窓会は豆陽会を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The alumni association of the school was called Toyo-kai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The alumni association of the school has been called Toyo-kai.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The alumni association of the school has been called Toyo-kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>明治12年4月に従妹のリクと結婚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1879, he married his cousin Riku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1879, he married his cousin Riku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1879, he married his cousin Riku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この頃北海道開拓の志を固める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, he made sure of his ambition for reclamation of Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, he made sure of his ambition for developing Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, he made sure of his ambition for developing Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>明治14年（1881年）単身北海道に渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1881, he went to Hokkaido alone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1881, he went to Hokkaido alone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1881, he went to Hokkaido alone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>北海道の調査</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Investigation of Hokkaido</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Investigation of Hokkaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Investigation of Hokkaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>明治14年（1881年）8月17日に北海道に渡った勉三は函館から胆振、函館に戻り根室に向かい釧路国・十勝国・日高国の沿岸部を調査し、苫小牧・札幌市を経て帰途につく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Benzo who had arrived at Hokkaido on August 17, 1881 went on an investigation trip leaving Hakodate for Iburi, and once back to Hakodate, leaving again for the destination of Nemuro to survey the coast of Kushiro-no-kuni, Tokachi-no-kuni and Hidaka-no-kuni, then back to the starting point by way of Tomakomai and Sapporo City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Benzo who had arrived in Hokkaido on August 17, 1881, went on an investigation trip leaving Hakodate for Iburi, and once coming back to Hakodate, he left again for Nemuro to survey the coastal areas of Kushiro-no-kuni Province, Tokachi-no-kuni Province and Hidaka-no-kuni Province, thereafter coming back to the starting point via Tomakomai and Sapporo City.</e>
<cmt>文法・表現上の修正を加えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Benzo who had arrived in Hokkaido on August 17, 1881, went on an investigation trip leaving Hakodate for Iburi, and once coming back to Hakodate, he left again for Nemuro to survey the coastal areas of Kushiro-no-kuni Province, Tokachi-no-kuni Province and Hidaka-no-kuni Province, thereafter coming back to the starting point via Tomakomai and Sapporo City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>明治15年（1882年）には郷里の静岡で依田佐二平・依田園・依田善吾と勉三を発起人に、晩成社を設立し資本金を5万円とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1882, he founded Banseikai in his hometown Shizuoka Prefecture along with Sajibei YODA, Sono YODA and Zengo YODA who all, including Benzo himself, became promoters of the company, with a capital of fifty thousands yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1882, he founded a company named Banseisha in his hometown Shizuoka along with Sajibei YODA, Sono YODA and Zengo YODA, who all, including Benzo himself, became the co-founders of the company, with a capital of fifty thousand yen.</e>
<cmt>誤訳および文法上の修正を加えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1882, he founded a company named Banseisha in his hometown Shizuoka along with Sajibei YODA, Sono YODA and Zengo YODA, who all, including Benzo himself, became the co-founders of the company, with a capital of fifty thousand yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>政府から未開地一万町歩を無償で払い下げを受け開墾しようというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their goal was to cultivate ten thousands hectares of the savage land disposed of by the government that they took over without compensation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their goal was to cultivate approximately ten thousand hectares of uncultivated land obtained as a grant from the government without compensation.</e>
<cmt>文法・表現上の修正を加えました。なお、一町歩は約１ヘクタール相当（1町歩 = 0.991735537 ヘクタール）です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their goal was to cultivate approximately ten thousand hectares of uncultivated land obtained as a grant from the government without compensation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>学友の鈴木銃太郎と共に横浜港から北海道に向かい札幌県庁にて開墾の許可を願い十勝に向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left for Hokkaido from Yokohama Port along with a school friend Jutaro SUZUKI, then applied for the permission of cultivation at Sapporo Prefectural Government Office in the Times of Sanken Ikkyoku (one of the periods divided from history of Hokkaido) to leave for Tokachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left for Hokkaido from Yokohama Port along with a school friend Jutaro SUZUKI, then applied for permission for cultivation at Sapporo Prefectural Government Office and left for Tokachi.</e>
<cmt>表現・文法上の修正を加えました。なお、原文「三県一局時代」はリンク先表示につき削除の上、対応箇所を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left for Hokkaido from Yokohama Port along with a school friend Jutaro SUZUKI, then applied for permission for cultivation at Sapporo Prefectural Government Office and left for Tokachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>7月16日に十勝国河西郡下帯広村（帯広市）を開墾予定地と定め鈴木は帯広に残り勉三は帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 16, he determined Shimo-Obihiro Village (Obihiro City), Kawanishi County, Tokachi-no-kuni as a candidate site for cultivation, then Benzo went back to hometown leaving Suzuki behind in Obihiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 16, they determined Shimo-Obihiro Village (present-day Obihiro City), Kasai-gun County, Tokachi-no-kuni Province as a candidate site for cultivation, then Benzo went back to his hometown, leaving Suzuki behind in Obihiro.</e>
<cmt>誤訳および文法・形式上の修正を加えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 16, they determined Shimo-Obihiro Village (present-day Obihiro City), Kasai-gun County, Tokachi-no-kuni Province as a candidate site for cultivation, then Benzo went back to his hometown, leaving Suzuki behind in Obihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その頃の帯広にはアイヌが10戸程と大和民族が1戸あるのみだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Obihiro of the time, there were about only ten residences of Ainu tribu and a residence of Yamato race.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Obihiro at that time, there were only ten households or so of the Ainu and one household of the Yamato race.</e>
<cmt>誤字・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Obihiro at that time, there were only ten households or so of the Ainu and one household of the Yamato race.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>静岡では渡辺勝が移民の募集をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shizuoka Prefecture, Masaru WATANABE recruited emigrants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shizuoka Prefecture, Masaru WATANABE recruited emigrants for Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>曖昧さ回避の為補足しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shizuoka Prefecture, Masaru WATANABE recruited emigrants for Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>明治16年4月に13戸27人が集まり横浜を出港した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1883, twenty-seven people in thirteen families got together to sail out from Yokohama Port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1883, a party of 27 people of 13 households got together to sail out from Yokohama Port.</e>
<cmt>統一形式に修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1883, a party of 27 people of 13 households got together to sail out from Yokohama Port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>4月14日函館に着いた一行は海陸二手に分かれ帯広に向かい、1ヶ月後の5月14日に帯広に到着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The group which had arrived at Hakodate on April 14 was divided into two groups; one took a sea route, another took a land route, to leave for Obihiro, then arrived at Obihiro in a month on May 14.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The party which had arrived at Hakodate on April 14 was divided into two groups to take a sea route and a land route and left for Obihiro, then arrived at Obihiro just a month later: on May 14.</e>
<cmt>表現・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The party which had arrived at Hakodate on April 14 was divided into two groups to take a sea route and a land route and left for Obihiro, then arrived at Obihiro just a month later: on May 14.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>帯広の開拓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reclamation of Obihiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land Reclamation in Obihiro</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land Reclamation in Obihiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>明治16年帯広に入った一行をまず鹿猟の野火が襲い、次にイナゴの大群が襲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The group that had settled in Obihiro in 1883 was firstly attacked by grass fire of deer hunting, then swarms of locusts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The party that had settled in Obihiro in 1883, was firstly attacked by wildfire caused by deer hunting, then by locust army.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The party that had settled in Obihiro in 1883, was firstly attacked by wildfire caused by deer hunting, then by locust army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>食糧としてアワを蒔き付けするも天候の不順やウサギ・ネズミ・鳥の被害に遭い殆ど収穫できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They planted foxtail millet to make provisions, but prolonged bad weather and damages by rabbits, rats and birds brought them almost nothing in the harvest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They attempted to produce food by planting foxtail millet seeds, but broken weather and pest damage due to rabbits, rats and birds brought them almost nothing in the harvest.</e>
<cmt>原文のリンク先表示を削除しました。表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They attempted to produce food by planting foxtail millet seeds, but broken weather and pest damage due to rabbits, rats and birds brought them almost nothing in the harvest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>明治17年もまた、天候が優れず開墾は遅々として進まず、開拓団の間に絶望が広まっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1884 also, the bad weather still continued that delayed their cultivation, so a despair was spreading in the settlers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Again in 1884, the bad weather continued and delayed their cultivation, and the feeling of despair spread among the pioneers.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Again in 1884, the bad weather continued and delayed their cultivation, and the feeling of despair spread among the pioneers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>勉三は米一年分を大津（現在の豊頃町）に貯蔵したが帯広への輸送が困難な状況であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Benzo stored rice worh of a year in Otsu (present Totokoro-cho), but it was difficult to transport to Obihiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Benzo stored a year&apos;s worth of rice in Otsu (present-day Toyokoro-cho), but it was difficult to transport it to Obihiro.</e>
<cmt>誤字・形式・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Benzo stored a year&apos;s worth of rice in Otsu (present-day Toyokoro-cho), but it was difficult to transport it to Obihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>食糧不足を打開するため、当縁郡当縁村生花苗（おいかまない、現在の広尾郡大樹町）に主畜農業を経営する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To break through the shortage of provisions, he launched agriculture mainly handling stockbreeding in Oikamanai, Tofuchi Village, Tofuchi County (present Taiki-cho, Hiroo County).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To overcome food shortage, he ran a livestock farm in Oikamanai, Tobui-mura Village, Tobui-gun County (present-day Taiki-cho, Hiroo County).</e>
<cmt>「主畜農業」の意味・定訳不明につき、「畜産（農業）農場を経営」と訳出しました。なお、「有畜農業」と同義なのであれば、agriculture with livestock as major sidelineという訳語があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To overcome food shortage, he ran a livestock farm in Oikamanai, Tobui-mura Village, Tobui-gun County (present-day Taiki-cho, Hiroo County).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>明治18年にはウマを導入しヒツジ・ブタを飼育しハム製造を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1885, he took in horses, then raised sheeps and pigs to produce hams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1885, he introduced horses to his farm, then raised sheep and pigs to produce hams.</e>
<cmt>文法・表現上の修正を加えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1885, he introduced horses to his farm, then raised sheep and pigs to produce hams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>ジャガイモデンプンを研究し、農耕の機械化を試みるが何れも上手く行かず、当初の移民は3戸にまで減少した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also studied potato starch and tried mechanization of farming, but nothing made a success, and the number of immigrants decreased to only three families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also studied potato starch and attempted mechanization of farming, but nothing succeeded, and the number of immigrants decreased to only three households.</e>
<cmt>文法・表現上の修正を加えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also studied potato starch and attempted mechanization of farming, but nothing succeeded, and the number of immigrants decreased to only three households.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>明治25年頃には状況が漸く好転し食糧は足り、アズキ・ダイズの収穫も目処がつくようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around 1892, the situation finally turned good that brought enough foods, and prospect for harvest of azuki beans and soybeans came to be a conviction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In around 1892, the situation finally turned good that brought enough foods, and prospect for harvest of adzuki beans and soybeans came to be a conviction.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In around 1892, the situation finally turned good that brought enough foods, and prospect for harvest of adzuki beans and soybeans came to be a conviction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>当初晩成社の設立に当たっては15年で1万町歩の土地を開墾しようとの目標を掲げていたが、目標には遠く及ばず30町歩を開墾するのに10年を要す有様であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The initial goal at the time of foundation of Banseisya was ten thousands hectares of land to be cultivated in fifteen years, but in fact, it was only thirty hectares having been cultivated in ten years, much far from the goal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The initial goal at the time of foundation of the Banseisha was to cultivate ten thousand hectares of land in fifteen years, but in fact, it was only thirty hectares having been cultivated in ten years, far from the goal.</e>
<cmt>誤字・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The initial goal at the time of foundation of the Banseisha was to cultivate ten thousand hectares of land in fifteen years, but in fact, it was only thirty hectares having been cultivated in ten years, far from the goal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>明治25年11月の佐二平・勉三兄弟の叙勲から奮起し晩成社の事業を拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1892, encouraged by the medal Sajibei and Benzo brothers were conferred, he extended the business of Banseisya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1892, encouraged by a medal Sajibei and Benzo brothers were conferred, Benzo extended the business of the Banseisha.</e>
<cmt>誤字・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1892, encouraged by a medal Sajibei and Benzo brothers were conferred, Benzo extended the business of the Banseisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>会社組織を合資会社とし社名を晩成合資会社と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He altered the company organization to partnership corporation, and the company name changed to Bansei Partnership Corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He altered the company organization to a partnership corporation, and the company name to Bansei Limited Partnership.</e>
<cmt>用語・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He altered the company organization to a partnership corporation, and the company name to Bansei Limited Partnership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>函館に牛肉店を開業し当別町に畜産会社を作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He opened a meat shop specializing beef in Hakodate, and founded a stockbreeding company in Tobetsu-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He opened a meat shop specializing in beef in Hakodate, and founded a stockbreeding company in Tobetsu-cho.</e>
<cmt>文法上の修正を加えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He opened a meat shop specializing in beef in Hakodate, and founded a stockbreeding company in Tobetsu-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>帯広には木工場を作り然別村（現在の音更町）に牧場を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He set up a woodwork factory in Obihiro, and a ranch in Shikaribetsu Village (present Otofuke-cho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He set up a woodwork factory in Obihiro, and opened a ranch in Shikaribetsu-mura Village (present-day Otofuke-cho).</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He set up a woodwork factory in Obihiro, and opened a ranch in Shikaribetsu-mura Village (present-day Otofuke-cho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>明治30年に社有地の一部を宅地として開放すると多くの移民が殺到した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1897, as soon as he opened to public a part of corporate land as residential land, a lot of people rushed to settle down as emmigrants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1897, as soon as he opened to public a part of company-owned land as residential land, many immigrants rushed to it.</e>
<cmt>用語・文法上の修正を加えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1897, as soon as he opened to public a part of company-owned land as residential land, many immigrants rushed to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>明治35年にはバター工場を創業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1902, he established a butter factory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1902, he established a butter factory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1902, he established a butter factory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>他にも缶詰工場・練乳工場等もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than it, there were also a canning factory, a condensed milk factory and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he also opened a cannery, a condensery, and so on.</e>
<cmt>用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he also opened a cannery, a condensery, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>勉三と晩成社が手掛けた事業は何れも現在の十勝・帯広に根付く産業となったが当時晩成社の経営は上手く行かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The businesses Benzo handled with Banseisya grew up to the industries that has settled in present Tokachi and Obihiro, but at the time, the management of Banseisya wasn&apos;t going well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although every business enterprise that Benzo handled with Banseisha LP grew up to be a local industry of present-day Tokachi and Obihiro, yet in those days the management of Banseisha LP did not go well.</e>
<cmt>用語・表記・文法上の修正を加えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although every business enterprise that Benzo handled with Banseisha LP grew up to be a local industry of present-day Tokachi and Obihiro, yet in those days the management of Banseisha LP did not go well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="42">
<j>大正5年に売買（うりかり、今の帯広市南東部）等の農場を売却する事によって晩成社の活動は事実上休止する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After selling out the ranch of Urikari (present south-eastern part of Obihiro City) in 1916, the activities of Banseisya virtually suspended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After selling out a ranch in Urikari (present-day south-eastern part of Obihiro City) in 1916, the activities of Banseisha LP virtually suspended.</e>
<cmt>表現・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After selling out a ranch in Urikari (present-day south-eastern part of Obihiro City) in 1916, the activities of Banseisha LP virtually suspended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="43">
<j>大正14年には勉三が中風症に倒れ、9月には勉三の看病をしていた妻が亡くなり、12月12日勉三は帯広町西2条9丁目の自宅で息を引き取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1925, Benzo succumbed to cerebral vascular disturbance, and in September, his wife having been looking after Benzo passed away, and on December 12, he died at home located at 9 chome 2 jo, Obihiro-machi-nishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1925, Benzo succumbed to palsy, and in September his wife who had been sitting by Benzo&apos;s bed passed away, and on December 12 he died at home located at 9-chome, Nishi 2-jo (West 2), Obihiro-cho.</e>
<cmt>表現・用語を修正しました。なお、原文のリンク先表示を対応wikiサイトに準じて修正し、再訳出しました。帯広市住所表記参考：http://www.city.obihiro.hokkaido.jp/shiminkatsudoubu/shinzenkouryuuka/e010108_2.jsp</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1925, Benzo succumbed to palsy, and in September his wife who had been sitting by Benzo&apos;s bed passed away, and on December 12 he died at home located at 9-chome, Nishi 2-jo (West 2), Obihiro-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>享年73であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The age at death was 73.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at death was 73.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age at death was 73.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>勉三の死後昭和7年に晩成合資会社は解散し、翌年の昭和8年帯広は北海道で7番目に市制を施行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1932 after Benzo&apos;s death, Bansei Partnership Corporation was dismissed, and in the following 1933, Obihiro became the 7th city of Hokkaido that put in force the municipal organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1932, after Benzo&apos;s death, Bansei LP was dismissed, and in the following year, 1933, Obihiro became the seventh city of Hokkaido that inaugurated municipal government.</e>
<cmt>表現・用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1932, after Benzo&apos;s death, Bansei LP was dismissed, and in the following year, 1933, Obihiro became the seventh city of Hokkaido that inaugurated municipal government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>勉三は、その死の間際「晩成社には何も残らん。しかし、十勝野には...」と述懐したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have reminisced before death saying, &quot;Nothing would be left in Banseisya. But in Tokachino……&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have reminisced before death, saying, &quot;Nothing will be left for Banseisha, but in Tokachino...&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to have reminisced before death, saying, &quot;Nothing will be left for Banseisha, but in Tokachino...&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>死後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>昭和16年（1941年）6月、中島武市によって帯広神社前に銅像が建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1941, a bronze statue was set up in front of Obihiro Shrine by Buichi NAKAJIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1941, a bronze statue was set up in front of Obihiro-jinja Shrine by Buichi NAKAJIMA.</e>
<cmt>統一表記に修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1941, a bronze statue was set up in front of Obihiro-jinja Shrine by Buichi NAKAJIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この銅像は戦時中に金属応召によって供された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This bronze statue was sacrificed for a decree of Kinzoku Osho (offering of metal for production of arms in war time) in war time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This bronze statue was sacrificed for a decree of Kinzoku Osho (offering of metal for production of arms in war time) during the war.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This bronze statue was sacrificed for a decree of Kinzoku Osho (offering of metal for production of arms in war time) during the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>昭和26年（1951年）7月に銅像が再建された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1951, another bronze statute was set up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1951, a new bronze statue was built.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1951, a new bronze statue was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>昭和29年（1954年）9月には北海道開拓神社に勉三が合祀される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1954, Benzo was enshrined together in Hokkaido Kaitaku Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1954, Benzo was enshrined together in Hokkaido Kaitaku-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>統一表記に修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1954, Benzo was enshrined together in Hokkaido Kaitaku-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>帯広市の菓子メーカー六花亭が作る｢マルセイバターサンド｣は勉三等の晩成社を記念したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Marusei Butter Sand&apos; produced by Rokkatei, a confectionery company of Obihiro City, is for celebrating Banseisya with Benzo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marusei bata sando&apos; (literally, Marusei&apos;s butter sandwiches) produced by Rokkatei Confectionery Co., Ltd of Obihiro City is designed to commemorate Benzo and his partners&apos; Banseisha.</e>
<cmt>用語・表記・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marusei bata sando&apos; (literally, Marusei&apos;s butter sandwiches) produced by Rokkatei Confectionery Co., Ltd of Obihiro City is designed to commemorate Benzo and his partners&apos; Banseisha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>平成元年（1989年）に、明治26年から大正4年頃まで勉三が当縁村生花苗で住んだ住居が復元され「依田勉三翁住居」として大樹町の史跡の一つになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1989, the residence located at Oikamanai, Tofuchi Village where Benzo had been living from 1893 to 1915 was reconstructed to be a historic site of Taiki-cho called &apos;YODA Benzo Oh Jyukyo (Resident of Benzo YODA)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1989, Benzo&apos;s ex-residence located at Oikamanai, Tobui-mura Village, where Benzo had lived from 1893 to 1915, was reconstructed to be a historic site of Taiki-cho and is called &apos;YODA Benzo O Jukyo&apos; (literally, a residence of the revered old Mr. Benzo YODA)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>用語・表記・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1989, Benzo&apos;s ex-residence located at Oikamanai, Tobui-mura Village, where Benzo had lived from 1893 to 1915, was reconstructed to be a historic site of Taiki-cho and is called &apos;YODA Benzo O Jukyo&apos; (literally, a residence of the revered old Mr. Benzo YODA)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>平成14年の開基120年を記念して勉三の生涯を綴る映画「新しい風 - 若き日の依田勉三 -」が製作され（勉三役は北村一輝）、第38回ヒューストン国際映画祭でグランプリに輝いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2002, a film portraying Benzo&apos;s life which title was &apos;Atarashii Kaze - Wakakihino YODA Benzo - (A New Wave - Benzo YODA in his youth -)&apos; was produced as a memorial for the 120th anniversary of foundation (Benzo acted by Kazuki KITAMURA), and it won a Grand-prix award at the 38th Houston International Film Festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2002, a film portraying Benzo&apos;s life, &quot;Atarashii kaze - Wakaki hi no Yoda Benzo&quot; (official English title: &quot;Frontier Dream&quot;), was produced as a memorial for the 120th anniversary of immigration of the Benzo&apos;s party in Hokkaido (Benzo acted by Kazuki KITAMURA), and it won a Grand Remi Award at the 38th Houston International Film Festival.</e>
<cmt>表現・表記・映画タイトル・賞名称を修正しました。「開基」は曖昧さ回避の為、「勉三一行の北海道移民」と言い換えました。映画名表記参考：[1] http://www.zahon.jp/modules/aboutzahon/content/jimoto/kaze.html [2] (2005年度) http://www.worldfest.org/PAGES/winners.htm [3] http://www.root-pictures.com/kaze/</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2002, a film portraying Benzo&apos;s life, &quot;Atarashii kaze - Wakaki hi no Yoda Benzo&quot; (official English title: &quot;Frontier Dream&quot;), was produced as a memorial for the 120th anniversary of immigration of the Benzo&apos;s party in Hokkaido (Benzo acted by Kazuki KITAMURA), and it won a Grand Remi Award at the 38th Houston International Film Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Lemon pie(id:66842), Mogumin(id:28886), Si-take.(id:91094), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), HOSOI Toshikatsu(id:74384), ZassouTori(id:136771), 松浸史(id:78240), Cprobot(id:97843), Kalz(id:92749), BAKU(id:55205), Akaloli(id:141644), 樒(id:35770), パの字(id:34188), 海亀(id:48936), Kouchiumi(id:19253), Azzurro t(id:110960), Tan90deg(id:40673), 代言人(id:33675), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>