<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>新島襄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joseph Hardy Neesima (Joe NIIJIMA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joseph Hardy Neesima (Joe NIIJIMA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joseph Hardy Neesima (Joe NIIJIMA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>新島 襄（にいじま じょう、英字表記：Joseph Hardy Neesima、天保14年1月14日 (旧暦)（1843年2月12日） - 明治23年（1890年）1月23日）はキリスト教の布教家で、同志社大学の前身となる同志社英学校の創立者である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joseph Hardy Neesima (who referred to Joe NIIJIMA in Japan) (February 12, 1843 - January 23, 1890) taught Christianity, and founded Doshisha Eigakko (Academy) which was the former of Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joseph Hardy Neesima (referred to as Joe NIIJIMA in Japan) (February 12, 1843 - January 23, 1890) taught Christianity, and founded Doshisha Eigakko (Academy) which was the former of Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joseph Hardy Neeshima (born February 12, 1843, died January 23, 1890, and known as Joe NIIJIMA in Japan) was a Christian proselytizer and founder of the Doshisha Eigakko (Academy), formerly known as Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>福澤諭吉らとならび、明治六大教育家の1人に数えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is one of the six major educators in the Meiji period, as was Yukichi FUKUZAWA, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is one of the six major educators in the Meiji period, as was Yukichi FUKUZAWA, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He ranks with Yukichi FUKUZAWA as one of the Meiji period&apos;s six greatest educators.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>密航者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Blockade Runner</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Blockade Runner</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Blockade Runner</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>天保14年（1843年）、江戸の神田 (千代田区)にあった上州安中藩板倉家江戸屋敷で、藩士の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1843, he was born as a son of a feudal retainer of domain at the Edo residence of the Itakura family of the Annnaka Domain in Joshu Province, which was located in Kanda (Chiyoda Ward) in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1843, he was born at the Edo residence of the Itakura family of the Annnaka Domain in Joshu Province, located in Kanda (Chiyoda Ward) in Edo, as the son of a feudal retainer of a domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The son of a domainal retainer, he was born in 1843 at the Edo residence (located in Kanda, Chiyoda Ward, in Edo) of the Itakura family, who were from the Annaka Domain in Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本名を七五三太（しめた）と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Shimeta.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Shimeta.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Shimeta.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この名前は、祖父弁治が女子が4人続いた後の初の男子誕生に喜び「しめた」と言った事から命名されたという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say that this name was after an episode that his grandfather, Benji, was glad at the birth of first son after births of four girls, and said &quot;Shimeta&quot; (great).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say he was nameed after an incident when his grandfather, Benji, was so happy at the birth of a first son after births of four girls, that he said &quot;Shimeta&quot; (great).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some claim his name originated with his grandfather Benji&apos;s exclamation of pleasure, &quot;Shimeta&quot; (&quot;wonderful&quot;), at the birth of a grandson after four granddaughters in a row</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>元服後、安中藩士となるが元治元年（1864年）、国禁を犯してのアメリカ合衆国への渡航を画策する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After attaining manhood, he became a clansman of the Annaka Domain, but, he laid a plan to travel to the United States in violation of the government ban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After attaining manhood, he became a clansman of the Annaka Domain, but, he planned to travel to the United States in violation of the government ban.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After reaching adulthood, he became a clansman of Annaka Domain, but in 1864 he plotted to travel to the United States in violation of the government ban on overseas travel.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>渡航に向け函館に潜伏中、当時ロシア領事館付の司祭だったニコライ・カサートキンと会う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While hiding in Hakodate for the purpose of traveling abroad, he met Nikolai Kasatokin who was a priest to the Russian Consulate at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While hiding in Hakodate for the purpose of traveling abroad, he met Nikolai Kasatokin who was a priest to the Russian Consulate at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was hiding in Hakodate trying to find a way of traveling abroad, he met Nikolai Kasatkin, who was a priest to the Russian Consulate at the time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>カサートキンは七五三太から日本語と日本の書物などの手ほどきを受け、また聖書に興味を持つ七五三太に自分の弟子になるよう勧めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasatokin who learned Japanese and Japanese literatures from Shimeta recommended him to take up Kasatokin&apos;s mantle because Shimeta had an interest in the Bible.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasatokin who learned Japanese and Japanese literatures from Shimeta recommended that he take up Kasatokin&apos;s mantle because Shimeta had an interest in the Bible.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasatkin, who with Shimeta&apos;s help was able to learn Japanese and study Japanese written works, recommended that Shimeta, who had expressed interest in the Bible, become his disciple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、七五三太のアメリカ行きの意思は変わらずカサートキンはそれに折れ七五三太の密航に協力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Shimeta did not change his mind of traveling to the United States, Kasatokin finally gave up and cooperated in Shimeta&apos;s illegal exit.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Shimeta was bent on traveling to the United States, Kasatokin finally gave up and cooperated with Shimeta&apos;s illegal exit.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But since Shimeta had his heart set on traveling to the United States, Kasatkin gave up and helped Shimeta make his illegal voyage.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>6月14日 (旧暦)（7月17日）、函館から米船ベルリン号で出国する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 17, Shimeta boarded on an American ship, Berlin, at Hakodate to leave Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 17, Shimeta boarded on an American ship, Berlin, at Hakodate to leave Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 17, at Hakodate, Shimeta boarded the Berlin, an American ship, and left Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>上海市でワイルド・ローヴァー号に乗り換え、船中で船長ホレイス・S・テイラーに「Joe（ジョー）」と呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He changed to another ship, Wild Rover, in Shanghai City, and was called &quot;Joe&quot; by the captain, Horace S. Taylor, while boarding it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed to another ship, Wild Rover, in Shanghai City, and was called &quot;Joe&quot; by the captain, Horace S. Taylor, while boarding it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shanghai, he transferred to another ship, the Wild Rover; while aboard Horace S. Taylor, the ship&apos;s captain, began calling him &quot;Joe.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>このことから以後その名を使い始め、後年の帰国後は「譲」「襄」と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why he started using such name thereafter, and he referred to himself as Joe (譲 or 襄 in kanji) after coming back to Japan in his later years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went by this name after that, and he referred to himself as Joe (譲 or 襄 in kanji) after returning to Japan in his later years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this point onwards he went by the name Joe, and even after he returned to Japan years later, he wrote his name with either the characters &quot;譲&quot; or &quot;襄,&quot; both of which can be pronounced &quot;Joe.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1865年（慶応元年）7月、ボストン着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1865, He arrived in Boston.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1865, He arrived in Boston.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July of 1865, he arrived in Boston.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ワイルド・ローヴァー号の船主・A.ハーディー夫妻の援助をうけ、フィリップス・アカデミーに入学することができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He could enter Phillips Academy with the help of Mr. and Mrs. A. Hardy, the owner of Wild Rover.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was able to enter Phillips Academy with the help of Mr. and Mrs. A. Hardy, the owner of Wild Rover.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the help of Mr. and Mrs. A. Hardy, the owners of the Wild Rover, he was able to enroll in Phillips Academy.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>岩倉使節団</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwakura Mission</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakura Mission</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakura Mission</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>1866年（慶応2年）12月、アンドーヴァー神学校付属教会で洗礼を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1866, Joe was baptized at a church attached to Andover Seminary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1866, Joe was baptized at a church attached to Andover Seminary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December of 1866, Joe was baptized at a church affiliated with Andover Seminary.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1867年（慶応3年）にフィリップス・アカデミーを卒業、1870年（明治3年）にアマースト大学を卒業（理学士）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1867, he graduated from Phillips Academy, and in 1870, he graduated from Amherst College (Bachelor of Science).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1867, he graduated from Phillips Academy, and in 1870, he graduated from Amherst College (Bachelor of Science).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He graduated from Phillips Academy in 1867, and graduated from Amherst College (with a Bachelor of Science degree) in 1870.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは日本人初の学士の学位取得であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first Japanese recipient of bachelor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first Japanese recipient of bachelor&apos;s degree.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first Japanese recipient of bachelor&apos;s degree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>アマースト大学では、後に札幌農学校教頭となるウィリアム・スミス・クラークから化学の授業を受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Amherst College, he learned chemistry from William Smith Clark who was the later assistant principal of Sapporo Agricultural School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Amherst College, he learned chemistry from William Smith Clark who was the later assistant principal of the Sapporo Agricultural School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Amherst College he studied chemistry under William Smith Clark, later the assistant headmaster of the Sapporo Agricultural School.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>クラークにとっては最初の日本人学生であり、この縁でクラークは来日することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joe was the first Japanese student for Clark, and this brought Clark to visit to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joe was the first Japanese student for Clark, and this motivated Clark to visit to Japan.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joe was Clark&apos;s first Japanese student, and this experience inspired Clark to visit Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>当初密入国者として渡米した襄であったが、初代の駐米公使となった森有礼によって正式な留学生として認可された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joe who firstly entered the United States as a blockade runner was officially admitted as a student studying abroad by Arinori MORI who became the first minister-counselor to the United States.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joe who first entered the United States as a blockade runner was officially admitted as a student studying abroad under Arinori MORI who became the first minister-counselor to the United States.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the auspices of Arinori MORI, Japan&apos;s first ambassador to the United States, Joe--who had first entered the U.S. as an illegal immigrant--was officially recognized as a legal foreign exchange student.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>1872年（明治5年）、アメリカ訪問中の岩倉使節団と会う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1872, Joe met the Iwakura Mission during their visit to the United States.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1872, Joe met the Iwakura Mission during their visit to the United States.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1872, Joe met with the Iwakura Mission during their tour of the United States.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>襄の語学力に目をつけた木戸孝允は、1872年（明治5年）4月16日から1873年（明治6年）1月にかけて自分付けの通訳として使節団に参加させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koin KIDO who paid notice to Joe&apos;s linguistic proficiency let Joe participate in the Mission as his interpreter from April 16, 1872 to January 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koin KIDO who noticed Joe&apos;s linguistic proficiency had Joe participate in the Mission as his interpreter from April 16, 1872 to January 1873.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joe&apos;s proficiency in English came to the attention of Takayoshi KIDO, who asked Joe to serve as his interpreter, so Joe joined the Mission and worked as an interpreter from April 16, 1872 to January of 1873.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>襄は使節団に参加する形でニューヨークからヨーロッパへ渡り、フランス、スイス、ドイツ、ロシアを訪ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joe traveled from New York to Europe, and visited France, Switzerland, Germany and Russia in the form of participating in the Mission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joe traveled from New York to Europe, and visited France, Switzerland, Germany, and Russia as a member of the Mission.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a member of the Mission, Joe crossed over to Europe from New York, visiting France, Switzerland, Germany, and Russia.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後ベルリンにもどって約7カ月間滞在し、使節団の報告書ともいうべき『理事功程』を編集した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he came back to and stayed in Berlin for about seven months, and organized &quot;Rijikotei&quot; which was comparable to the Mission&apos;s report.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he came back and stayed in Berlin for about seven months, and organized &quot;Rijikotei&quot; which was comparable to the Mission&apos;s report.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Mission, he returned to Berlin and stayed there for about seven months, compiling the &quot;Rijikotei&quot;, which could be called an account of the Iwakura Mission.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これは、明治政府の教育制度にも大きな影響を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Rijikotei also had a great impact on the educational system of the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Rijikotei had a great impact on the educational system of the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Rijikotei had a great impact on the educational system of the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また欧米教育制度調査の委嘱を受け、文部理事官・田中不二麿に随行して欧米各国の教育制度を調査した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joe who was asked to research educational systems in Europe and in the United States researched the educational system in each European country and in the United States, in attendance on Fujimaro TANAKA, commissioner of Education Department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joe who was asked to research educational systems in Europe and in the United States, carried this out in each European country and as well as the United States, while assisting Fujimaro TANAKA, The Commissioner of the Education Department.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joe had been asked to research educational systems in Europe and the U.S., so he made a study of each country&apos;s educational systems and assisted Fujimaro TANAKA, the Commissioner of the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>教育者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Educator</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Educator</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Educator</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>1874年（明治7年）、アンドーヴァー神学校を卒業する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1874, Joe graduated from Andover Seminary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1874, Joe graduated from Andover Seminary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1874, Joe graduated from Andover Seminary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>同年10月、アメリカン・ボード海外伝道部の年次大会で日本でキリスト教主義大学の設立を訴え、5,000ドルの寄付の約束を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October of the same year, he appealed for an establishment of Japanese university based on Christianity at the annual meeting of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, and obtained a commitment to donate 5,000 dollars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October of the same year, he made an appeal to establish of a Japanese university based on Christianity at the annual meeting of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, and obtained a commitment to donate 5,000 dollars.</e>
<cmt>revised wordiness for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October of the same year, at the annual meeting of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, Joe requested funding to establish a Christian university in Japan, and secured the promise of a donation of 5000 dollars.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>11月、横浜市に帰着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, he returned to Yokohama City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, he returned to Yokohama City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That November, he arrived back in Yokohama.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>旧主家の板倉氏が京都所司代を務めたこともある関係で、新島家は公家華族とも広く親交があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Itakura clan who was the former master had worked as Kyoto shoshidai (Kyoto deputy), the Niijima clan was broadly associated with court nobles and peerages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Itakura clan was the former master who had worked as Kyoto shoshidai (Kyoto deputy), the Niijima clan was broadly associated with court nobles and their peers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given that the Itakura clan--the Niijima family&apos;s former masters--had held the position of Kyoto shoshidai (Kyoto deputy), the Niijima family had a wide range of connection with court nobles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>明治8年（1875年）11月29日、かねてより親交の深かった公家華族の高松保実子爵より屋敷（高松家別邸）の約半部を借り受けることが出来たので校舎を確保することが出来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 29, 1875, as Joe could rent about half the residence (the villa of the Takamatsu family) from viscount Sasuzane TAKAMATSU who was one of court nobles and peerages with whom Joe had been deeply associated, he could secure the schoolhouse.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 29, 1875, as Joe could rent about half the residence (the villa of the Takamatsu family) from viscount Sasuzane TAKAMATSU who was one of court nobles and peers with whom Joe had been deeply associated, he was able to secure the schoolhouse.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 29, 1875, Joe was able to secure a building to serve as a schoolhouse by renting about half the residence (the Takamatsu family villa) of Viscount Sasuzane TAKAMATSU, a court noble with whom Joe had been long and closely connected.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>京都府知事・槇村正直、府顧問・山本覚馬の賛同を得て官許同志社英学校を開校し初代社長に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the support of Masanao MAKIMURA, Governor of Kyoto Prefecture, and Kakuma YAMAMOTO, advisor to the prefectural government, Joe opened Doshisha Eigakko under official permission, and assumed the office of first president.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the support of Masanao MAKIMURA, Governor of Kyoto Prefecture, and Kakuma YAMAMOTO, advisor to the prefectural government, Joe opened Doshisha Eigakko under official permission, and assumed the office of first president.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the support of Masanao MAKIMURA, Governor of Kyoto Prefecture, and Kakuma YAMAMOTO, advisor to the prefectural government, Joe secured official permission for his school and opened Doshisha Eigakko, becoming its first president.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>開校時の教員は襄とJ.D.デイヴィスの2人、生徒は元良勇次郎、中島力造、上野栄三郎ら8人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the school was opened, there were two teachers of Joe and J.D. Davis, and eight students including Yujiro MOTORA, Rikizo NAKAJIMA and Eizaburo UENO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the school opened, there were two teachers, Joe himself, and J.D. Davis, and eight students including Yujiro MOTORA, Rikizo NAKAJIMA, and Eizaburo UENO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At its opening, the school had two teachers, Joe himself and J.D. Davis, and eight students, including Yujiro MOTORA, Rikizo NAKAJIMA, and Eizaburo UENO.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>またこのときの縁で翌年（1876年）1月3日、山本覚馬の妹・新島八重と結婚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to this relationship, he married Yae NIIJIMA, young sister of Kakuma YAMAMOTO on January 3, 1986.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to this relationship, he married Yae NIIJIMA, young sister of Kakuma YAMAMOTO on January 3, 1986.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to his working relationship with Kakuma YAMAMOTO, Joe was able to marry Kakuma&apos;s younger sister Yae on January 3, 1876.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>教育者としては大隈重信とも親交があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an educator, he was also associated with Shigenobu OKUMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an educator, he was also associated with Shigenobu OKUMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an educator he also had friendly relations with Shigenobu OKUMA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>今日同志社大学と早稲田大学の間で学生交流（国内留学）制度があるのはそのためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why there currently exists a student exchange system (studying at a another school in Japan) between Doshisha University and Waseda University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why there currently exists a student exchange system program (studying at a another school in Japan) between Doshisha and Waseda Universities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is because of this friendship that the current student exchange program (in which students can study at another university within Japan) exists between Doshisha and Waseda Universities.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>明治13年（1880年）4月13日、朝礼の際、自分の掌を杖で打ち、自らを罰して生徒に訓した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the morning assembly on April 13, 1880, Joe beat own hand with a stick, and he gave a lesson to the students by punishing himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the morning assembly on April 13, 1880, Joe beat his own hand with a stick, and he gave a lesson to the students by punishing himself.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the morning assembly on April 13, 1880, Joe struck his own hand with a stick, instructing the students by punishing himself.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これは「自責の杖」事件と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called an event of &quot;self-accusing stick.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called the &quot;self-accusing stick.&quot; event.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This came to be known as the &quot;self-reproaching stick&quot; incident.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>明治17年（1884年）4月6日、2度目の海外渡航に出発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 6, 1884, Joe left Japan for the second overseas travel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 6, 1884, Joe left Japan on a second overseas trip.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 6, 1884, Joe departed Japan on his second overseas trip.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>ドイツでは訪問先のヨハネス・ヘッセ氏の家で幼少の息子ヘルマン・ヘッセと会っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He met Hermann Hesse, small son of Johannes Hesse, at his house in Germany during his trip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He met Hermann Hesse, the small son of Johannes Hesse, at his house in Germany..</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While in Germany, he visited the house of Johannes Hesse and met his son Hermann, who was still a young boy at the time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>明治21年（1888年）11月、『同志社大学設立ノ旨意』を全国の主要な雑誌・新聞に掲載された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, the &quot;Purpose of Establishment of Doshisha University&quot; was publicized on major magazines and newspapers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, the &quot;Purpose of the Establishment of Doshisha University&quot; was publicized in major magazines and newspapers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1888, the &quot;Statement of Purpose for the Founding of Doshisha University&quot; was published in the major magazines and newspapers.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>明治23年（1890年）、同志社設立運動中に群馬県の前橋で倒れ、静養先の神奈川県大磯の旅館・百足屋で徳富蘇峰、小崎弘道らに10か条の遺言を託して死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1890, Joe fell during the campaign for the establishment of Doshisha in Maebashi, Gunma Prefecture, and died at Mukade-ya, Japanese inn in Oiso, Kanagawa Prefecture, where he was recuperating, after entrusting the will of ten articles to Soho TOKUTOMI and Hiromichi KOZAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1890, Joe fell during the campaign for the establishment of Doshisha in Maebashi, Gunma Prefecture, and died at Mukade-ya, Japanese inn in Oiso, Kanagawa Prefecture, where he was recuperating, after entrusting the will of ten articles to Soho TOKUTOMI and Hiromichi KOZAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1890, in Maebashi in Gunma Prefecture, Joe collapsed while working to found Doshisha, and passed away while recuperating at the Mukade-ya, a Japanese-style inn in Oiso, Kanagawa Prefecture; he entrusted his ten-item will to Soho TOKUTOMI and Hiromichi KOZAKI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>46歳11ヶ月であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was forty six years and eleven months old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was forty six years and eleven months old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was forty-six and eleven months.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>1月27日13時より同志社前のチャペルで葬儀が営まれ、東山若王子山頂に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His funeral was held at the chapel in front of Doshisha from 13:00 on January 27, and he was buried at the summit of Mt. Nyakuoji in Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His funeral was held at the chapel in front of Doshisha from 13:00 on January 27, and he was buried at the summit of Mt. Nyakuoji in Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His funeral, which began at 1 PM on January 27, was held at the chapel in front of Doshisha, and he was buried on the summit of Mt. Nyakuoji in Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>墓碑銘は勝海舟の筆である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The calligraphy of Kaishu KATSU was used for the inscription of Joe&apos;s tombstone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The calligraphy of Kaishu KATSU was used for the inscription of Joe&apos;s tombstone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The calligraphy of Kaishu KATSU was used for the inscription of Joe&apos;s tombstone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>父親の新島民治（にいじま たみじ）は襄の伝道によりキリスト教に改宗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Tamiji NIIJIMA, was converted to Christianity by Joe&apos;s mission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Tamiji NIIJIMA, was converted to Christianity by Joe&apos;s mission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joe&apos;s evangelistic efforts converted his father Tamiji NIIJIMA to Christianity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>群馬県の上毛カルタのなかに襄が描かれた取り札がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jomo Karuta Card in Gunma Prefecture contains a card with a picture of Joe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jomo Karuta Card in Gunma Prefecture contains a card with a picture of Joe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jomo Karuta (a type of Japanese playing card) in Gunma Prefecture include one depicting Joe.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), ZassouTori(id:136771), 松浸史(id:78240), Tomony(id:136759), Cprobot(id:97843), 陽一(id:92099), Ttwo(id:82880), Yu-ki-na(id:115957), Onble(id:70481), Jazzy(id:3202), 秋の虹(id:18259), Greenland4(id:114494), HIw(id:187708), Mois(id:30596), Goki(id:7107), Lincoln Town Car(id:32492), IwaimBot(id:190695), Akinoniji(id:56111), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), Ahflahxh(id:11222), Clarin(id:60278), Cave cattum(id:41235), Akaloli(id:141644), 鷹之羽(id:102544), 紙の兵隊(id:252772), 上田隼人(id:23104), Shaorin(id:168139), 江戸ラー(id:30154), Kyoutanabe124(id:175304), Doe A Deer(id:237297), ＫＡＺＥ(id:10403), NIKE(id:16342), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>