<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源信雅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Nobumasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Nobumasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Nobumasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 信雅（みなもと の のぶまさ、承暦3年（1079年） - 保延元年（1135年））は、平安時代末期の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Nobumasa (10879 - 1135) was a nobleman in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Nobumasa (1079 - 1135) was a nobleman at the end of the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Date corrected. Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Nobumasa (1079 - 1135) was a nobleman at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>period. 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>村上源氏、源顕房の六男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the sixth son of MINAMOTO no Akifusa, Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the sixth son of MINAMOTO no Akifusa, Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the sixth son of MINAMOTO no Akifusa, Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正四位下・陸奥国国司。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and served as Kokushi (an officer of local government) in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His rank was Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and he served as a Kokushi (an officer of local government) in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His rank was Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and he served as a Kokushi (an officer of local government) in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>初め家定と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He first called himself Iesada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He first called himself Iesada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He first called himself Iesada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>馬寮の任にあった寛治7年（1093年）に昇殿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was admitted to the court in 1093 when he was Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was admitted to the court in 1093 when he entered the Meryo (the section taking care of the imperial horses).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was admitted to the court in 1093 when he entered the Meryo (the section taking care of the Imperial horses).</e>
<cmt>Imperial大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>永長元年（1096年）の田楽においては、源重資らとともに小鼓を打つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In dengaku (ritual music and dancing in shrines and temples) in 1096, he played Kotsuzumi, (small hand drum) with MINAMOTO no Shigesuke and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When dengaku (ritual music and dancing in shrines and temples) was performed in 1096, he played the kotsuzumi, (small hand drum) with MINAMOTO no Shigesuke and others.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When dengaku (ritual music and dancing in shrines and temples) was performed in 1096, he played the kotsuzumi (small hand drum) with MINAMOTO no Shigesuke and others.</e>
<cmt>不要なコンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>承徳2年（1098年）正月に右少将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In between February and March 1098, he became Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between February and March 1098, he became Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between February and March 1098, he became Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>長治元年（1104年）に従四位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1104, he became Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1104, he became Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1104, he became Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>加賀国介を長く務めた後に大治 (日本)3年（1128年）に陸奥守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as Kaga no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Kaga Province) for a long time and then became Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province) in 1128.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as Kaga no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Kaga Province) for a long time and then became Mutsu no kami (Governor of Mutsu Province) in 1128.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as Kaga no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Kaga Province) for a long time and then became Mutsu no kami (Governor of Mutsu Province) in 1128.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後重任し、在職のまま保延元年（1135年）に卒去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he was reappointed for a second term and demised in 1135 while in office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he was reappointed for a second term, but died in 1135 while in office.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he was reappointed for a second term, but died in 1135 while in office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>藤原忠実の家司を務め、その衆道の相手でもあったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as Keishi (household superintendent) of FUJIWARA no Tadazane and is reported to be his gay partner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as Keishi (household superintendent) to FUJIWARA no Tadazane and is reported to have been his gay partner.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as Keishi (household superintendent) to FUJIWARA no Tadazane and is reported to have been his gay partner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『富家語』には、忠実が信雅と成雅の容貌を比較して批評した話が収録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fukego,&quot; a collection of the sayings of FUJIWARA no Tadamitsu contains a story that Tadazane compared appearances of Nobumasa and Narimasa and criticized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fukego,&quot; a collection of the sayings of FUJIWARA no Tadamitsu contains a story where Tadazane compared the appearances of Nobumasa and Narimasa critically.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fukego&quot; (a collection of the sayings of FUJIWARA no Tadamitsu) contains a story where Tadazane compared the appearances of Nobumasa and Narimasa critically.</e>
<cmt>説明を括弧に入れました。コンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Masyu(id:31065), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>