<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>坂上苅田麻呂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAKANOUE no Karitamaro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAKANOUE no Karitamaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAKANOUE no Karitamaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>坂上苅田麻呂（さかのうえのかりたまろ、神亀4年（727年）- 延暦5年1月7日 (旧暦)（786年2月14日））は奈良時代の武人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAKANOUE no Karitamaro (male, 727 to February 14, 786) was a warrior in Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAKANOUE no Karitamaro (727-February 14, 786) was a warrior in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>male, 727 to February 14, 786 を 727-February 14, 786 に修正しました。Nara period に the を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAKANOUE no Karitamaro (727-February 14, 786) was a warrior in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karitamaro was ranked at Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official court rank was Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Karitamaro was ranked at をHis official court rank was に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official court rank was Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中衛府中将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as chuefu-chujo (the second-rank officer of the police for the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as Chuefu chujo (Middle Captain of the Inner-Most Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>appointed as 以下を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Chuefu chujo (Middle Captain of the Inner-Most Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>左京大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also appointed as Sakyo-daibu (a chief of handling general affairs in Sakyo which was the eastern half of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also appointed as Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>Sakyo-daibu (a chief of handling general affairs in Sakyo which was the eastern half of Kyoto) を Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also appointed as Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>坂上犬養の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of SAKANOUE no Inukai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of SAKANOUE no Inukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of SAKANOUE no Inukai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>坂上田村麻呂の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the father of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>坂上氏は中国の後漢の霊帝 (漢)の流れを汲むという東漢氏に繋がる家系で代々弓馬の道をよくする武門の一族として、数朝にわたり宮廷を守護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The SAKANOUE clan is a linage that is related to HIGASHIKAN clan which was said to be a branch of the holy Chinese Emperor (KAN) in Gokan period in China, and they guarded the Imperial Court for several emperors as a clan of martial arts who eagerly practiced archery and horse-back riding in all their generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SAKANOUE clan is a linage that is related to HIGASHIKAN clan which was said to be a branch of the holy Chinese Emperor (KAN) in the Later Han Dynasty in China, and they guarded the Imperial Court for several emperors as a clan of martial arts who eagerly practiced archery and horse-back riding in all their generations.</e>
<cmt>Gokan period を the Later Han Dynasty に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SAKANOUE clan is a linage that is related to HIGASHIKAN clan which was said to be a branch of the holy Chinese Emperor (KAN) in the Later Han Dynasty in China, and they guarded the Imperial Court for several emperors as a clan of martial arts who eagerly practiced archery and horse-back riding in all their generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>天平宝字年中に近衛兵令外官少尉に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karitamaro was appointed as Konoeheirei-gaikanshoi (the Imperial police soldier order external office of the second rank) in the first year of Tenpyo-hojinenen period (757.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karitamaro was appointed as Konoehei Ryoge no kan shojo (junior lieutenant of the imperial guard, a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts) during the Tenpyo hoji era (757-765).</e>
<cmt>appointed as 以下を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karitamaro was appointed as Konoehei Ryoge no kan shojo (junior lieutenant of the imperial guard, a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts) during the Tenpyo hoji era (757 - 765).</e>
<cmt>スペース調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>天平宝字8年（764年）9月、太師（太政大臣）藤原仲麻呂（恵美押勝）が謀反を起こすという密告があり、孝謙上皇は仲麻呂派の淳仁天皇の中宮院（御所）に少納言山村王を遣わし、皇権の発動に必要な玉璽と駅鈴を回収させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 764, it was secretly informed that the Daishi (Dajo-daijin (the political minister)), FUJIWARA no Nakamaro (Oshikatsu Emi) would raise a rebellion, and the Retired Emperor Koken sent Shonagon (lesser councilor of state), Yamamurao to Chuguin (the Imperial Palace) of the Emperor Junjin who was in the Nakamaro&apos;s fact, and caused Yamamurao to collect gyokuji (the jewelry emperor&apos;s seal) and ekirin (literally, a station bell) which were necessary for exercising the right of the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 764, it was secretly informed that the Daishi (Daijo-daijin [Grand Minister]), FUJIWARA no Nakamaro (EMI no Oshikatsu) would raise a rebellion, and the Retired Empress Koken sent Shonagon (lesser councilor of state), Prince Yamamura to Chuguin (the Imperial Palace) of the Emperor Junjin who was in the Nakamaro&apos;s fact, and caused Yamamurao to collect gyokuji (the jewelry emperor&apos;s seal) and ekirin (literally, a station bell) which were necessary for exercising the right of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 764, it was secretly informed that the Daishi (Daijo-daijin [Grand Minister]), FUJIWARA no Nakamaro (EMI no Oshikatsu) would raise a rebellion, and the Retired Empress Koken sent Shonagon (lesser councilor of state), Prince Yamamura to Chuguin (the Imperial Palace) of the Emperor Junjin who was in the Nakamaro&apos;s fact, and caused Yamamurao to collect gyokuji (the jewelry emperor&apos;s seal) and ekirin (literally, a station bell) which were necessary for exercising the right of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>仲麻呂は子の藤原訓儒麻呂を遣わし玉璽と駅鈴を奪おうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakamaro tried to forcibly take back the gyokuji and ekirin by sending his son, FUJIWARA no Norijumaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakamaro sent his son, FUJIWARA no Norijumaro to take back the gyokuji and ekirin by force.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakamaro sent his son, FUJIWARA no Norijumaro to take back the gyokuji and ekirin by force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>山村王は急報を送り、坂上苅田麻呂は将曹牡鹿嶋足とともに勅命を受け馳せかけて、訓儒麻呂を射殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamamurao sent an urgent report and SAKANOUE no Karitamaro rushed together with shoso (a general) Narito OJIKA, receiving an Imperial order shot to kill Norijumaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Yamamura sent an urgent report and SAKANOUE no Karitamaro rushed together with shoso (a general) Narito OJIKA, receiving an Imperial order shot to kill Norijumaro.</e>
<cmt>Yamamurao を Prince Yamamura に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Yamamura sent an urgent report and SAKANOUE no Karitamaro rushed together with shoso (a general) Narito OJIKA, receiving an Imperial order shot to kill Norijumaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、仲麻呂は平城京を脱出し、近江国で戦いに敗れて滅びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, Nakamaro escaped from Heijokyo and lost in fighting in Omi Province and collapsed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, Nakamaro escaped from Heijo-kyo Capital and lost in fighting in Omi Province and collapsed.</e>
<cmt>Heijokyo を Heijo-kyo Capital に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, Nakamaro escaped from Heijo-kyo Capital and lost in fighting in Omi Province and collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>（藤原仲麻呂の乱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s Rebellion)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro)</e>
<cmt>以下の出典に伴い、修正しました。http://books.google.com/books?id=F_CVHwpoWskC&amp;pg=PA319&amp;dq=Fujiwara+no+Nakamaro+rebellion&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=PpA5TL2CFc_IceOx0foO&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=Fujiwara%20no%20Nakamaro%20rebellion&amp;f=false</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>この功により苅田麻呂は従四位下勳二等を授かり、大忌寸の姓(カバネ)を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this exploit, Karitamaro was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was honored with the Second Order of Merit and a family name, daikisun was given to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this exploit, Karitamaro was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was honored with the Second Order of Merit and a family name, Oimiki was given to him.</e>
<cmt>daikisun を Oimiki に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this exploit, Karitamaro was promoted to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was honored with the Second Order of Merit and a family name, Oimiki was given to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>中衛少将に補任され、甲斐国国司を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was additionally appointed as chue-shosho (the third-rank officer of the Imperial police) and also appointed as the governor of Kai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was additionally appointed as Chue no shosho (Minor Captain of the Imperial Guard) and also appointed as the governor of Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>chue-shosho (the third-rank officer of the Imperial police) を Chue no shosho (Minor Captain of the Imperial Guard) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was additionally appointed as Chue no shosho (Minor Captain of the Imperial Guard) and also appointed as the governor of Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>宝亀元年（770年）称徳天皇（孝謙上皇が重祚）が崩御すると、道鏡の姦計を告げて、その排斥に功績があり、正四位下に進み、陸奥国鎮守将軍となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Emperor Shotoku (which name the Emperor Koken doubly used for himself) died in 770, Karitamaro reported a scandalous plan of Dokyo (a Buddhism priest deeply concerned the politics) and performed an exploit of expelling Dokyo and, therefore, Karitamaro was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was appointed as chinju-shogun (a general to guard the shrines) of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Empress Shotoku (which name the Empress Koken doubly used for herself) died in 770, Karitamaro reported a scandalous plan of Dokyo (a Buddhism priest deeply concerned the politics) and performed an exploit of expelling Dokyo and, therefore, Karitamaro was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was appointed as Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>Emperor Shotoku (which name the Emperor Koken doubly used for himself) をEmpress Shotoku (which name the Empress Koken doubly used for herself) に修正しました。chinju-shogun (a general to guard the shrines) をCommander-in-Chief of the Defense に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Empress Shotoku (which name the Empress Koken doubly used for herself) died in 770, Karitamaro reported a scandalous plan of Dokyo (a Buddhism priest deeply concerned the politics) and performed an exploit of expelling Dokyo and, therefore, Karitamaro was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and was appointed as Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>中衛中将、安芸国守、丹波国守などの国司を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karitamaro worked as a state officer in succession as chue-chujo (the second-rank officer of the Imperial police), the governor of Aki Province, the governor of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karitamaro worked as a state officer in succession as Chue no chujo (middle captain of the imperial guard), the governor of Aki Province, the governor of Tanba Province and so on.</e>
<cmt>chue-chujo (the second-rank officer of the Imperial police) をChue no chujo (middle captain of the imperial guard) に修正しました。「などの」訳漏れのため、文末に and so on を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karitamaro worked as a state officer in succession as Chue no chujo (middle captain of the imperial guard), the governor of Aki Province, the governor of Tanba Province and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天応 (日本)元年（781年）正四位上を授かり、右衛士督となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 781, Karitamaro was promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and was appointed as ueishitoku (an supervisor of police officers for western half of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 781, He was promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and was appointed as Ueji no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>Karitamaro を He に修正しました。ueishitoku (an supervisor of police officers for western half of Kyoto) をUeji no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 781, He was promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and was appointed as Ueji no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>延暦元年（782年）氷上川継の謀反事件（氷上川継の乱）に連座して職を解かれるが、間もなく許され復職する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 782, Karitamaro joined the members who raised the coup incident lead by Kawatsugu Hikami (Kawatsugu Hikami&apos;s Rebellion) and, due to this, was fired, however, he was forgiven soon and retuned to the position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 782, he was implicated in the rebellion lead by HIKAMI no Kawatsugu (Rebellion of HIKAMI no Kawatsugu) and fired due to it; however, he was forgiven soon and returned to the position.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 782, he was implicated in the rebellion lead by HIKAMI no Kawatsugu (Hikami no Kawatsugu&apos;s rebellion) and fired due to it; however, he was forgiven soon and returned to the position.</e>
<cmt>括弧内の表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>伊予国守、備前国守の国司を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karitamaro was appointed as a state officer in succession as the governor of Iyo Province and the governor of Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as a state officer in succession as the governor of Iyo Province and the governor of Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>Karitamaro を He に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as a state officer in succession as the governor of Iyo Province and the governor of Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>延暦4年（785年）従三位に進み、上表して宿禰の姓(カバネ)を許される（坂上宿禰苅田麻呂。さかのうえ・の・すくね・の・かりたまろ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 785, Karitamaro was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), sent a message to the Emperor and, thereby, was allowed to have the family name of SUKUNE (SAKANOUE no SUKUNE no Karitamaro).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 785, he was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), sent a message to the Emperor and, thereby, was allowed to have the family name of SUKUNE (SAKANOUE no SUKUNE no Karitamaro).</e>
<cmt>Karitamaro を he に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 785, he was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), sent a message to the Emperor and, thereby, was allowed to have the family name of SUKUNE (SAKANOUE no SUKUNE no Karitamaro).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>同年、左京大夫に任じられ、右衛士督と下総国守を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Karitamaro was appointed as sakyo-daibu and simultaneously worked also as ueshitoku and the governor of Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he was appointed as Sakyo no daibu and simultaneously worked also as Ueji no kami and the governor of Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>Karitamaro を he に修正しました。sakyo-daibu を Sakyo no daibu に修正しました。ueshitoku を Ueji no kami に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he was appointed as Sakyo no daibu and simultaneously worked also as Ueji no kami and the governor of Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>延暦5年（786年）死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karitamaro died in 786.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 786.</e>
<cmt>Karitamaro を He に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 786.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Novo(id:87875), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), Point136(id:211299), 味っ子(id:17086), こぶまき(id:38278), Junger(id:10282), 沢田(id:40580), GENMEI(id:31879), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>