<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳大寺維子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Husako TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Husako TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusako TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳大寺 維子（とくだいじ ふさこ、文明 (日本)13年（1481年） - 永禄9年3月8日 (旧暦)（1566年3月29日））は、戦国時代 (日本)の関白・近衛尚通の北政所（正室）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Husako TOKUDAIJI (1481 to April 8, 1566) was a Kita no Mandokoro (legal wife of regent or chief adviser to the Emperor) of Hisamichi KONOE, who was a Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>永禄9年3月8日 は西暦1566年4月8日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Husako TOKUDAIJI (1481 to April 8, 1566) was a Kita no Mandokoro (legal wife of regent or chief adviser to the Emperor) of Hisamichi KONOE, who was a Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusako TOKUDAIJI (1481 - April 8, 1566) was a Kita no Mandokoro (legal wife of regent or chief adviser to the Emperor) of Hisamichi KONOE, who was a Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正し、統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>太政大臣徳大寺実淳の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Saneatsu TOKUDAIJI, who held the title of Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Saneatsu TOKUDAIJI, who held the title of Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Saneatsu TOKUDAIJI, who held the title of Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近衛稙家らの生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the real mother of Taneie KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the real mother of Taneie KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the biological mother of Taneie KONOE.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>明応6年7月26日に婚儀が行われ、正室として扱われた（当時の公家社会では正式な婚儀を行わなければ正室として認められなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the wedding ceremony held on September 2, 1497, she practically became the lawful wife (in the court noble society at the time, the position of a lawful wife was granted only after the formal marriage ceremony).</e>
<cmt>明応6年7月26日：西暦1497年9月2日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the wedding ceremony held on September 2, 1497, she practically became the lawful wife (in the court noble society at the time, the position of a lawful wife was granted only after the formal marriage ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the wedding ceremony held on September 2, 1497, she practically became the lawful wife (in the court noble society at the time, the position of a lawful wife was granted only after the formal marriage ceremony).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>翌年6月7日には最初の女子を出産し、以後2男5女を儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After giving birth to the first daughter on July 5, 1498, she had two sons and five daughters.</e>
<cmt>翌年6月7日：西暦1498年7月5日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After giving birth to the first daughter on July 5, 1498, she had two sons and five daughters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After giving birth to the first daughter on July 5 in the following year, she had two sons and five daughters.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ただし、婚儀の前月に既に尚通は最初の関白の任を終えていたため、彼女が北政所とされることはなく、「北政所」として彼女が登場するのは永正10年（1513年）に尚通が関白に還補された直後（『後法成寺日記』永正10年10月27日条）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because Hisamichi had already retired from the position of Kanpaku in the month before their marriage, she didn&apos;t get to hold the position of Kita no Mandokoro until right after Hisamichi was reassigned to Kanpaku in 1513 (&quot;Gohojojinikki&quot;, the article dated December 4, 1513).</e>
<cmt>永正10年10月27日：西暦1513年12月4日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because Hisamichi had already retired from the position of Kanpaku in the month before their marriage, she didn&apos;t get to hold the position of Kita no Mandokoro until right after Hisamichi reassigned to Kanpaku in 1513 (&quot;Gohojojinikki,&quot; the article dated December 4, 1513).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because Hisamichi had already retired from the position of Kanpaku in the month before their marriage, she didn&apos;t get to hold the position of &apos;Kita no Mandokoro&apos; until right after Hisamichi reassigned to Kanpaku in 1513 (&quot;Gohojoji Nikki&quot; (The Diary of Hisamichi KONOE), the article dated October 27 in the tenth year of the Eisho era).</e>
<cmt>「後法成寺日記」は正しくは「後法成寺関白記」と思われますが、そのまま読み表記しています。the article dated December 4, 1513→the article dated October 27 in the tenth year of the Eisho era(日記のため）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、同年の11月20日に従三位に叙せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 27, 1513, she was granted the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>同年の11月20日：西暦1513年12月27日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 27, 1513, she was granted the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 27, 1513, she was granted the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>夫や息子の代わりに公的な場に出る場合があったことが知られ、稙家が関白・藤氏長者に任ぜられた天文 (日本)5年（1536年）の興福寺維摩会には、会翌日に関白就任の奏慶を控えた稙家の代理として興福寺を訪れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that Husako undertook official duties in place of her husband and sons; on the occasion of Yuimae (a Buddhist service for the Yuima Sutra held at Kofuku-ji Temple) held at Kofuku-ji Temple in 1536, the year when Taneie assumed the positions of Kanpaku Toshi choja (Chief advisor to the Emperor and the head of the Fujiwara clan), she visited the temple in place of Taneie, who was to offer thanks for being designated a Kanpaku the next day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that Husako undertook official duties in place of her husband and sons; on the occasion of Yuimae (a Buddhist service for the Yuima Sutra held at Kofuku-ji Temple) held at Kofuku-ji Temple in 1536, the year when Taneie assumed the positions of Kanpaku Toshi choja (Chief advisor to the Emperor and the head of the Fujiwara clan), she visited the temple in place of Taneie, who was to offer thanks for being designated a Kanpaku the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that Fusako undertook official duties in place of her husband and sons; on the occasion of Yuimae (a Buddhist service for the Yuima Sutra held at Kofuku-ji Temple) held at Kofuku-ji Temple in 1536, the year when Taneie assumed the positions of Kanpaku and Toshi choja (Chief advisor to the Emperor and the head of the Fujiwara clan), she visited the temple in place of Taneie, who was to offer thanks for being designated a Kanpaku the next day.</e>
<cmt>スペルなど修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、彼女の所生ではないものの、征夷大将軍足利義晴正室となった慶寿院の後見的立場にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although not her birth child, she served as a guardian of Keijuin, who was the lawful wife of Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although not her birth child, she served as a guardian of Keijuin, who was the lawful wife of Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although not her birth child, she served as a guardian of Keijuin, who was the lawful wife of seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>天文5年に慶寿院が義晴の嫡男（後の足利義輝）を生んだ際に立ち会っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She witnessed Keijuin giving birth to Yoshiharu&apos;s eldest son and heir (later Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA) in 1536.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She witnessed Keijuin giving birth to Yoshiharu&apos;s eldest son and heir (later Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA) in 1536.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She witnessed Keijuin giving birth to Yoshiharu&apos;s oldest son and heir (later Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA) in 1536.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、伊予国の河野通直から「近衛家大政所」を通して御相伴衆推挙の依頼が六角定頼及び内談衆大舘常興・大舘晴光父子に対してなされた事が知られている（『大舘常興日記』天文8年12月4・5日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is known that Michinao KONO of Iyo Province requested Sadayori ROKKAKU, Joko ODACHI, who held the position of naidanshu (another name of hikitsukeshu, coadjustor of the high court), and his son Harumitsu ODACHI, to put in a good word for him to be a member of Gohobanshu (officials who accompany shogun) via the &apos;Omandokoro (Mother of the chief Adviser to the Emperor) of the Konoe family&apos; (&quot;Odachi Joko Nikki&quot; (Diary of Joko ODACHI), the articles dated January 22 and 23, 1540).</e>
<cmt>天文8年12月4日は西暦1540年1月22日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is known that Michinao KONO of Iyo Province requested Sadayori ROKKAKU, Joko ODACHI, who held the position of naidanshu (another name of hikitsukeshu, coadjustor of the high court), and his son Harumitsu ODACHI, to put in a good word for him to become a member of Gohobanshu (officials who accompany shogun) via the &apos;Omandokoro (Mother of the chief Adviser to the Emperor) of the Konoe family&apos; (&quot;Odachi Joko Nikki&quot; (Diary of Joko ODACHI), the articles dated January 22 and 23, 1540).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is known that Michinao KONO of Iyo Province requested Sadayori ROKKAKU, Joko ODACH of naidanshu (another name of hikitsukeshu, coadjustor of the high court), and his son Harumitsu ODACHI, to put in a good word for him to become a member of Gohobanshu (officials who accompany shogun) via the &apos;Omandokoro (Mother of the chief Adviser to the Emperor) of the Konoe family&apos; (&quot;Odachi Joko Nikki&quot; (The Diary of Joko ODACHI), the articles dated January 22 and 23, 1540).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「近衛家大政所」とは維子のことであり、将軍後継者である義輝の実質上の外祖母として幕政にも影響を与えたと考えられている（結果的に天文9年4月12日に河野通直は御相伴衆に加えられた（『大舘常興日記』））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &apos;Omandokoro of the Konoe family&apos; refers to Husako, who is believed to have influenced the shogunate government as a virtual maternal grandmother to Yoshiteru, who was a successor of the shogunate (Michinao KONO eventually became a member of Gohobanshu on May 28, 1540 (&quot;Odachi Joko Nikki&quot;)).</e>
<cmt>天文9年4月12日は西暦1540年5月28日となるようです。http://maechan.net/kanreki/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &apos;Omandokoro of the Konoe family&apos; refers to Husako, who is believed to have influenced the shogunate government as a virtual maternal grandmother to Yoshiteru, who was a successor of the shogunate (Michinao KONO eventually became a member of Gohobanshu on May 28, 1540 (&quot;Odachi Joko Nikki&quot;)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;Omandokoro of the Konoe family&apos; refers to Fusako, who is believed to have influenced the shogunate government as a virtual maternal grandmother to Yoshiteru, who was a successor of the shogunate (Michinao KONO eventually became a member of Gohobanshu on May 28, 1540 (&quot;Odachi Joko Nikki&quot;)).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>永正14年（1517年）頃より更年期障害と想定される健康の悪化が見られるものの、鞍馬寺や清水寺などの寺社参詣や親族、細川高国など有力者との交流ぶりが『後法成寺日記』などに記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although her health condition deteriorated after 1517, presumably from menopause, it is depicted in &quot;Gohojojinikki&quot; that she visited temples including Kurama-dera Temple and Kiyomizu-dera Temple, and associated with relatives and influential figures such as Takakuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although her health deteriorated after 1517, presumably from menopause, it is depicted in &quot;Gohojojinikki&quot; that she visited temples including Kurama-dera Temple and Kiyomizu-dera Temple, and associated with relatives and influential figures such as Takakuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although her health deteriorated after 1517, presumably from menopause, it is depicted in &quot;Gohojoji Nikki&quot; that she visited temples including Kurama-dera Temple and Kiyomizu-dera Temple, and associated with relatives and influential figures such as Takakuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>永禄9年3月8日に86歳の高齢で没した（『言継卿記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died on April 8, 1566, at the age of 86, which is considerably old (&quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died on April 8, 1566, at the age of eighty-six, which was considerably old (&quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; - Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died on April 8, 1566, at the age of 86, which was considerably old (&quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (The Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA)).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>