<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>美作朝親</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomochika MIMASAKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomochika MIMASAKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomochika MIMASAKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>美作 朝親 （みまさか ともちか、生没年不詳）は、鎌倉時代初期の武士・御家人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomochika MIMASAKA (date of birth and death unknown) was a samurai (warrior) and gokenin (shogunal retainer) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomochika MIMASAKA (date of birth and death unknown) was a samurai (warrior) and gokenin (shogunal retainer) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomochika MIMASAKA (date of birth and death unknown) was a samurai (warrior) and gokenin (shogunal retainer) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>系譜については村上源氏の流れを汲むとされるが、一説には清和源氏とも云われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he followed Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan), and there is a theory that states that he belonged to Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he followed Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan) lineage, and there is a theory stating that he belonged to Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) lineage.</e>
<cmt>lineageと加えました。a theory that states that から、a theory stating thatと変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he followed Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan) lineage, and there is a theory stating that he belonged to Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>号は美作蔵人、美作左近大夫など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His title was Mimasaka Kurodo, Mimasaka Sakon Daifu, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (pen name) was Mimasaka Kurodo and Mimasaka Sakon Daifu.</e>
<cmt>「など」をand othersとしていますが、特に必要ないかと思われます（ドキュメント中に出てこないため）。また、号は用語集でgo (pen name)となっているので、こちらを使用します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (pen name) was Mimasaka Kurodo and Mimasaka Sakon Daifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に本郷有泰がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child was Ariyasu HONGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His child was Ariyasu HONGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His child was Ariyasu HONGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>承元3年（1209年）12月、宿所を相対する御家人橘公業と妻女を巡った争論から合戦へと発展しかけ、征夷大将軍源実朝の命によって駆け付けた北条時房の仲介により事を収めるという騒ぎがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He disputed over wife with TACHIBANA no Kiminari, a gokenin (shogunal retainer) who faced each other accommodation, which threatened to became a battle, but this problem was solved through the intermediation of Tokifusa HOJO who was dispatched by command of Seii Taishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) MINAMOTO no Sanetomo in December, 1209.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1209, there was a incident that he and a gokenin (shogunal retainer) TACHIBANA no Kiminari, who stayed at opposite accommodation as he, disputed over the wife and nearly became a battle, however the problem was solved with the intermediation of Tokifusa HOJO who was sent with an order of Seii Taishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) MINAMOTO no Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt>「宿所を相対する御家人」は相対する宿所に泊まっていた御家人、という意味だと思われますので、そのように訳しました。年月を文始めに移動しました。その他若干文構成・単語を変えています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the twelfth month of 1209, an incident occured in which he had a dispute with TACHIBANA no Kiminari, a gokenin (shogunal retainer) who was staying at an lodging directly opposite his own, over his wife; this dispute threatened to escalate into a duel, but the issue was resolved with the help of a mediator, Tokifusa HOJO who was sent by order of the Seii taishogun (literally, the &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) MINAMOTO no Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>建暦2年（1212年）には実朝の鶴岡八幡宮参拝に随行しているほか、建保元年（1213年）2月に設置された学問所番のうち二番の一人としてその名がみえている（『吾妻鏡』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He visited Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine as an escort for Sanetomo in 1212, and his name appeared as number 2 in the guard of Gakumonjo established in February, 1213.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He visited Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine as an escort for Sanetomo in 1212, and his name appeared as one of number 2 in the guard of Gakumonjo established in February 1213.</e>
<cmt>「二番の一人」とあるので、one of number 2と変えました。February, 1213 &gt;&gt; February 1213</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He visited Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine as an escort for Sanetomo in 1212, and his name appeared as one of number 2 in the guard of Gakumonjo established in February 1213.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>承久の乱の後、若狭国大飯郡本郷の地頭に任じられ同地に下向した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned to Jito (manager and lord of manor) in Hongo, Oi-gun, Wakasa Province after the Jokyu war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned to Jito (manager and lord of manor) in Hongo, Oi-gun, Wakasa Province after the Jokyu war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned to Jito (manager and lord of manor) in Hongo, Oi-gun, Wakasa Province after the Jokyu war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>子孫は本郷氏を称し、鎌倉期には在京の御家人として存続している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendents were named the Hongo clan and survived as gokenin (shogunal retainers) in Kyoto in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendents were named the Hongo clan and continued as gokenin (shogunal retainers) in Kyoto in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>survived &gt;&gt; continuedと変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendents were named the Hongo clan and continued as gokenin (shogunal retainers) in Kyoto in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>