<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊達邦直</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuninao DATE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuninao DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuninao DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊達 邦直（だて くになお、天保5年9月12日 (旧暦)（1835年11月2日） - 明治24年（1891年）1月12日）は、江戸時代末期の仙台藩一門・岩出山伊達家当主で、明治維新後は北海道開拓に身を投じ当別町の基礎を築く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuninao DATE (November 2, 1835 - January 12, 1891) was a head of the Iwadeyama Date family, Sendai Domain Sept in the end of Edo Period, devoted himself to the reclamation of Hokkaido after Meiji Restoration, and laid the foundation of Tobetsu-cho..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuninao DATE (November 2, 1835 - January 12, 1891) was a head of the Iwadeyama Date family, Sendai Domain Sept in the end of Edo Period, who devoted himself to development of Hokkaido after Meiji Restoration and laid the foundation of Tobetsu-cho.</e>
<cmt>形式・文法・用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuninao DATE (November 2, 1835 - January 12, 1891) was a head of the Iwadeyama Date family, Sendai Domain Sept in the end of Edo Period, who devoted himself to development of Hokkaido after Meiji Restoration and laid the foundation of Tobetsu-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>その功により正五位を贈られ、当別神社・北海道開拓神社に祀られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owing to the merits he was bestowed Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) and is enshrined in Tobetsu Shrine/Hokkaido shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owing to his outstanding achievements he was bestowed with a court rank of Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) and is enshrined in Tobetsu-jinja Shrine and Hokkaido Kaitaku-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>原文のリンク先表示を訂正の上再訳出しました。文法・用語・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owing to his outstanding achievements he was bestowed with a court rank of Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) and is enshrined in Tobetsu-jinja Shrine and Hokkaido Kaitaku-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、孫の伊達正人は邦直の功により男爵を授けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masato DATE, his grandson was also bestowed baronage owing to Kuninao&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masato DATE, his grandson, had conferred on him the Baronage owing to Kuninao&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masato DATE, his grandson, had conferred on him the Baronage owing to Kuninao&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>亘理伊達家十五代で有珠郡伊達村（現・伊達市 (北海道)）開拓に功があり男爵となった伊達邦成は実弟にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunishige DATE, the fifteenth generation of Watari DATE family, who contributed to the reclamation of Date-mura Usu-gun (now Date City in Hokkaido), and became Baron, was his younger brother by blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunishige DATE, who was the fifteenth head of the Watari-Date family, contributed to building Date-mura Village in Usu-gun County (present-day Date City in Hokkaido) and was therefore raised to Baron, was his younger brother by blood.</e>
<cmt>表現・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunishige DATE, who was the fifteenth head of the Watari-Date family, contributed to building Date-mura Village in Usu-gun County (present-day Date City in Hokkaido) and was therefore raised to Baron, was his younger brother by blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>邦直は、伊達義監・りんの長男として陸奥国（のち陸前国）玉造郡岩出山城に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuninao was born first son to 義監 and Rin in Iwadeyama Castle in Tamatsukuri-gun in Mutsu Province (later Rikuzen Province).</e>
<cmt>*義監（よしかん/ぎかん 読み方、不明）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuninao was born as the first son to 義監 DATE and his wife Rin in Iwadeyama-jo Castle in Tamatsukuri-gun County, Mutsu Province (the future Rikuzen Province).</e>
<cmt>義監の読み不明。「よしみ」・「ぎかん」の可能性も考えられます。用語・表現・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuninao was born as the first son to 義監 DATE and his wife Rin in Iwadeyama-jo Castle in Tamatsukuri-gun County, Mutsu Province (the future Rikuzen Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幼名を太刀、通称を英橘という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was 太刀, and his common name 英橘.</e>
<cmt>太刀 Taito、英橘Eikyoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Tachi, and his common name 英橘.</e>
<cmt>太刀の読みは「たち」しか無いようですので、そのように訳出しました。英橘は「えいきつ」という読みが存在しますが、伊達家の場合で確認がとれませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Tachi, and his common name 英橘.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>明治維新の際に奥羽越列藩同盟に参加した宗藩の命により、官軍と交戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Meiji Restoration by the order of the head clan that participating in Ou-Uetsu-reppan-domei, he fought against the Imperial Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Meiji Restoration, by the order of the head clan that participated in Ouetsu Reppan Domei (known as Northern Alliance), he battled with the Imperial Army.</e>
<cmt>表現・用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Meiji Restoration, by the order of the head clan that participated in Ouetsu Reppan Domei (known as Northern Alliance), he battled with the Imperial Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>山形で勝ち戦功を上げたが、味方の多くは官軍に下った為戦に敗れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got a victory in Yamagata, and made distinguished war service, but was defeated in the battle because many of his allies surrendered to the Imperial Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He won a battle in Yamagata and made distinguished war service, but was defeated in the end because many of his allies had surrendered to the Imperial Army.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He won a battle in Yamagata and made distinguished war service, but was defeated in the end because many of his allies had surrendered to the Imperial Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>戦後、それまで一万四千石あった禄高を六十五石に減封され、城は召し上げられ家臣の士分を剥奪された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war his rokudaka (stipend) was reduced from 14,000 koku to 65 koku, his castle was taken up, and his vassals were deprived of samurai class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war the amount of his stipend was reduced from 14,000 koku to 65 koku, his castle was confiscated, and his vassals were deprived of the social status of samurai class.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war the amount of his stipend was reduced from 14,000 koku to 65 koku, his castle was confiscated, and his vassals were deprived of the social status of samurai class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>侍ではなくなった家臣達は帰農を命ぜられたが、邦直は彼等が路頭に迷う事を憂い、私財を処分し得た資金で新政府の推し進めていた北海道開拓を志願する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His vassals, who were no longer samurai, were ordered to take up farming again: Kunionao, fearing that they would lose their means of livelihood, decided to volunteer for the reclamation of Hokkaido that the new government was promoting, using his fund obtained by disposing his personal properties..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His vassals, who were no longer samurai, were ordered to take up farming again, but Kuninao, fearing that they would lose their means of livelihood, decided to volunteer for development of Hokkaido that the new government was promoting, using money made by selling his personal properties.</e>
<cmt>表現・形式・文法を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His vassals, who were no longer samurai, were ordered to take up farming again, but Kuninao, fearing that they would lose their means of livelihood, decided to volunteer for development of Hokkaido that the new government was promoting, using money made by selling his personal properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>願は許され1869年（明治2年）石狩国空知郡の支配を命ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wish being permitted, he was ordered to rule Sorachi-gun in Ishikari no Kuni in 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuninao&apos;s application for permission being accepted, he was ordered to govern Sorachi-gun County in Ishikari Province in 1869.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuninao&apos;s application for permission being accepted, he was ordered to govern Sorachi-gun County in Ishikari Province in 1869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、この空知郡は内陸部に位置し物資の輸送等が困難であったことから海岸近くへの移転を申し入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this Sorachi-gun being located in the midland, and causing difficulty in transporting goods, Naonori made a request of relocation near the coast.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the Sorachi-gun County was located inland, which caused difficulty in transporting goods for example, Kuninao applied for permission to be relocated to a coastal area.</e>
<cmt>人名の誤訳・表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the Sorachi-gun County was located inland, which caused difficulty in transporting goods for example, Kuninao applied for permission to be relocated to a coastal area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>叶わず再度家老の吾妻謙が太政官に申し入れたところ、今度は不届きを理由に吾妻が自宅謹慎を命ぜられる始末であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it was not accepted, Ken AZUMA, a karo (chief retainer) appealed to the Dajokan again, which brought him house arrest because of his outrageous behavior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the application for relocation was not accepted, Ken AZUMA who was karo (chief retainer) appealed to Daijokan (Grand Council of State) again, which brought him to house arrest on the ground of his unscrupulous behavior.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the application for relocation was not accepted, Ken AZUMA who was karo (chief retainer) appealed to Daijokan (Grand Council of State) again, which brought him to house arrest on the ground of his unscrupulous behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>その年の12月、邦直は家臣に命じ現地を調査させ、その結果を元に翌年自ら北海道に渡り調査を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December in the same year Naonori, having ordered his vassals to have a close look at the place, visited Hokkaido and made research based on the results himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December in the same year, Kuninao, having ordered his vassals to conduct a field survey in advance, visited Hokkaido himself the following year and conducted a field investigation based on the results of the preceding survey.</e>
<cmt>人名誤訳・表現を修正のうえ、訳漏れ箇所を加筆しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December in the same year, Kuninao, having ordered his vassals to conduct a field survey in advance, visited Hokkaido himself the following year and conducted a field investigation based on the results of the preceding survey.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>政府から指定された入植地は極めて大雑把な指定であって具体的に何処を開拓するかは現地機関である開拓使との交渉が必要だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place for immigration specified by the government was quite a broad one, therefore, negotiation with the Hokkaido Development Commissioner in a local organization was required of as to the exact place to develop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the government&apos;s specification of the settlement site was quite sketchy, they needed to negotiate with the Hokkaido Development Commissioner which was the local government, as to the exact place to develop.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the government&apos;s specification of the settlement site was quite sketchy, they needed to negotiate with the Hokkaido Development Commissioner which was the local government, as to the exact place to develop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>空知郡では開拓の見込みが立たないことから、交渉の末厚田郡繋富（シップ・石狩市厚田区聚富）の荷揚場を借用する事が認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sorachi-gun was no promising place for reclamation, therefore, he gained permission after negotiation to borrow a landing place in Ship in Atsuta-gun (Ship Atsuta-ku, Ishikari City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sorachi-gun County was no promising place for land reclamation, and therefore, he negotiated and gained permission to borrow a landing place in Shippu, Atsuta-gun County (present-day Shippu, Atsuta-ku Ward, Ishikari City).</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記・形式・用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sorachi-gun County was no promising place for land reclamation, and therefore, he negotiated and gained permission to borrow a landing place in Shippu, Atsuta-gun County (present-day Shippu, Atsuta-ku Ward, Ishikari City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>岩出山で希望者を募り1871年（明治4年）3月2日に北海道へ向けて出発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He recruited applicants in Iwadeyama and left for Hokkaido on March 2, 1871.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He recruited those who are interested in Iwadeyama and left for Hokkaido on March 2, 1871.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He recruited those who are interested in Iwadeyama and left for Hokkaido on March 2, 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>移住者は約180人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of immigrants was about 180.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of immigrants was about 180.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of immigrants was about 180.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、繋富は土質が悪く砂地が多いため作物は育たなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ship had such a bad type of soil and a lot of sandy areas that crops did not grow well there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shippu had such a bad type of soil and a lot of sandy areas that crops did not grow well there.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shippu had such a bad type of soil and a lot of sandy areas that crops did not grow well there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>船で運んだ食糧等も着かなかったため、一同は困窮を極め開拓使に嘆願したところ、同地を視察に訪れた開拓使長官東久世通禧より開拓地を移ることを許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because they could not get the shipped food supply, they were in extreme poverty; therefore, they pleaded to the Development Commissioner and got permission from Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE, the chief of Hokkaido Development Commissioner to move to another outpost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the shipped food supply did not reach them, Kuninao&apos;s party were in extreme poverty and pleaded to the Hokkaido Development Commission, thereby getting permission to relocate the reclamation site from Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE, Hokkaido Development Commissioner, who came to inspect Shippu.</e>
<cmt>表現・用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the shipped food supply did not reach them, Kuninao&apos;s party were in extreme poverty and pleaded to the Hokkaido Development Commission, thereby getting permission to relocate the reclamation site from Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE, Hokkaido Development Commissioner, who came to inspect Shippu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>吾妻謙等に代替地の調査を命じたところ、当別が適しているとの結論に至り、開拓使より許可を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ordered Ken AZUMA to find an alternate place, concluded from his survey that Tobetsuu was a suitable place, and got permission from the Hokkaido Development Comissioner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuninao ordered Ken AZUMA and others to find an alternate place, and concluded based on their survey that Tobetsu was suitable, and got permission for relocation from the Hokkaido Development Commission.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記・表現・用語を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuninao ordered Ken AZUMA and others to find an alternate place, and concluded based on their survey that Tobetsu was suitable, and got permission for relocation from the Hokkaido Development Commission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>当別への移転は1872年（明治5年）を予定し、邦直は岩出山に戻り再度移住者を募った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having made a plan of relocating to Tobetsu in 1872, Kuninao returned to Iwadeyama to recruit immigrants again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having made a plan of relocating the site to Tobetsu in 1872, Kuninao returned to Iwadeyama to recruit immigrants to Hokkaido again.</e>
<cmt>表現を補足修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having made a plan of relocating the site to Tobetsu in 1872, Kuninao returned to Iwadeyama to recruit immigrants to Hokkaido again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>第2回の移住者は182人で第一陣と合流し当別の開拓に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second-time immigrants were 182 in number and, after having joined the first party, engaged in the reclamation of Tobetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pioneers of the second immigration were 182 in number and, after having joined the first party, engaged in developing Tobetsu.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pioneers of the second immigration were 182 in number and, after having joined the first party, engaged in developing Tobetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1879年（明治12年）の第3回移住者は250人に及び、これも邦直が募集に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third-time immigrants in 1879 reached 250 in number, and again Kuninao took charge of recruiting them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pioneers of the third immigration in 1879, reached 250 in number, and again, Kuninao took charge of recruiting them.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pioneers of the third immigration in 1879, reached 250 in number, and again, Kuninao took charge of recruiting them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、この年当別では新たに戸長を設ける事となり元家老の吾妻謙が就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that year it was newly decided that Tobetsu needed a kocho (head official of the settlement), and Ken AZUMA, the former Karo, took the job.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that year it was newly decided that Tobetsu needed a kocho (head official of the settlement), and Ken AZUMA, the former Karo, took the job.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that year it was newly decided that Tobetsu needed a kocho (head official of the settlement), and Ken AZUMA, the former Karo, took the job.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>開拓使当別詰所設置に伴い邦直は同年7月に開拓七等属・開拓使勧業課当別在勤を命ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the establishment of the Development Commissioner Tobetsu Office, Kuninao was appointed official in a &quot;Kaitaku-nanatozoku/kaitakushi-kangyo-ka-Tobetsu Service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon establishment of the Development Commissioner Tobetsu Office, Kuninao was appointed official of &quot;Kaitaku-nanatozoku, kaitakushi-kangyo-ka-Tobetsu-zaikin&quot; (literally, Development 7th grade, Industry Encouragement Service at Tobetsu, Development Commission).</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon establishment of the Development Commissioner Tobetsu Office, Kuninao was appointed official of &quot;Kaitaku-nanatozoku, kaitakushi-kangyo-ka-Tobetsu-zaikin&quot; (literally, Development 7th grade, Industry Encouragement Service at Tobetsu, Development Commission).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>1881年（明治14年）2月26日准陸軍少尉に任命され、3月には開拓七等属兼務となり従六位に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 26, 1881 he was appointed sub-second army lieutenant with an additional post of Kaitaku-nanatozoku in March, and was given Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 26, 1881, he was appointed sub-second army lieutenant, and an additional post of Kaitaku-nanatozoku (literally, Development 7th grade) in March, and was given Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank).</e>
<cmt>補足しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 26, 1881, he was appointed sub-second army lieutenant, and an additional post of Kaitaku-nanatozoku (literally, Development 7th grade) in March, and was given Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1882年（明治15年）には所属が陸軍省となり、1885年（明治18年）5月陸軍屯田兵少尉になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1882 his position was changed into the Ministry of Army, and in 1885 he became a second ex-legionary lieutenant in the army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1882, his position was changed into the Ministry of Army, and in May, 1885, he became a second ex-legionary lieutenant in the army.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを加筆修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1882, his position was changed into the Ministry of Army, and in May, 1885, he became a second ex-legionary lieutenant in the army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>以後も各開墾地の見分を行うが、1891年（明治24年）1月逝去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after that he conducted field research of reclaimed land in various places, but passed away in 1891.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after that he conducted a field research of reclaimed land in various places, but passed away in January, 1891.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを加筆修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after that he conducted a field research of reclaimed land in various places, but passed away in January, 1891.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>子の基理も同年5月逝去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child 基理 also died in the same year.</e>
<cmt>*基理 Motomachi, Motori不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His child 基理 also died in May in the same year.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを加筆修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His child 基理 also died in May in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>翌年8月旧臣等が内務省に阿蘇神社（後の当別神社）創建を願い出て、邦直が祀られる事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August, the next year, his old retainers made a request to the Department of Interior to found Aso-jinja Shrine (later Tobetsu Shrine) to enshrine Kuninao.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August the next year, Kuninao&apos;s old retainers made a request to the Ministry of Home Affairs to found Aso-jinja Shrine (the future Tobetsu-jinja Shrine), thereby enshrining Kuninao.</e>
<cmt>曖昧さ回避・用語・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August the next year, Kuninao&apos;s old retainers made a request to the Ministry of Home Affairs to found Aso-jinja Shrine (the future Tobetsu-jinja Shrine), thereby enshrining Kuninao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>同年10月には孫の正人が邦直の北海道開拓に掛る功績により男爵を授けられ華族に列せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December, next year his grandchild, Masato was bestowed baronage due to Kuninao&apos;s achievements in developing Hokkaido, and was raised to the peerage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October the next year his grandchild, Masato, was conferred the Baronage on the ground of Kuninao&apos;s achievements in developing Hokkaido and was thus raised to the peerage.</e>
<cmt>誤訳・表現・文法・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October the next year his grandchild, Masato, was conferred the Baronage on the ground of Kuninao&apos;s achievements in developing Hokkaido and was thus raised to the peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1915年（大正4年）11月には邦直に正五位が追贈される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, 1915 posthumous Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) was conferred on Kuninao.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1915, a court rank of Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) was conferred posthumously on Kuninao.</e>
<cmt>表現・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1915, a court rank of Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank) was conferred posthumously on Kuninao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1940年（昭和15年）、皇紀2600年を記念し北海道開拓神社に合祀される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1940, in commemoration of 2600 year of the Imperial reign he was also enshrined in Hokkaido Kaitaku Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1940, in commemoration of 2600 years of the Imperial reign Kuninao was enshrined in Hokkaido Kaitaku-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>表現・文法・形式を修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1940, in commemoration of 2600 years of the Imperial reign Kuninao was enshrined in Hokkaido Kaitaku-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mutimaro(id:164721), BAKU(id:55205), 下総大納言(id:43461), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), トメぞう(id:194000), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>