<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土御門有脩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arisue TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arisue TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arisue TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>土御門 有脩（つちみかど ありすえ、大永7年（1527年） - 天正5年1月2日 (旧暦)（1577年1月20日））は、室町時代から安土桃山時代の公卿・陰陽家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arisue TSUCHIMIKADO (1527-January 20, 1577) was a Kugyo (the top court official) and Inyoka (the Yin and Yang school of philosophy) who lived from the Muromachi period to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arisue TSUCHIMIKADO (1527-January 20, 1577) was a Kugyo (top court official) and Inyoka (a practitioner of the Yin and Yang school of philosophy) who lived from the Muromachi Period to the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arisue TSUCHIMIKADO (1527-January 20, 1577) was a Kugyo (top court official) and Inyoka (a practitioner of the Yin and Yang school of philosophy) who lived from the Muromachi Period to the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>堂上家（家格は、半家 (公家)・阿倍氏）である、土御門家の30代目当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the thirtieth family head of the TSUCHIMIKADO family which was Tosho-ke (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks) (the social standing was hange (kuge), kuge of lower rank and the ABE clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the thirtieth family head of the TSUCHIMIKADO family which was Tosho-ke, or the hereditary lineage of court nobles occupying relatively high ranks, of which the social standing was hange (kuge), kuge of lower rank and the ABE clan.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 30th family head of the Tsuchimikado family which was Tosho-ke, or the hereditary lineage of court nobles occupying relatively high ranks, of which the social standing was hange (kuge), kuge of lower rank and the Abe clan.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更大文字表記を頭文字のみ大文字に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>陰陽頭（非参議従二位）・土御門有春の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the child of Ariharu TSUCHIMIKADO, Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Bureau of Divination) (non-Councilor, Junii (Junior Second Court Rank)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of Ariharu TSUCHIMIKADO, Onmyo no kami (Director of the Onmyoryo, or Bureau of Divination), who was also a non-Councilor, Junii (Junior Second Court Rank).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of Ariharu TSUCHIMIKADO, Onmyo no kami (Director of the Onmyoryo, or Bureau of Divination), who was also Hisangi (advisor at large), Junii (Junior Second Court Rank).</e>
<cmt>非参議の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>実子に陰陽頭（非参議従三位）土御門久脩、准大臣・勧修寺晴豊の室（勧修寺光豊の母）らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His biological children included Hisanaga TSUCHIMIKADO, Onmyo no kami (non-Councilor, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)) and the wife of Haretoyo KAJUJI (the mother of Mitsutoyo KAJUJI.), Jun-daijin (Vice Minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His biological children included Hisanaga TSUCHIMIKADO, Onmyo no kami, non-Councilor, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), and the wife of Haretoyo KAJUJI (the mother of Mitsutoyo KAJUJI), Jun-daijin (Vice Minister).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His biological children included Hisanaga TSUCHIMIKADO, Onmyo no kami, Hisangi, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), and the wife of Haretoyo KAJUJI (the mother of Mitsutoyo KAJUJI), Jun-daijin (Vice Minister).</e>
<cmt>non-Councilor→Hisangi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>官途は、陰陽頭、刑部卿・従三位（非参議）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His kanto (government service) was Onmyo no kami, Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice), Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) (non-Councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His government service was as Onmyo no kami, Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice), Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), non-Councilor.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His government service was as Onmyo no kami, Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice), Jusanmi, Hisangi.</e>
<cmt>non-Councilor→Hisangi従三位の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>