<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>岩野平三郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heizaruro IWANO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heizaburo IWANO</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heizaburo IWANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>岩野 平三郎（いわの へいざぶろう）は和紙職人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heizaruro IWANO is a papermaker of traditional Japanese paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heizaburo IWANO is a maker of traditional Japanese washi paper.</e>
<cmt>Spelling Revised to make more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heizaburo IWANO is a maker of traditional Japanese washi paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>福井県出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>立命館大学経済学部卒業後紙漉きの修行に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">College of Economics, Ritsumeikan University, he commenced training of papermaking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After graduating from Ritsumeikan University&apos;s Department of Economics, he began studying papermaking.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After graduating from Ritsumeikan University&apos;s Department of Economics, he began studying papermaking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1975年福井県無形民俗文化財の指定を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1975, he was designated as Fukui Prefecture intangible folk cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1975, he was designated a Fukui Prefecture intangible folk cultural property.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1975, he was designated as a Fukui prefectural intangible folk cultural property.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1979年第3代岩野平三郎を襲名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1979, he succeeded to Heizaburo IWANO&apos;s name as the third one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1979, he became the third person to use the name Heizaburo IWANO.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1979, he succeeded to the third Heizaburo IWANO.</e>
<cmt>一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1982年桂離宮の「昭和の大修理」に使われた越前和紙を漉きあげ、吉田五十八記念芸術振興財団特別賞受賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1982, he made Echizen washi (Japanese paper made in former Echizen province) used for &quot;Showa no Daishuri (literally, large scale repair works in Showa)&quot; of Katsura Imperial Villa and received a special award from Yoshida Isohachi Kinen Geijutsu Shinko Zaidan [吉田五十八記念芸術振興財団 英語による名称不明].</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received a special award from the Yoshida Isoya Memorial Foundation for Promoting the Arts (Yoshida Isoya Kinen Geijutsu Shinko Zaidan) for the Echizen washi (paper made in the former Echizen province) he made for the 1982 &quot;Showa no Daishuri&quot; (literally, &quot;large scale repairs of the Showa period&quot;)&quot; of Katsura Imperial Villa.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received a special award from the Yoshida Isoya Memorial Foundation for Promoting the Arts (Yoshida Isoya Kinen Geijutsu Shinko Zaidan) for the Echizen washi (paper made in the former Echizen province) he made for the 1982 &apos;Showa no Daishuri&apos; (literally, &apos;large scale repairs of the Showa period&apos;)&apos; of Katsura Imperial Villa.</e>
<cmt>&quot; を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>越前和紙古来の紙漉き模様である「打雲」「飛雲」「水玉」の技術を今に継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He inherited technique of traditional watermark of &quot;uchigumo (paper with a lying cloud),&quot; &quot;tobikumo (a flying cloud-like pattern appearing on indigo-blue and purple fiber-included paper)&quot; and mizutama-shi (waterdrop paper)［定訳不明,].</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continues to preserve the art of making traditional &quot;uchigumo (paper with a lying cloud), &quot;tobikumo&quot; (a flying cloud-like pattern on indigo-blue and purple paper) and &quot;mizutama&quot; (polkadot) Echizen washi patterns.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He inherited the art of making traditional &apos;uchigumo (paper with a lying cloud) &apos;, &apos;tobikumo (a flying cloud-like pattern on indigo-blue and purple paper) &apos;and &apos;mizutama (polka dot)&apos; Echizen washi patterns.</e>
<cmt>&quot; を &apos; に変更しました。一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その手によって漉かれた紙は、平山郁夫画伯、東山魁夷画伯といった多くの日本画家に愛用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Papers made by him are used habitually many Japanese-style painters including Ikuo HIRAYAMA and Kaii HIGASHIYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His paper is regularly used by many Japanese-style painters, including Ikuo HIRAYAMA and Kaii HIGASHIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His paper is regularly used by many Japanese-style painters, including Ikuo HIRAYAMA and Kaii HIGASHIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 0null0(id:582), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>