<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鈴木馬左也</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaya SUZUKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaya SUZUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaya SUZUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鈴木 馬左也（すずき まさや、文久元年2月24日 (旧暦)（1861年4月3日） - 大正11年（1922年）12月25日）は、第三代住友総理事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaya SUZUKI (April 3, 1861 - December 25, 1922) was the third general director of Sumitomo Group.</e>
<cmt>「総理事」の訳：google booksで&quot;shunnosuke furuta sumitomo&quot;で検索（古田俊之助は第7代総理事）→&quot;Corporate Financing and Governance in Japan: The Road to the Future&quot;のp.71に&quot;general director&quot;とあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaya SUZUKI (April 3, 1861 - December 25, 1922) was the third general director of Sumitomo Group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaya SUZUKI (April 3, 1861 - December 25, 1922) was the third general director of Sumitomo Group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>文久元年（1861年）2月24日、高鍋藩家老の父秋月種節（たねよ）と久子の四男として、日向国高鍋（現・宮崎県児湯郡高鍋町）で生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzuki was born as the fourth son of Taneyo Akizuki, who was Karo (chief retainer) of Takanabe Domain, and his wife Hisako in Takanabe, Hyuga Province (present-day Takanabe-cho, Koyu County, Miyazaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>（）内の現住所：用語統一リスト（2009/8/5)に従いました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the fourth son of Karo (chief retainer) of the Takanabe clan, Taneyo Akizuki and his wife Hisako in Takanabe, Hyuga Province (present Takanabe-cho, Koyu County, Miyazaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the fourth son of Karo (chief retainer) of the Takanabe clan, Taneyo Akizuki and his wife Hisako in Takanabe, Hyuga Province (present Takanabe-cho, Koyu County, Miyazaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>明治元年、母方の大叔父鈴木翔房（たかふさ）が七五歳で没し、その養子衞房（もりふさ）も戊申の役に加わり、27歳で戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1868, maternal grand-uncle Takafusa SUZUKI died at age 75, and his adopted son Morifusa who joined Boshin War also died in the battlefield at age 27.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1868, his maternal grand-uncle Takafusa SUZUKI died at the age of 75, and Takafusa&apos;s adopted son Morifusa also died in the battle of the Boshin War at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一、わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1868, his maternal grand-uncle Takafusa SUZUKI died at the age of 75, and Takafusa&apos;s adopted son Morifusa also died in the battle of the Boshin War at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>翌2年、馬左也は鈴木家再興のため、戦死した衞房の養子となり同家を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869, Masaya was registered as an adopted child of war-dead Morifusa to rebuild Suzuki family and inherit the family headship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869, Masaya was registered as an adopted child of the war-dead Morifusa to rebuild the Suzuki family and inherit the family headship.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869, Masaya was registered as an adopted child of the war-dead Morifusa to rebuild the Suzuki family and inherit the family headship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>明治９年旧制宮崎中学を卒業し、同年金沢の啓明学校へ入学した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1876, he finished Miyazaki Junior High School under the old system of education and enrolled to Keimei School in Kanazawa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1876, he finished Miyazaki Junior High School under the old system of education and enrolled to Keimei School in Kanazawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1876, he finished Miyazaki Junior High School under the old system of education and enrolled to Keimei School in Kanazawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>だが翌年退学、11年から東京帝国大学予備門に入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Suzuki withdrew from Keimei school next year and began to learn at Preparatory School of Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he withdrew from Keimei School the next year and in 1878 entered the preparatory school of Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>数字漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he withdrew from Keimei School the next year and in 1878 entered the preparatory school of Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明治20年、27歳で東京大学を卒業すると内務省 (日本)に入り、22年愛媛県書記官として赴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1887, he graduated from Tokyo University and joined Ministry of Home Affairs at the age of 27, then he was transferred to Ehime Prefecture as a secretary.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1887 he graduated from Tokyo University at the age of 27 and joined the Ministry of Home Affairs, and in 1889 he was transferred to Ehime Prefecture as secretary.</e>
<cmt>数字漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1887 he graduated from Tokyo University at the age of 27 and joined the Ministry of Home Affairs, and in 1889 he was transferred to Ehime Prefecture as secretary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌年別子銅山開坑200年祭に来賓として新居浜に招かれ、住友との最初の出会いをはたす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1888, Suzuki was invited to the 200-year anniversary of the opening of Besshi-dozan Copper mine held in Nihama as a guest, which became his first encounter with Sumitomo Group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year he was invited to the 200th anniversary of the opening of the Besshi Copper Mine held in Niihama as a guest, which became his first encounter with the House of Sumitomo.</e>
<cmt>数字間違い、訳語選択ミスがあります。「新居浜」はNiihama。「住友」は住友家のことで、住友関連ホームページ表記に従います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year he was invited to the 200th anniversary of the opening of the Besshi Copper Mine held in Niihama as a guest, which became his first encounter with the House of Sumitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>明治29年1896年、農商務省 (日本)参事官を退官し、住友に入社、大阪本店の副支配人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1896, Suzuki resigned as a counselor of Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce to join Sumitomo Group as an assistant manager of Osaka headquarters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1896, he resigned as counselor of the Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce (Japan) to enter a company of the House of Sumitomo, and became assistant manager of the head office of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1896, he resigned as counselor of the Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce (Japan) to enter a company of the House of Sumitomo, and became assistant manager of the head office of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>明治32年（1899年）別子鉱業所支配人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1899, he became manager of Besshi Kogyo-sho (Besshi mining industry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1899, he became manager of Besshi Kogyo-sho (Sumitomo Copper Plant of Besshi).</e>
<cmt>固有名詞は住友金属ホームページに従います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1899, he became manager of Besshi Kogyo-sho (Sumitomo Copper Plant of Besshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>伊庭貞剛の別子大造林計画を継承し大正6年（1917年）から北海道北見から、九州宮崎県の椎葉村まで山林事業を起こし、また朝鮮の国有林にまで植林を敢行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inheriting Besshi great afforestation plan originally launched by Teigo IBA, Suzuki started forestation business in 1917 from Kitami in Hokkaido down to Shiba Village in Miyazaki Prefecture in Kyushu, and further extended afforestation to national forest in Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took over the project of planting a forest of Besshi originally launched by Teigo IBA, and in 1917 started afforestation business from Kitami in Hokkaido down to Shiiba Village of Miyazaki Prefecture in Kyushu, and further extended afforestation business to the national forest in Korea.</e>
<cmt>「椎葉」はShiiba。わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took over the project of planting a forest of Besshi originally launched by Teigo IBA, and in 1917 started afforestation business from Kitami in Hokkaido down to Shiiba Village of Miyazaki Prefecture in Kyushu, and further extended afforestation business to the national forest in Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>大正2年新居浜の煙害問題解決のひとつとして住友肥料製造所（現、住友化学）を開設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1913, Suzuki founded Sumitomo Hiryo Seizo-sho (Sumitomo fertilizer manufacturing, current Sumitomo Chemical) as a part of effort to solve Nihama&apos;s air pollution problem by smoke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1913, Suzuki founded Sumitomo Hiryo Seizo-sho (Sumitomo Fertilizer Factory, current Sumitomo Chemical) as a measure to control Niihama&apos;s smoke pollution.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1913, Suzuki founded Sumitomo Hiryo Seizo-sho (Sumitomo Fertilizer Factory, current Sumitomo Chemical) as a measure to control Niihama&apos;s smoke pollution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>明治37年（1904年）第三代総理事に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before that year, Suzuki was already appointed as the third general director in 1904.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before that year, Suzuki was already appointed as the third general director in 1904.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before that year, Suzuki was already appointed as the third general director in 1904.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>明治44年住友電線製造所（現、住友電工）を設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1911, he founded Sumitomo Densen Seizo-sho (Sumitomo electric wire manufacturing, current Sumitomo Electric Industries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1911, he founded Sumitomo Densen Seizo-sho (Sumitomo Electric Wire and Cable Works, current Sumitomo Electric Industries).</e>
<cmt>固有名詞は住友電工ホームページに従います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1911, he founded Sumitomo Densen Seizo-sho (Sumitomo Electric Wire and Cable Works, current Sumitomo Electric Industries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>明治45年には伸銅場（現、住友金属・住友軽金属）で継ぎ目なし鋼管の製造に着手し、海軍の復水管需要に応える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1912, he started the production of seamless steel pipes in Sumitomo Shindo-jo (Sumitomo copper processing, current Sumitomo Metals and Sumitomo Light Metal Industries) to meet with demand of condensate pipes from navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1912, he started the production of seamless steel pipes in Sumitomo Shindo-jo (Sumitomo Copper Plant, current Sumitomo Metals and Sumitomo Light Metal Industries) to meet the demand of the navy&apos;s condensation pipes.</e>
<cmt>固有名詞は住友金属ホームページに従います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1912, he started the production of seamless steel pipes in Sumitomo Shindo-jo (Sumitomo Copper Plant, current Sumitomo Metals and Sumitomo Light Metal Industries) to meet the demand of the navy&apos;s condensation pipes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大正2年（1913年）住友肥料製造所（現住友化学）を設立し、同8年大阪の臨海工業地帯建設のために大阪北港（後の、住友土地工務）を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1913, Suzuki founded Sumitomo Hiryo Seizo-sho (Sumitomo fertilizer manufacturing, current Sumitomo Chemical), followed by the foundation of Osaka Kita-ko (Osaka north port, subsequent Sumitomo Land and Construction) in 1919.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1913 he founded Sumitomo Hiryo Seizo-sho (current Sumitomo Chemical), and in 1919 built Osaka Hokko (the North Port of Osaka, the predecessor of Sumitomo Land and Construction) for the coastal industrial areas of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ、固有名詞読み間違いがあります。「北港」はHokko。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1913 he founded Sumitomo Hiryo Seizo-sho (current Sumitomo Chemical), and in 1919 built Osaka Hokko (the North Port of Osaka, the predecessor of Sumitomo Land and Construction) for the coastal industrial areas of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>さらに同年、別子鉱山の電源開発を目的に土佐吉野川水力電気（後の住友共同電力）、宮崎県の椎葉植林に関係して耳川の水利権を確保した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that year, Suzuki further founded Tosa Yoshino-gawa Suiryoku Denki (Tosa Yoshino-gawa river hydroelectric, subsequent Sumitomo Joint Electric Power), as well as the acquisition of water right of Mimikawa river in connection with the afforestation in Shiba, Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>土佐吉野川水力電気（設立？）（四国）と耳川水利権確保（九州）は別々の案件か不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that year, he also founded Tosa Yoshino-gawa Suiryoku Denki (Tosa Yoshino-gawa River Hydroelectric Power Plant, the predecessor of Sumitomo Joint Electric Power) for the development of the power supply in Besshi copper mine, and acquired the water right of Mimi-kawa River for the afforestation project in Shiiba, Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that year, he also founded Tosa Yoshino-gawa Suiryoku Denki (Tosa Yoshino-gawa River Hydroelectric Power Plant, the predecessor of Sumitomo Joint Electric Power) for the development of the power supply in Besshi copper mine, and acquired the water right of Mimi-kawa River for the afforestation project in Shiiba, Miyazaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これらが現在の四国・九州電力発足の遠因となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These played roles as an underlying cause of foundation of current Shikoku Electric Power and Kyushu Electric Power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those businesses became indirect causes of the foundations of current Shikoku Electric Power and of Kyushu Electric Power.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those businesses became indirect causes of the foundations of current Shikoku Electric Power and of Kyushu Electric Power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>大正7年日米板硝子（現、日本板硝子）を設立、同九年日本電気へ資本参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1918, Suzuki founded Nichibei Ita-garasu (Japan America Sheet Glass, current Nippon Sheet Glass), and since 1920 he had had a stake in NEC Corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1918, Suzuki founded Nichibei Ita-garasu (Japan America Sheet Glass, current Nippon Sheet Glass), and since 1920 he had had a stake in NEC Corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1918, Suzuki founded Nichibei Ita-garasu (Japan America Sheet Glass, current Nippon Sheet Glass), and since 1920 he had had a stake in NEC Corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また1921年には住友本店を合資会社に改組するなど、住友の発展の大いに貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1921 he reorganized Sumitomo headquarters into joint-stock company, thus Suzuki significantly contributed to the development of Sumitomo Group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As in 1921 he reorganized the head office of Sumitomo into a joint-stock company, he significantly contributed to the development of the Sumitomo Group.</e>
<cmt>訳語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As in 1921 he reorganized the head office of Sumitomo into a joint-stock company, he significantly contributed to the development of the Sumitomo Group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>秋月左都夫は兄にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satsuo Akizuki was Suzuki&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satsuo Akizuki was Suzuki&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satsuo Akizuki was Suzuki&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>商社設立禁止宣言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Declaration of Prohibition of Trading Firm Establishment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Declaration of Prohibition on Establishing Trading Company</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Declaration of Prohibition on Establishing Trading Company</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>住友には、戦前独立した商事部門がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitomo Group had no independent trading sector before the World War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumitomo Group had no independent trading sector before the World War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumitomo Group had no independent trading sector before the World War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>第一次世界大戦が勃発し、経済界は非常な好況期を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The outbreak of the World War I brought an unusual economic boom.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The outbreak of the World War I brought an unusual economic boom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The outbreak of the World War I brought an unusual economic boom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>大正7年（1918年）11月に休戦協定が成立した後も、輸出はますます活況を呈し、貿易商社は大きな収益を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the cease-fire agreement was concluded in November 1918, roaring export of Japan enabled trading companies to earn large profits.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the cease-fire agreement was concluded in November 1918, roaring export of Japan enabled trading companies to earn large profits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the cease-fire agreement was concluded in November 1918, roaring export of Japan enabled trading companies to earn large profits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これにより、多数の商社が続々と設立され貿易に乗り出していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This situation led to the continuous spout of companies and their getting into trading business.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This situation led to the continuous spout of companies and their getting into trading business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This situation led to the continuous spout of companies and their getting into trading business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>鈴木は、大正8年（1919年）3月、戦後の欧米の状況視察に外遊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzuki went abroad to inspect the postwar situation of the West in March, 1919.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suzuki went abroad to inspect the postwar situation of Europe and America in March, 1919.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suzuki went abroad to inspect the postwar situation of Europe and America in March, 1919.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その不在中に住友総本店幹部の間に、三井財閥、三菱財閥の隆盛に圧倒されていた状況もあって、住友も時流に乗って商事貿易に進出すべきであるとの意見が強まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his absence in Sumitomo general head office, executives began to argue that Sumitomo should join trading business along with the trend of the days, partly because they felt overwhelmed by emergence of Mitsui and Mitsubishi Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his absence, in the head office of Sumitomo, some executives began to insist that Sumitomo should start a trading business to keep up with the times, partly because they felt overwhelmed by the prosperities of the other conglomerates including the Mitsui-zaibatsu and the Mitsubishi-zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his absence, in the head office of Sumitomo, some executives began to insist that Sumitomo should start a trading business to keep up with the times, partly because they felt overwhelmed by the prosperities of the other conglomerates including the Mitsui-zaibatsu and the Mitsubishi-zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>幹部らは、「他所製品取り扱いの件」と題する、いわゆる商事会社設立構想の起案文書まで用意して、総理事の帰国を待った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Executives awaited return of general director, preparing a draft document about trading firm establishment plan titled &apos;Handling of Other Company&apos;s Products&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The executives waited the general director&apos;s return even preparing a draft of a framework for establishing a trading company titled &apos;Issue of Handling Other Company&apos;s Products.&apos;</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The executives waited the general director&apos;s return even preparing a draft of a framework for establishing a trading company titled &apos;Issue of Handling Other Company&apos;s Products.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>鈴木は欧米の視察を終えて帰途、大正9年（1920年）1月、上海市に立ち寄った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzuki completed his inspection in the West, and dropped by Shanghai City in January, 1920.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suzuki completed his visit to Europe and America, and dropped by Shanghai City in January, 1920.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suzuki completed his visit to Europe and America, and dropped by Shanghai City in January, 1920.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このとき住友上海洋行（支店）の支配人が、商事会社を設立することの必要性を力説し総本店の空気を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, manager of Sumitomo Shanghai-yoko (branch) strongly insisted the necessity of establishment of trading firm, and told Suzuki the mood of general head office.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the manager of Sumitomo Shanghai Yoko (branch) strongly insisted the necessity of the establishment of trading company, and told him the consensus of the head office.</e>
<cmt>訳語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the manager of Sumitomo Shanghai Yoko (branch) strongly insisted the necessity of the establishment of trading company, and told him the consensus of the head office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし鈴木は、これに同意しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Suzuki never agreed with that persuasion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Suzuki did not agree with that suggestion.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Suzuki did not agree with that suggestion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そればかりか、帰国すると直ちに関係者を呼び出し、厳しく商事の禁止を申し渡し、さらに主管者会議の席上「住友は絶対に商事はやってはならぬ」と宣言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Suzuki summoned the persons concerned as soon as he returned back to give them a strict order of prohibition from establishing trading firm, and declared at a supervisor&apos;s conference that Sumitomo absolutely must not have the trading firm.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he summoned the persons concerned as soon as he returned to Japan, and gave them a strict order of prohibition on establishing trading company, and declared at a supervisors&apos; conference that Sumitomo must not begin any trading business.</e>
<cmt>訳語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he summoned the persons concerned as soon as he returned to Japan, and gave them a strict order of prohibition on establishing trading company, and declared at a supervisors&apos; conference that Sumitomo must not begin any trading business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これが大正9年（1920年）1月の「商社設立禁止宣言」であり、戦後、商社が開設されるまで、住友では商社開設が禁句になってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this &apos;Declaration of Prohibition of Trading Firm Establishment&apos; issued in January 1920, establishment of trading firm became taboo until it opened after the World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was the &apos;Declaration of Prohibition on Establishing Trading Company&apos; of January, 1920, and since then nobody had said about establishment of trading company as taboo until a actual trading company of Sumitomo was opened after the World War II.</e>
<cmt>訳語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was the &apos;Declaration of Prohibition on Establishing Trading Company&apos; of January, 1920, and since then nobody had said about establishment of trading company as taboo until a actual trading company of Sumitomo was opened after the World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>三井・三菱が商いから身をたてたのに比較して、住友は別子銅山を中心に製造業で伸びてきた違いがあり、商事部門に対する見方が狭かったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitomo, which had developed thanks to the manufacturing industries focusing on Besshi-dozan Copper mine, had a narrow outlook on trading section, compared with Mitsui and Mitsubishi that had set themselves up from merchantry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike Mitsui and Mitsubishi which had developed from trading, Sumitomo had developed from industries, mainly Besshi copper mine, and had been biased against trading company.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike Mitsui and Mitsubishi which had developed from trading, Sumitomo had developed from industries, mainly Besshi copper mine, and had been biased against trading company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>このため、昭和20年に日本建設産業（現住友商事）が設立されるまで、四半世紀ものあいだ住友では、商社開設はタブーとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, establishment of trading firm was under taboo for almost quarter-century until Nippon Kensetsu Sangyo (current Sumitomo Corporation) was finally founded in 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, among Sumitomo, establishing trading company had been under taboo for almost a quarter of the century until Nippon Kensetsu Sangyo (current Sumitomo Corporation) was finally founded in 1945.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, among Sumitomo, establishing trading company had been under taboo for almost a quarter of the century until Nippon Kensetsu Sangyo (current Sumitomo Corporation) was finally founded in 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BBG(id:124711), Pica(id:9502), 松茸(id:27535), ウィキウィ2(id:83093), Complex01(id:10454), IwaimBot(id:190695), Component(id:146478), YukkeBot2(id:251491), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>