<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>織田信孝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutaka ODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutaka ODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutaka ODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>織田 信孝（おだ のぶたか）は、安土桃山時代の武将・大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutaka ODA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutaka ODA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord)of the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutaka ODA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord)of the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>織田氏の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from a family of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from a branch of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from a branch of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>伊勢国中部を支配する豪族神戸氏を継いだため、神戸 信孝（かんべ のぶたか）とも称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded the Kanbe clan,a local ruling family,which ruled middle region of Ise province,calling himself also Nobutaka KANBE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the successor of the Kanbe clan, a local ruling family, which ruled the middle region of Ise province, and so he also called himself Nobutaka KANBE.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, article, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the successor of the Kanbe clan, a local ruling family, which ruled the middle region of Ise Province, and so he also called himself Nobutaka KANBE.</e>
<cmt>Province を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>信長存命中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Nobunaga was alive</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Nobunaga&apos;s Lifetime</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Nobunaga&apos;s lifetime</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>永禄元年（1558年）、織田信長の三男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1558,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1558,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1558, he was born as the third son of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>２つに分かれていたセルを一つにまとめ、英文も修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>母は側室の坂氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a concubine Saka family (it was likely to be a branch family of Ise Kabuto family or a relative of Owari Senshu clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a concubine from the Saka family (likely a branch family of the Ise Kabuto family or related to the Owari Senshu clan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a concubine from the Saka clan.</e>
<cmt>セルを二つに分け、英文もそのように編集しました。family→ clan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（伊勢鹿伏兎氏庶流あるいは尾張千秋氏の所縁か。また『一豊公御武功記』によると二宮一楽斎が信孝母方祖父とされている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;tales of Kazutoyo&apos;s military exploits&quot;,Ichirakusai NINOMIYA was Nobutaka&apos;s maternal grandfather).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Tales of Kazutoyo&apos;s Military Exploits&quot;, Ichirakusai NINOMIYA was Nobutaka&apos;s maternal grandfather).</e>
<cmt>Capitalization, space inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(She was likely from a branch family of the Ise Kabuto clan or related to the Owari Senshu clan; according to &quot;Tales of Kazutoyo&apos;s Military Exploits,&quot; Ichirakusai NINOMIYA was Nobutaka&apos;s maternal grandfather.)</e>
<cmt>セルを二つに分け、英文もそのように編集しました。family→ clan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幼名は三七（3月7日生まれだったためとも）と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said his childhood name was Sanshichi (possibly from being born on March 7).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his childhood name was Sanshichi (possibly because he&apos;d been born on March 7).</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his childhood name was Sanshichi (literally, three and seven) (possibly because he&apos;d been born on March 7).</e>
<cmt>三七→literally, three and seven　とし、3月7日産まれであることと関連が分かるようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>実は次男織田信雄より数日先に生まれたが、母の身分が低く、また信長に報告するのが遅かったため、三男とされたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact was that he was born a few days earlier than the second son Nobukatsu ODA, but he was acknowledged as the third son possibly because his mother&apos;s status was low and his birth was reported late.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In actuality, he was born a few days earlier than Oda&apos;s second son, Nobukatsu ODA; however, possibly because his mother&apos;s status was low and because his birth was reported late, he was acknowledged as the third son.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In actuality, he was born a few days earlier than Oda&apos;s second son, Nobukatsu ODA; however, possibly because his mother&apos;s status was low and because his birth was reported late, he was acknowledged as the third son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし坂氏は伊勢国随一の豪族関氏平姓関氏の庶流鹿伏兎氏の庶流にあたり、けっして生駒氏に見劣りする出自ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However,his status by birth was not inferior to the Ikoma clan because Saka family was a branch family of Kabuto family,which was a branch family of the number one local ruling family of Ise province,the Seki clan Seki family originating from the Taira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his status by birth was not inferior to that of the Ikoma clan: the Saka family was a branch family of the Kabuto family, which was a branch family of the top local ruling family of Ise province, the Seki clan (which had originated from the Taira family).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his status by birth was not inferior to that of the Ikoma clan: the Saka clan was a branch family of the Kabuto clan, which was a branch family of the top local ruling clan of Ise Province, the Seki clan, which had originated from the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>family→ clan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>本来兄の信孝が信雄よりも信長亡き後の織田家一門の筆頭に相応しいという正嫡性の強調のため、あるいは兄である信雄に逆らったことを正当化するための意図的な創作話ではないかといわれ、実際は信孝が信雄より後に生まれたのではないかといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that such story was intentionally made up to emphasize Nobutaka&apos;s legitimacy of being the head of Oda family after Nobunaga&apos;s death or to justify his having opposed to Nobukatsu,and that he was actually born later than Nobukatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this story may have been intentionally made up to emphasize Nobutaka&apos;s legitimacy as the head of the Oda family after Nobunaga&apos;s death, or to justify his having opposed Nobukatsu, and that he actually was born later than Nobukatsu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this story may have been intentionally made up to emphasize Nobutaka&apos;s legitimacy as the head of the Oda family after Nobunaga&apos;s death, or to justify his having opposed Nobukatsu who was his older brother, and that he actually was born later than Nobukatsu.</e>
<cmt>「兄である」　の翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、信孝誕生を永禄元年（1558年）4月4日とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory has it that Nobutaka was born in April 4,1558.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory has it that Nobutaka was born on April 4,1558.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory has it that Nobutaka was born on May 2, 1558.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>生まれた場所は母方大叔父と言われる尾張衆（津島衆）の岡本良勝の屋敷とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born possibly at a residence of his maternal uncle Yoshikatsu OKAMOTO,people of Owari (people of Tsushima).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He may have been born at a residence belonging to his maternal uncle, Yoshikatsu OKAMOTO, of the Owari people (people of Tsushima).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He may have been born at a residence belonging to his maternal granduncle, Yoshikatsu OKAMOTO, of the Owari people (people of Tsushima).</e>
<cmt>大叔父→granduncle としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）、信長が伊勢国を平定した際に、降伏した神戸城（三重県鈴鹿市）城主・神戸具盛の養子となり、具盛が信長によって隠居させられた後の元亀3年（1572年）に神戸氏を継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1568,he was adopted by Tomomori KANBE,the castellan of Kanbe-jo Castle (Suzuka City, Mie Prefecture),when Nobunaga subdued Ise province and after Tomomori was forced to retire by Nobunaga,he took over the Kanbe clan in 1572.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1568, he was adopted by Tomomori KANBE, the lord of Kanbe-jo Castle (Suzuka City, Mie Prefecture); when Nobunaga subdued Ise province and forced Tomomori to retire, Nobutaka took over the Kanbe clan (in 1572).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutaka was adopted by Tomomori KANBE, the lord of Kanbe-jo Castle (Suzuka City, Mie Prefecture) which was surrendered when Nobunaga subdued Ise Province in 1568, and he took over the Kanbe clan in 1572 when Tomomori was forced to retire by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>一部語順を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>養子入りに際しては幸田彦右衛門が傳役として付けられ、信長家臣から岡本太郎右衛門、坂仙斎、三宅権右衛門、坂口縫殿助、山下三右衛門、末松吉左衛門、立木、河村以下の侍が信孝付きとして付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was adopted,Hikoemon KOUDA came along as Denyaku (adviser assigned directly by the shogun) and samurai such as Taroemon OKAMOTO,Sensai SAKA,Gonemon MIYAKE,Nuinosuke SAKAGUCHI,Sanemon YAMASHITA,Kichizaemon SUEMATSU,TACHIKI and KAWAMURA came to serve Nobutaka.</e>
<cmt>傳役（定訳不明です）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was adopted,Hikoemon KOUDA accompanied him as Denyaku (an adviser assigned directly by the shogun) and samurai such as Taroemon OKAMOTO, Sensai SAKA, Gonemon MIYAKE, Nuinosuke SAKAGUCHI, Sanemon YAMASHITA, Kichizaemon SUEMATSU, TACHIKI and KAWAMURA came to serve Nobutaka.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was adopted, Hikoemon KODA accompanied him as Denyaku (an adviser assigned directly by the shogun) and samurai who had been Nobunaga&apos;s vassals such as Taroemon OKAMOTO, Sensai SAKA, Gonemon MIYAKE, Nuinosuke SAKAGUCHI, Sanemon YAMASHITA, Kichizaemon SUEMATSU, TACHIKI and KAWAMURA came to serve Nobutaka.</e>
<cmt>Kouda →　Koda としました。信長家臣　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このほか関氏一族の関・峯・国府・鹿伏兎氏ら諸氏が与力とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the Seki clan,the Mine clan,,the Kokufu clan and the Kabuto clan of the Seki family were assigned as yoriki (a police sergeant).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Seki family&apos;s Seki, Mine, Kokufu and Kabuto clans were assigned as yoriki (police sergeants).</e>
<cmt>Word choice, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Seki clan&apos;s Seki, Mine, Kokufu and Kabuto clans were assigned as yoriki (police sergeants).</e>
<cmt>family→ clan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>相続後は神戸検地と呼ばれる検地を行い、城下に楽市楽座、伝馬制を敷くなど領地経営に力を注ぎ、神戸は伊勢参宮街道の宿場として大いに栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his succession,he introduced land survey called Kanbe land survey,Rakuichi-rakuza (Free markets and open guilds) near the castle and tenma (post horse) system,making Kanbe thrive as the posting station of Ise Shrine Pilgrimage Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his succession, Nobutaka introduced a land survey called the Kanbe land survey, rakuichi-rakuza (free markets and open guilds) near the castle and the tenma (post horse) system, and Kanbe thrived as a posting station on the Ise Shrine Pilgrimage Road.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his succession, Nobutaka put his efforts in the management of his territory such as introducing a land survey called the Kanbe land survey, rakuichi-rakuza (free markets and open guilds) near the castle and the tenma (post horse) system, and Kanbe thrived as a posting station on the Ise Shrine Pilgrimage Road.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>天正2年（1574年）から天正3年（1575年）にかけて、伊勢国長島一向一揆平定戦、越前一向一揆平定戦に参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between 1574 and 1575,he joined the battle to subdue Ise province Nagashima Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Nagashima) and Echizen ikko ikki(religious riot).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between 1574 and 1575, he joined the battle to subdue the Nagashima Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Nagashima) and Echizen ikko ikki(religious riot) in Ise province.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, articles, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between 1574 and 1575, he joined the battle to subdue the Nagashima Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Nagashima) in Ise Province and Echizen Ikko Ikki (religious riot).</e>
<cmt>province を大文字にしました。Ise Province を長島の後に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>天正5年（1577年）の紀州征伐、天正6年（1578年）には荒木村重討伐戦（有岡城の戦い）にも出陣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also joined the conquest of Kishu in 1577 and the subjugation of Murashige ARAKI (the battle of Arioka-jo Castle) in 1578.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also participated in the conquest of Kishu in 1577 and the subjugation of Murashige ARAKI (the battle of Arioka-jo Castle) in 1578.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also participated in the conquest of Kishu in 1577 and the subjugation of Murashige ARAKI (the battle of Arioka-jo Castle) in 1578.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>行政官としての活動もあり、天正8年（1580年）には村井貞勝を補佐して在京し禁裏との交渉にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also acted as executive officer and negotiated with Kinri (the Imperial Palace),helping Sadakatsu MURAI,staying in the capital in 1580.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he acted as an executive officer and, in 1580, stayed in the capital, assisting Sadakatsu MURAI and negotiating with the Kinri (the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>Word choice, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he acted as an executive officer and, in 1580, stayed in the capital, assisting Sadakatsu MURAI and negotiating with the Kinri (the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>同年7月、本願寺教如が退去するに際して誓詞を交わすため、信長を京に迎えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July of the same year,he greeted Nobunaga in the capital to make a vow with him when Kyonyo of Hongan-ji Temple retreated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July of the same year, when Kyonyo of Hongan-ji Temple retreated, Nobutaka greeted Nobunaga in the capital to make a vow with him.</e>
<cmt>Word order, punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August of the same year, when Kyonyo of Hongan-ji Temple retreated, Nobutaka greeted Nobunaga in the capital to make a vow with him.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>このころか丹波国、丹後国を所領として与えられたようであり、丹波衆、丹後衆に出した中国攻めの触書が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exists a furegaki (bakufu orders) of the attack on the Chugoku district issued to people of Tanba and Tango,indicating he was possibly given Tanba Province and Tango Province as his shoryo (territory) around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a furegaki (bakufu order) regarding the attack on Chugoku district which was issued to the people of Tanba and Tango, indicating that he may have been given Tanba Province and Tango Province as his shoryo (territory) around that time.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a furegaki (bakufu order) regarding the attack on Chugoku district which was issued to the people of Tanba and Tango, indicating that he may have been given Tanba Province and Tango Province as his shoryo (territory) around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>同時に伊勢では神戸城の拡張工事に着手、五層の天守閣や多数の櫓を持つ近世城郭を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He began expansion work of Kanbe-jo Castle in Ise Province at the same time,completing five-layered tenshukaku (keep or tower) and modern castles which have many turrets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He began expansion work on Kanbe-jo Castle in Ise Province at the same time, completing a five-story tenshukaku (keep or tower) and a modern castle with many turrets.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He began expansion work on Kanbe-jo Castle in Ise Province at the same time, completing a five-story tenshukaku (keep or tower) and a modern castle with many turrets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>天正10年（1582年）に四国征伐の総司令官に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582,he was assigned as a commander in chief of Shikoku Conquest (It is said Shikoku Conquest was put into practice due to his strong urge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, he was assigned as commander-in-chief of the Shikoku Conquest (which is said to have been executed due to his strong urging.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, he was assigned as commander-in-chief of the Shikoku Conquest.</e>
<cmt>原文を２つに分け、英文もそのように編集しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>（四国征伐は信孝の強い希望によって実現したともいう。神宮文庫所蔵文書には『三七様連々お望み候四国へ・・・』との文言のある文書が存在する。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exists a monjo (written material) including the wording&quot;Sanshichi sama went to Shikoku,which he had been wanted to for long time&quot;in The Jingu Library),</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a monjo (written document) which includes the words &quot;Sanshichi-sama went to Shikoku, which he had wanted to do for a long time&quot;in the Jingu Library).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is said to have been executed due to his strong urging, and there is a written document which includes the words &quot;Sanshichi-sama [Nobutaka] went to Shikoku, which he had wanted to do for a long time&quot; in the Jingu Library).</e>
<cmt>原文を２つに分け、英文もそのように編集しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>所領北伊勢、河曲・鈴鹿の二郡の15歳から60歳に至る名主・百姓を動員、牢人衆を召し抱え、伊賀・甲賀・雑賀の他国衆も集めて遠征軍を組織した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">mobilizing nanushi and peasants aged between 15 and 60 from Kawano-gun and Suzuka-gun which were in his territory north Ise,taking on ronin (samurai who left his master and lost his horoku [salary]),gathering people of Iga,Koka,Saiga,organizing the army of expedition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He mobilized village leaders and peasants aged between 15 and 60 from Kawano-gun and Suzuka-gun, which were in his territory of northern Ise, taking on ronin (samurai who had left their masters and lost their horoku [salary]), gathering people of Iga, Koka, and Saiga, and organizing the expedition army.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He mobilized village leaders and peasants aged between 15 and 60 from Kawano-gun and Suzuka-gun, which were in his territory of northern Ise, taking on ronin (samurai who had left their masters and lost their horoku [salary]), gathering people of Iga, Koka, and Saiga, and organizing the expedition army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>副将には織田氏の宿老丹羽長秀や従兄弟の津田信澄らを付された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assigned Nagahide NIWA,syukuro (a chief vassal of a samurai family) of Oda family,and his cousin Nobusumi TSUDA as vice-shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He appointed Nagahide NIWA as the Oda family&apos;s syukuro (a chief vassal of a samurai family), and his cousin Nobusumi TSUDA as vice-shogun.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He appointed Nagahide NIWA as the Oda family&apos;s shukuro (a chief vassal of a samurai family), and his cousin Nobusumi TSUDA as vice-shogun.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>なお、四国征伐にあたって、信孝は三好康長の養子になることが決定され、神戸具盛は再度神戸氏の当主扱いになったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shikoku Conquest,it was settled that Nobutaka was to be adopted by Yasunaga MIYOSHI,therefore,Tomomori KANBE was assumed as the family head of the Kanbe clan again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Shikoku Conquest it was decided that Nobutaka would be adopted by Yasunaga MIYOSHI, and so Tomomori KANBE was treated as the Kanbe clan&apos;s family head once more.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Shikoku Conquest it was decided that Nobutaka would be adopted by Yasunaga MIYOSHI, and so Tomomori KANBE was treated as the Kanbe clan&apos;s family head once more.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし、養子の話は破談となり、この際に新たに一家を興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However,it was broken off and he built Ikke (a title of the system, utsuro [family-related communities which existed in the late Muromachi period and the Azuchi-Momoyama period]) anew.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the adoption was broken off, and he took the opportunity to rebuild the Ikke (the name of a system [family-related communities which existed in the late Muromachi period and the Azuchi-Momoyama period]).</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the adoption was broken off, and he took the opportunity to build a new family.</e>
<cmt>一家を興す→build a new family としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>信長死後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga&apos;s death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga&apos;s death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga&apos;s death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>堺市にて渡海の準備中である6月2日に本能寺の変が勃発したが、逃亡兵が相次いだため積極的な行動はできず、明智光秀の娘婿である従兄弟の津田信澄を殺害した程度であった（しかし信澄が本能寺の変に加担した証拠は存在しない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 2,Honnoji Incident broke out while he was preparing to cross the sea in Sakai-City,but he only managed to kill Nobusumi TSUDA,who was a cousin of Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s son-in-law,restricted his act by a series of escaping soldiers (however,there is no evidence of Nobusumi&apos;s joining Honnoji Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 2, while he was preparing to cross the sea, the Honnoji Incident broke out in Sakai City, but he only managed to kill Nobusumi TSUDA, a cousin of Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s son-in-law, hampered by a series of escaping soldiers (however, there is no evidence that Nobusumi participated in the Honnoji Incident).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 1, while he was preparing to cross the sea, the Honnoji Incident broke out in Sakai City, but he only managed to kill Nobusumi TSUDA, his cousin and Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s son-in-law, hampered by a series of escaping soldiers (however, there is no evidence that Nobusumi participated in the Honnoji Incident).</e>
<cmt>津田信澄は信孝のいとこである、という表現に修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その後、摂津国富田 (高槻市)で「中国大返し」後の豊臣秀吉軍に合流、名目上の総大将として山崎の戦いに参戦し、仇である明智光秀を撃破した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that,he joined with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI,who had completed Chugoku Ogaeshi (the term refers to the reaction to Honnoji Incident by Hideyoshi Hashiba, in which he rushed back to Bichu even though he was in a battle with Mitsuhide Akechi in Yamazaki which is near the boundary between Settsu Province and Yamashiro Province when he learnt the news),in Tomita, Settsu Province (Takatsuki City),fighting in the battle of Yamazaki as a nominal supreme commander,defeating Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he joined forces with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who had completed the Chugoku Ogaeshi (the term refers to Hideyoshi&apos;s reaction to the Honnoji Incident, in which he rushed back to Bichu, even though he was fighting a battle with Mitsuhide Akechi in Yamazaki, near the boundary between Settsu Province and Yamashiro Province, when he learned the news) in Tomita, Settsu Province (Takatsuki City), and fought in the battle of Yamazaki as a nominal supreme commander, defeating Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he joined forces with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who had completed the &apos;Chugoku Ogaeshi&apos; (the term refers to Hideyoshi&apos;s reaction to the Honnoji Incident, in which he rushed back to Yamasaki, even though he had been fighting with the Mori clan in Bichu, when he learned the news) in Tomita, Settsu Province (Takatsuki City), and fought in the battle of Yamasaki as a nominal supreme commander, defeating Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>中国大返し→the term refers to Hideyoshi&apos;s reaction to the Honnoji Incident, in which he rushed back to Yamazaki, even though he had been fighting with the Mori clan in Bucchu, when he learned the news　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="34">
<j>信長の弔い合戦の総大将であったにも関わらず、清洲会議において織田氏の後継者は甥の織田秀信に決まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite his having been a supreme commander in the battle of Nobunaga&apos;s revenge,Hidenobu ODA was assigned as the successor to the Oda clan in the Kiyosu conference.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite his having been the supreme commander in the battle of Nobunaga&apos;s revenge, his nephew Hidenobu ODA was chosen as the Oda clan&apos;s successor in the Kiyosu conference.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite his having been the supreme commander in the battle of Nobunaga&apos;s revenge, his nephew Hidenobu ODA was chosen as the Oda clan&apos;s successor in the Kiyosu conference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>信孝は三法師の後見役として兄織田信忠の領地であった美濃国を与えられ、岐阜城主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutaka became the lord of Gifu-jo Castle,given Mino Province,which was the territory of his elder brother Nobutada ODA,as a conservator of Sanboshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the guardian of Sanboshi (Hidenobu), Nobutaka became the lord of Gifu-jo Castle and was given Mino Province, which was the territory of his elder brother Nobutada ODA.</e>
<cmt>Word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the guardian of Sanboshi (Hidenobu), Nobutaka became the lord of Gifu-jo Castle and was given Mino Province, which was the territory of his elder brother Nobutada ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>その後、秀吉と対立する柴田勝家に接近し、勝家と叔母のお市の方との婚儀を仲介した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that,he approached Katsuie SHIBATA,who was opposed to Hideyoshi,acting as go-between in the wedding between Katsuie and Oichi no kata,his aunt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He subsequently approached Katsuie SHIBATA, who stood in opposition to Hideyoshi, and acted as go-between in the wedding of Katsuie and Oichi no Kata, his aunt.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation, capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He subsequently approached Katsuie SHIBATA, who stood in opposition to Hideyoshi, and acted as go-between in the wedding of Katsuie and Oichi no Kata, his aunt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>こうして織田氏宿老格の柴田勝家・滝川一益らと結び、同年12月、三法師を擁し秀吉に対して挙兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way,he united with Katsuie SHIBATA and Kazumasu TAKIGAWA,chief vassals of the Oda clan,and raised an army against Hideyoshi,backing up Sanboshi in December of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, he allied himself with Katsuie SHIBATA and Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, chief vassals of the Oda clan, and raised an army against Hideyoshi, championing Sanboshi in December of the same year.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, he allied himself with Katsuie SHIBATA and Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, chief vassals of the Oda clan, and raised an army against Hideyoshi, championing Sanboshi in December of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかしこの挙兵は秀吉の迅速な行動によって降伏せざるを得なくなり、人質を出して三法師を秀吉に引き渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However,he was forced to surrender due to Hideyoshi&apos;s prompt action,handing Sanboshi over to Hideyoshi as a hostage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to Hideyoshi&apos;s prompt action, he was forced to surrender and hand Sanboshi over to Hideyoshi as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>Word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to Hideyoshi&apos;s prompt action, he was forced to surrender and hand Sanboshi over to Hideyoshi as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="39">
<j>天正11年（1583年）、賤ヶ岳の戦いが起きると、信孝は再度挙兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1583,he raised an army again as the Battle of Shizugatake broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1583, when the Battle of Shizugatake broke out, Nobutaka again raised an army.</e>
<cmt>Word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1583, when the Battle of Shizugatake broke out, Nobutaka again raised an army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>しかし兄・信雄によって同年4月に居城の岐阜城を包囲され、頼みの勝家も北ノ庄城で自害すると、岐阜城を開城して秀吉に降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However,Gifu-jo Castle,where he lived,was besieged in April of the same year,and his only hope Katsuie committed suicide in Kitanosho-jo Castle,he surrendered to Hideyoshi,opening Gifu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Gifu-jo Castle, where he lived, was besieged in April of the same year by his brother Nobukatsu; when Katsuie, his only hope, committed suicide in Kitanosho-jo Castle, Nobutaka surrendered to Hideyoshi and opened Gifu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice; added missing name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Gifu-jo Castle, where he lived, was besieged in May of the same year by his brother Nobukatsu; when Katsuie, his only hope, committed suicide in Kitanosho-jo Castle, Nobutaka surrendered to Hideyoshi and opened Gifu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="41">
<j>信孝は尾張国知多郡野間（愛知県美浜町 (愛知県)）の大御堂寺（野間大坊、平安時代末に源義朝が暗殺された場所）に送られ、自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutaka was sent to Omido-ji Temple (Nomadaibo,where MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo had been assassinated in late Heian period) in Noma Chita district, Owari Province (Mihama-cho, Aichi Prefecture[Aichi Prefecture]),and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutaka was sent to Omido-ji Temple (Nomadaibo, where MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo had been assassinated in the late Heian period) in Noma Chita district, Owari Province (Mihama-cho, Aichi Prefecture[Aichi Prefecture]), where he committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutaka was sent to Omido-ji Temple (Nomadaibo, where MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo had been assassinated in the late Heian period) in Noma, Chita-gun, Owari Province (Mihama-cho, Aichi Prefecture [Aichi Prefecture]), where he committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>Chita-gun としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>享年26。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 26.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 26.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 26.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>首は神戸城では受け取りを拒否され、検視大塚俄左衛門が伊勢関町の福蔵寺に持ち帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The coroner Gazaemon Ootsuka brought his head back to Fukuzo-ji Temple in Ise Sekimachi because Kanbe-jo Castle refused to accept it.</e>
<cmt>俄左衛門→Gazaemon(定訳不明。該当する読み方が見つかりませんでした。）伊勢関町(定訳不明。該当する読み方が見つかりませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanbe-jo Castle refused to accept Nobutaka&apos;s head, so the coroner, Gazaemon Ootsuka, brought it back to Fukuzo-ji Temple in Ise Sekimachi.</e>
<cmt>Word order, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanbe-jo Castle refused to accept Nobutaka&apos;s head, so the coroner, Gazaemon OTSUKA, brought it back to Fukuzo-ji Temple in Seki-machi, Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>伊勢関町→Seki-machi, Ise Province としました。名字を大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>寺では首塚を作り手厚く弔った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the temple, Kubizuka (tomb of the head) was made and the head was mourned cordially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the temple, a kubizuka (tomb for the head) was made, and Nobutaka was given proper mourning.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, capitalization, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the temple, a kubizuka (tomb for the head) was made, and Nobutaka was given proper mourning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="45">
<j>命日は4月29日（西暦6月19日）と5月2日（6月21日）の二説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory says his anniversary of the death is June 19,but the other June 21.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory says he died on June 19, but another theory says it was June 21.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory says he died on June 19, but another theory says it was June 21.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="46">
<j>辞世の句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death haiku (Japanese poem)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death haiku (Japanese poem)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death haiku (Japanese poem)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>辞世の句は「昔より 主を討つ身の 野間なれば 報いを待てや 羽柴筑前」（信孝の秀吉への激しい怒りが感じられる句である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His death haiku (Japanese poem) was &apos;You had killed the one you had served, may God strike you down, Hashiba Chikuzen.&apos;(it exudes Nobutaka&apos;s rage against Hideyoshi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutaka&apos;s death haiku (Japanese poem) exudes his rage against Hideyoshi: &apos;You killed the one you&apos;d long served, may God strike you down, Hashiba Chikuzen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutaka&apos;s death haiku exudes his rage against Hideyoshi: &apos;You killed the one you&apos;d long served, may god strike you down, Hashiba Chikuzen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>god を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかしたしなみある武将の信孝が、このような稚拙で露骨な辞世の句を残したとは考えにくく、この辞世の句が信孝の残したものかどうかは疑問である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However,it is unlikely Nobutaka,who had the accomplishment as busho (Japanese military commander),made such a poor and conspicuous death haiku,casting doubt whether he actually made it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is unlikely that Nobutaka, a polished busho (Japanese military commander), would have written such a poor and obvious death haiku, and there is doubt as to whether the poem is actually his.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is unlikely that Nobutaka, a polished busho, would have written such a poor and obvious death haiku, and there is doubt as to whether the poem is actually his.</e>
<cmt>武将　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>切腹の際に怒りのあまり臓物をなげつけたという説もあるが、医学的検証からそのようなことは不可能であること、腹に刀をいれたとたん介錯するという作法があることから、そういった逸話とともに創作された辞世の句か落首の類とも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a story that he threw his entrails with rage while Seppuku,however,it was impossible from the standpoint of medical validation and the manner of Kaishaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him),the head must have been cut off the moment the sword entered the abdomen, and it is likely the death haiku or rakushu (lampoon) was made up along with such fiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a story that he was so enraged during seppuku that he flung his entrails away; however, not only has this been proven impossible from a medical standpoint, due to the manner of Kaishaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him), his head must have been cut off the moment the sword entered his abdomen, so the story is fictitious, and it is likely that the death haiku or rakushu (satire) was made up along with it.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a story that he was so enraged during seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) that he flung his entrails away; however, not only has this been proven impossible from a medical standpoint, but also due to the manner of Kaishaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him), his head must have been cut off the moment the sword entered his abdomen, so the story is fictitious, and it is likely that the death haiku or rakushu (satire) was made up along with it.</e>
<cmt>切腹　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="50">
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>秀吉に降伏したとき、人質として差し出した生母・坂氏と妹、娘および側室神戸の板御前は、秀吉によって殺されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real mother Saka family,his sister,his daughter and Kanbe concubine Ita Gozen,who had been handed over to Hideyoshi as hostages,were killed by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>板御前(定訳不明。該当する読み方が見つかりませんでした。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutaka&apos;s biological mother (from the Saka family), his younger sister, his daughter and the Kanbe concubine Ita Gozen were handed over to Hideyoshi as hostages upon the surrender, and were killed by him.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutaka&apos;s biological mother (from the Saka clan), his younger sister, his daughter and his concubine named Kanbe no Ita Gozen were handed over to Hideyoshi as hostages upon the surrender, and were killed by him.</e>
<cmt>family →clanとしました。神戸の板御前　側室がそのように呼ばれていたようですので、Kanbe no Ita Gozen としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>このとき同じく人質に出されていた重臣岡本良勝、幸田彦右衛門尉両人の母も処刑されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mother of a senior vassal Yoshikatsu OKAMOTO and of Hikoemonnojyo KOUDA,who had been handed over as hostage,were also executed at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mother of Yoshikatsu OKAMOTO (a senior vassal) and of Hikoemonnojyo KOUDA had been handed over as a hostage as well, and was also executed at that time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mothers of senior vassals Yoshikatsu OKAMOTO and of Hikoemonnojo KODA had been handed over as a hostage as well, and were also executed at that time.</e>
<cmt>岡本良勝、幸田彦右衛門尉の母（2人）と解釈し、翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>このほか男子某が切腹時に処刑されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And his certain son was executed at the time of Seppuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A certain boy was executed at the time of his seppuku.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, capitalization [It doesn&apos;t specifically state that the boy was Nobutaka&apos;s son.]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A certain boy was executed at the time of his seppuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="54">
<j>このほか娘一人があり、織田信衡の正室となったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a daughter and she became a lawful wife of Nobuhira ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had one other daughter, who became a legal wife of Nobuhira ODA.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had one other daughter, who became a legal wife of Nobuhira ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="55">
<j>信孝の曾孫（神戸信茂の子）信章は越後高田松平家当主松平光長に仕え、高田藩士として存続したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutaka&apos;s grand-grandson Nobuaki (the son of Nobushige KANBE) lived out as a feudal retainer of Takada,serving Mitsunaga MATSUDAIRA,the family head of Echigo Takada Matsudaira Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutaka&apos;s great-grandson Nobuaki (the son of Nobushige KANBE) survived as a feudal retainer of Takada, serving Mitsunaga MATSUDAIRA, the family head of the Echigo Takada Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutaka&apos;s great-grandson Nobuaki (the son of Nobushige KANBE) survived as a feudal retainer of Takada Domain, serving Mitsunaga MATSUDAIRA, the family head of the Matsudaira family of Takada Domain, Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>越後高田松平家→Matsudaira family of Takada Domain, Echigo Province　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>高田では神戸三郎右衛門と称し、新田開発に功があったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuaki called himself as Saburoemon KANBE and contributed to the development of new field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuaki called himself Saburoemon KANBE and contributed to the development of new fields.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuaki called himself Saburoemon KANBE in Takada Domain and contributed to the development of new fields.</e>
<cmt>高田では　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>嫡男半助長経の存在も伝わるが、それ以降は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legend has it that he had a legitimate son Nagatsune HANSUKE,however,other than that nothing has revealed about him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Nobutaka had a legitimate son, Nagatsune HANSUKE; however, other than his name, nothing is known about him.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Nobutaka had a legitimate son, Hansuke Nagatsune (半助長経); however, other than his name, nothing is known about him.</e>
<cmt>半助長経　は名前（名字と名前ではなく）ではないかと解釈し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>藤沢宿に伝わる伝承には信孝の側室小妻氏の子織田信豊の次男織田信国の子孫と称する家（川上氏）も登場、現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legend coming down in Fujisawa-shuku has it that there exists the family claiming descent from Nobukuni ODA,the second son of Nobutoyo ODA who was the son of Nobutaka&apos;s concubine Oduma clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a legend in Fujisawa-shuku, a family appears which claims descent from Nobukuni ODA, the second son of Nobutoyo ODA, who was himself the son of Nobutaka&apos;s concubine from the Oduma clan; this family is still in existence.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a legend in Fujisawa-shuku (a posting station which was located in the present Fujisawa City, Kanagawa Prefecture), a family (Kawakami clan) appears which claims as the descent from Nobukuni ODA, the second son of Nobutoyo ODA, who was himself the son of Nobutaka&apos;s concubine from the Ozuma clan; this family is still in existence.</e>
<cmt>藤沢宿　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>信国は伊勢で出生し、成人後武者修行に出て藤沢宿に至ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobukuni was born in Ise Province,and left home to do a samurai warrior&apos;s quest after he came of age,reaching Fujisawa-shuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobukuni was born in Ise Province and, after he came of age, left home on a samurai warrior&apos;s quest, reaching Fujisawa-shuku.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobukuni was born in Ise Province and, after he came of age, left home on a samurai warrior&apos;s quest, reaching Fujisawa-shuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>徳川旗本となった織田氏の一族には、信豊を家祖として系図に記載する家が少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many families of the Oda clan which became hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) of Tokugawa registered Nobutoyo as the founder of a family in their family tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many families of the Oda clan that became hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) of the Tokugawa registered Nobutoyo as the family founder in their family tree.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many families of the Oda clan that became hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) of the Tokugawa registered Nobutoyo as the family founder in their family tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>これらの子孫、末裔が本当に信孝の血筋であるのかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However,it is not clear whether these descendants are actually descended from Nobutaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is not clear whether these truly are descendants of Nobutaka.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is not clear whether these truly are descendants of Nobutaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>貴種流離譚と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is probably a Kishuryuri-tan (a type of folktales that those like young deity or nobility get over trials to be a god or a blessed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is probably a Kishuryuri-tan (a type of folktale in which characters such as young deities or members of the nobility overcome trials to become a god or blessed).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is probably a Kishuryuri-tan (a type of folktale in which characters such as young deities or members of the nobility overcome trials to become a god or blessed).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>ただし、信孝は侍従にまで昇進した殿上人であり、貴人が血統を保存するために側室を持つことが当然だった当時からすると側室、側室所生の子が存在し、徳川の世になってから世に出たとするのは的外れではないとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However,it was natural at that time that a person of high rank had concubines to protect his blood line and Nobutaka was tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) who was promoted to as much as jiju (a chamberlain),therefore,it is likely his concubines and their children actually existed and appeared in Tokugawa era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was natural at that time for a person of high rank to have concubines in order to protect his blood line, and Nobutaka was a tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) who was promoted as high as jiju (a chamberlain); therefore, it is likely that his concubines and their children actually existed and made themselves known in the Tokugawa era.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was natural at that time for a person of high rank to have concubines in order to protect his blood line, and Nobutaka was a tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) who was promoted as high as jiju (a chamberlain); therefore, it is likely that his concubines and their children actually existed and made themselves known in the Tokugawa era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="64">
<j>明治25年11月24日付の「読売新聞」に、大阪府の平民が宮内大臣に系図などを添えて、信孝の嫡流、10世の子孫と称し、名乗りでたという記事を掲載している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 24 of the 25th year of Meiji era,the Yomiuri Shimbun had the article saying a commoner of Osaka Prefecture claimed to be a direct 10th descendant of Nobutaka,submitting the family tree to Imperial Household Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 24, 1892 (the 25th year of the Meiji era), the Yomiuri Shimbun ran an article saying that a commoner from Osaka Prefecture claiming to be a direct tenth-generation descendant of Nobutaka had submitted his family tree to the Imperial Household Minister.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, year inserted, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 24, 1892 (the 25th year of the Meiji period), the &apos;Yomiuri Shimbun&apos; (newspaper) ran an article saying that a commoner from Osaka Prefecture claiming to be a direct tenth-generation descendant of Nobutaka had submitted his family tree to the Imperial Household Minister.</e>
<cmt>読売新聞　にnewspaper と補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="65">
<j>このほか岐阜に神戸氏を名乗る子孫があり、廣瀬氏などの分家を輩出しているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than that,a descendant claiming to be the Kanbe clan in Gifu,producing branch families such as the Hirose clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides this, some in Gifu have claimed to be descendants of the Kanbe clan and have produced branch families such as the Hirose clan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides this, some in Gifu have claimed to be descendants of the Kanbe clan and have produced branch families such as the Hirose clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="66">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>信長の息子たちの中で一番容貌が父に似ていたと言われ、英雄百人一首に描かれている肖像は（服装を除けば）若き日の信長に酷似している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said Nobutaka resembled his father most of all Nobunaga&apos;s sons and his portrait in Hero Hyakunin Isshu (one hundred poems by one hundred poets) looks much like Nobunaga in his youth (except his costume).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, of all Nobunaga&apos;s sons, Nobutaka bore the closest resemblance to his father, and his portrait in the Hero Hyakunin Isshu (a collection of one hundred poems by one hundred poets) looks much like Nobunaga in his youth (except for his costume).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, of all Nobunaga&apos;s sons, Nobutaka bore the closest resemblance to his father, and his portrait in the Hero Hyakunin Isshu (a collection of one hundred poems by one hundred poets) looks much like Nobunaga in his youth (except for his costume).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="68">
<j>当時の資料によればその人物評は高く、「思慮あり、緒人に対して礼儀正しく、また大なる勇士である」（耶蘇会年報）「信孝もまた将軍の息男にして、智勇人に超えたり」（天正記）と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to documents at that time saying &apos;considerate,courteous to everyone and really courageous&apos;(annual report of Yasokai) &apos;Nobutaka was wiser and braver than others,being also a son of shogun&apos;(Tensho-ki),he was highly appreciated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to documents of the time, he was highly appreciated: it is written that he was &apos;considerate, courteous to everyone and really courageous&apos; (the annual report of the Yasokai), and that &apos;Nobutaka was wiser and braver than others, being also a son of the shogun&apos; (the Tensho-ki).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to documents of the time, he was highly appreciated: it is written that he was &apos;considerate, courteous to everyone and really courageous&apos; (the annual report of the Yasokai [Jesuit Society]), and that &apos;Nobutaka was wiser and braver than others, being also a son of the shogun&apos; (the Tensho-ki [War Chronicle on the Tensho era]).</e>
<cmt>耶蘇会→Jesuit Society と補足しました。天正記→War Chronicle on the Tensho era としました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="69">
<j>キリスト教のイエズス会に対する造詣が深く、宣教師からは「彼（織田信孝）はデウスのことをよく悟り、諸侯及び大身等と共に居る時、常にデウスのことを賛美し、しばしばわがガザに来り、パードレ等を大いに尊敬している」とその人物を高く評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was well-versed in the Society of Jesus,Christianity,and a missionary highly praised him saying&apos;He knows much about Deus,worshipping Deus whenever he is with lords and taishin (big feudal lord) and visits our Gaza (big church),respecting Padre&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was familiar with the Christian Society of Jesus, and a missionary praised him highly, saying, &apos;He knows much about Deus (God), glorifying Deus whenever he is with lords and taishin (big feudal lords); he visits our Gaza (big church) often and respects the padre (priest).&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was familiar with the Christian Society of Jesus, and a missionary praised him highly, saying, &apos;He knows much about Deus (God), glorifying Deus whenever he is with lords and taishin (big feudal lords); he visits our Gaza (big church) often and respects the padre (priest).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="70">
<j>山崎の合戦後に秀吉と並んで朝廷から太刀を授かり、洛中で明智与党の詮議を行い公家衆を震え上がらせていること、秀吉との戦いに際しては飯沼長継など、信孝に内通したとして斬られている秀吉家臣がおり、戦後に秀吉が信孝に仕えた武士を嫌って登用しなかったという事跡も伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legend says that he was given sword from Imperial Court along with Hideyoshi after the Battle of Yamasaki,frightening Kugeshu (court nobles) by carrying out the investigation of Akechi party inside the capital and that at the battle against Hideyoshi,Nagatsugu IINUMA,who was a vassal of Hideyoshi,was killed on suspicion of being collaborating with Nobutaka,and Hideyoshi never employed samurai who had served Nobutaka after the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend says that both he and Hideyoshi were given swords by the Imperial Court after the Battle of Yamasaki; that he frightened the kugeshu (court nobles) by carrying out the investigation of the Akechi party inside the capital; that, at the battle against Hideyoshi, Nagatsugu IINUMA (one of Hideyoshi&apos;s vassals) was killed on suspicion of collaborating with Nobutaka, and that after the battle Hideyoshi never employed samurai who had served Nobutaka.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend says that both he and Hideyoshi were given swords by the Imperial Court after the Battle of Yamasaki; that he frightened the kugeshu (court nobles) by carrying out the investigation of the Akechi party inside the capital; that, at the battle against Hideyoshi, Nagatsugu IINUMA (one of Hideyoshi&apos;s vassals) was killed on suspicion of collaborating with Nobutaka, and that after the battle Hideyoshi never employed samurai who had served Nobutaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="71">
<j>天正9年（1581年）の京都御馬揃えの際には信忠・信雄・織田信包に次いで第4位の序列であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1581,at the time of the great military parade in Kyoto,his rank was the forth after Nobutada,Nobukatsu,Nobukane ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1581, at the time of the great military parade in Kyoto, Nobutaka&apos;s rank was the forth after Nobutada, Nobukatsu, and Nobukane ODA.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1581, at the time of the great military parade in Kyoto, Nobutaka&apos;s rank was the forth after Nobutada, Nobukatsu, and Nobukane ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また跡継ぎの信忠を除けば、連枝衆で地方討伐の指揮を任されたのは信孝のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutaka was the only person from people of Renshi (brothers and sisters of nobles) who was entrusted to command the subdugation of the province,aside from Nobutada,who was the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among all the brothers and sisters of nobles, Nobutaka was the only person entrusted with commanding the subjugation of a province, aside from Nobutada, the successor.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among all the brothers and sisters of nobles, Nobutaka was the only person entrusted with commanding the subjugation of a province, aside from Nobutada, the successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また信忠・信雄と並んで信長から太刀を拝領している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given a sword by Nobunaga as well as Nobutada and Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given a sword by Nobunaga, as were Nobutada and Nobukatsu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, corrected name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given a sword by Nobunaga, as were Nobutada and Nobukatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ドルチェット(id:46458), Reggaeman(id:6214), 0null0(id:582), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Revth(id:12179), Andee(id:20421), 鞆(id:61733), 石原光秀(id:137932), ＩＤＳ(id:49634), Loveless(id:129239), Arawodas(id:213174), こぶまき(id:38278), Maakun(id:16735), Klesha(id:203751), Kouko0515(id:100370), KASAGI(id:24405), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Calvero(id:38360), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Izayohi(id:13095), Asura2007(id:78364), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), Yanahan(id:2437), 蚯蚓(id:254651), Rona(id:791), Carkuni(id:79281), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Safkan(id:423), Kuma83(id:31177), Comyu(id:58135), Jmho(id:10472), 歴史研究家(id:108842), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>