<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>後鳥羽院宮内卿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotobain Kunaikyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotobain Kunaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotobain Kunaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宮内卿（くない-きょう）または後鳥羽院宮内卿（ごとば/ごとばの-いん・くない-きょう）は、新古今期を代表する女房歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunaikyo or Gotoba/Gotobanoin Kunaikyo was a court-lady poet who represented a period when Sinkokin (Wakashu) (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) was made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunaikyo or Gotoba/Gotobanoin Kunaikyo was a court-lady poet who is representative of a period when Shinkokin (Wakashu, or New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) was made.</e>
<cmt>「represented」→「is representative of」, 「Sinkokin」→「Shinkokin」, 「)(」→「, or」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunaikyo or Gotoba/Gotobanoin Kunaikyo was a court-lady poet who is representative of a period when Shinkokin (Wakashu, or New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) was compiled.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>新三十六歌仙、女房三十六歌仙の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was one of the New Thirty-six Major Poets and the Thirty-six Immortal Lady Poets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is one of the New Thirty-six Major Poets and the Thirty-six Immortal Lady Poets.</e>
<cmt>「was」→「is」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is one of the New Thirty-six Major Poets as well as one of the Thirty-six Immortal Lady Poets.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一般には宮内卿とされることが多いが、同名の女房歌人と区別するために、特に後鳥羽院と冠することもある（『玉葉集』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is generally known as Kunaikyo, but sometimes called especially Gotobain Kunaikyo to distinguish her from the other court-lady poet who had the same name as hers (&quot;Gyokuyo shu&quot; etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is generally known as Kunaikyo, but sometimes specifically referred to as Gotobain Kunaikyo to distinguish her from another court-lady poet of the same name (&quot;Gyokuyo shu&quot; etc.).</e>
<cmt>「called especially」→「specifically referred to as」, 「the other」→「another」,「who had the same name as hers」→「of the same name」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is generally known as Kunaikyo, but sometimes specifically referred to as Gotobain Kunaikyo to distinguish her from another court-lady poet of the same name (&quot;Gyokuyo shu&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>生没年不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dates of birth and death are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her dates of birth and death are unknown.</e>
<cmt>「The」→「Her」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her dates of birth and death are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>二十歳あまりで夭折したとする説が一般的。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally considered that she died young over twenty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally considered that she died young, at a little over twenty.</e>
<cmt>「at a little」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally considered that she died young, at the age a little over twenty.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>家集をはじめとするまとまった著作は残っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remains no large collection of her poems such as a personal collection of poetry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No large collection of her poems along the line of a personal collection of poetry remains today.</e>
<cmt>「There remains」削除, 「such as」→「along the line of」,「remains today」挿入,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No large collection of her poems including the line of personal collections of poetry remains today.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>父は右京権大夫源師光（大納言源師頼の子）、母は後白河院女房安芸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Ukyo Gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Western Capital Offices) MINAMOTO no Moromitsu (a son of Dainagon (Chief Councillor of State) MINAMOTO no Moroyori), and her mother was Goshirakawain Nyobo (court lady) Aki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Ukyo Gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Western Capital Offices) MINAMOTO no Moromitsu (a son of Dainagon MINAMOTO no Moroyori, the Chief Councillor of State), and her mother was Goshirakawain Nyobo (court lady) Aki.</e>
<cmt>Parentheses removed, 「, the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was the Provisional Master of the Western Capital Offices, MINAMOTO no Moromitsu (a son of the Chief Councillor of State, MINAMOTO no Moroyori) and her mother was Aki, a court lady worked for Goshirakawain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>兄に源泰光、源具親がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her older brothers were MINAMOTO no Yasumitsu and MINAMOTO no Tomochika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her older brothers were MINAMOTO no Yasumitsu and MINAMOTO no Tomochika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her older brothers were MINAMOTO no Yasumitsu and MINAMOTO no Tomochika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>その生涯についてはほとんどはっきりしたことがわからないが、その歌才によって後鳥羽院の召しにあい院のもとに女房として出仕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although most of her life is not clearly known, she was invited to the Imperial court by Gotobain due to her outstanding talent for composing poems and she served there as a court lady.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although little of her life is clearly known, she was invited to the Imperial court by Gotobain due to her outstanding talent for composing poems and she served there as a court lady.</e>
<cmt>「most of her life is not」→「little of her life is」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although little of her life is clearly known, she was invited to the Imperial Court by Gotobain due to her outstanding talent for composing poems, then she served there as a court lady.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>正治二年（1200年）の正治後度百首、建仁元年（1201年）の老若五十首歌合、通親亭影供歌合、撰歌合、仙洞句題五十首、千五百番歌合、同二年（1202年）の仙洞影供歌合、水無瀬恋十五首歌合などに詠進・出詠している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She joined various utaawase (poetry contest): in 1200, Shojigodohyakushu; in 1201, Ronyaku gojusshu utaawase, Michichikatei eigu utaawase, Sen utaawase, Sentokudai gojisshu, and Sengohyaku ban Utaawase (One thousand and five hundreds Set of Poetry Match); in 1202, Sentoeigu Utaawase and Minase koijugoshu Utaawase.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She joined various utaawase (poetry contests): in 1200, Shojigodohyakushu, in 1201, Ronyaku gojusshu utaawase, Michichikatei eigu utaawase, Sen utaawase, Sentokudai gojisshu, and Sengohyaku ban Utaawase (One Thousand Five Hundred Sets of Poetry Match), and in 1202, Sentoeigu Utaawase and Minase koijugoshu Utaawase.</e>
<cmt>「contest」→「contests」, 「;」→「,」x2, 「thousand and five hundreds Set」→「Thousand Five Hundred Sets」, 「, and」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was entered various poetry contests: in 1200, Shojigodohyakushu (the second poetry contest in 1200), in 1201, Ronyaku gojusshu uta-awase (poetry contest by 50 poems by young and old poets), Michichikatei eigu uta-awase (poetry contest at Michichika residence, dedicated to KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro), Sen uta-awase (poetry contest in wakasho (the Office of Waka) gathering by Gotobain in 1201), Sentokudai gojisshu (poetry contest of 50 poems by 6 poets gathering by Gotobain in 1201), and Sengohyaku ban uta-awase (One Thousand Five Hundred Sets of Poetry Match), and in 1202, Sentoeigu uta-awase (poetry contest at Toba Jonan-ji Temple dedicated to KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro) and Minase koijugoshu uta-awase (poetry contest at Minase).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>正治後度百首は後鳥羽院近臣の新人歌人を中心に詠進したものであるから、宮内卿の出仕は正治二年の直前と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because those who joined the Shojigodohyakushu were mainly new poets of Gotobain&apos;s trusted vassals, it is considered that Kunaikyo began to attend at the court right before 1200.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because those who presented poems to the court for the Shojigodohyakushu were mainly new poets from Gotobain&apos;s trusted vassals, it is considered that Kunaikyo began to attend at the court just before 1200.</e>
<cmt>「joined」→「presented poems to the court for」, 「of」→「from」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because those who presented poems to the court for the Shojigodohyakushu were mainly new poets from Gotobain&apos;s trusted vassals, it is considered that Kunaikyo first attended at the court just before 1200.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また現在判明している歌作でもっとも時代が新しいのは元久元年（1204年）11月の春日社歌合であり、『増鏡』などの記述から、この後遠からずして亡くなったものと推測することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among her poems which are known today, the latest poem was made at Kasugasha Utaawase held in November, 1204, and the descriptions in &quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror) and so on suggest that she passed away soon after the utaawase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those of her poems which still exist today, the latest poem was made at Kasugasha Utaawase held in November, 1204, and the descriptions in &quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror) and other poems suggest that she passed away soon after the utaawase.</e>
<cmt>「her poems which are known」→「those of her poems which still exist」, 「so on」→「other poems」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those of her poems which still exist today, the latest poem was made at Kasugasha Uta-awase poetry contest held in November, 1204, and the descriptions in &quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror) and other poems suggest that she passed away soon after the uta-awase.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>鴨長明『無名抄』では宮内卿を「昔にも恥じぬ上手」と評し、「あまり歌を深く案じて病になりて」重篤に陥ったが、父の諌めをも聞かずに歌にうちこんだため早世した、という逸話を紹介している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KAMO no Chomei commented in &quot;Mumyosho&quot; (an essay on tanka poetry) that &apos;Kunaikyo is good at composing poems and can face the great poets in the past without embarrassment,&apos; introducing an anecdote which says &apos;she pondered poems so deeply that she fell sick&apos; and got worse, but she turned a deaf ear to the protests of her father, devoting herself to poetry, so she died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KAMO no Chomei commented in &quot;Mumyosho&quot; (an essay on tanka poetry) that &apos;Kunaikyo is good at composing poems and can face the great poets in the past without embarrassment,&apos; introducing an anecdote which says &apos;she pondered poems so deeply that she fell sick&apos; and got worse, but she turned a deaf ear to the protests of her father, devoting herself to poetry, and died young.</e>
<cmt>「so she」→「and」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KAMO no Chomei commented in &quot;Mumyosho&quot; (an essay on tanka poetry) that &apos;Kunaikyo is good at composing poems and can face the great poets in the past without embarrassment,&apos; referring to an episode that &apos;she pondered poems so deeply that she fell sick&apos; and got worse, but she turned a deaf ear to the protests of her father, devoting herself to poetry, and died young.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>『正徹物語』にも「宮内卿は廿よりうちになくなりにしかば」とあって、彼女が夭折したことは、中世期にひろく知られていた事実らしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shotetsu monogatari&quot; (Tale of Shotetsu) also states that &apos;Kunaikyo died under twenty,&apos; so her early death seems to have been widely known during the medieval period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shotetsu monogatari&quot; (Tale of Shotetsu) also states that &apos;Kunaikyo died under twenty,&apos; so her early death seems to have been widely known during the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shotetsu monogatari&quot; (Tale of Shotetsu) also states that &apos;Kunaikyo died under twenty&apos;; therefore, her early death seems to have been widely known during the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。コンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このほか典拠不明ながら、『古今著聞集』には甥と通じていたものの、後に男の通いが絶えて憂悶に苦しんだとする逸話を掲げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than this, &quot;Kokon Chomon ju&quot; (A Collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) tells that she had an affair with her niece, but later he stopped visiting her so she experienced anguish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than this, &quot;Kokon Chomon Ju&quot; (A Collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) tells that she had an affair with her nephew, but as he stopped visiting her she experienced anguish.</e>
<cmt>「ju」→「Ju」, 「niece」→「nephew」,「later」→「as」, 「so」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than this, &quot;Kokon Chomon Ju&quot; (A Collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) tells that she had an affair with her nephew, and as he stopped visiting her, she experienced anguish.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>現在まで300首前後の歌しか伝わっていない（『新古今集』に15首、『玉葉集』に9首など、計43首が勅撰集に入撰）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to today, only about 300 poems has come down to us (forty-three poems were selected for Chokusenshu (anthology of poems collected by Imperial command), for example, fifteen poems collected in &quot;Shin Kokinshu,&quot; nine poems in &quot;Gyokuyo shu,&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, only about 300 poems remain known (forty-three poems were selected for Chokusenshu (anthology of poems collected by Imperial command) for example, fifteen poems collected in &quot;Shin Kokinshu,&quot; nine poems in &quot;Gyokuyo shu,&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>「Up to」削除, 「has come down to us」→「remain known」, 「,」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only about 300 poems have remained (forty-three poems were selected for Chokusenshu (anthology of poems collected by Imperial command) for example, fifteen poems collected in &quot;Shin Kokinshu,&quot; nine poems in &quot;Gyokuyo shu,&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>歌風は視覚効果を意識したあざやかな色彩感覚や自然美を扱ったものが多く、叙景歌に佳作を多く残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She made many poems whose descriptions were full of color, trying to produce visual effects, and dealt with natural beauty in her works, so she left a lot of fine descriptive poems.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She wrote many poems with descriptions full of color, trying to produce visual effects, and dealt with natural beauty in her works, so she left a lot of fine descriptive poems.</e>
<cmt>「made」→「wrote」, 「whose descriptions were」→「with descriptions」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She wrote many poems with descriptions full of color, trying to produce visual effects, and dealt with natural beauty in her works, so she left a lot of fine descriptive poems.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>式子内親王・藤原俊成女と並んで新古今集を代表する女流歌人であり、後代に与えた影響も大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with Imperial Princess Shikishi and a daughter of FUJIWARA no Toshinari, she was a female poet who represented Shin Kokinshu, having a great influence on the posterity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with Imperial Princess Shikishi, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Toshinari, she was a female poet who represented Shin Kokinshu, leaving a great influence on posterity.</e>
<cmt>「and」→「,」, 「having a great influence on the」→「leaving a great influence on」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with Imperial Princess Shikishi and a daughter of FUJIWARA no Toshinari, she was a female poet who represented Shin Kokinshu, leaving a great influence on posterity.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>千五百番歌合に出詠した「うすくこき野辺のみどりの若草に跡までみゆる雪のむら消え」という歌があまりに優れていたために「若草の宮内卿」と呼ばれたという逸話が『増鏡』に見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Masukagami,&quot; the poem which was composed by her in 1500-Round Poetry Contest, &apos;I can see the green of young grass, which varies shades of light and dark, and patches of fading snow,&apos; was so excellent that she was called &apos;Wakakusa no Kunaikyo&apos; (wakakusa means young grass).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Masukagami,&quot; the poem which she composed in the 1500 Sets Poetry Contest, &apos;I can see the green of young grass, which varies shades of light and dark, and patches of fading snow,&apos; was so excellent that she was called &apos;Wakakusa no Kunaikyo&apos; (wakakusa means young grass).</e>
<cmt>「was composed by her」→「she composed」, 「1500-Rounds」→「the 1500 Sets」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Masukagami,&quot; the poem which she composed in the Sengohyaku ban uta-awase, &apos;I can see the green of young grass, which varies shades of light and dark, and patches of fading snow,&apos; was so good that she was called &apos;Wakakusa no Kunaikyo&apos; (wakakusa means young grass).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>後鳥羽院は時代不同歌合で宮内卿を和泉式部と番えており、ここからも院の彼女に対する高評価が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Jidaifudo Utaawase, Gotobain made Kunaikyo and Izumi Shikibu compete, which suggests that Gotobain appreciated her talent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jidaifudo Utaawase, Gotobain made Kunaikyo and Izumi Shikibu compete, which suggests that Gotobain appreciated her talent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the poetry contest by poets of various collections, Gotobain made Kunaikyo and Izumi Shikibu compete, which suggests that Gotobain appreciated her talent.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>代表作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most important works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most important works</e>
<cmt>「」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most Important Works</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>かきくらし猶ふる里の雪のうちに跡こそみえね春は来にけり（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the snow, which lay on the old village where I live being heartbroken, I cannot see a sign of spring but feel that the spring has come. (Shin Kokinshu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the snow, which lay on the old village where I live, being heartbroken I cannot see a sign of spring but yet feel that the spring has come. (Shin Kokinshu)</e>
<cmt>「,」箇所異動,「yet」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the snow, which lay on the old village where I live, being heartbroken I cannot see a sign of spring but yet feel that the spring has come (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を他と合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>うすくこき野辺のみどりの若草に跡までみゆる雪のむら消え（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I can see the green of young grass, which varies shades of light and dark, and patches of fading snow. (Shin Kokinshu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I can see the green of young grass, which varies shades of light and dark, and patches of fading snow. (Shin Kokinshu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I can see the green of young grass, which varies shades of light and dark, and patches of fading snow (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を他と合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>花さそふひらの山かぜ吹きにけりこぎゆく舟のあと見ゆるまで（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wind blows from Mt. Hira scattering the cherry blossoms, and the petals floating on the lake look like running boats which leave the track behind on the surface of the water. (Shin Kokinshu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wind blows from Mt. Hira scattering the cherry blossoms, and the petals floating on the lake look like running boats which leave tracks behind on the surface of the water. (Shin Kokinshu)</e>
<cmt>「the track」→「tracks」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wind blows from Mt. Hira scattering the cherry blossoms, and the petals floating on the lake look like running boats which leave tracks behind on the surface of the water (Shin Kokinshu)</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を他と合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>あふ坂や梢の花を吹くからに嵐ぞかすむ関の杉むら（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Osaka, the stormy wind blows scattering blossoms at the top of the trees and making a cedar forest around the barrier station hazy (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Osaka, the stormy wind blows scattering blossoms at the top of the trees and making the cedar forest around the barrier station hazy (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>「a」→「the」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Osaka, the stormy wind blows scattering blossoms at the top of the trees and making the cedar forest around the barrier station hazy (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>片枝さすおふのうらなし初秋になりもならずも風ぞ身にしむ（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early autumn, pears grow on the tree at Ou creek with its branch spreading to one way, but the cool wind is always biting me in spite of the season (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early autumn, pears grow on the tree at Ou Creek with its branches spreading one way, but the cool wind is always biting me in spite of the season (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>「creek」→「Creek」, 「branch spreading to one way」→「branches spreading one way」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early autumn, pears grow on the tree at Ou Creek with its branches spreading one way, but the cool wind is always biting me in spite of the season (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>思ふことさしてそれとはなきものを秋の夕べを心にぞとふ（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I should not have anything special to worry about, but somehow I cannot stop being lost in deep thought on autumn evenings, so I ask myself why (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I should not have anything special to worry about, but somehow I cannot stop being lost in deep thought on autumn evenings, so I ask myself why (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I should not have anything special to worry about, but somehow I cannot stop being lost in deep thought on autumn evenings, so I ask myself why (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>心あるをじまのあまの袂かな月やどれとはぬれぬ物から（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A diver of Matsushima who feels the pathos of nature makes his sleeve wet, but he does not intend to reflect the moonlight on his sleeve (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A shell diver of Matsushima who feels the pathos of nature makes her sleeve wet, but she does not intend to reflect the moonlight on her sleeve (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Shell&apos; added, as &apos;diver&apos; sounds modern on its own. Does あま refer to a woman?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shell diver of Matsushima who feels the pathos of nature makes her sleeve wet, but she does not intend to reflect the moonlight on her sleeve (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>月をなほ待つらんものかむら雨の晴れ行く雲の末の里人（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the rain stopped and the moon appeared here, I wonder if the villagers who live far away are still waiting for the moon under the sky which is gradually clearing (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the rain has stopped and the moon has appeared here, I wonder if the villagers who live far away are still waiting for the moon under a sky which is gradually clearing (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>「has」挿入x2, 「the」→「a」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the rain has stopped and the moon has appeared here, I wonder if the villagers who live far away are still waiting for the moon under a sky which is gradually clearing (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>まどろまでながめよとてのすさびかな麻のさ衣月にうつ声（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I did not to sleep from caprice, and there is the rhythmic sound of hempen robes under the moon (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I did not sleep from caprice, and there is the rhythmic sound of hempen robes under the moon (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>「to」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I did not sleep from caprice, and there is the rhythmic sound of hempen robes under the moon (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>と山なるならの葉までははげしくて尾花がすゑによわる秋風（続古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The autumn wind blows hard till it reaches the oak&apos;s leaves. But when it arrives to the tips of the Japanese plume grass, it blows gently (Shoku Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The autumn wind blows hard till it reaches the oak&apos;s leaves, but when it arrives at the tips of the Japanese plume grass, it blows gently (Shoku Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>「. But」→「, but」, 「to」→「at」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The autumn wind blows hard till it reaches the oak&apos;s leaves, but when it arrives at the tips of the Japanese plume grass, it blows gently (Shoku Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="31">
<j>霜をまつ籬(まがき)の菊の宵のまにおきまよふ色は山のはの月（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the early evening, when a chrysanthemum on the hedge is waiting for frost, it turns shiny white as if we had frost already ---the moonlight from the edge of the mountain is reflecting on the flower (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the early evening, as a chrysanthemum on the hedge awaits the frost, it turns shiny white as if we had frost already ---the moonlight from the edge of the mountain is reflecting on the flower (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>「when」→「as」, 「is waiting for」→「awaits the」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the early evening, as a chrysanthemum on the hedge awaits the frost, it turns shiny white as if we had frost already -- the moonlight from the edge of the mountain is reflecting on the flower (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>ハイフンのぞきスペースにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="32">
<j>たつた山あらしや嶺によわるらんわたらぬ水も錦たえけり（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I wonder if the stormy wind lashing at the peak of the mountain calmed down. The wind does not bring red leaves, so the brocade on the surface of the river ended, though nobody got across the river (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I wonder if the stormy wind lashing at the peak of the mountain calmed down. The wind does not bring red leaves, so the brocade on the surface of the river ended, though nobody got across the river (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I wonder if the stormy wind lashing at the peak of the mountain calmed down. The wind does not bring red leaves, so the brocade on the surface of the river ended, though nobody got across the river (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>訳文が2文ですが、和歌のためそのままにしています。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="33">
<j>からにしき秋のかたみや立田山ちりあへぬ枝に嵐ふくなり（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The colored leaves of autumn are like brocade. I wonder if the stormy wind broke this memento of autumn. At Mt. Tatsuta, a mountain wind seems to be blowing against the branches on which the leaves are still remaining (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The colored leaves of autumn are like brocade. I wonder if the stormy wind broke this memento of autumn. At Mt. Tatsuta, a mountain wind seems to be blowing against the branches on which the leaves still remain (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>「are still remaining」→「still remain」, &apos;broke&apos; seems awkward, but I&apos;m not sure what to replace it with.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The colored leaves of autumn are like brocade. I wonder if the stormy wind broke this memento of autumn. At Mt. Tatsuta, a mountain wind seems to be blowing against the branches on which the leaves still remain (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>訳文が3文ですが、和歌のためそのままにしています。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="34">
<j>きくやいかにうはの空なる風だにも松に音するならひありとは（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Do yo hear it? Even the wind in the skies rustles pines by habit (even a wind does not betray somebody who is waiting) (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Do you hear it? Even the wind in the skies rustles pines by habit (even a wind does not betray somebody who is waiting) (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>「yo」→「you」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Do you hear it? Even the wind in the skies rustles pines by habit (even a wind does not betray somebody who is waiting) (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>訳文が2文ですが、和歌のためそのままにしています。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="35">
<j>竹の葉に風ふきよわる夕ぐれの物のあはれは秋としもなし（新古今集）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At dusk, when the morning power of the wind which was blowing through the bamboo leaves weakens, I am overcome with nostalgia but it is not only limited to autumn (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At dusk, when the morning&apos;s strength of wind which was blowing through the bamboo leaves weakens, I am overcome with nostalgia, but it is not only limited to autumn (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>「morning power of the wind」→「morning&apos;s strength of wind」, 「,」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At dusk, when the morning&apos;s strength of wind which was blowing through the bamboo leaves weakens, I am overcome with nostalgia, but it is not only limited to autumn (Shin Kokinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>宮内卿に関する記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descriptions of Kunaikyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descriptions of Kunaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descriptions of Kunaikyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Loveless(id:129239), Kurz(id:1601), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 自閑(id:233807), Andee(id:20421), Ks8823(id:130146), Aotake(id:34929), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>