<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>お市の方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oichi no kata (Lady Oichi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oichi no Kata (Lady Oichi)</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oichi no Kata (Lady Oichi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>お市の方（おいちのかた、天文 (元号)16年（1547年）？ - 天正11年4月24日 (旧暦)（1583年6月14日））は戦国時代 (日本)の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oichi no kata (1547 ? - June 14, 1583) was a woman in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oichi no Kata (1547 ? - June 14, 1583) was a woman of the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oichi no Kata (1547 ? - June 14, 1583) was a woman of the Sengoku ｐeriod (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>大文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>近江国の浅井長政、のちに織田氏家臣の柴田勝家の妻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a wife of Nagamasa ASAI of Omi Province and later became a wife of Katsuie SHIBATA, a retainer of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a wife of Nagamasa ASAI of Omi Province and later became a wife of Katsuie SHIBATA, a retainer of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a wife of Nagamasa ASAI of Omi Province and later became a wife of Katsuie SHIBATA, a retainer of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は尾張国の武将織田信秀、母は側室、または正室（継室）の土田御前。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Nobuhide ODA, a Busho (Japanese military commander) of Owari Province and her mother was Dota-gozen, Sokushitsu (concubine) or Seishitsu (legal wife) (Keishitsu (second wife)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Nobuhide ODA, a busho (Japanese military commander) of Owari Province, and her mother was Dota-gozen, a sokushitsu (concubine) or seishitsu (legal wife) (keishitsu (second wife)).</e>
<cmt>Capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Nobuhide ODA, a busho (Japanese military commander) of Owari Province, and her mother was Dota-gozen, a sokushitsu (concubine) or seishitsu (legal wife) (keishitsu (second wife)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>織田信長の妹、ほか兄弟多数（それぞれ諸説あり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a younger sister of Nobunaga ODA and she had many other brothers and sisters (Various theories exist for each).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a younger sister of Nobunaga ODA and she had many other brothers and sisters (various theories exist for each).</e>
<cmt>Capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a younger sister of Nobunaga ODA and she had many other brothers and sisters (various theories exist for each).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に淀殿（豊臣秀吉側室＝淀殿）・常高院（京極高次正室）・崇源院（徳川秀忠正室）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her children included Yodo-dono (Concubine of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI = Yodo-dono), Joko-in (Legal wife of Takatsugu KYOGOKU) and Sugen-in (Legal wife of Hidetada TOKUGAWA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her children included Yodo-dono (concubine of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI = Yodo-dono), Joko-in (legal wife of Takatsugu KYOGOKU) and Sugen-in (legal wife of Hidetada TOKUGAWA).</e>
<cmt>Capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her children included Yodo-dono (concubine of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI = Yodo-dono), Joko-in (legal wife of Takatsugu KYOGOKU) and Sugen-in (legal wife of Hidetada TOKUGAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸幕府三代将軍徳川家光や豊臣秀頼は孫に、明正天皇は曾孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA of the Edo Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and Hideyori TOYOTOMI were her grandchildren and Emperor Meisho was her great-grandchild.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA of the Edo Bakufu (a Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and Hideyori TOYOTOMI were her grandchildren, and Emperor Meisho was her great-grandson.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third Shogun of the Edo Bakufu (a Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and Hideyori TOYOTOMI were her grandchildren, and Emperor Meisho was her great-granddaughter.</e>
<cmt>「三代」の訳を補う明正天皇は女帝</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>市姫とも小谷の方とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was called Ichihime or Odani no Kata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was called Ichihime or Odani no Kata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was called Ichihime or Odani no Kata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、『好古類纂』収録の織田家系譜には「秀子」という名が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the family tree of the Oda family recorded in &apos;Koko Ruisan,&apos; a name of Hideko appears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the name &quot;Hideko&quot; appears in the Oda family tree recorded in &apos;Koko Ruisan&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the name &quot;Hideko&quot; appears in the Oda family tree recorded in &apos;Koko Ruisan&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>永禄10年（1567年）に兄・信長の命により近江（現在の滋賀県）の浅井長政と政略結婚し織田家と浅井家は同盟を結ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was forced to marry Nagamasa ASAI of Omi Province (present Shiga Prefecture) for political reasons in 1567 by the order of Nobunaga, her elder brother, by which the Oda family concluded an alliance with the Asai family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1567, she was forced for political reasons to marry Nagamasa ASAI of Omi Province (present Shiga Prefecture) by the order of Nobunaga, her elder brother; the marriage concluded an alliance with the Asai family for the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1567, she was forced for political reasons to marry Nagamasa ASAI of Omi Province (present Shiga Prefecture) by the order of Nobunaga, her elder brother; the marriage concluded an alliance with the Asai family for the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>元亀元年（1570年）、信長が浅井氏と関係の深い越前国（福井県）の朝倉義景を攻めたため、浅井家と織田家の友好関係は断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Nobunaga attacked Yoshikage ASAKURA who was closely related with the Asai clan in Echizen Province (Fukui Prefecture) in 1570, the friendly relationship between the Asai family and the Oda family was severed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Friendly relations between the Asai family and the Oda family were severed in 1570, due to Nobunaga&apos;s attack on Yoshikage ASAKURA (who was closely related to the Asai clan) in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Friendly relations between the Asai family and the Oda family were severed in 1570, due to Nobunaga&apos;s attack on Yoshikage ASAKURA (who was closely related to the Asai clan) in Echizen Province (present Fukui Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>（福井県）の訳を補う</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、長政と市の夫婦関係は周りが羨むほど仲睦まじかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The marital relationship between Nagamasa and Ichi is said to have been harmonious, which was the envy of all around them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The marriage between Nagamasa and Ichi is said to have been a harmonious one, and the envy of all around them.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The marriage between Nagamasa and Ichi is said to have been a harmonious one, and the envy of all around them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>義景が姉川の戦いで敗北した後、天正元年（1573年）に小谷城が陥落し、夫・長政、長政の父・浅井久政も信長に敗れ自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshikage was defeated in the Battle of Anegawa, Odani-jo Castle fell in 1573, where Nagamasa and Hisamasa ASAI, Nagamasa&apos;s father were defeated by Nobunaga and killed themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshikage&apos;s defeat in the Battle of Anegawa, Odani-jo Castle fell in 1573; Nagamasa and Hisamasa ASAI (Nagamasa&apos;s father) were defeated by Nobunaga and killed themselves.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshikage&apos;s defeat in the Battle of Anegawa, Odani-jo Castle fell in 1573; Nagamasa and Hisamasa ASAI (Nagamasa&apos;s father) were defeated by Nobunaga and killed themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>市は3人の娘（淀殿、常高院、崇源院）とともに織田家に引き取られるが、長男の浅井万福丸は捕われて殺害され、次男の浅井万寿丸は出家させられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Ichi was taken on by the Oda family together with her daughters (Yodo-dono, Joko-in and Sugen-in), her eldest son, Manpukumaru ASAI was captured and killed and her second son, Manjumaru ASAI was forced to become a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Ichi and her daughters (Yodo-dono, Joko-in and Sugen-in) were taken in by the Oda family, her eldest son, Manpukumaru ASAI, was captured and killed and her second son, Manjumaru ASAI, was forced into the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Ichi and her daughters (Yodo-dono, Joko-in and Sugen-in) were taken in by the Oda family, her eldest son, Manpukumaru ASAI, was captured and killed and her second son, Manjumaru ASAI, was forced into the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後は清洲城にて兄の信長、織田信包の庇護を受け、三姉妹とともに九年余りを平穏に過ごしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After then, she is said to have lived in piece for over nine years in Kiyosu-jo Castle with her three daughters under the patronage of Nobunaga and Nobukane ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, she is said to have lived in peace in Kiyosu-jo Castle with her three daughters for more than nine years, under the patronage of her older brother Nobunaga and Nobukane ODA.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, she is said to have lived in peace in Kiyosu-jo Castle with her three daughters for more than nine years, under the patronage of her older brother Nobunaga and Nobukane ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このときの信長の市親子に対する待遇はたいへん厚く、市や三姉妹のことを気にかけ、贅沢をさせていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Nobunaga is said to have received Ichi and her children warmly, concerned about Ichi and her three daughters and let them live in luxury.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga is said to have received Ichi and her children very warmly at the time, to have been concerned for Ichi and her three daughters, and to have let them live in luxury.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga is said to have received Ichi and her children very warmly at the time, to have been concerned for Ichi and her three daughters, and to have let them live in luxury.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>信包も、「浅井家の血が絶えるのはしのびない」と言い、市や三姉妹を手元で保護し、姪たちを養育したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobukane ODA is also said to have protected Ichi and her three daughters under the eyes of him and brought up his nieces, saying that &apos;It is unbearable to think the Asai family line will die out.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobukane ODA is also said to have personally protected Ichi and her three daughters and fostered his nieces, saying, &apos;It is unbearable to think of the extinction of the Asai family line.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobukane ODA is also said to have personally protected Ichi and her three daughters and fostered his nieces, saying, &apos;It is unbearable to think of the extinction of the Asai family line.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>信長没後の天正10年（1582年）に柴田勝家と再婚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582 after the death of Nobunaga, she remarried Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, after the death of Nobunaga, she married Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, after the death of Nobunaga, she married Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>織田信孝の仲介によるとされて来たが、近年は、豊臣秀吉の仲介を伺わせる書状から、羽柴秀吉の仲介であった説が有力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the remarriage had been understood to be through the intermediation of Nobutaka ODA, a theory that it was through Hideyoshi HASHIBA became influential in recent years due to a letter suggesting it was through Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the remarriage was understood to have been mediated by Nobutaka ODA, a theory that it was through Hideyoshi HASHIBA has become influential in recent years, due to a letter suggesting it was through Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the remarriage was understood to have been mediated by Nobutaka ODA, a theory that it was through Hideyoshi HASHIBA has become influential in recent years, due to a letter suggesting it was through Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>同年、勝家の進めにより、京都の妙心寺で信長の百箇日法要を営む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the recommendation of Katsuie, she held a Buddhist memorial service on the one hundredth day after Nobunaga&apos;s death at Myoshin-ji Temple in Kyoto in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the recommendation of Katsuie, Ichi held a Buddhist memorial service at Myoshin-ji Temple in Kyoto on the one hundredth day after Nobunaga&apos;s death in the same year.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the recommendation of Katsuie, Ichi held a Buddhist memorial service at Myoshin-ji Temple in Kyoto on the one hundredth day after Nobunaga&apos;s death in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>翌・天正11年（1583年）、夫の勝家が羽柴秀吉と対立して賤ヶ岳の戦いで敗れ、その後勝家と共に越前北ノ庄城内で自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, 1583, Katsuie, her husband confronted Hideyoshi HASHIBA and was defeated in the Battle of Shizugatake, which later made her killed herself with Katsuie in the Kitanosho-jo Castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, 1583, her husband Katsuie confronted Hideyoshi HASHIBA and was defeated in the Battle of Shizugatake; as a result, Ichi later killed herself with Katsuie in Kitanosho-jo Castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, word order, punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, 1583, her husband Katsuie confronted Hideyoshi HASHIBA and was defeated in the Battle of Shizugatake; as a result, Ichi later killed herself with Katsuie in Kitanosho-jo Castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>享年37。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died at the age of 37.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died at the age of 37.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died at the age of 37.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>辞世は「さらぬだに　打ちぬる程も　夏の夜の 別れを誘ふ　ほととぎすかな」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She composed a farewell poem, &apos;In a summer night like this when we have worn out and couldn&apos;t fight off the drowsiness, even if we are not ready to die, As though urging us to part, a little cuckoo is singing.&apos;</e>
<cmt>下記サイトの「（既に死を覚悟しているのに）そうでなくてさえ、疲れ果ててウトウト気を失うほど眠気をさそうこの夏の夜に、あなた様との別れをせかせるようにホトトギスが鳴いていますよ」に基づき訳しました。http://hojiro.at.webry.info/200507/article_2.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She composed a farewell poem, &apos;On a summer night such as this, when we are worn out and can&apos;t fight off drowsiness, even were we not ready to die, a little cuckoo is singing, as though urging us to part.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Word choice, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She composed a farewell poem, &apos;On a summer night such as this, when we are worn out and can&apos;t fight off drowsiness, even were we not ready to die, a little cuckoo is singing, as though urging us to part.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>墓所：福井県福井市の西光寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her graveyard: Saiko-ji Temple in Fukui City, Fukui Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is in Saiko-ji Temple in Fukui City, Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is in Saiko-ji Temple in Fukui City, Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>菩提寺：福井県福井市の自性院 (福井市)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her family temple: Jishoin Temple (Fukui City) in Fukui City, Fukui Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her family temples: Jishoin Temple (Fukui City) in Fukui City, Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her family temples: Jishoin Temple (Fukui City) in Fukui City, Fukui Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>滋賀県高島市の幡岳寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bangaku-ji Temple in Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bangaku-ji Temple in Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bangaku-ji Temple in Takashima City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>戒名：東禅院殿直伝貞正大姉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist names): Zen templeDaishi (a lady Buddhist)</e>
<cmt>戒名の読み方、意味ともに、用語集、サイトでも検索できず、訳不能でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist names): Higashi Zen temple, ____________ Daishi (a lady Buddhist).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist names): Higashi Zen temple, ____________ Daishi (a lady Buddhist).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>（自性院照月宗貞とも伝わる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Another Kaimyo, Jishoin Temple---- has also come down)</e>
<cmt>戒名の読み方、意味ともに、用語集、サイトでも検索できず、訳不能でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Another Kaimyo, Jishoin Temple, ___________ has also been handed down.)</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Another Kaimyo, Jishoin Temple, ___________ has also been handed down.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>小谷城跡：滋賀県長浜市（旧浅井町）と湖北町にまたがる小谷山山頂に旧跡あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The site of Odani-jo Castle: It is on the top of Mt. Odani which extends between Nagahama City (the former Asai-cho) and Kohoku-cho, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site of the Odani-jo Castle ruins: Located on top of Mt. Odani, which extends between Nagahama City (former Asai-cho) and Kohoku-cho, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site of the Odani-jo Castle ruins: Located on top of Mt. Odani, which extends between Nagahama City (former Asai-cho) and Kohoku-cho, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>小谷寺には、市の念持仏と伝えられている愛染明王が納められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizen Myoo (Ragaraja) which is said to have been Nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person) of Ichi remains in Odani-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An Aizen Myoo (Ragaraja) which is said to have been a Nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person) belonging to Ichi remains in Odani-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An Aizen Myoo (Ragaraja) which is said to have been a Nenjibutsu (a small statue of Buddha kept beside the person) belonging to Ichi remains in Odani-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、戦国一の美女と賞され、さらに聡明だったとも伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been told that she was the most beautiful woman in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Ichi was the most beautiful woman in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Ichi was the most beautiful woman in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) and bright as well.</e>
<cmt>大文字「聡明」の訳を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>着物の「おはしょり」を作らない独特の着付け方をした肖像画（高野山　持明院蔵）が伝えられている（但し、この時代の着物は女性でも「対丈」に作られるため「おはしょり」がないのが普通である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remains a portrait of her (Owned by Jimyo-in Temple in Mt. Koya) with peculiar kimono-wearingin which she wore a Kimono without &apos;Ohashori&apos; (tucking up the bottom of a kimono) (However, a Kimono for a woman in those days was designed with &apos;Tsuitake&apos; (the length of one&apos;s body), which made it common not to have &apos;Ohashori&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There remains a portrait of her (owned by Jimyo-in Temple on Mt. Koya) in which she wears a kimono in a peculiar fashion, without &apos;Ohashori&apos; (tucking up the bottom of a kimono); however, in those days, kimono for women were designed to &apos;Tsuitake&apos; (the length of one&apos;s body), which made it common not to have &apos;Ohashori&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation, capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There remains a portrait of her (owned by Jimyo-in Temple on Mt. Koya) in which she wears a kimono in a peculiar fashion, without &apos;Ohashori&apos; (tucking up the bottom of a kimono); however, in those days, kimono for women were designed to &apos;Tsuitake&apos; (the length of one&apos;s body), which made it common not to have &apos;Ohashori&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>信長は「市が男だったなら、良き武将となったであろう」とまで述べたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga is said to have even mentioned that &apos;if Ichi had been a man, she would have become a good Busho (Japanese military commander).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga is even said to have mentioned that &quot;If Ichi had been a man, she would have been a good Busho (Japanese military commander).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga is even said to have mentioned that &quot;If Ichi had been a man, she would have been a good Busho (Japanese military commander).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、市は秀吉を毛嫌いしており、勝家が自害するときに城から脱出するように勧めたが、市は受け入れずに勝家と運命を共にしたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Ichi had an instinctive dislike of Hideyoshi, who urged Ichi to escape from the castle before Katsuie killed himself, however, Ichi is said to have not accept it and shared the fate with Katsuie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Ichi had an instinctive dislike of Hideyoshi; he urged Ichi to escape from the castle before Katsuie killed himself, but Ichi is said to have rejected this and shared Katsuie&apos;s fate.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word order, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Ichi had an instinctive dislike of Hideyoshi; he urged Ichi to escape from the castle before Katsuie killed himself, but Ichi is said to have rejected this and shared Katsuie&apos;s fate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>死を賭してまで秀吉を避けた理由としては、ただし、秀吉は彼女に熱烈な好意を抱いていたとされ、小谷落城の際も賤ヶ岳落城の際にも母子の生命を何とか救おうとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While she avoided Hideyoshi even at the risk of death, Hideyoshi is thought to have felt passionate affection for her and tried to save the lives of the mother and children by some means or other at the time of not only the surrender of the Odani-jo Castle but also of the surrender of the castle in Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt>文章をつなぐため、「死を賭してまで秀吉を避けたが、秀吉は」として訳しました。下記サイトでは、次の文章が「ただし」の前に入っています。これは省略されたものと解釈しました。「秀吉が猿顔で長政に比べるべくもない醜男であったこと、または秀吉が信長、長政や勝家と異なり成り上がり者であったこと、さらに、夫長政の死後、戦国の倣いとはいえ、市の生んだ長男とされる万福丸が秀吉の手によって磔にされた事項などが考えられている。」http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%81%8A%E5%B8%82%E3%81%AE%E6%96%B9</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While she avoided Hideyoshi even at the risk of death, Hideyoshi is thought to have felt passionate affection for her; he tried to somehow save the lives of both mother and children during both the surrender of the Odani-jo Castle and the surrender of the castle in Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word order, word choice, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While she avoided Hideyoshi even at the risk of death, Hideyoshi is thought to have felt passionate affection for her; he tried to somehow save the lives of both mother and children during both the surrender of the Odani-jo Castle and the surrender of the castle in Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また後年茶々（淀殿）を側室に迎えたのも、三姉妹の中で彼女が一番市に似ていたから、と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the reason why Hideyoshi got married with Chacha (Yodo-dono) as a concubine is said to have been that Chacha looked like Ichi most among the three sisters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Hideyoshi is said to have taken Chacha (Yodo-dono) as a concubine because, of her three sisters, Chacha most closely resembled Ichi.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Hideyoshi is said to have taken Chacha (Yodo-dono) as a concubine because, of her three sisters, Chacha most closely resembled Ichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>袋の両端を縛った「小豆袋」で信長に危機（挟み撃ち）を伝えた逸話などが知られるが、俗説である疑いが強い（彼女が夫と仲睦まじかったのは有名であり、当時の通例を考えても、完全に浅井側の人間であったとされる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known there is an anecdote about her having informed Nobunaga of a crisis (an attack on both sides) by giving him a &apos;bag of azuki beans&apos; sealed on both sides, however, it is strongly suspected of being a popular belief (It is well-known that she was harmonious with her husband and she was considered to have been completely on the side of the Asai family in view of the common practice in those day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known there is an anecdote about her having informed Nobunaga of a crisis (an attack from both sides) by giving him a &apos;bag of azuki beans&apos; sealed on both sides; however, because it is well-known that she lived in harmony with her husband and was considered to have been completely on the side of the Asai family, as was the common practice in those day, this is strongly suspected of being an old wives&apos; tale.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known there is an anecdote about her having informed Nobunaga of a crisis (an attack from both sides) by giving him a &apos;bag of azuki beans&apos; sealed on both sides; however, because it is well-known that she lived in harmony with her husband and was considered to have been completely on the side of the Asai family, as was the common practice in those day, this is strongly suspected of being an old wives&apos; tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>織田家は美男美女の家系で知られるが中でも市やその姉（または妹）、お犬の方の美しさは有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oda family was known as a family line of good looks and, especially, the beauty of Ichi and her elder sister (or younger sister) Oinu no kata was famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oda family was known for its good looks and the beauty of Ichi and her elder (or possibly younger) sister, Oinu no kata, was especially famous.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oda family was known for its good looks and the beauty of Ichi and her elder (or possibly younger) sister, Oinu no kata, was especially famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>兄弟では兄である信長も美形であったと伝わるが、信長や市の同腹の兄妹であるとされる織田秀孝は信長よりたいへんな美男子であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among her brothers, Nobunaga, her elder brother is also said to have been handsome and Hidetaka ODA who is regarded as an elder maternal half brother of Nobunaga and Ichi is said to have been more handsome than Nobunaga was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of her brothers, her elder brother Nobunaga is also said to have been handsome, and Hidetaka ODA, who is regarded as an elder maternal half-brother of Nobunaga and Ichi, is said to have been more handsome still.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of her brothers, her elder brother Nobunaga is also said to have been handsome, and Hidetaka ODA, who is regarded as an brother with the same mother, of Nobunaga and Ichi, is said to have been more handsome still.</e>
<cmt>同腹→brother with the same mother</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>三人の娘たちの行く末を心配していた市は、庇護を受ける羽柴秀吉に書状を送るなど母としての娘たちに対する深い愛情が伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichi who was feeling anxious about the future of the three daughters wrote letters to Hideyoshi, her guardian and so on, by which her deep affection as a mother for her daughters can be known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anxious about the futures of her three daughters, Ichi wrote letters to Hideyoshi, their guardian; these and other actions show her deep affection as a mother for her daughters.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anxious about the futures of her three daughters, Ichi wrote letters to Hideyoshi, their guardian; these and other actions show her deep affection as a mother for her daughters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>兄信長や信包の市に対する待遇が姉妹の中ではたいへん厚かったことから、最近では信長、信包の同腹の妹であるとされ母は土田御前であるという見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In view of the fact that her elder brothers, Nobunaga and Nobukane treated Ichi far warmly as compared with other sisters, there is a viewpoint recently that she was a younger maternal half sister of Nobunaga and Nobukane and her mother was Dota-gozen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the fact that her elder brothers Nobunaga and Nobukane treated Ichi with much more warmth than they did other sisters, a recent viewpoint claims that she was a younger sister with the same mother, of Nobunaga and Nobukane, and that her mother was Dota-gozen.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the fact that her elder brothers Nobunaga and Nobukane treated Ichi with much more warmth than they did other sisters, a recent viewpoint claims that she was a younger sister with the same mother, of Nobunaga and Nobukane, and that her mother was Dota-gozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>このため市の同腹の兄弟とされるのは信長、織田信行、信包、織田秀孝であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such being the case, it is understood that her maternal half brothers were Nobunaga, Nobuyuki ODA, Nobukane and Hidetaka ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this is the case, Nobunaga, Nobuyuki ODA, Nobukane and Hidetaka ODA are considered to have been her brothers with the same mother.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this is the case, Nobunaga, Nobuyuki ODA, Nobukane and Hidetaka ODA are considered to have been her brothers with the same mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また、信長が最も可愛がった妹であったと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is said to have been the younger sister loved by Nobunaga most.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is also said to have been Nobunaga&apos;s favorite younger sister.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is also said to have been Nobunaga&apos;s favorite younger sister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="43">
<j>因みに、信長は大名間の政略婚にはほとんど養女を用いていた（育てた訳ではなく、形式上養女にして送り出す形）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, Nobunaga used adopted daughters in most cases for marriages for political reasons into Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) families (He did not bring up but adopted those female persons for form&apos;s sake and gave the adopted daughters away in marriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, in most cases, Nobunaga used adopted daughters for political reasons, to marry into Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) families: rather than bringing them up, he adopted girls in form only and gave these adopted daughters away in marriage.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, in most cases, Nobunaga used adopted daughters for political reasons, to marry into Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) families: rather than bringing them up, he adopted girls in form only and gave these adopted daughters away in marriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>実の妹や娘で他国に嫁いだのは、この市を除けば松平信康に嫁いだ徳姫のみであり、それ以外は全て家臣か公家との縁組だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real sisters and daughters who married into other Provinces was only Tokuhime who married Nobuyasu MATSUDAIRA except Ichi, and all others married into the families of his retainers or Kuge (Court nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of his real sisters and daughters, except for Ichi, only Tokuhime married into another province by marrying Nobuyasu MATSUDAIRA; all others married into the families of his retainers or Kuge (court nobles).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of his real sisters and daughters, except for Ichi, only Tokuhime married into another province by marrying Nobuyasu MATSUDAIRA; all others married into the families of his retainers or Kuge (court nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="45">
<j>長女の淀殿は父の長政の十七回忌、母の市の七回忌に菩提を弔うために、肖像画を描かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodo-dono, Ichi&apos;s eldest daughter made portraits painted for Nagamasa, her father on the 16th anniversary of his death and for Ichi, her mother on the 6th anniversary of her death to pray to Buddha for the happiness of the dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodo-dono, Ichi&apos;s eldest daughter, had portraits painted for Nagamasa, her father, on the 16th anniversary of his death and for Ichi, her mother, on the 6th anniversary of her death, to pray to Buddha for their happiness.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodo-dono, Ichi&apos;s eldest daughter, had portraits painted for Nagamasa, her father, on the 16th anniversary of his death and for Ichi, her mother, on the 6th anniversary of her death, to pray to Buddha for their happiness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>市の肖像画は「戦国一の美人画」として名高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The portrait of Ichi is well-known as &apos;The best Bijinga (Beautiful Woman Picture) in the Sengoku period.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The portrait of Ichi is well-known as the best Bijinga (Beautiful Woman Picture) of the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The portrait of Ichi is well-known as the best Bijinga (Beautiful Woman Picture) of the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="47">
<j>市は落城の際、三姉妹に次のように言い聞かせたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the fall of the castle, Ichi is said to have advised her three daughters as follows:</e>
<cmt>セルを入れ替えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the fall of the castle, Ichi is said to have advised her three daughters as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the fall of the castle, Ichi is said to have advised her three daughters as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>「浅井の血を絶やしてはならない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Do not let the Asai family line die out.&apos;</e>
<cmt>セルを入れ替えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Do not let the Asai family line die out.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Changed single quotes to double quotes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Do not let the Asai family line die out.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>現在</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current situation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current situation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current situation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>滋賀県長浜市（旧浅井町）において、市が町のマスコットキャラクターとして親しまれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nagahama City (former Asai-cho), Shiga Prefecture, Ichi has been designed into a mascot of the city, which is popular among people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Nagahama City (former Asai-cho), Shiga Prefecture, Ichi has been designed into a city mascot which is quite popular.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nagahama City (former Asai-cho), Shiga Prefecture, Ichi has been designed into a city mascot which is quite popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Sat666(id:127263), ドルチェット(id:46458), Reggaeman(id:6214), Tom-spring(id:42457), Demeter(id:165620), Ultratomio(id:1090), Harupri(id:133581), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Sgi1962(id:80778), 鞆(id:61733), Instart(id:237878), Fumipon(id:46816), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), 代言人(id:33675), Goki(id:7107), W-SAMURAI(id:203698), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), Chao35(id:34986), LERK(id:4460), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Izayohi(id:13095), SINOBU(id:28887), Deepimpact(id:129352), Namunamu894(id:219510), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Yanahan(id:2437), ふたりはGoki鰤MaxHeart(id:19635), あいさと(id:146070), MULTIVAC(id:110454), Kagetudo(id:163875), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), MDR-SK(id:192066), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 村上ぽち(id:36746), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), Twilight2640(id:134273), Rute(id:53091), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>