<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利義持</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利 義持（あしかが よしもち）は室町幕府4代将軍である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA was the fourth shogun of Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>ローマ字表記は、対訳欄にかかわらず、いずれもヘボン式で統一</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA was the fourth shogun of Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA was the fourth shogun of Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は足利義満、母は安芸法眼の娘藤原慶子（ふじわらのよしこ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and his mother was Yoshiko FUJIWARA, a daughter of Aki Hougen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and his mother was Yoshiko FUJIWARA, a daughter of Aki Hougen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and his mother was Yoshiko FUJIWARA, a daughter of Aki Hougen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>兄弟に足利義教、足利義嗣ほか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had Yoshinori ASHIKAGA and Yoshitsugu ASHIKAGA as his brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had Yoshinori ASHIKAGA and Yoshitsugu ASHIKAGA as his brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had Yoshinori ASHIKAGA and Yoshitsugu ASHIKAGA as his brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正室は日野資康の娘日野栄子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legal wife was Eishi HINO, a daughter of Sukeyasu HINO.</e>
<cmt>資康は、他の人の名前で「すけやす」というのは見つけましたが、日野資康は確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legal wife was Eishi HINO, a daughter of Sukeyasu HINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legal wife was Eishi HINO, a daughter of Sukeyasu HINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子は足利義量。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a son named Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a son named Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a son named Yoshikazu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>義満との父子関係は険悪であったとされ、1394年（応永元）に9歳で義満より将軍職を譲られるが、太政大臣となった義満の在世中は実権がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the relationship between his father Yoshimitsu and him was bad, and even though he was given the shogun post by his father at the age of 9 in 1934 (Ouei 1), he had no real power while Yoshimitsu as Grand Minister was still alive.</e>
<cmt>太政大臣Daijyodaijinから変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the relationship between his father Yoshimitsu and him was bad, and even though he was given the shogun post by his father at the age of 9 in 1934, he had no real power while Yoshimitsu, who became the Grand Minister, was still alive.</e>
<cmt>元号。　大臣となった、で became。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the relationship between his father Yoshimitsu and him was bad, and even though he was given the shogun post by his father at the age of 9 in 1934 (Ouei 1), he had no real power while Yoshimitsu as Grand Minister was still alive.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幕府の評定も義満の居住する北山第で開催されて義持が参画する事はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Assembly of the government was also held at Kitayama-dai villa, where Yoshimitsu lived, and Yoshimochi never participated in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Assembly of the shogunate was held at Kitayama-dai villa, where Yoshimitsu lived, and Yoshimochi never participated in it.</e>
<cmt>幕府、で　shogunate。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Assembly of the shogunate was held at Kitayama-dai villa, where Yoshimitsu lived, and Yoshimochi never participated in it.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1406年（応永13）には側近の山科兄弟の事で叱責された記録が残っており、1408年（応永15）、義満死去直前に後小松天皇が「北山第」に御成した際も、義満が寵愛した異母弟の義嗣は天皇に謁見したが、義持自身は京都警備番をさせられる等、偏愛にも苦しんでいたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a record that he was reprimanded for his aides YAMASHINA brothers in 1406 (Ouei 13), and when Emperor Gokomatsu visited &quot;Kitayama-dai villa&quot; right before Yoshimitsu died, his half brother Yoshitsugu, having his father&apos;s favor, had an audience with the Emperor, but Yoshimochi was in charge of security in Kyoto, which shows he was also suffered from his father&apos;s favoritism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a record that he was reprimanded because of his aides, YAMASHINA brothers, in 1406, and when Emperor Gokomatsu visited &quot;Kitayama-dai villa&quot; right before Yoshimitsu&apos;s death, his half brother Yoshitsugu, having his father&apos;s favor, had an audience with the Emperor, but Yoshimochi was made in charge of security in Kyoto, which shows that he also suffered from his father&apos;s favoritism.</e>
<cmt>兄弟の事（が理由）で、と解釈。元号。させられる、で made を加えた。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a record that he was reprimanded because of his aides, YAMASHINA brothers, in 1406, and when Emperor Gokomatsu visited &quot;Kitayama-dai villa&quot; right before Yoshimitsu&apos;s death, his half brother Yoshitsugu, having his father&apos;s favor, had an audience with the Emperor, but Yoshimochi was made in charge of security in Kyoto, which shows that he also suffered from his father&apos;s favoritism.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>1408年（応永15）の義満死後は一時的に花の御所（室町第、京都市上京区）に住むが、翌年には2代将軍足利義詮の住んでいた三条坊門邸（京都市中京区）へ移っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshimitsu died in 1408 (Ouei 15), Yoshimochi lived in the Flower Palace (Muromachi-dai, Kamigyo ward, Kyoto city) temporarily, and moved to the residence in Sanjo-boumon (Nakagyo ward, Kyoto city) where the second shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA lived.</e>
<cmt>花の御所Hana no Gosho、三条坊門邸Sanjyoboumon-teiから変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshimitsu died in 1408, Yoshimochi lived in the Flower Palace (Muromachi-dai, Kamigyo ward, Kyoto city) temporarily, and moved to the residence in Sanjo-boumon (Nakagyo ward, Kyoto city) where the second shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA had lived.</e>
<cmt>元号。義詮は、この時代すでに亡くなっているので、had lived。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshimitsu died in 1408, Yoshimochi lived in the Flower Palace (Muromachi-dai, Kamigyo ward, Kyoto city) temporarily, and moved to the residence in Sanjo-boumon (Nakagyo ward, Kyoto city) where the second shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA had lived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、義満が造成した政務中枢「北山第」は鹿苑寺（金閣）をのぞいて全て取り壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he totally broke down &quot;Kitayama-dai villa&quot; Yoshimitsu had built as the political center, except Rokuon-ji temple (Kinkaku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he totally broke down &quot;Kitayama-dai villa&quot; which Yoshimitsu had built as the political center, with the exception of Rokuon-ji temple (Kinkaku).</e>
<cmt>文章がスムーズになるように、言葉を加えた。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he totally broke down &quot;Kitayama-dai villa&quot; which Yoshimitsu had built as the political center, with the exception of Rokuon-ji temple (Kinkaku).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>政治は、管領を務め宿老として影響力を持っていた斯波義将らに補佐され、幕政を守旧的なものに改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for his politics, he was supported by Yoshimasa SHIBA, who was in the post of Kanrei and influential as an political advisor called Shukuro, and others, and made the government administration in old-guard style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for his politics, he was supported by such persons as Yoshimasa SHIBA, who held the post of Kanrei and was influential as an political advisor called Shukuro, and others, and revised the shogunate administration to a conservative style.</e>
<cmt>義将ら、なので　such persons as。守旧的な、を　conservative　に。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for his politics, he was supported by such persons as Yoshimasa SHIBA, who held the post of Kanrei and was influential as an political advisor called Shukuro, and others, and revised the shogunate administration to a conservative style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これによって一度は失われた室町幕府の「武家政権」色を復活させようとしたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By doing so, he was allegedly trying to bring back &quot;military regime&quot; of Muromachi Shogunate, which had been once lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By doing so, he was allegedly trying to bring back &quot;military regime&quot; style of Muromachi Shogunate, which had been once lost.</e>
<cmt>色　を　styleに。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By doing so, he was allegedly trying to bring back &quot;military regime&quot; style of Muromachi Shogunate, which had been once lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>義満が庇護していた世阿弥を遠ざけ（ただし、これは義持個人の趣味の問題とする説もある）、朝廷からの父義満に対する太上天皇の追号を辞退し、1411年（応永18）には朝貢形式に対して反発の声もあった日明貿易（勘合貿易）を取り止めるなどした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He alienated Zeami, whom Yoshimitsu took under his wing, (this is also said to be a matter of Yoshimochi&apos;s personal interest, though,) declined the posthumous title as ex-Emperor to his father Yoshimitsu from the Imperial court, and ended the trade with Ming dynasty China (Kango trade), of which tribute style faced opposition, in 1411 (Ouei 18).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He alienated Zeami, whom Yoshimitsu took under his wing (however, this is also said to be a matter of Yoshimochi&apos;s personal interest), declined the posthumous title as ex-Emperor offered to his father Yoshimitsu, from the Imperial court, and ended the trade with Ming dynasty China (Kango trade), of which tribute style had faced some opposition, in 1411.</e>
<cmt>文章の順番を少し入れ替え。反発の声もあった、でみんなが反対だったわけではないので、some を加えた。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He alienated Zeami, whom Yoshimitsu took under his wing (however, this is also said to be a matter of Yoshimochi&apos;s personal interest), declined the posthumous title as ex-Emperor offered to his father Yoshimitsu, from the Imperial court, and ended the trade with Ming dynasty China (Kango trade), of which tribute style had faced some opposition, in 1411.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>1410年（応永17）には南朝 (日本)最後の天皇だった後亀山天皇が吉野へ出奔。（1416年に帰京）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1410 (Ouei 17), Emperor Gokameyama, who was the last emperor of the Southern Dynasty (Japan), took refuge in Yoshino. (He returned to Kyoto in 1416.)</e>
<cmt>南朝Nan-choから変更(1416年に帰京)は下の欄から上に移動。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1410, Emperor Gokameyama, who was the last emperor of the Southern Dynasty (Japan), took refuge in Yoshino. (He returned to Kyoto in 1416.)</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1410, Emperor Gokameyama, who was the last emperor of the Southern Dynasty (Japan), took refuge in Yoshino. (He returned to Kyoto in 1416.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1414年（応永21）にこれに呼応した北畠満雅が1412年（応永19）の称光天皇即位を不服とし、両統迭立の約束を守る事を要求する為に反乱を起こしたが、まもなく和解した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Responding this in 1414 (Ouei 21), Mitsumasa KITABATAKE expressed his dissatisfaction with accession of Emperor Shoko in 1412 (Ouei 19), and raised a revolt to demand for abiding by the agreement of the alternate enthronement, but entered settlement soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Responding to this in 1414, Mitsumasa KITABATAKE expressed his dissatisfaction with accession of Emperor Shoko in 1412, and raised a revolt to demand for abiding by the agreement of the alternate enthronement, but reconciled soon.</e>
<cmt>entered settlement だと現代ぽいので、reconciled に。元号。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Responding to this in 1414, Mitsumasa KITABATAKE expressed his dissatisfaction with accession of Emperor Shoko in 1412, and raised a revolt to demand for abiding by the agreement of the alternate enthronement, but reconciled soon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>同年には斯波義将の嫡子、斯波義重が義持の不興を買い、高野山に隠退した事件も起こっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Yoshishige SHIBA, the heir of Yoshimasa SHIBA, secluded in Mt. Koya, falling into disgrace with Yoshimochi.</e>
<cmt>義将はよしまさともよしゆきとも表記あり。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Yoshishige SHIBA, the heir of Yoshimasa SHIBA, fell into disgrace with Yoshimochi, and secluded in Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>原因→結果の順番にした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Yoshishige SHIBA, the heir of Yoshimasa SHIBA, fell into disgrace with Yoshimochi, and secluded in Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>1416年（応永23）には関東地方で上杉禅秀の乱が起こり、これに関与していた弟の義嗣を相国寺等に幽閉、2年後の1418年（応永25）に殺害している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1416 (Ouei 23), UENO Zenshu Rebellion broke out in Kanto region, and Yoshimochi confined his brother Yoshitsugu, getting involved in this, in Shokoku-ji temple, and killed him two years later in 1418 (Ouei 25).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1416, UENO Zenshu Rebellion broke out in Kanto region, and Yoshimochi confined his brother Yoshitsugu, who was involved in the rebellion, in Shokoku-ji temple, and killed him two years later in 1418.</e>
<cmt>言葉をわかりやすく。元号。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1416, UENO Zenshu Rebellion broke out in Kanto region, and Yoshimochi confined his brother Yoshitsugu, who was involved in the rebellion, in Shokoku-ji temple, and killed him two years later in 1418.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>更にその過程で義持側近の富樫満成が細川満元や斯波義重が義嗣に加担していたと告発、一説にはこの告発は義持の意向を受けたものでこれを機に一気に有力守護の発言力を削いで義持主導の幕政を確立を目指したものともいわれているが、逆に細川らの逆告発によって最終的には富樫が追放されるという事件が起こっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore in the process, Mitsunari TOGASHI, Yoshimochi&apos;s aide, accused Mitsumoto HOSOKAWA and Yoshishige SHIBA of supporting Yoshitsugu, which was also said to be planned by Yoshimochi to dampen the influence of powerful governors called Shugo at once, taking this opportunity, and to establish Yoshimochi-led government administration, but on the contrary, HOSOKAWA&apos;s reverse accusation eventually made TOGASHI outcast.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore in the process, Mitsunari TOGASHI, Yoshimochi&apos;s aide, accused Mitsumoto HOSOKAWA and Yoshishige SHIBA of supporting Yoshitsugu, which, according to a view, was planned by Yoshimochi to dampen the influence of powerful governors called Shugo at once, taking this opportunity, and to establish Yoshimochi-led shogunate administration, but on the contrary, counter-accusation by HOSOKAWA, etc., eventually resulted in TOGASHI&apos;s banishment.</e>
<cmt>一説には、でaccording to a view。最後の文の言葉を、わかりやすくするために、いくつか変えた。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore in the process, Mitsunari TOGASHI, Yoshimochi&apos;s aide, accused Mitsumoto HOSOKAWA and Yoshishige SHIBA of supporting Yoshitsugu, which, according to a view, was planned by Yoshimochi to dampen the influence of powerful governors called Shugo at once, taking this opportunity, and to establish Yoshimochi-led shogunate administration, but on the contrary, counter-accusation by HOSOKAWA, etc., eventually resulted in TOGASHI&apos;s banishment.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これら一連の事件を処理した後の1423年（応永30）に子の義量に将軍職を譲り、翌年6月に等持院で出家（実権は握り続けた）し、寺社参詣などを行いはじめるが、息子義量は1425年に早世する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1423 (Ouei 30) after settling a series of incidents, he gave the shogun post to his son Yoshikazu, and entered the priesthood in Toji-in temple in June in the following year (he kept holding real power though) and started to visit temples and shrines, but Yoshikazu died quite young in 1425.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1423, after settling a series of such incidents, he gave the shogun post to his son Yoshikazu, and entered the priesthood in Toji-in temple in June of the following year (he continued to hold real power) and started to visit temples and shrines, but Yoshikazu died quite young in 1425.</e>
<cmt>これら→　such。元号。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1423, after settling a series of such incidents, he gave the shogun post to his son Yoshikazu, and entered the priesthood in Toji-in temple in June of the following year (he continued to hold real power) and started to visit temples and shrines, but Yoshikazu died quite young in 1425.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>1427年（応永34）には赤松義則死後の赤松氏の相続の際、所領を近習の赤松持貞に預けようとすると、赤松満祐が京を出奔して領国の播磨国へ下国する事件なども起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the occasion of succession of the AKAMATSU clan after Yoshinori AKAMATSU died in 1427 (Ouei 34), he planned to leave the domain to his close aide Mochisada AKAMATSU, which made Mitsusuke AKAMATSU run away from Kyoto and go down to Harima, his governing province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the occasion of succession of the AKAMATSU clan after Yoshinori AKAMATSU died in 1427, Yoshimochi tried to leave the domain to his close aide Mochisada AKAMATSU, which made Mitsusuke AKAMATSU run away from Kyoto and go down to Harima, his governing province.</e>
<cmt>元号。その後は、混乱しないように he ではなく Yoshimochi　にした。Plan →ｔｒｙ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the occasion of succession of the AKAMATSU clan after Yoshinori AKAMATSU died in 1427, Yoshimochi tried to leave the domain to his close aide Mochisada AKAMATSU, which made Mitsusuke AKAMATSU run away from Kyoto and go down to Harima, his governing province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>義持は義量死後の後継者を定めないまま死去、享年43。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimochi died at the age of 43 without choosing a successor after Yoshikazu&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimochi died at the age of 43 without choosing a successor after Yoshikazu&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimochi died at the age of 43 without choosing a successor after Yoshikazu&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>義持の治世は懐良親王が制圧していた九州を有力大名の大友氏・大内氏・菊池氏が引き継いで統治していたり、関東地方の鎌倉公方は半独立国状態となるなど、不安定要素はいくつも存在したが、政治的には小康状態が続き、室町時代の中では比較的安定した時代であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the reign of Yoshimochi, there existed a number of unstable factors - the OHTOMO clan, the OHKOUCHI clan and the KIKUCHI clan, as powerful lords, took over and ruled Kyushyu where Prince Kanenaga had conquered, or the Kamakura ministry in Kanto region became a semi-independent state - but politically, a relaxed situation lasted and it was relatively stable times during Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt>鎌倉公方Kamakura-kuboから変更。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the reign of Yoshimochi, there existed a number of unstable factors - the OHTOMO clan, the OHKOUCHI clan and the KIKUCHI clan, as powerful lords, took over and ruled Kyushyu where Prince Kanenaga had conquered, or the Kamakura ministry in Kanto region became a semi-independent state - but politically, a brief period of tranquility lasted and it was relatively stable times during Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt>小康状態</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the reign of Yoshimochi, there existed a number of unstable factors - the OHTOMO clan, the OHKOUCHI clan and the KIKUCHI clan, as powerful lords, took over and ruled Kyushyu where Prince Kanenaga had conquered, or the Kamakura ministry in Kanto region became a semi-independent state - but politically, a brief period of tranquility lasted and it was relatively stable times during Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>義持の死後、将軍職は弟の義教が継ぐことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshimochi died, his brother Yoshinori succeeded to the shogun post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshimochi died, his brother Yoshinori succeeded to the shogun post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshimochi died, his brother Yoshinori succeeded to the shogun post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>義持は父・義満とは不仲であったといわれたが、実際の基本政策では義満の意を汲んだ政治を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshimochi was on bad terms with his father Yoshimitsu, he conducted politics taking Yoshimitsu&apos;s decision into account in his actual basic policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is said that Yoshimochi was on bad terms with his father Yoshimitsu, he conducted politics taking Yoshimitsu&apos;s intentions into account in his actual basic policy.</e>
<cmt>といわれたが、を加えた。「意」なので、intentions に。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is said that Yoshimochi was on bad terms with his father Yoshimitsu, he conducted politics taking Yoshimitsu&apos;s intentions into account in his actual basic policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>だが、義持自身が斯波義将ら有力守護に推されて政権を獲得し、有力守護に対抗するために形成した側近集団の富樫満成や赤松持貞が有力守護たちによって逆に失脚させられるなど、義満のような絶対的な将軍権威を確立する事は遂に成功しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshimochi himself came into power by the push from powerful Shugo such as Yoshimasa SHIBA, and his aide members formed to match powerful Shugo, Mitsunari TOGASHI and Mochisada AKAMATSU, were adversely ousted by powerful Shugo, which made him end up not establishing absolute authority of shogun like Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshimochi himself came into power by the push from powerful Shugo&apos;s such as Yoshimasa SHIBA, and Mitsunari TOGASHI and Mochisada AKAMATSU, who were members of his aide, formed to match powerful Shugo&apos;s, were adversely ousted by powerful Shugo&apos;s, and Yoshimochi, after all, did not succeed in establishing absolute authority of shogun as Yoshimitsu did.</e>
<cmt>Shugo を複数形に。最後の文章をわかりやすく書きなおした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshimochi himself came into power by the push from powerful Shugo&apos;s such as Yoshimasa SHIBA, and Mitsunari TOGASHI and Mochisada AKAMATSU, who were members of his aide, formed to match powerful Shugo&apos;s, were adversely ousted by powerful Shugo&apos;s, and Yoshimochi, after all, did not succeed in establishing absolute authority of shogun as Yoshimitsu did.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>法号：勝定院殿顕山道詮大禅門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist name: Shojo Inden Kenzan Dosen Daizenmon</e>
<cmt>ひとつひとつ区切って探しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist name: Shojo Inden Kenzan Dosen Daizenmon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist name: Shojo Inden Kenzan Dosen Daizenmon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>肖像画：京都市右京区の神護寺所蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Portrait: Possessed by Jingo-ji temple in Ukyo ward in Kyoto city</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Portrait: Possessed by Jingo-ji temple in Ukyo ward in Kyoto city</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Portrait: Possessed by Jingo-ji temple in Ukyo ward in Kyoto city</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of government positions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of government positions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of government positions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*date=lunar calendar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*date=lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*date=lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="31">
<j>1394年（応永元）12月17日、正五位下に叙し、左近衛中将に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 17,1934 (Ouei 19), assumed Sho Goi-ge and served as Sa-konoe chujo.</e>
<cmt>左近衛中将Sakonoechujyoから変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 17,1934, assumed Sho Goi-ge and appointed as Sa-konoe chujo.</e>
<cmt>任官なのでappointed　に。　</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 17,1934, assumed Sho Goi-ge and appointed as Sa-konoe chujo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>併せて征夷大将軍宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well as Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also appointed as Seii Taishogun by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>宣下</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also appointed as Seii Taishogun by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="33">
<j>1395年（応永2）6月3日、従四位下に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 3, 1395 (Ouei 2), promoted to Ju Shii-ge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 3, 1395, promoted to Ju Shii-ge.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 3, 1395, promoted to Ju Shii-ge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>左近衛中将兼任如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stayed as Sa-konoe chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stayed as Sa-konoe chujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stayed as Sa-konoe chujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>1396年（応永3）1月28日、美作国権守兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 28, 1396 (Ouei 3), served also as Mimasaka no Kuni Gonnokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 28, 1396, concurrently served also as Mimasaka no Kuni Gonnokami.</e>
<cmt>元号、兼任。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 28, 1396, concurrently served also as Mimasaka no Kuni Gonnokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>4月20日、正四位下に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 20, promoted to Sho Shii-ge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 20, promoted to Sho Shii-ge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 20, promoted to Sho Shii-ge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>9月12日、参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 12, appointed Councilor.</e>
<cmt>参議Sangiから変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 12, appointed Councilor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 12, appointed Councilor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>左近衛中将美作権守両官兼任如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stayed both as Sa-konoe chujo and Mimasaka no Kuni Gonnokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stayed as both Sa-konoe chujo and Mimasaka no Kuni Gonnokami.</e>
<cmt>both の位置。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stayed as both Sa-konoe chujo and Mimasaka no Kuni Gonnokami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="39">
<j>1397年（応永4）1月5日、従三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1397 (Ouei 4), promoted to Ju Sanmi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, 1397, promoted to Ju Sanmi.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1397, promoted to Ju Sanmi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>参議左近衛中将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stayed as Councilor/Sa-konoe chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stayed as Councilor/Sa-konoe chujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stayed as Councilor/Sa-konoe chujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>3月29日、権中納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 29, reassigned to Gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt>権中納言Goncyunagonから変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 29, reassigned to Gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 29, reassigned to Gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="42">
<j>1398年（応永5）1月5日、正三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1398 (Ouei 5), promoted to Sho Sanmi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, 1398, promoted to Sho Sanmi.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1398, promoted to Sho Sanmi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>権中納言如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stayed as Gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stayed as Gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stayed as Gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="44">
<j>1400年（応永7）1月5日、従二位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1400 (Ouei 7), promoted to Ju Nii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, 1400, promoted to Ju Nii.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1400, promoted to Ju Nii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>権中納言如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stayed as Gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stayed as Gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stayed as Gon chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="46">
<j>1401年（応永8）3月24日、権大納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 24, 1401 (Ouei 8), reassigned to Gon dainagon.</e>
<cmt>権大納言Gondainagonから変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 24, 1401, reassigned to Gon dainagon.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 24, 1401, reassigned to Gon dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="47">
<j>1402年（応永9）1月6日、正二位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 6, 1402 (Ouei 9), promoted to Sho Nii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 6, 1402, promoted to Sho Nii.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 6, 1402, promoted to Sho Nii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>権大納言如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stayed as Gon dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stayed as Gon dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stayed as Gon dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>11月19日、従一位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 19, promoted to Ju Ichii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 19, promoted to Ju Ichii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 19, promoted to Ju Ichii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>権大納言如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stayed as Gon dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stayed as Gon dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stayed as Gon dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="51">
<j>1406年（応永13）8月17日、右近衛大将兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 17, 1406 (Ouei 13), served also as U-konoe taisho.</e>
<cmt>右近衛大将Ukonoetaisyoから変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 17, 1406, concurrently served as U-konoe taisho.</e>
<cmt>元号、兼任。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 17, 1406, concurrently served as U-konoe taisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="52">
<j>1407年（応永14）1月5日、右馬寮御監兼務</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, 1407 (Ouei 14), served also as Umeryo Gogen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5, 1407, concurrently served as Umeryo Gogen.</e>
<cmt>元号、兼任。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1407, concurrently served as Umeryo Gogen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="53">
<j>1409年（応永16）3月23日、内大臣に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 23, 1409 (Ouei 16), reassigned to Nai daijin.</e>
<cmt>内大臣Naidaijinから変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 23, 1409, reassigned to Nai daijin.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 23, 1409, reassigned to Nai daijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>右近衛大将兼任如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stayed also as U-konoe taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also stayed also as U-konoe taisho.</e>
<cmt>Also の位置。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also stayed also as U-konoe taisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="55">
<j>1412年（応永19）5月、右近衛大将辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May, 1412 (Ouei 19), resigned as U-konoe taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May, 1412, resigned as U-konoe taisho.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May, 1412, resigned as U-konoe taisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="56">
<j>1413年（応永20）10月22日、淳和院奨学院源氏長者兼務</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 22, 1413 (Ouei 20), served also as Manager of both Junna-in and Shogaku-in.</e>
<cmt>当該両院別当を兼任することが「源氏長者」の要件であるようにWikipediaでは読み取れるので、こうしてみました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 22, 1413, concurrently served as Manager of both Junna-in and Shogaku-in.</e>
<cmt>元号、兼務。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 22, 1413, concurrently served as Manager of both Junna-in and Shogaku-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="57">
<j>1419年（応永26）8月29日、内大臣辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 29, 1419, (Ouei 26), resigned as Nai daijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 29, 1419, resigned as Nai daijin.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 29, 1419, resigned as Nai daijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="58">
<j>1422年（応永29）3月18日、征夷大将軍辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 18, 1422 (Ouei 29), resigned as Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 18, 1422, resigned as Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 18, 1422, resigned as Seii Taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>4月25日、出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 25, entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 25, entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 25, entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="60">
<j>1428年（応永35）1月18日、薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 18, 1428 (Ouei 35), died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 18, 1428, died.</e>
<cmt>元号</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 18, 1428, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>1月23日、贈太政大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 23, Given Dajo daijin as posthumous title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 23, given Dajo daijin as posthumous title.</e>
<cmt>Ｇ　小文字</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 23, given Dajo daijin as posthumous title.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>義持の偏諱を受けた人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People Yoshimochi gave part of his name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People Yoshimochi gave part of his name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People Yoshimochi gave part of his name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>二条持基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochimoto NIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochimoto NIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochimoto NIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>二条持通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochimichi NIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochimichi NIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochimichi NIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="64">
<j>赤松持貞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochisada AKAMATSU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochisada AKAMATSU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochisada AKAMATSU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="65">
<j>大内持盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochimori OUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochimori OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochimori OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="66">
<j>大内持世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiyo OUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiyo OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiyo OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="67">
<j>京極持清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochikiyo KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochikiyo KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochikiyo KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="68">
<j>京極持光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochimitsu KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochimitsu KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochimitsu KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="69">
<j>足利持氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="70">
<j>斯波持種</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochitane SHIBA</e>
<cmt>「もちたね」という表記のサイトあり。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochitane SHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochitane SHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="71">
<j>伊達持宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochimune SHIBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochimune DATE</e>
<cmt>姓の間違いを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochimune DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="72">
<j>土岐持益</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochimasu TOKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochimasu TOKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochimasu TOKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="73">
<j>畠山持国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="74">
<j>細川持有</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiari HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>確認とれず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiari HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiari HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="75">
<j>細川持賢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochikata HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochikata HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochikata HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="76">
<j>細川持元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochimoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochimoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochimoto HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="77">
<j>細川持之</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiyuki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiyuki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiyuki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="78">
<j>山名宗全（持豊）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Souzen (Mochitoyo) YAMANA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Souzen (Mochitoyo) YAMANA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Souzen (Mochitoyo) YAMANA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="79">
<j>山名持熙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochihiro YAMANA</e>
<cmt>確認とれず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochihiro YAMANA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochihiro YAMANA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>登場作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Books he appears in</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Books he appears in</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Books he appears in</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>山田風太郎『室町の大予言』（文藝春秋／文春文庫『室町少年倶楽部』収録、1995年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Great Prophecy in Muromachi&quot; by Futaro YAMADA (printed by Bungeishunju/Bunshun Bunko &quot;Muromachi Boys Club&quot;, 1995)</e>
<cmt>過去に参考文献名を英訳した際、特に英訳版が有名でない限り、訳せる言葉はそのまま訳しましたので、今回もそうしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Great Prophecy in Muromachi&quot; by Futaro YAMADA (published by Bungeishunju/included in Bunshun Bunko &quot;Muromachi Boys Club&quot;, 1995)</e>
<cmt>印刷ではなく出版。収録、を加えた。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Great Prophecy in Muromachi&quot; by Futaro YAMADA (published by Bungeishunju/included in Bunshun Bunko &quot;Muromachi Boys Club,&quot; 1995)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>坂口尚『あっかんべェ一休』（講談社／講談社漫画文庫、1993～1996年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Akkanbe Ikkyu&quot; by Hisashi SAKAGUCHI (printed by Kodansha/Kodansha Manga Bunko, 1993-1996)</e>
<cmt>上記同様。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Akkanbe Ikkyu&quot; by Hisashi SAKAGUCHI (published by Kodansha/Kodansha Manga Bunko, 1993-1996)</e>
<cmt>出版。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Akkanbe Ikkyu&quot; by Hisashi SAKAGUCHI (published by Kodansha/Kodansha Manga Bunko, 1993-1996)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), JAnDbot(id:66507), 花蝶風月雪月花警部(id:163674), Nnh(id:474), たね(id:10372), Reggaeman(id:6214), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Eskimbot(id:29676), Yanahan(id:2437), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kamakura(id:472), Ash Crow(id:26765), でここ(id:9565), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Natunohi(id:6550), Azusayumi7(id:21082), A-Taul(id:41790), 代言人(id:33675), こぶまき(id:38278), Louperibot(id:128971), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>