<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>康慶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>康慶（こうけい、生没年不詳）は、平安時代末期 - 鎌倉時代初期の仏師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokei (birth and death dates are unknown) was a Busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues) from the last years of the Heian era through the early years of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokei (birth and death dates are unknown) was a Busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues) from the last years of the Heian era through the early years of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokei (birth and death dates are unknown) was a Busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues) from the last years of the Heian period through the early years of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>慶派の基礎を築く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He established the foundation for Kei (Kokei) school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He established the foundation of the Kei (Kokei) school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established the foundation of the Keiha school.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>興福寺を中心に活動した仏師で、奈良仏師の系譜に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took an active role mainly in Kofuku-ji Temple and belonged to the family record of Nara Busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues in Nara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took an active role mainly in Kofuku-ji Temple and belonged to the family record of Nara Busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues in Nara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took an active role mainly in Kofuku-ji Temple and belonged to the family record of Nara Busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues in Nara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>康助または康朝の弟子とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have been a disciple of Kosuke or Kocho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have been a disciple of Kosuke or Kocho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to have been a disciple of Kosuke or Kocho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>平重衡の南都焼き討ち（治承4年・1180年）後の復興造仏の中心人物として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He played an central role in reconstructing Buddhist Statues after the fire of the southern capital set by TAIRA no Shigehira in 1180.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He played a central role in reconstructing Buddhist Statues after the fire of the southern capital set by TAIRA no Shigehira in 1180.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He played a central role in reconstructing Buddhist statues after Nanto Yakiuchi (the Incident of Heishi&apos;s army setting fire to the temples in Nanto) set by TAIRA no Shigehira in 1180.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、詳しい経歴には不明の部分が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, considerably less is known about his specific career.</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>康慶は「慶派」と呼ばれる仏師系譜の基礎を築いた人物で、子に運慶、弟子に快慶などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He established the foundation for a family record of Busshi called &quot;Kei school,&quot; having his son Unkei and disciples including Kaikei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He established the foundation for family records of Busshi called &quot;Kei school,&quot; with his son Unkei and disciples including Kaikei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established the foundation for family records of Busshi called &apos;Keiha school,&apos; with his son Unkei and disciples including Kaikei.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>康慶の生没年は未詳だが、仁平2年（1152年）に吉祥天像（現存しない）を制作したことが史料上の初見である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His birth and death dates are unknown but it is his first appearance in a historical record that he built a Statue of Kisshoten (not existing) in 1152.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His birth and death dates are unknown, but it is his first appearance in a historical record mentioning that he built a Statue of Kisshoten (not presently existing) in 1152.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His birth and death dates are unknown, but it is his first appearance in a historical record mentioning that he built a statue of Kisshoten (Laksmi) (not presently existing) in 1152.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>康慶は後白河天皇の蓮華王院五重塔の造仏の功をもって、治承元年（1177年）、法橋の僧位を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokei attained Hokkyo (the third highest rank or artists of Soi (rank of Buddhist monk) in 1177, in consideration of building a Gojunoto (five-story pagoda) of Rengeo-in for Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokei attained Hokkyo (the third highest rank or artists of Soi (rank of Buddhist monk) in 1177, in consideration of building a Gojunoto (five-story pagoda) of Rengeo-in for Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokei attained the Buddhist rank as hokkyo (the third highest rank for Buddhist priests) in 1177, in consideration of building the five-story pagoda of Rengeoin Temple for Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>康慶は、治承4年（1180年）の平重衡の焼き討ちで全焼した、奈良・興福寺の復興造仏に参加し、一門の仏師を率いて、興福寺南円堂の本尊・不空羂索観音像以下の諸仏の造像にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokei participated in the reconstruction of Buddhist Statues of Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara, which had been burnt down in the fire set by TAIRA no Shigehira in 1180, and then led Busshi of his school to construct statues which include statute of Honzon (the principal image (or group of images) of worship at a Buddhist temple) and the Statue of Fukukensaku Kannon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokei participated in the reconstruction of Buddhist Statues of Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara, which had been burnt down in the fire set by TAIRA no Shigehira in 1180, and then led Busshi of his school to construct statues which included the statute of Honzon (the principal image -or group of images, of worship at a Buddhist temple) and the Statue of Fukukensaku Kannon.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokei participated in the reconstruction of Buddhist statues of Kofuku-ji Temple in Nara, which had been burnt down in the fire set by TAIRA no Shigehira in 1180, and then led Busshi of his school to construct statues which included the principal image, the statue of Fukukenjaku Kannon (Kannon of the Never Empty Lasso).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>文治5年（1189年）に完成したこれらの像は現存し、康慶の代表作であるのみならず、鎌倉時代彫刻の最初を飾る名品とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These statues completed in 1189 are existing and recognized as fine arts marking the beginning of sculptures in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These statues completed in 1189 are existing and recognized as fine art marking the beginning of sculptures during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These statues completed in 1189 are existing and recognized not only an representative work of Kokei but also fine arts marking the beginning of sculptures during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>康慶は建久5年（1194年）以前に、法橋より一段上の僧位である法眼の位を得ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokei was granted the rank of Hogen (the second highest rank for artists of Buddhist sculpture), a step higher than Hokkyo before 1194.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokei was granted the rank of Hogen before 1194 (the second highest rank for artists of Buddhist sculpture), a step higher than Hokkyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before 1194 Kokei was granted the rank of Hogen (the second highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests), a step higher than Hokkyo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>建久7年（1196年）、東大寺大仏殿の脇侍像・四天王像の造立に参加したのが史料上確認できる最後の事績である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His last achievement recorded in historical records is participation in the construction of Wakiji zo (Attendants Statues) and Shitenno zo (Four Devas Statues) of Daibutsuden (the Great Buddha Hall) in Todai-ji Temple in 1196.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His last achievement recorded in historical records was his participation in the construction of Wakiji zo (Attendants Statues) and Shitenno zo (Four Devas Statues) of Daibutsuden (the Great Buddha Hall) in Todai-ji Temple in 1196.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His last achievement in historical records was his participation in the construction of Wakiji-zo (Attendants Statues) and Shitenno-zo (Four Devas Statues) of Daibutsuden (the Great Buddha Hall) in Todai-ji Temple in 1196.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>前述の仁平2年（1152年）の吉祥天像造立からは半世紀近くを経ており、ほどなく没したものと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that he died soon after this construction because almost a half century had passed since 1152--the year when he built Statue of Kisshoten as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that he died soon after this construction because almost a half century had passed since 1152--the year when he built the Statue of Kisshoten mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that he died soon after this construction because almost a half century had passed since 1152, the year when he built the statue of Kisshoten mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masterpieces</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masterpieces</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masterpieces</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>興福寺南円堂諸仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Statues of Nanendo hall in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statues of Nanendo hall in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statues of Nanendo hall in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>不空羂索観音像（国宝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Statue of Fukukensaku Kannon (National treasure)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Statue of Fukukensaku Kannon (National treasure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statue of Fukukensaku Kannon (National treasure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>四天王像（重要文化財） - 現在は中金堂に安置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shitenno zo (Four Devas Statues) (important cultural assets) - enshrined in Chukondo hall today</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shitenno zo (Four Devas Statues) (important cultural assets) - enshrined in Chukondo hall today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shitenno-zo (important cultural property): Enshrined in Chukondo hall today.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>法相六祖像（国宝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the images of Hosso Rokuso (six high priests of the Hosso Sect) (National treasure)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the images of Hosso Rokuso (six high priests of the Hosso Sect) (National treasure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Statues of Hosso Rokuso (six high priests of the Hosso Sect) (National treasure)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>以上の諸仏は、治承4年（1180年）の平重衡の南都焼き討ち後の再興像で、文治5年（1189年）に完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These statues were reconstructed after the fire of the southern capital set by TAIRA no Shigehira in 1180, and they were completed in 1189.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These statues were reconstructed after the fire of the southern capital set by TAIRA no Shigehira in 1180, and they were completed in 1189.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These statues were reconstructed after Nanto Yakiuchi set by TAIRA no Shigehira in 1180, and they were completed in 1189.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>興福寺は藤原氏の氏寺だが、中でも南円堂は藤原氏一門の崇敬が篤い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kofuku-ji Temple was the family temple of the Fujiwara clan; in particular Nanendo hall was greatly revered by the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofuku-ji Temple was the family temple of the Fujiwara clan; in particular the Nanendo hall was greatly revered by the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofuku-ji Temple was the family temple of the Fujiwara clan; in particular the Nanendo hall was greatly revered by the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>氏の長者の九条兼実が南円堂諸仏の復興に深く関わっていることは、兼実の日記『玉葉』から知ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanezane&apos;s diary &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; shows how deeply Kanezane KUJO, Uji no choja (chieftain of family), was related to the reconstruction of statues in Nanendo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanezane&apos;s diary &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; shows how deeply Kanezane KUJO, Uji no choja (chieftain of family), was related to the reconstruction of statues in Nanendo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanezane&apos;s diary &quot;Gyokuyo&quot; shows how deeply Kanezane KUJO, Uji no choja (chieftain of family), was related to the reconstruction of statues in Nanendo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>地蔵菩薩坐像（静岡・瑞林寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jizo-Bosatsu zazo (Buddhist statue of a sitting children&apos;s guardian deity) (Zuirin-ji Temple, Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jizo-Bosatsu zazo (Buddhist statue of a sitting children&apos;s guardian deity) (Zuirin-ji Temple, Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seated statue of Jizo Bosatsu (Jizo Bodhisattva) (Zuirin-ji Temple, Shizuoka Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>治承元年（1177年）、仏師法橋康慶が小仏師を率いて造立した旨の銘記を有する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue bears an inscription that Kokei led Sho bussi (disciples of Busshi) to construct the statue in 1177.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue bears an inscription that Kokei led Sho bussi (disciples of Busshi) constructed the statue in 1177.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue bears an inscription that Kokei led Sho busshi (disciples of Busshi) constructed the statue in 1177.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>銘記の「康慶」の「康」字は当初判読不能とされたが、その後の赤外線テレビによる解読によって「康」字であることが確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the inscription, a Kanji letters of &quot;Ko&quot;of &quot;Kokei,&quot; was illegible but have been confirmed as &quot;Ko&quot; of Kokei under infrared video.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the inscription, the Kanji characters of &quot;Ko&quot;of &quot;Kokei,&quot; was illegible, but have been confirmed as &quot;Ko&quot; of Kokei under infrared video.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the inscription, the Kanji characters of &apos;Ko&apos; of &apos;Kokei,&apos; was illegible, but have been confirmed as &apos;Ko&apos; of Kokei by the later deciphering under infrared TV.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>伎楽面（治道）（奈良・東大寺） - 建久7年（1196年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gigaku men (masks for Gigaku, an ancient masked drama) (Todai-ji Temple, Nara Prefecture) - in 1196</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gigaku men (masks for Gigaku, an ancient masked drama) (Todai-ji Temple, Nara Prefecture) - in 1196</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gigaku-men Mask (masks for Gigaku, an ancient masked drama) of Chido (the role of usher) (Todai-ji Temple, Nara Prefecture): In 1196.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>伎楽面（力士）（京都・神童寺） - 建久7年（1196年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gigaku men (role of a strong man) (Jindo-ji Temple, Kyoto Prefecture) - in 1196</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gigaku men (role of a strong man) (Jindo-ji Temple, Kyoto Prefecture) - in 1196</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gigaku men of Rikishi (role of a strong man) (Jindo-ji Temple, Kyoto Prefecture): In 1196.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 再通行人(id:157079), Yas(id:739), 浩(id:70121), Urania(id:7213), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>