<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>木曾基宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimune KISO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimune KISO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimune KISO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>木曾 義宗（きそ よしむね、生没年不詳）は、鎌倉時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimune KISO (dates of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimune KISO (year of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>統一用語のうちの一つにあったのでそれに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimune KISO (year of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>西筑摩郡誌では信濃国木曾谷木曾家初代当主としている人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Nishichikuma-gun shi (The Records of Nishichikuma-gun County), he was the first head of the Kiso family in the Kiso-dani Valley, Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>｢西筑摩郡誌」の定訳不明のため、&quot;Nishichikuma-gun shi&quot; (The Records of Nishichikuma-gun County)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Nishichikuma-gun shi (The Records of Nishichikuma-gun County), he was the first head of the Kiso family in the Kiso-dani Valley, Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Nishichikuma-gun shi (The Records of Nishichikuma-gun County), he was the first head of the Kiso family in the Kiso-dani Valley, Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「基宗」は大石系図による義宗の誤記であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese characters of his first name, &apos;基宗,&apos; as appear in the genealogical table of the Oishi family, are said to have been a writing error; it should be correctly written as &apos;義宗.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese characters of his first name recorded in the genealogical table of the Oishi family, &apos;基宗,&apos; are said to have been a writing error for &apos;義宗.&apos;</e>
<cmt>分かりやすいよう、書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese characters of his first name recorded in the genealogical table of the Oishi family, &apos;基宗,&apos; are said to have been a writing error for &apos;義宗.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>だが、義宗を木曽家初代とするのは西筑摩郡誌の考察のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is only speculation in the Nishichikuma-gun shi (The Records of Nishichikuma-gun County) that regarded Yoshimune as the first head of the Kiso family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is only Nishichikuma-gun shi (The Records of Nishichikuma-gun County) that regarded Yoshimune as the first head of the Kiso family.</e>
<cmt>speculationはｈ不要かと思い、除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is only Nishichikuma-gun shi (The Records of Nishichikuma-gun County) that regarded Yoshimune as the first head of the Kiso family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これに関東大石氏の伝承も絡まって、諸事不鮮明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It remains unclear as to who really was the first head of the Kiso family as there are various speculations, including the tradition handed down within the Oishi family of Kanto Region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It remains unclear as to who the real first head of the Kiso family was, as there are various speculations, including the tradition handed down within the Oishi family of Kanto Region.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすいよう、書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It remains unclear as to who the real first head of the Kiso family was, as there are various speculations, including the tradition handed down within the Oishi family of Kanto Region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>信濃国木曽の「木曽系図」では、義仲の三男義基（よしもと）を初代とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &apos;Kiso keizu&apos; (The Genealogical table of the Kiso family) of Kiso, Shinano Province, the third son of Yoshinaka, Yoshimoto, is said to have been the first head of the Kiso family.</e>
<cmt>「木曽系図」の定訳不明のため、&quot;Kiso keizu&quot; (the genealogical table of the Kiso family)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &apos;Kiso keizu&apos; (The Genealogical table of the Kiso family) of Kiso, Shinano Province, the third son of Yoshinaka, Yoshimoto, is said to have been the first head of the Kiso family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &apos;Kiso keizu&apos; (The Genealogical table of the Kiso family) of Kiso, Shinano Province, the third son of Yoshinaka, Yoshimoto, is said to have been the first head of the Kiso family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>通説では源義仲の四男とされ、母は巴御前とするものもあるが、不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a prevailing view that he was the fourth son of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka and his mother was Tomoe Gozen, but the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a prevailing view that he was the fourth son of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka and his mother was Tomoe Gozen, but the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a prevailing view that he was the fourth son of MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka and his mother was Tomoe Gozen, but the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>木曾義茂・木曾経義らの父という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Yoshimune was a father of Yoshishige and Tsuneyoshi KISO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Yoshimune was the father of Yoshishige and Tsuneyoshi KISO.</e>
<cmt>こちらの方が自然かと思い、書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Yoshimune was the father of Yoshishige and Tsuneyoshi KISO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal History</e>
<cmt>経歴はPersonal Historyを採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼の事項は木曾家の家譜『高遠記集成』（『木曽福島町史』）と併せて、『木曽考』、『西筑摩郡誌』、『木曽殿伝記』に見えるが、上記のごとく義基との混同が甚だしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his name appears in the &quot;Kiso-ko&quot; (A Study of the Kiso Family), &quot;Nishichikuma-gun shi&quot; (the Records of Nishi chikuma-gun County), &quot;Kiso-dono Denki&quot; (Biography of the Kiso Family), along with the historical record of the Kiso family, &quot;Takatoki Shusei&quot;(Collection of history of Takato) and &quot;Kiso-fukushima choshi&quot; (History of Kiso-fukushima), he is often confused with Yoshimune as has been noted above.</e>
<cmt>『高遠記集成』（『木曽福島町史』）、『木曽考』、『西筑摩郡誌』、『木曽殿伝記』定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his name appears in the &quot;Kiso-ko&quot; (A Study of the Kiso Family), &quot;Nishichikuma-gun shi&quot; (the Records of Nishi chikuma-gun County), &quot;Kiso-dono Denki&quot; (Biography of the Kiso Family), along with the historical record of the Kiso family, &quot;Takatoki Shusei&quot;(Collection of history of Takato) and &quot;Kiso-fukushima choshi&quot; (History of Kiso-fukushima city), he is often confused with Yoshimune as has been noted above.</e>
<cmt>説明を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his name appears in the &quot;Kiso-ko&quot; (A Study of the Kiso Family), &quot;Nishichikuma-gun shi&quot; (the Records of Nishi chikuma-gun County), &quot;Kiso-dono Denki&quot; (Biography of the Kiso Family), along with the historical record of the Kiso family, &quot;Takatoki Shusei&quot;(Collection of history of Takato) and &quot;Kiso-fukushima choshi&quot; (History of Kiso-fukushima city), he is often confused with Yoshimune as has been noted above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>それによると、父・義仲が近江国粟津で石田為久に討たれた後に、兄・源義高 (清水冠者)が北条氏に殺害されると、母・巴御前は郷里・信濃国で義宗を出産したとされ、信州木曽福島町の山奥に身を潜めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the records, after his father, Yoshinaka, was killed by Tamehisa ISHIDA in Awazu, Omi Province, and his older brother, MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka (Shimizu no Kanja), was killed by the Hojo clan, his mother, Tomoe Gozen, is said to have given birth to Yoshimune in her home town of Shinano Province, and hid deep in the mountains in Kiso fukushima Town, Shinsyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the records, after his father, Yoshinaka, was killed by Tamehisa ISHIDA in Awazu, Omi Province, and also his older brother, MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka (Shimizu no Kanja), by the Hojo clan, his mother, Tomoe Gozen, is said to have given birth to Yoshimune in her home town of Shinano Province, and hid herself with the baby deep in the mountains in Kiso fukushima Town, Shinsyu.</e>
<cmt>読みやすいように書き換え、説明も補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the records, after his father, Yoshinaka, was killed by Tamehisa ISHIDA in Awazu, Omi Province, and also his older brother, MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka (Shimizu no Kanja), by the Hojo clan, his mother, Tomoe Gozen, is said to have given birth to Yoshimune in her home town of Shinano Province, and hid herself with the baby deep in the mountains in Kiso fukushima Town, Shinsyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>後に、縁戚関係にある上野国沼田の豪族で、藤原秀郷沼田氏当主・沼田家国（伊予国守）を頼って、その庇護を受けたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, she is said to have looked to one of her relatives, Iekuni NUMATA (also known as Iyo no kuni no kami [Governor of Iyo Province]), the head of the local ruling family of Numata, Kozuke Province and the Numata clan of FUJIWARA no Hidesato house, for help and lived under their protection.</e>
<cmt>「藤原秀郷」は「藤原秀郷流」&quot;FUJIWARA no Hidesato house&quot;と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, she is said to have looked to one of her relatives, Iekuni NUMATA (also known as Iyo no kuni no kami [Governor of Iyo Province]), the head of the local ruling family of Numata, Kozuke Province and the Numata clan of FUJIWARA no Hidesato line, for help and lived under their protection.</e>
<cmt>流はhouseからlineに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, she is said to have looked to one of her relatives, Iekuni NUMATA (also known as Iyo no kuni no kami [Governor of Iyo Province]), the head of the local ruling family of Numata, Kozuke Province and the Numata clan of FUJIWARA no Hidesato line, for help and lived under their protection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その間に義宗は、家国の養子となり「沼田義宗」と称したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that time, Yoshimune is said to have been adopted by Iekuni and called himself &apos;Yoshimune NUMATA.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that time, Yoshimune is said to have been adopted by Iekuni and called himself &apos;Yoshimune NUMATA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that time, Yoshimune is said to have been adopted by Iekuni and called himself &apos;Yoshimune NUMATA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>あるいは、この木曾氏は義仲流と仮冒し、実際は秀郷流沼田氏の系統ともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that, although the Kiso family proclaimed themselves to be the descendants of Yoshinaka, they actually descended from the Numata clan of FUJIWARA no Hidesato house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that, although the Kiso family proclaimed themselves to be the descendants of Yoshinaka, they actually descended from the Numata clan of FUJIWARA no Hidesato line.</e>
<cmt>流はhouseからlineに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that, although the Kiso family proclaimed themselves to be the descendants of Yoshinaka, they actually descended from the Numata clan of FUJIWARA no Hidesato line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>彼から六代の子孫にあたる木曾家村が登場し、足利尊氏の武将として活躍し、木曾家再興の祖と称したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, Iemura KISO, the sixth generation descendent of Yoshimune, came to play an active role as a busho (Japanese military commander) of Takauji ASHIKAGA and called himself &apos;the restorer of the Kiso family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>木曾家村Iemura KISO</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, Iemura KISO, the sixth generation descendent of Yoshimune, came to play an active role as a busho (Japanese military commander) of Takauji ASHIKAGA and called himself &apos;the restorer of the Kiso family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, Iemura KISO, the sixth generation descendent of Yoshimune, came to play an active role as a busho (Japanese military commander) of Takauji ASHIKAGA and called himself &apos;the restorer of the Kiso family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), 赤井彗星(id:18381), 千村清文(id:241559), しるふぃ(id:11247), 由布(id:209183), Cpro(id:28341), 松茸(id:27535), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>