<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>二階堂行貞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukisada NIKAIDO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukisada NIKAIDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukisada NIKAIDO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二階堂 行貞（にかいどう ゆきさだ、1269年（文永6年） - 1329年3月3日（嘉暦4年2月2日 (旧暦)））は鎌倉幕府の政所執事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukisada NIKAIDO (1269 - March 3, 1329) was a Mandokoro Shitsuji (chief of Mandokoro, the Administrative Board) in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukisada NIKAIDO (1269 - March 3, 1329) was a Mandokoro Shitsuji (chief of Mandokoro, the Administrative Board) in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukisada NIKAIDO (1269 - March 3, 1329) was a Mandokoro Shitsuji (chief of Mandokoro, the Administrative Board) in the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>二階堂行忠の孫、二階堂行宗の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A grandson of Yukitada NIKAIDO and a child of Yukimune NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>二階堂行宗はYukimune NIKAIDOとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a grandson of Yukitada NIKAIDO and a child of Yukimune NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>sentenceにするためHe wasを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a grandson of Yukitada NIKAIDO and a child of Yukimune NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>行貞の父・二階堂行宗は引付衆まで進んだが、父親の行忠に先立って1286年（弘安9年）に没しており、1290年（正応3年）の行忠の没後は孫の行貞が22歳で政所執事に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The father of Yukisada, Yukimune NIKAIDO, promoted to hikitsukeshu (Coadjustor of the High Court), but he died before his father, Yukitada, in 1286, and after the death of Yukitada, a grandson of his, Yukisada, became Mandokoro Shitsuji (chief of Mandokoro, the Administrative Board) at the age of 22.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The father of Yukisada, Yukimune NIKAIDO, was promoted to hikitsukeshu (Coadjustor of the High Court), but he died before his father, Yukitada, in 1286, and after the death of Yukitada, his grandson, Yukisada, became Mandokoro Shitsuji (chief of Mandokoro, the Administrative Board) at the age of 22.</e>
<cmt>promoteは他動詞なのでwas を挿入しました。a grandson of his→his grandson（より自然なため）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The father of Yukisada, Yukimune NIKAIDO, was promoted to hikitsukeshu (Coadjustor of the High Court), but he died before his father, Yukitada, in 1286, and after the death of Yukitada, his grandson, Yukisada, became Mandokoro Shitsuji (chief of Mandokoro, the Administrative Board) at the age of 22.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その人事は単に家を継いだだけに等しかったが、その年は1285年（弘安8年）の霜月騒動によって得宗家被官・内管領の平頼綱が実権を握っていた時期にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the personnel affairs, he just acceded to the position, and hikan (low-level bureaucrat) the Tokuso family, TAIRA no Yoritsuna of Uchi-Kanrei (head of Tokuso Family) held the real power after the Shimotsuki Incident in 1285.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the personnel affairs, he just acceded to the position at the time that hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of the Tokuso family, TAIRA no Yoritsuna of Uchi-Kanrei (head of Tokuso Family) held the real power after the Shimotsuki Incident in 1285.</e>
<cmt>「時期にあたる」が訳出されていないため&quot;at that time&quot;を挿入しました。抜けていた&quot;of&quot;を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the personnel affairs, he just acceded to the position at the time that hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of the Tokuso family, TAIRA no Yoritsuna of Uchi-Kanrei (head of Tokuso Family) held the real power after the Shimotsuki Incident in 1285.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>それから3年後の1293年（正応6年）に北条貞時が平頼綱を討ち（平禅門の乱）、平頼綱の時代の人事を否定し、霜月騒動以前の北条時宗の時代への回帰を計る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1293, three years later, Sadatoki HOJO subjugated TAIRA no Yoritsuna (Heizenmon-no-ran (Heizen Gate Incident)), rejected the personnel affairs in the days of TAIRA no Yoritsuna and tried to restore the personnel affairs in the days of Sadatoki HOJO before the Shimotsuki Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1293, three years later, Sadatoki HOJO subjugated TAIRA no Yoritsuna (Heizenmon-no-ran [Heizen Gate Incident]), rejected the personnel affairs in the days of TAIRA no Yoritsuna and tried to restore the personnel affairs in the days of Tokimune HOJO before the Shimotsuki Incident.</e>
<cmt>カッコの中のカッコを[ ]に変更しました。Sadatoki→Tokimune</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1293, three years later, Sadatoki HOJO subjugated TAIRA no Yoritsuna (Heizenmon-no-ran [Heizen Gate Incident]), rejected the personnel affairs in the days of TAIRA no Yoritsuna and tried to restore the personnel affairs in the days of Tokimune HOJO before the Shimotsuki Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その煽りを食らったのか、二階堂行貞は同年10月に政所執事の職を罷免される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As its direct result, Yukisada NIKAIDO was dismissed from Mandokoro Shitsuji in October in the same way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As its direct result, Yukisada NIKAIDO was dismissed from Mandokoro Shitsuji in October in the same year.</e>
<cmt>同年を&quot;in the same way&quot;と誤訳していたため&quot;same year&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As its direct result, Yukisada NIKAIDO was dismissed from Mandokoro Shitsuji in October in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そしてこれまでは政所執事を出したことのない二階堂行村（（隠岐流）の祖孫・二階堂行藤（出羽備中家）が10月19日に政所執事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukifuji NIKAIDO (Dewa Bicchu (the western part of Okayama Prefecture)), who was a grandson of Yukimura NIKAIDO (Oki Province) and who had no experience in Mandokoro Shitsuji, became Mandokoro Shitsuji on October 19.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukifuji NIKAIDO (a family of Dewa Bicchu), who was a grandson of Yukimura NIKAIDO (of Oki family line) and had no Mandokoro Shitsuji in the family before, became Mandokoro Shitsuji on October 19.</e>
<cmt>「政所執事を出したことがない」の訳が&quot;who had no experience of&quot;では、意味が異なるため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukifuji NIKAIDO (a family of Dewa Bicchu), who was a grandson of Yukimura NIKAIDO (of Oki family line) and had no Mandokoro Shitsuji in the family before, became Mandokoro Shitsuji on October 19.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そしてその二階堂行藤が1302年（乾元 (日本)元年）8月に没したあと、3ヶ月の空白期間をおいて二階堂行貞が再任されるが、この空白の3ヶ月は得宗北条貞時の元での人事の迷走を物語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yukifuji NIKAIDO died in August, 1302, Yukisada NIKAIDO was reassigned three months later, this period indicated aberrance of personnel affairs under Tokuso Sadatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yukifuji NIKAIDO died in August, 1302, Yukisada NIKAIDO was reassigned three months later, this bland period indicated aberrance of personnel affairs under Tokuso Sadatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>「空白期間」が訳出されていなかったため&quot;blank&quot;を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yukifuji NIKAIDO died in August, 1302, Yukisada NIKAIDO was reassigned three months later, this bland period indicated aberrance of personnel affairs under Tokuso Sadatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>そしてこの二階堂行貞が『吾妻鏡』の編纂者の一人と目されているのだが、行貞の祖父で二階堂行盛の子・行忠の誕生を『吾妻鏡』に書き込んだのが行貞だとするならば、それは単なる自分の先祖の顕彰を越えて、二階堂行藤とその子・二階堂時藤の隠岐流に対して、二階堂行光、二階堂行盛から二階堂行忠、そして自分へとつながる政所執事の家系としての正当性を主張するものとして十分な動機が推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If it is said that Yukisada NIKAIDO was one of compilers of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), but if Yukisada wrote the story of the birth of Yukitada, a son of Yukimori NIKAIDO and a grandfather of Yukisada, it was more than honoring of his ancestors, and he had sufficient motive for insisting on rightness of his family line from Yukimitsu NIKAIDO, Yukitada NIKAIDO to Yukitada NIKAIDO to himself as Mandokoro Shitsuji, on the contrary to the Oki family line of Yukifuji NIKAIDO and his child, Tokifuji NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>二階堂時藤はTokifuji NIKAIDOとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If Yukisada NIKAIDO, who was allegedly one of compilers of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (the Mirror of the East), wrote the story of the birth of Yukitada, a son of Yukimori NIKAIDO and a grandfather of Yukisada in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, it was more than honoring of his ancestors, and he had sufficient motive for insisting on rightness of his family line from Yukimitsu NIKAIDO, Yukitada NIKAIDO to Yukitada NIKAIDO to himself as Mandokoro Shitsuji, on the contrary to the Oki family line of Yukifuji NIKAIDO and his child, Tokifuji NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>If it is said that Yukisada NIKAIDO was one of compilers of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), but if Yukisada wrote the story of the birth of Yukitada, a son of Yukimori NIKAIDO and a grandfather of Yukisadaが不自然なため書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If Yukisada NIKAIDO, who was allegedly one of compilers of &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (the Mirror of the East), wrote the story of the birth of Yukitada, a son of Yukimori NIKAIDO and a grandfather of Yukisada in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, it was more than honoring of his ancestors, and he had sufficient motive for insisting on rightness of his family line from Yukimitsu NIKAIDO, Yukitada NIKAIDO to Yukitada NIKAIDO to himself as Mandokoro Shitsuji, on the contrary to the Oki family line of Yukifuji NIKAIDO and his child, Tokifuji NIKAIDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>二階堂行貞は1329年（嘉暦4年）2月2日61歳で没するまで政所執事を務め、没後その職は子の二階堂貞衡が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukisada NIKAIDO served as Mandokoro Shitsuji until he died at the age of 61 on February 2, 1329, and after his death, his son Sadahira NIKAIDO succeeded his post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukisada NIKAIDO served as Mandokoro Shitsuji until he died at the age of 61 on February 2, 1329, and after his death, his son Sadahira NIKAIDO succeeded his post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukisada NIKAIDO served as Mandokoro Shitsuji until he died at the age of 61 on February 2, 1329, and after his death, his son Sadahira NIKAIDO succeeded his post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 VoidAimai(id:212464), Ktmchi(id:113301), Point136(id:211299), 玄史生(id:43670), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>