<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊東甲子太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kashitaro ITO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kashitaro ITO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kashitaro ITO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊東 甲子太郎（いとう かしたろう、天保6年（1835年） - 慶応3年11月18日 (旧暦)（1867年12月13日））は、新選組参謀。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kashitaro ITO (1835-Decemver 13, 1967) was a Shisengumi Staff Officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kashitaro ITO (1835 - December 13, 1967) was a staff officer in the Shisengumi (a police force based in Kyoto during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>Em dash &gt; hyphenAdded spacesSome kind of explanation of &quot;Shisengumi&quot; is needed, I think.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kashitaro ITO (1835 - December 13, 1967) was a staff officer in the Shinsengumi (a police force based in Kyoto during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>のち御陵衛士（高台寺党）盟主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he became the leader of Goryo-eiji (Kodai-ji-to Party).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later became the leader of the Goryo-eiji (Kodai-ji-to Party).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later became the leader of the Goryo-eiji (Kodai-ji-to Party).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は武明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina (real name) was Takeaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (personal name that was generally used posthumously or by one&apos;s parents or lord) was Takeaki.</e>
<cmt>&quot;real name&quot; alone as an explanation of 諱 is a little misleading, I think, so I have expanded the explanation a little.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name that was generally used posthumously or by one&apos;s parents or lord) was Takeaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名を祐之、初名は大蔵（大藏）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Hiroyuki and the first name is Taizo大蔵(大藏).</e>
<cmt>祐之はHiroyukiとしました。大蔵（大藏)は、Taizo (大蔵（大藏))としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Hiroyuki and his original name was Taizo.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think there is any need to make a distinction between 大蔵 and 大藏 in the English translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Hiroyuki and his original name was Taizo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>号は誠斎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Seisai.</e>
<cmt>誠斎はSeisaiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Buddhist name was Seisai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Seisai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>変名は宇田兵衛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His changed name was Utabe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later went under the name of Utabe.</e>
<cmt>Buddhist name, childhood name, etc., are fine but &quot;changed name&quot; is just chokuyaku.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later went under the name of Utabe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>常陸国志筑藩士（郷目付）・鈴木専右衛門忠明の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born as the first son of a feudal retainer of the Shizuku clan in Hitachi Province (Gometsuke), Senemon Tadaaki SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>郷目付はGometsukeとしました。鈴木専右衛門忠明は Senemon Tadaaki SUZUKIとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kashitaro ITO was born as the first son of Senemon Tadaaki SUZUKI, a retainer (Gometsuke) of the Shizuku domain in Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>Poor, inaccurate translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kashitaro ITO was born as the first son of Senemon Tadaaki SUZUKI, a retainer (Gometsuke) of the Shizuku Domain in Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>家老との諍いにより父忠明が隠居した後、伊東が家督を相続したものの、後に忠明の借財が明るみになったことから追放される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father Tadaaki retired due to a quarrel with a chief retainer, Ito inherited the family estate, but was expelled because a debt of Tadaaki became known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his father Tadaaki retired due to a dispute with a chief retainer, Ito inherited the family estate but was expelled because it became known that he was in debt to Tadaaki.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father Tadaaki retired due to a dispute with a chief retainer, Ito inherited the family estate but was expelled because it became known that he was in debt to Tadaaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>伊東は水戸市へ遊学し、水戸藩士・金子健四郎に剣（神道無念流剣術）を学び、また、水戸学を学んで勤王思想に傾倒する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ito moved to Mito City, mastered fencing from a feudal retainer of Mito Domain, Kenshiro Kaneko, learned Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) and devoted himself to imperialism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ito left to study in Mito City where he studied swordsmanship under Kenshiro Kaneko, a retainer of the Mito Domain, learned Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) and devoted himself to imperialism.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ito left to study in Mito City where he studied swordsmanship (swordplay in Shindo-Munen ryu style) under Kenshiro KANEKO, a retainer of the Mito Domain, learned Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) and devoted himself to imperialism.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>追放後の忠明は東大橋（現：石岡市）にて村塾（俊塾）を主宰し、遊学を終えて帰郷した伊東も教授に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the banishment, Tadaaki ran a Sonjuku (village juku) (Shunjuku) in Higashi-ohashi (present Ishioka City), and Ito who finished his study and returned to home also taught there.</e>
<cmt>俊塾はShunjukuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his banishment, Tadaaki ran a sonjuku (private village-school) (Shunjuku) in Higashi-ohashi (present Ishioka City) where Ito taught after completing his studies and returning to his hometown.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his banishment, Tadaaki ran a sonjuku (private village-school) (Shunjuku) in Higashi-ohashi (present Ishioka City) where Ito taught after completing his studies and returning to his hometown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>のちに深川 (江東区)佐賀町の北辰一刀流剣術伊東道場に入門するが、道場主伊東精一に力量を認められて婿養子となり、伊東大蔵と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he became a pupil of the Ito hokushin-ittoryu fencing school in Sagacho, Fukagawa (Koto Ward), his ability was recognized by the school master, Seiichi ITO, and he became a member of his wife&apos;s family and named Taizo ITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He subsequently became a pupil of the Ito Hokushin-ittoryu fencing school in Saga-cho, Fukagawa (Koto Ward) where his ability was recognized by school master Seiichi ITO who adopted him and named him Taizo ITO.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He subsequently became a pupil of the Ito Hokushin-ittoryu fencing school in Saga-cho, Fukagawa (Koto Ward) where his ability was recognized by school master Seiichi ITO who adopted him and named him Taizo ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>新選組</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsengumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsengumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsengumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>元治元年（1864年）10月、同門の藤堂平助の仲介で新選組に加盟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, 1864, he joined Shinsengumi through the agency of his fellow student, Heisuke TODO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, 1864, he joined the Shinsengumi through the agency of his fellow student, Heisuke TODO.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1864, he joined the Shinsengumi through the agency of his fellow student, Heisuke TODO.</e>
<cmt>カンマ削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同年11月、弟の鈴木三樹三郎、盟友の篠原泰之進や加納鷲雄、服部武雄、門人の内海二郎や中西昇らと上洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of the same year, he went up to Kyoto together with his brother Mikisaburo SUZUKI, his colleagues Tainoshin SHINOHAWA, Washio KANO,Takeo HATTORI, and his disciples Jiro UTSUMI and Noboru NAKANISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, he went to Kyoto with his brother Mikisaburo SUZUKI, his colleagues Tainoshin SHINOHAWA, Washio KANO and Takeo HATTORI, and his disciples Jiro UTSUMI and Noboru NAKANISHI.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;up&quot;Deleted &quot;together with&quot;, &gt; and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the same year, he went to Kyoto with his brother Mikisaburo SUZUKI, his colleagues Tainoshin SHINOHARA, Washio KANO and Takeo HATTORI, and his disciples Jiro UTSUMI and Noboru NAKANISHI.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このとき、上洛の年（甲子）に因んで伊東甲子太郎と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he called himself Kashitaro ITO after the year (Kinoene) when he went up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was at this time that he called himself Kashitaro ITO after the name of the year (Kinoene) in which he traveled to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was at this time that he called himself Kashitaro ITO after the name of the year (Kinoene) in which he traveled to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>参謀兼文学師範に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed a staff officer and literary instructor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed a staff officer and literary instructor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed a staff officer and literary instructor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>容姿端麗で巧みな弁舌から、伊東に対する人望が高かったと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is reported that Ito won popularity due to his attractive face and figure and eloquence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Ito won popularity due to his attractive appearance and eloquence.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Ito won popularity due to his attractive appearance and eloquence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、伊東と新選組は攘夷という点で結ばれていたが、新選組は佐幕派で、勤王（倒幕）を説こうとする方針をめぐり、密かに矛盾が生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ito agreed with Shinsengumi on expulsion of the foreigners, but since Shisengumi were Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun), he conflicted with them regarding the policy of loyalty to the Emperor (overthrow of the shogunate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ito agreed with the Shinsengumi on the expulsion of the foreigners, but since the Shisengumi were Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun), he opposed them regarding the policy of loyalty to the Emperor (overthrow of the shogunate).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ito agreed with the Shinsengumi on the expulsion of the foreigners, but since the Shisengumi were Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun), he opposed them regarding the policy of loyalty to the Emperor (overthrow of the shogunate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>御陵衛士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goryo-eiji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goryo-eiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goryo-eiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>西国を遊説した後の慶応3年3月20日、薩摩藩の動向探索と御陵警備任務の拝命の名目に新選組を離脱し、篠原や鈴木など同志14名と共に御陵衛士（高台寺党）を結成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 20, 1867, after campaigning the Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)), he separated from Shinsengumi to check the moves of Satsuma Domain and receive an official appointment as guards of the Emperor&apos;s tomb, and formed Goryo-eiji (Kodaiji-to Party) with 14 comrades, such as Shinohara and Suzuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 20, 1867, after campaigning in Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)), he separated from the Shinsengumi to investigate the movements of the Satsuma Domain and receive an official appointment as guard of the Emperor&apos;s tomb, and formed Goryo-eiji (Kodaiji-to Party) with 14 comrades including Shinohara and Suzuki.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 24, 1867, after campaigning in Saigoku (western part of Japan (especially Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)), he separated from the Shinsengumi to investigate the movements of the Satsuma Domain and receive an official appointment as guard of the Emperor&apos;s tomb, and formed Goryo-eiji (Kodaiji-to Party) with 14 comrades including Shinohara and Suzuki.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、新選組内で失脚しつつあった武田観柳斎らの御陵衛士加盟の要望は拒絶している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he rejected a request to join Goryo-eiji from Kanryusai TAKEDA and others who were losing their positions in Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he rejected requests from Kanryusai TAKEDA and others who were losing their positions within in the Shinsengumi to join Goryo-eiji.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he rejected requests from Kanryusai TAKEDA and others who were losing their positions within the Shinsengumi to join Goryo-eiji.</e>
<cmt>不要な単語削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このころ、伊東摂津と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he named Settsu ITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was at this time that he named himself Settsu ITO.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was at this time that he named himself Settsu ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>暗殺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assasination</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assasination</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>慶応3年11月18日、近藤は妾宅にて伊東を歓待して酔わせ、帰途にあった油小路の本光寺門前にて同隊士の大石鍬次郎ら数名により暗殺され（油小路事件）、「奸賊ばら」と叫んで絶命したと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 18, 1867, Kondo welcomed Ito in the house of his mistress and got him drunk, and Ito was killed by several Shinsengumi members, such as Kuwajiro OISHI, in front of the gate of the Honko-ji Temple (Abura-no-koji Incident), and it was reported that he died while crying &apos;you villans&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 18, 1867, Kondo welcomed Ito to house of his mistress where he got him drunk before he was assassinated (Abura-no-koji Incident) on the way home in front of the gate of Honko-ji Temple on Abura-no-koji Street by several Shinsengumi members including Kuwajiro OISHI, and it is said that he died while crying &quot;you villains.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 13, 1867, Kondo welcomed Ito to house of his mistress where he got him drunk before he was assassinated (Abura-no-koji Incident) on the way home in front of the gate of Honko-ji Temple on Abura-no-koji Street by several Shinsengumi members including Kuwajiro OISHI, and it is said that he died while crying &apos;you villains.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>享年33。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died aged 33.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died aged 33.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 33.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>酒に酔わせたうえでの暗殺を企んだのは、北辰一刀流剣術の道場主であった伊東を警戒したためと思料される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It would appear that he was killed after he got drunk because they took precautions against Ito who was the master of the Hokushin-ittoryu fencing school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that they planned to get him drunk before assassinating Ito because he was he master of the Hokushin-ittoryu fencing school.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that they planned to get him drunk before assassinating Ito because he was the master of the Hokushin-ittoryu fencing school.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>伊東の遺体は路上に放置され、御陵衛士を誘い出す手段として使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ito&apos;s body was left on the road to lure Gryo-eiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ito&apos;s body was left on the road to lure the Gryo-eiji.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ito&apos;s body was left on the road to lure the Gryo-eiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>収容に来た御陵衛士は待ち伏せていた新選組と戦闘となり、藤堂らが戦死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Goryo-eiji members who came to pick up his body were attached by Shinsengumi members, and Todo and others were killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Goryo-eiji members who came to pick up his body were attached by Shinsengumi members, and Todo and others were killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Goryo-eiji members who came to pick up his body were attached by Shinsengumi members, and Todo and others were killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>墓は、京都市東山区の戒光寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His tomb is located in Kaiko-ji Temple in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His tomb is located at Kaiko-ji Temple in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>in &gt; at</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His tomb is located at Kaiko-ji Temple in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>慶応4年3月13日、御陵衛士により京都市下京区の光縁寺から改葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 13, 1968, Goryo-eiji moved the tomb from Koen-ji Temple in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 13, 1968, the Goryo-eiji moved the tomb from Koen-ji Temple in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 5, 1968, the Goryo-eiji moved the tomb from Koen-ji Temple in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>日付修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notes</e>
<cmt>Remarks &gt; Notes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>深川佐賀町の伊東道場は盛んで塾生や門下生も多く、小旗本程度の規模を誇ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Ito school in Sagacho, Fukagawa flourished, had many students and disciples, and had almost the same size as a small direct retainer of the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Ito school in Sagacho, Fukagawa flourished, had many students and disciples, and had almost the same size as a small direct retainer of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Ito school in Sagacho, Fukagawa flourished, had many students and disciples, and had almost the same size as a small direct retainer of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>慶応3年に4通の建白書を朝廷に提出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1867, four memorials were addressed to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1867, four memorials were addressed to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1867, four memorials were addressed to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>大政奉還の行われた直後の3通目の建白書では、公家中心の新政府を作り、一和同心をスローガンに広く天下から人材を求め、畿内5ヶ国を新政府の直轄領とするなど、国民皆兵などを提唱している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third memorial immediately after restoration of imperial rule advocated that a new government centered on court nobles was established, human resources were called in from various parts of the country with a slogan of Ichiwa Doshin (common wishes or cooperative spirit), five territories in the immediate vicinity of Kyoto was put under direct imperial rule of the new government, and universal conscription was performed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third memorial immediately after restoration of imperial rule advocated that a new government centered on court nobles was established, personnel were called in from various parts of the country with a slogan of Ichiwa Doshin (common wishes or cooperative spirit), five territories in the immediate vicinity of Kyoto were put under direct imperial rule of the new government, and universal conscription was performed.</e>
<cmt>human resources &gt; personnelDelete space before opening commawas &gt; were</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third memorial immediately after restoration of imperial rule advocated that a new government centered on court nobles was established, personnel were called in from various parts of the country with a slogan of Ichiwa Doshin (common wishes or cooperative spirit), five territories in the immediate vicinity of Kyoto were put under direct imperial rule of the new government, and universal conscription was performed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、1通目の建白書では神戸開港反対を唱えていたが、3通目では「大開国、大強国」を唱え、積極的開国による富国強兵策に近い考え方を示している（ただし、神戸開港は孝明天皇の遺志に反するとしてあくまでも反対している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first memorial insisted on opposition to opening of the Kobe port, but the third one advocated &apos;opening of the country (Japan) to the world and enriching it&apos;, and showed a measure to enrich and strengthen the country by opening it positively (however, it opposed to opening of the Kobe port because it was against the will of Emperor Komei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first memorial insisted on opposition to opening of the Kobe port, but the third one advocated &apos;opening of the country (Japan) to the world and enriching it&apos;, and showed a measure to enrich and strengthen the country by opening it positively (however, it opposed to opening of Kobe port because it was against the will of Emperor Komei).</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first memorial insisted on opposition to opening of the Kobe port, but the third one advocated &apos;opening of the country (Japan) to the world and enriching it,&apos; and showed a measure to enrich and strengthen the country by opening it positively (however, it opposed to opening of Kobe port because it was against the will of Emperor Komei).</e>
<cmt>カンマ位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、暗殺時の懐に5通目の草稿があり、同時代の記録によるとほとんど3通目の写しに近く、この案で近藤を説得しようとしていたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a draft of the fifth memorial in his inside breast pocket at the time of assassination, and the record of the time says that it was similar to the copy of the third memorial and he wanted to persuade Kondo based on this idea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ito had a draft of the fifth memorial in his inside breast pocket at the time of his assassination, and records of the time state that it was similar to the copy of the third memorial and he wanted to persuade Kondo based on this idea.</e>
<cmt>He &gt; ItoAdded &quot;his&quot;the record &gt; recordssays &gt; state</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ito had a draft of the fifth memorial in his inside breast pocket at the time of his assassination, and records of the time state that it was similar to the copy of the third memorial and he wanted to persuade Kondo based on this idea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>当時の一級資料「鳥取藩丁卯筆記」では、薩摩の吉井幸輔が越前の中根雪江に、この建白を「いちいち尤も」と言っていたと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The then first-rate document &apos;Tottori Domain Hinoeushi Nikki (Notes)&apos; says that Kosuke YOSHII of Satsuma told Yukie NAKANE of Echizen that this memorial was &apos;very reasonable.</e>
<cmt>鳥取藩丁卯筆記はTottori Domain Hinoeushi Nikki (Notes)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The then first-rate document &apos;Tottori Domain Hinoeushi Nikki (Notes)&apos; says that Kosuke YOSHII of Satsuma told Yukie NAKANE of Echizen that this memorial was &apos;very reasonable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Added closing quotation mark.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The then first-rate document &apos;Tottori Domain Hinoeushi Nikki&apos; (Notes) says that Kosuke YOSHII of Satsuma told Yukie NAKANE of Echizen that this memorial was &apos;very reasonable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>甲子太郎は｢きねたろう｣とも読まれるが、天意が革まって徳を備えた人に天命が下される「革令」の年とされる「甲子」にあやかったこと、同時代史料に「樫太郎」という表記も見られることから、「かしたろう」が正しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">甲子太郎 can also be read as &apos;Kinetaro&apos;, but &apos;Kashitaro&apos; is correct because he was named after &apos;Kasshi (first of the sexagenary cycle)&apos;, which is a year of &apos;Kakurei&apos; when the divine will is renewed and the God&apos;s will is sent to a virtuous person and historical records of the time contain a notation of &apos;樫太郎 (Kashitaro)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>甲子太郎と樫太郎は、漢字の読みに関することなので漢字のままにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">甲子太郎 can also be read as &apos;Kinetaro&apos;, but &apos;Kashitaro&apos; is correct because he was named after &apos;Kasshi (first of the sexagenary cycle)&apos;, which is a year of &apos;Kakurei&apos; when the divine will is renewed and the God&apos;s will is sent to a virtuous person and historical records of the time contain a notation of &apos;樫太郎 (Kashitaro)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese kanji for Kashitaro (甲子太郎) can also be read as &apos;Kinetaro&apos;, but the former reading is correct because the first two kanji of his given name were taken from &apos;Kasshi&apos; (written as &apos;甲子&apos;, meaning the first year in the Japanese 60-year calendar cycle, which is a year of &apos;Kakurei&apos; when the will of heaven is renewed and heaven&apos;s decree is revealed to the virtuous); further evidence that Kashitaro is the correct reading is the fact that his name was sometimes written as &apos;樫太郎&apos; (pronounced &apos;Kashitaro&apos;) in historical records of that time.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣのコメントを受けて再翻訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>伊東は新選組離脱後、同志に英語を学ばせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After separation from Shinsengumi, Ito advised his comrades to learn English.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After separating from the Shinsengumi, Ito advised his comrades to learn English.</e>
<cmt>separation &gt; separatingAdded &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After separating from the Shinsengumi, Ito advised his comrades to learn English.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>明治後、伊東暗殺の嫌疑により相馬主計が八丈島に流されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, Kazue SOMA was sentenced to exile to Hachijo Island on a charge of assassination of Ito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, Kazue SOMA was sentenced to exile to Hachijo Island on the charge of assassinating Ito.</e>
<cmt>a &gt; theassassination of &gt; assassinating</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, Kazue SOMA was sentenced to exile to Hachijo Island on the charge of assassinating Ito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>大正7年（1918年）に従五位を贈位され、昭和7年（1932年）4月には靖国神社へ合祀されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1918, he was conferred posthumous honors of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and was enshrined in Yasukuni Shrine in April, 1932.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1918, he was conferred the posthumous honor of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and was enshrined in Yasukuni Shrine in April, 1932.</e>
<cmt>posthumous honors &gt; the posthumous honor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1918, he was conferred the posthumous honor of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and was enshrined in Yasukuni Shrine in April, 1932.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>伊東の加盟を近藤勇は歓迎したが、土方歳三は策士として警戒したと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isami KONDO welcomed participation of Ito, but Toshizo HIJIKATA took precautions against him as an intriguer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isami KONDO welcomed the participation of Ito, but it is said that Toshizo HIJIKATA took precautions against him, believing him to be a schemer.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isami KONDO welcomed the participation of Ito, but it is said that Toshizo HIJIKATA took precautions against him, believing him to be a schemer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>山南敬助の切腹に対し、伊東は4首の和歌を詠んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Keisuke YAMANAMI committed hara-kiri, Ito composed four waka poems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Keisuke YAMANAMI committed hara-kiri, Ito composed four waka poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Keisuke YAMANAMI committed hara-kiri, Ito composed four waka poems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), パイク・ビショップ(id:114349), たね(id:10372), Yanahan(id:2437), 土方　誠(id:3651), Greenland4(id:114494), ロココ(id:80572), Inukawa(id:842), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Mitsu Nokotobane(id:100231), JOKER(id:22180), ふんにゃらにゃ(id:27740), 寒(id:53831), KO G(id:131448), 上田隼人(id:23104), おきた(id:18906), Morio(id:35464), トホホ川(id:50502), Alexbot(id:157199), Maakun(id:16735), Junger(id:10282), 歴史研究家(id:108842), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>