<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujiwara Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fujiwara Clan</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原（ふじわら）氏は、日本の古代から近世までの貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fujiwara clan is a noble clan that existed in Japan from the ancient period until the early modern period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fujiwara were a noble clan that existed in Japan from the ancient period until the early modern period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fujiwara were a noble clan that existed in Japan from the ancient period until the early modern period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>天児屋命を祖と伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan is believed to have descended from Amenokoyane no Mikoto, a legendary ancestor deity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan is believed to have descended from Amenokoyane no Mikoto, a legendary ancestral deity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan is believed to have descended from Amenokoyane no Mikoto, a legendary ancestral deity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代は、本姓の藤原を称するが、鎌倉時代以降は、姓の藤原ではなく、家名（苗字に該当）である近衛、鷹司、九条、二条、一条などを名のり、公式文書以外では藤原とは名のらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families that belonged to the clan used the clan name Fujiwara as their family name during the Heian period, but from the Kamakura period onward, they each used their respective family names, such as Konoe, Kujo, Nijo and Ichijo, without using the clan name Fujiwara except in official documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Families that belonged to the clan used the clan name Fujiwara as their family name during the Heian period, but from the Kamakura period onward they each used their respective family names, such as Konoe, Kujo, Nijo and Ichijo, and therefore used the clan name Fujiwara only in official documents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Families that belonged to the clan used the clan name Fujiwara as their family name during the Heian period, but from the Kamakura period onward they each used their respective family names, such as Konoe, Takatsukasa, Kujo, Nijo and Ichijo, and therefore used the clan name Fujiwara only in official documents.</e>
<cmt>Takatsukasa補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Origin of the Clan</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Origin of the Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>中臣鎌足が大化の改新の功により天智天皇より賜った氏カバネ「藤原朝臣」を姓とする氏族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fujiwara clan descended from NAKATOMI no Kamatari, who was awarded an official status title (called Uji-Kabane) &quot;FUJIWARA no Asomi&quot; from Emperor Tenji for his outstanding contributions to the Taika Reform (Taika-no-kaishin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fujiwara clan was descended from NAKATOMI no Kamatari, who had been awarded an official status title (called Uji-Kabane) &quot;FUJIWARA no Asomi&quot; from Emperor Tenji for his outstanding contributions to the Taika Reform (Taika-no-kaishin).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fujiwara clan was descended from NAKATOMI no Kamatari, who had been awarded an official status title (called Uji-Kabane) &apos;FUJIWARA no Asomi&apos; from Emperor Tenji for his outstanding contributions to Taika-no-kaishin (the Taika Reform).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にTaika Reform (Taika-no-kaishin)→Taika-no-kaishin (the Taika Reform)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>源氏・平氏・藤・橘氏のいわゆる四姓の一つであり、藤原氏はその筆頭名門氏族であり、藤氏（とうし）とも略称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujiwara is one of the four major family names (Genji, Taira, To (or Fujiwara) and Tachibana), and the Fujiwara family, also known as the To family, was the oldest member of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiwara is one of the four major family names (Genji, Taira, To (or Fujiwara) and Tachibana), and the Fujiwara family, also known as the To family, was the earliest member of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiwara is one of the four major family names (Minamoto, Taira, To (or Fujiwara) and Tachibana), and the Fujiwara family, also known as the To clan, was the earliest member of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Genji→MinamotoTo family→clan藤原氏は通常Fujiwara clanを使いますが、左記文中ではわかりやすくするため、一部Fujiwara familyを使用しています。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原の姓は当初は死を目前とした鎌足に与えられ、鎌足の死後、中臣氏を率いた右大臣中臣金が壬申の乱で処刑された事もあって、乱とは無関係の鎌足流も一時衰亡の危機を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official title Fujiwara was awarded to Kamatari on the verge of death, and after his death, due partly to the fact that NAKATOMI no Kane, Udaijin (chief of Dajokan) and head of the Nakatomi Family, was executed in the Jinshin no Ran War, the Kamatari Group was temporarily faced with a serious decline, although they took no part in the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiwara, as an official title, was awarded to Kamatari upon the approach of death, and after his death, due partly to the fact that NAKATOMI no Kane, the Udaijin (chief of Dajokan) and head of the Nakatomi Family, had been executed in the Jinshin no Ran War, the Kamatari Group temporarily faced a serious decline, although they had taken no part in the war.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiwara, as an official title, was awarded to Kamatari upon the approach of death, and after his death, due partly to the fact that NAKATOMI no Kane, the Udaijin (minister of the right) and head of the Nakatomi clan, had been executed in the Jinshin no Ran War, the Kamatari Group temporarily faced a serious decline, although they had taken no part in the war.</e>
<cmt>chief of Dajokan→minister of the rightNakatomi Family→Nakatomi clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、天武天皇の時代に八色の姓が定められた折に藤原朝臣の範囲を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scope of those who were entitled to the title FUJIWARA no Asomi was subsequently defined explicitly when Yakusa no Kabane (official ranking system) was established during the reign of Emperor Temmu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the scope of those who were entitled to the title FUJIWARA no Asomi was defined when Yakusa no Kabane (the official ranking system) was established during the reign of Emperor Temmu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the scope of those who were entitled to the title FUJIWARA no Asomi was defined when Yakusa no Kabane (the official ranking system) was established during the reign of Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>Temmu→Tenmu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その際藤原不比等がまだ若かった事もあって鎌足の従兄弟で娘婿でもあった中臣意美麻呂が不比等が成長するまでの中継ぎとして暫定的に氏上となったらしく、それ以外の成員にも不比等が成長するまで暫定的に藤原朝臣が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since FUJIWARA no Fuhito was still too young at the time, Kamatari&apos;s cousin and son-in-law, NAKATOMI no Omimaro is likely to have assumed the responsibility of the head of the clan to govern it as a temporary successor until Fuhito was ready to take on the leadership, and other members of the Nakatomi family were also permitted to use the title FUJIWARA no Asomi until Fuhito was old enough.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because FUJIWARA no Fuhito was still too young at the time, it is likely that Kamatari&apos;s cousin and son-in-law, NAKATOMI no Omimaro, assumed the responsibility as the head of the clan in order to govern it as a temporary successor until Fuhito was ready to take on the leadership; additionally, other members of the Nakatomi family were permitted to use the title FUJIWARA no Asomi until Fuhito was old enough.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because FUJIWARA no Fuhito was still too young at the time, it is likely that Kamatari&apos;s cousin and son-in-law, NAKATOMI no Omimaro, assumed responsibility as the head of the clan in order to govern it as a temporary successor until Fuhito was ready to take on the leadership; additionally, other members of the Nakatomi family were permitted to use the title FUJIWARA no Asomi until Fuhito was old enough.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞不要。 “assumed the responsibility”=&gt;”assumed responsibility”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのため、後に不比等が成長し頭角を現すと、藤原氏が太政官を中臣氏が神祇官を領掌する体制とするために、鎌足嫡男の不比等以外は元の中臣姓に戻された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, when Fuhito grew old enough to assume the leadership, the official name of clan members other than Fuhito, the rightful successor to Kamatari, was changed to the original Nakatomi in order to create a system that enabled Dajokan (Grand Council of state) to be governed by the Fujiwara family and Jingikan (department of worship) by the Nakatomi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, when Fuhito grew old enough to assume the leadership, the official name of clan members other than Fuhito, the rightful successor to Kamatari, was changed to the original Nakatomi in order to create a system that enabled Dajokan (the grand council of state) to be governed by the Fujiwara family and Jingikan (the Department of Worship) by the Nakatomi family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, when Fuhito grew old enough to assume the leadership, the official name of clan members other than Fuhito, the rightful successor to Kamatari, was changed to the original Nakatomi in order to create a system that enabled Dajokan (the grand council of state) to be governed by the Fujiwara clan and Jingikan (the Department of Worship) by the Nakatomi clan.</e>
<cmt>family→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>（なお、意美麻呂は中臣姓に復帰後に不比等の推薦で中納言となり、その七男の大中臣清麻呂は右大臣まで昇ったため、以後はこの子孫が中臣氏の嫡流とされて特に「大中臣氏」と称されるようになった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Omimaro was appointed as the vice councillor of state based on the recommendation of Fuhito after Omimaro&apos;s official name was changed back to Nakatomi, and since his seventh son, ONAKATOMI no Kiyomaro, rose to Udaijin (chief of Dajokan), his descendants were regarded as being the main branch of the Nakatomi family and were called the Onakatomi (great Nakatomi) clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Omimaro was appointed as the vice councillor of state based on the recommendation of Fuhito after Omimaro&apos;s official name was changed back to Nakatomi, and since his seventh son, ONAKATOMI no Kiyomaro, rose to the post of Udaijin (chief of Dajokan), his descendants were regarded as being the main branch of the Nakatomi family and were called the Onakatomi (great Nakatomi) clan.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Omimaro was appointed as Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) based on the recommendation of Fuhito after Omimaro&apos;s official name was changed back to Nakatomi, and since his seventh son, ONAKATOMI no Kiyomaro, rose to the post of Udaijin (minister of the right), his descendants were regarded as being the main branch of the Nakatomi clan and were called the Onakatomi (great Nakatomi) clan.)</e>
<cmt>chief of Dajokan→minister of the rightfamily→clanthe vice councillor of state→Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>藤原不比等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Fuhito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Fuhito</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Fuhito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>鎌足の後継者として認められた藤原不比等は下毛野古麻呂らとともに大宝律令を編纂して律令制度の確立に貢献、娘の宮子を文武天皇の後宮に入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Fuhito, who was recognized as the rightful successor to Kamatari, formulated the Taiho Code in collaboration with SHIMOTSUKE no Nokomaro, thereby contributing to the establishment of the ancient legal system (Ritsuryo system), and also sent his daughter Kyushi to Emperor Mommu&apos;s Kokyu (imperial harem).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Fuhito, who was recognized as the rightful successor to Kamatari, formulated the Taiho Code in collaboration with SHIMOTSUKE no Nokomaro, thereby contributing to the establishment of the ancient legal system (Ritsuryo system), and also sent his daughter Kyushi to Emperor Mommu&apos;s kokyu (imperial harem).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Fuhito, who was recognized as the rightful successor to Kamatari, formulated the Taiho Code in collaboration with SHIMOTSUKE no Nokomaro, thereby contributing to the establishment of the Ritsuryo system (ancient legal system), and also sent his daughter Kyushi to Emperor Monmu&apos;s kokyu (imperial harem).</e>
<cmt>the ancient legal system (Ritsuryo system)→the Ritsuryo system (ancient legal system)Mommu→Monmu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>首皇子（後の聖武天皇）が生まれると、娘藤原光明子（後の光明皇后）を後宮に入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Obitono-oji (later Emperor Shomu) was born, Fuhito sent his another daughter, FUJIWARA no Komyoshi (later Empress Komyo), to Kokyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Obitono-oji (later Emperor Shomu) was born, Fuhito sent his other daughter, FUJIWARA no Komyoshi (later Empress Komyo), to the kokyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Obitono-oji (later Emperor Shomu) was born, Fuhito sent his other daughter, FUJIWARA no Komyoshi (later Empress Komyo), to the kokyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、『興福寺縁起』には不比等の出生につき「公避くる所の事有り」とあり、大鏡、公卿補任、尊卑分脈には明記され、天智天皇の御落胤であるとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in Kofuku-ji Engi (Origin of Kofuku-ji Temple) that there are certain matters about Fuhito&apos;s birth that are not officially recorded; meanwhile, it is explicitly stated in Okagami, Kugyo Bunin (office records of the ancient government) and Sonpi Bunmyaku (ancient family tree charts) that Fuhito was Emperor Tenchi&apos;s child born out of wedlock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is written in &quot;Kofuku-ji Engi (Origin of Kofuku-ji Temple)&quot; that there are certain matters about Fuhito&apos;s birth that haven&apos;t been officially recorded; meanwhile, it is explicitly stated in &quot;Okagami, Kugyo Bunin (Official Records of the Ancient Government)&quot; and &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku (Ancient Family Tree Charts)&quot; that Fuhito was Emperor Tenchi&apos;s child born out of wedlock.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is written in &quot;Kofuku-ji Engi (Origin of Kofuku-ji Temple)&quot; that there are certain matters about Fuhito&apos;s birth that haven&apos;t been officially recorded; meanwhile, it is explicitly stated in Okagami, Kugyo Bunin (Official Records of the Ancient Government) and Sonpi Bunmyaku (Ancient Family Tree Charts) that Fuhito was Emperor Tenchi&apos;s child born out of wedlock.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;　&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>藤原氏四家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four Families of the Fujiwara Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four Families of the Fujiwara Clan</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four Families of the Fujiwara Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>不比等の死後、首皇子が皇位に就くと、不比等の4人の男子（藤原四兄弟）と長屋王ら反対派の対立が深まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Obitono-oji succeeded to the throne after Fuhito&apos;s death, there arose a conflict between the four sons of Fuhito (Fujiwara four brothers) and their opponents led by Nagayao, which deepened as time went by.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Obitono-oji succeeded to the throne after Fuhito&apos;s death, there arose a conflict between the four sons of Fuhito (four Fujiwara brothers) and their opponents led by Nagayao, which deepened as time progressed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Obitono-oji succeeded to the throne after Fuhito&apos;s death, there arose a conflict between the four sons of Fuhito (four Fujiwara brothers) and their opponents led by Nagayao, which deepened as time progressed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>729年に長屋王の変が起こり長屋王は自害するが、これは四兄弟が自分達の異母妹で天皇の妃である光明子を史上初の皇族以外出自の皇后に立てるため、それに反対する長屋王を讒言により陥れた陰謀事件であったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayao no Hen (the Conspiracy of Nagayao) in 729, which led to his suicide, is believed to have been a conspiracy organized by the four brothers in order to slander and expel Nagayao, who was opposed to their attempt to make Komyoshi, their half-sister and Emperor&apos;s wife, the first Empress chosen from outside the imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nagayao no Hen (the Conspiracy of Nagayao) in 729, which led to his suicide, is believed to have been a conspiracy organized by the four brothers in order to slander and expel Nagayao, who had been opposed to their attempt to make Komyoshi, their half-sister and the Emperor&apos;s wife, the first Empress chosen from outside the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nagayao no Hen (the Conspiracy of Nagayao) in 729, which led to his suicide, is believed to have been a conspiracy organized by the four brothers in order to slander and expel Nagayao, who had been opposed to their attempt to make Komyoshi, their half-sister and the Emperor&apos;s wife, the first Empress chosen from outside the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、藤原四兄弟は南・北・式・京の4家に分かれそれぞれ藤原四家の祖となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fujiwara four brothers later split into four families (Nan, Hoku, Shiki and Kyo) and became the founders of the Fujiwara four families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The four Fujiwara brothers later split into four families (Nan, Hoku, Shiki and Kyo) and became the founders of the four Fujiwara families.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The four Fujiwara brothers later split into four families (Nan, Hoku, Shiki and Kyo) and became the founders of the four Fujiwara families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>731年役人達の投票によって、四兄弟全員が議政官に昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 731, the four brothers all rose to the position of Giseikan legislator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 731, each of the four brothers rose to the position of Giseikan legislator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 731, each of the four brothers rose to the position of Giseikan legislator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは藤原氏が単に後宮政策のみならず、不比等以来律令編纂に関わってきた実績をもって官僚組織を掌握していった事の証でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This provides evidence to show that the Fujiwara clan had control of the bureaucracy not only through its Kokyu policy, but also through its involvement in the establishment of the legal code (Ritsuryo system) since Fuhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This provides evidence to show that the Fujiwara clan had control of the bureaucracy not only through its Kokyu policy but also through its involvement in the establishment of the legal code (Ritsuryo system) since Fuhito.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This provides evidence to show that the Fujiwara clan had control of the bureaucracy not only through its Kokyu policy but also through its involvement in the establishment of the Ritsuryo system (legal code) since Fuhito.</e>
<cmt>the legal code (Ritsuryo system)→the Ritsuryo system (legal code)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>737年に天然痘の大流行で藤原四兄弟が相次いで病死すると、橘諸兄、僧玄昉、吉備真備らが藤原氏の突出を抑えようと努めるが、藤原仲麻呂により抑えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Fujiwara four brothers died one after another in 737 due to a smallpox epidemic, TACHIBANA no Moroe, priest Genbo and KIBI no Makibi attempted to curtail the power of the Fujiwara clan, but they were overpowered by FUJIWARA no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Fujiwara four brothers died one after another in 737 due to an epidemic of smallpox, TACHIBANA no Moroe, the priest Genbo and KIBI no Makibi attempted to curtail the power of the Fujiwara clan, but they were overpowered by FUJIWARA no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Fujiwara four brothers died one after another in 737 due to an epidemic of smallpox, TACHIBANA no Moroe, the priest Genbo and KIBI no Makibi attempted to curtail the power of the Fujiwara clan, but they were overpowered by FUJIWARA no Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後も橘奈良麻呂が仲麻呂排斥クーデターを起すが失敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Nakamaro subsequently organized a coup to drive Nakamaro out of power, but this coup also resulted in failure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Nakamaro subsequently organized a coup to drive Nakamaro out of power, but this coup also failed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Nakamaro subsequently organized a coup to drive Nakamaro out of power, but this coup also failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>初めはこの内の京家は振るわずに他の3家が争いつつ朝廷の廟堂に参画する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the four Fujiwara families, the Kyo Family failed to prosper but other three families participated in the political affairs of the Imperial court, with each family trying to overpower the other two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of the four Fujiwara families, the Kyo Family failed to prosper but the other three families participated in the political affairs of the Imperial Court, whereby each family tried to overpower the other two.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the four Fujiwara families, the Ceremonial House failed to prosper but the other three families participated in the political affairs of the Imperial Court, whereby each family tried to overpower the other two.</e>
<cmt>Kyo Family→Ceremonial House</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>一時期においては南家や式家が栄えた時期もあったが、政争や一族の反乱で平安時代前期には衰退し、代わって最も栄えたのは北家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were times when the Nan or Shiki familyprospered, but they both fell into decline during the early Heian period as a result of political conflicts and internal rebellions, after which the Northern House came to enjoy the greatest prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were times when either the Nan or the Shiki family prospered, but they both fell into decline during the early Heian period as a result of political conflicts and internal rebellions, after which the Hoku Family came to enjoy the greatest prosperity.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were times when either the Southern or the Ceremonial Houses prospered, but they both fell into decline during the early Heian period as a result of political conflicts and internal rebellions, after which the Northern House came to enjoy the greatest prosperity.</e>
<cmt>the Nan or the Shiki family→the Southern or the Ceremonial HousesHoku Family→the Northern House</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、藤原氏の嫡流については、不比等の長男・藤原武智麻呂を祖とする藤原南家説と兄よりも出世が早かった次男・藤原房前を祖とする藤原北家説の両説があるが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are arguments about the rightful successor to the Fujiwara clan: some people regard FUJIWARA no Muchimaro, Fuhito&apos;s eldest son, as the rightful successor (Fujiwara Nanke theory), while others argue that FUJIWARA no Fusasaki, Fuhito&apos;s second son who rose to prominence earlier than his older brother, was the successor (Fujiwara Hokke theory).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are arguments about the rightful successor to the Fujiwara clan: some people regard FUJIWARA no Muchimaro, Fuhito&apos;s eldest son, as the rightful successor (the Fujiwara Nanke theory), while others argue that FUJIWARA no Fusasaki, Fuhito&apos;s second son who rose to prominence earlier than his older brother, was the successor (the Fujiwara Hokke theory).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are arguments about the rightful successor to the Fujiwara clan: some people regard FUJIWARA no Muchimaro, Fuhito&apos;s eldest son, as the rightful successor (the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan theory), while others argue that FUJIWARA no Fusasaki, Fuhito&apos;s second son who rose to prominence earlier than his older brother, was the successor (the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan theory).</e>
<cmt>the Fujiwara Nanke→the Southern House of the Fujiwara clanthe Fujiwara Hokke→the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>房前が生前元明天皇や聖武天皇の信任厚く特に祖父・鎌足と同じ内臣の地位が与えられたのは事実であるが、当時の慣習として高官の嫡男が父親の存命中に高位に昇る事が憚られていた事を考えると、当初は南家が藤原氏の嫡流であったと考えるのが妥当とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it is true that Fusasaki was trusted during his life by Emperor Gemmei and Emperor Shomu and was awarded the same Naishin post (government post) as his grandfather Kamatari, considering the general custom at the time that prohibited the rightful male successor to a high-ranking official from holding an important government post, it is more likely that the Nan Family was the rightful successor to the Fujiwara Clan at the beginning.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it is true that Fusasaki was trusted during his life by Emperor Gemmei and Emperor Shomu and was awarded the same Naishin post (government post) as his grandfather Kamatari, considering the general custom that prohibited the rightful male successor to a high-ranking official from holding an important government post, it is more likely that the Nan Family was initially the rightful successor of the Fujiwara Clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it is true that Fusasaki was trusted during his life by Emperor Genmei and Emperor Shomu and was awarded the same Naishin post (government post) as his grandfather Kamatari, considering the general custom that prohibited the rightful male successor to a high-ranking official from holding an important government post, it is more likely that the Southern House was initially the rightful successor of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Gemmei→GenmeiNan Family→Southern HouseFujiwara Clan→Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>藤原氏北家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hokke (Hoku Family) of the Fujiwara Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hokke (Hoku Family) of the Fujiwara Clan</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Northern House of the Fujiwara Clan</e>
<cmt>Hokke (Hoku family)→the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>その後4家は盛衰し、平安時代中期から北家のみが栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The four families continued to rise and fall, and from the mid-Heian period onward, the Hoku Family alone came to enjoy prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The four families continued to rise and fall, and from the mid-Heian period onward the Hoku Family alone came to enjoy prosperity.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The four families continued to rise and fall, and from the mid-Heian period onward the Northern House alone came to enjoy prosperity.</e>
<cmt>theの重複。 “ onward the the Northern,”=&gt; “onward the Northern ”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>藤原冬嗣の子藤原良房は清和天皇の外戚となり人臣で初めての摂政となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, the son of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, married into the maternal line of Emperor Seiwa, becoming the first regent chosen from among imperial subjects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, the son of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, married into the maternal line of Emperor Seiwa, becoming the first regent chosen from among imperial subjects.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, the son of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, married into the maternal line of Emperor Seiwa, becoming the first regent chosen from among imperial subjects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>皇室と姻戚関係を結ぶことにより他氏を排斥し権力を増強する路線は良房の養子藤原基経に引き継がれ陽成天皇の外戚として、幼帝の摂政、成人してからは関白を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The strategy aimed at driving other clans out of power and strengthening one&apos;s own power through marriage with the Imperial family was inherited by FUJIWARA no Mototsune, the adopted son of Yoshifusa and a maternal relative of Emperor Yozei, who acted as regent for the young emperor and as chief adviser to the Emperor after he grew up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The strategy aimed at driving other clans out of power and strengthening one&apos;s own power through marriage with the Imperial Family was inherited by FUJIWARA no Mototsune, the adopted son of Yoshifusa and a maternal relative of Emperor Yozei, who acted as regent for the young Emperor and as chief adviser to the Emperor once he had reached adulthood.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The strategy aimed at driving other clans out of power and strengthening one&apos;s own power through marriage with the Imperial Family was inherited by FUJIWARA no Mototsune, the adopted son of Yoshifusa and a maternal relative of Emperor Yozei, who acted as regent for the young Emperor and as chief adviser to the Emperor once he had reached adulthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>以後、江戸末期まで摂政関白は（豊臣氏を除き）藤原北家のこの系統に限られていくようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From that time until the late Edo period, the posts of regent and chief adviser to the Emperor were gradually monopolized by this family line of the Fujiwara Hoku Family (except for the Toyotomi clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From that time until the late Edo period, the posts of regent and chief adviser to the Emperor were gradually monopolized by this family line of the Fujiwara Hoku Family (except for the Toyotomi clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From that time until the late Edo period, the posts of regent and chief adviser to the Emperor were gradually monopolized by this family line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (except for the Toyotomi clan).</e>
<cmt>the Fujiwara Hoku family→the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>藤原北家以外で関白となったのは豊臣秀次ただ一人（秀吉は藤原秀吉として任官）であり、五摂家以外からの摂政は例がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI was the only person other than members of the Fujiwara Hoku Family who was appointed as chief adviser to the Emperor (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was appointed under the name of FUJIWARA no Hideyoshi), and there is no example of a person other than members of the five major Fujiwara families (called Gosekke) who was appointed as regent to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI was the only person other than members of the Fujiwara Hoku Family who was appointed to serve as chief adviser to the Emperor (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was appointed under the name of FUJIWARA no Hideyoshi), and there is no example of a person other than members of the five major Fujiwara families (called Gosekke) who was appointed as regent to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI was the only person other than members of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan who was appointed to serve as chief adviser to the Emperor (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was appointed under the name of FUJIWARA no Hideyoshi), and there is no example of a person other than members of the five major Fujiwara families (called Gosekke) who was appointed as regent to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>the Fujiwara Hoku family→the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>摂関政治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rule by Sekkan (Regent to the Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rule by Sekkan (Regent to the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rule by Sekkan (Regent to the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>そして10世紀の安和の変で藤原氏の他氏排斥が完了すると、藤原道長・藤原頼通父子の時代に藤原氏摂関政治の最盛期を迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having driven other clans completely out of power by the Anna no Hen Conspiracy in the 10th century, the Fujiwara clan reached its heyday in the golden age of the rule by Sekkan when FUJIWARA no Michinaga and his son FUJIWARA no Yorimichi held power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fujiwara clan, aving driven other clans completely out of power by the Anna no Hen Conspiracy in the tenth century, the Fujiwara clan reached its nadir during the golden age of the rule by Sekkan, when FUJIWARA no Michinaga and his son FUJIWARA no Yorimichi held power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having driven other clans completely out of power by the Anna no Hen Conspiracy in the tenth century, the Fujiwara clan reached its peak during the golden age of the rule by Sekkan, when FUJIWARA no Michinaga and his son FUJIWARA no Yorimichi held power.</e>
<cmt>余分。最初の “The Fujiwara clan, ”削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>平安時代後期になると藤原氏と姻戚関係を持たない上皇による院政がはじまり、さらに源平両氏の武家政権と移行するにつれ藤原氏の権勢は後退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, political rule by ex-emperors who did not have marriage relationships with the Fujiwara clan started in the late Heian period, and as the focus of political activities shifted toward the military rule by Genji and Heishi, the Fujiwara clan gradually fell from power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, political rule by ex-emperors who did not have marriage relationships with the Fujiwara clan started during the late Heian period, and as the focus of political activities shifted toward the military rule by Genji and Heishi the Fujiwara clan gradually fell from power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, political rule by retired emperors who did not have marriage relationships with the Fujiwara clan started during the late Heian period, and as the focus of political activities shifted toward the military rule by the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan the Fujiwara clan gradually fell from power.</e>
<cmt>ex-emperors→retired emperorsGenji and Heishi→the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>姓から家名へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Official Status Titles to Family Names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Titles of Official Status to Family Names</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Titles of Official Status to Family Names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>鎌倉時代に入ると藤原氏の嫡流は近衛家・鷹司家・九条家・二条家・一条家の五摂家に分立し、五摂家が交代で摂政・関白を独占し続け公家社会においては一定の影響力を持ち続けるが、政治の中枢とは隔絶し明治に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, the descendants of the Fujiwara clan split into five different families (Konoe, Takatsukasa, Kujo, Nijo and Ichijo) and these five families continued to monopolize the posts of regent and chief adviser to the Emperor, exercising their influence within the narrow circle of court nobles, but they remained isolated from mainstream politics until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants of the Fujiwara clan split into five different families (Konoe, Takatsukasa, Kujo, Nijo and Ichijo) during the Kamakura period, and these five families continued to monopolize the posts of regent and chief adviser to the Emperor, exercising their influence within the narrow circle of court nobles; however, they remained isolated from mainstream politics until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendants of the Fujiwara clan split into five different families (Konoe, Takatsukasa, Kujo, Nijo and Ichijo) during the Kamakura period, and these five families continued to monopolize the posts of regent and chief adviser to the Emperor, exercising their influence within the narrow circle of court nobles; however, they remained isolated from mainstream politics until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>五摂家以外にも、三条家・西園寺家・閑院家・花山院家・御子左家・四条家・勧修寺家・日野家・中御門家など数多くの多くの支流・庶流がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the five major families, there are a large number of offshoots and branches of the Fujiwara clan, such as the Sanjo, Saionji, Kan-in, Kazanin, Miko-hidari, Shijo, Kajuji, Hino and Nakamikado Families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the five major families, there were numerous offshoots and branches of the Fujiwara clan, such as the Sanjo, Saionji, Kan-in, Kazanin, Miko-hidari, Shijo, Kajuji, Hino and Nakamikado families.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the five major families, there were numerous offshoots and branches of the Fujiwara clan, such as the Sanjo, Saionji, Kan in, Kazanin, Miko hidari, Shijo, Kajuji, Hino and Nakamikado families.</e>
<cmt>Kan-in→Kan inMiko-hidari→Miko hidari</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>公家の他に、北家の藤原道兼の子孫の宇都宮氏流や、同じく北家の藤原長家の子孫の那須氏流、同じく北家の藤原房前の子の藤原魚名の子孫の藤原利仁、藤原秀郷からは、多くの武家も輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides court noble families, a number of samurai families also descended from the descendants of the Fujiwara clan, including the Utsunomiya clan group, which descended from FUJIWARA no Michikane of the Hoku Family, the Nasu clan group, which descended from FUJIWARA no Nagaie of the Hoku Family, and FUJIWARA no Toshihito and FUJIWARA no Hidesato, who descended from FUJIWARA no Uona, the son of FUJIWARA no Fusasaki of the Hoku Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides court noble families, various samurai families in turn descended from the descendants of the Fujiwara clan, including the Utsunomiya clan group, which descended from FUJIWARA no Michikane of the Hoku Family, the Nasu clan group, which descended from FUJIWARA no Nagaie of the Hoku Family, and FUJIWARA no Toshihito and FUJIWARA no Hidesato, who descended from FUJIWARA no Uona, the son of FUJIWARA no Fusasaki of the Hoku Family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides court noble families, various samurai families in turn descended from the descendants of the Fujiwara clan, including the Utsunomiya clan group, which descended from FUJIWARA no Michikane of the Northern House, the Nasu clan group, which descended from FUJIWARA no Nagaie of the Northern House, and FUJIWARA no Toshihito and FUJIWARA no Hidesato, who descended from FUJIWARA no Uona, the son of FUJIWARA no Fusasaki of the Northern House.</e>
<cmt>the Hoku Family→the Northern House</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>現代の藤原（氏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujiwara in the Contemporary Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiwara in the Contemporary Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiwara in the Contemporary Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>公卿や大名の藤原氏には、「藤原」という家名や苗字はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no family by the name of Fujiwara among the families of former court nobles or feudal lords that belong to the former Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no family with the Fujiwara name among the families of former court nobles or feudal lords that belong to the former Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no family with the Fujiwara name among the families of former court nobles or feudal lords that belong to the former Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>現代の藤原家は、かつての姓ではなく苗字であり、歴史に登場する藤原氏とはまず関係がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fujiwara&quot; is no longer used as an official title of a rank but a family name, and Fujiwara families in contemporary Japan are unlikely to be related to the Fujiwara clan that appear in history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fujiwara&quot; is no longer used as an official title of a rank but as a family name, and Fujiwara families in contemporary Japan are unlikely to be related to the historical Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Fujiwara&quot; is no longer used as an official title of a rank but as a family name, and Fujiwara families in contemporary Japan are unlikely to be related to the historical Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>藤原氏一門なら近衛家や九条家のような藤原氏の家名の苗字となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families belonging to the Fujiwara clan use their own family names, such as Konoe and Kujo, other than the clan name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Families belonging to the Fujiwara clan use their own family names, such as Konoe and Kujo, instead of the clan name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Families belonging to the Fujiwara clan use their own family names, such as Konoe and Kujo, instead of the clan name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>もっとも、苗字としての「藤原」氏は江戸時代以前にも下級武士などに散見される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were a number of low-ranking samurai families that used Fujiwara as their family name even before the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were numerous low-ranking samurai families that used Fujiwara as the family name even before the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were numerous low-ranking samurai families that used Fujiwara as the family name even before the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、藤原純友一門などは、家来も主を慕って名を冠することもあったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the members of FUJIWARA no Sumitomo&apos;s group, retainers also often adopted their lords&apos; family name to show respect to their lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the members of FUJIWARA no Sumitomo&apos;s group, retainers would often adopt their lords&apos; family names as a sign of respect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the members of FUJIWARA no Sumitomo&apos;s group, retainers would often adopt their lords&apos; family names as a sign of respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>現在の研究では、庶民の苗字は明治初めにもともと先祖伝来のものを戸籍に載せたとされるが、記録が伝わらないのでその正確な由来を尋ねることは不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, it is generally acknowledged that the family names of ordinary families that were recorded in the family register compiled in the early Meiji period were those inherited from their ancestors, but since no written records are available, it is impossible to accurately identify the origin of these names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, it is generally acknowledged that the names of ordinary families that were recorded in the family register compiled during the early Meiji period had been inherited from their ancestors, but since no written records are available it is impossible to accurately identify the origins of these names.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, it is generally acknowledged that the names of ordinary families that were recorded in the family register compiled during the early Meiji period had been inherited from their ancestors, but since no written records are available it is impossible to accurately identify the origins of these names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="42">
<j>藤裔会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toeikai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toeikai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toeikai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>年1回、秋頃に全国の藤原氏の末裔が奈良市の春日大社に集まり、親睦を兼ねた会合などを執り行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fall every year, the descendants of the Fujiwara clan across Japan gather together at Kasuga Taisha Shrine in Nara City in order to have friendly meetings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toeikai</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toeikai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Flamelai(id:34490), Obto(id:27689), Non-stop24(id:10471), 講師(id:71860), Andre Engels(id:202), Nnh(id:474), 紀州太政大臣(id:42479), Eskimbot(id:29676), 陽一(id:92099), 味っ子(id:17086), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Andee(id:20421), Sutou(id:32), 沢田(id:40580), Robert De Smith(id:28533), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), でここ(id:9565), Mourisan(id:160230), Gig(id:2773), NPD(id:58640), 十月之交(id:586), BotMultichill(id:132395), Muhammad jp(id:89111), Shimoxx(id:9332), Kzhr(id:131), Toki-ho(id:10691), Mnd(id:15140), 福いたら里(id:33988), Law soma(id:45202), STBot(id:137943), Riekanu(id:65656), ごまふあざ(id:36855), 松平定治(id:146386), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), YurikBot(id:18605), Tan90deg(id:40673), Doripoke(id:18028), おうみや(id:41553), Alexbot(id:157199), Junger(id:10282), SieBot(id:126695), 小太刀(id:18154), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>