<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>四辻善成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>四辻 善成（よつつじ よしなり、嘉暦元年（1326年） - 応永9年9月3日 (旧暦)（1402年9月29日））は、南北朝時代 (日本)から室町時代中期にかけての公家・学者・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI (1326-September 29, 1402) was the kuge (aristocrat), academia, and kajin (poet for Japanese poetry), who lived between the Nanbokucho (the Southern and Northern Court) and mid-Muromachi Periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI (1326-September 29, 1402) was a kuge (aristocrat), academia, and kajin (poet for Japanese poetry), who lived between the Nanbokucho (the Southern and Northern Court) and mid-Muromachi Periods.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI (1326-October 8, 1402) was a kuge (aristocrat), academia, and kajin (poet for Japanese poetry), who lived between the Northern and Southern Courts period and mid-Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>西暦をグレゴリオ暦に修正、the Northern and Southern Courts period and mid-Muromachi periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>号は松岩寺左大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His go (rank) was Shoganji Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (rank) was Shoganji Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (title) was Shoganji Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>rank→titleに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は尊雅王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Songao (Prince Songa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Songao (Prince Songa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Prince Songa.</e>
<cmt>Prince Songaのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>祖父は善統親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandfather was Imperial Prince Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather was Imperial Prince Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather was Imperial Prince Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>順徳天皇は曽祖父にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His great-grandfather was the Emperor Juntoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His great-grandfather was the Emperor Juntoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His great-grandfather was the Emperor Juntoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>順徳天皇の末裔で代々「四辻宮」を号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the descendant of Emperor Juntoku, and each generation received the go of &quot;Yotsutsuji no miya.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the descendant of Emperor Juntoku, and each generation received the go of &quot;Yotsutsuji no miya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the descendant of Emperor Juntoku, and each generation received the go of &apos;Yotsutsuji no miya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>妹に石清水八幡宮祀官・紀通清妻、智泉聖通がおり、その女良子が足利義満・足利満詮の生母となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger sisters were the wife of KI no Tsusei, who was the Shikan (祀官) of Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine, Chisen Shotsu and her daughter, Yoshiko (KI no Yoshiko) became the birth mother to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and Mitsuakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger sisters were the wife of KI no Tsusei, who was the Shikan (祀官) of Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine, Chisen Shotsu and her daughter, Yoshiko (KI no Yoshiko) became the birth mother to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and Mitsuakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger sisters were the wife of KI no Tsusei, who was the Shikan (祀官) of Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine, Chisen Shotsu and her daughter, Yoshiko (KI no Yoshiko) became the birth mother to Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and Mitsuakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1356年（延文元年）源氏（順徳源氏）を賜り臣籍に下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received the last name of Juntoku Genji (Minamoto Clan) and left the imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the last name of Juntoku Genji (Minamoto Clan) and left the imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the last name of Juntoku Genji (Minamoto clan) and left the imperial family in 1356.</e>
<cmt>「1356年」を訳出、Clanの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>関白二条良基の猶子となり、その庇護を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by Yoshimoto NIJO, who had the title of Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) and received his protection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by Yoshimoto NIJO, who had the title of Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) and received his protection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by Yoshimoto NIJO, who had the title of Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) and received his protection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1370年（応安3年）権大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor) in 1370.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor) in 1370.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the Gon Dainagon (Provisional Chief Councilor of State) in 1370.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの&quot;Dainagon&quot;の表記に基づき、Gon Dainagon (Provisional Chief Councilor of State)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さらに征夷大将軍足利義満・管領斯波義将の後援があり、1395年（応永2年）に左大臣となり、まもなく出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the Sadaijin (minister of the left) by gaining the support from Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, who had the title of seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians,&quot; and Yoshimasa (Yoshiyuki) SHIBA, who had the title of Kanrei (Shogunal Deputy), and he eventually underwent Shukke (became the priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the Sadaijin (minister of the left) by gaining the support from Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, who had the title of seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians,&quot; and Yoshimasa (Yoshiyuki) SHIBA, who had the title of Kanrei (Shogunal Deputy), and he eventually underwent Shukke (became the priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the Sadaijin (minister of the left) by gaining the support from Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, who had the title of Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), and Yoshimasa (Yoshiyuki) SHIBA, who had the title of Kanrei (Shogunal Deputy), and he eventually became the priest.</e>
<cmt>他のtitle表記に合わせ、Seii Taishogunとし、カッコの片方を追加、underwent Shukke (became the priest)→became the priestのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>法名常勝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Homyo (Dharma Name) was Josho (常勝).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Homyo (Dharma Name) was Josho (常勝).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Homyo (Dharma Name) was Josho (常勝).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>但し出家の時に親王宣下を望んだというが(『荒暦』)、斯波義将の反対で果たせなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he wished to declare Senge (imperial proclamation) as the Shin-o (crown prince) (&quot;Koryaku&quot; (diary of Tsunetsugu ICHIJO)), he could not achieve it due to the opposition from Yoshiyuki SHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he wished to declare Senge (imperial proclamation) as the Shin-o (crown prince) (&quot;Koryaku&quot; (diary of Tsunetsugu ICHIJO)), he could not achieve it due to opposition from Yoshiyuki SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he wished to be given the title of Imperial Prince when he became the priest (&quot;Koryaku&quot; (diary of Tsunetsugu ICHIJO)), he could not achieve it due to opposition from Yoshiyuki SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>「出家の時に」を訳出、および「親王宣下」の表現を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>歌人・古典学者としても知られ、若いころに河内流の源氏学者で二条派歌人の丹波忠守の薫陶を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known as the kajin and Japanese classics scholar and received the training of TANBA no Tadamori, who was the scholar of the Kawachi School of Minamoto clan and the Kajin of the Nijo school (of poetry) when he was young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known as the kajin and Japanese classics scholar and received training from TANBA no Tadamori, who was a scholar of the Kawachi School of Minamoto clan and the Kajin of the Nijo school (of poetry) when he was young.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known as the kajin and Japanese classics scholar and received training from TANBA no Tadamori, who was a scholar of the Kawachi school of Minamoto clan and the kajin of the Nijo school (of poetry) when he was young.</e>
<cmt>他の表記に合わせ、Kajin→kajin、School→schoolとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>大臣や将軍をはじめ、地方国人にも古典を講じて人望があり、「正六位上物語博士源惟良」の筆名で、貞治年間、「源氏物語」の注釈書である河海抄を将軍足利義詮に献じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was highly demanded from ministers and shogun to people of the local district for his lectures on Japanese classics and presented the &quot;Kakaisho,&quot; which was the annotation of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (Tale of Genji) under the pen name of &quot;Shorokuinojo Monogatari Hakushi MINAMOTO no Iryo&quot; (MINAMOTO no Iryo, who is the scholar of stories with the rank of Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade)) during Shoji (1362-1368) years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was in high demand by ministers and shogun to people of the local district for his lectures on Japanese classics and presented the &quot;Kakaisho,&quot; which was the annotation of &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (Tale of Genji) under the pen name of &quot;Shorokuinojo Monogatari Hakushi MINAMOTO no Iryo&quot; (MINAMOTO no Iryo, who was a scholar of stories holding the rank of Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade)) during Shoji (1362-1368) years.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was in high demand by ministers and shogun to people of the local district for his lectures on Japanese classics and presented the Kakaisho, which was the annotation of &apos;Genji Monogatari&apos; (Tale of Genji) under the pen name of &apos;Shorokuinojo Monogatari Hakushi MINAMOTO no Iryo&apos; (MINAMOTO no Iryo, who was a scholar of stories holding the rank of Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade)) during Shoji (1362-1368) years.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ、Kakaishoのクォーテーション削除、他の作品のクォーテーションをシングルに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>河海抄は、源氏物語のいわゆる古注のなかで最高の水準にあるものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakaisho is considered to have the highest quality among the old annotations of the Tale of Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakaisho is considered to have the highest quality among the old annotations of the Tale of Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakaisho is considered to have the highest quality among the old annotations of the Tale of Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、その源氏の秘説を集めた書が「珊瑚秘抄」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the document that contained the secret story about Minamoto clan was &quot;Sangohisho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the document that contained the secret story about Minamoto clan was &quot;Sangohisho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the document that contained the secret story about the Minamoto clan was &apos;Sangohisho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Minamoto clan→the Minamoto clanとし、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「千鳥抄」は、嘉慶元年に始められた善成の講義を、大内氏の家臣平井相（道）助が記録したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chidorisho&quot; was the lectures of Yoshinari started in 1387 and recorded by Sosuke (Dojo) HIRAI, who was the servant of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chidorisho&quot; were lectures by Yoshinari that started in 1387 and were recorded by Sosuke (Dojo) HIRAI, who was the servant of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chidorisho&apos; were lectures by Yoshinari that started in 1387 and were recorded by Sosuke (Dojo) HIRAI, who was the servant of the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>和歌は「風雅和歌集」以下の勅撰和歌集にも入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Japanese poems were collected even within &quot;Fuga Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Japanese Poetry of Elegance, 17th imperial anthology), one of the chokusen wakashu (poems collected by emperors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Japanese poems were collected even within &quot;Fuga Wakashu&quot; (Collection of Japanese Poetry of Elegance, 17th imperial anthology), one of the chokusen wakashu (poems collected by emperors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Japanese poems were collected even within &apos;Fuga Wakashu&apos; (Collection of Japanese Poetry of Elegance, 17th imperial anthology), one of the chokusen wakashu (poems collected by emperors).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), Andee(id:20421), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 123456(id:67803), 編集仁王(id:208160), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>