<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>春日局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga no Tsubone</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga no Tsubone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga no Tsubone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>春日局（かすが の つぼね、天正7年（1579年） - 寛永20年9月14日 (旧暦)（1643年10月26日））は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代前期の女性で、江戸幕府3代征夷大将軍・徳川家光の乳母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga no Tsubone (1579 ~ October 26, 1643) was a woman of the Azuchi-Momoyama period and early Edo period, who was a nan of the third Seii taishogun (literally, great general who subdues the barbarians) of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasuga no Tsubone (1579 - October 26, 1643) was a woman of the Azuchi-Momoyama period and early Edo period, who was a nan of the third Seii taishogun (literally, great general who subdues the barbarians) of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasuga no Tsubone (1579 - October 26, 1643), a woman who lived during the Azuchi-Momoyama period and into early Edo period, who the wet nurse of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third Shogun of the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「春日局」とは朝廷から賜った称号で、本名は斎藤 福（さいとう ふく）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born as Fuku Saito and &quot;Kasuga no Tsubone&quot; (literally, Lady Kasuga) was a title given by Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born as Fuku Saito, and &quot;Kasuga no Tsubone&quot; (literally, Lady Kasuga) was a title given by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real name was Fuku SAITO; &apos;Kasuga no Tsubone&quot; (&apos;Lady Kasuga&apos;) was a title granted to her by the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は美濃国の名族斎藤氏（美濃国守護代）の一族で明智光秀の重臣であり甥（実際には従弟）とも言われる斎藤利三で、母は稲葉良通の娘・稲葉あん。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was a member of a distinguished clan of Mino Province, the Saito clan (Deputy military governor of Mino Province) and a key vassal of Mitsuhide AKECHI, who was said to be a nephew of Mitsuhide (actually, a cousin,) Toshimitsu SAITO, and her mother was a daughter of Yoshimichi INABA, &apos;An INABA.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was a member of a distinguished clan of Mino Province, the Saito clan (Deputy military governor of Mino Province) and a key vassal of Mitsuhide AKECHI, who was said to be a nephew of Mitsuhide (actually a cousin), Toshimitsu SAITO, and her mother was a daughter of Yoshimichi INABA, &apos;An INABA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father, Toshimitsu SAITO, was a member of the prestigious Saito clan (who held the position of deputy military governor of Mino Province) and was a key vassal of Mitsuhide AKECHI, and indeed was referred to as Mitsuhide&apos;s nephew (but was actually his cousin); her mother, An INABA was the daughter of Yoshimichi INABA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>稲葉正成の妻で、稲葉正勝、稲葉正吉、稲葉正利は実子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was wife of Masanari INABA, and real mother of Masakatsu INABA, Masayoshi INABA and Masatoshi INABA..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the wife of Masanari INABA and the real mother of Masakatsu INABA, Masayoshi INABA and Masatoshi INABA.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsubono was the wife of Masanari INABA and the biological mother of Masakatsu INABA, Masayoshi INABA and Masatoshi INABA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>養子に堀田正俊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She also had an adopted child, Masatoshi HOTTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She also had an adopted child, Masatoshi HOTTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She also had an adopted child, Masatoshi HOTTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大奥の礎を築いた人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a person who had built a cornerstone of O-oku (literally, great interior, the inner halls of Edo Castle where the wife of the Shogun and her servants resided.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had been a cornerstone of O-oku (literally, great interior, the inner halls of Edo Castle where the wife of the shogun and her servants resided).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsubono was one of the most powerful figures in the O-oku (the quarters in Edo-jo Castle where the Shogun&apos;s wife and consorts resided).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>松平信綱、柳生宗矩とともに家光を支えた「鼎の脚」の一人に数えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was counted in as &quot;a leg of tripod&quot; together with Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA and Munenori YAGYU who supported Iemitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was counted as &quot;a leg of a tripod&quot; together with Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA and Munenori YAGYU, who supported Iemitsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is counted alongside Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA and Muneyori YAGYU as one of the Three Tripod Legs, who supported and propped up Iemitsu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>実家の斉藤氏は美濃国の守護代を代々務めた武家の名門だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her family home, the Saito was a prominent samurai family who worked as Deputy military governor of Mino Province for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her family home, the Saito, was a prominent samurai family that had served as deputy military governors of Mino Province for generations.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her birth family, the Saito clan, was a prestigious warrior house that had served for generations as deputy military governors of Mino province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>春日局は、その当時父の所領のあった丹波国（現・兵庫県および京都府）の黒井城下館（興禅寺 (丹波市)）で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born at Kuroi-jo Castle shimokata (Kozen-ji Temple, Tanba City) of Tanba no kuni (Tanba Province, today&apos;s Hyogo Prefecture and Kyoto Prefecture) where there was a territory of his father at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born at Kuroi-jo Castle Shimokata (Kozen-ji Temple, Tanba City) of Tanba no kuni (Tanba Province, the modern-day Hyogo Prefecture and Kyoto Prefecture), where there was a territory of her father.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born at Shimokata in Kuroi-jo Castle (Kozen-ji Temple in the city of Tanba) of Tanba province (comprising modern-day Hyogo and Kyoto Prefectures), which is where her father&apos;s territory was then located.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>丹波国は明智光秀の所領であり斎藤利三は家臣として丹波国内に光秀から領地を与えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanba Province was a territory of Mitsuhide AKECHI and Toshimitsu SAITO was given a fief in the territory by Mitsuhide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanba Province was a territory of Mitsuhide AKECHI, and Toshimitsu SAITO was given a fief in the territory by Mitsuhide.</e>
<cmt>punctuationunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanba Province was under the overlordship of Mitsuhide AKECHI, and so Toshimitsu SAITO, as his vassal, was enfeoffed on that territory by Mitsuhide.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後父・斎藤利三は主君の光秀に従い、ともに本能寺の変で織田信長を討つが、豊臣秀吉に山崎の合戦で敗戦し帰城後に坂本城下の近江国堅田で捕らえられて処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, her father Toshimichi SAITO beat Nobunaga ODA at the Honnoji Incident following his master Mitsuhide, however, they were beaten back by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI at the Battle of Yamazaki and after Toshimichi retreated back to the castle, he was caught by the enemy at Katata, Omi Province near Sakamoto-jo castle and executed, and it is thought that his other brothers were fleeing the enemy and roamed about one place after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, her father Toshimichi SAITO beat Nobunaga ODA at the Honnoji Incident following his master Mitsuhide, however, they were beaten back by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI at the Battle of Yamazaki and after Toshimichi retreated back to the castle, he was caught by the enemy at Katata, Omi Province near Sakamoto-jo castle and executed, and it is thought that his other brothers were fleeing the enemy and roamed about one place after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, her father Toshimitsu SAITO followed his overlord Mitsuhide in the strike against Nobunaga ODA in the Honnoji Incident, but they were defeated by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in the Battle of Yamazaki, and Toshimitsu retreated back to his castle; later he was caught at Katata in Omi province, near Sakamoto-jo Castle, and was executed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>他の兄弟は落ち武者となって各地を流浪していたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that his various brothers, having become defeated and hunted warriors, wandered from place to place trying to escape the enemy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>福は女であることから追われることはなく、母方の親戚に当たる三条西公国に養育された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Fuku was a woman and not traced by the enemy, she was raised by her maternal relative, a court noble Kinkuni SANJONISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Fuku was a woman who could not be traced by the enemy, she was raised by her maternal relative, the court noble Kinkuni SANJONISHI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Fuku was a woman she could not be driven away by the enemy, so she was raised by her maternal relative, the aristocrat Kinkuni SANJONISHI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これによって、公家の素養である書道・歌道・香道等の教養を身につけることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, she could acquire culture such as an art of calligraphy, waka poetry and incense burning, etc. which were thought to be cultivation of court nobles&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, she was able to acquire culture such as the art of calligraphy, waka poetry and incense burning, etc., which were thought to be court nobles&apos; cultivations.</e>
<cmt>punctuationunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of her aristocratic upbringing, she learned those arts considered essential to court nobles, including the arts of calligraphy, waka poetry, and incense mixing.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後、伯父稲葉重通の養女となり、稲葉一鉄の縁者で小早川秀秋の家臣である稲葉正成の後妻となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, she became an adopted daughter of her uncle, Shigemichi INABA and became the second wife of Masanari INABA who was a relative of Ittetsu INABA, a member of Inaba clan and a subject of Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, she became an adopted daughter of her uncle, Shigemichi INABA, and became the second wife of Masanari INABA who was a relative of Ittetsu INABA, a member of the Inaba clan and a subject of Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>punctuationunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was later adopted by her uncle, Shigemichi INABA, and became the second wife of one of Ittetsu INABA&apos;s relatives, namely Masanari INABA, a member of the Inaba clan and a vassal of Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>稲葉正成は、関ヶ原の戦いにおいて、主君・秀秋を説得して小早川軍を東軍に寝返らせ、徳川家を勝利に導いた功労者である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanari INABA was a person who had done a distinguished service to persuade his master Kobayakawa and made his army changed sides to the Eastern army, and led the Tokugawa family to the victory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanari INABA was a person who had done a distinguished service in persuading his master Kobayakawa to have his army change sides to the Eastern army, and led the Tokugawa family to victory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanari INABA had rendered distinguished service in persuading his overlord Hideaki to have his Kobayakawa army change sides and join the Eastern army, and thus helped lead the Tokugawa family to victory.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>のちに、将軍家の乳母となるために夫の正成と離婚する形をとり、慶長9年（1604年）に2代将軍徳川秀忠の嫡子・竹千代（家光）の乳母に正式に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, she took a form of divorcing his husband Masanari in order to become a nan of Shogunate family, and in 1604, she was formally appointed to a nan of the legitimate son Takechiyo (childhood name of Iemitsu) of the second Shogun, Hidetada Tokugawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, she took the form of divorcing her husband Masanari in order to become a nan of the shogunate family, and in 1604 she was formally appointed as a nan of the legitimate son Takechiyo (childhood name of Iemitsu) of the second shogun, Hidetada Tokugawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, she took the step of divorcing her husband Masanari in order to become a wet nurse to the shogunal family, and in 1604 she was formally appointed as the wet nurse to Takechiyo (the childhood name of Iemitsu), the legitimate son and heir of the second shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>選考にあたり、福の家柄および公家の教養と、夫正成の戦功が評価されたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Fuku&apos;s good family lineage, her cultivation of court nobles&apos;, and her ex-husband Masanari&apos;s military exploits were appreciated at the time of selection of a nan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Fuku&apos;s good family lineage, her cultivation of court nobles and her ex-husband Masanari&apos;s military exploits were appreciated as a nan was to be selected.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Fuku&apos;s excellent pedigree, her refined, aristocratic upbringing, and her ex-husband Masanari&apos;s military exploits were all positive factors in her selection as wet nurse.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>家光死後の貞享3年（1686年）に成立した『春日局略譜』によれば、秀忠夫妻が竹千代の実弟・国松（徳川忠長）を溺愛している様子を憂慮し、自害しようとした家光を諌め、元和元年、駿府にいた大御所の徳川家康に竹千代の世継を確定させるように直訴したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kasuga no Tsubone Ryakufu (literally, History of Kasuga no Tsubone in brief)&quot; completed in 1686 after the death of Iemitsu, she remonstrated with Iemitsu (Childhood name, Takechiyo) who tried to commit suicide seeing the state that his parents, Hidetada and his wife were overfond of Takechiyo&apos;s real younger brother, Kunimatsu (childhood name of Tadanaga TOKUGAWA), and in 1615, she petitioned directly to &apos;Ogosho&apos; (leading or influential figure,) Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who was retired in Sunpu (today&apos;s Shizuoka City) to confirm the succession of the reign of shogunate by Takechiyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Kasuga no Tsubone Ryakufu&quot; (literally, History of Kasuga no Tsubone in brief), completed in 1686 after the death of Iemitsu, she remonstrated with Iemitsu (childhood name, Takechiyo) who had tried to commit suicide seeing the state in which his parents, Hidetada and his wife were overly fond of Takechiyo&apos;s real younger brother, Kunimatsu (childhood name, Tadanaga TOKUGAWA), and in 1615 she petitioned directly to &apos;Ogosho&apos; (leading or influential figure), Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who was retired in Sunpu (today&apos;s Shizuoka City) to confirm the succession of the reign of the shogunate by Takechiyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Kasuga no Tsubone Ryakufu&quot; (literally, The Abridged History of Kasuga no Tsubone), which was completed in 1686 after the death of Iemitsu, Tsubone remonstrated with Takachiyo (Iemitsu)--who had tried to commit suicide out of anguish that his parents, Hidetada and his wife, were overly fond of Takechiyo&apos;s biological younger brother, Kunimatsu (whose adult name was Tadanaga TOKUGAWA), and in 1615 she appealed directly to the &apos;Ogosho&apos; (leading or influential figure) Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who was living in retirement in Sunpu (what is today the city of Shizuoka), asking him to confirm that the Shogunal succession would pass to Takechiyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この直訴はその時は失敗し、後に家康が江戸城を訪れたときにその江与の溺愛ぶりを見て考え直した、という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an opinion that Kasuga no Tsubone&apos;s direct petition failed, and when Ieyasu visited Edo and saw the way Eyo (the brothers&apos; mother) doted upon the younger brother and reconsidered the petition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an opinion that Kasuga no Tsubone&apos;s direct petition failed, and when Ieyasu visited Edo and saw the way Eyo (the brothers&apos; mother) doted upon the younger brother he reconsidered the petition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory holds that Tsubone&apos;s direct petition to Ieyasu was rejected, and it was only after Ieyasu visited Edo-jo Castle and saw the way Eyo (the brothers&apos; mother) was doting upon the younger brother that he reconsidered.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>一方でまた、大奥大奥総取締という呼称についてに任ぜられて、奥向きの公務を取り仕切るようになり、将軍の権威を背景に老中をも上回る実質的な権力を握る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meanwhile, she was entitled to the head of O-oku and administered official works of O-oku, and she held substantial power stronger than that of members of shogun&apos;s council of elders under the authority of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>原文に重複がある様です「大奥」。この個所は無視しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, she was entitled to the head of O-oku and administered official works of O-oku, and she held power exceeding that of members of the shogun&apos;s council of elders under the authority of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, she was appointed to the position of Overseer of the O-oku, which gave her the right to decide all official business related to the O-oku, and as such her de facto power, backed by the Shogun&apos;s authority, exceeded that of the Shogun&apos;s Roju (Council of Elders).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>寛永6年（1629年）には、家光の天然痘治癒祈願のため伊勢神宮に参拝し、そのまま10月には上洛して御所への昇殿を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She visited Ise Jingu Shrine and prayed for the cure of Iemitsu who suffered from smallpox in 1629 and in October, she visited Kyoto on her way back to Edo and tried to access to the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She visited Ise Jingu Shrine and prayed for the cure of Iemitsu, who suffered from smallpox in 1629, and in October she visited Kyoto on her way back to Edo and tried to gain access to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>punctuationunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1629, when Iemitsu was stricken with smallpox, she visited Ise Jingu Shrine to pray that he would be cured, and in the tenth month of that year she went to Kyoto on her way back and tried to arrange an audience at court.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし武家である齋藤家の娘の身分のままでは御所に昇殿するための資格を欠くため、血族であり（春日局は三条西公条の玄孫になる）、また育ての親でもある三条西公国の養女になろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Kasuga no Tsubone was not qualified to visit imperial court with her lineage as a daughter of the Saito samurai family, she tried to become an adopted daughter of Kinkuni SANJONISHI who was her relative (she was a great-great-grandchild of Kineda SANJONISHI) and raised her when she was younger.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Kasuga no Tsubone was not qualified to visit the Imperial Court with her lineage as a daughter of the Saito samurai family, she tried to become an adopted daughter of Kinkuni SANJONISHI, who was her relative (she was a great-great-grandchild of Kineda SANJONISHI) and had raised her when she was younger.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But with her pedigree as a daughter of the Saito clan, a warrior house, Kasuga no Tsubone was not qualified to enter the imperial court, so she tried to arrange to be adopted by Kinkuni SANJONISHI, who was both her blood relative (Tsubone was the great-great-grandchild of Kineda SANJONISHI) and had raised her when she was younger.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>が、既に他界していたため、やむをえずその息子三条西実条と猷妹の縁組をし、公卿三条西家の娘として参内する資格を得、後水尾天皇や中宮徳川和子に拝謁、また従三位の位と「春日局」の称号、および天杯をも賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kinkuni was already dead at the time and she was obliged to become a sister of Kinkuni&apos;s son Saneeda SANJONISHI and then she was qualified as a member of a court noble, Sanjonishi family to visit the palace and had an audience by Emperor Gomizunoo and Chugu (the second consort of an emperor) Kazuko TOKUGAWA, and was given the name of &quot;Kasuga no Tsubone&quot; and the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and &apos;tempai&apos; (sake given by the emperor.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。猷妹の訳が不明です。義理の縁組でしょうが左記の様にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kinkuni had already died, so she was obliged to become a sister of Kinkuni&apos;s son Saneeda SANJONISHI; thus she was qualified as a member of a court noble, the Sanjonishi family, to visit the palace and had an audience with Emperor Gomizunoo and Chugu (the second consort of an emperor) Kazuko TOKUGAWA, and was given the name &quot;Kasuga no Tsubone&quot; and the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and &apos;tempai&apos; (sake given by the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>spunctuationaceunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinkuni had already died, however, so she had no choice but to become a sister of Kinkuni&apos;s son Saneeda SANJONISHI instead; with this she was now qualified, as a full member of the aristocratic Sanjonishi family, to visit the palace, and succeeded in having an audience with Emperor Gomizunoo and with the Chugu (the second consort of an emperor) Kazuko TOKUGAWA, and was subsequently awarded the name &apos;Kasuga no Tsubone&apos; and given the Junior Third Rank at court, and moreover was honored with tempai (sake given by the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>後に官位は従二位にまで昇叙した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, she was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, she was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was later promoted to junior second rank.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>崇源院の死後は家光の側室探しに尽力し、伊勢国慶光院の院主であった永光院や、宝樹院、順性院などの女性たちを次々と奥入りさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Sugen-in (Iemitsu&apos;s mother, Eyo), Kasuga no Tsubone made efforts to find his concubines and had the women such as Eikoin who was the chief of Keiko-in Temple in Ise Province, Hojuin and Junshoin, etc. entered into O-oku one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Sugen-in (Iemitsu&apos;s mother, Eyo), Kasuga no Tsubone endeavored to find his concubines and had the women such as Eikoin, who was the chief of Keiko-in Temple in Ise Province, Hojuin and Junshoin, etc., enter into O-oku one after another.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Sugen-in (another name for Iemitsu&apos;s mother Eyo), Kasuga no Tsubone exerted herself to the utmost to find consorts for him, convincing a succession of women including Eikoin, the abbess of Keiko-in Temple in Ise Province, as well as Hojuin and Junshoin, to enter the O-oku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>寛永20年（1643年）9月に死去、享年64。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died in September in 1643 at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died in September 1643 at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died in October 1643 at the age of 64.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ歴に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>辞世の句は「西に入る 月を誘い 法をへて 今日ぞ火宅を逃れけるかな」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her death waka poem was literally, &quot;Now I could finally escape from the world full of agonies with the setting moon in the west after I understood the doctrine of Buddhism.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her death waka poem was literally, &quot;Now I can finally escape from the world full of agonies with the setting moon in the west, having understood the doctrine of Buddhism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poem she wrote upon her death reads, &quot;As it sinks into the West, the moon beckons me to transcend the law; today at last, I shall surely escape the Burning House (a Buddhist metaphor for the current world of passions and agony).&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>法号：麟祥院殿仁淵了義尼大姉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her posthumous Buddhist title was Rinsho-in dennin-ryogini-daishi.</e>
<cmt>戒名の読みが不明です。仮に左記の様にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her posthumous Buddhist title was Rinsho-in dennin-ryogini-daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her posthumous Buddhist title was Rinsho-in dennin-ryogini-daishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Graves</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Graves</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Where she is buried</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>麟祥院（東京都文京区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinsho-in Temple (Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinsho-in Temple (Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinsho-in Temple (Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>紹太寺（神奈川県小田原市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another grave: Shotai-ji Temple (Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another grave: Shotai-ji Temple (Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tomb dedicated to her also exists at Shotai-ji Temple (Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>肖像画：狩野探幽筆の肖像画が、麟祥院に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Portrait: A portrait painted by Tanyu KANO was in possession of Rinsho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her portrait: A portrait painted by Tanyu KANO was in possession of Rinsho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her portrait: it was painted by Tanyu KANO, and is currently in the possession of Rinsho-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>異説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different Views on Her Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Different Views on Her Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conflicting theories about her</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>徳川将軍家の乳母に登用された経緯には、京都所司代板倉勝重が一般公募した話などが伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a tradition about the circumstances she became a nan of the Tokugawa family that the Governor-General of Kyoto, Katsushige ITAKURA auditioned publicly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a tradition regarding the circumstances in which she became a nan of the Tokugawa family, for which the Governor-General of Kyoto, Katsushige ITAKURA, had held public auditions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One tradition about her selection as wet nurse to the Tokugawa family holds that the governor-general of Kyoto, Katsushige ITAKURA, posted a general public advertisement about the open position, and it was in response to this that she was selected.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>あるいは、秀忠の正室お江与の侍女である民部卿局の仲介で乳母となったともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that she became a nan with the mediation of Minbukyo no Tsubone (a court lady waited for the Minister of Popular Affairs) who served to Eyo, the legal wife of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that she became a nan through the mediation of Minbukyo no Tsubone (a court lady who waited on the Minister of Popular Affairs) who served Eyo, the legal wife of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that she became a wet nurse through the mediation of Minbukyo no Tsubone (a court lady who waited on the Minister of Popular Affairs) who served Eyo, the legal wife of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt>nan→wet nurse</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、家康の手が付いていたという見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other view, Ieyasu became intimate with her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another assessment is that Ieyasu had become intimate with her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another assessment is that Ieyasu had become intimate with her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>乳母に過ぎない身分の者が将軍世継ぎ問題で家康に直訴したとしても、通常家康が会うとは考えにくいので、お福がかつて愛妾の一人であったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that as it is difficult to think that Kasuga no Tsubone who was only a nan could meet Ieyasu when she tried to directly petition regarding the heir of the shogunate, she once was one of the favorite concubines of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory asserts that because it&apos;s difficult to think that Kasuga no Tsubone, who was only a nan, could meet Ieyasu when she tried to directly petition regarding the heir of the shogunate, she had once been one of Ieyasu&apos;s favorite concubines.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A different theory argues that she must have been one of Ieyasu&apos;s favorite concubines, or it would be inconceivable that she, a mere wet nurse, could have petitioned him directly about the Shogunal succession.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is not certain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is not certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is not certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>映画「女帝 春日局」（1990年）はこの異説で描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A movie &quot;The Empress Kasuga no tsubone&quot; (1990) was depicted from this divergent view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movie &quot;The Empress Kasuga no tsubone&quot; (1990) depicted this divergent view.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movie &apos;The Empress Kasuga no tsubone&apos; (1990) depicted this divergent view.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また近年、春日局が家光の生母という説があり、テレビの歴史番組などにも取り上げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A new theory that Kasuga no Tsubone was a real mother of Iemitsu was presented recently and this view was introduced in a historical program on TV.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A new theory that Kasuga no Tsubone was actually the mother of Iemitsu has been presented, and this view was introduced in a historical program on TV.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, a new theory has arisen that Kasuga no Tsubone was actually the biological mother of Iemitsu; this viewpoint has since been expressed by a variety of groups, including by history programs on television.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>大奥では、乳母は黒子のように覆面をして授乳する奇習があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a peculiar custom that a nan put on a mask like a &apos;kuroko&apos; (stage assistants dressed in black to conceal oneself) when breast-feeding a baby in O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a peculiar custom that a nan would put on a mask such as a &apos;kuroko&apos; (stage assistants dressed in black for concealment) when breast-feeding a baby in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a peculiar custom that a wet nurse would put on a mask such as a kuroko (stage assistants dressed in black for concealment) when breast-feeding a baby in O-oku.</e>
<cmt>nan→wet nurse原文に「」のない&apos;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これは春日局の権勢に懲りた幕閣が、将来の将軍と乳母のつながりが深くなり、後に政治に介入されるのを避けるために考案した風習という説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that this custom was a device thought out by the cabinet officials of the shogunate who learnt from the sour experience of Kasuga no Tsubone who held the reins of the power for the purpose that a nan could not have too strong tie with a shogun and intervene in politics later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is theorized that this custom was a device thought out by the cabinet officials of the shogunate, who learned from the sour experience of Kasuga no Tsubone, who held the reins of power, for the purpose that a nan shouldn&apos;t have a very strong tie with a shogun and consequently intervene in politics.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory argues that this custom was conceived by shogunal officials who had learned by bitter experience with Kasuga no Tsubone what can happen when the bond between the Shogun and his wet nurse becomes too strong, and thus was designed to prevent any future incidents of wet nurses using their close relationships with the Shogun to intervene in politics.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>山崎の戦いの後、義理の叔父である長宗我部元親を頼り、土佐国の岡豊城で過ごしたという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an opinion that she asked for a help from her uncle by marriage and spent sometime in Tosa Province (today&apos;s Kochi Province) after the Battle of Yamazaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an opinion that she had asked for a help from her uncle by marriage and spent time in Tosa Province (the present-day Kochi Province) after the Battle of Yamazaki.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One school of thought holds that after the Battle of Yamazaki, she had relied on Motochika CHOSOKABE, her uncle by marriage, for help, and had spent some time at Oko-jo Castle in Tosa province (modern-day Kochi Pref.).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>縁故により出世した人たち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nepotism</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nepotism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people whose careers she helped out of nepotism</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>春日局が参内できるよう画策した三条西実条は、後に朝廷から武家伝奏に任じられ、最終的には右大臣になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saneeda SANJONISHI who was planned that Kasuga no Tsubone could visit the imperial palace was appointed to &apos;buke tenso&apos; (liaison officer between the imperial court and the military government) by the imperial court, and finally became the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saneeda SANJONISHI, who had hoped that Kasuga no Tsubone could visit the Imperial Palace, was appointed to &apos;buke tenso&apos; (liaison officer between the Imperial Court and the military government) by the Court, and finally became the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saneeda SANJONISHI, who had created a plan by which Kasuga no Tsubone could visit the Imperial Palace, was appointed to the position of Buke tenso (the official in charge of communications between the shogunate and the Imperial Court) by the Court, and in the end rose to the position of Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>子孫の前田玄長は、幕府に高家として迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her descendant Harunaga MAEDA was appointed to a &apos;Koke&apos; (a privileged family under Tokugawa Shogunate.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her descendant, Harunaga MAEDA, was appointed to a &apos;Koke&apos; (a privileged family under the Tokugawa shogunate).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsubone&apos;s descendant Harunaga MAEDA was welcomed by the shogunate as a member of an elite family (a &apos;Koke&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>その際、縁のあった武家名字「前田氏」を名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time, he announced himself &quot;Maeda,&quot; a surname of samurai clan which he had relations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, he announced himself as &quot;Maeda,&quot; a surname of the samurai clan with which he had relations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then on, he referred to himself as a member of the Maeda clan, with whom they had a connection.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>春日局が強く望んで大奥入りさせられた永光院は、三条西家の同僚の和歌の家である六条家の娘である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eikoin whom Kasuga no Tsubone strongly desired to receive in O-oku was a daughter of a house of waka poet Rokujo Family, a colleague of Sanjonishi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eikoin, whom Kasuga no Tsubone deeply wanted to receive in O-oku, was a daughter of a house of the waka poet Rokujo family, a colleague of the Sanjonishi family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eikoin, whom Kasuga no Tsubone had fervently wanted to join the O-oku, was a daugher of the Rokujo family, a family of waka poets who were associated with the Sanjonishi family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>後に彼女の弟も幕府から高家として迎えられ、その際、こちらも縁のあった武家名字「戸田氏」を名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, her younger brother was also appointed to &apos;Koke&apos; and he announced himself &quot;Toda,&quot; a surname of samurai clan which he had relations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, her younger brother was also appointed to &apos;Koke&apos; and he announced himself as &quot;Toda,&quot; a surname of the samurai clan with which he had relations.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years, Tsubone&apos;s younger brother was also welcomed by the shogunate as a member of an elite family, so he began referring to himself as a member of the Toda clan, with whom they had a connection.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>離縁した稲葉家の再興にも尽力し、浪人していた元夫の稲葉正成は松平忠昌の家老として召し出され、のち大名に取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She also made efforts to revive the Inaba family and her ex-husband Masanari INABA who was a &apos;ronin&apos; (masterless samurai), and he was adopted as &apos;Karo&apos; (one of the chief retainers) of Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA and later, he was promoted to a Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She also endeavored to revive the Inaba family and her ex-husband Masanari INABA, who was a &apos;ronin&apos; (masterless samurai), and he was adopted as &apos;Karo&apos; (one of the chief retainers) of Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA; subsequently, he was promoted to Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She also endeavored to revive the fortunes of the Inaba family, even arranging for her ex-husband Masanari INABA, who had become a ronin (masterless samurai), to be adopted as a Karo (chief retainers) of Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA; subsequently, he was promoted to the status of daimyo (feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>家光の小姓から老中に出世した者は多いが、その中には春日局の縁者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is famous that many pageboys of Iemitsu advanced their career, and especially among them, there are many those who had relations with Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is well known that many pageboys of Iemitsu advanced their careers, and among them there were many who had relations with Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of Iemitsu&apos;s pageboys managed to rise in rank as far as the rank of Roju (member of the Shogun&apos;s council of elders), and among this group many were relatives of Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>特に実子である稲葉正勝と義理の孫に当たる堀田正盛が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the cases of her real son, Masakatsu INABA and a grandson by marriage, Masamori HOTTA are famous.</e>
<cmt>義理の孫の表現が分かりません。左記の様にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, the cases of her real son, Masakatsu INABA, and Masamori HOTTA, a grandson by marriage, are famous.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly famous is the case of her biological son Masakatsu INABA and the case of Masamori HOTTA, her grandson by marriage.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>姪の祖心尼とその夫・町野幸和が蒲生氏改易に伴い浪人したさいには、祖心尼を自分の補佐として出仕させ、また祖心尼の外孫・自証院を大奥に入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When her niece Soshinni&apos;s husband Yukikazu MACHINO became a &apos;ronin&apos; in accordance with &apos;Kaieki&apos; (to forfeit rank of Samurai and properties) of his master GAMO clan, Kasuga no Tsubone had Soshinni served as her aide and had Soshinni&apos;s &apos;sotomago&apos; (grandchild from a daughter married into another family), Jishoin (Ofuri) entered into O-oku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When her niece Soshinni&apos;s husband, Yukikazu MACHINO, became a &apos;ronin&apos; in accordance with &apos;Kaieki&apos; (to forfeit the samurai rank and properties) of his master, the GAMO clan, Kasuga no Tsubone had Soshinni serve as her aide and had Soshinni&apos;s &apos;sotomago&apos; (grandchild from a daughter married into another family), Jishoin (Ofuri) enter into O-oku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When her niece Soshinni and her husband, Yukikazu MACHINO, became ronin as a result of the Kaieki (demotion) of his overlords, the GAMO clan, Kasuga no Tsubone employed Soshinni as her aide and arranged to have Soshinni&apos;s granddaughter (from a daughter who had married into another family) Jishoin enter the O-oku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>お振は家光の側室となり千代姫を産んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ofuri became a concubine of Iemitsu and gave birth to Chiyohime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ofuri became a concubine of Iemitsu and gave birth to Chiyohime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ofuri became a concubine of Iemitsu and gave birth to Chiyohime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>幸和も幕府直参旗本として取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukikazu was also able to serve as a direct retainer of the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukikazu was also able to serve as a direct retainer of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukikazu was also able to serve as a direct retainer of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 模様砂漠(id:254067), ブレーム(id:214600), Sogiya(id:82968), ZassouTori(id:136771), 瑞雲(id:27410), Urania(id:7213), Cprobot(id:97843), 二八(id:10408), Extrahitz(id:26245), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Revth(id:12179), 飲んでも飲まれるな(id:120588), Flanc(id:47280), 行動で挽回するしかない(id:31799), でここ(id:9565), Shelling ford 221b(id:35237), Natunohi(id:6550), ニート谷(id:124391), A6M4(id:14155), Myopia(id:9335), Shelling ford(id:35136), 代言人(id:33675), Chobot(id:20846), こぶまき(id:38278), 寂華(id:83725), 麦塚ほとり(id:54917), Fwng3431(id:31854), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Izayohi(id:13095), ゆず湯(id:190382), やりたこ(id:113528), PANYNJ(id:38638), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), 이형주(id:216007), 松茸(id:27535), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Yanahan(id:2437), Sh(id:2707), 彩華1226(id:64711), Kagetudo(id:163875), Hatsune(id:26654), Shimotsuke(id:19741), ゐ(id:795), 海衛士(id:19229), 史さん(id:25829), アスタロト(id:81932), 663highland(id:18755), 今紫(id:9521), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>