<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊福部都牟自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ifukube no tsumuji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ifukube no tsumuji</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ifukube no tsumuji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊福部都牟自（いふくべのつむじ、生年不詳 - 斉明天皇4年（658年）3月11日 (旧暦)）は因幡国の古代豪族、伊福部氏の人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ifukube no tsumuji (year of birth unknown, April 21, 658 [March 11, 658, in old calendar]) is a member of Ifukube clan which was an ancient local ruling family in Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ifukube no tsumuji (year of birth unknown, April 21, 658 [March 11, 658, in old calendar]) is a member of Ifukube clan which was an ancient local ruling family in Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ifukube no tsumuji (year of birth unknown, April 21, 658) is a member of Ifukube clan which was an ancient local ruling family in Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>延暦3年（784年）に伊福部富成が編纂した同氏の系譜である『因幡国伊福部臣古志』によれば、父伊福部久遅良（くぢら）と母熊媛（くまひめ）との間の子で、同氏の26代目当主にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Koshi of Akira IFUKUBE in Inaba Province, &quot;the genealogy of Ifukube no Tomishige compiled by Ifukube no Tomishige in 784, he is the child between his father, Ifukube no kujira and his mother, Kumahime, and he is the twenty sixth generation of the Ifukube clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Inaba no Kuni Ifukube no Omi Koshi, &quot; the genealogy of Ifukube clan compiled by Ifukube no Tomishige in 784, Ifukube no tsumuji is the child between his father, Ifukube no kujira and his mother, Kumahime, and he is the twenty sixth generation of the Ifukube clan.</e>
<cmt>・『因幡国伊福部臣古志』はインターネットで調べてみましたが、読み方が確認できませんでした。tran1の対応部分が&quot;Koshi of Akira IFUKUBE in Inaba Province, &quot;となっていますが、原文と位置していないように思いますので、仮の読み方で修正しました。・伊福部富成の読み方も調べた結果、見当たらなかったのですが、trans1にある読みで問題ないのではないかと思いそのままにしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Inaba no Kuni Ifukube no Omi Koshi,&quot; the genealogy of Ifukube clan compiled by Ifukube no Tomishige in 784, Ifukube no tsumuji is the child between his father, Ifukube no kujira and his mother, Kumahime, and he is the twenty sixth generation of the Ifukube clan.</e>
<cmt>スペース調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>孝徳天皇の（大化）2年（646年）、初めて水依評を設置、それと同時に評督に任ぜられて小智冠が授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 646 (the period of Emperor Kotoku), he established 水依評 for the first time in Japan, and he was appointed to kori no kami (district chieftains) and 小智冠 was granted at the same time.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。 水依評→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。小智冠→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 646 (the period of Emperor Kotoku), he established 水依評 for the first time in Japan, and he was appointed to kori no kami (district chieftains) and 小智冠 was granted at the same time.</e>
<cmt>・水依評とはネット検索によると、「因幡国最初の郡であった」という記述があります。http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:65a620Nh72AJ:houki.yonago-kodaisi.com/F-B1-Wamyousyou.html+%E6%B0%B4%E4%BE%9D%E8%A9%95&amp;cd=3&amp;hl=ja&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=jp・小智冠とは、下記のサイトによれば、当時の冠位のひとつで「しょうちかん」と読むのではないかと思われます。http://www.weblio.jp/content/%E5%86%A0%E4%BD%8D%E3%83%BB%E4%BD%8D%E9%9A%8E%E5%88%B6%E5%BA%A6%E3%81%AE%E5%A4%89%E9%81%B7</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 646 (the period of Emperor Kotoku), he established 水依評 for the first time in Japan, and he was appointed to kori no kami (district chieftains) and 小智冠 was granted at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>翌3年（647年）に小黒冠が、同5年（649年）には大乙下が授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 647, 小黒冠 was granted to him, and daiotsuge (the sixteenth grade of nineteen grades of cap rank, which corresponds to Juhachiinojo and Juhachiinoge, Junior Eighth Rank, Upper and Lower Grades of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code) was granted in 649.</e>
<cmt>小黒冠→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 647, 小黒冠 was granted to him, and daiotsuge (the sixteenth grade of nineteen grades of cap rank, which corresponds to Juhachiinojo and Juhachiinoge, Junior Eighth Rank, Upper and Lower Grades of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code) was granted in 649.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 647, 小黒冠 was granted to him, and daiotsuge (the sixteenth grade of nineteen grades of cap rank, which corresponds to Juhachiinojo and Juhachiinoge, Junior Eighth Rank, Upper and Lower Grades of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code) was granted in 649.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、斉明天皇4年に大乙上に昇り、同年正月には水依評を壊して高草郡を設置、同年3月11日 (旧暦)に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he promoted to daiotsujo (the fifteenth grade of nineteen grades of cap rank, which corresponds to Shohachiinojo and Shohachiinoge, Senior Eighth Rank, Upper and Lower Grades of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code) in 658 (the period of Empress Saimei), established Takakusa Country on New year&apos;s days in 658 after braking 水依評, and passed away on April 21, 658.</e>
<cmt>高草郡→定訳不明ですが→Takakusa countryと訳出しています。水依評→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he promoted to daiotsujo (the fifteenth grade of nineteen grades of cap rank, which corresponds to Shohachiinojo and Shohachiinoge, Senior Eighth Rank, Upper and Lower Grades of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code) in 658 (the period of Empress Saimei), established Takakusa County in January 658 after braking 水依評, and passed away on April 21, 658.</e>
<cmt>・高草郡は「たかくさぐん」または「たかくさのこおり」と読むようです。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E9%AB%98%E8%8D%89%E9%83%A1・翻訳者の方はTakakusa countryとされていますが、「郡」なのでTakakusa countyに修正しました。・「正月」は旧暦では一月を示すので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he promoted to daiotsujo (the fifteenth grade of nineteen grades of cap rank, which corresponds to Shohachiinojo and Shohachiinoge, Senior Eighth Rank, Upper and Lower Grades of Taiho Ritsuryo, Taiho Code) in 658 (the period of Empress Saimei), established Takakusa County in January 658 after braking 水依評, and passed away on April 21, 658.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子は、同族の女である伊比頭売（いひづめ）との間に伊福部国足（くにたり）、味野の伊和氏の女、小宮刀自（こみやとじ）との間に伊福部与佐理（よさり）、伊福部与曽布（よそふ）の3子がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had three children, Ifukube no kunitari, the child of Ihizume; the daughter of a member of the same clan, Ifukube no yosari, the child of Komiyatoji; the daughter of a member of the Iwa clan in Ajino, and Ifukube no yosofu.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。味野→定訳不明ですが→Ajinoと訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had three children, Ifukube no kunitari, the child of Ihizume; the daughter of a member of the same clan, Ifukube no yosari, the child of Komiyatoji; the daughter of a member of the Iwa clan in Ajino, and Ifukube no yosofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had three children, Ifukube no kunitari, the child of Ihizume; the daughter of a member of the same clan, Ifukube no yosari, the child of Komiyatoji; the daughter of a member of the Iwa clan in Ajino, and Ifukube no yosofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>国足は法美郡の、与佐理・与曽布の2人は邑美郡の郡領となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunitari became the hereditary district magistrate (the generic name which refers to chief magistrates and assistant magistrates) of Homi country, while Yosari and Yosofu became the hereditary district magistrates of 邑美郡.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。邑美郡→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunitari became the hereditary district magistrate (the generic name which refers to chief magistrates and assistant magistrates) of Homi county, while Yosari and Yosofu became the hereditary district magistrates of Omi county.</e>
<cmt>・邑美郡は「おうみのこおり」または「おうみぐん」と読むようです。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E9%82%91%E7%BE%8E%E9%83%A1・翻訳者の方は countryとされていますが、「郡」なのでcountyに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunitari became the hereditary district magistrate (the generic name which refers to chief magistrates and assistant magistrates) of Homi county, while Yosari and Yosofu became the hereditary district magistrates of Omi county.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、評・郡の設置年については、『国府町誌』が「意図的に吉祥年を選んで立評の年にあてている」と指摘するように検討の余地がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year when 評 and country were established should be reviewed since someone pointed out that &quot;国府町誌&quot; `intentionally selected the lucky year to establish 評.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。、『国府町誌』, 評→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year when hyo (unit of the local administration) and county were established should be reviewed since &quot;Kokufucho shi&quot; indicated that `it was intentionally selected the lucky year to establish hyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>・国府町誌は下記のサイトを参考にすると「こくふちょうし」と読むのではないかと考えられます。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%9B%BD%E5%BA%9C%E7%94%BA_(%E9%B3%A5%E5%8F%96%E7%9C%8C)・評とは、当時の地方行政組織で「ひょう」あるいは「こおり」と読むようです。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E8%A9%95・「意図的に吉祥年を選んで立評の年にあてている」と指摘するの主語は、『国府町誌』と思われたため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year when hyo (unit of the local administration) and county were established should be reviewed since &quot;Kokufucho shi&quot; indicated that &apos;it was intentionally selected the lucky year to establish hyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>高草郡設置に関しても『古志』には「始壊水依評、作高草郡」とあって、水依評がそのまま高草郡になったのか、水依評を法美・邑美の2郡に分け、別に新たに高草郡を設けたのかで説が別れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two theories in terms of the establishment of Takakusa Country; the theory that 水依評 became Takakusa Country, based on &quot;Koshi&quot; which states `始壊水依評、作高草郡,&apos; and another theory that 水依評 was divided into two countries; Homi and 邑美 Takakusa Country was newly established.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。高草郡→定訳不明ですが→Takakusa countryと訳出しています。`始壊水依評、作高草郡,&apos; →意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two theories in terms of the establishment of Takakusa Country; the theory that 水依評 became Takakusa County, based on &quot;Koshi&quot; which states `始壊水依評、作高草郡,&apos; and another theory that 水依評 was divided into two counties, Homi and Omi to establish Takakusa County.</e>
<cmt>・「始壊水依評、作高草郡」とは漢字の意味から推測すると「水依評が崩壊し、高草郡をつくる」というようなことではないかと思います。（定かではないので保留としました）・「郡」に当たる箇所はcountyに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two theories in terms of the establishment of Takakusa Country; the theory that 水依評 became Takakusa County, based on &quot;Koshi&quot; which states &apos;始壊水依評、作高草郡,&apos; and another theory that 水依評 was divided into two counties, Homi and Omi to establish Takakusa County.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>いずれにせよ、もし『古志』に記す高草郡設置が事実であれば、建郡の最古例となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyway, if &quot;the establishment of Takakusa Country&quot;, which was stated in &quot;Koshi,&quot; was true, it would be the oldest example of the establishment of country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anyway, if &quot;the establishment of Takakusa County&quot;, which was stated in &quot;Koshi,&quot; was true, it would be the oldest example of establishing a county.</e>
<cmt>・「郡」に当たる箇所はcountyに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anyway, if &quot;the establishment of Takakusa County,&quot; which was stated in &quot;Koshi,&quot; was true, it would be the oldest example of establishing a county.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 村上太郎左衛門(id:201096), 胡亂堂(id:263343), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>