<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五条頼元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimoto GOJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimoto GOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimoto GOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>五条 頼元（ごじょう　よりもと、正応3年（1290年） - 正平 (日本)22年（1367年）5月）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimoto GOJO (1290 - May 1367) was a Court noble in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimoto GOJO (1290 - May 1367) was a Court noble during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimoto GOJO (1290 - June, 1367) was a Court noble during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>南朝 (日本)の皇子征西将軍懐良親王に付き従い、九州における一時の南朝勢力隆盛を助けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served seisei shogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) Imperial Prince Kanenaga of the Southern Court and helped prosperity of the Southern Court in a period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served the seisei shogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) Imperial Prince Kanenaga of the Southern Court and helped the prosperity of the Southern Court during the period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served the seisei shogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the western barbarians&quot;) Imperial Prince Kanenaga of the Southern Court and helped the prosperity of the Southern Court in Kyushu region during the period.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大外記清原良枝の二男として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the second son of Daigeki (Senior Secretary) 清原良枝.</e>
<cmt>「清原良枝」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the second son of Daigeki (Senior Secretary) 清原良枝.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the second son of Daigeki (Senior secretary of the Council of State) KIYOHARA no Yoshie (清原良枝).</e>
<cmt>推定される読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>自身も事務方の公家として経験を積み、建武の新政にあたっては大外記に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He himself gained experience as a clerical Court noble and was appointed to Daigeki during the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gained experience as a clerical Court noble and was appointed to Daigeki during the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gained experience as a clerical Court noble and was appointed to Daigeki during the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その際に、実務能力を買われたらしく、雑訴決断所、記録所、恩賞方など、新政の主要な機関の職員を歴任し、勘解由使にまで進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, it seems that his clerical ability was evaluated and he successively worked as an official in in major positions of the Restoration including Zasso-Ketsudansho (agency of Kenmu government to file lawsuits), Kirokujo (Land Record Office), and Onshokata (office to do desk works of Onsho award) and was finally promoted to Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, it seems that his clerical ability was evaluated and he successively worked as an official in in major positions of the Restoration including Zasso-Ketsudansho (agency of Kenmu government filing lawsuits), Kirokujo (Land Record Office), and Onshokata (office - desk work for Onsho awards) and was finally promoted to Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, it seems that his clerical ability was evaluated and he successively worked as an official in in major positions of the Restoration including Zasso-Ketsudansho (agency of Kenmu government filing lawsuits), Kirokujo (Land Record Office), and Onshokata (office - desk work for Onsho awards) and was finally promoted to Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners).</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>建武 (日本)3年（1336年）に新政が終止符を打たれると、そのまま北朝 (日本)の光厳天皇方にとどまり、文殿の職員となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Restoration finished in 1336, he remained in the side of Emperor Kogen in the Northern Court and became an worker of Fumidono (the retired emperor&apos;s Documents Bureau).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Restoration ended in 1336, he remained on the side of Emperor Kogen in the Northern Court and became a worker at the Fumidono (the retired emperor&apos;s Documents Bureau).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Restoration ended in 1336, he remained on the side of Emperor Kogen in the Northern Court and became a worker at the Fumidono (the retired emperor&apos;s Documents Bureau).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、建武5年（1338年）9月には、懐良親王に少納言の官位で随行して吉野を発している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1338, however, he accompanied Imperial Prince Kanenaga as shonagon (Lesser counselor) and left Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1338, however, he accompanied Imperial Prince Kanenaga as shonagon (Lesser counselor) and left Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1338, however, he accompanied Imperial Prince Kanenaga as Shonagon (lesser councilor of state) and left Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この間に南朝方に転向したと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that he went over to the Southern Court side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that he went over to the Southern Court side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that he went over to the Southern Court side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>懐良親王は当時10歳に満たなかったと思われ、九州およびその途次の瀬戸内の各武士への令旨は、ほとんどが頼元によるものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kanenaga is thought to be under 10 years old then, and most ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses, etc.) to warriors in Kyushu and Setouchi on the way seem to have been issued by Yorimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Kanenaga is thought to have been under 10 years old then, and most ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses, etc.) to warriors in Kyushu and Setouchi on the way seem to have been issued by Yorimoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kanenaga is thought to have been under 10 years old then, and most ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses, etc.) to warriors in Kyushu and Setouchi on the way seem to have been issued by Yorimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、これら武士勢力の懐柔だけでなく、懐良親王の征西将軍宮としての教育なども頼元の監督下で行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well as conciliation of the warriors, education of Imperial Prince Kanenaga as seisei shogun was also done under supervision of Yorimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As well as conciliation of the warriors, education of Imperial Prince Kanenaga as seisei shogun was also done under the supervision of Yorimoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As well as conciliation of the warriors, education of Imperial Prince Kanenaga as seisei shogun was also done under the supervision of Yorimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>他の後醍醐皇子の地方下向には、多くの場合武士や南朝を代表する公家が随行していたにも関わらず、懐良親王の下向では頼元をはじめ、地位の低い実務官僚が随行していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While warriors and powerful Court Nobles of the Southern Court often accompanied Prince Godaigo when he went down to provinces, Imperial Prince Kanenaga was accompanied by low-ranking governmental officials responsible for practical works including Yorimoto when he went down to provinces.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While warriors and powerful Court Nobles of the Southern Court often accompanied Prince Godaigo when he went to the provinces, Imperial Prince Kanenaga was accompanied by low-ranking governmental officials responsible for practical works including Yorimoto when he went to the provinces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While warriors and powerful Court Nobles of the Southern Court often accompanied Prince Godaigo when he went to the provinces, Imperial Prince Kanenaga was accompanied by low-ranking governmental officials responsible for practical works including Yorimoto when he went to the provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その武力動員にはまったく令旨の力に頼るしかなかった中、頼元は興国3年（1342年）の九州上陸以降も精力的に令旨の発給を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As ryoji was the only way of calling out forces, Yorimoto actively continued issuing ryoji after landing Kyushu in 1342.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As ryoji was the only way of calling out forces, Yorimoto actively continued issuing ryoji after landing in Kyushu during 1342.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As ryoji was the only way of calling out forces, Yorimoto actively continued issuing ryoji after landing in Kyushu during 1342.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>すべてが頼元を奉者とするものばかりではないが、今日残っているものだけでも150通を超えるとされる令旨の最多の奉者であり、懐良親王の九州制圧時代を現出した功労者と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimoto was not the dedicant of all of them, but he was the dedicant of the most ryoji, more than 150 that exist today, and it is appropriate to say he was the person of merit who realized the era of Imperial Prince Kanenaga&apos;s capture of Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimoto was not the dedicant of all of them, but he was the dedicant of the most ryoji, more than 150 that exist today, and it is appropriate to say he was a person of merit who realized the era of Imperial Prince Kanenaga&apos;s capture of Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimoto was not the dedicant of all of them, but he was the dedicant of the most ryoji, more than 150 that exist today, and it is appropriate to say he was a person of merit who realized the era of Imperial Prince Kanenaga&apos;s conquering of Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>正平16年（1361年）には懐良親王はついに九州の中心である大宰府に入り、北朝勢力を北九州の一角に押し込め、ほぼ九州を統治下に置くことに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1361, Imperial Prince Kanenaga finally entered Dazaifu, the center of Kyushu, and forced the power of Northern Court in a corner and succeeded to virtually place Kyushu under his rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1361, Imperial Prince Kanenaga finally entered Dazaifu, the center of Kyushu, and forced the power of the Northern Court into a corner and succeeded to virtually place Kyushu under his rule.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1361, Imperial Prince Kanenaga finally entered Dazaifu, the center of Kyushu, and forced the power of the Northern Court into a corner of north Kyushu and succeeded to virtually place Kyushu under his rule.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>結局、頼元の生存中はこの状態が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This status continued while Yorimoto was alive.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This status continued while Yorimoto was alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This status continued while Yorimoto was alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>正平20年（1365年）ごろに引退し、その2年後に死去した時点でも、懐良親王の九州政権は健在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned around 1365 and deceased two years later, at which time Imperial Prince Kanenaga&apos;s Kyushu regime was still in good condition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned around 1365 and died two years later, whle Imperial Prince Kanenaga&apos;s Kyushu regime was still in good condition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned around 1365 and died two years later, while Imperial Prince Kanenaga&apos;s Kyushu regime was still in good condition.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この間、倭寇の取締りを期待する明との間で親密な外交関係を構築し、懐良親王を日本国王と認めさせるに至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, he built a close diplomatic relations with Ming, which expected crackdown of wako (Japanese pirates) and finally made them acknowledge Imperial Prince Kanenaga as the King of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, he built close diplomatic relations with Ming, which expected a crackdown of wako (Japanese pirates) and finally made them acknowledge Imperial Prince Kanenaga as the King of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, he built close diplomatic relations with Ming, which expected a crackdown of wako (Japanese pirates) and finally made them acknowledge Imperial Prince Kanenaga as the King of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 CalendrierChien(id:242664), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>