<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寂源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jakugen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jakugen</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jakugen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寂源（じゃくげん、？－治安 (日本)4年3月2日 (旧暦)（1024年4月12日））は、平安時代中期の天台宗の僧侶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jakugen (Birth Date unknown-April 12, 1024) was the monk of Tendai Sect, who lived during the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jakugen (birth date unknown-April 12, 1024) was a monk of the Tendai Sect, who lived during the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jakugen (year of birth unknown - April 18, 1024) was a monk of the Tendai Sect, who lived during the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストより、year of birth unknown に訂正しました。スペース補足しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗名は源 時叙（みなもと の ときのぶ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His alias was MINAMOTO no Tokinobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His alias was MINAMOTO no Tokinobu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His alias was MINAMOTO no Tokinobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>左大臣源雅信の8男、母は藤原穆子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eighth son of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, who had the title of Sadaijin (Minister of Left) and his mother was FUJIWARA no Bokushi (also pronounced as FUJIWARA no Atsuko).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eighth son of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, who had the title of Sadaijin (Minister of Left) and his mother was FUJIWARA no Bokushi (also pronounced as FUJIWARA no Atsuko).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eighth son of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, who had the title of Sadaijin (Minister of Left) and his mother was FUJIWARA no Bokushi (also pronounced as FUJIWARA no Atsuko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>源倫子（藤原道長正室）は同母姉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His maternal sibling was MINAMOTO no Rinshi (the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His maternal sibling was MINAMOTO no Rinshi (the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His maternal sibling was MINAMOTO no Rinshi (the legal wife of FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>生年は不詳であるが、兄弟の年齢や後述の藤原斉信のエピソードから安和元年（968年）もしくは同2年（969年）と推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His birth year was uncertain but is estimated that he was born in 968 or 969 by comparing the age of his siblings and the incident with FUJIWARA no Tadanobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His birth year was uncertain but is estimated that he was born in 968 or 969 by comparing the age of his siblings and the incident with FUJIWARA no Tadanobu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His birth year was uncertain but is estimated that he was born in 968 or 969 by comparing the age of his siblings and the incident with FUJIWARA no Tadanobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>永観2年（984年）に当時侍従であった時叙が同僚の藤原斉信、蔵人の藤原宣孝とともに賀茂臨時祭への出席をさぼって花山天皇の激怒を買い、年長の宣孝は処分されたものの、時叙と斉信は「年歯太若」であることを理由に両親の前で誡められたことが藤原実資の『小右記』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokinobu was the jiju (a chamberlain) at that time, but did not attend Kamo no rinjisai (Kamo shrine, special festival) along with his coworker FUJIWARA no Tadanobu and FUJIWARA no Nobutaka, who was the Kurodo (Chamberlain), and received the disapproval of Emperor Hanayama, and Tadanobu being the oldest among two was dismissed from the oldest Nobutaka while Tokinobu and Tadanobu were lectured in front of his parents as &apos;年歯太若&apos; as according to &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke.</e>
<cmt>年歯太若[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokinobu was the jiju (a chamberlain) at that time, but did not attend Kamo no rinjisai (Kamo shrine, special festival) along with his coworker FUJIWARA no Tadanobu and FUJIWARA no Nobutaka, who was the Kurodo (Chamberlain), and received the disapproval of Emperor Hanayama, and Tadanobu being the oldest among the two was dismissed from the oldest Nobutaka while Tokinobu and Tadanobu were lectured in front of his parents as &apos;年歯太若&apos; as according to &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke) of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokinobu was the jiju (a chamberlain) at that time, but did not attend Kamo no rinjisai (Kamo shrine, special festival) along with his coworker FUJIWARA no Tadanobu and FUJIWARA no Nobutaka, who was the Kurodo (Chamberlain), and received the disapproval of Emperor Kazan, and Nobutaka being the oldest among the three was dismissed from his post, while Tokinobu and Tadanobu were lectured in front of his parents in consideration of their youth according to &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke).</e>
<cmt>Emperor Kazanに訂正しました。「 of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke」削除しました。Nobutaka being the oldest among the three was dismissed from his post, while Tokinobu and Tadanobu were lectured in front of his parents in consideration of their youth と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>藤原斉信が当時17歳であること、源雅信の子息の初任官がいずれも16歳（大学寮に入って文章生を経た源扶義を除く）であったことから、この頃16・17歳と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu was seventeen years old at that time, and since the son of MINAMOTO no Masanobu was first assigned with the court duty when he was sixteen years old (excluding MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi who became the monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial University) once entering Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system)), it is believed that he was sixteen or seventeen years old at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu was seventeen years old at that time, and since the son of MINAMOTO no Masanobu was first assigned with court duty when he was sixteen years old (excluding MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi who became the monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial University) once entering Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system)), it is believed that he was sixteen or seventeen years old at that time.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu was 17 years old at that time, and since the son of MINAMOTO no Masanobu was first assigned with court duty when he was 16 years old (excluding MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi who became the monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial University) once entering Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system)), it is believed that he was 16 or 17 years old at that time.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同じく『小右記』には翌寛和元年6月22日 (旧暦)に時叙が昇殿を許されたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; he was allowed to undergo Shoden (visit the imperial court) on July 12, 985.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, according to &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; he was allowed to undergo Shoden (visit the imperial court) on July 12, 985.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Shoyuki,&quot; he was allowed to undergo Shoden (visit the Imperial Court) on July 17, 985.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、右近衛少将に任じられた（『尊卑分脈』）が、天延元年（987年）頃、同年に出家した兄の源時通の後を追うかのように出家した（三善為康の『拾遺往生伝』には天元 (日本)年間に19歳で出家と記すが、年齢はともかく年代は誤りである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned later as Ukone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) (&quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy)) but underwent shukke (become the Buddhist monk), following the example of his older brother, MINAMOTO no Tokimichi of the same year (&quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot;(Gleaning passing on to the next life (dying)) of MIYOSHI no Tameyasu stated that he underwent shukke when he was nineteen years old during the Tengen Period (978-983), but while the age seems suitable, time period is wrong).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned later as Ukone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) (&quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy)) but underwent shukke (become the Buddhist monk), following the example of his older brother, MINAMOTO no Tokimichi in the same year (&quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot;(Gleaning passing on to the next life (dying)) of MIYOSHI no Tameyasu stated that he underwent shukke when he was nineteen years old during the Tengen Period (978-983), but while the age seems suitable, the time period is wrong).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned later as Ukone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) (&quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy)) but underwent shukke (become the Buddhist monk), following the example of his older brother, MINAMOTO no Tokimichi in the same year (&quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot;(Gleaning passing on to the next life (dying)) of MIYOSHI no Tameyasu stated that he underwent shukke when he was 19 years old during the Tengen period (978 - 983), but while the age seems suitable, the time period is wrong).</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。period小文字にしました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>動機は不明であるが、当時摂政藤原兼家を牽制しうる政治力を有した左大臣源雅信の子である時叙に将来性に問題があるとは考えにくく、『拾遺往生伝』・『元亨釈書』などが記す厭世観によるものとする可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The motive is uncertain, but it is hard to believe that Tokinobu, who was the son of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, who was Sadaijin, and had the political power which could suppress the Sessho (regent) FUJIWARA no Kaneie at that time, and was probably due to pessimistic view on life as according to &quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot; and &quot;Genko shakusho&quot; (History of Buddhism of the Genko era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The motive is uncertain, but it is hard to believe that Tokinobu, who was the son of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, who was Sadaijin, and had the political power which could suppress the Sessho (regent) FUJIWARA no Kaneie at that time, and was probably due to a pessimistic view on life according to &quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot; and &quot;Genko shakusho&quot; (History of Buddhism of the Genko era).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The motive is uncertain, but it is hard to believe that Tokinobu, who was the son of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, who was Sadaijin, and had the political power which could suppress the Sessho (regent) FUJIWARA no Kaneie at that time, and was probably due to a pessimistic view on life according to &quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot; and &quot;Genko shakusho&quot; (History of Buddhism of the Genko era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>『栄花物語』には相次ぐ息子の出家に憤る雅信の姿が描かれている（『栄花物語』の著者と言われている赤染衛門は寂源と交流があったことが知られている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) depicted Masanobu angered over the consecutive shukke of his sons (Akazome Emon, who was the author of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; supposedly had a relation with Jakugen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) depicted Masanobu angered over the consecutive shukke of his sons (Akazome Emon, who was the author of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; supposedly had a relation with Jakugen).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) depicted Masanobu angered over the consecutive shukke of his sons (Akazome Emon, who was the author of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; supposedly had a relation with Jakugen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>出家後は比叡山に登って覚忍に師事して永祚 (日本)2年6月27日 (旧暦)（990年）に覚忍から両部灌頂を受け、後に皇慶の年長の弟子となって寛弘9年（1012年）3月に胎蔵界・金剛界の灌頂を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He climbed up the Mount Hiei after he underwent shukke and studied under Kakunin and received Ryobu Kanjo (両部灌頂) on July 21, 990 before becoming the elder disciple of Kokei to receive Taizokai (Womb Realm and physical principles) and Vajradhatu kanjo(ceremony to be the successor) in April 1012.</e>
<cmt>両部灌頂→Ryobu Kanjo[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He climbed up Mount Hiei after he underwent shukke and studied under Kakunin and received Ryobu Kanjo (両部灌頂) on July 21, 990 before becoming the elder disciple of Kokei to receive Taizokai (Womb Realm and physical principles) and Vajradhatu kanjo (ceremony to be the successor) in April 1012.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He climbed up Mount Hiei after he underwent shukke and studied under Kakunin and received Ryobu Kanjo a ceremony to confer the rank of Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest)) on July 26, 990 before becoming the elder disciple of Kokei to receive Taizokai (Womb Realm and physical principles) and Vajradhatu kanjo (ceremony to be the successor) in April 1012.</e>
<cmt>両部灌頂→Ryobu kanjo (a ceremony to confer the rank of Ajari (a master in esoteric Buddhism; a high priest)) 用語集より訂正しました。新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>長和2年（1013年）に延暦寺と園城寺の対立を避ける形で大原 (京都市)に移り住み、勝林院を再興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He moved to Ohara, Kyoto City to avoid the conflict between Enryaku-ji Temple and Onjo-ji Temple, and reestablished Shorin-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He moved to Ohara, Kyoto City to avoid the conflict between Enryaku-ji Temple and Onjo-ji Temple, and reestablished Shorin-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He moved to Ohara, Kyoto City to avoid the conflict between Enryaku-ji Temple and Onjo-ji Temple, and reestablished Shorin-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>寂源は大原で浄土信仰・法華信仰の研鑽に励んで様々な苦行を行い、その度に毘沙門天が現れて寂源を守護したと伝えられている（『古今著聞集』・『元亨釈書』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jakugen performed various Kugyo (ascetic) following the Jodo-shinko (the Pure Land faith) and Study, devoted oneself to one&apos;s studies Hokke faith, and bishamonten, Vaisravana (guardian god of Buddhism) is said to have appeared before Jakugen each time to protect him (&quot; &quot;Kokon Chomon ju&quot; (A Collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) and &quot;Genko shakusho&quot; (History of Buddhism of the Genko era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jakugen performed various Kugyo (ascetic) following the Jodo-shinko (the Pure Land faith) and Study, devoted himself to his studies of Hokke faith, and bishamonten, Vaisravana (guardian god of Buddhism) is said to have appeared before Jakugen each time to protect him (&quot;Kokon Chomon ju&quot; (A Collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) and &quot;Genko shakusho&quot; (History of Buddhism of the Genko era).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jakugen performed various Kugyo (ascetic) following the Jodo-shinko (the Pure Land faith) and Study, devoted himself to his studies of Hokke faith, and bishamonten, Vaisravana (guardian god of Buddhism) is said to have appeared before Jakugen each time to protect him (&quot;Kokon Chomon ju&quot; (A Collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) and &quot;Genko shakusho&quot; (History of Buddhism of the Genko era)).</e>
<cmt>)補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、義兄である藤原道長が度々寂源を尋ねて講説を受ほか、赤染衛門ら多くの人々から崇敬を受けて出家前の官名より「大原近衛少将」とも称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His brother-in-law, FUJIWARA no Michinaga occasionally visited Jakugen to hear his lecture as well as being respected by Akazome Emon and many that he was called as &apos;Ohara Konoe no shosho&apos; (Minor Captain of the Palace Guards from Ohara) from the court rank he had before he underwent shukke.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His brother-in-law, FUJIWARA no Michinaga occasionally visited Jakugen to hear his lecture as well as being respected by Akazome Emon and many, he was called as &apos;Ohara Konoe no shosho&apos; (Minor Captain of the Palace Guards from Ohara) from the court rank he had before he underwent shukke.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His brother-in-law, FUJIWARA no Michinaga occasionally visited Jakugen to hear his lecture as well as being respected by Akazome Emon and many, he was called as &apos;Ohara Konoe no shosho&apos; (Minor Captain of the Palace Guards from Ohara) from the court rank he had before he underwent shukke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>臨終においては磬を打って合殺し、十念成就の後に往生を遂げた（『拾遺往生伝』）と伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He supposedly hit kin, kei, inverted copper or iron bell shaped like a bowl (sounded when reciting sutras) just before his death and Kassatsu, and passed away after Junen joju (ten invocations bringing about completion) (&quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He supposedly hit kin, kei, inverted copper or iron bell shaped like a bowl (sounded when reciting sutras) just before his death and Kassatsu, and passed away after Junen joju (ten invocations bringing about completion) (&quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot;).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He supposedly hit kin, kei, inverted copper or iron bell shaped like a bowl (sounded when reciting sutras) just before his death and Kassatsu, and passed away after Junen joju (ten invocations bringing about completion) (&quot;Shui Ojo-den&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MCHC(id:208548), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>