<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今村昌平</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shouhei IMAMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shouhei IMAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shohei IMAMURA</e>
<cmt>長音表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>今村 昌平（いまむら しょうへい、1926年9月15日 - 2006年5月30日）は、日本の映画監督、脚本家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shouhei IMAMURA (September 15, 1926-May 30, 2006) was a film director and playwright in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shouhei IMAMURA (September 15, 1926-May 30, 2006) was a Japanese director and playwright.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shohei IMAMURA (September 15, 1926-May 30, 2006) was a Japanese director and playwright.</e>
<cmt>長音表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>株式会社今村プロダクションの代表取締役を務めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as the managing director of IMAMURA Production.</e>
<cmt>今村プロダクション→IMAMURA Production と訳出しています。（定訳不明のため）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as the managing director of IMAMURA Production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as the managing director of IMAMURA Production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>今村半次郎（開業医）の四男として東京で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born the fourth boy of Hanjiro IMAMURA (medical practitioner) in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth son of Hanjiro IMAMURA (a medical practitioner) in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth son of Hanjiro IMAMURA (a medical practitioner) in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>東京高等師範学校附属中学校（現筑波大学附属高等学校）、早稲田大学第一文学部卒業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He graduated from Junior High School attached to Tokyo Higher Normal School (present-day High School attached to Tsukuba University), the First Department of Literature, Waseda University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He graduated from the Junior High School attached to the Tokyo Higher Normal School (present-day High School attached to Tsukuba University), the First Department of Literature, Waseda University.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He graduated from the Junior High School attached to the Tokyo Higher Normal School (present-day High School attached to Tsukuba University), the First Department of Literature, Waseda University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>家族は妻と2男1女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family was a family of five with the wife, two boys, a girl, and himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family included his wife, 2 sons and a daughter.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family included his wife, 2 sons and a daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>長男は脚本家で映画監督の天願大介。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eldest son is Daisuke TENGAN; he was a playwright and film director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His eldest son is Daisuke TENGAN; he was a playwright and film director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His eldest son is Daisuke TENGAN; he was a playwright and film director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>次男は今村プロダクション代表取締役の今村竑介（いまむら ひろすけ、1963年3月22日 -）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second son is Hirosuke IMAMURA (March 22, 1963-); he is the managing director of IMAMURA Production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second son is Hirosuke IMAMURA (March 22, 1963-); he is the managing director of IMAMURA Production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second son is Hirosuke IMAMURA (March 22, 1963 -); he is the managing director of IMAMURA Production.</e>
<cmt>スペースを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>人間の欲望をユーモラスに描いた作品に定評があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His films that describe human desire in a humorous way had an established reputation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His films which describe human desire in a humorous way, had a steady reputation.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His films, which satirize human desires, have earned steady popular and critical acclaim.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ファンの間での愛称はイマヘイ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His nickname named by his fans was Imahei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His nickname from his fans was Imahei.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His nickname among his fans was &quot;Imahei&quot; (a fusion of his first and last names).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>50年余の映画監督人生の中で、20作品を監督している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He directed twenty films in his career over the past 50 years as a film director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He directed twenty films in his career of over 50 years as a film director.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He directed twenty films in his roughly 50-year career as a film director.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>1951年、大学を卒業し、松竹大船撮影所に入社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He graduated from the university and entered Shochiku Ofuna Studios in 1951.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He graduated from university and entered Shochiku Ofuna Studios in 1951.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951, he graduated from university and began working at Shochiku Ofuna Studios.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>初の助監督公募で2000人中8人という難関を突破しての合格だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He acquired the position as an assistant director through the exam that was a difficult obstacle for many, in which only eight out of two thousands people could pass.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He acquired q position as an assistant director, passing an exam that was a difficult obstacle for many, in which only 8 out of 2,000 people could pass.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He secured a position for himself as assitant director by passing an exam so difficult that only 8 out of 2000 applicants managed to pass.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>主に小津安二郎の助監督をつとめ、松竹大船助監督部の幹事にまでなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He mainly served as an assistant director of Yasujiro OZU, and he was even promoted to a board member of Shouchiku Ofuna Assistant Director Department.</e>
<cmt>松竹大船助監督部→Shouchiku Ofuna Assistant Director Department と訳出しました。一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He mainly served as an assistant director of Yasujiro OZU, and he was even promoted to being a board member of Shouchiku Ofuna Assistant Director Department.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked as assitant director mainly to Yasujiro OZU, and even managed to be promoted to board member of the Shochiku Ofuna Assistant Directors Department.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかしながら、収入や仕事で不満を感じ、1954年に日活に移籍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was not happy with his salary and jobs; he transferred to Nikkatsu Corporation in 1954.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was not happy with his salary and work; so he transferred to Nikkatsu Corporation in 1954.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was unsatisfied with his salary and work opportunities, however, so in 1954 he quit and began working for Nikkatsu Corporation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>のちに「松竹では束縛だらけだったが、日活はまったくなかったから驚いた」と松竹と日活のギャップを語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, he mentioned about the difference he found between Shouchiku and Nikkatsu, saying, `A lot of restrictions were placed on me in Shouchiku, while they were not on me in Nikkatsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, he mentioned about the difference he found between Shouchiku and Nikkatsu, saying, &quot;A lot of restrictions were placed on me at Shouchiku, while they were not at Nikkatsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he would discuss the major difference between Shochiku and Nikkatsu: &quot;At Shochiku I was hampered by endless restrictions, so was very surprised to find that Nikkatsu was not like this at all.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>1957年の名作・川島雄三監督『幕末太陽伝』や浦山桐郎監督の『キューポラのある街』の脚本も書いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scenarios written by him include &quot;Bakumatsu Taiyo den: The sun in the end of edo period&quot;; known as a masterpiece in 1957 by the film director Yuzo KAWASHIMA, and &quot;Kyuupora no aru machi: The town which has Kyuupora&quot; by Kirio URAYAMA, film director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scenarios written by him include &quot;Bakumatsu Taiyo den: The sun at the end of edo period&quot;; a masterpiece made in 1957 by the director Yuzo KAWASHIMA, and &quot;Kyuupora no aru machi: The town which has Kyuupora&quot; by the director Kirio URAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also wrote screenplays to two famous films, that for director Yuzo KAWASHIMA&apos;s 1957 masterpiece &quot;Bakumatsu taiyo den&quot; and that for &quot;Kyupora no aru machi&quot; by Kirio URAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>学生時代からの友人であるフランキー堺や小沢昭一、加藤武と親交が深い事でも知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known for the close relationship with his friends from school; Frankie SAKAI, Shoichi OZAWA, Takeshi KATO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known for his close relationship with his friends from school; Frankie SAKAI, Shoichi OZAWA, and Takeshi KATO.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imamura is also well known for his close relationship with Frankie SAKAI, Shoichi OZAWA, and Takeshi KATO, friends from his school days.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>『神々の深き欲望』の過酷な撮影現場に耐え切れず脱走を試みては連れ戻されたという 嵐寛寿郎のエピソードは有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The episode of Kanjuro ARASHI; he was not able to tolerate the harsh situation of the filming location of `Kamigami no Fukaki Yokubo: Deep desires of Gods&apos; and tried to run away from the filming location, and was brought back, is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The episode of Kanjuro ARASHI, where he was unable to tolerate the harsh situation of the filming location of `Kamigami no Fukaki Yokubo: Deep desires of the gods&apos; and tried to run away from the filming location, but was brought back, is famous.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His incident with Kanjuro ARASHI, who could not bear the harsh circumstances of the filming on location for &quot;Kamigami no Fukaki Yokubo&quot; and tried to run away only to be forced by Imamura to return, is also very well known.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>1961年の『豚と軍艦』、1963年の『にっぽん昆虫記』、1964年の『赤い殺意』などで監督として世間に認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was recognized as a film director through the films including: &quot;Buta to Gunnkan: Pigs and Battleships&quot; in 1961, &quot;Nippon Konchu ki: Record of Japanese Insects&quot; in 1963, &quot;Akai Satsui: Red Intention to Kill&quot; in 1964.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was recognized as a director through films including: &quot;Buta to Gunnkan: Pigs and Battleships&quot; in 1961, &quot;Nippon Konchu ki: Record of Japanese Insects&quot; in 1963, &quot;Akai Satsui: Red Intention to Kill&quot; in 1964.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established his reputation as one of Japan&apos;s premier directors through such films as the 1961 &quot;Buta no Gunkan&quot;, the 1963 &quot;Nippon Konchu ki&quot;, and the 1964 &quot;Akai satsui&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、一時は企画がまったく受け入れられず、胃潰瘍を患い、明日の米にも困るほどの赤貧生活を経験している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his plan was not accepted at all for some time, and he lived in miserable poverty to the extent that he didn&apos;t have rice to eat for tomorrow suffering from gastric ulcer.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his plans were not accepted at all for some time, and he lived in such poverty that he did not have enough rice to eat and also suffered from a gastric ulcer.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet for a period of several years thereafter no one was willing to support his projects; during these lean years he was forced to live in such poverty he never knew where his next meal was coming from, and he also came down with a gastric ulcer.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>1979年、佐木隆三の『復讐するは我にあり』の映画化権を多くのライバルから奪い、公開までこぎつけて見事に復活を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1979, he honorably came back gaining the right to picturize `Fukushu suruha ware ni ari: Revenge is mine&apos; over the competition against many rivals.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1979, he made his comeback gaining the right to make the movie `Fukushu suruha ware ni ari: Revenge is mine&apos; in competition with many rivals.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1979 he staged a brilliant comeback, earning the right to make the film version of Ryuzo SAKI&apos;s &quot;Fukushu suru wa ware ni ari&quot; and beating out many rivals in the process.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、1981年の『ええじゃないか (映画)』の大失敗で一時は「天下の今平も終わったな」と観客を失望させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his subsequent film in 1979 `Ee jya naika: Isn&apos;t this OK?&apos; made the audience disappointed; they said `Shohei&apos;s reputation was over.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his subsequent film in 1979, `Ee ja naika: Isn&apos;t this OK?&apos; made the audience disappointed; they said `Shohei&apos;s career is over.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But his next film, the 1981 flop &quot;E ja nai ka&quot; disappointed moviegoers to such a degree that for a time people began to mutter &quot;The era where Imamura had the whole world at his fingertips is sure over.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし1983年、起死回生の『楢山節考』を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1983, he released &quot;Narayamabushiko: The Ballad of Narayama&quot;aiming to revive his reputation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1983, he released &quot;Narayamabushiko: The Ballad of Narayama&quot;aiming to revive his career.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But then in 1983 he released &quot;Narayamabushiko&quot; in a bid to revive his career.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>本作と『うなぎ (映画)』（1997年）で、日本人では初めてカンヌ国際映画祭で2度グランプリ（現・パルム・ドール）を受賞するという快挙を成し遂げた（他にフランシス・フォード・コッポラ監督など5名がいる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He achieved the brilliant performance winning the Grand prix of the Cannes Film Festival for two films: &quot;Narayamabushiko: The Ballad of Narayama&quot;, &quot;Unagi: Eel (movie)&quot;, which was the first for Japanese film directors (five film directors including Francis Ford Coppola ever won such award twice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He achieved a brilliant performance, winning the Grand prix of the Cannes Film Festival for two films: &quot;Narayamabushiko: The Ballad of Narayama&quot;, &quot;Unagi: Eel (movie)&quot;, which was a first for Japanese directors (only five film directors including Francis Ford Coppola have ever won the award twice).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His efforts were wildly successful, with &quot;Narayamabushiko&quot; and his 1997 &quot;Unagi&quot; both winning the Grand Prix (today&apos;s Palme d&apos; Or) at the Cannes Film Festival, the first time a Japanese director had ever won twice (only five directors, including Francis Ford Coppola, have ever won the top prize twice).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>なお本人は『楢山節考』を出品した際には「カンヌ（映画祭）出品のために作った作品ではない」とカンヌ映画祭を欠席。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He didn&apos;t attend the Cannes Film Festival when &quot;Narayamabushiko: The Ballad of Narayama&quot; was submitted, saying `the film was not produced for the Cannes Film Festival.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He didn&apos;t attend the Cannes Film Festival when &quot;Narayamabushiko: The Ballad of Narayama&quot; was submitted, saying `the film was not produced for the Cannes Film Festival.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was not in attendance at the Cannes Film Festival when &quot;Narayamabushiko&quot; was entered, commenting that &quot;I did not make this film just for the Cannes Film Festival.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>『うなぎ』の時は出席はしているが、作品を発表する前に帰国している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attended the Cannes Film Festival when &quot;Unagi: Eel&quot; was submitted, but he returned to Japan before the film was shown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attended the Cannes Film Festival when &quot;Unagi: Eel&quot; was submitted, but he returned to Japan before the film was shown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attended the Cannes Film Festival when &quot;Unagi&quot; (Eel) was submitted, but he returned to Japan before the film was shown.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>1975年、横浜放送映画専門学院（現・日本映画学校）を開校し、校長をつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1975, he opened Yokohama Broadcast Film Vocational School (present-day Nihon Film School) and served as the principal.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。横浜放送映画専門学院（現・日本映画学校）→Yokohama Broadcast Film Volcational School (present-day Nihon Film School)（データベースに登録がなく、検索しても不明であったため、暫定的に訳出しました）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1975, he opened the Yokohama Broadcast Film Vocational School (present-day Nihon Film School) and served as the principal.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1975, he opened the Yokohama Broadcast Film Vocational School (the present-day Nihon Film School) and served as its principal.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>同校からは三池崇史・細野辰興・金秀吉・佐々部清・本広克行・李相日などの映画監督、鄭義信などの脚本家・芥川賞作家阿部和重、さらに、タレントのウッチャンナンチャン、俳優の長谷川初範、隆大介などの人材を輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Film directors including: Takashi MIIKE, Tatsuoki HOSONO, Sugiru KIM, Kiyoshi SASABE, Katsuyuki MOTOHIRO, Sang Il, LEE, screenwriters including Wishing, CHONG, an Akutagawa Prize-winning writer, Kazushige ABE, Ucchan Nacchan, a talent and actors such as Hatsunori HASEGAWA and Daisuke RYU graduated from the school.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。安部和重→Kazushige ABE（読みかたが検索不明のため暫定的な訳出です）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graduates of the school include directors such as Takashi MIIKE, Tatsuoki HOSONO, Sugiru KIM, Kiyoshi SASABE, Katsuyuki MOTOHIRO, and Sang Il LEE, screenwriters such as Wishing CHONG, an Akutagawa Prize-winning writer, and Kazushige ABE, the entertainers Ucchan Nanchan, and actors such as Hatsunori HASEGAWA and Daisuke RYU.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">School graduates include such directors as Takashi MIIKE, Tatsuoki HOSONO, Sugiru KIM, Kiyoshi SASABE, Katsuyuki MOTOHIRO, and Sang Il LEE, as well as screenwriter Wishing CHONG, Akutagawa Prize-winning author Kazushige ABE, entertainer Utchan Nanchan, and actors Hatsunori HASEGAWA and Daisuke RYU.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>1998年、新潮別冊『コマネチ!』にて北野武と対談。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1998, he had a conversation with Takeshi KITANO in the separate publication of Shinchou &quot;Comaneci !&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1998, he had a conversation with Takeshi KITANO in the supplement of Shinchou titled &quot;Comaneci !&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1998, he had a dialogue with Takeshi KITANO that is included in the Shincho supplement &quot;Komanechi!&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>2006年5月30日午後3時49分、転移性肝腫瘍のため東京都渋谷区の病院で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died of metastatic liver tumor at 3:49 PM on May 30, 2006 at the hospital in Shibuya Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died of a metastatic liver tumor at 3:49 PM on May 30, 2006 at a hospital in Shibuya Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At 3:49 PM on May 30, 2006, he died at a hospital in Shibuya in Tokyo, of a metastatic liver tumor</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>享年79。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 79.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 79.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 79.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>遺作は『110901/セプテンバー11』中の短編。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His last film was the short film of &quot;110901/September 11.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His last film was the short film &quot;110901/September 11.&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His last film was a short entitled &quot;110901/September 11.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>葬儀には、私淑していたマーティン・スコセッシが「彼は私の師でした」と記した弔文を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the funeral, Martin SCORSESE who modeled on him offered him a condolence note which stated `He was my teacher.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the funeral, Martin SCORSESE who waas strongly influenced by him offered a condolence note which stated `He was my teacher.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At his funeral, Martin SCORSESE, who has acknowledge he was heavily influenced by Imamura, offered a condolence message stating that &quot;He was my teacher.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>今村昌平を語る上で、川島雄三、浦山桐郎との日活での3人トリオの時代は無視できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To talk about Shouhei IMAMURA, the period when he worked together with Yuzo KAWASHIMA, Kirio URAYAMA as trio can&apos;t be forgotten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When talking about Shouhei IMAMURA, the period when he worked together with Yuzo KAWASHIMA, Kirio URAYAMA as a trio cannot be forgotten.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whenever one discusses Shohei IMAMURA it is impossible to ignore the vital period in which he worked as part of a trio with Yuzo KAWASHIMA and Kirio URAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="35">
<j>今村が松竹から日活へ移籍した後、川島が同じく日活に移籍、また監督試験で「松竹に落選」した浦山が鈴木清順監督の計らいで日活入所となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After IMAMURA transferred from Shouchiku to Nikkatsu, KAWASHIMA also transferred to Nikkatsu, as well as URAYAMA who `failed the exam for film director of Shouchiku&apos; and then entered Nikkastu through the arrangement of the film director, Seijun SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After IMAMURA transferred from Shouchiku to Nikkatsu, KAWASHIMA also transferred to Nikkatsu, and also URAYAMA who `failed the Shouchiku exam for directors&apos; and then entered Nikkastu through the arrangements of the director, Seijun SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Imamura left Shochiku and began working at Nikkatsu, Kawashima also left Shochiku to work at Nikkatsu, and Urayama--who had failed Shochiku&apos;s exam for directors--managed to enter Nikkatsu through the good offices of film director Seijun SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>このようにして、3人は「戦後日活の代表作品」を生み出すこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, he produced `Representative films of Nikkatsu after the war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, he produced `Representative films of Nikkatsu after the war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brought together in this way, it was these three that went on to create Nikkatsu&apos;s postwar masterpieces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="37">
<j>川島が監督した『洲崎パラダイス・赤信号』で、彼らは「戦後の好景気から疎外された社会の底辺」に蠢く庶民のヴァイタリティーを基本に据えた作風を確立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through &quot;Suzaki paradise aka shingo: Suzaki Paradise Red Traffic Light&quot; directed by KAWASHIMA, the style based on the vitality of common people around `the bottom of the society which was isolated from the blooming economy after the war&apos; was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through &quot;Suzaki paradise aka shingo: Suzaki Paradise Red Traffic Light&quot; directed by KAWASHIMA, the style based on the vitality of common people around `the bottom of the society which was isolated from the booming economy after the war&apos; was established.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in Kawashima&apos;s &quot;Suzaki paradaisu, aka shingo&quot; that the three established their directorial style, which centered on the vitality of ordinary people, the &quot;rock-bottom of society, who did not see any benefits from the postwar economic boom.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="38">
<j>川島は幕末太陽傳での製作にかかる予算配分を巡って日活と対立し、結局日活を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KAWASHIMA conflicted with Nikkatsu over budget allocation for production of Bakumatsu Taiyo den: The sun in the end of edo period, and left Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>幕末太陽傳→幕末太陽伝（セルB 26）と判断し訳出しました。一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KAWASHIMA conflicted with Nikkatsu over the budget allocation for production of &quot;Bakumatsu Taiyo den: The sun at the end of Edo period&quot;, and left Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawashima clashed with Nikkatsu over the budget allocation for &quot;Bakamatsu taiyo den&quot;, and ended up leaving Nikkatsu over the dispute.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>今村は日活に残り、『にっぽん昆虫記』、『赤い殺意』などの製作を行なう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IMAMURA stayed in Nikkatsyu, and produced films including &quot;Nippon Konchu ki: Record of Japanese Insects&quot;, &quot;Akai Satsui: Red Intention to Kill.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IMAMURA stayed at Nikkatsyu, and produced films including &quot;Nippon Konchu ki: Record of Japanese Insects&quot; and &quot;Akai Satsui: Red Intention to Kill.&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imamura, however, remained at Nikkatsu, going on to make several more films including &quot;Nippon konchu ki&quot; and &quot;Akai satsui.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>今村は常に川島を意識して、東北土着の「基層心理」をベースにした作風（本人の言葉で言えば重喜劇）をこのとき確立させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IMAMURA was always aware of KAWASHIMA, and he established his style that was based on `underlying psychology&apos; which was indigenous Tohoku area (heavy comedy according to his words).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。基層心理→underlying phsychorogyと訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IMAMURA was always aware of KAWASHIMA, and he established his style based on `underlying psychology&apos; which was indigenous to the Tohoku area (heavy comedy according to his words).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imamura always showed an awareness of Kawashima&apos;s work, establishing his own style based on the Tohoku region&apos;s &apos;underlying psychology&apos; (which in Imamura&apos;s own words was &quot;heavy comedy&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>のちに今村はこの基層心理を推し進めてドキュメントタッチの作風に変化して行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IMAMURA subsequently developed the underlying psychology into the style with a documentary touch.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IMAMURA subsequently developed the underlying psychology into the style with a documentary-like touch.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imamura subsequently adapted this idea of underlying psychology to create a style with a documentary-like touch.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>主人公は常に庶民であり、有名人の故事来歴的作品は一切取り上げなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main characters of his films are always common people, and he never worked on a celebrity&apos;s origin and history.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main characters of his films are always common people, and he never worked on a film dealing with the origin or history of a celebrity.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main characters of his films are invariably ordinary people; never once did he work on a film that dealt with the origins or history of a famous person.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="43">
<j>彼の師匠川島雄三についての追悼録、『サヨナラだけが人生だ 映画監督川島雄三の生涯』では、川島の生涯を実証的に取り上げ、川島が筋萎縮性側索硬化症に侵されながらそれを一切他言せず、最後まで映画製作の現場に立っていたことを取り上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the memorial record: &quot;The life is to just say goodbye, The life of the film director, Yuzo KAWASHIMA&quot; on his teacher, Yuzo KAWASHIMA, he followed his Teacher&apos;s life in a documentary way; he described on the book that KAWASHIMA kept working at the filming location until his last without telling others anything about Lou Gehrig&apos;s disease he was suffering from.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the memorial record: &quot;Life is to just say goodbye, The life of the film director, Yuzo KAWASHIMA&quot; about his teacher, Yuzo KAWASHIMA, he followed his Teacher&apos;s life in a documentary style; he described in the book that KAWASHIMA kept working at the filming location until the end without telling anyone that he was suffering from Lou Gehrig&apos;s disease.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the memorial record he created about and in memory of his mentor, Yuzo KAWASHIMA, entitled &quot;Sayonara dake ga jinsei da: Eiga kantoku Kawashima Yuzo no shogai&quot; (Life is only a chorus of goodbyes: the life of director Yuzo KAWASHIMA), he chronicled Kawashima&apos;s life using a documentary style; in it, he recounted how Kawashima kept working right on to the end, filming on location without breathing a single word to anyone that he was suffering from Lou Gehrig&apos;s disease.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これ以降、川島ファンが映画通の間で一勢力を築くが、その最初は今村のこの著作であったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ever since then, it has been the fans of KAWASHIMA who formulated a major stream among film lovers; the beginning of the stream was this book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ever since then, it has been the fans of KAWASHIMA who have been a major group among film lovers; the beginning was this book.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since publication, Kawashima fans have become a major force among cinephiles, and it could well be said that Imamura&apos;s book was their impetus.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>世界的な巨匠でありながらも今村の作品には『うなぎ』も含め多くの作品で女優のヌードシーンが登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a great master in the movies; an actress&apos;s nude scene was seen on IMAMURA&apos;S many films including &quot;Unagi: Eel.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a master director, and many of IMAMURA&apos;S films including &quot;Unagi: Eel&quot;, include nude scenes involving actresses.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imamura was a master craftsman with a global outlook, and many of his films, including &quot;Unagi,&quot; feature scenes involving female nudity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また『ええじゃないか (映画)』の女優の放尿シーンは映像倫理審査会の規定に触れるとしてで物議をかもした事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, The scene in which an actress passed water in &quot;Ee jya naika: Isn&apos;t this OK?&quot; caused controversy in that the scene was against the regulations of Film Ethical Review Board.</e>
<cmt>定訳が不明のため下記のとおり暫定的に訳出しています。映像倫理審査会→Film Ethical Review Board</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, the scene in which an actress urinated in &quot;Ee ja naika: Isn&apos;t this OK?&quot; caused controversy as the scene was against the regulations of the Film Ethical Review Board.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the scene in his film &quot;E ja nai ka&quot; where an actress urinates generated considerable controversy, as it was against the regulations of the Film Ethical Review Board.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>受賞歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Award-winning History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awards</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>1963年 ブルーリボン賞 (映画)監督賞・脚本賞『にっぽん昆虫記』（63年映画配収 6位、3億3000万円）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1963, Blue Ribbon Prize for Film director, Screenplay &quot;Nippon Konchu ki: Record of Japanese Insects&quot; (the 6th dividend income in 1963, 330 million yen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1963, he won the Blue Ribbon Prize for Film director and screenplay for &quot;Nippon Konchu ki: Record of Japanese Insects&quot; (with the 6th highest dividend income in 1963, 330 million yen)</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1963, he won the Blue Ribbon Prize for best director and best screenplay for his film &quot;Nippon konchu ki&quot; (which brought in 330 million yen, making it Japan&apos;s sixth-highest grossing film in 1963).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>1979年 ブルーリボン賞監督賞・日本アカデミー賞監督賞・キネマ旬報賞監督賞　『復讐するは我にあり』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1979, Blue Ribbon Prize for director, the Japan Academy Prize, Kinema Junposha Prize for director &quot;Fukushu suruha ware ni ari: Revenge is mine&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1979, he won the Blue Ribbon Prize for director, the Japan Academy Prize, and the Kinema Junposha Prize for director for &quot;Fukushu suruha ware ni ari: Revenge is mine&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1979, he won three directorial prizes, the Blue Ribbon Prize, the Japan Academy Prize, and the Kinema Junpo Prize for his film &quot;Fukushu suru wa ware ni ari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>1989年 日本アカデミー賞監督賞・キネマ旬報賞監督賞・日刊スポーツ映画大賞監督賞　『黒い雨 (映画)』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1989, the Japan Academy Prize for director, Kinema Junposha Prize for director, Nikkan Sports Film Prize for director &quot;Black Rain (film)&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1989, he won the Japan Academy Prize for director, the Kinema Junposha Prize for director, and the Nikkan Sports Film Prize for director for &quot;Black Rain (film)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1989 he again won three directorial prizes, the Japan Academy Prize, the Kinema Junpo Prize, and the Nikkan Sports Film Prize, for his film &quot;Kuroi ame&quot; (Black Rain).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>1997年 日本アカデミー賞監督賞・毎日映画コンクール監督賞　『うなぎ』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1997, the Japan Academy Prize for director, Mainichi Film Contest Prize for director, &quot;Unagi: Eel&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1997, he won the the Japan Academy Prize for director, and the Mainichi Film Contest Prize for director for &quot;Unagi: Eel&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1997, he won directorial prizes from the Japan Academy and the Mainichi Film Contest for his film &quot;Unagi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>死に際して毎日映画コンクール、フランス共和国より芸術文化勲章が贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he passed away, Mainichi Film Contest Prize and Art and Culture Order from France were granted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he passed away, he was awarded the Mainichi Film Contest Prize and the French &apos;Order of Arts and Letters&apos;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he passed away, he was awarded the Mainichi Film Contest Prize and the French &apos;Order of Arts and Letters&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>著作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His books</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Books</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Books</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>映画は狂気の旅である（2004年、日本経済新聞社） ISBN 4-532-16471-0</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Film is a crazy journey (Nikkei Inc., 2004)ISBN 4-532-16471-0</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Film is a crazy journey (Nikkei Inc., 2004)ISBN 4-532-16471-0</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Film is a crazy journey (Nikkei Inc., 2004)ISBN 4-532-16471-0</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>『サヨナラだけが人生だ　映画監督川島雄三の生涯』（ノーベル書房：昭和43年）この川島雄三の追悼録が、今村の著作の中でもっとも有名なものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The life is to just say goodbye, The life of the film director, Yuzo KAWASHIMA&quot; (Novel Shobo in 1968) was the most famous book among his books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Life is to just say goodbye, The life of the film director, Yuzo KAWASHIMA&quot; (Novel Shobo in 1968) was the most famous of his books.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all the books he wrote, the most famous is &quot;Sayonara dake ga jinsei da: Eiga kantoku Kawashima Yuzo no shogai&quot; (&quot;Life is only a chorus of goodbyes: the life of director Yuzo KAWASHIMA,&quot; published by Nobel Shobo in 1968).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 てら1971(id:131768), 仮面ドライバー(id:217314), Suutaroka(id:174573), 0null0(id:582), Joex(id:42285), Eskimbot(id:29676), BLUE MONDAY(id:96831), Akoyano(id:56905), Mercurius(id:57130), Eroica(id:28630), Qazzx(id:8772), TouConsul(id:200717), Oneuchi(id:70845), こうのいち(id:1215), パの字(id:34188), 代言人(id:33675), Azucar(id:20348), Loveless(id:129239), ヴィンセント・ハナ(id:102376), 野良人(id:58574), Kone(id:377), Point136(id:211299), 細野辰興(id:58398), Yas(id:739), Amikake3(id:89826), Mark-zero(id:48822), DirlBot(id:262995), Khhy(id:13490), GENMEI(id:31879), Okc(id:17021), Kzt007(id:25003), Kandy(id:22601), しるふぃ(id:11247), STBot(id:137943), Robotje(id:11192), Tsujigiri(id:30242), VolkovBot(id:105371), Tietew(id:4054), 西村修三(id:39151), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Kuuri(id:38498), 桃の木(id:90241), Alexbot(id:157199), NDR(id:5500), NIKE(id:16342), Louperibot(id:128971), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>