<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>花山院通定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michisada KAZANIN</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michisada KAZANIN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michisada KAZANIN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>花山院 通定（かざいん みちさだ、生年不詳－応永7年4月14日 (旧暦)（1400年5月8日））は、南北朝時代 (日本)・室町時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michisada KAZANIN (it is not known when he was born - May 8, 1400) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (in Japan) and in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michisada KAZANIN date of birth unknown - May 8, 1400) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (in Japan) and during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michisada KAZANIN (year of birth unknown - May 17, 1400) was a kugyo (court noble) who lived during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (in Japan) and during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>光明天皇（北朝2代）から後小松天皇（100代）にわたって北朝のち統一朝廷に仕え、官位は従一位右大臣まで昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Emperor Komyo (the second emperor in the Northern Court and then Emperor Gokomatsu (the 100th emperor), or the Northern Court and then the unified Imperial Court, and advanced up to Udaijin (minister of the right) at the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Emperor Komyo, the second emperor in the Northern Court and then Emperor Gokomatsu (the 100th emperor), or the Northern Court and then the unified the Imperial Court, and advanced to Udaijin (minister of the right) at the rank of Juichii (Junior 1st Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Emperor Komyo, the second emperor in the Northern Court and then Emperor Gokomatsu (the 100th emperor), or the Northern Court and then the unified the Imperial Court, and advanced to Udaijin (minister of the right) at the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は権大納言花山院兼定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Kanesada KAZANIN, Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Kanesada KAZANIN, Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Kanesada KAZANIN, Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は権大納言九条光経の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Mitsutsune KUJO, Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Mitsutsune KUJO, Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Mitsutsune KUJO, Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>用語統一 (provisional chief councilor of state)前出のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>興国7年/貞治2年（1346年）に叙爵して以降累進し、侍従・左近衛中将を経て、建徳元年/応安3年（1370年）従三位となり、公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Continued being promoted after being ennobled in 1346, he was awarded Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1370, becoming a kugyo, after assuming jiju (a chamberlain) and Sakone no chujo (a middle captain of the left division of inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Continuing to being promoted after being ennobled in 1346, he was awarded Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank) in 1370, becoming a kugyo, after assuming jiju (chamberlain) and Sakone no chujo (middle captain of the left division of inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Continuing to being promoted after being conferred to a peerage in 1346, he was awarded Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1370, becoming a kugyo, after assuming jiju (chamberlain) and Sakone no chujo (middle captain of the left division of inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後も伊予介・権中納言を経て、弘和元年/永徳元年（1381年）権大納言に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Gon Dainagon in 1381, after assuming Iyo no suke (an assistant governor of Iyo Province) and Gon Chunagon (a provisional middle counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Gon Dainagon in 1381, after assuming Iyo no suke (assistant governor of Iyo Province) and Gon Chunagon (provisional middle counselor).</e>
<cmt>word spacing, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Gon Dainagon in 1381, after assuming Iyo no suke (assistant governor of Iyo Province) and Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語統一vice－councilor→vice-councilor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元中7年/明徳元年（1390年）右近衛大将を兼務。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1390, he assumed Ukone no daisho (the major captain of the right division of inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1390, he assumed Ukone no daisho (major captain of the right division of inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1390, he assumed Ukone no daisho (major captain of the right division of inner palace guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>応永元年（1394年）内大臣に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1394, he was appointed to Naidaijin (minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1394, he was appointed to Naidaijin (minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1394, he was appointed to Naidaijin (minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>応永2年（1395年）右近衛大将を辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1395, he resigned from Ukone no daisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1395, he resigned from Ukone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1395, he resigned from Ukone no daisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>右大臣に任じられ、従一位に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) and was promoted to Juichii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) and was promoted to Juichii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Udaijin (minister of the right) and was promoted to Juichii.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後に出家している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>