<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>桐野利秋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiaki KIRINO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshiaki KIRINO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshiaki KIRINO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>桐野 利秋（きりの としあき、天保9年（1838年）12月 - 明治10年（1877年）9月24日）は、江戸時代後期（幕末）の薩摩藩士、明治初期の軍人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiaki KIRINO (December 1838 - September 24, 1877) was a feudal retainer of Satsuma in the late Edo Period and a military man in the early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshiaki KIRINO (December 1838 - September 24, 1877) was a feudal retainer of Satsuma dduring the late Edo Period and a military man during the early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshiaki KIRINO (born in December, 1838; died September 24, 1877) was a feudal retainer of Satsuma domain during the late Edo period and a military man during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は利秋、通称は半次郎、桐野に復姓後は信作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Toshiaki and the common name was Hanjiro, and, after changing back the family name to Kirino, Shinsaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (personal name) was Toshiaki and the common name was Hanjiro, and, after changing back his family name to Kirino, Shinsaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (personal name) was Toshiaki and the common name, Hanjiro, but after changing back his family name to Kirino, Shinsaku.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初め中村半次郎と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, he called himself as Hanjiro NAKAMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning, he called himself Hanjiro NAKAMURA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning, he called himself Hanjiro NAKAMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自・城下士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His status by birth was jokashi (retainer living in castle town).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His status by birth was jokashi (retainer living in a castle town).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His status by birth was a samurai retainer living in a castle town (jokashi).</e>
<cmt>城下士の訳を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>天保9年（1838年）12月、鹿児島郡吉野村字実方で城下士の中村与右衛門（桐野兼秋）の第三子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1838, he was born as the third child of Yoemon NAKAMURA (Kaneaki KIRINO), who was jokashi in Aza Sanekata, Yoshino-mura, Kagoshima County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1838, he was born as the third child of Yoemon NAKAMURA (Kaneaki KIRINO), who was jokashi in Aza Sanekata, Yoshino-mura, Kagoshima County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1838, he was born as the third child of Yoemon NAKAMURA (Kaneaki KIRINO), who was a samurai retainer living in a castle town in Sanekata, Yoshino Village, Kagoshima County.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>5人兄姉弟妹で、上から与左衛門邦秋、姉、半次郎利秋、山内半左衛門重邦（山内家の養子となる。西南戦争に従軍）、妹の順。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had four brothers and sisters and their order was Yozaemaon Kuniaki, elder sister, Hanjiro Toshiaki, Hanzaemon Shigekuni YAMANOUCHI (adopted by the Yamanouchi family; he took part in the Seinan War.) and younger sister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had four brothers and sisters and their order was Yozaemaon Kuniaki, elder sister, Hanjiro Toshiaki, Hanzaemon Shigekuni YAMANOUCHI (adopted by the Yamanouchi family; he took part in the Seinan War.) and a younger sister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had four brothers and sisters, including Yozaemaon Kuniaki, a sister, Hanjiro Toshiaki, Hanzaemon Shigekuni YAMANOUCHI, (who was adopted by the Yamanouchi family and took part in the Seinan War), and a younger sister in order of age.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>別府晋介は母方の従弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsuke BEPPU was a cousin on the maternal side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsuke BEPPU was a cousin on the maternal side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsuke BEPPU was a cousin on the maternal side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>家系は坂上苅田麻呂（坂上田村麻呂の父）に起こると称し、安土桃山時代、島津義久の家老平田増宗を暗殺した押川強兵衛の道案内をした桐野九郎左衛門尉の末裔という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They said that the family line began from SAKANOUE no Karitamaro (father of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro) and they were descendants of Kurozaemonnojo KIRINO, who led the way for Tsuyobei OSHIKAWA who assissinated Masumune HIRATA, who was karo (chief retainer) of Yoshihisa SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>「押川強兵衛」の読みが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They said the family line began from SAKANOUE no Karitamaro (father of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro) and they were descendants of Kurozaemonnojo KIRINO, who led the way for Tsuyobei OSHIKAWA who assissinated Masumune HIRATA, who was karo (chief retainer) of Yoshihisa SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They said the family went to SAKANOUE no Karitamaro (father of SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro) and they were descendants of Kuro KIRINO, the third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guard, who showed the way for Tsuyobei OSHIKAWA, the assassin of Masumune HIRATA, the chief retainer (karo) of Yoshihisa SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>10歳頃、広敷座の下僚であった父が徳之島に流罪に処せられ、家禄5石を召し上げられたのちは兄を助けていたが、18歳のときに兄の病没後は小作や開墾畑で家計を支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was around ten years old, after his father, who was a lower-level retainer of Hiroshikiza (), was exiled to Tokunoshima Island and Karoku (hereditary stipend), 5 koku (approx. 902 liters), was expropriated, he helped his elder brother and, after the elder brother died when Toshiaki was 18 years old, he supported the family through tenant farming and reclaimed farm land.</e>
<cmt>「広敷座」を説明できる情報を得ることができませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was around ten years old, after his father, who was a lower-level retainer of Hiroshikiza (), was exiled to Tokunoshima Island and Karoku (hereditary stipend), five koku (approx. 902 liters), was expropriated, he helped his elder brother and, after the elder brother died when Toshiaki was eighteen years old, he supported the family through tenant farming and reclaimed farm land.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father, who was a lower-rank official of the inner palace (ooku) guard (hiroshikiza), was exiled to Tokunoshima Island and expropriated his hereditary stipend of five koku (approx. 902 liters) when he was around ten years old, he helped the elder brother, but after the death of the elder brother when he was eighteen years old, he supported the family through tenant farming and land reclamation.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>二才（にせ＝若者。15歳頃から24歳頃）時代に石見半兵衛に決闘を申し込まれ、それを論難して以来、石見が属する上之園方限（ほうぎり）の郷中の士と親交を結んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was nise (youngster of the age of 15 to 24), he was challenged to fight a duel by Hanbei IWAMI and, after he refuted Hanbei, he became good friends with members of goju (Satsuma&apos;s educational organization) of Uenosono-hogiri to which Iwami belonged.</e>
<cmt>「論難」は「論破」の誤りと考えられるため、そのように訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was nise (youngster of the age of fifteen to twenty-four), he was challenged to fight a duel by Hanbei IWAMI and, after he refuted Hanbei, he became good friends with members of goju (Satsuma&apos;s educational organization) of Uenosono-hogiri to which Iwami belonged.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was greenhorn, he was challenged to a duel by Hanbei IWAMI, and after he refuted Hanbei, he became good friends with residents of the Ueno residential district of samurai to which Iwami belonged.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>因みに、この郷中には、寺田屋事件の鎮撫使となった奈良原繁や抵抗して死んだ弟子丸龍助など、精忠派の士が多くいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, many members of Seichuha group including Shigeru NARAHARA, who acted as chinbushi (envoy to calm down) in the Teradaya Incident and Ryusuke DESHIMARU, who died resisting in the Incident, belonged to this goju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, many members of Seichuha group including Shigeru NARAHARA, who acted as chinbushi (envoy to calm down) in the Teradaya Incident and Ryusuke DESHIMARU, who died resisting in the Incident, belonged to this goju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the connection to the Ueno district, many members of Seichuha (a loyalist clique) including Shigeru NARAHARA, who acted as a peacemaker in the Teradaya Incident, and Ryusuke DESHIMARU, who died resisting in the Incident, belonged to it.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>幕末</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End of the Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">End of the Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">End of the Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>文久2年（1862年）、島津久光に随って上京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1862, he came up to the capital following Hisamitsu SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1862, he came up to the capital following Hisamitsu SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1862, he came up to the capital following Hisamitsu SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>尹宮（朝彦親王）附きの守衛列藩を務めるなど諸国の志士たちと交際し、家老・小松帯刀ら藩の重臣から重用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While working as a guard for Innomiya (Imperial Prince Asahiko), he had intercourse with patriots from various districts and he got gradually to be treated preferentially by senior vassals including Tatewaki KOMATSU, who was karo (chief retainer).</e>
<cmt>「守衛列藩」の意味が確認できておりません。訳文のように解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While working as a guard for Innomiya (Imperial Prince Asahiko), he had intercourse with patriots from various districts and was gradually treated preferentially by senior vassals including Tatewaki KOMATSU, who was karo (chief retainer).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While working as a guard for Innomiya (Imperial Prince Asahiko), he knew patriots from various provinces and came to be entrusted by senior vassals, such as Tatewaki KOMATSU, a chief retainer (karo).</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>元治元年（1864年）4月16日、土佐の山本頼蔵の『洛陽日記』に「当日石清（中岡慎太郎の変名、石川清之助の略）、薩ノ肝付十郎、中村半二郎ニ逢テ問答ノヨシ。此両人ハ随分正義ノ趣ナリ」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 21, 1864, &quot;Rakuyo Nikki (literally, diary in Kyoto)&quot; by Yorizo YAMAMOTO for Tosa recorded, &quot;I heard that, today, Ishisei (abbreviation of Seinosuke ISHIKAWA, an alias of Shintaro NAKAOKA) met and discussed with Juro KIMOTSUKI and Hanjiro NAKAMURA of Satsuma. Both of them were said to be righteous persons.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置。三つの原文を一緒にして、再度、三つに分割しました。「山本頼蔵」の読みが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 21, 1864, &quot;Rakuyo Nikki (literally, diary in Kyoto)&quot; by Yorizo YAMAMOTO for Tosa recorded, &quot;I heard that, today, Ishisei (abbreviation of Seinosuke ISHIKAWA, an alias of Shintaro NAKAOKA) met and had a discussion with Juro KIMOTSUKI and Hanjiro NAKAMURA of Satsuma. Both of them were said to be righteous persons.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 16, 1864, &quot;Rakuyo Nikki (literally, Kyoto diary)&quot; by Raizo YAMAMOTO of the Tosa domain recorded, &apos;I heard that today Ishisei (abbreviation of Seinosuke ISHIKAWA, an alias of Shintaro NAKAOKA) met and had a discussion with Juro KIMOTSUKI and Hanjiro NAKAMURA of Satsuma. Both of them were said to be quite righteous.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文末の&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>それを裏付けるように、6月14日、大久保利通宛の西郷隆盛書簡には、「中村半次郎は暴客（尊攘激派）の中へ入って、長州藩邸にも出入りしているので、長州側の事情はよくわかった」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As if to prove it, in a letter dated July 17 by Takamori SAIGO to Toshimichi OKUBO, it is described &quot;Hanjiro NAKAMURA entered into bokyaku (radical Sonno Joi faction) and he visits the residence of Choshu Domain), we could know situations of Choshu very well.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置。三つの原文を一緒にして、再度、三つに分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As if to prove it, in a letter dated July 17 by Takamori SAIGO to Toshimichi OKUBO, it is described &quot;Hanjiro NAKAMURA entered into bokyaku (radical Sonno Joi faction) and he visits the residence of the Choshu Domain), we are able to know the situation of Choshu very well.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As if to prove it, there is a letter dated June 14 from Takamori SAIGO to Toshimichi OKUBO, reading &apos;As Hanjiro NAKAMURA associates with ruffians (radical antiforeign imperialists) and visits the residence of the Choshu domain, we are able to know the situation of Choshu very well.&apos;</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>続けて「本人が長州へ行きたいといっているので、脱藩したことにして探索させたい。本当に脱藩してしまうかもしれないが、帰ってきたら役にたつだろう」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It continued &quot;As he wants to visit Choshu, I would like him to make search pretending to leave the domain without permission. He might really leave the domain, but, if he comes back, he would be of great help for us.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置。三つの原文を一緒にして、再度、三つに分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It continued &quot;As he wants to visit Choshu, I would like him to make a search pretending to leave the domain without permission. He might really leave the domain, but, if he comes back, he would be of great help for us.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It continued, &apos;As he wants to visit Choshu, I would like him to make a search pretending to leave the domain without permission. He might really leave the domain, but, if he comes back, he would be of great help for us.&apos;</e>
<cmt>にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、5日後の西郷書簡には「中村半次郎を長州へ行かせたが、藩境でとめられ入国できなかった」とあって、当時の状況では、京都藩邸はともかく、長州本国へ薩摩藩士が入国することは不可能だったと知れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a letter of Saigo five days later, however, it is recorded &quot;Although let Hanjiro NAKAMURA visit Choshu, but he was stopped at the border of the domain and could not enter,&quot; and we can know that, under the situations at that time, retainers of Satsuma domain could not enter the territory of Choshu domain even if they might be able to go into the residence of the domain in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a letter of Saigo five days later, however, it is recorded &quot;Although allowing Hanjiro NAKAMURA visit Choshu, he was stopped at the border of the domain and could not enter,&quot; and we can know that, under the situation at that time, retainers of Satsuma domain could not enter the territory of Choshu domain even if they might be going into the residence of the domain in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a letter of Saigo five days later, however, it is recorded, &apos;Although I allowed Hanjiro NAKAMURA to visit Choshu, he was stopped at the border of the domain and could not enter,&apos; and we can know that under the situation at that time the retainers of the Satsuma domain could not enter the territory of Choshu domain even if they might be going into the residence of the domain in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このころから、長州寄りの考えを持ち、薩摩と長州の和解を策して動こうとしていたらしいことがうかがえるが、結局、長州は暴発し禁門の変となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although we can gather that, since around this time, he had a though which was close to that of Choshu and he tried reconciliation between Satsuma and Choshu, but finally Choshu went off and Kinmon no Hen (Incident of Hamaguri-gomon) occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although we can gather that, since around this time, he was close to Choshu and he tried reconciliation between Satsuma and Choshu, but finally Choshu went off and the Kinmon no Hen (Incident of Hamaguri-gomon) occurred.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We can guess that since then he had been close to Choshu and tried reconciliation between Satsuma and Choshu, but Choshu went berserk after all to cause the Kinmon Incident.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>禁門の変においては、一薩摩藩兵として、長州勢と戦わざるをえなかったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that he was obliged to fight as a soldier of Satsuma clan with soldiers of Choshu clan in the Kinmon no Hen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that he was obliged to fight as a soldier of the Satsuma clan with soldiers of the Choshu clan in the Kinmon no Hen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that he was obliged to fight as a soldier of the Satsuma clan against the soldiers of the Choshu clan in the Kinmon Incident.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>積極的に戦っていたという話と、極力戦闘を避けて長州人を助けたというような話と、後世、正反対の証言が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remained completely different stories, one is that he fought actively and the other that he tried to avoid fighting and to help people of Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were completely different stories, one that he fought actively and the other that he tried to avoid fighting and to help people of the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were completely different stories, one that he fought actively and the other that he tried to avoid fighting and to help people of the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>この年の11月26日、小松帯刀の大久保利通宛書簡に、「中村半次郎が兵庫入塾を願っているのでかなえてやってくれないか」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tatewaki KOMATSU&apos;s letter to Toshimichi OKUBO dated November 26 of this year, it is wrtten &quot;As Hanjiro NAKAMURA wants to join Hyogo juku (schoold in Hyogo), help him to realize it.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tatewaki KOMATSU&apos;s letter to Toshimichi OKUBO dated November 26 of this year, it is wrtten &quot;As Hanjiro NAKAMURA wants to join Hyogo juku (schoold in Hyogo), help him to realize it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a letter from Tatewaki KOMATSU to Toshimichi OKUBO dated November 26 of this year, reading, &apos;I would like you to help Hanjiro NAKAMURA to be granted admission to the Hyogo school.&quot;</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>つまり神戸海軍操練所に学びたいと希望していたことになるが、翌年には閉鎖となるので、実質、学ぶことができたかどうかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, he wanted to learn in Kobe Naval Training Center, but, because it was closed in the next year, it is not known if he could actually learn there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, he wanted to learn in the Kobe Naval Training Center, but, because it was closed during the next year, it is not known if he could actually learn anything there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, he wanted to learn in the Kobe Naval Training Center, but it was closed the next year, so it is not clear whether he could actually learn anything there.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>天狗党の乱のとき、単身その偵察に赴いたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the occasion of Tenguto no Ran (Rebellion of Tenguto party), reportedly, he went alone for seraching.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the occasion of Tenguto no Ran (Rebellion of Tenguto party), reportedly, he went alone to serach.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Rebellion of Tenguto party he reportedly went scouting alone.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>慶応元年（1865年）3月3日、土佐脱藩の土方久元『回天実記』に「中村半次郎、訪。この人真に正論家。討幕之義を唱る事最烈なり」と見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 29, 1865, Hisamoto HIJIKATA, who left Tosa clan without permission, wrote in &quot;Kaiten Jikki (literally, true record of changing situations),&quot; &quot;Hanjiro NAKAMURA visited me. He has right opinions He insisted on overthrowing shogunate.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 29, 1865, Hisamoto HIJIKATA, who left Tosa clan without permission, wrote in &quot;Kaiten Jikki (literally, true record of changing situations),&quot; &quot;Hanjiro NAKAMURA visited me. He has right opinions He insisted on overthrowing the shogunate.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 29, 1865, Hisamoto HIJIKATA, who left Tosa clan without permission, wrote in &quot;Kaiten Jikki&quot; (literally, true record of changing situations), &apos;Hanjiro NAKAMURA visited me. He has right opinions He insisted on overthrowing the shogunate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;&quot;を&apos;&apos;に代えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>薩長同盟後は、さらに両藩の親和のために活動し、木戸孝允、品川弥二郎などと交際を重ねていたことが、種々の日記、書簡などで確認される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be verified with various diaries and letters that after formation of Satsuma-Choshu alliance, he acted to further advance friendship between them and had close intercourses with Koin KIDO, Yajiro SHINAGAWA and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be verified with various diaries and letters that after the formation of the Satsuma-Choshu alliance, he acted to further advance friendship between them and had close intercourses with Koin KIDO, Yajiro SHINAGAWA and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be verified with various diaries and letters that after the formation of the Satsuma-Choshu alliance, he acted to develop friendship between them further and was on good terms with Takayoshi KIDO, Yajiro SHINAGAWA and so on.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）5月10日には伊集院金次郎とともに馬関から長州藩士山縣狂介・鳥尾小弥太を京都の薩摩屋敷まで護衛した（山縣有朋『葉桜日記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 12, 1867, he escorted, in cooperation with Kinjiro IJUIN, Kyosuke YAMAGATA and Koyata TORIO, who were feudal retainers of the Choshu, from Bakan to the residence of Satsuma clan in Kyoto (Aritomo YAMAGATA &quot;Hazakura Nikki (literally diary of cherry tree in leaf)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 12, 1867, he provided escort, in cooperation with Kinjiro IJUIN, Kyosuke YAMAGATA, and Koyata TORIO, who were feudal retainers of the Choshu, from Bakan to the residence of Satsuma clan in Kyoto (Aritomo YAMAGATA &quot;Hazakura Nikki (literally diary of cherry tree in leaf)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May10, 1867, he escorted Kyosuke YAMAGATA and Koyata TORIO with Kinjiro IJUIN, both from samurai from Choshu, from Shimonoseki to the residence of Satsuma clan in Kyoto (Aritomo YAMAGATA &quot;Hazakura Nikki&quot; [literally, the diary of cherry tree in leaf]).</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>同年秋、ほぼ毎日のように数人で京都見回りをしていたが、9月3日、薩摩藩で陸軍教練をしていた公武合体派の軍学者赤松小三郎と京都市中で遭遇し、幕府の密偵として白昼暗殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In autumn of the same year, he had patrolled Kyoto almost every day in a small group and, on September 30, he encountered Kosaburo AKAMATSU, a scholar of military sciences supporting the idea of uniting the court and the shogunate, who had been engaged in military training for army in Satsuma clan and assassinated him in the daytime as a spy of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In autumn of the same year, he had patrolled Kyoto almost every day in a small group and, on September 30, he encountered Kosaburo AKAMATSU, a scholar of military sciences supporting the idea of uniting the court and the shogunate, who had been engaged in military training for the army in the Satsuma clan and assassinated him in the daytime as a spy of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In autumn of the same year, he had patrolled Kyoto almost every day in a small group, and on September 30, when he encountered Kosaburo AKAMATSU, who was a scholar of military sciences supporting the idea of uniting the court and the shogunate, and engaged in military training for the army in the Satsuma clan, he assassinated him in the daytime as a spy of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>中村には「人斬り半次郎」という（後世の）異名があるが、実際に明らかとなっている暗殺はこの1件だけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakamura had a nickname of &quot;Hitokiri Hanjiro (Hanjiro, the killer)(given later), but only this case was the confirmed actual assassination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakamura had the nickname;&quot;Hitokiri Hanjiro (Hanjiro, the killer) (given later), but only this case was the confirmed actual assassination.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakamura had the nickname (given later), &apos;Hanjiro, the killer,&apos; but only this case was the confirmed actual assassination.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、同年10月に坂本龍馬が暗殺された際には、犯人捜しや海援隊 (浪士結社)・陸援隊との連絡等に奔走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, when Ryoma SAKAMOTO was assassinated in October of the same year, he exert himself in searching for assassins and communication with Kaientai (an association of roshi organized by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) and Rikuentai (an association of roshi organized by Shintaro NAKAOKA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, when Ryoma SAKAMOTO was assassinated during October of the same year, he exerted himself in searching for assassins and communicated with Kaientai (an association of roshi organized by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) and Rikuentai (an association of roshi organized by Shintaro NAKAOKA).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, when Ryoma SAKAMOTO was assassinated in October of the same year, he exerted himself in searching for assassins and communicating with Kaientai (association of masterless samurai organized by Ryoma), a trading company, and Rikuentai (the anti-shogunate army of masterless samurai organized by Shintaro NAKAOKA).</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>幕末京都時代にもっとも親しかったのは、伏見で戦死した伊集院金二郎、上野で戦死した肝付十郎、そして永山弥一郎だったが、異色の友人として大政奉還建白書に手を入れた中井弘（桜洲）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his stay in Kyoto around the end of Tokugawa shogunate, him most close friends were Kinjiro IJUIN, who died in war at Fushimi, Juro KIMOTSUKI, who died in war in Ueno and Yaichiro NAGAYAMA and he also had a unique friend, Hiroshi (Oshu) NAKAI who made correction to the Petition to transfer the power back to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his stay in Kyoto around the end of the Tokugawa shogunate, most of his close friends were Kinjiro IJUIN, who died in the war at Fushimi, Juro KIMOTSUKI, who died in the war in Ueno and Yaichiro NAGAYAMA, and he also had a unique friend, Hiroshi (Oshu) NAKAI who made a correction to the Petition to transfer power back to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his stay in Kyoto around the end of the Tokugawa shogunate, his closest friends were Kinjiro IJUIN, who died in the war at Fushimi, Juro KIMOTSUKI, who died in the war in Ueno, and Yaichiro NAGAYAMA, as well as Hiroshi (Oshu) NAKAI, a unique personality, who obtain the petition to transfer power back to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>戊辰戦争・大総督府軍監</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boshin War and gunkan (deputy commander) of Daisotokufu (troop organized for defeating Tokugawa shogunate)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boshin War and gunkan (deputy commander) of Daisotokufu (troop organized for defeating Tokugawa shogunate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The deputy commander of the government general (the anti-shogunate army) in the Boshin War</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>戊辰戦争（明治元年、1868年）では、城下一番小隊に属して伏見の戦いで御香宮に戦い、功を以て小隊の小頭見習いを務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Boshin War (1868), he belonged to Joka Ichiban shotai (platoon) and fought in the War of Fushimi at Gokogu and he was appointed to Kogashira minarai (assistant chief) of shotai due to his merits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Boshin War (1868), he belonged to Joka Ichiban shotai (platoon) and fought in the War of Fushimi at Gokogu and he was appointed to Kogashira minarai (assistant chief) of shotai due to his merits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Boshin War (1868), he belonged to the first platoon in the castle town (joka ichiban shotai) and fought in the battle of Fushimi at the headquarters set up in Gokonomiya Shrine, and due to distinguished services he was appointed to assistant chief (kogashira minarai) of the platoon.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>東征大総督府下参謀・西郷隆盛が東海道先鋒隊を率いて先発東上した際、城下一番小隊隊長に抜擢されて静岡・小田原を占領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takamori SAIGO, who was shimo-sambo staff of Tosei-daisotokufu, departed toward the east leading Tokaido vanguard, he was selected as the chief of Joka Ichiban shotai and occupied Shizuoka and Odawara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Takamori SAIGO, who was shimo-sambo staff of Tosei-daisotokufu, departed toward the east leading the Tokaido vanguard, he was selected as the chief of Joka Ichiban shotai and occupied Shizuoka and Odawara.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Takamori SAIGO, the junior staff officer of the government general (the anti-shogunate army), departed toward the east leading the Tokaido vanguard, he was selected for the chief of the first platoon in the castle town (joka ichiban shotai) and occupied Shizuoka and Odawara.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>2月27日、西郷は中村を小田原まで来た輪王寺宮公現法親王のもとに派遣し、西上の事由を尋問して随従してきた諸藩兵を撤退させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 27, Saigo sent Nakamura to Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen who came up to Odawara and asked the reason for coming down to the west and made accompanying soldiers of various domains to retreat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 27, Saigo sent Nakamura to Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen who came up to Odawara and asked the reason for coming down to the west and made accompanying soldiers of various domains retreat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 27, Saigo sent Nakamura to Cloistered Imperial Prince Rinojinomiya Kogen who came up to Odawara and asked the reason for coming down to the west and made accompanying soldiers of various domains retreat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>のち、静岡での西郷と山岡鉄舟の会談を護衛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he acted as a guard for the meeting between Saigo and Tesshu YAMAOKA in Shizuoka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he acted as a guard for the meeting between Saigo and Tesshu YAMAOKA in Shizuoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he acted as a guard for the meeting between Saigo and Tesshu YAMAOKA in Shizuoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>次いで江戸にのぼり、西郷と勝海舟との会談を護衛し、上野の彰義隊との戦いにも西郷指揮のもと黒門口攻撃に参戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he came up to Edo and acted as a guard for the meeting between Saigo and Kaishu KATSU and, with respect to the battle with Shogitai in Ueno, he took part in attack to Kuromonguchi under command of Saigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he went to Edo and acted as a guard for the meeting between Saigo and Kaishu KATSU and, with respect to the battle with Shogitai in Ueno, he took part in the attack on Kuromonguchi under the command of Saigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he went to Edo and acted as a guard for the meeting between Saigo and Kaishu KATSU and, in the battle against Shogitai army (the Brigade of Righteousness) in Ueno, he took part in the attack on the Kuromon gate under the command of Saigo.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この戦いののち、河野四郎左衛門を伴っての湯屋からの帰りに神田三河町で一刀流の剣客鈴木隼人ら3人の刺客に襲われ、1人を斬り撃退したが、左手中指と薬指を失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this battle, he was attacked by three assassins including Hayato SUZUKI, who was, in Kanda Mikawa-cho on his way back from a bathhouse accompanied by Shirozaemon KONO and, although he killed one with his sword and held off other assassins, he lost the middle finger and ring finger of the left hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this battle, he was attacked by three assassins including Hayato SUZUKI, who was, in Kanda Mikawa-cho on his way back from a bathhouse accompanied by Shirozaemon KONO and, although he killed one with his sword and held off the other assassins, he lost the middle and ring finger of the left hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this battle, he was attacked by three assassins including Hayato SUZUKI, an Ittoryu swordmaster, on his way back from a bathhouse at Kanda-mikawa-cho Town, accompanied by Shirozaemon KONO, and lost the middle and ring finger of the left hand, although he killed one with his sword and held off the other assassins.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>この傷を養ったのちの8月21日、西郷の推挙によって大総督府直属の軍監に任じられ、鹿児島・宇都宮の2藩兵を率いて藤原口（日光口）に派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After curing the would, on August 21, he was appointed to gunkan of Daisotokufu by Saigo&apos;s recommendation, and he was dispatched to Fujiwara-guchi (Nikko-guchi leading soldiers of Kagoshima and Utsunomiya clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After curing the would, on August 21, he was appointed to gunkan of Daisotokufu upon Saigo&apos;s recommendation, and he was dispatched to Fujiwara-guchi (Nikko-guchi leading soldiers from the Kagoshima and Utsunomiya clans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After curing the would, on August 21, he was appointed to the deputy commander of the government general (the anti-shogunate army) by Saigo&apos;s recommendation, and dispatched to Fujiwara gate (Nikko gate) leading soldiers from the Kagoshima and Utsunomiya domains.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>9月1日に大内に到着し、会津若松攻略のための軍議を主催し、栃原進撃を部署した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 1, he arrived in Ouchi and held a council of war for attacking Aizu-Wakamatsu and determined to proceed to Tochihara.</e>
<cmt>原文の後半は意味が確認できておらず、訳文のように解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 1, he arrived in Ouchi and held a council of war for attacking Aizu-Wakamatsu and determined to proceed to Tochihara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 1, he arrived in Ouchi and held a meeting for the attack on Aizu-Wakamatsu and thought out a strategy for the attack on Tochihara.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>翌日から4日にかけての関山の戦い、9月5日から8日までの若松南部の戦いを経て若松城近郊へ進出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the battle of Sekiyama from the next day to September 4, and battles in the south of Wakamatsu from September 5 to 8, he proceeded to the neighborhood of Wakamatsu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the battle of Sekiyama from the next day to September 4, and battles in the south of Wakamatsu from September 5 to 8, he proceeded to the neighborhood of Wakamatsu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the battle of Sekiyama from the next day to September 4, and battles in the south of Wakamatsu from September 5 to 8, he proceeded to the neighborhood of Wakamatsu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>9月10日、伊地知正治・板垣退助・山縣有朋らと軍議し、攻城の分担区域を定める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 10, he held a council of war with Masaharu IJICHI, Taisuke ITAGAKI, Aritomo YAMAGATA and so on and determined allocation of responsible areas for attacking the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 10, he held a council of war with Masaharu IJICHI, Taisuke ITAGAKI, Aritomo YAMAGATA and so on and determined the allocation of responsible areas for attacking the castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 10, he discussed with Masaharu IJICHI, Taisuke ITAGAKI, Aritomo YAMAGATA and so on and determined the battle array for attacking the castle.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この際、指揮下の藤原口部隊は城の南西部が割り当てられたが、実際に部隊が攻城戦に参戦したのは9月14日であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, the southeastern part of the castle was allocated to Fujiwaraguchi troop under his command but his troop joined actual battle for attacking the castle was on September 14.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, the southeastern part of the castle was allocated to the Fujiwaraguchi troops under his command, but his troops joined the actual battle for attacking the castle on September 14.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, he was in charge of the southeastern part of the castle around the Fujiwara gate, but his troops joined the actual battle for attacking the castle on September 14.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>9月22日、会津藩降伏後の開城の式では、官軍を代表して城の受け取り役を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 22, on the occasion of ceremony for opening the castle after the Aziza clan had surrendered, he played a role to receive the castle representing the Imperial army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 22, on the occasion of a ceremony for opening the castle after the Aziza clan had surrendered, he played a role to receive the castle representing the Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 22, on the ceremony of the evacuation of the castle after the surrender of the Aziza clan, he played a role to receive the castle representing the Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これら戊辰戦争の功で、のちに賞典禄200石を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For his merits in Boshin War, he received Shotenroku (premium) of 200 koku (55.6 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For his merits in Boshin War, he received Shotenroku (premium) of 200 koku (55.6 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For his merits in Boshin War, he received the reward stipend of 200 koku of rice.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>明治新政府・陸軍少将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New Meiji Government; Army Major General</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New Meiji Government; Army Major General</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major general of the army in the new Meiji government</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>明治2年（1869年）、鹿児島常備隊がつくられとき、第一大隊の隊長となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869, when Kagoshima Jobitai (regular army) was established, he was appointed to the commander of Daiichi Daitai (literally, first battalion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869, when Kagoshima Jobitai (regular army) was established, he was appointed to the commander of Daiichi Daitai (literally, first battalion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869, when the Kagoshima regular army was established, he was appointed to the commander of the first battalion.</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>明治4年（1871年）、廃藩置県に備えて西郷隆盛が兵を率いて上京したとき、大隊を率いて随い、御親兵に編入され、陸軍大佐に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, when Takamori SAIGO went up to Tokyo accompanied by troop to prepare for Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), he followed leading his battalion and incorporated into Goshinpei (army to convoy the Emperor) and he was appointed to Colonel of the Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, when Takamori SAIGO went up to Tokyo accompanied by troop to prepare for Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), he followed leading his battalion and incorporated into Goshinpei (army to convoy the Emperor) and he was appointed to Colonel of the Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, when the army under the command of Takamori SAIGO went up to Tokyo to prepare against contingencies after the enforcement of the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures (haihan chiken), he followed him leading his battalion, and when his battalion was incorporated into the imperial convoy, he was appointed colonel.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>7月、陸軍少将に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, he was promoted to Army Major General.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, he was promoted to Army Major General.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, he was promoted to major general.</e>
<cmt>小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>明治5年（1872年） 4月、鎮西鎮台（熊本鎮台）の司令長官に任命され、熊本に赴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1872, he was appointed to the Commander in chief of Chinzei Chindai (garrison in the Meiji Period)(Kumamoto Chindai) and he moved to Kumamoto to take his new post</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1872, he was appointed as the Commander in chief of Chinzei Chindai (garrison in the Meiji Period) (Kumamoto Chindai) and moved to Kumamoto to take his new post</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1872, he was appointed commander in chief of the Kumamoto garrison (Chinzei Chindai) and moved to Kumamoto to take his new post.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>このときの経験から、11月に徴兵令が発布されたときは批判的であった（桐野は新制の軍隊を「農民兵」と侮蔑したという話が伝わっており、こうした見方が西南戦争の際に油断を生んだのではと見る者もいる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From his experiences on this occasion, he was critical when the Conscription Ordinance was promulgated in November (It is told that Kirino disdained troops under new system as &quot;peasant soldiers&quot; and some say that such way of thinking caused carelessness in the Seinan War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From his experiences, on this occasion, he was criticized when the Conscription Ordinance was promulgated in November (It is told that Kirino disdained troops under the new system as &quot;peasant soldiers&quot; and some say that such a way of thinking caused carelessness in the Seinan War).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From his experiences there, when the conscription ordinance promulgated in November, he looked at it critically, (and it is told that Kirino disdained the army under the new system and called it &apos;peasant soldiers&apos; and some say that such a way of thinking caused carelessness in the Seinan War).</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>同年7月、桐野は北海道に視察に行き（樺山愛輔『父、樺山資紀』）、帰ってきてからは札幌に鎮台を設置する必要を上申した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July of the same year, Kirino made inspection tour to Hokkaido (Aisuke KABAYAMA &quot;Sukenori KABAYAMA, my father&quot;) and, after his return, he submitted his report on the necessity of Chindai in Sapporo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July of the same year, Kirino made inspection tour to Hokkaido (Aisuke KABAYAMA &quot;Sukenori KABAYAMA, my father&quot;) and, after his return, he submitted his report on the necessity of Chindai in Sapporo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July of the same year, Kirino made an inspection of Hokkaido (Aisuke KABAYAMA &quot;Sukenori KABAYAMA, my father&quot;), and on his return he submitted his report on the necessity to establish a garrison in Sapporo.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>これがのちの屯田兵設置の嚆矢となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became a background of establishment of Tondenhei (ex-legionary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became the background for establishing Tondenhei (ex-legionary).</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became the background for establishing the colonial troops(tondenhei).</e>
<cmt>屯田兵の訳を代えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>明治6年（1873年）4月、陸軍裁判所の所長に転任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1873, he was transferred to the chief of rikugun saibansho (court of army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1873, he was transferred to the chief of the rikugun saibansho (court of army).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1873, he was transferred to the chief of the court of the army.</e>
<cmt>音訳を略しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>10月ぼ明治六年の政変（俗にいう征韓論）で西郷隆盛が下野するや、辞表を提出して帰郷した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, when Takamori SAIGO retired to private life because of the political upheaval of the 6th year of Meiji (commonly called Seikanron (debate on subjugation of Korea)), he submitted a letter of resignation and returned to his home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, when Takamori SAIGO retired to private life because of the political upheaval during the sixth year of Meiji (commonly called Seikanron - debate on subjugation of Korea), he submitted a letter of resignation and returned to his home.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, when Takamori SAIGO left the government in the political disturbancere in the sixth year of the Meiji (as is commonly said, the dispute over the subjugation of Korea), he submitted his resignation and returned to his home.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>西南戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seinan War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seinan War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seinan War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>明治6年11月、鹿児島へ帰った桐野は、鹿児島郡吉田郷本城村字宇都谷にある久部山の原野を開墾して日を過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1873, Kirino returned to Kagoshima and spent days by reclaiming wilderness in Mt. Kube-yama located in Aza Utsunoya in Honjo-mura, Yoshida-go, Kagoshima county.</e>
<cmt>「久部山」の読みが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During November 1873, Kirino returned to Kagoshima and spent days reclaiming wilderness in Mt. Kube-yama located in Aza Utsunoya in Honjo-mura, Yoshida-go, Kagoshima county.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1873, Kirino returned to Kagoshima and spent his days reclaiming wilderness in Mt. Kube located in Utsunoya in Honjo Village, Yoshida District, Kagoshima County.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>明治7年（1874年）、辞職軍人有志の発議で鹿児島の青少年の教養のために私学校がつくられたとき、篠原国幹が銃隊学校、村田新八が砲隊学校・賞典学校（幼年学校）を監督し、桐野は翌年つくられた吉野開墾社を指導して、率先して開墾事業に励んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1874, when shigakko (literally, private schools) were established for education of juveniles in Kagoshima by initiative of volunteers of retired military persons, Kunimoto SHINOHARA supervised jutai gakko (literally, school for shooting squad) and Shinpachi MURATA supervised hotai gakko (school for battery) and shoten gakko (school for little boys) and Kirino led Yoshino Kaikonsha (literally, reclaiming company in Yoshino) established next year and took initiative of reclaiming business.</e>
<cmt>「教養」は「教育」の誤りと判断し、そのように訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1874, when shigakko (literally, private schools) were established for the education of juveniles in Kagoshima by the initiative of volunteers of retired military persons, Kunimoto SHINOHARA supervised jutai gakko (literally, school for the shooting squad) and Shinpachi MURATA supervised hotai gakko (school for battery) and shoten gakko (school for little boys) and Kirino led Yoshino Kaikonsha (literally, reclaiming company in Yoshino) established next year and took initiative of reclaiming business.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1874, when Shigakko (literally, private school) was established for the education of youths in Kagoshima on the initiative of interested retired soldiers, Kunimoto SHINOHARA supervised a school for the shooting squad, Shinpachi MURATA, a school for battery and a school for little boys, and Kirino, the Yoshino reclaimation company, which was established the next year, and he took the initiative of reclaimation activity.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>同年の台湾出兵ののち石川県士族石川九郎・中村俊次郎が桐野を訪ね、明治六年政変および台湾出兵の内情について質問したときの応答「桐陰仙譚」が新聞『日本』及び『西南記伝』上巻に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Toin Sentan&quot; which recorded questions and answers when Kuro ISHIKAWA and Shunjiro NAKAMURA, who were shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors) from Ishikawa Prefecture visited Kirino after the Taiwan expedition in the same year, and asked Kirino about inside details of political upheaval of the 6th year of Meiji and the Taiwan expedition is recorded in a newspaper &quot;Nippon&quot; and &quot;Seinan Kiden&quot;, Vol. 1.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Toin Sentan&quot; recorded questions and answers when Kuro ISHIKAWA and Shunjiro NAKAMURA, who were shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors) from Ishikawa Prefecture visited Kirino after the Taiwan expedition in the same year, and asked Kirino about inside details of political upheaval of the sixth year of Meiji and the Taiwan expedition is recorded in a newspaper &quot;Nippon&quot; and &quot;Seinan Kiden,&quot; Vol. 1.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Questions and answers of Kirino about inside details of the political upheaval of the sixth year of Meiji and the Taiwan expedition was recorded by Kuro ISHIKAWA and Shunjiro NAKAMURA, both the samurai class of Ishikawa Prefecture, who visited Kirino after the Taiwan expedition, in the column of &apos;Toin Sentan&apos; (the conversation with Mr. Kirino) in the newspaper &quot;Nippon&quot; and &quot;The Records of Seinan War,&quot; vol. 1.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="56">
<j>明治10年（1877年）、2月6日、火薬庫襲撃事件・中原尚雄の西郷刺殺計画を聞いて開かれた私学校本校での大評議は、桐野主導で議論され、大軍を率いて北上することに決した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 6, 1877, in daihyogi (literally, deliberation in large group) held in the principal campus of shigakko after attack to powder magazine and intrigue to kill Saigo by Hisao NAKAHARA, discussions were carried out under guidance of Kirino and it decided to go to the north accompanied by a large troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 6, 1877, in daihyogi (literally, deliberation in a large group) held in the principal campus of shigakko after an attack on the powder magazine and intrigue to kill Saigo by Hisao NAKAHARA, discussions were carried out under guidance of Kirino and it was decided to go to the north accompanied by a large number of troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 6 in 1877, when a conference was held in the Shigakko main campus to consider taking countermeasures in the attack on the explosives warehouse and the assassination plan of Saigo intrigued by Hisao NAKAHARA, discussions were led by Kirino and it was decided to make the large troops go to the north with them.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>出兵のために池上四郎 (薩摩藩士)が募兵、篠原国幹が部隊編制、村田新八が兵器の調達整理、永山弥一郎が新兵教練、桐野は各種軍備品の収集調達を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For dispatch of troops, Shiro IKEGAMI (feudal retainer of Satsuma) was in charge of recruiting, Kunimoto SHINOHARA organization of troops, Shinpachi MURATA procurement of and arrangement for arms, and Kirino collection and procurement of various armaments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For dispatching troops, Shiro IKEGAMI (feudal retainer of Satsuma) was in charge of recruiting, Kunimoto SHINOHARA organization of troops, Shinpachi MURATA procurement of and arrangement of arms, and Kirino collection and procurement of various armaments.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For dispatching troops, Shiro IKEGAMI (feudal retainer of Satsuma) was in charge of recruiting, Kunimoto SHINOHARA, organization of troops, Shinpachi MURATA, procurement and arrangement of weapons, and Kirino collection and procurement of various armaments.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>2月13日、大隊編制が行われ、一番大隊指揮長に篠原国幹、二番大隊指揮長に村田新八、三番大隊指揮長に永山弥一郎、五番大隊指揮長に池上四郎、六番・七番大隊連合指揮長に別府晋介が選任され、桐野は四番大隊指揮長となり、総司令を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 13, organization of battalion was determined, Kunimoto SHINOHARA was appointed to the commander of Ichiban daitai (first battalion), Shinpachi MURATA the commander of Niban daitai (second battalion), Yaichiro NAGAYAMA the commander of Sanban daitai (third battalion) Shiro IKEGAMI the commander of Goban daitai (fifth battalion), and Shinsuke BEPPU the commander for the united Rokuban daitai (sixth battalion) and Nanaban daitai (seventh battalion), and Kirino was appointed to the commander of Yonban daitai (fourth battalion) and concurrently Commander in General.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 13, the organization of the battalion was determined, Kunimoto SHINOHARA was appointed to the commander of Ichiban daitai (first battalion), Shinpachi MURATA the commander of Niban daitai (second battalion), Yaichiro NAGAYAMA the commander of Sanban daitai (third battalion) Shiro IKEGAMI the commander of Goban daitai (fifth battalion), and Shinsuke BEPPU the commander for the united Rokuban daitai (sixth battalion) and Nanaban daitai (seventh battalion), and Kirino was appointed to the commander of Yonban daitai (fourth battalion) and concurrently General Commander.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 13, the organization of battalions was determined, and Kunimoto SHINOHARA was appointed to the commander of the first battalion, Shinpachi MURATA, the second battalion, Yaichiro NAGAYAMA, the third battalion, Shiro IKEGAMI, the fifth battalion, and Shinsuke BEPPU, the united battalions of the sixth and the seventh, and Kirino, the fourth battalion and concurrently general commander.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="59">
<j>2月20日、先発した別府晋介の部隊が川尻に着し、熊本鎮台偵察隊と衝突し、西南戦争（西南の役）の実戦が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 20, troops of Shinsuke BEPPU, which started earlier, arrived in Kawajiri and encountered the reconnaissance troops of Kumamoto Chindai and actual fight of the Seinan War (Seinan no eki (Satsuma Rebellion)) began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 20, troops of Shinsuke BEPPU, who started earlier, arrived in Kawajiri and encountered the reconnaissance troops of Kumamoto Chindai and the actual fight of the Seinan War (Seinan no eki - Satsuma Rebellion) began.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 20, the advance force of Shinsuke BEPPU arrived in Kawajiri and encountered the scouts of the Kumamoto garrison, when the actual fight of the Seinan War began.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>22日、相次いで到着した薩軍の大隊は熊本鎮台を包囲攻撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 22, battalions of Satsu-gun (Satsuma Army) arrived one after another besieged and attacked Kumamoto Chindai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 22, battalions of Satsu-gun (Satsuma Army) arrived one after another besieged and attacked Kumamoto Chindai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 22, when the battalions of the Satsuma army arrived at the Kumamoto garrison one after another, they besieged and attacked it.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>桐野は池上とともに正面軍を指揮したが、熊本城は堅城ですぐには陥ちなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirino, together with Ikegami, commanded the troops in the front, but, as the Kumamoto-jo Castle was an adamant castle and did not fall in a short time period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirino, together with Ikegami, commanded the troops on the front, but, Kumamoto-jo Castle was an adamant castle and did not fall during a short time period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirino, together with Ikegami, commanded the front troops, but the Kumamoto Castle was sturdy and did not fall at once.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>本営軍議で桐野・篠原らが主張する全軍攻城論と池上四郎・野村忍介・西郷小兵衛らが主張する種々の分進論が折り合わず、軍議が長引いている間に、政府軍の第一旅団（野津鎮雄）・第二旅団（三好重臣）の南下が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While war council took a long time because an opinion to attack the castle with whole troops insisited by Kirino, Shinohara and so on and an opinion to march in separate groups insisted by Shiro IKEGAMI, Ninsuke NOMURA, Kohei SAIGO and so on did not reach an agreement, Daiichi ryodan (the first brigade) (Shizuo NOZU) and Dainiryodann (Shigeomi MIYOSHI) of the government forces started movement to the south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the war council took a long time because the opinion to attack the castle with the total troop force insisited on by Kirino, Shinohara and so on and the opinion to march in separate groups insisted on by Shiro IKEGAMI, Ninsuke NOMURA, Kohei SAIGO and so on did not reach agreement, Daiichi ryodan (the first brigade) (Shizuo NOZU) and Dainiryodann (Shigeomi MIYOSHI) of the government forces started movement to the south.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the war council took a long time because the opinion to attack the castle with the total force insisited on by Kirino, Shinohara and the opinion to march in separate groups insisted on by Shiro IKEGAMI, Oshisuke NOMURA, Kohei SAIGO did not reach agreement, the first brigade (Shizuo NOZU) and the second brigate (Shigeomi MIYOSHI) of the government army started to the south.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>これに対処するために、熊本城攻囲を池上にまかせ、永山に海岸線を抑えさせ、篠原（六箇小隊）が田原に、村田・別府（五箇小隊）が木留に進出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to cope with this, siege of the Kumamoto-jo castle was left to Ikegami, and Nagayama was asked to control the coast line and Shinohara (six platoons) proceeded to Tahara and Murata and Beppu (five platoons) to Kitome.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置; 「田原」の読みが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to cope with this, siege of the Kumamoto-jo castle was left to Ikegami, and Nagayama was asked to control the coast line and Shinohara (six platoons) proceeded to Tahara and Murata and Beppu (five platoons) to Kitome.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to cope with this, siege of the Kumamoto-jo castle was left to Ikegami, Nagayama was to control the coast line, Shinohara (with six platoons) proceeded to Tabaru, and Murata and Beppu (with five platoons) to Kidome.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。田原は「たばる」、木留は「きどめ」です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>桐野は自ら三箇小隊を率いて山鹿に向かい、政府軍を挟撃して高瀬を占領しようとしたが、互いに勝敗あって戦線が膠着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirino led three platoons toward Yamaga and tried to conduct pincer operation against the government forces and occupy Takase, but the front stucked with both parties having win and defeat.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirino led three platoons toward Yamaga and tried to conduct a pincer operation against the government forces and occupy Takase, but the front got stuck with both parties having wins and defeats.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirino led three platoons toward Yamaga and tried to conduct a pincer operation against the government forces and occupy Takase, but the front got stuck with both parties having wins and defeats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="65">
<j>3月20日の田原の戦い、4月8日の安政橋口の戦いで敗れ、4月14日、薩軍（党薩各派を含む）が熊本城の囲みを解いて木山に退却したとき、桐野は殿りとなり二本木で退却軍を指揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Satsugun (including Tosatsukakuha (troops of pro-Satsuma group)) was defeated in the battle of Tahara on March 20 and the battle of Anseihashiguchi, and Satsugun discontinued siege of Kumamoto-jo Castle and retreated to Kiyama, Kirino fight a rearguard action and commanded retreating troops at Nihongi.</e>
<cmt>「田原」の読みが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Satsugun (including Tosatsukakuha - troops of the pro-Satsuma group) was defeated in the battle of Tahara on March 20 and the battle of Anseihashiguchi, and Satsugun discontinued the siege of Kumamoto-jo Castle and retreated to Kiyama, Kirino fiought a rearguard action and commanded the retreating troops at Nihongi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the defeat in the battle of Tabaru on March 20 and the battle of Anseihashiguchi, the Satsuma army (and the pro-Satsuma forces) discontinued the siege of Kumamoto-jo Castle and retreated to Kiyama, when Kirino brought up the rear and commanded the retreating troops at Nihongi.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>4月21日、薩軍は矢部浜町に退却し、西郷・桐野・村田・池上らが軍議して薩隅日の三州盤踞をなし、機を見て攻勢に転ずると方針を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 21, Satsugun retreated to Yabehama-machi and Saigo, Kirino, Murata, Ikegami and so on held a war council and determined their policy to spread over in three Provision of Satsuma, Osumi and Hyuga and change to attacking seeing change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 21, Satsugun retreated to Yabehama-machi and Saigo, Kirino, Murata, Ikegami and so on held a war council and determined their policy to spread over three Provisions of Satsuma, Osumi, and Hyuga and change to attacking seeing the change.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 21, the Satsuma army retreated to Yabehama-machi and Saigo, Kirino, Murata, Ikegami discussed and determined that the Satsuma, Osumi, and Hyuga Provinces should watch and wait for a chance to switch over to the offensive.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>4月27日、人吉まで退却した西郷らに続き、桐野は江代まで退却し、再びここで軍議して諸方面の部署を定め、新たに編制した中隊を各地に派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 27, following Saigo and so on who retreated to Hitoyoshi, Kirino retreated to Ｅshiro and a war council was held here again and posts in various directions were determined and newly organized companies were dispatched to various places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 27, following Saigo and so on who retreated to Hitoyoshi, Kirino retreated to Ｅshiro, and a war council was held here again and posts in various directions were determined and newly organized companies were dispatched to various places.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 27, following Saigo&apos;s retreat to Hitoyoshi, Kirino retreated to Eshiro, where they discussed again to decide the disposition of each troop and dispatched newly organized companies to various places.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>以後しばらく桐野は人吉本営で指揮していたが、戦況が不利と見て、軍を立て直すべく宮崎に赴き、5月28日、宮崎支庁を軍務所と改称して根拠地とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Kirino commanded from the headquarters in Hitoyoshi for a while, but after judging that war situations was deteriorated, he went to Miyazaki to reorganize troops and on May 28, he renamed Miyazaki Shicho to Gunmusho and determined it to be the base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Kirino commanded from the headquarters in Hitoyoshi for a while, but after judging that the war situation was deteriorating, he went to Miyazaki to reorganize the troops and on May 28, he renamed Miyazaki Shicho to Gunmusho and determined it to be the base.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Kirino commanded from the headquarters in Hitoyoshi for a while, but after judging that the war situation was deteriorating, he went to Miyazaki to reorganize the troops and on May 28, he renamed the Miyazaki branch office to the bureau of military affairs as their base.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>人吉陥落が間近に迫ったので、池上に護衛された西郷をここに迎え、本営とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As fall of Hitoyoshi in near future was expected, Saigo guarded by Ikegami was received to this place which were determined to be the headquarters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the fall of Hitoyoshi was expected in near future, Saigo, guarded by Ikegami, was received to this place which were determined to be the headquarters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the fall of Hitoyoshi was close at hand, he invited Saigo, guarded by Ikegami, and set up the headquarters there.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>ここでは桐野の命で軍票（西郷札）がつくられ、逼迫した軍の財政の立て直しが試みられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, military currency (Saigosatsu (bill)) was manufactured by Kirino&apos;s order and improvement of fragile financial condition was tried.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, the military currency (Saigosatsu bill) was manufactured upon Kirino&apos;s order and improvement of fragile financial condition was tried.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, the military currency (Saigo bill) was issued upon Kirino&apos;s order to improve the fragile financial condition of the army.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="71">
<j>6月、桐野は宮崎本営で諸軍を指揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, Kirino commanded various troops from the headquarters in Miyazaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, Kirino commanded various troops from the headquarters in Miyazaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, Kirino commanded various troops from the headquarters in Miyazaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>7月24日に村田指揮部隊が都城で大敗し、7月25日に始まった宮崎の戦いが31日に敗れると、桐野は西郷を追って高鍋に赴いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 24, troops commanded by Murata was bitterly defeated in Miyakonojo and after the battle of Miyazaki which began on July 25 ended on 31 in their defeat, Kirino moved to Takanabe following Saigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 24, troops commanded by Murata was bitterly defeated in Miyakonojo and after the battle of Miyazaki which began on July 25 ended on 31 in their defeat, Kirino moved to Takanabe following Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 24, troops commanded by Murata was bitterly defeated in Miyakonojo and after the battle of Miyazaki which began on July 25 ended on 31 in their defeat, Kirino moved to Takanabe following Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>8月1日、桐野は佐土原で敗れ、政府軍に宮崎を占領された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1, Kirino was defeated in Sadohara and the government forces occupied Miyazaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, Kirino was defeated at Sadohara and the government forces occupied Miyazaki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 1, Kirino was defeated at Sadohara and the government forces occupied Miyazaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>8月2日には高鍋で敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 2, they were defeated in Takanabe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 2, they were defeated at Takanabe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 2, they were defeated at Takanabe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>8月3日、桐野は平岩、村田は富高新町、池上は延岡にあって諸軍を指揮したが、美々津の戦で敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 3, Kirino commanded troops in Hiraiwa, Murata in Tomitaka-shinmachi and Ikegami in Nobeoka, they were defeated in the battle of Mimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 3, Kirino commanded troops in Hiraiwa, Murata in Tomitaka-shinmachi and Ikegami in Nobeoka, they were defeated in the battle of Mimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 3, Kirino commanded troops in Hiraiwa, Murata in Tomitaka-shinmachi and Ikegami in Nobeoka, but they were defeated in the battle of Mimitsu.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>8月13日、14日、桐野・村田・池上らは長井村から来て延岡進撃を部署し、本道で指揮したが、延岡の戦いで別働第二旅団・第三旅団・第四旅団・新撰旅団・第一旅団に敗北し、延岡を総退却して和田峠に依った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 13 and 14, Kirino, Murata, Ikegami and so on came from Nagai-mura and took up their position for charging forward to Nobeoka and commanded from Hondo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置; 「本道」の読みが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 13 and 14, Kirino, Murata, Ikegami and so on came from Nagai-mura and took up their positions for charging forward to Nobeoka and were commanded from Hondo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 13 and 14, Kirino, Murata, Ikegami advanced from Nagai-mura and commanded the charge against Nobeoka in the main road of Tabaruzaka.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>8月13日、14日、桐野・村田・池上らは長井村から来て延岡進撃を部署し、本道で指揮したが、延岡の戦いで別働第二旅団・第三旅団・第四旅団・新撰旅団・第一旅団に敗北し、延岡を総退却して和田峠に依った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they were defeated in the battle of Nobeoka by Betsudo Daini ryodan (the second stand-alone brigade), Daisan ryodan (the third brigade), Daiyon ryodan (the fourth brigade), Shinsen Ryodan brigade and Daiichi ryodan (the first brigade) and fully retreated from Nobeoka and based at Wadatoge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they were defeated in the battle of Nobeoka by Betsudo Daini ryodan (the second stand-alone brigade), Daisan ryodan (the third brigade), Daiyon ryodan (the fourth brigade), Shinsen Ryodan brigade and Daiichi ryodan (the first brigade) and fully retreated from Nobeoka and were based at Wadatoge.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they were defeated in the battle of Nobeoka by the second stand-alone brigade, the third brigade, the fourth brigade, Shinsen brigade and the first brigade of the government army, and fully retreated from Nobeoka and were based at Wada Pass.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="78">
<j>8月15日、和田峠を中心に布陣し、政府軍と西南の役最後の大戦を試みた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 15, they took up their positions centering on Wada-toge and tried the last mighty battle in Seinannoeki with the government forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 15, they took up their positions centering on Wada-toge and tried the last mighty battle in Seinannoeki with the government forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 15, they took up their positions centering on Wada Pass and tried the last do-or-die battle in Seinan War against the government forces.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>早朝、西郷隆盛自ら桐野・村田・池上・別府らを随えて和田峠頂上で指揮したが、大敗して延岡の回復はならず、長井村へ退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early morning, Takamori SAIGO himself commanded from the top of Wadatoge accompanied by Kirino, Murata, Ikegami, Beppu and so on, but they were bitterly defeated and could not recover Nobeoka and retreated to Nagai-mura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In early morning, Takamori SAIGO himself commanded from the top of Wadatoge accompanied by Kirino, Murata, Ikegami, Beppu and so on, but they were bitterly defeated and could not recover Nobeoka and retreated to Nagai-mura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In early morning, Takamori SAIGO himself commanded from the top of Wada Pass, accompanied by Kirino, Murata, Ikegami, and Beppu, but they were bitterly defeated and could not recover Nobeoka, and retreated to Nagai-mura.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>これを追って政府軍は長井包囲網をつくった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following them, the government forces formed a encirclement around Nagai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following them, the government forces formed a encirclement around Nagai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following them, the government forces formed a encirclement around Nagai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>8月17日夜12時頃、西郷に従い、可愛嶽（えのたけ）を突囲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around twelve o&apos;clock in the night, he run through the siege through Mt. Enotake accompanying Saigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around twelve o&apos;clock at night, he ran through the siege through Mt. Enotake accompanying Saigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around twelve o&apos;clock at night, he ran through the siege through Mt. Enotake accompanying Saigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>突囲軍は精鋭300～500名で、前軍は河野主一郎・辺見十郎太、中軍は桐野・村田新八、後軍は中島健彦・貴島清が率い、池上と別府が約60名を率いて西郷を警護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Troops running through the siege consisted of 300 to 500 elite soldiers and the advanced troops were led by Shuichiro KONO and Jurota HENMI, the middle troops by Kirino and Shinpachi MURATA, and the rear troops by Takehiko NAKAJIMA and Kiyoshi KIJIMA, and Ikegami and Beppu led approx. 60 soldiers to guard Saigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Troops running through the siege consisted of 300 to 500 elite soldiers and the advanced troops were led by Shuichiro KONO and Jurota HENMI, the middle troops by Kirino and Shinpachi MURATA, and the rear troops by Takehiko NAKAJIMA and Kiyoshi KIJIMA, and Ikegami and Beppu led approx. sixty soldiers to guard Saigo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The breakout troop consisted of 300 to 500 elite soldiers, and the advance guard were led by Shuichiro KONO and Jurota HENMI, the middle force by Kirino and Shinpachi MURATA, and the rear guard by Takehiko NAKAJIMA and Kiyoshi KIJIMA, and Ikegami and Beppu led about 60 soldiers to guard Saigo.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>この後、宮崎・鹿児島の山岳部を踏破すること10余日、三田井を経て鹿児島へ帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After travelling on foot mountainous area in Miyazaki and Kagoshima for ten and some days, they returned to Kagoshima through Mitai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After travelling on foot in the mountainous area in Miyazaki and Kagoshima for ten and some days, they returned to Kagoshima through Mitai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After travelling on foot in the mountainous area in Miyazaki and Kagoshima for ten and some days, they returned to Kagoshima through Mitai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="84">
<j>9月1日、突囲した薩軍が鹿児島に入り、城山 (鹿児島市)を占拠した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 1, Satsugun that ran through the siege entered Kagoshima and occupied Shiroyama (Kagoshima City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 1, the Satsugun who ran through the siege entered Kagoshima and occupied Shiroyama (Kagoshima City)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 1, the Satsuma army who succeeded the breakout operation through the siege entered Kagoshima and occupied Shiroyama (Kagoshima City).</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>一時、薩軍は鹿児島城下の大半を制したが、上陸展開した政府軍が9月3日に城下の大半を制し、9月6日には城山包囲態勢を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a while, Satsugun occupied almost whole castle town of Kagoshima, but the government forces that landed and threw out occupied almost whole castle town by September 3 and completed besieging Shiroyama by September 9.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a while, Satsugun occupied almost the whole castle town of Kagoshima, but the government forces landed and occupied almost the whole castle town by September 3 and completed besieging Shiroyama by September 9.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a while, the Satsuma army occupied almost the whole castle town of Kagoshima, but the government forces made a seaborne invasion and occupied almost the whole castle town by September 3 and completed besieging Shiroyama by September 6.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>9月19日、桐野に内緒で山野田一輔・河野主一郎が西郷救命の軍使となって参軍川村純義のもとに出向いたとき、桐野は激怒したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been handed down that Kirino got very angry when Ichisuke YAMANODA and Shuichiro KONO visited Sumiyoshi KAWAMURA, who was sangun (commander), on September 19, as heralds to negotiate to save Saigo&apos;s life without consulting Kirino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been handed down that Kirino got very angry when Ichisuke YAMANODA and Shuichiro KONO visited Sumiyoshi KAWAMURA, who was sangun (commander), on September 19, as heralds to negotiate to save Saigo&apos;s life without consulting Kirino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been handed down that Kirino got very angry when Ippo YAMANODA and Shuichiro KONO visited Sumiyoshi KAWAMURA, the chief of staff, on September 19, as heralds to negotiate to save Saigo&apos;s life without consulting Kirino.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>9月24日、政府軍が城山を総攻撃したとき、西郷隆盛・桐野・桂久武・村田新八・池上四郎・別府晋介・辺見十郎太ら40余名は洞前に整列し、岩崎口に進撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 24, when the government forces mount a full-scale attack to Shiroyama, around 40 persons including Takamori SAIGO, Kirino, Hisatake KATSURA, Shinpachi MURATA, Shiro IKEGAMI, and Shinsuke BEPPU lined up in front of the cave and marched to Iwasakiguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 24, when the government forces mounted a full-scale attack on Shiroyama, around fourty persons including Takamori SAIGO, Kirino, Hisatake KATSURA, Shinpachi MURATA, Shiro IKEGAMI, and Shinsuke BEPPU lined up in front of the cave and marched to Iwasakiguchi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 24, when the government forces made a full-scale attack on Shiroyama, around 40 persons including Takamori SAIGO, Kirino, Hisatake KATSURA, Shinpachi MURATA, Shiro IKEGAMI, Shinsuke BEPPU, and Jurota HENMI lined up in front of the cave and marched to Iwasakiguchi.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>途中で西郷が被弾し、島津応吉久能邸門前にて別府の介錯で自決すると、跪いて西郷の自決を見届けた桐野らはさらに進撃し、岩崎口の一塁に籠もって交戦し、相次いで銃弾に斃れ、刺し違え、或は自刃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Saigo was hit and committed suicide by Beppu&apos;s kaishaku (assisting someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him) in front of the mansion of Okichi Hisayoshi SHIMAZU, Kirino and so on who witnessed Saigo&apos;s suicide getting down on the knees marched further and fought based on a fort in Iwasakiguchi and they were shot down one by one or stabbed each other or fall on their sword.</e>
<cmt>「島津応吉久能」の読みが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Saigo was hit and committed suicide by Beppu&apos;s kaishaku (assisting someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him) in front of the mansion of Okichi Hisayoshi SHIMAZU, Kirino and so on who witnessed Saigo&apos;s suicide on his knees marched further and fought based on a fort in Iwasakiguchi and they were shot down one by one or stabbed each other or fell on their swords.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way there, Saigo was hit and committed suicide with the beheading assistance of Beppu in front of the residence of Okichi Hisayoshi SHIMAZU, which Kirino and others saw through on their knees, and then marching further, they occupied a fort in Iwasakiguchi and fought there, but they were shot down, stabbed or killed themselves one by one.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>このとき桐野は塁に籠もって勇戦し、額を打ち抜かれて戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, Kirino fought bravely staying in the fort and died in war being shot at this forehead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, Kirino fought bravely staying in the fort and died in war being shot in the forehead.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Kirino fought bravely staying in the fort and died in war being shot in the forehead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>享年40。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 40.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of fourty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of fourty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="91">
<j>桐野は明治10年（1877年）2月25日に「行在所達第四号」で官位を褫奪（ちだつ）され、死後、賊軍の将として遇されたが、大正5年（1916年）に正五位を追贈されて名誉回復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirino was deprived of his official rank by Anzaisho Tatsu, dai 4 go (message of provisional palace for Gyoko (Emperor&apos;s outing) No. 4) on February 25, 1877 and, after his death, he was treated as a commander of the rebel army, but, in 1916, he was conferred Senior Fifth Rank posthumously and rehabilitated..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirino was deprived of his official rank by Anzaisho Tatsu, dai four go (message of provisional palace for Gyoko (Emperor&apos;s outing No. 4) on February 25, 1877 and, after his death, he was treated as a commander of the rebel army, but, in 1916, was conferred Senior Fifth Rank posthumously and rehabilitated..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirino was deprived of his official rank by the fourth notice of the temporary imperial abode (angusho tatsu) on February 25, 1877, and treated as a commander of the rebel army after his death, but in 1916 he was conferred the senior fifth rank posthumously and rehabilitated.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="92">
<j>『西南記伝』四番大隊将士伝に桐野利秋を評して「利秋、天資英邁（えいまい）、気宇宏闊（こうかつ）、其人を待つや、憶を開き、胆を露はし、毫も畛域（しんいき）を設けず、然れども志気一発、眉を揚げ気を吐くに当たりては、その概、猛将勇卒と雖ども仰ぎ視ること能はざるものありしと云ふ」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;stories of commanders and soldiers of Yonban Daitai&quot; in &quot;Seinan Kiden,&quot; Toshiaki KIRINO was commented as &quot;Toshiaki had excellent talent and open spirit and 其人を待つや,憶を開き,胆を露はし,毫も畛域(しんいき)を設けず, but when he is motivated and expresses his will, even variant generals or brave soldiers cannot compete.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「其人を待つや、憶を開き、胆を露はし、毫も畛域（しんいき）を設けず」の個所の意味が確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;stories of commanders and soldiers of Yonban Daitai&quot; in &quot;Seinan Kiden,&quot; Toshiaki KIRINO was commented as &quot;Toshiaki had excellent talent and open spirit and 其人を待つや,憶を開き,胆を露はし,毫も畛域(しんいき)を設けず, but when he is motivated and expresses his will, even variant generals or brave soldiers cannot compete.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the stories of commanders and soldiers of the fourth battalion of &quot;The records of Seina War&quot; (Seinan Kiden), Toshiaki KIRINO was commented as &apos;Toshiaki was an gifted and large-minded person. He was so hospitable and talked in a friendly manner and opened his heart to anyone without discrimination, but once he was enthusiastic and asserting his opinion, even variant generals or brave soldiers cannot compete.&apos;</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>西郷隆盛は「彼をして学問の造詣あらしめば、到底吾人の及ぶ所に非ず」と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamori SAIGO commented on him as &quot;If he would have been well-versed in scholarship, we could not compete with him.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamori SAIGO commented about him as &quot;If he would have been well-versed in scholarship, we could not compete with him.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamori SAIGO commented about him as &apos;If he would have acquired an education, we could not compete with him.&apos;</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="94">
<j>桐野は、慶応3年（1867年）の在京中のことを記した『桐野利秋日記』（旧称「京在日記」など日記3篇を含む）を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirino left &quot;Kirino Toshiaki Nikki (diary of Toshiaki KIRINO)&quot;(including three diaries such as &quot;Kyozai Nikki (diary in Kyoto)&quot;(previous name)) in which affairs during his stay in Kyoto in 1867.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirino left &quot;Kirino Toshiaki Nikki (diary of Toshiaki KIRINO)&quot;(including three diaries such as; &quot;Kyozai Nikki - diary in Kyoto&quot;- previous name) in which affairs during his stay in Kyoto in 1867 were recorded.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirino wrote &quot;Diary of Toshiaki KIRINO&quot; (including three diaries such as &apos;Diary in Kyoto&apos; [the former title]) in which affairs during his stay in Kyoto in 1867 were recorded.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>今これを視ると、達筆とは言えないが、雄勁な筆運びで、勇武な気性がよくあらわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We cannot say that it is good handwriting but it is written with pithy brushwork showing his brave spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We cannot say that it was good handwriting, but it is written with pithy brushwork showing his brave spirit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We cannot say that he had good handwriting, but the pithy brushwork showed his brave spirit.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>桐野は禄5石という貧窮の家で育ったが故に農民同様の生活を送り、系統的な学問をせず、剣術も小示現流の伊集院鴨居門下あるいは薬丸自顕流の薬丸兼義（江夏仲左衛門とも）門下というが、多くは独力で修得し、達人の域に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he was brought up in poor family with roku (stipend) 5 koku 902 liters, approx.), he lived same as a farmer and could not learn systematically and, with respect to kenj;utsu (swordplay), although it is said that he learned from Kamoi IJUIN of Kojigenryu or Kaneyoshi YAKUMARU (or Chuzaemon ENATSU) of Yakumaru Jigenryu, he learned mainly by himself and reached the level of master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he was brought up in a poor family with roku (stipend) five koku 902 liters, approx.), he lived the same as a farmer and could not learn systematically and, with respect to kenj;utsu (swordplay), although it is said that he learned from Kamoi IJUIN of Kojigenryu or Kaneyoshi YAKUMARU (or Chuzaemon ENATSU) of Yakumaru Jigenryu, he learned mainly by himself and reached the level of master.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he was brought up in a poor samurai family with a stipend of only five koku and lived the same as a farmer, he could not study systematically, and although he was said to learn swordplay from Kamoi IJUIN of the Kojigenryu school or Kaneyoshi YAKUMARU (or Chuzaemon ENATSU) of the Yakumaru-jigenryu school, he learned it almost by himself and reached the level of master.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>無学文盲というのは誤りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is wrong to say that he was ignorant and illiterate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is wrong to say that he was ignorant and illiterate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is wrong to say that he was ignorant and illiterate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>日記中の記述（上手とは言えないが、和歌さえつくっている）を見る限り、読み書きに充分な教養があったことは確かである（読み書きは主に外祖父別府四郎兵衛から教わった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As far as we judge on descriptions in the diaries (he even made waka, although we cannot say it is a good one), it is sure that he was learned sufficient for reading and writing.. (He learned reading and writing from his maternal grandfather Shirobei BEPPU.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As far as we can judge on descriptions in the diaries (he even created waka, although we cannot say it was a good one), it is sure that he was learned sufficiently for reading and writing.. (He learned reading and writing from his maternal grandfather Shirobei BEPPU.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As far as we can judge on descriptions in the diaries (he even created waka poems, although we cannot say they were good), he was certain to have enough education for reading and writing, (and he learned reading and writing from his maternal grandfather, Shirobei BEPPU).</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>ただ当時の武士の教養であった漢文を正確に読み書きできず、話中の漢語が理解できなかったから、彼らから嫉みも込めて無学と呼ばれたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he could not read and write classical Chinese, which was culture for samurai at that time, correctly and could not understand Chinese words in conversation, it is inferred that he was criticized as ignorant partly because of jealousy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he could not read and write classical Chinese, which was culture for samurai at that time, correctly and could not understand Chinese words in conversation, it is inferred that he was criticized as ignorant partly because of jealousy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed that he was called an ignorant in jealous contempt because he could not read or write classical Chinese correctly, nor understand Chinese words in conversation, which was a general education for the samurai class at that time.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>西郷の評語が「学問あらしめば」ではなく、「学問の造詣あらしめば」となっていることを吟味すべきであろう（この場合の学問は四書五経を意味している。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It should be considered that Saigo&apos;s comment was not &quot;If he had scholarship&quot; but &quot;well-versed in scholorship.&quot; (In this case, &quot;scholarship&quot; means shishogokyo (the Four Books and Five Classics of Confucianism, the Nine Chinese Classics).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be considered that Saigo&apos;s comment was not &quot;If he had scholarship&quot; but &quot;well-versed in scholorship.&quot; (In this case, &quot;scholarship&quot; means shishogokyo (the Four Books and Five Classics of Confucianism, the Nine Chinese Classics).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted that Saigo&apos;s comment was not &apos;if he had a talent for education&apos; but &apos;if he would have acquired an education,&apos; (and in this case &apos;education&apos; means the learning of the Nine Chinese Classics).</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="101">
<j>市来四郎の『丁丑擾乱記』には、「世人、これ（桐野）を武断の人というといえども、その深きを知らざるなり。六年の冬掛冠帰省の後は、居常国事の救うべからざるを憂嘆し、皇威不墜の策を講じ、国民をして文明の域に立たしめんことを主張し、速に立憲の政体に改革し、民権を拡張せんことを希望する最も切なり」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Teigo Joranki&quot; by Shiro ICHIKI describes as &quot;Although people say that he (Kirino) was a militarist, but it is because they do not know his deepness. After he resigned and returned to home in the winter of 1873, he was afraid that affairs of the state cannot be corrected, and insisted to take measures to prevent degradation of authority of the emperor and enlighten citizens and he wished to improve to a constitutional state and expand people&apos;s right.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「丁丑擾乱記」の読みが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Teigo Joranki&quot; by Shiro ICHIKI describes; &quot;Although people say he (Kirino) was a militarist, it is because they do not know his depth. After he resigned and returned home in the winter of 1873, he was afraid that the affairs of state could not be corrected, and insisted taking measures to prevent the degradation of authority of the emperor and enlighten citizens and he wished to improve the constitutional state and expand people&apos;s rights.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;The Record of the Disturbance in 1877&quot; (Teichu Joranki) by Shiro ICHIKI he was described as &apos;Although people say he (Kirino) was a militarist, they do not know his profound idea. After he resigned and returned home in the winter of 1873, he always worried that the affairs of state could not be corrected, thought up measures to prevent the degradation of the imperial authority and insisted that it was necessary to enlighten the people. And most of all, he wished to establish the constitutional state and expand people&apos;s rights.&apos;</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>また同書には、「桐野は廉潔剛胆百折不撓の人というべし。最も慈悲心あり。文識はなはだ乏し。自ら文盲を唱う。しかりといえども実務上すこぶる思慮深遠、有識者に勝れり」ともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had bowels of mercy. Kirino should be called a man of integrity, nerves of steel, toughness and adamancy. His knowledge on books was poor. He called himself illiterate. However, he was vary capable with practical matters and superior to learned persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had bowels of mercy. Kirino should be called a man of integrity, nerves of steel, toughness and adamancy. His knowledge on books was poor. He called himself illiterate. However, he was vary capable with practical matters and superior to learned persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was another description, reading as &apos;Kirino should be called a man of integrity, valiant and fearless with an unyielding spirit. He is the most merciful, but poorly educated and called himself an illiterate. But once he is in duty, he becomes an able commander with prudence, even superior to the learned person.&apos;</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="103">
<j>会津戦争での会津若松城受け取りの時、堂々とした態度で軍監としての作法を勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the occasion of receiving Aizu Wakamatsu-jo Castle in the Aizu War, he performed proper manner for the commander&apos;s attitude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the occasion of receiving Aizu Wakamatsu-jo Castle in the Aizu War, he performed proper manner for a commander&apos;s attitude.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the ceremony of receiving Aizu Wakamatsu-jo Castle in the Aizu War, he performed it in a proper manner as a commander.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>後に「あのような作法をどこで学んだのか」と訪ねられたとき、「愛宕の小屋で忠臣蔵の芝居を見て、赤穂城明け渡しの部分をそっくり真似ただけだ」と答えたという逸話が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an episode that, later when he was asked &quot;Where have you learned such manner?, &quot;he replied &quot;I watched the play of Chushingura in a playhouse in Atago and I just imitated the scene of transferring Ako-jo Castle.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an episode where, later when he was asked &quot;Where have you learned such manners?, &quot;he replied &quot;I watched the play of Chushingura in a playhouse in Atago and I just imitated the scene transferring it to Ako-jo Castle.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an episode that when he was asked later, &apos;Where have you learned such manners?,&apos; he replied, &apos;I watched Chushingura in a theater house in Atago, so I just imitated the scene of the surrender and evacuation of Ako Castle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="105">
<j>後年、勝海舟は「（西郷の）部下にも、桐野とか村田とかいうのは、なかなか俊才であった」（『氷川清話』）、大隈重信は「西南の役に大西郷に次いでの薩摩の驍将桐野利秋、彼はすこぶる才幹の男であったが、これがやはり派手であった。身体も大きくて立派なら容貌態度ともに優れた男であったが、着物をぶざまに着るようなまねはせず、それも汚れ目の見えぬきれいな物づくめであった」（『早稲田清話』）と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later Kaishu KATSU commented, &quot;Among Saigo&apos;s subordinates, Kirino and Murata had exceptional talent.&quot;(Hikawa Seiwa (Quiet talks at the Hikawa mansion)) and Shigenobu OKUMA commented, &quot;Concerning Toshiaki KIRINO who was a formidable leader of Satsuma next to Saigo in the Seinan War, he was a very capable man and he was also gaudy. He had a large and splendid body, and he also had splendid appearance and attitude and he did not wear kimono awkwardly and all of his clothes were very clean without any dirtiness.&quot;(Waseda Seiwa (Quiet talks in Waseda)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later Kaishu KATSU commented, &quot;Among Saigo&apos;s subordinates, Kirino and Murata had exceptional talent.&quot;(Hikawa Seiwa - Quiet talks at the Hikawa mansion) and Shigenobu OKUMA commented, &quot;Concerning Toshiaki KIRINO who was a formidable leader of Satsuma next to Saigo in the Seinan War, he was a very capable man and he was also gaudy. He had a large and splendid body, and he also had splendid appearance and attitude and he did not wear kimono awkwardly and all of his clothes were very clean without any dirtiness.&quot;(Waseda Seiwa - Quiet talks in Waseda).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years Kaishu KATSU commented, &apos;Among Saigo&apos;s men, Kirino and Murata had an exceptional talent&apos; (in &quot;Kaishu&apos;s Talks at the Hikawa Mansion&quot; [Hikawa Seiwa]), while Shigenobu OKUMA talked, &apos;Concerning Toshiaki KIRINO who was a formidable leader of Satsuma next to Saigo in the Seinan War, he was a very capable man and also gaudy. He had a large and splendid body as well as splendid appearance and attitude, and he never wore kimono awkwardly and all of his clothes were very clean without any dirtiness&apos; (&quot;Shibenobu&apos;s Talks in Waseda&quot; [Waseda Seiwa]).</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="106">
<j>なお、西南戦争60年会編『西南役側面史』（1939）に記載する桐野の屍体検査書に「衣服　績縞上着縮緬襦袢。創所　左大腿内面筋骨銃創、右脛骨刀創、左中指旧切痕、下腹部より腰部貫通銃創、前頭より顳顬部貫通銃創、左前頭より傾頂部に刀創、左中指端傷、陰嚢肥腫」とあるので、桐野は西郷と同じくフィラリアを病んでいたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it was recorded in the postmortem certificate for Kirino shown in &quot;Seinaneki Sokumensi (literally, byways of history of the Seinan War)&quot; compiled by Seinan Senso 60 Nen Kai (1939), as &quot;Clothing: Tsumugi shima (striped) outerwear and Crepe juban (undershirts for kimono); wounds: Bullet wound on muscle and bone of the inside of the left thigh, sword wound of the right tibia, old cut of the middle finder on the left hand, a piercing bullet wound from the lower bowel to the waist, piercing bullet would from the forehead to the temple, sword wound from the left forehead to the 傾頂部, wound on the tip of the middle finger of the left hand and hypertrophy in the code, it seems that Kirino had been suffering from filarial infection</e>
<cmt>「傾頂部」の意味、訳語の確認ができておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it was recorded in the postmortem certificate for Kirino shown in &quot;Seinaneki Sokumensi (literally, byways of history of the Seinan War)&quot; compiled by Seinan Senso 60 Nen Kai (1939), as &quot;Clothing: Tsumugi shima (striped) outerwear and Crepe juban (undershirts for kimono); wounds: Bullet wound on muscle and bone of the inside of the left thigh, sword wound of the right tibia, old cut of the middle finder on the left hand, a piercing bullet wound from the lower bowel to the waist, piercing bullet was from the forehead to the temple, sword wound from the left forehead to the 傾頂部, wound on the tip of the middle finger of the left hand and hypertrophy in the code, it seems that Kirino had been suffering from filarial infection</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The postmortem certificate of Kirino in &quot;The Side History of the Seinan War&quot; (Seinaneki Sokumenki) compiled by the-60-Years-Since-Seinan-War Society (1939) recorded as &apos;clothing: striped pongee (tsumugi jima) outerwear and silk crepe undershirts (chirimen juban); wounds: a bullet wound on muscle and bone of the inside of the left thigh, a sword wound of the right tibia, an old cut of the middle finder on the left hand, a piercing bullet wound from the lower bowel to the waist, a piercing bullet from the forehead to the temple, a sword wound from the left forehead to the crown, an wound on the tip of the middle finger of the left hand and scrotum hypertrophy, which suggested that Kirino had been suffering from filarial infection as well as Saigo.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>光明寺跡で裸にされての検屍を樹上から見物していた竹内少年（竹内才次郎『西南役前後の思出の記』）らはこれを目撃したであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Saijiro TAKEUCHI, as a boy (&quot;Memories around the time of Seinan War&quot; by Takeuchi) who was looking on the scene in which the naked body was examined in the ruin of Komyoji, must have seen it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Saijiro TAKEUCHI, as a boy (&quot;Memories around the time of Seinan War&quot; by Takeuchi) who was looking on the scene in which the naked body was examined in the ruins of Komyoji, must have seen it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saijiro TAKEUCHI, as a boy, must have seen it when he was looking down from a tree at the examination of corpses stripped of clothes in the ruins of Komyo-ji Temple (&quot;Memories Before and After the Seinan War&quot; by Saijiro TAKEUCHI).</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="108">
<j>洒落者（しゃれもの）として有名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was famous as a dandy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was famous as a dandy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was famous as a dandy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>陸軍少将時代には金無垢の懐中時計を愛用し、軍服はフランス製のオーダーメイドであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was an Army Major General, he used regularly a pocket watch of solid gold and his military uniform was order made one made in France.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was an Army Major General, he used regularly a pocket watch of solid gold and his military uniform was an order made one, made in France.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was the army major general, he used regularly a pocket watch of solid gold and his military uniform was a made-to-order article made in France.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>軍刀の拵えも純金張の特注品を愛用し、フランス香水を付けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also used regularly custom-made mounting for his sword of pure gold-plated and used French perfume.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also used a regularly custom-made mounting for his sword of pure gold-plated and used French perfume.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sword was mounted of made-to-order parts plated with pure gold, which he treasured, and he used French perfume.</e>
<cmt>左記のとおり変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>城山で戦死した際にも遺体からは香水の香りがしていたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that, when he died in war in Shiroyama, perfume smelled from his body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is told that, when he died in war at Shiroyama, perfume could be smelled from his body.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is told that, when he died in war at Shiroyama, perfume could be smelled from his body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 パイク・ビショップ(id:114349), Tomzo(id:16777), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), Cprobot(id:97843), ロナルド(id:9943), Николай Булганин(id:196360), Hyman-roth0512(id:48989), 味っ子(id:17086), March(id:9468), Iratume(id:110099), 認定者(id:99098), 木村秀海(id:25727), でここ(id:9565), Boa(id:20845), 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), NICE(id:43269), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), Kanetan(id:281040), Maakun(id:16735), Bankokuya(id:91191), M-sho-gun(id:88956), 松茸(id:27535), Tiyoringo(id:70026), M9(^Д^)(id:62174), Petronius(id:41844), Clarin(id:60278), Aboshi(id:9318), Rusk(id:9895), 上田隼人(id:23104), Alexbot(id:157199), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>