<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原兼房 (中宮亮)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanefusa (Chugu no suke, Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kanefusa (Chugu no suke, Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanefusa (Chugu no suke, Assistant Master of the Consort&apos;s Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原兼房 （ふじわら の かねふさ、 長保3年（1001年） - 延久元年6月4日 (旧暦)（1069年6月25日））は平安時代の貴族政治家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanefusa (1001 ~ June 25, 1069) was a court noble statesman of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kanefusa (1001 ~ June 25, 1069) was a court noble statesman of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanefusa (1001 - July 1, 1069) was a court noble statesman of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>(1001 ~ June 25, 1069)(1001 - July 1, 1069) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は中納言藤原兼隆（粟田関白藤原道兼の嫡男）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was a Chunagon (middle counselor), FUJIWARA no Kanetaka (the legitimate son of Awata no Kanpaku, a chief adviser to the Emperor, Fujiwara no Michikane)</e>
<cmt>「粟田関白」の正確な読みが分かりません。左記の様にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was a Chunagon (middle counselor), FUJIWARA no Kanetaka (the legitimate son of Awata no Kanpaku, a chief adviser to the Emperor, Fujiwara no Michikane)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was a Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), FUJIWARA no Kanetaka (the legitimate son of Awata no Kanpaku, a chief adviser to the Emperor, Fujiwara no Michikane)</e>
<cmt>middle counselor をvice-councilor of state に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は源扶義の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正四位下、中宮亮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ranked to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and Chugu no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was held the rank and title of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and Chugu no suke.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was held the rank and title of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and Chugu no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原道長の側近として一定の政治力を持つ父の後を継ぎ、讃岐国守、備中国守、右少将などを歴任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded to his father who had a certain political power as an aide of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and filled successively the posts of Sanuki no kuni no kami (Governor of Sanuki Province), Bicchu no kuni no kami (Governor of Bicchu Province) and Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded his father, who had a certain political power, as an aide of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and successively filled the posts of Sanuki no kuni no kami (Governor of Sanuki Province), Bicchu no kuni no kami (Governor of Bicchu Province) and Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), etc.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded his father, who had a certain political power, as an aide of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and successively filled the posts of Governor of Sanuki Province, Governor of Bicchu Province, and Ushosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), etc.</e>
<cmt>Sanuki no kuni no kami (Governor of Sanuki Province), Bicchu no kuni no kami (Governor of Bicchu Province) をGovernor of Sanuki Province, Governor of Bicchu Province, に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>時として粗暴な振る舞いも多く、寛仁2年（1018年）に藤原定頼を宮中で追いかけまわしたことや、治安 (元号)元年（1021年）に源経定と乱闘したこと、同3年（1023年）に藤原明知に集団で暴行を加えたことなどが記録に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He acted sometimes rudely and there were records that he chased FUJIWARA no Sadayori in the palace in 1018, scuffled with MINAMOTO no Tsunesada in 1021 and did a mob violence on FUJIWARA no Akitomo in 1023.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sometimes acted rudely and there were records that he chased FUJIWARA no Sadayori in the palace in 1018, scuffled with MINAMOTO no Tsunesada in 1021, and incited mob violence on FUJIWARA no Akitomo in 1023.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sometimes acted rudely and there were records that he chased FUJIWARA no Sadayori in the palace in 1018, scuffled with MINAMOTO no Tsunesada in 1021, and incited mob violence on FUJIWARA no Akitomo in 1023.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>こうしたことも影響してか、政治家として多くの人望を集めることはなく、公卿昇任は果たせずに終わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems these behaviors of him might have influenced on his career that he could not gain popularity as a stateman and he was not be promoted to Kugyo (the top court official) in his life time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems these behaviors might have influenced his career such that he could not gain popularity as a stateman and he was not be promoted to Kugyo (top court official) in his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems these behaviors might have influenced his career such that he could not gain popularity as a stateman and he was not be promoted to Kugyo (high court noble) in his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>top court official をhigh court noble に修正しました。出典：http://books.google.com/books?id=ni05jo2PfQEC&amp;pg=PA64&amp;dq=kugyo+high+court+noble&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;hl=ja&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=kugyo%20high%20court%20noble&amp;f=false※top court official は wikipedia 出典の訳と思われます。http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emperor_K%C5%8Dbun</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>その一方、歌人としては名を著し、勅撰集に16首が入首している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meanwhile, he won himself a reputation as a waka poet and 16 of his poems were selected into anthology of poems collected by Imperial command.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meanwhile, he won himself a reputation as a waka poet and 16 of his poems were selected into an anthology of poems collected by Imperial command.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meanwhile, he won himself a reputation as a poet and 16 of his poems were selected into an anthology of poems collected by Imperial command.</e>
<cmt>a waka poet をa poet に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>柿本人麻呂を崇敬するあまり、夢にその姿を見て、それを絵に描かせて秘蔵していたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he adored KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro so much that he saw Hitomaro&apos;s figure in his dream and he had it painted in a picture and stored in secrecy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he adored KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro so much that he saw Hitomaro&apos;s figure in his dream and he had it painted in a picture and stored in secrecy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he adored KAKINOMOTO no Hitomaro so much that he saw Hitomaro&apos;s figure in his dream and he had it painted in a picture and stored in secrecy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>能因や相模 (歌人)、出羽弁といった歌人達と交流があり、江侍従との間には一女（左大臣家少輔）を儲けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had exchanges with poets such as Noin, Sagami (a waka poet) and Idewanoben, and even had a daughter (Shoyu of the House of the Minister of the Left) with Gonojijyu.</e>
<cmt>「左大臣家少輔」の正確な読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had exchanges with poets such as Noin, Sagami (a waka poet), and Idewanoben, and even had a daughter (Shoyu of the House of the Minister of the Left) with Gonojijyu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had exchanges with poets such as Noin, Sagami (a waka poet), and Idewa no ben, and even had a daughter (Shoyu of the House of the Minister of the Left) with Gonojijyu.</e>
<cmt>Idewanoben をIdewa no ben に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>また尊卑分脈や宇都宮系図などによると、兼房の子に藤原宗円がおり宇都宮氏の祖となったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Sonpi Bunmyaku (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) and Utsunomiya family record, it is said that he had a son, FUJIWARA no Soen who became the founder of Utsunomiya clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Sonpi Bunmyaku (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) and Utsunomiya family records, it is said that he had a son, FUJIWARA no Soen, who became the founder of the Utsunomiya clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Sonpi Bunmyaku (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy) and Utsunomiya family records, it is said that he had a son, FUJIWARA no Soen, who became the founder of the Utsunomiya clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかしこの説には異論もあり、正確なことは分かっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some disagree with this opinion, and it is not known exactly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some disagree with this opinion, and the exact truth is not known.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some disagree with this opinion, and the exact truth is not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Amler(id:101250), Ks8823(id:130146), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>