<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原彰子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshi FUJIWARA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshi FUJIWARA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Shoshi</e>
<cmt>Shoshi FUJIWARA</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 彰子（ふじわら の あきこ（しょうし）、永延2年（988年） - 承保元年10月3日 (旧暦)（1074年10月25日）は、第66代一条天皇の皇后（号は中宮）で、第68代後一条天皇・第69代後朱雀天皇の生母（国母）、女院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akiko (Shoshi) (988-October 25, 1074) was the empress (Chugu) of 66th Emperor Ichijio and a mother (Kokumo, Nyoin) of 68th Emperor Goichijo and 69th Emperor Suzaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Akiko (Shoshi) (988-October 25, 1074) was the empress (Chugu - or consort) of 66th Emperor Ichijio and the mother (Kokumo, Nyoin) of the 68th Emperor Goichijo and the 69th Emperor Suzaku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a mother&quot; →&quot;the mother&quot;.&quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;68th&quot;and &quot;69th&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress FUJIWARA no Akiko (her given name can also be pronounced &quot;Shoshi&quot;) (988 - October 25, 1074) was the chugu (a court title given to a consort of the Emperor) of the sixty-sixth Emperor, Ichijio, and the mother of the sixty-eighth Emperor, Goichijo, and the sixty-ninth Emperor, Gosuzaku (she also held the title Kokumo, meaning empress dowager, and Nyoin).</e>
<cmt>Some explanations were needed in places, I think.Also, a comma is grammatically required between &quot;66th Emperor&quot; and &quot;Ichijio&quot;, for example. Otherwise this means that there have been 65 Emperor Ichijios prior to this one.スペース挿入Suzaku→Gosuzaku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>院号を上東門院といい、大女院などとよばれて尊崇された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her honorific title was Jotomonin and was admired by being called as Dainyoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her honorific title was Jotomonin and she was also known by such revered titles as Dainyoin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;admired by being called as Dainyoin&quot;→&quot;also known by such revered titles as Dainyoin&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her honorific title was Jotomonin and she was also known by such titles as Dainyoin as a mark of respect.</e>
<cmt>Grammatically, &quot;revered titles&quot; means that the title itself is revered rather than the person.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>女房に『源氏物語』の作者・紫式部、王朝有数の歌人・和泉式部、歌人で『栄花物語』正編の作者と伝えられる赤染衛門、同じく歌人の伊勢大輔などを従え、華麗な文芸サロンを形成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her female attendants included &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; author, Murasaki Shikibu, the prominent poet of the dynasty, Izumi Shikibu (who is the possible author of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;), poet Akazome Emon, and poet Ise no Taifu who formed flamboyant literature salon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had several literary ladies-in-waiting, including &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; author, Murasaki Shikibu; the greatest poet of her time, Izumi Shikibu; the poet Akazome Emon (who is the possible author of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;) and the poet Ise no Taifu.</e>
<cmt>The original translation had a mistranslation: Akazome Emon, not Izumi Shikibu, is considered the author of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;.&quot;the prominent poet of the dynasty&quot;→&quot;the greatest poet of her time&quot;.&quot;Her female attendants…who formed flamboyant literature salon&quot;→&quot;She had several literary ladies-in-waiting&quot;, moved to start of sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had several literary ladies-in-waiting, including &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; author, Murasaki Shikibu; the greatest poet of her time, Izumi Shikibu; the poet Akazome Emon (who is the possible author of &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot;); and the poet Ise no Taifu.</e>
<cmt>Just one semi colon missing.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原道長の長女に生まれ、母は左大臣源雅信の女源倫子（964-1053）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born as the eldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, her mother was MINAMOTO no Rinshi (964-1053), the daughter of Sadaijin MINAMOTO no Masanobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshi was the eldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and MINAMOTO no Rinshi (964-1053), the daughter of Sadaijin (Senior Minister of State) MINAMOTO no Masanobu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Born as&quot;→&quot;Shoshi was&quot;, &quot;, her mother was&quot;→&quot;and&quot;Explanation of Sadaijin inserted.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshi was the eldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Michinaga and MINAMOTO no Rinshi (964-1053), the daughter of MINAMOTO no Masanobu, who held the office of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>意味を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同母の弟妹に、関白太政大臣藤原頼通（992-1074）・同藤原教通（996-1075）と、三条天皇中宮藤原妍子（994-1027）・後一条天皇中宮藤原威子（999-1036）・後朱雀天皇妃藤原嬉子（1007-1025）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maternal siblings included Kampaku (imperial regent) Dajo Daijin (grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Yorimichi (992-1074), Kampaku Dajo Daijin FUJIWARA no Norimichi (996-1075), Emperor Sanjo&apos;s Chugu FUJIWARA no Kenshi (994-1027), Emperor Goichijo&apos;s Chugu FUJIWARA no Ishi (999-1036), and Emperor Suzaku&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Kishi (1007-1025).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maternal siblings included Kampaku Dajo Daijin (Regent and Chancellor of the Realm) FUJIWARA no Yorimichi (992-1074), Kampaku Dajo Daijin FUJIWARA no Norimichi (996-1075), Emperor Sanjo&apos;s Chugu FUJIWARA no Kenshi (994-1027), Emperor Goichijo&apos;s Chugu FUJIWARA no Ishi (999-1036), and Emperor Suzaku&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Kishi (1007-1025).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kampaku (imperial regent) Dajo Daijin (grand minister of state)&quot;→&quot;Kampaku Dajo Daijin (Regent and Chancellor of the Realm)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maternal siblings included Kanpaku Dajo Daijin (Regent and Chancellor of the Realm) FUJIWARA no Yorimichi (992-1074), Kanpaku Dajo Daijin FUJIWARA no Norimichi (996-1075), Emperor Sanjo&apos;s Chugu FUJIWARA no Kenshi (994-1027), Emperor Goichijo&apos;s Chugu FUJIWARA no Ishi (999-1036), and Emperor Gosuzaku&apos;s Empress FUJIWARA no Kishi (1007-1025).</e>
<cmt>Kampaku→KanpakuSuzaku→Gosuzaku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、右大臣藤原頼宗・権大納言藤原能信・同藤原長家らは異腹の弟である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Udaijin FUJIWARA no Yorimune, Gon dainagon FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu, and Gon dainagon Fujiwara no Nagaie were her paternal younger brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her paternal younger brothers were Udaijin (Junior Minister of State) FUJIWARA no Yorimune, Gon dainagon (Great Councillor) FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu, and Gon dainagon Fujiwara no Nagaie.</e>
<cmt>Eplanation of Udaijin and Gon Dainagon inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her paternal younger brothers were Udaijin (Minister of the Rght) FUJIWARA no Yorimune, Gon dainagon (Great Councillor) FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu, and Gon dainagon Fujiwara no Nagaie.</e>
<cmt>Junior Minister of State→minister of the right</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>入内</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judai (Female Imperial Court Entrance by Marriage)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judai (Entry into the Imperial Court)</e>
<cmt>&quot;Female Imperial Court Entrance by Marriage&quot;→&quot;Entry into the Imperial Court&quot;―not an exact translation but maybe easier to understand for tourists</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judai (Entry into the Imperial Court)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>長徳元年（995年）、彰子8歳の時に、父道長が内覧の宣旨を蒙り政権を掌握し、それ以後、執政者の長女として世人の嘱目のもとに育つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Shoshi was 8 years old in 995, her father Michinaga opposed the imperial order and took over power. Since then, she grew up closely guarded by her attendants as the daughter of the court administrator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After her father Michinaga had ignored an imperial order and seized power in 995, when Shoshi was 8 years old, she was raised as the daughter of the court administrator, closely supervised by her attendants.</e>
<cmt>―Reverted to one sentence&quot;When Shoshi was 8 years old...took over power.&quot;→&quot;After her father Michinaga had ignored an imperial order and seized power in 995, when Shoshi was 8 years old,&quot;&quot;grew up&quot;→&quot;was raised&quot;&quot;guarded&quot;→&quot;supervised&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After her father Michinaga had ignored an imperial order and seized power in 995, when Shoshi was 8 years old, she was raised as the daughter of the court administrator, closely supervised by her attendants.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>長保元年（999年）2月9日、裳着と同日に従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gained the title of Jusanmi on the same day as her Mogi ceremony (Coming of Age Ceremony) on February 9, 999.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 9, 999, the same day as her Mogi (Coming of Age) ceremony, she was given the title of Jusanmi.</e>
<cmt>―Date moved to start of sentence, first clause moved to end&quot;gained&quot;→&quot;given&quot;,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 9, 999, the same day as her Mogi (Coming of Age) ceremony, she was given the title of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>(Junior Third Rank)を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年11月1日、8歳年上の従兄一条天皇に入内し、同月7日に女御宣下（同日、中宮藤原定子が第一皇子敦康親王を出産）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 1 of the same year, she entered the court of her 8 years older cousin, Emperor Ichijo, and declared herself as Nyogo on November 7 (It was on the same day as when Chugu FUJIWARA no Teishi gave birth to first crown prince, Prince Atsuyasu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 1 of the same year, she entered the court of her cousin, Emperor Ichijo, who was 8 years her senior and declared a Nyogo on November 7 (the same day that Chugu FUJIWARA no Teishi gave birth to first crown prince, Prince Atsuyasu).</e>
<cmt>&quot;8 years older&quot;→&quot;who was 8 years her senior&quot;― moved to after &quot;Emperor Ichijo&quot;&quot;herself&quot; deleted&quot;It was on&quot; deleted, &quot;as when&quot;→&quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 1 of the same year, she entered the court of her cousin, Emperor Ichijo, who was 8 years her senior and declared a Nyogo on November 7 (the same day that Chugu FUJIWARA no Teishi gave birth to first crown prince, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu).</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。Imperialを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>翌年2月25日、皇后に冊立され「中宮」を号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 25 of the following year, she was officially raised to empress and gained the &apos;Chugu&apos; title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 25 of the following year, she was officially made empress and given the title &apos;Chugu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>&quot;raised to&quot;→&quot;made&quot;&quot;gained&quot;→&quot;given&quot;&quot;the title&quot; moved to in front of &quot;Chugu&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 25 of the following year, she was officially made empress and called herself Chugu.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを&apos;の中に入れました。統一リストに準拠: given the title &apos;Chugu.&apos;→called herself Chugu.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『栄花物語』でも「かかやく飛香舎」と称されたその華やかさは先立の皇后定子を凌駕する勢いを持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described as &apos;Kakayaku Higyosha (Shining Higyosha)&apos; in &quot;Eiga Monogatari,&quot; her beauty far surpassed preceding Empress Teishi. She became the only empress in both the name and in reality when Teishi died during labor in the same year.</e>
<cmt>Kaka</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Described as &apos;Kakayaku Higyosha (Shining Higyosha)&apos; in &quot;Eiga Monogatari,&quot; her beauty far surpassed that of the preceding Empress Teishi. She became the sole empress, in both name and reality, when Teishi died during labor in the same year.</e>
<cmt>&quot;As&quot; deleted&quot;that of the&quot; inserted&quot;only&quot;→&quot;sole&quot;&quot;the&quot; deleted&quot;in&quot; deleted&quot;,&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Described as &apos;Kakayaku Higyosha (Shining Higyosha)&apos; in &quot;Eiga Monogatari,&quot; her beauty far surpassed that of the preceding Empress Teishi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同年末定子が難産で死去した後は名実共に唯一の后となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She became the sole empress, in both name and in reality, when Teishi died during labor in the same year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処表現スタイル。 “in both name and reality” =&gt; “in both name and in reality”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかしあまりに若すぎたためかなかなか懐妊せず、定子所生の敦康親王を手元に引き取って養育した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, she had a difficulty with conception due to her extremely young age and raised Teishi&apos;s Prince Atsuyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, she had a difficulty conceiving due to her extremely young age and raised Teishi&apos;s son, Prince Atsuyasu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;with conception&quot;→&quot;conceiving&quot;son&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, she had a difficulty conceiving due to her extremely young age and raised Teishi&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu.</e>
<cmt>Imperialを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>寛弘5年（1008年）9月11日、土御門殿にて第二皇子敦成親王（後一条天皇）を出産。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 11, 1008, she gave birth to the second crown prince, Prince Atsuhira (Emperor Goichijo), in Tsuchimikado dono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 11, 1008, she gave birth to the second crown prince, Prince Atsuhira (Emperor Goichijo), in Tsuchimikado dono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 11, 1008, she gave birth to the second crown prince, Imperial Prince Atsuhira (Emperor Goichijo), in Tsuchimikado dono.</e>
<cmt>Imperialを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>長年皇子誕生を待望していた父道長の狂喜ぶりは、『紫式部日記』に詳しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the long-waited birth of the prince, father Michinaga elatedness was described in detail in &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Dairy.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father&apos;s joy at the long-awaited birth of the prince was described in detail in the &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Dairy.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;From the... elatedness&quot;→&quot;Her father&apos;s joy at the long-awaited birth of the prince&quot;&quot;the&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father&apos;s joy at the long-awaited birth of the prince was described in detail in the &quot;Murasaki Shikibu Dairy.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>翌年、さらに敦良親王（後朱雀天皇）を産む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the following year, Shoshi gave birth to Prince Atsunaga (Emperor Suzaku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, Shoshi gave birth to Prince Atsunaga (Emperor Gosuzaku).</e>
<cmt>&quot;On&quot; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, Shoshi gave birth to Prince Atsunaga (Emperor Gosuzaku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この二皇子が、道長一家の繁栄の基盤となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These two princes gave ground for the prosperity of Michinaga Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These two princes laid the foundations for the prosperity of Michinaga Family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;gave ground&quot;→&quot;laid the foundations&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These two princes laid the foundations for the prosperity of Michinaga family.</e>
<cmt>Family→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>寛弘8年（1011年）6月13日、死の床にあって一条天皇は従兄居貞親王（三条天皇）に譲位、彰子所生の敦成親王の立太子が決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While in the death bed on June 13, 1011, Emperor Ichijo handed power over to his cousin, Prince Okisada (Emperor Sanjo), and Shoshi&apos;s Prince Atsuhira was designated as the crown prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While on his death bed on June 13, 1011, Emperor Ichijo handed power over to his cousin, Prince Okisada (Emperor Sanjo), and Shoshi&apos;s son, Prince Atsuhira, was designated as the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in the&quot;→ &quot;on his&quot;&quot;son&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While on his death bed on June 13, 1011, Emperor Ichijo handed power over to his cousin, Imperial Prince Okisada (Emperor Sanjo), and Shoshi&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Atsuhira, was designated as the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>Imperialを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、帝の真意が長子敦康親王にあったことを体していた彰子は、敦成親王の立太子を後押しした父を怨んだという（『権記』『栄花物語』ほか）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshi is said to have bore grudge against her father who supported Prince Atsuhira to be the crown prince while she knew that Emperor Ichijo&apos;s true intention was to promote her eldest son (&quot;Gonki,&quot; &quot;Eiga Monogatari,&quot; and etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshi is said to have borne a grudge against her father who supported Prince Atsuhira to be the crown prince while she knew that Emperor Ichijo&apos;s true intention was to promote his eldest son (&quot;Gonki,&quot; &quot;Eiga Monogatari,&quot; etc.).</e>
<cmt>&quot;bore&quot;→&quot;borne a&quot;&quot;her&quot;→&quot;his&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshi is said to have borne a grudge against her father who supported Imperial Prince Atsuhira to be the crown prince while she knew that Emperor Ichijo&apos;s true intention was to promote his eldest son (&quot;Gonki,&quot; &quot;Eiga Monogatari,&quot; etc.).</e>
<cmt>Imperialを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この説の真偽の程はともかく、彰子は合理的な考え方を持った賢明な女性であったらしく、道長の対立者であった藤原実資からも「賢后」の誉れを得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether this rumor was true or not, Shoshi seemed to be a rational minded wise woman who gained the title of &quot;Kenko&quot; even from Michinaga&apos;s enemy, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether this rumor was true or not, Shoshi seemed to be a rational and wise woman, whom even her father&apos;s enemy, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, called &quot;Kenko (Honourable Empress)&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;rational minded wise&quot;→&quot;rational and wise&quot;&quot; who gained... Sanesuke&quot;→&quot;, whom even her father&apos;s enemy, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, called &quot;Kenko (Honourable Empress)&quot;&quot;&quot;(Honourable Empress)&quot; added to aid foreign understanding</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether this rumor was true or not, Shoshi seemed to be a rational and wise woman, whom even her father&apos;s enemy, FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, called &apos;Kenko (Honorable Empress)&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。原文の「」に合わせ、&quot;を&apos;にしました。Honourable→Honorable</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>国母へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To Kokumo (Mother of the Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Becoming Kokumo (Mother of the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>&quot;To&quot;→&quot;Becoming&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Becoming Kokumo (Mother of the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>長和元年（1012年）2月14日皇太后、寛仁2年（1018年）正月7日太皇太后となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 14, 1012, she gained the title of Empress Dowager and became Grand Empress Dowager on January 7, 1018.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 14, 1012, she gained the title of Empress Dowager and became Grand Empress Dowager on January 7, 1018.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 14, 1012, she gained the title of Empress Dowager and became Grand Empress Dowager on January 7, 1018.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この間、長和5年（1016年）正月29日には彰子所生の後一条天皇が即位し、道長は念願の摂政に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Shoshi&apos;s Emperor Goichijo ascended to the throne, and Michinaga gained the long dreamed position of regent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Shoshi&apos;s son, Emperor Goichijo, ascended the throne in 1016, and Michinaga gained the position of regent, something he had long desired.</e>
<cmt>&quot;son&quot; inserted&quot;to&quot; deleted&quot;long dreamed position of regent.&quot;→&quot;position of regent, something he had long desired.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Shoshi&apos;s son, Emperor Goichijo, ascended the throne on January 29, 1016, and Michinaga gained the position of regent, something he had long desired.</e>
<cmt>in→on January 29</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>翌年、道長は摂政・氏長者をともに嫡子頼通にゆずり、出家して政界から身を引いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the following year, he passed the regent and family head position to his eldest son, Yorimichi, and retired from the political world by entering a Buddhist monastery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, he passed the regent and family head position to his eldest son, Yorimichi, and retired from the political world by entering a Buddhist monastery.</e>
<cmt>&quot;On&quot; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, he passed the regent and family head position to his eldest son, Yorimichi, and retired from the political world by entering a Buddhist monastery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その後、彰子は指導力に乏しい弟たちに代えて一門を統率し、頼通らと協力して摂関政治を支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, Shoshi substituted for younger brothers with poor leadership skills and united the family to support politics with Yorimichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over the next few years, by replacing younger brothers lacking leadership skills, Shoshi assumed leadership of the family and, with the support of Yorimichi and others, helped sustain the system of regents.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Afterwards&quot;→&quot;Over the next few years&quot;―Changed translation slightly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over the next few years, by replacing younger brothers lacking leadership skills, Shoshi assumed leadership of the family and, with the support of Yorimichi and others, helped sustain the system of regents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>万寿3年（1026年）正月19日、落飾し法名を清浄覚とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She shaved off her head to become a Buddhist priest on January 19, 1026 and gained the Buddhist name of Shojogaku.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明、清浄覚→Shojogaku と読めると思います[http://www.yamadera.info/seiten/e/endnote.htm]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On becoming a Buddhist priest on January 19, 1026, she shaved off her hair and took the Buddhist name Shojogaku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;head&quot;→&quot;hair&quot;&quot;gained&quot;→&quot;took&quot;&quot;to become&quot;→&quot;On becoming&quot;, moved to start of sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On becoming a Buddhist priest on January 19, 1026, she shaved off her hair and took the Buddhist name Shojogaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>同日、一条天皇母后で、彼女にとっては伯母で、義母でもあった藤原詮子の先例にならって女院号を賜り、上東門院を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the same day, she was honored with Jotomoi in title following the path of her grandmother, Emperor Ichijo&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Senshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the same day, she was honored with the title Jotomonin following in the footsteps of her aunt, Emperor Ichijo&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Senshi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in title&quot;→&quot;with the title&quot;&quot;the path&quot;→&quot;in the footsteps&quot;&quot;grandmother&quot;→&quot;aunt&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the same day, she was honored with the title Jotomonin following in the footsteps of her aunt and mother in law, Emperor Ichijo&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Senshi.</e>
<cmt>and mother in law を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>後年、父道長が建立した法成寺の内に東北院を建てて、晩年ここを在所としたため、別称を東北院ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because she later built and spent her late years in Tohokuin within Hojo-ji Temple founded by her father Michinaga, she was also called as Tohokuin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because she later built and spent her final years in Tohokuin within Hojo-ji Temple, which had been founded by her father Michinaga, she was also known as Tohokuin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;late&quot;→&quot;final&quot;&quot;founded&quot;→&quot;which had been founde&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because she later built and spent her final years in Tohokuin within Hojo-ji Temple, which had been founded by her father Michinaga, she was also known as Tohokuin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>長元9年（1036年）4月17日に後一条天皇、寛徳2年（1045年）正月18日に後朱雀天皇が崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Goichijo passed away on April 17, 1036 and Emperor Suzaku on January 18, 1045.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Goichijo passed away on April 17, 1036 and Emperor Suzaku on January 18, 1045.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goichijo passed away on April 17, 1036 and Emperor Gosuzaku on January 18, 1045.</e>
<cmt>Suzaku→Gosuzaku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>十年の間に二人の子を失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She lost her two children within the span of a decade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She lost her two children within the space of a decade.</e>
<cmt>&quot;span&quot;→&quot;space&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She lost her two children within the space of a decade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その後は孫の後冷泉天皇が即位したが、女官に髪を梳かせていた彰子は、その代に息子藤原師実へ関白職を譲りたい頼通からそのつもりを聞かされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an episode where she was asked by Yorimichi who wanted to put his son FUJIWARA no Morozane as the Kanpaku (chief advisor) to her newly throne grandson, Emperor Goreizei, while her lady-in-waiting combed her hair.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an episode where, while her lady-in-waiting combed her hair, she was asked by Yorimichi who wanted to put his son FUJIWARA no Morozane as the Kanpaku (chief advisor) to her newly enthroned grandson, Emperor Goreizei.</e>
<cmt>&quot;while her lady-in-waiting combed her hair&quot; moved to near start of sentence&quot;who wanted... (chief advisor)&quot;→&quot;who wanted to put his son FUJIWARA no Morozane as the Kanpaku (chief advisor)&quot;&quot;throne&quot;→&quot;enthroned&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an episode where, while her lady-in-waiting was combing her hair, she was asked by Yorimichi to appoint his son FUJIWARA no Morozane as the Kanpaku (chief advisor) to her newly enthroned grandson, Emperor Goreizei.</e>
<cmt>表現スタイル。英語では、何を聞かれたかを明確に修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>彰子はにわかに機嫌を悪くし、内裏へ「父道長の遺令に背くのでお許しにならぬように」との旨を奏上させ、ために頼通は弟教通へ譲らざるをえなかったエピソードがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She showed her disapproval by sending a written claim to the emperor stating, &apos;do not approve for it opposes father Michinaga&apos;s will,&apos; forcing Yorimichi to pass the position to his younger brother Norimichi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mood darkened instantly and she sent written instructions to the emperor stating, &apos;do not approve for it opposes my father Michinaga&apos;s will,&apos; forcing Yorimichi to pass the position to his younger brother Norimichi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;She showed... written claim&quot;→&quot;Her mood darkened instantly and she sent written instructions&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mood darkened instantly and she sent written instructions to the emperor stating, &apos;do not approve for it opposes my father Michinaga&apos;s will,&apos; forcing Yorimichi to pass the position to his younger brother Norimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その後、後冷泉のみならず、父が全盛を築いた摂関政治を終焉に導く事となった後三条天皇と、二人の孫にまで先立たれてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She outlived Goreizei, Emperor Gosanjo who contributed to the fall of Regiment Politics prospered by her father, and two grandchildren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She outlived two of her grandchildren, Goreizei and Emperor Gosanjo, who contributed to the demise of the Regent system built up by her father.</e>
<cmt>―changed translation slightly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She outlived two of her grandchildren, Goreizei and Emperor Gosanjo, who contributed to the demise of the Regent system built up by her father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>彼女は比較的に多くの和歌を残したが、なかでも後一条天皇の死後に詠んだ「ひと声も君に告げなんほととぎす　この五月雨は闇にまどふと」等、夫や子供の死を悼んだ歌が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She left fairly many waka (Japanese poem) but especially those poems that mourned the death of her husband and children such as &apos;Hitokoto mo Kimini tsugenan hototgisu kono samidare wa yamini madofuto (Please tell my late son even just a single word, hototogisu (lesser cuckoo), that I am shrouded in darkness thinking about my child in this summer rain)&apos; read after the death of Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She left a relatively large number of waka (Japanese poems), many of which mourned the death of her husband and children such as &apos;Hitokoe mo Kimini tsugenan hototogisu kono samidare wa yamini madofuto (Please just tell my late son this, hototogisu (lesser cuckoo), that this summer rain shrouds me in darkness)&apos; composed after the death of Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;fairly many&quot;→&quot;a relatively large number of&quot;&quot;but especially those poems that&quot;→&quot;, many of which&quot;&quot;hitokoto&quot;→&quot;hitokoe&quot;― changed translation of waka slightly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She left a relatively large number of waka (Japanese poems), many of which mourned the death of her husband and children such as &apos;Hitokoe mo Kimini tsugenan hototogisu kono samidare wa yamini madofuto (Please just tell my late son this, hototogisu (lesser cuckoo), that this summer rain shrouds me in darkness)&apos; composed after the death of Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>曾孫・白河天皇の代、承保元年（1074年）10月3日に87歳で崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She passed away during the rein of her great-grandson, Emperor Shirakawa, on October 3, 1074 when she was 87 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She passed away during the reign of her great-grandson, Emperor Shirakawa, on October 3, 1074 at the age of 87.</e>
<cmt>&quot;rein&quot;→&quot;reign&quot;&quot;when she was 87 years old&quot;→&quot;at the age of 87&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She passed away during the reign of her great-grandson, Emperor Shirakawa, on October 3, 1074 at the age of 87.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>同年2月2日に薨去した弟頼通に遅れること八ヶ月であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her death came 8 months after the death of her younger brother Yorimichi on February 2 of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her death came 8 months after the death of her younger brother Yorimichi on February 2 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her death came 8 months after the death of her younger brother Yorimichi on February 2 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>翌年には次の弟教通も没し、院政開始への道が敷かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her next younger brother Norimichi died on the following year, opening the path to the beginning of a cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her next younger brother Norimichi&apos;s death the following year eventually led to the period of cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt>&quot;died on&quot;→&quot;death&quot;&quot;opening... beginning of a&quot;→ &quot;eventually led to the period of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her next younger brother Norimichi&apos;s death the following year eventually led to the period of cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), Nnh(id:474), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 海衛士(id:19229), 松茸(id:27535), Point136(id:211299), 平惣衛門(id:99387), トホホ川(id:50502), Flénu(id:159955), 呆庵入道(id:74721), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>