<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原為任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tameto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tameto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tameto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 為任（ふじわら の ためとう、生年不詳 - 寛徳2年（1045年））は、平安時代中期の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tameto (Date of birth unknown - 1045) was a nobleman in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tameto (Date of birth unknown - 1045) was a nobleman in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tameto (year of birth unknown - 1045) was a nobleman in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>year of birth unknown 用語統一リストより訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原済時の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of FUJIWARA no Sumitoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of FUJIWARA no Sumitoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of FUJIWARA no Sumitoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正四位・伊予国国司。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded the rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) and was appointed as Iyo no Kuni Kokushi (the provincial governor of Iyo Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attained the rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) and was appointed Kokushi (Governor) of Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attained the rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank) and was appointed Kokushi (Governor) of Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>右馬助・少納言を経て、父の死後に彼が庇護していた異母妹の娍子が東宮居貞親王（後の三条天皇）に入内した正暦2年（991年）には従五位下右少弁であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After serving as Umanosuke (Asst. Captain, Right Division of Bureau of Horses) and Shonagon (lesser councilor of state), he was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Usoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 991 when his half sister Seishi who had been under his protection entered into court as a bride of Crown Prince Okisada (later Emperor Sanjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After serving as Umanosuke (Assistant Captain, Right Division of the Bureau of Horses) and Shonagon (Lesser Councilor of State), he was was made Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) with the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 991 when his half sister, Seishi, who had been under his protection since their father&apos;s death, entered into court as a bride of Crown Prince Okisada (later Emperor Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After serving as Umanosuke (Assistant Captain, Right Division of the Bureau of Horses) and Shonagon (Lesser Councilor of State), he was made Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) with the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 991 when his half sister, Seishi, who had been under his protection since their father&apos;s death, entered into court as a bride of Crown Prince Okisada (later Emperor Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>was 繰り返し削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>だが、常に嫡男とされた弟の通任よりも下位にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his rank was always lower than that of his younger brother Michito who had been acknowledged as a legitimate son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his rank was always lower than that of his younger brother, Michito, who had been acknowledged as a legitimate son.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his rank was always lower than that of his younger brother, Michito, who had been acknowledged as a legitimate son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>長徳2年（995年）には蔵人に任ぜられるが、自己の昇進の遅滞に不満を抱き、民部大輔であった寛弘3年（1006年）には、1年以上の不参を理由に除籍されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was appointed as Kurodo (Chamberlain) in 995, he was unhappy about his slow promotion, and in 1006 when he was Minbu taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs), his name was removed from the record because he did not attend his office for more than a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was appointed Kurodo (Chamberlain) in 995, he was unhappy about his slow promotion, and in 1006, when he was Minbu Taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs), his name was removed from the record because he did not attend his office for more than a year.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionPunctuationCapital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was appointed Kurodo (Chamberlain) in 995, he was unhappy about his slow promotion, and in 1006, when he was Minbu Taifu (Senior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs), his name was removed from the record because he did not attend his office for more than a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>三条天皇の即位後、藤原娍子が后妃に立てられると思われていたが、内覧左大臣である藤原道長は、自分の娘藤原妍子を入内させて后妃に立てようと図り、これを阻もうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the enthronement of Emperor Sanjo, FUJIWARA no Seishi was expected to be put up as empress, but Nairan-sadaijin FUJIWARA no Michinaga attempted to thwart it by scheming to have his daughter FUJIWARA no Genji enter into court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the enthronement of Emperor Sanjo, FUJIWARA no Seishi was expected to made Empress, but Nairan-sadaijin FUJIWARA no Michinga attempted to thwart it by scheming to have his daughter FUJIWARA no Genji enter into court.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityCapital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the enthronement of Emperor Sanjo, FUJIWARA no Seishi was expected to made Empress, but Nairan-sadaijin FUJIWARA no Michinga attempted to thwart it by scheming to have his daughter FUJIWARA no Genji enter into court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、長年正妃的な地位にあり、3人もの親王を儲けた娍子の存在を無視することは道長でも困難であり、漸く娍子を皇后・妍子を中宮とすることで折り合いをつけたが、その後も道長は娍子側に圧迫を加えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Michinaga came to terms with having Seishi as empress and Genji as chugu (the second consort of an emperor) for the time being because even Michinaga could not ignore the presence of Seishi who had been in a position similar to a lawful wife and had three imperial princes, but he kept exerting pressure on Seishi and her supporters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even Michinaga could not ignore the the fact that Seishi&apos;s position was similar to a lawful wife and that she had given birth to three imperial princes, so he compromised for the time being by having Seishi as Empress and Genji as Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor), but he kept exerting pressure on Seishi and her supporters.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even Michinaga could not ignore the fact that Seishi&apos;s position was similar to a lawful wife and that she had given birth to three imperial princes, so he compromised for the time being by having Seishi as Empress and Genji as Chugu (the second consort of the Emperor), but he kept exerting pressure on Seishi and her supporters.</e>
<cmt>the 繰り返し削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後に為任が道長を呪詛しているという風説が流れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, a rumor went around that Tameto was cursing Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, a rumor went around that Tameto was cursing Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, a rumor went around that Tameto was cursing Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>長和2年（1012年）に娍子が御所に参内した際には、自邸を里邸として娍子を庇護していた為任は未だ従四位皇后宮職であり、前年に従三位参議修理大夫に昇進して公卿となっていた通任が仕切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1012 when Seishi visited the Imperial Palace, Tameto who was using his own house as a village residence to protect Seishi was still at the rank of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) Kogogushiki (the Queen consort&apos;s Household Agency), and Michito, who had become a Court noble in the previous year by being promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) Sangi (councilor) Shuri no daifu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs), took the leadership.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1012 when Seishi visited the Imperial Palace, Tameto, who was looking after Seishi in his own house, was still at the rank of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) in the Empress Consort&apos;s Household Agency (Kogogushiki), so Michito, who had become a Court noble the previous year by being promoted to Sangi (councilor) and Shuri no Daifu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs) with the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), took charge.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1012 when Seishi visited the Imperial Palace, Tameto, who was looking after Seishi in his own house, was still at the rank of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) in the Empress Consort&apos;s Household Agency (Kogogushiki), so Michito, who had become a Court noble the previous year by being promoted to Sangi (councilor) and Shuri no Daifu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs) with the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), took charge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、天皇は道長が通任の昇任を働きかけた際、道長は娍子の庇護者は為任であり、通任は偶々その代理をしたに過ぎないことを指摘した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, when the emperor encouraged Michinaga to promote Michito, Michinaga pointed out that Seishi&apos;s protector was Tameto and that Michito just happened to stand in for him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, when the Emperor encouraged Michinaga to promote Michito, Michinaga pointed out that Seishi&apos;s guardian was actully Tameto and that Michito just happened to stand in for him.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, when the Emperor encouraged Michinaga to promote Michito, Michinaga pointed out that Seishi&apos;s guardian was in fact Tameto and that Michito just happened to stand in for him.</e>
<cmt>actually→in fact</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>もし参内の功労で通任が叙位されれば、為任の功績をもって通任が賞を受けることとなり、「伊賀の人が（大国の格式を持つとされた）伊勢の人と偽るようなものだ（然伊賀人借伊勢人歟）」と天皇の姿勢を批判した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If Michito had been conferred a court rank for his services of sending Seishi to the Imperial Palace, it would have meant that Michito was rewarded for Tameto&apos;s achievements, and therefore Michinaga criticized the emperor&apos;s stance by saying &apos;it would be like people of Iga pretending to be the people of Ise&apos; (which was considered to have the social status of a big province) (然伊賀人借伊勢人歟).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If Michito had been conferred a court rank for his service in sending Seishi to the Imperial Palace, it would have meant that Michito was rewarded for Tameto&apos;s achievements, and therefore Michinaga criticized the emperor&apos;s stance, saying &apos;it would be like the people of Iga pretending to be the people of Ise&apos; (which was considered to have the social status of a big province).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If Michito had been conferred a court rank for his service in sending Seishi to the Imperial Palace, it would have meant that Michito was rewarded for Tameto&apos;s achievements, and therefore Michinaga criticized the emperor&apos;s stance, saying &apos;it would be like the people of Iga pretending to be the people of Ise&apos; (which was considered to have the social status of a big province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その結果、為任が従四位上に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, Tameto was awarded the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Tameto was awarded the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Tameto was awarded the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、藤原実資と結んでその家司的な役割を果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also joined forces with FUJIWARA no Sanesuke and played a role similar to that of keishi (household superintendent).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also joined forces with FUJIWARA no Sanesuke and played a role similar to that of keishi (household superintendent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also joined forces with FUJIWARA no Sanesuke and played a role similar to that of keishi (household superintendent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>長和3年（1013年）、為任は当時最も富裕な令制国の1つと考えられていた伊予守に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1013, Tameto was appointed as Iyo no Kami (Governor of Iyo Province) that was considered to be one of the wealthiest ryosheikoku (provinces) in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1013, Tameto was appointed Kami (Governor) of Iyo Province, which at the time was considered to be one of the wealthiest provinces.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1013, Tameto was appointed Kami (Governor) of Iyo Province, which at the time was considered to be one of the wealthiest provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>だが、三条天皇の退位、娍子所生の敦明親王の皇太子辞退、そして娍子の死などもあり、従四位上伊予守を極位極官として遅くても万寿年間には出家していたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it appears that he retired from the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) Iyo no Kami which was his gokui gokkan (his best rank and his best position) and entered into priesthood from 1024 to 1027 at the latest due to the abdication of Emperor Sanjo, Seishi&apos;s son Imperial Prince Atsuaki&apos;s renouncing his claim to the title of Crown Prince and Seishi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, following the abdication of Emperor Sanjo, Seishi&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Atsuaki&apos;s renouncement of his claim to the title of Crown Prince and Seishi&apos;s death, it appears that he retired as Kami of Iyo with the rank of Jushiinojo, the highest positions he reached, and sometime between 1024 and 1027 at the latest he entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, following the abdication of Emperor Sanjo, Seishi&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Atsuaki&apos;s renouncement of his claim to the title of Crown Prince and Seishi&apos;s death, it appears that he retired as Kami of Iyo with the rank of Jushiinojo, the highest positions he reached, and sometime between 1024 and 1027 at the latest he entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そして、『尊卑分脈』には寛徳2年に射殺されたとのみ記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And &quot;Sonpibunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineage of the aristocracy) simply states that he was shot to death in 1045.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Sonpibunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineage of the aristocracy) simply states that he was killed by an arrow in 1045.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Sonpibunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineage of the aristocracy) simply states that he was killed by an arrow in 1045.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>晩年の動向及び殺害に至る経緯については不明のままである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What he did in his final years and the details leading up to the killing remain unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What he did in his final years and the details leading up to his murder remain unknown.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What he did in his final years and the details leading up to his murder remain unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Snap55(id:89773), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>