<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平知盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomomori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tomomori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomomori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 知盛（たいら の とももり）は、平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomomori was a warlord in the late Heian era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tomomori was a warlord in the late Heian era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomomori was a warlord in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Heian era→Heian periodに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平清盛の四男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the forth son of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth son of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth son of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は平時子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was TAIRA no Tokiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tokiko was his mother.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokiko was his mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同母兄弟に平宗盛、平重衡、平徳子がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Munemori, TAIRA no Shigehira and TAIRA no Tokuko were his brothers and sister uterine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Munemori, TAIRA no Shigehira and TAIRA no Tokuko were his maternal brothers and sister.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Munemori, TAIRA no Shigehira and TAIRA no Tokuko were his maternal brothers and sister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>官位は従二位中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His office and rank were the vice councilor of state with Junii rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the office of vice councilor of state with the rank of Junii.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the office of Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) with the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>「従二位」「中納言」を統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>世に新中納言と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Shin-Chunagon publicly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was publicly called Shin-Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was publicly called Shin-Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomomori&apos;s Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Life of TAIRA no Tomomori</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>平氏の全盛期に清盛の正室・平時子を母として生まれ、わずか8歳で従五位下となり、その後も栄進していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born of TAIRA no Tokiko, the legal wife of TAIRA no Kiyomori, in the time of the greatest vigor of the Taira clan and promoted to Jugoi-no-ge rank when he was 8 years old and he continued to be promoted to higher ranks..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born of TAIRA no Tokiko, the legal wife of TAIRA no Kiyomori, in a time when the Taira enjoyed their greatest prosperity. He was first promoted to Jugoi-no-ge rank at the age of eight, and continued to receive promotions to higher ranks..</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born of TAIRA no Tokiko, the legal wife of TAIRA no Kiyomori, in a time when the Taira clan enjoyed their greatest prosperity, and he was first promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) rank at the age of eight, and continued to receive promotions to higher ranks..</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、およびTaira→Taira clan、Jugoi-no-ge→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>知盛は武蔵国の国司・知行国主として、同国から多数の平氏家人を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kokushi and Chigyo-kokushi (sovereign of the fief) of Musashi-no-kuni, TAIRA no Tomomori acquired a large number of Heishi Iebito (servers of Taira Family) from Musashi-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kokushi and Chigyo-kokushi (sovereign of the fief) of Musashi-no-kuni, TAIRA no Tomomori acquired a large number of Heishi Iebito (servants of Taira Family) from Musashi-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>mistranslation identified in red lettering.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kokushi (provincial governors) and Chigyo-kokushi (sovereign of the fief) of Musashi Province, TAIRA no Tomomori acquired a large number of Heishi Iebito (servants of the Taira family) from Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>Kokushiの補足を追加、Musashi-no-kuni→Musashi Province, Taira Family→the Taira familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>武蔵は源氏の勢力が強い地域であり、知盛の武将としての才能・人間的魅力が大きく作用したと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Musashi was an area in which Genji had great influence, it can be surmised that Tomomori&apos;s capability as a warlord and his personal magnetism worked greatly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Musashi was in an area in which the Genji had great influence, it is thought that Tomomori&apos;s capability as a warlord and his personal magnetism worked effectively.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Musashi was in an area in which the Minamoto clan had great influence, it is thought that Tomomori&apos;s capability as a warlord and his personal magnetism worked effectively.</e>
<cmt>the Genji→the Minamoto clanに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>兄の重盛・宗盛は後白河に対して優柔不断であったため、清盛は知盛に期待をかけたらしく「最愛之息」と呼ばれた（『玉葉』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his elder brothers, Shigemori and Munemori behaved indecisively toward Goshirakawa, it seems that Kiyomori placed his expectation on Tomomori and, therefore, called him &quot;much-loved son.&quot; (&quot;Gyokuyo (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary)&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his elder brothers, Shigemori and Munemori, behaved indecisively toward Goshirakawa, it appears that Kiyomori placed his expectations on Tomomori and, therefore, called him &quot;much-loved son&quot; (&quot;Gyokuyo (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation, wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his elder brothers, Shigemori and Munemori, behaved indecisively toward Goshirakawa, it appears that Kiyomori placed his expectations on Tomomori and, therefore, called him &apos;much-loved son&apos; (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Kanezane KUJO&apos;s diary)).</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ&apos;much-loved son&apos;をシングルクォーテーションに変更、および&quot;Gyokuyo&quot;の補足の位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>治承4年（1180年）12月、美濃国と近江国で源氏が叛乱を起こした時には総大将として鎮圧にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1180, when Genji rose insurrections in Mino-no-kuni and Omi-no-kuni, he suppressed the insurrections as the supreme commander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1180, when the Genji rose in insurrection in Mino-no-kuni and Omi-no-kuni, he was the supreme commander to suppress the insurrection.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1180, when the Minamoto clan rose in insurrection in Mino Province and Omi Province, he was the supreme commander to suppress the insurrection.</e>
<cmt>the Genji→the Minamoto clanに修正、Mino Province, Omi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>知盛はその後、清盛の命令で東国追討も命じられたが、この時に病に倒れて京都に戻ることを余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Kiyomori ordered Tomomori to go to Togoku to conduct search and kill, but Tomomori was obliged to come back to Kyoto because of his illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Kiyomori ordered Tomomori to go to Togoku to conduct a search-and-destroy mission, but Tomomori was forced to return to Kyoto due to illness.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Kiyomori ordered Tomomori to go to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) to conduct a search-and-destroy mission, but Tomomori was forced to return to Kyoto due to illness.</e>
<cmt>Togokuの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>治承5年（1181年）閏2月4日、清盛が死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the forth day of the intercalary second month in 1181, Kiyomori died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori died on the fourth day of the intercalary second month in 1181.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori died on the fourth day of the intercalary second month in 1181.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>清盛の後は同母兄の宗盛が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munemori, Tomomori&apos;s elder brother-uterine, succeeded Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munemori, Tomomori&apos;s elder maternal brother, succeeded Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munemori, Tomomori&apos;s elder maternal brother, succeeded Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>知盛は、同母弟の重衡とともに宗盛を補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomori, together with Shigehira, his brother-uterine, assisted Munemori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomomori assisted Munemori, together with Shigehira, his maternal brother.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomomori assisted Munemori, together with Shigehira, his maternal brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同年10月の平氏遠征軍の編成は、北陸道は知度・清房（宗盛の異母弟）・重衡・資盛、東海道・東山道は維盛・清経（重盛の子）、熊野は頼盛の子息2名、最も重要な洛中守護は宗盛・教盛・経盛・頼盛・知盛が担当した（『玉葉』10月10日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1181, Heishi expeditionary force was organized so that Hokuriku-do was covered by Tomomori, Kiyofusa (Munemori&apos;s younger brother by a different mother), Shigehira and Sukemori, Tokaido and Tozando road by Koremori and Kiyotsune (a son of Shigemori), Kumano by two sons of Yorimori and most important Rakuchu Shugo by Munemor, Norimori, Tsunemori, Yorimori and Tomomori. (Article for October 10 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;)</e>
<cmt>.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1181, a Heishi expeditionary force was organized so that Hokuriku-do was charged to Tomomori, Kiyofusa (Munemori&apos;s younger brother by a different mother), Shigehira and Sukemori, Tokaido and Tozando road was charged to Koremori and Kiyotsune (a son of Shigemori), Kumano was charged to the two sons of Yorimori, with the most important point, Rakuchu Shugo, charged to Munemori, Norimori, Tsunemori, Yorimori and Tomomori. (Source: Article for October 10 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation, citation format</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1181, the Taira clan expeditionary force was organized so that Hokuriku-do was charged to Tomomori, Kiyofusa (Munemori&apos;s younger brother by a different mother), Shigehira and Sukemori, Tokai-do and Tozan-do roads were charged to Koremori and Kiyotsune (a son of Shigemori), Kumano was charged to the two sons of Yorimori, with the most important point, Rakuchu Shugo (military governor of Kyoto), charged to Munemori, Norimori, Tsunemori, Yorimori and Tomomori. (Source: Article for October 10 in &quot;Gyokuyo&quot;).</e>
<cmt>a Heishi→the Taira clanに修正、Hokuriku-doに合わせTokai-do, Tozan-doとし、road was→roads wereに修正、Rakuchu Shugoの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この時、宗盛とともに洛中に留まった者が政権中枢にあったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that those persons who stayed in Kyoto with Munemori were key persons in the political power at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the people who stayed in Kyoto with Munemori were the key people in political power at that time.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the people who stayed in Kyoto with Munemori were the key people in political power at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）2月、宗盛が内大臣を辞任する際、宗盛のもとに知盛・重衡・頼盛・時忠・親宗が集まっている（『吉記』2月27日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1183, when Munemori resigned as Naidaijin, Tomomori, Shigehira, Yorimori, Tokitada and Chikanume turned out to Munemori&apos;s place. (Articles for February 27 in &quot;Kikki (Tsunefusa YOSHIDA&apos;s diary)&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1183, when Munemori resigned as Naidaijin, Tomomori, Shigehira, Yorimori, Tokitada and Chikanume turned out to Munemori&apos;s place. (Source: Articles for February 27 in &quot;Kikki (Tsunefusa YOSHIDA&apos;s diary)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1183, when Munemori resigned as Naidaijin (inner minister), Tomomori, Shigehira, Yorimori, Tokitada and Chikanume turned out to Munemori&apos;s place (Source: Articles for February 27 in &quot;Kikki&quot; (Tsunefusa YOSHIDA&apos;s diary)).</e>
<cmt>Naidaijinの補足を追加、余分なピリオド削除、クォーテーション内のカッコ文の位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>知盛が、平氏一門において中枢を担っていたことがうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those facts implicate that Tomomori played an important role in Taira Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This implies that Tomomori played an important role in the Taira Family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This implies that Tomomori played an important role in the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>the Taira Family→the Taira familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）、倶利伽羅峠の戦いで平氏軍が壊滅すると、知盛は宗盛とともに都落ちを決める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1183, when Taira clan army was defeated and fell apart in the Battle of Kurikara-toge, Tomomori, together with Munemori, decided to exile from the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1183, when the Taira clan army was decimated in the Battle of Kurikara-toge, Tomomori, together with Munemori, resolved to leave the capital in exile.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1183, when the Taira clan army was decimated in the Battle of Kurikara-toge, Tomomori, together with Munemori, resolved to leave the capital in exile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>翌寿永3年（1184年）2月7日、一ノ谷の戦いで大敗して子の平知章を失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 7, 1184, Taira clan army was severely defeated and Tomomori lost his son, TAIRA no Tomoaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 7, 1184, the Taira clan army suffered a terrible blow, and Tomomori lost his son, TAIRA no Tomoaki.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 7, 1184, the Taira clan army suffered a terrible blow at the Battle of Ichinotani, and Tomomori lost his son, TAIRA no Tomoaki.</e>
<cmt>「一ノ谷の戦い」を訳出</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>元暦2年（1185年）3月24日、壇ノ浦の合戦で平氏滅亡の様を見届けた知盛は、海へ身を投げ自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 24, 1185, after watching demolition of Taira clan in the naval battle of Danno-ura, Tomomori committed a suicide by throwing himself into the sea..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 24, 1185, after witnessing the destruction of the Taira in the naval battle of Danno-ura, Tomomori drowned himself in the sea..</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 24, 1185, after witnessing the destruction of the Taira clan in the naval battle of Danno-ura, Tomomori drowned himself in the sea..</e>
<cmt>Taira→Taira clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>享年34。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 34 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 34 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 34 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>なお、平氏滅亡後に反乱を起こす平知忠は、知盛の息子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomotada, who rose an insurrection after demolition of Taira clan, was Tomomori&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tomotada, who rose in insurrection after the destruction of the Taira, was Tomomori&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomotada, who rose in insurrection after the destruction of the Taira clan, was Tomomori&apos;s son.</e>
<cmt>Taira→Taira clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>碇知盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomori IKARI</e>
<cmt>[碇]は、知盛の姓ではありませんが、これでよいのでしょうか？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomomori IKARI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikari Tomomori (Tomomori with the Anchor)</e>
<cmt>姓名ではないため、表記を修正、補足を追加 (参照: http://www.artic.edu/aic/collections/artwork/31660)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>このとき、知盛は碇を担いだとも、鎧を二枚着てそれを錘にし、「見るべき程の事をば見つ。今はただ自害せん」と言い残して入水したとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to legend, Tomomori shouldered an anchor or he wore two suits of armor as a weight and threw himself into the sea saying &quot;I have seen what I should see. Now I am just going to suicide myself.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to legend, Tomomori either shouldered an anchor or donned two suits of armor as a weight, and he threw himself into the sea after proclaiming, &quot;I have seen what I should see. Now I shall end my life.&quot;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to legend, Tomomori either shouldered an anchor or donned two suits of armor as a weight, and he threw himself into the sea after proclaiming, &apos;I have seen what I should see. Now I shall end my life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>共に入水後遺体となるか、あるいは生きたまま浮かび上がって晒し物になるなどの辱めを受けるのを避ける心得である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a precaution to avoid suffering indignity of being shown by coming up after throwing himself into the sea either as a dead body or alive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He did this to avoid the indignity of being seen floating on the surface of the sea as a dead body or still alive.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did this to avoid the indignity of being seen floating on the surface of the sea as a dead body or still alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>これに想を得た歌舞伎『義経千本桜』の「渡海屋」および「大物浦」は別名「碇知盛」（いかりとももり）とも呼ばれ、知盛が崖の上から碇と共に仰向けに飛込み入水する場面がクライマックスとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tokai-ya&quot; and &quot;Daimotsu-ura&quot; of &quot;Yoshitsune Sembon-zakura&quot; ballad drama of Kabuki (traditional performing art) based on such legend is also called &quot;Tomomori IKARI&quot; and its climax is the scene in which Tomomori throws himself into the sea by jumping backward from the top of the cliff shouldering an anchor.</e>
<cmt>35行のコメントをご参照ください。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tokai-ya&quot; and &quot;Daimotsu-ura&quot; of the &quot;Yoshitsune Sembon-zakura&quot; ballad drama of Kabuki (traditional performing art) were based on this legend, which is also called &quot;Tomomori IKARI&quot;. At its climax is the scene when Tomomori throws himself into the sea by leaping backward from the top of the cliff shouldering an anchor.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokai-ya&apos; and &apos;Daimotsu-ura&apos; of the &quot;Yoshitsune Sembon-zakura&quot; ballad drama of Kabuki (traditional performing art) are based on this legend, which is also called &apos;Ikari Tomomori,&apos; and at its climax is the scene when Tomomori throws himself into the sea by leaping backward from the top of the cliff shouldering an anchor.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、原文に合わせクォーテーションを変更、were→areとし、「碇知盛」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Official Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* Date = Chinese calendar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Date = Chinese calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Date = Chinese calendar</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>保元4年のち改元して平治元年（1159年）（8歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1159 (8 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1159 (8 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1159 (8 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>正月7日蔵人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 7, Kurodo (staff of Kurodo-dokoro)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 7, he became a Kurodo (staff of Kurodo-dokoro).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 7: He became a Kurodo (staff of Kurodo-dokoro).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>正月21日従五位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 21, Jugoi-no-ge rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 21, he was granted the rank of Jugoi-no-ge.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 21: He was granted the rank of Jugoinoge.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Jugoinogeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>平治2年のち改元して永暦元年（1160年）（9歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1160 (9 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1160 (9 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1160 (9 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>2月28日武蔵守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 28, Musashi-no-kami (chief of Musashi-no-kuni)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 28, he was assigned to the position of Musashi-no-kami (chief of Musashi-no-kuni).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 28: He was assigned to the position of Governor of Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、武蔵守→Governor of Musashi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>応保2年（1162年）（11歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1162 (11 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1162 (11 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1162 (11 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>9月28日左兵衛権佐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 28, Sahyoe-no-gon-no-suke (supernumerary vice minister of Sahyoe-fu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 28, he was assigned to the position of Sahyoe-no-gon-no-suke (supernumerary vice minister of Sahyoe-fu).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 28: He was assigned to the position of Sahyoe no gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「左兵衛権佐」の表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="38">
<j>長寛2年（1164年）（13歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1164 (13 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1164 (13 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1164 (13 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>正月5日従五位上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5, Jugoi-no-jo rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5, he was granted the rank of Jugoi-no-jo.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5: He was granted the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Jugoinojoとし、初出のため補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="40">
<j>永万2年のち改元して仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）（15歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1166 (15 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1166 (15 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1166 (15 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>8月27日正五位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 27, Shogoi-no-ge rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 27, he was granted the rank of Shogoi-no-ge.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 27: He was granted the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Shogoinogeとし、初出のため補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>10月10日春宮大進（東宮・憲仁親王）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 10, Togu-no-Daishin (inspector of Togubo government office) (Togu: Imperial prince Norihito)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 10, he was assigned to the position of Togu-no-Daishin (inspector of Togubo government office) (Togu: Imperial prince Norihito).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 10: He was assigned to the position of Togu no Daishin (Senior official of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) (Togu: Imperial prince Norihito).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「春宮大進」の表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>10月21日中務権大輔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 21, Nakatsukasa-no-Gon-no-Taifu (supernumerary assistance administrator of Nakatsukasa Ministry of Imperial court)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 21, he was assigned to the position of Nakatsukasa-no-Gon-no-Taifu (supernumerary assistance administrator of Nakatsukasa Ministry of Imperial court).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 21: He was assigned to the position of Nakatsukasa no Gon no Taifu (Provisional Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「中務権大輔」の表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>春宮大進・武蔵守如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togu-no-Daishin and Musashi-no-kami, as they are</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Togu-no-Daishin and Musashi-no-kami, as they are</e>
<cmt>Unclear meaning</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Togu no Daishin and Governor of Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>「如元」→統一リストに基づき修正、Togu no Daishin, Governor of Musashi Provinceとし、上記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="45">
<j>右近衛権少将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukon-e-no-Gon-no-Shosho (supernumerary lowest general of Ukon-e-fu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukon-e-no-Gon-no-Shosho (supernumerary lowest general of Ukon-e-fu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukone no Gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>表記を修正、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="46">
<j>仁安2年（1167年）（16歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1167 (16 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1167 (16 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1167 (16 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>2月11日従四位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 11, Jushii-no-ge rank</e>
<cmt>他の記載例に合わせ、「Jushii-no-ge」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 11, he was granted the rank of Jushii-no-ge.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 11: He was granted the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Jushiinogeとし、初出のため補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>武蔵守如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Musashi-no-kami, as it is</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Musashi-no-kami, as it is</e>
<cmt>Unclear meaning</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Governor of Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>「如元」→統一リストに基づき修正、Governor of Musashi Provinceとし、上記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="49">
<j>12月30日武蔵守を辞任（後任・平知重）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 30, resigned as Musashinokami (successor: TAIRA no Tomoshige)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 30, he resigned as Musashinokami (successor: TAIRA no Tomoshige).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 30: He resigned as Governor of Musashi Province (successor: TAIRA no Tomoshige).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Governor of Musashi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="50">
<j>仁安3年（1168年）（17歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1168 (17 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1168 (17 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1168 (17 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>正月6日従四位上（平盛子御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 6, Jushii-no-jo rank (TAIRA no Seishi, to be given)</e>
<cmt>「御給 = to be given」の意味が確認できず、そのまま表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 6, he was granted the rank of Jushii-no-jo (TAIRA no Seishi, to be given).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 6: He was granted the rank of Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) (TAIRA no Seishi, to be given).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Jushiinojoとし、初出のため補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>2月19日新帝（高倉天皇）昇殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 19, new emperor (Emperor Takakura) Shoden (to access to the imperial court)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 19, he was granted Shoden (to access to the imperial court) to the new emperor (Emperor Takakura).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 19: He was granted Shoden (to access to the imperial court) to the new emperor (Emperor Takakura).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>3月23日左近衛権中将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 23, Sakonoe-Gonchujo (supernumerary lieutenant general of Sakon-e-fu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 23, he was promoted to Sakonoe-Gonchujo (supernumerary lieutenant general of Sakon-e-fu).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 23: He was promoted to Sakone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「左近衛権中将」の表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>8月4日正四位下（後白河上皇御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 4, Shoshii-no-ge rank (Ex-emperor Goshirakawa, to be given)</e>
<cmt>「御給 = to be given」の意味が確認できず、そのまま表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 4, he was granted the rank of Shoshii-no-ge (Ex-emperor Goshirakawa, to be given).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 4: He was granted the rank of Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) (the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa, to be given).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Shoshiinogeとし、初出のため補足を追加、Ex-emperor Goshirakawa→the Rerired Emperor Goshirakawaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="55">
<j>安元3年のち改元して治承元年（1177年）（26歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1177 (26 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1177 (26 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1177 (26 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>正月24日従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 24, Jusammi rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 24, he was granted the rank of Jusammi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 24: He was granted the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Jusanmiの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>左中将如元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sachujo, as it is</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sachujo, as it is</e>
<cmt>Unclear meaning</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retained his position as Sachujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>「如元」→統一リストに基づき修正、Sachujoの補足を追加、上記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="58">
<j>治承2年（1178年）（27歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1178 (27 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1178 (27 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1178 (27 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>正月28日丹波権守兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 28, Tamba-no-Gon-no-Kami (supernumerary chief of Tamba-no-kuni) concurrently</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 28, he served concurrently as Tamba-no-Gon-no-Kami (supernumerary chief of Tamba-no-kuni).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 28: He served concurrently as Provisional Governor of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「丹波権守」→○○守の統一事項に基づき、Provisional Governor of Tanba Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="60">
<j>治承3年（1179年）（28歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1179 (28 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1179 (28 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1179 (28 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>正月19日春宮権大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 19, Togu-gon-no-daibu (supernumerary chief of Togubo government organization)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 19, he became Togu-gon-no-daibu (supernumerary chief of Togubo government organization).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 19: He became Togu Gon no daibu (Provisional Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「春宮権大夫」の表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>右兵衛督</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uhyoe-no-kami (minister of Uhyoe-fu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uhyoe-no-kami (minister of Uhyoe-fu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>表記を修正、上記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="63">
<j>8月春宮権大夫を辞任（重盛の死去）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, resigned as Togu-gon-no-daibu (Shigemori&apos;s death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, he resigned as Togu-gon-no-daibu (Shigemori died).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August: He resigned as Togu Gon no daibu (Shigemori died).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Togu Gon no daibuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>9月5日正三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 5, Shosammi rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 5, he was granted the rank of Shosammi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 5: He was granted the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Shosanmiの補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>春宮権大夫に復任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reappointed to Togu-gon-no-daibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was reappointed to the position of Togu-gon-no-daibu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was reappointed to the position of Togu Gon no daibu.</e>
<cmt>Togu Gon no daibuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="66">
<j>10月9日左兵衛督</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 9, Sahyonoe-no-kami (head of Sahyoefu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 9, he became Sahyonoe-no-kami (head of Sahyoefu).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 9: He became Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「左兵衛督」の表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="67">
<j>治承4年（1180年）（29歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1180 (29 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1180 (29 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1180 (29 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>2月21日春宮権大夫を辞任（安徳天皇践祚）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 21, he resigned as Togu-gon-no-daibu (Emperor Antoku became the emperor.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 21, he resigned as Togu-gon-no-daibu (Emperor Antoku became the emperor).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 21: He resigned as Togu Gon no daibu (Emperor Antoku became the emperor).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Togu Gon no daibuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>2月25日新院（高倉上皇）別当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 25, the attendant for Shin-in (newer ex-emperor)(Ex-emperor Takakura)</e>
<cmt>ここでは「別当 = chief priest」 ではなく「attendant」が適切と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 25, he also became the attendant for Shin-in (newer ex-emperor)(Ex-emperor Takakura).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 25: He also became the attendant for the new Retired Emperor (the Retired Emperor Takakura).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Shin-in (newer ex-emperor)→the new Retired Emperor、およびEx-emperor Takakura→the Retired Emperor Takakuraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>御厩別当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mimaya-Betto (chief of Umaya-no-tsukasa, ministry of stable)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mimaya-Betto (chief of Umaya-no-tsukasa, ministry of stable)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mimaya Betto (chief of Umaya no tsukasa, ministry of stable).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、上記に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="71">
<j>治承5年のち改元して養和元年（1181年）（30歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1181 (30 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1181 (30 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1181 (30 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>2月左兵衛督を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February, へresigned as Sahyonoe-no-kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, he resigned as Sahyonoe-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>wording, Japanese 入力ミス</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February: He resigned as Sahyoe no kami.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Sahyoe no kamiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>3月26日参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 26, he was appointed to a councilor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 26, he was appointed to the position of councilor.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 26: He was appointed to the position of Sangi (Royal Advisors).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「参議」→Sangi (Royal Advisors)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>左兵衛督に復任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reappointed to Sahyonoe-no-kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was reappointed to Sahyonoe-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was reappointed to Sahyoe no kami.</e>
<cmt>Sahyoe no kamiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="75">
<j>9月23日参議を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 23, he resigned as a councilor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 23, he resigned from the position of councilor.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 23: He resigned from the position of Sangi.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、Sangiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="76">
<j>養和2年のち改元して寿永元年（1182年）（31歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1182 (31 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1182 (31 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1182 (31 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>3月8日左兵衛督を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigned as Sahyonoe-no-kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned as from the position of Sahyonoe-no-kami.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned as from the position of Sahyoe no kami.</e>
<cmt>Sahyoe no kamiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>10月3日権中納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 3, the supernumerary second-ranked councilor of state</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 3, he became the supernumerary second-ranked councilor of state.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 3: He became Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正、「権中納言」の表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>10月6日帯剣を許される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 6, he allowed wearing a sword</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 6, he was allowed to wear a sword.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 6: He was allowed to wear a sword.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>11月23日従二位（建礼門院御給）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November, Junii (Kenreimonin, to be given)</e>
<cmt>「御給 = to be given」の意味が確認できず、そのまま表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, he was granted the rank of Junii (Kenreimonin, to be given).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November: He was granted the rank of Junii (Kenreimonin, to be given).</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="81">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）（32歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1183 (32 years old)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1183 (32 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1183 (32 years old)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>8月6日解官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 6, removal from office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 6, he was removed from office.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 6: He was removed from office.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Non-stop24(id:10471), Nnh(id:474), 茂雄(id:53805), Cprobot(id:97843), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), Eskimbot(id:29676), Petrusbarbygere(id:25578), 三浦大輔(id:93377), Yanahan(id:2437), 味っ子(id:17086), ふたりはGoki鰤MaxHeart(id:19635), Andee(id:20421), Ash Crow(id:26765), Martin(id:6394), 小者(id:172526), Zwobot(id:23873), Kurz(id:1601), Enosi(id:19649), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Azusayumi7(id:21082), ゐ(id:795), 代言人(id:33675), 海衛士(id:19229), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), Nekosuki600(id:21263), Klesha(id:203751), Kouko0515(id:100370), Louperibot(id:128971), シェーラ(id:17988), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>