<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利藤氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujiuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiuji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利 藤氏（あしかが ふじうじ、生年不詳 - 永禄9年（1566年））は戦国時代 (日本)の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujiuji ASHIKAGA (year of birth unknown - 1566) was a person in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiuji ASHIKAGA (year of birth unknown - 1566) was a person in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiuji ASHIKAGA (year of birth unknown - 1566) was a person in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>古河公方（在位：1561年？ - 1562年？）として擁立され、当時の関白にもその地位を承認されているが、現代においては歴代公方には数えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was put up as Kogakubo (descendants of one of the Ashikaga families that held the office of the Kanto district administrator) (reign: 1561? - 1562?) and its position was approved by Kanpaku of that time but at the present day he is not included among the successive kubos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to become Kogakubo (descendants of one of the Ashikaga families that held the office of the Kanto district administrator) (reign: 1561? - 1562?) and its position was approved by Kanpaku of that time but at the present day he is not included among the successive kubos.</e>
<cmt>put up asをpromoted to becomeに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to become Kogakubo (descendants of one of the Ashikaga families that held the office of the Kanto district administrator) (reign: 1561? - 1562?) and its position was approved by Kanpaku of that time but at the present day he is not included among the successive kubos.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>父は足利晴氏、母は簗田高助の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Haruuji ASHIKAGA and his mother was a daughter of Takasuke YANADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Haruuji ASHIKAGA and his mother was a daughter of Takasuke YANADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Haruuji ASHIKAGA and his mother was a daughter of Takasuke YANADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>弟に足利家国、足利藤政、足利輝氏、足利義氏 (古河公方)（このうち義氏は異母弟）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His brothers were Iekuni ASHIKAGA, Fujimasa ASHIKAGA, Teruuji ASHIKAGA, Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (Kogakubo) (Among them, Yoshiuji was younger paternal brother).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brothers were Iekuni ASHIKAGA, Fujimasa ASHIKAGA, Teruuji ASHIKAGA, Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (Kogakubo) (Among them, Yoshiuji was a half brother with the same mother).</e>
<cmt>his brothersをhis younger brothersに訂正しました。　younger paternal brotherをhalf brotherに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brothers were Iekuni ASHIKAGA, Fujimasa ASHIKAGA, Teruuji ASHIKAGA, Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (Kogakubo) (Among them, Yoshiuji was a half brother with the same mother).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幼名は幸千代王丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Yukichiyo-omaru.</e>
<cmt>「幸千代王丸」は読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Yukichiyo-omaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Yukichiyo-omaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>本来は古河公方の正統な後継者の立場だったが、晴氏の側室である北条氏の娘に足利義氏が産まれたため、義氏を当主にしたい北条氏により迫害を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, he was in the position of legitimate successor of Kogakubo, but a daughter of the Hojo clan who was a concubine of Haruuji had Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA and as a result he was persecuted by the Hojo clan who wanted Yoshiuji to be the head of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, he was the legitimate successor of Kogakubo, but a daughter of the Hojo clan, who was a concubine of Haruuji, gave birth to Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, and as a result he was persecuted by the Hojo clan who wanted Yoshiuji to be the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>in the position ofを省略。  had Yoshiuji ASHIKAGAをgave birth to Yoshiujiに訂正しました。 　　　,をwhoの前とHaruujiの後、and as a resultの前に追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, he was the legitimate successor of Kogakubo, but a daughter of the Hojo clan, who was a concubine of Haruuji, gave birth to Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, and as a result he was persecuted by the Hojo clan who wanted Yoshiuji to be the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>越後の守護で関東管領でもあった上杉謙信の助力により足利義氏を追放し古河御所に入ることができ一時期古河公方となった（歴代には数えず）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By assistance of Kenshin UESUGI who was Shugo (provincial constable) of Echigo and Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), he was able to expel Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA to enter Kogagosho and he became Kogakubo for a period of time (he was not included among the successive kubos).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With assistance of Kenshin UESUGI who was Shugo (provincial constable) of Echigo and Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), he was able to expel Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, which enabled him to enter Koga Imperial Palace and become Kogakubo for a period of time (he was not included among the successive kubos).</e>
<cmt>by assistanceをwith assistanceに訂正しました。　to expel Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA to enter Kogagosho and he became Kogakuboを to expel Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, which enabled him to enter Koga Imperial Palace and become Kogakuboに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With assistance of Kenshin UESUGI who was Shugo (provincial constable) of Echigo and Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), he was able to expel Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, which enabled him to enter Koga Imperial Palace and become Kogakubo for a period of time (he was not included among the successive kubos).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、上杉軍が関東から引き上げると、後北条氏が再び攻撃を始め、古河御所の陥落以後、消息がわからなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the Uesugi army pull out of Kanto region, then the Gohojo clan launched an attack again and he disappeared after the fall of Kogagosho (residence of Kogakubo).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the Uesugi army withdrew from Kanto region, the Gohojo clan launched an attack again and he disappeared after the fall of Kogagosho (residence of Kogakubo).</e>
<cmt>pull out ofを withdrew fromに訂正しました。　　thenを省略しました。　KogagoshoをKoga Imperial Palaceに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the Uesugi army withdrew from Kanto region, the Gohojo clan launched an attack again and he disappeared after the fall of Kogagosho (residence of Kogakubo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、越相同盟にて謙信が義氏の古河公方就任を認めたため、歴代から完全に除外されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Kenshin approved Yoshiuji to assume office as Kogakubo through the Etsu-So Alliance (the Echigo and Sagami alliance) and as a result Fujiuji was completely excluded from the successive kubos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Kenshin approved Yoshiuji to assume office as Kogakubo under the Etsu-So Alliance (the Echigo and Sagami alliance) and as a result Fujiuji was completely excluded from the successive kubos.</e>
<cmt>throughをunderに変換しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Kenshin approved Yoshiuji to assume office as Kogakubo under the Etsu-So Alliance (the Echigo and Sagami alliance) and as a result Fujiuji was completely excluded from the successive kubos.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>藤氏は足利晴氏の長男であり、13代将軍足利義藤（後の義輝）の一字を名乗っている事からでも明らかなように、京都の室町幕府からも認められた次代古河公方であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujiuji was the first son of Haruuji ASHIKAGA and, as apparent from the fact that one character of his name was taken from 13th shogun Yoshifuji (later Yoshiteru) ASHIKAGA, he was the next generation of Kogakubo approved by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujiuji was the first son of Haruuji ASHIKAGA and, as apparent from the fact that one character of his name was taken from 13th shogun Yoshifuji (later Yoshiteru) ASHIKAGA, he was the next generation of Kogakubo approved by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujiuji was the first son of Haruuji ASHIKAGA and, as apparent from the fact that one character of his name was taken from 13th shogun Yoshifuji (later Yoshiteru) ASHIKAGA, he was the next generation of Kogakubo approved by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>祖父・簗田高助は家中の親北条派の中心として、晴氏の後添えの正室に北条氏綱の娘・芳春院 (曖昧さ回避)を迎え入れるように尽力した実力者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandfather Takasuke YANADA was a person of influence, as the key figure in pro-Hojo group in the family, who worked hard to marry Hoshunin (disambiguation) who was a daughter of Ujitsuna HOJO off to Haruuji as second lawful wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather Takasuke YANADA was the key figure in pro-Hojo group in the family, who worked hard to welcome a daughter of Ujitsuna HOJO, Hoshunin (disambiguation) as Haruuji&apos;s second lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>グラマーに問題がありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather Takasuke YANADA was the key figure in pro-Hojo group in the family, who worked hard to welcome a daughter of Ujitsuna HOJO, Hoshunin (disambiguation) as Haruuji&apos;s second lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>ところが、次第に晴氏と北条氏の関係が悪化していき、ついには河越夜戦で北条氏康と戦って敗北してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the relationship between Haruuji and the Hojo clan was gradually deteriorated and finally Haruuji fought against Ujiyasu HOJO in the night battle of Kawagoe and he was defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the relationship between Haruuji and the Hojo clan was gradually deteriorated and finally Haruuji fought against Ujiyasu HOJO in the night battle of Kawagoe and he was defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the relationship between Haruuji and the Hojo clan was gradually deteriorated and finally Haruuji fought against Ujiyasu HOJO in the night battle of Kawagoe and he was defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、北条氏康の圧迫で晴氏は隠退させられて、藤氏の庶弟にあたる足利義氏（芳春院の子）が次の古河公方に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Haruuji was forced to be retired under pressure from Ujiyasu HOJO and Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (child of Hoshunin) who was younger paternal brother of Fujiuji was put up as the next Kogakubo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Haruuji was forced to retire under pressure from Ujiyasu HOJO, and Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (child of Hoshunin), who was a younger brother-in-law of Fujiuji, was promoted to become the next Kogakubo.</e>
<cmt>be retireをretireに訂正しました。　  who was younger paternal brother of Fujiuji was put up as the next Kogakuboを,who was a younger brother-in-law of Fujiuji, was promoted to become the next Kogakuboに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Haruuji was forced to retire under pressure from Ujiyasu HOJO, and Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (child of Hoshunin), who was a younger brother-in-law of Fujiuji, was promoted to become the next Kogakubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>弘治 (日本)3年（1557年）、藤氏は挙兵して古河城奪還を試みるが失敗し、晴氏は幽閉され、藤氏も追放されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1557, Fujiuji raised an army and tried to recover Koga-jo Castle but failed, then Haruuji was confined and Fujiuji was expelled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1557, after Fujiuji&apos;s attempt to raise an army in order to take back Koga-jo Castle was failed, Haruuji was confined and Fujiuji was expeled.</e>
<cmt>全体の文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1557, after Fujiuji&apos;s attempt to raise an army in order to take back Koga-jo Castle was failed, Haruuji was confined and Fujiuji was expeled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>それでも、藤氏は簗田晴助（高助の子）や安房国の里見義堯を頼って再起の機会を窺った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Still, Fujiuji depended on Harusuke YANADA (child of Takasuke) and Yoshitaka SATOMI in Awa Province and watched for a chance to make a comeback..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even then, Fujiuji waited for a chance to make a comeback by relying on Harusuke YANADA (child of Takasuke) and Yoshitaka SATOMI in Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>グラマーに問題がありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even then, Fujiuji waited for a chance to make a comeback by relying on Harusuke YANADA (child of Takasuke) and Yoshitaka SATOMI in Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>晴助らは越後に滞在中の関東管領上杉憲政と彼を助けていた上杉謙信（後の上杉謙信）に藤氏救援を依頼した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harusuke and others asked Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) Norimasa UESUGI who stayed in Echigo and Kenshin UESUGI (later Kenshin UESUGI) who helped Norimasa UESUGI to rescue Fujiuji.</e>
<cmt>「上杉謙信（後の上杉謙信）」は、「長尾景虎（後の上杉謙信）」の誤りと思われますが、原文通り訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harusuke and others asked Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) Norimasa UESUGI who stayed in Echigo and Kenshin UESUGI (later Kenshin UESUGI) who helped Norimasa UESUGI to rescue Fujiuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harusuke and others asked Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) Norimasa UESUGI who stayed in Echigo and Kenshin UESUGI (later Kenshin UESUGI) who helped Norimasa UESUGI to rescue Fujiuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>藤氏救援と北条討伐のため、永禄4年（1561年）、関東管領上杉憲政・関白近衛前久を擁して10万余の大軍で関東に出兵した長尾景虎は小田原城の完全攻略には失敗したものの、古河御所は完全に制圧し、御所に籠る北条氏傀儡の足利義氏を追放する（代って藤氏が古河に入った）など、関東の大半を制した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To rescue Fujiuji and put down the Hojo clan, in 1561, Kagetora NAGAO who sent a large force of over hundred thousand soldiers to Kanto region having Kanto Kanrei Norimasa UESUGI and Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) Sakihisa KONOE as the leader failed to completely capture Odawara-jo Castle, but he completely conquered Kogagosho and banished Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, a puppet of the Hojo clan who was holed up in gosho (instead, Fujiuji entered Koga) and finally ruled over much of Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1561, although Kagetora NAGAO&apos;s attempt to fully conquer Odawara-jo Castle in order to rescue Fujiuji and put down the Hojo clan by sending a large force of over hundred thousand soldiers including Kanto Kanrei Norimasa UESUGI and Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) Sakihisa KONOE to Kanto region was unsuccessful, he brought most of Kanto region under his control by completely conquering Koga Imperial Palace and banishing a puppet of the Hojo clan Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA who barricaded himself in the Imperial Palace (Fujiuji entered Koga instead).</e>
<cmt>グラマーに問題がありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1561, although Kagetora NAGAO&apos;s attempt to fully conquer Odawara-jo Castle in order to rescue Fujiuji and put down the Hojo clan by sending a large force of over hundred thousand soldiers including Kanto Kanrei Norimasa UESUGI and Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) Sakihisa KONOE to Kanto region was unsuccessful, he brought most of Kanto region under his control by completely conquering Koga Imperial Palace and banishing a puppet of the Hojo clan Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA who barricaded himself in the Imperial Palace (Fujiuji entered Koga instead).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>上杉憲政に代わって、関東管領の本来の職務である古河公方を擁護することに成功した長尾景虎は、上杉憲政から上杉の家督と関東管領の地位を譲られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of Norimasa UESUGI, Kagetora NAGAO successfully protected Kogakubo which was original duty of Kanto Kanrei and he was handed over the estate of the Uesugi family and the position of Kanto Kanrei from Norimasa UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagetora NAGAO was handed over the estate of the Uesugi family as well as the position of Kanto Kanrei from Norimasa UESUGI since he successfully guarded Kogakubo instead of Norimasa UESUGI, which was Kanto Kanrei&apos;s original duty.</e>
<cmt>文の順番を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagetora NAGAO was handed over the estate of the Uesugi family as well as the position of Kanto Kanrei from Norimasa UESUGI since he successfully guarded Kogakubo instead of Norimasa UESUGI, which was Kanto Kanrei&apos;s original duty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>上杉謙信（便宜上、以後は謙信とする）は、上杉憲政・近衛前久らと相談、義氏の古河公方就任を完全に否定し、関白・関東管領の名において藤氏を足利晴氏（前年死去）の後継として正式に古河公方として任命することを決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI (for convenience, hereafter referred to as Kenshin) consulted with Norimasa UESUGI, Sakihisa KONOE and others and then completely denied Yoshiuji&apos;s assumption of Kogakubo and decided to officially appoint Fujiuji as Kogakubo as a successor of Haruuji ASHIKAGA (who died in the previous year) in the name of Kanpaku and Kanto Kanrei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin UESUGI (for convenience, hereafter referred to as Kenshin) consulted with Norimasa UESUGI, Sakihisa KONOE and others and then completely denied Yoshiuji&apos;s assumption of Kogakubo and decided to officially appoint Fujiuji as Kogakubo as a successor of Haruuji ASHIKAGA (who died in the previous year) in the name of Kanpaku and Kanto Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI (for convenience, hereafter referred to as Kenshin) consulted with Norimasa UESUGI, Sakihisa KONOE and others and then completely denied Yoshiuji&apos;s assumption of Kogakubo and decided to officially appoint Fujiuji as Kogakubo as a successor of Haruuji ASHIKAGA (who died in the previous year) in the name of Kanpaku and Kanto Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>これを佐竹氏・里見氏ら反北条氏の関東諸大名も受け入れたため、数年の間、古河公方は足利藤氏となったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The decision was accepted by anti-Hojo territorial lords in Kanto region such as the Satake clan and the Satomi clan and therefore Fujiuji ASHIKAGA served as Kogakubo for several years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decision was accepted by anti-Hojo territorial lords in Kanto region such as the Satake clan and the Satomi clan, and therefore Fujiuji ASHIKAGA served as Kogakubo for several years.</e>
<cmt>コンマをand thereforeの前に追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The decision was accepted by anti-Hojo territorial lords in Kanto region such as the Satake clan and the Satomi clan, and therefore Fujiuji ASHIKAGA served as Kogakubo for several years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>だが、謙信が藤氏を残し越後に帰国すると、直ちに北条氏康が反撃を開始し、その年の10月には古河を攻撃したので、藤氏は上総国の多賀信家（蔵人・高明、里見氏家臣）の元へ逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Kenshin returned to Echigo with Fujiuji left behind, Ujiyasu HOJO immediately launched a counterattack and attacked Koga in October of the same year, then Fujiuji escaped to Nobuie TAGA (Kurodo, Takaaki, vassal of the Satomi clan) in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Kenshin returned to Echigo without Fujiuji, Ujiyasu HOJO immediately launched a counterattack and attacked Koga in October of the same year, which resulted in Fujiuji escaping to Nobuie TAGA (Kurodo, Takaaki, vassal of the Satomi clan) in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>with Fujiuji left behindを withoutに訂正しました。 then Fujiuji escaped toを,which resulted in Fujiuji escaping toに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Kenshin returned to Echigo without Fujiuji, Ujiyasu HOJO immediately launched a counterattack and attacked Koga in October of the same year, which resulted in Fujiuji escaping to Nobuie TAGA (Kurodo, Takaaki, vassal of the Satomi clan) in Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>その後も古河を巡っては、上杉派と北条派が争奪戦を繰り広げて、その度に藤氏は古河に入ったり上総に脱出したりを繰り返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, as well, the Uesugi group and the Hojo group engaged in a struggle for Koga, and each time Fujiuji repeated the entrance to Koga and the escape to Kazusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after that, the Uesugi group and the Hojo group kept fighting over Koga, and Fujiuji made the entrance to Koga and the escape to Kazusa everytime the fighting occured.</e>
<cmt>文全体を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after that, the Uesugi group and the Hojo group kept fighting over Koga, and Fujiuji made the entrance to Koga and the escape to Kazusa everytime the fighting occured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>だが、永禄5年（1562年）に北条軍が古河御所を攻略した際に藤氏は捕虜となって小田原に送られてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1562 when the Hojo army conquered Kogagosho, Fujiuji was taken prisoner and sent to Odawara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1562 when the Hojo army conquered Koga Imperial Palace, Fujiuji was taken prisoner and sent to Odawara.</e>
<cmt>Kogagoshoを Koga Imperial Palaceに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1562 when the Hojo army conquered Koga Imperial Palace, Fujiuji was taken prisoner and sent to Odawara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>その後、藤氏の身柄は相模国・伊豆国を転々としたとされるが、永禄9年（1566年）以降はその消息が不明になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Fujiuji was said to be transferred from Sagami Province to Izu Province, but he disappeared after 1566.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Fujiuji was said to be transferred from Sagami Province to Izu Province, but he disappeared after 1566.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Fujiuji was said to be transferred from Sagami Province to Izu Province, but he disappeared after 1566.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>北条氏康によって処刑されたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to be executed by Ujiyasu HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to be executed by Ujiyasu HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to be executed by Ujiyasu HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="26">
<j>古河公方・足利藤氏を失った事により、上杉謙信の関東経営は大打撃を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The loss of Kogakubo Fujiuji ASHIKAGA significantly affected administration of Kanto region by Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The loss of Kogakubo Fujiuji ASHIKAGA significantly affected administration of Kanto region by Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The loss of Kogakubo Fujiuji ASHIKAGA significantly affected administration of Kanto region by Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>後に越相同盟が締結された時にも、唯一の古河公方となった足利義氏 (古河公方)を擁立する北条氏康が謙信に対して優位に交渉を進めていくのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when the Etsu-So Alliance (the Echigo and Sagami alliance) was concluded, Ujiyasu HOJO backing up Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (Kogakubo) who was the only Kogakubo took advantage of continuing negotiation with Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even when the Etsu-So Alliance (the Echigo and Sagami alliance) was later formed, Ujiyasu HOJO who was backing up the only Kogakubo Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, carried on negotiation with Kenshin favoring Hojo.</e>
<cmt>concluded をformedに訂正しました。　　 who was the only Kogakubo took advantage of continuing negotiation with Kenshin をwho was backing up the only Kogakubo Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, carried on negotiation with Kenshin favoring Hojoに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even when the Etsu-So Alliance (the Echigo and Sagami alliance) was later formed, Ujiyasu HOJO who was backing up the only Kogakubo Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, carried on negotiation with Kenshin favoring Hojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>一方で、藤氏の弟の家国、藤政、輝氏が古河公方の再興を目指し活動した形跡も確認されているが、その影響力は微々たるものであり、天正年間を境にその活動はみられなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there were signs that Fujiuji&apos;s younger brothers Iekuni, Fujimasa and Teruuji took action with the aim of restoration of Kogakubo, but their influence was negligible and their activities were not seen around Tensho era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there were signs that Fujiuji&apos;s younger brothers Iekuni, Fujimasa and Teruuji took action for the restoration of Kogakubo, but their influence was very small and their activities were not seen around Tensho era.</e>
<cmt>took action with the aim of restoration をtook action for the restoration ofに訂正しました。　  negligible をvery smallに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there were signs that Fujiuji&apos;s younger brothers Iekuni, Fujimasa and Teruuji took action for the restoration of Kogakubo, but their influence was very small and their activities were not seen around Tensho era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 模様砂漠(id:254067), やりたこ(id:113528), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 水野白楓(id:22811), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Nalc(id:139567), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>