<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平時継</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitsugu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tokitsugu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitsugu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 時継（たいら の ときつぐ、貞応元年（1222年）－永仁2年7月10日 (旧暦)（1294年8月2日））は、鎌倉時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitsugu (1222-August 2, 1294) was a court noble in the middle of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tokitsugu (1222 - August 2, 1294) was a court noble during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitsugu (1222 - August 9, 1294) was a court noble during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>正二位権大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonii Gon Dainagon (Senior Second Rank, Provisional Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the rank of Shonii Gon Dainagon (Senior Second Rank, Provisional Chief Councilor).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the rank of Shonii Gon Dainagon (Senior Second Rank, Provisional Chief Councilor of State).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>参議平有親の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a child of Sangi (councilor), TAIRA no Arichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of Sangi (councilor) TAIRA no Arichika.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of Sangi (councilor) TAIRA no Arichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正室は修理大夫高階経雅の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs), TAKASHINA no Tsunemasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was the daughter of Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs) TAKASHINA no Tsunemasa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was the daughter of Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs) TAKASHINA no Tsunemasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に平忠世・平経親がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadatsugu and TAIRA no Tsunechika were his children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tadatsugu and TAIRA no Tsunechika were his children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadatsugu and TAIRA no Tsunechika were his children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>建長4年（1252年）に蔵人頭となり、治部卿・宮内卿などを歴任後、建長7年（1255年）に参議となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1252, he became a Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), and became a Sangi (councilor) in 1225 after successively holding posts such as jibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) and Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1252, Tokitsugu became a Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), and then became a Sangi (councilor) in 1255 after successively holding posts such as Jibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) and Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>rewording;correct date</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1252, Tokitsugu became a Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), and then became a Sangi (councilor) in 1255 after successively holding posts such as Jibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) and Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>正嘉元年（1257年）に正三位に叙され、文永3年（1266年）に正二位に叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1257, he was appointed to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), and was appointed to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1266.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1257 and then to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1266.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 1257 and then to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1266.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>文永6年（1269年）に権中納言となるが同年中に辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1269, he became a Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), but resigned within the same year.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1269, he became a Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), but resigned within the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1269, he became a Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state), but resigned within the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>亀山天皇への譲位後、不遇であった後深草天皇に仕えた数少ない側近であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of few close advisers who served Emperor Gofukakusa during the period of time when the emperor was unfortunate after abdicating the throne to Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of few close advisors who served Emperor Gofukakusa during a period of misfortune which continued after relinquishing of the throne to Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of few close advisors who served Emperor Gofukakusa during a period of misfortune which continued after relinquishing of the throne to Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>弘安10年（1287年）の伏見天皇の即位に伴う後深草上皇院政開始によって一躍院近臣の筆頭として院執権、伝奏、評定衆を歴任、正応2年（1289年）には彼の家系では異例の権大納言に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the commencement of the Cloister government by the retired Emperor Gofukakusa owing to the Emperor Fushimi&apos;s accession to the throne in 1287, he held posts such as innoshikken (regent of the cloister government), denso (job title to relay messages of court&apos;s people to Emperor), hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) as the head of In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier), and he was promoted to Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) in 1289, which was unusual for his family line.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the commencement of the Cloister government by the retired Emperor Gofukakusa, which followed the accession of Emperor Fushimi to the throne in 1287, Tokitsugu was able to hold posts such as Innoshikken (Regent of the Cloister Government), Denso (message courier between the court&apos;s people and the Emperor), Hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) as the head of In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier), and he was promoted to Gon Dainagon (Provisional Chief Councilor) in 1289, which was unusual for his family line.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the commencement of the Cloister government by the Retired Emperor Gofukakusa, which followed the accession of Emperor Fushimi to the throne in 1287, Tokitsugu was able to hold posts such as Innoshikken (Regent of the Cloister Government), Denso (message courier between the court&apos;s people and the Emperor), Hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) as the head of In no Kinshin (the Retired Emperor&apos;s courtier), and he was promoted to Gon Dainagon (Provisional Chief Councilor of State) in 1289, which was unusual for his family line.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>翌年2月11日、辞任して出家する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 11, in the following year, he resigned and became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 11 of the following year, Tokitsugu resigned from his post and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 20 of the following year, Tokitsugu resigned from his post and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>