<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平公雅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Kinmasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Kinmasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Kinmasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 公雅（たいら の きんまさ、生没年不詳）は、平安時代中期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Kinmasa (date of birth and death unknown) is a busho (Japanese military commander) in mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Kinmasa (date of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>過去の事実なので過去形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Kinmasa (date of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) during mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>in→during</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平公正、平公雄、平忠望も同一人物とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Kinmasa, TAIRA no Kino, and TAIRA no Tadamochi are said to be the same person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Kinmasa, TAIRA no Kino, and TAIRA no Tadamochi are said to be the same person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Kinmasa (with different characters, 平公正), TAIRA no Kimio, and TAIRA no Tadamochi are all said to be the same person.</e>
<cmt>all を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>平良兼の長子で、弟に平公連、平公元らがあり、子に平致秋、平致成、平致頼らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the eldest son of TAIRA no Yoshikane, his younger brother was TAIRA no Kintsura and his children were TAIRA no Tomonari, TAIRA no Tomonari, and TAIRA no Muneyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of TAIRA no Yoshikane, his younger brother was TAIRA no Kintsura and his children were TAIRA no Muneaki, TAIRA no Munenari, and TAIRA no Muneyori.</e>
<cmt>過去の事実なので過去形にし、平致秋をTAIRA no Muneaki、平致成をTAIRA no Munenariにしました。調べても「致」を「とも」と読ませる例を見つけられませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of TAIRA no Yoshikane, his younger brother was TAIRA no Kintsura and his children were TAIRA no Muneaki, TAIRA no Munenari, and TAIRA no Muneyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>安房守、武蔵守、右衛門少尉、従四位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Awa no kami (Governor of Awa province), Musashi no kami (Governor of Musashi province), Uemon no shojo, and Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Awa no kami (Governor of Awa province), Musashi no kami (Governor of Musashi province), Uemon no shojo, and Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Awa no kami (Governor of Awa province), Musashi no kami (Governor of Musashi province), Uemon no shojo, and Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>父良兼らが従兄弟の、平将門と度々争い、勝利して将門の妻子を捕らえ上総に拉致すると、弟の公連と共にこれを将門の許に逃がしたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Yoshikane often fought with his cousin TAIRA no Masakado, and won, captured Masakado&apos;s wife and children, and abducted them to Shimousa province who were escaped to be with Masakado by TAIRA no Kinmasa and his brother Kintsura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Yoshikane often fought with his cousin TAIRA no Masakado, and when he beat Masakado and captured and abducted Masakado&apos;s wife and children to Shimousa province, Kinmasa and his elder brother Kintsura let them go to Masakado.</e>
<cmt>who were escapedの前後関係が不明だったので、変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Yoshikane often fought with his cousin TAIRA no Masakado, and when he beat Masakado and captured and abducted Masakado&apos;s wife and children to Shimousa province, Kinmasa and his elder brother Kintsura let them go to Masakado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>承平7年（937年）に将門の訴状により朝廷から下された追捕の官符で父らと共に対象になっている為、この頃は父と共に将門と争っていたと見られるが、天慶2年（939年）6月に父が病死すると、将門と対立する平貞盛らとは距離を置いて中立的立場になったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was summoned along with his father under &quot;the search and capture kanpu&quot; that was issued according to Kadomasa&apos;s complaint, they are said to have been on bad terms with Masakado, however, when the father died in June 939, he became neutral by keeping his distance from TAIRA no Sadamori who was in conflict with Masakado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he and his father were to be searched and caputured on the order of Kanpu, the official document issued by the Imperial court according to Kadomasa&apos;s complaint, they seem to have had a fight with Masakado frequently, however, when the father died in June 939, he became neutral by keeping his distance from TAIRA no Sadamori, who was in conflict with Masakado.</e>
<cmt>「追捕」とsummonedでは少し意味が違うように思ったのでbe to searched and captured「追捕されることになっている」とし、又TAIRA no Sadamoriは固有名詞のためカンマを加え非制限用法の関係詞にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he and his father were to be searched and caputured on the order of Kanpu, the official document issued by the Imperial court according to Kadomasa&apos;s complaint, they seem to have had a fight with Masakado frequently, however, when the father died in June 939, he became neutral by keeping his distance from TAIRA no Sadamori, who was in conflict with Masakado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>12月に将門が「新皇」を自称し叛乱をおこすと、翌天慶3年（940年）1月14日、将門の牽制の為に任命された8人（坂東8ヶ国）の東国国司の一人となり、将門の乱の鎮圧後に安房国国司となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masakado called himself the &apos;new emperor&apos; in December and caused a insurrection, he became one of the eight Kokushi (provincial governor) of Togoku (the eastern part of Japan) who were assigned to divert Masakado, and after the Taira no Masakado Rebellion was suppressed, he became the Kokushi of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masakado called himself the &apos;new emperor&apos; and caused a insurrection in January, on February 29, 940 Kinmasa became one of the eight Kokushi (provincial governor) of Togoku (the eastern part of Japan) who were assigned to divert Masakado, and after the Taira no Masakado Rebellion was suppressed, he became the Kokushi of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>日付の訳抜けだったので加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masakado called himself the &apos;new emperor&apos; and caused a insurrection in January, on February 29, 940 Kinmasa became one of the eight Kokushi (provincial governor) of Togoku (the eastern part of Japan) who were assigned to divert Masakado, and after the Taira no Masakado Rebellion was suppressed, he became the Kokushi of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>天慶5年（942年）藤原秀郷の後任として武蔵国守となり、将門の乱によって荒廃していた武蔵国・金龍山浅草寺を再建したことで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 942, he became Musashi no kuni no kami as a successor of FUJIWARA no Hidesato and he is known to have re-build Senso-ji Temple, Kinryuzan in Musashi Province which was devastated by the Taira no Masakado Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 942, he became the Governor of Musashi Province as a successor of FUJIWARA no Hidesato and he is known to have rebuilt Kinryuzan Senso-ji Temple in Musashi Province, which was devastated by the Taira no Masakado Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>武蔵国守は、ローマ字より英訳してある方が分かりやすいと思い変えました。またhave re-build は have rebuiltが正しいと思い変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 942, he became the Governor of Musashi Province as a successor of FUJIWARA no Hidesato and he is known to have rebuilt Kinryuzan Senso-ji Temple in Musashi Province, which was devastated by the Taira no Masakado Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>また、天慶八年（945年）の3月18日に公雅の枕元に観音様が立ち「この沖合に生ずる青、赤、黒三通りの海草を食すれば、無病開運、来世は必ず仏果を得べし。」と告げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there is a legend that says on March 18, 945, kannonsama stood by Kinmasa&apos;s bed who said &apos;if you eat the blue, red, and black seaweeds available off this island, you will be healthy, fortunate, and earn Buddha hood in after life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it is said that on March 18, 945, Kannon (Deity of Mercy) stood by Kinmasa&apos;s bed and said &apos;if you eat the blue, red, and black seaweeds available off this island, you will be healthy, fortunate, and earn Buddhahood in after life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理内容も修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it is said that on March 18, 945, Kannon (Deity of Mercy) stood by Kinmasa&apos;s bed and said &apos;if you eat the blue, red, and black seaweeds available off this island, you will be healthy, fortunate, and earn Buddhahood in after life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>よって、教えの通りにそれらの海草を集めて食してみたところ、非常に美味しくて体にも良いことから「観音様の法（のり、教え）だから『アサクサノリ』だ」と評判になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So Kinmasa gathered, ate those seaweeds, and said &apos;it is a teaching by kannonsama so it is &quot;Asakusa nori&quot; (Porphyra tenera)&apos; since they were tasty and healthy.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So after Kinmasa gathered and ate those seaweeds, he found that they were tasty and healthy so he said &apos;it is a teaching (which is pronounced in Japanese as &apos;nori&apos;) by kannon so it should be called &quot;Asakusa nori&quot; (Porphyra tenera).&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理内容も修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So after Kinmasa gathered and ate those seaweeds, he found that they were tasty and healthy so he said &apos;it is a teaching (which is pronounced in Japanese as &apos;nori&apos;) by kannon so it should be called &quot;Asakusa nori&quot; (Porphyra tenera).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このような伝説も知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legend such as this is well-known.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理内容も修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legend such as this is well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Masyu(id:31065), 味っ子(id:17086), 伏儀(id:142093), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>