<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>マキノ光雄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuo MAKINO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuo MAKINO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuo MAKINO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>マキノ 光雄（-みつお、1909年11月15日 - 1957年12月9日）は、日本の映画プロデューサーである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuo MAKINO (November 15, 1909-December 9, 1957) was a movie producer in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuo MAKINO (November 15, 1909-December 9, 1957) was a movie producer in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuo MAKINO (November 15, 1909-December 9, 1957) was a movie producer in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「日本映画の父」として知られる牧野省三の第六子（次男）であるが、母方の姓を継いだので本名は多田 光次郎（ただ みつじろう）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the sixth child (the second son) of Shozo MAKINO which was known as &apos;Father of Japanese cinema&apos; and his real name was Mitsujiro TADA because he succeeded his mother&apos;s family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the sixth child (the second son) of Shozo MAKINO who was known as the &apos;Father of Japanese cinema&apos; and his real name was Mitsujiro TADA because he succeeded his mother&apos;s family name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the sixth child (the second son) of Shozo MAKINO who was known as the &apos;Father of Japanese cinema,&apos; and his real name was Mitsujiro TADA because he succeeded his mother&apos;s family name.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。コンマの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子役時代の芸名は牧野 光次郎、別名として多田 満男、牧野 満男、マキノ 満男がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When acting as a child actor, his actor&apos;s name was Kojiro MAKINO, and he had another names such Mitsuo TADA and Mitsuo MAKINO (牧野満男、マキノ満男)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When acting as a child actor, he went by the name of Kojiro MAKINO, and he had another names such Mitsuo TADA and Mitsuo MAKINO (牧野満男、マキノ満男)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a child actor, he went by the name of Kojiro MAKINO, and he had another names such as Mitsuo TADA and Mitsuo MAKINO.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父の没後のマキノ・プロダクション御室撮影所総務部長、日活撮影所製作部次長、同多摩川撮影所企画部長、満洲映画協会娯楽映画部長、東映東京撮影所長、同社専務取締役製作部長を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father&apos;s death, he continued to take the post of the general manager of the general affairs department of Makino Production Omuro Movie Studio, the assistant general manager of the production department of Nikkatsu Studio, the general manager of the planning department of the Nikkatsu Tamagawa Movie Studio, the general manager of the entertainment movie department of Manchuria Film Association, the head of Toei Movie Studios and the senior managing director and general manager of the production department of Toei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his father&apos;s death, he continued in the post of general manager of the general affairs department of Makino Production Omuro Movie Studio, assistant general manager of the production department of Nikkatsu Studio, general manager of the planning department of the Nikkatsu Tamagawa Movie Studio, general manager of the entertainment movie department of Manchuria Film Association, head of Toei Movie Studios and senior managing director and general manager of the production department of Toei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father&apos;s death, he continued in the positions of general manager of the general affairs department of Makino Production Omuro Movie Studio, assistant general manager of the production department of Nikkatsu Studio, general manager of the planning department of the Nikkatsu Tamagawa Movie Studio, general manager of the entertainment movie department of Manchuria Film Association, head of Toei Movie Studios and senior managing director and general manager of the production department of Toei.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>来歴・人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical trail and profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical trail and profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography and Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>英語としてより自然な表現にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>1909年（明治42年）11月15日、京都市西陣に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born on November 15, 1909 in Nishijin Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born on November 15, 1909 in Nishijin Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born on November 15, 1909 in Nishijin, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>多田姓は母方の姓である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family name, Tada, is his mother&apos;s family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family name, Tada, is his mother&apos;s family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family name, Tada, is the family name of his mother&apos;s parents&apos; house.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子供の頃から父の映画に子役として「牧野光次郎」名義で出演、映画業界の息吹の中で成長する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had appeared in his father&apos;s movies as a child actor using a name &apos;Mitsujiro MAKINO&apos; since his childhood and grew in the changing cinema industry.</e>
<cmt>”息吹”の意味が定かでなかったので、変化するという訳にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had appeared in his father&apos;s movies as a child actor using the name &apos;Mitsujiro MAKINO&apos; since his childhood and grew in the changing cinema industry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had appeared in his father&apos;s movies as a child actor by the name &apos;Mitsujiro MAKINO&apos; since his childhood, and grew in the changing cinema industry.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1921年（大正10年）に同志社高等学校に入学するとラグビーに熱中する傍らキリスト教に入信。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he entered Doshisha High School in 1921, he became interested in playing rugby and got to believe in Christianity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he entered Doshisha High School in 1921, he became interested in playing rugby and became a Christian.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he entered Doshisha High School in 1921, he became a Christian while getting involved in rugby.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>一方で、放蕩を尽くし中学卒業前日に退学させられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other side, he lived a dissipated life and was kicked out of school on a day just before graduation of the junior high school.</e>
<cmt>時系列からすると、”高校卒業前日”の間違いかと思いますが、日本語どおりに英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other side, he lived a dissipated life and was kicked out of school on the day just before graduating from junior high school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he led a dissipated life and was dismissed from school on the day just before graduating from junior high school.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1927年（昭和2年）に勉強の名目で東京へ出るが、都内の映画館にかかるマキノ・プロダクションの映画の歩合金を横取りして飲み遊ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left for Tokyo under the guise of studying in 1927, but he picked up the commissions related to Makino Production&apos;s movies at movie theaters in Tokyo and spent the money for alcohol and his pleasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left for Tokyo under the guise of studying in 1927, but he picked up his commissions related to movies being shown in Tokyo movie theaters from Makino Production&apos;s and spent the money for alcohol and his pleasure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left for Tokyo under the guise of studying in 1927, but he embezzled his commissions related to movies being shown in Tokyo movie theaters from Makino Production&apos;s and spent the money for alcohol and his pleasure.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>厳格だが愛情深い省三はこれを怒らず、京都に戻った光雄を御室撮影所に毎日連れていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shozo was a strict and loving father, and after he was back to Kyoto, his father did not get upset at him and took Mitsuo to Omuro Movie Studio every day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shozo was a strict and loving father, and after he returned to Kyoto, his father was not upset with him and he took Mitsuo to the Omuro Movie Studio every day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozo was a strict and loving father, even after Mitsuo returned to Kyoto, his father was not upset with him and he took Mitsuo to the Omuro Movie Studio every day.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）の本宅の焼失、スターの大量退社に揺れるマキノプロで逆境に燃えた光雄の兄・弱冠20歳のマキノ雅弘は、山上伊太郎と時代劇の傑作『浪人街』を生むが、翌年の1929年（昭和4年）7月25日、省三が亡くなるとマキノプロの経営は困難になり1930年（昭和5年）に年末給料不払で争議が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Mitsuo&apos;s older brother, Masahiro MAKINO was as young as the age of twenty, to overcome the adverse situations such as the loss of his family&apos;s house by fire in 1928 and the quit of many actors and actresses from Makino Production, he produced a masterpiece of period drama &quot;Roningai&quot;(Ronin Town) with Itaro YAMAGAMI, but upon Shozo&apos;s death on July 25, 1929 the next year, the operation of Makino Production became difficult and there occurred a conflict about the non-payment of salaries at the end of 1930.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Mitsuo&apos;s older brother, Masahiro MAKINO was as young as twenty, to overcome adverse situations such as the loss of his family&apos;s house in a fire in 1928 and the loss of many actors and actresses who quit Makino Productions, he produced a masterpiece of period drama &quot;Roningai&quot; (Ronin Town) with Itaro YAMAGAMI, but upon Shozo&apos;s death on July 25, 1929 the next year, it became difficult to continue operations of Makino Productions and there was a conflict about the non-payment of salaries at the end of 1930.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Mitsuo&apos;s older brother Masahiro MAKINO was as young as twenty to overcome adverse situations such as the loss of his family&apos;s house in a fire in 1928 and the loss of many actors and actresses who quit Makino Productions, he produced a masterpiece of period drama &quot;Roningai&quot; with Itaro YAMAGAMI, but upon Shozo&apos;s death on July 25, 1929 the next year, it became difficult to continue the operation of Makino Productions and there was a conflict about the non-payment of salaries at the end of 1930.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この後、光雄は正博の反対を押して支援者を募ろうと上京し、逆に散財する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he left for Tokyo to seek support from other people in spite of Masahiro&apos;s objection, but on the contrary, he threw his money away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he left for Tokyo to seek support from other people in spite of Masahiro&apos;s objections, but he ended up just throwing his money away.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he left for Tokyo to seek support from other people in spite of Masahiro&apos;s objections, but he just threw his money away.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>結果、失敗するが正博はこれを叱らずに「光雄はいい勉強をした」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, Masahiro did not blame him for his failure and said &quot;Mitsuo had a good lesson.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all this, Masahiro did not blame him for his failure and said &quot;Mitsuo had a good lesson.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all, Masahiro did not blame him for his failure and said &apos;Mitsuo had a good lesson.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>正映マキノキネマで巻き返そうとした兄・正博は1932年（昭和7年）御室撮影所の焼失で全てを失い、マキノ一党を率いて日活に入社した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although his brother Masahiro attempted to take a chance to be successful in Shoei Makino Cinema, he lost everything from the fire of Omuro Movie Studio in 1932, and joined Nikkatsu Corporation with other people from Makino families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his brother Masahiro attempted to take a chance and become successful in Shoei Makino Cinema, he lost everything from the fire of Omuro Movie Studio in 1932, and joined Nikkatsu Corporation with other people from the Makino families.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his brother Masahiro attempted to take a chance and become successful in Shoei Makino Cinema, he lost everything from the fire of the Omuro Movie Studio in 1932, and joined Nikkatsu Corporation with other people from the Makino families.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>光雄は現代劇の製作に携わり、製作部次長となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There, he was involved in the production of period dramas and took the post of the assistance general manager of the production department.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There, he was involved in the production of period dramas and took the post of assistant general manager of the production department.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There, he was involved in the production of period dramas and took the position of assistant general manager of the production department.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1934年（昭和9年）に多摩川撮影所（のちの角川大映撮影所）に移るが翌年、根岸寛一が同撮影所長となると企画部長として活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1934 he was relocated to Nikkatsu Tama-gawa Studio, and with Kanichi NEGISHI assigned to a new head of the studio in the following year, he was working hard at the post of the general manager of the planning department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1934 he was relocated to the Nikkatsu Tama-gawa Studio, and together with Kanichi NEGISHI, was assigned as the new head of the studio in the following year, he was working hard at the post of the general manager of the planning department.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1934 he was relocated to the Nikkatsu Tamagawa Studio, and together with Kanichi NEGISHI, who was assigned as the new head of the studio in the following year, he was working hard at the position of the general manager of the planning department.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>1938年(昭和13年)に元宝塚の星玲子を主演女優として使ったことが縁で結婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He hired a former Takarazuka star, Reiko HOSHI for a leading star in his movie in 1938 and got married with her.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He hired a former Takarazuka star, Reiko HOSHI as the leading star in his movie in 1938 and married her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He hired a former Takarazuka star Reiko HOSHI as the leading star in his movie in 1938, and married her.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この年、森田佐吉が多摩川撮影所で根岸を排斥すると、根岸は職を辞し「満洲映画協会」（満映）の理事として大陸に渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, when Negishi was rejected to stay at Nikkatsu Tama-gawa Studio by Sakichi MORITA, he quit the job and left for the Chinese continent to work at &apos;Manchuria Movie Association&apos; (Manei) as a director.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, when Negishi was rejected from Nikkatsu Tama-gawa Studio by Sakichi MORITA, he quit the job and left for the Chinese continent to work at &apos;Manchuria Movie Association&apos; (Manei) as a director.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, when Negishi was rejected from Nikkatsu Tamagawa Studio by Sakichi MORITA, Mitsuo quit the job and left for the Chinese continent to work at &apos;Manchuria Movie Association&apos; (Manei) as a director.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>光雄も6月に根岸を慕って満州に渡り、満映の製作部長として言葉の通じず自然条件も風習も違う異国で苦労を重ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuo left for Manchuria in June following after Negishi with respect, and experienced a lot of hardships in a foreign country where the language, natural conditions and customs were different in the post of the general manager of the production department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuo left for Manchuria in June following Negishi with respect, and experienced a lot of hardship in a foreign country where anguage, natural conditions, and customs were different, he took up the post of general manager of the production department.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuo left for Manchuria in June following Negishi with respect, and took up the position of general manager of the production department, while experiencing a lot of hardship in a foreign country where language, natural conditions, and customs were different.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>李香蘭を満映入りさせ、ただの歌手から主演女優にするのに一役買う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He played an important role to hire Rikoran for Manei and build her up from just a singer to a leading actress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He played an important role in hiring Rikoran for Manei and build her up from just a singer to a leading actress.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He played an important role in hiring Rikoran (Li Xianglan, 李香蘭) for Manei and built her up from just a singer to a leading actress.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>多くの映画をプロデュースし、満映の基礎を築く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He produced many movies, resulting in the construction of the foundation of Manei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He produced many movies, resulting in building the foundation of Manei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He produced many movies, building the foundation of Manei.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>1943年（昭和18年）、東京支社詰めから、松竹へ移り松竹京都撮影所に拠る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he quit Tokyo branch in 1943, he joined Shochiku Co., Ltd. and started working at Shochiku Kyoto Studios.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he quit the Tokyo branch in 1943, he joined Shochiku Co., Ltd. and started working at Shochiku Kyoto Studios.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he quit the Tokyo branch in 1943, he joined Shochiku Co., Ltd. and started working at the Shochiku Kyoto Studios.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>1946年（昭和21年）に根岸の誘いにより東京急行電鉄資本の東横映画（東映の前身）に参加するために松竹を退社する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Negishi&apos;s request, he quit Shochiku Co., Ltd. to join Toyoko Film Company (the predecessor of Toei) which was owned by Tokyu Corporation in 1946.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Negishi&apos;s request, he quit Shochiku Co., Ltd. to join Toyoko Film Company (the predecessor of Toei) which was owned by Tokyu Corporation in 1946.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1946, at Negishi&apos;s request, he quit Shochiku Co., Ltd. to join Toyoko Film Company (the predecessor of Toei) which was owned by Tokyu Corporation.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1949年の『白虎』まで牧野満男の名を使っていたが、同年の『獄門島』よりマキノ光雄の名を使うようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He used 牧野満男 for his name until the production of &quot;Byakko&quot; in 1949, and started using マキノ光雄 when &quot;Gokumonjima&quot; (Gokumon Island) was produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He used 牧野満男 for his name until the production of &quot;Byakko&quot; in 1949, and started using マキノ光雄 when &quot;Gokumonjima&quot; (Gokumon Island) was produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He used 牧野満男 for his name until the production of &quot;Byakko&quot; in 1949, and started using マキノ光雄 when &quot;Gokumonjima&quot; (Gokumon Island) was produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>1951年（昭和26年）4月1日に大川博社長のもと東映が発足すると、本社製作部長、ついで東映東京撮影所長に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Toei was incorporated on April 1, 1951with President Hiroshi OKAWA, he took the post of the general manager of the production department of the head office and then, the head of Toei Movie Studios.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Toei was incorporated on April 1, 1951 with President Hiroshi OKAWA, he took the post of general manager of the production department at the head office and then, became the head of Toei Movie Studios.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Toei was incorporated on April 1, 1951 with President Hiroshi OKAWA, he took the position of general manager of the production department at the head office and then, became the head of Toei Movie Studios.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1952年（昭和27年）常務取締役製作本部長として製作の前線に立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1952, he stood at the forefront of production as managing director and chief general manager of the production department.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1952, he stood at the forefront of production as managing director and chief general manager of the production department.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1952, he stood at the forefront of production as the managing director and chief general manager of the production department.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>『ひめゆりの塔』（1953年）、『笛吹童子』（1954年）とヒットを飛ばし専務取締役となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He hit &quot;Himeyuri No To&quot;(The Tower of Lilies) (in 1952) and &quot;Fuefuki doji&quot; (Flute playing boy) (in 1954) out of the park and became a senior managing director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With his hits; &quot;Himeyuri No To&quot;(The Tower of Lilies) (in 1952) and &quot;Fuefuki doji&quot; (Flute playing boy) (in 1954) he became a senior managing director.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With his hits &quot;Himeyuri No To&quot; (The Tower of Lilies) (1953) and &quot;Fuefuki doji&quot; (Flute playing boy) (1954), he became a senior managing director.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>中村錦之助、東千代之介、大川橋蔵、高倉健らの俳優を売り出す一方で、満州で苦労をした内田吐夢に『血槍富士』（1955年）を撮らせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was endeavoring to promote actors such as Kinnosuke NAKAMURA, Chiyonosuke AZUMA, Hashizo OKAWA and Ken TAKAKURA, he had Tomu UCHIDA with an experience of hardships in Manchuria shoot for &quot;Chiyari Fuji&quot; (A Bloody Spear on Mount Fuji) (1955.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was endeavoring to promote actors such as Kinnosuke NAKAMURA, Chiyonosuke AZUMA, Hashizo OKAWA and Ken TAKAKURA, he had Tomu UCHIDA, experiencing the hardships of Manchuria, he shot &quot;Chiyari Fuji&quot; (A Bloody Spear on Mount Fuji) (1955.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was managing to promote actors such as Kinnosuke NAKAMURA, Chiyonosuke AZUMA, Hashizo OKAWA and Ken TAKAKURA, he had Tomu UCHIDA, who had experienced the hardships of Manchuria, shoot &quot;Chiyari Fuji&quot; (A Bloody Spear on Mount Fuji) (1955).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>やる気をなくし麻雀ばかりしていた若き日の深作欣二らを怒ることもなく、みんなで集まりエロ話をして笑わせていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he saw young people including Kinji FUKASAKU playing the mah-jong all the time without motivation, he did not blame them for their behaviors and instead, made them laugh with erotic stories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he saw young people including Kinji FUKASAKU playing mah-jong all the time without any motivation, he did not blame them for their behavior and instead, made them laugh telling them erotic stories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he saw youngsters including Kinji FUKASAKU playing mah-jong all the time without any motivation, he did not blame them for their behavior, but rather made them laugh telling them erotic stories.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、製作会議で起用しようとした映画監督（一説に今井正とされる）が思想的に「左翼であるから」と嫌う周囲を笑って、「右も左もあるかい。わいは大日本映画党じゃ。」と言い放ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a production meeting where the employment of a certain movie director (Tadashi IMAI, according to information) was proposed, it is said that he told &quot;Right or Left does matter. I belong to Dainippon Movie Party&quot; laughing to other members who were rejecting the proposed director because of his &apos;left wing&apos; ideology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During a production meeting where the employment of a certain movie director (Tadashi IMAI, according to information) was proposed, it&apos;s rumored that he said &quot;Right or Left does matter, I belong to the Dainippon Movie Party,&quot; laughing to other members who were rejecting the proposed director because of his &apos;left wing&apos; ideology.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During a production meeting where the employment of a certain movie director (Tadashi IMAI, according to a source) was proposed but attendants were rejecting the proposed director because of his &apos;left wing&apos; ideology; Mitsuo allegedly laughed them off by saying &quot;Right or Left does matter, I belong to the Dainippon Movie Party.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。コンマをピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>1957年（昭和32年）10月に病む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got sick in October 1957.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He got sick in October 1957.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became ill in October 1957.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>同年12月9日没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on December 9, 1957.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on December 9, 1957.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on December 9, 1957.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>48歳の若さだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was forty eight years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was forty eight years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was forty-eight years old.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>早死にしなければ次期東映社長といわれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If he had not died young, he was believed that he would have become the next president of Toei Company, Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If he had not died so young, it was believed that he would have become the next president of Toei Company, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If he had not died so early, it was believed that he would have become the next president of Toei Company, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kdo84221(id:6188), 兇状旅(id:137772), Kmrt(id:101778), FLHC(id:175370), ゐ(id:795), 木島無名(id:29709), GENMEI(id:31879), らぬき(id:33852), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>