<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>福羽美静</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bisei FUKUBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bisei FUKUBA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bisei FUKUBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>福羽 美静（ふくば びせい、「よししず」とも天保2年7月17日 (旧暦)（1831年8月24日） - 明治40年（1907年）8月14日）は日本の武士･津和野藩士、国学者、歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bisei (also pronounced &apos;Yoshishizu&apos;) FUKUBA (August 24, 1831-August 14, 1907) was a Japanese samurai, a feudal retainer of the Tsuwano Domain, a scholar of Japanese classical literature, and a poet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bisei (also pronounced &apos;Yoshishizu&apos;) FUKUBA (August 24, 1831-August 14, 1907) was a Japanese samurai, a feudal retainer of the Tsuwano Domain, a scholar of Japanese classical literature, and a poet.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bisei (also pronounced &apos;Yoshishizu&apos;) FUKUBA (August 24, 1831-August 14, 1907) was a Japanese samurai, a feudal retainer of the Tsuwano Domain, a scholar of Japanese classical literature, and a poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称は文三郎、号は木園、硯堂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly known as &apos;Bunzaburo,&apos; and his pen names were &apos;Mokuen&apos; and &apos;Gendo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文三郎、木園、硯堂　読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly known as &apos;Bunzaburo,&apos; and his nick names were &apos;Mokuen&apos; and &apos;Gendo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>pen names → nick names. 文三郎、木園、硯堂　読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly known as &apos;Bunzaburo,&apos; and his nick names were &apos;Mokuen&apos; and &apos;Gendo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a viscount.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>貴族院議員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Profile</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>津和野藩士福羽美質の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born the eldest son of Bishitu FUKUBA, a feudal retainer of the Tsuwano Domain.</e>
<cmt>「福羽美質」読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the eldest son of Bishitu FUKUBA, a feudal retainer of the Tsuwano Domain.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the eldest son of Bishitsu FUKUBA, a feudal retainer of the Tsuwano Domain.</e>
<cmt>Bishitu→Bishitsu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>嘉永2年（1849年）、19歳で藩校養老館に入学して漢学や山鹿流兵学を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1849, at the age of 19, he enrolled in Yoro College, a domain school, where he studied Sinology and Yamagaryu (Yamaga school) military science.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1849, at the age of 19, he enrolled in Yoro College, a domain school, where he studied Sinology and Yamagaryu (Yamaga school) military science.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1849, at the age of 19, he enrolled in Yoro College, a domain school, where he studied Sinology and Yamagaryu (Yamaga school) military science.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>津和野藩主亀井茲監の命を受け、嘉永6年（1853年）京都に上り、大国隆正の門に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By order of Koremi KAMEI, the lord of the Tsuwano Domain, Bisei went to Kyoto in 1853 and became a pupil of Takamasa OKUNI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the order of Koremi KAMEI, the lord of the Tsuwano Domain, Bisei went to Kyoto in 1853 and became a pupil of Takamasa OKUNI..</e>
<cmt>by order → by the order. Added a period at the end of the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the order of Koremi KAMEI, the lord of the Tsuwano Domain, Bisei went to Kyoto in 1853 and became a pupil of Takamasa OKUNI..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この際に国学思想の影響を受けて尊皇攘夷論に関心を抱き、次第に意を国事に用いるようになったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that on that occasion, influenced by the philosophy of Japanese classical literature, he showed interest in the argument of Sonno-joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and developed a passion for domestic politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that on that occasion, influenced by the philosophy of Japanese classical literature, he showed interest in the argument of Sonno-joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and developed a passion for domestic politics.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that on that occasion, influenced by the philosophy of Japanese classical literature, he showed interest in the argument of Sonno-joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and developed a passion for domestic politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>安政4年（1857年）に帰藩し、養老館で教授を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1857, he returned to the Tsuwano Domain and worked as a lecturer at Yoro College.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1857, he returned to the Tsuwano Domain and worked as a lecturer at Yoro College.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1857, he returned to the Tsuwano Domain and worked as a lecturer at Yoro College.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>文久3年（1863年）、御所に召され孝明天皇に近侍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863, he was stationed to the Imperial Court and served Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863, he was called upon by the Imperial Court to serve Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt>changed the sentence for a better flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1863, he was called upon by the Imperial Court to serve Emperor Komei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>八月十八日の政変に際しては、七卿落ちと共に西下し帰藩、藩主亀井に認められ、藩政刷新に尽くすところがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Coup of August 18, upon the exile of the seven nobles from Kyoto (Shichikyo-ochi), he went westwards with the seven nobles and returned to the Tsuwano Domain, where he won the support of the Lord Kamei and played an important role in the reforms of domain duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the coup of August 18, upon the exile of the seven nobles from Kyoto (Shichikyo-ochi), he went westwards with seven nobles and returned to the Tsuwano Domain, where he won the support of Lord Kamei and played an important role in the reforms of the domain duties.</e>
<cmt>Coup → coup. Tsuwano Domain → the Tsuwano Domain. Reforms → the reforms.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the coup of August 18, upon the exile of the seven nobles from Kyoto (Shichikyo-ochi), he went westwards with seven nobles and returned to the Tsuwano Domain, where he won the support of Lord Kamei and played an important role in the reforms of the domain duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>慶応2年（1866年）の第二次長州征伐時には、藩の方針を長州藩寄りにまとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Second conquest of the Choshu Domain of 1856, he adopted the pro-Choshu strategy as the policy of the Tsuwano Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the second conquest of the Choshu Domain in 1856, he adopted the pro-Choshu strategy as the policy for the Tsuwano Domain.</e>
<cmt>Second → second. Of 1856 → in 1856. policy of → policy for</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the second conquest of the Choshu Domain in 1866, he adopted the pro-Choshu strategy as the policy for the Tsuwano Domain.</e>
<cmt>1856→1866</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そして明治元年（1868年）、茲監が明治維新政府神祇官の要職につくに及び、微士神祇事務局権判事となり、主に神祇制度の復興確立に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Koremi assumed the important post of Jingikan (senior official at the Ministry of Divinities) for the Meiji restoration government in 1868, Bisei was appointed as a Gonhanji (assistant judicial officer) of the Jingi Jimukyoku (Shintō Worship Bureau), where he greatly contributed to the restoration and establishment of the Jingi system (Ministry of Divinities system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Koremi assumed the important post of Jingikan (senior official at the Ministry of Divinities) for the Meiji restoration government in 1868, Bisei was appointed as a Gonhanji (assistant judicial officer) of the Jingi Jimukyoku (Shintō Worship Bureau), where he greatly contributed to the restoration and establishment of the Jingi system (Ministry of Divinities system).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Koremi assumed the important post of Jingikan (senior official at the Ministry of Divinities) for the Meiji restoration government in 1868, Bisei was appointed as a Gonhanji (assistant judicial officer) of the Jingi Jimukyoku (Shintō Worship Bureau), where he greatly contributed to the restoration and establishment of the Jingi system (Ministry of Divinities system).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除「微士」は訳出不要と考えられたと解釈します。「神祇官神祇官」はウェブで確認し「神祇制度」と原文も訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>明治2年（1869年）には明治天皇の侍講、同年大学御用掛、明治3年（1870年）に神祇大福、明治5年（1872年）に教部大輔となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as a tutor to Emperor Meiji in 1869, an official in charge of the Imperial Household at Daigaku (Bureau of Education) in 1869, a Jingi taifu (deputy minister of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony) in 1870, and an aide to the Minister of Religion in 1872.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as a tutor to Emperor Meiji in 1869, an official in charge of the Imperial Household at Daigaku (Bureau of Education) in 1869, a Jingi taifu (deputy minister of the institution for dedications at religious ceremonies) in 1870, and an aide to the Minister of Religion in 1872.</e>
<cmt>dedicating in → dedications at. Ceremony → ceremonies. 一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as a tutor to Emperor Meiji in 1869, an official in charge of the Imperial Household at Daigaku (Bureau of Education) in the same year, a Jingi taifu (deputy minister of the institution for dedications at religious ceremonies) in 1870, and an aide to the Minister of Religion in 1872.</e>
<cmt>二度目の in 1869→in the same year</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>「外国の長所を取り入れるべきだ」との意見に反対意見が続出したため免官され、宮内省歌道文学御用掛となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facing a wave of dissenting voices against his suggestion that &quot;Merits of foreign countries should be introduced,&quot; he was removed from the Ministry of Religion and appointed as an official in charge of poetry and literature at the Imperial Household Ministry afterwards.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facing a wave of dissenting opinions against his suggestion that &quot;Merits of foreign countries should be introduced,&quot; he was removed from the Ministry of Religion and was appointed as an official in charge of poetry and literature at the Imperial Household Ministry afterwards.</e>
<cmt>voices → opinions. Grammar corrected for better flow. 一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facing a wave of dissenting opinions against his suggestion that &apos;Merits of foreign countries should be introduced,&apos; he was removed from the Ministry of Religion and was appointed as an official in charge of poetry and literature at the Imperial Household Ministry afterwards.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>明治9年（1876年）に国憲調査委員、明治12年（1879年）に東京学士会会員、明治13年（1880年）に文部省御用掛、明治18年（1885年）に元老院議官となり、明治20年（1887年）には子爵を授爵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as a Constitution Investigation Commissioner in 1876, a member of the Tokyo Academy in 1879, an official in charge of the Imperial Household at the Ministry of Education in 1880, and a Genroin gikan (councilor of Chamber of Elders or Senate) in 1885, and created a viscount in 1887.</e>
<cmt>国憲調査委員」[東京学士会」定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as a Constitution Investigation Commissioner in 1876, a member of the Tokyo Academy in 1879, an official in charge of the Imperial Household at the Ministry of Education in 1880, and a Genroin gikan (councilor of Chamber of Elders or Senate) in 1885, and created a viscount in 1887.</e>
<cmt>OK. 国憲調査委員」[東京学士会」定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as a Constitution Investigation Commissioner in 1876, a member of the Tokyo Academy in 1879, an official in charge of the Imperial Household at the Ministry of Education in 1880, and a Genroin gikan (councilor of Chamber of Elders or Senate) in 1885, and created a viscount in 1887.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>この間、明治13年（1880年）から翌年までお茶の水女子大学摂理（校長）を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, he assumed the post of the setsuri (president) of Ochanomizu University from 1880 to 1881.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, he assumed the post of setsuri (president) of Ochanomizu University from 1880 to 1881.</e>
<cmt>the setsuri → setsuri</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, he assumed the post of setsuri (president) of Ochanomizu University from 1880 to 1881.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>明治23年（1890年）、貴族院 (日本)議員に選出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1890, he was elected a member of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1890, he was elected a member of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1890, he was elected a member of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>同年、公職を退いて隠居生活に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he stepped down from the public service and went into retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he stepped down from public service and went into retirement.</e>
<cmt>the public → public</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he stepped down from public service and went into retirement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>園芸・造園家・宮中顧問官の 福羽逸人 農学博士（子爵）は、養嗣子にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hayato FUKUBA, a senior official at the Imperial Household Ministry and the Doctor of Agriculture (viscount) who was also known as a horticulturist and landscape architect, was his adopted son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hayato FUKUBA, a senior official of the Imperial Household Ministry and a doctor of agriculture (viscount) who was also known as a horticulturist and landscape architect, was his adopted son.</e>
<cmt>offical at → official of. Doctor of Agriculture → doctor of agriculture</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hayato FUKUBA, a senior official of the Imperial Household Ministry and a doctor of agriculture (viscount) who was also known as a horticulturist and landscape architect, was his adopted son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>エピソード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Episodes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Episodes</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episodes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>幼少の頃に軽業（かるわざ、曲芸のこと）師の真似をしようとして綱渡りをし、この際誤って転落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his childhood, pretending to be an acrobat, Bisei tried to walk a tightrope but fell from the tightrope.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his childhood, pretending to be an acrobat, Bisei tried to walk a tightrope but fell from the tightrope.</e>
<cmt>Ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his childhood, pretending to be an acrobat, Bisei tried to walk a tightrope but fell from the tightrope.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>腰部の関節を挫傷した為に身長が伸びなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, he injured waist joints, which prevented him from growing taller.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, he injured his waist joints and that prevented him from growing taller.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;his&quot; and &quot;and that&quot; 一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, he injured his waist joints and that prevented him from growing taller.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>大人になっても5尺（約151.5cm）に満たなかったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said his height did not reach 150cm even in his adulthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his height did not reach 150cm even in his adulthood.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;that&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his height did not reach 150cm even in his adulthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、父の友人から諭され、また荒木田守武の和歌に感銘を受けるなどして勉学に励んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite this misfortune, he immersed himself in study, encouraged by his father&apos;s friends and influenced by Moritake ARAKIDA&apos;s poetry (waka, Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite this misfortune, he immersed himself in studies, encouraged by his father&apos;s friends and was influenced by Moritake ARAKIDA&apos;s poetry (waka, Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt>study →studies. Added &quot;was&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite this misfortune, he immersed himself in studies, encouraged by his father&apos;s friends and was influenced by Moritake ARAKIDA&apos;s poetry (waka, Japanese poetry).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>明治天皇が京都より東京へ行幸（東京奠都）する際、伊勢神宮より早馬が到着して｢神宮の鳥居が倒れた、御神意は天皇の行幸に反対なのでは｣という連絡を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Meiji moved out from Kyoto to Tokyo (Tokyo Tento, or transfer of the national capital to Tokyo), an express mail by horse came from Ise-jingu Shrine, which read that &quot;A torii (gate) of the Shrine collapsed. This may be a sign that divines say no to Emperor&apos;s transfer to Tokyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Meiji moved out of Kyoto to Tokyo (Tokyo Tento, or transfer of the national capital to Tokyo), an express mail sent by horse came from Ise-jingu Shrine, which read as follows: &quot;A torii (gate) of the Shrine has collapsed. This may be a sign that the divine spirits are against the Emperor&apos;s transfer to Tokyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Corrected the grammar and added a few words to make sense. 一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Meiji moved out of Kyoto to Tokyo (Tokyo Tento, or transfer of the national capital to Tokyo), an express mail sent by horse came from Ise-jingu Shrine, which read as follows: &apos;A torii (gate) of the Shrine has collapsed. This may be a sign that the divine spirits are against the Emperor&apos;s transfer to Tokyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>福羽は｢人が作ったものなら倒れるのも当然じゃないか｣と相手にしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUKUBA, however, did not bother listening to the message, snapping, &quot;Is it unusual that a man-made gate collapsed?&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUKUBA, however, did not bother listening to the message, snapping, &quot;Is it unusual that a man-made gate collapsed?&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuba, however, did not bother listening to the message, snapping, &apos;Is it unusual that a man-made gate collapsed?&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;FUKUBA→Fukuba</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>他の国学者、神祇官僚とは一線を画した福羽の合理的精神の一端と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this episode is a good example that reflects Fukuba&apos;s practical spirit, which kept him ahead of the pack of other classical Japanese literature scholars and government officials in charge of religious ceremonies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this episode is a good example that reflects Fukuba&apos;s practical spirit, which kept him ahead of the pack of other classical Japanese literature scholars and government officials in charge of religious ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>OK.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this episode is a good example that reflects Fukuba&apos;s practical spirit, which kept him ahead of the pack of other classical Japanese literature scholars and government officials in charge of religious ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 みょうじ(id:124419), 神祇官(id:99217), ファービィ(id:129184), 水野白楓(id:22811), R28Bot(id:177951), Ikedat76(id:34218), 松茸(id:27535), 陽一(id:92099), あるふぁるふぁ(id:209526), M3HR(id:45797), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>