<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>松平定敬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>松平 定敬（まつだいら さだあき）は、幕末の桑名藩第4代藩主（藩主在任：安政6年（1859年） - 慶応4年（1868年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA was the 4th lord of the Kuwana domain at the end of the Edo Period (Years in office: 1859 - 1868)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA was the 4th lord of the Kuwana Domain at the end of the Edo Period (Years in office: 1859 - 1868)</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaaki MATSUDAIRA was the fourth lord of the Kuwana Domain at the end of the Edo Period (Years in office: 1859 - 1868)</e>
<cmt>数字スペルアウト</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都所司代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>定綱系久松松平家13代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 13th head of the Sadatsuna family line of the Hisamatsu-Matsudaira family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 13th head of the Sadatsuna family line of the Hisamatsu-Matsudaira family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 13th head of the Sadatsuna family line of the Hisamatsu-Matsudaira family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は従四位近衛府（明治維新後に従二位）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His office and rank was Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and Konoe-fu (the Imperial Guard Division) (Promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) after the Meiji Restoration)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His office and rank were Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and Konoe-fu (the Imperial Guard Division) (Promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) after the Meiji Restoration)</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His office and rank were Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and Konoe-fu (the Imperial Guard Division) (Promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank) after the Meiji Restoration)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>美濃国高須藩（岐阜県海津市）藩主松平義建の八男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 8th son of Yoshitatsu MATSUDAIRA, the lord of the Takasu Domain in Mino Province (Kaizu City, Gifu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 8th son of Yoshitatsu MATSUDAIRA, the lord of the Takasu Domain in Mino Province (Kaizu City, Gifu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eighth son of Yoshitatsu MATSUDAIRA, the lord of the Takasu Domain in Mino Province (Kaizu City, Gifu Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>数字スペルアウトPrefecture 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>兄に会津藩主松平容保、尾張藩主徳川慶勝、一橋家当主徳川茂徳などがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had several older brothers, the Lord of Aizu Domain, Katamori MATSUDAIRA, the Lord of Owari Domain Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA and the head of the Hitotsubashi family Mochinaga TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had several older brothers, including the Lord of Aizu Domain, Katamori MATSUDAIRA; the Lord of Owari Domain, Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA; and the head of the Hitotsubashi family Mochinaga TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had several older brothers, including the Lord of Aizu Domain, Katamori MATSUDAIRA; the Lord of Owari Domain, Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA; and the head of the Hitotsubashi family Mochinaga TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>弘化3年（1847年）12月2日、松平義建の八男として江戸市ヶ谷の高須藩江戸邸で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaaki was born the 8th son to Yoshitatsu MATSUDAIRA on December 2, 1847 at the residence maintained by the lord of Takasu Domain in Ichigaya, Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaaki was born the 8th son to Yoshitatsu MATSUDAIRA on December 2, 1847 at the residence maintained by the lord of the Takasu Domain in Ichigaya, Edo.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaaki was born the eighth son to Yoshitatsu MATSUDAIRA on Janyuary 18, 1847 at the residence maintained by the lord of the Takasu Domain in Ichigaya, Edo.</e>
<cmt>数字スペルアウト December 2→Janyuary 18に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幼名は銈之助。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Keinosuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Keinosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Keinosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>安政6年（1859年）に桑名藩主・松平定猷が死ぬと、長男・万之助（後の桑名藩主・松平定教）が3歳と幼少であったため、14歳で定猷の娘・初姫（当時3歳）の婿養子として迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1859, when Sadamichi MATSUDAIRA, Lord of Kuwana Domain died, his eldest son Mannosuke (later the Lord of Kuwana Domain, Sadanori MATSUDAIRA) was only 3 years old; and Sadaaki, aged 14 at the time, married into the MATSUDAIRA family, as the husband to their then a 3 year-old daughter, Hatsuhime.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1859, when Sadamichi MATSUDAIRA, Lord of Kuwana Domain, died, his eldest son, Mannosuke (later the Lord of Kuwana Domain, Sadanori MATSUDAIRA), was only 3 years old; and Sadaaki, aged 14 at the time, married into the MATSUDAIRA family, as the husband to their then 3-year-old daughter, Hatsuhime.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1859, when Sadamichi MATSUDAIRA, Lord of Kuwana Domain, died, his eldest son, Mannosuke (later the Lord of Kuwana Domain, Sadanori MATSUDAIRA), was only 3 years old; and Sadaaki, aged 14 at the time, married into the MATSUDAIRA family, as the husband to their then three-year-old daughter, Hatsuhime.</e>
<cmt>「られ」→「られた。」数字スペルアウト</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>藩主となり、従五位越中国に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaaki, who became head of the family, was awarded Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed to rule Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaaki, who became head of the family, was awarded Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed to rule Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaaki, who became head of the family, was awarded Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and appointed to rule Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>初姫の祖母・順祥院は薩摩藩主の娘で、藩政に干渉する順祥院と事あるごとに対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatsuhime&apos;s grandmother, Junshoin, was a daughter of the lord of Satsuma Domain, and she had many conflicts with Sadaaki regarding the rule of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatsuhime&apos;s grandmother, Junshoin, was a daughter of the lord of the Satsuma Domain, and she had many conflicts with Sadaaki regarding the rule of the domain.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatsuhime&apos;s grandmother, Junshoin, was a daughter of the lord of the Satsuma Domain, and she had many conflicts with Sadaaki regarding the rule of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>万延元年（1860年）、従四位に叙せられ、侍従を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1860, he was promoted to Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and concurrently held the post of Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1860, he was promoted to Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and concurrently held the post of Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1860, he was promoted to Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and concurrently held the post of Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>伺候席となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Shikoseki (Japanese territorial lord rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He achieved Shikoseki (Japanese territorial lord rank).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He achieved shikoseki (anteroom seats for feudal lords and direct retainer of the shogun at the Edo-jo castle).</e>
<cmt>伺候席</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>文久3年（1863年）の徳川将軍家・徳川家茂の上洛の際には、京都警護を勤めるために随行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863, he attended Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA when he went to capital as a police escort.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863, he attended Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA when he went to the capital as a police escort.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1863, he attended Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA when he went to the capital as a police escort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>元治元年（1864年）に京都所司代に任命され、同年の禁門の変では会津藩とともに長州藩の兵を撃退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, he was appointed Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto), and during the Kinmon no Hen (Conspiracy of Kinmon), he fought off the Choshu Domain army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, he was appointed Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto), and during the Kinmon no Hen (Conspiracy of Kinmon), he fought off the Choshu Domain army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, he was appointed Kyoto Shoshidai (local governor of Kyoto), and during the Kinmon Incident, he fought off the Choshu Domain army with the Aizu Clan.</e>
<cmt>「し、」→「した。」禁門の変の訳、変更会津藩とともに、追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>天狗党の乱でも出兵している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also fought in the Tenguto no Ran (Rebellion of Tenguto).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also fought in the Tenguto no Ran (Rebellion of Tenguto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also fought in the Tenguto War.</e>
<cmt>天狗党の乱の訳、変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>慶応元年（1865年）、近衛府に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1865, he was transferred to the post of Konoe-fu (the Imperial Guard Division).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1865, he was transferred to the post of Konoe-fu (the Imperial Guard Division).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1865, he was transferred to the post of Konoe-fu (the Imperial Guard Division).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>越中守は兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He concurrently held the post of Ecchu-no-kami (Provincial Governor of Ecchu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He concurrently held the post of Ecchu-no-kami (Provincial Governor of Ecchu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He concurrently held the post of Ecchu-no-kami (Provincial Governor of Ecchu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>慶応4年（1868年）に鳥羽伏見の戦いが起こり戊辰戦争がはじまると、徳川慶喜に従い江戸の霊巌寺（江東区）にて謹慎した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Battle of Toba and Fushimi broke out and Boshin War started, he accompanied Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA and was detained in the Reigan-ji Temple (Koto Ward) in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Battle of Toba and Fushimi broke out and the Boshin War started, he accompanied Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA and was detained in Reigan-ji Temple (Koto Ward) in Edo.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Battle of Toba and Fushimi broke out and the Boshin War started in 1868, he accompanied Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA and was detained in Reigan-ji Temple (Koto Ward) in Edo.</e>
<cmt>in 1868を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>江戸城では抗戦派と恭順派が争い、大久保一翁と勝海舟により恭順工作が進められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Edo Castle, the resistance force and deference faction fought, and the plot for deference to new government by Ichio OKUBO and Kaishu KATSU moved forward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Edo Castle, the resistance force and deference faction fought, and the plot for deference to the new government by Ichio OKUBO and Kaishu KATSU moved forward.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Edo-jo Castle, the resistance force and deference faction fought, and the plot for deference to the new government by Ichio OKUBO and Kaishu KATSU moved forward.</e>
<cmt>Edo→Edo-jo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>更に桑名藩は会津と並んで新政府側からは敵視されており、国元では新政府軍が押し寄せてくる懸念から先代当主の遺児・万之助（後の定教）をかついで恭順する事を家老達が決めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, both the Aizu and Kuwana Domains were harrassed by the new government; therefore, at domain&apos;s local level, chief retainers decided to submit to the new government and appointed the bereaved child of the former family head, Mannosuke (later Sadanori) head of the family out of fear that the new government force would attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, both the Aizu and Kuwana Domains were harrassed by the new government; therefore, at the domain&apos;s local level, chief retainers decided to submit to the new government and appointed the bereaved child of the former family head, Mannosuke (later Sadanori), head of the family, out of fear that the new government force would attack.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, both the Aizu and Kuwana Domains were harrassed by the new government; therefore, at the domain&apos;s local level, chief retainers decided to submit to the new government and appointed the bereaved child of the former family head, Mannosuke (later Sadanori), head of the family, out of fear that the new government force would attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そのため、徹底抗戦派と見られていた定敬の帰国は困難な状況となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This made it difficult for Sadaaki, who was a member of the resistance force, to return home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This made it difficult for Sadaaki, who was a member of the resistance force, to return home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This made it difficult for Sadaaki, who was a member of the resistance force, to return home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>定敬は一翁から桑名藩の分領である越後国柏崎へ赴く事を勧められ、横浜市からプロシア船「コスタリカ号」で柏崎へ渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichio suggested that Sadaaki go to Kashiwazaki, Echigo Province, which was the divided territory of the Kuwana clan, and he boarded the Prussian ship &quot;Costa Rica&quot; from Yokohama City bound for Kashiwazaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichio suggested that Sadaaki go to Kashiwazaki, Echigo Province, which was the divided territory of the Kuwana clan, and he boarded the Prussian ship &quot;Costa Rica&quot; from Yokohama City bound for Kashiwazaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichio suggested that Sadaaki go to Kashiwazaki, Echigo Province, which was the divided territory of the Kuwana domain, and he boarded the Prussian ship &apos;Costa Rica&apos; from Yokohama City bound for Kashiwazaki.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;clan→domain (地理的なことのため）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後は若松城で兄の松平容保と再会し、仙台市から榎本武揚の艦隊で函館市へ渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he met with his older brother, Katamori MATSUDAIRA, at Wakamatsu Castle, and he then traveled from Sendai to Hakodate City with</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he met with his older brother, Katamori MATSUDAIRA, at Wakamatsu Castle, and he then traveled with him from Sendai to Hakodate City.</e>
<cmt>missing word (him)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he met with his older brother, Katamori MATSUDAIRA, at Wakamatsu-jo Castle, after which he traveled by the fleet of Takeaki ENOMOTO from Sendai to Hakodate City.</e>
<cmt>Wakamatsu→Wakamatsu-jowith him とは原文にないので削除しました。「榎本武揚の艦隊で」追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>明治2年（1869年）に横浜へ戻り降伏し、明治5年（1872年）1月6日に赦免される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869, he returned to Yokohama, admitting defeat, and given absoultion on January 6, 1973.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869, he returned to Yokohama, admitting defeat, and he was given absolution on January 6, 1973.</e>
<cmt>misspelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869, he returned to Yokohama, admitting defeat, and he was given absolution on January 6, 1872.</e>
<cmt>1973→1872</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>同年2月に許嫁の初子と結婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February of the same year, he married his bride elect, Hatsuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February of the same year, he married his bride elect, Hatsuko.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February of the same year, he married his bride elect, Hatsuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>明治10年（1877年）に起こった西南戦争には、旧桑名藩士を率いて遠征した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1877, he fought in the Seinan War, leading the old feudal retainers of Kuwana domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1877, he fought in the Seinan War, leading the old feudal retainers of the Kuwana Domain.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1877, he fought in the Seinan War, leading the old feudal retainers of the Kuwana Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>明治27年（1894年）、日光東照宮の宮司となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the Chief Shinto Priest at the Nikko Toshogu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the Chief Shinto Priest at the Nikko Toshogu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the Chief Shinto Priest at the Nikko Toshogu Shrine in 1894.</e>
<cmt>1894年、追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>明治41年（1908年）7月12日、死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died July 12, 1908</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died July 12, 1908</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died July 12, 1908</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="30">
<j>法号：大心院殿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hogo (priest names): Daishinin-dono</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hogo (priest name): Daishinin-dono</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hogo (priest name): Daishinin-dono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>墓所は東京都豊島区の染井霊園にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is buried at the Somei Reien in Toshima Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is buried at the Somei Reien in Toshima Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is buried at the Somei Reien in Toshima Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Asura2007(id:78364), 砂の妖精(id:24382), Woyzzeck(id:8923), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 松茸(id:27535), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 松平定治(id:146386), HATO(id:35585), Rusk(id:9895), 上田隼人(id:23104), こぶまき(id:38278), Maakun(id:16735), Kouko0515(id:100370), シェーラ(id:17988), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>