<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>村田実</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minoru MURATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minoru MURATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minoru MURATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>村田實（むらたみのる、1894年3月2日 - 1937年6月26日）は、大正・昭和初期の映画監督、脚本家、俳優。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minoru MURATA (March 2, 1894-June 26, 1937) was a movie director, scriptwriter and actor who lived from the Taisho period to the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minoru MURATA (March 2, 1894-June 26, 1937) was a movie director, scriptwriter and actor who lived from the Taisho period to the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minoru MURATA (March 2, 1894-June 26, 1937) was a movie director, scriptwriter and actor who lived from the Taisho period to the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本映画監督協会初代理事長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first administrative director of the Directors Guild of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first administrative director of the Directors Guild of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first administrative director of the Directors Guild of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>新劇から帰山教正の「映画芸術協会」に参加、小山内薫の「松竹キネマ研究所」で『路上の霊魂』を監督したことで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left Shingeki (literally, new play) to join &apos;Eiga Geijutsu Kyokai (literally, Movie Art Association)&apos; which had been established by Norimasa KAERIYAMA, and is known to have worked on &quot;Rojo no Reikon&quot; (Souls on The Road) as a director when he was at Shochiku Cinema Laboratory established by Kaoru OSANAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left Shingeki (literally, new play) to join &apos;Eiga Geijutsu Kyokai (literally, Movie Art Association)&apos; which had been established by Norimasa KAERIYAMA, and is known to have worked on &quot;Rojo no Reikon&quot; (Souls on The Road) as a director when he was at Shochiku Cinema Laboratory established by Kaoru OSANAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left Shingeki (literally, new play) to join &apos;Eiga Geijutsu Kyokai&apos; (literally, Movie Art Association) which had been established by Norimasa KAERIYAMA, and is known to have worked on &quot;Rojo no Reikon&quot; (Souls on The Road) as a director when he was at Shochiku Cinema Laboratory established by Kaoru OSANAI.</e>
<cmt>位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>洋画の手法を積極的に取り入れ、松竹の「蒲田調」に対して男性的で重厚な日活現代劇の基礎を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active to adopt foreign film methods and contributed to establish a foundation to give Nikkatsu mordern play which are manlike, deep and heavy features, unlike &apos;Kamata Style&apos; of Shochiku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active to adopt foreign film methods and contributed to establish a foundation to give Nikkatsu mordern plays that are manlike, have deep and heavy features, unlike the &apos;Kamata Style&apos; of Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active to adopt foreign film methods and contributed to establish a foundation to give Nikkatsu modern plays that are manlike, have deep and heavy features, unlike the &apos;Kamata Style&apos; of Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>映画監督栗山富夫の父の従兄弟にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a cousin of the father of Tomio KURIYAMA, a movie director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a cousin of the father of Tomio KURIYAMA, a movie director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a cousin of the father of Tomio KURIYAMA, a movie director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>少年時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Childhood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>東京市神田小川町（現千代田区神田小川町）に大日本図書重役村田五郎の一人息子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as an only son of Goro MURATA, a director of Dainippon-tosho Co., Ltd., whose residence was located in Ogawa-machi (present-day Ogawa-machi, Kanda, Chiyoda Ward,) Kanda (Chiyoda Ward,) Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as an only son of Goro MURATA, a director of Dainippon-tosho Co., Ltd., whose residence was located in Ogawa-machi (present-day Ogawa-machi, Kanda, Chiyoda Ward), Kanda (Chiyoda Ward), Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as an only son of Goro MURATA, a director of Dainippon-tosho Co., Ltd., whose residence was located in Ogawa-machi (present-day Ogawa-machi, Kanda, Chiyoda Ward), Kanda, Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt>(千代田区)原文、訳文から削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>当時会社が京橋 (東京都中央区)にあったので、やがて銀座に引っ越すが、神田の家に士族であった農商務省 (日本)鑑定官の祖父が残っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because his father&apos;s office was in Kyobashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo,) they soon moved to Ginza leaving his grandfather in the house in Kanda, who was from the warrior class and an Official Appraiser in the Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce (Japanese.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because his father&apos;s office was in Kyobashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo), they soon moved to the Ginza leaving his grandfather in the house in Kanda, who was from the warrior class and an Official Appraiser in the Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce (Japanese.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his father&apos;s office was in Kyobashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo), they soon moved to the Ginza leaving his grandfather in the house in Kanda, who was from the warrior class and an Official Appraiser in the Ministry of Agriculture and Commerce (Japanese.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>銀座と神田とを行き来するようになり、父の職業の関係上読書に親しみ、また祖父の趣味・職業の関係上古美術に親しみ品評にならされて育った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started going back and forth between Kinza and Kanda, and grew up enjoying reading books influenced from his father&apos;s occupation and being familiar with appraisal in close contact with old art from his grandfather&apos;s hobbies and occupation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started going back and forth between the Ginza and Kanda, and grew up enjoying reading books influenced from his father&apos;s occupation and being familiar with appraisal in close contact with old art from his grandfather&apos;s hobbies and occupation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started going back and forth between the Ginza and Kanda, and grew up enjoying reading books influenced from his father&apos;s occupation and being familiar with appraisal in close contact with old art from his grandfather&apos;s hobbies and occupation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また敬虔なクリスチャンの家であったので幼時に洗礼を受けている（洗礼名「ヨゼフ」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family faithfully believed in Christianity and he was baptized in his childhood (&apos;Joseph&apos; as Christian name.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family faithfully believed in Christianity and he was baptized in his childhood (&apos;Joseph&apos; as Christian name.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family faithfully believed in Christianity and he was baptized in his childhood (&apos;Joseph&apos; as Christian name.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1906年、東京高等師範学校附属小学校から東京高等師範学校附属中学校に入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1906 he finished Elementary School attached to Tokyo Higher Normal School and entered Junior High School attached to Tokyo Higher Normal School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1906 he finished Elementary School attached to Tokyo Higher Normal School and entered Junior High School attached to Tokyo Higher Normal School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1906 he finished Elementary School attached to Tokyo Higher Normal School and entered Junior High School attached to Tokyo Higher Normal School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>中学の先輩である永井荷風を愛読し、家に芝居見物を禁止されていたため近所の洋画専門上映館「神田錦輝館」に替り日ごとに通う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He loved reading books of Kafu NAGAI who was his senior at junior high school, and also went to &apos;Kanda kinki-kan,&apos; a theater specializing in foreign movies every time the showing was renewed since his family did not allow him to see stages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He loved reading books of Kafu NAGAI who was his senior at junior high school, and also went to &apos;Kanda kinki-kan,&apos; a theater specializing in foreign movies every time the showing was renewed since his family did not allow him to see stages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He loved reading books of Kafu NAGAI who was his senior at junior high school, and also went to &apos;Kanda kinki-kan,&apos; a theater specializing in foreign movies every time the showing was renewed since his family did not allow him to see stages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この時期の錦輝館には中学の先輩である帰山教正、島津保次郎、五所平之助も足繁く通っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Norimasa KAERIYAMA, Yasujiro SHIMAZU and Heinosuke GOSHO who were his seniors at junior high school often visited Kinki-kan, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Norimasa KAERIYAMA, Yasujiro SHIMAZU and Heinosuke GOSHO who were his seniors at junior high school, often visited Kinki-kan, too.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Norimasa KAERIYAMA, Yasujiro SHIMAZU and Heinosuke GOSHO who were his seniors at junior high school, often visited Kinki-kan, too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そして中学卒業前に初めて舞台を観劇し、エドワード・ゴードン・クレイグの舞台デザインに感銘を受け、演劇の道を志すことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just before he finished junior high school, he saw a stage drama for the first time and was greatly impressed with Edward Gordon Craig&apos;s stage design and decided to study about play.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before he finished junior high school, he saw a stage drama for the first time and was greatly impressed with Edward Gordon Craig&apos;s stage design and decided to study about plays.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before he finished junior high school, he saw a stage drama for the first time and was greatly impressed with Edward Gordon Craig&apos;s stage design and decided to study about plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>家には進学を勧められたが、当時の「教育制度に反感をおこして」いた上に病気がちのため医者が進学を勧めなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though his parents told him to get higher education, he &apos;had a feeling of opposition about the education system&apos; at that time and his doctor did not recommend him to go to higher school due to his unhealthy condition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though his parents told him to get a higher education, he &apos;had a feeling of opposition about the education system&apos; at that time and his doctor did not recommend him to go to higher school due to his unhealthy condition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though his parents told him to get a higher education, he &apos;had a feeling of opposition about the education system&apos; at that time and his doctor did not recommend him to go to higher school due to his unhealthy condition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>卒業後は慶應義塾文科の聴講生となり、白馬会の葵橋洋画研究所へ絵を習いに通った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he finished middle school, he became a part-time student at Keio University Literature Department and study drawing at Aoibashi Western painting school (葵橋洋画研究所) of Hakuba-kai (白馬会.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he finished middle school, he became a part-time student at Keio University Literature Department and studied drawing at Aoibashi Western painting school (葵橋洋画研究所) of Hakuba-kai (白馬会.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he finished middle school, he became a part-time student at Keio University Literature Department and studied drawing at Aoibashi Western painting school of Hakuba-kai</e>
<cmt>(葵橋洋画研究所) (白馬会.)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>帝劇文芸部の給仕を経て、栗島狭衣（栗島すみ子の義父）や石川木舟の書生として働いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After working as a waiter at Teigeki Bungei-bu (帝劇文芸部,) he took on a job of Shosei (a student who is given room and board in exchange for performing domestic duties) for Sagoromo KURISHIMA (Sumiko KURISHIMA&apos;s father-in-law) and 石川木舟.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After working as a waiter at Teigeki Bungei-bu (帝劇文芸部,) he took a job of Shosei (a student who is given room and board in exchange for performing domestic duties) for Sagoromo KURISHIMA (Sumiko KURISHIMA&apos;s father-in-law) and 石川木舟.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After working as a waiter at Teigeki Bungei-bu, he took a job of Shosei (a student who is given room and board in exchange for performing domestic duties) for Sagoromo KURISHIMA (Sumiko KURISHIMA&apos;s father-in-law) and 石川木舟.</e>
<cmt>(帝劇文芸部,)削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>とりで社時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Days at Toride Co.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Days at Toride Co.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Days at Toride Co.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1912年9月、家の金を使い、ゴードン・クレイグやマックス・ラインハルト、メーテルリンクなどに大きく影響を受けた演劇美術雑誌『とりで』を発行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1912, using his family&apos;s money, he published a play and art magazine &quot;Toride&quot; which was greatly affected by Gordon CRAIG, Maeterlinck, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1912, using his family&apos;s money, he published a play and art magazine &quot;Toride&quot; which was greatly affected by Gordon CRAIG, Maeterlinck, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1912, using his family&apos;s money, he published a play and art magazine &quot;Toride&quot; which was greatly affected by Gordon CRAIG, Max Reinhardt and Maeterlinck, etc.</e>
<cmt>Max Reinhardt 補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>表紙を岸田劉生、安堵久左、清宮彬、岡本帰一らが手がけ、自身も毎号カット画を描いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryusei KISHIDA, Hisa ANDO, Hitoshi SEIMIYA and Kiichi OKAMOTO produced the front pages and he drew pictures by himself for each issue.</e>
<cmt>安堵久左、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryusei KISHIDA, Hisa ANDO, Hitoshi SEIMIYA and Kiichi OKAMOTO produced the front pages and he drew pictures by himself for each issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryusei KISHIDA, Hisa ANDO, Hitoshi SEIMIYA and Kiichi OKAMOTO produced the front pages and he drew pictures by himself for each issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>三号までの刊行が大方の同種の雑誌の中で、この『とりで』は翌年10月の八号まで続いたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While most of the same types of magazines were discontinued with the third issue, this magazine &quot;Toride&quot; lasted to the eighth issue which was published in October of the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While most of the same types of magazines were discontinued with the third issue, this magazine &quot;Toride&quot; lasted to the eighth issue which was published in October of the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While most of the same types of magazines were discontinued with the third issue, this magazine &quot;Toride&quot; lasted to the eighth issue which was published in October of the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また同10月には新劇団「とりで社」を結成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He formed Shingeki (new drama) group &quot;Toridesha&quot; in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He formed Shingeki (new drama) group &quot;Toridesha&quot; in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He formed Shingeki (new drama) group &apos;Toridesha&apos; in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>後に宝塚歌劇の演出家となる岸田辰弥、舞踊家として海外で活躍することになる伊藤道郎、画家の木村荘八らが参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The group had another members including Tatsuya KISHIDA who became a producer in Takarazuka Revue Company later, Michiro ITO who became a famous dancer abroad and Sohachi KIMURA as an artist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The group had other members including Tatsuya KISHIDA who became a producer in Takarazuka Revue Company later, Michiro ITO who became a famous dancer abroad, and Sohachi KIMURA an artist.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The group had other members including Tatsuya KISHIDA who became a producer in Takarazuka Revue Company later, Michiro ITO who became a famous dancer abroad, and Sohachi KIMURA an artist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>築地精養軒ホールや有楽座、福沢桃介邸の小劇場で公演を行い、この間に沢田正二郎、小山内薫らと知り合う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The group gave performances at Tsukiji Seiyo-ken Hall, Yuraku-za and a small theater located in Momosuke Fukuda&apos;s residence, and during these performance, he got acquainted with Shojiro SAWADA, Kaoru OSANAI, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The group gave performances at Tsukiji Seiyo-ken Hall, Yuraku-za and a small theater located in Momosuke Fukuda&apos;s residence, and during these performance, he got acquainted with Shojiro SAWADA, Kaoru OSANAI, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The group gave performances at Tsukiji Seiyo-ken Hall, Yuraku-za and a small theater located in Momosuke Fukuda&apos;s residence, and during these performance, he got acquainted with Shojiro SAWADA, Kaoru OSANAI, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし家の経済に負担をかけ、1914年に解散。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in 1914, the group was dissolved due to economical burden on his family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in 1914, the group was dissolved due to economical burden on his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in 1914, the group was dissolved due to economical burden on his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>河合武雄、伊庭孝、喜多村緑郎門下などの新劇団を転々とし下積み生活を送る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He joined Shingeki groups one after another such as the groups led by Takeo KAWAI, Takashi IBA and Rokuro KITAMURA and experienced very slowly life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined Shingeki groups one after another, such as the groups led by Takeo KAWAI, Takashi IBA, and Rokuro KITAMURA, and experienced a very slow life.</e>
<cmt>word spacing, punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He spent a number of years in obscurity, changing from one new drama group to another, including groups such as those led by Takeo KAWAI, Takashi IBA, and Rokuro KITAMURA.</e>
<cmt>原文赤字部分を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、この間に父の事業が失敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During these years, his father failed in business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During those years, his father failed in business.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During those years, his father failed in business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>踏路社・映画芸術協会時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Days at Toro-sha and Eiga Geijutsu Kyokai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Days at Toro-sha and Eiga Geijutsu Kyokai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Days at Toro-sha and Eiga Geijutsu Kyokai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1917年2月、心を新しくして青山杉作、近藤伊与吉、後のドイツ語学者関口存男らと新劇団「踏路社」を結成し、芸術倶楽部で長与善郎作『画家とその弟子』を公演。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To make a new start in February 1917, he formed a new drama group &apos;Toro-sha&apos; with Sugisaku AOYAMA, Iyokichi KONDO, and Tsugio SEKIGUCHI who became a Germanist later and performed Yoshiro NAGAYO&apos;s product &quot;Gaka to sono deshi (An Artist and His Disciples) &quot; at Bijutsu Club.</e>
<cmt>演目名、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To make a new start in February 1917, he formed a new drama group &apos;Toro-sha&apos; with Sugisaku AOYAMA, Iyokichi KONDO, and Tsugio SEKIGUCHI who became a Germanist later and performed Yoshiro NAGAYO&apos;s product &quot;Gaka to sono deshi (An Artist and His Disciples) &quot; at Bijutsu Club.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To make a new start in February 1917, he formed a new drama group &apos;Toro-sha&apos; with Sugisaku AOYAMA, Iyokichi KONDO, and Tsugio SEKIGUCHI who became a Germanist later and performed Yoshiro NAGAYO&apos;s product &quot;Gaka to sono deshi&quot; (An Artist and His Disciples) at Bijutsu Club.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この時、関口の助言で、日本で初めて「演出」という言葉を使ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that at Sekiguchi&apos;s advice, he first used a term &apos;stage-managing (enshutsu)&apos; in Japan at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that at Sekiguchi&apos;s advice, he first used the term &apos;stage-managing (enshutsu)&apos; in Japan at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that at Sekiguchi&apos;s advice, he first used the term &apos;stage-managing&apos; (enshutsu) in Japan at that time.</e>
<cmt>位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1918年、新劇仲間の紹介で帰山教正の「映画芸術協会」に「踏路社」の仲間と参加し、『生の輝き』・『深山の乙女』（帰山教正監督）に「日本最初の映画女優」とされる花柳はるみと共に主演する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1918, he and members of &apos;Toha-sha&apos; joined Eiga Geijutsu Kyokai which had been established by Norimasa KAERIYAMA through Shingeki group&apos;s member, and he starred in &quot;Sei no Kagayaki&quot; (The Shining Life) and &quot;Miyama no Otome&quot; (The Maiden of Deep Mountain) (directed by Norimasa KERIYAMA) with Harumi HANAYAGAGI as a lead actress, who was thought to be &apos;the first cinema actress in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>映画名、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1918, he and members of &apos;Toha-sha&apos; joined Eiga Geijutsu Kyokai which had been established by Norimasa KAERIYAMA through Shingeki group&apos;s member, and he starred in &quot;Sei no Kagayaki&quot; (The Shining Life) and &quot;Miyama no Otome&quot; (The Maiden of Deep Mountain) (directed by Norimasa KERIYAMA) with Harumi HANAYAGAGI as a lead actress, who was thought to be &apos;the first cinema actress in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1918, he and members of &apos;Toha-sha&apos; joined Eiga Geijutsu Kyokai which had been established by Norimasa KAERIYAMA through Shingeki group&apos;s member, and he starred in &quot;Sei no Kagayaki&quot; (The Shining Life) and &quot;Miyama no Otome&quot; (The Maiden of Deep Mountain) (directed by Norimasa KAERIYAMA) with Harumi HANAYAGI as a lead actress, who was thought to be &apos;the first cinema actress in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>近藤伊与吉の回想によると『生の輝き』のシナリオを読んだ際、村田が帰山に「脚本の作法と言うものは吾々には解らないが、そのままではその脚本は新派劇ですよ」と発言し、帰山・近藤と三晩徹夜してシナリオを直したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Iyokichi KONDO&apos;s reminiscences, when reading a scenario of &quot;Sei no kagayaki, &quot; Murata told Kaeriyama, &apos;A method of how to make scenarios is not understandable to us, but this scenario is Shinpa-Geki (a New-School Play) like this.&apos; and stayed up all night long for three straight nights to revise the scenario with Kaeriyama and Kondo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Iyokichi KONDO&apos;s reminiscences, when reading a scenario of &quot;Sei no kagayaki, &quot; Murata told Kaeriyama, &apos;The method of how to make scenarios is not understandable to us, but this scenario is Shinpa-Geki (a New-School Play) like this.&apos; and stayed up all night long for three straight nights to revise the scenario with Kaeriyama and Kondo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Iyokichi KONDO&apos;s reminiscences, when reading a scenario of &quot;Sei no kagayaki,&quot; Murata told Kaeriyama, &apos;The method of how to make scenarios is not understandable to us, but this scenario is Shinpa-Geki (a New-School Play) like this.&apos; and stayed up all night long for three straight nights to revise the scenario with Kaeriyama and Kondo.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これにより新劇から映画に情熱的にうちこむようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This made him get enthusiastically involved in films, departing from Shingeki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This made him get enthusiastically involved in films, departing from Shingeki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This made him get enthusiastically involved in films, departing from Shingeki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし1919年、四作目の『さらば青春』（近藤伊与吉監督）で演出意見の衝突により脱退。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, however, there was a conflict of ideas over the production of the fourth film &quot;Saraba Seishun&quot; (Goodbye Youth) (directed by Iyokichi KONDO) and he left the group.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919, however, there was a conflict of ideas over the production of the fourth film &quot;Saraba Seishun&quot; (Goodbye Youth) (directed by Iyokichi KONDO) and he left the group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1919, however, there was a conflict of ideas over the production of the fourth film &quot;Saraba Seishun&quot; (Goodbye Youth) (directed by Iyokichi KONDO) and he left the group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>同年には『東京日日新聞』主催の乙種活動写真（全年齢対象）向けの脚本募集に二位入選している（一位は後の東宝専務の森岩雄、三位は後の松竹蒲田の脚本家北村小松）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he was a second winner in a scenario contest for second-type movies (available for all generations) which was sponsored by Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper (the first winner was Iwao MORI who became a director of Toho Co., Ltd. later and the third winner was Komatsu KITAMURA, a scenario writer in Shochiku Kamata.)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he was a second winner in a scenario contest for second-type movies (available for all generations) which was sponsored by Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper (the first winner was Iwao MORI who became a director of Toho Co., Ltd. later and the third winner was Komatsu KITAMURA, a scenario writer in Shochiku Kamata.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he was a second winner in a scenario contest for second-type movies (available for all generations) which was sponsored by Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper (the first winner was Iwao MORI who became a director of Toho Co., Ltd. later and the third winner was Komatsu KITAMURA, a scenario writer in Shochiku Kamata.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>松竹キネマ時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Days in Shochiku Cinema</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Days in Shochiku Cinema</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Days in Shochiku Cinema</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>1920年3月、小山内薫校長の「松竹キネマ俳優学校」に入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1920, he entered &apos;Shochiku Cinema School of Acting&apos; of which Kaoru OSANAI was a school head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1920, he entered &apos;Shochiku Cinema School of Acting&apos; of which Kaoru OSANAI was the school head.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1920, he entered &apos;Shochiku Cinema School of Acting&apos; of which Kaoru OSANAI was the school head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>牛原虚彦、島津保次郎、伊藤大輔、鈴木傳明、北村小松らと講義を受け、松竹蒲田撮影所で松竹第一作として製作された『奉仕の薔薇』（西洋模倣の行き過ぎにより公開が見送られる）、『光に立つ女（女優伝）』の脚本・監督を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had lectures with Kiyohiko USHIHARA, Yasujiro SHIMAZU, Daisuke ITO (movie director,) Denmei SUZUKI and Komatsu KITAMURA, and wrote the scenarios of &quot;Hoshi no Bara,&quot; (The Rose of the Service) (the showing was postponed due to excessive Western mimicry) as the Schochiku&apos;s first film produced at Shochiku Kamata Studio and &quot;Hikari ni tatsu onna (Joyu-den)&quot;(The Woman Standing in the Light - Memoir of an Actress) and directed these movies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had lectures with Kiyohiko USHIHARA, Yasujiro SHIMAZU, Daisuke ITO (movie director,) Denmei SUZUKI and Komatsu KITAMURA, and wrote the scenarios of &quot;Hoshi no Bara,&quot; (The Rose of the Service) (the showing was postponed due to excessive Western mimicry) as the Schochiku&apos;s first film produced at Shochiku Kamata Studio and &quot;Hikari ni tatsu onna (Joyu-den)&quot;(The Woman Standing in the Light - Memoir of an Actress) and directed these movies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had lectures with Kiyohiko USHIHARA, Yasujiro SHIMAZU, Daisuke ITO, Denmei SUZUKI and Komatsu KITAMURA, and wrote the scenarios of &quot;Hoshi no Bara,&quot; (The Rose of the Service) (the showing was postponed due to excessive Western mimicry) as the Schochiku&apos;s first film produced at Shochiku Kamata Studio and &quot;Hikari ni tatsu onna (Joyu-den)&quot; (The Woman Standing in the Light - Memoir of an Actress) and directed these movies.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動(映画監督) (movie director)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>やがて社内の商業主義監督たちとの対立により「俳優学校」が廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, &apos;Shochiku Cinema School of Acting&apos; was closed due to confrontations with in-house directors who were focused on the commercialism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, &apos;Shochiku Cinema School of Acting&apos; was closed due to confrontations with in-house directors who were focused on commercialism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, &apos;Shochiku Cinema School of Acting&apos; was closed due to confrontations with in-house directors who were focused on commercialism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>小山内が「松竹キネマ研究所」を設立すると行動をともにし、その最初の作品『路上の霊魂』の監督、出演をこなす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When OSANAI established &apos;Shochiku Cinema Laboratory,&apos; he joined him and was involved in the first production &quot;Rojo no Reikon (Souls on The Road)&quot; as both a director and actor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When OSANAI established the &apos;Shochiku Cinema Laboratory,&apos; he joined him and was involved in the first production &quot;Rojo no Reikon (Souls on The Road)&quot; as both a director and an actor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Osanai established the &apos;Shochiku Cinema Laboratory,&apos; he joined him and was involved in the first production &quot;Rojo no Reikon&quot; (Souls on The Road) as both a director and an actor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし完成直後に村田が大病に罹り、牛原虚彦（脚本・出演）の母、水谷文次郎（撮影）と島津保次郎（光線）の父が急逝する事態になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just after the movie was complete, Murata got seriously sick and the mother of Kiyohiko USHIHARA (he wrote the scenario and appeared in it) and fathers of Monjiro MIZUTANI (shooting) and Yasujiro SHIMAZU (lighting) died a sudden death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just after the movie was complete, Murata got seriously sick and the mother of Kiyohiko USHIHARA (he wrote the scenario and appeared in it) and fathers of Monjiro MIZUTANI (shooting) and Yasujiro SHIMAZU (lighting) died a sudden death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just after the movie was complete, Murata got seriously sick and the mother of Kiyohiko USHIHARA (he wrote the scenario and appeared in it) and fathers of Monjiro MIZUTANI (shooting) and Yasujiro SHIMAZU (lighting) died a sudden death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>当時の反響は大きく、今日まで残る日本の芸術映画黎明期を伝える資料となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movie had a great deal of response at that time, and still exists as a material telling about the earliest days of the Japanese art films.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movie had a great deal of response at that time, and still exists as a material telling about the earliest days of Japanese art films.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movie had a great deal of response at that time, and still exists as a material telling about the earliest days of Japanese art films.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="43">
<j>浪人・日活向島撮影所時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Days of unemployment and in Nikkatsu Mukojima Studios</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Days of unemployment and in Nikkatsu Mukojima Studios</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Days of unemployment and in Nikkatsu Mukojima Studios</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>1921年8月に「松竹キネマ研究所」は解散し、村田は製作費に糸目をつけず松竹の経済を圧迫した責任で辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1921, &apos;Shochiku Cinema Laboratory&apos; was dissolved and Murata took the responsibility for weighing on Shochiku&apos;s financial position because he spared no expense to production costs, and resigned from the company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1921, &apos;Shochiku Cinema Laboratory&apos; was dissolved and Murata took the responsibility for weighing on Shochiku&apos;s financial position because he spared no expense for production costs, and resigned from the company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1921, &apos;Shochiku Cinema Laboratory&apos; was dissolved and Murata took the responsibility for weighing on Shochiku&apos;s financial position because he spared no expense for production costs, and resigned from the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>東京シネマ商会で化粧品の宣伝映画などを作ったり、一日五円の日当てでカッティングや編集の仕事を引き受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Tokyo Cinema Shokai, he made an advertisement movie for cosmetics companies and took a job of cutting or editing at a day wage of five yen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Tokyo Cinema Shokai, he made advertising commercial for cosmetics companies and took a job of cutting or editing at a day wage of only five yen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Tokyo Cinema Shokai, he made advertising commercial for cosmetics companies and took a job of cutting or editing at a day wage of only five yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>潰れかかった国際活映に入社して女形（日活向島を退社した衣笠貞之助が出演）を使った映画を撮ったりもした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he joined Kokusai katsuei which was going to fold up and made films starring an actor of female roles (starring Teinosuke KINUGASA who had quit Nikkatsu Mukojima.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he joined Kokusai katsuei which was going to fold up and made films starring an actor of female roles (starring Teinosuke KINUGASA who had quit Nikkatsu Mukojima.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he joined Kokusai katsuei which was going to fold up and made films starring an actor of female roles (starring Teinosuke KINUGASA who had quit Nikkatsu Mukojima).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>1923年、近藤伊与吉の仲介で日活撮影所に入所するが、当初はつまらない脚本や売れない役者を押し付けられるなど不遇であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1923, he joined Nikkatsu Studio through Iyokichi KONDO, but he experienced a hardship in which he was at first forced to use poor scenarios and unknown actors and actresses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1923, he joined Nikkatsu Studio through Iyokichi KONDO, but he experienced hardship in which he was at first forced to use poor scenarios and unknown actors and actresses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1923, he joined Nikkatsu Studio through Iyokichi KONDO, but he experienced hardship in which he was at first forced to use poor scenarios and unknown actors and actresses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>近藤の回想によると初めて村田を見た本社の根岸耕一支配人に「あんな小さな男で監督が出来るかッ」と叱られたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Kondo&apos;s reminiscences, when Koichi NEGISHI, general manager of the head office saw Murata for the first time, Kondo was accused by him saying &apos;Such a small man can&apos;t be a director.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kondo&apos;s reminiscences, when Koichi NEGISHI, general manager of the head office saw Murata for the first time, Kondo was accused by him saying &apos;Such a small man can&apos;t be a director.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Kondo&apos;s reminiscences, when Koichi NEGISHI, general manager of the head office saw Murata for the first time, Kondo was accused by him saying &apos;Such a small man can&apos;t be a director.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>またこの頃は向島での仕事を終えると毎晩のように小石川博文館の長屋で開かれていた職工演劇（労働演劇）の指導に通った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, he went to Koishikawa Hakubunkan museum almost every night after finishing his work in Mukaijima and gave guidance on Artisan Theater (Labor Theater)held at long house of the museum.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, he went to the Koishikawa Hakubunkan museum almost every night after finishing his work in Mukaijima and gave guidance on the Artisan Theater (Labor Theater)held in the long house of the museum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, he went to the Koishikawa Hakubunkan museum almost every night after finishing his work in Mukojima and gave guidance on the Artisan Theater (Labor Theater)held in the long house of the museum.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>後のプロレタリア作家徳永直が感謝の言葉を綴っており、社会主義者片山潜から村田に宛てた手紙が『新映画』一九二三年七月号に掲載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sunao TOKUNAGA who became a proletarian writer later wrote appreciative words, and a letter from Sen KATAYAMA, a socialist to Murata was published in &quot;Shin eiga&quot; (literally &quot;New Movie&quot;) in July 1923 issue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sunao TOKUNAGA who became a proletarian writer later wrote appreciative words, and a letter from Sen KATAYAMA, a socialist to Murata was published in &quot;Shin eiga&quot; (literally &quot;New Movie&quot;) in July 1923 issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sunao TOKUNAGA who became a proletarian writer later wrote appreciative words, and a letter from Sen KATAYAMA, a socialist to Murata was published in &quot;Shin eiga&quot; (literally &quot;New Movie&quot;) in July 1923 issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="51">
<j>日活大将軍撮影所時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Days in Nikkatsu Taishogun movie studio</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Days at Nikkatsu Taishogun movie studio</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Days at Nikkatsu Taishogun movie studio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>関東大震災で向島撮影所が全壊し、日活現代劇部は京都の日活撮影所に「第二部」として移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The studio in Mukojima was torn down in the Great Kanto Earthquake and Nikkatsu gendai geki department (日活現代劇部) was moved into Nikkatsu Studio in Kyoto and named &apos;Dainibu (第二部.)&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The studio in Mukojima was destroyed during the Great Kanto Earthquake and Nikkatsu gendai geki department (日活現代劇部) was moved into Nikkatsu Studio in Kyoto and named &apos;Dainibu (第二部.)&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The studio in Mukojima was destroyed during the Great Kanto Earthquake and Nikkatsu gendai geki department was moved into Nikkatsu Studio in Kyoto and named &apos;Dainibu&apos; (Second Department).</e>
<cmt>(日活現代劇部) (第二部.)削除(Second Department)補足→定訳不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>1924年、日本最初の反戦映画とされる『清作の妻』が新人浦辺粂子の熱演もあり、好評を得、1925年には『街の手品師』で「大正14年度朝日新聞最優秀映画」を日本映画で初めて受賞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1924, &quot;Seisaku no tsuma&quot; (A wife of Seisaku,) which is thought to be the first anti-war movie in Japan was well received, supported by the great performance of a new actress Kumeko URABE, and in 1925, he first won an award of &apos;1925 Asahi Shimbun Best Movie of the Year&apos; for &quot;Machi no Tejinashi&quot; (The Magician of the City) in Japanese movie category.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1924, &quot;Seisaku no tsuma&quot; (A wife of Seisaku,) which is thought to be the first anti-war movie in Japan was well received, supported by the great performance of a new actress Kumeko URABE, and in 1925, he first won an award of &apos;1925 Asahi Shimbun Best Movie of the Year&apos; for &quot;Machi no Tejinashi&quot; (The Magician of the City) in Japanese movie category.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1924, &quot;Seisaku no tsuma&quot; (A wife of Seisaku,) which is thought to be the first anti-war movie in Japan was well received, supported by the great performance of a new actress Kumeko URABE, and in 1925, he first won an award of &apos;1925 Asahi Shimbun Best Movie of the Year&apos; for &quot;Machi no Tejinashi&quot; (The Magician of the City) in Japanese movie category.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>新劇出身の岡田嘉子が一躍スター女優となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiko OKADA who had belonged to Shingeki (literally, new play) instantly became a famous actress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiko OKADA who had belonged to Shingeki (literally, new play) instantly became a famous actress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiko OKADA who had belonged to Shingeki (literally, new play) instantly became a famous actress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>村田はカットごとに演出を細分化する、いわゆる映画的技法を最初に確立した監督の一人と言われているが、容赦なく自分の型に俳優をはめ込もうとして演技指導は苛烈を極め、岡田をはじめ当時の大女優とトラブルが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murata is thought to be a director who first established the so-called film technique in which a play was broken up by cutting, and since he tried to mold actors and actresses into his style, his acting instruction was so harsh that there were a lot of troubles with leading actresses of that time including Okada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murata is thought to be a director who first established the so-called film technique in which a play was broken up by cutting, and since he tried to mold actors and actresses into his style, his acting instruction was so harsh that there was a lot of trouble with leading actresses of that time including Okada.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murata is thought to be a director who first established the so-called film technique in which a play was broken up by cutting, and since he tried to mold actors and actresses into his style, his acting instruction was so harsh that there was a lot of trouble with leading actresses of that time including Okada.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>この『街の手品師』撮影・封切前後は木村荘十二を等持院の自宅の書生に招き、日活野球部にいた中野英治を俳優部に採用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the time when this &quot;Machi no Tejinashi&quot; was being shot to around the time this movie started to show, he invited Sotoji KIMURA to his house in Tojiin as shosei (a student who is given room and board in exchange for performing domestic duties,) and headhunt Eiji NAKANO from Nikkatsu Baseball Team to employ him for Haiyubu (俳優部).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the time when this &quot;Machi no Tejinashi&quot; was being shot to around the time this movie started to show, he invited Sotoji KIMURA to his house in Tojiin as shosei (a student who is given room and board in exchange for performing domestic duties,) and headhunt Eiji NAKANO from Nikkatsu Baseball Team to employ him for Haiyubu (俳優部).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the time when this &quot;Machi no Tejinashi&quot; was being shot to around the time this movie started to show, he invited Sotoji KIMURA to his house in Tojiin as shosei (a student who is given room and board in exchange for performing domestic duties), and headhunt Eiji NAKANO from Nikkatsu Baseball Team to employ him for Haiyubu (Actors Department).</e>
<cmt>(Actors Department)補足→定訳不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>次作『大地は微笑む』の撮影直前に急病で倒れ、溝口健二が代わり成功させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just before the shooting of a next film &quot;Daichi wa hohoemu&quot; (The Earth Smiles) was about to start, he fell sick and Kenji MIZOGUCHI substituted for him and made the film successful.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before the shooting of a next film &quot;Daichi wa hohoemu&quot; (The Earth Smiles) was about to start, he fell sick and Kenji MIZOGUCHI substituted for him and made the film successful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before the shooting of a next film &quot;Daichi wa hohoemu&quot; (The Earth Smiles) was about to start, he fell sick and Kenji MIZOGUCHI substituted for him and made the film successful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>同年7月、ドイツのウエスチ社のすすめで『街の手品師』を携え、脚本を担当した森岩雄とともに尾上松之助ら日活重役に見送られて渡欧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July of the same year, at the advice of Ueschi-sha (ウエスチ社) in Germany, Mizoguchi left for Europe to hold a show of &quot;Machi no Tejinashi&quot; with Iwao MORI who wrote the scenario, leaving Nikkatsu&apos;s directors including Matsunosuke ONOE who came to see them out at the airport.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July of the same year, at the advice of Ueschi-sha (ウエスチ社) in Germany, Mizoguchi left for Europe to hold a show of &quot;Machi no Tejinashi&quot; with Iwao MORI who wrote the scenario, leaving Nikkatsu&apos;s directors including Matsunosuke ONOE who came to see them out at the airport.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July of the same year, at the advice of Ueschi-sha in Germany, Mizoguchi left for Europe to hold a show of &quot;Machi no Tejinashi&quot; with Iwao MORI who wrote the scenario, leaving Nikkatsu&apos;s directors including Matsunosuke ONOE who came to see them out at the airport.</e>
<cmt>(ウエスチ社)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>パリ、ベルリンで上映会を開くが、上映機材の不具合や「絵の暗いこと、欧州臭いこと、特種国は特種国らしい味を出していればそれでいいのだ」（仏『シネ・ミロア』誌）などと大不評であり、ショックを受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While they held a show in Paris and Berlin, they were shocked with problems occurred to screening equipment and bad critics, &apos;The pictures are too dark and have a Western air too much; it is enough for such a unique country to add its own taste to the movie as a unique country.&apos; (French magazine &quot;Shine-miroa (シネ・ミロア.)&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While they held a show in Paris and Berlin, they were shocked with problems that occurred with screening equipment and bad critics, &apos;The pictures are too dark and have too much of a Western air too; it is enough for such a unique country to add its own taste to the movie as a unique country.&apos; (French magazine &quot;Shine-miroa (シネ・ミロア.)&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While they held a show in Paris and Berlin, they were shocked with problems that occurred with screening equipment and bad critics, &apos;The pictures are too dark and have too much of a Western air too; it is enough for such a unique country to add its own taste to the movie as a unique country&apos; (French magazine &quot;Shine-miroa&quot;).</e>
<cmt>(シネ・ミロア.)削除ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>しかし、ドイツのループピック監督が興味を示し上映会を開くという約束を取り付け、一応の面目を施して1926年1月に帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Germany director Lupu Pick got interested in the movie, and he was back home in January 1926 with his promise of holding a show for face-saving.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Germany director Lupu Pick got interested in the movie, and he was back home in January 1926 with his promise of holding a show to save face.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Germany director Lupu Pick got interested in the movie, and he was back home in January 1926 with his promise of holding a show to save face.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>帰国後、第二部主席監督となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he was back, he became the chief film director of the Second Department (第二部主席監督.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was back, he became the chief film director of the Second Department (第二部主席監督.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was back, he became the chief film director of the Second Department.</e>
<cmt>(第二部主席監督.)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>同年5月、連合映画芸術家協会の伊藤大輔との競作『日輪』では、ロシア構成主義者村山知義の抽象画風の装置を演出に取り入れ話題となり、第3回（1926年度）キネマ旬報ベストテンで第2位に選出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May of the same year, he was nominated as the second winner in the Third Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1926) because he used the setting featuring the abstract painting style of Tomoyoshi MURAYAMA as Russian Constructivism in a movie &quot;Nichirin (日輪)&quot; a joint film with Daisuke ITO (movie director) and drew a lot of attention.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処競作は、共作の誤りと思い、共作と英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May of the same year, he was nominated as the second winner in the Third Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1926) because he used the setting featuring the abstract painting style of Tomoyoshi MURAYAMA as Russian Constructivism in a movie &quot;Nichirin (日輪)&quot; a joint film with Daisuke ITO (movie director) and drew a lot of attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May of the same year, he was nominated as the second winner in the Third Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1926) because he used the setting featuring the abstract painting style of Tomoyoshi MURAYAMA as Russian Constructivism in a movie &quot;Nichirin&quot; a joint film with Daisuke ITO and drew a lot of attention.</e>
<cmt>(日輪)削除(映画監督) (movie director)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>師小山内薫も監督術を絶賛している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His master Kaoru OSANAI highly praised their ability and technique as a director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His master Kaoru OSANAI highly praised their ability and technique as a director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His master Kaoru OSANAI highly praised their ability and technique as a director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>しかし、当時の日活現代劇は松竹蒲田に大きく遅れをとっており、その対策として、同年6月に常務に昇格した根岸耕一の了解を得、森岩雄と丸の内の本社内に企画本部「日活金曜会」を設立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Nikkatsu gendai geki (日活現代劇) of that time was significantly behind Shochiku Kamata Studio and for countermeasures, he and Iwao MORI established planning headquarters &apos;Nikkatsu Kinyo-kai (日活金曜会)&apos; in the Marunouchi head office with the approval of Koichi NEGISHI who had been promoted to a director in June of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nikkatsu gendai geki (日活現代劇) of that time was significantly behind the Shochiku Kamata Studio and for countermeasures, he and Iwao MORI established the planning headquarters &apos;Nikkatsu Kinyo-kai (日活金曜会)&apos; at the Marunouchi head office with the approval of Koichi NEGISHI who had been promoted to director in June of the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nikkatsu gendai geki of that time was significantly behind the Shochiku Kamata Studio and for countermeasures, he and Iwao MORI established the planning headquarters &apos;Nikkatsu Kinyo-kai&apos; at the Marunouchi head office with the approval of Koichi NEGISHI who had been promoted to director in June of the same year.</e>
<cmt>(日活現代劇) (日活金曜会)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>本社に残っていた田中栄三をはじめ、益田甫、岩崎昶、山本嘉次郎ら社外の者が会員となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eizo TANAKA who was still in the head office and Hajime MASUDA, Akira IWASAKI and Kajiro YAMAMOTO who were persons outside of Nikkatsu joined Nikkatsu Kinyo-kai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eizo TANAKA who was still in the head office and Hajime MASUDA, Akira IWASAKI and Kajiro YAMAMOTO who were persons outside of Nikkatsu joined Nikkatsu Kinyo-kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eizo TANAKA who was still in the head office and Hajime MASUDA, Akira IWASAKI and Kajiro YAMAMOTO who were persons outside of Nikkatsu joined Nikkatsu Kinyo-kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>阿部豊ら日活監督のために清新なシナリオや企画を生産立案して、日活現代劇のモダン・イメージの形成に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They wrote new and fresh scenarios or made new and fresh plans for Nikkatsu&apos;s directors including Yutaka ABE, and succeeded in forming a modern image for Nikkatsu gendai geki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They wrote new and fresh scenarios or made new and fresh plans for Nikkatsu&apos;s directors including Yutaka ABE, and succeeded in forming a modern image for Nikkatsu gendai geki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They wrote new and fresh scenarios or made new and fresh plans for Nikkatsu&apos;s directors including Yutaka ABE, and succeeded in forming a modern image for Nikkatsu gendai geki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>1927年3月には『映画時代』三月号の「監督人気投票」で第一位（第二位は牛原虚彦）に選出され、監督としての確固たる地位を築く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1927, he was elected for the first rank in &apos;Director popularity poll&apos; in the magazine called &quot;Eiga Jidai&quot; (literally meaning movie era) March issue (Kiyohiko USHIHARA for the second rank) and established himself as movie director.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1927, he was elected for the first rank in the &apos;Director popularity poll&apos; in the magazine called &quot;Eiga Jidai&quot; (literally meaning movie era) March issue (Kiyohiko USHIHARA for the second rank) and established himself as a movie director.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1927, he was elected for the first rank in the &apos;Director popularity poll&apos; in the magazine called &quot;Eiga Jidai&quot; (literally meaning movie era) March issue (Kiyohiko USHIHARA for the second rank) and established himself as a movie director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>しかし、直後に開始された「金曜会」企画の『椿姫』の撮影中に主役の岡田嘉子に群衆の前で罵倒に近い叱声を浴びせかけ、私生活の縺れも重なって、岡田が相手役の竹内良一と駆け落ちし一時失踪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after that, when the shooting of &quot;Tsubaki hime&quot; (The Lady of the Camelias) as a project planned by &apos;Kinyo-kai&apos; was goin on, he blew up a leading character Yoshiko OKADA with his scorching-like words in front of crowds, and Okada ran off together with her opposite Ryoichi TAKEUCHI, also because of stress and frustration in her private life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after that, when the shooting of &quot;Tsubaki hime&quot; (The Lady of the Camelias) as a project planned by &apos;Kinyo-kai&apos; was goin on, he blew up a leading character Yoshiko OKADA with his scorching-like words in front of crowds, and Okada ran off together with her opposite Ryoichi TAKEUCHI, also because of stress and frustration in her private life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after that, when the shooting of &quot;Tsubaki hime&quot; (The Lady of the Camelias) as a project planned by &apos;Kinyo-kai&apos; was goin on, he blew up a leading character Yoshiko OKADA with his scorching-like words in front of crowds, and Okada ran off together with her opposite Ryoichi TAKEUCHI, also because of stress and frustration in her private life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>スキャンダルとして大騒ぎになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It caused a scandalous big fuss.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It caused a scandalous big fuss.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It caused a scandalous big fuss.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>会社が「岡田がやらないのなら、脚本をひっこめる」という森岩雄と嫌がる夏川静江をなだめ、ミスキャストに変更せざるを得なくなったが、興業的には大ヒットした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company persuaded Iwao MORI who was saying that &apos;Unless Okada takes the role, I will take back the scenario&apos; and Shizue NATSUKAWA who was reluctant to join, and the movie achieved a financial success, though they were compelled to change the characters to the imperfect casting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The company persuaded Iwao MORI who was saying that &apos;Unless Okada takes the role, I will take back the scenario&apos; and Shizue NATSUKAWA who was reluctant to join, and the movie achieved a financial success, though they were compelled to change the characters to the imperfect casting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The company persuaded Iwao MORI who was saying that &apos;Unless Okada takes the role, I will take back the scenario&apos; and Shizue NATSUKAWA who was reluctant to join, and the movie achieved a financial success, although they were compelled to change the characters to the imperfect casting.</e>
<cmt>though →although</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この頃から文芸部長として日活現代劇のプロデューサー的存在となり、1928年には田坂具隆の『結婚二重奏』（第5回（1928年度）キネマ旬報ベストテン第8位）の演出を手がけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this time, as a general manager of liberal art, he started taking a role of producing Nikkatsu modern drama and was involved in the production of Tomotaka TASAKA&apos;s &quot;Kekkon Nijuso&quot; (Marriage Duet) (the 8th place of the Fifth Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1928.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From that time, as a general manager of liberal art, he started taking on the role of producing Nikkatsu modern drama and was involved in the production of Tomotaka TASAKA&apos;s &quot;Kekkon Nijuso&quot; (Marriage Duet) (the 8th place of the Fifth Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1928.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From that time, as a general manager of liberal art, he started taking on the role of producing Nikkatsu modern drama and was involved in the production of Tomotaka TASAKA&apos;s &quot;Kekkon Nijuso&quot; (Marriage Duet) (the 8th place of the Fifth Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1928.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>同年6月に牛原虚彦と『映画科学研究』を創刊するなど、後進の指導にも注力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June of the same year, he published &quot;Eiga Kagaku Kenkyu&quot; which means &quot;Movie Science Research,&quot;with Kiyohiko USHIHARA and was devoted to teaching young people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year, he published &quot;Eiga Kagaku Kenkyu&quot; which means &quot;Movie Science Research,&quot;with Kiyohiko USHIHARA and was devoted to teaching young people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of the same year, he published &quot;Eiga Kagaku Kenkyu&quot; (Movie Science Research), with Kiyohiko USHIHARA and was devoted to teaching young people.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>そして年末には日本の思想風土の問題点を主題にした徳富蘆花原作の悲劇『灰燼』の撮影にとりかかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the year, he started shooting &quot;Kaijin,&quot; Roka TOKUTOMI&apos;s original tragedy featuring the issues of the climate of thought in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the year, he started shooting &quot;Kaijin,&quot; Roka TOKUTOMI&apos;s original tragedy featuring issues of the climate of thought in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the year, he started shooting &quot;Kaijin,&quot; Roka TOKUTOMI&apos;s original tragedy featuring issues of the climate of thought in Japan.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>翌1929年3月の封切を観た当時映画青年であった新藤兼人は、叡山ケーブルから中野英治扮する西郷軍の敗残兵の姿を追う青島順一郎の俯瞰移動撮影を「日本映画ではじめて見る壮大な映像美であった」と回想している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneto SHINDO who was a movie fan and watched Kaijin first-run in March 1929 the next year, reviewed that the movable long shots made by Junichiro AOSHIMA in Eizan cable car to follow Eiji NAKANO acting as a straggler of Saigo&apos;s army provided the beautiful spectacular scenes he had for the first time seen in Japanese movie history.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneto SHINDO who was a movie fan and watched Kaijin first-run in March 1929 the next year, reviewed that the movable long shots made by Junichiro AOSHIMA in Eizan cable car to follow Eiji NAKANO acting as a straggler of Saigo&apos;s army provided beautiful spectacular scenes he had, for the first time, seen in Japanese movie history.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneto SHINDO who was a movie fan and watched Kaijin first-run in March 1929 the next year, reviewed that the movable long shots made by Junichiro AOSHIMA in Eizan cable car to follow Eiji NAKANO acting as a straggler of Saigo&apos;s army provided beautiful spectacular scenes he had, for the first time, seen in Japanese movie history.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>「これは今日に至るまで、日本に於て作られた映画の中で、その最も優れたるものの一つである」と評され第6回（1929年度）キネマ旬報ベストテン第2位を獲得。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This movie was appreciated that &apos;This movie is one of the best movies which have been made in Japan so far&apos; and won the second prize in the Sixth Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1929.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This movie was appreciated; &apos;This movie is one of the best movies which have been made in Japan so far&apos; and won the second prize in the Sixth Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1929.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This movie was appreciated; &apos;This movie is one of the best movies which have been made in Japan so far&apos; and won the second prize in the Sixth Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1929.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>名実ともにトップ監督として大将軍撮影所を後にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a number one director both in name and reality and left Taishogun Film Studios.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a number one director both in name and reality and left Taishogun Film Studios.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a number one director both in name and reality and left Taishogun Film Studios.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="77">
<j>日活太秦撮影所時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Days in Nikkatsu Uzumasa movie studio</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Days at Nikkatsu Uzumasa movie studio</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Days at Nikkatsu Uzumasa movie studio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>1929年4月に日活撮影所への現代劇部の移転が完了、企画部長・監督部長・脚本部長を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1929, the moving of Gendai geki bu into Nikkatsu Studio was completed, and he took the posts of the general managers of the planning, director and scenario departments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1929, the moving of Gendai geki bu into Nikkatsu Studio was completed, and he took the posts of the general manager of the planning, director, and scenario departments.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1929, the moving of Gendai geki bu into Nikkatsu Studio was completed, and he took the posts of the general manager of the planning, director, and scenario departments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>ジョセフ・フォン・スタンバーグに大きく影響された作品『摩天楼・争闘篇』が『灰燼』とともに第6回キネマ旬報ベストテン第5位、翌1930年8月には「第一回日本優秀映画監督投票」で伊藤大輔（457票）に次いで第二位（388票）に選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both &quot;Matenro/Sotohen&quot; (Skyscraper/Fighting version) a product strongly impacted by Josef von Sternberg and &quot;Kaijin&quot; won the fifth place in the Sixth Kinema Junpo Top Ten, and in August 1930 the next year, he was voted the second place in &apos;the First Japanese Best Movie Directors Election after Daisuke ITO (a movie director) (four hundred and fifty seven votes.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both &quot;Matenro/Sotohen&quot; (Skyscraper/Fighting version) a product strongly impacted by Josef von Sternberg and &quot;Kaijin&quot; won the fifth place in the Sixth Kinema Junpo Top Ten, and in August 1930 the next year, he was voted second place in &apos;the First Japanese Best Movie Directors Election after Daisuke ITO (a movie director) (four hundred and fifty seven votes.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both &quot;Matenro/Sotohen&quot; (Skyscraper/Fighting version) a product strongly impacted by Josef von Sternberg and &quot;Kaijin&quot; won the fifth place in the Sixth Kinema Junpo Top Ten, and in August 1930 the next year, he was voted second place (388 votes) in &apos;the First Japanese Best Movie Directors Election&apos; after Daisuke ITO (457 votes).</e>
<cmt>補足(388 votes)補足ピリオド位置移動(映画監督) (movie director)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>さらに同年12月発行の『日活の社史と現勢』には「現代劇計画部長兼社長秘書」と紹介されることになるが、この頃の日活現代劇は既に溝口健二、田坂具隆、内田吐夢らの若い才能が台頭してきており、重役間の紛糾による「金曜会」の解散、時代の反映として激しくなる従業員と会社の対立、トーキー化に伴う製作形態の変化（会社側による監督の自由・自主的な作品製作の制限）に苦悩することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it was stated in &quot;Nikkatsu no shashi to gensei&quot; (literally, the history and status of Nikkatsu) issued in December of the same year that his post was &apos;general manager of Gendai geki planning department and president&apos;s secretary,&apos; he started suffering from the following: young talented persons such as Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Tomotaka TASAKA and Tomu UCHIDA were appearing in Nikkatsu gendai geki around this time, the dissolution of &apos;Kinyo-kai&apos; due to the embarrassment by directors, increasing confrontation between the company and its employees reflecting the period, changes in production style due to talking picture (the company put restrictions on directors to produce movies freely and independently.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it was stated in &quot;Nikkatsu no shashi to gensei&quot; (literally, the history and status of Nikkatsu) issued in December of the same year that his post was &apos;general manager of Gendai geki planning department and president&apos;s secretary,&apos; he started suffering from the following: young talented persons such as Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Tomotaka TASAKA, and Tomu UCHIDA were appearing in Nikkatsu gendai geki around this time, the dissolution of &apos;Kinyo-kai&apos; due to the embarrassment of the directors, increasing confrontations between the company and its employees reflecting the period, changes in production style due to talking pictures (the company placed restrictions on directors ability to produce movies freely and independently.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it was stated in &quot;Nikkatsu no shashi to gensei&quot; (literally, the history and status of Nikkatsu) issued in December of the same year that his post was &apos;general manager of Gendai geki planning department and president&apos;s secretary,&apos; he started suffering from the following: young talented persons such as Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Tomotaka TASAKA, and Tomu UCHIDA were appearing in Nikkatsu gendai geki around this time, the dissolution of &apos;Kinyo-kai&apos; due to the embarrassment of the directors, increasing confrontations between the company and its employees reflecting the period, changes in production style due to talking pictures (the company placed restrictions on directors ability to produce movies freely and independently).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>以前（1927年頃）『小型映画』に講座を執筆している関係で京極キネマ倶楽部の小型映画審査に出向き、そこで出会った当時住友銀行員でアマチュア映画を制作していた依田義賢が1930年に村田付きの助監督・スクリプターとして入社している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he visited Kyogoku Kinema Kurabu to judge small scale movies by the relations with writing for courses in &quot;Kogata Eiga&quot; before (around 1927,) he met Yoshikata YODA, an employee of Sumitomo Bank and an amateur movie producer and in 1930, hired him as Murata&apos;s assistant-director and scripter.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he visited Kyogoku Kinema Kurabu to judge small scale movies because of his relations with writing for courses in &quot;Kogata Eiga&quot; before (around 1927,) he met Yoshikata YODA, an employee of Sumitomo Bank and an amateur movie producer and in 1930, hired him as Murata&apos;s assistant-director and script writer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he visited Kyogoku Kinema Kurabu to judge small scale movies because of his relations with writing for courses in &quot;Kogata Eiga&quot; (Small Scale Movies) before (around 1927), he met Yoshikata YODA, an employee of Sumitomo Bank and an amateur movie producer and in 1930, hired him as Murata&apos;s assistant-director and script writer.</e>
<cmt>英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>彼は、『海のない港』（1931年）以降は「製作している村田の姿にも勢いがなく、持病の糖尿病が嵩じてきているのではないかと思える元気のなさや、セットに身を投げ、悩むように頭をかかえて、演出を案ずる姿など痛いたしいこともあった」と回想している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoda was recollecting that since &quot;Umi no nai minato&quot; (The Port without Ocean, 1931,) &apos;when producing a movie, Murata lost his vigor and was weak enough to think that his chronic disease diabetes were worsening, and looked painful when he was thinking about production, laying himself to stage sets and putting his head in his hands.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoda recollected that since &quot;Umi no nai minato&quot; (The Port without an Ocean, 1931,) &apos;when producing a movie, Murata lost his vigor and was weak enough to think that his chronic disease diabetes were worsening, and looked painful when he was thinking about production, laying himself to stage sets and putting his head in his hands.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoda recollected that since &quot;Umi no nai minato&quot; (The Port without an Ocean, 1931), &apos;when producing a movie, Murata lost his vigor and was weak enough to think that his chronic disease diabetes were worsening, and looked painful when he was thinking about production, laying himself to stage sets and putting his head in his hands.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>1932年8月には中谷貞頼専務が、名物所長として知られた池永浩久とその一派を駆逐し所内の実権を握ろうとした内紛劇が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1932, an internal battle was caused by Director Sadayori NAKATANI, who attempted to get rid of Tsunehisa IKENAGA known as a popular manager and his group of people to grasp powers in the company.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1932, an internal battle was caused by Director Sadayori NAKATANI, who attempted to get rid of Tsunehisa IKENAGA known as a popular manager and his group of people to grab the power in the company.</e>
<cmt>grammr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1932, an internal battle was caused by Director Sadayori NAKATANI, who attempted to get rid of Tsunehisa IKENAGA known as a popular manager and his group of people to grab the power in the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>さらに中谷が経営合理化の名目で撮影所従業員186名を大量解雇したことによる労働争議が勃発、他の幹部監督らと従業員側に立って争議を指導した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Nakatani executed massive layoffs of a hundred and eighty six employees of the studio in the name of operation efficiency, resulting in a labor dispute, and Murata and other key directors gave guidance for the labor dispute on the side of the employees.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Nakatani executed massive layoffs of a hundred and eighty six employees of the studio in the name of operation efficiency, resulting in a labor dispute, and Murata and other key directors gave guidance for the labor dispute on the side of the employees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Nakatani executed massive layoffs of 186 employees of the studio in the name of operation efficiency, resulting in a labor dispute, and Murata and other key directors gave guidance for the labor dispute on the side of the employees.</e>
<cmt>数字表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>しかし、やがて激化する従業員側と会社側との板挟みになり、9月には争議を「収拾する能力なくその任に耐えず」と伊藤大輔・内田吐夢・田坂具隆・小杉勇・島耕二・製作部の芦田勝の「脱退七人組」と共に退社した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was caught in the crossfire of the escalating employees side and the company side soon, and in September, quit the company with &apos;The Retiring Seven&apos; including Daisuke ITO, Tomu UCHIDA, Tomotaka TASAKA, Isamu KOSUGI and Koji SHIMA, and Masaru ASHIDA, saying that he is not capable of settling the dispute and is inappropriate to take the role.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was soon caught in the crossfire of the escalating employee side and the company side, and in September, quit the company with &apos;The Retiring Seven&apos; including Daisuke ITO, Tomu UCHIDA, Tomotaka TASAKA, Isamu KOSUGI, and Koji SHIMA, and Masaru ASHIDA, saying that he is not capable of settling the dispute and was inappropriate to take on the role.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was soon caught in the crossfire of the escalating employee side and the company side, and in September, quit the company with &apos;The Retiring Seven&apos; including Daisuke ITO, Tomu UCHIDA, Tomotaka TASAKA, Isamu KOSUGI, and Koji SHIMA, and Masaru ASHIDA from the Production Department, saying that he is not capable of settling the dispute and was inappropriate to take on the role.</e>
<cmt>from the Production Department補足→定訳不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>同時期に長女を亡くしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he lost his daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he lost his daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he lost his daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="87">
<j>新映画社・新興キネマ時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Days at Shin eigasha (New Film Company) and Shinko Cinema</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Days at Shin eigasha (New Film Company) and Shinko Cinema</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Days at Shin eigasha (New Film Company) and Shinko Cinema</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>退社と同時に「脱退七人組」で設立した「新映画社」は当初日活更生の一助に異色作品をもって新風を送ろうという外郭製作が目的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after quitting the company, &apos;The Retiring Seven&apos; established Shin eigasha (New Film Company) and their initial purpose was to send a new wind by introducing the external production of unique products in an attempt to assist in the renewal of Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after quitting the company, &apos;The Retiring Seven&apos; established Shin eigasha (New Film Company) and their initial purpose was to send a new wind by introducing the external production of unique products in an attempt to assist in the renewal of Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after quitting the company, &apos;The Retiring Seven&apos; established Shin eigasha (New Film Company) and their initial purpose was to send a new wind by introducing the external production of unique products in an attempt to assist in the renewal of Nikkatsu.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>しかし、途中から自主経営に方針を変え、森岩雄の支援で12月に村田実・田坂具隆監督、伊藤大輔脚本の第一回作品『昭和新選組』をPCLで撮影した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the halfway they changed their policy of their own independent management, and with assistance of Iwao MURATA, shot &quot;Showa Shinsen-gumi&quot; the first product based on the scenario of Daisuke ITO (movie director) by PCL in December, under directors Minoru MURATA and Tomotaka TASAKA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, halfway they changed their policy on their own independent management, and with the assistance of Iwao MURATA, shot &quot;Showa Shinsen-gumi&quot; the first product based on the scenario of Daisuke ITO (movie director) by PCL in December, under directors Minoru MURATA, and Tomotaka TASAKA.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, halfway they changed their policy on their own independent management, and with the assistance of Iwao MURATA, shot &quot;Showa Shinsen-gumi&quot; the first product based on the scenario of Daisuke ITO by PCL in December, under directors Minoru MURATA, and Tomotaka TASAKA.</e>
<cmt>(映画監督) (movie director)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>しかし、経営的手腕の問題で1933年5月に解散、新興キネマに吸収され短命な存在を終えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, the company was dissolved in May 1933 due to management capability and was absorbed into Shinko Cinema, closing a short-term life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, the company was dissolved in May 1933 due to poor management capability and was absorbed into Shinko Cinema, closing a short-term life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, the company was dissolved in May 1933 due to poor management capability and was absorbed into Shinko Cinema, closing a short-term life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>村田も東映京都撮影所に入所し、気のない凡作を矢継ぎ早に作るかと思われていたが、1934年、大仏次郎原作の『霧笛』で久々の高評価を受け、第11回（1934年度）キネマ旬報ベストテン第9位に選出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Murata joined Toei Kyoto Movie Studios, people thought that he would make mediocre products quickly one after another, but in 1934 he was highly appreciated about &quot;Muteki&quot; (A Foghorn) which was Jiro DAIBUTSU&apos;s original novel after a long-term interval and won the ninth prize in the Eleventh Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1934.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Murata joined Toei Kyoto Movie Studios, people thought that he would make mediocre products quickly one after another, but in 1934 he was highly appreciated about &quot;Muteki&quot; (A Foghorn) which was Jiro DAIBUTSU&apos;s original novel after a long-term interval and won the ninth prize in the Eleventh Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1934.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Murata joined Toei Kyoto Movie Studios, people thought that he would make mediocre products quickly one after another, but in 1934 he was highly appreciated about &quot;Muteki&quot; (A Foghorn) which was Jiro DAIBUTSU&apos;s original novel after a long-term interval and won the ninth prize in the Eleventh Kinema Junpo Top Ten (1934.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>この『霧笛』から村田は「国広周禄（國廣周祿）」の脚本名を使い始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this &quot;Muteki,&quot; he started using a name &apos;Shuroku Kunihiro&apos; for a scenario writer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After &quot;Muteki,&quot; he started using a name &apos;Shuroku Kunihiro&apos; as a scenario writer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After &quot;Muteki,&quot; he started using a name &apos;Shuroku Kunihiro&apos; as a scenario writer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="93">
<j>日本映画監督協会創立と晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of the Directors Guild of Japan and his later years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the Directors Guild of Japan and his later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the Directors Guild of Japan and his later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>1936年二・二六事件当日、「五社協定」の桎梏からの解放、映画監督の主体性と権利の確立のため、神田駿河台の駿台荘で集まった劇映画監督東西代表（村田、牛原虚彦、衣笠貞之助、伊藤大輔、伊丹万作）の間に「日本映画監督協会」設立の同意が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the day in 1936 when February 26th Incident occurred, east and west representatives (Murata, Kiyohiko USHIHARA, Teinosuke KINUGASA, Daisuke ITO (movie director) and Mansaku ITAMI) of theater movie directors got together at Sundai-so in Kanda Surugadai and reached an agreement on establishing &apos;Directors Guild of Japan&apos; in an attempt to relieve themselves from &apos;Five Company Agreement&apos; as a fetter and secure movie director&apos;s independence and rights.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the day in 1936 when the February 26th Incident occurred, east and west representatives (Murata, Kiyohiko USHIHARA, Teinosuke KINUGASA, Daisuke ITO (movie director) and Mansaku ITAMI) of theater movie directors got together at Sundai-so in Kanda Surugadai and reached an agreement on establishing the &apos;Directors Guild of Japan&apos; in an attempt to relieve themselves from &apos;Five Company Agreement&apos; as a fetter and secure movie director&apos;s independence and rights.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the day in 1936 when the February 26th Incident occurred, east and west representatives (Murata, Kiyohiko USHIHARA, Teinosuke KINUGASA, Daisuke ITO and Mansaku ITAMI) of theater movie directors got together at Sundai-so in Kanda Surugadai and reached an agreement on establishing the &apos;Directors Guild of Japan&apos; in an attempt to relieve themselves from &apos;Five Company Agreement&apos; as a fetter and secure movie director&apos;s independence and rights.</e>
<cmt>(映画監督) (movie director)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>3月1日に東京會舘で発会式が開かれ、初代理事長に選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 1, an inaugural ceremony was held at Tokyo Kaikan Hall and he was appointed as the first administrative director of directors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 1, an inaugural ceremony was held at Tokyo Kaikan Hall and he was appointed the first administrative director of directors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 1, an inaugural ceremony was held at Tokyo Kaikan Hall and he was appointed the first administrative director of directors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>監督の力を確立し、業界に認めさせ、その創作力を芸術にまで向上させるために努力した功績によるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was because of his great performance that he endeavored to establish director&apos;s power, make it accepted by the industry and enhance their creating ability up to art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was because of his great performance that he endeavored to establish the director&apos;s power, make it accepted by the industry and enhance their creating ability to an art.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was because of his great performance that he endeavored to establish the director&apos;s power, make it accepted by the industry and enhance their creating ability to an art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>しかし同年秋、『新月抄』を撮影中に持病の糖尿病で倒れ東大病院に入院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In autumn of the same year, when shooting &quot;Shingetsusho,&quot; (&quot;The New Moon Story&quot;, literally,) he broke down from his chronic disease diabetes and was hospitalized in Todai Hospital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In autumn of the same year, when shooting &quot;Shingetsusho,&quot; (&quot;The New Moon Story&quot;, literally,) he broke down from his chronic disease diabetes and was hospitalized in Todai Hospital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In autumn of the same year, when shooting &quot;Shingetsusho,&quot; (&quot;The New Moon Story&quot;, literally,) he broke down from his chronic disease diabetes and was hospitalized in Todai Hospital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>入院中は牛原虚彦をつづけざまの速達で呼び出し、監督協会の将来を論じ合ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that when staying in hospital, he asked Kiyohiko USHIHARA to visit him by repeated express mails and discussed with him about the future of Kantoku kyokai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when staying in hospital, he asked Kiyohiko USHIHARA to visit him by repeated express mails and discussed with him about the future of Kantoku kyokai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when staying in hospital, he asked Kiyohiko USHIHARA to visit him by repeated express mails and discussed with him about the future of Kantoku kyokai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>翌1937年6月、肋膜炎を併発し44歳（満43歳）の若さで世を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1937 the following year, he also developed pleurisy and died young at the age of forty four (the forty three birthday.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1937 the following year, he also developed pleurisy and died young at the age of forty four (his forty third birthday.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1937 the following year, he also developed pleurisy and died young at the age of forty four (his forty third birthday.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>葬儀は小石川の東京カテドラル聖マリア大聖堂で初の映画監督協会葬として盛大に開かれ、棺は溝口健二、牛原虚彦、島津保次郎、衣笠貞之助、井上金太郎、青島順一郎の肩に担がれ祭壇に安置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Directors Guild of Japan held the first large-scaled corporate funeral for Murata at Tokyo St. Mary&apos;s cathedral in Koishikawa and Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Kiyohiko USHIHARA, Yasujiro SHIMAZU, Teinosuke KINUGASA, Kintaro INOUE and Junichiro AOSHIMA carried the coffin over their shoulders and placed it on an alter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Directors Guild of Japan held the first large-scaled corporate funeral for Murata at Tokyo St. Mary&apos;s cathedral in Koishikawa and Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Kiyohiko USHIHARA, Yasujiro SHIMAZU, Teinosuke KINUGASA, Kintaro INOUE, and Junichiro AOSHIMA carried the coffin over their shoulders and placed it on an alter.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Directors Guild of Japan held the first large-scaled corporate funeral for Murata at Tokyo St. Mary&apos;s cathedral in Koishikawa and Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Kiyohiko USHIHARA, Yasujiro SHIMAZU, Teinosuke KINUGASA, Kintaro INOUE, and Junichiro AOSHIMA carried the coffin over their shoulders and placed it on an alter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>盧溝橋事件の十日前であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was ten days prior to Rokokyo bridge Incident (the Marco Polo Bridge Incident.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was ten days prior to the Rokokyo bridge Incident (the Marco Polo Bridge Incident.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was ten days prior to the Rokokyo bridge Incident (the Marco Polo Bridge Incident.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>1985年、黒澤明が映画人初の文化勲章を授与した際に行われた共同記者会見で、「今回の受賞は自分が映画界の長老になってしまったということであって、あの人たちが生きていれば当然あの人たちも受賞の対象になったはずだ」として溝口健二、小津安二郎、成瀬巳喜男、最後に村田実の四人の名前を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Akira KUROSAWA was first conferred the Order of Culture among film related persons in 1985, he said in an interview &apos;This award meant that I am the oldest person in the film industry, and if those people were alive, they should have been for this award.&apos; pointing out the names of four persons including Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Yasujiro OZU, Mikio NARUSE and last, Minoru MURATA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Akira KUROSAWA was first conferred the Order of Culture among film related persons in 1985, he said in an interview &apos;This award meant that I am the oldest person in the film industry, and if those people were alive, they should have received this award.&apos; pointing out the names of four persons including Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Yasujiro OZU, Mikio NARUSE, and last, Minoru MURATA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Akira KUROSAWA was first conferred the Order of Culture among film related persons in 1985, he said in an interview &apos;This award meant that I am the oldest person in the film industry, and if those people were alive, they should have received this award.&apos; pointing out the names of four persons including Kenji MIZOGUCHI, Yasujiro OZU, Mikio NARUSE, and last, Minoru MURATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>中野英治は次のように語った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eiji NAKANO said &apos;It&apos;s not for sure, but if Murata were alive, he should have ascended to a much higher rank, though he, of course, was already a top-class person at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eiji NAKANO said &apos;It&apos;s not for sure, but if Murata were alive, he should have ascended to a much higher rank, though he, of course, was already a top-class person at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eiji NAKANO said as follows.</e>
<cmt>原文を修正。一原文一訳文になるように、次のセルに移動。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>「これはわからないことですが、生きていれば村田さんはもっとトップ・クラスの人、もちろんその当時でもトップでしたが、になっていたと思いますよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s not for sure, but if Murata were alive, he should have ascended to a much higher rank, though he, of course, was already a top-class person at that time.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文を修正。一原文一訳文になるように、次のセルに移動。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>「四十四歳で亡くなってしまいましたけど。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of forty four, though.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of forty four, though.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of forty four, though.&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>「溝口健二よりははるかに上になったと思います。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He would have gone up to a much higher rank than Kenji MIZOGUCHI.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He would have reached a much higher rank than Kenji MIZOGUCHI.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He would have reached a much higher rank than Kenji MIZOGUCHI.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>依田義賢は「私がついた頃の村田さんはだいぶ調子が落ちてた頃で」と断った上で、以下のように評価した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka YODA, adding &apos;Around the time I started working for Murata, his condition was pretty bad,&apos; said &apos;I can&apos;t help but compare him to Kenji MIZOGUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka YODA, adding &apos;Around the time I started working for Murata, his condition was pretty bad,&apos; said &apos;I can&apos;t help but compare him to Kenji MIZOGUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka YODA, adding &apos;Around the time I started working for Murata, his condition was pretty bad,&apos; evaluated as follows.</e>
<cmt>原文文頭をセル118に移動スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>「私の場合、どうしても溝口健二と比べてしまう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I can&apos;t help but compare him to Kenji MIZOGUCHI.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文にするため、セル122の原文を分けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>「すると、なんや、これは……となってしまう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, I feel like &quot;what on earth is this film?&quot;</e>
<cmt>日本語原文の意味が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, I feel like &quot;what on earth is this film?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, I feel like &quot;what on earth is this film?&quot;&apos;</e>
<cmt>補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>「（中略）村田実の没落はね、そのバタ臭さがもう古うなってしまった、時代と合わなくなったことにあると思うんです。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Snip) The reason why Minoru MURATA lost popularity seems his Western style is too old to fit with the times.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Snip) The reason why Minoru MURATA lost popularity seemed to be that his Western style was too old to fit with the times.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Snip) The reason why Minoru MURATA lost popularity seemed to be that his Western style was too old to fit with the times.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>語り部によって毀誉褒貶の差が激しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on the persons, difference between approval and disapproval was big.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending on the person, the difference between approval and disapproval was great.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on the person, the difference between approval and disapproval was great.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>戦前の日活のフィルム倉庫の火災などにより、初期の習作『路上の霊魂』と新興キネマで撮った『霧笛』の二作しか現存していないため、最も評価の困難な監督の一人として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to a fire occurred in Nikkatsu&apos;s film warehouse before the war, only two movies exist, &quot;Rojo no Reikon&quot; (Souls on The Road) as an initial study product and &quot;Muteki&quot;which he shot in Shinko Cinema, so he is said to be one of the most difficult directors for evaluation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to a fire that occurred in Nikkatsu&apos;s film warehouse before the war, only two movies exist, &quot;Rojo no Reikon&quot; (Souls on The Road) as an initial study product and &quot;Muteki&quot;which he shot in Shinko Cinema, so he is said to be one of the most difficult directors to evaluate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to a fire that occurred in Nikkatsu&apos;s film warehouse before the war, only two movies exist, &quot;Rojo no Reikon&quot; (Souls on The Road) as an initial study product and &quot;Muteki&quot; which he shot in Shinko Cinema, so he is said to be one of the most difficult directors to evaluate.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Arpeggio(id:9385), なおぞー(id:80442), Cprobot(id:97843), Complex01(id:10454), Point136(id:211299), ヤキューまん(id:117497), 松木完之(id:26818), Bokka7568(id:275377), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>