<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平田鐵胤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetane HIRATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetane HIRATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetane HIRATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平田 銕胤（ひらた かねたね、1799年12月31日（寛政11年12月6日 (旧暦)） - 1880年（明治13年）10月25日）は、日本の国学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetane HIRATA (December 31, 1799 – October 25, 1880 according to old lunar calendar) was a scholar of ancient Japanese literature and culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetane HIRATA (December 31, 1799 – October 25, 1880 according to the old lunar calendar) was a scholar of ancient Japanese literature and culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetane HIRATA (December 31, 1799 – October 25, 1880) was a scholar of ancient Japanese literature and culture.</e>
<cmt>according to the old lunar calendar 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>伊予国（愛媛県）出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from Iyo Province (present Ehime Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from Iyo Province (present Ehime Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from Iyo Province (present Ehime Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Ehime Province→Ehime Prefecture</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>喜多郡新谷藩士・加藤大蔵少輔家来・碧川衛門八の長子で篤眞（あつま）と称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of Emohachi MIDORIKAWA, a statesman of the Niiya Domain (Kita County) and a liegeman of Okuranoshoyu (junior assistant minister of the Ministry of Finance) Kato, and he called himself Atsuma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of Emohachi MIDORIKAWA, a statesman of the Niiya Domain (Kita County) and a liegeman of Okuranoshoyu (junior assistant minister of the Ministry of Finance) Kato, and he called himself Atsuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of Emohachi MIDORIKAWA, a feudal retainer of the Niiya clan (Kita County) and a liegeman of Okuranoshoyu (junior assistant minister of the Ministry of Finance) Kato, and he called himself Atsuma.</e>
<cmt>藩士を定訳に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄の影響を受け文政5年5月には弟の碧川好尚（みどりかわよしひさ）が氣吹舎に正式に入門をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Ibukinoya School, and by his influence, his brother Yoshihisa MIDORIKAWA also formally entered the same school in May 1822 (according to old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered Ibukinoya School, and by his influence, his brother Yoshihisa MIDORIKAWA also formally entered the same school in May 1822 (according to the old lunar calendar)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered Ibukinoya School, and by his influence, his brother Yoshihisa MIDORIKAWA also formally entered the same school in May 1822 (according to the old lunar calendar)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>文政7年1月15日、兄である篤眞(鐡胤)は縁により国学者平田篤胤翁の養子となり、篤胤の娘おてう（後に織瀬と改名した）と結婚し、名を篤実（あつさね）、通称内蔵助（くらのすけ）のちに大角（だいがく）と改め、篤胤の後継者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 15,1824 (according to old lunar calendar), Atsuma (Kanetane) was adopted into Atsutane HIRATA, a famous scholar of ancient Japanese literature and culture, got married to Atsutane&apos;s daughter Oteu (later she called herself Orise), and changed his name to Atsusane, calling himself Kuranosuke (later he called himself Daigaku), then practically he became the successor to Atsutane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 15,1824 (according to the old lunar calendar), Atsuma (Kanetane) was adopted by Atsutane HIRATA, a famous scholar of ancient Japanese literature and culture, got married to Atsutane&apos;s daughter Oteu (later she called herself Orise), and changed his name to Atsusane, calling himself Kuranosuke (later he called himself Daigaku), then, he practically became the successor to Atsutane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 15,1824 (according to the old lunar calendar), Atsuma (Kanetane) was adopted by Atsutane HIRATA, a famous scholar of ancient Japanese literature and culture, got married to Atsutane&apos;s daughter Oteu (later she called herself Orise), and changed his name to Atsusane, calling himself Kuranosuke (later he called himself Daigaku), then, he practically became the successor to Atsutane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>明治元年、神祇官判事に任じられ、明治天皇の侍講となり、ついで大學大博士に進み、大教正となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1868 (the first year of the Meiji era), he was appointed to Jingikan Hanji (judge of the department of worship) and Jico (teacher) of Emperor Meiji; later he became Daigaku Daihakusi (senior doctor of college), then finally became Daikyosei (the highest-ranking post of the department of worship).</e>
<cmt>神祇省(the department of worship)は教部省に名前が変わり、教正は教部省のポストらしいですが、省としての役割は同じなので訳the department of worshipは変えませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1868 (the first year of the Meiji era), he was appointed to Jingikan Hanji (judge of the department of worship) and Jico (teacher) of Emperor Meiji; later he became Daigaku Daihakusi (senior doctor of college), then finally became Daikyosei (the highest-ranking post of the department of worship).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1868 (the first year of the Meiji period), he was appointed to Jingikan Hanji (judge of the department of worship) and Jiko (teacher) of Emperor Meiji; later he became Daigaku Daihakusi (senior doctor of college), then finally became Daikyosei (the highest-ranking post of the department of worship).</e>
<cmt>era→periodjico→jiko</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>著書に『大壑君御一代略記』『祝詞正訓』『毀誉相半書本教道統傳』『児の手かしハ』その他がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left many works including &quot;Daigaku-kun Goichidai Ryakuki&quot; (Short Story of Great Daigaku-kun&apos;s Life), &quot;Norito Seikun&quot; (Correct Reading for Prayers), &quot;Kiyosohan-sho, Honkyo-doto-den&quot; (The Controversial Study, Orthodox Line of the Moral Teachings), &quot;Konote-gashiwa&quot; (Konote-oak).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left many works including &quot;Daigaku-kun Goichidai Ryakuki&quot; (Short Story of Great Daigaku-kun&apos;s Life), &quot;Norito Seikun&quot; (Correct Reading for Prayers), &quot;Kiyosohan-sho, Honkyo-doto-den&quot; (The Controversial Study, Orthodox Line of the Moral Teachings), and &quot;Konote-gashiwa&quot; (Konote-oak).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left many works including &quot;Daigaku-kun Goichidai Ryakuki&quot; (Short Story of Great Daigaku-kun&apos;s Life), &quot;Norito Seikun&quot; (Correct Reading for Prayers), &quot;Kiyosohan-sho, Honkyo-doto-den&quot; (The Controversial Study, Orthodox Line of the Moral Teachings), and &quot;Konote-gashiwa&quot; (Konote-oak).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>篤胤が生前に残した多額の借財をすべて返済し、ひたすら古道の普及と顕彰に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He cleared off all the enormous debts that Atsutane had accumulated while he had been alive, and worked hard to popularize Kodo (ancient method, ancient moral teachings and the way of learning).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He cleared off all the enormous debts that Atsutane had accumulated while he had been alive, and worked hard to popularize Kodo (ancient method, ancient moral teachings and the way of learning).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He cleared off all the enormous debts that Atsutane had accumulated while he had been alive, and worked hard to popularize Kodo (ancient method, ancient moral teachings and the way of learning).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>享年82。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 82.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 82.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 82.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>鐵胤の人物は温厚・学者肌・学問一筋の勉学家であり、人と競わず緻密で物事をおろそかにせず、生一本の人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetane devoted his life to the study and work hard with a lot of endowments as a scholar; he was a good-tempered person, disliked arousing rivalry, earnestly devoted himself close examinations, and had never neglected his duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetane devoted his life to studying and worked hard for which he obtained a lot of endowments as a scholar; he was a good-tempered person, disliked arousing rivalry, earnestly devoted himself to close examinations, and never neglected his duties.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetane devoted his life to studying and worked hard for which he obtained a lot of endowments as a scholar; he was a good-tempered person, disliked arousing rivalry, earnestly devoted himself to close examinations, and never neglected his duties.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣが二文に分けられていますが、原文が訳文どおりに分けられないため、再び一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この人柄は質実剛健な父と良妻賢母の母の影響であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Presumably his character had been formed by his father, who had been a simple and sturdy person, and his mother, who had been a good wife and wise mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presumably his character had been formed by his father, who had been a simple and sturdy person, and his mother, who had been a good wife and wise mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presumably his character had been formed by his father, who had been a simple and sturdy person, and his mother, who had been a good wife and wise mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>彼は八歳にして手習いを始め、十歳には書を学び素読を習い、十五歳で元服、二十歳頃には和学を学び、其の師の指導により古今和歌集にしたしみ、やがて本居宣長の存在を読書によって知り国学に関心を抱くようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of eight, he learn how to write; at the age of ten, began to read basic Chinese literature; at the age of fifteen, celebrated his coming of age; at about the age of twenty, he began to learn ancient Japanese literature and became attached to &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) by the influence of his teacher, besides he knew Norinaga MOTOORI, a great scholar of ancient Japanese literature and culture, through his works, and became interested in such studies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of eight, he learnt how to write; at the age of ten, he began to read basic Chinese literature; at the age of fifteen, he celebrated his coming of age; at about the age of twenty, he began to learn ancient Japanese literature and became attached to &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) by the influence of his teacher, besides, he knew Norinaga MOTOORI, a great scholar of ancient Japanese literature and culture, through his works, and became interested in such studies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of eight, he learned how to write; at the age of 10, began to read basic Chinese literature; at the age of 15, celebrated his coming of age; at about the age of 20, he began to learn ancient Japanese literature and became attached to &quot;Kokin Wakashu&quot; (A Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry) by the influence of his teacher, besides, he knew Norinaga MOTOORI, a great scholar of ancient Japanese literature and culture, through his works, and became interested in such studies.</e>
<cmt>learn→learned数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>文政3年夏に、書肆の主人の紹介で、篤胤の『霊能真柱』『古史成文』『古史徴』その他に目を通し皇国に伝わる古道の学に憧憬思慕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the summer of 1820, by a shopkeeper of a bookshop, Kanetane was introduced Atsutane HIRATA&apos;s works including &quot;Tama no Mihashira&quot; (Concept of Afterlife), &quot;Koshi Seibun&quot; (Early History) and &quot;Koshicho&quot; (Clarification of Early History), then he grew a longing for the study of Japanese Kodo (ancient method, ancient moral teachings and the way of learning).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the summer of 1820, a shopkeeper of a bookshop introduced Kanetane to Atsutane HIRATA&apos;s works including &quot;Tama no Mihashira&quot; (Concept of Afterlife), &quot;Koshi Seibun&quot; (Early History) and &quot;Koshicho&quot; (Clarification of Early History), then he grew a longing for the study of Japanese Kodo (ancient method, ancient moral teachings and the way of learning).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the summer of 1820, a shopkeeper of a bookshop introduced Kanetane to Atsutane HIRATA&apos;s works including &quot;Tama no Mihashira&quot; (Concept of Afterlife), &quot;Koshi Seibun&quot; (Early History) and &quot;Koshicho&quot; (Clarification of Early History), then he grew a longing for the study of Japanese Kodo.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そして切に平田門下に連なる事を希望し、正式に入門することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And finally he formally entered Atsutane HIRATA&apos;s school (Ibukinoya School) with the dearest wish of his heart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And finally he formally entered Atsutane HIRATA&apos;s school (Ibukinoya School) with the dearest wish of his heart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And finally, he formally entered Atsutane Hirata&apos;s school (Ibukinoya School) with the dearest wish of his heart.</e>
<cmt>HIRATA→Hirata</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後、文政5年5月15日に兄の影響により16歳になった実弟の好尚が誓詞を提出して氣吹舎(平田塾)に入門している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, on May 15, 1822 (according to old lunar calendar), by his influence, his brother Yoshihisa (at the age of sixteen) also submitted the oath as student and entered Ibukinoya School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, on May 15, 1822 (according to the old lunar calendar), by his influence, his brother Yoshihisa (at the age of sixteen) also took the oath as student and entered Ibukinoya School.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, on May 15, 1822 (according to the old lunar calendar), by his influence, his brother Yoshihisa (at the age of 16) also took the oath as student and entered Ibukinoya School (Hirata school).</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更「(平田塾)」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>兄同様弟も求道の念篤く学問好きで後に師の遺著『大道或問』を編集して上梓し、安政2年には自ら神代巻を大要した『稽古要略』『神武沿革考』を著している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like his brother, Yoshihisa studied hard with his deep longing for Kodo; later he edited and published one of their teacher&apos;s literary remains &quot;Daido Wakumon&quot; (Studies on the Great Kodo), besides, in 1855, he wrote &quot;Keiko Yoryaku&quot;, the summary of the volume of Jindai (the period of gods) of his teacher&apos;s work, as well as &quot;Jinmu Enkaku-ko&quot; (Studies on the History of the First Emperor Jinmu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like his brother, Yoshihisa studied hard with a deep longing for Kodo; later he edited and published one of their teacher&apos;s literary remains &quot;Daido Wakumon&quot; (Studies on the Great Kodo), besides, in 1855, he wrote &quot;Keiko Yoryaku&quot;, the summary of the volume of Jindai (the period of gods), which was his teacher&apos;s work, as well as &quot;Jinmu Enkaku-ko&quot; (Studies on the History of the First Emperor Jinmu).</e>
<cmt>grammar and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like his brother, Yoshihisa studied hard with a deep longing for Kodo; later he edited and published one of their teacher&apos;s literary remains &quot;Daido Wakumon&quot; (Studies on the Great Kodo), besides, in 1855, he wrote &quot;Keiko Yoryaku&quot;, the summary of the volume of Jindai (the period of gods), which was his teacher&apos;s work, as well as &quot;Jinmu Enkaku-ko&quot; (Studies on the History of the First Emperor Jinmu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また「三神山餘考」や「大道或問」など師の著作の序文も記しているが、篤胤門下平田塾に於ける高弟の一人でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa was one of leading disciples of Ibukinoya School and wrote the prefaces of his teacher&apos;s works such as &quot;Sanshinzan Yoko&quot; (Additional Study on the Three Mysterious Mountain of China) and &quot;Daido Wakumon&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa was one of the leading disciples of Ibukinoya School and wrote the prefaces of his teacher&apos;s works such as &quot;Sanshinzan Yoko&quot; (Additional Study on the Three Mysterious Mountains of China) and &quot;Daido Wakumon&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa was one of the leading disciples of Ibukinoya School and wrote the prefaces of his teacher&apos;s works such as &quot;Sanshinzan Yoko&quot; (Additional Study on the Three Mysterious Mountains of China) and &quot;Daido Wakumon&quot;.</e>
<cmt>書籍名が原文では「」ですが、ここ以外は『』ですので、訳文は訂正していません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>「神のお計らいは不測である」とは篤胤が弟子達に常々申し述べていたことではあるが、伊予出身の碧川篤眞が入門から二年後に平田大角と改称し、娘お長（千枝子）の婿養子になり平田家の跡目を継ぐようになるとは、さすがの彼も予見できなかったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their teacher, Atsutane often told his students &quot;the plans of the gods are unforeseen&quot;, however, presumably, he really hadn&apos;t been able to foreseen that his student Atsuma MIDORIKAWA from Iyo Province got married to his daughter Oteu (her real name was Chieko), changed his name to Daigaku HIRATA by being adopted into the Hirata family, and became the successor to his family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their teacher, Atsutane often told his students &quot;the plans of the gods are unforeseen&quot;, however, presumably, he really hadn&apos;t been able to foresee that his student Atsuma MIDORIKAWA from Iyo Province will get married to his daughter Oteu (her real name was Chieko) and later change his name to Daigaku HIRATA after being adopted into the Hirata family, and become the successor to his family.</e>
<cmt>grammar and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their teacher, Atsutane often told his students &apos;the plans of the gods are unforeseen&apos;, however, presumably, he really hadn&apos;t been able to foresee that his student Atsuma MIDORIKAWA from Iyo Province would get married to his daughter Oteu (her real name was Chieko) and later change his name to Daigaku HIRATA after being adopted into the Hirata family, and become the successor to his family.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;will → would</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>篤胤逝去後に同郷の死後の門人矢野玄道が、大角の依頼により未完の古史伝を完成させたのも奇しき巡り合わせであり、古道普及の為に東奔西走しては門人の拡張や復古神道の教義普及に努め、父であり師でもある篤胤の遺教を普く宣布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether it was the gods&apos; plan or not, after Atsutane had died, Kanetane (by that time he had changed his name to Daigaku) committed the continuation of Atsutane&apos;s &quot;Koshi-den&quot; (Annotation of Early History) to Harumichi YANO from Iyo Province, who had entered the school after Atsutane had died and completed &quot;Koshi-den&quot; at last; besides Kanetane worked hard to popularizing Kodo by increasing students and teaching the doctrine of the classical Shinto, and succeeded in propagating the thoughts that his father-in-low and his teacher, Atsutane had left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether it was the gods&apos; plan or not, after Atsutane died, Kanetane (by that time he had changed his name to Daigaku) committed the continuation of Atsutane&apos;s &quot;Koshi-den&quot; (Annotation of Early History) to Harumichi YANO from Iyo Province, who had entered the school after Atsutane had died and eventually completed &quot;Koshi-den&quot;; besides that, Kanetane worked hard to popularize Kodo by increasing the number of students and teaching the doctrine of the classical Shinto, and succeeded in propagating the thoughts that his father-in-law and his teacher, Atsutane had left.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether it was the gods&apos; plan or not, after Atsutane died, Kanetane (by that time he had changed his name to Daigaku) committed the continuation of Atsutane&apos;s &quot;Koshi-den&quot; (Annotation of Early History) to Harumichi YANO from Iyo Province, who had entered the school after Atsutane had died and eventually completed &quot;Koshi-den&quot;; besides that, Kanetane worked hard to popularize Kodo by increasing the number of students and teaching the doctrine of the classical Shinto, and succeeded in propagating the thoughts that his father-in-law and his teacher, Atsutane had left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また鐵胤は篤胤の死後、放漫な家政を整理し莫大な借金の返済を成し遂げたのみならず、平田家の財を築き上げるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What&apos;s more, following Atsutane&apos;s death, Kanetane had to manage the household that had been treated a little irresponsibly, cleared off the enormous debts, and surprisingly made a fortune for the Hirata family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What&apos;s more, following Atsutane&apos;s death, Kanetane had to manage the household that had been treated a little irresponsibly, cleared off the enormous debts, and surprisingly made a fortune for the Hirata family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What&apos;s more, following Atsutane&apos;s death, Kanetane had to manage the household that had been treated a little irresponsibly, cleared off the enormous debts, and surprisingly made a fortune for the Hirata family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その蔭には、銕胤の妻で実の娘織瀬こと千枝子の内助の功があったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife and Atsutane&apos;s daughter Orise (Chieko) seems to have been always helping him, while keeping herself in shadow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife, Atsutane&apos;s daughter Orise (Chieko) seemed to have been helping him always, but keeping herself in the background.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife, Atsutane&apos;s daughter Orise (Chieko) seemed to have been helping him always, but keeping herself in the background.</e>
<cmt>全角符号を半角に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>古史伝続修の依頼文書簡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The letter that Kanetane asked Harumichi to complete &quot;Koshi-den&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The letter that Kanetane wrote to Harumichi asking him to complete &quot;Koshi-den&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The letter that Kanetane wrote to Harumichi asking him to complete &quot;Koshi-den&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>父であり師でもある亡き篤胤の未完の古史伝は、28巻迄出来上がり29巻～30巻の一部は書きかけで、それ以降は手付かずの状態であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetane&apos;s father-in-low and his teacher, Atsutane HIRATA left a fragment of &quot;Koshi-den&quot; (Annotation of Early History); volume one to twenty-eight had been already finished, however, volume twenty-nine and thirty had been left halfway, and from volume thirty-one hadn&apos;t been written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetane&apos;s father-in-law and teacher, Atsutane HIRATA, left a fragment of &quot;Koshi-den&quot; (Annotation of Early History); volumes one to twenty-eight had already been finished, however, volumes twenty-nine and thirty had been left halfway, and volume thirty-one onwards hadn&apos;t been written.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetane&apos;s father-in-law and teacher, Atsutane HIRATA, left a fragment of &quot;Koshi-den&quot;; volumes 1 to 28 had already been finished, however, volumes 29 and 30 had been left halfway, and volume 31 onwards hadn&apos;t been written.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>当初銕胤は学統を継承する長男の延胤に古史伝の完成を所望していたが、明治5年正月廿四日に45歳で逝去した為、苦渋の選択をせざるを得なかつた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, Kanetane hoped Nobutane, his oldest son to be the next successor to Hirata&apos;s school, complete the work, however, Nobutane died at the age of 45 on 24 January 1872, so he had to look for another proper scholar for the work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, Kanetane hoped Nobutane, his oldest son would be the next successor to Hirata&apos;s school, and complete the work, however, Nobutane died at the age of 45 on 24th January 1872, so he had to look for another suitable scholar for the work.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, Kanetane hoped Nobutane, his oldest son would be the next successor to Hirata&apos;s school, and complete the work, however, Nobutane died at the age of 45 on 24th January 1872, so he had to look for another suitable scholar for the work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>普通の著書と異なり神代史解釈であるが故に、熟慮に熟慮を重ねた末に、平田門下の逸材の一人でもある大洲の矢野玄道に白羽の矢をたてた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike normal works, &quot;Koshi-den&quot; was the annotation of the history of Jindai (the period of gods) and demanded deep understanding from the writer, so Kanetane deliberated about the most likely person for a long time, and finally, among his school&apos;s students, chose Harumichi YANO, a student of great talent from Ozu Domain (Iyo Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike normal works, &quot;Koshi-den&quot; was the annotation of the history of Jindai (the period of gods) and demanded deep understanding from the writer, so Kanetane deliberated on who was the most suitable person for a long time, and finally, among his school students, chose Harumichi YANO, a student of great talent from Ozu Domain (Iyo Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike normal works, &quot;Koshi-den&quot; was the annotation of the history of Jindai and demanded deep understanding from the writer, so Kanetane deliberated on who was the most suitable person for a long time, and finally, among his school students, chose Harumichi YANO, a student of great talent from Ozu clan (Iyo Province).</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除Domain→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>最初は鄭重に断った玄道であったが、三顧の礼を尽くす銕胤の熱意に、ついに承諾する事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially Harumichi politely refused the request, however, for Kanetane&apos;s repeated requests with all eagerness, at last he accepted it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially Harumichi politely refused the request, however, for Kanetane&apos;s repeated requests with all eagerness, at last he accepted it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially Harumichi politely refused the request, however, for Kanetane&apos;s repeated requests with all eagerness, at last he accepted it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その原因の一つに、師篤胤から不思議な知らせを夢で受け取ったからだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially Harumichi politely refused the request, however, for Kanetane&apos;s repeated requests with all eagerness, at last he accepted it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially Harumichi politely refused the request, however, because Kanetane requested repeatedly with all eagerness, he finally accepted it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the reasons why Harumichi accepted the request is that he received a strange message from his deceased teacher, Atsutane, in a dream.</e>
<cmt>前文と同じ文章が訳されていたので新たに翻訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>では、その依頼文書簡を、矢野太郎編『矢野玄道』S8年版、古史伝の続修より抜粋する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the letter that Kanetane requested Harumichi to complete the book; the passages are extracted from the article &apos;the continuation of Koshi-den&apos; of &quot;Yano Hiromichi&quot; (edited by Taro YANO, published in 1933).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is the letter that Kanetane wrote requesting Harumichi to complete the book; the passages are extracted from the article &apos;the continuation of Koshi-den&apos; of &quot;Yano Hiromichi&quot; (edited by Taro YANO, published in 1933).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is the letter that Kanetane wrote requesting Harumichi to complete the book; the passages are extracted from the article &apos;the continuation of Koshi-den&apos; of &quot;Yano Hiromichi&quot; (edited by Taro YANO, published in 1933).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>『今般改めてご依頼申したき儀これあり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I have a request to make of you.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I have a request to make to you.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I have a request to make to you.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>すなわち左に御意を得候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I am sorry to trouble you, but I would like you to read this letter and consider my request.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I am sorry to trouble you, but I would like you to read this letter and consider my request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I am sorry to trouble you, but I would like you to read this letter and consider my request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>右は先人著述の事、在世中に自分は存分に出来候も数部之有り候へども、又名目ばかりにて、稿本成らざるものあり、又半端にして余義なく打ち置きたるもあり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While our teacher was still alive, I assisted him in writing a few works of his, however, for my limited talents, some drafts haven&apos;t been completed and some works have been left halfway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While our teacher was still alive, I assisted him in writing a few of his works, however, because of my limited talents, some drafts haven&apos;t been completed and some works have been left halfway.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While our teacher was still alive, I assisted him in writing a few of his works, however, because of my limited talents, some drafts haven&apos;t been completed and some works have been left halfway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>生涯苦心致され候中にも、古史伝は最初文化の末頃より草稿取り掛かり、文政の始め頃に、成文一二巻程は、ざっと稿本成り候ところ、段々見識博くあいなり、殊に故鈴屋大人の御遺教をも相伺れ候て、いよいよ以って、世界悉く我が皇大神達の御鎔造（ツクリカタメ）なされたる事を感得致され候に付、古史伝は先ず差し置き、赤縣州を始め、印度及び西洋の古伝をも悉く皆探索網羅して、其の上にて、充分に古史の註解をと存し込まれ候て、文政の半ば頃より、専ら外国の学に困苦致され、凡そ廿余年も歳月を過ごされ候て、赤縣太古傳を初め、即ち今此れある丈の著述は出来候へ共、中々もって先人の心底に叶ひ候事には此れ無く候へ共、大抵は見当も付き候に依っては、私を始め門人の中の所存にも、段々時節後れ、先人も老年に成られ候に付き、先ず先ず外国の所は大抵にして差し置かれ、古史伝の清撰をしきりて、相願い催促致し候て、天保10年頃より、漸々と其の方にも趣かれ候所、言語規則の書之無きに付き、余儀なく五十音義の撰にかかり、凡そ一ヵ年ほど打ち過ぎられ候所、旧幕府の命に依って秋田へ放逐、尤も同所は本国の事、親族共も少なからず、第一旧君侯より厚く恩遇も之有りて会計の辛苦は薄らぎ候へ共、著述致す可き遑なく、此処両三年心配致され候内に病を発し入幽致され候次第にて残念至極にて御座候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Our teacher dedicated his life to the study requiring great pains; as to &quot;Koshi-den&quot;, at the end of the Bunka era (1804-1818), he began to write the draft, and by the early Bunsei era (1818-1830), about twelve volumes had been completed; however, by that time, he had also gradually gained an insight into the study and understood the teachings of the master of Suzunoya (Norinaga MOTOORI), then he realized that this world was the product of our great gods of Japan, so he decided to temporarily leave &quot;Koshi-den&quot; and first explore and read through all the past annotations of the histories of our country as well as those of India and Europe to use new knowledge to advantage in writing &quot;Koshi-den&quot;; therefore, since the middle of the Bunsei era, he studied hard mainly foreign literature and culture, and during over twenty years, he had completed almost all his works, which remain for us, including &quot;Sekiken Taiko-den&quot; (Japanese Early History); although he was never satisfied with his works, his students, of course, including myself, with a feeling of gratitude, thought that our master had succeeded in completing most his researches and studies, and concerned about the delay of completing &quot;Koshi-den&quot; and of our master&apos;s age, so we repeatedly begged him for restarting of writing it, then thankfully at about the tenth year of the Tenpo era (1839), he began to write it; however, at the request for writing linguistic method, he began to write &quot;Goju Ongi&quot; (Pronunciation and Meaning of Fifty Kana) while leaving &quot;Koshi-den&quot; again; after a year, he was banished to Akita Province by order of the former bakufu (the Tokugawa Shogunate), fortunately since Akita was his hometown and there were many relatives of his, besides the former load treated him very kindly, they eased him off the poor living, although under that conditions, he had no time to finish remaining works; he always concerned about those unfinished works, and after only a few years, he became sick and regrettably died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Our teacher dedicated his life to the study requiring great pains; as to &quot;Koshi-den&quot;, at the end of the Bunka era (1804-1818), he began to write the draft, and by the early Bunsei era (1818-1830), about twelve volumes had been completed; however, by that time, he had also gradually gained an insight into the study and understood the teachings of the master of Suzunoya (Norinaga MOTOORI), then he realized that this world was the product of our great gods of Japan, so he decided to suspend &quot;Koshi-den&quot; temporarily, and first explore and read through all the past annotations of the histories of our country as well as those of India and Europe to use new knowledge to his advantage in writing &quot;Koshi-den&quot;; therefore, since the middle of the Bunsei era, he intensly studied foreign literature and culture mainly, and during a period of over twenty years, he completed almost all his works, which he left for us, including &quot;Sekiken Taiko-den&quot; (Japanese Early History); although he was never satisfied with his works, his students, of course, including myself, with a feeling of gratitude, thought that our master had succeeded in completing most his researches and studies, and were concerned about the delay in completing &quot;Koshi-den&quot; and because of our master&apos;s age, we repeatedly begged him to restart the writing, then thankfully at about the tenth year of the Tenpo era (1839), he restarted; however, he was requested to write on linguistic methods so he began to write &quot;Goju Ongi&quot; (Pronunciation and Meaning of Fifty Kana) and suspended &quot;Koshi-den&quot; again; after a year, he was banished to Akita Province by order of the former bakufu (the Tokugawa Shogunate), fortunately since Akita was his hometown and there were many relatives of his, besides the former load treated him very kindly, they relieved him off poor living, although under those conditions, he had no time to finish the remaining works; he was always concerned about those unfinished works, and after only a few years, he became sick and regrettably died.</e>
<cmt>Re-wrote the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Our teacher dedicated his life to the study requiring great pains; as to &quot;Koshi-den&quot;, at the end of the Bunka era (1804-1818), he began to write the draft, and by the early Bunsei era (1818-1830), about 12 volumes had been completed; however, by that time, he had also gradually gained an insight into the study and understood the teachings of the master of Suzunoya (Norinaga MOTOORI), then he realized that this world was the product of our great gods of Japan, so he decided to suspend &quot;Koshi-den&quot; temporarily, and first explore and read through all the past annotations of the histories of our country as well as those of India and Europe to use new knowledge to his advantage in writing &quot;Koshi-den&quot;; therefore, since the middle of the Bunsei era, he intensly studied foreign literature and culture mainly, and during a period of over 20 years, he completed almost all his works, which he left for us, including &quot;Sekiken Taiko-den&quot; (Japanese Early History); although he was never satisfied with his works, his students, of course, including myself, with a feeling of gratitude, thought that our master had succeeded in completing most his researches and studies, and were concerned about the delay in completing &quot;Koshi-den&quot; and because of our master&apos;s age, we repeatedly begged him to restart the writing, then thankfully at about the 10th year of the Tenpo era (1839), he restarted; however, he was requested to write on linguistic methods so he began to write &quot;Goju Ongi&quot; (Pronunciation and Meaning of 50 Kana) and suspended &quot;Koshi-den&quot; again; after a year, he was banished to Akita Province by order of the former bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), fortunately since Akita was his hometown and there were many relatives of his, besides the former load treated him very kindly, they relieved him off poor living, although under those conditions, he had no time to finish the remaining works; he was always concerned about those unfinished works, and after only a few years, he became sick and regrettably died.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更幕府の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>然れば古史伝は全く初稿のままにて行き届かず、中々以って上木致すには之無きに候へ共、門人中一同の懇願に付き、差し置き難く上木を初め、第廿八巻まで刻成り申し候段、御見聞の通りに御座候、さて古史成文第百四十四段より第百五十段迄は、大抵草稿出来居り候間、即ち古史伝第廿九巻、三十巻、以上二巻として未定ながら、近々上木仕えまつり候筈に候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left only the first draft, so we hesitated to print it at first, however, for all the students&apos; earnest requests, we eventually printed volume one to twenty-eight, as you had already known; we also edited it from paragraphs 144 to 150, so soon those are going to be printed as volume twenty-nine and thirty, although dates are still to be arranged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left only the first draft, so we hesitated to print it at first, however, for all the students&apos; earnest requests, we eventually printed volume one to twenty-eight, as you already know; we have also edited paragraphs 144 to 150, so those are going to be printed soon as volumes twenty-nine and thirty, although the dates are still to be arranged.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left only the first draft, so we hesitated to print it at first, however, for all the students&apos; earnest requests, we eventually printed volume 1 to 28, as you already know; we have also edited paragraphs 144 to 150, so those are going to be printed soon as volumes 29 and 30, although the dates are still to be arranged.</e>
<cmt>全角符号を半角に訂正数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>さて成文第百五十一段・火須勢理命御幸がえの処より、巻末百六十五段迄は、草稿少しも之無く候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The problem is that our teacher left no draft from paragraph 151 in which Hosuseri no Mikoto (one of Japanese ancient gods) changed his destination, to the last paragraph 165.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The problem is that our teacher left no draft from paragraph 151 in which Hosuseri no Mikoto (one of the ancient Japanese gods) changed his destination, to the last paragraph 165.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The problem is that our teacher left no draft from paragraph 151 in which Hosuseri no Mikoto (one of the ancient Japanese gods) changed his destination, to the last paragraph 165.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>拙老儀は兼ねて御見分け候はむ、不学不才、とても著述は出来申さず、その内先人遺言も之有り、延胤義は少々心がけ候へども、存外不孝致し、何共仕方之無く、当惑至極に罷り在り事にござ候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You know my poor talent, I couldn&apos;t write it; of course, following our teacher&apos;s will, my son Nobutane made some effort, however he was a bad son and died, so now we are helplessly sitting and watching our teacher&apos;s uncompleted work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You know I do not have much talent, so I couldn&apos;t write it; of course, following our teacher&apos;s will, my son Nobutane made some effort, however he was a bad son and died, so now we are helplessly sitting and watching our teacher&apos;s uncompleted work.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You know I do not have much talent, so I couldn&apos;t write it; of course, following our teacher&apos;s will, my son Nobutane made some effort, however he was a bad son and died, so now we are helplessly sitting and watching our teacher&apos;s uncompleted work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>茲に依り御頼み申し候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore I would like to request you.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore I would like to request you.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore I would like to request you.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="36">
<j>貴君御事、ご自身御著述御多端なる御事は十分御察し申し居り候へ共、御門人中に、差当り外に御依頼致す可き御仁之無く候間、なにとぞ右第百五十一段より末迄の所、御註解成し下されたく御頼み申し候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I understand that you are very busy with your own study and work, however, there is not more talented person among the students to accomplish the book, so I earnestly request you to write the annotation from paragraph 151 to the end of the book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I understand that you are very busy with your own studies and work, however, there is not other talented person among the students that complete this book, so I earnestly request you to write the annotation from paragraph 151 to the end of the book.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I understand that you are very busy with your own studies and work, however, there is not other talented person among the students that complete this book, so I earnestly request you to write the annotation from paragraph 151 to the end of the book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>右御出来下さ候はば、先人の霊もさぞさぞ致さり候はむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you accepted this difficult request, our teacher would be glad in another world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you accepted this difficult request, our teacher would be glad in another world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you accepted this difficult request, our teacher would be glad in another world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>猶委曲の義は、深見速雄主より、御頼み申し上げ被らる可く申し上げ候間、御承引下さる可く候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I am sorry to trouble you, but as to the details, Hayao FUKAMI would explain to you.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I am sorry to trouble you, but as to the details, Hayao FUKAMI would explain to you.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I am sorry to trouble you, but as to the details, Hayao FUKAMI would explain to you.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>古史成文の儀も、兼ては推古天皇の御紀まで撰述の心組みにて、云々、右ご依頼申し上げたく書中を以ってかくのごとく御坐候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since our teacher originally intended to write &quot;Koshi&quot; (Early History) to the period of Emperor Suiko, we would like to accomplish the annotation as well, so I wrote this letter and bother you; I do ask you again to consider approving my request.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since our teacher originally intended to write &quot;Koshi&quot; (Early History) to the period of Emperor Suiko, we would like to accomplish the annotation as well, so I wrote you this letter; I do ask you again to consider approving my request.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since our teacher originally intended to write &quot;Koshi&quot; (Early History) to the period of Emperor Suiko, we would like to accomplish the annotation as well, so I wrote you this letter; I do ask you again to consider approving my request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="40">
<j>頓首謹言 明治七年 十一月廿七日 平田鐵胤(花押) 矢野玄道様』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sincerely yours, 27 November, the seventh year of the Meiji era (1874), Kanetane HIRATA, (his signature), Mr. Harumichi YANO&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sincerely yours, 27 November, the seventh year of the Meiji era (1874), Kanetane HIRATA, (his signature), Mr. Harumichi YANO&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sincerely yours, 27 November, the seventh year of the Meiji period (1874), Kanetane HIRATA, (his signature), Mr. Harumichi YANO&quot;</e>
<cmt>era→period</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="41">
<j>当初玄道は東京にて古史伝の草稿に取り掛かる予定でいたが、神道本局からの教典編集の依頼や種々の著述や平田先生の遺書の校訂などもあり、結局京都で執筆することに改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumichi was initially planning to write &quot;Koshi-den&quot; in Tokyo, however, for other works such as editing of the doctrine offered by the head office of Shinto, editing Atsutane&apos;s works and writing his own books, he came to Kyoto and started writing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumichi was initially planning to write &quot;Koshi-den&quot; in Tokyo, however, for other works such as editing of the doctrine offered by the head office of Shinto, editing Atsutane&apos;s works and writing his own books, he came to Kyoto and started writing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumichi was initially planning to write &quot;Koshi-den&quot; in Tokyo, however, for other works such as editing of the doctrine offered by the head office of Shinto, editing Atsutane&apos;s works and writing his own books, he came to Kyoto and started writing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>この時期重病に罹り、古史伝の続行は思うように捗らなかったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he had a serious illness and had to delay the progress of the work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he had a serious illness and had to delay the progress of the work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he had a serious illness and had to delay the progress of the work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>取り合えず古史伝の廿九巻上・中・下並びに第三十巻の四冊は完成させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he had finished volume twenty-nine (first, middle, last) and volume thirty by 1879.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he had finished volume twenty-nine (first, middle, last) and volume thirty by 1879.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he had finished four books, volume 29 (first, middle, last) and volume 30.</e>
<cmt>「四冊」訳漏れ対応しました。「by 1879」は原文にないので削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="44">
<j>明治12年に皇室制度やその他に関する調査も一段落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he finished his researches on the Imperial House system and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he finished his researches on the Imperial House system and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1879, he finished his researches on the Imperial House system and others.</e>
<cmt>the same year→1879</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>そんな折に重病だった銕胤が古史伝の完成を願いつつ逝去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Tetsutane, who had been seriously ill for a while, regretfully died with hope of completing &quot;Koshi-den&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Tetsutane, who had been seriously ill for a while, regretfully died with the hope of completing &quot;Koshi-den&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Tetsutane, who had been seriously ill for a while, regretfully died with the hope of completing &quot;Koshi-den&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>玄道は深く感じ入る事もあって意を決し、ようやく七～八年をかけて、成文百六十四段(第37巻)までの註釈をほどこし、篤胤の念願であった古史伝を明治19年9月に遂に完結させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On that occasion, Harumichi reflected on himself and determined to complete the book, and in the following eight years, made all the annotation (to paragraph 164, volume 37); in September of 1886,at last he completed &quot;Koshi-den&quot; that Atsutane had left with the dearest wish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that occasion, Harumichi reflected on himself and determined to complete the book, and in the following eight years, made all the annotations (to paragraph 164, volume 37); in September of 1886,at last he completed &quot;Koshi-den&quot; that Atsutane had left with his dearest wish.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that occasion, Harumichi reflected on himself and determined to complete the book, and in the following eight years, made all the annotations (to paragraph 164, volume 37); in September of 1886, at last he completed &quot;Koshi-den&quot; that Atsutane had left with his dearest wish.</e>
<cmt>at の前にスペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>以後も古史成文の学習を続けて頂く様に、畏友角田忠行や門弟の木野戸勝隆を始めとして弟子達がお願いしたが、聞き入れず、郷里の大洲の地に帰郷し、翌年の五月十九日に逝去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumichi was asked to continue the study of Atsutane&apos;s &quot;Koshi&quot; by his friend Tadayuki TSUNODA and students including Katsutaka KINOTO, however, he rejected it and went back his hometown, Ozu, then soon in the next year, on 19 May, he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumichi was asked to continue the study of Atsutane&apos;s &quot;Koshi&quot; by his friend Tadayuki TSUNODA and students including Katsutaka KINOTO, however, he rejected it and went back to his hometown, Ozu, then soon in the next year, on 19th May, he died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumichi was asked to continue the study of Atsutane&apos;s &quot;Koshi&quot; by his friend Tadayuki TSUNODA and students including Katsutaka KINOTO, however, he rejected it and went back to his hometown, Ozu, then soon in the next year, on 19th May, he died.</e>
<cmt>全角符号を半角に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>冥府と幽事への関心</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interest in the underworld and mysterious things</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interest in the underworld and mysterious things</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interest in the underworld and mysterious things</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>篤胤は若い頃より、この世界が幽顕一如で構成されていると考え、その本質をなんとか解明する事が出来ないものかと常日頃から思案し「霊能真柱」「古史成文」「仙境異聞」「古今妖魅考」他数多の本の中に次々に書き表して証明しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was young, Atsutane HIRATA had been thinking that the Dark (&apos;幽&apos; hidden or mysterious things) and the Light (&apos;顕&apos; appeared or clear things) were the one and the same, and that this world was formed by the working of those opposite factors; Atsutane wanted to analyze the true nature of the world and tried to demonstrate his ideas in many works including &quot;Tama no Mihashira&quot; (Concept of Afterlife), &quot;Koshi Seibun&quot; (Early History), &quot;Senkyo Ibun&quot; (Another Story of Unworldly Men&apos;s World) and &quot;Kokon Yomi-ko&quot; (Studies on Mysterious Things of Ancient and Modern Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he was young, Atsutane HIRATA had been thinking that the Dark (&apos;幽&apos; hidden or mysterious things) and the Light (&apos;顕&apos; appeared or clear things) were the one and the same, and that this world was formed by the working of those opposing factors; Atsutane wanted to analyze the true nature of the world and tried to demonstrate his ideas in many works including &quot;Tama no Mihashira&quot; (Concept of Afterlife), &quot;Koshi Seibun&quot; (Early History), &quot;Senkyo Ibun&quot; (Another Story of Unworldly Men&apos;s World) and &quot;Kokon Yomi-ko&quot; (Studies on Mysterious Things of Ancient and Modern Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he was young, Atsutane HIRATA had been thinking that the Dark (&apos;幽&apos; hidden or mysterious things) and the Light (&apos;顕&apos; appeared or clear things) were the one and the same, and that this world was formed by the working of those opposing factors; Atsutane wanted to analyze the true nature of the world and tried to demonstrate his ideas in many works including &apos;Tama no Mihashira&apos; (Concept of Afterlife), &apos;Koshi Seibun&apos; (Early History), &apos;Senkyo Ibun&apos; (Another Story of Unworldly Men&apos;s World) and &apos;Kokon Yomi-ko&apos; (Studies on Mysterious Things of Ancient and Modern Japan).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>文化3年頃に江戸市中に冥府と往き来できると言う天狗少年仙童寅吉が出現し、奇しくも後に知人を介して邂逅する事により、本人から直接異境の有様や幽事の秘め事などを聞き質し、幽界冥府が厳然と実在し、大なり小なり深く現界に影響を及ぼしている有様に気づき、篤胤自らが常日頃考えていた幽顕の理念と奇しくも符節融合する事を悟り、幽顕一如を再確信すると共に敬神の念を更に深めて古道を敷衍し実践して行く事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 1806, in Edo City appeared a young Tengu (one of Japanese ghost) Torakichi (called &apos;Sendo&apos;), who was claiming that he could come and go to the underworld; Atsutane was introduced to the boy and directly asked him about another world and secrets of mysterious things, then Atsutane realized that the underworld really existed and exerted a great or a little influence on this world; and he thought that the boy&apos;s story surprisingly corresponded to the idea of the Dark and the Light which he had been considering for years; after that, with conviction of the idea and deeper worship, he continued his studies and practice of Kodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 1806, in Edo City, a young Tengu (one of Japanese ghost) Torakichi (called &apos;Sendo&apos;) appeared, who claimed that he could come and go to the underworld; Atsutane was introduced to him and directly asked him about the other world and secrets of mysterious things, then Atsutane realized that the underworld really existed and exerted great or little influence on this world; and he thought that the boy&apos;s story surprisingly corresponded to the idea of the Dark and the Light which he had been considering for years; after that, with conviction of the idea and deeper worship, he continued his studies and practice of Kodo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 1806, in Edo City, a young Tengu (one of Japanese ghost) Torakichi (called &apos;Sendo&apos;) appeared, who claimed that he could come and go to the underworld; Atsutane was introduced to him and directly asked him about the other world and secrets of mysterious things, then Atsutane realized that the underworld really existed and exerted great or little influence on this world; and he thought that the boy&apos;s story surprisingly corresponded to the idea of the Dark and the Light which he had been considering for years; after that, with conviction of the idea and deeper worship, he continued his studies and practice of Kodo.</e>
<cmt>全角符号を半角に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>篤胤が気吹屋として最初に入門の弟子を迎えたのは文化元年で、以後陸続と門人は増えていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1804, Atsutane established Ibukinoya School and took his first pupil; students fast increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1804, Atsutane established Ibukinoya School and took in his first pupil; the number of students increased fast.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1804, Atsutane established Ibukinoya School and took in his first pupil; the number of students increased fast.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>特に文化から文政年間にかけては、俊英な弟子達が出揃った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the Bunka era (1804-1818) and the Bunsei era (1818-1830), very talented students entered his school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the Bunka era (1804-1818) and the Bunsei era (1818-1830), very talented students entered his school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the Bunka era (1804-1818) and the Bunsei era (1818-1830), very talented students entered his school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>中でも羽州の佐藤信淵 駿府の柴崎直古・同郷の新庄道雄 山城国の六人部是香 上州の生田萬 下総国の宮負定雄 同郷の宮内嘉長 芦澤洞栄そして平田鐵胤など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some students were well-known, such as Nobuhiro SATO from Dewa Province, Naofuru SHIBASAKI from Sunpu Province, Michio SHINJO from Sunpu, Yoshika MUTOBE from Yamashiro Province, Yorozu IKUTA from Kozuke Province, Yasuo MIYAOI from Shimousa Province, Yoshinaga MIYAUCHI, Toei ASHIZAWA and Kanetane HIRATA from Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some students were well-known, such as Nobuhiro SATO from Dewa Province, Naofuru SHIBASAKI from Sunpu Province, Michio SHINJO from Sunpu, Yoshika MUTOBE from Yamashiro Province, Yorozu IKUTA from Kozuke Province, Yasuo MIYAOI from Shimousa Province, Yoshinaga MIYAUCHI, Toei ASHIZAWA and Kanetane HIRATA from Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some students were well-known, such as Nobuhiro SATO from Dewa Province, Naofuru SHIBASAKI from Suruga Province, Michio SHINJO from Suruga, Yoshika MUTOBE from Yamashiro Province, Yorozu IKUTA from Kozuke Province, Yasuo MIYAOI from Shimousa Province, Yoshinaga MIYAUCHI, Toei ASHIZAWA and Kanetane HIRATA from Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>Ｓｕｎｐｕ→Suruga</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="53">
<j>彼らは篤胤の八家の学問を吸収するとともに、篤胤同様に死後の世界の存在に深く関心を抱いており、夫々の弟子達がさらにその研究を敷衍し、各人が独自の解釈に於ける幽冥観の認識を持ち其々の立場から幽冥思想を展開して敷衍して行く事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They not only learned classical literature and thought (&apos;hakka&apos;) from Atsutane but also had deep interest in the underworld like their teacher, and each of them evolved the theory of mysterious things by their own views.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They not only learned classical literature and ideas (&apos;hakka&apos;) from Atsutane but also had deep interest in the underworld like their teacher, and each of them evolved theories of mysterious things based on their own views.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They not only learned classical literature and ideas (&apos;hakka&apos;) from Atsutane but also had deep interest in the underworld like their teacher, and each of them evolved theories of mysterious things based on their own views.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>中でも篤胤も一目置いた山城の向日神社神官・六人部是香が篤胤の幽顕弁を敷衍し講説した産土信仰や顕幽順考の論は幽冥の神秘を穿つ貴重な論考として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshika MUTOBE was a Shinto priest of Muko-jinja Shrine of Yamashiro Province and gained even Atsutane&apos;s respect; evolving Atsutane&apos;s theory of the Dark and the Light, he wrote a paper about Ubusuna-shinko (belief that native gods keep protecting people before and after they are born) and wrote &quot;Kenyu-junko&quot; (Study on the theory of the Dark and the Light); his works are known as distinguished idea to shed the light on the dark mysteries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshika MUTOBE was a Shinto priest of the Muko-jinja Shrine of Yamashiro Province and gained even Atsutane&apos;s respect; based on Atsutane&apos;s theory of the Dark and the Light, he wrote a paper about Ubusuna-shinko (belief that native gods keep protecting people before and after they are born) and wrote &quot;Kenyu-junko&quot; (Study on the theory of the Dark and the Light); his works are known as distinguished ideas that shed light on the dark mysteries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshika MUTOBE was a Shinto priest of the Muko-jinja Shrine of Yamashiro Province and gained even Atsutane&apos;s respect; based on Atsutane&apos;s theory of the Dark and the Light, he wrote a paper about Ubusuna-shinko (belief that native gods keep protecting people before and after they are born) and wrote &quot;Kenyu-junko&quot; (Study on the theory of the Dark and the Light); his works are known as distinguished ideas that shed light on the dark mysteries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="55">
<j>篤胤の提唱する古道に於ける幽顕の弁や神仙思想とは、実は皇国に古来から伝播した玄学(神仙道)の事であり、玄学とは現象を動かす物の奥にある本質を解明する学問の事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of the Dark and the Light and the idea of unworldly men&apos;s world, which Atsutane taught based on Kodo, were, in fact, Chinese ancient philosophy which had been introduced in centuries past, especially Gengaku (&apos;玄学xuanxue&apos;, philosophy fused by Confucianism and Taoism during the period from the third century until the fifth century) and Shinsendo (&apos;神仙道shenxiandao&apos;, method for becoming unworldly man); Gengaku was regarded as the scholarship to analyze the essence beneath the surface of phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>オリジナルは、玄学の意味などを取り違えている他の文章を書き写したもののようなので、オリジナル著者の全体的な解釈を曲げずに、わかりやすく整理しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of the Dark and the Light and the idea of unworldly men&apos;s world, which Atsutane taught based on Kodo, were, in fact, Chinese ancient philosophies that had been introduced in centuries past, especially Gengaku (&apos;玄学xuanxue&apos;, philosophy fused by Confucianism and Taoism during the period from the third century until the fifth century) and Shinsendo (&apos;神仙道shenxiandao&apos;, method for becoming unworldly man); Gengaku was regarded as the scholar to analyze the essence beneath the surface of the phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of the Dark and the Light and the idea of unworldly men&apos;s world, which Atsutane taught based on Kodo, were, in fact, Chinese ancient philosophies that had been introduced in centuries past, especially Gengaku (&apos;xuanxue&apos;, philosophy fused by Confucianism and Taoism during the period from the third century until the fifth century) and Shinsendo (&apos;shenxiandao&apos;, method for becoming unworldly man); Gengaku was regarded as the scholar to analyze the essence beneath the surface of the phenomenon.</e>
<cmt>漢字は不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>篤胤にとって古道学とは日本古来の神代思想と支那の老荘道家の思想を融合した皇国伝来の独自な神仙道の思想である事に気づく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In brief, while advocating Kodo, Atsutane had been studying Japanese original Shinsendo that was a fusion of Japanese ancient philosophy about gods and Chinese Taoism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In brief, while advocating Kodo, Atsutane had been studying Japanese original Shinsendo that was a fusion of Japanese ancient philosophy about gods and Chinese Taoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In brief, while advocating Kodo, Atsutane had been studying Japanese original Shinsendo that was a fusion of Japanese ancient philosophy about gods and Chinese Taoism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この日本古来から連綿と伝わりたる教義を広める為に、山城の是香は篤胤の理論を更に敷衍して、郷里の地で私塾を開き活躍することとなるが、是香同様にその学才を高く評価した篤胤が娘の養子にと嘱望していた生田萬は儚くも夭折してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese original Shinsendo had been inherited for generations in Japan, and Yoshika, one of Atsutane&apos;s leading disciples, applied Atsutane&apos;s theory to evolve the Japanese Shinsendo and established his own school in his hometown Yamashiro Province; Atsutane also had a high regard for Yorozu IKUTA&apos;s ability and hoped him would become his heir and his daughter&apos;s husband, however, Yorozu died at an early age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese original Shinsendo had been inherited for generations in Japan, and Yoshika, one of Atsutane&apos;s leading disciples, applied Atsutane&apos;s theory to evolve the Japanese Shinsendo and established his own school in his hometown Yamashiro Province; Atsutane also had a high regard for Yorozu IKUTA&apos;s ability and hoped he would become his heir and his daughter&apos;s husband, however, Yorozu died at an early age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese original Shinsendo had been inherited for generations in Japan, and Yoshika, one of Atsutane&apos;s leading disciples, applied Atsutane&apos;s theory to evolve the Japanese Shinsendo and established his own school in his hometown Yamashiro Province; Atsutane also had a high regard for Yorozu IKUTA&apos;s ability and hoped he would become his heir and his daughter&apos;s husband, however, Yorozu died at an early age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>この前後の時期は篤胤にとって最も厳しい試練の時節でもあり、最愛の妻織瀬を亡くし、息子二人も夭折した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those days Atsutane had to bear the hardest time, because he lost his dearest wife and two sons died at an early age as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those days, Atsutane went through the hardest time, because he lost his dearest wife and his two sons died at an early age as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those days, Atsutane went through the hardest time, because he lost his dearest wife and his two sons died at an early age as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>悲しみ覚めやらむ妻への思慕と日々の生活苦に喘ぎ苦悶した篤胤ではあったが、やがて一陽来復し、周囲の忠告を受け容れて門人の富豪・山崎篤利の養女りよ(お里勢)と再婚し後妻として迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After recovered from grief for wife&apos;s death and poverty, by everyone&apos;s advice, Atutane remarried Riyo (her real name was Orise), an adopted daughter of Atsutoshi YAMAZAKI, who was a student of his school and very rich.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After recovering from grief because of his wife&apos;s death and poverty, by everyone&apos;s advice, Atutane remarried Riyo (her real name was Orise), an adopted daughter of Atsutoshi YAMAZAKI, who was a student of his school and very rich.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After recovering from grief because of his wife&apos;s death and poverty, by everyone&apos;s advice, Atsutane remarried Riyo (her real name was Orise), an adopted daughter of Atsutoshi YAMAZAKI, who was a student of his school and very rich.</e>
<cmt>Atutane→Atsutane</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この時節には暗雲もしずかに去り往きて、伊予から春秋に富む二人の兄弟が篤胤の元に入門した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As dark clouds had gone without notice, about the same year, young Midorikawa brothers entered his school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As dark clouds had gone by without notice, about the same year, the young Midorikawa brothers entered his school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As dark clouds had gone by without notice, about the same year, the young Midorikawa brothers entered his school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="61">
<j>後になって碧川兄弟の兄の方を娘おてう（千枝改名して織瀬）が見初めて、篤胤も同意し嗣子として平田家に入り婿する事を許可される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Atsutane&apos;s daughter Oteu (her real name was Chieko or Orise) fell in love with the elder of Midorikawa brothers, and Atutane allowed the marriage and to adopt the bridegroom as the heir to the Hirata family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Atsutane&apos;s daughter Oteu (her real name was Chieko or Orise) fell in love with the elder of the Midorikawa brothers, and Atutane allowed the marriage and to adopt the bridegroom as the heir to the Hirata family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Atsutane&apos;s daughter Oteu (her real name was Chieko or Orise) fell in love with the elder of the Midorikawa brothers, and Atutane allowed the marriage and to adopt the bridegroom as the heir to the Hirata family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>やがて平田学を継承する鐵胤の誕生である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The groom was Kanetane who became the successor to Hirata&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The groom was Kanetane who became the successor to Hirata&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The groom was Kanetane who became the successor to Hirata&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>婚姻後に実母の名を継ぐことになる妻の織瀬は、中々の才女でありまして、一度目に通したものは、すべて諳んじ父篤胤の著述については、何を尋ねてもすらすら答えることが出来たと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the marriage, Oteu changed her real name to Orise after her biological mother&apos;s name; she was a quite talented woman with incredible remembrance, she didn&apos;t forget anything she had read once, and could answer any question about her father&apos;s works with no difficulty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the marriage, Oteu changed her real name to Orise after her biological mother&apos;s name; she was quite a talented woman with an incredible memory, she didn&apos;t forget anything she had read once, and could answer any question about her father&apos;s works with no difficulty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the marriage, Oteu changed her real name to Orise after her biological mother&apos;s name; she was quite a talented woman with an incredible memory, she didn&apos;t forget anything she had read once, and could answer any question about her father&apos;s works with no difficulty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>英語もできたし、文章も巧みで文字は美しく、父の詠んだ和歌を短冊に代筆している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides she understood English; she wrote well with beautiful handwriting which remains in oblong cards she wrote her father&apos;s waka (poetry) for him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides she understood English; she wrote well with beautiful handwriting which remains in oblong cards when she wrote her father&apos;s waka (poetry) for him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides she understood English; she wrote well with beautiful handwriting which remains in oblong cards when she wrote her father&apos;s waka (poetry) for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>臨終のときには、きちんと正座して皆に臨終の挨拶をして、それではと床につき、そのまま帰幽したそうだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At her deathbed, she sat up straight, said goodbye to everyone, lay down saying just &quot;then&quot; and died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At her deathbed, she sat up straight, said goodbye to everyone, lay down saying just &quot;then&quot; and died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At her deathbed, she sat up straight, said goodbye to everyone, lay down saying just &quot;then&quot; and died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>伊予大洲の矢野玄道翁の臨終を髣髴とさせるものがあるが、多分仙家伝来の脱魂法や古道の鎮魂や帰神術を秘かに学ばれていた事に起因があるのではないかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her end seems to be similar to the end of Harumichi YANO of Ozu (Iyo Province) and it is considered that she had secretly learnt unworldly men&apos;s Dakkonho (method for undoing the body), or Kodo&apos;s Chinkon (method for organizing spirit) or Kishinjutsu (method for returning spirit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her end seems to be similar to the end of Harumichi YANO of Ozu (Iyo Province) and it is considered that she had secretly learnt unworldly men&apos;s Dakkonho (method for undoing the body), or Kodo&apos;s Chinkon (method for organizing the spirit) or Kishinjutsu (method for returning the spirit).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her end seems to be similar to the end of Harumichi YANO of Ozu (Iyo Province) and it is considered that she had secretly learnt unworldly men&apos;s Dakkonho (method for undoing the body), or Kodo&apos;s Chinkon (method for organizing the spirit) or Kishinjutsu (method for returning the spirit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>因みに鎮魂とは己の神魂をその身体の中封に鎮め敢て妄りに動き去らしめず、以って天神の心霊と妙応感合して一体を相成さしむる法を云う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When doing Chinkon, the person has to collect his own spirit at the center of the body and keep it still without releasing it; as a result of the exercise, the collected spirit would react with the gods&apos; spirits each other and become one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When doing Chinkon, the person has to collect his own spirit at the center of the body and keep it still without releasing it; as a result of the exercise, the collected spirit would react with the gods&apos; spirits to become one.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When doing Chinkon, the person has to collect his own spirit at the center of the body and keep it still without releasing it; as a result of the exercise, the collected spirit would react with the gods&apos; spirits to become one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="68">
<j>25歳で婿入りした鐵胤は、新婚当初から父の跡目を継ぐ重責と、また平田家の莫大な借財の重さをひしひしと体感していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since getting married at the age of 25, Kanetane had been feeling the heavy responsibility to inherit the study and enormous debts of his father-in-low had accumulated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since getting married at the age of 25, Kanetane had been feeling the heavy responsibility to inherit the study and enormous debts that his father-in-law had accumulated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since getting married at the age of 25, Kanetane had been feeling the heavy responsibility to inherit the study and enormous debts that his father-in-law had accumulated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>篤胤亡き後に、借財や負債はすべて返済し平田宗家伝来の復古神道の道を守り更に進展させた事は美談として今日まで語り継がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he cleared off all the debts and succeeded in protecting and evolving the classical Shinto that the head family of the Hirata family had inherited for generations; those works are still being told as moving stories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he cleared off all the debts and succeeded in protecting and evolving the classical Shinto that the head family of the Hirata family had inherited for generations; those works are still being told as moving stories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he cleared off all the debts and succeeded in protecting and evolving the classical Shinto that the head family of the Hirata family had inherited for generations; those works are still being told as moving stories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>本来学者肌で研究熱心な勉学家あったが、置かれた立場の責任上自著を書き著すゆとりがなかったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was originally endowed with talents as a scholar and studied hard, however, under the situation as the successor, he had no time to write his own book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was originally endowed with talents as a scholar and studied hard, however, under the situation as the successor, he had no time to write his own book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was originally endowed with talents as a scholar and studied hard, however, under the situation as the successor, he is said to have had no time to write his own book.</e>
<cmt>「言われている」は訳出不要と考えられたのかもしれませんが、訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>入門当初から鐡胤は薄々感じ取っていたが、父篤胤の幽冥・死後の世界の研究は、失われて埋没され、そして封印された古代信仰の雛形を元の姿に復元させる為の学問であり、其の為に古道の道に足を踏み入れて幽冥の存在を立証しようと試みていた事も知悉していたが、文政3年頃に知友屋代弘賢を通じ下谷長者町の博学の好事家山崎美成を介在して、後に父のもとを訪ねてきた異境を往来すると言う仙童寅吉の姿形を目の当たりに見て、父篤胤が唱える幽冥界の実在をしかと確認し、以後は自らも寸暇を惜しみ、不可解な奇譚の情報やその他の幽冥関連の資料類の蒐集に没頭する事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since entered the school, Kanetane knew that his teacher Atsutane studied mysterious things and the underworld to restore the ancient belief which had been lost or sealed up, besides Kanetane understood that Atsutane tried to prove the existence of mysterious things by Kodo; about 1820, by Yoshinari YAMAZAKI, a learned amateur living at Shitayachoja-machi and an acquaintance of Kanetane&apos;s friend Hirokata YASHIRO, Kanetane was introduced to Sendo Torakichi, who could come and go freely to the underworld, then Kanetane was convinced of the existence of the underworld, and began to put in serious efforts to collect information of mysterious stories and materials of such things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since entering the school, Kanetane knew that his teacher Atsutane studied mysterious things and the underworld to restore the ancient belief which had been lost or sealed up, besides Kanetane understood that Atsutane tried to prove the existence of mysterious things by Kodo; about 1820, by Yoshinari YAMAZAKI, a learned amateur living in Shitayachoja-machi and an acquaintance of Kanetane&apos;s friend Hirokata YASHIRO, Kanetane was introduced to Sendo Torakichi, who could come and go freely to the underworld, then Kanetane became convinced of the existence of the underworld, and began to put in serious efforts to collect information of mysterious stories and materials of such things.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since entering the school, Kanetane knew that his teacher Atsutane studied mysterious things and the underworld to restore the ancient belief which had been lost or sealed up, besides Kanetane understood that Atsutane tried to prove the existence of mysterious things by Kodo; about 1820, by Yoshinari YAMAZAKI, a learned amateur living in Shitayachoja-machi and an acquaintance of Kanetane&apos;s friend Hirokata YASHIRO, Kanetane was introduced to Sendo Torakichi, who could come and go freely to the underworld, then Kanetane became convinced of the existence of the underworld, and began to put in serious efforts to collect information of mysterious stories and materials of such things.</e>
<cmt>全角符号を半角に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="72">
<j>東京大學の内科創始者、青山胤通博士は平田門下青山景通の三男で、医道の道に進まなかったら、平田宗家の三代目平田延胤の後継者と目された人物であります。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dr. Tanemichi AOYAMA, the founder of the department of internal medicine of Tokyo University, was the third son of Kagemichi AOYAMA, a student of Hirata&apos;s school, and he had been hoped to become the successor to Nobutane HIRATA (the third head teacher of Hirata&apos;s school) before he had decided to become a medical student.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dr. Tanemichi AOYAMA, the founder of the department of internal medicine of Tokyo University, was the third son of Kagemichi AOYAMA, a student of Hirata&apos;s school, and he had been expected to become the successor to Nobutane HIRATA (the third head teacher of Hirata&apos;s school) before he decided to become a medical student.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dr. Tanemichi AOYAMA, the founder of the department of internal medicine of Tokyo University, was the third son of Kagemichi AOYAMA, a student of Hirata&apos;s school, and he had been expected to become the successor to Nobutane HIRATA (the third head teacher of Hirata&apos;s school) before he decided to become a medical student.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>明治天皇のご臨終をみとった人としても知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known as the doctor who was at the side of Emperor Meiji when the emperor died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known as the doctor who was at the side of Emperor Meiji when the emperor died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also known as the doctor who was at the side of Emperor Meiji when the emperor died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>東北大学医学部の熊谷岱蔵博士は青山博士とは姻戚関係で、平田宗家とも関係深く、現在では昭和天皇の手術で一躍世界に知られた東京大學の森岡恭彦博士は、手術のとき平田神社のお守りを肌身につけて手術に臨まれたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dr. Taizo KUMAGAI of medical school of Tohoku University was a relative of Dr. Aoyama, and had deep relationship with the Hirata family; Dr. Yasuhiko MORIOKA, one of the world-class doctors and had operated on Emperor Showa, also had a relationship with the Hirata family and he was wearing a good-luck charm of Hirata-jinja Shrine at the operations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dr. Taizo KUMAGAI of the medical school of Tohoku University was a relative of Dr. Aoyama, and had a deep relationship with the Hirata family; Dr. Yasuhiko MORIOKA, one of the world-class doctors and had operated on Emperor Showa, also had a relationship with the Hirata family and he used to wear a good-luck charm from the Hirata-jinja Shrine when performing operations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dr. Taizo KUMAGAI of the medical school of Tohoku University was a relative of Dr. Aoyama, and had a deep relationship with the Hirata family; Dr. Yasuhiko MORIOKA, who became world-famous when he operated on Emperor Showa, also had a relationship with the Hirata family and he wore a good-luck charm from the Hirata-jinja Shrine when performing the operation.</e>
<cmt>「昭和天皇の手術で一躍世界に知られた」ことと、お守りは「その手術をする時に身につけていた」と変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>平田神社の責任役員総代でもありますが、すべてが、目に見えない奇霊な糸で紡がれて導かれている事がわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the representative of the board of Hirata-jinja Shrine; considering the relationship between those people and the Hirata family, everything seems to be connected and led by unseen, mysterious power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the representative of the board of Hirata-jinja Shrine; considering the relationship between those people and the Hirata family, everything seems to be connected and led by unseen, mysterious power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the representative of the board of Hirata-jinja Shrine; considering the relationship between those people and the Hirata family, everything seems to be connected and led by unseen, mysterious power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>仙境異聞と神界物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senkyo Ibun (Another Story of Unworldly Men&apos;s World) and Shinkai Monogatari (Story of Gods&apos; World)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senkyo Ibun (Another Story of Unworldly Men&apos;s World) and Shinkai Monogatari (Story of Gods&apos; World)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senkyo Ibun (Another Story of Unworldly Men&apos;s World) and Shinkai Monogatari (Story of Gods&apos; World)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>平田家には廿五部秘書というものがあり、外書に対する内書として厳重に区別されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hirata family had preserved Nijugobu Hisho (secret books categorized into twenty-five) as naisho (inside books) closely separated from gaisho (outside books).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hirata family had preserved Nijugobu Hisho (secret books categorized into twenty-five areas) as naisho (inside books) closely separated from gaisho (outside books).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hirata family had preserved Nijugobu Hisho (secret books categorized into 25 areas) as naisho (inside books) closely separated from gaisho (outside books).</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>この他見厳禁の書籍類は、天文や易学・密教などを除くと大半が道家玄学の書であり、仙境異聞附再生記聞なども含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those books were forbidden to be shown to others, and except for books of astronomy, Ekigaku (&apos;易yi&apos;, Chinese scholarship of fortune telling) and Esoteric Buddhism, those books were mostly about Taoism and Gengaku including &quot;Senkyo Ibun Saisei Kibun&quot; (Another Story of Unworldly Men&apos;s World and Resuscitation Stories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those books were forbidden to be shown to others, and except for books on astronomy, Ekigaku (&apos;易yi&apos;, Chinese scholarship of fortune telling) and Esoteric Buddhism, those books were mostly about Taoism and Gengaku including &quot;Senkyo Ibun Saisei Kibun&quot; (Another Story of Unworldly Men&apos;s World and Resuscitation Stories).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those books were forbidden to be shown to others, and except for books on astronomy, Ekigaku (&apos;yi&apos;, Chinese scholarship of fortune telling) and Esoteric Buddhism, those books were mostly about Taoism and Gengaku including &quot;Senkyo Ibun Saisei Kibun&quot; (Another Story of Unworldly Men&apos;s World and Resuscitation Stories).</e>
<cmt>漢字は不要と考え、削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>仙童寅吉と邂逅した篤胤は、年来の疑念も晴れ目から鱗が落ちた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the meeting with Sendo Torakichi, Atsutane felt that his doubt of many years had been swept away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon meeting with Sendo Torakichi, Atsutane felt that his doubt of many years had been swept away.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon meeting with Sendo Torakichi, Atsutane felt that his doubt of many years had been swept away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>やがて寅吉少年を幽冥から啓導されている、岩間山の山人・杉山僧正なる異人に興味を抱き信仰を重ねていく間に、道家の玄学思想に魅せられて、我が国に伝来する古道の思想と道家玄学の思想を折衷した神仙道の教義をうち立て、弟子達にこの秘教密儀的な秘儀を伝授することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he became interest in an unworldly man, Sojo (the highest-ranking monk) Sugiyama in Mt. Iwama, and grew belief in such mysterious existence, then he gradually became fascinated over Gengaku of Taoism and formed new theory of Shinsendo by fusing Japanese Kodo and Chinese Gengaku, what&apos;s more, he inducted his students into the theory as some kind of esoteric ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he became interest in an unworldly man, Sojo (the highest-ranking monk) Sugiyama in Mt. Iwama, and grew belief in such mysterious existence, then he gradually became fascinated with Gengaku of Taoism and formed a new theory of Shinsendo by fusing Japanese Kodo and Chinese Gengaku, what&apos;s more, he inducted his students into the theory as some kind of an esoteric ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also became interested in an unworldly man from Mt. Iwama called Sojo (meaning &quot;highest-ranking monk&quot;) Sugiyama, who had enlightened Torakichi from the other world, and grew to believe in such a mysterious existence; having become fascinated with the Gengaku of Taoism, he then formed a new theory of Shinsendo by fusing Japanese Kodo and Chinese Gengaku and began inducting his students into the theory as some kind of esoteric ceremony.</e>
<cmt>「寅吉少年を幽冥から啓導されている」訳漏れに対応しました。interest →interested</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>その教義の奥伝として、一部の熱心な道士に道家尊崇の五岳真形図を伝授していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He even showed earnest students the picture of Gogaku-shingyo-zu (Five Miraculous Mountain of China) which Taoist had treasured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He even showed earnest students the picture of Gogaku-shingyo-zu (Five Miraculous Mountain of China) which Taoist had treasured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He even showed earnest students the picture of Gogaku-shingyo-zu (Five Miraculous Mountain of China) which Taoist had treasured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="81">
<j>この五岳図については、平成16年に出版された米田勝安・荒俣宏編 平凡社 別冊太陽 平田篤胤の中で一部写真公開されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The photo of some part of Gogaku-shingyo-zu, which the Hirata family had preserved, is shown in &quot;Bessatsu Taiyo, Hirata Atsutane&quot; (edited by Katsuyasu MAITA and Hiroshi ARAMATA, published by Heibonsha in 2004).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The photo of some parts of Gogaku-shingyo-zu, which the Hirata family had preserved, is shown in &quot;Bessatsu Taiyo, Hirata Atsutane&quot; (edited by Katsuyasu MAITA and Hiroshi ARAMATA, published by Heibonsha in 2004).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The photo of some parts of Gogaku-shingyo-zu, which the Hirata family had preserved, is shown in &quot;Bessatsu Taiyo, Hirata Atsutane&quot; (edited by Katsuyasu MAITA and Hiroshi ARAMATA, published by Heibonsha in 2004).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>又篤胤の神仙研究と題して未公開の幽境の絵図類も公開している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other forbidden pictures of mysterious world are also shown in the article &apos;Atsutane&apos;s Studies on unworldly men&apos; of the same magazine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other forbidden pictures of the mysterious world are also shown in the article &apos;Atsutane&apos;s Studies on unworldly men&apos; in the same magazine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other forbidden pictures of the mysterious world are also shown in the article &apos;Atsutane&apos;s Studies on unworldly men&apos; in the same magazine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>篤胤の神仙道・玄学研究に関する論考は、玉川大学教授の小林健三著『平田神道の研究』の中で詳しく論じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenzo KOBAYASHI, a professor of Tamagawa University, dissected Atsutane&apos;s studies on Shinsendo and Gengaku in &quot;Hirata Shinto no Kenkyu&quot; (Study on Hirata Shinto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenzo KOBAYASHI, a professor of Tamagawa University, dissected Atsutane&apos;s studies on Shinsendo and Gengaku in &quot;Hirata Shinto no Kenkyu&quot; (Study on Hirata Shinto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenzo KOBAYASHI, a professor of Tamagawa University, dissected Atsutane&apos;s studies on Shinsendo and Gengaku in &quot;Hirata Shinto no Kenkyu&quot; (Study on Hirata Shinto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="84">
<j>嘉永の時代に、紀州若山在住の若い町医者島田幸安は、その城下町で「神力睹薬調合所」を開き、彼の神通力と神の導きによる薬の調合は実に霊験あらたかで、和歌山市中ではかなりの評判を呼んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kaei era (1848-1854), a young general practitioner, Yukiyasu SHIMADA had been treating people in his &apos;Jinriki Toyaku-chogojo&apos; (gods&apos; power pharmacy) in Wakayama City (Kii Province), and his treatment and prescription by gods&apos; power had a high popularity among the city as demonstration of gods&apos; power with great effects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kaei era (1848-1854), a young general practitioner, Yukiyasu SHIMADA had been treating people in his &apos;Jinriki Toyaku-chogojo&apos; (gods&apos; power pharmacy) in Wakayama City (Kii Province), and his treatment and prescription by gods&apos; power was very popular among the city as the demonstration of gods&apos; power had great effects.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kaei era (1848-1854), a young general practitioner, Yukiyasu SHIMADA had been treating people in his &apos;Jinriki Toyaku-chogojo&apos; (gods&apos; power pharmacy) in Wakayama City (Kii Province), and his treatment and prescription by gods&apos; power was very popular among the city as the demonstration of gods&apos; power had great effects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>紀州藩の下級藩士参澤宗哲は天保11年8月10日本居内遠の紹介によって、鐡胤の主宰する平田門に入門しているが、宗哲は地元の住民達の噂話を伝聞することによって幸安の存在を知る事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotetsu MISAWA, a junior statesman of the Kishu Domain (Kii Province), entered Tetsutane&apos;s school on 10 August 1840 on the introduction of Uchito MOTOORI; Sotetsu heard about Yukiyasu from people of his hometown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotetsu MISAWA, a junior statesman of the Kishu Domain (Kii Province), entered Tetsutane&apos;s school on 10th August 1840 on the introduction of Uchito MOTOORI; Sotetsu heard about Yukiyasu from people of his hometown.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotetsu MISAWA, a junior statesman of the Kishu Domain (Kii Province), entered Tetsutane&apos;s school on 5th September 1840 on the introduction of Uchito MOTOORI; Sotetsu heard about Yukiyasu from people of his hometown.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>宗哲は師である平田篤胤が、30年前に調べあげた仙童寅吉事件のことが深く記憶の底にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotetsu had known well about Sendo Torakichi whom Atsutane HIRATA had researched thirty years ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotetsu had ample knowledge about Sendo Torakichi whom Atsutane HIRATA had researched thirty years ago.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotetsu had ample knowledge about Sendo Torakichi whom Atsutane HIRATA had researched 30 years ago.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>縁あって幸安の話を知人の同心組頭茨木某より更に詳細に伝え聞くや感ずる処もあって、早速若山の島田幸安の寓居に訪ねて行き正式に入門の誓詞を提出して直接教えを乞う事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By a strange coincidence, his friend and Doshin-kumigashira (head of a police constable) Ibaraki told him about more details of Yukiyasu&apos;s treatments, then he felt something and soon went to Wakayama to meet Yukiyasu, at last he submitted the oath and became Yukiyasu&apos;s pupil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By a strange coincidence, his friend and Doshin-kumigashira (head of a police constable) Ibaraki gave him more details of Yukiyasu&apos;s treatments, then he felt something and soon went to Wakayama to meet Yukiyasu, and he eventually took the oath and became Yukiyasu&apos;s pupil.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By a strange coincidence, his friend and Doshin-kumigashira (head of a police constable) Ibaraki gave him more details of Yukiyasu&apos;s treatments, then he felt something and soon went to Wakayama to meet Yukiyasu, and he eventually took the oath and became Yukiyasu&apos;s pupil.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="88">
<j>師である幸安の話によると、嘉永4年頃に夢中に枕元に立った老人に導かれて九州の赤山(霧島山)に連れて行かれそこで、その老人は清浄利仙君と名乗る仙人を紹介した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukiyasu told Sotetsu about his strange experience; about 1851, an old man appeared in Yukiyasu&apos;s dream, the old man took him to Mt. Aka (Mt. Kirishima) of the Kyushu region and introduced him to an unworldly man who called himself Seijorisen-kun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukiyasu told Sotetsu about his strange experience; about 1851, an old man appeared in Yukiyasu&apos;s dream, the old man took him to Mt. Aka (Mt. Kirishima) of the Kyushu region and introduced him to an unworldly man who called himself Seijorisen-kun.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukiyasu told Sotetsu about his strange experience; about 1851, an old man appeared in Yukiyasu&apos;s dream, the old man took him to Mt. Aka (Mt. Kirishima) of the Kyushu region and introduced him to an unworldly man who called himself Seijorisen-kun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>利仙君は仁徳天皇時代の人で、少名彦の神の導きで仙界に入り、齢は千五百歳との事であり、その導きを受けている神様の風貌から妻帯されている妻の名前まで聞かされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seijorisen-kun told that he had been born in the period of Emperor Nintoku (313-399), came to the unworldly men&apos;s world by the leading of Sukunahikona no mikoto (one of Japanese ancient gods), and he was 1500 years of age; he described the appearance of Sukunahikona no mikoto and even told the name of his wife he had married in that world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seijorisen-kun said that he had been born in the period of Emperor Nintoku (313-399), came to the unworldly men&apos;s world by the leading of Sukunahikona no mikoto (one of Japanese ancient gods), and he was 1500 years of age; he described the appearance of Sukunahikona no mikoto and even said the name of his wife that he had married in that world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seijorisen-kun said that he had been born in the period of Emperor Nintoku (313-399), came to the unworldly men&apos;s world by the leading of Sukunahikona no mikoto (one of Japanese ancient gods), and he was 1500 years of age; he described the appearance of Sukunahikona no mikoto and even said the name of his wife that he had married in that world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>参澤は奇想天外な話を聞かされ、驚きを隠せなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotetsu MISAWA was very surprised at that strange story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotetsu MISAWA was very surprised at that strange story.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotetsu MISAWA was very surprised at that strange story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>早速この情報を江戸の平田宗家に文に認めて伝達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And soon he wrote a letter and informed the Hirata family of Edo City on the information.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And soon he wrote a letter and informed the Hirata family of Edo City on the information.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And soon he wrote a letter and informed the Hirata family in Edo City of the information.</e>
<cmt>of→inon→of</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>父からの薫陶により、玄学には特に興味を抱いていた銕胤が、この情報に飛びつかない筈はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not surprising that Tetsutane was excited about the information since he had been interested in Gengaku and Shinsendo by the influence of his father-in-low Atsutane.</e>
<cmt>オリジナルは玄学＝神仙道と勘違いして書き写したものらしく、そのままでは話の筋が見えないので、オリジナル著者の解釈を曲げず、言葉を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not surprising that Tetsutane was excited about the information since he had been interested in Gengaku and Shinsendo due to the influence of his father-in-law Atsutane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not surprising that Tetsutane was excited about the information since he had been interested in Gengaku and Shinsendo due to the influence of his father-in-law Atsutane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>嘉永6年9月6日正式に入門の手続きを幸安宛てに提出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on 6 September 1853, Tetsutane formally submitted the document for becoming a pupil to Yukiyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on 6th September 1853, Tetsutane formally submitted the document to become a pupil to Yukiyasu.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on 8th October 1853, Tetsutane formally submitted the document to become a pupil to Yukiyasu.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>また三度の飯よりも神秘好きな房総の宮負定雄も安政元年12月9日に香取郡から和歌山の島田の元へ訪れているが、既に幸安は消息を絶っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasuo MIYAOI of Katori County (Shimousa Province), one of Atsutane&apos;s leading disciples, had been enthusiastic about mysterious things; he heard about Yukiyasu and went all the way to Wakayama to meet him on 9 December 1854, however, Yukiyasu had already disappeared without leaving any trace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuo MIYAOI of Katori County (Shimousa Province), one of Atsutane&apos;s leading disciples, had been enthusiastic about mysterious things; he heard about Yukiyasu and went all the way to Wakayama to meet him on 9th December 1854, however, Yukiyasu had already disappeared without leaving any trace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasuo MIYAOI of Katori County (Shimousa Province), one of Atsutane&apos;s leading disciples, had been enthusiastic about mysterious things; he heard about Yukiyasu and went all the way to Wakayama to meet him on 26th January 1855, however, Yukiyasu had already disappeared without leaving any trace.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>この日を境に、嘉永年間に入門した愛弟子の参澤宗哲と紀州で邂逅し意気投合、安政6年に貞雄が死ぬまでの五年間、相互の交流や互いの自著や情報を交換したりして交遊関係を続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yasuo couldn&apos;t meet Yukiyasu, in Wakayama he met Yukiyasu&apos;s pupil Sotetsu MISAWA and became friends; they had kept close relationship by introducing friends or sending works and information until Yasuo died in 1859.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yasuo couldn&apos;t meet Yukiyasu, in Wakayama he met Yukiyasu&apos;s pupil Sotetsu MISAWA and they became friends; they had kept a close relationship by introducing friends or sending works and information to each other until Yasuo died in 1859.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yasuo couldn&apos;t meet Yukiyasu, in Wakayama he met Yukiyasu&apos;s pupil Sotetsu MISAWA and they became friends; they had kept a close relationship by introducing friends or sending works and information to each other until Yasuo died in 1859.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="96">
<j>幸安の生業は当世風に言えば、患者の病に応じて治療を施し皇漢薬の調剤をする町医者の事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explaining in up-to-date terms, Yukiyasu SHIMADA was a doctor in a small town, who treated sick and wounded people with appropriate measures for each case, and also compounded chemicals or herbs into Japanese herbal medicine or Chinese herbal medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Explaining in up-to-date terms, Yukiyasu SHIMADA was a doctor in a small town, who treated sick and wounded people with appropriate measures for each case, and also compounded chemicals or herbs into Japanese herbal medicine or Chinese herbal medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Explaining in up-to-date terms, Yukiyasu SHIMADA was a doctor in a small town, who treated sick and wounded people with appropriate measures for each case, and also compounded chemicals or herbs into Japanese herbal medicine or Chinese herbal medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>複雑な悩みを抱える相談者には、自らの鎮魂に依り神懸りして託宣を述べ、神霊界に鎮まる東海司大神仙様からの御幽導によって、人の前世や行く末などを的確に予言したり、処世の大道を諭す、スビリチュアル・カウンセリングのようなものを行っていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for patient having deep trouble, he did Chinkon and became a medium of gods to tell gods&apos; message, see patient&apos;s previous incarnation and predict the future by the leading of Tokainotsukasa Daishinsen-sama (Sukunahikona no mikoto), and teach the way of living in this world like present spiritual counselor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For patients that were deeply troubled, he performed Chinkon and became a medium for gods to tell of gods&apos; message, see patient&apos;s previous incarnation and predict the future by the leading of Tokainotsukasa Daishinsen-sama (Sukunahikona no mikoto), and teach the way of living in this world like a present spiritual counselor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For patients that were deeply troubled, he performed Chinkon and became a medium for gods to tell of gods&apos; message, see patient&apos;s previous incarnation and predict the future by the leading of Tokainotsukasa Daishinsen-sama (Sukunahikona no mikoto), and teach the way of living in this world like a present spiritual counselor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>ある時期を境として突然幸安は消息不明となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, one day Yukiyasu suddenly disappeared and hadn&apos;t come back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, one day Yukiyasu suddenly disappeared and never returned.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, one day Yukiyasu suddenly disappeared and never returned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>一説によると、生きながらにして異界へ出入したと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people said that Yukiyasu had been coming and going to another world without dying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people said that Yukiyasu had been coming and going to another world without dying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people said that Yukiyasu had been coming and going to another world without dying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>生前に師幸安からの口授を聞き書きした、宗哲の『神界物語』は全20巻にも及ぶが、この神界の有様を記録した内容の一部が物議をかもす事となり、安政末年の間に於いて平田宗家との間に軋轢が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Yukiyasu had been alive, his pupil Sotetsu MISAWA listened his lectures and wrote those in &quot;Shinkai Monogatari&quot; (Story of Gods&apos; World) in twenty volumes, however, some part of the description of gods&apos; world aroused much controversy between Sotetsu and the Hirata family about at the end of the Ansei era (1854-1860)..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Yukiyasu was alive, his pupil Sotetsu MISAWA listened to his lectures and wrote them down in &quot;Shinkai Monogatari&quot; (Story of Gods&apos; World) in twenty volumes, however, some parts of the description of the gods&apos; world aroused much controversy between Sotetsu and the Hirata family at about the end of the Ansei era (1854-1860)..</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Yukiyasu was alive, his pupil Sotetsu MISAWA listened to his lectures and wrote them down in &quot;Shinkai Monogatari&quot; (Story of Gods&apos; World) in 20 volumes, however, some parts of the description of the gods&apos; world aroused much controversy between Sotetsu and the Hirata family at about the end of the Ansei era (1854-1860)..</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>銕胤は全平田門下に対して、参澤宗哲の著書を焚書し以後流布させないように指示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetane ordered all the students of Hirata&apos;s school to reject all books by Sotetsu and make the print stopped as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetane ordered all the students of Hirata&apos;s school to reject all books by Sotetsu and stopped the printing as well.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetane ordered all the students of Hirata&apos;s school to reject all books by Sotetsu and stopped the printing as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>そして参澤を平田門から破門したのだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides he excommunicated Sotetsu from Hirata&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides he excommunicated Sotetsu from Hirata&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides he excommunicated Sotetsu from Hirata&apos;s school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>一説によると一部の平田門下のものが、参澤の力説する神仙思想に魅せられて彼の主催する塾に入門したり、参澤を崇めるようになったからだとも言われているが詳細は藪の中であります。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The truth is unknown, however, some people said that several students of Hirata&apos;s school had become interested in the theory of unworldly men which Sotetsu had been teaching, and had entered Sotetsu&apos;s school or respected him, so Tetsutane had worried about it and reacted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The truth is unknown, however, some people said that several students of Hirata&apos;s school had become interested in the theory of unworldly men which Sotetsu had been teaching, and had entered Sotetsu&apos;s school or respected him, so Tetsutane became worried about it and reacted.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The truth is unknown, however, some people said that several students of Hirata&apos;s school had become interested in the theory of unworldly men which Sotetsu had been teaching, and had entered Sotetsu&apos;s school or respected him, so Tetsutane became worried about it and reacted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>よってこの神界物語の版本は市場にでる事はなく、出ても数巻の写本でのみ伝わっていると聞く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, at present, the original of &quot;Shinkai Monogatari&quot; can&apos;t be seen and only the copies of some volumes remain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, at present, the original copies of &quot;Shinkai Monogatari&quot; cannot be found and only copies of some volumes remain.</e>
<cmt>rewrote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, at present, the original copies of &quot;Shinkai Monogatari&quot; cannot be found and only copies of some volumes remain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), Straysheep(id:42448), 与左衛門(id:159462), 下総大納言(id:43461), 草薙(id:23262), Greenleaf(id:126500), Point136(id:211299), 伊(id:146699), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>