<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源高明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Takaakira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Takaakira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Takaakira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 高明（みなもと の たかあきら、延喜14年（914年） - 天元 (日本)5年12月26日 (旧暦)（983年1月17日））は、平安時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Takaakira born December 26, 914, died on January 17, 983, was a court noble in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Takaakira born on December 26, 914, died on January 17, 983, was a court noble in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Takaakira (914 - January 17, 983) was a court noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>醍醐天皇の第10皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Emperor Daigo&apos;s 10th prince in line to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Emperor Daigo&apos;s 10th prince in line to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Emperor Daigo&apos;s 10th prince.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は源周子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was MINAMOTO no Chikako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was MINAMOTO no Chikako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was MINAMOTO no Chikako.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法名は覚念。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Kakunen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name was Kakunen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Kakunen.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>京都右京四条に壮麗な豪邸を建設し、「西宮左大臣」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He erected a magnificent estate in Shijo, Ukyo, Kyoto, called &apos;Saikyu-sadaijin&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He erected a magnificent estate in Shijo, Ukyo, Kyoto, called &apos;Saikyu-sadaijin&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He erected a magnificent estate in Shijo of Ukyo in Kyoto, called &apos;Saikyu-sadaijin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置などを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同母姉妹に勤子内親王、雅子内親王ほか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sisters from the same mother were Imperial Princess Isoko and Imperial Princess Gashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sisters from the same mother were Imperial Princess Isoko and Imperial Princess Gashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sisters from the same mother were Imperial Princess Isoko (also known as Imperial Princess Kinshi) and Imperial Princess Gashi (also known as Imperial Princess Masako).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>一世源氏の尊貴な身分であり、学問に優れ朝儀に通じており、また実力者藤原師輔、その娘の中宮藤原安子の後援も得て朝廷で重んじられ、左大臣にまで進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Issei Genji was a noble personage who excelled as a scholar at the chogi (Imperial court ceremony) and was highly respected at court through the patronge of the capable FUJIWARA no Morosuke and his daughter, FUJIWARA no Anshi, an Imperial Prince&apos;s wife, and advanced to the post of Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Takaakira was also known as Issei Genji, a noble personage who excelled as a scholar at the chogi (Imperial court ceremony) and was highly respected at court through the patronage of the capable FUJIWARA no Morosuke and his daughter, FUJIWARA no Anshi, the wife of an Imperial Prince, and advanced to the post of Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt>rewording, spelling, clarificationnot sure of relation between Takakira and Genji</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Takaakira was also known as Issei Genji (Emperor&apos;s son who went out of Imperial family and had Genji name), a noble personage who excelled as a scholar at the chogi (Imperial court ceremony) and was highly respected at court through the patronage of the capable FUJIWARA no Morosuke and his daughter, FUJIWARA no Anshi, the wife of an Imperial Prince, and advanced to the post of Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。(check欄に記載されていたコメントは「trans2」「comment」に続けてコピーしました（太字部分））</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>師輔・安子の死後、藤原氏に忌まれて安和の変で失脚し、政界から退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the deaths of Morosuke and Anshi, he was shunned by the Fujiwara clan and, losing his position during the Anwa Incident, was forced out of political life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the deaths of Morosuke and Anshi, Issei Genji was shunned by the Fujiwara clan and, losing his position during the Anwa Incident, was forced out of political life.</e>
<cmt>substituted name for &quot;he&quot;not sure who &quot;he&quot; refers to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the deaths of Morosuke and Anshi, Issei Genji was shunned by the Fujiwara clan and, losing his position during the Anna Incident, was forced out of political life.</e>
<cmt>(check欄に記載されていたコメントは「trans2」「comment」に続けてコピーしました（太字部分））</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『源氏物語』の主人公光源氏のモデルの一人とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is one model for the character of Hikaru GENJI in the &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is one model for the character of Hikaru GENJI in the &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (Tale of Genji)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one model for the character of Genji HIKARU in the &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt>過去形にし用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>延喜20年（920年）7歳で臣籍降下し、源氏の姓を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 920, at the age of 7, he became of subject of the state and took the name Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 920, at the age of 7, Takaakira became a subject of the state and took the name Genji.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 920, at the age of 7, Takaakira demoted from nobility to subject and took the name Genji.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>延長 (日本)7年（929年）、従四位上に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 929, he was promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 929, he was promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 929, he was promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天慶2年（939年）、参議に昇進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 929, he was elevated to the post of Sangi (councillor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 929, he was elevated to the post of Sangi (councillor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 939, he was elevated to the position of Sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>中納言、大納言を経て、康保3年（967年）右大臣を拝し、左近衛大将を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He rose to the rank of chunagon (post at Imperial Court) and dainagon (chief councilor of state), in 967 becoming Minister of the Right as well as sakonenodaisho (Right General of the Imperial Guard).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He rose to the rank of chunagon (post at Imperial Court) and dainagon (chief councilor of state), and in 967 became Minister of the Right as well as sakonenodaisho (Right General of the Imperial Guard).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He rose to the rank of Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) and Dainagon (chief councilor of state), and in 967 assumed the position of udaijin (Minister of the Right) as well as Sakone no daisho (Right General of the Imperial Guard).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>高明は学問を好み、朝儀、有職故実に練達し、『西宮記』（さいきゅうき）を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaakira had a liking for academics, excelling at Imperial Court ceremony, yusokukojitsu (ancient rules of the Imperial court and military commander) and wrote the &quot;Saikyuki&quot; (Chronicles of the Western Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaakira had a liking for academics, excelling at Imperial Court ceremony, yusokukojitsu (ancient rules of the Imperial court and military command), and wrote the &quot;Saikyuki&quot; (Chronicles of the Western Palace).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaakira had a liking for academics, excelling at chogi (Imperial Court ceremony), Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette), and wrote the &quot;Saikyuki&quot; (Chronicles of the Western Palace).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>朝廷の実力者でかつ高明と同じく故実に通じた藤原師輔の三女を妻とし、この妻が没すると五女の愛宮を娶って友好関係を結び、師輔は高明の後援者となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being proficient in the chogi (Imperial Court ceremony), he took as his wife the third daughter of FUJIWARA no Morosuke, who also excelled at the ancient customs, after her death marrying fifth daughter Aimiya, further cementing their alliance and establishing Morosuke as Takaakira&apos;s supporter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being proficient in the chogi (Imperial Court ceremony), he took as his wife the third daughter of FUJIWARA no Morosuke, who also excelled at the ancient customs; after her death, he married Morosuke&apos;s fifth daughter, Aimiya, further cementing their alliance and establishing Morosuke as Takaakira&apos;s supporter.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took as his wife the third daughter of FUJIWARA no Morosuke, who had power in the Imperial Court and also excelled at the ancient customs; after her death, he married Morosuke&apos;s fifth daughter, Aimiya, further cementing their alliance and establishing Morosuke as Takaakira&apos;s supporter.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、妻の姉の安子は村上天皇の中宮であり、東宮（皇太子）冷泉天皇、為平親王、円融天皇を産み、高明は安子に信任され中宮大夫を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife&apos;s older sister Anshi became the wife of Emperor Murakami and gave birth to Imperial Prince Emperor Reizen, Imperial Prince Tamehira and Emperor Enyu, entrusting Takaakira as the chugudaibu (The chief administrator of the Empress&apos;s household).</e>
<cmt>chugudaibu : The chief administrator of the Empress&apos;s household (http://books.google.com/books?id=M76Xesfoy3sC&amp;pg=PA1162&amp;lpg=PA1162&amp;dq=chugu+daibu&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Yi69_FnWBN&amp;sig=DCyvfRlIMJJjC2QCWt4-Hgxsf9s&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=kEN2SrLIGsaIkAWx-ISRDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4#v=onepage&amp;q=chugu%20daibu&amp;f=false)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife&apos;s older sister Anshi became the wife of Emperor Murakami and gave birth to Imperial Prince Emperor Reizen, Imperial Prince Tamehira, and Emperor Enyu, and entrusted Takaakira as the chugudaibu (The chief administrator of the Empress&apos;s household).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife&apos;s older sister Anshi became the wife of Emperor Murakami and gave birth to Imperial Prince Emperor Reizei, Imperial Prince Tamehira, and Emperor Enyu, and entrusted Takaakira as the chugudaibu (The chief administrator of the Empress&apos;s household).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>高明は自身の娘を為平親王の妃とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahira made his own daughter the Empress of Imperial Prince Tamehira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahira made his own daughter the Empress of Imperial Prince Tamehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaakira made his own daughter the Empress of Imperial Prince Tamehira.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>康保4年（968年）憲平親王（冷泉天皇）の即位に伴い左大臣に昇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 968, he rose to the post of Minister of the Left with the accession of Imperial Prince Norihira (Emperor Reizen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 968, he rose to the post of Minister of the Left with the accession of Imperial Prince Norihira (Emperor Reizen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 968, he rose to the position of sadaijin (Minister of the Left) with the accession of Imperial Prince Norihira (later Emperor Reizei).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>冷泉天皇は狂気の病があったため、早急に後嗣を立てる必要があり、同母弟であった為平親王は東宮の有力候補だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Emperor Reizen was mentally ill, there was an urgent need to install a successor and Imperial Prince Tamehira, his younger brother from the same mother, was a front runner for Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Emperor Reizen was mentally ill, there was an urgent need to install a successor; Imperial Prince Tamehira, his younger brother from the same mother, was a front runner for Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Emperor Reizei was mentally ill, there was an urgent need to install a successor; Imperial Prince Tamehira, his younger brother from the same mother, was a front runner for Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>だが、冷泉天皇の東宮には為平の弟の守平親王（円融天皇）が立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tamehira&apos;s younger brother Imperial Prince Morihira (Emperor Enyu) was established as Emperor&apos;s Reizen&apos;s crown prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tamehira&apos;s younger brother, Imperial Prince Morihira (Emperor Enyu), was established as Emperor&apos;s Reizen&apos;s crown prince.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tamehira&apos;s younger brother, Imperial Prince Morihira (later Emperor Enyu), was established as Emperor&apos;s Reizei&apos;s crown prince.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>高明は大いに失望した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaakira was terribly disappointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaakira was terribly disappointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaakira was terribly disappointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これは高明が将来外戚となることを藤原氏が恐れたためで、この時には既に師輔も安子も死去しており、高明は宮中で孤立していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaakira&apos;s becoming a maternal relative in the future was what the Fujiwara clan had feared and as at this time Morosuke and Anshi had both passed away, Takaakira was isolated at court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaakira&apos;s becoming a maternal relative in the future was what the Fujiwara clan had feared and, as at this time Morosuke and Anshi had both passed away, Takaakira was isolated at court.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaakira&apos;s becoming a maternal relative in the future was what the Fujiwara clan had feared and, as at this time Morosuke and Anshi had both passed away, Takaakira was isolated at court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>安和2年（969年）、源満仲と藤原善時が橘繁延と源連の謀反を密告。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 969, MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka and FUJIWARA no Yoshitoki informed on the treachery of Tachibana no Shigenobu and MINAMOTO no Tsuranu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 969, MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka and FUJIWARA no Yoshitoki reported the treachery of Tachibana no Shigenobu and MINAMOTO no Tsuranu.</e>
<cmt>changed verbtrans1 is unclear about whether the two named reported the treachery or someone reported it to them. If the latter, change to &quot;...Yoshitoki were informed of the treachery&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 969, both MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka and FUJIWARA no Yoshitoki informed the treachery of Tachibana no Shigenobu and MINAMOTO no Tsuranu.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。(check欄に記載されていたコメントは「trans2」「comment」に続けてコピーしました（太字部分））</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>右大臣藤原師尹は諸門を閉じて諸公卿と廷議を開き、密告文を関白藤原実頼に送り、検非違使を派遣して関係者を逮捕させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minister of the Right FUJIWARA no Morotada closed gates and convened a discussion at Imperial Court, sending a report of this statement to Chief Advisor to the Emperor FUJIWARA no Saneyori, and dispatching the police to arrest those involved.</e>
<cmt>諸門: probably gates of the Imperial Court. Could you please change the translation?</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minister of the Right FUJIWARA no Morotada closed the gates of the Imperial Court and convened a discussion, sending a report of this statement to Chief Advisor to the Emperor FUJIWARA no Saneyori, and dispatching the police to arrest those involved.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Udaijin FUJIWARA no Morotada closed the gates of the Imperial Court and convened a discussion, sending a report of this statement to kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Saneyori, and dispatching kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) to arrest those involved.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その中には高明の従者の藤原千晴（藤原秀郷の子）も含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among those was a servant of Takaakira, FUJIWARA no Chiharu (FUJIWARA no Hidesato).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those involved was a servant of Takaakira, FUJIWARA no Chiharu (FUJIWARA no Hidesato).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;involved&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those involved was a servant of Takaakira, FUJIWARA no Chiharu (a son of FUJIWARA no Hidesato).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>謀反の容疑は高明にも及び検非違使が邸を取り囲み、大宰権帥に左遷する詔を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suspicion of involvement in the plot also fell upon Takaakira and police surrounded his residence, delivering an Imperial edict informing him that he was demoted to Dazaigonnosochi (Deputy Commander of Dazaifu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suspicion of involvement in the plot also fell upon Takaakira and police surrounded his residence, delivering an Imperial edict informing him that he was demoted to Dazaigonnosochi (Deputy Commander of Dazaifu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suspicion of involvement in the plot also fell upon Takaakira and the kebiishi surrounded his residence, delivering an Imperial edict informing him that he was demoted to Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これは事実上の流罪であり、高明は長男の源忠賢ともども出家して京に留まることを願うが許されず、大宰府へ流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was in fact banishment, and Takaakira and eldest son MINAMOTO no Tadakata&apos;s pleas that they be allowed to enter the priesthood in Kyoto went unnoticed and they were removed to Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was in fact banishment, and the pleas by Takaakira and his eldest son MINAMOTO no Tadakata&apos;s pleas that they be allowed to enter the priesthood in Kyoto went unnoticed, and they were removed to Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was in fact banishment, and the pleas by Takaakira and his eldest son MINAMOTO no Tadakata&apos;s pleas that they be allowed to enter the priesthood in Kyoto went unnoticed, and they were removed to Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>これは、師輔の死後、高明と確執を深めていた藤原氏の策謀であったとされる（安和の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Morosuke&apos;s death, this was considered to have been a strategy of the Fujiwara clan, with whom relations had worsened. (The Anwa Incident)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Morosuke&apos;s death, this was considered to have been a strategy of the Fujiwara clan, with whom relations had worsened. (The Anwa Incident)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Morosuke&apos;s death, this was considered to have been a strategy of the Fujiwara clan, with whom relations with Takaakira had worsened (The Anna Incident).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>翌天禄2年（971年）、許されて帰京するも、政界に復帰することは無く葛野に隠棲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 971, he was forgiven and allowed to return to Kyoto, although he was unable to return to the political arena and lived in seclusion in his residence at Kadanokori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 971, Takaakira was forgiven and allowed to return to Kyoto, although he was unable to return to the political arena and lived in seclusion in his residence at Kadanokori.</e>
<cmt>substituted name for &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 971, Takaakira was forgiven and allowed to return to Kyoto, although he was unable to return to the political arena and lived in seclusion in his residence at Kadono.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>天元5年（982年）、69歳で没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 982, he died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 982, he died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 982, he died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>伴廉平という人相を善く見る者がいて、高明の顔を見たところ、これほどの貴相を見たことがなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a fortune teller by the name of Renpei, who upon seeing Takaakira&apos;s face, declared that he had never before seen such a noble face.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a fortune teller by the name of Renpei, who, upon seeing Takaakira&apos;s face, declared that he had never before seen such a noble face.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a fortune teller named TOMO no Kadohira, who, upon seeing Takaakira&apos;s face, declared that he had never before seen such a noble face.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、その背中を見て、恐らくは左遷の禍を受けるだろうと予見したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when viewing him from behind, he predicted that he would probably meet with the misfortune of demotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when viewing him from behind, he predicted that Takaakira would probably meet with the misfortune of demotion.</e>
<cmt>substituted name for &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when viewing him from behind, he predicted that Takaakira would probably meet with the misfortune of demotion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>『今昔物語』には高明の左遷にまつわる説話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Konjaku Monogatarishu&quot; (Tales of Times Now Past) is related the account of Takaakira&apos;s demotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Konjaku Monogatarishu&quot; (Tales of Times Now Past) relates the account of Takaakira&apos;s demotion.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Konjaku Monogatarishu&quot; (Tales of Times Now Past) has a story related the account of Takaakira&apos;s demotion.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>高明が桃園の邸宅に居たとき、寝殿の柱の節穴から毎夜、少児の手が出てしきりに差し招く怪異が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A mysterious phenomenon frequently occurred when Takaakira was in the peach orchard of his residence, and from a knothole in a pillar of the Imperial residence there frequently appeared the hand of a child, beckoning him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A mysterious phenomenon frequently occurred when Takaakira was in the peach orchard of his residence; from a knothole in a pillar of the Imperial residence there frequently appeared the hand of a child, beckoning him.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A mysterious phenomenon frequently occurred when Takaakira was in Toen of his residence; from a knothole in a pillar of the Imperial residence there frequently appeared the hand of a child, beckoning him.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>柱に経典、仏画を掛けても怪異は止まず、征矢を刺して穴を塞ぐと怪異はようやく止んだが、やがて、左遷の禍が起きたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite hanging Buddhist pictures and sutras on the pillar, the visitations continued and though finally stopped when the hole was sealed and pierced with an arrow from a battlefield, it was said that at this time he suffered his downfall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite hanging Buddhist pictures and sutras on the pillar, the visitations continued and although they finally stopped when the hole was sealed and pierced with an arrow from a battlefield, it was said that at this time he suffered his downfall.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite hanging Buddhist pictures and sutras on the pillar, the visitations continued and although they finally stopped when the hole was sealed and pierced with an arrow from a battlefield, it was said that at this time he suffered his downfall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="37">
<j>かつて高明が国司を兼ねていた備前国の住民が祠を建てて祭っており、その請いにより、文安5年（1448年）に従一位が追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaakira was formerly provincial governor of Bizen Province, where the local populace erected a shrine to honor him, and in 1448 he was promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaakira was formerly provincial governor of Bizen Province, where the local populace erected a shrine to honor him, and in 1448 he was promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaakira was formerly provincial governor of Bizen Province, where the local populace erected a shrine to honor him, and in 1448 he was promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="38">
<j>子のうち長男の忠賢は安和の変で出家したが、源俊賢と源経房は後に政界で昇進して活躍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among his children, eldest son Tadakata was forced to become a monk because of the Anwa Incident, but MINAMOTO no Toshikata and MINAMOTO no Tsunefusa were later promoted and were active in the political world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his children, eldest son Tadakata was forced to become a monk because of the Anwa Incident, but MINAMOTO no Toshikata and MINAMOTO no Tsunefusa were later promoted and were active in the political world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among his children, eldest son Tadakata was forced to become a monk because of the Anna Incident, but MINAMOTO no Toshikata and MINAMOTO no Tsunefusa were later promoted and were active in the political world.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>また、娘の源明子は藤原道長の妻となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughter MINAMOTO no Akiko became the wife of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughter MINAMOTO no Akiko became the wife of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughter MINAMOTO no Akiko became the wife of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>著作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Published works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Published works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Published Works</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>『西宮記』　当時の儀式・年中行事の式次第・内容を詳細に記した有職故実書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Saikyuki&quot; (Chronicles of the Western Palace), a well used book in which was detailed the subject matter and points of ceremonies and annual functions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Saikyuki&quot; (Chronicles of the Western Palace), a well used book which detailed the subject matter and points of ceremonies and annual functions.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Saikyuki,&quot; a well used book which detailed the subject matter and points of ceremonies and annual functions.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>平安時代中期の宮中儀礼の様子を知ることが出来る一級史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are records of the finest quality which allow one to understand the etiquette of the Imperial Court during the middle Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are records of the finest quality which allow one to understand the etiquette of the Imperial Court during the middle Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are records of the finest quality which allow one to understand the etiquette of the Imperial Court during the middle Heian period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Ks8823(id:130146), 玄史生(id:43670), Equaly(id:89792), 代言人(id:33675), Stanislaus(id:1806), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Yume149(id:17504), 味っ子(id:17086), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), 唐棣色(id:64681), 諸星団(id:72202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>