<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊達政宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune DATE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊達 政宗（だて まさむね、1567年9月5日 - 1636年6月27日）は、戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune DATE (September 5, 1567 - June 27, 1636) was a feudal warlord during the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune DATE (September 5, 1567 - June 27, 1636) was a feudal warlord during the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune DATE (September 5, 1567 - June 27, 1636) was a feudal warlord who lived during the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>出羽国（羽州）と陸奥国（奥州）の戦国大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a feudal lord of Dewa Province (Ushu) and Mutsu Province (Oshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a feudal lord with the territories including Dewa Province (Ushu) and Mutsu Province (Oshu).</e>
<cmt>1. 原文が説明不足なための問題なのですが、「出羽の国と陸奥の国の戦国大名」の意味するところを考えると多少i意訳が必要だと思います。「出羽の国、陸奥の国を領土とした戦国大名」という訳にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a feudal lord with the territories including Dewa Province (Ushu) and Mutsu Province (Oshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>陸奥仙台藩の初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first lord of Sendai Domain in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first lord of Sendai Domain in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first lord of Sendai Domain in Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>本姓は藤原氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original family name was Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original family name was Fujiwara of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「藤原」の名前で日本人は多くを理解できますが、ここでは「藤原氏」の血筋であることが本来の意味であると思います。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original family name was Fujiwara of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家系は伊達朝宗を祖とする伊達氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family belonged to Date clan founded by Tomomune Date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family lineage originated from Date clan founded by Tomomune DATE.</e>
<cmt>1. 「belonged」の用法は多少意味が異なる者になってしまうと思います。対訳をもとに、より適切と思われる者に修正しました。2. 姓名の表記がルールに従っていないため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family lineage originated from the Date clan of Tomomune DATE as an ancestor.</e>
<cmt>founded by というのは祖先をさす場合はおかしいと思いますので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>第16代当主・伊達輝宗と最上義守の娘・義姫（最上義光の妹）の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date Masamune was a legitimate son of the 16th lord, Terumune DATE, and a daughter of Yoshimori MOGAMI, Yoshihime (a younger sister of Yoshiaki MOGAMI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune DATE was a legitimate son of the 16th lord, Terumune DATE and Yoshihime, a daughter of Yoshimori MOGAMI. (a younger sister of Yoshiaki MOGAMI).</e>
<cmt>1. 姓名の表記がルールに従っていないため修正しました。2. 語順を変更し、両者の子であるという意味を読み取りやすくしています。（青字）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune DATE was a legitimate son of the 16th lord, Terumune DATE and Yoshihime, a daughter of Yoshimori MOGAMI (a younger sister of Yoshiaki MOGAMI).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幼名は梵天丸、字は藤次郎、諡号は貞山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Bontenmaru, Chinese style name was Tojiro and posthumous name was Teizan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Bontenmaru, azana (commonly used name) was Tojiro, and shigo (posthumous name) was Teizan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「字」と「諡号」は読みを記述、内容を括弧内で説明する形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Bontenmaru, name commonly used was Tojiro, and a posthumous name was Teizan.</e>
<cmt>azana, shigo は英訳のみにしました。ネイティブには特にazana, shigo などの情報は必要ないかと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>神号は武振彦命で、青葉神社に祭られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the god title, Takefuruhikonomikoto and enshrined at the Aoba-jinjya Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given shingo (the god title) as Takefuruhikonomikoto, and enshrined at the Aoba-jinjya Shrine.</e>
<cmt>1. 「神号」は読みを記述、内容を括弧内で説明する形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the god title as Takefuruhikonomikoto, and enshrined at the Aoba-jinjya Shrine.</e>
<cmt>shingo は英訳のみにしました。ネイティブには特にazana, shigo などの情報は必要ないかと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>幼少時に患った疱瘡（天然痘）により右目を失明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a child, smallpox robbed him of sight in his right eye.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He contracted smallpox in his youth, and lost his eyesight of the right eye.</e>
<cmt>1. 訳は意訳のし過ぎだと思います。（口語的）より一般的な表現に書き換えましました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He contracted smallpox in his youth, and lost his eyesight of the right eye.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、戦国屈指の教養人として、豪華絢爛を好むことで知られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known as the greatest educated person during the Sengoku period and as a person who liked great flamboyance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known as one of the most prominent cultured person during the Sengoku period, while he preferred grand and flamboyant styles.</e>
<cmt>1. 文の内容から、教養人を「educated person」から「cultured person」と変更しています。戦国武将であれば通常高度な教育は受けていますので、その中でも際立つよう配慮しました。2. 「屈指」の意味を「greatest」で表していますが、これも意訳と言えます。わかりやすくはありますが細かいニュアンスがどんどん欠落していきますので、原文に合わせる形で修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known as one of the most prominent cultured person during the Sengoku period, while he preferred grand and flamboyant styles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>諱の「政宗」は伊達家中興の祖といわれる室町時代の第9代当主・伊達政宗 (大膳大夫)にあやかったもので、この大膳大夫政宗と区別するべく藤次郎政宗と呼ぶことも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first name &quot;Masamune&quot; was named after the 9th lord, Masamune DATE (Daizen no daibu [Master of the Palace Table]) who was the founder of a renaissance during the Muromachi period, and he was often called Tojiro-Masamune to distinguish from Daizen no daibu, Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first name &quot;Masamune&quot; was named after the 9th lord of Date clan, Masamune DATE (Daizen no daibu [Master of the Palace Table]) who was the founder of a revival during the Muromachi period; therefore, he was often called Tojiro-Masamune to distinguish from Masamune DATE of Daizen no daibu.</e>
<cmt>1. 内容的に2分されたほうが良い文章ですので、「；」により分割し、run-on sentenceを避けました。2. 定訳でも「中興の祖」を「founder of renaissance」としていますが、「renaissance」をより狭義の「revival」として限定しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first name &quot;Masamune&quot; was named after the 9th lord of Date clan, Masamune DATE (Daizen no daibu [Master of the Palace Table]) who was the founder of a revival during the Muromachi period; therefore, he was often called Tojiro-Masamune to distinguish from Masamune DATE of Daizen no daibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>幼年期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Childhood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Childhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>永禄10年（1567年）、出羽国米沢市の米沢城に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune DATE was born at the Yonezawa-jo Castle in Yonezawa City, Dewa Province in 1567.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1567, Masamune DATE was born in Dewa Province, at Yonezawa-jo Castle located in today&apos;s Yonezawa City.</e>
<cmt>1. 「出羽国」と「米沢市」をごっちゃにしてよいのか疑問に思いましたので、語順を変更することにより各要素を分け、問題とならないものにしました。2. 米沢城の定冠詞を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1567, Masamune DATE was born in Dewa Province, at Yonezawa-jo Castle located in today&apos;s Yonezawa City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>元亀2年（1571年）、疱瘡（天然痘）に罹り右目を失明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1571, he lost the sight in his right eye due to smallpox.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1571, he lost his eyesight of the right eye due to smallpox.</e>
<cmt>1. 先述に倣い同じ訳に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1571, he lost his eyesight of the right eye due to smallpox.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>当時、天然痘を治す治療方法はなく、死の病であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, there were no treatments for smallpox, and it was a deadly disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, there was no treatment for curing smallpox, thus it was a fatal disease.</e>
<cmt>1. At that timeは特定の事柄の前後を表します。ここではより一般的な時代の意味ですので、「In those days」としました。2. 「方法はなく」ということは一つもないと断定することになり、複数形ではなく単数計とすべきです。「deadly」は「死にそうなぐらい危険」の意味で、「死に至る」からは多少意味が異なります。「fatal」を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, there was no treatment for curing smallpox, thus it was a fatal disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>豊臣秀吉や徳川家康に「右目はどうしたのか？」と聞かれた際において、政宗は「木から落ちたとき、右目が出てきてしまったが、あまりに美味しそうだったので、食べてしまった」と語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA asked him about his right eye, he answered &quot;My right eye popped out when I fell from a tree, and then I ate it because it looked so delicious&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA asked him about his right eye, he answered &quot;My right eye popped out when I fell from a tree, and then I ate it because it looked so delicious&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA asked him about his right eye, he answered &quot;My right eye popped out when I fell from a tree, and then I ate it because it looked so delicious&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、片倉景綱が容貌を悪くしていた右目を短刀で摘出したという逸話もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some said that Kagetsuna KATAKURA removed Masamune&apos;s right eye, which made Masamune&apos;s appearance look bad, by a short sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An anecdote is told that Kagetsuna KATAKURA, with his short sword, enucleated Masamune&apos;s right eye that spoiled his appearance.</e>
<cmt>1. 「逸話」の意味で修正しました。2. コンマで文節を区切っているだけで、それらのつながりが示されておらず、意味が通じません。修正しました。3. 「look bad」は口語的ですので適切と思われる者に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An anecdote is told that Kagetsuna KATAKURA, with his short sword, enucleated Masamune&apos;s right eye that spoiled his appearance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>元亀3年（1572年）、政宗の将来を心配した父・伊達輝宗が招いた臨済宗の虎哉宗乙（こさいそういつ）禅師による厳しい教育が始められ、仏教や漢学を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s father, Terumune DATE, who was concerned about Masamune&apos;s future, invited a monk of the Rinzai sect, Kosai Soitsu, and Masamune learned Buddhism and Sinology under intense instruction of Kosai Soitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The father of Masamune, Terumune DATE was concerned about the future of Masamune, then he invited a Zen priest of the Rinzai sect, Kosai Soitsu for Masamune to teach Buddhism and Sinology with strict instruction.</e>
<cmt>1. 非常にコンマによる分割が多いです。できる限りコンマや関係代名詞による文節を必要としない語順に修正しました。また同様に、アポストロフィの多用も避けました。2. 禅宗の「禅師」の意味がかけていましたので修正しました。結果的に「教える」と「学ぶ」が逆転する形になってしまいましたが、大きな問題はないと思います。3. ここでの「厳しい」教育は「intense」ですと「激しい」や「濃密」の意味になり、多少異なると思います。禅の教えによる修行とみなし、「strict」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The father of Masamune, Terumune DATE was concerned about the future of Masamune, then he invited a Zen priest of the Rinzai sect, Kosai Soitsu for Masamune to teach Buddhism and Sinology with strict instruction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天正3年（1575年）、神職の子である片倉景綱が守り役を命ぜられ側近となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1575, Kagetsuna KATAKURA, who was a son of a Shinto priest, became Masamune&apos;s personal attendant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1575, Kagetsuna KATAKURA, who was a son of a Shinto priest, was appointed as the personal guardian of Masamune to become his attendant.</e>
<cmt>1. 「守り役」は従者以上の役割であると思います。「後見」とは異なるため迷いましたが、「personal guardian」としました。その上で、側近になったの意味としています。「命ぜられ」の意味が欠如していますので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1575, Kagetsuna KATAKURA, who was a son of a Shinto priest, was appointed as the personal guardian of Masamune to become his attendant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>景綱は政宗の側近中の側近として、時には軍師として生涯忠誠を尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagetsuna was relied upon as the closest aide and sometimes as a strategist by Masamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagetsuna served and devoted his life to Masamune, sometimes as the closest aide, and sometimes as a strategist next to Masamune.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文の「生涯尽くす」と訳文の「信頼される」では主語が異なり、さらに相当意味が異なると思います。原文に即し訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagetsuna served and devoted his life to Masamune, sometimes as the closest aide, and sometimes as a strategist next to Masamune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>家督相続から摺上原の戦いまで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From succession to the family to the Suriagehara War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the succession to the headship of the family to the Suriagehara War</e>
<cmt>1. 定冠詞に問題があります。追加しました。2. 「家督」について、「headship」を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the succession to the headship of the family to the Suriagehara War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>天正5年（1577年）に元服、天正7年（1579年）には仙道の戦国大名で三春城主田村清顕の娘愛姫を正室とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune came of age in 1577, and married Aihime, a daughter of Kiyoaki TAMURA who was a warlord of Sendo and a lord of the Miharu-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1577, Masamune celebrated his coming of age, and in 1579, he got married with Aihime whose father was a warlord of Sendo and the lord of the Miharu-jo Castle, Kiyoaki TAMURA.</e>
<cmt>1. 元服は晴れの式ですので、きちんと「ceremony」を追加しました。2. 結婚した年が訳で欠けています。追加しました。3. 原文で「田村清顕の娘、愛姫」となっているところを「愛姫の父は田村清顕」としています。読みやすさを重視しての判断です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1577, Masamune celebrated his coming of age, and in 1579, he got married with Aihime whose father was a warlord of Sendo and the lord of the Miharu-jo Castle, Kiyoaki TAMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>天正9年（1581年）、隣接する戦国大名・相馬氏への侵攻に15歳で初陣し、勝利を収める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 15 in 1581, Masamune went on his first campaign, attacked SOMA clan which ruled a neighboring domain, and won the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1581, when Masamune was 15 years old, he went on his first battle to attack the adjacent province ruled by SOMA clan, and won a victory.</e>
<cmt>1. 年号と年齢が重なりますので、訳文では不自然です。修正しました。2. 「Campaigne」は一連の戦争をさしますので、「battle」にしました。訳者も特定の戦い（一つの）として後半は訳しています。3. 「隣接」をneighboring domainとすると隣り合わせでなくても良くなってしまいます。原文に合わせ修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1581, when Masamune was 15 years old, he went on his first battle to attack the adjacent province ruled by SOMA clan, and won a victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>天正12年（1584年）に18歳で家督を相続し、伊達家17代を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1584, Masamune succeeded to the family at the age of 18, and became the 17th lord of Date clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1584, Masamune succeeded to the family at the age of 18, and became the 17th lord of Date clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1584, Masamune succeeded to the family at the age of 18, and became the 17th lord of Date clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>父・輝宗は41歳の働き盛りでもあり、政宗は当初、年少を理由に辞退を申し出たが、政宗の武将としての素質を見抜いていた輝宗の決意は固く、家督を相続することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, his father, Terumune was 41 years old and still in his prime, so Masamune had refused succession because he thought that it was too early, but Terumune, who believed that Masamune got what it takes to be a great warlord, did not change his decision, and eventually Masamune succeeded to the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, his father Terumune was 41 years old and still in his prime, thus Masamune first declined to succeed family headship insisting on his immaturity; however, the determination of Terumune was strong as he saw through the talent of Masamune as a military commander; eventually Masamune accepted the succession of family headship.</e>
<cmt>1. 「so」は口語的ですので「thus」としました。2. 「辞退」を「refuse」とすると立場のある人間が断る、あるいは拒絶するの意味になりますので、「decline」としました。3. 「武将」としての才能と「warlord」としての才能は異なる次元の者だと思います。ここでは「戦いの才能」を意味していると思われますので、「military commandar」としました。4. （才能を）「見抜く」、「決意が固い」など意訳により意味がかわってしまっています。修正しました。分割した方が良い場所で「；」により分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, his father Terumune was 41 years old and still in his prime, thus Masamune first declined to succeed family headship insisting on his immaturity; however, the determination of Terumune was strong as he saw through the talent of Masamune as a military commander; eventually Masamune accepted the succession of family headship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>小手森城主の戦国大名・大内定綱は二本松城主の戦国大名・畠山義継と手を組み、田村氏からの支配を脱却し、政宗に対抗しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lord of the Odamori-jo Castle, Sadatsuna OUCHI and a lord of the Nihonmatsu-jo Castle, Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA cooperated to be free from domination of Tamura clan, and they opposed Masamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lord of the Odamori-jo Castle Sadatsuna OUCHI allied with the lord of the Nihonmatsu-jo Castle Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA, in order to free themselves from the ruling of Tamura clan, and then to oppose against Masamune.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文では「大内定綱が畠山義継と手を組み」としており、「定綱」が首謀し「義継」と手を組んだの意味があると思います。訳文は「両者が同時に歩み寄りの上」手を組んだの意味になってしまいます。原文にあわせて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lord of the Odamori-jo Castle Sadatsuna OUCHI allied with the lord of the Nihonmatsu-jo Castle Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA, in order to free themselves from the ruling of Tamura clan, and then to oppose against Masamune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>天正13年（1585年）、政宗は小手森城へ兵を進める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1585, Masamune attacked the Odamori-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1585, Masamune advanced his troops to the Odamori-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文は「兵を進める」とあり、「攻撃した」の意味は短文のため含まれるとはいえ意訳になっています。原文にならいました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1585, Masamune advanced his troops to the Odamori-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>討伐の際は、降伏を認めないなどの徹底した粛清（小手森城政宗の撫で斬り）を行い、非道な一面を見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the attack, Masamune remained unsparing attitudes such as refusing surrender of enemy soldiers, and purged the entire hostile troop (Masamune&apos;s clean sweep at the Odemori castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the attack, Masamune revealed the cruel side of his nature by refusing the surrender of enemy soldiers and throughgoingly purged the entire enemy troops (Masamune&apos;s enemy mow down at the Odemori-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>1. 「非道な一面を見せた」をより適切と思われる者に修正しました。2. 「撫で斬り」は文意から、「全滅させる」の意味があると思います。訳文ではその意味が軽く表現されてしまいますので、「根こそぎの大量殺戮」の意味のある「mow down」に修正しました。3. 「〜城」の表記をルールに即して修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the attack, Masamune revealed the cruel side of his nature by refusing the surrender of enemy soldiers and throughgoingly purged the entire enemy troops (Masamune&apos;s enemy mow down at the Odemori-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>豪族が殆ど親戚・縁戚同士という奥州では皆殺し戦術は前代未聞の大事件であり、近隣の戦国大名を恐怖に陥れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Oshu, almost all ruling families were related by blood one another, so even during wars, extermination of enemies had never happened before, and Masamune&apos;s wiping-out strategy terrorized feudal lords of neighboring domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His tactics of annihilating the enemy troops was an unprecedented event in Oshu region, where almost all ruling clans were relatives and kinsmen; this incident terrorized those feudal lords of neighboring territories.</e>
<cmt>1. 語順が原文にあわせてありますが、意味が分散し非常にわかりづらいため、英文としてわかりやすいものに修正しています。2. 「exterminate」は動植物の「駆除」の意味が強いと思います。「annihilate」に変更しました。3. 「前代未聞」の意味が弱まってしまっていますので修正しました。4. 「strategy」は戦略としてより大きな作戦や長い期間の作戦をさします。ここはある特定の戦闘ですので、「tactics」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His tactics of annihilating the enemy troops was an unprecedented event in Oshu region, where almost all ruling clans were relatives and kinsmen; this incident terrorized those feudal lords of neighboring territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>これは、近隣諸国への見せしめである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This attack was set an example to neighboring countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This annihilation tactics was set as a warming to neighboring countries.</e>
<cmt>1. ここでは訳者の言う「攻撃」そのものよりも「皆殺し戦術」が見せしめであった、という意味ですので、そのように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This annihilation tactics was set as a warming to neighboring countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし、一方で政宗は後年、戦略的見地から定綱を家臣の列に加えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, on the other hand, Masamune appointed Sadatsuna as his vassal later, from the strategic point of view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Masamune later accepted Sadatsuna as his vassal from the strategic point of view.</e>
<cmt>1. 「But」による書き出しは口語的です。修正しました。マイナー修正です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Masamune later accepted Sadatsuna as his vassal from the strategic point of view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>大内定綱の没落を間近で見た畠山義継は、和議を申し出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA, who knew the fall of Sadatsuna OUCHI, attempted to make peace with Masamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Closely witnessed the decline of Sadatsuna OUCHI, Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA asked Masamune to have a peace negotiation.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文の「没落を間近で見た」の意味が単に「知った」となってしまっています。原文に倣いました。2. 「和議」のフレーズを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Closely witnessed the decline of Sadatsuna OUCHI, Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA asked Masamune to have a peace negotiation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>輝宗の取りなしにより5ヶ村のみを畠山領として安堵することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HATAKEYAMA family was secured only 5 villages as their territory, but the problem was settled down due to Terumune&apos;s meditation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The peace talk was settled by the mediation of Terumune by limiting the territory of HATAKEYAMA family to 5 villages.</e>
<cmt>1. 「取りなし」が「meditation」となっており完全に誤訳です。「mediation」のところのミスと思われますが、推敲で発見可能と思われます。2. 訳では「畠山家は5か村のみ保証されたが、輝宗の取りなしによって事態が収まった」となっており、「輝宗の取りなし」の範囲が原文と異なっているように思います。和議交渉が主語でありながらここでは欠けていたため、追加した上で全体修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The peace talk was settled by the mediation of Terumune by limiting the territory of HATAKEYAMA family to 5 villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ところが輝宗が、所領安堵の件などの礼に来ていた畠山義継を城門まで見送りに行った所を拉致される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, Terumune was kidnapped when he came to a castle gate to see off Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA who had visited Terumune to thank for his meditation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Terumune was abducted when he came to a castle gate to see off Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA, who had visited Terumune to express his gratitude for mediating the peace talk and securing his territory.</e>
<cmt>1. ここでも「取りなし」が「meditation」となっており完全に誤訳です。2. 「But」を文頭にしている点を修正しました。3. kidnapは誘拐につかわれ、拉致とは多少異なるように思います。「abducted」を用いました。4. 「礼」の訳がこの場合単純すぎますので、より形式的な意味を持つものに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Terumune was abducted when he came to a castle gate to see off Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA, who had visited Terumune to express his gratitude for mediating the peace talk and securing his territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>政宗は事件の時、狩りに出かけていたが急遽戻り、畠山一行を追跡し、父・輝宗もろとも鉄砲を放って一人も残さず殺害したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Masamune was out hunting, but he promptly returned to the castle, chased HATAKEYAMA&apos;s entourage, and shot to kill to the last man including this father, Terumune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When this incident occurred, Masamune was out in the field for hunting, but he rushed back to the castle and chased after the entourage of HATAKEYAMA, and shot everyone to death along with his father, Terumune.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文を訳す際、この訳者は簡略化／意訳化しすぎるように思います。ここでも「mediation」を「meditation」としたと同様、「his」を「this」としたままになっています。これはケアレスミスと思われます。2. 「急遽」を「prompt」とすると「時間通りに」といった意味になります。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When this incident occurred, Masamune was out in the field for hunting, but he rushed back to the castle and chased after the entourage of HATAKEYAMA, and shot everyone to death along with his father, Terumune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この事件は、輝宗が自分とともに義継を撃てと命じたとの説や追跡してきた政宗の軍勢がすでに鉄砲で武装していたことから、政宗の父殺しの陰謀だったとする説など発生原因も含めて諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for this incident, there are various theories such as that Terumune ordered Masamune to shoot Yoshitsugu even at the cost of his own life, and that guessing from the fact that Masamune&apos;s troop was armed with guns, Masamune plotted to kill his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for this incident, there are various theories regarding the causes and consequences; Terumune ordered Masamune to shoot Yoshitsugu together with him; or it was a plot of Masamune to kill his father, judging from the fact that the troops of Masamune coming after the group of Hatakeyama was prepared with guns.</e>
<cmt>1. 訳文で「発生原因も含めて」が欠けています。追加しました。2. 文章を「；」で分割し、諸説を明確に分けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for this incident, there are various theories regarding the causes and consequences; Terumune ordered Masamune to shoot Yoshitsugu together with him; or it was a plot of Masamune to kill his father, judging from the fact that the troops of Masamune coming after the group of Hatakeyama was prepared with guns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>その後、初七日法要を済ますと輝宗の弔い合戦のため早くも二本松氏の二本松城を包囲し、畠山氏救出のため集結した、佐竹氏・蘆名氏など3万の反伊達連合軍と安達郡人取橋で死闘を演じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after the memorial service on the sixth day after Terumune&apos;s death, Masamune besieged the Nihonmatsu-jo Castle of Nihonmatsu clan to revenge for Terumune&apos;s death, and was engaged in mortal combat at the Hitotori-bashi Bridge in Adachi District against 30,000 anti-DATE allied forces organized by SATAKE and ASHINA clans for saving HATAKEYAMA clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after the memorial service on the sixth day after Terumune&apos;s death, Masamune besieged the Nihonmatsu-jo Castle of Nihonmatsu clan for an avenging battle of Terumune&apos;s death; his troops engaged in a fierce battle against anti-DATE allied forces of Satake and Ashina clans with 30,000 soldiers organized for saving Hatakeyama clan, at the Hitotori-bashi Bridge in Adachi District.</e>
<cmt>1. 「revenge」は私憤に用いられ、弔い合戦のような戦国時代には義憤と考えられていた場合には「avenge」が用いられます。言い回し含め修正しました。2. 「死闘」については、ここでは激しさを示すもので意訳すべきだと思います。「fierece battle」としました。3. 重要度の違い（軍勢内容と地名では、軍勢内容の方がここでは重要です）により語順修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after the memorial service on the sixth day after Terumune&apos;s death, Masamune besieged the Nihonmatsu-jo Castle of Nihonmatsu clan for an avenging battle of Terumune&apos;s death; his troops engaged in a fierce battle against anti-DATE allied forces of Satake and Ashina clans with 30,000 soldiers organized for saving Hatakeyama clan, at the Hitotori-bashi Bridge in Adachi District.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>数の上で五分の一以下の戦力であった伊達軍は重臣・鬼庭良直を討たれ窮地に立つものの辛くも持ち堪え、反伊達連合軍の撤退により政宗は勝利をおさめた（人取橋の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The DATE troop, which had only one fifth soldiers of the allied forces, faced many predicaments such as death of a senior vassal, Yoshinao ONINIWA, but they barely withstood, made the allied forces withdraw, and finally won the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The DATE troop had less than one-fifth of soldiers compared to the allied forces, and the troops faced difficulties when a senior retainer Yoshinao ONINIWA was killed in the battle; however, they narrowly withstood against the enemy attacks and made the allied forces withdraw, and consequently Masamune won a victory (the Battle of Hitotoribashi).</e>
<cmt>1. 原文では「重臣〜が討たれたために窮地に立った」とありますが、訳文は「重臣〜が討たれるなど数々の窮地に直面した」とあり、意味がまったく異なるものになっています。原文に即したものに修正しました。2. 「1/5以下」の「以下」が欠けているなど、意味があちこちで抜け落ちています。追加しました。3. 括弧で説明されている部分が訳文から抜けています。追加しました。4. これは「戦術的には負けたものの戦略的には勝利した」というケースだと思います。この点考慮し、「勝利」の意味が広い意味となる「victory」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The DATE troop had less than one-fifth of soldiers compared to the allied forces, and the troops faced difficulties when a senior retainer Yoshinao ONINIWA was killed in the battle; however, they narrowly withstood against the enemy attacks and made the allied forces withdraw, and consequently Masamune won a victory (the Battle of Hitotoribashi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="38">
<j>政宗は更なる侵攻を行い、天正16年（1588年）に郡山合戦にて相手国の領土を奪う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune made more attacks, and in 1588, at the Battle of Koriyama, he conquered enemies&apos; domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune promoted further invasion operations; in 1588, he conquered the territory of the opponent after the victory of the Battle of Koriyama.</e>
<cmt>1. 「侵攻」を「atacks」としていますが、戦略的な意味が強い侵攻に局所的な戦術攻撃の意味であるattacksは適切ではありません。一般的な「invation」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune promoted further invasion operations; in 1588, he conquered the territory of the opponent after the victory of the Battle of Koriyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>正妻愛姫の実家田村氏の協力を得て、現在の福島県中通り中部にあたる地域まで支配下におく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to TAMURA clan who was the family of Masamune&apos;s wife, Aihime, Masamune succeeded in seizing a territory of present the middle area of Nakadori, Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Receiving the support from the Tamura clan, the parents house of his wife Aihime, Masamune expanded his territory and influence to the middle part of Nakadori region in today&apos;s Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>「現在の福島県」前後の訳が文法的に成立していません。非常にわかりづらいため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Receiving the support from the Tamura clan, the parents house of his wife Aihime, Masamune expanded his territory and influence to the middle part of Nakadori region in today&apos;s Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="40">
<j>関白豊臣秀吉は関東・東北の諸大名、特に関東の北条氏と東北の伊達氏に対して、惣無事令を発令した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A chancellor, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI issued the Peace Edicts for feudal lords of Kanto and Tohoku Regions, especially for HOJO clan in Kanto Region and Date clan in Tohoku Region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanpaku (a chancellor, a chief advisor to the Emperor) Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI issued a peace edicts to the feudal lords in Kanto and Tohoku regions, intended especially for the Hojo clan in Kanto region and the Date clan in Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>1. 「関白」は英訳部分を括弧内の説明付記としました。直訳調です。原文で「特に〜に対して」を「especially for〜」とすると特に「何」なのかが説明されません。「intended especially for」としました。2. 「惣無事令」はこの際特定事例としてではないと想定し、定冠詞を不定冠詞としました。3. その他、前置詞用法でより適切と思われるものに修正し、また大文字用法の不適切と思われたものも修正しました。（Tohoku Regionsなど）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanpaku (a chancellor, a chief advisor to the Emperor) Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI issued a peace edicts to the feudal lords in Kanto and Tohoku regions, intended especially for the Hojo clan in Kanto region and the Date clan in Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし、政宗は秀吉の命令を無視して戦争を続行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Masamune ignored the Hideyoshi&apos;s edicts and continued battles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Masamune continued his warfare by ignoring the order from Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>1. 繰り返しますが「battle」は特定の戦闘をさす場合が多いです。「warfare」としました。2. 文節順も変更しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Masamune continued his warfare by ignoring the order from Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="42">
<j>同年、北方の大崎氏家中の内紛に介入、兵1万を以て攻め入ったものの大崎氏の頑強な抵抗、及び味方であった黒川晴氏の裏切りと大雪により敗北。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Masamune attacked Osaki clan with 10,000 soldiers to intervene in family conflict of Osaki clan, but Masamune was defeated due to stiff resistance of Osaki clan, betrayal of Haruuji KUROKAWA, and heavy snowfall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Masamune intervened in the family conflict of Osaki clan by invading the territory of Osaki clan with 10,000 soldiers, but Masamune was defeated due to the stiff resistance of Osaki clan, the betrayal of his ally Haruuji KUROKAWA, and the weather condition during the battle with a heavy snow.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文に「同年」とありますが、それに先立つ年号が前項目に見当たりません。郡山合戦の年号でしょうか。その場合、同年というには文章間隔が大きくわかりづらいと思います。2. 原文「渦中の内紛に介入、攻め入る」の順序のところ、訳文では逆の説明です。原文にあわせました。（青字で変更を示しています）3. なお敗北の3つの理由ですが、書式を3者あわせるようにしました。原文では単に「大雪」とありますが、「気象条件」のフレーズを加えています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Masamune intervened in the family conflict of Osaki clan by invading the territory of Osaki clan with 10,000 soldiers, but Masamune was defeated due to the stiff resistance of Osaki clan, the betrayal of his ally Haruuji KUROKAWA, and the weather condition during the battle with a heavy snow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これに乗じて伊達領南部に蘆名氏、二階堂氏らが侵攻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asian clan and Mikado clan seized the opportunity to invade a southern territory of Date clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashina clan and Nikaido clan seized this defeat as the opportunity to invade the Southern part of the Date clan territory.</e>
<cmt>1. 「蘆名氏」が「Asian clan」に、「二階堂氏」が「Mikado clan」なっています。2. 「伊達領南部」を「a southern territory of Date clan」とすると、「伊達氏の南部の領地」となり原文の意味と微妙に異なる、あるいは曖昧になります。原文にあわせ修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashina clan and Nikaido clan seized this defeat as the opportunity to invade the Southern part of the Date clan territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また伯父・最上義光とも一触即発の事態となるが義姫の仲介により和議が成立し窮地を脱した（大崎合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune could barely avoid a fight with his uncle, Yoshiaki MOGAMI and succeeded in amiable settlement with Yoshiaki thanks to mediation of Yoshihime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Masamune came close to an explosive situation with his uncle Yoshiaki MOGAMI, but Yoshihime intermediated between them to reconcile their relationship, thus Masamune managed to escape from his predicament.</e>
<cmt>訳文で「amirable settlement」とありますが、原文にそのようなくだりは見当たりません。逆に、「窮地を脱した」の訳が見当たりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Masamune came close to an explosive situation with his uncle Yoshiaki MOGAMI, but Yoshihime intermediated between them to reconcile their relationship, thus Masamune managed to escape from his predicament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="45">
<j>天正17年（1589年）には東北地方の覇権を賭けて会津の蘆名義広・佐竹氏の連合軍と戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1589, Masamune fought with the allied forces of Yoshihiro ASHINA and SATAKE clan of Aizu District for hegemony in Tohoku Region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1589, Masamune fought against the allied forces of Yoshihiro ASHINA and Satake clan from Aizu region in order to gain supremacy in Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>1. 「fought with the allied forces of〜」という訳では、「〜の連合軍と共に戦う」という意味にもとれてしまうため誤解を招きます。「fight against」としました。2. 「Aizu District」ですと特定の「会津郡」の意味になります。会津は地域名であり特定の地名ではありませんので、会津地方と訳しました。3. 「hegemony」は間違いではありませんが、別の意味にも使われますので、より一般的な「supremacy」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1589, Masamune fought against the allied forces of Yoshihiro ASHINA and Satake clan from Aizu region in order to gain supremacy in Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>この戦いを摺上原の戦い（磐梯山麓・猪苗代町付近）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This battle was called the Suriagehara War (around Inawashiro Town at the foot of the Bandai-san Mountain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This battle is called the Suriagehara War (the battle was fought near Inawashiro-cho, at the foot of the Bandai-san Mountain).</e>
<cmt>1. 過去形で訳されていますが、事後現在に至るまでこの名称だと思いますので、現在形に訂正しました。2. 括弧内の説明は、直訳で「摺上原の戦い」の説明になっていません。加筆修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This battle is called the Suriagehara War (the battle was fought near Inawashiro-cho, at the foot of the Bandai-san Mountain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>蘆名氏はすでに関白、秀吉傘下の大名となっており、政宗が蘆名氏と戦うことは秀吉への挑戦を意味していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Yoshihiro ASHINA had already become a chancellor and a subject of Hideyoshi, so fighting with ASHINA clan had the same meaning as treason against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the time of this war, Yoshihiro ASHINA had already become one of those many warlords coming under the umbrella of the chancellor Hideyoshi, therefore fighting against Ashina clan meant a defiance against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>1. 「蘆名氏が関白秀吉の傘下の大名になっていた」という原文が「蘆名氏がすでに関白になっていた」という訳になっており、誤訳です。訂正しました。2. ここでも「fight with〜」の問題がありましたので「fight against〜」としました。3. 「秀吉への挑戦」を「treason」としていますが、treasonは正義や国家に対しての否定的な「大逆」の意味ですので避けました。原文の意味する通り、「defiance」としています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the time of this war, Yoshihiro ASHINA had already become one of those many warlords coming under the umbrella of the chancellor Hideyoshi, therefore fighting against Ashina clan meant a defiance against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>蘆名義広は1万5千の兵を率い、政宗も2万1千を率いて磐梯山の中腹に陣を敷いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The troop of Yoshihiro ASHINA consisted of 15,000 soldiers, and Masamune&apos;s troop which consisted of 21,000 placed their base on the side of the Bandai-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The troops of Yoshihiro ASHINA consisted of 15,000 soldiers, while the troops of Masamune consisted of 21,000 soldiers; Masamune took up a position on the halfway up the Bandai-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>1. 「troop」は軍隊として用いる場合通常troopsの複数形です。ほかにも同じ間違いが多数ありましたので修正しました。2. 「The troops of〜」の形に2者を統一しました。3. 「Masamune placed their base」は文法上誤りです。修正しました。4. 「陣を敷く」のフレーズが適切ではありませんので訂正しました。5. 「山の中腹」のフレーズが適切ではありませんので訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troops of Yoshihiro ASHINA consisted of 15,000 soldiers, while the troops of Masamune consisted of 21,000 soldiers; Masamune took up a position on the halfway up the Bandai-san Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>この戦いで伊達軍は騎馬武者300騎、兵2千余りを討ち取ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this battle, Masamune&apos;s troop killed about 300 mounted warriors and 2,000 foot soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this battle, Masamune&apos;s troops killed 300 cavalrymen and 2,000 infantrymen.</e>
<cmt>1. troopは軍隊として用いる場合通常troopsの複数形です。2. 日本でも騎馬武者は雑兵ではなく、ある程度の身分のある武士ですので、単に馬に乗っている兵の意味のある訳者の訳ではなく、「cavalrymen」としました。逆に、兵については「infantrymen」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this battle, Masamune&apos;s troops killed 300 cavalrymen and 2,000 infantrymen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>黒川城を陥落させ蘆名氏を滅ぼし会津地方を支配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune seized the Kurokawa-jo Castle, defeated ASHINA clan, and ruled Aizu Region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kurokawa-jo Castle fell to the troops of Masamune; Masamune took control of the Aizu region after the fall of Ashina clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「城を陥落させた」の意味を、「奪い取った」の意味のあるseizeで訳していますが、ニュアンスがかわってしまうと考え修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kurokawa-jo Castle fell to the troops of Masamune; Masamune took control of the Aizu region after the fall of Ashina clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>さらに兵を須賀川へ進め二階堂氏を滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also sent his troop to the Suka-gawa River and defeated NIKAIDO clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune further advanced his troops to Suka-gawa River; consequently Masamune overthrew Nikaido clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「二階堂氏を滅ぼした」を「defeated Nikaido」としてしまうと、単にある戦いで勝利したの意味になってしまいます。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune further advanced his troops to Suka-gawa River; consequently Masamune overthrew Nikaido clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この戦いと前後して、戦国大名・白河義親、石川昭光、岩城常隆が次々と政宗に服属した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before and after this battle, feudal lords such as Yoshichika SHIRAKAWA, Akimitsu ISHIKAWA and Tsunetaka IWAKI gave in to Masamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before and after this battle, feudal lords such as Yoshichika SHIRAKAWA, Akimitsu ISHIKAWA and Tsunetaka IWAKI yielded to Masamune one after another, and served under him.</e>
<cmt>1. 「服属」の訳ですが、降伏と帰属の両方の意味があります。またgive inは口語的ですので、一般的な「yeild」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before and after this battle, feudal lords such as Yoshichika SHIRAKAWA, Akimitsu ISHIKAWA and Tsunetaka IWAKI yielded to Masamune one after another, and served under him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="53">
<j>このとき政宗は現在の福島県の中通り地方と会津地方、及び山形県の南部、宮城県の南部を領し全国的にも屈指の領国規模を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Masamune seized the area of present Nakadori Region in Fukushima Prefecture, Aizu Region, the southern part of Yamagata Prefecture, and the southern part of Miyagi Prefecture, and Masamune&apos;s territory became one of the largest in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By that time, Masamune territorialized the Nakadori region and Aizu region of today&apos;s Fukushima Prefecture, the Southern part of Yamagata Prefecture, and the Southern part of Miyagi Prefecture; Masamune acquired one of the largest areas of domain among other warlords in Japan.</e>
<cmt>1. seizeのここでの用法は誤りだと思います。単純に原文の「領した」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By that time, Masamune territorialized the Nakadori region and Aizu region of today&apos;s Fukushima Prefecture, the Southern part of Yamagata Prefecture, and the Southern part of Miyagi Prefecture; Masamune acquired one of the largest areas of domain among other warlords in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>これに加え上述の白河結城氏といった南陸奥の諸豪族や、また今の宮城県や岩手県の一部を支配していた大崎氏・葛西氏も政宗の勢力下にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to that, local ruling families of South Mutsu Province such as SHIRAKAWA-YUKI clan, OSAKI clan who occupied a part of present Miyagi Prefecture and Iwate Prefecture, and KASAI clan also gave in to Masamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further to those own domains, Masamune also took control of those local ruling families in Southern Mutsu Province area such as Shirakawa Yuki clan, and the ruling families of today&apos;s Miyagi Prefecture to Iwate Prefecture area such as Osaki clan and Kasai clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「勢力下にあった」と「降伏した」では意味に微妙な差異があると思います。1. 白川結城氏をルールに則り修正しました。1. 白川結城氏のフレーズと、大崎／葛西氏のフレーズを同様にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further to those own domains, Masamune also took control of those local ruling families in Southern Mutsu Province area such as Shirakawa Yuki clan, and the ruling families of today&apos;s Miyagi Prefecture to Iwate Prefecture area such as Osaki clan and Kasai clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>豊臣秀吉との対立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confrontation with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confrontation with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confrontation with Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>この頃、中央では豊臣秀吉が織田信長の統一事業を継承しており、政宗は秀吉と鋭く対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI succeeded to unification of Jaoan from Nobunaga ODA, and Masamune was opposed to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was carrying out the unification process of Japan as a single nation, which he took over from Nobunaga ODA; Masamune strongly opposed to this unification process of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>1. 「この頃」の訳を適切なものに修正しました。事業の継承の「継承」は、より適切と思われる「take over」としました。2. このケースでは原文が説明不足と思われたため、多少の意訳と追記を行っています。3. 「鋭く」の訳が欠落しています。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was carrying out the unification process of Japan as a single nation, which he took over from Nobunaga ODA; Masamune strongly opposed to this unification process of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>秀吉から上洛して恭順の意を示すよう促す書状が何通か届けられており、政宗はこれを黙殺していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi sent several letters to urge Masamune&apos;s deference, but Masamune ignored them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several letters were sent from Hideyoshi trying to persuade Masamune to visit Kyoto for swearing allegiance, but Masamune ignored them.</e>
<cmt>1. 「上洛して」の訳が欠けています。追加しました。2. 「恭順」の「自発的に服する」意味の訳を「deference」とすると、「強制的に服従させる」の意味で、強すぎます。「allegiance」としました。同様に、「促す」も「urge」では強すぎますので、「persuage」としました。歴史的に秀吉は服属の「強制」を政宗のような大大名にはしていません。あくまで強大な勢力を背景にした「お願い」の形をとっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several letters were sent from Hideyoshi trying to persuade Masamune to visit Kyoto for swearing allegiance, but Masamune ignored them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>政宗は父、伊達輝宗の時代から後北条氏と同盟関係にあったため、秀吉と戦うべきか小田原に参陣すべきか、直前まで迷っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune had kept the alliance with GOHOJO clan built by his father, Terumune DATE, so he wondered if he should fight against Hideyoshi or join the Odawara Attack until just before the attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune had kept the alliance with Gohojo clan formed by his father, Terumune DATE, thus he was irresolute until the last moment whether he should fight against Hideyoshi, or join the Odawara Attack (the war led by Hideyoshi Toyotomi and his allies against Hojo clan).</e>
<cmt>1. 「同盟を結ぶ」で「built」を用いていますが、「form」に変更しました。2. 「so」による文の接続を避けました。3. 「迷う」を「wonder」としていますが口語的です。「was irresolute」としました。4. 「小田原に参陣」の意味が直訳だけですとわからないと思いますので、括弧により説明を追加しました。5. 「直前まで」は訳においてかなり意訳されていますので、原文に即したものとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune had kept the alliance with Gohojo clan formed by his father, Terumune DATE, thus he was irresolute until the last moment whether he should fight against Hideyoshi, or join the Odawara Attack (the war led by Hideyoshi Toyotomi and his allies against Hojo clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし、1590年、秀吉の兵動員数を考慮した政宗は秀吉に服属し、秀吉は政宗の本領を安堵した（ただし、会津領攻略は秀吉の令に反した行為であるとされ、会津領などは没収され、72万石になった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1590, Masamune showed deference to Hideyoshi in consideration of the size of Hideyoshi&apos;s troop, and Hideyoshi promised to secure Masamune&apos;s territory (but later, since the Invasion of Aizu was considered as rebellion against Hideyoshi, Masamune was deprived of Aizu, and Masamune&apos;s territorial land value became 720,000 koku [a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1590, Masamune finally yielded to Hideyoshi considering the number of soldiers making up the troops of Hideyoshi; Hideyoshi acknowledged to secure the fief of Masamune (however, the territory in Aizu region was forfeited, since the invasion of Aizu region was considered as a rebellious act against the order of Hideyoshi; Masamune&apos;s territorial land value became 720,000 koku [a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter]).</e>
<cmt>1. 「服属し」は「show deference to」だと通常「敬意を表する」の意味になります。Yeild toとしました。2. 「本領」はその意味を持つ単語に変更しました。3. 「没収」もより適切な「forfeit」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1590, Masamune finally yielded to Hideyoshi considering the number of soldiers making up the troops of Hideyoshi; Hideyoshi acknowledged to secure the fief of Masamune (however, the territory in Aizu region was forfeited, since the invasion of Aizu region was considered as a rebellious act against the order of Hideyoshi; Masamune&apos;s territorial land value became 720,000 koku [a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>記録ではこのとき小田原攻めに遅参したという理由で秀吉が政宗を事実上監禁して脅したが、政宗は詰問に来た前田利家らに千利休の茶の指導を受けたいと申し出、秀吉らを感嘆させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to historical records, Hideyoshi virtually placed Masamune under restraint and threatened him for the reason that Masamune was late for the Odawara Attack, but Masamune asked Toshiie MAEDA, who interrogated Masamune, for instruction of SEN no Rikyu&apos;s tea ceremony, and Masamune&apos;s performance impressed Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to historical records, Hideyoshi threatened Masamune by virtually placing him under restraint for his tardiness at the Odawara Attack; however, upon the demand of explanation from Toshiie MAEDA who came to interrogate him, Masamune unexpectedly responded to ask for the instruction session of tea ceremony from SEN no Rikyu; Hideyoshi marveled at his tactful behavior.</e>
<cmt>1. 非常に堅い訳であると同時に、読んで意味を取るのが非常に難しいと思います。また、意訳の問題があります。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to historical records, Hideyoshi threatened Masamune by virtually placing him under restraint for his tardiness at the Odawara Attack; however, upon the demand of explanation from Toshiie MAEDA who came to interrogate him, Masamune unexpectedly responded to ask for the instruction session of tea ceremony from SEN no Rikyu; Hideyoshi marveled at his tactful behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この行為は秀吉の派手好みの性格を知っての行いと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that Masamune intentionally acted like this because he knew that Hideyoshi was fond of this kind of stunt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Masamune intentionally acted in this manner because he knew the preference of Hideyoshi who was fond of flamboyant styles and behaviors.</e>
<cmt>1. 口語的な文章で緩いです。「like」を「〜のように」の形容詞の意味で用いるのは、文章では避けられるのが通常です。同様に、「this kind of」も避けられます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Masamune intentionally acted in this manner because he knew the preference of Hideyoshi who was fond of flamboyant styles and behaviors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>政宗が秀吉に服属したため、政宗と同盟を結んでいた北条氏政・北条氏直親子は秀吉に降伏し、政宗の居城、会津・黒川城へ入城した秀吉は奥州仕置を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Masamune surrendered to Hideyoshi, Ujimasa HOJO and his son, Ujinao HOJO, who had allied with Masamune, also gave in to Hideyoshi, and then Hideyoshi was based in Masamune&apos;s Kurokawa-jo (Aizu-jo) Castle and conducted Oshu Shioki (punishment to the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Masamune swore allegiance to Hideyoshi, the ally of Masamune, Ujimasa HOJO and his son Ujinao HOJO also surrendered to Hideyoshi; then Hideyoshi entered Masamune&apos;s Kurokawa-jo Castle in Aizu region, and conducted Oshu Shioki (punishment to the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power).</e>
<cmt>1. 「Since」の用法がここでは適切ではないと考え「After」に修正しました。2. 「服属」を「降伏」ではなく恭順を示すの「swore allegiance to」にしました。北条の場合は実際に戦に関わる形での帰属ですので、降伏とみなしました。ただし、「give in to」の形はわかりやすくするため「surrender」と一般的にしました。3. 「入城した」が「was based in」に意訳されています。原文にならったものとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Masamune swore allegiance to Hideyoshi, the ally of Masamune, Ujimasa HOJO and his son Ujinao HOJO also surrendered to Hideyoshi; then Hideyoshi entered Masamune&apos;s Kurokawa-jo Castle in Aizu region, and conducted Oshu Shioki (punishment to the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>ここに秀吉の「日本統一」が達成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Hideyoshi finally attained &quot;unification of Japan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the completion of this conduct, Hideyoshi finally achieved the &quot;unification of Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「ここに」を「At this time」としていますが、「奥州仕置」が終了した時点でという説明が原文にないため、「この時点で」という説明ができません。よって、「ここに」の内容を再記述しました。2. 定冠詞の欠如など修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the completion of this conduct, Hideyoshi finally achieved the &quot;unification of Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>参陣前に母親に毒殺されそうになり、母親を成敗する代わりに弟の伊達政道を斬殺したという説が通説となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was commonly believed that before joining the war, Masamune was about to be poisoned to death by his mother, and in return for it, Masamune killed his younger brother instead of his mother.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a commonly-held story that his mother had attempted to poison Masamune before he left to join the troops of Hideyoshi, and Masamune put his younger brother to the sword instead of executing his mother for punishment.</e>
<cmt>1. 「通説」になっているのは現在ですので、現在形に修正しました。また、フレーズもより一般的なものとしました。2. 原文では受動形になっていますが、受動形だと利用できるフレーズが限定され、訳者の訳のように直訳的になってしまいます。ここでは主語を倒置して、母親が毒殺しようとしたという肯定形としてより一般的なフレーズになるようにしました。3. 「斬殺」が訳文に欠けています。追加しました。4. 「参陣前」の訳ですが、訳にある「戦いに参加する」という意味以上に、ここでは「北条に敵対する秀吉の軍に参陣する」の意味を込めなくては母親が政宗を毒殺しようとした意味を想定できません。（原文が説明不足でこれでも読者が気付くかどうか微妙ですが）5. 説明が原文にないのですが、母親は政宗ではなく弟を溺愛しており、政宗に冷たかったという背景があったように思います。本来はこの説明がないとシーンをイメージできないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a commonly-held story that his mother had attempted to poison Masamune before he left to join the troops of Hideyoshi, and Masamune put his younger brother to the sword instead of executing his mother for punishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>しかし、毒殺創作説も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But some historians insisted that this story was just fiction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is also a theory that this story of poisoning Masamune is a fiction.</e>
<cmt>1. 「But」による書き出しを修正しました。2. この訳は意訳しすぎと思われます。訂正しました。3. 現在言われている説や考証に対し過去形を用いているケースが多いです。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is also a theory that this story of poisoning Masamune is a fiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>母・義姫（保春院）はその後も伊達家にとどまったが、四年後に実家の兄・最上義光のいる山形城へ突如出奔した（詳細は義姫参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the attempted murder, Masamune&apos;s mother Yoshihime (Hoshunin) still stayed in the DATE family, but 4 years later, she suddenly fled to the Yamagata-jo Castle of her brother, Yoshiaki MOGAMI (please refer to &quot;Yoshihime&quot; page for further information).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Masamune&apos;s mother Yoshihime (Hoshunin) remained at the Date family even after this incident, she suddenly fled to the Yamagata-jo Castle after 4 years of the incident, where her elder brother, Yoshiaki MOGAMI resided (please refer to &quot;Yoshihime&quot; page for further information).</e>
<cmt>1. 「兄」の記述が抜けていましたので追加しました。「実家の」は「兄」で代用できていると考え加えませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Masamune&apos;s mother Yoshihime (Hoshunin) remained at the Date family even after this incident, she suddenly fled to the Yamagata-jo Castle after 4 years of the incident, where her elder brother, Yoshiaki MOGAMI resided (please refer to &quot;Yoshihime&quot; page for further information).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>翌天正19年（1591年）には蒲生氏郷とともに葛西大崎一揆を平定するが、政宗自身が葛西大崎一揆を扇動していた嫌疑をかけられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1591, Masamune worked together with Ujisato GAMO to suppress the KASAI-OSAKI Ikki (the revolt of the former retainers of the KASAI clan and the OSAKI clan), but later Masamune was suspected of having abetted the KASAI-OSAKI Ikki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1591, Masamune subjugated the Kasai-Osaki Ikki (the revolt of the former retainers of the Kasai clan and the Osaki clan) with Ujisato GAMO, but Masamune himself was suspected of provoking the Kasai-Osaki Ikki.</e>
<cmt>1. 「平定」をsupressと訳していますが、適切な語ではないと思います。一般的な語に修正しました。2. 大文字の用法を修正しました。3. 「扇動」を適切な「provoking」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1591, Masamune subjugated the Kasai-Osaki Ikki (the revolt of the former retainers of the Kasai clan and the Osaki clan) with Ujisato GAMO, but Masamune himself was suspected of provoking the Kasai-Osaki Ikki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>これは氏郷が「政宗が書いた」とされる一揆勢宛の書状を入手した事に端を発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This suspicion was raised because Ujisato obtained a letter believed to be &quot;written by Masamune&quot; and sent to.KASAI clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This suspicion originated from a letter obtained by Ujisato, which was supposed to be &quot;written by Masamune&quot; to the ikki group.</e>
<cmt>1. 「一揆勢宛」の訳が、「葛西氏」宛と訳されていますが、はっきり説明されていない以上ここでは一応原文にあわせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This suspicion originated from a letter obtained by Ujisato, which was supposed to be &quot;written by Masamune&quot; to the ikki group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また、京都では政宗から京都に人質として差出した夫人は偽者であるとか、一揆勢が立て篭もる城には政宗の幟（のぼり）や旗が立てられているなどの噂が立ち、秀吉の耳にも届いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, it was rumored that Masamune sent an imposter of his wife to Kyoto as a hostage, and that Masamune&apos;s flags were placed at the castle of the rebels, and Hideyoshi heard those rumors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, various rumors were spread that the wife of Masamune sent to Kyoto as a hostage was the double of the real one, or the banners and flags of Masamune were put up at the castle where the ikki group was taking up a position; those rumors had reached the ears of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>1. 語順が適切ではないと思います。訳のニュアンスがかわっていきますので修正しました。2. 「imposter」は名称詐称や詐欺などに用いられます。「the double of」としました。3. 「一揆勢が」がrebelsとなり意味があいまいになってしまうので、意訳せず原文にあわせました。4. 「幟や旗」とあるところ、「flag」としか訳されていません。bannerを追加しました。5. 「立て篭る」の訳がありませんでしたので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, various rumors were spread that the wife of Masamune sent to Kyoto as a hostage was the double of the real one, or the banners and flags of Masamune were put up at the castle where the ikki group was taking up a position; those rumors had reached the ears of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>そこで政宗は上洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Masamune had to go to the capital (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Masamune headed to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>1. 訳では、「そこで、政宗は上洛しなければならなかった」の意味になっており、自発的に弁明するために行ったかもしれないにもかかわらず意味が限定されてしまっています。原文に合わせ、曖昧なままにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Masamune headed to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>一揆扇動の書状は偽物である旨秀吉に弁明し許されるが、米沢城から玉造郡岩手沢城に58万石に減らされての転封となり、城名を岩出山城に変えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune insisted to Hideyoshi that the letter of abetting the revolt was fake, and succeeded in dispelling Hidesyoshi&apos;s doubt, but still, his territory was reduced to 580,000 koku and he was transferred from the Yoneyama-jo Castle to the Iwate-jo Castle in Tamatsukuri District which was changed its name to the Iwadeyama-Jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune explained to Hideyoshi that the letter of instigating the ikki revolt was a forgery, then he was forgiven; however, he was order to transfer from the Yoneyama-jo Castle to the Iwate-jo Castle in Tamatsukuri District after the decision to reduce his territory to 580,000 koku; the name of the castle was changed to the Iwadeyama-Jo Castle since then.</e>
<cmt>1. 「弁明し許される」の原文が「主張して疑いを晴らすのに成功した」に変わっています。修正しました。2. 訳文では「領地が減らされ、城を移った」となっていますが、原文では「城を転封となったために石高が減った（石高を減らすための転封）」の意味で、意味が異なります。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune explained to Hideyoshi that the letter of instigating the ikki revolt was a forgery, then he was forgiven; however, he was order to transfer from the Yoneyama-jo Castle to the Iwate-jo Castle in Tamatsukuri District after the decision to reduce his territory to 580,000 koku; the name of the castle was changed to the Iwadeyama-Jo Castle since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="71">
<j>文禄2年（1593年）秀吉の朝鮮出兵に従軍して朝鮮半島へ渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1593, Masamune went to Korean Peninsula to serve Hideyoshi for the Korean Invasions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1593, Masamune participated in the troops of Hideyoshi organized for the Invasion of Korea, and went to the front in Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文に則していない訳です。意味があいまいすぎて伝わらないと判断しほぼ全体を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1593, Masamune participated in the troops of Hideyoshi organized for the Invasion of Korea, and went to the front in Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また、普請事業なども行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also engaged in construction works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also engaged in construction projects.</e>
<cmt>1. 「works」より大きな意味のある「projects」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also engaged in construction projects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>朝鮮出兵時に政宗が伊達家の部隊にあつらえさせた戦装束は非常に絢爛豪華なもので、上洛の道中において盛んに巷間の噂となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the Korean Invasion, Masamune prepared so gorgeous armors for his soldiers, and they got public attention on the way to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The armored costumes, which Masamune prepared for the troops of the Date clan were extremely gorgeous and splendid that their costume gave people a lot to talk about on the way to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>1. 「Korean Invasion」を対訳に合わせ修正しました。2. 「so gorgeous armors」が会話的、また文法的に問題があるため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The armored costumes, which Masamune prepared for the troops of the Date clan were extremely gorgeous and splendid that their costume gave people a lot to talk about on the way to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>三千人もしくは千五百人の軍勢であったとの記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a record, Masamune&apos;s troop consisted of 3,000 or 1,500 soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some records that the troops consisted of 3,000 soldiers, or rather 1,500 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>1. 3000人か1500人か特定できていないということは、記録が複数であったと考えられます。ここでは「〜の記録がある」と原文にあわせた方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some records that the troops consisted of 3,000 soldiers, or rather 1,500 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>他の軍勢が通過する際、静かに見守っていた京都の住民も伊達勢の軍装の見事さに歓声を上げたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Residents in Kyoto kept quiet when other troops passed through, but they cheered when they saw Masamune&apos;s gorgeous troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the residents of Kyoto were quietly observing the passing troops, they cheered for the splendidness of the military uniforms of the Date troops.</e>
<cmt>1. 「静かに見守る」が「静かにしている」になってしまっています。追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the residents of Kyoto were quietly observing the passing troops, they cheered for the splendidness of the military uniforms of the Date troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>これ以来派手な装いを好み着こなす人を指して「伊達者（だてもの）」と呼ぶようになった、と伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, people, who were fond of showy clothes, began to be called &quot;Date mono&quot; (a person like DATE).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this event, people began to call &quot;Date mono&quot; (a person as if from the Date troops) for someone who preferred flamboyant style in cloth and wore it skillfully.</e>
<cmt>1. 「一般人が派手好きを伊達ものと呼ぶようになった」の原文が、「派手ものを好む人が伊達ものと呼ばれるようになった」となっており、単なる受動／能動の変換による主語の倒置ではなく、対象そのものが変わってしまっていますので問題です。訂正しました。2. その他言い回しの修正です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this event, people began to call &quot;Date mono&quot; (a person as if from the Date troops) for someone who preferred flamboyant style in cloth and wore it skillfully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>これは、派手好みの秀吉が気に入るような戦装束を自分の部隊に着させることで本陣に近い配置を狙い、損害を受けやすい最前線への配置を避けるよう計算したものと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Masamune appealed to Hideyoshi who liked outstanding stuff with his gorgeous troop so that they could be placed close to the center base, not in the front line, to avoid getting a large damage during the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in order to avoid being sent to the foremost front where the possibility of getting damages is higher, Masamune calculated and sought for the position of his troops to be near the headquarter, by applying his troops with the military uniforms, which would please Hideyoshi with showy character.</e>
<cmt>1. 文節の並び順により意味が通じなくなっています。ほぼ全体書き直しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in order to avoid being sent to the foremost front where the possibility of getting damages is higher, Masamune calculated and sought for the position of his troops to be near the headquarter, by applying his troops with the military uniforms, which would please Hideyoshi with showy character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="78">
<j>豊臣政権においては、秀吉の天下統一事業の際早くから秀吉に服属して五大老に選ばれた大名たちとはことなり、政宗は北条氏と同盟して秀吉と対立したため、五大老には選ばれなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under Hideyoshi&apos;s regime, feudal lords who had served from the beginning of Hideyoshi&apos;s unification of Japan could be appointed Council of Five Elders, but Masamune was not appointed because at first he had allied with HOJO clan and conflicted with Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the ruling of Hideyoshi, Masamune was not chosen as the member of the Council of Five Elders because he had allied with Hojo clan and opposed against Hideyoshi, unlike those feudal lords who had served under Hideyoshi from the early stage of the unification process of Japan promoted by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>1. 前置詞などが欠けており、文節がきちんと接続されていません。2. 「対立」と「争う(conflict)」は立場や主体など異なりますので、「opose against」を用いました。3. 「早くから」を「beginning」としていたところを「early stage」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the ruling of Hideyoshi, Masamune was not chosen as the member of the Council of Five Elders because he had allied with Hojo clan and opposed against Hideyoshi, unlike those feudal lords who had served under Hideyoshi from the early stage of the unification process of Japan promoted by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="79">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）、秀吉から謀反の疑いをかけられた関白豊臣秀次が切腹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1595, a chancellor, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI killed himself by disembowelment on suspicion of treason against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1595, Kanpaku (a chancellor) Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI committed seppuku (ritual suicide performed by samurai) after he was suspected of treason against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>1. 「切腹」を「disembowelment」としていますが、まず使われず別の意味に取られると思います。「seppuku」とし括弧で説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1595, Kanpaku (a chancellor) Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI committed seppuku (ritual suicide performed by samurai) after he was suspected of treason against Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>秀次と親しかった政宗の周辺は緊迫した状況となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People associated with Masamune were tensed because Masamune had a close relationship with Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relatives and fellows of Masamune were put under strain because Masamune had a close relationship with Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>1. 「政宗の周辺」は意訳しました。「associated with Masamune」ですと「政宗と関係やつきあいのあった人」という意味になります。あまり親族などには使われませんので、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relatives and fellows of Masamune were put under strain because Masamune had a close relationship with Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>この時母方の従姉妹に当たる最上義光の娘・駒姫は、秀次の側室になる為に上京したばかりであったが、秀次の妻子らと共に処刑されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Komahime, who was a daughter of Yoshiaki MOGAMI and Masamune&apos;s maternal cousin, was killed together with Hidetsugu&apos;s other wives and children even though she had just arrived in Kyoto to marry Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that time, Komahime, the daughter of Yoshiaki MOGAMI and maternal cousin of Masamune, was executed together with the other wives and children of Hidetsugu just after she arrived in Kyoto to become the concubine of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>1. 処刑は「killed」では表現されません。訂正しました。2. 「the daughter of〜」といったように、書式を他の同様例でも統一しました。3. 「側室」が無視されて訳されています。追加修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that time, Komahime, the daughter of Yoshiaki MOGAMI and maternal cousin of Masamune, was executed together with the other wives and children of Hidetsugu just after she arrived in Kyoto to become the concubine of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>政宗も秀吉から謀反への関与を疑われるも、最終的には無関係であるとされ連座の難を逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune was also suspected of being implicated in treason, but eventually he could prove his innocence and avoid being punished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune was also suspected of taking part in treason, but eventually he was considered not related, escaping from the difficulty of being implicated.</e>
<cmt>1. 受動形が２回続けて現れ、つながっている形になっています。非常に読みづらいため修正しました。2. 「政宗が無関係を証明することに成功した」という訳になっています。これは「無関係であるとされ」とは異なる意味です。訂正しました。3. 「連座の難」は「punished」では訳しきれません。追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune was also suspected of taking part in treason, but eventually he was considered not related, escaping from the difficulty of being implicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="83">
<j>秀吉の死後、五大老・徳川家康と政宗は秀吉の遺言を破り、慶長4年（1599年）、政宗の長女・五郎八姫と家康の6男松平忠輝を婚約させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death, one of Council of Five Elders, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Masamune betrayed Hideyoshi&apos;s will and made Masamune&apos;s first daughter, Irohahime and Ieyasu&apos;s 6th son, Tadateru MATSUDAIRA marry in 1599.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Hideyoshi, one of the Council of Five Elders, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Masamune broke the last will and testament of Hideyoshi, by setting up the engagement between Irohahime, the first daughter of Masamune, and Tadateru MATSUDAIRA, the 6th son of Ieyasu in 1599.</e>
<cmt>1. 「遺言を破る」を「betrayed」とすると意訳となります。原文にならいました。遺言はこの場合正式でより契約制の高いものとして訳しています。2. 原文は「婚約させた」とありますが、「結婚した」と訳されています。意味が異なりますので訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Hideyoshi, one of the Council of Five Elders, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Masamune broke the last will and testament of Hideyoshi, by setting up the engagement between Irohahime, the first daughter of Masamune, and Tadateru MATSUDAIRA, the 6th son of Ieyasu in 1599.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原合戦と最上陣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Sekigahara and Battle with MOGAMI clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Sekigahara and the participation of war by Date troops for Mogami troops</e>
<cmt>1. 定冠詞の付加、および大文字の修正を行っています。2. なお、「Battle with Mogami clan」は原文と意味がまったく異なるものになります。政宗は最上氏を助ける戦いをしており、その際の陣という意味です。訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Sekigahara and the participation of war by Date troops for Mogami troops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>豊臣秀吉死後の慶長5年（1600年）に家康が会津領主・上杉景勝に謀反容疑をかけ、上杉討伐を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, in 1600, Ieyasu charged a feudal lord of Aizu, Kagekatsu UESUGI with treason, and attacked UESUGI clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Ieyasu launched a campaign against Uesugi clan in 1600 upon suspecting the proprietor of Aizu region Kagekatsu UESUGI of treason.</e>
<cmt>1. 語順とフレーズをより適切と思われるものにの修正しました。2. 不定冠詞や前置詞が不適切なものがあったため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Ieyasu launched a campaign against Uesugi clan in 1600 upon suspecting the proprietor of Aizu region Kagekatsu UESUGI of treason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>正宗は、討伐に従軍して、7月25日に上杉の支城で登坂式部勝乃が守る白石城を陥落させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune joined the attack and on July 25, seized UESUGI&apos;s subsidiary castle, the Shiraishi castle protected by 登坂式部勝乃.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　　登坂式部勝乃の読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune joined this campaign, and he captured a subsidiary castle of Uesugi clan Shiroishi-jo Castle defended by TOSAKA shikibu no Katsunori.</e>
<cmt>1. 「attack」は特定の戦いですので、「討伐」という総合的な戦争にはあいません。修正しました。2. 「登坂式部勝乃」は「とさか　しきぶ　の　かつのり」としました。白石城は「しらいし」ではなく「しろいし」です。(加えて城の記述が訳規定にのっとっていませんでした）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune joined this campaign, and he captured a subsidiary castle of Uesugi clan Shiroishi-jo Castle defended by TOSAKA shikibu no Katsunori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>家康の留守中に五奉行の石田三成らが家康に対して毛利輝元を総大将として挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Ieyasu went out to attack the Shiraishi-jo Castle, one of Five Commissioners, Mitsunari ISHIDA appointed Terumoto MORI as a supreme commander, and rose in arms.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Ieyasu was out on this campaign, one of the members of the Council of Five Elders, Mitsunari ISHIDA raised an army against Ieyasu with Terumoto MORI as a supreme commander.</e>
<cmt>1. 「家康が白石城を攻撃している」という記述はありませんので明らかな誤解による誤訳です。訂正しました。2. ここでの「五奉行」は、先述の「the Council of Five Elders」です。統一を図るため修正しました。3. 「家康に対し」が欠けており、三成挙兵の意味がまったく伝わらない文章になっています。追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Ieyasu was out on this campaign, one of the members of the Council of Five Elders, Mitsunari ISHIDA raised an army against Ieyasu with Terumoto MORI as a supreme commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>そのため、小山まで北上していた家康は西へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Ieyasu&apos;s troop, which moved toward the north and reached Koyama, had to change their route to the west.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon hearing this news, the troops of Ieyasu, which had been moving northward, changed their direction to the west at Oyama.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文の「そのため」は訳にある「therefore」では説明されません。「これを聞いて」などの意訳が必要と考え修正しました。2. 「小山」は「こやま」ではなく「おやま」です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon hearing this news, the troops of Ieyasu, which had been moving northward, changed their direction to the west at Oyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>この際、家康は政宗に、戦勝の暁には現在の所領58万石に加え、新たに49万石の領土を与えるという内容の書状（「百万石のお墨付き」仙台市博物館・蔵）を送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Ieyasu sent a letter which promised to give Masamune new territory of 490,000 koku value in addition to present Masamune&apos;s 580,000 koku if Masamune won the battle (&quot;Promise of 1 million koku&quot; stored at the Sendai City Museum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Ieyasu sent a letter to Masamune indicating the reward of a new, additional territory of 490,000 koku value on top of his existing 580,000 koku upon victory (&quot;Assurance of Hyakumangoku [1 million koku]&quot; owned by the Sendai City Museum).</e>
<cmt>1. 原文には、「〜の領土を与えるという内容の書状を送っている」とあるだけで、「約束する」とは書かれていないにもかかわらず意訳により付記されています。修正しました。2. 「現在の〜に加え」のフレーズを修正しました。3. 「所蔵」を適切なものに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Ieyasu sent a letter to Masamune indicating the reward of a new, additional territory of 490,000 koku value on top of his existing 580,000 koku upon victory (&quot;Assurance of Hyakumangoku [1 million koku]&quot; owned by the Sendai City Museum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>これは、家康が上杉景勝を会津に釘付けにしておくため、政宗の東軍参加が是非とも必要であったことから、100万石のお墨付きを与え、東軍参加を促したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Ieyasu made the Promise of 1 million koku because Masamune&apos;s troop force was essential for his Eastern Army to block Kagekatsu UESUGI in Aizu Region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that Ieyasu gave this &quot;Assurance of Hyakumangoku&quot; to urge the participation of Masamune to his Eastern Army, because his participation to the Eastern Army was critical in order to hold Kagekatsu UESUGI to Aizu region.</e>
<cmt>1. 上述にならい「お墨付き」部分を修正しました。2. 「東軍参加を促した」の訳が見当たりません。追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Ieyasu gave this &quot;Assurance of Hyakumangoku&quot; (Hyakumangoku meaning 1,000,000 koku of land) to urge the participation of Masamune to his Eastern Army, because his participation to the Eastern Army was critical in order to hold Kagekatsu UESUGI to Aizu region.</e>
<cmt>Hyakumankoku の説明を記載しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="90">
<j>同年9月、関ヶ原の戦いになると、家康ら東軍に属した政宗は、上杉氏の将直江兼続率いる軍が最上氏居城山形城を攻撃すると、留守政景を名代として最上に援軍を派遣した（長谷堂城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September in the same year, Masamune joined Ieyasu&apos;s Eastern Army for the Sekigahara War, and when UESUGI&apos;s troop led by Kanetsugu NAOE attacked the Yamagata-jo Castle of MOGAMI clan, Masamune sent a reinforcement led by his deputy, Masakage RUSU to Mogami (Battle of Hasedo-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Sekigahara War broke out in September of the same year, Masamune joined the Eastern Army led by Ieyasu; when the troops of Uesugi clan led by Kanetsugu NAOE attacked the Yamagata-jo Castle where Mogami family resides, Masamune sent reinforcements led by his deputy, Masakage RUSU for Mogami clan (the Battle of Hasedo-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>1. 訳文だと「9月に政宗は関ヶ原の戦いに向けた家康の東軍に参加した」となります。この場合、「9月に関ヶ原の戦いが起こった」という意味が訳文でははっきりと説明されなくなります。訳文では「関ヶ原の戦いに向けた家康の東軍」とされており関ヶ原の戦いについては言及されていますが、9月に起こった事柄は、「政宗の東軍への参加」として示されており、関ヶ原の戦いの勃発ではありません。2. このケースでは原文も文法的におかしいのですが、一応時系列を確認した上で、左記のように修正しました。3. 「最上氏の居城」が欠けており、「最上氏の最も重要な城」という意味がこれにより欠落してしまうため追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Sekigahara War broke out in September of the same year, Masamune joined the Eastern Army led by Ieyasu; when the troops of Uesugi clan led by Kanetsugu NAOE attacked the Yamagata-jo Castle where Mogami family resides, Masamune sent reinforcements led by his deputy, Masakage RUSU for Mogami clan (the Battle of Hasedo-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="91">
<j>9月25日には茂庭綱元に命じて、上杉領の湯原城を攻略させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 25, Masamune ordered Tsunamoto MONIWA to attack the Yuhara-jo Castle in UESUGI&apos;s domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 25, Masamune ordered Tsunamoto MONIWA to capture the Yuhara-jo Castle located in the domain of Uesugi.</e>
<cmt>1. 「城を攻略する」に則した「capture」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 25, Masamune ordered Tsunamoto MONIWA to capture the Yuhara-jo Castle located in the domain of Uesugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="92">
<j>政宗は長谷堂城の戦い後、直江兼続が米沢に帰ったのを見て取ると、仙道方面への侵略を開始、10月6日宮代で本庄繁長の上杉軍を破った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Battle of Hasedo-jo Castle, as soon as Kanetsugu NAOE went back to Yonezawa, Masamune started invasion of the Sendo area and beat the UESUGI&apos;s troop led by Sigenaga HONJO at Miyashiro on October 6.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once Masamune learned that Kanetsugu NAOE had gone back to Yonezawa after the Battle of Hasedo-jo Castle, he launched a campaign to the Sendo area, and on October 6, Masamune defeated the troops of Uesugi led by Sigenaga HONJO at Miyashiro.</e>
<cmt>1. 文節同士の接続に注意が向けられていません。つながりがスムーズになるよう語順など変更しています。2. その他、「侵略を開始」や「〜軍を破った」などについて変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once Masamune learned that Kanetsugu NAOE had gone back to Yonezawa after the Battle of Hasedo-jo Castle, he launched a campaign to the Sendo area, and on October 6, Masamune defeated the troops of Uesugi led by Sigenaga HONJO at Miyashiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>伊達軍は更に福島城を囲んだが、城の防御は堅く、翌日には撤退した（宮代表合戦、上杉家俗称松川の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The DATE troop also besieged the Fukushima-jo Castle, but they were hampered by the castle&apos;s stiff defense and had to surrender on the following day (the Battle of Miyashiroomote, UESUGI clan called this battle the Battle of Matsugaoka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the troops of Date clan besieged the Fukushima-jo Castle, while the troops withdrew on the following day of the siege because of the strong defense of the castle (the Battle of Miyashiroomote, while Uesugi clan called this battle as the Battle of Matsugaoka).</e>
<cmt>1. 「更に」の意味で用いられたと見られるalsoを変更しました。2. 「撤退」が「降伏」と訳されています。誤訳ですので「withdraw」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the troops of Date clan besieged the Fukushima-jo Castle, while the troops withdrew on the following day of the siege because of the strong defense of the castle (the Battle of Miyashiroomote, while Uesugi clan called this battle as the Battle of Matsugaoka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="94">
<j>戦後、政宗が密かに白石宗直に支援させて、南部氏領国で和賀忠親に一揆を煽動させていた策略が発覚した（一揆軍は翌慶長6年4月に敗北）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the battle, it was exposed that Masamune secretly ordered Munenao SHROISHI to support Tadachika WADA, and urged Tadachika to stage an uprising in the territory of NANBU clan (The uprising troop was defeated in April, 1601).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battle of Sekigahara, a scheme of Masamune was exposed that he secretly ordered Munenao SHROISHI to support Tadachika WAGA for instigating ikki (uprising of peasant) in the territory of Nanbu clan (The uprising troops were defeated in April, 1601).</e>
<cmt>1. この項目では関ヶ原の戦いについて説明されていますので、「After the battle」としてしまうと宮代における戦いなのか、関ヶ原の戦いなのかがわからなくなってしまいます。関ヶ原の戦い後と明記しました。2. 和賀が「わが」のところ、「わだ」と訳されています。次の項目では正しく「わが」となっていますので、チェックミスと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, a scheme of Masamune was exposed that he secretly ordered Munenao SHROISHI to support Tadachika WAGA for instigating ikki (uprising of peasant) in the territory of Nanbu clan (The uprising troops were defeated in April, 1601).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>この「和賀一件」を重く見た家康は、事件追及の構えを見せ、49万石加増、すなわち計100万石の約束手形を反故にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu took this &quot;WAGA incident&quot; seriously and investigated Masamune, and then he broke the promise of giving Masamune an additional territory of 490,000koku, in a word, allowing Masamune to rule territories of 1,000,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu took this &quot;Waga incident&quot; seriously, and he declared a thorough investigation regarding the incident; he annulled the promissory note of adding 490,000 koku, that is, to allow Masamune for acquiring hyakumangoku (1 million koku).</e>
<cmt>1. 「事件追及の構えを見せ」の意味するところがよくわからないのですが（通常、構えを見せるは「〜しようとする」状態で実際には「していない」ことを意味します）次の項目とあわせて考えると、やはり「追求のポーズをとったが、追求はしなかった」の意味でしょうか。49万石に及ぶ加増はなかったものの、2万石は加増しており、咎を受けたのか受けなかったのかが判断できません。「declare」を用い、宣言したとだけ訳すことで原文と同様その後の動向については言及しない訳としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu took this &quot;Waga incident&quot; seriously, and he declared a thorough investigation regarding the incident; he annulled the promissory note of adding 490,000 koku, that is, to allow Masamune for acquiring hyakumangoku (1 million koku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>結果的に政宗への恩賞は、仙台開府の許可と陸奥国刈田郡（白石）合わせて2万石の加増のみにとどまり、領地は60万石となった（後に近江国と常陸国に小領土の飛び地2万石の加増で62万石となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, as reward grants, Masamune could get only permission of opening of Sendai Domain and seize Katta District (Shiraishi) in Mutsu Province valued 20,000 koku, and his territorial land value became total 600,000 koku (later, he was additionally given Omi Province, Hitachi Province and small outlands, and then his territorial land value became total 620,000 koku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, the rewards granted to Masamune were limited to the permission of establishing Sendai Domain, along with the territorial gain of 20,000 koku by adding Katta District (Shiroishi) in Mutsu Province; his territorial land value became 600,000 koku in total (later, he acquired additional small and scattered territories in Omi Province and Hitachi Province, making his territorial land value to 620,000 koku in total).</e>
<cmt>1. 細かい文節に途切れないよう修正しています。また原文の単語の細かい意味消失や意訳による誤訳がありましたので変更しました。（ex. 「飛び地」を「僻地」としていますが、意味が全く異なります）2. ここでも「しろいし」が「しらいし」になっていましたので訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, the rewards granted to Masamune were limited to the permission of establishing Sendai Domain, along with the territorial gain of 20,000 koku by adding Katta District (Shiroishi) in Mutsu Province; his territorial land value became 600,000 koku in total (later, he acquired additional small and scattered territories in Omi Province and Hitachi Province, making his territorial land value to 620,000 koku in total).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>仙台開府と慶長遣欧使節</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opening of Sendai Domain and Keicho Mission to Europe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opening of Sendai Domain and Keicho Mission to Europe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opening of Sendai Domain and Keicho Mission to Europe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>慶長6年（1601年）には仙台城、仙台城下町の建設をはじめ、居城を移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1601, Masamune started construction of the Sendai-jo Castle and its castle town, and then he moved to the Sendai-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1601, Masamune started the construction of the Sendai-jo Castle and its castle town; later he moved to the Sendai-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>1. 定冠詞を追加しました。2. 「居城を移す」は後ほどと考えられるため、いったん文を区切り、「later」を追加しました。（thenでは時間経過を示せません）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1601, Masamune started the construction of the Sendai-jo Castle and its castle town; later he moved to the Sendai-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>ここに、伊達政宗を藩祖とする仙台藩が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Sendai Domain was born and Masamune became the original forefather of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune as the founder, Sendai Domain was established there in Sendai.</e>
<cmt>1. 「ここに」の訳が直訳です。2. 「誕生した」は「established」としました。3. 「藩祖」は「forefather」というここではあまりそぐわない慣用的なものではなく単純に「founder」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune as the founder, Sendai Domain was established there in Sendai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>仙台藩・62万石 (単位)は加賀・前田氏、薩摩・島津氏に次ぐ全国第3位であるが、それは表高であり、仙台藩の実高は優に100万石を越えていたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The territorial land value of Sendai Domain, 620,000 koku was the third largest in Japan after Kaga Domain of MAEDA clan and Satsuma Domain of SHIMAZU clan, but that value was just a face value assessed by the feudal government and its actual land value of Sendai Domain was thought to be over 1,000,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The territorial land value of Sendai Domain was the third highest in Japan for its 620,000 koku value, next to Kaga Domain of Maeda clan and Satsuma Domain of Shimazu clan; however, this figure was a face value, and the actual land value of Sendai Domain was estimated to exceed well over 1,000,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>1. 「land value」と記述するからには「largest」では形容できず、「highest」が正しいものになります。2. 「優に」が欠けていましたので追加しています。その前後、「超えていたと言われる」は「estimate」「exceed well over」を用いています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The territorial land value of Sendai Domain was the third highest in Japan for its 620,000 koku value, next to Kaga Domain of Maeda clan and Satsuma Domain of Shimazu clan; however, this figure was a face value, and the actual land value of Sendai Domain was estimated to exceed well over 1,000,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="100">
<j>仙台城は山城で天然の地形を利用した防御であるものの、仙台城下の城下町は全面的な開発であるため、のべ百万人を動員した大工事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sendai-jo Castle was a castle built on a mountain to take advantage of mountain&apos;s natural topography, but the construction of the Sendai castle town was a full-scale development which required a total of 1,000,000 workers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sendai-jo Castle was a mountain castle with a defense system utilizing the natural topography of the mountain, while the construction of the castle town at the foot of the Sendai-jo Castle became a full-scale construction mobilizing 1 million people in total for the comprehensive development throughout the area.</e>
<cmt>1. 山城の訳を原文にあわせました。（山城は平城とは違うものであり、山に立てられたから山城になるわけではありません。山にあっても一般的な平城は存在します）2. 「動員した」が訳出されていません。通常こうした開発は単なる作業者だけでなく、様々なサポート（サービスなど含め）の総動員数を指します。よって「workers」は「people」に変更しています。3. 「大工事となった」が訳出されていません。「全面的な開発」に集約されてしまったようです。ここでは、「山の地形を利用できた城建設」とは異なり、「全面的な開発」は地域一帯をゼロから開発することになったの意味で訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sendai-jo Castle was a mountain castle with a defense system utilizing the natural topography of the mountain, while the construction of the castle town at the foot of the Sendai-jo Castle became a full-scale construction mobilizing 1 million people in total for the comprehensive development throughout the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>藩内の統治には48ヶ所の館を置き家臣を配置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For administration of the domain, Masamune newly established 48 offices and allocated his subjects to each office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the administration of the domain, Masamune established 48 offices and allocated his vassals to each office.</e>
<cmt>1. 「For administration of〜」は文法的に誤りです。前置詞の後にはこの場合「the administration」とするか、「administrating the domain」となるはずです。ここでは不定冠詞を加えたのみにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the administration of the domain, Masamune established 48 offices and allocated his vassals to each office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="102">
<j>伊達政宗は仙台藩とスペインとの通商（太平洋貿易）を企図し、1613年（慶長18年）、仙台領内において、スペイン帝国国王フェリペ3世 (スペイン王)の使節セバスティアン・ビスカイノの協力によってガレオン船・サン・フアン・バウティスタ号を建造した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune planned to start trade between Sendai Domain and Spain (the Pacific Trade), and in 1613 in Sendai Domain, Masamune constructed a galleon ship, San Juan Bautista by working with Sebastián Vizcaíno who was an envoy of the King of Spain, Felipe III.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune came up with a project plan to open trade between Sendai Domain and Spain (a trading oversea via Pacific Ocean); in 1613, Masamune built a galleon ship within Sendai Domain with the cooperation of Sebastián Vizcaíno, the envoy of the King of Spain, Felipe III, which was then named as San Juan Bautista.</e>
<cmt>1. 細かいフレーズがぎこちないものが多いため修正しています。2. ここでの「太平洋貿易」は固有名ではないと思いますので、一般的な説明文に変更しています。船は通常「build」を用います。3. 定冠詞／不定冠詞の誤用を修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune came up with a project plan to open trade between Sendai Domain and Spain (a trading oversea via Pacific Ocean); in 1613, Masamune built a galleon ship within Sendai Domain with the cooperation of Sebastián Vizcaíno, the envoy of the King of Spain, Felipe III, which was then named as San Juan Bautista.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>政宗は家康の承認を得ると、ルイス・ソテロを外交使節に任命し、家臣・支倉常長ら一行180余人をヌエバ・エスパーニャ（メキシコ）、エスパーニャ、およびローマへ派遣した（慶長遣欧使節）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Masamune obtained Ieyasu&apos;s permission, he appointed Luis Sotelo as a diplomatic envoy and dispatched over 180 people including his retainer, Tsunenaga HASEKURA to Viceroyalty of New Spain (Mexico), Spain and Rome (Keicho Mission).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once Masamune obtained an approval of Ieyasu, he appointed Luis Sotelo as the ambassador of the delegation, and dispatched over 180 people including his retainer Tsunenaga HASEKURA to Viceroyalty of New Spain (Mexico), Spain and Rome (Keicho era mission to Europe).</e>
<cmt>1. 「許可」を意味する「permission」と、「承認」は微妙に違いがあります。ここではある計画をもってその特定の内容を認めるの意味がありますので、その場合に用いられる「approval」としました。2. 「使節」についてですが、日本に少人数もしくは一人代表としてきている先述のスペイン王使節と異なり、ここでは大人数の使節団が送られており、その場合は「mission」もしくはより一般的な「delegate」を用いた方が良いと思います。さらに、そのリーダーとしては「ambassador」がより適切かと思います。3. 慶長遣欧使節は定訳にあるものに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once Masamune obtained an approval of Ieyasu, he appointed Luis Sotelo as the ambassador of the delegation, and dispatched over 180 people including his retainer Tsunenaga HASEKURA to Viceroyalty of New Spain (Mexico), Spain and Rome (Keicho era mission to Europe).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="104">
<j>慶長19年（1614年）の大坂の役では、片倉重長が後藤基次らを討ち取り、真田信繁（幸村）の攻勢を受けて立つなど大きな功があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Siege of Osaka in 1614, Shigenaga KATAKURA defeated Mototsugu GOTO and defended against the attack of Nobushige (Yukimura) SANADA, and such Shigenaga&apos;s performance greatly contributed to victory of the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Siege of Osaka in 1614, Shigenaga KATAKURA felled Mototsugu GOTO, while he even withstood against the offensive movements of Nobushige (Yukimura) SANADA and greatly contributed to the victory.</e>
<cmt>1. 「defeat」をこのケースでより適切と思われる「fell」に変更しました。2. 「攻勢を受けて立つ」は「defended」ですと防御するの意味のみで、防ぎきったという意味がありません。「withstood against the offensive movements」に変更しました。3. 大きな功のフレーズが冗長でしたので簡略化しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Siege of Osaka in 1614, Shigenaga KATAKURA felled Mototsugu GOTO, while he even withstood against the offensive movements of Nobushige (Yukimura) SANADA and greatly contributed to the victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="105">
<j>世情が落ち着いてからは、もっぱら領国の開発に力を入れ、後に貞山堀と呼ばれる運河を整備した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the settlement of state of society, Masamune concentrated on development of Sendai Domain, and later, he constructed a canal called Teizanbori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the social conditions calmed and settled, Masamune mainly put of his effort on the development of his territory lands, and he developed Teizan-bori Canal since then.</e>
<cmt>1. 「世情が落ち着いてから」は定冠詞がないため現状不十分です。ここではより一般的なものに変更しています。2. 「もっぱら〜に力をいれ」とありますので、訳にある「集中した」とは多少意味が異なると感じました。修正しています。3. 領国は仙台藩だけではありませんので、原文どおり「領国」としました。4. 定冠詞問題を修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the social conditions calmed and settled, Masamune mainly put of his effort on the development of his territory lands, and he developed Teizan-bori Canal since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>北上川水系の流域を整理し開拓、現代まで続く穀倉地帯とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also developed watershed areas around the Kitakami-gawa River and its tributaries, and those areas became a leading grain-growing region which lasted until even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He developed and made adjustment to the Kitakami-gawa River basin system, turning those areas into a grain-growing district, which still remains until today.</e>
<cmt>1. この項は直前の項目を引き継いだ説明と思われます。よって、「also」により「〜に加え」の意味とすると誤訳になります。修正しました。2. 「北上川水系の流域」をより一般的なものに整理しました。3. 「leading」と訳された内容は原文にありません。削除しました4. 文章を整理して文節レベルにし、簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He developed and made adjustment to the Kitakami-gawa River basin system, turning those areas into a grain-growing district, which still remains until today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>この結果、仙台藩は表高62万石に対し、実高100万石を越える米の生産量を確保した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Sendai Domain realized rice production of 1,000,000 koku, even though its face value assessed by the feudal government was only 620,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result of this development, Sendai Domain achieved the actual yield of rice crop in the amount of 1,000,000 koku, while the reported face value based on the original territory condition was 620,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>1. 「この結果」を前項目を引き継いでいることを示すため再記述しています。2. 「実高」の説明が不足していますので追加しました。3. 「表高」も同様にしています。「assessed by〜」の部分については&quot;the feudal governmentの指し示すものが不明瞭（秀吉？江戸幕府？仙台藩？）で、実際のところ確かではありませんので、「当初の石高」という訳としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result of this development, Sendai Domain achieved the actual yield of rice crop in the amount of 1,000,000 koku, while the reported face value based on the original territory condition was 620,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>文化的には上方の文化を積極的に導入し、技師・大工らの招聘を行い、桃山文化に特徴的な荘厳華麗さに北国の特性が加わった様式を生み出し、国宝の大崎八幡宮、瑞巌寺、また塩竈神社、陸奥国分寺などの建造物を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it comes to culture, Masamune actively introduced the culture of Kyoto and Osaka, invited engineers and carpenters, created an original culture form by adding a unique northern culture to the gorgeous Momoyama culture, and built many outstanding architectures such as the present National Treasure, Osaki-Hachiman-gu Shrine, Zuigan-ji Temple, Shiogama-jinja Shrine and Mutsu-Kokubun-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of the cultural development, Masamune actively introduced the Kyoto and its vicinity cultures by inviting technical experts, artisans and carpenters, and created a style based on the solemn and splendid Momoyama style with the mixture of those qualities found in northern regions; Masamune left various buildings such as Osaki Hachiman-gu Shrine and Zuigan-ji Temple that are designated as the national treasures today, and Shiogama-jinja Shrine and Mutsu Kokubun-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>1. 「先述の技術的な発展に対して文化的な発展については」という意味と考え多少修正しています。（訳文は問題ないですが口語的ととらえました）2. 「様式を生みだし」は特定の様式として、文化という大きな枠組みではなく「style」としました。3. 「荘厳華麗」は「goegeous」ですと適切とは思われないため、「solemn and splendid」と2語による説明にしました。4. 「北国の特性」は意味が広義過ぎてあいまいな「northern culture」ではなく、「qualities found in northern region」としました。5. 「建造物を残した」で「architectures」としていますが、「architecture」は建築というコンセプトやセオリーに通常用いられ、そのため複数形にはなりませんので文法的に誤りです。ごく普通に「buildings」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of the cultural development, Masamune actively introduced the Kyoto and its vicinity cultures by inviting technical experts, artisans and carpenters, and created a style based on the solemn and splendid Momoyama style with the mixture of those qualities found in northern regions; Masamune left various buildings such as Osaki Hachiman-gu Shrine and Zuigan-ji Temple that are designated as the national treasures today, and Shiogama-jinja Shrine and Mutsu Kokubun-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>さらに近江在住の技師・川村孫兵衛を招き、北上川の河口に石巻港を設けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune invited an engineer, Magobe KAWAMURA who was living in Omi Province, and ordered him to construct the Port of Ishinomaki at the mouth of the Kitakami-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune invited Magobe KAWAMURA, a technical expert in Omi Province, and constructed the Port of Ishinomaki at the mouth of the Kitakami-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>1. マイナーな修正ですが、「招いた」というからには「ordered to construct」は適切ではありません。ここでは単純に削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune invited Magobe KAWAMURA, a technical expert in Omi Province, and constructed the Port of Ishinomaki at the mouth of the Kitakami-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>これにより北上川流域水運を通じ石巻から江戸へ東廻り航路で米を移出する体制が整う（江戸時代の多くの期間において、江戸で流通する米の半分は仙台藩石巻港からの廻米であった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Port of Ishinomaki contributed to development of rice transportation using the route of the Kitakami-gawa River from Ishinomaki to Edo (During the most of the Edo period, a half of total rice amount consumed in Edo was transported from the Port of Ishinomaki of Sendai Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Port of Ishinomaki enabled to provide the system of transporting the rice produce in the eastern bound shipping route, from the canals of Kitakami-gawa River basin to Edo via Ishinomaki (Most of the time throughout Edo period, half of the total rice produce distributed in Edo was the transported rice from the Port of Ishinomaki of Sendai Domain).</e>
<cmt>1. 「contributed to development」はdevelopmentの前に定冠詞をつけるか、動詞がこないと文法的に誤りです。いずれにせよこの部分は意訳のし過ぎで原文の意味が損なわれていますので訂正しました。2. 北上川流域水運の「水運」が訳出されていませんでした。先述の運河整備につながるため重要ですので、追加しました。「東廻り航路」が訳出されていませんが、これは北前航路に比較して重要という意味が暗に含まれますので、訳出しました。3. 「during the most of the Edo period」のフレーズは直訳で、適切ではありません。「Most of the time throughout Edo period」としました。4. 廻米の意味がきちんと訳出されていません。この項目で重要な意味がありますので修正しました。5. 原文で「流通」となっているところを、訳文では「消費」となっていて誤訳です。修正しました。6. 説明の括弧が文末で片方欠けています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Port of Ishinomaki enabled to provide the system of transporting the rice produce in the eastern bound shipping route, from the canals of Kitakami-gawa River basin to Edo via Ishinomaki (Most of the time throughout Edo period, half of the total rice produce distributed in Edo was the transported rice from the Port of Ishinomaki of Sendai Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="111">
<j>2代将軍徳川秀忠、3代徳川家光の頃まで仕え、寛永13年（1636年）5月江戸で死亡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served the 2nd Shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA and 3rd Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, but he died in Edo in May, 1636.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to serve for Edo Bakufu under the 2nd Shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA till the 3rd Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA; in May, 1636, he died in Edo.</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜の頃まで仕え」という部分から、この項目は江戸幕府将軍2-3代目まで仕えたという意味とし、その説明を追記しました。2. 第3代に不定冠詞が欠けていましたので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to serve for Edo Bakufu under the 2nd Shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA till the 3rd Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA; in May, 1636, he died in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>享年70。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 70.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>死因は癌性腹膜炎あるいは食道癌（食道噴門癌）と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cause of his death was thought to be cancerous pleurisy or esophageal cancer (esophageal cardiac cancer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cause of his death is considered to be cancerous pleurisy or esophageal cancer (esophageal cardiac cancer).</e>
<cmt>1. 現在想定されている訳ですので、現在形に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cause of his death is considered to be cancerous pleurisy or esophageal cancer (esophageal cardiac cancer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>「たとえ病で失ったとはいえ、親より頂いた片目を失ったのは不孝である」という政宗の考えから死後作られた木像や画にはやや右目を小さくして両目が入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Masamune&apos;s thought &quot;My eyes were given by my parents, so it was unfilial that I lost my right eye even because of illness&quot;, wooden statues and pictures of Masamune created after his death had both eyes even though their right eye was little bit smaller.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those wooden statues and pictures of Masamune produced after his death were given both eyes, while the right eye was represented slightly smaller than the other; this was based on the thought of Masamune, &quot;my eyes were given by my parents, thus it is unfilial that I lost my right eye, even if the cause of that loss was an illness.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. （両目を）「入れられている」は「行為」として、訳文にある「had」の「状態」ではない形、「were given」としました。2. 1. に加え、それを表現しているとの行為の意味で「represented」を用いました。3. 「little bit smaller」は口語的です。「slightly smaller」としました。4. 「不孝である」は会話形の中にあり、その現在時、彼が「不孝である」と言っていると考え、現在形としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those wooden statues and pictures of Masamune produced after his death were given both eyes, while the right eye was represented slightly smaller than the other; this was based on the thought of Masamune, &quot;my eyes were given by my parents, thus it is unfilial that I lost my right eye, even if the cause of that loss was an illness.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="115">
<j>辞世の句は、「曇りなき　心の月を　先だてて　浮世の闇を　照してぞ行く」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His death poem was &quot;I was just going the way I believed the best as if going with the help of the moon light in this unpredictable warring world&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「先のわからない戦国の世を月の光を頼りに道を進むかのごとく、自分が信じた道を頼りにただひたすら歩いてきた」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His death poem was &quot;I was just going the way I believed the best as if going with the help of the moon light in front of me, in this unpredictable warring world&quot;.</e>
<cmt>1. この短歌の意味内容は、「先のわからない戦国の世を月の光を頼りに道を進むかのごとく、自分が信じた陰りない光を頼りにただひたすら歩いてきた」だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His death poem was &quot;I was just going the way I believed the best as if going with the help of the moon light in front of me, in this unpredictable warring world&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="116">
<j>法名：瑞巌寺殿貞山禅利大居士（尊称：貞山公）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name: Zuiganjiden-Teizan-Zenri-Daikoji (honorific title: Teizan-ko).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name is Zuiganjiden-Teizan-Zenri-Daikoji (honorific title: Teizan-ko).</e>
<cmt>1. コンマがついていますので文章と考えます。文の形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name is Zuiganjiden-Teizan-Zenri-Daikoji (honorific title: Teizan-ko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>居城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s residential castles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Resided castles of Masamune</e>
<cmt>1. 「residential」の用法が不適切です。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Resided castles of Masamune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>米沢城（山形県米沢市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonezawa-jo Castle (Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonezawa-jo Castle (Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonezawa-jo Castle (Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>- 永禄10年（1567年）～天正13年（1585年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1567 - 1585</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1567 - 1585</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1567 - 1585</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>小浜城 (陸奥国)（福島県二本松市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obama-jo Castle (Mutsu Province) (Nihonmatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Obama-jo Castle (Mutsu Province) (Nihonmatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Obama-jo Castle (Mutsu Province) (Nihonmatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="118">
<j>- 天正13年（1585年）～天正14年（1586年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1585 - 1586</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1585 - 1586</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1585 - 1586</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>米沢城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonezawa-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonezawa-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonezawa-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="119">
<j>- 天正14年（1586年）～天正17年（1589年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1586 - 1589</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1586 - 1589</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1586 - 1589</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>若松城（福島県会津若松市追手町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakamatsu-jo Castle (Oute-machi, Aizuwakamatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakamatsu-jo Castle (Oute-machi, Aizuwakamatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakamatsu-jo Castle (Oute-machi, Aizuwakamatsu City, Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="120">
<j>- 天正17年（1589年）～天正18年（1590年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1589 - 1590</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1589 - 1590</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1589 - 1590</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>米沢城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonezawa-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonezawa-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonezawa-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>- 天正18年（1590年）～天正19年（1591年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1590 - 1591</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1590 - 1591</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1590 - 1591</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>岩出山城（宮城県大崎市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwadeyama-jo Castle (Osaki City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwadeyama-jo Castle (Osaki City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwadeyama-jo Castle (Osaki City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>- 天正19年（1591年）～慶長5年（1601年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1591 - 1601</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1591 - 1601</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1591 - 1601</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>仙台城（宮城県仙台市青葉区 (仙台市)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sendai-jo Castle (Aoba Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendai-jo Castle (Aoba Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendai-jo Castle (Aoba Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="123">
<j>- 慶長5年（1601年）～寛永4年（1627年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1601 - 1627</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1601 - 1627</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1601 - 1627</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>若林城（宮城県仙台市若林区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakabayashi-jo Castle (Wakabayashi Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakabayashi-jo Castle (Wakabayashi Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakabayashi-jo Castle (Wakabayashi Ward, Sendai City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="124">
<j>- 寛永4年（1627年）～寛永13年（1636年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1627 - 1636</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1627 - 1636</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1627 - 1636</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s graveyard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tomb of Masamune</e>
<cmt>1. 墓は、埋葬のみならず付随の建物などある場合がありますので、「tomb」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tomb of Masamune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="125">
<j>墓所：仙台市青葉区 (仙台市)霊屋下の瑞鳳殿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graveyard: Zuiho-den Mausoleum in Aoba Ward, Sendai City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His tomb is located at Zuiho-den morgue in Aoba Ward, Sendai City</e>
<cmt>1. 句読点がありますので文章としました。graveyardを上記同様変更しました。2, 「霊屋下」は「Mausoleum」と訳されていますが、このケースでは遺体が安置されているとされる建物をさします。その場合morgueのほうがわかりやすいと考え、ここちらを用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His tomb is located at Zuiho-den morgue in Aoba Ward, Sendai City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>これは政宗の死後、伊達忠宗によって寛永14年（1637年）10月に建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Masamune&apos;s death, Zuiho-den was built by Tadamune DATE in October, 1637.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuiho-den was built by Tadamune DATE in October, 1637 after the death of Masamune.</e>
<cmt>1. より適切と思われる語順に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuiho-den was built by Tadamune DATE in October, 1637 after the death of Masamune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>昭和6年（1931年）に国宝に指定されたが、昭和20年（1945年）の戦災で焼失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designated as a national treasure in 1931, but in 1945, the original mausoleum was burned down during the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designated as a national treasure in 1931, but the original building suffered war damage and it was burned down in 1945.</e>
<cmt>1. 「戦災により」が訳されていませんでしたので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designated as a national treasure in 1931, but the original building suffered war damage and it was burned down in 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>現在の瑞鳳殿は昭和54年（1979年）に再建されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present Zuiho-den was rebuilt in 1979.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuiho-den seen today is the one rebuilt in 1979.</e>
<cmt>1. 「present」で現在を示す訳はあまり適切ではないと考え修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuiho-den seen today is the one rebuilt in 1979.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="129">
<j>再建に先駆けて、昭和49年（1974年）には発掘調査が行われ、遺骨の学術的調査から身長は159.4センチメートル（当時の平均的身長）であることや、 遺骸毛髪から血液型がABO式血液型であることが判明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to the reconstruction, excavation and research of the graveyard were conducted, and analysis of Masamune&apos;s ashes found that his height was 159.4 cm (it was an average height of that time) and analysis of his hair found that his blood belonged to the ABO blood group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the reconstruction, excavation and research of the graveyard were conducted in 1974; the scientific analysis of the bunes of the deceased revealed that his height was 159.4 cm (it was an average height of that time), while the analysis of the hair of the deceased showed his blood type was ABO type.</e>
<cmt>1. 「遺骨」を「灰」と訳しています。荼毘に付していない以上誤訳ですので訂正しました。(身長がわかるのですから埋葬状態で骨全体像がわかるということだと理解しました）2. 「1974年」の年号が訳されていませんでしたので追加しました。3. これは原文の間違いではないかと思います。通常の「A, B, O blood group」であればABO型は存在しません。仕方がありませんのでそのままとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the reconstruction, excavation and research of the graveyard were conducted in 1974; the scientific analysis of the bunes of the deceased revealed that his height was 159.4 cm (it was an average height of that time), while the analysis of the hair of the deceased showed his blood type was ABO type.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>また、副葬品として太刀、具足、蒔絵を施した硯箱、鉛筆、懐中日時計兼磁石、懐中鏡、煙管、銀製ペンダント、黄金製のロザリオなど、30余点が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 30 burial goods were found, such as sword, armor, gold-lacquered ink stone box, pencil, pocket sun watch with a compass, pocket mirror, pipe, silver pendant, gold rosary, and etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 30 burial goods were found, such as sword, armor, gold-lacquered ink stone box, pencil, pocket sun watch with a compass, pocket mirror, pipe, silver pendant, gold rosary, and etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 30 burial goods were found, such as sword, armor, gold-lacquered ink stone box, pencil, pocket sun watch with a compass, pocket mirror, pipe, silver pendant, gold rosary, and etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="131">
<j>父輝宗は伊達家中興の祖と呼ばれる第9代政宗にあやかって、息子に政宗と名づけたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s father, Terumune named his son Masamune after the 9th lord, Masamune who was the founder of a renaissance of DATE family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune&apos;s father Terumune named his son as Masamune, after the 9th lord of Date clan Masamune who was the founder of a revival of Date clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「founder of renaissance」を「founder of revival」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s father Terumune named his son as Masamune, after the 9th lord of Date clan Masamune who was the founder of a revival of Date clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>本人もそのことを誇りにしていたようで、実際政宗はその先祖にまつわるところへの埋葬を望み結果的にそこへ埋葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune was proud of his name, so he hoped to be buried in a place associated with the 9th lord and actually got his desire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune seemed to be proud of the origin of his name, and he wished to be buried in the place associated with this particular ancestor; consequently he was buried at the location of his wish.</e>
<cmt>1. 「名前を誇りにしていた」という訳文ではなく、「名が9代政宗にあやかっておりそのことを誇りにしていた」の原文にあわせて修正しています。2. 場所はここでは特定の場所として不定冠詞から定冠詞に修正しています。3. 「結果的にそこへ埋葬された」概訳されていますので原文に則して修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune seemed to be proud of the origin of his name, and he wished to be buried in the place associated with this particular ancestor; consequently he was buried at the location of his wish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="133">
<j>隻眼の行者、満海上人の生まれ変わりであるという逸話は、政宗の存命中から広く知れ渡っており、東北地方の昔話の中には「仙台様（政宗のこと）の霊力で母親の病気を治してもらうために旅に出る農民の話」などが伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rumor that Masamune was a reincarnation of one-eyed high priest, Mankai was widely spread even while Masamune was alive, and &quot;story about a peasant who set out on a journey to ask Sendai-sama (Masamune) to cure his mother&apos;s illness by Masamune&apos;s psychic power&quot; became a folk tale of Tohoku Region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rumor of believing Masamune as the reincarnation of one-eyed high priest Mankai was widely spread from the days of Masamune; among those folklores in Tohoku regions, some stories related with this belief have been transmitted, such as &quot;the story of a peasant who set out on a journey for asking Sendai-sama (Lord Masamune) to cure the illness of his mother by the spiritual energy of Masamune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「存命中から」を文から文節に下げ簡略化しました。その上で分割すべき場所で文章を「；」により分割しています。2. 「東北地方の昔話の中にはこの逸話がいくつかの話になって伝わっている」の意味のところ、「この話が東北地方の昔話になった」と意訳されています。原文にあわせ修正しました。3. 「霊力」を「psychic power」と訳すのは意訳のし過ぎです。「spiritual energy」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rumor of believing Masamune as the reincarnation of one-eyed high priest Mankai was widely spread from the days of Masamune; among those folklores in Tohoku regions, some stories related with this belief have been transmitted, such as &quot;the story of a peasant who set out on a journey for asking Sendai-sama (Lord Masamune) to cure the illness of his mother by the spiritual energy of Masamune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="134">
<j>正室・愛姫と、少なくとも七人の側室がおり、五郎八姫など十男四女をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune had the legal wife, Aihime and at least 7 concubines, and became the father of 10 sons and 4 daughters including Irohahime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune had the legal wife, Aihime and at least 7 concubines, and became the father of 10 sons and 4 daughters including Irohahime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune had the legal wife, Aihime and at least 7 concubines, and became the father of 10 sons and 4 daughters including Irohahime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="135">
<j>政宗の側室の中には外国人の側室もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a foreigner among Masamune&apos;s concubines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a foreigner among those concubines of Masamune.</e>
<cmt>1. マイナーですがアポストロフィ形を避けたものとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a foreigner among those concubines of Masamune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>この側室は、政宗が出兵に従軍した際、捕虜として連れ帰った朝鮮人の女性である</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This foreign concubine was a Korean woman taken as a captive by Masamune when he joined the Korean Invasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This concubine was a Korean woman brought back with him as a captive when he went to the front in Korean Invasion.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文が「政宗が出兵に従軍した際」となっており、朝鮮が欠如しておりミスと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This concubine was a Korean woman brought back with him as a captive when he went to the front in Korean Invasion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="137">
<j>衆道関係においては、小姓の只野作十郎（只野勝吉）へ宛てた書状が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune was also somewhat of homosexual, and there was Masamune&apos;s letter to a pageboy, Sakujuro TADANO (Katsuyoshi TADANO) as evidence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the possibility of a homosexual relationship, there is a letter sent to a pageboy Sakujuro TADANO (Katsuyoshi TADANO) suggesting such relationship.</e>
<cmt>1. 「政宗はホモセクシュアルのようであった」という記述は原文にありません。「ホモセクシュアルな関係については、〜書状が残されている」という記述にとどまっています。また、多少意訳は込めましたが原文に近いように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the possibility of a homosexual relationship, there is a letter sent to a pageboy Sakujuro TADANO (Katsuyoshi TADANO) suggesting such relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>同じく衆道の関係にあった片倉景綱の息子片倉重長に対しても、大坂の役出陣の前夜、翌日の先陣を願った重綱に、「そのほうに御先鋒仰せ付けられず候て、誰に仰せ付けられるべきや」と言って重綱の頬に接吻した、との記述が『片倉代々記』に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune also had a gay relationship with Shigenaga KATAKUEA who was a son of Kagetsuna KATAKURA, and according to &quot;KATAKURA clan&apos;s historical records&quot;, at the night before joining the Siege of Osaka, Shigenaga asked Masamune to entrust him with spearhead, then Masamune replied to Shigenaga, &quot;I can entrust nobody except you with spearhead&quot; and kissed on Shigenaga&apos;s cheek.</e>
<cmt>片倉重長の名前について、一つの文中で「重長」と「重綱」の両方が使われていますが、「重長」の方が後でつけられた正式名のようなので重長に統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also another example suggesting a homosexual relationship of Masamune with Shigenaga KATAKURA, the son of Kagetsuna KATAKURA; referring to &quot;the Historical Records of KATAKURA clan,&quot; there is a description regarding the night before joining the Siege of Osaka, stating that Masamune kissed on the cheek of Shigenaga by saying, &quot;who am I supposed to appoint a vanguard if I can not ask you for that&quot; upon the request of Shigenaga to be the vanguard of the battle on the next day.</e>
<cmt>1. 「gay relationship」は口語で用いられる形のため、「homosexual relationship」としました。2. 片倉重長の訳が「Shigenaga KATAKUEA」などととミスタイプのままになっていましたので訂正しました。3. いくつかの単語が細かく抜け落ちています。「翌日の」先陣、「記述が残っている」などです。追加しました。4. 「先鋒」についてですが、訳にある「spearhead」は確かに使われるのですが、その場合単なる「槍先」ではないとの説明にあたるフレーズと組み合わせての用法になります。より単純なvanguardとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also another example suggesting a homosexual relationship of Masamune with Shigenaga KATAKURA, the son of Kagetsuna KATAKURA; referring to &quot;the Historical Records of KATAKURA clan,&quot; there is a description regarding the night before joining the Siege of Osaka, stating that Masamune kissed on the cheek of Shigenaga by saying, &quot;who am I supposed to appoint a vanguard if I can not ask you for that&quot; upon the request of Shigenaga to be the vanguard of the battle on the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="139">
<j>政宗は正室・愛姫との間にもうけた嫡出の次男忠宗を後継者とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune and his legal wife, Aihime had a legitimate son, Tadamune, and Masamune appointed Tadamune as his heir.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune named his legitimate son Tadamune as his successor, while he was the second son of Masamune with his legal wife, Aihime.</e>
<cmt>1. 2文の組み合わせによる文章ですが、その順序が原文にあわせてあり文意の主題が明確になっていませんので入れ替えました。2. 「次男」が訳出されていません。次項目と合わせ、ここでは最も重要な語に相当します。（この説明による理解がないと次項目は意味をなしません）追加しました。3. 「後継者」を「heir」を用いて訳しています。政宗の戦国大名としての立場を考えると当てはまらない訳ではないとも考えましたが、外国の王などに通常用いる語である意味文語的な語ですので、より一般的な「successor」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune named his legitimate son Tadamune as his successor, while he was the second son of Masamune with his legal wife, Aihime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>側室飯坂氏（通称・猫御前）との間に生まれた長男・秀宗はあくまで庶子とみなし、また豊臣家との関係もあったため本家を継がせなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune and his concubine, a daughter of IISAKA clan (common name: Nekogozen) also had the first son, Hidemune, but Masamune considered Hidemune just as an illegitimate son and did not allow him to succeed to the family in consideration of the relationship with TOYOTOMI clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune did not hand over the family headship to Hidemune, the first son of Masamune with his concubine, the lady of Izaka (a daughter of Izaka clan, commonly called as &quot;Nekogozen,&quot; meaning &quot;cat mistress&quot;) by determinedly placing Hidemune as an illegitimate child in consideration to the connection of Hidemune with Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 飯坂氏は訳にある「いいさか」ではなく、「いざか」です。2. これは原文の問題もあるのですが（wikipediaページではここには注釈があるため、理解できるのですが）この訳ですと「豊臣家との関係」がどのような経緯か読み取れません。「in consideration to the connection of Hidemune with Toyotomi clan」としました。（秀宗は秀吉から宇和島藩主にと10万石下治されていると注釈にはあります）3. ここは意訳して、「あくまで庶子と見なされた理由は秀吉とのつながりを徳川時代において考慮したため」という推察ができるような余地を残した訳としました。4. こうした理由から、「あくまで」は重要な単語ですがここでは訳出されていません。「determinedly」を充てました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune did not hand over the family headship to Hidemune, the first son of Masamune with his concubine, the lady of Izaka (a daughter of Izaka clan, commonly called as &quot;Nekogozen,&quot; meaning &quot;cat mistress&quot;) by determinedly placing Hidemune as an illegitimate child in consideration to the connection of Hidemune with Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="141">
<j>摺上原の戦いの後、政宗が黒川城に入城する際、戦勝を祝って一族の伊達重宗が即興で「音もせで　茅野（かやの）の夜の時雨来て　袖にさんさとぬれかからぬらん」と歌った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Surigahara War, when Masamune entered the Kurokawa-jo Castle, a family member, Shigemune DATE improvised a song &quot;Kayano had a quiet light shower at night, and it drizzled my sleeve&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masamune entered the Kurokawa-jo Castle after the battle of the Surigahara War, Date family member Shigemune DATE improvised a Tanka (a form of a Japanese traditional poetry) saying, &quot;Otomosede Kayanono Yoruno shigure kite Sodeni sansato Nure kakaranuran&quot; (Silently a light shower came to the night of Kayano, and softly and incessantly drizzled on my sleeve&quot;)</e>
<cmt>1. 「After〜, when〜」の訳は、どちらが主語となっているのか、修飾しているのかがはっきりせず、また時系列を読み取りやすくするのに適切とは言えません。これらを明らかにするよう修正しました。（語順修正のため青字）2. 「一族の伊達重宗が」は「a family member Shigemune DATE」と直訳されていますが、ここは「Date family member」としました。3. 「歌った」を「improvised a song」としていますが、これは読めば間違いなく「短歌」であることがわかります。修正し、短歌の説明も加えています。4. 以前他の訳者が常に短歌などを原文の読みを示し、その後に翻訳を加えていました。（自分もそのようにしていました）ここでも同様にしています。5. 短歌の内容については多少手直ししました。（ex.「 さんさんと」の追加など）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masamune entered the Kurokawa-jo Castle after the battle of the Surigahara War, Date family member Shigemune DATE improvised a Tanka (a form of a Japanese traditional poetry) saying, &quot;Otomosede Kayanono Yoruno shigure kite Sodeni sansato Nure kakaranuran&quot; (Silently a light shower came to the night of Kayano, and softly and incessantly drizzled on my sleeve&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>これが後に結婚式などのおめでたい席で歌われることがある東北民謡「さんさ時雨」の元歌になったと言われるが、俗説であり事実ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this is an original song of a folk song of Tohoku Region, &quot;Sansa Shigure&quot;(Drizzling Light Shower) sung in auspicious occasions such as a wedding ceremony, but this theory is just a popular belief and not true.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this tank became the origin of a minyo (a traditional folk song) in Tohoku Region called &quot;Sansa Shigure&quot; (incessantly drizzling light shower) in later years, which is sometimes sung in such celebratory occasions as a wedding ceremony; however this is not a fact but a popular belief.</e>
<cmt>1. 先述したように、元歌とは短歌であり、songではないと思います。修正しました。2. 「さんさ」の意味を追加しています。また、「さんさ時雨」の括弧内説明が大文字で示されていますが、説明であり固有名ではないため小文字としました）3. 「おめでたい席」を「auspicious occasion」とするのは口語、あるいはスピーチなどで縁起をかつぐ際に使われますが、ここではごく一般的に祝祭の場のいみとして、「celebratory occasion」としました。なお、訳では「occasion」が「occaision」のミススペルのままになっていました。4. 「後に〜になった」の後にが訳出されていませんので追加しました。5. 歌われる「ことがある」という意味が訳文に示されていません。微妙なニュアンスともとれますが、訳文のままだと東北地方ではごく一般的にこうした席でこの歌を歌うの意味にも取れてしまいます。6. 最後の「俗説であり事実ではない」ノブ分は、前部の事例説明と明確に分けるため「；」で区切りました。7. 「just」は口語的であるため、断定的な意味を強める「not〜, but〜」の構文を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this tank became the origin of a minyo (a traditional folk song) in Tohoku Region called &quot;Sansa Shigure&quot; (incessantly drizzling light shower) in later years, which is sometimes sung in such celebratory occasions as a wedding ceremony; however this is not a fact but a popular belief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>福島県北部と宮城県では、現在でも結婚披露宴等の祝いの席ではさんさ時雨が歌われるが、一方、福島県会津地方ではさんさ時雨を歌うとひんしゅくを買うことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a northern part of Fukushima Prefecture and Miyagi Prefecture, Sansa Shigure is often sung in auspicious occasions such as a wedding reception, but in Aizu Region in Fukushima Prefecture, if a person sings Sansa Shigure in auspicious occasions, he or she will be frowned on by other people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the northern part of Fukushima Prefecture, and in Miyagi Prefecture, Sansa Shigure is often sung in such celebratory occasions as a wedding banquet; however, singing Sansa Shigure in Aizu region of Fukushima Prefecture could be rude and make people feel unpleasant.</e>
<cmt>1. 「福島県北部と宮城県」の訳が「In a northern part of Fukushima Prefecture and Miyagi Prefecture」となっており、コンマで区切るか同列化するため再度前置詞を加えるかしないと、「福島県および宮城県の北部」の意味になってしまいます。コンマで区切り、かつ前置詞inを再度加え修正しました。2. 「ひんしゅく」を辞書で引くとこの定義になっていますが、訳文はこれを当てはめようと非常に冗長な説明になっています。同義語はほかにもあるわけで、訳文に合う内容にすべきだと思います。さらに個人的に「be frown on」はここでは説明不足になると考え修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the northern part of Fukushima Prefecture, and in Miyagi Prefecture, Sansa Shigure is often sung in such celebratory occasions as a wedding banquet; however, singing Sansa Shigure in Aizu region of Fukushima Prefecture could be rude and make people feel unpleasant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="144">
<j>大崎一揆煽動の疑惑で豊臣秀吉に呼び出され、証拠の文書を突きつけられた際証拠文書の鶺鴒の花押に針の穴がない事を理由に言い逃れを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masamune was summoned by Hideyoshi Toyotomi on suspicion of urging Osaki Ikki (the revolt of the former retainers of Osaki clan) and was confronted with an evidential letter, Masamune excused that the letter was fake because a written seal mark of wagtail on the letter did not have a pinhole.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masamune was summoned and confronted with an evidential letter by Hideyoshi Toyotomi upon the suspicion of instigating Osaki Ikki (the revolt of the former retainers of Osaki clan with the peasants of the region), Masamune made an excuse regarding the letter by indicating the lack of a pinhole on the letter at his seal mark of wagtail.</e>
<cmt>1. 「扇動」をurgingとしていますが、適切な用法ではありません。「instigating」としました。2.　一揆は通常領民の反乱を指す語ですので、大崎一揆の説明ページにもあるように領民との乱として追記しました。4. 「言い逃れ」を適切なフレーズに修正しました。3. 意訳による説明は正しいですが原文にはない内容が付記され冗長になっています。原文に沿った内容で理解できるよう修正しました。(青字は語順変更箇所です）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masamune was summoned and confronted with an evidential letter by Hideyoshi Toyotomi upon the suspicion of instigating Osaki Ikki (the revolt of the former retainers of Osaki clan with the peasants of the region), Masamune made an excuse regarding the letter by indicating the lack of a pinhole on the letter at his seal mark of wagtail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>それまで送られた他の文書との比較で証拠文書のみに穴がなかったため、やり過ごす事が出来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune showed other letters, and all of them had a pinhole, so Masamune could clear himself of suspicion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune succeeded to take his way out since it was proved only this evidential letter did not have the pinhole by comparing with all the other letters sent to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>1. 「それまで送られた他の文書」は秀吉の元にあるはずであり、訳文ですと「政宗が他の手紙を見せた」の部分が原文にはない創作の可能性が生まれます。可能性としてはこのケースもありますが、別の人が証拠を確認した可能性もある訳で、いずれにせよ確認できないためこの形で意訳するべきではないと思い訂正しました。2. 原文では「証拠文書のみに穴がなかったため」としているところを訳文は意訳し、「別の全ての手紙は穴があったため」としています。間違いではないとしても原文と異なる方法で説明するべきではないとし、原文に則して訂正しました。3. 「やり過ごすことができた」を「clear himself of suspicion」としていますが、次項でもあるとおり完全に疑いを晴らした訳ではなく、あくまで言い逃れてやり過ごしたの意味です。その意味を削がない形に修正しました。＊結果的に全文書き直しです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune succeeded to take his way out since it was proved only this evidential letter did not have the pinhole by comparing with all the other letters sent to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>実際には二種類の花押を使い分けていた可能性が高く、秀吉も疑ったらしいのだが確証が得られなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, it was highly possible that Masamune used 2 kinds of written seal marks, and it was a reason why Hideyoshi suspected Masamune, but Hideyoshi could not have decisive proof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In truth, there is a high possibility that Masamune utilized two kinds of written seal marks depending on an occasion; although Hideyoshi suspected of this possibility, he could not acquire conclusive evidence.</e>
<cmt>1.「実際には」の訳を直訳調のものではなく「本当のところは」という意味に修正しました。2. 可能性については現在その是非を検討している訳ですので現在形としました。3. 「使い分ける」について、単に「2種類の花押を使った」とするのではなく「機会に応じて」を付記することでより原文の意味に則したものとしました。4. 「2種類の花押を使った可能性があり、それは秀吉が政宗を疑った理由でもある」は明らかに意訳のし過ぎか誤読によるものです。その事実は書かれておらず確証も得られません。秀吉は「2種類の花押を使った可能性についてを疑ったらしい」が原文の意味するところですのでそのように修正しました。5. 「確証が得られなかった」の訳は、不定冠詞がないと文法上誤りです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In truth, there is a high possibility that Masamune utilized two kinds of written seal marks depending on an occasion; although Hideyoshi suspected of this possibility, he could not acquire conclusive evidence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>但し、現存する政宗の書状の中に花押に穴の開いたものはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, written seal marks with a pinhole were not found on existing letters of Masamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, there is no example among those existing letters sent from Masamune with a pinhole at the written seal marks.</e>
<cmt>1. Butによる書き出しを修正しました。なおここでの「ただし」の意味するところは、「Actually」の意味であると思います。2. ここでもまた主語が倒置されて訳されており、「書状の中に穴の開いたものはない」が「花押に穴のある書状は見つからなかった」と意訳されています。原文を尊重する意味で原文に則した形に修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, there is no example among those existing letters sent from Masamune with a pinhole at the written seal marks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="148">
<j>政宗は朝鮮出兵に同行していない説があるが、俗説であり事実ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that Masamune did not join the Korean Invasion, but it&apos;s just a popular belief and not true.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is a theory stating Masamune did not accompany with the troops set out to the Japanese invasion of Korean, it is an untrue belief and different from a fact.</e>
<cmt>1. 「朝鮮出兵」は定訳に則したものに修正しました。2. 「出兵に同行していない」を「did not join」としていますが、これだと「同行する」という特定の意味が示せないために「政宗は同行しなかった」という読解だけでなく、「伊達家は朝鮮出兵に参加しなかった」という意味にもとれてしまいます。「did not accompany with the troops set out to〜」として「出兵した軍には同行しなかった」という形にしました。3. ここでの「俗説」は「一般的に信じられているもの」という意味よりは、「事実に基づかない低俗な説」という意味が強いと思います。低俗な説というフレーズは加えませんでしたが、「本当ではなく事実とことなっている」という訳としました。4. it&apos;sと短縮形にしていますが、口語形で文章には適切ではありません。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is a theory stating Masamune did not accompany with the troops set out to the Japanese invasion of Korean, it is an untrue belief and different from a fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>政宗らが渡鮮したことを実証するものとして、隠居所である若林城（現宮城刑務所）と政宗が再建した瑞厳寺に、朝鮮から持ち帰らせた「臥龍梅」が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As evidence of Masamune&apos;s going to Korea, &quot;Garyubai&quot; (Lying-dragon shaped plum) which Masamune brought back from Korea still can be seen at the Wakabayashi-jo Castle and the Zuigan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the evidences of Masamune and his fellows visiting Korean Peninsula, &quot;Garyubai&quot; (a plum tree shaped in a form resembling a lying dragon) that Masamune brought back from Korea can be found at the Wakabayashi-jo Castle and the Zuigan-ji Temple rebuilt by Masamune.</e>
<cmt>1. ここで証拠となっているものは一つでなく、訳文にあるように単数形にはなり得ません。複数形に修正しました。また、特定される事柄として定冠詞を加えています。2. 「of Masamune&apos;s going to Korea」を名詞節と扱っているようですが、適切ではありませんし強引な訳です。修正しました。3. この臥龍梅はここでは木をさしていますので、plumだけでは不十分です。4. 「政宗が再建した」が訳出されていません。追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the evidences of Masamune and his fellows visiting Korean Peninsula, &quot;Garyubai&quot; (a plum tree shaped in a form resembling a lying dragon) that Masamune brought back from Korea can be found at the Wakabayashi-jo Castle and the Zuigan-ji Temple rebuilt by Masamune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="150">
<j>政宗は家康に従って後の天下取りの機会をうかがうことを優先し、旧領である上杉領に進攻し100万石のお墨付き分の領地を自らの手で獲得することを狙った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune decided to serve Ieyasu once and wait for opportunity for seizing the seat of the shogun, and invaded UESUGI&apos;s territory which used to be his former territory to retrieve it by himself so that he could realize having the territory of 1,000,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune prioritized to find out any opportunity of conquering the country; he first aimed for retrieving his former territory by invading the land of Uesugi clan, in order to acquire the total territory of worth 1,000,000 koku with his own hands, which was comparable to the amount promised in the &quot;Assurance of Hyakumangoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 訳文にある「いったんは家康に従い、将軍の席をつかみ取る機会を待った」という部分は、「天下取り」が結果的に「将軍となる」ことであったか特定できるものではないと考え、修正しました。原文の意味については、「政宗は家康に従いつつ天下取の機会をうかがった」という基本的な意味にとる以外ないと判断しました。（天下取りの機会をうかがうことを「優先する」が「100万石を自ら獲得する」ことにつながっているとすると、まずは家康が関ヶ原の戦いに関わっている間に勢力拡大しておき、関ヶ原終了時には家康に比肩しうる勢力になっておく、ということかと思われます）文章がrun-on化しましたので、最初の一文後いったん区切りました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By following Ieyasu, Masamune prioritized finding an opportunity to conquer the country in the future; he first aimed to retrieve his former territory by invading the land of the Uesugi clan, in order to acquire a total territory worth 1,000,000 koku with his own hands, which was the amount promised in the &quot;Assurance of Hyakumangoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>文法および表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>しかし、関ヶ原の戦いが予想以上に短期間で終結したためにその試みは頓挫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the Battle of Sekigahara was over sooner than Masamune had expected, his scheme failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his scheme was brought to a halt since the Battle of Sekigahara lasted in shorter period of time than Masamune had expected.</e>
<cmt>1. 語順が原文に合わせてあり、重要度順になっていません。修正しました。2. 上杉攻略そのものが失敗した訳ではありませんので（一部成功しています）原文にある通り「試みは頓挫した」の意味に修正しました。3. 「予想以上に短期間」の訳が「予想より早く」と意訳されています。間違いではありませんが、一応修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his scheme was brought to a halt since the Battle of Sekigahara lasted in shorter period of time than Masamune had expected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="152">
<j>最上氏の居城である山形城が上杉家の攻撃を受けた際、片倉景綱が共倒れを狙い、漁夫の利を奪うよう進言したが政宗は母親の安全を理由にこれを却下し援軍を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Yamagata-jo Castle of MOGAMI clan was attacked by UESUGI&apos;s troop, Kagetsuna KATAKURA recommend Masamune to lead both MOGAMI clan and UESUGI clan to go down together and fish in troubled waters, but Masamune rejected it to protect his mother and sent a reinforcement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the residence castle of Mogami clan, the Yamagata-jo Castle was attacked by the troops of Uesugi clan, Kagetsuna KATAKURA offered an advice for Masamune to watch for the opportunity of Mogami clan and Uesugi clan going down together and profit from it; however, Masamune rejected this advice for reason of protecting his mother, and sent a reinforcement.</e>
<cmt>1. 「最上氏の居城である」が訳出されていません。「本拠地」の意味ですので重要なものですので追加しました。2. 「漁父の利を奪う」が定訳のままはめ込まれ前後と全くつながっていません。（基本的にこのファイル全体で文節の接続が丁寧に処理されていません）3. 「共倒れを狙い」を「lead both〜to go down」としていますが、ここでの共倒れは政宗がこの時点でどうこうできるものではありません。よって、「両者共倒れの機会をうかがい〜」という訳にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the residence castle of Mogami clan, the Yamagata-jo Castle was attacked by the troops of Uesugi clan, Kagetsuna KATAKURA offered an advice for Masamune to watch for the opportunity of Mogami clan and Uesugi clan going down together and profit from it; however, Masamune rejected this advice for reason of protecting his mother, and sent a reinforcement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>しかしこの説は定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, it is still unknown whether this story is true or not.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is still unknown whether this story is true or not.</e>
<cmt>1. 「But」による書き出しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is still unknown whether this story is true or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>しかし、援軍は上杉軍が最上軍を攻めるのを傍観していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, the reinforcement just stood by and watched UESUGI&apos;s troop attacked MOGMI&apos;s troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Masamune sent a reinforcement for Mogami clan, the troops just stood by and watched while the troops of Uesugi clan attacked the Mogami troops.</e>
<cmt>1. 前項目も「しかし」ではじまっているため、ここでの「しかし」は意味をなしません。ここでの「しかし」は、前項目の「説は定かではない」を受けてというよりは、前々項目の「政宗は援軍を送った」に対するものと思われます。このため、その内容を引き継いで「Although Masamune sent a reinforcment」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Masamune sent a reinforcement for Mogami clan, the troops just stood by and watched while the troops of Uesugi clan attacked the Mogami troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>上杉軍が山形城を落としてから動く陰謀を抱いていたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This fact indicates that Masamune planned to take action after UESUGI&apos;s troop seized the Yamagata-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This fact indicates that Masamune had plotted a scheme to take action once Uesugi troop captured the Yamagata-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>1. 「陰謀を抱いていた」を単なる「planned」から「plotted a scheme」としました。2. なお、時系列を明らかにするため「had plotted」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This fact indicates that Masamune had plotted a scheme to take action once Uesugi troop captured the Yamagata-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="156">
<j>大坂夏の陣後には天下安泰を願う家康に心服し、松平忠輝の改易などもあり天下取りの野望をあきらめざるをえず、領国経営に努めたようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), Masamune had to give up being the ruler of Japan because he was impressed by Ieyasu who tried to realize peace in the nation and Tadateru MATSUDAIRA forfeited the status as a warlord, and then he put in his efforts to administer his territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After &quot;Osaka Natsu no Jin&quot; (the Summer Siege of Osaka), Masamune had to abandon his ambition of conquering Japan, especially after seeing the decline and forfeiture of Tadateru MATSUDAIRA (the 6th son of Ieyasu and the husband of the daughter of Masamune, Irohahime); Masamune began to follow Ieyasu with respect by recognizing his wish for the peace and the security of the nation; he put in his efforts to the management of his territory.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文に問題があるのですが、それでも訳文は「家康に心服し」と「〜の改易などもあり」を同列に扱っています（というより基本的にこの2事項の文節をandで結んでいるだけです）どちらかに重点を置くか、原文の真意を読解する必要があります。ここでは、1: 「大阪夏の陣後は」 2: 「〜の改易などもあり天下取りの野望をあきらめざるを得ず」 3: 「〜家康に心服し」 4: 「領国経営に務めた」の順に分解しました。2. なお松平忠輝についてですが、説明を加えるべきだと判断しました。忠輝は家康の6男で、政宗の娘五郎八姫と結婚しています。3. 「天下安泰を願う家康に心服し」の部分はあまり適切な訳がなされていませんので修正しました。4. 「領国経営」について、「to administer」としていますが、より広い意味を持つ「management」を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After &quot;Osaka Natsu no Jin&quot; (the Summer Siege of Osaka), Masamune had to abandon his ambition of conquering Japan, especially after seeing the decline and forfeiture of Tadateru MATSUDAIRA (the 6th son of Ieyasu and the husband of the daughter of Masamune, Irohahime); Masamune began to follow Ieyasu with respect by recognizing his wish for the peace and the security of the nation; he put in his efforts to the management of his territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>しかし、この説は、政宗の野望説を唱える史料（政宗は徳川幕府を倒し、婿の松平忠輝を将軍職に就ける構想を立てていたとするもの）などから否定されることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, this story is often refuted because some records indicates that Masamune did not give up his ambition (Masamune plotted to overthrow the Tokugawa Shogunate and induct his son-in-law, Tadateru MATSUDAIRA as the shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this view is often denied because there are some historical materials advocating the ambition of Masamune (the theory stating that Masamune had plotted a scheme to overthrow the Tokugawa Shogunate and put his son-in-law, Tadateru MATSUDAIRA in the position of shogun).</e>
<cmt>1. 「But」による書き出しを修正しました。2. 「records indicates」となっており、複数形の名詞に対し単数形の動詞で受けており基本的なミスです。3. 「史料」は歴史資料の意味とし、さらに「野望説を唱える史料」ということで「事実の記録にとどまらない資料」とし、「records」ではなく「materials」としてこの点ぼかしました。4. 「Masamune did not give up his ambition」としていますが、そのような記述は見当たりませんので意訳です。原文に則して訂正しました。5. 「induct」はよく受動形で用いられる語です。*これは原文に関する指摘なのですが、「徳川幕府を倒し、婿の松平忠輝（家康の息子、よって徳川家）を将軍につけるということは「徳川幕府をたおすわけではなく、すげかえる」だけです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this view is often denied because there are some historical materials advocating the ambition of Masamune (the theory stating that Masamune had plotted a scheme to overthrow the Tokugawa Shogunate and put his son-in-law, Tadateru MATSUDAIRA in the position of shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="158">
<j>大坂夏の陣の際に、5月7日船場口で伊達勢の前方に展開していた神保相茂隊が明石全登隊の奇襲を受けて全滅した</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), on May 7, the troop of Sukeshige JINBO was stationed at Senbaguchi in front of DATE&apos;s troop, but they were suddenly attacked by the troop of Takenori AKASHI and completely defeated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 7 during Osaka Natsu no Jin (the Summer Siege of Osaka), the party of Sukeshige JINBO deployed at Senbaguchi in front of other Date troops, was completely defeated by the surprise attack made by the party of Takenori AKASHI.</e>
<cmt>1. 「展開していた」は「deployed」に修正しました。2.「奇襲を受けて」は原文に則した体にしました。3. 「隊」については、より小さな部隊という意味で「party」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 7 during Osaka Natsu no Jin (the Summer Siege of Osaka), the party of Sukeshige JINBO deployed at Senbaguchi in front of other Date troops, was completely defeated by the surprise attack made by the party of Takenori AKASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>これは、政宗による味方討ちではとの風聞が立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a rumor that this sudden attack was plotted by Masamune who was on the same side as Sukeshige JINBO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was rumored that this incident was an internecine strife plotted by Masamune.</e>
<cmt>1. 味方討ちの意味での語「internecine strife」を充てました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was rumored that this incident was an internecine strife plotted by Masamune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>政宗は、神保隊が明石隊によって総崩れになったため、これに自軍が巻き込まれるのを防ぐため仕方なく処分したと主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune insisted that since JINBO&apos;s troop suffer a debacle, he had no choice but to abandon JINBO&apos;s troop so as to prevent his own troop from being involved in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune insisted that he had no choice but to finish up the Jinbo party himself, in order not to let his own troops dragged into the debacle of the Jinbo party upon the attack of the Akashi party.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文では「仕方なく処分した」と「味方を討った」ことを認めています。訳にあるように単に「abandon」ですと「見捨てた」の意味で、非常に大きな違いがあります。訂正しました。2. 「明石隊によって」が訳出されていません。読み取れるものですが原文にあるので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune insisted that he had no choice but to finish up the Jinbo party himself, in order not to let his own troops dragged into the debacle of the Jinbo party upon the attack of the Akashi party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>この事件は、幕府が最終的に伊達家の見解を追認して決着したが、事件直後から様々な興味と憶測を生んだ（詳細は神保相茂の項を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident was finally settled after the shogunate gave retrospective acceptance of the allegation of Date clan, but even after the settlement, this incident encouraged people&apos;s interest and all sorts of interpretations (Please refer to the page of Sukeshige JINBO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In consequence, this incident was settled when bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) confirmed after the insistence of Date clan, while this incident drew attention and promoted conjectures in various degree (refer to the section of Sukeshige JINBO).</e>
<cmt>1. 「最終的に〜して決着した」を「finally settled after〜」としていますが、これは「結果としては決着した」の意味を持つ原文の意味が損なわれ、「〜してとうとう（ようやく）決着した」という別の意味を提案するものになりかねません。修正しました。2. 「幕府」はこの場合「将軍」である家康のみが追及に関わっていたというより、すでに幕府の機能としての追及があったと考えられるため、きちんと訳出しました。（説明は追加しています）3. 「encourage」はあまり適切でないと考え修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In consequence, this incident was settled when bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) confirmed after the insistence of Date clan, while this incident drew attention and promoted conjectures in various degree (refer to the section of Sukeshige JINBO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="162">
<j>砂金常房（砂金貞常の嫡男）は大坂の役で、軍令違反を起したが咎められず逆に一族に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunefusa ISAGO (a legitimate son of Sadatsune ISAGO) violated a military order during the Siege of Osaka, but he was not punished, and to the contrary, could join DATE family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunefusa ISAGO (a legitimate son of Sadatsune ISAGO) violated a military order during the Siege of Osaka, but he joined DATE family rather than being punished.</e>
<cmt>1. 「he was not punished, and to the contrary, could join DATE family」は強引に「and to the contrary」が挿入されたk達になっています。つながりをスムーズにするため修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunefusa ISAGO (a legitimate son of Sadatsune ISAGO) violated a military order during the Siege of Osaka, but he joined DATE family rather than being punished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>それゆえに、政宗の落胤ではないかとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, people said that Tsunefusa was an illegitimate son of Masamune.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why there is a theory considering Tsunefusa as an illegitimate son of Masamune.</e>
<cmt>1. 「ではないかとの説もある」の原文が「人々は言った」となっており、意味は似ていますが違うものになっています。原文にあわせ修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why there is a theory considering Tsunefusa as an illegitimate son of Masamune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="164">
<j>徳川家光からは非常に尊敬されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune was held in high respect by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune was highly respected from Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>訳文は間違いではないでしょうが読みづらいものになっています。単純に訳せば良いと思われます。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune was highly respected from Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>政宗本人の器量に加え、自らを将軍として立ててくれた後見人であり、また敬神する祖父・家康とも渡り合った戦国の雄でもあった。、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was because Masamune was a capable man, a guardian who supported Iemitsu to be the shogun, and a great warlord who could deal with his most revered grandfather, Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Iemitsu, Masamune was a person of ability, a tutelage to bring him up and support to be a shogun, and a leading figure in the period of warring states even competed against his grandfather, Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>1. 「That was because」としていますが、確かにそのように解釈しても良いですがその記述自体はありません。単純に、「家光に取っては」と変更しました。2. 「後見人」については、正式なものではないですし教育者の意味合いも込めて「tutelage」としました。3. 「戦国の雄」を「great warlord」から戦国時代の第一人者の意味に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Iemitsu, Masamune was a person of ability, a tutelage to bring him up and support to be a shogun, and a leading figure in the period of warring states even competed against his grandfather, Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>家光にしてみればあらゆる面で父親替わりだったのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, for Iemitsu, Masamune was a father figure in every aspect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune would have been the substitute figure of his own father for Iemitsu in every aspect.</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜だったのであろう」を示すよう、「was」を「would have been」に変更しました。2. 「〜替わり」の訳として「substitute」を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune would have been the substitute figure of his own father for Iemitsu in every aspect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>幕府の意向はどうあれ、家光個人が政宗に向けた処遇は、明らかに外様に遇する程度を超えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whatever the intention of the shogunate might be, Iemitsu gave obviously too preferential treatment to Masamune who became the Tokugawa vassal only after the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether it was the intention of bakufu or not, the treatment of Masamune by Iemitsu himself was obviously beyond the degree of common practice, among those who were not hereditary or the original vassals of Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「家光個人が政宗に向けた処遇」の訳について、「幕府」を「shogunate」としていることで、「幕府」と「将軍家光」の関係が明確に説明されていません。言い換えれば、「将軍」は「幕府そのもの」ではないということがこうした記述ではわからないということです。誤解を避けるために幕府は定訳通り「bakufu」と記述すべきだと思います。2. 「幕府の意向はどうあれ」は「幕府の意向であったかなかったかはどうあれ」の訳にし、「それに対して将軍家光自身は〜」という形にしています。これは、訳文では「家光は個人的に高すぎる処遇を与えた」としているためで、主語になるべきものがずれてしまっているためです。3. 「外様」の訳が説明不足ですので、追記修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether it was the intention of bakufu or not, the treatment of Masamune by Iemitsu himself was obviously beyond the degree of common practice, among those who were not hereditary or the original vassals of Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="168">
<j>将軍の前での脇差帯刀を許されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune was allowed to put on a sword and short sword even in front of the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune was allowed to put on a sword and a short sword even in front of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>1. 脇差しに不定冠詞がありませんので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune was allowed to put on a sword and a short sword even in front of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>側近が酔って居眠りする政宗の刀を調べると中身は木刀であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A close associate of the shogun checked Masamune&apos;s sword while Masamune was drunk and asleep, and found his sword was a wooden one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a close vassal of the shogun examined those swords of Masamune as he got drunk and fell asleep, he found those swords were wooden ones.</e>
<cmt>1. 細かいですが、将軍の側近は家臣であり対等な立場にいる同僚ではありません。「the vassal」としました。2. 先述でも脇差し帯刀とあり、刀は2本で複数です。それに合わせ修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a close vassal of the shogun examined those swords of Masamune as he got drunk and fell asleep, he found those swords were wooden ones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="170">
<j>二条城へと参内する際、御三家でも許されなかった紫の馬の総を伊達に与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masamune visited the Nijo-jo Castle, Iemitsu allowed Masamune to use a purple fringe to grace his horse even though even three privileged branch families of TOKUGAWA were not be allowed to use purple color.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iemitsu allowed Masamune to use a purple fringe to grace his horse for the occasion of visiting the Nijo-jo Castle, while this was not allowed even among gosanke (the three privileged branch families of Tokugawa).</e>
<cmt>1. 語順を替え重要な部分を文頭におきました。2, 御三家は直接英訳となっていますが、定訳でもある通りまず読みで紹介し、説明を括弧で加える形としました。3. 「families of TOKUGAWA were not be allowed」と文法的に誤りとなっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iemitsu allowed Masamune to use a purple fringe to grace his horse for the occasion of visiting the Nijo-jo Castle, while this was not allowed even among gosanke (the three privileged branch families of Tokugawa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="171">
<j>政宗が病床についた際は、医者を手配した上で江戸中の寺社に快癒の祈祷を行わせ、死の3日前には家光自らが見舞いにきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masamune became ill, Iemitsu arranged a doctor and ordered all shrines and temples in Edo to pray for Masamune&apos;s complete recovery, and 3 days before Masamune&apos;s death, Iemitsu visited Masamune by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masamune became ill, Iemitsu arranged a doctor and ordered all shrines and temples in Edo to offer a prayer for his recovery; Iemitsu himself visited Masamune 3 days before Masamune&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>1. 祈祷についてより適切になるよう修正しました。2. 「by himself」は「〜自らで」というより「一人で」を意味します。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masamune became ill, Iemitsu arranged a doctor and ordered all shrines and temples in Edo to offer a prayer for his recovery; Iemitsu himself visited Masamune 3 days before Masamune&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>政宗が亡くなると、父・秀忠が死んだ時よりも嘆き入り、江戸で7日、京都で3日の間殺生や遊興が禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masamune was dead, Iemitsu moaned more than when his father, Hidetada was dead, and destruction of life and entertainments were prohibited for 7 days in Edo and 3 days in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masamune passed away, Iemitsu moaned for his death more than the death of his father Hidetada; all the activities of taking lives of living, and amusements or entertainments were then prohibited for 7 days in Edo, and 3 days in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>1. 「亡くなる」はdeadですと直接的すぎますので「passed away」としました。2. 「殺生」を「destruction of life」としています。辞書でも一例としてそのようになっていますが、仏典内で用いられるような訳ですので、ここではより一般的に「take lives of living」としました。実際上は狩猟や漁業の停止であったといいます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masamune passed away, Iemitsu moaned for his death more than the death of his father Hidetada; all the activities of taking lives of living, and amusements or entertainments were then prohibited for 7 days in Edo, and 3 days in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="173">
<j>政宗には離間、扇動工作等をした色々な嫌疑が絶えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune was always suspected of many things such as plotting to estrange enemy&apos;s troops and urging uprising.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no end to the various suspicions against Masamune, regarding his possible involvement in plotting schemes of alienating targeted parties or instigating uprisings.</e>
<cmt>1. 「政宗には〜な嫌疑が絶えなかった」について、「政宗は常に疑われていた」という訳になっています。間違いではないですが、主語／述語が倒置されていますので、これを避けるため一応原文に則して変更しました。2. 原文が「〜等を『した』」と説明不足のため、ここでは訳文でも多少の意訳がなされています。原文の意味するところは「嫌疑が絶えなかった」という点で、実際にそうした嫌疑が証明された訳ではない、とも別の項で説明されています。これを考慮し、「〜した可能性」という説明や「scheme」などの語を加えて曖昧さを強調しています。3. 「離間」については、これも原文が説明不足ですが訳にあるように「estrange enemy&apos;s troops」は意訳であり、可能性を「敵軍の間」と限定してしまっていますので、「狙いを定めた両者間」としました。また「alienating」のほうが一般的かと考え変更しています。4. urgingは「instigate」に統一修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no end to the various suspicions against Masamune, regarding his possible involvement in plotting schemes of alienating targeted parties or instigating uprisings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>また、黒脛巾組という忍者集団がいたと仙台藩士の半田道時の伊達秘鑑には掲載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to DATE&apos;s secret written by a retainer of Sendai Domain, Michitoki HANDA, Masamune owned a group of Ninja (covert agents) named Kurohabakigumi (Black Foot Ornament Group).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Date Hikan&quot; (the secret records of Date) written by a retainer of Sendai Domain, Michitoki HANDA has a description stating there was a group of ninja (Japanese covert agent in feudal times) called Kurohabagigumi (Black shin guards Corps).</e>
<cmt>1. 「伊達秘鑑」は読み＋（説明）の形に修正しました。現状では本のタイトルであることも続きを読むまで判読不可能です。2. 「忍者集団がいた」の訳が「Masamune owned a group〜」となっており、実際に政宗が所有していたかどうか記述されていない中での意訳です。「there was a group of〜」としました。3. 忍者の説明が不足していると感じましたので追記しました。4. 「脛巾」は「はばき」ではなく一般には「はばぎ」のようです。修正しました。なおこの説明では「足部分の飾り」となってしまい、脛当ての意味と異なりますので、説明も修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Date Hikan&quot; (the secret records of Date) written by a retainer of Sendai Domain, Michitoki HANDA has a description stating there was a group of ninja (Japanese covert agent in feudal times) called Kurohabagigumi (Black shin guards Corps).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>その一方で、『政宗記』などには、黒脛巾組という名称の記述は見あたらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the name, Kurohabakigumi did not appear on &quot;Masamuneki&quot; (Masamune&apos;s Biography).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, any description regarding the name Kurohabagigumi can not be found in &quot;Masamuneki&quot; (the chronicle of Masamune).</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜の名称の記述は見当たらない」に関して、「〜の名称に関する記述」が単に「〜の名前は見当たらない」になってしまっています。原文の「この名称のグループに関する記述」が「この名前が見受けられない」となっており、ニュアンスが抜け落ちますので修正しました。2. 「政宗記」についてはより内容範囲の広い「chronicle」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, any description regarding the name Kurohabagigumi can not be found in &quot;Masamuneki&quot; (the chronicle of Masamune).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>参考(葛西大崎一揆や和賀忠親一揆等)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reference (Kasai-Osaki Ikki [the revolt of the former retainers of the Kasai clan and the Osaki clan], the revolt of Tadachika WADA and so on)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reference (regarding events such as Kasai-Osaki Ikki [the revolt of the former retainers of the Kasai clan and the Osaki clan], the revolt of Tadachika WADA)</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜等」を「and so on」としているところ、「regarding events such as」と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reference (regarding events such as Kasai-Osaki Ikki [the revolt of the former retainers of the Kasai clan and the Osaki clan], the revolt of Tadachika WADA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="177">
<j>実戦経験がない将軍家光はしばしば政宗など実戦経験豊かな大名に合戦について質問をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun Iemitsu had no war experience, so he often asked feudal lords of war expert such as Masamune about wars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since shogun Iemitsu did not have any experience of participating in a war, he often asked Masamune or other feudal lords with multiple experiences of joining wars about the details of those battles.</e>
<cmt>1. 「so」による接続を避け「since」を用いています。2. 「実戦経験豊な」が「war expert」と意訳されていますが、一応原文に則し修正しました。3. 「合戦について」ですが、修正では「実戦経験」を「experience of war」としてより大きなくくりとし、「合戦」を「battle」と各戦闘の意味としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since shogun Iemitsu did not have any experience of participating in a war, he often asked Masamune or other feudal lords with multiple experiences of joining wars about the details of those battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>ある日、政宗と佐竹義宣 (右京大夫)を招いて摺上原の戦いについて色々質問したが、勝者であった政宗が雄弁であったのに対し、敗者の佐竹義宣は始終無言で、唇を噛みしめているだけであったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, when Iemitsu invited Masamune and Yoshinobu SATAKE (Master of the Western Capital Offices) and asked them many questions about the Suriagehara War, Masamune who had won the battle talked a lot, but Yoshinobu SATAKE who had lost the battle kept silent biting his lip all the while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, Iemitsu invited Masamune and Yoshinobu SATAKE (chief general of the Western Capital Offices) and asked various questions regarding the Suriagehara War; Masamune as the winner of the war was eloquent, while Yoshinobu SATAKE as the looser of the war remained silent with his lip bit throughout the meeting.</e>
<cmt>1. 「右京大夫」の説明は定訳にもある「Master of」から「Chief general of」としました。2. 「勝者」と「敗者」の説明を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, Iemitsu invited Masamune and Yoshinobu SATAKE (chief general of the Western Capital Offices) and asked various questions regarding the Suriagehara War; Masamune as the winner of the war was eloquent, while Yoshinobu SATAKE as the looser of the war remained silent with his lip bit throughout the meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="179">
<j>遺品にロザリオがあったことなどから、政宗は密かにキリスト教に帰依していたのではないかと伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since some rosaries were found among Masamune&apos;s personal mementos, some historians believed that Masamune secretly converted himself to Christianity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been told that Masamune might have embraced the Christianity himself since there was a rosary among his relics.</e>
<cmt>1. 「遺品にロザリオがあった」という原文が「いくつかのロザリオが見つかった」と意訳されています。複数であったことは原文からは読み取れません。主語述語の倒置とともに修正しました。2. 「帰依する」について、訳では「converted himself to Christianity」としていますが、この訳ですとある別の宗教から改宗したという意味になります。その事実はここからは読み取れません。文語的用法とのことですが、定訳にある「embrace」を用いました。3. 「遺品」を「personal mementos」としていますが、これは客観的な「遺品」の意味ではなく、「ある人にとって亡くなった人を偲ばせる個人的な形見」の意味で適切ではありません。「relic」に修正しました。4. 「帰依していたのではないか」という過去仮定形が、「historians believed」となっており、a. 仮定形が「信じる」と断定形になっているb. 「believed」と過去形になっており、筆者にとっても完全に過去の事柄として切り離されています。原文では、「筆者が現在においても伝え聞いた」の意味が含まれ、過去と現在がつながっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been told that Masamune might have embraced the Christianity himself since there was a rosary among his relics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>政宗の長女の五郎八姫は一時期キリシタンだったことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s first daughter, Irohahime was Christian for a period of her life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, it is known that Irohahime, the eldest daughter of Masamune, was Christian for a period of time in her life.</e>
<cmt>1. 意訳になりますが、前項目とつながっての説明と思われますので、「In fact」を文頭に置きつながりを持たせました。2. 原文は「キリシタンだったことがある」と断定していますので、その証拠も見つかっていると考え、「it is known」を加えてその意味を示しました。3. 長女の訳を原文に合わせました。4. 「for a period of her life」は不自然な気がします。「for a period of time in her life」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, it is known that Irohahime, the eldest daughter of Masamune, was Christian for a period of time in her life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="181">
<j>養生法が変わっていて、冬に炬燵の片側を開けさせていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune took an unique way to keep healthy such as rolling up one side of Futon which covered Kotatsu (table with heater).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune took an unique way to maintain his health, by opening up one side of kotatsu (covered table with heat source beneath) to the air.</e>
<cmt>1. 「keep healty」は文法的に誤りだと思います。「maintain his health」としました。2. 「こたつの片側を開けさせて」と原文にありますが、訳は意訳されて「布団を片側で巻き上げて」のようになっています。実際そうだったと想定はできますが、違う可能性もなくはないため、ここでは単純に直訳しディテール記述を避けました。3. こたつの説明で「heater」とありますが、一応「heat source beneath」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune took an unique way to maintain his health, by opening up one side of kotatsu (covered table with heat source beneath) to the air.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="182">
<j>朝は早く目が覚めても、定時に側の者が起こしに行くまでは起床しないという拘りがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune obsessively did not get out of Futon until a servant came to get him up at the fixed time in the morning even though he was awake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune had a self-imposed rule not to get up in the morning until an attendant came to wake him up at a fixed time, even if he work up earlier.</e>
<cmt>1. 「拘り」をobsessivelyとしていますが、それに続く「obsessively did not get out of futon」はあまり考えられて訳されたと思えません。この訳だと「変な癖、もしくは異常な性癖があった」のようにとられてしまいます。原文そのものも「拘り」という言葉を使うべきか疑問ですが、ここでは「self-imposed rule」とし、「規則正しいこと、周囲の役割を尊重すること」を暗に示すような肯定的な訳にしました。2. 「even though」の用法がここでは不適切です。正しくは「even when」か「even if」になります。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune had a self-imposed rule not to get up in the morning until an attendant came to wake him up at a fixed time, even if he work up earlier.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="183">
<j>料理が趣味。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s hobby was cooking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune&apos;s hobby was cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s hobby was cooking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>元々は兵糧開発のために行っていたのだが、戦国が終わり太平の世になると美食を極めるために料理の研究をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune originally started cooking to invent preservative foods for wars, but after the Sengoku period was over and the peaceful period came, he began to study dishes to enjoy gourmet foods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally Masamune was experimenting on cooking to develop military provisions, but he pursued cooking in search of gourmet meals once the Warring States period was over and the society was at peace.</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜のために行っていたのだが」とあり、過去進行形の形ですが、訳文では「started cooking」と過去形＋行為の開始の形になっています。原文に則したものとし、さらに「開発のために」から単にcookingではなく「experimenting on cooking」としています。2. 「兵糧」を「preservative foods for wars」としていますが、まず「preservative foods」は訳者の意図したと見られる「保存可能な食料」の意味にはなりません。「preservative」は「保存がきくようにする保存料」など、食料そのものではなく添加物を指します。兵糧の定訳として「provisions」がありますので、そちらを用いました。3. 「戦国が終わり太平の世になると」のフレーズを適切なものに修正しました。4. 「美食を極めるために料理の研究をしていた」の訳ですが、かなり稚拙なものになっています。これも1. と同様、「当時〜していた」と行為は既に起こっている状態を示していますが、訳では「began to study」とし、「研究を始めた」と変更されています。また、「美食を極めるため」が「to enjoy gourmet foods」（美食を楽しむため）と意訳されており、真意が伝わりませんので、「pursued cooking in search of gourmet meals」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally Masamune was experimenting on cooking to develop military provisions, but he pursued cooking in search of gourmet meals once the Warring States period was over and the society was at peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>政宗は、料理について「馳走とは旬の品をさり気なく出し、主人自ら調理して、もてなす事である」と言う名言を命期集に残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Meigosyu&quot; (Masamune&apos;s great remarks), Masamune said about dishes as &quot;Feast can be prepared when a host simply serves delicacies of the season, cooks dishes by himself, and treats them to guests&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune left a wise saying regarding cooking in &quot;Meigosyu&quot; (collection of remarks by Masamune in his life time), &quot;serving a meal means to modestly provide a seasonal food cooked by the host himself, to entertain his guest.</e>
<cmt>1. 「名言」が訳出されていません。また、「名言を〜に残した」という形にも訳されていません。追加、訂正しました。2. 「命期集」の説明は、「命期」の意味を解していないもののように思いました。追加修正しています。3. 政宗の名言部分の訳ですが、かなり意訳されています。「Feast can be prepared」との訳は「（饗宴のような）馳走は〜で準備できる／提供できる」の「行為」を指します。原文は、「〜である」と断定の「事柄」を指しています。4. 「さりげなく出し」が「simply serve」となり、「単に／ただ出す」の意味にも取れる曖昧なものです。「modestly」を充てました。5. 「主人自ら調理して」が「cooks dishes by himself」となっていますが、ここでの「by himself」の用法は「一人で」の意味を強調するもので誤りです。「cooked by the host himself」としました。6. 「もてなす」の部分は「treats them to guests」となっており、「them」は料理を指しているようですが、treatの直後には人が来るのが通例であり、ここでの「treat」が誤用になっています。「treats guests」もしくは「serve」で置き換えれば適切ですが、ここでは「もてなす」の意味（馳走と同様の意味がありますが）を強調するため「entertain」を充てました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune left a wise saying regarding cooking in &quot;Meigosyu&quot; (collection of remarks by Masamune in his life time), &quot;serving a meal means to modestly provide a seasonal food cooked by the host himself, to entertain his guest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>仙台市発祥の料理が多いのは、政宗の影響と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of specialties of Sendai City resulted from the inventions of Masamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible to say that there are influences of Masamune, for the fact that there are many dishes originated from Sendai.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文ではこのことは「〜と思われる」と想定の域を出ない憶測としていますが、訳文は「政宗の発明の結果」と断定する形に訳しています。修正しました。2. 「specialities of Sendai City」ですと料理のみならず仙台の特産品一般をさすことになります。普通に「dishes」を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible to say that there are influences of Masamune, for the fact that there are many dishes originated from Sendai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>また仙台城下では味噌倉を建てていたが、大規模な味噌生産体制が行われたのは、これが最初といわれているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune built storehouses of Miso (fermented soybean paste) around the Sendai-jo Castle, and started the first large Miso production in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune built storehouses of Miso (fermented soybean paste) in the castle town of the Sendai-jo Castle, and this example is considered to be the first establishment of a large-scale Miso manufacturing system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜が最初と言われているという」と推定であることを示していますが、訳文は「政宗が日本で初めて〜した」と確定の事実として示しています。訂正しました。2. 「仙台城下」をその字義通りに修正しました。3. 原文がおかしいのですが、「行われた」は一応「establishment」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune built storehouses of Miso (fermented soybean paste) in the castle town of the Sendai-jo Castle, and this example is considered to be the first establishment of a large-scale Miso manufacturing system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="188">
<j>岩出山名物の凍り豆腐と納豆は、政宗の料理研究の末に開発されたものであるが、元々は兵糧用だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specialties of Iwadeyama, kori-dofu (frozen bean curd) and Natto (fermented soybeans) were invented by Masamune&apos;s study of foods, and they were originally preservative foods for wars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specialties of Iwadeyama, kori-dofu (frozen bean curd) and Natto (fermented soybeans) were the results of the study of cooking developed by Masamune, while those foods were originally intended for the usage as military provisions.</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜の末に開発されたもの」という「もの」を表す原文が「were invented」と「行為」に置き換えられていますので、原文に即し修正しました。2. 「兵糧用」の訳は先述にもあるように原文が適切でないため、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specialties of Iwadeyama, kori-dofu (frozen bean curd) and Natto (fermented soybeans) were the results of the study of cooking developed by Masamune, while those foods were originally intended for the usage as military provisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>仙台名物のずんだ餅も政宗が考案したという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People say that a specialty of Sendai, zunda mochi (rice cake covered in sweetened mashed green soybeans) was invented by Masamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a story that Masamune invented a specialty of Sendai, zunda mochi (rice cake covered in sweetened mashed green soybeans).</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜という説がある」という原文に即し「People say that〜」という訳から修正しました。2. 主語述語が倒置され、受動形として訳されているため原文に即し能動形に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a story that Masamune invented a specialty of Sendai, zunda mochi (rice cake covered in sweetened mashed green soybeans).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="190">
<j>料理の他にも多くの趣味を持ち、晩年は一日たりとも無駄に過ごすことがなかったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to cooking, Masamune had many hobbies and used every single day for them in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune appeared to have had many hobbies other than cooking, thus it is said he did not waste even a single day in his later years.</e>
<cmt>1. これも同様に伝聞の推定でありながら、断定に訳されていますので原文に合わせました。2. 「無駄に過ごすことがなかった」を「全ての日を趣味に使った」としており、可能性としてありますが憶測でもあり意訳です。原文に即したものとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune appeared to have had many hobbies other than cooking, thus it is said he did not waste even a single day in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="191">
<j>喫煙者で、毎日起床後・昼・睡眠前と、規則正しく3回煙草を吸っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune liked smoking and regularly smoked 3 times a day, after getting up, in the afternoon and at bedtime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a smoker, and he smoked 3 times a day in regular basis, after getting up, at noon, and before sleeping.</e>
<cmt>1. 「喫煙者で」とありますが、「喫煙が好きで」という訳は意訳です。規則正しく日に3回吸ったとあり、日課に近いものに思えます。訂正しました。2. 「昼」が「in the afternoon」となっていますが午後の意味で正しくありません。また、bedtimeも原文の「睡眠前」より広い時間を意味しますので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a smoker, and he smoked 3 times a day in regular basis, after getting up, at noon, and before sleeping.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>遺品に、愛用のキセルがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s favorite smoking pipe was found among his personal mementos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his relics, there is his favorite Oriental pipe (a pipe with a long straight shank and a small bowl).</e>
<cmt>1. 「キセル」はアジア独特のものだったようですので、辞書にあるように訳し、説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among his relics, there is his favorite Oriental pipe (a pipe with a long straight shank and a small bowl).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="193">
<j>隙のない印象の政宗であるが、酒にだけは滅法弱く、酔って失敗した逸話がいくつか残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune was thought to be a person who was always thoroughly guarded, but he could not hold his drink and made a lot of failure stories by being drunk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune gives impression as a person with no unguarded moment, but he could not keep control only of his drinking habit, and left some stories regarding his failures under the influence of alcohol.</e>
<cmt>1. 「was thought to be a person」と過去形で表されていますが、現在の印象を述べた文ですので、現在形としました。2. 「印象」を訳出しました。3. 原文の「酒にだけはめっぽう弱く」は次項目など読むと「酒に酔いやすい」の意味ではなく「酒に目がない」の意味だと思います。訳文の「could not hold his drink」の「could not hold」部分は良いのですが、「his drink」ですと彼の現在飲んでいる飲み物を指すため少なくとも「his drinking」とし、「could not hod off from his drinking」などとすれば正しいです。修正では「keep controle of his drinking habit」とし、より明確に「酒癖」の意味を付加しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune gives impression as a person with no unguarded moment, but he could not keep control only of his drinking habit, and left some stories regarding his failures under the influence of alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>中には将軍秀忠との約束を二日酔いですっぽかし、仮病を使って言い抜けたという話まである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among his failure stories, an outstanding one was that Masamune missed a meeting with Shogun Hidetada due to a hangover, and faked sick as an excuse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those stories, there is an outstanding one that Masamune even missed a meeting with Shogun Hidetada due to the hangover from drinking, while he made his way out by pretending to be sick.</e>
<cmt>1. 全般にそうですが、「failur」と「stories」の名詞を並べるだけでは通常複合語にはなりません。分節動詞を接続する仕方と同様、語を並べただけの訳と言えます。2. 「faked sick」は「faked sickness」であれば問題ないかと思いますが、fakeそのものがあまりこうした使われ方をしないともいますので「pretend to be」を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those stories, there is an outstanding one that Masamune even missed a meeting with Shogun Hidetada due to the hangover from drinking, while he made his way out by pretending to be sick.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="195">
<j>映画『スター・ウォーズ』のダース・ベイダーのマスクは仙台市博物館所蔵の「黒漆五枚胴具足 伊達政宗所用」の兜をモチーフにデザインされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mask of Darth Vader which appeared in the movie &quot;Star Wars&quot; was modeled after the helmet of &quot;black-lacquered five corselets armor used by Masamune DATE&quot; owned by the Sendai City Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mask of Darth Vader appeared in the movie &quot;Star Wars&quot; was modeled after the kabuto (a headpiece of a Japanese warrior) of &quot;the black-lacquered armor with 5 pieced cuirass used by Masamune DATE,&quot; which is currently owned by Sendai City Museum.</e>
<cmt>1. 「corselets」は「〜let」から、「コルセットのような」という簡易的なものであることを示しています。この５枚胴は金属製で西洋伝来のものの影響もあることから、西洋の鉄鎧から胴部分のパーツ名をとりました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mask of Darth Vader appeared in the movie &quot;Star Wars&quot; was modeled after the kabuto (a headpiece of a Japanese warrior) of &quot;the black-lacquered armor with 5 pieced cuirass used by Masamune DATE,&quot; which is currently owned by Sendai City Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="196">
<j>大悲願寺13世海譽の元で弟子として在山していた弟・秀雄のもとを政宗が訪れ四方山話をし庭にあった白萩を気に入り所望し貰い受け、臥龍梅を大悲願寺に贈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masamune visited his young brother, Shuyu who trained as a disciple of the 13th chief priest of the Daihigan-ji Temple, 海譽, they had a small talk, and Masamune wanted white Lespedeza in a garden and gave Garyubai (Lying-dragon plum) to the Daihigan-ji Temple in return.</e>
<cmt>海譽の読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masamune visited his young brother Shuyu, who was at the Daihigan-ji Temple as a disciple of the 13th chief priest Kaiyo, they had a talk in various topics; Masamune was pleased with Japonica flowers in a garden and asked for them; in return he sent Garyubai (Lying-dragon plum) to the Daihigan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>1. 海譽の読みは「かいよ」でした。ネットで調べればすぐに見つかります。2. 「白萩」をLespedezaとしていますが、これは萩全般の総称で、白萩は「Japonica」になります。修正しました。3. 「〜を気に入り」が訳出されていませんでしたので「was pleased with」を用いて追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masamune visited his young brother Shuyu, who was at the Daihigan-ji Temple as a disciple of the 13th chief priest Kaiyo, they had a talk in various topics; Masamune was pleased with Japonica flowers in a garden and asked for them; in return he sent Garyubai (Lying-dragon plum) to the Daihigan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="197">
<j>明治天皇は政宗の事を以下のようにと評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Meiji described Masamune as follows;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Meiji commented on Masamune as follows;</e>
<cmt>1. 「described」は間違いではないと思いますが、より一般的な「commented on」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Meiji commented on Masamune as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>「政宗は、武将の道を修め、学問にも通じ、外国の事情にも思いをはせて交渉を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I ordered Masamune to negotiate because he mastered the way of the warlord, excelled at learning, and was familiar with foreign affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Masamune pursued the precepts of a warlord, while he was also after studies and learning, and then he thought and dreamed of foreign affairs to actually conducted the negotiations with foreigners.&quot;</e>
<cmt>口語ですので説明が足りないため、多少の意訳が必要と考えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Masamune pursued the precepts of a warlord, while he was also after studies and learning, and then he thought and dreamed of foreign affairs to actually conducted the negotiations with foreigners.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>文武に秀でた武将とは、実に政宗のことである」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The warlord who excelled at academics and military arts was indeed Masamune&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is Masamune who shall be called as a warlord excelled in both literary and military arts.</e>
<cmt>1. 「it is〜who〜」の構文を用いて口語の口調に近づけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is Masamune who shall be called as a warlord excelled in both literary and military arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="200">
<j>宮城県宮城郡松島町にある伊達光宗の菩提寺円通院には、伊達一本締めという仙台藩祖・伊達政宗ゆかりの一本締めが伝承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Entsu-in Temple in Matsushima-cho, Miyagi District, Miyagi Prefecture, which was a family temple of Date clan, handed down a form of ceremonial rhythmic hand clapping called DATE Ipponjime which was associated with the first lord of Sendai Domain, Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A unique form of a ceremonial rhythmic hand clapping called Date Ipponjime (three sets of three claps and one final clap performed at the end of a special event) associated with the first lord of Sendai Domain Masamune DATE has been transmitted at the family temple of Mitsumune DATE, the Entsu-in Temple located in Matsushima-cho, Miyagi District, Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>1. 説明部分が非常に長い文章のため、訳文のように主語節と述語節を倒置すると重要な意味の部分が長い説明のあとに来る形になります。（原文は受動形ですので、能動形にされた訳文を基に戻したことになります）2. 「伊達光宗の菩提寺」が「伊達家の菩提寺」になぜか簡略化されています。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A unique form of a ceremonial rhythmic hand clapping called Date Ipponjime (three sets of three claps and one final clap performed at the end of a special event) associated with the first lord of Sendai Domain Masamune DATE has been transmitted at the family temple of Mitsumune DATE, the Entsu-in Temple located in Matsushima-cho, Miyagi District, Miyagi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>「いよ～っ、パパパン！、いよ～っ、パン！」という「3」と「1」の拍子の組み合わせが「三国一」を表しており天下を狙った政宗の夢が込められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ipponjime consists of three claps and one final clap like &quot;Iyo&apos;o (call), clap clap clap! Iyo&apos;o, clap!&quot; and combination of &quot;3&quot; and &quot;1&quot; represents &quot;Sangokuichi&quot; (literally means the best of 3 countries, but it actually means the best of the world), and &quot;Sangokuichi&quot; represents Masamune&apos;s ambition for ruling Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ipponjime consists of three claps and one final clap as &quot;Iyo&apos;o (call), clap clap clap! Iyo&apos;o, clap!&quot; and this combination of &quot;3&quot; and &quot;1&quot; represents &quot;Sangokuichi&quot; (the word is used to mean &quot;unparalleled in Japan, China and India&quot; meaning unparallel in the world), metaphorical to the dream of Masamune who sought for ruling Japan.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文では、”「三国一を表す一本締め」には天下を狙った「正宗の夢」が込められている”という意味のところ、訳文では「正宗の夢」が抜け落ちているために「一本締め」は「正宗の野望」を「表している」という役になっています。追加修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ipponjime consists of three claps and one final clap as &quot;Iyo&apos;o (call), clap clap clap! Iyo&apos;o, clap!&quot; and this combination of &quot;3&quot; and &quot;1&quot; represents &quot;Sangokuichi&quot; (the word is used to mean &quot;unparalleled in Japan, China and India&quot; meaning unparallel in the world), metaphorical to the dream of Masamune who sought for ruling Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>慶長遣欧使節の支倉常長もこの”伊達一本締め”で見送られ、徳川政権が安定してからは秘めた意味が露見しないよう姿を消したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leader of the Keicho Mission, Tsunenaga HASEKURA was sent off with this &quot;DATE Ipponjime&quot;, but after the reign of the TOKUGAWA shogunate was settled, &quot;DATE ipponjime&quot; fell into disuse in order to hide Masamune&apos;s ambition for ruling Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ambassador of the Keicho Mission, Tsunenaga HASEKURA was also sent off with this &quot;Date Ipponjime,&quot; although this custom was concealed and disappeared not to reveal its hidden meaning, once TOKUGAWA shogunate became stable and solid.</e>
<cmt>1. 「姿を消す」は原文では「風習を諌め意図的に隠す、消す」の意味があります。「fell into disuses」はフレーズとしてもあまり一般的でありませんので、こちらで意訳しました。2. 「徳川政権が安定して」は冗長でしたので簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ambassador of the Keicho Mission, Tsunenaga HASEKURA was also sent off with this &quot;Date Ipponjime,&quot; although this custom was concealed and disappeared not to reveal its hidden meaning, once TOKUGAWA shogunate became stable and solid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>そのため資料が一切残っておらず、伊達家所縁の円通院に代々人づてに伝えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, no written records about Date Ipponjime remained, and it was handed down for generations only within the Entsu-in Temple which was associated with Date clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there is no reference left regarding Date Ipponjime details; it was handed down for generations only within the Entsu-in Temple associated with Date clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「no〜」構文は口語的ですので、「there is no」に修正しました。2. 冗長部分の削除を行っています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there is no reference left regarding Date Ipponjime details; it was handed down for generations only within the Entsu-in Temple associated with Date clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>政宗の野望</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s ambition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune&apos;s ambition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s ambition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="204">
<j>政宗は豊臣政権時代から、隙あらば天下を簒奪しようと何度も策略していたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune had tried to take every opportunity for getting the seat of the ruler since the time of TOYOTOMI&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that Masamune had repeatedly plotted to usurp the position of ruling the country by taking any opportunity since the time of the reign of Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「とされている」の推測の形に修正しました。2. 「簒奪」は奪うの意味であり、訳文ですと「〜の地位に座る」の意味で違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Masamune had repeatedly plotted to usurp the position of ruling the country by taking any opportunity since the time of the reign of Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="205">
<j>秀吉の小田原の役のとき、参陣に遅延したのは、奥州、特に新たに手に入れた芦名家領土の「経略多端」の故と弁明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Siege of Odawara led by Hideyoshi, Masamune made an excuse for his delay in joining the battle that he was &quot;so busy with administering&quot; his territories such as Oshu and especially the former territory of ASHINA clan that he newly seized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Siege of Odawara led by Hideyoshi, Masamune made an excuse for his delay in joining the battle, stating that he was &quot;so busy with the management&quot; of Oshu, especially the territory of Ashina clan that he newly acquired.</e>
<cmt>1. 冗長な部分が多いため削除した箇所が幾つかあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Siege of Odawara led by Hideyoshi, Masamune made an excuse for his delay in joining the battle, stating that he was &quot;so busy with the management&quot; of Oshu, especially the territory of Ashina clan that he newly acquired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>佐竹氏一派と対抗し、同盟関係にあった後北条氏と手を結んで秀吉を倒そうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune tried to defeat Hideyoshi by being opposed to allies of SATAKE clan and cooperating with his alliance partner, GOHOJO clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune tried to overthrew Hideyoshi, by first overcoming the influence of Satake clan, and then joining hands with his ally, Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>1. defeatは戦いなどで使われるため、「overthrow」をあてました。2. 「佐竹一派」は佐竹氏の総体勢力という意味に意訳しました。3. 原文には時系列が示されていませんが、東北での勢力争いをまず制し、次に関東を固め、京都へ、という順序を簡単に示しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune tried to overthrew Hideyoshi, by first overcoming the influence of Satake clan, and then joining hands with his ally, Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>秀吉は、伊達氏を従えて奥州仕置を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi conducted Oshu Shioki (punishment to the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power) with Date clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi conducted Oshu Shioki (punishment to the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power) accompanied by Date clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「従えて」の意味を「accompanied by」で加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi conducted Oshu Shioki (punishment to the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power) accompanied by Date clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>また、伊達家を中心に奥州の諸大名の連合軍を組織し後北条氏と連携、徳川家康ら豊臣家中の不穏分子の蜂起を待つという構想も持っていたようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And also Hideyoshi planned to organize allied forces of territorial lords of Osu led by Date clan, cooperate with GOHOJO clan, and wait for uprising of suspicious TOYOTOMI subjects such as Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Masamune planned to organize allied forces of territorial lords of Oshu led by Date clan, and then the forces would cooperate with Gohojo clan, while he also anticipated and waited for the rise of seditious groups within the Toyotomi administration such as Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>1. 「Hideyoshi planned」としていますが完全に誤読です。正宗の構想の説明です。2. 時系列を整理するため、接続詞の用法（ex. And then) に留意しました。またalsoなどを加え同時性なども明確にしようとしています。3. 「豊臣家中の不穏分子」を「suspicious TOYOTOMI subjects」としていますが何を意味するのかパッと見ではわかりませんでした。「suditious groups within the Toyotomi administration」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Masamune planned to organize allied forces of territorial lords of Oshu led by Date clan, and then the forces would cooperate with Gohojo clan, while he also anticipated and waited for the rise of seditious groups within the Toyotomi administration such as Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="209">
<j>葛西大崎一揆を扇動して、密かに領土拡大を狙ったという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Masamune secretly urged the Kasai-Osaki-Ikki in order to expand his territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory stating that Masamune secretly conspired to expand his territory by agitating the Kasai-Osaki Ikki.</e>
<cmt>1. 「という説がある」は文字通りにしました。2. 原文の「密かに領土拡大を狙った」が訳文では「密かに一揆を扇動した」になっており、誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory stating that Masamune secretly conspired to expand his territory by agitating the Kasai-Osaki Ikki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="210">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いのとき、和賀忠親を扇動して南部利直の領土を侵略しようとしたが失敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Battle of Sekigahara, Masamune urged Tadachika WADA to launch uprising, and tried to seize the territory of Toshinao NANBU by taking advantage of the uprising, but his scheme failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Battle of Sekigahara, Masamune took in Tadachika WADA to promote a revolt in order to invade the territory of Toshinao NANBU, but his scheme failed.</e>
<cmt>1. 余分な説明を削除しました。2. 「to launch uprising」は適切とは思いません。「uprising」は計画して起こす（launch）というものではないからです。3. 「侵略」が「seize」となっており、行為と目的とで意味が異なります。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Battle of Sekigahara, Masamune took in Tadachika WADA to promote a revolt in order to invade the territory of Toshinao NANBU, but his scheme failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="211">
<j>政宗の裏切りに対して家康は報復し、刈田郡のみの加増にとどめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu retaliated for Masamune&apos;s betrayal by cancelling all the reward grants of Masamune except giving Katta District.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu retaliated for Masamune&apos;s betrayal by canceling his assurance of granting rewards, and limited the reward of Masamune only to the addition of Katta District.</e>
<cmt>1. 刈田郡のみの加増について、これは百万石のお墨付きに含まれていたとの説明はなく、（可能性は有り）まったく別のオプションであった可能性が高いため、「すべてのお墨付きのうち刈田郡の加増を除いて」の意味の訳文は意訳になります。原文に即した形で修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu retaliated for Masamune&apos;s betrayal by canceling his assurance of granting rewards, and limited the reward of Masamune only to the addition of Katta District.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>これは東軍参加の武将の中では加増の伸び率が最も少ない部類である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among warlords who joined Ieyasu&apos;s eastern army, Masamune was given the smallest territory as reward grants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the lowest territory gains among those warlords participated in the Eastern army.</e>
<cmt>1. 「加増の伸び率が最も少ない部類である」の訳が「正宗は最も少ない加増を受け取った」と違訳されています。最小とは言われていませんので、その内容についてきちんと訳すべきです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is one of the lowest territory gains among those warlords participated in the Eastern army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="213">
<j>政宗の関ヶ原直前の所領58万石は度量衡改定以前の一反三百六十歩で計算されたものという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some said that Masamune&apos;s 580,000 koku at the time before the Battle of Sekigahara was calculated with the old unit of measurement used before the unit reform which represented 1 tan (991.74 m²) was equal to 360 bu (1 bu was 2.4m).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory stating that the territorial value of his own land right before the Battle of Sekigahara, presented as 580,000 koku, had been calculated with the outdated measurement unit used before the scale and measurement revision, which was based on the unit of 1 tan (991.74m²) equal to 360 bu (1 bu was 3.3m²).</e>
<cmt>1. 一反と一部が面積と長さの別単位で示されておりおかしいと思って調べると、「一歩は六尺四方の面積」でもあるとわかりました。（以前の訳で例がありました）坪と同じ単位で、一歩約3.3m²です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory stating that the territorial value of his own land right before the Battle of Sekigahara, presented as 580,000 koku, had been calculated with the outdated measurement unit used before the scale and measurement revision, which was based on the unit of 1 tan (991.74m²) equal to 360 bu (1 bu was 3.3m²).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>これが正しいとすると豊臣政権において定められた一反三百歩で計算した場合、67万石にまで上昇する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this theory was true, in case that Masamune&apos;s territorial land value was recalculated using the new unit defined under Hideyoshi&apos;s regime which represented 1 tan was equal to 300 bu, it became 670,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this theory is true, the recalculated territorial value increases to 670,000 koku if applied with the unit defined as 1 tan equal to 300 bu by Toyotomi administration.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文の日本語に即した訳文の語順により無理が発生しており、最も重要な数字が文末に来ています。英文では修飾節が長い場合、主語・述語がまず示されてから、そこに修飾節が続き主題がわかりやすいようなっています。 2. 「〜まで上昇する」が「it became」となっています。意味が抜け落ちているのと、時制が過去形になっており現在説を当てはめているという原文の意味から外れています。修正しました。3. 同様に、「in case〜was recalculated」は当初仮定の形のために「was」が用いられているのかと思いましたが、単純に上記同様過去時制で考えているようです。ここでは「if」を用い簡略化しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this theory is true, the recalculated territorial value increases to 670,000 koku if applied with the unit defined as 1 tan equal to 300 bu by Toyotomi administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>また仙台平野には開墾に適した三角州などの土地が多数存在し、当初から土地には余裕があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sendai Plain was rich in lands such as deltas which could be easily developed, so Masamune could use lands abundantly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendai Plain has plenty of land spaces suitable for reclamation such as triangle sandbars, therefore the territory had a room for growth from the original condition.</e>
<cmt>1. 「rich in land」は土地が豊かという意味は範囲が広すぎ、土壌が優れているのか土地が余っているのかあいまいです。2. 「三角州」はデルタでも良いとは思いましたが、北上川水系にはこうした砂州が多数存在すると想定し、「sandbars」を当てました。「triangle sandbars」で三角州になります。3. 「開墾に適した」土地が「容易に開発できる」の意味かどうかは判断できない部分です。より容易とは言えるかもしれませんが。4. 「当初から」の説明がありません。追加しました。5. 「土地には余裕があった」で「Masamune could use lands」としていますが、原文にはそのような形で書かれていませんので修正しました。6. 「use lands abundantly」での「abundantly」は「use abundant lands freely」を意図したと思われますがここでは文法的に誤りです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendai Plain has plenty of land spaces suitable for reclamation such as triangle sandbars, therefore the territory had a room for growth from the original condition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>政宗は関ヶ原以降、開拓地を知行として与える方式を取りら各領主に開墾を奨励、仙台平野の新田開発を推し進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Sekigahara War, Masamune introduced a new system that if Masamune&apos;s subject developed a new field, he was secured the right to rule that field as enfeoffment, and this system promoted development of the Sendai Plain (In 1628, a lord of the Shiraishi-jo Castle, Shigenaga KATAKURA developed a new field and got an additional territory of 1,000 koku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Sekigahara War, Masamune encouraged each proprietor of a domain for reclamation works by introducing a system to award the reclaimed land as a domain of the developer; this system promoted the development of new rice fields in the Sendai Plain.</e>
<cmt>*この原文には一部重大な欠落があります。「〜方式を取り＿ら各領主に開墾を奨励」の「＿」部分に固有名が入るべきところ抜けています。これは、参照元のwikipediaページでも同様でした。よって、「〜ら各領主」は削除しています。1. 「enfeoffment」なる語があり何かのスペルミスだと思いますがわかりません。スペルチェックしたのでしょうか。2. 非常に固い訳文だと感じました。「that if」など、接続詞と仮定詞が連続しているのも先述同様の分節接続のぎこちなさによります。また、原文に語順があっているのも同様問題です。3. 普通に「方式」とあるところ、訳では「new system」としており未確認状態での意訳です。4. 「開墾を奨励」の部分が訳出されていません。意訳に引っ張られて原文を訳しきれていません。5. 「新田」が欠けていましたので追加しました。6. 「白石城」の読み修正しました。7. 「新田開発を行ない千石相当の石高を新たに獲得している」について、「行う」「新田」「相当」「新たに」を追記し、「獲得」については「acauired」に変更しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Sekigahara War, Masamune encouraged each proprietor of a domain for reclamation works by introducing a system to award the reclaimed land as a domain of the developer; this system promoted the development of new rice fields in the Sendai Plain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>（1628年には、白石城主片倉重長が新田開発を行い千石相当の石高を新たに獲得している。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In 1628, the lord of the Shiroishi-jo Castle Shigenaga KATAKURA conducted the development of a new rice field, and newly acquired the territory of worth 1,000 koku.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In 1628, the lord of the Shiroishi-jo Castle Shigenaga KATAKURA conducted the development of a new rice field, and newly acquired the territory of worth 1,000 koku.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>この政宗に始まる開墾事業は後の藩主たちにも受け継がれ、仙台藩の実高はみるみる増大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune&apos;s reclamation work was succeeded by later lords, and the land value of Sendai Domain rapidly increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reclamation work started by Masamune was taken over by the succeeding feudal lords of the domain, therefore the actual land value of Sendai Domain rapidly increased.</e>
<cmt>1. 「正宗に始まる」の始まるが訳出されていませんでしたので追加しました。2. 「受け継がれる」は「後の藩主」を「succeeding lords of the domain」とするため、重複しないよう「taken over」に置き換えました。3. 「後の藩主」とあり、単なる「lords」ですと城主や重要家臣など含まれてしまいます。「succeeding feudal lords of the domain」とし差別化しました。4. 「実高」の意味が欠落していましたので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reclamation work started by Masamune was taken over by the succeeding feudal lords of the domain, therefore the actual land value of Sendai Domain rapidly increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>寛文年間以降は藩自らが主動した新田開発も行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Kanbun eras, the domain sometimes initiated development of new fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Kanbun eras, the domain itself initiated and conducted the development of new rice fields.</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜自らが」が訳出されていませんでしたので追加しました。2. 「主動（主導？）した」と「行われた」が訳文ではひとまとめになっています。「行われた」を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kanbun eras, the domain itself initiated and conducted the development of new rice fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>100年後の江戸時代中期には実高200万石とも謳われる日本最大級の藩に成長した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A century later, during the middle of the Edo period, Sendai Domain, which had the territory of 2,000,000 koku, became the largest domain in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A century later, Sendai Domain became one of the largest domains in Japan by mid Edo period, which was considered to reach 2,000,000 koku in its actual territorial value.</e>
<cmt>1. 接続詞やコンマなどで細かく分節化され、冗長かつ読みづらいものになっていますので、語順を修正し整理しました。2. 「日本最大級」とあり「日本最大」とは違います。修正しました。3. 「〜とも謳われる」で推定を示しているところ、訳文は断定しています。「considered to reach」を追加しました。4. 「実高」が欠けていますので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A century later, Sendai Domain became one of the largest domains in Japan by mid Edo period, which was considered to reach 2,000,000 koku in its actual territorial value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>政宗が江戸に廻送を始めて以降、江戸に供給される米の大半は仙台の米となり、作の豊凶は江戸の米相場を支配するほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Masamune started sending rice to Edo, the most part of rice provided to Edo was produced in Sendai, and rice price in Edo varied depending on rice production condition in Sendai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the time Masamune had started forwarding the rice to Edo, most of the rice supplied to Edo became the produce of Sendai Domain, thus the market price of rice in Edo was controlled and depended on the crop conditions in Sendai.</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜以降」の意味を強調するため「Since the time」を用い、時制の違いで時間経過も示せるようにしています。2. 「供給」はより適切な「supply」を当てました。3. 「米の大半は仙台の米となり」は「〜となる」の変化の状況を示しており、訳文の断定の状況とは異なります。「became」を用いました。4. 「相場」が訳出されていませんでしたので追加しました。5. 作柄にあたる「crop」と「rice production condition」を入れ替えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the time Masamune had started forwarding the rice to Edo, most of the rice supplied to Edo became the produce of Sendai Domain, thus the market price of rice in Edo was controlled and depended on the crop conditions in Sendai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>最盛期には表高の1/3にあたる二十万石もの米が江戸に出荷されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At its height, one third of the face value of Sendai Domain, 200,000 koku was sent to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At its height, one third of the face value of Sendai Domain, 200,000 koku of rice was sent to Edo.</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜もの米が」が欠けています。外国人には「石」の意味が伝わりにくく、これが欠けると何のことかわからなくなる可能性があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At its height, one third of the face value of Sendai Domain, 200,000 koku of rice was sent to Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>享保17年（1732年）には、西国の蝗害により江戸で米価の暴騰が起こり、例年の倍以上の米が出荷されたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1732, rice price rose sharply in Edo due to poor harvest by locust plague in the western part of Japan, amount of rice sent from Sendai Domain to Edo doubled from the past years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1732, rice price had a sharp rise in Edo due to poor harvest in the western part of Japan by locust plague, therefore double amount of rice was shipped from Sendai Domain compared to an average year.</e>
<cmt>1. 語順の問題で内容が読み取りづらいです。修正しました。（青字）2. 「出荷」の意味を表すため「sent」を「shipped」に変更しています。3. 「例年」が「the past years」と訳されていますが、より適切な「an average year」を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1732, rice price had a sharp rise in Edo due to poor harvest in the western part of Japan by locust plague, therefore double amount of rice was shipped from Sendai Domain compared to an average year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>なお、このときの収益は約50万両にものぼったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this year, income of Sendai Domain came to about 500,000 ryo (a unit of currency used during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this year, the profit of Sendai Domain reached to roughly 500,000 ryo (a unit of currency used during the Edo period. The value of 1 ryo at that time is roughly about 40,000 yen in today&apos;s value, thus it is roughly 20 billion yen).</e>
<cmt>1. 「収益」はより適切な「profit」としました。なお定冠詞が必要です。2. 日本銀行金融研究所貨幣博物館によると1730年当時の1両は現在価値で4万円ほど、よって200億円相当だそうです。いかに大金であったかを示すため、一応付記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this year, the profit of Sendai Domain reached to roughly 500,000 ryo (a unit of currency used during the Edo period. The value of 1 ryo at that time is roughly about 40,000 yen in today&apos;s value, thus it is roughly 20 billion yen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>この豊かさは広く知られており、安井息軒の『読書余滴』に「二百万石余」、帆足万里の『東潜夫論』には「二百五十万石」との記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">High production capacity of Sendai Domain was so famous all over Japan, so its territorial land value was described as &quot;Over 2,000,000&quot; in &quot;Dokusyo-Yoteki&quot; (spin-offs from reading) written by Sokken YASUI and as &quot;2,500,000&quot; koku in &quot;Tosenpuron&quot; (the book about political ideology) written by Banri HOASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wealth of Sendai Domain was widely known throughout Japan; &quot;Dokusyo-Yoteki&quot; (readings from a dripping of a pen) written by Sokken YASUI describes its territorial value as &quot;over 2,000,000 koku,&quot; while &quot;Tosenpuron&quot; (the critics and reformation plan for politics) written by Banri HOASHI states as &quot;2,500,000&quot; koku.</e>
<cmt>1. 「この豊かさ」を「high production capacity of Sendai」としていますが、事実だとしても意訳です。また、ここでは前項目も引き継いでいると考えられ、米による収益によって蓄えられる豊という意味にとどめたほうが良いと思います。2. 書物の括弧内解説が不適切でした。両者とも修正しています。3. 語順修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wealth of Sendai Domain was widely known throughout Japan; &quot;Dokusyo-Yoteki&quot; (readings from a dripping of a pen) written by Sokken YASUI describes its territorial value as &quot;over 2,000,000 koku,&quot; while &quot;Tosenpuron&quot; (the critics and reformation plan for politics) written by Banri HOASHI states as &quot;2,500,000&quot; koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="226">
<j>政宗は幕府転覆を図るために、支倉常長を使者としてローマに派遣した（慶長遣欧使節）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune aimed at overthrow of the shogunate and dispatched Tsunenaga HASEKURA to Rome as an envoy (Keicho Mission).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plotting to overthrow bakufu, Masamune dispatched Tsunenaga HASEKURA to Rome as an ambassador (the Keicho era mission to Europe).</e>
<cmt>1. 「転覆を図るため」はより一般的な「plot to」に置き換え、名詞節として主語に置きました。2. この使節は大人数によるものでしたので、その長としての「ambassador」としました。3. 慶長遣欧使節は定訳に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plotting to overthrow bakufu, Masamune dispatched Tsunenaga HASEKURA to Rome as an ambassador (the Keicho era mission to Europe).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>このときのことを示す有力な史料もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some evidential historical records proved Masamune&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a convincing records describing this whole event in details.</e>
<cmt>1. 形容詞が連続し、ぎこちない訳です。修正しました。2. 「有力な」が欠けていますので追加しました。3. 「この時のことを示す」を「proved Masamune&apos;s intention」としていますが、「このときのこと」とは「使節派遣に関すること」の意味だと思います。意訳ですので修正しました。4. 現在形に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a convincing records describing this whole event in details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>支倉常長はローマとの軍事同盟交渉のとき、国王・フェリペ3世に対して、以下のように発言している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Tsunenaga HASEKURA was negotiating military alliance with Rome, he told King Felipe III about Masamune as follows;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Tsunenaga HASEKURA was negotiating with Rome for concluding military alliance, he told King Felipe III as follows;</e>
<cmt>1. 「軍事同盟交渉のとき」の訳に「for concluding」を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Tsunenaga HASEKURA was negotiating with Rome for concluding military alliance, he told King Felipe III as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>「政宗は勢力あり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Masamune has a strong influence.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Masamune has a strong influence.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Masamune has a strong influence.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>「また勇武にして、諸人が皆、皇帝となるべしと認める人なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also so brave, and everybody would like him to be a king.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;He is also known for his bravery, and everyone recognizes him as a person to be the emperor.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「so brave」は原文にない説明になっています。修正しました。2. 「正宗に王になって欲しい」というのは意訳であり誤訳です。「皇帝になるべき人物だと考えている」の意味であり修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;He is also known for his bravery, and everyone recognizes him as a person to be the emperor.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>「けだし日本においては、継承の権は一に武力によりて得るものなり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now in Japan, the seat of the ruler should be grabbed by power&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Essentially the right of succession is acquired by a force in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「けだし」は色々な意味がありますが、ここでは元来、本質的にの意味にとりました。「Now」はその意味で当てはまらないと思います。2. 「継承の権」の訳は実際に「継承権」を知るスペイン王に対しての説明として、きちんと説明されるべきです。意訳され、「王の座は力によって掴みとる」となっており、適切ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Essentially the right of succession is acquired by a force in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>また、仙台藩の庇護を受けていた宣教師のジェロニモ・デ・アンジェリスも、次のような手紙を本国に送っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A missionary, Jeronimo de Angelis, who was under the patronage of Sendai Domain, sent the following letter to his country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A missionary of Spain under the care of Sendai Domain, Jeronimo de Angelis also sent the following letter to his country;</e>
<cmt>1. 分節の多用を御純変更で避けました。2. 「庇護」の訳ですが、これは宣教師の記述であり、あまり経済的な支えの意味に近い「patronage」は適切ではありません。「care」を当てました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A missionary of Spain under the care of Sendai Domain, Jeronimo de Angelis also sent the following letter to his country;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="233">
<j>「テンカドノ（家康）は政宗がスペイン国王に遣わした使節のことを知っており、政宗はテンカに対して謀反を起こす気であると考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tenkadono (Ieyasu) already knew that Masamune dispatched a mission to the King of Spain and he thought that Masamune aimed at a rebellion against him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tenkadono (Ieyasu) was aware of the mission dispatched by Masamune to meet with the King of Spain, and he thought Masamune was thinking of a revolt against Tenka (Ieyasu, meaning the whole country).</e>
<cmt>1. 「使節」はここでは不定冠詞ではなく定冠詞が必要です。2. 「mission to the King of Spain」は多少説明不足と考え「to meet with」を加えています。3. 「aim at a rebellion」ですと「反逆を狙う」であり、反逆は目的で本来のゴールは天下ですので、語弊があります。「think of a revolt」としています。4. 「テンカ」は読みを表記し、その説明を加える形としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tenkadono (Ieyasu) was aware of the mission dispatched by Masamune to meet with the King of Spain, and he thought Masamune was thinking of a revolt against Tenka (Ieyasu, meaning the whole country).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>彼ら（家康・秀忠父子）は政宗がテンカに対して謀反を起こすため、スペイン国王およびキリシタンと手を結ぶ目的で大使（支倉常長）を派遣したと考えた」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They (Ieyasu and his son, Hidetada) thought that Masamune dispatched a envoy (Tsunenaga HASEKURA) to allied with the King of Spain and Christians, and it was preparation for a rebellion against Ieyasu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They (Ieyasu and his son, Hidetada) thought that Masamune dispatched an ambassador (Tsunenaga HASEKURA) to join hands with the King of Spain and Christian Authority, as a preparation for a revolt against Tenka.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「大使」とあり、派遣団の長の意味です。「envoy」は一人での使者に使われますので「ambassador」に変更しました。2. 「手を結ぶ」の「to allied with」は文法的に誤りです。ここは文字通り手を結ぶの形に修正しています。3. ここでの「キリシタン」は単にキリスト教信者という意味ではなく、その権威ですので、「Christian Authority」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They (Ieyasu and his son, Hidetada) thought that Masamune dispatched an ambassador (Tsunenaga HASEKURA) to join hands with the King of Spain and Christian Authority, as a preparation for a revolt against Tenka.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="235">
<j>支倉常長はローマ教皇にも謁見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunenaga HASEKURA also met the Pope.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunenaga HASEKURA was also granted an audience with the Pope.</e>
<cmt>1. 「謁見」を適切なものに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunenaga HASEKURA was also granted an audience with the Pope.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>この時代の日本人がローマ教皇に謁見した史実は、日本の外交史の中で特筆される実績である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that Japanese person met the Pope at that time was particularly notable in Japanese diplomatic history.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This historical fact, that a single Japanese person was allowed to meet with the Pope in this period of time, is an achievement worth mentioning among other events in the diplomatic history of Japan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「史実」を示すよう「historical fact」に修正しました。2. 「この時代の日本人がローマ教皇に謁見した」に含まれる意味は、「ある一人の日本人が教皇に謁見を許されたという事実」というものだと考え修正しています。3. 「特筆される実績である」の「実績」の訳が欠落しています。追加しました。4. 「外交史の中で特筆される」を適切なものに修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This historical fact, that a single Japanese person was allowed to meet with the Pope in this period of time, is an achievement worth mentioning among other events in the diplomatic history of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>また、今でもスペインのコリア・デル・リオには現地に留まった仙台藩士の末裔が多数存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some retainers of Sendai Domain remained in Spain, and even now, many of their descendants are still living in Coria del Rio.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many descendants of the retainers of Sendai Domain who remained and settled in Coria del Rio of Spain still exist there.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文の語順のままでつながっているため内容重要度が示せていない状態のため、修正しました。2.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many descendants of the retainers of Sendai Domain who remained and settled in Coria del Rio of Spain still exist there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>彼らは「日本」を意味する「ハポン」を姓として名乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They use &quot;Hapon&quot; which means &quot;Japan&quot; as their family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They have taken &quot;Harpoon&quot; as their family name, which means &quot;Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「名乗る」をより適切な形に修正しました。2. 関係代名詞「which」は通常、コンマで文章が分割された際に後の文章全体を付け加える際に用いられるのが通常です。直前の単語を受けるのであれば、この「which」ではなく、「whose」がここでは使えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They have taken &quot;Harpoon&quot; as their family name, which means &quot;Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="239">
<j>また、政宗は幕府軍と天下を賭けて戦うことになった場合には、という、幕府軍との決戦に備えた図上演習、すなわち作戦立案をしていたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And also it is said that Masamune prepared a map exercise, in a word, a war strategy named &quot;The strategy in case that Sendai was attacked&quot; in case that Masamune fought with the army of the shogunate for ruling of Japan.</e>
<cmt>調べましたが、「仙台御陣の御触に付御内試」のはっきりした現代語訳が見つからなかったので、ここから、377行目までは自分の解釈で翻訳させていただきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that Masamune thought of the scenario of the decisive battle against the army of bakufu seeking for the reign of Japan, then he was preparing a draft tactical strategy on a map for this battle as &quot;an internal tentative strategy upon the order of the council of war of Sendai Domain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「ここでの「また」は削除しました。2. 「仙台御陣の御触に付御内試」についてですが、「御陣」は正宗含む「軍事参謀」、「御触」は「命令」、「内試」は「演習立案」と考えました。訳文では「仙台が攻撃を受けた場合の戦略」となっていますが、文の流れからも明らかに誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Masamune thought of the scenario of the decisive battle against the army of bakufu seeking for the reign of Japan, then he was preparing a draft tactical strategy on a map for this battle as &quot;an internal tentative strategy upon the order of the council of war of Sendai Domain.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="240">
<j>「元和二年大坂御陣落去以後。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;After the fall of the Osaka-jo Casle in the 2nd year of the Genna era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;After the fall of the Osaka-jo Casle in the 2nd year of the Genna era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;After the fall of the Osaka-jo Casle in the 2nd year of the Genna era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>仙台出馬之由にて御陣触御座候。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">仙台出馬之由にて, the edict of rising in arms was issued.</e>
<cmt>仙台出馬之由にての解釈が分かりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Sendai Domain was going to participate in the war, the order was issued to prepare for going into the battle.</e>
<cmt>1. 「仙台出馬之由にて」は「仙台藩が参軍する事になった際」と訳しました。2. 出陣準備に「edict」はそぐわないため修正しました。3. 「出陣」を「rising in arms」は「挙兵」の意味であり、出陣の準備とは意味が異なります。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Sendai Domain was going to participate in the war, the order was issued to prepare for going into the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>此時貞山（政宗）様御内試に。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the map exercise of Teizan (Masamune).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this case study exercise with my lord Teizan (Masamune),</e>
<cmt>1. 「According to map exercise」は「この演習によると」の意味になります。ここは単に「〜において」の意味だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this case study exercise with my lord Teizan (Masamune),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>御家中の妻子人しち御取なされ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Take a wife and children of warlords hostage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">My lord gathered all the waves and children of Date vassals for this exercise to listen.</e>
<cmt>1.文章は「東奥老士夜話」という後の世の本に書かれている内容です。実際の試案かどうか明らかではないようで「夜話」の域の話なのか、事実に基づいているのかは定かではありません。ただ、これは「東奥」、すなわち「伊達家の女性の詰所での夜話として、「人質」とは実際に人質を取られるとかの意味ではなく、奥に住まう家中の者の妻子を捕まえて「御内試」について話をしたという意味ではないかと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">My lord gathered all the waves and children of Date vassals for this exercise to listen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>さて仙台川を藤塚閑上辺にてせき留藤塚へ番勢を被指置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Block water of the Sendai-gawa River at Fujizuka-Yuriage, and place the force at Fujizuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the war, Sendai troops blocks the water of the Sendai-gawa River at Fujizuka-Yuriage, and position a surveillance party at Fujizuka.</e>
<cmt>1. 「番勢」は見張りグループと考えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the war, Sendai troops blocks the water of the Sendai-gawa River at Fujizuka-Yuriage, and position a surveillance party at Fujizuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>御裏林より砂押へ御馬を被出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go from Ourabayashi to Sunaoshi on a horse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">My lord is supposed to move with troops from the woods behind the base to Sunaoshi.</e>
<cmt>1. 「御裏林」は地名ではないと思います。陣地の裏の林、の意味でしょうか。2. 「御馬」は正宗本人が、という意味でしょうか。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">My lord is supposed to move with troops from the woods behind the base to Sunaoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>砂押御鉄砲薬蔵の南の山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mountain located on the south of a storehouse of guns at Sunaoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sunaoshi is the mountain located on the south, storing guns and their ammunition.</e>
<cmt>1. これは前項目の説明だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sunaoshi is the mountain located on the south, storing guns and their ammunition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>にか峯に御旗を被立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the crest of the mountain, place flags.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the crest of the mountain, place flags of the Sendai troops.</e>
<cmt>1. 「仙台軍の旗」を意味するようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the crest of the mountain, place flags of the Sendai troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>御対陣可被成との御内試にて。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The map exercise targets a battle against the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once my lord considers possible to face with the enemy troops by the preparatory map exercise,</e>
<cmt>1. 「御対陣可被成との御内試にて」は「対陣できると軍議で判断なされたならば」としました。訳文は突然意味が元に戻っており、話の経過をたどれません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once my lord considers possible to face with the enemy troops by the preparatory map exercise,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>其節ひしと御裏林よりかの地へ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that case, go from Ourabayashi to a battle place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">then quietly, from the woods behind the base to that prepared battle field (Sunaoshi),</e>
<cmt>1. 「其節ひしと御裏林よりかの地へ」は「その時には静かに裏の林から準備された場所へ」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">then quietly, from the woods behind the base to that prepared battle field (Sunaoshi),</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>御出御見分被遊候」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">御出御見分被遊候&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処  すいません、解釈が分かりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">my lord shall move and observe yourself.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「御出御見分被遊候」は「おいでになり、見聞なされませ」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">my lord shall move and observe yourself.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>（仙台川（現在の名取川）を堰き止めて仙台南部を水浸しにして幕府軍の進軍を阻止し、さらに狭隘地に幕府軍を誘い込んで迎撃する。一方で、一揆衆を幕府軍後方で扇動し、後方を撹乱するつもりだった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Masamune planned to block water of the Sendai-gawa River (now Natori-gawa River) and flood a southern part of Sendai to stick the shogunate army, and then lead the shogunate army into a narrow place and siege them. In addition to that, Masamune planned to urge uprising to derange the base of the shogunate army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Masamune made a scheme to block the movement of bakufu army by flooding the southern part of Sendai after blocking the water of the Sendai-gawa River [today it is called Natori-gawa River], and then intercept the bakufu army by luring into a narrow place. In addition to that, Masamune planned to induce groups of ikki [revolt of peasants] to disturb the enemy into a confusion from behind.)</e>
<cmt>1. 「Masamune planned to〜」という訳だと直後の「block」にしかかかりません。「Masamune made a scheme〜」とし、計画全体の説明であることを明確にしています。2. 文の重要度からすると、a. 「幕府軍の進軍を阻止し」と b. 「迎撃する」が重要です。まず、a. を述べてからその方法である「堰き止め・洪水を起こす」の分節で修飾、また b. でも同様にしました。（語順変更のため青字で示しています）3. 「誘いこんで」を「lure」に変更しました。4. 「一揆衆を扇動し」を「induce groups of ikki」としました。5. 「後方を撹乱する」を「disturb the enemy into a confusion from behind」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Masamune made a scheme to block the movement of bakufu army by flooding the southern part of Sendai after blocking the water of the Sendai-gawa River [today it is called Natori-gawa River], and then intercept the bakufu army by luring into a narrow place. In addition to that, Masamune planned to induce groups of ikki [revolt of peasants] to disturb the enemy into a confusion from behind.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="252">
<j>「大軍を御引受。御境目之御一戦。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;大軍を御引受.</e>
<cmt>申し訳ございません、色々調べましたが、こちらの現代語訳や解釈が分かりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By facing with a large enemy troops, this will be the decisive battle to divide the fate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「大軍をお引き受けになる、」「この戦いは運の分かれ目となる御一戦となりましょう」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By facing with a large enemy troops, this will be the decisive battle to divide the fate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>「万一御おくれの刻。右に書付御内試之通。横川筋へ御馬を被入候節。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">万一御おくれの刻.</e>
<cmt>申し訳ございません、色々調べましたが、こちらの現代語訳や解釈が分かりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If my lord happened to be behind or lost in the battle, as described in this prepared strategy plan, it is the time my lord shall head for the Yoko-kawa River orientation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「万一御おくれの刻」は「万一遅れをとった時には」としました。「右に書付御内試之通」は「この書付に示された事前試案計画のとおりに、」としました。「横川筋へ御馬を被入候節」は「横川方面へ向かわれる時でございます」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If my lord happened to be behind or lost in the battle, as described in this prepared strategy plan, it is the time my lord shall head for the Yoko-kawa River orientation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>「御定かかりの地と申候。自然御運命尽夫も不被為叶時節に候はば。御最期之場と思召にて、瑞巌寺御菩提所に御取立被成候よし」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">御定かかりの地と申候.</e>
<cmt>申し訳ございません、色々調べましたが、こちらの現代語訳や解釈が分かりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I shall say this is a place the destiny of my lord would be settled, naturally, this means all the luck of my lord ran out and the wish can not be fulfilled, then it is the time when my lord shall head for the final destination, Zuigan-ji Temple as your soul will rest.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「御定かかりの地と申候」は「御運命の定まる地であると申しましょう」としました。「自然御運命尽夫も不被為叶時節に候はば」は「自然、御運も尽き、望みの叶う時ではないということでありましょうから、」としました。「御最期之場と思召にて、瑞巌寺御菩提所に御取立被成候よし」は「殿も最期の時とお考えになり、菩提である瑞巌寺にお向かいくださるがよろしいでしょう」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I shall say this is a place the destiny of my lord would be settled, naturally, this means all the luck of my lord ran out and the wish can not be fulfilled, then it is the time when my lord shall head for the final destination, Zuigan-ji Temple as your soul will rest.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>（政宗は幕府軍に敗れた場合は、松島瑞巌寺にて自害するつもりだった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(If Masamune had been beaten by the Shogunate troop, he would have committed suicide at the Zuigan-ji Temple in Matsushima).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In case if Masamune looses against the bakufu army, he was going to commit suicide at the Zuigan-ji Temple in Matsushima).</e>
<cmt>1. 「敗れる」を「be beaten」とするのはこうした大きな戦いの記述としては適切ではないと思います。「loose」と単純なものを選びました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In case if Masamune looses against the bakufu army, he was going to commit suicide at the Zuigan-ji Temple in Matsushima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>（『東奥老子夜話』より抜粋）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those Masamune&apos;s remarks were quoted from &quot;Tooroshi-yowa&quot; (Stories of Laozi in Too).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Quoted from &quot;Too roshi yowa&quot; [Bedtime story by an old man at the ladies&apos; chambers])</e>
<cmt>1. 上記したように、作者がわからず、これが正宗の言葉であるとの確証はないようです。奥での夜話ということで、それが可能なのは藩主である政宗である、と考えることもできますが、ある老人とのみ記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Quoted from &quot;Too roshi yowa&quot; [Bedtime story by an old man at the ladies&apos; chambers])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="257">
<j>しかし、政宗と親密であった徳川家の家臣、大久保長安が死後に一族もろとも処罰され（大久保長安事件）、娘婿の松平忠輝（家康の六男）が改易され、スペインとの同盟が不調に終わり、倒幕は実現されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, Masamune&apos;s ambition for overthrowing the shogunate was not realized for the reason that all the family of Nagayasu OKUBO, who was TOKUGAWA&apos;s subject and had a close relationship with Masamune, was punished after Nagayasu&apos;s death (Nagayasu OKUBO Incident), that Masamune&apos;s son-in-law, Tadateru MATSUDAIRA (6th son of Ieyasu) forfeited the status as a warlord, and that Masamune failed to ally with Spain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, his ambition to overthrow the bakufu was not realized since; Nagayasu OKUBO, who was a vassal of Tokugawa clan and had close relationship with Masamune, was punished after his death along with his all family members (Nagayasu OKUBO Incident); the son-in-law of Masamune, Tadateru MATSUDAIRA (6th son of Ieyasu) was deprived his status as a feudal lord and forfeited the territory; the attempt of Masamune to ally with Spain ended in failure.</e>
<cmt>1. 「but」による書き出しは上記全体を受け継いでいます。よって、「結果的には」に置き換えました。2. 3つの理由を「and」で結び冗長化するのを防ぐため、、「；」で各理由を区切っています。3. 「改易」は「大名としての立場の剥奪と領地の没収」としました。訳文は「立場の剥奪」のみになっています。4. 「スペインとの同盟が不調に終わり」はその原文に倣うよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, his ambition to overthrow the bakufu was not realized since; Nagayasu OKUBO, who was a vassal of Tokugawa clan and had close relationship with Masamune, was punished after his death along with his all family members (Nagayasu OKUBO Incident); the son-in-law of Masamune, Tadateru MATSUDAIRA (6th son of Ieyasu) was deprived his status as a feudal lord and forfeited the territory; the attempt of Masamune to ally with Spain ended in failure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="258">
<j>幕府は政宗存命中は、政宗がいつ謀叛を起こすかと常に警戒していたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Masamune was alive, the shogunate always suspected that Masamune would raise a rebellion and was keeping an eye on Masamune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered bakufu was always keeping an eye on Masamune while he was alive, whether he would rise in revolt against bakufu or not.</e>
<cmt>1. 「幕府は」とここでの主語は政宗ではなく幕府です。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered bakufu was always keeping an eye on Masamune while he was alive, whether he would rise in revolt against bakufu or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="259">
<j>家康晩年の元和 (日本)2年（1616年）1月23日のイギリス商館長・リチャード・コックスの日記では、以下のように記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Ieyasu&apos;s later years, on January 23, 1616, the head of the British East India Company, Richard Cocks wrote in his diary as follows;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 10, 1616, during the late years of Ieyasu, the director of a British merchant office in Japan, Richard Cocks wrote in his diary as follows;</e>
<cmt>1. 「イギリス商館長・リチャード・コックス」を「the head of the British East India Company」としていますが、これでは「イギリス東インド会社長官」とでもなってしまいます。そのような事実はありませんので修正しました。2. 旧暦のままになっていましたので修正しました。3. 商館は日本にあるの意味を意訳し追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 10, 1616, during the late years of Ieyasu, the director of a British merchant office in Japan, Richard Cocks wrote in his diary as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>「風評によれば、戦争は今や皇帝（家康）とその子カルサ様（松平上総介忠輝）との間で起こらんとし、義父政宗殿は、カルサ殿の後援をなすべし云々」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;According to rumors, the battle between the King (Ieyasu) and his son, Karusa (Kazusa no suke Tadateru MATSUDAIRA) was about to break out, and Karusa&apos;s father-in-law, Masamune would side with Karusa&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;According to rumors, the war between the Emperor (Ieyasu) and his son, lord Karusa (Kazusa no suke [Governor of Kazusa Province] Tadateru MATSUDAIRA) was about to break out, and the father-in-law of lord Karusa, Masamune would give support for lord Karusa&quot;.</e>
<cmt>1. 「上総の介」の説明を加えました。2. 「殿」を「lord〜」で示しました。「Sir」と同様、重要かと思います。3. 「後援」は「〜の側につく」の意味の一部ですが、それより弱い「支援」の意味ですので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;According to rumors, the war between the Emperor (Ieyasu) and his son, lord Karusa (Kazusa no suke [Governor of Kazusa Province] Tadateru MATSUDAIRA) was about to break out, and the father-in-law of lord Karusa, Masamune would give support for lord Karusa&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="261">
<j>寛永5年（1628年）3月12日、政宗は徳川秀忠を仙台藩江戸屋敷に招待して供応した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 12, 1628, Masamune invited Hidetada TOKUGAWA to Sendai Domain&apos;s office in Edo and entertained him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 16, 1628, Masamune invited Hidetada TOKUGAWA to the Edo office of Sendai Domain and entertained him.</e>
<cmt>1. 旧暦を修正しています。1628年4月16日2. 仙台藩江戸屋敷を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 16, 1628, Masamune invited Hidetada TOKUGAWA to the Edo office of Sendai Domain and entertained him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>このとき、政宗自らが秀忠の前に膳を運んだのだが、そのとき秀忠側近の内藤正重が、「伊達殿に鬼見（毒見）をしてほしい」と声をかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the visit, Masamune served dishes to Hidetada by himself, but seeing that, Masashige NAITO who was a close associate of Hidetada said &quot;I&apos;d like Masamune to take food to confirm that it did not contain poisons&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the visit, Masamune himself served dishes to Hidetada; then the close vassal of Hidetada, Masashige NAITO spoke to Masamune saying, &quot;I&apos;d like you lord Masamune to taste food before serving for proving poison free.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. これも先述同様、「by himself」の誤用です。「served himself」と修正しました。2. 「毒見」は「taste food before serving」でその意味を表すそうなのですが、一応「for proving poison free」を追加しました。3. 「声をかけた」の意味となるよう「spoke to Masamune」を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the visit, Masamune himself served dishes to Hidetada; then the close vassal of Hidetada, Masashige NAITO spoke to Masamune saying, &quot;I&apos;d like you lord Masamune to taste food before serving for proving poison free.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>政宗はこれに対して、激怒して以下のように返答したと、『政宗公御名語集』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Masamune&apos;s great remarks&quot;, Masamune was outraged by Masashige&apos;s request and said as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;the wise saying of the lord Masamune,&quot; it is described that Masamune was outraged by this request and responded as follows;</e>
<cmt>1. 「に記されている」を加えました。2. 「〜のように返答した」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;the wise saying of the lord Masamune,&quot; it is described that Masamune was outraged by this request and responded as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>「外記（正重）言はれぬ事を被申候。政宗程の者が御成を申自身御膳を上るうへ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I heard what the Secretary (Masashige) said. But, the lord, Masamune came to serve dishes by myself.&apos;&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State [Masashige]) speaks of unreasonable thing when someone such as Masamune asked your visit and serves dishes myself.&apos;</e>
<cmt>1. 「外記（正重）言はれぬ事を被申候」は「外記は理由のないことを言われます」としました。2. 「外記」は定訳のものに修正しました。3. 「政宗程の者が御成を申自身御膳を上るうへ」は「政宗のような者がおいで頂くようお申し出し、膳を自身で給仕するようなこの機会に、」としました。4. 「by myself」の誤用を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State [Masashige]) speaks of unreasonable thing when someone such as Masamune asked your visit and serves dishes myself.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="265">
<j>「おにする（毒見する）所にてはなきぞ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It&apos;s disgraceful that you ordered me to confirm the dishes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is not the occasion necessary to test dishes for poisoning.&apos;</e>
<cmt>1. 「おにする（毒見する）所にてはなきぞ」は「毒見をするような席ではありませんぞ」としました。訳文は「貴殿が毒見をお命じになるとはなんとも不名誉である」という意味の意訳で、内容的に誤っていると思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is not the occasion necessary to test dishes for poisoning.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>「御膳に毒を入るるは、早十年前の事なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If it had been 10 years ago, I could have plotted to put poison into dishes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Putting poison is an old method used 10 years ago in unstable time.&apos;</e>
<cmt>1. 「御膳に毒を入るるは、早十年前の事なり」が「10年前であれば自分も食事に毒を入れる索を練ったかもしれない」という意訳になっていますが、これは次の項目と矛盾します。「10年前、時代が不安定だった時の方法だ」の意味にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Putting poison is an old method used 10 years ago in unstable time.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="267">
<j>「十年前にも,日本の神かけて毒などにて。殺し奉るべきとは夢々思はぬぞ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, even 10 years ago, I swear by god. I never killed someone by poisoning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereas even 10 years ago, I swear to gods of Japan that I would never utilize a cowardly method such as poisoning, and never think of murdering.&apos;</e>
<cmt>1.次項目に続くにせよ 「毒などにて」までは原文に含まれており、訳出しました。2. 「日本の神かけて」で「I swea by god」としていますが、「swear to gods」の誤りです。前置詞用法、及び日本の神は複数です。日本の神としているのはキリスト教禁止後の日本では重要ではないでしょうか。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereas even 10 years ago, I swear to gods of Japan that I would never utilize a cowardly method such as poisoning, and never think of murdering.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>「一度は乗寄てこそとは思ひ候」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When I killed people, it was always in combat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I will go into the battle and fight myself at least once.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「一度は乗寄てこそとは思ひ候」を「人を殺すときは、常に戦いによる」と訳しています。この訳ですと「人」が秀忠など特定の人物ではなくなっていますし、実際には「もし徳川家と戦う機会があったならば、一度は合戦し自ら出陣して」の意味だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I will go into the battle and fight myself at least once.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="269">
<j>つまり、10年前の元和4年（1618年）なら、（徳川幕府の基盤がまだ磐石ではなかったため）謀反を起こす気もあったが、その時でさえ、この政宗は毒殺などというせせこましいことはせず、一槍交えて戦おうとしただろうと言っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It meant that if it had been 10 years ago (1618), (since the reign of Tokugawa Shogunate was not settled yet) Masamune could have plotted to raise a rebellion, but even 10 years ago, Masamune did not use cowardly measures such as poisoning, and I always fought a battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, he was saying that Masamune would have plotted a revolt if it was 10 years ago (1618), (since the foundation of Tokugawa Shogunate was not stable and solid yet), but Masamune would not utilize such trivial method as poisoning even at that time, but to fight directly in a battle.</e>
<cmt>1. 過去完了仮定の構文ですが、両方が過去完了形になっており文法的に誤りです。修正しました。2. 「一槍交えて戦おうとしただろう」の仮定形が失われていますので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, he was saying that Masamune would have plotted a revolt if it was 10 years ago (1618), (since the foundation of Tokugawa Shogunate was not stable and solid yet), but Masamune would not utilize such trivial method as poisoning even at that time, but to fight directly in a battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>正重を厳しく叱責しているのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune rebuked Masashige sharply.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is that Masamune rebuked Masashige.</e>
<cmt>1. rebukeには強く非難するの意味があります。「sharply」を加えると２重説明になりますので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is that Masamune rebuked Masashige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="271">
<j>秀忠は御簾の向こうでこのやりとりを聞き、「さすがは伊達の親父殿よ」と涙したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi heard their conversation behind a bamboo blind and shed a tear being impressed and said, &quot;That&apos;s Date&apos;s lord&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetada heard their exchanges behind a bamboo blind, and shed tears in saying, &quot;that is just what the lord Date, a lofty, admirable man.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「秀忠」が「秀吉」になっています。2. 「shead a tear」は誤用だと思います。通常「shead tears」の複数形を用います。3. 「さすがは伊達の親父殿よ」の訳は、もう少々意味が強調される形としました。「a lofty, admirable man」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetada heard their exchanges behind a bamboo blind, and shed tears in saying, &quot;that is just what the lord Date, a lofty, admirable man.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="272">
<j>徳川秀忠は寛永9年（1632年）1月に死去したが、このとき秀忠は政宗を枕元に呼び、次のように述べたと『政宗公御名語集』にはある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Masamune&apos;s great remarks&quot;, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, who died in January, 1632, called Masamune in his last extremity and said as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;the wise saying of the lord Masamune,&quot; Hidetada TOKUGAWA, who died in January, 1632, called Masamune at his deathbed and spoke as follows;</e>
<cmt>1. 政宗公御名語は先述どおりにしました。2. 死去した際の意味は、「his last extremity」と訳されていますが、絶体絶命の意味の訳はそぐわないと思います。「死の床」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;the wise saying of the lord Masamune,&quot; Hidetada TOKUGAWA, who died in January, 1632, called Masamune at his deathbed and spoke as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="273">
<j>「年月より病気次第に心重く覚候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I&apos;m suffering my illness which was getting worse from year to year.</e>
<cmt>調べましたが、はっきりした現代語訳が見つからなかったので、自分の解釈で翻訳させていただきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After suffering for long years, my illness has gradually made me feel depressed.&apos;</e>
<cmt>1. 「年月より病気次第に心重く覚候」は「年月が経つにつれ病気が心に次第に重く感じるように思います」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After suffering for long years, my illness has gradually made me feel depressed.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="274">
<j>「兎角して快気難成覚候間。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">My illness imperceptibly became so difficult to be cured.</e>
<cmt>調べましたが、はっきりした現代語訳が見つからなかったので、自分の解釈で翻訳させていただきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, I feel it is difficult to fully recover from this illness any more.&apos;</e>
<cmt>1. 「兎角して快気難成覚候間」は「いずれにせよ、もう回復するのは難しいと感じます」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, I feel it is difficult to fully recover from this illness any more.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="275">
<j>「少も本心の有内に。其方へ掛御目度事は昔より今日至迄。御心指一ツとしてわするる事なし。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although I did not hope that at all. I have been giving preferential treatment to you until today. Never forget my will.</e>
<cmt>調べましたが、はっきりした現代語訳が見つからなかったので、自分の解釈で翻訳させていただきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the time I have my consciousness, every happy events and incidents between you and me from the past until today, Lord Hidetada did not even forget any details of our happy times.&apos;</e>
<cmt>1. 「少も本心の有内に」は訳文の「それを望んだわけでは少しもないが」という意味ではなく、「少しでも正気な意識のある間に」という意味だと思います。全体書き直しました。2. 「其方へ掛御目度事は昔より今日至迄」は「昔から今日にいたるまでのそなたに関わるめでたい事は、」の意味で、原文の「今日まで自分はそなたに特別な待遇を与えてきた」は誤訳だと思います。3. 「御心指一ツとしてわするる事なし」は「そのお心は些細にいたるまで、忘れてはいなかった」という意味としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the time I have my consciousness, every happy events and incidents between you and me from the past until today, Lord Hidetada did not even forget any details of our happy times.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="276">
<j>大御所（家康）様駿河の御殿にて御病気重き折節悪き者の申入候にて、己に其方謀反のよし其聞へ候間。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ogosho (Ieyasu) was on his deathbed at the Sunpu-jo Castle, a bad person told to Ieyasu that you plotted to raise a rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the illness of my lord Ogosho (Ieyasu) was serious and he was held at his residence in the Sunpu-jo Castle, an ill-informed person told us that you rose in revolt against bakufu.</e>
<cmt>1. 下記説明項目があり、そこでは「死の床」とありますが、ここは「後病気重き折」とあり、「病気が重い時」とあります。原文に合わせ修正しました。2. 「筋悪き者」は「悪い者」というよりは、「事情に詳しくない者」という意味かと思います。「ill-informed person」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the illness of my lord Ogosho (Ieyasu) was serious and he was held at his residence in the Sunpu-jo Castle, an ill-informed person told us that you rose in revolt against bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="277">
<j>我等も御病気にもかまはず奥州へと心掛候」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keep in your mind that we also would invade Oshu despite my illness&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then we could not care less, thus we were going to head for Oshu in such case, even though my lord Ogosho was still in sickbed.</e>
<cmt>1. 「我等も御病気にもかまはず奥州へと心掛候」は「（秀忠含む）我々も家康様のご病気にもかまっていられずに奥州へ向かうことを想定した」という意味かと思います。訳文は、現在仮定の形になっており、「（そなたに謀反の動きがあるならば） 私（秀忠）が病気であるとしても我々（幕府）は奥州へ攻め入るだろうことを心にとどめ置かれよ」の意味です。ここでは彼らは昔話をしており、次項目の説明からもあるように家康が死の床にあった時の話をしているので、訳文は意訳でまた誤訳であると思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then we could not care less, thus we were going to head for Oshu in such case, even though my lord Ogosho was still in sickbed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="278">
<j>（家康が駿府城で死の床に臥していたとき、政宗が謀反を起こすという噂が立ったので、家康は自分の病気にかまわず奥州討伐のための軍を起こそうとしていた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(When Ieyasu was on his deathbed at the Sunpu-jo Castle, he heard a rumor that Masamune would raise a rebellion, so he tried to rise in arms to invade Oshu despite his illness.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(When Ieyasu was on his deathbed at the Sunpu-jo Castle, he heard a rumor that Masamune would rise in revolt, thus Ieyasu was going to organize a punitive force to Oshu regardless of his illness.</e>
<cmt>1. 「奥州討伐」は「invade Oshu」とありますが、これだと「討伐」ではなく「侵略」になり、目的が違いますので「punitive force to Oshu」に修正しました。2. 「軍を起こそうとしていた」を「tried to rise in arms」とありますが、「〜しようとしていた」を「tried to」と訳すと「〜する可能性があったが（計画などだけで）しなかった」の意味が消え、「何らかの行動は起こした」となってしまいます。「was going to organize」を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(When Ieyasu was on his deathbed at the Sunpu-jo Castle, he heard a rumor that Masamune would rise in revolt, thus Ieyasu was going to organize a punitive force to Oshu regardless of his illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="279">
<j>晩年の政宗は、『酔余口号』という漢詩を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune wrote a Chinese poem &quot;Suiyo-Kogo&quot; (impromptu poems that people write when they are drunk) in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his late years, Masamune left a Kanshi (Chinese-style poem) &quot;Suiyo-Kogo&quot; (impromptu poems that people write when they are drunk).</e>
<cmt>1. 「漢詩」は「かんし」の音読みを表記し、括弧で説明する形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his late years, Masamune left a Kanshi (Chinese-style poem) &quot;Suiyo-Kogo&quot; (impromptu poems that people write when they are drunk).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="280">
<j>「馬上少年過、世平白髪多、残躯天所赦、不楽是如何。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;馬上少年過、世平白髪多、残躯天所赦、不楽是如何.&apos;</e>
<cmt>詩の意味が下の行で説明されているので、この行は訳さず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Bajo ni shonen sugi, yo tairanishite hakuhatsu oosi, zannku ha tenno yurusu tokoro, tanoshimazareba kore ikan&apos;</e>
<cmt>1. 「下記で説明があるので訳さず」とありますが、読みを表記する必要はあります。定かではありませんが一応推測しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Bajo ni shonen sugi, yo tairanishite hakuhatsu oosi, zannku ha tenno yurusu tokoro, tanoshimazareba kore ikan&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="281">
<j>前半の三句は以下のように解釈できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First 3 paragraphs can be translated as follows;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First three phrases csan be interpreted as follows;</e>
<cmt>1. 「句」を「paragraph」としていますが誤訳であり、正しくは「phrase」になります。2. 「解釈」は「translation」ではなく「interpretation」に変更しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First three phrases can be interpreted as follows;</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>「若い頃は馬に乗って戦場を駆け抜けたが、世は太平になり自分にも白髪が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;When I was young, I run around on horseback in a battlefield, but now the peaceful period came and my hair was gradually turning gray.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;When I was young, I run through battlefields on a horseback, but once the world became peaceful, I grew old and my hair gradually turned gray.</e>
<cmt>1. 「駆け抜けた」の意味を出すために、「run around」（駆けまわる）ではなく「ran through」としました。また現在形となっており、ここでは過去形が正しいため修正しました。2. 「自分にも白髪が増えた」は「I grew old」の意訳を追加しました。なお、すでに余生を送っている老人の句ととして、「白髪が増えた」は既に過去形と考えました。訳は過去進行形となっており、「今、世は太平となり」の訳（now)との時制ともそろっておらず、適切ではないと考えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;When I was young, I run through battlefields on a horseback, but once the world became peaceful, I grew old and my hair gradually turned gray.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="283">
<j>天に与えられた余生が残ってはいるが」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though I was given a little more time by heaven.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though there is some time left for me to spend as heaven allowed,</e>
<cmt>1. 「余生が残っている」の原文にあわせ、「there is some time left for me to spend」としました。訳文でも良いかと思いますが、余生の意味が弱いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though there is some time left for me to spend as heaven allowed,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>しかし最後の句は「楽しまずんば是いかん（これを楽しまずしてどうしようか）」あるいは「楽しまず是如何に（楽しいとは思えないのはどうしたことか）」と全く違う二通りの解釈ができてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the last paragraph can be translated in completely different 2 ways such as &quot;I cannot help enjoying the rest of my life&quot; or &quot;But I cannot enjoy the rest of my life&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the last phrase allows two completely different ways of interpretation as &quot;what am I supposed to do without enjoying it,&quot; or &quot;what is the reason that I cannot enjoy it?&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「But」による書き出しを修正しました。(なおコンマもないため、この文章が独立した文章でなく、別の文につながる文または文節としないと文法的にも誤りになります。2. 「全く違う二通り」の訳は直訳されており、「completely different 2 ways」となっており、文章として適切でないものになっています（同時に、二通りを2 wayと数字で表しているのも適切ではありません）3. 二通りの解釈ですが、漢文の原文は、「是如何」により疑問の形をとったものです。それは明確にされるべきと考えました。そのため訳文はどちらも説明不足の気がします。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the last phrase allows two completely different ways of interpretation as &quot;what am I supposed to do without enjoying it,&quot; or &quot;what is the reason that I cannot enjoy it?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="285">
<j>政宗自身がどちらともとれるように作ったとも言われているが、政宗の残した大きな謎となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Masamune intentionally wrote the last paragraph in the way that they could be translated in different meanings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Masamune intentionally composed the last phrase in such manner in order to leave the room for interpretation in either way; this is a big mystery, which Masamune left.</e>
<cmt>1. ここでの「作った」は詩作の意味ですので、「compose」を用いました。2. 「paragraph」「translate」を先述同様修正しました。3. 「政宗の残した大きな謎となっている」が訳出されていません。追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Masamune intentionally composed the last phrase in such manner in order to leave the room for interpretation in either way; this is a big mystery, which Masamune left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="286">
<j>仙台城は山城で平和な世の治世には適さぬとして、自分の死後、平城へ移ることを奨めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune thought that a castle built on the mountain top like the Sendai-jo castle was not convenient to live in the peaceful period, and recommended his family to transfer to another castle built on flat land after he was dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune recommended his family members and vassals to move to a castle built on a flat land after his death, since he thought such mountain castle as the Sendai-jo castle was not suitable for governing in a peaceful times.</e>
<cmt>1. 意味内容の重要度を考え文節・語順変更しています。2. 冠詞の用法が非常に不適切です。追加もしくは変更しています。3. 「平和な世の治世には適さぬ」は「not convenient」ではなく、「not suitable for governing in a peaceful times」としました。「治世」の意味が抜け落ちていると思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune recommended his family members and vassals to move to a castle built on a flat land after his death, since he thought such mountain castle as the Sendai-jo castle was not suitable for governing in a peaceful times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="287">
<j>逆に言えば生前は死の前まで天下を取る野心を捨てていなかったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But this story also indicates that Masamune did not give up being a ruler of Japan until he was dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, this indicates and allows to say that Masamune did not give up his ambition in his lifetime until the moment of his death, to acquire the right of ruling Japan.</e>
<cmt>1. 「逆に言えば」を「In other words」のフレーズに言い換えました。2. 「〜といわれる」の推定形がここでも使われています。「allows to say」を加え、この意味に近い形としました。3. 「生前は死の前まで」について、「until he was dead」としていますが、「生前」が抜け落ちていますし、「死の前まで」の意味とは微妙に違います。この言葉を残したことからも死の前にはさすがに諦めたという意味になりますので、「until he was dead」とすると結局死ぬまで諦めず、その野望は死をもって潰えたという意味になり原文と異なります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, this indicates and allows to say that Masamune did not give up his ambition in his lifetime until the moment of his death, to acquire the right of ruling Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="288">
<j>上述のように隙あらば天下を取ろうと狙っていた彼は、中央から常に警戒されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore Masamune, who was always aiming at the seat of the ruler, was always kept an eye on by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, Masamune, who persistently sought for acquiring the right of ruling in any possible opportunity, was cautiously watched by bakufu all the time.</e>
<cmt>1. 「上述のように」が抜け落ちていましたので追加しました。2. 「隙あらば天下を取ろうと狙っていた」は「persistently sought for acquiring the right of ruling in any possible opportunity」と修正しました。「always aiming at the seat of the ruler」は意訳ですし、露骨に狙っていたの意味が強くなります。3. また意訳により「隙あらば」が抜け落ちていますので追加しました。4. 「was always kept an eye on by」は結果的に前置詞が重なるなどぎこちないものになっています。「was cautiously watched by bakufu all the time」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, Masamune, who persistently sought for acquiring the right of ruling in any possible opportunity, was cautiously watched by bakufu all the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="289">
<j>彼は「あと20年早く生まれていれば……（天下が取れたのに）」と悔しがっていたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was always chagrined and said &quot;If I was born 20 years earlier (I could be the ruler of Japan)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was always chagrined and said, &quot;if only I was born twenty years earlier... (I could conquer Japan)&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「〜といわれる」を追加しました。2. クオテーションマークによる会話が始まる前に、コンマを追加しています。3. 「if only I was born twenty years earlier」と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was always chagrined and said, &quot;if only I was born twenty years earlier... (I could conquer Japan)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="290">
<j>その一方で、家光の代においては「かつては天下を狙っていたが、今は家光を支える立場である」という事を示す逸話が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is an anecdote that during Iemitsu&apos;s regime, Masamune said &quot;I used to aim at the seat of the shogun, but now I supported Iemitsu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there is an anecdote describing his opinion, quoted as &quot;once I sought for acquiring the right of ruling Japan, but now I am in the position to support Iemitsu&quot; when bakufu came under the administration of Iemitsu.</e>
<cmt>1. 逸話が「見られる」をan anecdote describing his opinion, quoted as」で示しました。2. 「now I supported」は時制が定まらず文法的に誤りです。修正しました。3. 「家光の代においては」は「when bakufu came under the administration of Iemitsu」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there is an anecdote describing his opinion, quoted as &quot;once I sought for acquiring the right of ruling Japan, but now I am in the position to support Iemitsu&quot; when bakufu came under the administration of Iemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="291">
<j>家光の就任の宣言は以下のような大変威圧的なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Iemitsu succeeded to the shogun, he made the following pretty highhanded declaration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inaugural speech addressed by Iemitsu for succeeding the position of shogun was highly overbearing one as follows;</e>
<cmt>1. 就任の際の宣言は「innaugural speech」としました。2. 「大変」を「pretty」で訳していますが、口語的です。「highly」を通常用います。3. 「highhanded」は「high-handed」です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inaugural speech addressed by Iemitsu for succeeding the position of shogun was highly overbearing one as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="292">
<j>「祖父、父とは違い、自分は生まれながらの将軍であるから、大名方は今後は臣従の礼をとるべきだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Unlike my grandfather and father, I&apos;m a born shogun, so every lord should pay deference to me as a subject from now.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Unlike my grandfather and father, I am shogun by birth, therefore every feudal lord shall swear allegiance and show deference to me from now on.</e>
<cmt>1. 「生まれながらの将軍」を「I am shogun by birth」としました。2. 「臣従」は「swear allegiance」を加え、その「礼をとるべき」で「show deference」を意味するようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Unlike my grandfather and father, I am shogun by birth, therefore every feudal lord shall swear allegiance and show deference to me from now on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="293">
<j>異論があるならば国へ帰り戦の準備をされよ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;If you raise an objection to my decision, go back to your domain and prepare for a battle against me&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you raise an objection, go back to your country and prepare for a war against me.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. マイナーですが、文頭のクオテーションを削除しました。2. 「戦」は一戦ではなく戦争と考え、「battle」から「war」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you raise an objection, go back to your country and prepare for a war against me.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="294">
<j>政宗はこれに対し「政宗はもとより、異論のある者などおるはずがありませぬ」と即座に継ぎ、その場の皆が平伏したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune promptly responded to Iemitsu, &quot;Not only Masamune but also everybody never have an objection&quot;, and all who were there prostrated themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To those words of Iemitsu, it is said that Masamune immediately responded saying, &quot;there is no way anyone here has objection to your lord, of course Masamune as well,&quot; and everyone presented at the inauguration prostrated themselves.</e>
<cmt>1. 「即座に」は「immediately」に変更しました。2. 政宗の言葉は全体書き直しました。「everybody」と「have」、「but」と「everybody」の用法など、文法的にも多々問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To those words of Iemitsu, it is said that Masamune immediately responded saying, &quot;there is no way anyone here has objection to your lord, of course Masamune as well,&quot; and everyone presented at the inauguration prostrated themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="295">
<j>この家光の発言は政宗の助言によるものだったとも、あるいは幕閣が政宗に予め根回して即座に返答するよう依頼したとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some theories about this declaration, one is that Iemitsu made this declaration on Masamune&apos;s advice and another is that Iemitsu&apos;s subject asked Masamune in advance to reply to Iemitsu&apos;s declaration promptly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some possibilities regarding the context of this incident, as one states this speech of Iemitsu was based on the advice of Masamune, or another suggests the cabinet members of bakufu asked Masamune in advance to reply to the words of Iemitsu on the spot.</e>
<cmt>1. 「この出来事の背景に関して」というフレーズを加え、理解しやすくしています。2. 「〜とも言われている」がここでは「There are some theories」と訳されていますが、「theories」は「possibilities」で置き換えました。3. 「幕閣」は「cabinet members of bakufu」としました。4. 「即座に」はここでは「on the spot」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some possibilities regarding the context of this incident, as one states this speech of Iemitsu was based on the advice of Masamune, or another suggests the cabinet members of bakufu asked Masamune in advance to reply to the words of Iemitsu on the spot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="296">
<j>家光が鷹狩に没頭し、下宿（外泊）を頻繁に行うのに困った幕閣が政宗に説得を頼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Iemitsu became absorbed in falconry and repeatedly stayed out, Iemitsu&apos;s subjects were bothered by his behavior and asked Masamune to convince Iemitsu to stop staying out.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When cabinet members of bakufu were at a loss, since Iemitsu was enthusiastic about falconry and frequently away overnight, they requested Masamune to persuade Iemitsu to stop being away overnight.</e>
<cmt>1. 「外泊」は「stay out」とすると「手を出さない、関わりを持たない」の意味で適切ではありません。「be away overnight」という慣用句を用いました。その他より適切と思われる語、フレーズに修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When cabinet members of bakufu were at a loss, since Iemitsu was enthusiastic about falconry and frequently away overnight, they requested Masamune to persuade Iemitsu to stop being away overnight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="297">
<j>正宗は家光にに言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Masamune said to Iemitsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune told Iemitsu.</e>
<cmt>1. 「言った」はある命令の意味が込められていますので、その意味を持つ「told」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune told Iemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="298">
<j>「下宿はお止め下さい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Please stop staying out.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I would like you to stop being away overnight.</e>
<cmt>1. 「Please〜」は懇願の意味が強いため、より厳しく説得の意味とするため「I would like you to stop〜」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I would like you to stop being away overnight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="299">
<j>私も家康公の御首を何度か狙ったことがございます」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I had tried to murder Ieyasu several times when he stayed out&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I used to try taking the life of lord Ieyasu in such occasion.&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. 「家康公」の尊敬形にするため「lord Ieyasu」としました。2. 訳文では「家康公が外泊したときに」と断定していますが、ここでははっきりそのように示されていませんので、「in such occasion」でぼかしつつ暗示するようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I used to try taking the life of lord Ieyasu in such occasion.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="300">
<j>すると、以後下宿を行わなくなったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Iemitsu stopped staying out.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Iemitsu stopped being away overnight.</e>
<cmt>1. 先述と同様の「外泊」の修正です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Iemitsu stopped being away overnight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List of Masamune&apos;s careers and job grades</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The career record of his official titles and court ranks</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The career record of his official titles and court ranks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="301">
<j>※日付＝旧暦（明治5年12月2日まで）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* Dates are according to the old calendar (until December 2, 1872)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Dates are according to the old calendar (until December 2, 1872)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Dates are according to the old calendar (until December 2, 1872)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>天正12年（1584年）10月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, 1584</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October, 1584</e>
<cmt>1. Inは削除しています</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October, 1584</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="302">
<j>- 家督継承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succession to the family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succession to the family headship</e>
<cmt>1. 「家督」を意味付記しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succession to the family headship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>天正13年（1585年）閏8月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the leap month August, 1585</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The intercalary month, August of 1585</e>
<cmt>1. 旧暦でのうるう調整ですので、leap monthよりはっきりと調整月を意味する「intercalary」を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The intercalary month, August of 1585</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="303">
<j>- 従五位美作国に叙任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appointed the Junior Fifth Rank, and the Governor of Mimasaka Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the title of jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and was appointed as the Governor of Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。2. 「位」について、ルールに則り修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the title of jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) and was appointed as the Governor of Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>天正14年（1586年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1586</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1586</e>
<cmt>1. Inは削除しています</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1586</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="304">
<j>- 左京大夫に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reassigned the Master of Eastern Capital Office</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was transferred as sakyo no daibu (the Master of Eastern Capital Office)</e>
<cmt>1. 「Reassign」は再任の意味だと思います。対訳通り転任の訳としました。2. 左京大夫は通常の「読み」＋解説の形としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was transferred as sakyo no daibu (the Master of Eastern Capital Office)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>天正19年（1591年）3月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, 1591</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March, 1591</e>
<cmt>1. Inは削除しています</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March, 1591</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="305">
<j>- 侍従に遷任し、越前国を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appointed the Chamberlain and the Governor of Echizen Province at the same time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was transferred as jijyu (the Chamberlain) and he also served as the Governor of Echizen Province at the same time.</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。2. 「位」について、ルールに則り修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was transferred as jijyu (the Chamberlain) and he also served as the Governor of Echizen Province at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="306">
<j>羽柴氏の苗字を関白豊臣秀吉から授かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allowed to use the family name &quot;HASHIBA&quot; by the chief adviser to the Emperor, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the family name of &quot;Hashiba&quot; (the original family name of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) from kanpaku (the Chancellor, the chief adviser to the Emperor) Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。2. 位について、ルールに則り修正しました。3. 「羽柴」の意味を追加しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the family name of &quot;Hashiba&quot; (the original family name of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) from kanpaku (the Chancellor, the chief adviser to the Emperor) Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>慶長2年（1597年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1597</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1597</e>
<cmt>1. Inは削除しています</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1597</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="307">
<j>- 従四位に昇叙し、近衛府に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to the Junior Fourth Rank, and transferred to the Division of Inner Palace Guards</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and was transferred to Konoefu (the Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。2. 「位」について、ルールに則り修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) and was transferred to Konoefu (the Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="308">
<j>越前守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Continuously, remained the Governor of Echizen Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to remain as the Governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to remain as the Governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>慶長13年（1608年）1月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, 1608</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January, 1608</e>
<cmt>1. Inは削除しています</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January, 1608</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="309">
<j>- 陸奥国を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doubled as the Governor of Mutsu Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the post of the Governor of Mutsu Province in addition to the post of the Governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>1. 「doubled」の用法は適切ではありません。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the post of the Governor of Mutsu Province in addition to the post of the Governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>越前守任替。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigned the Governor of Echizen Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned from the post of the Governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。2. 前置詞追加しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned from the post of the Governor of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="311">
<j>松平氏の苗字を第2代征夷大将軍徳川秀忠より授かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allowed to use the family name &quot;MATSUDAIRA&quot; by the 2nd Seiitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary), Hidetada TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the family name of &quot;Matsudaira&quot; from the 2nd Seiitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary), Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the family name of &quot;Matsudaira&quot; from the 2nd Seiitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary), Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="312">
<j>元和 (日本)元年（1615年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1615</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1615</e>
<cmt>1. Inは削除しています</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1615</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>閏6月19日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the leap month, June 19</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The intercalary month June, 19</e>
<cmt>1. 書式変更とうるうの単語変更しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The intercalary month June, 19</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="313">
<j>- 正四位に昇叙し、参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to the Senior Fourth Rank and appointed Sangi (Councilor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to shoshii (the Senior Fourth Rank) and was appointed as sangi (a Councilor).</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。2. 「位」について、ルールに則り修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to shoshii (the Senior Fourth Rank) and was appointed as sangi (a Councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>月日不詳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The exact date was unknown</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The exact date is unknown.</e>
<cmt>1. これは「現在において不詳」なので現在形としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The exact date is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="314">
<j>- 参議辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigned Sangi (Councilor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned from sangi (a Councilor).</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned from sangi (a Councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>寛永3年（1626年）8月19日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 19, 1626</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 19, 1626</e>
<cmt>1. Onは削除しています</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 19, 1626</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="315">
<j>- 従三位中納言に昇叙転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoted to the Junior Third Rank and transferred to the Middle Counselor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to jusani (the Junior Third Rank, Vice-councilor of state) while he was transferred to chunagon (the Vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。2. 中納言の訳が対訳やルールによらず創造されています。修正しました。3. 位について、ルールに則り修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to jusani (the Junior Third Rank, Vice-councilor of state) while he was transferred to chunagon (the Vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>寛永11年（1634年）8月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1634</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August, 1634</e>
<cmt>1. Inは削除しています</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August, 1634</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="316">
<j>- 所領石高62万5000石となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allowed to rule the territory valued 625,000 koku (a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The value of his territory valued increased to 625,000 koku (a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter).</e>
<cmt>1. 文章化が必要です。修正しました。2. あまり適切な訳とは思えません。石高増加を説明しているので、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The value of his territory valued increased to 625,000 koku (a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>大正7年（1918年）11月18日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 18, 1918</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 18, 1918</e>
<cmt>1. Onは削除しています</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 18, 1918</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="317">
<j>- 贈従二位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rendered the Junior Second Rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was rendered junii (the Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>1.文章化が必要です。修正しました。2. 位について、ルールに則り修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was rendered junii (the Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="30">
<tit>
<j>別名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Alias names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alias names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alias names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="318">
<j>伊達美作守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date Mimasaka no kami (Governor of Mimasaka Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date Mimasaka no kami (Date the Governor of Mimasaka Province)</e>
<cmt>1. 説明部分に名称追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date Mimasaka no kami (Date the Governor of Mimasaka Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="319">
<j>伊達左京大夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date Sakyo no daibu (Date the Master of the Eastern Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt>1. 説明部分に名称追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date Sakyo no daibu (Date the Master of the Eastern Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="320">
<j>羽柴伊達侍従</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashiba Date Jiju (Imperial Household Agency Staff)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashiba Date Jiju (Hashiba Date the Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>1. ここでの侍従を現在の天皇制における侍従職にしています。上では正しくなっていたので、理解せずに自動的に対訳をコピーしたものと思われます。訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashiba Date Jiju (Hashiba Date the Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="321">
<j>羽柴長井侍従</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashiba Nagai Jiju (Imperial Household Agency Staff)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashiba Nagai Jiju (Hashiba Nagai the Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>1. ここでの侍従を現在の天皇制における侍従職にしています。訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashiba Nagai Jiju (Hashiba Nagai the Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="322">
<j>羽柴陸奥侍従</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashiba Mutsu Jiju (Imperial Household Agency Staff)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashiba Mutsu Jiju (Hashiba the Chamberlain and the Governor of Mutsu Province)</e>
<cmt>1. ここでの侍従を現在の天皇制における侍従職にしています。訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashiba Mutsu Jiju (Hashiba the Chamberlain and the Governor of Mutsu Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="323">
<j>羽柴侍従</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashiba Jiju (Imperial Household Agency Staff)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashiba Jiju (Hashiba the Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>1. ここでの侍従を現在の天皇制における侍従職にしています。訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashiba Jiju (Hashiba the Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="324">
<j>羽柴大崎侍従</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashiba Osaki Jiju (Imperial Household Agency Staff)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashiba Osaki Jiju (Hashiba the Chamberlain of Osaki)</e>
<cmt>1. ここでの侍従を現在の天皇制における侍従職にしています。訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashiba Osaki Jiju (Hashiba the Chamberlain of Osaki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="325">
<j>大崎侍従</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaki Jiju (Imperial Household Agency Staff)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaki Jiju (the Chamberlain of Osaki)</e>
<cmt>1. ここでの侍従を現在の天皇制における侍従職にしています。訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaki Jiju (the Chamberlain of Osaki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="326">
<j>大崎少将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaki Shosho (minor captain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaki Shosho (a vice-Provincial Governor of Osaki)</e>
<cmt>1. ここでの少将を戦時中の軍隊職にしています。訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaki Shosho (a vice-Provincial Governor of Osaki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="327">
<j>羽柴越前守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashiba Echizen no kami (Governor of Echizen Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashiba Echizen no kami (Hashiba the Governor of Echizen Province)</e>
<cmt>1. 説明部分に名称追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashiba Echizen no kami (Hashiba the Governor of Echizen Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="328">
<j>松平陸奥守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsudaira Mutsu no kami (Governor of Mutsu Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsudaira Mutsu no kami (Matsudaira the Governor of Mutsu Province)</e>
<cmt>1. 説明部分に名称追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsudaira Mutsu no kami (Matsudaira the Governor of Mutsu Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="329">
<j>仙台宰相</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sendai Prime Minister</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendai Saisho (the Chancellor of Sendai)</e>
<cmt>1. 「宰相」は「Prime Minister」で良いか微妙です。一般的にはChancellorかと思いこちらにしました。2. 位について、ルールに則り修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendai Saisho (the Chancellor of Sendai)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="330">
<j>仙台中納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sendai Chunagon (Middle Counselor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendai Chunagon (the Vice-councilor of state of Sendai)</e>
<cmt>1. 位階の訳が適当にされていましたので対訳に倣いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendai Chunagon (the Vice-councilor of state of Sendai)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="331">
<j>※ 他に独眼竜、仙台黄門など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune also had other unofficial names such as Dokuganryu (one-eyed dragon) and Sendai Komon (another name of the Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune was often called by nicknames such as Dokuganryu (one-eyed dragon) or Sendai Komon (the Vice-councilor of state of Sendai).</e>
<cmt>1. 原文にあるのはいわゆるニックネームですので、訳の「Masamune also had other unofficial names」という表現は適切とは思えません。「Masamune was often called」としました。2. なお「黄門」は、「中納言」を中国における同様の役職をさしていますので訳者の判断はただしいのですが、訳規定から外れた訳になっていますので修正しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune was often called by nicknames such as Dokuganryu (one-eyed dragon) or Sendai Komon (the Vice-councilor of state of Sendai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="31">
<tit>
<j>政宗の異名『独眼竜』について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About Masamune&apos;s nickname &quot;Dokuganryu&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About the nickname of Masamune as &quot;Dokuganryu&quot;</e>
<cmt>1. アポストロフィを用いないより適切と思われる書式にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About the nickname of Masamune as &quot;Dokuganryu&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="332">
<j>『独眼竜伊達政宗』（高橋紫燕・著，久保天随・校、大阪：鍾美堂，明34（1901）9月刊行）が出典。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This nickname first appeared in &quot;Dokuganryu Masamune DATE&quot; (written by Shien TAKAHASHI, emended by Tenzui KUBO, published by Shobido: Osaka in September, 1901).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This nickname first appeared in &quot;Dokuganryu Masamune DATE&quot; (written by Shien TAKAHASHI, emended by Tenzui KUBO, published by Shobido: Osaka in September, 1901).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This nickname first appeared in &quot;Dokuganryu Masamune DATE&quot; (written by Shien TAKAHASHI, emended by Tenzui KUBO, published by Shobido: Osaka in September, 1901).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="333">
<j>本の名前である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Dokuganryu Masamune DATE&quot; was a title of a book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This nickname &quot;Dokuganryu&quot; was used in the title of the book.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文がひどいですが、ここは「本のタイトルとしてこのニックネームが用いられた」の意味であると判断しました。訳もそれにあわせ修正しています。2. 不定冠詞の用法が不適切です。定冠詞に変更しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This nickname &quot;Dokuganryu&quot; was used in the title of the book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="334">
<j>なお、本文中で奥羽の覇王という用語も使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another nickname, Violent King of Ou, also appeared in this book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than this nickname, &quot;the Conqueror of Ou&quot; was also used in this book to describe him.</e>
<cmt>1. 「覇王」を「Conqueror」にしました。2. 意訳するにせよ、「使用されている」という行為の語を「appeared」の状態の語に置き換えるべきではないと思います。修正しました。3. 「to describe him」を加えた意訳となっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than this nickname, &quot;the Conqueror of Ou&quot; was also used in this book to describe him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="335">
<j>独眼竜伊達政宗、奥羽の覇王、いずれも、伊達政宗存命中の呼称ではなく、後世の命名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those nicknames such as Dokuganryu Masamune DATE and Violent King of Ou were created not while Masamune was alive, but after he was dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those nicknames of Masamune as &quot;Dokuganryu Masamune DATE&quot; or &quot;the Conqueror of Ou&quot; were not the nickname of his days, but the naming in later years.</e>
<cmt>1. 意訳された訳文は一見okなのですが、原文の意味とのずれがあります。原文にできるだけあわせています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those nicknames of Masamune as &quot;Dokuganryu Masamune DATE&quot; or &quot;the Conqueror of Ou&quot; were not the nickname of his days, but the naming in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="336">
<j>『太閤記』では、奥州の太守となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Taikoki&quot; (the biography of Toyotomi Hideyoshi), Masamune was called Taishu (governor-general) of Oshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Taikoki&quot; (the biography of Toyotomi Hideyoshi), Masamune was called Taishu (governor-general) of Oshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Taikoki&quot; (the biography of Toyotomi Hideyoshi), Masamune was called Taishu (governor-general) of Oshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="337">
<j>なお、それに先駆け、独眼竜とは旧陸軍第一師団長・陸軍中将・山地元治を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Masamune, the name, Dokuganryu represented a head of 1st Division of the former Army/a lieutenant general of the Army, Motoharu YAMAJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before this nickname was applied to Masamune, the name Dokuganryu had referred to Motoharu YAMAJI, the lieutenant general of the Imperial Japanese Army and the divisional commander of the 1st Army Division.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文は、「この独眼竜の呼称が使われたのは旧陸軍〜が先」という意味ですが、訳ではそれがはっきりと説明されていません。「Before Masamune」としか説明しないと、政宗より以前と読み取られ、外国人には政宗より以前に生きた人ととられるでしょう。この点留意し修正しました。2. 旧陸軍はその意味でもきちんと「Imperial Japanese Army」とすべきです。また、「師団長」も単に「head of division」とせず、きちんとした定訳とすべきです。3. 不定冠詞利用や定冠詞の欠如など多々見受けられます。追加／修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before this nickname was applied to Masamune, the name Dokuganryu had referred to Motoharu YAMAJI, the lieutenant general of the Imperial Japanese Army and the divisional commander of the 1st Army Division.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="338">
<j>出典は『支那征討英傑伝』（堀本柵・著、東京：東雲堂，明27（1894）11月刊行）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YAMAJI&apos;s nickname appeared in &quot;Heroes of the Conquest in Shina (China)&quot; (written by 堀本柵, published by Toundo: Tokyo in November, 1894).</e>
<cmt>堀本柵の読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The source of this example is a book called &quot;Heroes of the Conquest in Shina (China)&quot; (written by Saku HORIMOTO, published by Toundo Tokyo, in November, 1894).</e>
<cmt>1. 「出典」の原文を尊重し修正しました。2. 堀本柵のよみは「ほりもと　さく」でした。検索ですぐ出ました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The source of this example is a book called &quot;Heroes of the Conquest in Shina (China)&quot; (written by Saku HORIMOTO, published by Toundo Tokyo, in November, 1894).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="339">
<j>『独眼竜政宗』は1987年のNHK大河ドラマのほか、1942年の大映映画などでもタイトルとして使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot; Dokuganryu Masamune DATE&quot; was used for the title of the NHK Historical Drama in 1987 and the movie of Daiei Motion Picture Company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nickname of Masamune, &quot;Dokuganryu Masamune DATE&quot; was used for the title of a NHK (Nihon Hoso Kyokai, Japan National Broadcasting Corporation) historical drama in 1987, and also for the movie of the Daiei Motion Picture Company.</e>
<cmt>1.「呼称」の説明を加えました。2. 「NHK」はそれだけだと何のことかわからないはずです。説明を加えました。3. 大文字として固有名のように訳されているのを一般形として小文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nickname of Masamune, &quot;Dokuganryu Masamune DATE&quot; was used for the title of a NHK (Nihon Hoso Kyokai, Japan National Broadcasting Corporation) historical drama in 1987, and also for the movie of the Daiei Motion Picture Company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="340">
<j>上記著書は、国立国会図書館近代デジタルライブラリーで原文の詳細を読むことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The books mentioned above can be read by using the Digital Library from the Meiji Era of the National Diet Library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The books mentioned above can be found and accessed for their details through the Digital Library from the Meiji Era of the National Diet Library.</e>
<cmt>原文にある、「原文の詳細を読むことができる」の意味するところを判断しかねますが、一応訳者の訳通り、「原文を読むことができr」のままとしました。ただし、「詳細」が欠如していますので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The books mentioned above can be found and accessed for their details through the Digital Library from the Meiji Era of the National Diet Library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="32">
<tit>
<j>主要家臣団</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main vassals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major vassals of Date clan</e>
<cmt>1. 訳では説明不足と考え追記しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major vassals of Date clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="341">
<j>このうち、伊達成実・片倉景綱および鬼庭綱元を伊達三傑、片倉景綱と伊達成実を伊達の双璧と言うことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the main vassals, Shigezane DATE, Kagetsuna KATAKURA and Tsunamoto ONINIWA were especially called the three outstanding vassals of DATE, and Kagetsuna KATAKURA and Shigezane DATE were called the matchless vassals of DATE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those major vassals, Shigezane DATE, Kagetsuna KATAKURA and Tsunamoto ONINIWA are sometimes referred as the three outstanding vassals of Date clan, while Kagetsuna KATAKURA and Shigezane DATE are named as the two finest vassals of Date clan.</e>
<cmt>1. 訳にあるespeciallyの用法に疑問があります。現在時制に修正しました。2. 「双璧」の訳を原文に近いよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those major vassals, Shigezane DATE, Kagetsuna KATAKURA and Tsunamoto ONINIWA are sometimes referred as the three outstanding vassals of Date clan, while Kagetsuna KATAKURA and Shigezane DATE are named as the two finest vassals of Date clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="33">
<tit>
<j>遺訓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instructions for descendant</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Late instructions Masamune to descendant</e>
<cmt>1. 「遺訓」を意味するように追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late instructions Masamune to descendant</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="342">
<j>一、仁に過ぐれば弱くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you care about others too much, you will be timid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you go too far into &apos;jin&apos; (the terms of Confucianism referring to humanity with sympathy or compassion to others), you will become weak.</e>
<cmt>1. 意訳のし過ぎで語が訳者の主観で置き換えられているのと、それにより語が簡略化され説明されておらず、非常に一般的な意味になってしまっています。2. ここでは儒教における「五常」の項目をあげています。よってまずこの点について読者が気付くことが必要です。その上で、五常の一つである「仁」の意味は非常に重要だと思いますので、きちんと訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you go too far into &apos;jin&apos; (the terms of Confucianism referring to humanity with sympathy or compassion to others), you will become weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="343">
<j>義に過ぐれば固くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you adhere to being justice too much, you will be stubborn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you go too far into &apos;gi&apos; (the terms of Confucianism referring to righteousness among others), you will become inflexible.</e>
<cmt>1. 「義」の意味は非常にここでは重要だと思いますので、きちんと訳出しました。2. 「固くなる」は訳者の意味は一理ありますが、それに加えて「動きがとれなくなる」の意味もありますので、「inflexible」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you go too far into &apos;gi&apos; (the terms of Confucianism referring to righteousness among others), you will become inflexible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="344">
<j>礼に過ぐれば諂(へつらい)となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you are polite too much, it will be flattery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you go too far into &apos;rei&apos; (the general terms of Confucianism indicating rituals based on the moral standards and behavior models as manners developed for establishing social order), you will become flattery.</e>
<cmt>1. 「礼」の意味は非常にここでは重要だと思いますので、きちんと訳出しました。1. 「too much」の用法が文法的に誤りです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you go too far into &apos;rei&apos; (the general terms of Confucianism indicating rituals based on the moral standards and behavior models as manners developed for establishing social order), you will become flattery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="345">
<j>智に過ぐれば嘘を吐く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you have too much knowledge, you will tell a lie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you go too far into &apos;chi&apos; (the terms of Confucianism referring to knowledge acquired by studying), you will tell untruth.</e>
<cmt>1. 「智」の意味は非常にここでは重要だと思いますので、きちんと訳出しました。2. 嘘については、「智」と「嘘を吐く」の組み合わせから、単純な嘘という意味ではなく「真実でないものを語る」の意味としました。Untruthはlieと同様の意味もあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you go too far into &apos;chi&apos; (the terms of Confucianism referring to knowledge acquired by studying), you will tell untruth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="346">
<j>信に過ぐれば損をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you believe people too much, you will suffer a loss.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you go too far into &apos;chi&apos; (the terms of Confucianism referring to integrity by keeping promise and being truthful to others), you will come out on the loosing end.</e>
<cmt>1. 「信」の意味は非常にここでは重要だと思いますので、きちんと訳出しました。2. 「損をする」の訳を、「損をする側になる」の意味もある一般訳に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you go too far into &apos;chi&apos; (the terms of Confucianism referring to integrity by keeping promise and being truthful to others), you will come out on the loosing end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="347">
<j>一、気長く心穏やかにして、よろずに倹約を用い金銀を備ふべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Be patient and gentle, and always cut cost to save gold and silver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Take a leisurely pace with calm mind, while economize in every cases to save money for preparation.</e>
<cmt>1. 意訳のし過ぎで語が訳者の主観で置き換えられています。訳者の知識によるのか、原文と訳文で剥離が大きい場合には修正しています。2. 逆に「金銀」は直訳されています。文字通りの可能性もありますが、「金と銀を貯めよ」では前後と意味がうまくつながらないため、一般的な「お金」の意味と考え修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Take a leisurely pace with calm mind, while economize in every cases to save money for preparation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="348">
<j>倹約の仕方は不自由なるを忍ぶにあり、この世に客に来たと思へば何の苦しみもなし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The way of saving is putting up with inconveniences, and if you think that you just a visitor of this life, you are no more bothered by anything.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The way of thriftiness is to endure various inconveniences; however, you do not feel any hardship once you consider yourself as a visitor to this world.</e>
<cmt>1. 「倹約」がここでは「saving」となっており、原文の意味以外のものもさしてしまう単語が使われているため、「thriftiness」としました。2. 訳文の場合、現在進行形と同形になってしまっています。誤解を避けるため修正しました。3. 「忍ぶ」を文章においてより適切と思う「endure」に修正しました。4. 「if you think that you just a visitor of this life」は文法的な誤りを含みます。その他、単語などの変更含め修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way of thriftiness is to endure various inconveniences; however, you do not feel any hardship once you consider yourself as a visitor to this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="349">
<j>一、朝夕の食事はうまからずとも褒めて食ふべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You should praise a taste of every meal even it&apos;s not delicious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You shall have every meal by speak well of it even it is unpalatable.</e>
<cmt>1. 「うまからずとも褒めて食う」は「味を賞賛して食べる」と味について言及しているわけではなく、「味がどうこうではなく食事そのものを褒め、そのありがたさを重視する」の意味と考えました。2. 「おいしくない」はそれに直接当てはまる単語を充てました。3. 「It&apos;s」の短縮形は口語的ですので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You shall have every meal by speak well of it even it is unpalatable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="350">
<j>元来客の身に成れば好き嫌ひは申されまじ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you are a guest, you cannot show your likes and dislikes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As long as you are in a position of a temporal visitor to this world, speaking of likes and dislikes is not worth mentioning.</e>
<cmt>1. これは先述の「この世の客」を引き継いでの話と思われますが、この訳ですと意図するしないに関わらず、「客に呼ばれたときに好き嫌いを言えないのと同じように」の意味に取られてしまいます。こうした場合に意訳による簡略化の問題があることが明らかになります。ここでは、「過客」の意味を明確にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As long as you are in a position of a temporal visitor to this world, speaking of likes and dislikes is not worth mentioning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="351">
<j>一、今日行くをおくり、子孫兄弟によく挨拶して、娑婆の御暇申すがよし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We are not sure when we are gone, so every time you go out, you should see your descendants and brothers and bid farewell to them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Let go of the passing day, exchange greetings with your descendants and brothers, with the words of taking your leave for this world.</e>
<cmt>1. 「今日行くをおくり」の訳は「we are not sure when we are gone」（時制に問題があります）となっていますが、ここでは文字通り「過ぎ行く今日を見届け」のような意味だと思います。2. 「so every time you go out」は原文に見当たりません。意訳のし過ぎだと思います。「娑婆の御暇申す」はこの世に暇を告げるの意味ととりました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Let go of the passing day, exchange greetings with your descendants and brothers, with the words of taking your leave for this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 1990+1997二世(id:133705), ポコポコ(id:229914), Nnh(id:474), Shizhao(id:1325), Isuka(id:1126), 紀州太政大臣(id:42479), Cprobot(id:97843), PATMAN(id:145791), Jidaigeki.db(id:197318), Lupinoid(id:68), Kamakura(id:472), Halfd(id:145364), Hokahoka(id:37244), 南部信彦(id:43608), でここ(id:9565), Jugger90(id:17088), らりた(id:1327), A-Taul(id:41790), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), 5816K(id:102574), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), 独楽(id:32400), Maakun(id:16735), Nuun99uu(id:196711), Sampo(id:1041), Kouko0515(id:100370), せくそろじすと(id:9002), YukkeBot2(id:251491), Haeha(id:9372), 松茸(id:27535), とめみぃはぁ(id:135255), S kitahashi(id:10307), Philippa1025(id:253085), 立つのかよ(id:111350), Kagetudo(id:163875), トメぞう(id:194000), Rusk(id:9895), Nopimroel(id:93722), R28Bot(id:177951), 海衛士(id:19229), Okztosh(id:27983), 神奈川大学2年経済学部経済学科(id:1107), 人造人間だみゃ～ん(id:119413), Suisui(id:69), King-wise(id:19033), Bontenmaru(id:108782), Broad-Sky(id:68334), Hjkg78899(id:190034), Codd(id:85057), Que Louloua(id:284223), ドルチェット(id:46458), K66星雲(id:16609), M.F(id:84868), Mutimaro(id:164721), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Ash Crow(id:26765), Sgi1962(id:80778), タナトス(id:28234), HqB774PW0(id:311341), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Kinori(id:443), Siwulek(id:271851), Loveless(id:129239), Chobot(id:20846), Fgdrt5666(id:190235), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 茶々(id:87918), Yosemite(id:5808), KASAGI(id:24405), Bankokuya(id:91191), Kirk1701(id:137417), Lonicera(id:20638), ミッドランドライダー(id:40104), 水野白楓(id:22811), Taisyo(id:6896), Yanahan(id:2437), Clara(id:10579), 総州之毛豆(id:26880), Kamitani(id:30757), 前田左衛門佐(id:194701), Carkuni(id:79281), Yonoemon(id:55450), Liferoot(id:15768), SEKIUCHI(id:637), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), Bokka7568(id:275377), あずまえびすっ子(id:270794), Shinsei(id:88829), Los688(id:12316), 松本ゆきお(仮)(id:117128), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), かがみ(id:137074), KurmUmy(id:202680), Nikm(id:245385), Cozycoji(id:87757), Re:RENA(id:86666), Tribot(id:186681), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), 酒井貴広(id:52017), ヨッサン(id:212562), Gombe(id:27), 怪人アンターダレダー(id:188410), 丁度氷(id:64000), SKI(id:37176), 赤井彗星(id:18381), Michey.M(id:906), Dr jimmy(id:111486), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Blowback(id:173308), たなしん(id:162581), ハニーハニー00(id:263775), ゆーりん(id:164919), Calvero(id:38360), DumZiBoT(id:230315), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Mnd(id:15140), もね～るmoner(id:28477), 浩(id:70121), ニコタマ二子多摩川(id:228848), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), GoGoDoll(id:131511), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Nallimbot(id:230812), ツカケン(id:212942), D.328(id:29724), Fx(id:485), ＫｏＺ(id:48584), 小者(id:172526), 彩華1226(id:64711), はるひ(id:59079), ぷらんたん(id:58446), ひろくん(id:79638), 上(id:14148), Yzayz(id:104048), Kishitak(id:9134), HASIDATE(id:181052), JAnDbot(id:66507), Si-take.(id:91094), Bunkichi(id:94956), MIsogi(id:20599), Reggaeman(id:6214), ジャンショーグン(id:57919), 春野秋葉(id:36725), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Ohura(id:5986), 百人(id:16483), Uraios(id:72687), Uminumin(id:205875), Tnm(id:58695), Gakuinryou(id:9665), 玄史生(id:43670), Goki(id:7107), Nevylax(id:38464), 怪蘇(id:45514), Nopira(id:29335), 孝宏(id:56494), Ijuin2525(id:232687), Nihonsi(id:255350), Romonen(id:55439), 学問好き(id:309655), Getus.getus(id:199090), 怪盗蓬月(id:132496), Norio-abc(id:106785), Lucas0123(id:130266), アンサイクロペディアン(id:89886), VolkovBot(id:105371), ゐ(id:795), Magcup(id:207843), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), ほくなん(id:17810), シルザッド(id:139606), 663highland(id:18755), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 暇編集(id:222403), Tokugawa(id:61656), 一騎当千(id:56448), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>