<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>九条武子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeko KUJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeko KUJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeko KUJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>九条 武子（くじょう たけこ、1887年（明治20年）10月20日 - 1928年（昭和3年）2月7日）は、教育者・歌人、後年には社会運動活動家としても活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeko KUJO (October 20, 1887 - February 7, 1928) was an educator and tanka poet, also actively engaged in a social movement in after years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeko KUJO (October 20, 1887 - February 7, 1928) was an educator and tanka poet, also actively engaged in the social movement in her later years.</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeko KUJO (October 20, 1887 - February 7, 1928) was an educator and tanka poet, also actively engaged in the social movement in her later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>Pronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>西本願寺第21代門主・大谷光尊の次女（母・藤子は光尊の側室で紀州藩士族の子女）として京都で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born as the second daughter of Koson OTANI, the 21st head abbot of the Nishi Hongwan-ji Temple, in Kyoto (her mother Fujiko, a concubine of Koson, was born in the family of the ex-samurai class in the Kishu domain.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born as the second daughter of Koson OTANI, the 21st head abbot of the Nishi Hongwan-ji Temple, in Kyoto (her mother Fujiko, a concubine of Koson, was born into an ex-samurai family from Kishu Domain).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born as the second daughter of Koson OTANI, the 21st head abbot of the Nishi Hongwan-ji Temple, in Kyoto (her mother Fujiko, a concubine of Koson, was born into a warrior class family from Kishu Domain).</e>
<cmt>士族を warrior class に用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>義姉・大谷籌子裏方（大谷光瑞夫人）を助けて仏教婦人会を創設し、1911年（明治44年）､大谷籌子が30歳の若さで早世の際は本部長に就任、同会運営の重責を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She founded the Buddhist Women&apos;s Association (BWA, Fujinkai in Japanese), supporting her sister-in-law Kazuko OTANI, urakata (spouse of the current monshu (head abbot)) (wife of Kozui OTANI), and when Kazuko OTANI died young at the age of 30 in 1911, Takeko took office as a general manager and met her solemn responsibilities of operating the Association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She helped her sister-in-law, Kazuko OTANI, the wife of then head abbot, Kozui OTANI, found the Buddhist Women&apos;s Association (BWA, Fujinkai in Japanese) and when Kazuko OTANI died young at the age of 30 in 1911, Takeko became general manager, taking on the solemn responsibilities of operating the Association.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She helped her sister-in-law, Kazuko OTANI, the wife of then head abbot, Kozui OTANI, found the Buddhist Women&apos;s Association (BWA, Fujinkai in Japanese) and when Kazuko OTANI died young at the age of 30 in 1911, Takeko became general manager, taking on the solemn responsibilities of operating the Association.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>仏教主義に基づく京都女子専門学校（現・京都女子学園、京都女子大学）を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She founded Kyoto Joshi Sermon gakko (Kyoto Women&apos;s College; present Kyoto Joshi Gakuen (Kyoto Women&apos;s Educational Institution), Kyoto Women&apos;s University) based on the Buddhist principle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She founded Kyoto Joshi Senmon Gakko (Kyoto Women&apos;s College; present Kyoto Joshi Gakuen (Kyoto Women&apos;s Educational Institution), Kyoto Women&apos;s University), basing it on Buddhist principles.</e>
<cmt>Revised for claritySpellingCapital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She founded Kyoto Joshi Senmon Gakko (Kyoto Women&apos;s College; present Kyoto Joshi Gakuen (Kyoto Women&apos;s Educational Institution), Kyoto Women&apos;s University), basing it on Buddhist principles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1923年（大正12年）9月1日の関東大震災で自身も被災するが一命を取りとめ、全壊した築地本願寺の再建、震災による負傷者・孤児の救援活動（「あそか病院」などの設立）などさまざまな事業を推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She narrowly escaped death in the Great Kanto Earthquake of September 1, 1923, and promoted many projects such as reconstruction of the completely destroyed Tsukiji Hongwan-ji Temple, activities to aid the seriously injured and the orphaned (establishment of the &quot;Asoka Hospital&quot;), and the like.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After narrowly escaping death in the Great Kanto Earthquake of September 1, 1923, she promoted many projects such as the reconstruction of the completely destroyed Tsukiji Hongwan-ji Temple and activities to aid the seriously injured and the orphaned (establishment of the &quot;Asoka Hospital&quot;).</e>
<cmt>PrepositionArticleDeleted &quot;and the like&quot; - unnecessary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After narrowly escaping death in the Great Kanto Earthquake of September 1, 1923, she promoted many projects such as the reconstruction of the completely destroyed Tsukiji Hongwan-ji Temple and activities to aid the seriously injured and the orphaned (establishment of the &apos;Asoka Hospital&apos;).</e>
<cmt>&quot; を &apos; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>佐佐木信綱に師事し和歌にも長け歌人としても、『金鈴』『薫染』などの歌集がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a disciple of Nobutsuna SASAKI, and excelled in composing waka and left collections of waka &quot;Kinrei (金鈴, Golden Bell)&quot;, &quot;Kunzen (薫染, Fragrant Influences)&quot;, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She studied under Nobutsuna SASAKI and excelled in composing waka; her collections of waka include &quot;Kinrei&quot; (金鈴, &quot;Golden Bell&quot;) and &quot;Kunzen&quot; (薫染, &quot;Fragrant Influences&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She studied under Nobutsuna SASAKI and excelled in composing waka; her collections of waka include &quot;Kinrei&quot; (金鈴, &quot;Golden Bell&quot;) and &quot;Kunzen&quot; (薫染, &quot;Fragrant Influences&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>愛唱されている仏教讃歌の「聖夜」は、1927年（昭和2年）7月に出版された随筆『無憂華』の中に収められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous of her Buddhism admiration song &apos;Seiya (聖夜, Splendor of an Evening Sky)&apos; was contained in her collection of essays &quot;Muyuge (無憂華, Flower Without Sorrow)&quot; published in September, 1927.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her much-loved Buddhism hymn &apos;Seiya&apos; (聖夜, &quot;Splendor of an Evening Sky&quot;) was contained in her collection of essays &quot;Muyuge&quot; (無憂華, &quot;Flower Without Sorrow&quot;), published in September, 1927.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her much-loved Buddhism hymn &apos;Seiya&apos; (聖夜, &quot;Splendor of an Evening Sky&quot;) was contained in her collection of essays &quot;Muyuge&quot; (無憂華, &quot;Flower Without Sorrow&quot;), published in September, 1927.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「聖夜」の作曲は、中山晋平（1887年～1952年）で、歌詞は七五調で構成され、夜空に輝く美しい数多の星のようにおわする仏たちに護られて生きていることの歓喜と安らぎが表現されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lyrics of &apos;Seiya&apos;, for which the music was written by Shinpei NAKAYAMA (1887 - 1952), are in seven-and-five syllable meter, expressing joy and peace of a person who is protected by infinite Buddhas filling the universe like the splendor of millions of sparkling stars in the evening sky.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lyrics of &apos;Seiya&apos;, for which the music was written by Shinpei NAKAYAMA (1887 - 1952), are in seven-and-five syllable meter, and express the joy and peace of a person who is protected by infinite Buddhas filling the universe like the splendor of millions of sparkling stars in the evening sky.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityArticle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lyrics of &apos;Seiya&apos;, for which the music was written by Shinpei NAKAYAMA (1887 - 1952), are in seven-and-five syllable meter, and express the joy and peace of a person who is protected by infinite Buddha&apos;s filling the universe like the splendor of millions of sparkling stars in the evening sky.</e>
<cmt>Buddhas を Buddha&apos;s に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>1928年（昭和3年）2月7日、震災復興事業での奔走の無理がたたり敗血症発症、42歳の若さで念仏のうちに往生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 7, 1928, she had blood poisoning caused by overstrain in devoting herself to the earthquake disaster reconstruction project and passed away young at the age of 42, while the name of Amitabha Buddha was recited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 7, 1928, she contracted blood poisoning due to overexertion from her efforts in the earthquake reconstruction projects and passed away at the young age of 42, while the name of Amitabha Buddha was recited.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 7, 1928, she contracted blood poisoning due to overexertion from her efforts in the earthquake reconstruction projects and passed away at the young age of 42, while the name of Amitabha Buddha was recited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>宗門では、九条武子の命日を如月忌（きさらぎき）と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the religious sect, Takeko KUJO&apos;s memorial day is called Kisaragi-ki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the Jodo Shinshu sect, Takeko KUJO&apos;s memorial day is called Kisaragi-ki.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - added name of the sect although it wasn&apos;t in the original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the Jodo Shinshu sect, Takeko KUJO&apos;s anniversary of the death is called Kisaragi-ki.</e>
<cmt>命日をanniversary of the deathに用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>武子は才色兼備としてもてはやされ、柳原白蓮（大正天皇生母・柳原愛子の姪）、江木欣々とともに大正三美人と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeko was praised as a woman of intelligence and beauty, and called Taisho san bijin (three beautiful women in the Taisho period) with Byakuren YANAGIHARA (niece of the real mother of the Emperor Taisho, Aiko YANAGIHARA) and Kinkin EGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeko was praised for her intelligence and beauty, and was known as one of the &apos;Taisho san bijin&apos; (three beautiful women of the Taisho period) along with Byakuren YANAGIHARA (niece of Emperor Taisho&apos;s mother, Aiko YANAGIHARA) and Kinkin EGI.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeko was praised for her intelligence and beauty, and was known as one of the &apos;Taisho san bijin&apos; (three beautiful women of the Taisho period) along with Byakuren YANAGIHARA (niece of Emperor Taisho&apos;s mother, Aiko YANAGIHARA) and Kinkin EGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>私生活では1909年、公爵家出身で正金銀行勤務・九条良致（くじょう・よしむね）に嫁いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the private life, in 1909, she married Yoshimune KUJO who came from the family of duke and worked at Yokohama Specie Bank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for her private life, in 1909, she married Yoshimune KUJO, who came from a family of dukes and worked at Yokohama Specie Bank.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationGrammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for her private life, in 1909, she married Yoshimune KUJO, who was from a family of dukes and worked at Yokohama Specie Bank.</e>
<cmt>cameをwasに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>武子は結婚後良致の勤務先兼留学先（ケンブリッジ大学）・ロンドンに随行したが、渡英一年半で武子が帰国・良致はそのまま英国滞在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After they married, Takeko accompanied Yoshimune to London (the University of Cambridge) where Yoshimune worked and studied, and after one and a half years of their life in Britain, Takeko returned to Japan and Yoshimune still stayed in Britain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they married, Takeko accompanied Yoshimune to Britain, where he studied at the University of Cambridge and worked in London, but after one and a half years, Takeko returned to Japan while Yoshimune stayed in Britain.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - Cambridge University isn&apos;t in London</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they married, Takeko accompanied Yoshimune to Britain, where he studied at the University of Cambridge and worked in London, but after one and a half years, Takeko returned to Japan while Yoshimune stayed in Britain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この別居状態が十数年続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, they lived separately for more than ten years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, they lived separately for more than ten years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, they lived separately for more than ten years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これには美貌・教養・家柄（大谷家は伯爵家）の誉れ高き武子に、良致がなじめなかったからではないか等、夫婦不和の憶測もあったが、武子は離婚どころか浮いた言動一つとらず良致の帰国をひたすら待ちつづけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There has been speculation that the couple was in discord because Yoshimune could not become attached to Takeko who had been famous for her beauty, intelligence, and high lineage (the OTANI family was the family of count); on the contrary, Takeko intently waited for Yoshimune&apos;s return without doing any frivolous behavior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There has been speculation that there was friction between the couple because Yoshimune was uncomfortable with Takeko&apos;s beauty, intelligence, and high lineage (the OTANI family was a family of counts) but Takeko made no mention of divorce and intently waited earnestly for Yoshimune&apos;s return.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There has been speculation that there was a friction between the couple because Yoshimune was uncomfortable with Takeko&apos;s beauty, intelligence, and high lineage (the OTANI family was a family of counts) but Takeko made no mention of divorce and intently waited earnestly for Yoshimune&apos;s return.</e>
<cmt>frictionの前にaを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1920年年末に良致が帰国し夫婦同居が実現、武子・良致の間に子はなかったものの関東大震災などを経て武子自身の死までこれ以降は良致とよき夫婦関係であったと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of 1920, Yoshimune returned to Japan and the couple restarted to live together, and they allegedly lived in peace through the Great Kanto Earthquake and other incidents until Takeko&apos;s death, even though they had no child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of 1920, Yoshimune returned to Japan and the couple started to live together again and although they had no children, they allegedly had a good relationship through the Great Kanto Earthquake and other incidents until Takeko&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of 1920, Yoshimune returned to Japan and the couple started to live together again and although they had no children, they allegedly had a good relationship through the Great Kanto Earthquake and other incidents until Takeko&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歌碑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stone Monuments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inscriptions</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monument engraved waka poem</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>おほいなるものの ちからにひかれゆく わがあしあとの おぼつかなしや（東京築地本願寺境内）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drawn by the power of Great Things; Ah, how unsteady are my steps. (in the precincts of Tsukiji Hongwan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Drawn by the power of Great Things; Ah, how unsteady are my steps&quot; (in the precincts of Tsukiji Hongwan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drawn by the power of Great Things; Ah, how unsteady are my steps (in the precincts of Tsukiji Hongwan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>&quot;を除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>山の院連子の端にせきれいの巣あり雛三つ母待ちて鳴く（比叡山西塔）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a nest of wagtails in the corner of the latticework in a Mountain Hall,Three chicks cry, waiting for their mother. (at the West Tower on Mount Hiei)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;In a nest of wagtails in the corner of the latticework in a Mountain Hall,Three chicks cry, waiting for their mother&quot; (at the West Tower on Mount Hiei)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a nest of wagtails in the corner of the latticework in a Mountain Hall,Three chicks cry, waiting for their mother (at the West Tower on Mount Hiei)</e>
<cmt>&quot;を除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Lemon pie(id:66842), 杉山真大(id:2297), Resto1578(id:168692), Deepimpact(id:129352), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), Ttwo(id:82880), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Jade0416(id:104181), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>