<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京極高久</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahisa KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahisa KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahisa KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京極 高久（きょうごく たかひさ、享保14年4月24日 (旧暦)（1729年5月21日）- 文化 (元号)5年4月20日 (旧暦)（1808年5月15日））は、丹後国峰山藩の第6代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahisa KYOGOKU (May 21,1729 - May 15, 1808) was the sixth lord of Mineyama Domain, Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahisa KYOGOKU (May 21,1729 - May 15, 1808) was the sixth lord of Mineyama Domain, Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahisa KYOGOKU (May 21,1729 - May 15, 1808) was the sixth lord of Mineyama Domain, Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>峰山藩分家で1000石を領した旗本・京極高庭の四男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the forth son of 京極高庭 who had been a hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which was a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and occupied 1000 koku in a branch family of Mineyama Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth son of 京極高庭 who had been a hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which was a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and was bestowed 1,000 koku in a branch family of Mineyama Domain.</e>
<cmt>occupied を was bestowed に修正しました。1000 を 1,000 に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth son of 京極高庭 who had been a hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which was a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and was bestowed 1,000 koku in a branch family of Mineyama Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は京極高方の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Takakata KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Takakata KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Takakata KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正室は木下利潔の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Toshikiyo KINOSHITA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was a daughter of Toshikiyo KINOSHITA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Toshikiyo KINOSHITA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>弟に瀬名孫助、大岡直往、池田富郷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brothers were Magosuke SENA, Naoyuki Ooka, and Tomisato IKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brothers were Magosuke SENA, Naoyuki OOKA, and Tomisato IKEDA.</e>
<cmt>Ooka を OOKA に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brothers were Magosuke SENA, Naoyuki OOKA, and Tomisato IKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>子に京極高備（長男）、京極高有（五男、但馬国豊岡藩主）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons were Takamasa KYOGOKU (the eldest son) and, Takaari KYOGOKU (the fifth son, the lord of Toyooka Domain of the Tajima Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons were Takamasa KYOGOKU (first son) and, Takaari KYOGOKU (fifth son, lord of Toyooka Domain in Tajima Province).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons were Takamasa KYOGOKU (first son) and, Takaari KYOGOKU (fifth son, lord of Toyooka Domain in Tajima Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>官位は従五位下、備前国守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official court rank was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and he was the Governor of Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official court rank was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and he was the Governor of Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official court rank was Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and he was the Governor of Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>享保14年（1729年）4月24日、江戸にて生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Apeil 24, 1729, he was born in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 21, 1729, he was born in Edo.</e>
<cmt>Apeil 24 を May 21 に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 21, 1729, he was born in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幼名は千之助。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Sennosuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Sennosuke.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Sennosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>寛保元年（1741年）、第5代藩主・京極高長の養子となり、明和2年（1765年）8月8日の高長の隠居により、その後を継いで藩主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1741 he was adopted by Takanaga KYOGOKU, the fifth lord, and after Takanaga&apos;s retirement at August 8, 1765 he succeeded him to become the lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1741 he was adopted by Takanaga KYOGOKU, the fifth lord of the domain, and after Takanaga&apos;s retirement on September 22, 1765, he succeeded to the position.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1741, he was adopted by Takanaga KYOGOKU, the fifth lord of the domain, and after Takanaga&apos;s retirement on September 22, 1765, he succeeded to the position of lord of the Toyooka Domain.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>大坂青屋口の加番や大番頭を務めた後の天明8年（1788年）、若年寄に任じられて寛政の改革期の幕政に参与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he had worked as kaban (a person in charge of guard) at aoyaguchi gate of Osaka-jo Castle and Oban gashira (captains of the great guards), he was appointed as wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in the Edo bakufu) in 1788 to participate in the shogunate government in the Kansei Reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he had worked as kaban (a person in charge of guard) at aoyaguchi gate of Osaka-jo Castle and Oban gashira (captains of the great guards), he was appointed as wakadoshiyori (junior councilor) in 1788 to participate in the shogunate government in the period of Kansei Reforms.</e>
<cmt>a managerial position in the Edo bakufu を junior councilor に修正しました。寛政の改革期　in the Kansei Reforms をin the period of Kansei Reforms に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he had worked as kaban (a person in charge of guard) at aoyaguchi gate of Osaka-jo Castle and Oban gashira (captains of the great guards), he was appointed as wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in the Edo bakufu) in 1788 to participate in the shogunate government in the period of Kansei Reforms.</e>
<cmt>wakadoshiyori (junior councilor)→wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in the Edo bakufu)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>このため、峰山藩の藩政は長男・高備が取り仕切ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, duties of Mineyama Domain were to be managed by his eldest son, Takamasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, duties of Mineyama Domain were managed by his oldest son, Takamasa.</e>
<cmt>to be managed by his eldest son を managed by his oldest son に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, duties of Mineyama Domain were managed by his oldest son, Takamasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>寛政3年（1791年）、病気を理由に若年寄の辞任を求めたが許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1791 because of his illness he asked for resignation from wakadoshiyori, but it was not accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1791, he asked for resignation from wakadoshiyori due to his illness, but it was not accepted.</e>
<cmt>前半部を全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1791, he asked for resignation from wakadoshiyori due to his illness, but it was not accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>丹後峰山藩京極家と同じく、藩祖で丹後一国を支配した京極高知の子孫で同族に当たる但馬豊岡藩京極家に五男・高有を養子に出したことでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known to adopted out his fifth son to Kyogoku family of Toyooka Domain of Tajima Province, the Kyogoku family which was the same kin and a descendant of Takatomo KYOGOKU who had been the founder of the domain and governed the whole of Tango Province, as was the Kyogoku family of Mineyama Domain, Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known to have adopted out his fifth son to Kyogoku family of Toyooka Domain in Tajima Province, the Kyogoku family which was the same kin and a descendant of Takatomo KYOGOKU who had been the founder of the domain and governed the whole of Tango Province, as was the Kyogoku family of Mineyama Domain, Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>adopted out を have adopted out に修正しました。of Tajima Province を in Tajima Province に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known to have adopted out his fifth son to Kyogoku family of Toyooka Domain in Tajima Province, the Kyogoku family which was the same kin and a descendant of Takatomo KYOGOKU who had been the founder of the domain and governed the whole of Tango Province, as was the Kyogoku family of Mineyama Domain, Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>文化5年（1808年）4月20日、江戸にて死去し、後を高備が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 20, 1808, he died in Edo and Takamasa succeeded him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 15, 1808, Takahisa died in Edo and Takamasa succeeded to him.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 15, 1808, Takahisa died in Edo and Takamasa succeeded to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>享年80。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 80.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>法号：謙徳院明誉高久道徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His hogo (a Buddhist name): 謙徳院明誉高久道徴</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name: 謙徳院明誉高久道徴</e>
<cmt>hogo (a Buddhist name) を posthumous Buddhist name に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name: 謙徳院明誉高久道徴</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>墓所：京都府京丹後市峰山町吉原の安泰山常立寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His graveyard: in Antaizan Joryu-ji Temple in Yoshiwara, Mineyama-cho, Tango City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His graveyard: in Joryu-ji Temple on Mt. Antai in Yoshiwara, Mineyama-cho, Tango City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Antaizan Joryu-ji Temple を Joryu-ji Temple on Mt. Antai に修正しました。文末にピリオドを追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His graveyard: in Joryu-ji Temple on Mt. Antai in Yoshiwara, Mineyama-cho, Tango City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>高久は「京極備前守」の名で池波正太郎の時代小説『鬼平犯科帳』にも登場し、鬼平こと長谷川平蔵の良き理解者として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahisa appeared in a series of period novels written by Shotaro IKENAMI titled &quot; Onihei Hankacho&quot;, by the name of &quot; Bizen no kami (the governor of Bizen Province) of Kyogoku&quot;, and was described as a good understanding of Heizo HASEGAWA known by the name of Onihei.</e>
<cmt>「鬼平犯科帳」はシリーズものなので「a series of」をつけました。また、現在も販売、講読されていますが、著者は死去しており、過去に書かれているものなので、過去形を用いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahisa appeared in a series of period novels written by Shotaro IKENAMI titled &quot; Onihei Hankacho&quot; (Onihei&apos;s crimes note), by the name of &quot; Bizen no kami (the governor of Bizen Province) of Kyogoku&quot;, and was described as a good understanding of Heizo HASEGAWA known by the name of Onihei.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Bizen no kami&quot;をシングルコーテーションに修正しました。&quot;Onihei Hankacho&quot;に (Onihei&apos;s crimes note) を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahisa appeared in a series of period novels written by Shotaro IKENAMI titled &quot; Onihei Hankacho&quot; (Onihei&apos;s crimes note), by the name of &quot; Bizen no kami (the governor of Bizen Province) of Kyogoku&quot;, and was described as a good understanding of Heizo HASEGAWA known by the name of Onihei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Yanahan(id:2437), Richknight(id:141069), 松茸(id:27535), Autoblinda(id:100335), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>