<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>森鴎外</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai MORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai MORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai MORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>森 鷗外（もり おうがい、文久2年1月19日 (旧暦)（1862年2月17日）- 大正11年（1922年）7月9日）は、明治・大正期の小説家、評論家、翻訳家、劇作家、帝国陸軍軍医、官僚（高等官一等）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai MORI (February 17, 1862 - July 9, 1922) was a novelist, critic, translator, playwright, army surgeon of Imperial Army and bureaucracy (Senior Official First Class).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai MORI (February 17, 1862 - July 9, 1922) was a novelist, critic, translator, playwright, surgeon of the Imperial Army and Bureaucrat (Senior Official First Class).</e>
<cmt>army surgeon&gt;surgeon as &apos;army&apos; appear after Imperial also. bureacracy&gt;bureacrat</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai MORI (February 17, 1862 - July 9, 1922) was a novelist, critic, translator, playwright, surgeon of the Imperial Army and Bureaucrat (Senior Official First Class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>軍医総監（中将相当）・正四位・勲二等・功三級・医学博士・文学博士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A General Office Director of Army Surgeon (corresponding to Lieutenant General), Shoshii, Order of Second Class, Ko Third Grade, Doctor of Medical Science and Doctor of Literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also Army Surgeon General (equivalent to Lieutenant General), Shoshii, Order of Merit Second Class, Ko Third Grade, Doctor of Medical Science and had a doctorate in Literature.</e>
<cmt>博士：Doctor of&gt;had a doctorate in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also Army Surgeon General (equivalent to Lieutenant General), Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), Order of Merit Second Class, Ko Third Grade, Doctor of Medical Science and had a doctorate in Literature.</e>
<cmt>英語説明補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>第一次世界大戦以降、夏目漱石と並ぶ文豪と称されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considered as a great writer in the post-World War I ranked with Soseki NATSUME.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is considered one of the great writers of the post-First World War Period ranked alongside Soseki NATSUME.</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;he is&apos; as subject, a great writere&gt;one of. ranked with&gt;alongside</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is considered one of the great writers of the post-First World War Period ranked alongside Soseki NATSUME.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本名、林太郎（りんたろう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name is Rintaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Rintaro.</e>
<cmt>change to past tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Rintaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>石見国津和野（現・島根県津和野町）出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Tsuwano Domain, Iwami Province (present Tsuwano-cho, Shimane Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Tsuwano Domain, Iwami Province (present Tsuwano-cho, Shimane Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>from&gt;born in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Tsuwano Domain, Iwami Province (present Tsuwano-cho, Shimane Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>東京大学医学部 卒業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graduated from the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He graduated from the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine.</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;he&apos; as subject</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He graduated from the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>大学卒業後、陸軍軍医になり、陸軍省派遣留学生としてドイツで4年過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his graduation, he became an army surgeon and spent four years in Germany as an oversea student under Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After graduation, he became an army surgeon and spent four years in Germany as an overseas student under the Department of War.</e>
<cmt>removed &apos;his&apos;, oversea&gt;overseas. Ministry of Army&gt;Department of War</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After graduation, he became an army surgeon and spent four years in Germany as an overseas student under the Department of War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>帰国後、訳詩編『於母影』、小説『舞姫』、翻訳『即興詩人』を発表し、また自ら文芸雑誌『しがらみ草紙』を創刊して文筆活動に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After coming back to Japan, he published a book of songs &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos;, a novel &apos;Maihime (The Dansing Girl)&apos; and a translated book &apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&apos;, and also began to issue a literary magazine &apos;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&apos; by himself to start his career as a writer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After coming back to Japan, he published a book of songs &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos;, a novel &apos;Maihime (The Dansing Girl)&apos; and a translated book &apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&apos;, and also began to issue a literary magazine &apos;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&apos; by himself to start his career as a writer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After coming back to Japan, he published a book of songs &quot;Omokage&quot; (Vestiges), a novel &quot;Maihime&quot; (The Dancing Girl) and a translated book &quot;Sokkyo Shijin&quot; (Improvising Poet), and also began to issue a literary magazine &quot;Shigarami Soshi&quot; (Constraint Brochure) by himself to start his career as a writer.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、軍医総監（中将相当）となり、一時期創作活動から遠ざかったが、『スバル (文芸雑誌)』創刊後に『ヰタ・セクスアリス』『雁 (小説)』などを執筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he became a General Office Director of Army Surgeon (corresponding to Lieutenant General), and it temporalily withdrew him from his creation activities, but he later began to issue &apos;Subaru (a literary magazine)&apos;, then wrote &apos;Vita Sexualis&apos;, &apos;The Wild Geese (novel)&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he became Army Surgeon General (equivalent to Lieutenant General), and temporalily withdrew from creative activities, but he later began to issue &apos;Subaru (a literary magazine)&apos;, then wrote &apos;Vita Sexualis&apos;, &apos;The Wild Geese (novel)&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>changed title to match 5. it withdrew him&gt;he withdrew. creation&gt;creative</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he became Army Surgeon General (equivalent to Lieutenant General), and temporarily withdrew from creative activities, but he later began to issue &quot;Subaru&quot; (a literary magazine), then wrote &quot;Vita Sexualis,&quot; &quot;&apos;The Wild Geese&quot; (novel) and so on.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>乃木希典の殉死に影響されて『興津弥五右衛門の遺書』発表後は、『阿部一族』『高瀬舟 (小説)』などの歴史小説、史伝『渋江抽斎』を書いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After publishing &apos;The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon&apos; inspired by the incident that Maresuke NOGI followed his master to his grave, he wrote the historical novels such as &apos;The Abe Clan&apos; and &apos;Takasebune (The Boat on the River Takase)&apos; and a biography based on a historical evidence, &apos;Chusai SHIBUE&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After publishing &apos;The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon&apos; inspired by the incident of Maresuke NOGI followed his master to his grave, he wrote the historical novels such as &apos;The Abe Clan&apos; and &apos;Takasebune (The Boat on the River Takase)&apos; and a biography based on a historical evidence, &apos;Chusai SHIBUE&apos;.</e>
<cmt>incident that...followed&gt;incident of...following</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After publishing &quot;The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon&quot; inspired by the incident of Maresuke NOGI followed his master to his grave, he wrote the historical novels such as &quot;The Abe Clan&quot; and &quot;Takasebune&quot; (The Boat on the River Takase) and a biography based on a historical evidence, &quot;Chusai SHIBUE.&quot;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。ピリオドの調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、帝室博物館（現在の東京国立博物館、奈良国立博物館、京都国立博物館）総長や帝国美術院（現日本芸術院）初代院長なども歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, he successively assumed office as Director of Imperial Museum (Present Tokyo National Museum, Nara National Museum and Kyoto National Museum) and the first director of Imperial Art Academy (present The Japan Art Academy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, he successively assumed office as Director of Imperial Museum (Present Tokyo National Museum, Nara National Museum and Kyoto National Museum) and the first director of Imperial Art Academy (present The Japan Art Academy).</e>
<cmt>なお＞further</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, he successively assumed office as Director of Imperial Museum (Present Tokyo National Museum, Nara National Museum and Kyoto National Museum) and the first director of Imperial Art Academy (present The Japan Art Academy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生い立ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Backgrounds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upbringing</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upbringing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>1862年2月17日（文久2年1月19日）、石見国津和野町(現島根県)で生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born at Tsuwano-cho, Iwami Province (present Shimane Prefecture) on February 17, 1862.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born at Tsuwano-cho, Iwami Province (present Shimane Prefecture) on February 17, 1862.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born at Tsuwano-cho, Iwami Province (present Shimane Prefecture) on February 17, 1862.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>代々津和野藩主、亀井公の御典医をつとめる森家では、祖父と父を婿養子として迎えているため、久々の跡継ぎ誕生であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Mori Family which successively served as gotenni (doctor who is hired by bakufu) for KAMEI Lord of Tsuwano Domain, his grandfather and father were adopted as son-in-law, so it was a birth of a heir after a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Mori Family who successively served as gotenni (doctor hired by the bakufu) for Lord KAMEI of Tsuwano Domain, his grandfather and father had both been adopted in the family as son-in-laws for lack of a male successor, so Ogai was the first heir born for a long time.</e>
<cmt>KAMEI Lord&gt;Lord KAMEI. 婿養子の部分については説明文を入れてみました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Mori family who successively served as goteni (doctor hired by the bakufu) for Lord KAMEI of Tsuwano Domain, his grandfather and father had both been adopted in the family as son-in-laws for lack of a male successor, so Ogai was the first heir born for a long time.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また前年、祖父の白仙が東海道の土山宿で病死したため、とくに祖母は鴎外を白仙の生まれ変わりといって喜び、後年、鴎外が留学と出征から無事帰国するたびに、はらはらと涙を落としたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in the previous year, his grandfather, Hakusen, died of a disease at Tsuchiyama-juku Station of Tokaido, so his grandmoter was particularly delighted with Ogai&apos;s birth, looking at him as reincarnation of his grandfather, and later, whenever he safely came back to Japan from his study abroad or the front, she is said to have cried silently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, as his grandfather Hakusen had died of disease the previous year at Tsuchiyama-juku Station on the Tokaido road, his grandmother was particularly delighted with Ogai&apos;s birth, looking at him as reincarnation of his grandfather, and it is said that later, whenever he safely came back to Japan from his study abroad or the front she would shed silent tears.</e>
<cmt>Changed the order. Corrected spelling of grandmother</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, as his grandfather Hakusen had died of disease the previous year at Tsuchiyama-juku Station on the Tokaido road, his grandmother was particularly delighted with Ogai&apos;s birth, looking at him as reincarnation of his grandfather, and it is said that later, whenever he safely came back to Japan from his study abroad or the front she would shed silent tears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>藩医の嫡男として、幼い頃から論語や孟子やオランダ語などを学び、藩校の養老館では四書五経を復読。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a heir of Edo-period doctor working at a public clinic, he learned Rongo Analects, The Book of Mencius, Dutch and so on from his childhood, and repeatedly read shishogokyo (the Four Books and Five Classics of Confucianism, the Nine Chinese Classics) at Yoro College, a hanko(domain school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the heir of a Han&apos;i (doctor working at a public clinic), he had learned the Analects of Confucius, The Book of Mencius, Dutch and so on from childhood, and repeatedly read shishogokyo (the Four Books and Five Classics of Confucianism, the Nine Chinese Classics) at Yoro College, a hanko (domain school).</e>
<cmt>Gave the name of 藩医 and explanation. he learned&gt;he had learned.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the heir of a Hani (doctor working at a public clinic), he had learned the Analects of Confucius, The Book of Mencius, Dutch and so on from childhood, and repeatedly read shishogokyo (the Four Books and Five Classics of Confucianism, the Nine Chinese Classics) at Yoro College, a hanko (domain school).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>当時の記録から、9歳で15歳相当の学力と推測されており、激動の明治維新に家族と周囲から将来を期待されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the records of the times, his academic ability at 9 is presumed the same level as 15 years old, so his family and surroundings being in the upturn of Meiji Restoration put their hope in his future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From records of the time, his academic ability at 9 was said to be the same level as a 15 year-old, so his family and those around him, amidst the upheaval of Meiji Restoration, put their hope in his future.</e>
<cmt>records of the times&gt;records of the time. presumed&gt;was said. surroundings&gt;those around him. being in the upturn&gt;amidst the upheaval.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From records of the time, his academic ability at 9 was said to be the same level as a 15 year-old, so his family and those around him, amidst the upheaval of Meiji Restoration, put their hope in his future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>1872年（明治5年）、廃藩置県等をきっかけに10歳で父と上京し、翌年、住居などを売却して残る家族も故郷を離れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1872, taking the opportunity of Haihan-chiken and so on, he went down to Tokyo along with his father at 10, and in the following year, the rest of his family also sold their residence and left their hometown to join them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1872 at the age of 10, prompted by the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures, he moved to Tokyo with his father, and the following year, the rest of his family also sold their residence and left their hometown to join them.</e>
<cmt>Haihan-chikenの説明文を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1872 at the age of 10, prompted by the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures, he moved to Tokyo with his father, and the following year, the rest of his family also sold their residence and left their hometown to join them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>東京では、官立医学校（ドイツ人教官がドイツ語で講義）への入学に備え、ドイツ語を習得するため、1872年10月に私塾の進文学社に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered the Shinbungakusha school, a private school, in October 1872 in order to learn German preparing for the admission to Kanritsu Igakko (National Medical School) (where German instructors gave a lecture in German).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered the private Shinbungakusha school in October 1872 in order to learn German in preparation for admission to Kanritsu Igakko (National Medical School) where lectures were given in German by German instructors.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the private Shinbungakusha school in October 1872 in order to learn German in preparation for admission to Kanritsu Igakko (National Medical School) where lectures were given in German by German instructors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その際に通学の便から、政府高官の親族西周 (啓蒙家)（にし・あまね）の邸宅に寄食した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time, he lodged with Amane NISHI (illuminator), a relative who was a governmental high official, because of the convenience for commuting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, he lodged with philosopher Amane NISHI, a relative who was a High Governmental Official, because of the convenience for commuting.</e>
<cmt>Illuminator&gt;philosoper http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nishi_Amane</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, he lodged with philosopher Amane NISHI, a relative who was a High Governmental Official, because of the convenience for commuting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このような幼少期を過ごした鴎外は、ドイツ人学者にドイツ語で反論して打ち負かすほど、語学に堪能であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai who had such childhood was proficient in the foreign languages enough to defeat a German professor by bringing forward a counterargument in German.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having had such a childhood, Ogai was proficient enough in foreign languages to get the better of a German professor by bringing forward a counterargument in German.</e>
<cmt>Ogai who had&gt;Having had...Ogai. defeat&gt;get the better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having had such a childhood, Ogai was proficient enough in foreign languages to get the better of a German professor by bringing forward a counterargument in German.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>著作でドイツ語やフランス語などを多用しており、また中国古典からの引用も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He used German and French a lot in his books and took citation from Chinese classics often.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He used German and French a lot in his books and often took quotes from Chinese classics.</e>
<cmt>citation&gt;quotes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He used German and French a lot in his books and often took quotes from Chinese classics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>なお、西洋語学を習得する秘訣として、作品内で語源を学習に役立てる逸話を記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, as a key to learning western languages, he put an anecdote to use the origin of a word for learning in a book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, as a aid for those learning western languages, he added anecdotes to help memorize the derivation of words.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, as a aid for those learning western languages, he added anecdotes to help memorize the derivation of words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>ドイツ留学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Study in Germany</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Study in Germany</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Study in Germany</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>1873年（明治6年）11月、入校試問を受け、第一大学区医学校（現東京大学医学部）予科に実年齢より2歳多く偽り、11歳で入学。。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took the entrance exam and entered the preparatory school of Daiichi Daigaku-ku Igakko (present the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine) in November 1873, at the age of 11, faking his age two years older than his real age (a fellow pupil, Moriharu MIURA, who later graduated at the top of the list, also entered in November).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took the entrance exam and entered the preparatory school Daiichi Daigaku-ku Igakko (present University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine) in November 1873 at the age of 11, faking his age to be two years older than he really was.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took the entrance exam and entered the preparatory school Daiichi Daigaku-ku Igakko (present University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine) in November 1873 at the age of 11, faking his age to be two years older than he really was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>（のちに首席で卒業する同級生の三浦守治も同年11月に入学）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fellow pupil, Moriharu MIURA, who later graduated at the top of the class, entered in November of the same year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fellow pupil, Moriharu MIURA, who later graduated at the top of the class, entered in November of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1881年（明治14年）7月4日、19歳で本科を卒業（今後も破られないであろう最年少卒業記録）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 4 in 1881, he graduated from the regular course at 19 (this is the youngest record of graduation which would never be broken).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 4 1881, he graduated from the regular course at the age of just 19 (the youngest recorded age of graduation which has never been broken).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 4 1881, he graduated from the regular course at the age of just 19 (the youngest recorded age of graduation which has never been broken).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>卒業席次が8番であり、大学に残って研究者になる道が閉ざされたものの、文部科学省派遣留学生としてドイツに行く希望を持ちながら、父の病院を手伝っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he missed the option to remain in the university to become a researcher because his class order at graduation was the 8th place, he held a hope to visit Germany as an oversea student under Ministry of Education, helping his father&apos;s clinic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He did not have the chance to remain at the university to become a researcher as he only ranked 8th in his graduating class, but went on to help out his father&apos;s clinic, all the time dreaming of visiting Germany as an overseas student with the Ministry of Education,.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did not have the chance to remain at the university to become a researcher as he only ranked 8th in his graduating class, but went on to help out his father&apos;s clinic, all the time dreaming of visiting Germany as an overseas student with the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>Education,. &gt; Education.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その進路未定の状況を見かねた同窓生の小池正直は、陸軍省医務局次長の石黒忠悳に鴎外を採用するよう長文の熱い推薦状を出しており、また小池と同じく陸軍軍医になっていた親友の賀古鶴所（かこ･つると）は、鴎外に陸軍省入りを勧めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fellow pupil, Masanao KOIKE, who was anxious about him who couldn&apos;t move on to the next step, submit a long enthusiastique recommendation letter to Tadanori ISHIGURO, the vice-chief of Medical Bureau of Ministry of Army, requesting to employ Ogai, while his closest friend, Tsuruto KOGA, was encouraging him to join the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fellow pupil, Masanao KOIKE, who was concerned about Ogai being unable to progress to the next step, submitted a long, enthusiastic recommendation letter to Tadanori ISHIGURO, the vice-chief of the Medical Bureau of the Department of War requesting him to employ Ogai, and his closest friend Tsuruto KOGA (who had become a Army Surgeon like Masanao) also encouraged him to join the Department of War.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fellow pupil, Masanao KOIKE, who was concerned about Ogai being unable to progress to the next step, submitted a long, enthusiastic recommendation letter to Tadanori ISHIGURO, the vice-chief of the Medical Bureau of the Department of War requesting him to employ Ogai, and his closest friend Tsuruto KOGA (who had become a Army Surgeon like Masanao) also encouraged him to join the Department of War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>結局のところ鴎外は、同年12月16日に陸軍軍医副（中尉相当）になり、東京陸軍病院に勤務した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, Ogai was hired as Gunni-fuku of Army (corresponding to lieutenant) to work at Tokyo Army Hospital on December 16 of the year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Ogai was hired as Gunni-fuku of Army (equivalent to lieutenant) to work at Tokyo Army Hospital from December 16 of that year.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Ogai was hired as Guni-fuku of Army (equivalent to lieutenant) to work at Tokyo Army Hospital from December 16 of that year.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>なお妹、小金井喜美子の回想によれば、若き日の鴎外は、四君子を描いたり、庭を写生したり、職場から帰宅後しばしば寄席に出かけたり（喜美子と一緒に出かけたとき、ある落語家の長唄を聴いて中座）したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to his younger sister, Kimiko KOGANEI&apos;s recollection, Ogai in his youth depicted Shikunshi (four plants with high virtue), sketched their courtyard and often went to yose (storyteller theater) after coming back from his work (she writes that he once took Kimiko, and intolerantly left before a Rakugo story teller finished his nagauta (long epic song with shamisen accompaniment).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the memoirs of his younger sister, Kimiko KOGANEI, Ogai in his youth made depictions of Shikunshi (four plants with high virtue), sketched their courtyard and often went to the yose (storyteller theater) after coming back from work; she writes that he once took her, but left halfway through before the Rakugo story teller finished his nagauta (long epic song with shamisen accompaniment).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the memoirs of his younger sister, Kimiko KOGANEI, Ogai in his youth made depictions of Shikunshi (four plants with high virtue), sketched their courtyard and often went to the yose (storyteller theater) after coming back from work; she writes that he once took her, but left halfway through before the Rakugo story teller finished his nagauta (long epic song with shamisen accompaniment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>入省して半年後の1882年（明治15年）5月、東京大学医学部卒の同期8名の中で最初の陸軍省医務局付となり、プロイセンの陸軍衛生制度に関する文献調査に従事し、早くも翌年3月には『医政全書稿本』全十二巻を役所に納めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1882, half a year after his joining the Ministry, he was appointed to work at the medical bureau of Ministry of Army, for the first time for the eight graduates in the same class from the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine, and engaged in the research of the literature on the Prussian army hygiene system, and handed over the total twelve volumes of &apos;Isei Zensho Kohon (Manuscript of Medical Science)&apos; he had wrote to the public office as early as March of the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1882, half a year after joining the Ministry, he was appointed among 8 graduates from the same class at the University of Tokyo to be the first to work at the medical bureau of Department of War, Faculty of Medicine, and engaged in research of literature on the Prussian army hygiene system, and as early as March of the following year submitted the entire twelve volumes of his work &apos;Isei Zensho Kohon (Manuscript of Medical Science)&apos; to the public office.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1882, half a year after joining the Ministry, he was appointed among 8 graduates from the same class at the University of Tokyo to be the first to work at the medical bureau of Department of War, Faculty of Medicine, and engaged in research of literature on the Prussian army hygiene system, and as early as March of the following year submitted the entire twelve volumes of his work &quot;Isei Zensho Kohon&quot; (Manuscript of Medical Science) to the public office.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。日付補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1884年（明治17年）6月、衛生衛生学を修めるとともにドイツ陸軍の衛生制度を調べるため、ドイツ留学を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1884, he completed the course of hygiene, and followed the order to go to Germany to look into the German Army&apos;s hygiene system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1884, he completed a course on hygiene, and followed an order to go to Germany to look into the German Army&apos;s hygiene system.</e>
<cmt>the course of&gt;a course on hygiene</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1884, he completed a course on hygiene, and followed an order to go to Germany to look into the German Army&apos;s hygiene system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>7月28日、明治天皇に拝謁し、賢所（かしこどころ）に参拝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 28, he was granted an audience with Meiji Emperor, and visited the Kashikodokoro (a palace sanctuary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 28, he was granted an audience with the Meiji Emperor, and visited the Kashikodokoro (palace sanctuary).</e>
<cmt>Meiji Emperor&gt;the Meiji Emperor　,　a palace &gt; palace</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 28, he was granted an audience with the Meiji Emperor, and visited the Kashikodokoro (palace sanctuary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>8月24日、陸軍省派遣留学生として横浜港から出国し、10月7日にフランスのマルセイユ港に到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 24, he left Yokohama Port as an oversea student under Ministry of Army, and arrived at Marseille Port in France on October 7.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 24, he left Yokohama Port as an overseas student under the Department of War and arrived at the Port of Marseille in France on October 7.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 24, he left Yokohama Port as an overseas student under the Department of War and arrived at the Port of Marseille in France on October 7.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>同月11日に首都ベルリンに入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he entered Berlin, the capital city of Germany, on 11 of the month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then entered Berlin, the capital of Germany, on the 11th of the same month.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then entered Berlin, the capital of Germany, on the 11th of the same month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>最初の一年をすごしたライプツィヒ（1884年11月22日－翌年10月11日）で、生活に慣れていない鴎外を助けたのが、昼食と夜食をとっていたフォーゲル家の人達であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Leipzig where he spent the first year (from November 22, 1884 to October 11, 1885), Ogai who hadn&apos;t got used to his new life was supported by the Vogel Family who served him lunch and dinner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai spent his first year (from November 22, 1884 to October 11, 1885) in Leipzig, and not yet accustomed to his new life, was supported by the Vogel Family who served him lunch and dinner.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai spent his first year (from November 22, 1884 to October 11, 1885) in Leipzig, and not yet accustomed to his new life, was supported by the Vogel family who served him lunch and dinner.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、黒衣の女性ルチウスなど下宿人たちとも親しくつきあい、ライプツィヒ大学ではフランツ・ホフマンなど良き師と同僚に恵まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also got along with other lodgers such as Lucius in black gown, and had a chance to get to know good collegues and master such as Franz Hoffmann in Universität Leipzig.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also got along well with other lodgers such as Lucius &apos;The woman in black&apos;, and was fortunate to have good collegues and masters such as Franz Hoffmann at the Universität Leipzig.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also got along well with other lodgers such as Lucius &apos;The woman in black,&apos; and was fortunate to have good colleagues and masters such as Franz Hoffmann at the Universität Leipzig.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>演習を観るために訪れたザクセン王国の首都ドレスデンでは、ドレスデン美術館にも行き、ラファエロ・サンティの「サン･シストの聖母」を鑑賞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Dresden, the capital city of Kingdom of Saxony, which he visited to see the maneuvers, he went to Dresden Art Museum to view &apos;Madonna of San Sisto&apos; of Raffaello Santi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Dresden, capital of the Kingdom of Saxony, which he visited to watch military practice, he went to Dresden Art Museum to view &apos;Madonna of San Sisto&apos; by Raffaello Santi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Dresden, capital of the Kingdom of Saxony, which he visited to watch military practice, he went to Dresden Art Museum to view &apos;Madonna of San Sisto&apos; by Raffaello Santi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>次の滞在地ドレスデン（1885年10月11日－翌年3月7日）では、主として軍医学講習会に参加するため、5ケ月ほど生活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, he stayed in Dresden for about five months (from October 11, 1885 to March 7, 1886) in order to take part in the workshop on the army surgeon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, he stayed in Dresden for about five months (from October 11, 1885 to March 7, 1886) in order to take part in an army surgeon&apos;s workshop.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, he stayed in Dresden for about five months (from October 11, 1885 to March 7, 1886) in order to take part in an army surgeon&apos;s workshop.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>王室関係者や軍人との交際が多く、王宮の舞踏会や貴族の夜会や宮廷劇場などに出入りした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He frequently saw the royal-family-related persons and military men, and frequented the royal ball, nobles&apos; evening party, the theater in the imperial court and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had many encounters with people connected to the royal family and military men, and frequented royal balls, nobles&apos; evening parties, theater in the Royal court and so on.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had many encounters with people connected to the royal family and military men, and frequented royal balls, nobles&apos; evening parties, theater in the Royal court and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、二人の大切な友人を得ており、一人は鴎外の指導者ザクセン軍医監のウィルヘルム･ロートで、もう一人は外国語が堪能な同僚軍医のキルケである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also established two precious friendships with Wilhelm Roth, Sergeon major general of Saxony, who was a master of Ogai, and Kirke, an army sergeon, one of Ogai&apos;s co-workers, who excelled at foreign languages.</e>
<cmt>「キルケ=Kirke」としましたが、webで検索したものの本当のスペルは確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also established two valued friendships with Wilhelm Roth, Surgeon Major General of Saxony, who was a master of his, and Kirke, an army surgeon and one of his co-workers, who excelled at foreign languages.</e>
<cmt>キルケの件は、Kierkeというのがよくあるドイツの名前ですからKierkeにすればいいのではないかと思っております。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also established two valued friendships with Wilhelm Roth, Surgeon Major General of Saxony, who was a master of his, and Keirke, an army surgeon and one of his co-workers, who excelled at foreign languages.</e>
<cmt>NCのアドバイスに従い、名前を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>なお、ドレスデンを離れる前日、ハインリッヒ・エドムント・ナウマンの講演に反論しており、のちにミュンヘンの一流紙で論争が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, the day before he left Dresden, he put forward a counterargument to Heinrich Edmund NAUMANN, and it later caused a dispute in the most famous newspaper of Munich.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the day before he left Dresden, he put forward a counterargument to Heinrich Edmund NAUMANN which later caused a dispute in Munich&apos;s most famous newspaper.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the day before he left Dresden, he put forward a counterargument to Heinrich Edmund NAUMANN which later caused a dispute in Munich&apos;s most famous newspaper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>ミュンヘン（1886年3月8日－翌年4月15日）では、ミュンヘン大学のマックス・フォン・ペッテンコーファーに師事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Munich (March 8, 1886 - April 15, 1887), he studied under Max von Pettenkofer of Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whilst in Munich (from March 8, 1886 - April 15, 1887), he studied under Max von Pettenkofer of the Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whilst in Munich (from March 8, 1886 - April 15, 1887), he studied under Max von Pettenkofer of the Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>研究のかたわら、邦人の少なかったドレスデンと違って同世代の原田直次郎や近衛篤麿など名士の子息と多く交際し、また、よく観劇していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spare moments from his study, unlike in Dresden where Japanese people were few, he frequently saw the sons of prominent figures such as Naojiro HARADA and Atsumaro KONOE of the same generation as him, and also frequented the theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his spare time from studying, unlike in Dresden where there were few Japanese people, he frequently saw his contemporaries. the sons of prominent figures such as Naojiro HARADA and Atsumaro KONOE as well as frequenting the theater.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike in Dresden where there were few Japanese people, he frequently went out with his contemporaries such as Naojiro HARADA and Atsumaro KONOE, the sons of of prominent figures, and attended theaters in his spare time from studying.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>次のベルリン（1887年4月16日－翌年7月5日）でも、早速北里柴三郎とともにロベルト・コッホに会いに行っており、細菌学の入門講座をへてコッホの衛生試験所に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his next destination Berlin (April 16, 1887 - July 5, 1888), he went to see Robert Koch along with Shibasaburo KITASATO as soon as his arrival, then joined Koch&apos;s hygienic laboratory after completing a beginner&apos;s course of bacteriology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his next destination Berlin (April 16, 1887 - July 5, 1888), he went to visit Robert Koch and Shibasaburo KITASATO as soon as he arrived, later joining Koch&apos;s Sanitation Laboratory after completing a beginner&apos;s course on bacteriology.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his next destination Berlin (April 16, 1887 - July 5, 1888), he went to visit Robert Koch and Shibasaburo KITASATO as soon as he arrived, later joining Koch&apos;s Sanitation Laboratory after completing a beginner&apos;s course on bacteriology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>9月下旬、カールスルーエで開催される第四回赤十字社会議の日本代表（首席）としてドイツを訪れていた石黒忠悳軍医監に随行し、通訳官として同会議に出席。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late September, he accompanied Tadanori ISHIGURO, Sergeon Major General, who were staying in Germany as a representative of Japan (head) to take part in the 4th Red Cross Society Conference held at Karlsruhe, in order to attend the conference as his interpreter official.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In late September, he accompanied Tadanori ISHIGURO, Surgeon Major General - visiting Germany as head Japanese representative at the 4th Red Cross Society Conference in Karlsruhe - to the conference as his interpreter official.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In late September, he accompanied Tadanori ISHIGURO, Surgeon Major General - visiting Germany as head Japanese representative at the 4th Red Cross Society Conference in Karlsruhe - to the conference as his interpreter official.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>9月26･27日に発言し、とりわけ最終日の27日は「ブラボー」と叫ぶ人が出るなど大きな反響があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They made statements on September 26 and 27, and on 27 especially, their statements called forth an echo of audiences, and one of them shouted &apos;Bravo&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They made statements on September 26th and 27th, and on the latter day in particular their statements brought loud reactions from the audience, some people even shouting &apos;Bravo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They made statements on September 26 and 27, and on the latter day in particular their statements brought loud reactions from the audience, some people even shouting &apos;Bravo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>日付表記を統一しました。ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>会議を終えた一行は、9月28日ウイーンに移動し、万国衛生会に日本政府代表として参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The party which had finished the conference moved on to Wien on Spetember 28 to take part in the International Health Exhibition as a representative of Japanese Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One group who had finished at the conference moved on to Wien on September 28th to take part in the International Health Exhibition as representatives of the Japanese Government.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One group who had finished at the conference moved on to Vienna on September 28 to take part in the International Health Exhibition as representatives of the Japanese Government.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を統一しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>11日間の滞在中、鴎外は恩師や知人と再会した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the eleven days of stay, Ogai met his master and acquaintances again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the eleven days he stayed, Ogai was reunited with his master and acquaintances.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the eleven days he stayed, Ogai was reunited with his master and acquaintances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>1888年（明治21年）1月、大和会の新年会でドイツ語の講演をして公使の西園寺公望に激賞されており、18日から田村怡与造大尉の求めに応じてカール・フォン・クラウゼヴィッツの『戦争論 (クラウゼヴィッツ)日本での成立』を講じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1888, he made a lecture in German at the New Year&apos;s party hosted by Yamatokai Society, that was highly praised by Minister Kinmochi SAIONJI, and from 18th, he began to make a lecture about &quot;On War (Clausewitz) settled down in Japan&quot; of Carl von Clausewitz, in response to the request of Iyozo TAMURA, Senior Lieutenant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1888, he made a lecture in German at a New Year&apos;s party hosted by Yamatokai Society, that was highly praised by Minister Kinmochi SAIONJI, and from the 18th of January he began to lecture on &quot;Carl von Clausewitz&apos;s &apos;On War&apos; and its establishment in Japan&quot;, in response to a request by Iyozo TAMURA, Senior Lieutenant.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1888, he made a lecture in German at a New Year&apos;s party hosted by Yamatokai Society, that was highly praised by Minister Kinmochi SAIONJI, and from January 18 he began to lecture on &quot;Carl von Clausewitz&apos;s &apos;On War&apos; and its establishment in Japan,&quot; in response to a request by Iyozo TAMURA, Senior Lieutenant.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を統一しました。カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>なお、留学を一年延長した代わりに、地味な隊付勤務（プロイセン近衛歩兵第二連隊の医務）も経験しており、そうしたベルリンでの生活は、ミュンヘンなどに比べ、より「公」的なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he experienced a modest work in the army (medical work for the second infantry regiment of the imperial guard of Prussia) in exchange of getting extended his stay for another year, and his life in Berlin was more &apos;public&apos; compared to that of Munich or other cities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he experienced basic work in the army (medical work for the second infantry regiment of the imperial guard of Prussia) in exchange for an extension of his stay for another year, and as such his life in Berlin was more &apos;public&apos; than it had been in Munich and other cities.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he experienced basic work in the army (medical work for the second infantry regiment of the imperial guard of Prussia) in exchange for an extension of his stay for another year, and as such his life in Berlin was more &apos;public&apos; than it had been in Munich and other cities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>ただし、後述するドイツ人女性と出会った都市でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it also was the city where he met a German woman mentioned later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was also the city where he met the German woman mentioned below.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was also the city where he met the German woman mentioned below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="52">
<j>1888年7月5日、石黒とともにベルリンを発ち、帰国の途についた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 5, 1888, he left Berlin with Ishiguro to go back to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 5, 1888, he left Berlin with Ishiguro to go back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 5, 1888, he left Berlin with Ishiguro to go back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>ロンドン（保安条例によって東京からの退去処分を受けた尾崎行雄に会い詩を4首おくった）やパリに立ち寄りながら、7月29日マルセイユ港を後にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He stopped by London (he saw Yukio OZAKI who took the punishment of leaving Tokyo complying with the regulations for the preservation of law and order, and gifted him four poems) and Paris, then left Marseille Port on July 29.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He stopped by London (visiting Yukio OZAKI who had been deported from Tokyo under regulations for the preservation of law and order, whom he gifted four poems) and Paris, then left Marseille Port on July 29th.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He stopped by London (visiting Yukio OZAKI who had been deported from Tokyo under regulations for the preservation of law and order, whom he gifted four poems) and Paris, then left Marseille Port on July 29.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>その4日前の7月25日、あるドイツ人女性がブレーメン港から日本に向かっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 25, four days before that, a German woman was on the way to Japan after leaving Port Bremen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four days previously on July 25th, the German woman left Port Bremen heading for Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four days previously on July 25, the German woman left Port Bremen heading for Japan.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>9月8日、横浜港に着き、午後帰京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 8, he arrived at Yokohama Port and returned to Tokyo in the afternoon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 8, Ogai arrived at Yokohama Port and returned to Tokyo in the afternoon.</e>
<cmt>he&gt;Ogai</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 8, Ogai arrived at Yokohama Port and returned to Tokyo in the afternoon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>同日付けで陸軍軍医学校の教官に補され、11月には陸軍大学校日本陸軍の陸大教官の兼補を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as an instructor of Army Doctor School on the same day, and further appointed as an instructor of the Army War College in November, thus he held the two posts concurrently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed instructor of the Army Medical School the same day, and further appointed as instructor of the Army War College in November, thus he held the two posts concurrently.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed instructor of the Army Medical School the same day, and further appointed as instructor of the Army War College in November, thus he held the two posts concurrently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>なお帰国直後、ドイツ人女性が来日して滞在一月（9月12日-10月17日）ほどで離日する出来事があり、小説『舞姫』の素材の一つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, just after his coming back to Japan, the German woman who had been in Japan for about one month (September 12 - October 17) had a reason to leave Japan, and this incident was used as a material for his novel &apos;Maihime (The Dancing Girl)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, just after Ogai returned to Japan, the German woman who had been there for about one month (September 12 - October 17) had to suddenly leave, and this incident was used as material for his novel &apos;Maihime (The Dancing Girl)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, just after Ogai returned to Japan, the German woman who had been there for about one month (September 12 - October 17) had to suddenly leave, and this incident was used as material for his novel &quot;Maihime&quot; (The Dancing Girl).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>後年、文通をするなど、その女性を生涯忘れることは無かったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after that, he kept in touch with her by correspondance, and seemed to never forget the woman in his whole life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after that, he kept in touch with her in writing, and seemed to never forget her his whole life.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after that, he kept in touch with her in writing, and seemed to never forget her his whole life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>初期の文筆活動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Writing activities in the initial period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early literary activities</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early literary activities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>1889年（明治22年）1月3日、読売新聞の付録に『小説論』を発表し、また同日の読売新聞から、弟の三木竹二とともにカルデロン・デ・ラ・バルカの戯曲『調高矣津弦一曲』（原題：サラメヤの村長）を共訳して随時発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 3, 1889, he published the &apos;Shosetsu-ron (theory of novel)&apos; as an appendix of the newspaper of Yomiuri Shimbun, and from the same day, he began to publish the translation of &apos;El Alcalde de Zalamea (original title : (The Mayor of Zalamea)&apos;, a play of Calderón de la Barca, which he and his younger brother Takeji MIKI translated into Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 3, 1889, he published the &apos;Shosetsu-ron (theory of the novel)&apos; as an appendix of the newspaper Yomiuri Shimbun, and from the same day, he began to publish a translation of &apos;El Alcalde de Zalamea (original title : (The Mayor of Zalamea)&apos;, a play of Calderón de la Barca, which he and his younger brother Takeji MIKI translated into Japanese.</e>
<cmt>theory of novel &gt;theory of the novel</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 3, 1889, he published the &quot;Shosetsu-ron&quot; (theory of the novel) as an appendix of the newspaper Yomiuri Shimbun, and from the same day, he began to publish a translation of &quot;El Alcalde de Zalamea&quot; (original title: The Mayor of Zalamea), a play of Calderón de la Barca, which he and his younger brother Takeji MIKI translated into Japanese.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>その翻訳戯曲を高く評価したのが徳富蘇峰であり、8月に蘇峰が主筆をつとめる民友社の雑誌『国民之友』夏期文芸付録に、訳詩集『於母影』（署名は「S･S･S」（新声社の略記））を発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soho TOKUTOMI highly evaluated his translating play, and Ogai published a book of poems &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos; which he translated into Japanese as an appendix of the summer literature issue of &apos;Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend)&apos;, a magazine of Minyusya, for which Soho was working as a chief editor, in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soho TOKUTOMI regarded his translation highly, and in August Ogai published a book of poems &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos; which he translated into Japanese as an appendix to the summer issue of &apos;Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend)&apos;, a magazine published by Minyusha, for which Soho was working as a chief editor.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soho TOKUTOMI regarded his translation highly, and in August Ogai published a book of poems &quot;Omokage&quot; (Vestiges) (his signature was S. S. S) which he translated into Japanese as an appendix to the summer issue of &quot;Kokumin no tomo&quot; (The Nation&apos;s Friend), a magazine published by Minyusha, for which Soho was working as a chief editor.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>その『於母影』は、日本近代詩の形成などに大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omokage (Vestiges) gave a great impact on the formation of the modern-style poetry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omokage (Vestiges) had a great influence on the development of modern poetry.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Omokage&quot; (Vestiges) had a great influence on the development of modern poetry.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また『於母影』の原稿料50円をもとに、竹二など同人たちと日本最初の評論中心の専門誌『しがらみ草紙』を創刊した（日清戦争の勃発により59号で廃刊）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also began to issue &apos;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&apos;, the first journal focusing on criticism in Japan, along with his coteries including Takeji, with the fund of 50 yen he had earned from his manuscript of &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos; (The publication was continued until vol. 59, then the Sino-Japanese War broke out).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also began to issue &apos;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&apos;, the first journal in Japan focusing on comment and criticism, along with coteries including Takeji, with funds of 50 yen he had earned from his manuscript of &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos; (The publication was continued until vol. 59, when the Sino-Japanese War broke out).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also began to issue &quot;Shigarami Soshi&quot; (Constraint Brochure), the first journal in Japan focusing on comment and criticism, along with coteries including Takeji, with funds of 50 yen he had earned from his manuscript of &quot;Omokage&quot; (Vestiges) (The publication was continued until vol. 59, when the Sino-Japanese War broke out).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>このように、外国文学などの翻訳を手始めに（『即興詩人』『ファウスト』などが有名）、熱心に評論的啓蒙活動をつづけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, he passionately continued his critical enlightenment activities, beginning with translation of foreign literature (&apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&apos; and &apos;Faust&apos; are well-known).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, he passionately continued his critical enlightenment activities, starting with translations of foreign literature (&apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&apos; and &apos;Faust&apos; are well-known).</e>
<cmt>beginning with translation&gt;starting with translations</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, he passionately continued his critical enlightenment activities, starting with translations of foreign literature (&quot;Sokkyo Shijin&quot; (Improvising Poet) and &quot;Faust&quot; are well-known).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>当時、情報の乏しい欧州ドイツを舞台にした『舞姫』『うたかたの記』『文づかひ』を相次いで発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also successively published &apos;Maihime (The Dancing Girl)&apos;, &apos;Foam on the Waves&apos; and &apos;The Courier&apos; which location were set in Germany, Europe, which was almost unknown by Japanese people at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also successively published &apos;Maihime (The Dancing Girl)&apos;, &apos;Foam on the Waves&apos; and &apos;The Courier&apos; which location were set in Germany, a country almost unknown to Japanese people at the time.</e>
<cmt>Europe, which was almost unknown by &gt;a country almost unknown to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also successively published &quot;Maihime&quot; (The Dancing Girl), &quot;Foam on the Waves&quot; and &quot;The Courier&quot; which location were set in Germany, a country almost unknown to Japanese people at the time.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>とりわけ、日本人と外国人が恋愛関係になる『舞姫』は、読者を驚かせたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, &apos;Maihime (The Dancing Girl)&apos; which was a love story between a Japanese man and a German woman seemed to surprise Japanese readers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, &apos;Maihime (The Dancing Girl)&apos;- a love story between a Japanese man and a German woman - seemed to shock Japanese readers.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, &quot;Maihime&quot; (The Dancing Girl) - a love story between a Japanese man and a German woman - seemed to shock Japanese readers.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>ちなみに、そのドイツ三部作をめぐって石橋忍月と論争を、また『しがらみ草紙』上で坪内逍遥の記実主義を批判して没理想論争を繰り広げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, he had a dispute with Ningetsu ISHIBASHI on his three books which were related to Germany, and he also rolled out a dispute on &quot;anti-idealism&quot;, by putting his critical comments on realism advocated by Shoyo TSUBOUCHI in his Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furhtermore, he had a dispute with Ningetsu ISHIBASHI about his three books on Germany, and also instigated a dispute on &quot;anti-idealism&quot;, by publishing critical comments in his Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure) about realism as advocated by Shoyo TSUBOUCHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he had a dispute with Ningetsu ISHIBASHI about his three books on Germany, and also instigated a dispute on &quot;anti-idealism,&quot; by publishing critical comments in his &quot;Shigarami Soshi&quot; (Constraint Brochure) about realism as advocated by Shoyo TSUBOUCHI.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>1889年（明治22年）に東京美術学校（現東京藝術大学）の美術解剖学講師を、1892年（明治25年）9月に慶應義塾大学の審美学（美学の旧称）講師を委嘱された（いずれも日清戦争出征時と小倉転勤時に解嘱））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was asked to be an instructor of artistic anatomy for Tokyo School of Fine Arts (present Tokyo University of the Arts) in 1889 as well as an instructor of aesthetics (old name of aesthetics) for Keio University in September 1892 (relieved of these posts respectively at the time of departure for the front of Sino-Japanese War and transfer to Ogura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was asked to be an instructor of art analysis at the Tokyo School of Fine Arts (present Tokyo University of the Arts) in 1889 as well as an instructor of aesthetics at Keio University in September 1892 (However he was relieved of both these posts when he had to leave for the front line of the Sino-Japanese War and was transferred to Ogura.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was asked to be an instructor of art analysis at the Tokyo School of Fine Arts (present Tokyo University of the Arts) in 1889 as well as an instructor of aesthetics at Keio University in September 1892 (However he was relieved of both these posts when he had to leave for the front line of the Sino-Japanese War and was transferred to Ogura).</e>
<cmt>)補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>日清戦争出征と小倉「左遷」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Departure for the front of Sino-Japanese War and &apos;Demotion transfer&apos; to Ogura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Departure for the front line of the Sino-Japanese War and &apos;Demotion and transfer&apos; to Ogura</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Departure for the front line of the Sino-Japanese War and &apos;Demotion and transfer&apos; to Ogura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>1894年（明治27年）夏、日本と清が軍事衝突･開戦（8月1日、日本が宣戦布告）したため、鴎外は8月29日に東京を離れ、9月2日に広島の宇品港を発った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Japan and Qing caused a military confrontation and opened war in Summer 1894 (Japan made a proclamation of war on August 1), Ogai left Tokyo on August 29, then Ujina Port in Hiroshima on September 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Japan and Qing China collided and embarked on war in Summer 1894 (Japan made the proclamation of war on August 1), Ogai left Tokyo on August 29, then departed from Ujina Port in Hiroshima on September 2.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Japan and Qing China collided and embarked on war in Summer 1894 (Japan made the proclamation of war on August 1), Ogai left Tokyo on August 29, then departed from Ujina Port in Hiroshima on September 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>下関条約の締結後、1895年（明治28年）5月10日に近衛師団つきの従軍記者、正岡子規が帰国のあいさつのため、鴎外を訪ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 10, 1895 after the conclusion of Treaty of Shimonoseki, Shiki MASAOKA, a war correspondent serving with the Guards Division, visited Ogai for a greeting to welcome his back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 10, 1895 after the conclusion of the Treaty of Shimonoseki, Shiki MASAOKA, a war correspondent serving with the Guards Division, visited Ogai to welcome him back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Ogai for a greeting to welcome his back &gt; Ogai to welcome him back to Japan.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 10, 1895 after the conclusion of the Treaty of Shimonoseki, Shiki MASAOKA, a war correspondent serving with the Guards Division, visited Ogai to welcome him back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>清との戦争が終わったものの、鴎外は日本に割譲された台湾での勤務を命じられた（朝鮮勤務の小池正直とのバランスをとった人事とされる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the war with Qing was over, Ogai was ordered to work in Taiwan which was ceded to Japan (this placement is considered to balance with Masanao KOIKE who was working in Korea), so he went to Ujina Port on May 22 (Ogai saw his younger brother Takeji who visited him representing his family worring about), then, after two days, left for Taiwan along with Sukenori KABAYAMA, the first governor of Taiwan, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the war with Qing was over, Ogai was ordered to work in Taiwan which had been ceded to Japan (this placement was considered to be in harmony with that of Masanao KOIKE who was working in Korea).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the war with Qing was over, Ogai was ordered to work in Taiwan which had been ceded to Japan (this placement was considered to be in harmony with that of Masanao KOIKE who was working in Korea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>出発前は5月22日に宇品港に着き（心配する家族を代表して訪れた弟の竹二と面会）、2日後には初代台湾総督の樺山資紀等とともに台湾に向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before leaving he went to Ujina Port on May 22 (meeting his younger brother Takeji who visited him representing his concerned family), then after two days left for Taiwan along with Sukenori KABAYAMA, the first governor of Taiwan, and others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before leaving he went to Ujina Port on May 22 (meeting his younger brother Takeji who visited him representing his concerned family), then after two days left for Taiwan along with Sukenori KABAYAMA, the first governor of Taiwan, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>4ヶ月ほどの台湾勤務を終え、10月4日に帰京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came back to Japan after about four-month work in Tawan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came back to Japan after about four months&apos; work in Tawan.</e>
<cmt>four-month &gt; four months&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 4, he came back to Japan after about four months&apos; work in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>日付を補足しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>翌1896年（明治29年）1月、『しがらみ草紙』の後を受けて幸田露伴、斎藤緑雨とともに『めさまし草』を創刊し、合評「三人冗語」を載せ、当時の評壇の先頭に立った（1902年廃刊）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1896, in form of succeeding Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure), he began to issue Mezamashi-gusa (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine in association with Rohan KODA and Ryokuu SAITO, in which they put a joint review &apos;Sannin Jogo (redundant words by three people)&apos;, which put them at the top of the critics&apos; world of the times (the publication disconnected in 1902).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1896, he began to publish the magazine Mezamashi-gusa as a successor to Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure) in association with Rohan KODA and Ryokuu SAITO, in which they issued joint reviews &apos;Sannin Jogo (Three men&apos;s redundant words)&apos;, which put them at the top of the world of critics at the time (publication was discontinued in 1902).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1896, he began to publish the magazine &quot;Mezamashi-gusa&quot; as a successor to &quot;Shigarami Soshi&quot; (Constraint Brochure) in association with Rohan KODA and Ryokuu SAITO, in which they issued joint reviews &apos;Sannin Jogo&apos; (Three men&apos;s redundant words), which put them at the top of the world of critics at the time (publication was discontinued in 1902).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>また、このころより、評論的啓蒙活動は、戦闘的ないし論争的なものから、穏健的なものに変わっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, from around this time, his critical enlightenment activities turned from fighting or disputatious features to a moderate one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, from around this time, the nature of his activities became less confrontational and more moderate.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, from around this time, the nature of his activities became less confrontational and more moderate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="75">
<j>陸軍内で対ロシア戦の準備が進む中、1899年（明治32年）6月に軍医監（少将相当）に昇進し、東京（東部）・大阪（中部）とともに都督部が置かれていた小倉市（西部）の第12師団 (日本軍)軍医部長に「左遷」された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the preparation for the battle with Russia going on in the Army, he moved on to Surgeon major general (corresponding to Shosho) in June 1899, then was &apos;demoted&apos; to the post of Director of the army surgeon department of the twelfth division in Kokura City (western area) where the department of Totoku governor general was placed like Tokyo (eastern area) and Osaka (middle area) (During this time, he wrote &apos;Kokura Nikki (Kokura Diary)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whilst the Army was undergoing preparations for war with Russia, he was promoted to Surgeon major general in June 1899, then was &apos;demoted&apos; to the post of Director of the army surgeon department of the twelfth division in Kokura City (Western area, in contrast to Tokyo (Eastern area) and Osaka (Central area)).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whilst the Army was undergoing preparations for war with Russia, he was promoted to Surgeon major general (corresponding to Shosho) in June 1899, then was &apos;demoted&apos; to the post of Director of the army surgeon department of the twelfth division in Kokura City (Western area, in contrast to Tokyo (Eastern area) and Osaka (Central area)).</e>
<cmt>(corresponding to Shosho)補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>（このとき『小倉日記』が書かれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, he wrote &apos;Kokura Nikki (Kokura Diary).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, he wrote &quot;Kokura Nikki&quot; (Kokura Diary).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>世紀末から新世紀の初頭をすごした小倉時代には、歴史観と近代観にかかわる一連の随筆などが書かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While his staying in Kokura from the end of the century to the early new century, he wrote a series of essay about his historical view and modern view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While his staying in Kokura from the end of the 19th Century to the start of the 20th, he wrote a series of essay about his views on history and the modern age.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While his staying in Kokura from the end of the 19th Century to the start of the 20th, he wrote a series of essay about his views on history and the modern age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>「鴎外漁史とは誰ぞ」（文壇時評）、「原田直次郎」（日本の近代西洋絵画）、「潦休録」（近代芸術）、「我をして九州の富人たらしめば」（社会問題）、「義和団の乱の一面の観察」（講演録）、「新社会合評」（矢野竜渓『新社会』の評論で社会主義などを記述）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Who is Ogai Gyoshi ?&apos; (criticism on the literary world), &apos;Naojiro HARADA&apos; (about western painting in the modern period of Japan), &apos;Ryokyuroku&apos; (about modern art), &apos;If I were a wealthy man in Kyushu&apos; (about social issue), &apos;Observation on an aspect of Giwadan War&apos; (lecture records), &apos;Joint review on the new society&apos; (a criticism on &apos;New Sociery&apos; written by Ryukei YANO, in which he put a mention on socialism and so on).</e>
<cmt>タイトルはすべて自分で英訳したものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Who is Ogai Gyoshi ?&apos; (criticism on the literary world), &apos;Naojiro HARADA&apos; (about western painting in the modern period of Japan), &apos;Ryokyuroku&apos; (about modern art), &apos;If I were a wealthy man in Kyushu&apos; (about social issues), &apos;Observations on one aspect of the Boxer Uprising&apos; (lecture records), &apos;Joint review on new society&apos; (a criticism of &apos;New Sociery&apos; written by Ryukei YANO, in which mentioned socialism and so on).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Who is Ogai Gyoshi ?&apos; (criticism on the literary world), &apos;Naojiro HARADA&apos; (about western painting in the modern period of Japan), &apos;Ryokyuroku&apos; (about modern art), &apos;If I were a wealthy man in Kyushu&apos; (about social issues), &apos;Observations on one aspect of the Boxer Uprising&apos; (lecture records), &apos;Joint review on new society&apos; (a criticism of &quot;New Society&quot; written by Ryukei YANO, in which mentioned socialism and so on).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>またドイツ留学中、田村怡与造に講じていた難解なクラウゼヴィッツの『戦争論』について、師団の将校たちに講義をするとともに、井上光師団長などの依頼で翻訳をはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gave a lecture to officers on the very difficult book, &apos;On War&apos; of Clausewitz, he used to do for Iyozo TAMURA during his stay in Germany, and also translated it by the request of Hikaru INOUE, a division chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gave a lecture to officers on the very profound and subtle book, &apos;On War&apos; by Clausewitz, a lecture he used to give for Iyozo TAMURA during his stay in Germany, and also translated it on the request of Hikaru INOUE, a division chief.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gave a lecture to officers on the very profound and subtle book, &quot;On War&quot; by Clausewitz, a lecture he used to give for Iyozo TAMURA during his stay in Germany, and also translated it on the request of Hikaru INOUE, a division chief.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>その内部資料は、ほかの部隊も求めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The internal materials were also wanted by the other troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other troops also wanted access to these internal materials.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other troops also wanted access to these internal materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="81">
<j>小倉時代に「圭角」がとれ、「胆が練れて来」たと末弟の森潤三郎が記述したように、そのころ鴎外は、社会の周縁ないし底辺に生きる人々への親和、慈しみの眼差しを獲得していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his youngest brother, Junzaburo MORI, mentioned on him that &apos;he was becoming calm and not afraid of anything&apos; during his stay in Kokura, Ogai, in the times, looking at the people living at the bottom of the society with his gentle affectionate eyes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his youngest brother Junzaburo MORI observed, &quot;he was becoming calm and not afraid of anything&quot; during his stay in Kokura, and at that time started to look upon people living at the bottom of society with affectionate eyes.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his youngest brother Junzaburo MORI observed, &apos;he was becoming calm and not afraid of anything&apos; during his stay in Kokura, and at that time started to look upon people living at the bottom of society with affectionate eyes.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>私生活でも、徴兵検査の視察時などで各地の歴史的な文物、文化、事蹟との出会いを通し、とくに後年の史伝につながる掃台（探墓）の趣味を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He met historical products, culture, legacy and so on in the various places he visited to carry out the examination for conscription, and through those, in his personal life also, he found out a hobby to visit tombs which later inspired the biography based on historical evidence he wrote in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He encountered historical artefacts, culture, legacies and so on in the various places he visited to carry out the examination for conscription, through which in his personal life also, he discovered a hobby of visiting tombs which later inspired a biography based on historical evidence he wrote in his later years.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He encountered historical artifacts, culture, legacies and so on in the various places he visited to carry out the examination for conscription, through which in his personal life also, he discovered a hobby of visiting tombs which later inspired a biography based on historical evidence he wrote in his later years.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>新たな趣味を得ただけではなく、1900年1月に赤松登志子（旧妻）が結核で死亡したのち、母の勧めるまま1902年1月、18歳年下の荒木志げと見合い結婚をした（再婚同士）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he lost his wife, Toshiko AKAMATSU (ex-wife), to tuberculosis in January 1900, he found out not only a new hobby but also a new wife, Shige ARAKI, eighteen years younger than him, whom he married in January 1902 after a formal marriage interview with her, which he had had, encouraged by his mother (second marriage for the both).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he lost his wife Toshiko AKAMATSU to tuberculosis in January 1900, he found out not only a new hobby but also a new wife, Shige ARAKI, eighteen years younger than him, whom he married in January 1902 after a formal marriage interview with her, which had been encouraged by his mother (it was a second marriage for both of them).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he lost his wife Toshiko AKAMATSU to tuberculosis in January 1900, he found out not only a new hobby but also a new wife, Shige ARAKI, eighteen years younger than him, whom he married in January 1902 after a formal marriage interview with her, which had been encouraged by his mother (it was a second marriage for both of them).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>さらに、随筆「二人の友」に登場する友人も得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he got friends who appeared in his essay &apos;My two friends&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he made new friends who appear in his essay &apos;My two friends&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he made new friends who appear in his essay &apos;My two friends.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>一人は曹洞宗の僧侶、玉水俊虠（通称、安国寺）で、もう一人は同郷の俊才福間博である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of them was 玉水俊虠 (his common name was Ankoku-ji Temple), a buddhist monk of the Soto sect of Zen, and the other was Hiroshi FUKUMA, a briliant man from the same village.</e>
<cmt>「玉水俊虠」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of them was 玉水俊虠 (commonly called Ankoku-ji after a Temple of the same name), a buddhist monk of the Soto sect of Zen, and the other was Hiroshi FUKUMA, a man from the same village known for his genius.</e>
<cmt>「玉水俊虠」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of them was 玉水俊虠 (commonly called Ankoku-ji after a Temple of the same name), a buddhist monk of the Soto sect of Zen, and the other was Hiroshi FUKUMA, a man from the same village known for his genius.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>二人は、鴎外の東京転勤とともに上京し、鴎外の自宅近くに住み、交際をつづけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two men went down to Tokyo accompanying Ogai who was transferred, and lived near Ogai&apos;s home to keep their friendship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ogai was transferred to Tokyo the two men went down with him and lived near Ogai&apos;s home to maintain their friendship.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ogai was transferred to Tokyo the two men went down with him and lived near Ogai&apos;s home to maintain their friendship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>軍医トップへの就任と旺盛な文筆活動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assumption of office as the top of army surgeon and writing activities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acquisiton of office as top army surgeon and writing activities</e>
<cmt>Assumption &gt;Acquisiton, the top of army &gt; top army</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acquisition of office as top army surgeon and writing activities</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>1902年（明治35年）3月、第一師団軍医部長の辞令を受け、新妻とともに東京に赴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left for Tokyo to assume office as director of the army surgeon department of the first division along with his new wife in March 1902.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left for Tokyo to assume office as director of the Army Medical department of the first division along with his new wife in March 1902.</e>
<cmt>the army surgeon department&gt;the Army Medical department</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left for Tokyo to assume office as director of the Army Medical department of the first division along with his new wife in March 1902.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>6月、廃刊になっていた『めざまし草』と上田敏の主宰する『芸苑』とを合併し、『芸文』を創刊（その後、出版社とのトラブルで廃刊したものの、10月に後身の『万年艸』を創刊）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, he began to issue &quot;Geibun&quot;, by merging Mezamashi-gusa (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine which publication had been disconnected into &quot;Geien&quot; (artistic and literary circles) edited by Bin UEDA (although the publication was later disconnected due to a trouble with the publisher, he newly began to issue &apos;Mannengusa&apos; as a replacement in October).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, he began to issue &quot;Geibun&quot;, by merging the discontinued Mezamashi-gusa with &quot;Geien&quot; (artistic and literary circles) edited by Bin UEDA (although the publication was later disconnected due to troubles with the publisher, he began to issue &apos;Mannengusa&apos; as a replacement in October).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, he began to issue &quot;Geibun,&quot; by merging the discontinued &quot;Mezamashi-gusa&quot; with &quot;Geien&quot; (artistic and literary circles) edited by Bin UEDA (although the publication was later disconnected due to troubles with the publisher, he began to issue &quot;Mannengusa&quot; as a replacement in October).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>その頃は、12月に初めて戯曲を執筆するなど、戯曲にかかわる活動が目立っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the period, he particularly worked on plays and wrote his first play in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, he worked on plays particularly and wrote his first in December.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, he worked on plays particularly and wrote his first in December.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>1904年（明治37年）2月から1906年（明治39年）1月まで日露戦争に第2軍 (日本軍)日露戦争における第2軍軍医部長として出征。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From February 1904 to January 1906, he was in front of Russo-Japanese War as director of army surgeon department of the second army (Japanese army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From February 1904 to January 1906, he was at the front line of the Russo-Japanese War as director of the Army Medical department of the second Army of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From February 1904 to January 1906, he was at the front line of the Russo-Japanese War as director of the Army Medical department of the second Army of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>1907年（明治40年）10月、軍医総監（中将相当）に昇進し、陸軍省医務局（人事権をもつ軍医のトップ）に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1907, he moved on to General Office Director of Army Surgeon (corresponding to Lieutenant General), then assumed office as Medical bureau of Ministry of Army (the top of army surgeon having a right for personnel affairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1907, he moved on to General Office Director of Army Medicine (corresponding to Lieutenant General), then assumed office at the Medical bureau of the Department of War (the top army surgeon with authority over human resources).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1907, he moved on to General Office Director of Army Medicine (corresponding to Lieutenant General), then assumed office at the Medical bureau of the Department of War (the top army surgeon with authority over human resources).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>なお同年9月、美術審査員に任じられ、第一回日本美術展覧会官展の歴史（初期文展）西洋画部門審査の主任になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of the same year, he was appointed as an art examiner, and assumed office as a chief examiner of the historical western painting department of the 1st Kanten, the Japan Fine Arts Exhibition (Bunten exhibition in the early times).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of the same year, he was appointed as art examiner, and assumed office as chief examiner of the Western Historical Painting Department of the 1st Kanten (the Japan Fine Arts Exhibition, originally called Bunten).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September of the same year, he was appointed as art examiner, and assumed office as chief examiner of the Western Historical Painting Department of the 1st Kanten (the Japan Fine Arts Exhibition, originally called Bunten).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>このころまでは翻訳が多かったが、1909年（明治42年）に『スバル (文芸雑誌)』が創刊されると、これに毎号寄稿して創作活動を再開した（木下杢太郎のいう「豊熟の時代」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until around then, he mainly did translation, but after the issue of &apos;Subaru (literature magazine) in 1909, he started again his writing and contributed to the magazine every month (&apos;the times of harvest&apos;, according to Mokutaro KINOSHITA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until around then, he mainly did translation, but after the issue of &apos;Subaru (literature magazine) in 1909, he started writing again and contributed to the magazine every month (A time Mokutaro KINOSHITA referred to as &apos;The Time of Harvest&apos;).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until around then, he mainly did translation, but after the issue of &quot;Subaru&quot; (literature magazine) in 1909, he started writing again and contributed to the magazine every month (A time Mokutaro KINOSHITA referred to as &apos;The Time of Harvest&apos;).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>『半日』『ヰタ・セクスアリス』『鶏』『青年 (小説)』などを『スバル』に載せ、『仮面』『静』などの戯曲を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He put &apos;Hannichi (Half a Day)&apos;, &apos;Niwatori (The Chicken)&apos;, &apos;Seinen (Youth) (novel)&apos; in the magazine, and published the plays such as &apos;Kamen (The Mask)&apos;, &apos;Shizuka (Silence)&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>『静』はweb上で確認できなかったため、私自身の英訳によるものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He exhibited &apos;Hannichi (Half a Day)&apos;, &apos;Vita Sexualis&apos;, &apos;Niwatori (The Chicken)&apos;, and the novel &apos;Seinen (Youth)&apos; in the magazine, and published plays such as &apos;Kamen (The Mask)&apos; and &apos;Shizuka (Silence)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He exhibited &quot;Hannichi&quot; (Half a Day), &quot;Vita Sexualis,&quot; &quot;Niwatori&quot; (The Chicken), and the novel &quot;Seinen&quot; (Youth) in the magazine, and published plays such as &quot;Kamen&quot; (The Mask) and &quot;Shizuka&quot; (Silence).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>その『スバル』創刊年の7月、鴎外は、東京帝国大学から文学博士の学位を授与された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July of the year in which &apos;Subaru&apos; began to be issued, Ogai was awarded the degree of doctor of literatue by Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July of the year &apos;Subaru&apos; began to be issued, Ogai was awarded the degree of Doctor of Literature by Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>deleted “in which ”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July of the year &quot;Subaru&quot; began to be issued, Ogai was awarded the degree of Doctor of Literature by Tokyo Imperial University.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>しかし、直後に『ヰタ・セクスアリス』（『スバル』7月号）が発売禁止処分を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, just after that, his &apos;Vita Sexualis&apos; (&apos;Subaru&apos; vol. July) was prohibited to publish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However directly after this, his work &apos;Vita Sexualis&apos; (&apos;Subaru&apos; vol. July) was banned form publishing.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However directly after this, his work &quot;Vita Sexualis&quot; (&quot;Subaru&quot; vol. July) was banned form publishing.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>しかも、内務省 (日本)の警保局が陸軍省を訪れた8月、鴎外は石本陸軍省陸軍次官から戒飭（かいちょく）された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, he was admonished by ISHIMOTO Vice-chief of Ministry of Army, when Keihokyoku of prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) visited Ministry of Army in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, he was admonished by ISHIMOTO Vice-chief of Ministry of Army, when the Keihokyoku of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) visited the Department of War in August.</e>
<cmt>Besides&gt;Further, Keihokyoku&gt;the Keihokyoku, of prewar&gt; of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs,visited Ministry of Army i&gt;visited the Department of War</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, he was admonished by Ishimoto Vice-chief of Ministry of Army, when the Keihokyoku of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) visited the Department of War in August.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>同年12月、「予が立場」でレジグナチオン（諦念）をキーワードに自らの立場を明らかにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, he made his position clear with the keyword of &apos;resignation&apos; in his piece &apos;Yogatachiba (My position)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, he made his position clear by using the English word &apos;resignation&apos; in his piece &apos;Yogatachiba (My position)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>with the keyword of &gt; by using the English word</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, he made his position clear by using the English word &apos;resignation&apos; in his piece &apos;Yogatachiba&apos; (My position).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="99">
<j>慶應義塾大学の文学科顧問に就任（教授職に永井荷風を推薦）した1910年（明治43年）は、5月に大逆事件の検挙がはじまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1910 when he assumed office as an advisor of Department of Literature of Keio University (he recommended Kafu NAGAI as an instructor), the arrest of people involved in the Case of High Treason began in May, Ogai and his wife&apos;s name were shown in the sixth of a serial called &apos;A dangerous foreign book&apos; The Asahi Shinbun started in September, and Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument on legitimacy of either Northern or Southern Dynasty) got worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1910 when he assumed office as advisor to the Department of Literature of Keio University (he recommended Kafu NAGAI as an instructor), from May people involved in the Case of High Treason began to be arrested.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1910 when he assumed office as advisor to the Department of Literature of Keio University (he recommended Kafu NAGAI as an instructor), from May people involved in the Case of High Treason began to be arrested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>9月に朝日新聞が「危険なる洋書」という連載を開始して6回目に鴎外と妻の名が掲載され、さらに南北朝正閏論南北朝正閏問題が大きくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai and his wife&apos;s names appeared in the sixth edition of a serial called &apos;Dangerous foreign books&apos; started by the Asahi Shinbun in September, and the Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument over legitimacy of Northern or Southern Courts) became further divided.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai and his wife&apos;s names appeared in the sixth edition of a serial called &apos;Dangerous foreign books&apos; started by the Asahi Shinbun in September, and the Nanbokucho-Seijunron (argument over legitimacy of Northern or Southern Courts) became further divided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>そうした閉塞感がただよう年に『ファスチェス』（発禁問題）、『沈黙の塔』（学問と芸術）、『食堂』（クロポトキンや無政府主義等を記述）などを発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such stifling year, he published &quot;ファスチェス&quot; (about the issue of ban), &apos;Chinmoku no to (The Tower of Silence)&apos; (about learning and art), &apos;Shokudo (diner)&apos; (mention on Kropotkin, anarchism and so on).</e>
<cmt>『ファスチェス』 webで検索しましたがスペル不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such stifling year, he published &quot;ファスチェス&quot; (about the issue of the ban), &apos;Chinmoku no to (The Tower of Silence)&apos; (about learning and art), &apos;Shokudo (diner)&apos; (covering Kropotkin, anarchism and so on).</e>
<cmt>ban&gt;the ban</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such stifling year, he published &quot;ファスチェス&quot; (about the issue of the ban), &quot;Chinmoku no to&quot; (The Tower of Silence) (about learning and art), &quot;Shokudo&quot; (diner) (covering Kropotkin, anarchism and so on).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>翌1911年（明治44年）にも『カズイスチカ』『妄想』を発表し、『青年』の完結後、『雁』と『灰燼』の2長編の同時連載を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1911 also, he published &apos;Casuistica&apos; and &apos;Delusion&apos;, then after completing &apos;Seinen (Youth)&apos;, he began to issue two serial long stories such as &apos;The Wild Geese&apos; and &apos;Kaijin (Ashes of Destruction)&apos; at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1911 also, he published &apos;Casuistica&apos; and &apos;Delusion&apos;, then after completing &apos;Seinen (Youth)&apos;, he began to issue two serial long stories: &apos;The Wild Geese&apos; and &apos;Kaijin (Ashes of Destruction)&apos; simultaneously.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1911 also, he published &quot;Casuistica&quot; and &quot;Delusion,&quot; then after completing &quot;Seinen&quot; (Youth), he began to issue two serial long stories: &quot;The Wild Geese&quot; and &quot;Kaijin&quot; (Ashes of Destruction) simultaneously.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>同年4月の「文芸の主義」（原題：文芸断片）では、次のように記述した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April of the same year, he put a statement in &apos;Bungei no Shugi (Principle of Literature) (original title : Literary Fragments)&apos; as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April of the same year, he put the following statement in &apos;Bungei no Shugi (Principle of Literature) (original title : Literary Fragments)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>a&gt;the,deleted “ as follows”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of the same year, he put the following statement in &apos;Bungei no Shugi&apos; (Principle of Literature) (original title : Literary Fragments).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>冒頭「芸術ジャンルに主義というものは本来ないと思う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">he wrote in the beginning, &apos;I think the genre of art has no principle.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The foreword was, &apos;I think the genre of art has no principles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>he wrote in the beginning,&gt;The foreword was,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foreword was, &apos;I think the genre of art has no principles.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>」とした上で、「無政府主義と、それと一しょに芽ざした社会主義との排斥をする為に、個人主義という漠然たる名を附けて、芸術に迫害を加えるのは、国家のために惜むべき事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he concluded that &apos;giving the indistinct name of &apos;individualism&apos; to persecute the art, for the purpose of removing anarchism and socialism which grew up together, should be ceased for the sake of our nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, he concluded that &apos;For the sake of our nation, we must stop persecuting art and labelling it as &apos;individualistic&apos; or &apos;egotistical&apos; simply for the purpose of removing anarchism and socialism which grew up together</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, he concluded that &apos;For the sake of our nation, we must stop persecuting art and labelling it as &apos;individualistic&apos; or &apos;egotistical&apos; simply for the purpose of removing anarchism and socialism which grew up together</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>学問の自由研究と芸術の自由発展とを妨げる国は栄えるはずがない。」と結んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The country which prevents the independent research of learning as well as the independent evolution of art could never flourish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A country which prevents the independent research of learning as well as the independent evolution of art can never flourish.</e>
<cmt>can&gt;could</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A country which prevents the independent research of learning as well as the independent evolution of art can never flourish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>1912年-1913年（大正元年-2年）には、『かのように』から『槌一下』まで五条秀麿を主人公にした連作を、また司令官を揶揄するなど戦場体験も描かれた『鼠坂』などを発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between 1912 and 1913, he published a serial work with the same main character called Hidemaro GOJO from &apos;Kanoyoni (in this way)&apos; to &apos;Tsuchiikka&apos;, as well as &apos;Nezumizaka Slope&apos; in which he described the episode from his own experience in the battlefield such as teasing a commandor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between 1912 and 1913, he published a serial work with the same main character called Hidemaro GOJO from &apos;Kanoyoni (in this way)&apos; to &apos;Tsuchiikka&apos;, as well as &apos;Nezumizaka Slope&apos; in which he described episodes from his own experience in the battlefield such as teasing a commander.</e>
<cmt>the episodes&gt;episodes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between 1912 and 1913, he published a serial work with the same main character called Hidemaro GOJO from &quot;Kanoyoni&quot; (in this way) to &quot;Tsuchiikka,&quot; as well as &quot;Nezumizaka Slope&quot; in which he described episodes from his own experience in the battlefield such as teasing a commander.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>このころは、身辺に題材をとった作品や思想色の濃い作品や教養小説や戯曲などを執筆した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, he wrote the pieces inspired by his familiar things, what was deeply poured his thoughts in, the educational novels or plays, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, he wrote pieces inspired by things around him, deep pieces about things he was concerned about, educational novels and plays.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, he wrote pieces inspired by things around him, deep pieces about things he was concerned about, educational novels and plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>もっとも公務のかたわら、『ファウスト』などゲーテの三作品をはじめ、外国文学の翻訳・紹介・解説もつづけていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spare moments from his public service, he continued his translation, introduction and commenting on the foreign literatures, including Goethe&apos;s three masterpieces such as &apos;Faust&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spare moments from his public service, he continued his translation, introduction and comment on foreign literature, including Goethe&apos;s three masterpieces such as &apos;Faust&apos;.</e>
<cmt>commenting on the foreign literatures&gt; comment on foreign literature</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spare moments from his public service, he continued his translation, introduction and comment on foreign literature, including Goethe&apos;s three masterpieces such as &quot;Faust.&quot;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="110">
<j>なお、1910-1911年、懸案とされてきた軍医の人事権をめぐり、件（くだん）の石本次官と医務局長の鴎外とが激しく対立し、鴎外が石本に辞意を告げる事態にまでなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between 1910 and 1911, Ishimoto, Vice-chief, mentioned above and Ogai, Medical Office Director, were seriously opposed to each other over the right of personnel affairs of army surgeon which had been a long-term concern, then it developed to the situation that Ogai announced his resignation to Ishimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between 1910 and 1911, the aforementioned Vice-chief Ishimoto and Ogai, as Medical Office Director, conflicted over the right to human resources in Army medicine which had been a long-term concern, developing to the extent that Ogai announced his resignation to Ishimoto.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between 1910 and 1911, the aforementioned Vice-chief Ishimoto and Ogai, as Medical Office Director, conflicted over the right to human resources in Army medicine which had been a long-term concern, developing to the extent that Ogai announced his resignation to Ishimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>結局のところ、医学優先の人事が鴎外の退官後もつづいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, the personnel affairs with the priority to medical science continued even after Ogai&apos;s resignation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Medical students continued to be prioritised in personnel affairs even after Ogai&apos;s resignation.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Medical students continued to be prioritized in personnel affairs even after Ogai&apos;s resignation.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>階級社会の軍隊で、それも一段低い扱いを受ける衛生部の鴎外の主張がとおった背景の一つに、山県有朋の存在があったと考えられている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As one of the reasons why Ogai&apos;s insistence could get through altough he belonged to the hygiene department which was somehow an inferior section in the strict class society of the Army, it is considered that Aritomo YAMAGATA backed up him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that one of the reasons why Ogai&apos;s insistence was effective even though he belonged to the hygiene department (an inferior department under the strict class society of the Army), was that he was backed by Aritomo YAMAGATA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that one of the reasons why Ogai&apos;s insistence was effective even though he belonged to the hygiene department (an inferior department under the strict class society of the Army), was that he was backed by Aritomo YAMAGATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="113">
<j>1912年（大正元年）8月、「実在の人間を資料に拠って事実のまま叙述する、鴎外独自の小説作品の最初のもの」である『羽鳥千尋』を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1912, he published &apos;Chihiro HATORI&apos; which was a first novel written in his original style to describe a reality with a real person according to the material.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1912, he published &apos;Chihiro HATORI&apos; which was the first novel written in his original style to describe the real life of a real person based on historical resources.</e>
<cmt>a reality with a real person according to the material.&gt;the real life of a real person based on historical resources.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1912, he published &quot;Chihiro HATORI&quot; which was the first novel written in his original style to describe the real life of a real person based on historical resources.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>翌9月13日、乃木希典の殉死に影響を受けて5日後に『興津弥五右衛門の遺書』（初稿）を書き終えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 13, he completed &apos;The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon&apos; (first draft), five days after he was inspired by Maresuke NOGI&apos;s death following his master to the grave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 13, he completed &apos;The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon&apos; (first draft), having been inspired five days previously by Maresuke NOGI&apos;s death following his master to the grave.</e>
<cmt>five days after he was inspired &gt;having been inspired five days previously</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 13, 1913, he completed &quot;The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon&quot; (first draft), having been inspired five days previously by Maresuke NOGI&apos;s death following his master to the grave.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。年号を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>これを機に歴史小説に進み、「歴史其儘」の『阿部一族』、「歴史離れ」の『山椒大夫』『高瀬舟 (小説)』などののち、史伝『渋江抽斎』に結実した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This occasion let him advance to the historical novels, and he wrote &quot;The Abe clan&quot; of &apos;Rekishi Sonomama&apos;, &quot;Sanshodayu&quot; and &quot;Takasebune (The Boat on the River Takase) (novel)&quot; of &apos;Rekishi Banare&apos; and so on, and finally &quot;Chusai SHIBUE&quot;, Shiden, was produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This occasion let him advance to historical novels, and he wrote &quot;The Abe clan&quot; of &apos;Rekishi Sonomama&apos;, &quot;Sanshodayu&quot; and &quot;Takasebune (The Boat on the River Takase) (novel)&quot; from &apos;Rekishi Banare&apos; and so on, and finally he produced the historical biography &quot;Chusai SHIBUE&quot;.</e>
<cmt>the histrical&gt;histrical,&quot;Chusai SHIBUE&quot;, Shiden, was produced&gt;he produced the historical biography &quot;Chusai SHIBUE&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This occasion let him advance to historical novels, and he wrote &quot;The Abe clan&quot; of &apos;Rekishi Sonomama,&apos; &quot;Sanshodayu&quot; and &quot;Takasebune&quot; (The Boat on the River Takase) (novel) from &apos;Rekishi Banare&apos; and so on, and finally he produced the historical biography &quot;Chusai SHIBUE.&quot;</e>
<cmt>カンマ、ピリオド位置移動しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>ただし、1915年（大正4年）頃まで、現代小説も並行して執筆していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he also wrote the modern novel until about 1915.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he also wrote modern novels until about 1915.</e>
<cmt>deleted “the”, novel&gt;novels</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he also wrote modern novels until about 1915.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>1916年（大正5年）には、後世の鴎外研究家や評論家から重要視される随筆「空車」（むなぐるま）を、ロシア革命の翌年1918年（大正7年）1月には随筆「礼儀小言」を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote &apos;Munaguruma (empty car)&apos;, a essay in 1916, regarded as important by the researchers and critics in the later generations, then &apos;Reigi kogoto (Grumblings about Social Propriety)&apos;, a essay, in January 1918, the following year of Russian Revolution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote &apos;Munaguruma (empty car)&apos;, a essay in 1916, regarded as important by researchers and critics in later generations, then an essay &apos;Reigi kogoto (Grumblings about Social Propriety)&apos;, in January 1918 the year following the Russian Revolution.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote &apos;Munaguruma&apos; (empty car), a essay in 1916, regarded as important by researchers and critics in later generations, then an essay &apos;Reigi kogoto&apos; (Grumblings about Social Propriety), in January 1918 the year following the Russian Revolution.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His later years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later years</e>
<cmt>delated &quot;His&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="118">
<j>1916年（大正5年）4月、任官時の年齢が低いこともあり、トップの陸軍省医務局長を8年半つとめて退き、予備役に編入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1916, he retired from the post of Director of Medical Office of Ministry of Army, the highest post, after his service of eight and a half years, because his age had been low when he had been appointed, then, was incorporated into reserve duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1916, partly because of how young he had been on appointment, he retired from the post of Director (the highest post) of the Medical Office of the Department of War, a service of eight and a half years and was incorporated into the reserve.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1916, partly because of how young he had been on appointment, he retired from the post of Director (the highest post) of the Medical Office of the Department of War, a service of eight and a half years and was incorporated into the reserve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>その後、1917年（大正7年）12月、帝室博物館（現東京国立博物館）総長兼図書寮宮内省図書頭（ずしょのかみ） に、翌年1月に帝室制度審議会御用掛に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he assumed office as a director general of Imperial Museum (present Tokyo National Museum) and Zushonokami of Zushoryo, Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) at the same time in December 1917, then Goyogakari of Council for the Imperial House System in January of the following year.</e>
<cmt>web上の記載を参照したところ、二番目の「図書頭」が「図書寮」となっていましたので、オリジナルを訂正後、英訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in December 1917 he simultaneously assumed office as director general of Imperial Museum (present Tokyo National Museum) and Head of Books of the Zushoryo (Bureau of Drawings and Books) and Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household), then Goyogakari of Council for the Imperial House System in January of the following year.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in December 1917 he simultaneously assumed office as director general of Imperial Museum (present Tokyo National Museum) and Head of Books of the Zushoryo (Bureau of Drawings and Books) and Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household), then Goyogakari of Council for the Imperial House System in January of the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>さらに1918年（大正8年）9月、帝国美術院（現日本芸術院）初代院長となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, he became the first director of Imperial Art Academy (present The Japan Art Academy) in September 1918.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, he became the first director of the Imperial Art Academy (present The Japan Art Academy) in September 1918.</e>
<cmt>Impelial&gt;The Imperial</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, he became the first director of the Imperial Art Academy (present The Japan Art Academy) in September 1918.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>元号の「明治」と「大正」に否定的であったため、宮内省図書頭として天皇の諡（おくりな）と元号の考証・編纂に着手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he was opposed to &apos;Meiji&apos; and &apos;Taisho&apos; as the name of era, he launched a historical investigation and compilation on the Emperor&apos;s Okurina (a posthumous name) and era, as a position of Zusho no kami of Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he was opposed to &apos;Meiji&apos; and &apos;Taisho&apos; as era names, he launched a historical investigation and compilation on the Emperor&apos;s Okurina (a posthumous name) and era, in his position as Head of Books at the Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he was opposed to &apos;Meiji&apos; and &apos;Taisho&apos; as era names, he launched a historical investigation and compilation on the Emperor&apos;s Okurina (a posthumous name) and era, in his position as Head of Books at the Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>しかし『天諡考』は刊行したものの、病状の悪化により、自ら見いだした吉田増蔵に後を託しており、後年この吉田が未完の『元号考』の刊行に尽力し、元号案「昭和」を提出することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he managed to issue his &apos;Consideration on the Emperor&apos;s&apos; Posthumous Names&apos;, he asked Masuzo YOSHIDA he had recruited by himself to succeed his work due to his medical condition worsen, and Yoshida later contributed to issueing &apos;Gengoko (Consideration on the Era)&apos; half-done by Ogai, and proposed the name of era called &apos;Showa&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite managing to publish his &apos;Consideration on the Emperor&apos;s&apos; Posthumous Names&apos;, his health began to worsen so he personally selected and asked Masuzo YOSHIDA to succeed his work, and Yoshida later contributed to completing the unfinished &apos;Gengoko (Consideration on the Era)&apos; and proposed the era name &apos;Showa&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite managing to publish his &quot;Consideration on the Emperors&apos; Posthumous Names,&quot; his health began to worsen so he personally selected and asked Masuzo YOSHIDA to succeed his work, and Yoshida later contributed to completing the unfinished &quot;Gengoko&quot; (Consideration on the Era) and proposed the era name &apos;Showa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="123">
<j>1922年（大正11年）7月9日、萎縮腎、肺結核のために死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed away from contracted kidney and pulmonary tuberculosis on July 9, 1922.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away from contracted kidney and pulmonary tuberculosis on July 9, 1922.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away from contracted kidney and pulmonary tuberculosis on July 9, 1922.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>享年61。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 61.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at death was 61.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age at death was 61.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>「余ハ石見人森林太郎トシテ死セント欲ス」という遺言は有名で、遺言により一切の栄誉、称号を排して墓には「森林太郎ノ墓」とのみ刻されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left a famous will to be buried under the name of &apos;Rintaro MORI, a person from Iwami (his birthplace)&apos;, so his grave has only a simple inscription of &apos;Grave of Rintaro MORI&apos; on it, omitting all his honor and title, respecting his will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is famous for leaving a will to be buried under the name of &apos;Rintaro MORI, a person from Iwami (his birthplace)&apos;, so respecting this his grave has only a simple inscription of &apos;Grave of Rintaro MORI&apos; on it, omitting all his honours and titles.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is famous for leaving a will to be buried under the name of &apos;Rintaro MORI, a person from Iwami (his birthplace),&apos; so respecting this his grave has only a simple inscription of &apos;Grave of Rintaro MORI&apos; on it, omitting all his honors and titles.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>向島弘福寺に埋葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried at Gufuku-ji Temple, Mukojima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried at Gufuku-ji Temple, Mukojima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried at Gufuku-ji Temple, Mukojima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>墓碑銘は、遺言により中村不折によって筆された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His epitaph on the tombstone was drawn by Fusetsu NAKAMURA, respecting his will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His epitaph on the tombstone was written by Fusetsu NAKAMURA, in accordance with his will.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His epitaph on the tombstone was written by Fusetsu NAKAMURA, in accordance with his will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>戒名は貞献院殿文穆思斎大居士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Kaimyo was 貞献院殿文穆思斎大居士.</e>
<cmt>「貞献院殿文穆思斎大居士」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Kaimyo (Buddhist posthumous name) was 貞献院殿文穆思斎大居士.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Kaimyo (Buddhist posthumous name) was 貞献院殿文穆思斎大居士.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>なお、関東大震災後、東京都三鷹市の禅林寺 (三鷹市)と津和野町の永明寺に改葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Great Kanto Earthquake, his grave was relocated to Zenrin-ji Temple, Mitaka City, Tokyo Prefecture as well as Yomei-ji Temple, Tsuwano-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Great Kanto Earthquake, his grave was relocated to Zenrin-ji Temple, Mitaka City, Tokyo Prefecture as well as Yomei-ji Temple, Tsuwano-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Great Kanto Earthquake, his grave was relocated to Zenrin-ji Temple, Mitaka City, Tokyo Prefecture as well as Yomei-ji Temple, Tsuwano-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>人物評</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An assessment of a person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Criticism</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal criticism</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>評論的啓蒙活動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Critical enlightenment activities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Critical Philosophical activites</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Critical philosophical activities</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>鴎外は自らが専門とした文学・医学、両分野において論争が絶えない人物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai was always involved in dispute in the field of literature and medical science which he specialized in both.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai was always involved in dispute in the fields of literature and medical science, both of which he specialized in.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai was always involved in dispute in the fields of literature and medical science, both of which he specialized in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>文学においては理想や理念など主観的なものを描くべきだとする理想主義を掲げ、事物や現象を客観的に描くべきだとする写実主義的な没理想を掲げる坪内逍遥と衝突する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the literature, he held up the idealism to describe something subjective such as ideal or principle, so it caused a confrontation with Shoyo TSUBOUCHI who contrarily held up the realistic anti-idealism to describe things and phenomenons objectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the field of literature, he pointed at idealism to describe subjective concepts, such as ideals and principles, which caused confrontation with Shoyo TSUBOUCHI who contrarily looked to realistic anti-idealism to describe things and phenomenons objectively.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the field of literature, he pointed at idealism to describe subjective concepts, such as ideals and principles, which caused confrontation with Shoyo TSUBOUCHI who contrarily looked to realistic anti-idealism to describe things and phenomenons objectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>また医学においては近代の西洋医学を旨とし、和漢方医と激烈な論争を繰り広げたこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in the medical science, he relied on the modern western medicine, and rolled out a severe dispute with Chinese and Japanese medicine doctors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in medical science, he relied on modern western medicine, and initiated serious dispute with Chinese and Japanese doctors.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in medical science, he relied on modern western medicine, and initiated serious dispute with Chinese and Japanese doctors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>和漢方医が7割以上を占めていた当時の医学界は、ドイツ医学界のような学問において業績を上げた学者に不遇であり、日本の医学の進歩を妨げている、大卒の医者を増やすべきだ、などと批判する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He criticized that the medical world of Japan was occupied over 70% by Chinese and Japanese medicine doctors, so the specialists who made an achievement in a study of other fields such as German medical science were disregarded, and this phenomenon prevented the medical progression of Japan, so the doctors who graduated from medical school should be increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He criticized the medical world of Japan, saying it was over 70% occupied by Chinese and Japanese doctors, so specialists who made progress studying other fields such as German medical science were disregarded, and this situation prevented the medical progression of Japan, so the number of doctors graduating from medical school should be increased.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He criticized the medical world of Japan, saying it was over 70% occupied by Chinese and Japanese doctors, so specialists who made progress studying other fields such as German medical science were disregarded, and this situation prevented the medical progression of Japan, so the number of doctors graduating from medical school should be increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>松本良順など近代医学の始祖と呼ばれている長老などと6年ほど論争を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued the dispute for six years with veterans including Ryojun MATSUMOTO who was called a founder of the modern medical science.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued the dispute for six years with veterans including Ryojun MATSUMOTO who was known as the founder of modern medical science.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued the dispute for six years with veterans including Ryojun MATSUMOTO who was known as the founder of modern medical science.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="135">
<j>また、鴎外の論争癖を発端として論争が起きた事もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, some of the disputes were caused by his causing-dispute habit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, some of the disputes were caused by his argumentative nature.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, some of the disputes were caused by his argumentative nature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>逍遥が「早稲田文学」にウィリアム・シェイクスピアの評釈に関して加えた短い説明に対し、批判的な評を『しがらみ草紙』に載せたことから論争が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the disputes began with Ogai&apos;s criticism put in the &apos;Shigarami Soshi&apos;, on the short explanation which Shoyo added to his own comments on William SHAKESPEARE in &apos;Waseda Bungaku (Waseda Literature)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the disputes began with Ogai&apos;s criticism in &apos;Shigarami Soshi&apos;, of the short explanation which Shoyo added to his own comments on William SHAKESPEARE in &apos;Waseda Bungaku (Waseda Literature)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the disputes began with Ogai&apos;s criticism in &quot;Shigarami Soshi,&quot; of the short explanation which Shoyo added to his own comments on William SHAKESPEARE in &apos;Waseda Bungaku&apos; (Waseda Literature).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>このような形で鴎外が関わってきた論争は「戦闘的評論」や「論争的啓蒙」などと評される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dispute Ogai was involved in was sometimes called &apos;fighting dispute&apos; or &apos;critical enlightenment&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dispute Ogai was involved in was sometimes called &apos;aggressive criticism&apos; or &apos;controversial philosophy&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dispute Ogai was involved in was sometimes called &apos;aggressive criticism&apos; or &apos;controversial philosophy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>もっとも三十歳代になると、日清戦争後に『めさまし草』を創刊して「合評」をするなど、評論的啓蒙活動は、戦闘的ないし論争的なものから、穏健的なものに変わっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his thirties, however, his critical enlightenment activities changed from something like fighting or critical to a moderate one, such as beginning to issue the Mezamashi-gusa (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine and putting a joint review in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his thirties, however, the nature of his critical philosophical activities changed from one of fighting and criticism to a moderate one, for instance beginning to issue the Mezamashi-gusa (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine and publishing joint reviews in it.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his thirties, however, the nature of his critical philosophical activities changed from one of fighting and criticism to a moderate one, for instance beginning to issue the Mezamashi-gusa (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine after the Sino-Japanese War and publishing joint reviews in it.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>さらに、小倉時代に「圭角が取れた」という家族の指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, one of his family members pointed out that he became calm during his stay in Kokura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, his family members also pointed out that he became calm during his stay in Kokura.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, his family members also pointed out that he became calm during his stay in Kokura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>幅の広い文芸活動と交際</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wide range of literary activities and human relationships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wide range of literary activities and human relationships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wide range of literary activities and human relationships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="140">
<j>肩書きの多いことに現れているように、鴎外は文芸活動の幅も広かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his many professions show, Ogai had a wide range of literary activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his many professions show, Ogai had a wide range of literary activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his many professions show, Ogai had a wide range of literary activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>たとえば、訳者としては、上記の訳詩集『於母影』（共訳）と、1892-1901年に断続的に発表された『即興詩人』とが初期の代表的な仕事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For exemple, his initial representative works as a translator were &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos; (joint translation) mentioned above and &apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&apos; intermittently published from 1892 to 1901.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For exemple, his initial representative works as a translator were &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos; (joint translation) mentioned above and &apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&apos; intermittently published from 1892 to 1901.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, his initial representative works as a translator were &quot;Omokage&quot; (Vestiges) (joint translation) mentioned above and &quot;Sokkyo Shijin&quot; (Improvising Poet) intermittently published from 1892 to 1901.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>『於母影』は明治詩壇に多大な影響を与えており、『即興詩人』は、流麗な雅文で明治期の文人を魅了し、その本を片手にイタリア各地をまわる文学青年（正宗白鳥など）が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omokage (Vestiges)&apos; gave a great impact on the poet world of Meiji, while &apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&apos; attracted men of literature in the Meiji Period with its flowing elegant sentences, so a lot of young literary enthusiasts (for exemple, Hakucho MASAMUNE) visited each region in Italy with the book in hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omokage (Vestiges)&apos; had a great impact on the poetry world of Meiji, while &apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&apos; appealed to Meiji period literary men with its flowing elegant sentences, to the extent a lot of young literary enthusiasts (for exemple, Hakucho MASAMUNE) toured each region of Italy with the book in hand.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Omokage&quot; (Vestiges) had a great impact on the poetry world of Meiji, while &quot;Sokkyo Shijin&quot; (Improvising Poet) appealed to Meiji period literary men with its flowing elegant sentences, to the extent a lot of young literary enthusiasts (for example, Hakucho MASAMUNE) toured each region of Italy with the book in hand.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="143">
<j>また鴎外は、戯曲の翻訳も多く（弟の三木竹二が責任編集をつとめる雑誌『歌舞伎』に掲載されたものは少なくない）、歌劇（オペラ）の翻訳まで手がけていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai also translated a lot of plays (it&apos;s not few what were put in the magazine &apos;Kabuku&apos; his younger brother edited as a responsible person), and even translated the opera.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai also translated a lot of plays (of which a considerable number were put in the magazine &apos;Kabuku&apos; which his younger brother was responsible for editing), and even translated opera too.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai also translated a lot of plays (of which a considerable number were put in the magazine &quot;Kabuki&quot; which his younger brother Takeji MIKI was responsible for editing), and even translated opera too.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>ちなみに、訳語（和製漢語）の「交響楽、交響曲」をつくっており、6年間の欧米留学を終えた演奏家、幸田延（露伴の妹）と洋楽談義をした（「西楽と幸田氏と」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also created new Japanese words (Japanese Chinese words) such as &apos;Kokyogaku, Kokyokyoku (the both means symphony)&apos;, and had a discussion on the western music with Nobu KODA (a younger sister of Rohan), a player, who had come back to Japan after her six-year study in Enrope and America (&apos;With western music, with MS. Koda).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also created new Japanese words (based on Chinese characters) such as &apos;Kokyogaku, Kokyokyoku (both meaning symphony)&apos;, and gave a lecture on western music with Nobu KODA (a younger sister of Rohan), a musician who had come back to Japan after six-years&apos; studying in Europe and America (&apos;With western music and MS. Koda).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also created new Japanese words (based on Chinese characters) such as &apos;Kokyogaku, Kokyokyoku&apos; (both meaning symphony), and gave a lecture on western music with Nobu KODA (a younger sister of Rohan), a musician who had come back to Japan after six-years&apos; studying in Europe and America (&apos;With western music and Ms. Koda&apos;).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>そうした外国作品の翻訳だけでなく、帰国後から演劇への啓蒙的な評論も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only such translation of the foreign pieces, he also made not a few enlightenmental criticism on the play, after his back to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He not only translated such foreign pieces, he also made a good deal of philosophical critiques of plays after his return to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He not only translated such foreign pieces, he also made a good deal of philosophical critiques of plays after his return to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="146">
<j>翻訳は、文学作品を超え、ハルトマン『審美学綱領』のような審美学（美学の旧称）も対象となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The subject of his translation was not within the literature, and he also dealt with aesthetics such as &apos;Shinbigaku Koryo (aesthetic program)&apos; of Hartmann.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The subject of his translations was not limited to literature; he also dealt with aesthetics such as &apos;Shinbigaku Koryo (aesthetic program)&apos; by Hartmann.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The subject of his translations was not limited to literature; he also dealt with aesthetics such as &quot;Shinbigaku Koryo&quot; (aesthetic program) by Hartmann.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>単なる訳者にとどまらない鴎外の審美学は、坪内逍遥との没理想論争にも現れており、田山花袋にも影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai&apos;s aesthetics were more than a translator&apos;s one as shown in the dispute on &quot;anti-idealism&quot; with Shoyo TSUBOUCHI, and it also affected on Katai TAYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai&apos;s study of aesthetics went further than that of a translator, as shown in the dispute on &quot;anti-idealism&quot; with Shoyo TSUBOUCHI, which also affected Katai TAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai&apos;s study of aesthetics went further than that of a translator, as shown in the dispute on &quot;anti-idealism&quot; with Shoyo TSUBOUCHI, which also affected Katai TAYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>その鴎外は、上記のとおり東京美術学校（現東京藝術大学）の嘱託教員（美術解剖学・審美学・西洋美術史）をはじめ、慶應義塾大学の審美学講師、「初期文展」西洋画部門などの審査員、帝室博物館総長や日本芸術院初代院長などをつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beginning with a part-time professor (of artistic anatomy, aesthetics and western art history) of Tokyo School of Fine Arts (present Tokyo University of the Arts), Ogai also served as an istructor of aesthetics of Keio University, an examiner of the western painting department of &apos;the initial Bunten exhibition&apos;, the director general of Imperial Museum, the 1st director of The Japan Art Academy ans so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting as a part-time professor (of artistic anatomy, aesthetics and western art history) at Tokyo School of Fine Arts (present Tokyo University of the Arts), Ogai also served as an istructor of aesthetics at Keio University, an examiner of the western painting department of &apos;the 1st Bunten exhibition&apos;, the director general of Imperial Museum, the 1st director of The Japan Art Academy and so on.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting as a part-time professor (of artistic anatomy, aesthetics and western art history) at Tokyo School of Fine Arts (present Tokyo University of the Arts), Ogai also served as an instructor of aesthetics at Keio University, an examiner of the western painting department of &apos;the 1st Bunten exhibition,&apos; the director general of Imperial Museum, the 1st director of The Japan Art Academy and so on.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="149">
<j>交際も広く、その顔ぶれが多彩であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a wide circle of acquaintances in every field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a wide circle of acquaintances in every field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a wide circle of acquaintances in every field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>しかし、教師でもあった夏目漱石のように弟子を取ったり、文壇で党派を作ったりはしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, he didn&apos;t take apprentices or establish a new group in the literary world like Soseki NATSUME who was also a professor like him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, he didn&apos;t take apprentices or establish a new group in the literary world like Soseki NATSUME who was also a professor like him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, he didn&apos;t take apprentices or establish a new group in the literary world like Soseki NATSUME who was also a professor like him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>ドイツに4年留学した鴎外は、閉鎖的で縛られたような人間関係を好まず、西洋風の社交的なサロンの雰囲気を好んでいたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai who had spent four years in Germany seemed to prefer the social atmosphere of salon in western style to the closed bound-like human relationship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai who had spent four years in Germany seemed to prefer the socialable atmosphere of Wester style lounges to closed, restricted human relationships.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai who had spent four years in Germany seemed to prefer the sociable atmosphere of Western style lounges to closed, restricted human relationships.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>高等官生活の合間も、書斎にこもらず、同人誌を主宰したり、自宅で歌会を開いたりして色々な人々と交際した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spare moments from his work as a senior official, he edited a publication aimed at a particular hobby group or held a poetry reading at home to make a communication with different people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spare moments from his work as a senior official, he edited publications aimed at a particular hobby groups or held poetry readings at home to make contact with various different people.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spare moments from his work as a senior official, he edited publications aimed at a particular hobby groups or held poetry readings at home to make contact with various different people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="153">
<j>文学者・文人に限っても、訳詩集『於母影』は5人による共訳であり、同人誌の『しがらみ草紙』と『めさまし草』にも多くの人が参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if limited to literary persons and men of letters, the Omokage (Vestiges), a translated book of poems, was translated by five persons, and &apos;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&apos; and &apos;Mezamashi-gusa (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine&apos;, a publication aimed at a particular hobby group, were handled by a lot of people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though it was limited to literary people and men of letters, the Omokage (Vestiges), a translated book of poems, was translated by five people, and &apos;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&apos; and &apos;Mezamashi-gusa (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine&apos;, a publication aimed at a particular hobby group, were circulated to many people.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though it was limited to literary people and men of letters, the &quot;Omokage&quot; (Vestiges), a translated book of poems, was translated by five people, and &quot;Shigarami Soshi&quot; (Constraint Brochure) and &quot;Mezamashi-gusa&quot; (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine, a publication aimed at a particular hobby group, were circulated to many people.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>とりわけ、自宅（観潮楼）で定期的に開催された歌会が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, the poetry reading periodically took place at his home (Kanchoro House) is well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poetry readings that periodically took place at his home (Kanchoro House) are especially well known.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poetry readings that periodically took place at his home (Kanchoro House) are especially well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>その観潮楼歌会は、1907年（明治40年）3月、鴎外が与謝野鉄幹の「新詩社」系と正岡子規の系譜「根岸」派との歌壇内対立を見かね、両派の代表歌人をまねいて開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Poetry Reading at Kanchoro House took place in March 1907, from Ogai&apos;s concerns about the confrontation in the literary world, between Tekkan YOSANO&apos;s group following the line of &apos;Shinshisya (New Poetry Society)&apos; and &apos;Negishi&apos; School tracing the line back to Shiki MASAOKA, to invite the representative poet from each school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Poetry Readings at Kanchoro House began in March 1907, and as Ogai was concerned about causing confrontation in the literary world between Tekkan YOSANO&apos;s school, the &apos;Shinshisya (New Poetry Society)&apos; and the &apos;Negishi&apos; School which originated with Shiki MASAOKA, he invited a representative poet from each school.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Poetry Readings at Kanchoro House began in March 1907, and as Ogai was concerned about causing confrontation in the literary world between Tekkan YOSANO&apos;s school, the &apos;Shinshisha&apos; (New Poetry Society) and the &apos;Negishi&apos; School which originated with Shiki MASAOKA, he invited a representative poet from each school.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>以後、毎月第一土曜日に集まり、1910年（明治43年）4月までつづいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, they began to get together on every first Saturday, and it continued until April 1910.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, they began to get together on every first Saturday of the month, and it continued until April 1910.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, they began to get together on every first Saturday of the month, and it continued until April 1910.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>伊藤左千夫・平野万里・上田敏・佐佐木信綱等が参加し、「新詩社」系の北原白秋・吉井勇・石川啄木・木下杢太郎、「根岸」派の斉藤茂吉・古泉千樫等の新進歌人も参加した（与謝野晶子を含めて延べ22名）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from Sachio ITO, Banri HIRANO, Bin UEDA, Nobutsuna SASAKI and others, the attendees were Hakushu KITAHARA, Isamu YOSHII, Takuboku ISHIKAWA and Mokutaro KINOSHITA from the group following the line of &apos;Shinshisya&apos; and the new poets from &apos;Negishi&apos; School such as Mokichi SAITO and Chikashi KOIZUMI (twenty-two people at total including Akiko YOSANO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As well as Sachio ITO, Banri HIRANO, Bin UEDA, and Nobutsuna SASAKI, Hakushu KITAHARA, Isamu YOSHII, Takuboku ISHIKAWA and Mokutaro KINOSHITA from the &apos;Shinshisya&apos; school and the new poets from &apos;Negishi&apos; School such as Mokichi SAITO and Chikashi KOIZUMI also took park (twenty-two people in total including Akiko YOSANO).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As well as Sachio ITO, Banri HIRANO, Bin UEDA, and Nobutsuna SASAKI, Hakushu KITAHARA, Isamu YOSHII, Takuboku ISHIKAWA and Mokutaro KINOSHITA from the &apos;Shinshisha&apos; school and the new poets from &apos;Negishi&apos; School such as Mokichi SAITO and Chikashi KOIZUMI also took park (twenty-two people in total including Akiko YOSANO).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="158">
<j>また、当時としては女性蔑視が少なく、樋口一葉をいち早く激賞しただけでなく、与謝野晶子と平塚らいてうも早くから高く評価した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, the women were barely despised in this gathering contrary to the times, so Ichiyo HIGUCHI was soon found out as an excellent poet, and Akiko YOSANO and Raicho HIRATSUKA were also highly evaluated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, as the group was relatively undiscriminatory against women for its time, Ichiyo HIGUCHI was soon discovered as an excellent poet, and Akiko YOSANO and Raicho HIRATSUKA were also highly evaluated.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, as the group was relatively undiscriminatory against women for its time, Ichiyo HIGUCHI was soon discovered as an excellent poet, and Akiko YOSANO and Raicho HIRATSUKA were also highly evaluated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>晶子（出産した双子の名付け親が鴎外）やらいてうや純芸術雑誌「番紅花」（さふらん）を主宰した尾竹一枝など、個性的で批判されがちな新しい女性達とも広く交際した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai got along with the modern women with a strong individuality who tended to be criticized such as Akiko (whose twins were named by Ogai), Raicho, Kazue OTAKE who edited &apos;Saffron&apos;, a high art magazine, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai got along with modern women who had a strong sense of individuality and thus were subject to criticism, for example Akiko (whose twins were named by Ogai), Raicho, Kazue OTAKE who edited high art magazine &apos;Saffron&apos;, and so on.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai got along with modern women who had a strong sense of individuality and thus were subject to criticism, for example Akiko (whose twins were named by Ogai), Raicho, Kazue OTAKE who edited high art magazine &apos;Saffron,&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>その鴎外の作品には、女性を主人公にしたものが少なくなく、ヒロインの名を題名にしたものも複数ある（『安井夫人』、戯曲『静』、『花子』、翻訳戯曲『ノラ』（イプセン作『人形の家』））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai produced not a few works which main character was female, and some of those had a title from the heroine&apos;s name (&quot;Yasui fujin (The Wife of Yasui)&quot;, a play &quot;Shizuka&quot; and &quot;Hanako&quot;, a translated play &quot;Nora&quot; (original title &quot;A Doll&apos;s House&quot; of Ibsen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai produced a fair number of works in which main character was female, and some of these had the heroine&apos;s name as a title, such as the plays &quot;Yasui fujin (The Wife of Yasui)&quot;, &quot;Shizuka&quot; and &quot;Hanako&quot;, plus the translated play &quot;Nora&quot; (original title &quot;A Doll&apos;s House&quot; by Ibsen).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai produced a fair number of works in which main character was female, and some of these had the heroine&apos;s name as a title, such as the plays &quot;Yasui fujin&quot; (The Wife of Yasui), &quot;Shizuka&quot; and &quot;Hanako,&quot; plus the translated play &quot;Nora&quot; (original title &quot;A Doll&apos;s House&quot; by Ibsen).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>軍医として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an army surgeon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life as an army surgeon</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Life as an army surgeon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="161">
<j>上記のとおり鴎外は、東京大学で近代西洋医学を学んだ陸軍軍医（第一期生）であり、医学先進国ドイツに4年間留学し、最終的に軍医総監（中将相当）・医務局長にまで上りつめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, Ogai was an army surgeon (a member of the inaugural class) who learned the modern Western medicine at The University of Tokyo, then went to study in Germany, a medically advanced country, for four years, and finally moved on to the General Office Director of Army Surgeon (corresponding to Lieutenant General), Medical Office Director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, Ogai was an army surgeon (a member of the inaugural class) who learned modern Western medicine at The University of Tokyo, then went to study for four years in medically advanced Germany, finally moving on to be General Office Director of Military Medicine (corresponding to Lieutenant General), and Medical Office Director.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, Ogai was an army surgeon (a member of the inaugural class) who learned modern Western medicine at The University of Tokyo, then went to study for four years in medically advanced Germany, finally moving on to be General Office Director of Military Medicine (corresponding to Lieutenant General), and Medical Office Director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>当時軍事衛生上の大きな問題であった脚気の原因について細菌による感染症との説を主張し、のちに海軍軍医総監になる高木兼寛（及びイギリス医学）と対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He insisted on his theory that beriberi which was a big concern in the military hygiene of the times was an infectious disease through germs, and was opposed to Kanehiro TAKAKI (and the British medical science) who later became the General Office Director of Navy Surgeon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He asserted his theory that beriberi, a major concern in the military at the time, was an infectious disease spread through germs, in opposition to Kanehiro TAKAKI, who later became the General Office Director of Navy Surgeon, and British medical science.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He asserted his theory that beriberi, a major concern in the military at the time, was an infectious disease spread through germs, in opposition to Kanehiro TAKAKI, who later became the General Office Director of Navy Surgeon, and British medical science.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>自説に固執し、当時海軍で採用していた脚気対策の治療法として行われていた麦飯を禁止する通達を出し、さらに日露戦争でも兵士に麦飯を支給するのを拒んだ（自ら短編「妄想」で触れている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was so obsessed by his theory that he issued an announcement to forbid eating barley rice which was taken as a diet for beriberi in the Navy of the times, and in the Russo-Japanese War also, he refused to supply barley rice to soldiers (as he mentioned in his short story &apos;Moso (Delusion)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was so convinced of his theory that he issued an announcement to forbid eating barley rice which was taken as a diet supplement for beriberi in the Navy of the times, and in the Russo-Japanese War also, he refused to supply barley rice to soldiers (as he mentioned in his short story &apos;Moso (Delusion)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was so convinced of his theory that he issued an announcement to forbid eating barley rice which was taken as a diet supplement for beriberi in the Navy of the times, and in the Russo-Japanese War also, he refused to supply barley rice to soldiers (as he mentioned in his short story &apos;Moso&apos; (Delusion).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>但し当時の医学水準上（ビタミンの未発見）麦飯食と脚気改善の相関関係は(ドイツ医学的には)科学的に立証されておらず、高木側は脚気の原因を(イギリス医学の手法である、患者と食料の統計学的分析から)蛋白質不足であるとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the correlation between barley rice and the improvement of beriberi hadn&apos;t been scientifically proved (in the field of German medical science) because of the undeveloped medical standard of the times (vitamins hadn&apos;t been found yet), and Takagi considered the cause of beriberi as a short of protein (from the statistical analysis on the patients and foods).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because of the undeveloped medical standards of the time (vitamins were as yet unknown) the correlation between consuming barley rice and the improvement of beriberi had not been scientifically proven (in the field of German medical science), and Takagi considered the cause of beriberi to be a shortage of protein (from statistical analysis of patients and foods based on a british model).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because of the undeveloped medical standards of the time (vitamins were as yet unknown) the correlation between consuming barley rice and the improvement of beriberi had not been scientifically proven (in the field of German medical science), and Takagi considered the cause of beriberi to be a shortage of protein (from statistical analysis of patients and foods based on a British model).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>ともあれ結果的に陸軍は25万人の脚気患者を出し、3万名近い兵士を病死させる事態となった（同時期、海軍では脚気患者はわずか87名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the consequence, the Army made 250 thousands beriberi patients, and near 30 thousands soldiers died from beriberi (meanwhile, the Navy had only 87 beriberi patients.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a consequence, 250,000 people in the army suffered from beriberi, and nearly 30,000 soldiers died, however the Navy had only 87 beriberi patients.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a consequence, 250,000 people in the army suffered from beriberi, and nearly 30,000 soldiers died, however the Navy had only 87 beriberi patients.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>高木により食品と脚気の相関関係が予測され、兵員に麦飯が支給されたためである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because Takagi anticipated the correlation between foods and beriberi, and supplied barley rice to soldiers.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because Takagi anticipated the correlation between foods and beriberi, and supplied barley rice to soldiers.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because Takagi anticipated the correlation between foods and beriberi, and supplied barley rice to soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>実に2個師団に相当する兵士が脚気で命を落とし、また戦闘力低下のために戦死した兵も少なくなく「（鴎外は）ロシアのどの将軍よりも多くの日本兵を殺した」との批判も存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The soldiers corresponding to the number of two divisions died from beriberi, and not a few soldiers were killed in the war because of losing their fighting energy due to beriberi, so Ogai was criticized that he had killed Japanese soldiers much more than any Russian general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two divisions&apos; worth of soldiers died from beriberi, and many soldiers were killed in the war through lack of energy due to the disease, so Ogai was criticised for contributing more to the deaths of Japanese soldiers than any Russian general.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two divisions&apos; worth of soldiers died from beriberi, and many soldiers were killed in the war through lack of energy due to the disease, so Ogai was criticized for contributing more to the deaths of Japanese soldiers than any Russian general.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>日露戦争終戦直前、業を煮やした陸軍大臣寺内正毅が鴎外の頭越しに麦飯の支給を決定、鴎外の面目は失われることとなった（寺内は日清戦争当時、具申した脚気対策に麦を送れと言う要望を鴎外により握り潰された経緯がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just before the end of the Russo-Japanese War, Masatake TERAUCHI, a Minister of Army, got impatient and decided to supply barley rice ignoring Ogai attending there, thus, Ogai disgraced himself (Terauchi used to demand to send barley rice as a diet for beriberi during the Sino-Japanese War, but it was turned down by Ogai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before the end of the Russo-Japanese War, Masatake TERAUCHI, the Minister of the Army, became impatient and decided to ignore the attendant Ogai and supply barley rice, making Ogai lose face (During the Sino-Japanese War Terauchi also demanded barley rice as a supplement for beriberi, but was turned down by Ogai).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before the end of the Russo-Japanese War, Masatake TERAUCHI, the Minister of the Army, became impatient and decided to ignore the attendant Ogai and supply barley rice, making Ogai lose face (During the Sino-Japanese War Terauchi also demanded barley rice as a supplement for beriberi, but was turned down by Ogai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>「予は陸軍内で孤立しつつあり」とは、この頃の鴎外の述懐である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai later recalled, &apos;I was being isolated in the Army&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai later recalled, &apos;I was being isolated in the Army&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai later recalled, &apos;I was being isolated in the Army.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="170">
<j>後に鈴木梅太郎が脚気の特効薬であるオリザニン（＝ビタミンB1）を発見し、脚気との因果関係が証明されて治癒の報告が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umetaro SUZUKI later discovered オリザニン (=vitamin B1), a specific for beriberi, and the correlation with beriberi was proved, and the effect was reported one after anoter.</e>
<cmt>webで検索しましたが、「オリザニン」のスペル不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umetaro SUZUKI later discovered Oryzanin (Vitamin B1), a wonder drug for beriberi, and having proved its correlation with the disease, reports of its effectiveness were issued in quick succession.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umetaro SUZUKI later discovered Oryzanin (Vitamin B1), a wonder drug for beriberi, and having proved its correlation with the disease, reports of its effectiveness were issued in quick succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>しかしその後も鴎外はかたくなに鈴木および学会の見解を批判した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after that, however, Ogai obstinately criticized the view of Suzuki and the learned society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after that, however, Ogai obstinately criticized the views of Suzuki and academic society.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after that, however, Ogai obstinately criticized the views of Suzuki and academic society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>また、赤痢菌を見つけた志賀潔などが脚気の栄養由来説を支持したこともあり、医学界でも脚気栄養起源説が受け入れられつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Kiyoshi SHIGA who had discovered a dysentery bacillus also supported the theory on beriberi deriving from nutrition, so even in the medical world, the theory on beriberi deriving from nutrtition began to be accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Kiyoshi SHIGA, the man who discovered the dysentery bacillus, also supported the theory that beriberi was related to nutrition, so even in the medical world this theory began to be accepted.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Kiyoshi SHIGA, the man who discovered the dysentery bacillus, also supported the theory that beriberi was related to nutrition, so even in the medical world this theory began to be accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>この頃より鴎外の医学界での孤立はますます深まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this time around, Ogai&apos;s isolation in the medical world was getting deeper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around this time, Ogai&apos;s isolation in the medical world was getting deeper.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around this time, Ogai&apos;s isolation in the medical world was getting deeper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>結局、鴎外は死ぬまで「脚気は細菌による感染症である」との自説を撤回しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, Ogai never turned down his theory that beriberi was an infectious disease through germs, until his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Ogai never let go of his theory that beriberi was an infectious disease spread through germs his whole life.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Ogai never let go of his theory that beriberi was an infectious disease spread through germs his whole life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>脚気栄養起源説の国家としての見識が示されたのは鴎外の死の2年後であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was two years after Ogai&apos;s death that the nation discerned the view of beriberi deriving from nutrition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was two years after Ogai&apos;s death that the nation accepted the view that beriberi derived from nutrition.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was two years after Ogai&apos;s death that the nation accepted the view that beriberi derived from nutrition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="176">
<j>鴎外を擁護する立場からは、下士官・兵 (日本軍)達の「入隊したからには白米を食べたい」という声があり、当時、麦飯は白米に比べ美味でないとされていた（麦の精白技術が現代ほど発達していなかったため）こと（脚気歴史）を考慮すべきとの意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the point of view of the people who protect Ogai, people should consider the fact that, in the times, most of noncommissioned officers and soldiers (Japanese army) longed for eating polished rice after joining army, because barley rice was less tasty than polished rice (the rice polishing technology hadn&apos;t been developed yet compared to today), and also the history of beriberi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also those who defend Ogai, suggesting that people should consider the fact that, at the time, most noncommissioned officers and soldiers longed to eat polished white rice after joining the army, because barley rice was less tasty (rice polishing technology was not as advanced as it is today).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also those who defend Ogai, suggesting that people should consider the fact that, at the time, most noncommissioned officers and soldiers longed to eat polished white rice after joining the army, because barley rice was less tasty (rice polishing technology was not as advanced as it is today).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="177">
<j>麦飯食を推進した高木兼寛は都市衛生問題で「高木兼寛貧民散布論」を提案し、東京から貧民を追い出すべきとの主張をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanehiro TAKAKI who had recommended eating barley rice proposed &apos;the theory on scattering the poor&apos; to resolve the urban hygiene issue, and insisted on kicking the poor out of Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanehiro TAKAKI, who recommended eating barley rice, proposed &apos;Dissemination of Poverty&apos; to resolve the urban hygiene issue, and insisted on kicking the poor out of Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanehiro TAKAKI, who recommended eating barley rice, proposed &apos;Dissemination of Poverty&apos; to resolve the urban hygiene issue, and insisted on kicking the poor out of Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>この主張はたしかに医学的・公衆衛生学的にはある程度評価できるものであったが、人道上の大きな問題があり、その立場から「貧民散布論」を徹底批判したのが鴎外ということもあって、両者の間には感情的にも深い対立関係が存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This insistence was certainly acceptable to some extent from the medical or public hygienic point of view, but there was a big problem of humanity, from which Ogai criticized the &apos;theory on scattering the poor&apos; to the bottom, so they were deeply opposed each other even emotionally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whilst this insistence may have been acceptable to some extent from a medical or public hygiene point of view, there was a major humanitarian issue, and even Ogai fundamentally disagreed with the &apos;Dissemination of Poverty&apos; so the two were deeply opposed each other emotionally and otherwise.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whilst this insistence may have been acceptable to some extent from a medical or public hygiene point of view, there was a major humanitarian issue, and even Ogai fundamentally disagreed with the &apos;Dissemination of Poverty&apos; so the two were deeply opposed each other emotionally and otherwise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="179">
<j>加えて脚気細菌起源説は鴎外のドイツ留学実現に尽力した石黒忠悳の主張だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the theory on beriberi deriving from germs was originally insisted by Tadanori ISHIGURO who contributed to the realization of Ogai&apos;s study in Germany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the theory of beriberi deriving from germs was originally suggested by Tadanori ISHIGURO who contributed to realising Ogai&apos;s study in Germany.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the theory of beriberi deriving from germs was originally suggested by Tadanori ISHIGURO who contributed to realizing Ogai&apos;s study in Germany.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>このため当時ドイツ留学が国費留学以外に不可能だったという事情を鑑みる向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, some people point out such circumstances of the times when the study in Germany could not be possible without the government&apos;s financial support.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been pointed that the situation at the time was such that study in Germany was not possible without the government&apos;s financial support.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been pointed that the situation at the time was such that study in Germany was not possible without the government&apos;s financial support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>なお、森鴎外も食事上の栄養価については考慮していて、日露戦争時は新たに兵に十分な肉と野菜を与えるように指示していたが、脚気は細菌に由来すると考えていたため、脚気を考慮していたものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Ogai MORI recognized the importance of nutrition value of meal enough, and instructed to supply enough meat and vegetables to soldiers during the Sino-Japanese War, but he believed beriberi derived from germs, so it was not because of concerns with beriberi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Ogai MORI did recognise the importance of the nutritional value of food, and gave instruction for sufficient supplies of meat and vegetables to soldiers during the Sino-Japanese War, but as he believed beriberi derived from germs he did not think nutrition played a role in the disease.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Ogai MORI did recognize the importance of the nutritional value of food, and gave instruction for sufficient supplies of meat and vegetables to soldiers during the Sino-Japanese War, but as he believed beriberi derived from germs he did not think nutrition played a role in the disease.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>（ただし、当時肉として主に使われていた豚肉には大量のビタミンB1が含まれているため、森鴎外の指示が行われていたら、脚気は発生しなかった可能性が高い)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(however, pork which was eaten the most among meat in the times contains a lot of vitamin B1, so if Ogai MORI&apos;s instruction had actually been carried out, beriberi might not have occurred).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, pork, which the most consumed meat at the time contains a lot of vitamin B1, so if Ogai MORI&apos;s instruction had actually been carried out, beriberi might not have occurred.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, pork, which the most consumed meat at the time contains a lot of vitamin B1, so if Ogai MORI&apos;s instruction had actually been carried out, beriberi might not have occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>日露戦争では補給が滞り現地調達も困難であったため、米のみで熱量（カロリー）を補給する事態となり、鴎外らによって麦飯の補給を止められた陸軍では、大量の脚気患者と死者を生み出す結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Russo-Japanese War, the food supply got disconnected and it was also difficult to procure on the spot, so soldiers had to take energy (calories) only through rice, but in the Army, the supply of barley rice was stopped by Ogai and others, so it led to bringing a lot of beriberi patients and deads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Russo-Japanese War, the food supply got disconnected and it was difficult to procure on the spot, so the soldiers&apos; energy (calories) came purely through rice, and as the supply of barley rice to the army was stopped by Ogai and others, it led to many cases of beriberi and many deaths.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Russo-Japanese War, the food supply got disconnected and it was difficult to procure on the spot, so the soldiers&apos; energy (calories) came purely through rice, and as the supply of barley rice to the army was stopped by Ogai and others, it led to many cases of beriberi and many deaths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="184">
<j>『森鴎外全集』には医学に関する論文が多数収められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;MORI Ogai Zenshu (the Complete Works of Ogai MORI)&apos;, a lot of theses on the medical science were contained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lot of theses on medical science are recorded in &apos;MORI Ogai Zenshu (the Complete Works of Ogai MORI)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lot of theses on medical science are recorded in &quot;MORI Ogai Zenshu&quot; (the Complete Works of Ogai MORI).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>また、なぜビールに利尿作用があるのか、といった研究も行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also studied on the theme why beer had the diuretic effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also studied the question of why beer had a diuretic effect.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also studied the question of why beer had a diuretic effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>軍医であったためか「情勢を報告する・させる」目的から「情報」という言葉を考え出した人物とも言われる（異論もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably because of an army surgeon, he is told to have created the term of &apos;Information&apos; for the purpose of &apos;reporting the situation&apos; (there is also an objection).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Perhaps because he was an army surgeon, he is said to have created the Chinese-derived word Joho (&apos;Information&apos;) stemming from the first characters of the words Reporting (&apos;Hokoku&apos;) and Situation (&apos;Josei&apos;), however this theory is disputed.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Perhaps because he was an army surgeon, he is said to have created the Chinese-derived word Joho (&apos;Information&apos;) stemming from the first characters of the words Reporting (&apos;Hokoku&apos;) and Situation (&apos;Josei&apos;), however this theory is disputed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="187">
<j>医学功績と脚気問題から見た再評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public re-estimation from the point of view of his medical achievement and beriberi issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public re-evaluation considering his medical achievements and the beriberi issue.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public re-evaluation considering his medical achievements and the beriberi issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>鴎外の医学業績として、とくに二つの点が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for Ogai&apos;s medical achievement, the following two things can be taken up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for Ogai&apos;s medical achievements, the following two things may be noted.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for Ogai&apos;s medical achievements, the following two things may be noted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>一つは、ドイツから帰国した翌年の陸軍兵食試験（1889年8月-12月）であり、その試験は当時の栄養学の最先端に位置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One thing is the examination on the army soldier food which took place in the following year of his coming back from Germany (August - December, 1889), and the examination was in the forefront of the nutritional science of the times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first is the examination of soldiers&apos; food which took place in the year following his return from Germany (August - December, 1889), which was at the forefront of nutritional science of the time.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first is the examination of soldiers&apos; food which took place in the year following his return from Germany (August - December, 1889), which was at the forefront of nutritional science of the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>もう一つは、陸軍省医務局長就任後の臨時脚気病調査会の創設（1908年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another thing was the foundation of the Provisional Investigation Committee of Beriberi after his assumption of the Director of Medical Bureau, Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second is his foundation of the Provisional Investigation Committee of Beriberi after assuming the role of Director of the Medical Bureau, Department of War.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second is his foundation of the Provisional Investigation Committee of Beriberi in 1908 after assuming the role of Director of the Medical Bureau, Department of War.</e>
<cmt>年号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>脚気病の原因究明を目的としたその調査会は、陸軍大臣の監督する国家機関として、当代一流の研究者が総動員され、多額の予算がつぎ込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The investigation committee having the purpose of looking deep into the causes of beriberi involved all top grade researchers of the times and took a huge amount of budget, as a state institution directed by Minister of Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The investigation committee, a state institution directed by the Minister of the Army, was dedicated to looking deep into the causes of beriberi, included all the top researchers of the time and took a huge amount of money.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The investigation committee, a state institution directed by the Minister of the Army, was dedicated to looking deep into the causes of beriberi, included all the top researchers of the time and took a huge amount of money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>脚気ビタミン説が確定して廃止（1924年）されたものの、その後の脚気病研究会の母体となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was abolished upon the theory on the correlation between beriberi and vitamins (1924) settled down, it became a parent organization of the later study group of beriberi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was abolished in 1924 when the theory of correlation between beriberi and vitamins became accepted, it became a parent organization to a later study group of beriberi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was abolished in 1924 when the theory of correlation between beriberi and vitamins became accepted, it became a parent organization to a later study group of beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>鴎外が創設に尽力した臨時脚気病調査会は、脚気研究の土台をつくり、ビタミン研究の基礎をきずいたとして位置づけられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The investigation committee for the purpose of looking deep into the causes of beriberi for which Ogai contributed to the establishment is now cosidered to have built the foundation of study on beriberi and vitamins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The investigation committee to research the causes of beriberi which Ogai helped establish is now cosidered to have built the foundations for the study of beriberi and vitamins.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The investigation committee to research the causes of beriberi which Ogai helped establish is now considered to have built the foundations for the study of beriberi and vitamins.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>もっとも、脚気問題について高木兼寛は、海軍の兵食改革で海軍の脚気を「根絶」したとして賞賛されるのに対し、鴎外は陸軍の脚気惨害を助長したとして非難されやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on the beriberi issue, Kanehiro TAKAKI is praised to have &apos;exterminated&apos; beriberi in the Navy by his soldier food reform, while Ogai tends to be blamed to have worsened the Army&apos;s beriberi disaster.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on the beriberi issue, Kanehiro TAKAKI is praised to have &apos;exterminated&apos; the disease in the Navy through his food reform, whilst Ogai tends to be blamed for worsening the Army&apos;s beriberi situation.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on the beriberi issue, Kanehiro TAKAKI is praised to have &apos;exterminated&apos; the disease in the Navy through his food reform, whilst Ogai tends to be blamed for worsening the Army&apos;s beriberi situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>しかし、その対照的な評価には、「内実を知らない浅薄な見方にすぎない」との批判がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some people criticize such completely opposed evaluation that &apos;it is nothing but a shallow view of someone who doesn&apos;t know the truth&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some evaluate the situation in a completely opposite way, criticising such opinions as &apos;nothing but the shallow view of someone who doesn&apos;t know the truth&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some evaluate the situation in a completely opposite way, criticising such opinions as &apos;nothing but the shallow view of someone who doesn&apos;t know the truth.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>第一に海軍で「根絶」したはずの脚気病が大正期の中頃から急増した事実がある（たとえば昭和期に入っても1928年に1,153人、また1937年から1941年まで1,000人を下回ることがなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Firstly, there is a fact that beriberi which ought to have &apos;exterminated&apos; in the Navy surged again from the mid-Taisho Period (for exemple, even in Showa Period, the number of patients was 1,153 in 1928, and staying over 1,000 between 1937 and 1941).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Firstly, there is the fact that beriberi which was supposed to have been &apos;exterminated&apos; in the Navy emerged again from the mid-Taisho Period (for example, even in Showa Period, the number of patients was 1,153 in 1928, and remained over 1,000 between 1937 and 1941).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Firstly, there is the fact that beriberi which was supposed to have been &apos;exterminated&apos; in the Navy emerged again from the mid-Taisho period (for example, even in Showa period, the number of patients was 1,153 in 1928, and remained over 1,000 between 1937 and 1941).</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>海軍で患者が増加した理由として、次のことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reasons of patients&apos; increase in the Navy are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reasons for the increase in sufferers in the Navy are as follows.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons for the increase in sufferers in the Navy are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>兵食の問題（実は航海食がビタミン欠乏状態）、艦船の行動範囲拡大、高木の脚気原因説（たんぱく質と炭水化物の比例の失衡）の誤りの影響、「海軍の脚気は撲滅した」という信仰がくずれたこと（脚気診断の進歩もあって見過ごされていた患者を把握できるようになった（それ以前、神経疾患に混入していた可能性がある））である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The problem on the soldier food (the food on board was short of vitamins), the expansion of sailing area, the affect by Takagi&apos;s wrong theory on the causes of beriberi (unbalance between protein and carbohydrate), the collapse of the belief that &apos;beriberi in the Navy was exterminated&apos; (thanks to the progress of the diagnosis standard of beriberi, the patients who might have been given another diagnosis could come to be diagnosed properly &lt;before that, those patients might have been diagnosed as nervous disorder&gt;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The quality of army food (food on board was short in vitamins), expansion of the sailing area, the effect of Takagi&apos;s incorrect theory on the causes of beriberi (unbalance between protein and carbohydrate), the collapse of the belief that &apos;beriberi in the Navy has been exterminated&apos; (thanks to the progress of diagnostic standards of beriberi, patients who might before have been been diagnosed with nervous disorder could now receive a correct diagnosis).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The quality of army food (food on board was short in vitamins), expansion of the sailing area, the effect of Takagi&apos;s incorrect theory on the causes of beriberi (unbalance between protein and carbohydrate), the collapse of the belief that &apos;beriberi in the Navy has been exterminated&apos; (thanks to the progress of diagnostic standards of beriberi, patients who might before have been diagnosed with nervous disorder could now receive a correct diagnosis).</e>
<cmt>重複削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>第二に、鴎外が陸軍の脚気惨害を助長したという批判に対し、次のような見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Secondly, there is a view mentioned below in order to counter the criticism that Ogai worsened the beriberi disaster in the Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, there is also opposition to the criticism that Ogai made the Army&apos;s beriberi situation worse.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, there is also opposition to the criticism that Ogai made the Army&apos;s beriberi situation worse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>まず、陸軍の脚気惨害の責任について、戦時下で陸軍の衛生に関する総責任を負う大本営陸軍部の大本営組織（日清戦争日本軍の損害・石黒忠悳、日露戦争講和へ・小池正直）ではなく、隷下の一軍医部長を矢面に立たせることへの疑問である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all, the responsibility for the beriberi disaster should have been taken by the organization of Imperial headquarters in the Army Department because it was supposed to bear the whole responsibility for the Army hygiene during the war (Tadanori ISHIGURO, the damage to Japanese Army in the Sino-Japanese War, Masanao KOIKE, to the peace after Russo-Japanese War), but a director of the army surgeon department, a lower position than the above, was weirdly imposed the responsibility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First of all, there is doubt surrounding the fact that responsibility for the beriberi disaster was not taken by the Army Department of the Imperial headquarters which was supposed to bear all responsibility for Army hygiene during the war (Tadanori ISHIGURO, in charge of Japanese Army casualties in the Sino-Japanese War, Masanao KOIKE, in charge of securing peace after the Russo-Japanese War), but by a director of the military medicine department, who was of a lower rank than them.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First of all, there is doubt surrounding the fact that responsibility for the beriberi disaster was not taken by the Army Department of the Imperial headquarters which was supposed to bear all responsibility for Army hygiene during the war (Tadanori ISHIGURO, in charge of Japanese Army casualties in the Sino-Japanese War, Masanao KOIKE, in charge of securing peace after the Russo-Japanese War), but by a director of the military medicine department, who was of a lower rank than them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>次に、鴎外が白米飯を擁護したことが陸軍の脚気惨害を助長したという批判については、日露戦争当時、麦飯派の寺内正毅が陸軍大臣であった（麦飯を主張する軍医部長がいた）にもかかわらず、大本営が「勅令」として指示した戦時兵食は、日清戦争と同じ白米飯（精白米6合）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, as for the criticism that Ogai worsened the beriberi disaster of the Army by insisting on the supply of polished rice, although the Minister of Army during the Russo-Japanese War was Masatake TERAUCHI who supported barley rice (he had a director of army surgeon department who insisted on the barley rice), the soldier food the Imperial headquarters instructed to supply by the &apos;Imperial edict&apos; was the polished rice (polished rice 6 go) just like in the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the criticism that Ogai worsened the beriberi disaster by insisting on polished rice, although the Minister of Army during the Russo-Japanese War, Masatake TERAUCHI, supported the use of barley rice (the director of military insisted on it), the Imperial headquarters themselves instructed the supply of polished rice (6 go) to soldiers by the Imperial edict, just like in the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the criticism that Ogai worsened the beriberi disaster by insisting on polished rice, although the Minister of Army during the Russo-Japanese War, Masatake TERAUCHI, supported the use of barley rice (the director of military insisted on it), the Imperial headquarters themselves instructed the supply of polished rice (6 go) to soldiers by the Imperial edict, just like in the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>その理由として「麦は虫がつきやすい、変敗しやすい、味が悪い、輸送が困難などの反対論がつよく」、その上、脚気予防（理屈）とは別のもの（情）もあったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the opinions mentioned the negative effect of barley rice such as, &apos;the barley rice was easily infested with vermin or deteriorated, the taste was bad, the tranport was difficult&apos;, besides, there seemed to be another reason (emotional) apart from the prevention of beriberi (logical).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reasons for this included the fact barley rice easily deteriorated and became infested with vermin, tasted bad and was difficult to transport, besides which practical concerns it is said there was another emotional resistance to barley rice.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons for this included the fact barley rice easily deteriorated and became infested with vermin, tasted bad and was difficult to transport, besides which practical concerns it is said there was another emotional resistance to barley rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>白米飯は庶民あこがれのご馳走であり、麦飯は貧民の食事として蔑まれていた世情を無視できず、また部隊長の多くも死地に行かせる兵士に白米を食べさせたいという心情があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The polished rice used to be a big meal common people admired, while barley rice was despised as the food the poor ate, so such people&apos;s thoughts couldn&apos;t be ignored, besides, most of the troop leaders wanted the soldiers to eat the polished rice before leaving for the front where they might be killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Polished rice used to be considered a feast common people dreamed of, while barley rice was looked down on as the food of the poor, and such thoughts could not be ignored, besides, most troop leaders wanted to give their soldiers the treat of polished rice before leaving for the front where they might be killed.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Polished rice used to be considered a feast common people dreamed of, while barley rice was looked down on as the food of the poor, and such thoughts could not be ignored, besides, most troop leaders wanted to give their soldiers the treat of polished rice before leaving for the front where they might be killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>最後に、鴎外の「陸軍兵食試験」が脚気発生を助長したという批判については、兵食試験の内容（当時として正しい試験で正しい結論）を把握せず、しかもビタミンの存在を知っている後世から、その存在を知らなかった前世への暴論である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, as for the criticism that Ogai&apos;s &apos;examination on the Army solders&apos; food&apos; prompted beriberi to occur, the people in the later generation even don&apos;t know the contents of the examination on the soldier food (it was a right test and a right conclusion at the time), and it was nothing but a wild view of the later generation who knows what the vitamins are, imposed to the earlier generation who had no idea on the vitamins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, as for the criticism that Ogai&apos;s &apos;examination of soldiers&apos; food&apos; prompted beriberi to occur, it is simply an irrational argument imposed by later generations with the knowledge of vitamins, on an earlier generation whose methods and conclusions were suitable and correct for the knowledge that existed at the time.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, as for the criticism that Ogai&apos;s &apos;examination of soldiers&apos; food&apos; prompted beriberi to occur, it is simply an irrational argument imposed by later generations with the knowledge of vitamins, on an earlier generation whose methods and conclusions were suitable and correct for the knowledge that existed at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>ただし兵食試験の成績は、上官の石黒によってゆがめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the results of the soldier food examination were distorted by his superior officer, Ishigro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the results of the examination of soldier&apos;s food were distorted by his superior officer, Ishigro.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the results of the examination of soldier&apos;s food were distorted by his superior officer, Ishiguro.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>その誤用を看過したことは、階級社会の軍隊でも、部下の鴎外に責任がまったく無いといえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if taking account of the Army with a strict class system, it couldn&apos;t be said that Ogai had no responsibility at all for his superior officer&apos;s wrong use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even taking account of the strict class system of the Army, it can&apos;t be said that Ogai had no responsibility at all for his superior officer&apos;s actions.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even taking account of the strict class system of the Army, it can&apos;t be said that Ogai had no responsibility at all for his superior officer&apos;s actions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>以上より、鴎外が脚気問題で批判される多くは、筋違いという意見がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned so far, some people say most of the criticism toward Ogai on the beriberi issue are out of point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As we have seen, some say most of the criticism towards Ogai on the beriberi issue is misdirected.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As we have seen, some say most of the criticism towards Ogai on the beriberi issue is misdirected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>鴎外への批判が起こった理由として、海軍の兵食改良を批判しすぎたこと、論理にこだわりすぎて学術的権威に依拠しすぎたこと、日清戦争時の上官の石黒に同調したことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reasons why Ogai had to be criticized are that he criticized the Navy&apos;s soldier food reform too much, insisted on the logic and relied on the academic authorities too much, sympathized with Ishiguro, his superior officer in the Sino-Japanese War, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reasons Ogai was targeted include the fact he overly criticised the Navy&apos;s soldier food reform, relied on logic and the academic authorities too much and sympathized with Ishiguro, his superior officer in the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons Ogai was targeted include the fact he overly criticized the Navy&apos;s soldier food reform, relied on logic and the academic authorities too much and sympathized with Ishiguro, his superior officer in the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>なお、脚気問題で批判される根拠としては、日露戦争後に鴎外がトップの陸軍省医務局長になったとき、麦飯を禁止して違反者を取り締まった事実や「脚気減少は果して麦を以て米に代へたるに因する乎」という論説を衛生関連の7雑誌に掲載したことで牽制する結果を招いた事（『鴎外全集』第34巻、165-168頁）、｢勝てば官軍」等に表されるように軍人は特に経過を問われずに結果だけで評価されやすい事などがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, the reasons why he was criticized on the beriberi issue are that he punished the people who violated the ban of barley rice when he became the Director of the Medical Office in the Ministry of Army, that he put his theory about &apos;whether decrease of beriberi could be brought by barley rice instead of polished rice&apos; in the seven magazines related to hygiene, which led to restraining his counterparty (&apos;MORI Ogai Zenshu (the Complete Works of Ogai MORI)&apos;, Vol. 34, page 165 to 168), that the military men particularly tended to be evaluated only by the results regardless of the story behind as&apos; shown in the phrase &apos;If win, it&apos;s Imperial army&apos;, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the reasons he was criticized on the beriberi issue are that he punished those who violated the ban of barley rice when he became the Director of the Medical Office in the Ministry of War, that he published his opinion on &apos;Can a decrease in beriberi be brought about by using barley rice instead of polished rice&apos; in seven magazines related to hygiene, thus leaving no room for his competitors (&apos;MORI Ogai Zenshu (the Complete Works of Ogai MORI)&apos;, Vol. 34, page 165 to 168), and that military men tended to be evaluated only on results, regardless of circumstances, as shown in the phrase &apos;Winning is what makes the Imperial army&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the reasons he was criticized on the beriberi issue are that he punished those who violated the ban of barley rice when he became the Director of the Medical Office in the Ministry of War, that he published his opinion on &apos;Can a decrease in beriberi be brought about by using barley rice instead of polished rice&apos; in seven magazines related to hygiene, thus leaving no room for his competitors (&apos;MORI Ogai Zenshu (the Complete Works of Ogai MORI),&apos; Vol. 34, page 165 to 168), and that military men tended to be evaluated only on results, regardless of circumstances, as shown in the phrase &apos;Winning is what makes the Imperial army.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド、カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>年譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronological list of the main events</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronological list of major events</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronological list of major events</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="210">
<j>年齢は数え年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age by the traditional Japanese system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age was counted using the traditional Japanese system.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age was counted using the traditional Japanese system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="211">
<j>1862年2月17日（文久2年1月19日・1歳） - 石見国津和野藩の津和野（現・島根県鹿足郡津和野町）に、津和野藩医・森静泰（後に静男と改名）、峰子の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as first son to Seitai MORI (later, changed his first name to Shizuo), a doctor of Tsuwano Domain, and Mineko, in Tsuwano (present Tsuwano Town, Kanoashi District, Shimane Prefecture) on February 17, 1862.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as a first son to Seitai MORI (later changed his first name to Shizuo), a doctor of Tsuwano Domain, and Mineko, in Tsuwano (present Tsuwano Town, Kanoashi District, Shimane Prefecture) on February 17, 1862.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as a first son to Seitai MORI (later changed his first name to Shizuo), a doctor of Tsuwano Domain, Ishimi Province, and Mineko, in Tsuwano (present Tsuwano-cho, Kanoashi-gun, Shimane Prefecture) on February 17, 1862.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>1867年（慶応3年・6歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six years old in 1867.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1867 he was six.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1867 he was six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="212">
<j>11月、村田久兵衛に論語を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November, he learned Rongo Analects from Kyube MURATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, he learned the Rongo Analects from Kyube MURATA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, he learned the Rongo Analects from Kyube MURATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>1868年（慶応4年・7歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seven years old in 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1868 he was seven.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1868 he was seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="213">
<j>3月、米原綱善に孟子を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March, he learned The Book of Mencius from Tsunayoshi YONEHARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he learned The Book of Mencius from Tsunayoshi YONEHARA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he learned The Book of Mencius from Tsunayoshi YONEHARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>1869年（明治2年・8歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eight years old in 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869 he was eight.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869 he was eight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="214">
<j>- 藩校の養老館で、四書を一から読み直す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started reading again the Four Chinese Books from the beginning at Yoro College.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started rereading the Four Chinese Books from the beginning at Yoro College.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started rereading the Four Chinese Books from the beginning at Yoro College.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>1870年（明治3年・9歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nine years old in 1870.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1870 he was nine.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1870 he was nine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="215">
<j>- 五経、オランダ語を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned the Five Classics texts of Confucianism and Dutch.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned the Five Classics texts of Confucianism and Dutch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned the Five Classics texts of Confucianism and Dutch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>1871年（明治4年・10歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten years old in 1871.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871 he was ten.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871 he was ten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="216">
<j>藩医の室良悦にオランダ語を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Dutch from Ryoetsu MURO, a domain doctor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned Dutch from Ryoetsu MURO, a domain doctor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned Dutch from Ryoetsu MURO, a domain doctor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>1872年（明治5年・11歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eleven years old in 1872.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1872 he was eleven.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1872 he was eleven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="217">
<j>- 6月、父とともに津和野を発ち、8月に東京入り（向島小梅村）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, he left Tsuwano with his father, and in August, entered Tokyo (Koume Village, Mukojima).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, he left Tsuwano with his father, and in August, entered Tokyo (Koume Village, Mukojima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, he left Tsuwano with his father, and in August, entered Tokyo (Koume Village, Mukojima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>その後、向島曳舟通りに転居。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, moved to Hikifune Street, Mukojima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, moved to Hikifune Street, Mukojima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, moved to Hikifune Street, Mukojima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>10月、ドイツ語習得のため、本郷の進文学社（私塾）に入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, enrolled in Shinbungakusya school (a private school) in Hongo to learn German.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he enrolled in Shinbungakusya school (a private school) in Hongo to learn German.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he enrolled in Shinbungakusha school (a private school) in Hongo to learn German.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>1873年（明治6年・12歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twelve years old in 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1873 he was twelve.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1873 he was twelve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="220">
<j>- 6月、津和野町の家を売却し、祖母、母なども上京。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, his grandmother, mother and others went down to Tokyo after selling out their house in Tsuwano Town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, his grandmother, mother and others went down to Tokyo after selling their house in Tsuwano Town.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, his grandmother, mother and others went down to Tokyo after selling their house in Tsuwano Town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>11月、第一大学区医学校予科（現在の東京大学医学部）に入学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, enrolled in the preparatory course of Daiichi Daigaku-ku, Igakko (present the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, he enrolled in the preparatory course of Daiichi Daigaku-ku, Igakko (present the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, he enrolled in the preparatory course of Daiichi Daigaku-ku, Igakko (present the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>同校は、のちに東京医学校に改称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The school later changed the name to Tokyo Igakko (the predecessor of the Medical Faculty of Tokyo University).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The school later changed its name to Tokyo Igakko (the predecessor of the Medical Faculty of Tokyo University).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The school later changed its name to Tokyo Igakko (the predecessor of the Medical Faculty of Tokyo University).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>1877年（明治10年・16歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sixteen years old in 1877.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1877 he was sixteen.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1877 he was sixteen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="223">
<j>- 東京医学校は、東京開成学校と合併して東京大学医学部に改組され、その本科生になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Igakko was merged into Tokyo Kaisei Gakko (Kaisei School) to form the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine, and he became the regular course student.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Igakko was merged into Tokyo Kaisei Gakko (Kaisei School) to form the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine, and he became a regular student.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Igakko was merged into Tokyo Kaisei Gakko (Kaisei School) to form the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine, and he became a regular student.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>1880年（明治13年・19歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nineteen years old in 1880.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1880 he was nineteen.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1880 he was nineteen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="224">
<j>本郷龍岡町の下宿屋「上条」に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moved into &apos;Kamijo&apos;, a boarding house in Hongo-tatsuoka-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He moved into &apos;Kamijo&apos;, a boarding house in Hongo-tatsuoka-cho.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He moved into &apos;Kamijo,&apos; a boarding house in Hongo-tatsuoka-cho.</e>
<cmt>カンマ位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>翌年3月、下宿先で火災に遭い、講義ノートなどを失う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following March, he was caught in a fire, and lost his stuff including lecture notebooks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following March, he was caught in a fire, and lost many belongings including lecture notebooks.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following March, he was caught in a fire, and lost many belongings including lecture notebooks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>1881年（明治14年・20歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty years old in 1881.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1881 he was twenty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1881 he was twenty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="226">
<j>春、肋膜炎にかかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Spring, he caught a pleurisy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Spring, he caught a pleurisy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Spring, he caught a pleurisy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>7月、東京大学医学部を卒業。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, he graduated from the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, he graduated from the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, he graduated from the University of Tokyo, Faculty of Medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>父 森静男の経営する南足立郡千住町の橘井堂医院に転居。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He moved into the Kisseido-iin (Kisseido Clinic) in Senju Town, Minamiadachi-gun County, which his father Shizuo was managing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He moved into the Kisseido-iin (Kisseido Clinic) in Senju Town, Minamiadachi-gun County, which his father Shizuo was managing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He moved into the Kisseido-iin (Kisseido Clinic) in Senju Town, Minamiadachi County, which his father Shizuo was managing.</e>
<cmt>住所表記修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>文部省広報に「東京府士族 森林太郎 十九年八ヶ月」とみえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a PR brochure of Ministry of Education, a description such as &apos;Rintaro MORI, in the warrior class of Tokyo, 19 years and 8 months&apos; was shown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He appeared In a PR brochure of Ministry of Education, described as &apos;Rintaro MORI, in the warrior class of Tokyo, 19 years and 8 months&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He appeared in a PR brochure of Ministry of Education, described as &apos;Rintaro MORI, in the warrior class of Tokyo, 19 years and 8 months.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>その後、明治政府に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he served the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he served the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he served the Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>9月、読売新聞に寄稿した「河津金線君に質す」が採用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, a work &apos;Kawazu Kinsen Kimi-ni Tadasu&apos; he sent to The Yomiuri Shimbun was accepted.</e>
<cmt>「河津金線君に質す」は、WEBで検索しましたが読み仮名がヒットしなかったので、私自身の推測によるものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, his work &apos;Kawazu Kinsen Kimi-ni Tadasu&apos; was accepted by The Yomiuri Shimbun Newspaper.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, his work &apos;Kawazu Kinsen Kimi-ni Tadasu&apos; was accepted by The Yomiuri Shimbun Newspaper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>これが鴎外の初めて公にされた文章であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This should be his first sentences Ogai exposed in the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the first piece of Ogai&apos;s writing the public saw.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the first piece of Ogai&apos;s writing the public saw.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>12月、東京陸軍病院課僚を命じられて、陸軍軍医の副の任務につく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, he was appointed as Karyo (a position name) of Tokyo Military Hospital, and assumed office as Fuku (assistant head) of Army Surgeon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, he was appointed as Karyo (a position name) of Tokyo Military Hospital, and assumed office as Fuku (assistant head) of military medicine.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, he was appointed as Karyo (a position name) of Tokyo Military Hospital, and assumed office as Fuku (assistant head) of military medicine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>1882年（明治15年・21歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-one years old in 1882.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1882 he was twenty-one.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1882 he was twenty-one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="234">
<j>- 2月、第一軍管区徴兵副医官（中尉相当）になり、従七位の勲等を授かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, he became an assistant of conscription Ikan (medical officer) of Daiichi Gunkan-ku (the first military district), and was conferred a medal for merit of Jushichii.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, he became the vice-conscription medical officer of Daiichi Gunkan-ku (the first military district), and was conferred a medal of merit of the Junior Seventh Rank.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, he became the vice-conscription medical officer of Daiichi Gunkan-ku (equivalent to lieutenant) (the first military district), and was conferred a medal of merit of the Jushichii (Junior Seventh Rank).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>5月、陸軍軍医本部課僚になり、プロシア陸軍衛生制度の調査に駆り出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, he moved on to Karyo of the Army Surgeon Headquarters, and was assigned the investigation on the Prussian army&apos;s hygiene system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, he was promoted to Karyo of the Military Medicine Headquarters, and was assigned to investigate the Prussian army&apos;s hygiene system.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, he was promoted to Karyo of the Military Medicine Headquarters, and was assigned to investigate the Prussian army&apos;s hygiene system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>1884年（明治17年・23歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-three years old in 1884.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1884 he was twenty-three.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1884 he was twenty-three.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="236">
<j>- 6月、陸軍衛生制度、衛生学研究の目的で、ドイツ留学を命じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, he was ordered to study in Germany on the Army&apos;s hygiene system and the research on hygiene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, he was ordered to study the Army&apos;s hygiene system in Germany and do general research on hygiene.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, he was ordered to study the Army&apos;s hygiene system in Germany and do general research on hygiene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>8月、横浜を出航。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, he left Yokohama Port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, he left Yokohama Port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, he left Yokohama Port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>10月、ドイツに到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, arrived at Germany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he arrived in Germany.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he arrived in Germany.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>ライプツィヒ大学でホフマン教授などに学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned from Professor Hoffmann and others at Universität Leipzig.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under Professor Hoffmann and others at Universität Leipzig.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under Professor Hoffmann and others at Universität Leipzig.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>『ビイルの利尿作用に就いて』の研究を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He began his research on &apos;the diuretic effect of beer&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He began his research on &apos;the diuretic effect of beer&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He began his research on &quot;The Diuretic Effect of Beer.&quot;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。ピリオド位置移動しました。研究タイトルを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>1885年（明治18年・24歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-four years old in 1885.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1885 he was twenty-four.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1885 he was twenty-four.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="241">
<j>1月、ハウフの童話を翻訳した『盗侠行』を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he published &apos;Thieves&apos;, a nursery story of Hauff he translated into Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he published &apos;Thieves&apos;, a nursery story by Hauff he translated into Japanese.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he published &quot;Thieves,&quot; a nursery story by Hauff he translated into Japanese.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>2月には、ドイツ語で『日本兵食論』『日本家屋論』を執筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, he wrote &apos;Nippon Heisyoku Ron (the comments on the soldier food of Japan)&apos; and &apos;Nippon Kaoku Ron (the comments on the houses of Japan)&apos; in German.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, he wrote &apos;Nippon Heisyoku Ron (discussion on army food of Japan)&apos; and &apos;Nippon Kaoku Ron (discussion on the houses of Japan)&apos; in German.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, he wrote &quot;Nippon Heishoku Ron&quot; (discussion on army food of Japan) and &quot;Nippon Kaoku Ron&quot; (discussion on the houses of Japan) in German.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>5月、陸軍一等軍医（大尉相当）に昇進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, he moved on to the Army Surgeon in the First Class of the Army (corresponding to Taijo, Captain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, he was promoted to Army Surgeon of the First Class (equivalent to Taijo, Captain).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, he was promoted to Army Surgeon of the First Class (equivalent to Taijo, Captain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>10月、ドレスデンに移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he transferred to Dresden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he transferred to Dresden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he transferred to Dresden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>1886年（明治19年・25歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-five years old in 1886.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1886 he was twenty-five.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1886 he was twenty-five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="245">
<j>3月、ミュンヘンに移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, transferred to Munich.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, transferred to Munich.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, transferred to Munich.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>大学衛生部に入学し、マックス・フォン・ペッテンコーファーに衛生学を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He enrolled in the faculty of hygienics of the university, and learned hygienics from Max von Pettenkofer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He enrolled in the faculty of hygienics of the university, and learned hygienics from Max von Pettenkofer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He enrolled in the faculty of hygienics of the university, and learned hygienics from Max von Pettenkofer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>1887年（明治20年・26歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-six years old in 1887.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1887 he was twenty-six.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1887 he was twenty-six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="247">
<j>4月、ベルリンに移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transferred to Berlin in April.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He transferred to Berlin in April.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He transferred to Berlin in April.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>5月、北里柴三郎とともにロベルト・コッホを訪ね、衛生試験所に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, he visited Robert Koch along with Shibasaburo KITASATO, and joined the hygienic laboratory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, he visited Robert Koch along with Shibasaburo KITASATO, and joined the hygiene laboratory.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, he visited Robert Koch along with Shibasaburo KITASATO, and joined the hygiene laboratory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>1888年（明治21年・27歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-seven years old in 1888.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1888 he was twenty-seven.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1888 he was twenty-seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="249">
<j>3月、プロシア近衛歩兵第二連隊の軍隊任務につく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he joined the military service in the Second Infantry Regiment of Prussian Imperial Guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he joined the military service in the Second Infantry Regiment of Prussian Imperial Guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he joined the military service in the Second Infantry Regiment of Prussian Imperial Guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>9月、日本（横浜港）に帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, arrived at Japan (Yokohama Port).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, he arrived back in Japan (Yokohama Port).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, he arrived back in Japan (Yokohama Port).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>10月、陸軍大学校教官に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he assumed office as the Instructor of Rikugun Daigakko (the Army War College).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he assumed office as the Instructor of Rikugun Daigakko (the Army War College).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he assumed office as the Instructor of Rikugun Daigakko (the Army War College).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="252">
<j>12月、『非日本食論将失其根拠』を自費出版。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, he published &quot;Theory on Non Japanese Food is about to loose the evidence&quot; at his own expense.</e>
<cmt>日本語タイトルの読み方は、「ヒ ニホンショク ロン マサニ ソノ コンキョ オ ウシナワントス」です。http://porta.ndl.go.jp/Result/R000000008/I000083833 英訳は私自身によるものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, he published &quot;How the Argument for Non-Japanese Food is losing its Support&quot; at his own expense.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, he published &quot;How the Argument for Non-Japanese Food is losing its Support&quot; at his own expense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>1889年（明治22年・28歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-eight years old in 1889.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1889 he was twenty-eight.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1889 he was twenty-eight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="253">
<j>1月東京医事新誌』を主宰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he began to issue &apos;Tokyo Iji Shinshi (Tokyo Medical Journal)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he began to issue &apos;Tokyo Iji Shinshi (Tokyo Medical Journal)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he began to issue &quot;Tokyo Iji Shinshi&quot; (Tokyo Medical Journal).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>その後、読売新聞に『医学の説より出でたる小説論』が発表され、本格的な文筆活動が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he started his professional writing career by publishing &apos;The Comments on the Novel coming out of the Theory on Medical Science&apos; in the Yomiuri Shimbun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he started his professional writing career by publishing &apos;Comments on Novels based on the Theory on Medical Science&apos; in the Yomiuri Shimbun.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he started his professional writing career by publishing &quot;Comments on Novels based on the Theory on Medical Science&quot; in the Yomiuri Shimbun.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>3月、写真婚で、海軍中将赤松則良の長女登志子と婚約。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he got engaged to Toshiko, the first daughter of the Vice Admiral Noriyoshi AKAMATSU, and they only took photos for the celebration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he got engaged to Toshiko, the first daughter of the Vice Admiral Noriyoshi AKAMATSU, however the ceremony consisted simply of taking photos.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he got engaged to Toshiko, the first daughter of the Vice Admiral Noriyoshi AKAMATSU, however the ceremony consisted simply of taking photos.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>5月、東京藝術大学専修科の美術解剖学講師に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, he assumed office as the Instructor of the artistic anatomy in the special course of Tokyo University of the Arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, he assumed office as Instructor of art analysis in the special course of Tokyo University of the Arts.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, he assumed office as Instructor of art analysis in the special course of Tokyo University of the Arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>8月、『国民之友』に訳詩編「於母影」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, he published &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos;, a book of songs, in &apos;Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, he published &apos;Omokage (Vestiges)&apos;, a book of songs, in &apos;Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, he published &apos;Omokage&apos; (Vestiges), a book of songs, in &quot;Kokumin no tomo&quot; (The Nation&apos;s Friend).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>10月、軍医学校陸軍二等軍医正（中佐相当官）教官心得になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he became an assistant instructor of the Senior Army Surgeon in the Second Class of Army Doctor School (an official corresponding to Lieutenant Colonel).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he became assistant instructor to the Senior Army Surgeon in the Second Class of the Army Doctor School (equivalent to Lieutenant Colonel).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he became assistant instructor to the Senior Army Surgeon in the Second Class of the Army Doctor School (equivalent to Lieutenant Colonel).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="30">
<tit>
<j>1890年（明治23年・29歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twenty-nine years old in 1890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1890 he was twenty-nine.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1890 he was twenty-nine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="259">
<j>1月、『医事新論』を創刊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he began to issue &apos;Iji Shinron (Medical News)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he began to issue &apos;Iji Shinron (Medical News)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he began to issue &quot;Iji Shinron&quot; (Medical News).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>『国民之友』に「舞姫」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Published &apos;Maihime (The Dancing Girl)&apos; in Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also published &apos;Maihime (The Dancing Girl)&apos; in Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also published &apos;Maihime&apos; (The Dancing Girl) in &quot;Kokumin no tomo&quot; (The Nation&apos;s Friend).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>8月、『しからみ草紙』に「うたかたの記」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, published &apos;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&apos; and &apos;Foam on the Waves&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, he published &apos;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&apos; and &apos;Foam on the Waves&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, he published &apos;Foam on the Waves&apos; in &quot;Shigarami Soshi&quot; (Constraint Brochure).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。原文に合うよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>この作品は、石橋忍月との論争の火種になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This work became an origin of a dispute with Ningetsu ISHIBASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This work became the source of a dispute with Ningetsu ISHIBASHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This work became the source of a dispute with Ningetsu ISHIBASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>9月、長男森於菟誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, his first son, Oto MORI, was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, his first son, Oto MORI, was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, his first son, Oto MORI, was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>しかし、まもなく妻登志子と離婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he divorced his wife Toshiko soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he divorced his wife Toshiko soon after.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he divorced his wife Toshiko soon after.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="265">
<j>10月、本郷駒込千駄木町57に居住を移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he relocated his residence to 57 Sendagi-cho, Komagome, Hongo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he relocated to 57 Sendagi-cho, Komagome, Hongo.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he relocated to 57 Sendagi-cho, Komagome, Hongo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>鴎外は、そこを「千朶山房」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogai called the place &apos;Sendasanbo&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogai called the place &apos;Sendasanbo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogai called the place &apos;Sendasanbo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="31">
<tit>
<j>1891年（明治24年・30歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty years old in 1891.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1891 he was thirty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1891 he was thirty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="267">
<j>1月、『文づかひ』を刊行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he issued &apos;The Courier&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he issued &apos;The Courier&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he issued &quot;The Courier.&quot;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>8月、博士 (医学)の学位を授与される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, he was gtanted the degree of Doctor (medical science).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, he was awarded the degree of Doctor (medical science).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, he was awarded the degree of Doctor (medical science).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="269">
<j>9月、『しからみ草紙』に「山房論文」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, he published &apos;Sanbo Ronbun&apos; in &quot;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, he published &apos;Sanbo Ronbun&apos; in &quot;Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, he published &apos;Sanbo Ronbun&apos; in &quot;Shigarami Soshi&quot; (Constraint Brochure).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>「早稲田文学」で坪内逍遥と没理想論争を交わす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He exchanged a dispute on &quot;anti-idealism&quot; with Shoyo TSUBOUCHI in Waseda Bungaku (Waseda Literature).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had a dispute on &quot;anti-idealism&quot; with Shoyo TSUBOUCHI in Waseda Bungaku (Waseda Literature).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had a dispute on &quot;anti-idealism&quot; with Shoyo TSUBOUCHI in Waseda Bungaku (Waseda Literature).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="32">
<tit>
<j>1892年（明治25年・31歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-one years old in 1892.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1892 he was thirty-one.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1892 he was thirty-one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="271">
<j>7月、翻訳小説集『美奈和集』（春陽堂）を刊行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, he published &apos;Minawashu&apos;, a book of translated novels, (Shunyodo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, he published &apos;Minawashu&apos;, a book of translated novels, (Shunyodo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, he published &quot;Minawashu,&quot; a book of translated novels (Shunyodo).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。カンマ削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>8月、医学と文学の論争から離れて休息を取るため、自宅（観潮楼）を建設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, he built a home (Kanchoro House) to take a rest there, away from the dispute on the medical science and literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, he built a home (Kanchoro House) to take refuge from his dispute on medical science and literature.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, he built a home (Kanchoro House) to take refuge from his dispute on medical science and literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="273">
<j>11月、『しからみ草紙』にハンス・クリスチャン・アンデルセンの「即興詩人」を連載。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, he began to put a serial piece, &apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet) &apos; of Hans Christian Andersen, in Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, he began a serial, &apos;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet) &apos; by Hans Christian Andersen, in Shigarami Soshi (Constraint Brochure).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, he began a serial, &apos;Sokkyo Shijin&apos; (Improvising Poet) by Hans Christian Andersen, in &quot;Shigarami Soshi&quot; (Constraint Brochure).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="33">
<tit>
<j>1893年（明治26年・32歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-two years old in 1893.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1893 he was thirty-two.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1893 he was thirty-two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="274">
<j>11月、陸軍一等軍医正（大佐相当）に昇進し、軍医学校長になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, he moved on to the Senior Army Surgeon of the First Class of the Army (corresponding to Colonel of the Army) to become the Principal of the Army Medical School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, he was promoted to Senior Army Surgeon, First Class (equivalent to Army Colonel) and became the Principal of the Army Medical School.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, he was promoted to Senior Army Surgeon, First Class (equivalent to Army Colonel) and became the Principal of the Army Medical School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="34">
<tit>
<j>1894年（明治27年・33歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-three years old in 1894.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1894 he was thirty-three.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1894 he was thirty-three.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="275">
<j>- 8月、日清戦争開戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, the Sino-Japanese War broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, the Sino-Japanese War broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, the Sino-Japanese War broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="276">
<j>軍医部長として清（盛京省花園口）に上陸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arrived at Qing (Kaenko, Shengjing Province) as an Army Surgeon Department Director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He arrived at Qing (Kaenko, Shengjing Province) as Department Director of MIlitary Medicine.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He arrived at Qing (Kaenko, Shengjing Province) as Department Director of Military Medicine.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="277">
<j>10月、広島大本営のある広島市で執務をし、11月大連市に上陸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he worked in Hiroshima City where the Hiroshima Imperial headquarters were, and in November, arrived at Dalian City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he worked in Hiroshima City where the Hiroshima Imperial headquarters were, and in November, arrived at Dalian City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he worked in Hiroshima City where the Hiroshima Imperial headquarters were, and in November, arrived at Dalian City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="35">
<tit>
<j>1895年（明治28年・34歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-four years old in 1895.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1895 he was thirty-four.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1895 he was thirty-four.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="278">
<j>- 5月、下関条約の調印後、帰国（帰京することなく広島市にとどまる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, he went back to Japan (stayed in Hiroshima City witout visiting his hometown) after the signature of Treaty of Shimonoseki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May after the signing of the Shimonoseki Treaty, he went back to Japan and stayed in Hiroshima City instead of visiting his hometown.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May after the signing of the Shimonoseki Treaty, he went back to Japan and stayed in Hiroshima City instead of visiting his hometown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="279">
<j>8月、台湾総督府陸軍局軍医部長になり、台湾に赴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, he became the Army Surgeon Department Director of the Military Bureau in Taiwan Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, he became the Military Medicine Department Director of the Military Bureau in Taiwan Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, he became the Military Medicine Department Director of the Military Bureau in Taiwan Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="280">
<j>9月、帰国の途につく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, he went back to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, he went back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, he went back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="36">
<tit>
<j>1896年（明治29年・35歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-five years old in 1896.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1896 he was thirty-five.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1896 he was thirty-five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="281">
<j>- 1月、『めさまし草』を創刊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he began to issue &quot;Mezamashi-gusa (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he began to issue &quot;Mezamashi-gusa (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he began to issue &quot;Mezamashi-gusa&quot; (Eye-awakening grasses) magazine.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>3月、幸田露伴、斎藤緑雨らとともに『めさまし草』に「三人冗語」を連載。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he began to put a joint review &apos;Sannin Jogo (redundant words by three people)&apos; in Mezamashi-gusa magazine along with Rohan KODA and Ryokuu SAITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he began publish joint reviews &apos;Sannin Jogo (Three men&apos;s redundant words)&apos; in Mezamashi-gusa magazine along with Rohan KODA and Ryokuu SAITO.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he began publishing joint reviews &apos;Sannin Jogo&apos; (Three men&apos;s redundant words) in &quot;Mezamashi-gusa&quot; magazine along with Rohan KODA and Ryokuu SAITO.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="283">
<j>4月、父静男死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, his father Shizuo passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, his father Shizuo passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, his father Shizuo passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="37">
<tit>
<j>1897年（明治30年・36歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-six years old in 1897.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1897 he was thirty-six.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1897 he was thirty-six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="284">
<j>1月、中浜東一郎（ジョン万次郎＝ジョン万次郎の長男）、青山胤通らとともに公衆医事会を設立、『公衆医事』を創刊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he founded the Koshu Iji (Public Medical Affairs) Society along with Toichiro NAKAHAMA (the first son of John Manjiro), Tanemichi AOYAMA and others, and began to issue &apos;Koshu Iji&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he founded the Koshu Iji (Public Medical Affairs) Society along with Toichiro NAKAHAMA (the first son of John Manjiro), Tanemichi AOYAMA and others, and began to issue &apos;Koshu Iji&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he founded the Koshu Iji (Public Medical Affairs) Society along with Toichiro NAKAHAMA (the first son of John Manjiro), Tanemichi AOYAMA and others, and began to issue &quot;Koshu Iji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="38">
<tit>
<j>1898年（明治31年・37歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-seven years old in 1898.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1898 he was thirty-seven.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1898 he was thirty-seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="285">
<j>- 10月、近衛師団軍医部長兼軍医学校長に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he assumed office as the Imperial Guard Army Surgeon Department Director as well as the Principal of the Army Doctor School concurrently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he assumed office as the Imperial Guard Military Medicine Department Director as well as the Principal of the Army Doctor School concurrently.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he assumed office as the Imperial Guard Military Medicine Department Director as well as the Principal of the Army Doctor School concurrently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="39">
<tit>
<j>1899年（明治32年・38歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty-eight years old in 1899.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IN 1899 he was thirty-eight.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1899 he was thirty-eight.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="286">
<j>6月、軍医監（少将相当）に昇任し、第12師団 (日本軍)軍医部長として福岡県の小倉に赴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, he moved on to the Surgeon Major General (corresponding to shosho (major general)) to work as the Army Surgeon Department Director of the Twelve Division in Kokura, Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, he was promoted to Surgeon Major General (equivalent to shosho (major general)) to work as the MIlitary Medicine Department Director of the Twelfth Division in Kokura, Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, he was promoted to Surgeon Major General (equivalent to shosho (major general)) to work as the Military Medicine Department Director of the Twelfth Division in Kokura, Fukuoka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="40">
<tit>
<j>1902年（明治35年・41歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourty-one years old in 1902.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1902 he was fourty-one.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1902 he was fourty-one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="287">
<j>1月、大審院判事荒木博臣の長女志げと再婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he remarried Shige, the first daughter of Hakushin ARAKI, a Justice of Daishin-in (Predecessor of the Supreme Court of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he remarried Shige, the first daughter of Hakushin ARAKI, a Judge of Daishin-in (Predecessor of the Supreme Court of Japan).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he remarried Shige, the first daughter of Hakushin ARAKI, a Judge of Daishin-in (Predecessor of the Supreme Court of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="288">
<j>3月、東京に転勤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he was transferred to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he was transferred to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he was transferred to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="41">
<tit>
<j>1903年（明治36年・42歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourty-two years old in 1903.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1903 he was fourty-two.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1903 he was fourty-two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="289">
<j>1月、長女森茉莉誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, his first daughter Mari MORI was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, his first daughter Mari MORI was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, his first daughter Mari MORI was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="42">
<tit>
<j>1904年（明治37年・43歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourty-three years old in 1904.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1904 he was fourty-three.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1904 he was fourty-three.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="290">
<j>- 2月、日露戦争開戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, the Russo-Japanese War broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, the Russo-Japanese War broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, the Russo-Japanese War broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="291">
<j>4月、第2軍 (日本軍)日露戦争における第2軍軍医部長として、広島市の宇品港をたつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, he left Ujina Port in Hiroshima City as the Army Surgeon Department Director of the Second Army in the Second Army (Japanese Army) of the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, he left Ujina Port in Hiroshima City as the Military Medicine Department Director of the Second Army of the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, he left Ujina Port in Hiroshima City as the Military Medicine Department Director of the Second Army of the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="292">
<j>『うた日記』を書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote &apos;Verse Diary &apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote &apos;A Diary in Verse&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote &quot;A Diary in Verse.&quot;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="43">
<tit>
<j>1905年（明治38年・44歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourty-four years old in 1905.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1905 he was fourty-four.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1905 he was fourty-four.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="293">
<j>奉天会戦勝利後、残留していたロシア赤十字社員の護送に尽力。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the victory in the Battle of Mukden, he contributed to the transport of the remained employees of the Russian Red Cross Society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the victory in the Battle of Mukden, he contributed to the transport of the remaining employees of the Russian Red Cross Society.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the victory in the Battle of Mukden, he contributed to the transport of the remaining employees of the Russian Red Cross Society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="294">
<j>翌年、1月帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following January, he went back to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following January, he went back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following January, he went back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="44">
<tit>
<j>1906年（明治39年・45歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourty-five years old in 1906.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1906 he was fourty-five.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1906 he was fourty-five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="295">
<j>6月、賀古鶴所らとともに歌会「常磐会」を設立（のちに山縣有朋などが参加）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, he founded &apos;Tokiwakai Society&apos;, an Uta-kai (poem competition), along with Tsuruto KAKO and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, he founded &apos;Tokiwakai Society&apos;, an Uta-kai (poem competition), along with Tsuruto KAKO and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, he founded &apos;Tokiwakai Society,&apos; an Uta-kai (poem competition), along with Tsuruto KAKO and others (Aritomo YAMAGATA and other joined later).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="45">
<tit>
<j>1907年（明治40年・46歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourty-six years old in 1907.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1907 he was fourty-six.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1907 he was fourty-six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="296">
<j>- 3月、与謝野鉄幹、伊藤左千夫、佐佐木信綱らと自宅で「観潮楼歌会」を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he held a &apos;Kanchoro Uta-kai&apos; at home inviting Tekkan YOSANO, Sachio ITO, Nobutsuna SASAKI and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he held a &apos;Kanchoro Uta-kai&apos; at home inviting Tekkan YOSANO, Sachio ITO, Nobutsuna SASAKI and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he held a &apos;Kanchoro Uta-kai&apos; at home inviting Tekkan YOSANO, Sachio ITO, Nobutsuna SASAKI and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="297">
<j>6月、西園寺公望が主催した歌会「雨声会」に出席。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, he attended &apos;Usei-kai&apos;, a Uta-kai hosted by Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, he attended &apos;Usei-kai&apos;, an Uta-kai hosted by Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, he attended &apos;Usei-kai,&apos; an Uta-kai hosted by Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="298">
<j>8月、次男不律誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, his second son, Fritz, was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, his second son, Fritz, was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, his second son, Fritz, was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="299">
<j>10月、軍医総監、陸軍省医務局となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he became an Army Surgeon General in the Medical Bureau of the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he became Army Surgeon General in the Medical Bureau of the Department of War.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he became Army Surgeon General in the Medical Bureau of the Department of War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="46">
<tit>
<j>1908年（明治41年・47歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourty-seven years old in 1908.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1908 he was fourty-seven.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1908 he was fourty-seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="300">
<j>1月、弟三木竹二死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, his younger brother Takeji MIKI passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, his younger brother Takeji MIKI passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, his younger brother Takeji MIKI passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="301">
<j>2月、次男不律死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, his second son Fritz passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, his second son Fritz passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, his second son Fritz passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="302">
<j>5月、文部省の臨時仮名遣調査委員会委員になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, he became a member of the Provisional Kana Usage Investigation Committee of the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, he became a member of the Provisional Kana Usage Investigation Committee of the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, he became a member of the Provisional Kana Usage Investigation Committee of the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="47">
<tit>
<j>1909年（明治42年・48歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourty-eight years old in 1909.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1909 he was fourty-eight.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1909 he was fourty-eight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="303">
<j>3月、『スバル (文芸雑誌)』に口語体小説「半日」を寄稿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he wrote &apos;Hannichi (Half a Day)&apos;, a spoken style novel, for &quot;Subaru (literature magazine)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he wrote &apos;Hannichi (Half a Day)&apos;, a novel in spoken style, for &quot;Subaru (a literary magazine)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he wrote &apos;Hannichi&apos; (Half a Day), a novel in spoken style, for &quot;Subaru&quot; (a literary magazine).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="304">
<j>以後、頻繁に寄稿する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he frequently wrote for the magazine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he frequently wrote for the magazine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he frequently wrote for the magazine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>5月、次女小堀杏奴誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, his second daughter, Annu KOBORI, was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, his second daughter, Annu KOBORI, was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, his second daughter, Annu KOBORI, was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="306">
<j>7月、文学博士の学位を授与され、また『ヰタ・セクスアリス』が発売禁止となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, he was granted the degree of Doctor of Literature, and also his &quot;Vita Sexualis&apos; was banned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, he was awarded the degree of Doctor of Literature, and also his work &quot;Vita Sexualis&apos; was banned.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, he was awarded the degree of Doctor of Literature, and also his work &quot;Vita Sexualis&quot; was banned.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="48">
<tit>
<j>1910年（毎時43年・49歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourty-nine years old in 1910.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1910 he was fourty-nine.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1910 he was fourty-nine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="307">
<j>- 2月、慶應義塾大学の文学科顧問になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, he became an adviser of the Faculty of Literature in Keio University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, he became an adviser of the Faculty of Literature in Keio University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, he became an adviser of the Faculty of Literature in Keio University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="49">
<tit>
<j>1911年（明治44年・50歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty years old in 1911.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1911 he was fifty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1911 he was fifty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="308">
<j>2月、三男森類誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, his third son, Rui MORI, was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, his third son, Rui MORI, was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, his third son, Rui MORI, was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>5月、文芸委員会委員になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, he became a member of the Literature Committee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, he became a member of the Literature Committee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, he became a member of the Literature Committee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>9月、『スバル』に「雁 (小説)」を連載。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, he began to put his serial novel &apos;The Wild Geese&apos; in &quot;Subaru (Sterope)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, he began to put his serial novel &apos;The Wild Geese&apos; in &quot;Subaru&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, he began to put his serial novel &apos;The Wild Geese&apos; in &quot;Subaru.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="50">
<tit>
<j>1912年（明治45年・51歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty-one years old in 1912.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1912 he was fifty-one.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1912 he was fifty-one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="311">
<j>1月、文芸委員会に頼まれていた戯曲『ファウスト』の訳を完結させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he achieved his translation of the play &quot;Faust&quot; requested by the Literature Committee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he completed his translation of the play &quot;Faust&quot; requested by the Literature Committee.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he completed his translation of the play &quot;Faust&quot; requested by the Literature Committee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="312">
<j>10月、鴎外にとって初の歴史小説「興津弥五右衛門の遺書」を『中央公論』に発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he published his first historical novel &apos;The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he published his first historical novel &apos;The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he published his first historical novel &apos;The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="51">
<tit>
<j>1913年（大正2年・52歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty-two years old in 1913.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1913 he was fifty-two.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1913 he was fifty-two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="313">
<j>- 1月、『中央公論』に「阿部一族」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he published &apos;The Abe Clan&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he published &apos;The Abe Clan&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he published &apos;The Abe Clan&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="52">
<tit>
<j>1914年（大正3年・53歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty-three years old in 1914.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1914 he was fifty-three.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1914 he was fifty-three.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="314">
<j>- 1月、『中央公論』に「大塩平八郎」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he published &apos;Heihachiro OSHIO&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he published &apos;Heihachiro OSHIO&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he published &apos;Heihachiro OSHIO&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="315">
<j>2月、『新小説』に「堺事件」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, he published &apos;Sakai Incident&apos; in &quot;Shinshosetsu (New Novel)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, he published &apos;Sakai Incident&apos; in &quot;Shinshosetsu (New Novels)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, he published &apos;Sakai Incident&apos; in &quot;Shinshosetsu&quot; (New Novels).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="53">
<tit>
<j>1915年（大正4年・54歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty-four years old in 1915.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1915 he was fifty-four.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1915 he was fifty-four.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="316">
<j>- 1月、『中央公論』に「山椒大夫」を、『心の花』に「歴史其儘と歴史離れ」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he published &apos;Sanshodayu&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, and &apos;Rekishi Sonomama to Rekishi Banare (History As It Is and History Abandoned)&apos; in &quot;Kokoro no Hana (Flower in heart)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he published &apos;Sanshodayu&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, and &apos;Rekishi Sonomama to Rekishi Banare (History As It Is and History Abandoned)&apos; in &quot;Kokoro no Hana (Flower in heart)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he published &apos;Sanshodayu&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; and &apos;Rekishi Sonomama to Rekishi Banare&apos; (History As It Is and History Abandoned) in &quot;Kokoro no Hana&quot; (Flower in heart).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="317">
<j>11月、大嶋陸軍省陸軍次官に辞意を表明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, he announced his resignation to Oshima Vice-Minister of the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, he announced his resignation to Oshima, Vice-Minister of the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, he announced his resignation to Oshima, Vice-Minister of the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="318">
<j>同年、渋江抽斎の調査研究を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he began an investigative research of Chusai SHIBUE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he began investigative research on Chusai SHIBUE.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he began investigative research on Chusai SHIBUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="54">
<tit>
<j>1916年（大正5年・55歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty-five years old in 1916.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1916 he was fifty-five.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1916 he was fifty-five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="319">
<j>- 1月、『中央公論』に「高瀬舟 (小説)」を、『新小説』に「寒山拾得」を発表。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he published &apos;Takasebune (The Boat on the River Takase)&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, and &apos;Kanzan Jittoku&apos; in &quot;Shinshosetsu (New Novel)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he published &apos;Takasebune (The Boat on the River Takase)&apos; in &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, and &apos;Kanzan Jittoku&apos; in &quot;Shinshosetsu (New Novels)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he published &apos;Takasebune&apos; (The Boat on the River Takase) in &quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; and &apos;Kanzan Jittoku&apos; in &quot;Shinshosetsu&quot; (New Novels).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="320">
<j>東京日日新聞と大阪毎日新聞に「渋江抽斎」を連載。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He began to put a serial piece, &apos;Chusai SHIBUE&apos; in Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper and Osaka Mainichi Shimbun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He began to write a serial piece, &apos;Chusai SHIBUE&apos; for the Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper and Osaka Mainichi Shimbun.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He began to write a serial piece, &apos;Chusai SHIBUE&apos; for the Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper and Osaka Mainichi Shimbun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="321">
<j>3月、母峰子死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, his mother Mineko passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, his mother Mineko passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, his mother Mineko passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="55">
<tit>
<j>1917年（大正6年・56歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty-six years old in 1917.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1917 he was fifty-six.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1917 he was fifty-six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="322">
<j>12月、帝室博物館総長に就任し、高等官一等に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, he assumed office as the Director General of the Imperial Museum, and was granted the Senior Official in the First Class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, he assumed office of Director General of the Imperial Museum, and was granted title of Senior Official, First Class.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, he assumed office of Director General of the Imperial Museum, and was granted title of Senior Official, First Class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="56">
<tit>
<j>1918年（大正7年・57歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty-seven years old in 1918.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1918 he was fifty-seven.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1918 he was fifty-seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="323">
<j>- 11月、正倉院宝庫開封に立ち会うため奈良に一時滞在。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, he made a short stay in Nara to see the unsealing of Shoso-in Treasure House.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, he made a short stay in Nara to see the unsealing of Shoso-in Treasure House.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, he made a short stay in Nara to see the unsealing of Shoso-in Treasure House.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="324">
<j>以後1921年まで毎秋、奈良を訪れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that until 1921, he visited Nara every Autumn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that until 1921, he visited Nara every Autumn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that until 1921, he visited Nara every Autumn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="57">
<tit>
<j>1919年（大正8年・58歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty-eight years old in 1919.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919 he was fifty-eight.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1919 he was fifty-eight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="325">
<j>- 9月、日本芸術院の初代院長に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, he assumed office as the First Principal of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, he assumed the office of First Principal of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, he assumed the office of First Principal of the Japan Art Academy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="58">
<tit>
<j>1920年（大正9年・59歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifty-nine years old in 1920.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1920 he was fifty-nine.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1920 he was fifty-nine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="326">
<j>- 1月、腎臓を病む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, he had kidney trouble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, he suffered from kidney trouble.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, he suffered from kidney trouble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="59">
<tit>
<j>1921年（大正10年・60歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sixty years old in 1921.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1921 he was sixty.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1921 he was sixty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="327">
<j>6月、臨時国語調査会長に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, he assumed office as the Chairman of the Rinji Kokugo Chosakai (Extraordinary Investigation Committees on the Japanese Language).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, he assumed office as Chairman of the Rinji Kokugo Chosakai (Special Investigation Committee on the Japanese Language).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, he assumed office as Chairman of the Rinji Kokugo Chosakai (Special Investigation Committee on the Japanese Language).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="328">
<j>秋、足に浮腫が出来はじめるなど、腎臓病の兆候が見られ始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Autumn, the first sign of renal disease such as edema on feet began to appear on him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Autumn, he began to show the first signs of renal disease such as swollen feet.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Autumn, he began to show the first signs of renal disease such as swollen feet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="60">
<tit>
<j>1922年（大正11年・61歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sixty-one years old in 1922.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1922 he was sixty-one.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1922 he was sixty-one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="329">
<j>- 4月、イギリス皇太子の正倉院参観に合わせ、奈良へ5度目の旅行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, he made a fifth trip to Nara, fitting his schedule to Prince of England&apos;s visit to Shosoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, he made a fifth trip to Nara, fitting his schedule around the Prince of England&apos;s visit to Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, he made a fifth trip to Nara, fitting his schedule around the Prince of England&apos;s visit to Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="330">
<j>途中、いくどか病臥する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the time, he got ill in bed sometimes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his trip he was confined to his bed several times due to illness.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his trip he was confined to his bed several times due to illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="331">
<j>6月29日、萎縮腎と診断される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 29, he was diagnosed as atrophic kidney.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 29, he was diagnosed with an atrophic kidney.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 29, he was diagnosed with an atrophic kidney.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="332">
<j>また、肺結核の兆候も見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sign of pulmonary tuberculosis also appeared on him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also showed signs of pulmonary tuberculosis.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also showed signs of pulmonary tuberculosis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="333">
<j>7月6日、友人の賀古鶴所に遺言の代筆を頼む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 6, he asked a friend Tsuruto KAKO to write down his will for him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 6, he asked a friend Tsuruto KAKO to write down his will for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 6, he asked a friend Tsuruto KAKO to write down his will for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="334">
<j>7月9日、午前7時死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 9, he passed away at 7 in the morning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 9, he passed away at 7 in the morning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 9, he passed away at 7 in the morning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="335">
<j>向島弘福寺に埋葬される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His ashes were buried at Gufuku-ji Temple, Mukojima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His ashes were buried at Gufuku-ji Temple, Mukojima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His ashes were buried at Gufuku-ji Temple, Mukojima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="61">
<tit>
<j>1927年（昭和2年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1927.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1927</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1927</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="336">
<j>- 墓が三鷹市禅林寺に移される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave was transferred to Zenrin-ji Temple, Mitaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave was transferred to Zenrin-ji Temple, Mitaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave was transferred to Zenrin-ji Temple, Mitaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="337">
<j>分骨され津和野町永明寺にも墓がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of his ashes was buried in another grave at Yomei-ji Temple, Tsuwano-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of his ashes were buried in another grave at Yomei-ji Temple, Tsuwano-cho.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of his ashes were buried in another grave at Yomei-ji Temple, Tsuwano-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="62">
<tit>
<j>主な作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His principal masterpieces</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His principal works</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His principal works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="63">
<tit>
<j>小説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Novels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="338">
<j>舞姫 （『国民之友』、1890年1月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maihime (The Dancing Girl) (&quot;Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend)&quot;), January 1890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maihime (The Dancing Girl) (&quot;Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend)&quot;), January 1890.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maihime (The Dancing Girl) (&quot;Kokumin no tomo&quot; (The Nation&apos;s Friend)), January 1890.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="339">
<j>うたかたの記 （『国民之友』、1890年8月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foam on the Waves (&quot;Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend)&quot;, August 1890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Foam on the Waves (&quot;Kokumin no tomo (The Nation&apos;s Friend)&quot;, August 1890.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Foam on the Waves (&quot;Kokumin no tomo&quot; (The Nation&apos;s Friend), August 1890.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="340">
<j>文づかひ （吉岡書店、1891年1月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Courier (Yoshioka Shoten Publishing, January 1891).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Courier (Yoshioka Shoten Publishing, January 1891).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Courier (Yoshioka Shoten Publishing, January 1891).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="341">
<j>半日 （『スバル』、1909年3月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hannichi (Half a Day) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, March 1909).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hannichi (Half a Day) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, March 1909).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hannichi (Half a Day) (&quot;Subaru,&quot; March 1909).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="342">
<j>魔睡 （『スバル』、1909年6月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masui (Enchanted Sleep) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, June 1909).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masui (Enchanted Sleep) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, June 1909).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masui (Enchanted Sleep) (&quot;Subaru,&quot; June 1909).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="343">
<j>ヰタ・セクスアリス （『スバル』、1909年7月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vita Sexualis (&quot;Subaru&quot;, July 1909).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vita Sexualis (&quot;Subaru&quot;, July 1909).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vita Sexualis (&quot;Subaru,&quot; July 1909).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="344">
<j>鶏 （『スバル』、1909年8月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Niwatori (The Chicken) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, August 1909).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Niwatori (The Chicken) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, August 1909).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Niwatori (The Chicken) (&quot;Subaru,&quot; August 1909).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="345">
<j>金貨 （『スバル』、1909年9月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gold Coin (&quot;Subaru&quot;, September 1909).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gold Coin (&quot;Subaru&quot;, September 1909).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gold Coin (&quot;Subaru,&quot; September 1909).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="346">
<j>杯 （『中央公論』、1910年1月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakazuki (Cups) (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1910).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakazuki (Cups) (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1910).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakazuki (Cups) (&quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; January 1910).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="347">
<j>青年 (小説) （『スバル』、1910年3月 - 11年8月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seinen (Youth) (Novel) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, March 1910 - August 1911).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seinen (Youth) (Novel) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, March 1910 - August 1911).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seinen (Youth) (Novel) (&quot;Subaru,&quot; March 1910 - August 1911).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="348">
<j>普請中 （『三田文学』、1910年6月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushinchu (Under Reconstruction) (&quot;Mita Bungaku (literary magazine)&quot;, June 1910).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushinchu (Under Reconstruction) (&quot;Mita Bungaku (literary magazine)&quot;, June 1910).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushinchu (Under Reconstruction) (&quot;Mita Bungaku (literary magazine),&quot; June 1910).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="349">
<j>花子 （『三田文学』、1910年7月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanako (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, July 1910).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanako (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, July 1910).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanako (&quot;Mita Bungaku,&quot; July 1910).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="350">
<j>あそび （『三田文学』、1910年8月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asobi (Play) (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, August 1910).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asobi (Play) (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, August 1910).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asobi (Play) (&quot;Mita Bungaku,&quot; August 1910).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="351">
<j>食堂 （『三田文学』、1910年12月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jikido (dining hall) (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, December 1910).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jikido (dining hall) (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, December 1910).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jikido (dining hall) (&quot;Mita Bungaku,&quot; December 1910).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="352">
<j>蛇 （『中央公論』、1911年1月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hebi (Snake) (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1911).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hebi (Snake) (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1911).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hebi (Snake) (&quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; January 1911).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="353">
<j>妄想 （『三田文学』、1911年4月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moso (Delushion) (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, April 1911).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moso (Delusion) (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, April 1911).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moso (Delusion) (&quot;Mita Bungaku,&quot; April 1911).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="354">
<j>雁 (小説) （『スバル』、1911年9月 - 1913年5月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Wild Geese (novel) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, September 1911 - May 1913).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Wild Geese (novel) (&quot;Subaru&quot;, September 1911 - May 1913).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Wild Geese (novel) (&quot;Subaru,&quot; September 1911 - May 1913).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="355">
<j>灰燼 （『三田文学』、1911年10月 - 1912年12月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaijin (Ashes of Destruction) (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, October 1911 - December 1912).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaijin (Ashes of Destruction) (&quot;Mita Bungaku&quot;, October 1911 - December 1912).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaijin (Ashes of Destruction) (&quot;Mita Bungaku,&quot; October 1911 - December 1912).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="356">
<j>百物語 （『中央公論』、1911年10月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakumonogatari (rougly &quot;100 Stories&quot;) (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, October 1911).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakumonogatari (100 Stories) (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, October 1911).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakumonogatari (100 Stories) (&quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; October 1911).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="357">
<j>かのように （『中央公論』、1912年1月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanoyoni (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1912).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanoyoni (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1912).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanoyoni (&quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; January 1912).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="358">
<j>興津弥五右衛門の遺書 （1912年10月、『中央公論』）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon (October 1912, &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon (October 1912, &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Last Testament of Okitsu Yagoemon (October 1912, &quot;the Chuo koron&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="359">
<j>阿部一族 （『中央公論』、1913年1月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Abe Clan (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1913).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Abe Clan (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1913).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Abe Clan (&quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; January 1913).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="360">
<j>大塩平八郎 （『中央公論』、1914年1月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heihachiro OSHIO (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1914).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heihachiro OSHIO (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1914).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heihachiro OSHIO (&quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; January 1914).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="361">
<j>堺事件 （『新小説』、1914年2月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai Incident (&quot;Shinshosetsu (New Novel)&quot;, February 1914).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai Incident (&quot;Shinshosetsu (New Novels)&quot;, February 1914).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai Incident (&quot;Shinshosetsu&quot; (New Novels), February 1914).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="362">
<j>安井夫人 （『太陽』、1914年4月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasui fujin (The Wife of Yasui) (&quot;Taiyo (Sun)&quot;, April 1914).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasui fujin (The Wife of Yasui) (&quot;Taiyo (Sun)&quot;, April 1914).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasui fujin (The Wife of Yasui) (&quot;Taiyo (Sun),&quot; April 1914).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="363">
<j>山椒大夫 （『中央公論』、1915年11月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanshodayu (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, November 1915).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanshodayu (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, November 1915).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanshodayu (&quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; November 1915).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="364">
<j>じいさんばあさん （『新小説』、1915年9月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jisan Basan (Grandpa and Grandma) (&quot;Shinshosetsu&quot;, September 1915).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jisan Basan (Grandpa and Grandma) (&quot;Shinshosetsu&quot;, September 1915).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jisan Basan (Grandpa and Grandma) (&quot;Shinshosetsu,&quot; September 1915).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="365">
<j>高瀬舟 (小説) （『中央公論』、1916年1月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasebune (The Boat on the River Takase) (Novel) (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1916).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasebune (The Boat on the River Takase) (Novel) (&quot;the Chuo koron&quot;, January 1916).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasebune (The Boat on the River Takase) (Novel) (&quot;the Chuo koron,&quot; January 1916).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="366">
<j>寒山拾得 （『新小説』、1916年1月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanzan Jittoku (&quot;Shinshosetsu&quot;, January 1916).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanzan Jittoku (&quot;Shinshosetsu&quot;, January 1916).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanzan Jittoku (&quot;Shinshosetsu,&quot; January 1916).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="367">
<j>戯曲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Play</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plays</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="368">
<j>生田川 (戯曲)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikuta-gawa River (play)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikuta-gawa River (play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikuta-gawa River (play)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="64">
<tit>
<j>翻訳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Translation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Translations</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Translations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="369">
<j>カルデロン・デ・ラ・バルカ『調高矣津弦一曲』、1889年。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;El Alcalde de Zalamea, (The Mayor of Zalamea)&quot; by Calderón de la Barca, 1889.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;El Alcalde de Zalamea, (The Mayor of Zalamea)&quot; by Calderón de la Barca, 1889.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;El Alcalde de Zalamea&quot; (The Mayor of Zalamea) by Calderón de la Barca, 1889.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="370">
<j>※三木竹二との共訳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*Joint translation with Takeji MIKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">*Joint translation with Takeji MIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">*Joint translation with Takeji MIKI</e>
<cmt>全角削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="371">
<j>『於母影』 （新声社訳『国民之友』夏期付録、1889年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omokage (Vestiges) (summer appendix of &quot;Kokumin no tomo&quot;, translated by Shinseisya, 1889).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omokage (Vestiges) (summer appendix of &quot;Kokumin no tomo&quot;, translated by Shinseisya, 1889).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Omokage&quot; (Vestiges) (summer appendix of &quot;Kokumin no tomo,&quot; translated by Shinseisha, 1889).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="372">
<j>ハンス・クリスチャン・アンデルセン『即興詩人』 （『しからみ草紙』1892年11月 から掲載され、『めさまし草』1901年2月完）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&quot; by Hans Christian Andersen (began to appear in &quot;Shigarami Soshi Magazine&quot; in November 1892 and ended in &quot;Mezamashi-gusa Magazine&quot; in February 1901).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sokkyo Shijin (Improvising Poet)&quot; by Hans Christian Andersen (began to appear in &quot;Shigarami Soshi Magazine&quot; in November 1892 and ended in &quot;Mezamashi-gusa Magazine&quot; in February 1901).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sokkyo Shijin&quot; (Improvising Poet) by Hans Christian Andersen (began to appear in &quot;Shigarami Soshi Magazine&quot; in November 1892 and ended in &quot;Mezamashi-gusa Magazine&quot; in February 1901).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="373">
<j>ヨハン・ヴォルフガング・フォン・ゲーテ『ファウスト』 （第一部：1913年1月、第二部：3月、冨山房）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Faust&quot; by Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (Part 1 : January 1913, Part 2 : March, Fuzanbo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Faust&quot; by Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (Part 1 : January 1913, Part 2 : March, Fuzanbo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Faust&quot; by Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (Part 1: January 1913, Part 2: March, Fuzanbo)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="374">
<j>『サロメ (戯曲)』 オスカー・ワイルド</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Salome (play)&quot; by Oscar Wilde.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Salome (play)&quot; by Oscar Wilde.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Salome (play)&quot; by Oscar Wilde</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="65">
<tit>
<j>史伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical Biographies</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical Biographies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="375">
<j>渋江抽斎 （東京日日新聞・大阪毎日新聞、1916年1月 - 5月）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chusai SHIBUE (Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper, Osaka Mainichi Shimbun, January - May 1916).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chusai SHIBUE (Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper, Osaka Mainichi Shimbun, January - May 1916).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chusai SHIBUE (Tokyo Nichinichi Newspaper, Osaka Mainichi Shimbun, January - May 1916).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="376">
<j>伊沢蘭軒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranken IZAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranken IZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranken IZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="377">
<j>北条霞亭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katei HOJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katei HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katei HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="378">
<j>続篇として『狩谷棭斎』を執筆する予定だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He planed to write &quot;Ekisai KARIYA&quot; as a sequel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He planed to write &quot;Ekisai KARIYA&quot; as a sequel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He planed to write &quot;Ekisai KARIYA&quot; as a sequel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="66">
<tit>
<j>家族 親族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="379">
<j>妻子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wife and children</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wife and children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wife and children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="380">
<j>先妻 登志子（海軍中将赤松則良娘）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His ex-wife Toshiko (a daughter of Vice Admiral, Noriyoshi AKAMATSU).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His ex-wife Toshiko (daughter of Vice Admiral Noriyoshi AKAMATSU).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His ex-wife Toshiko (daughter of Vice Admiral Noriyoshi AKAMATSU).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="381">
<j>長男 森於菟（おっと、医学者、台北帝国大学医学部教授などを歴任）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first son Oto MORI (A Medical Scientist, successively worked in differenct positions such as a professor of Faculty of Medicine, Taipei Imperial University).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first son Oto MORI (A Medical Scientist, who successively worked in differenct positions such as a professor of Faculty of Medicine, Taipei Imperial University).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first son Oto MORI (A Medical Scientist, who successively worked in different positions such as a professor of Faculty of Medicine, Taipei Imperial University).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="382">
<j>後妻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second wife</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second wife</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second wife</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="383">
<j>- 森志け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shige MORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shige MORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shige MORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="384">
<j>小説「波瀾」を著しており（『樋口一葉・明治女流文学・泉鏡花集』現代日本文学大系5、筑摩書房、1972年）、義妹の小金井喜美子とともに雑誌『青鞜』の賛助員になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She wrote &quot;Haran (disturbance)&quot; (The Collection of Kyoka IZUMI, The Meiji Female Literature, Ichiyo HIGUCHI&quot; Modern Japanese Literary System 5, Chikuma Shobo Publishers, 1972), and became a supporting member of Magazine &quot;Seito&quot; along with her sister-in-law Kimiko KOGANEI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She wrote &quot;Haran (disturbance)&quot; (The Collection of Kyoka IZUMI, The Meiji Female Literature, Ichiyo HIGUCHI&quot; Modern Japanese Literary System 5, Chikuma Shobo Publishers, 1972), and became a supporting member of Magazine &quot;Seito&quot; along with her sister-in-law Kimiko KOGANEI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She wrote &apos;Haran&apos; (disturbance) (&quot;The Collection of Kyoka IZUMI, The Meiji Female Literature, Ichiyo HIGUCHI&quot; Modern Japanese Literary System 5, Chikuma Shobo Publishers, 1972), and became a supporting member of Magazine &quot;Seito&quot; along with her sister-in-law Kimiko KOGANEI.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="385">
<j>長女 森茉莉（まり、随筆家・小説家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first daughter, Mari MORI (Essayist, Novelist)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first daughter, Mari MORI (Essayist, Novelist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first daughter, Mari MORI (Essayist, Novelist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="386">
<j>次女 小堀杏奴（あんぬ、随筆家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second daughter, Annu KOBORI (Essayist)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second daughter, Annu KOBORI (Essayist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second daughter, Annu KOBORI (Essayist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="387">
<j>次男 不律（ふりっつ、夭折)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second son, Fritz (premature death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second son, Fritz (died prematurely)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second son, Fritz (died prematurely)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="388">
<j>三男 森類（るい、随筆家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His third son, Rui MORI (Essayist)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His third son, Rui MORI (Essayist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His third son, Rui MORI (Essayist)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="389">
<j>4人の子供はいずれも鴎外について著作を残しており、とりわけ茉莉（国語教科書に載った『父の帽子』）と杏奴（『晩年の父』）が有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of these four children left some literary work on Ogai, particularly, Mari&apos;s (&quot;My Father&apos;s Hat&quot; put in a Japanese text book) and Annu&apos;s (&quot;Bannen-no Chichi (My father in his last years)&quot; are well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of these four children wrote literary works on Ogai, in particular, Mari&apos;s (&quot;My Father&apos;s Hat&quot; published in a Japanese text book) and Annu&apos;s (&quot;Bannen-no Chichi (My father in his last years)&quot; are well known.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of these four children wrote literary works on Ogai, in particular, Mari&apos;s (&quot;My Father&apos;s Hat&quot; published in a Japanese text book) and Annu&apos;s (&quot;Bannen-no Chichi&quot; (My father in his last years) are well known.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="390">
<j>弟妹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brother and sister</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother and sister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother and sister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="391">
<j>弟 森篤次郎（三木竹二）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brother, Tokujiro MORI (Takeji MIKI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother, Tokujiro MORI (Takeji MIKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother, Tokujiro MORI (Takeji MIKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="392">
<j>明治期を代表する劇評家で、内科医。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A critic of play representing Meiji Period as well as a physician.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A representative play critic of the Meiji Period as well as a physician.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A representative play critic of the Meiji period as well as a physician.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="393">
<j>演劇雑誌『歌舞伎』を主宰し、歌舞伎批評に客観的な基準を確立した（三木竹二『観劇偶評』、渡辺保編、岩波文庫、2004年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He edited a play magazine &quot;Kabuki&quot;, and built a subjective standard in the field of criticism of Kabuki (&quot;Kangeki Guhyo (Reviews on theater play)&quot; written by Takeji MIKI, edited by Tamotsu WATANABE, published by Iwanami bunko, 2004)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He edited a play magazine &quot;Kabuki&quot;, and established the subjective standard in the field of Kabuki criticism (&quot;Kangeki Guhyo (Reviews on theater play)&quot; written by Takeji MIKI, edited by Tamotsu WATANABE, published by Iwanami bunko, 2004)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He edited a play magazine &quot;Kabuki,&quot; and established the subjective standard in the field of Kabuki criticism (&quot;Kangeki Guhyo&quot; (Reviews on theater play) written by Takeji MIKI, edited by Tamotsu WATANABE, published by Iwanami bunko, 2004).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="394">
<j>妹 小金井喜美子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger sister, Kimiko KOGANEI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger sister, Kimiko KOGANEI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger sister, Kimiko KOGANEI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="395">
<j>明治期に若松賤子と並び称された翻訳家で、また随筆家・歌人でもあった（『鴎外の思い出』岩波文庫、1999年。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A translator who ranked with Shizuko WAKAMATSU in Meiji Period, an essayist and a poet (&quot;Ogai no Omoide (My memory for Ogai)&quot; published by Iwanami bunko, 1999.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A translator who ranked with Shizuko WAKAMATSU in Meiji Period, an essayist and a poet (&quot;Ogai no Omoide (My memory for Ogai)&quot; published by Iwanami bunko, 1999.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A translator who ranked with Shizuko WAKAMATSU in Meiji period, an essayist and a poet (&quot;Ogai no Omoide&quot; (My memory for Ogai) published by Iwanami bunko, 1999.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="396">
<j>『森鴎外の系族』岩波文庫、2001年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Mori Ogai no Keizoku (Ogai MORI&apos;s descendants)&quot; published by Iwanami bunko, 2001).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Mori Ogai no Keizoku (Ogai MORI&apos;s descendants)&quot; published by Iwanami bunko, 2001).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Mori Ogai no Keizoku&quot; (Ogai MORI&apos;s descendants) published by Iwanami bunko, 2001).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="397">
<j>義弟 小金井良精</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brother-in-law, Yoshikiyo KOGANEI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother-in-law, Yoshikiyo KOGANEI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother-in-law, Yoshikiyo KOGANEI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="398">
<j>喜美子の夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Husband of Kimiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Husband of Kimiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Husband of Kimiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="399">
<j>初期の文部省派遣留学生（鴎外の前年にドイツ留学）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An overseas student under Ministry of Education in the early years (he went to Germany for his study in the previous year of Ogai&apos;s).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an one of the first overseas student under the Ministry of Education (he went to Germany to study the year before Ogai).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the first overseas student under the Ministry of Education (he went to Germany to study the year before Ogai).</e>
<cmt>余計な単語を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="400">
<j>24歳で帰国し、27歳のとき高給の外国人教師に代わって東京帝国大学医学部教授に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came back to Japan at 24, and at the age of 27, he assumed office as the professor of Faculty of Medicine, Tokyo Imperial University, replacing an foreign professor who was drawing a high salary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came back to Japan at 24, and at the age of 27, he assumed office as professor of the Faculty of Medicine, Tokyo Imperial University, replacing a foreign professor who was earning a high salary.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came back to Japan at 24, and at the age of 27, he assumed office as professor of the Faculty of Medicine, Tokyo Imperial University, replacing a foreign professor who was earning a high salary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="401">
<j>小金井夫妻の孫の一人が小説家の星新一。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the grandchildren of Mr. and Mrs. Koganei was Shinichi HOSHI, a novelist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the grandchildren of Mr. and Mrs. Koganei was the novelist Shinichi HOSHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the grandchildren of Mr. and Mrs. Koganei was the novelist Shinichi HOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="402">
<j>傍系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collateral line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extended family</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extended family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="403">
<j>西周 (啓蒙家)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amane NISHI (keimoka (illuminator))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amane NISHI (keimoka (Member of the Enlightenment movement))</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amane NISHI (keimoka (Member of the Enlightenment movement))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="404">
<j>鴎外の曾祖父の次男、森覚馬が西家を継いで生まれた子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second son of Ogai&apos;s great-grandfather, a child who was born to the NISHI Family which was succeeded by Kakuma MORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second son of Ogai&apos;s great-grandfather, born to the NISHI Family which was succeeded by Kakuma MORI.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second son of Ogai&apos;s great-grandfather, born to the Nishi family which was succeeded by Kakuma MORI.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="405">
<j>幕末明治維新の西洋法学者・啓蒙家で、貴族院 (日本)や元老院議官などの要職を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A western law scholar as well as an illuminator in the Meiji restoration in the end of Edo Period, and he successively worked in different positions such as an important post in the house of peers (Japan) and a councilor of the senate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a western law scholar as well as being part of Enlightenment movement in the Meiji restoration in the end of Edo Period, and he successively worked in different positions such as an important post in the house of peers and as councilor of the senate.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a western law scholar as well as being part of Enlightenment movement in the Meiji restoration in the end of Edo period, and he successively worked in different positions such as an important post in the house of peers and as councilor of the senate.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="406">
<j>上京後の一時期、鴎外少年は、西周邸から進文学社に通学した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Young Ogai who had just settled down in Tokyo went to Shinbungakusha school from Amane NISHI&apos;s home where he lodged for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Young Ogai, having just settled down in Tokyo, lodged for a while at Amane NISHI&apos;s home whilst commuting to Shinbungakusha school.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Young Ogai, having just settled down in Tokyo, lodged for a while at Amane NISHI&apos;s home whilst commuting to Shinbungakusha school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="67">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family tree</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family tree</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family tree</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="407">
<j>森氏 典医としての森家は慶安年間から明治2年の版籍奉還に及ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mori Family as the Mori Clan which had been serving as doctor for generations continued from Keian Era to the time of the return of lands and people to the emperor in 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mori Clan which had been serving as doctors for generations, carried on from the Keian Era until 1869 when the lands and people were returned to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mori clan which had been serving as doctors for generations, carried on from the Keian era until 1869 when the lands and people were returned to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="68">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="408">
<j>常日頃、文人の自分と武人のそれを厳格に分けて考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He always strictly separated his two personalities such as a man of literatue and a warrior when he was conscious of himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He always separated his thoughts into two personalities: those of a man of literature and those of a warrior.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He always separated his thoughts into two personalities: those of a man of literature and those of a warrior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="409">
<j>あるとき文壇の親しい友人が軍服を着て停車場にいた森に何気なく話しかけたら、その友人を怒鳴りつけたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, a familiar friend from the literary world unconsciously talked to Mori who was standing at a stop in military uniform, then he got upset and shouted at the friend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once, when Mori was standing at a station wearing military uniform, a close friend from the literary world casually started talking to him, making Mori get upset and shout at him.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once, when Mori was standing at a station wearing military uniform, a close friend from the literary world casually started talking to him, making Mori get upset and shout at him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="410">
<j>軍人としての誇りが高く、娘と散歩する時にも必ず軍服に着替えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was so proud of being a military man that he put on his uniform whenever he took a walk with his daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was so proud of being a military man that he put on his uniform whenever he took a walk with his daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was so proud of being a military man that he put on his uniform whenever he took a walk with his daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="411">
<j>あるとき杏奴と散歩をしていると、「わー中将が歩いているぞ」と子供たちがバラバラと駆け寄ってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, when he was taking a walk with Annu, children ran to them, shouting &apos;Here comes a lieutenant general&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, when he was taking a walk with Annu, children ran up to them, shouting &apos;Here comes a lieutenant general&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, when he was taking a walk with Annu, children ran up to them, shouting &apos;Here comes a lieutenant general.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="412">
<j>日露戦争後で、軍人が子供たちのヒーローであったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Russo-Japanese War had just been over, so a military man was children&apos;s hero.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Russo-Japanese War had just ended, so military men were children&apos;s heros.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Russo-Japanese War had just ended, so military men were children&apos;s heroes.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="413">
<j>得意満面の鴎外を、あこがれの目で見つめていた子供たちの一人が、襟の深緑色を見て、「おい、なんだ、軍医だよ」と声をあげると、「なーんだ、軍医かあ」と言いながら子供たちは散ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, one of the children staring Ogai&apos;s face in full of satisfaction noticed his dark green badge on the collar and shouted, &apos;Oh, no, he is an army surgeon.&apos;, then the other children shouted &apos;Oh, boy, he&apos;s just an army surgeon.&apos;, and ran away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, one of the children, seeing Ogai&apos;s self-satisfied expression, noticed the dark green badge on hus collar and shouted, &apos;What&apos;s that? He&apos;s just an army surgeon,&apos; then the other children shouted &apos;Ooh, he&apos;s just an army surgeon.&apos;, and ran away.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, one of the children, seeing Ogai&apos;s self-satisfied expression, noticed the dark green badge on his collar and shouted, &apos;What&apos;s that? He&apos;s just an army surgeon,&apos; then the other children shouted &apos;Ooh, he&apos;s just an army surgeon,&apos; and ran away.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="414">
<j>あとには呆然として立ち尽くす父娘が残され、がっかりとした鴎外は帰宅するまで、一言もしゃべらなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stunned, the father and daughter were left behind alone, and Ogai, so disappointed, is told to not have said even a word on the way home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stunned, the father and daughter were left alone, and it is said Ogai was so upset he didn&apos;t say a word on the way home.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stunned, the father and daughter were left alone, and it is said Ogai was so upset he didn&apos;t say a word on the way home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="415">
<j>1892年に東京都文京区へ建設し、晩年まで過ごした住居「観潮楼」跡地に、文京区立本郷図書館鴎外記念室がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the site in Bunkyo-ku Ward where &quot;Kanchoro House&quot;, a residence which Ogai built in 1892 and lived in until his later years, used to be, there is now the Ogai Memorial Hall in Hongo Public Library belonging to Bunkyo-ku Ward.</e>
<cmt>web上の記載を参照したところ、「本郷図書館鴎外記念室」という文言が抜けていましたので、オリジナルに挿入し、英訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the old site of &quot;Kanchoro House&quot; in Bunkyo-ku Ward, a residence which Ogai built in 1892 and lived in until his later years, there now stands the Ogai Memorial Hall and Hongo Public Library.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the old site of &apos;Kanchoro House&apos; in Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo, a residence which Ogai built in 1892 and lived in until his later years, there now stands the Ogai Memorial Hall and Hongo Public Library.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。記号を修正しました。用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="416">
<j>細菌学を究めて以来、ルイ・パスツール同様潔癖症になってしまい、どんな食べ物も加熱しないと食べられなくなってしまったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he had mastered the bacteriology, Ogai was obsessed with being clean just like Louis PASTEUR, and he came to be unable to eat anything not heated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having mastered bacteriology, Ogai was obsessed with being clean just like Louis PASTEUR, and he came to be unable to eat anything not cooked.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having mastered bacteriology, Ogai was obsessed with being clean just like Louis PASTEUR, and he came to be unable to eat anything not cooked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="417">
<j>その一方で、風呂嫌いでもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he hated taking a bath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he hated bathing.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he hated bathing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="418">
<j>大の甘党でもあり、娘（茉莉・杏奴）の著書によると饅頭を茶漬けにして食べていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a sweet tooth, and according to his daughters&apos; (Mari and Annu) books, he ate Manju (a bun stuffed with azuki-bean paste) soaked in Japanese tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a sweet tooth, and according to the books of his daughters Mari and Annu, he used to eat Manju (a bun stuffed with azuki-bean paste) soaked in Japanese tea.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a sweet tooth, and according to the books of his daughters Mari and Annu, he used to eat Manju (a bun stuffed with azuki-bean paste) soaked in Japanese tea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="419">
<j>これは潔癖症も原因で、食品を砂糖漬けにしたり、熱湯をかけたりすれば細菌は死滅するから、という考えもあったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His obsession with being clean made a part of the reason, and he seemed to consider any preserved food in sugar or food soaked in boiled water would be safe because germs died out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Part of the reason for this was his obsession with cleanliness, and he is said to have considered any food preserved in sugar or soaked in boiling water to be safe because germs would be killed off.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Part of the reason for this was his obsession with cleanliness, and he is said to have considered any food preserved in sugar or soaked in boiling water to be safe because germs would be killed off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kanejan(id:78613), Shugakuin(id:118787), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 銀色しっぽ(id:197919), Nnh(id:474), Nekomiminarikin(id:199247), BMX(id:165458), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Rakka(id:17457), Lupinoid(id:68), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), March(id:9468), Akoyano(id:56905), Kamuin(id:5241), 0太郎(id:7375), マイカル(id:67759), Jazzy(id:3202), Mishika(id:276), でここ(id:9565), 赤井彗星(id:18381), Northface(id:70750), Pontormo(id:12606), 男の教室(id:62924), 代言人(id:33675), Amagiri(id:101077), Adriano(id:12894), Point136(id:211299), 1028miki3(id:200855), Yas(id:739), Kzhr(id:131), YukkeBot2(id:251491), Calvero(id:38360), M-sho-gun(id:88956), 拳王(id:22115), Kurayamizaka(id:7150), Carbuncle(id:346), Sweeper tamonten(id:183520), DOERAX(id:25212), 松茸(id:27535), Complex01(id:10454), わがまま小皇帝(id:39717), Huemat(id:19503), Kkmdynd(id:35942), 安部祥太郎(id:238256), Ymym(id:187488), Rusk(id:9895), Tietew(id:4054), SuisuiBot(id:10165), R28Bot(id:177951), Meme Jellyfish(id:167587), あんも騎士(id:139357), KSKS(id:97637), Mackygin(id:47311), PolarBot(id:131835), 完璧主義(id:24971), Overwork(id:205646), 悟郎(id:31934), Suisui(id:69), TT(id:46431), Straysheep(id:42448), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Reggaeman(id:6214), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), ウィキウィ2(id:83093), 陽一(id:92099), D.h(id:79056), 黄金もち(id:102311), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Im224(id:57113), Charon(id:9162), 矢刺幹人(id:10639), Hhst(id:13720), MDL(id:144298), Classictext(id:299748), さららゆら(id:12274), 下総大納言(id:43461), Goki(id:7107), Darkmagus(id:52740), 鸞(id:159219), Clair.S.F.(id:59514), 端くれの錬金術師(id:23040), Hinonbey(id:56556), พริกขี้หนู(id:131976), Izayohi(id:13095), クロウ(id:21337), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), 水野白楓(id:22811), Jamie(id:71992), まじかんと(id:10923), Aphaia(id:3132), LaaknorBot(id:220851), 一砂(id:94355), Forest135(id:173772), Kafuka1964(id:105407), Neo chemistry(id:143489), VolkovBot(id:105371), 那智の大白木(id:25213), ゐ(id:795), 上田隼人(id:23104), Rainy71(id:180905), Kaboyose-DSD(id:123658), SEKIUCHI(id:637), Sandra-horn(id:46974), Muyo(id:14948), HistorianJ(id:28007), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Louperibot(id:128971), Tokugawa(id:61656), Aryarya(id:35365), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>