<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大石造酒蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikizo OOISHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikizo OOISHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikizo OISHI</e>
<cmt>表記</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大石造酒蔵（おおいし　みきぞう、? - 慶応2年2月5日 (旧暦)（1866年3月21日））は、幕末の一橋徳川家家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikizo OOISHI (date of birth is unknown - March 21, 1866) was a vassal of the Hitotsubashi family of the Tokugawa clan at the last days of the Tokugawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikizo OOISHI (date of birth is unknown - March 21, 1866) was a vassal of the Hitotsubashi family, a branch of the Tokugawa Clan, who lived during the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikizo OOISHI (date of birth is unknown - March 21, 1866) was a vassal of the Hitotsubashi family, a branch of the Tokugawa Clan, who lived during the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>新選組隊士・大石鍬次郎の実弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a younger brother of Kuwajiro OOISHI, a member of Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a younger brother of Kuwajiro OOISHI, a member of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a younger brother of Kuwajiro OISHI, a member of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大石捨次郎の実子で、実名は源守仲（みなもと もりなか?）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a real son of Sutejiro OOISHI and his real name was Morinaka MINAMOTO (pronunciation is uncertain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of Sutejiro OOISHI and his real name was Morinaka MINAMOTO (pronunciation is uncertain).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of Sutejiro OISHI and his real name was Morinaka MINAMOTO (pronunciation is uncertain).</e>
<cmt>表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>文久2年(1862年)8月、父捨次郎の隠居により家督を相続。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1862, when his father Sutejiro retired, he succeeded his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1862, he bacame head of the family when his father, Sutejiro, retired.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1862, he bacame head of the family when his father, Sutejiro, retired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>大石家の家督を継いでいたためか一般に「鍬次郎の兄」とされることも多いが、過去帳や佐藤彦五郎日記(日野市発行)によると弟が正しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikizo OOISHI is generally considered as &apos;an elder brother of Kuwajiro&apos;, supposedly because Mikizo succeeded his father; however, according to the necrology and the diary of Hikogoro SATO (published by Hino City), it is correct that Mikizo was a younger brother of Kuwajiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Mikizo succeeded his father, he is often considered to be &apos;an elder brother of Kuwajiro&apos;; however, according to the register of deaths and Hikogoro SATO&apos;s diary (published by Hino City), he was actually a younger brother of Kuwajiro.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Mikizo succeeded his father, he is often considered to be &apos;an elder brother of Kuwajiro&apos;; however, according to the register of deaths and Hikogoro SATO&apos;s diary (published by Hino City), he was actually a younger brother of Kuwajiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>壬生光縁寺、松原忠司ら12名の合同墓碑と、山南敬助ら5名の合同墓碑とに挟まれて墓碑が立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His gravestone stands between the mass gravestone of the twelve including Chuji MATSUBARA and the mass gravestone of the five including Keisuke YAMANAMI in the Koen-ji Temple in Mibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His gravestone stands between a joint gravestone for twelve people, including Chuji MATSUBARA, and a joint gravestone for five people, including Keisuke YAMANAMI, in Koen-ji Temple in Mibu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His gravestone stands between a joint gravestone for twelve people, including Chuji MATSUBARA, and a joint gravestone for five people, including Keisuke YAMANAMI, in Koen-ji Temple in Mibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>施主は兄・鍬次郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The donor is his elder brother Kuwajiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was paid for by his elder brother, Kuwajiro.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was paid for by his elder brother, Kuwajiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>新選組隊士・今井祐次郎に斬殺された話が伝わるが、近藤勇・土方歳三書簡によると病死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of a story that Mikizo OOISHI was killed with a sword by Yujiro IMAI, a member of Shinsengumi, he died of illness according to letters of Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is a story that Mikizo OOISHI was killed in a sword fight with Shinsengumi member Yujiro IMAI,, according to the correspondence of Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA., he died of illness.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is a story that Mikizo OISHI was killed in a sword fight with a Shinsengumi member Yujiro IMAI,, according to the correspondence of Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA., he died of illness.</e>
<cmt>表記冠詞</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ただし佐藤彦五郎日記の慶応二年四月の記録によると「相果候」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The record in April in Keio 2 (Japanese calendar) of the diary of Hikogoro SATO, however, reads &quot;he died&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The April, 1866 entry in Hikogoro SATO&apos;s diary, however, reads &quot;he died&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The April, 1866 entry in Hikogoro SATO&apos;s diary, however, reads &quot;he was killed&quot;.</e>
<cmt>原文の流れからすると、killed　がよいと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>大石家家督について近藤らが奔走した形跡があるが鍬次郎は相続せず、慶応2年12月に妹婿の荘之助が相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although KONDO and others seems to have made efforts to make Kuwajiro succeed to the head of the family, Kuwajiro did not succeeded, and in December, Keio 2 (Japanese calendar), his younger sister&apos;s husband Shonosuke succeeded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KONDO and others seem to have tried, without success, to make Kuwajiro the head of the family and, in December 1866, his younger sister&apos;s husband, Shonosuke, succeeded to the headship.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KONDO and others seem to have tried, without success, to make Kuwajiro the head of the family and, in January 1867, his younger sister&apos;s husband, Shonosuke, succeeded to the headship.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>諸資料による最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Death according to several Materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Death according to several Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Death according to several Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>慶応2年2月、祇園石段下で今井祐三郎（祐次郎）と斬り合い、殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikizo OOISHI fought Yuzaburo (Yujiro) IMAI with swords at the Gion Ishidan-shita, and killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikizo OOISHI was killed in a sword fight with Yuzaburo (Yujiro) IMAI at Gion Ishidan-shita in February 1866.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikizo OISHI was killed in a sword fight with Yuzaburo (Yujiro) IMAI at Gion Ishidan-shita in March 1866.</e>
<cmt>表記グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>兄を殺された鍬次郎は今井を恨みに思った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuwajiro held a grudge against IMAI for killing his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuwajiro held a grudge against IMAI for killing his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuwajiro held a grudge against IMAI for killing his elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それを察した土方が「私闘を禁ずる」法度をもって鍬次郎に注意を促すが、執念深い鍬次郎は今井を付け狙う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having sensed that, HIJIKATA gave caution to Kuwajiro by reminding him of the ordinance against the private war, but Kuwajiro was as revengeful as to track IMAI down.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIJIKATA, sensing this, reminded him of the ordinance forbidding &apos;private wars&apos;, but Kuwajiro, intent on vengeance, nevertheless went after IMAI.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIJIKATA, sensing this, reminded him of the ordinance forbidding &apos;private wars&apos;, but Kuwajiro, intent on vengeance, nevertheless went after IMAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そこで近藤に意を含められた土方が「自分は近藤から大切な預かり物をしたが大変な物なので大石にも共同責任を負ってほしい、その預かり物とは今井の命であり、今井に万一があれば土方・大石両名は切腹せねばならぬ」と釘を刺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under instructions of Kondo, HIJIKATA made it clear to Kuwajiro that KONDO left HIJIKATA so important thing that HIJIKATA wanted Kuwajiro to share the responsibility for that thing, which was the life of IMAI, with a determination to expiate the death of IMAI by committing seppuku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At KONDO&apos;s suggestion, HIJIKATA told Kuwajiro that KONDO had entrusted to him something so important but also so terrible that he wanted Kuwajiro to share responsibility for it, that thing being IMAI&apos;s life; and if anything happened to IMAI, both HIJIKATA and Kuwajiro would have to commit seppuku.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - though might be better split in two</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At KONDO&apos;s suggestion, HIJIKATA told Kuwajiro that KONDO had entrusted to him something so important but also so terrible that he wanted Kuwajiro to share responsibility for it, that thing being IMAI&apos;s life; and if anything happened to IMAI, both HIJIKATA and Kuwajiro would have to commit seppuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これで、ようやく鍬次郎も諦めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, HIJIKATA persuaded Kuwajiro out of revenging IMAI in the end.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing these words, Kuwajiro finally abandonned his vendetta.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing these words, Kuwajiro finally abandonned his vendetta.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これを伝え聞いた今井は近藤・土方への恩義を強く感じ、鳥羽・伏見の戦いで奮戦して果てるまで活躍したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having heard that story from others, IMAI strongly felt indebted to KONDO and HIJIKATA, and he fought desperately in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having heard that story from others, IMAI felt strongly indebted to KONDO and HIJIKATA, and he fought to the death in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having heard that story from others, IMAI felt strongly indebted to KONDO and HIJIKATA, and he fought to the death in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>『壬生浪士始末記』（西村兼文）や『新選組始末記』（子母澤寛）に掲載されている話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That story is written in &quot;Mibu Roshi Shimatsuki&quot; (Kanefumi NISHIMURA) and &quot;Shinsengumi Shimatsuki&quot; (Kan SHIMOZAWA).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story appears in &quot;Mibu Roshi Shimatsuki&quot; (Kanefumi NISHIMURA) and &quot;Shinsengumi Shimatsuki&quot; (Kan SHIMOZAWA).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story appears in &quot;Mibu Roshi Shimatsuki&quot; (Kanefumi NISHIMURA) and &quot;Shinsengumi Shimatsuki&quot; (Kan SHIMOZAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは造酒蔵を「兄」として描かれたものであり、実際は造酒蔵が鍬次郎の弟であることから、現在では事実ではないと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story is considered a fiction now, because Mikizo is described as an elder brother of Kuwajiro, although he was actually a younger brother of Kuwajiro</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is nowadays believed to be untrue because Mikizo is described as Kuwajiro&apos;s elder brother when he was actually his younger brother.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is nowadays believed to be untrue because Mikizo is described as Kuwajiro&apos;s elder brother when he was actually his younger brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ちなみにこの話では、造酒蔵が今井と切り結んでいる丁度その頃、鍬次郎も伊勢国藩士・安西某なる武士を斬り殺し、お互いに屯所の前で鉢合わせをした、というドラマチックな描き方をされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the story has a dramatic description: While Mikizo is fighting IMAI, Kuwajiro is putting a samurai, So-and-So ANZAI who was a statesman of Ise Province, to the edge of the sword, and later, the brothers encountered in front of quarters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the story has a dramatic touch as shown in the anecdote that while Mikizo was crossing swords with IMAI, Kuwajiro was fighting to the death with a certain ANZAI, a samurai from Ise Province and, later, the two brothers encountered each other in front of their quarters.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the story has a dramatic touch as shown in the anecdote that while Mikizo was crossing swords with IMAI, Kuwajiro was fighting to the death with a certain ANZAI, a samurai from Ise Province and, later, the two brothers encountered each other in front of their quarters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), おきた(id:18906), Mymelo(id:122034), ふんにゃらにゃ(id:27740), Artfan(id:15278), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>