<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>真田信繁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobushige SANADA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobushige SANADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobushige SANADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>真田 信繁 （さなだ のぶしげ）は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代初期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobushige SANADA was a busho (Japanese military commander) over the Azuchi-momoyama to the early period of the Edo Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobushige SANADA was a busho (Japanese military commander) over the Azuchi-momoyama in the early years of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobushige SANADA was a busho (Japanese military commander) over the Azuchi-momoyama in the early years of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>永禄10年（1567年）とされる生年は没年の49歳から逆算されたもので、月日は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His year of birth is said to be 1567, which is back-calculated from his age at death, 49, and the month and date are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His year of birth is said to be 1567, which is back-calculated from his age at death (49), but the month and date aren&apos;t known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His year of birth is said to be 1567, which is back-calculated from his age at death (49), but the month and date aren&apos;t known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>武田信玄の家臣であった真田幸隆の孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a grandchild of Yukitaka SANADA who was a vassal of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a grandchild of Yukitaka SANADA, a vassal of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a grandchild of Yukitaka SANADA, a vassal of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大坂の役で活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He performed brilliantly in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He performed brilliantly in Osaka no Eki (the Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He performed brilliantly in Osaka no Eki (the Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>特に大坂の役では、寡兵を持って徳川本陣まで攻め込み、徳川家康を後一歩のところまで追いつめたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in Osaka no Eki, it is said that he pushed into the headquarters of Tokugawa with an outnumbered troop and was just one step away to hunting down Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, in regard to Osaka no Eki, it is said that he pushed into the headquarters of Tokugawa with outnumbered troops and was just one step away from hunting down Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, in regard to Osaka no Eki, it is said that he pushed into the headquarters of Tokugawa with outnumbered troops and was just one step away from hunting down Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸期以降、講談や小説などで真田十勇士を従えて大敵徳川に挑む天才軍師真田幸村（さなだ ゆきむら）として取り上げられ、広く一般に知られることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and after the Edo period, he was spotlighted in kodan storytelling and novels as a genius strategist Yukimura SANADA who challenged his archenemy Tokugawa with an entourage of Sanada Juyushi (Sanada ten braves), and became to be known widely to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In and after the Edo period, he was spotlighted in kodan storytelling and novels as a genius strategist Yukimura SANADA, who challenged his arch enemy Tokugawa with an entourage of Sanada Juyushi (ten Sanada braves), and became widely known among the public.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In and after the Edo period, he was spotlighted in kodan storytelling and novels as a genius strategist Yukimura SANADA, who challenged his arch enemy Tokugawa with an entourage of Sanada Juyushi (ten Sanada braves), and became widely known among the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名前について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About his name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About his name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About his name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>本名の信繁（のぶしげ）は、武田信玄の弟・武田信繁の名を是にと父真田昌幸が信繁の息子に言って使わせて貰った名であるため改名はしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobushige&apos;s father Masayuki SANADA asked a son of Nobushige TAKEDA who was a younger brother of Shingen Takeda to let him use the name Nobushige and he was allowed to do so, so Nobushige did not change his name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobushige&apos;s father, Masayuki SANADA, asked a son of Nobushige TAKEDA, who was a younger brother of Shingen Takeda, to let him use the name Nobushige, and he was allowed to do so, so Nobushige did not change his name.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobushige&apos;s father, Masayuki SANADA, asked a son of Nobushige TAKEDA, who was a younger brother of Shingen TAKEDA, to let him use the name Nobushige, and he was allowed to do so, so Nobushige did not change his name.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>「真田幸村」の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of &apos;Yukimura Sanada&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of &apos;Yukimura Sanada&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of &apos;Yukimura SANADA&apos;</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>講談などの影響で「真田幸村（さなだゆきむら）」の名で広く知られているが、信繁直筆の書状を始め、信繁が生きていた同時代の史料で「幸村」の名が使われているものは存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he is widely known as &apos;Yukimura Sanada&apos; due to influence of kodan storytelling, there are no historical materials in the years when Nobushige was alive, including letters written by Nobushige himself, in which the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he is widely known as &apos;Yukimura Sanada&apos; due to the influence of kodan storytelling, there are no historical materials from the years when Nobushige was alive, including letters written by Nobushige himself, in which the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; is used.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he is widely known as &apos;Yukimura SANADA&apos; due to the influence of kodan storytelling, there are no historical materials from the years when Nobushige was alive, including letters written by Nobushige himself, in which the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; is used.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>従って歴史上の人物の名としては「信繁」が正しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, &apos;Nobushige&apos; is proper as the name of the historical character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, &apos;Nobushige&apos; is proper as the name of the historical character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, &apos;Nobushige&apos; is proper as the name of the historical character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>講談などで語られる「幸村」の活躍に関しては後述する真田幸村の節を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For successes of &apos;Yukimura&apos; told in kodan storytelling etc., refer to the section of Yukimura Sanada described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the successes of &apos;Yukimura&apos; told in kodan storytelling, etcetera, refer to the section on Yukimura Sanada described below.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the successes of &apos;Yukimura&apos; told in kodan storytelling, etcetera, refer to the section on Yukimura SANADA described below.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>「幸村」の初出は江戸時代の寛文12年（1672年）成立の軍記物語『難波戦記』にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimura&apos; first appeared in a war chronicle &quot;Namba senki&quot; established in 1672 in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukimura&apos; first appeared in a war chronicle &quot;Namba senki,&quot; which was established in 1672 during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukimura&apos; first appeared in a war chronicle &quot;Nanba senki,&quot; which was established in 1672 during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その本が爆発的に売れたため、「幸村」とすることのほうが一般的となり、後には兄・信之の子孫である松代藩の史書にまで「幸村」が採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because that book sold in huge numbers, the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; became more common, and later, &apos;Yukimura&apos; was adopted even in the history book of Matsushiro Domain, who were descendants of his older brother Nobuyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because that book sold in huge numbers, the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; became more common, and later &apos;Yukimura&apos; was adopted even in the history book of the Matsushiro Domain, who were descendants of his older brother Nobuyuki.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because that book sold in huge numbers, the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; became more common, and later &apos;Yukimura&apos; was adopted even in the history book of the Matsushiro Domain, who were descendants of his older brother Nobuyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>新井白石著の藩翰譜に、幸村と記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hankanpu (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) written by Hakuseki ARAI, there is a description of &apos;Yukimura.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hankanpu (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) written by Hakuseki ARAI, there is a description of &apos;Yukimura.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hankanpu (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) written by Hakuseki ARAI, there is a description of &apos;Yukimura.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>「幸」は真田家(厳密には真田家の主家にあたる海野家)の通字である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuki&apos; is the tsuji (distinctive character used in the names of all people belonging to a single clan or lineage) of the Sanada family (to be exact, the Unno family, the master&apos;s house of the Sanada family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuki&apos; is the tsuji (distinctive character used in the names of all people belonging to a single clan or lineage) of the Sanada family (specifically, the Unno family, the master&apos;s house of the Sanada family).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuki&apos; is the tsuji (distinctive character used in the names of all people belonging to a single clan or lineage) of the Sanada family (specifically, the Unno family, the master&apos;s house of the Sanada family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「村」については信繁の姉の村松や、信繁の子孫が仕えた伊達家当主の伊達綱村、徳川家を呪ったとされる妖刀村正に由来しているとする説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For &apos;mura&apos;, there are theories such as the origin is Nobushige&apos;s older sister Muramatsu, Head of the Date family Tsunamura DATE to whom Nobushige&apos;s descendants served, or the yoto (a mysterious sword) Muramasa that alleged to curse the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For &apos;mura,&apos; there are theories such as that the origin is Nobushige&apos;s older sister Muramatsu, head of the Date family Tsunamura DATE, whom Nobushige&apos;s descendants served, or the yoto (a mysterious sword) Muramasa, which was alleged to curse the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For &apos;mura,&apos; there are theories such as that the origin is Nobushige&apos;s older sister Muramatsu, head of the Date family Tsunamura DATE, whom Nobushige&apos;s descendants served, or the yoto (a mysterious sword) Muramasa, which was alleged to curse the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>「幸村」という名は信繁の死後100年以内で広まっているため、真田昌幸の死後に昌幸の片諱を継承して実際に「幸村」と名乗ったのではないかとの推測もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; spread within 100 years after Nobushige&apos;s death, there is an assumption that he actually called himself &apos;Yukimura,&apos; inheriting Kataimina (taking a character from a person in the family) of Masayuki Sanada after Masayuki&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; spread within 100 years after Nobushige&apos;s death, it is assumed that he actually called himself &apos;Yukimura,&apos; inheriting Kataimina (taking a character from a person in the family) of Masayuki Sanada after Masayuki&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; spread within 100 years after Nobushige&apos;s death, it is assumed that he actually called himself &apos;Yukimura,&apos; inheriting Kataimina (taking a character from a person in the family) of Masayuki SANADA after Masayuki&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>ただし、可能性としてありうるものの「幸村」という名が記された史料が見つかっておらず、現状では立証が不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is feasible, however, no historical materials that contains the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; has been found, so it is impossible to verify it as matters now stand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is possible, no historical materials containing the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; has been found, so it is impossible to verify it as matters now stand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is possible, no historical materials containing the name &apos;Yukimura&apos; has been found, so it is impossible to verify it as matters now stand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>夏の陣での死の二ヶ月前に「幸村」と改名したため、という説もあるが史料に残っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another theory that he changed his name to &apos;Yukimura&apos; two months before his death in Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), but there are no existing historical materials.</e>
<cmt>「夏の陣」は「大阪夏の陣」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another theory that he changed his name to &apos;Yukimura&apos; two months before his death in Osaka Natsu no Jin (the Summer Siege of Osaka), but there are no existing historical materials to verify it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another theory that he changed his name to &apos;Yukimura&apos; two months before his death in Osaka Natsu no Jin (the Summer Siege of Osaka), but there are no existing historical materials to verify it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>大阪冬の陣と大阪夏の陣の半ばの慶長20年2月に叔父にあてた手紙や、兄・姉にあてた手紙にも信繁の名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the letter to his uncle in February 1615, in between Osaka Fuyu no Jin (the Siege of Osaka in Winter) and Osaka Natsu no Jin, and in letters to his older brother and sister, the name Nobushige is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the letter to his uncle written in February 1615, in between Osaka Fuyu no Jin (the Siege of Osaka in Winter) and Osaka Natsu no Jin, and in letters to his older brother and sister, the name Nobushige is used.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the letter to his uncle written in February 1615, in between Osaka Fuyu no Jin (the Siege of Osaka in Winter) and Osaka Natsu no Jin, and in letters to his older brother and sister, the name Nobushige is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>武田家臣時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period in which he was a vassal of Takeda clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period as a vassal of the Takeda clan</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period as a vassal of the Takeda clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>永禄10年（1567年）真田昌幸（当時は武藤喜兵衛）の次男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the second son of Masayuki Sanada (then Kihei MUTO) in 1567).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1567 as the second son of Masayuki Sanada (then Kihei MUTO).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1567 as the second son of Masayuki SANADA (then Kihei MUTO).</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>母は正室の山手殿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Masayuki&apos;s lawful wife Yamanotedono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Masayuki&apos;s lawful wife, Yamanotedono.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Masayuki&apos;s lawful wife, Yamanotedono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>天正3年（1575年）信繁が9歳の時、真田氏の主家で甲斐国・信濃国を治める武田勝頼が、長篠の戦いで織田氏・徳川氏連合軍に敗北する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1575, when Nobushige was nine years old, Katsuyori TAKEDA, who was the master of the Sanada clan and was governing Kai and Shinano Provinces, was defeated by the Oda and Tokugawa allied forces in the Battle of Nagashino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1575, when Nobushige was nine years old, Katsuyori TAKEDA, who was the master of the Sanada clan and was governing Kai and Shinano provinces, was defeated by the Oda and Tokugawa allied forces in the Battle of Nagashino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1575, when Nobushige was nine years old, Katsuyori TAKEDA, who was the master of the Sanada clan and was governing Kai and Shinano provinces, was defeated by the Oda and Tokugawa allied forces in the Battle of Nagashino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この際、父・昌幸の2人の兄も亡くなったため、真田家は昌幸が継ぐこととなり、信繁は父に付き従い古府中（甲府市）を離れ上州（岩櫃城）に移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Masayuki&apos;s two older brothers died at this time, so Masayuki succeeded the Sanada family, and Nobushige left Kofuchu (Kofu City) and moved to Joshu (Iwabitsu-jo Castle) following his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Masayuki&apos;s two older brothers died at that time, so Masayuki succeeded the Sanada family; thus Nobushige left Kofuchu (Kofu City) and moved to Joshu (Iwabitsu-jo Castle), following his father.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Masayuki&apos;s two older brothers died at that time, so Masayuki succeeded the Sanada family; thus Nobushige left Kofuchu (Kofu City) and moved to Joshu (Iwabitsu-jo Castle), following his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これより信繁も真田を称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, Shigenobu also called himself Sanada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, Shigenobu also called himself Sanada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, Shigenobu also called himself Sanada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>天正10年（1582年）3月11日 (旧暦)、織田・徳川・後北条氏連合軍の甲斐侵攻で武田氏が滅亡すると、真田氏は織田信長に恭順した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 13, 1582, when the Oda, Tokugawa, Gohojo allied forces invaded Kai and destroyed the Takeda clan, the Sanada clan obeyed Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 13, 1582, when the Oda, Tokugawa and Gohojo allied forces invaded Kai and destroyed the Takeda clan, the Sanada clan obeyed Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 13, 1582, when the Oda, Tokugawa and Gohojo allied forces invaded Kai and destroyed the Takeda clan, the Sanada clan obeyed Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>3月19日 (旧暦)、武田遺領の分割が行われ、真田氏は所領を安堵された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 21, property inheritance of Takeda clan was divided and the Sanada clan was authorized for land ownership.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 21, the property inheritance of the Takeda clan was divided and the Sanada clan was authorized for land ownership.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 21, the property inheritance of the Takeda clan was divided and the Sanada clan was authorized for land ownership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>本能寺の変の後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Honnoji Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Honnoji Incident</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Honnoji Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>同年6月2日 (旧暦)に信長が本能寺の変で家臣の明智光秀に討たれると、織田家の関東管領であった滝川一益は、神流川の戦いで後北条氏に敗れて伊勢に引き上げてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga was killed by his vassal Mitsuhide AKECHI on July 1, 1582 in Honnoji Incident, Kazumasu TAKIGAWA who was the Oda family&apos;s Kanto Kanrei (A shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) was defeated by Gohojo clan in Battle of Kannagawa River and retreated to Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga was killed by his vassal Mitsuhide AKECHI on July 1, 1582 in the Honnoji Incident, Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, who was the Oda family&apos;s Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) was defeated by the Gohojo clan in the Battle of Kannagawa River and retreated to Ise.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga was killed by his vassal Mitsuhide AKECHI on July 1, 1582 in the Honnoji Incident, Kazumasu TAKIGAWA, who was the Oda family&apos;s Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) was defeated by the Gohojo clan in the Battle of Kannagawa River and retreated to Ise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>信長という後援が無くなった真田氏は、所領を守るために上杉氏・北条・徳川など周辺の諸大名の傘下を渡り歩くことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanada clan, who lost Nobunaga&apos;s backup, was forced to cross between umbrellas of neighboring territorial lords such as Uesugi clan, Hojo clan, and Tokugawa clan to keep shoryo (territory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanada clan, which had lost Nobunaga&apos;s backup, was forced to cross between the umbrellas of neighboring territorial lords such as the Uesugi clan, Hojo clan and Tokugawa clan in order to keep shoryo (territory).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanada clan, which had lost Nobunaga&apos;s backup, was forced to cross between the umbrellas of neighboring territorial lords such as the Uesugi clan, Hojo clan and Tokugawa clan in order to keep shoryo (territory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この際に当主の息子である信繁は、人質として諸大名の下を転々としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Nobushige, the son of the head of the family, wandered from a territorial lord to another as a hostage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Nobushige, the son of the head of the family, wandered from one territorial lord to another as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Nobushige, the son of the head of the family, wandered from one territorial lord to another as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>徳川家康との間で第一次上田合戦があったのはこの時期で、豊臣秀吉の仲介で和解する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first battle of Ueda against Ieyasu Tokugawa was around this period, and they reached a settlement at the mediation of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first battle of Ueda against Ieyasu Tokugawa occurred in or around this period, and they reached a settlement at the mediation of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first battle of Ueda against Ieyasu TOKUGAWA occurred in or around this period, and they reached a settlement at the mediation of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>昌幸は最終的に秀吉の傘下に入ったため信繁は秀吉の下に留まり、のちに秀吉の家臣・大谷吉継の娘を正妻に迎えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Masayuki eventually obeyed Hideyoshi, Nobushige stayed at Hideyoshi&apos;s side, and later he married his legal wife, a daughter of Hideyoshi&apos;s vassal Yoshitsugu Otani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Masayuki eventually obeyed Hideyoshi, Nobushige stayed at Hideyoshi&apos;s side, and later he married his legal wife, a daughter of Hideyoshi&apos;s vassal Yoshitsugu Otani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Masayuki eventually obeyed Hideyoshi, Nobushige stayed at Hideyoshi&apos;s side, and later he married his lawful wife, a daughter of Hideyoshi&apos;s vassal Yoshitsugu OTANI.</e>
<cmt>用語統一人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>文禄3年（1594年）11月2日、豊臣氏名義で従五位下左衛門佐に叙任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 13, 1954, he was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Saemon no suke (assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) in the name of Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 13, 1954, he was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Saemon no suke (assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) in the name of the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 13, 1954, he was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Saemon no suke (assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) in the name of the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原の合戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>秀吉死後の慶長5年（1600年）に、五大老の徳川家康が同じく五大老の一人だった会津の上杉景勝討伐の兵を起こすと従軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1600, after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, when Ieyasu Tokugawa, a member of Gotairo (Council of Five Elders), rose in arms against another member of Gotairo Kagekatsu UESUGI in Aizu, he took a part in the campaign.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1600, after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, when Ieyasu Tokugawa, a member of the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders), rose in arms against another member of the Gotairo, Kagekatsu UESUGI, in Aizu, he took part in the campaign.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1600, after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, when Ieyasu Tokugawa, a member of the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders), rose in arms against another member of the Gotairo, Kagekatsu UESUGI, in Aizu, he took part in the campaign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>留守中に五奉行の石田三成らが挙兵して関ヶ原の戦いに至ると、父と共に西軍に加勢し、妻が本多忠勝の娘（小松姫）で徳川方の東軍についた兄・真田信之と袂を分かつことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When one of Gobugyo (five major magistrates) Mitsunari ISHIDA rose in arms while they were absence to cause the Battle of Sekigahara, he backed up the Western Camp with his father, parting ways with his older brother Nobuyuki SANADA, who sided the Eastern Camp because his wife was a daughter of Tadakatsu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When one of the Gobugyo (five major magistrates), Mitsunari ISHIDA, rose in arms during their absence and caused the Battle of Sekigahara, he backed up the Western Camp with his father, parting ways with his older brother Nobuyuki SANADA, who sided with the Eastern Camp because his wife was a daughter of Tadakatsu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When one of the Gobugyo (five major magistrates), Mitsunari ISHIDA, rose in arms during their absence and caused the Battle of Sekigahara, he backed up the Western Camp with his father, parting ways with his older brother Nobuyuki SANADA, who sided with the Eastern Camp because his wife (Komatsuhime) was a daughter of Tadakatsu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>徳川方の東軍は東海道と中山道を分かれて進軍し、昌幸と信繁は居城上田城に籠り、中山道を進んできた東軍の徳川秀忠軍と上田城にて迎え撃った（第二次上田合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eastern Camp, the Tokugawa side, split up and advanced Tokai-do Road and Nakasen-do Road, and Masayuki and Shigenobu secluded in their castle Ueda-jo Castle to fight against Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s army which belonged to the Eastern Camp at Ueda-jo Castle (the second battle of Ueda).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eastern Camp, the Tokugawa side, split up and advanced along Tokai-do Road and Nakasen-do Road, while Masayuki and Shigenobu remained secluded in their stronghold, Ueda-jo Castle, to fight against Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s army, which belonged to the Eastern Camp at Ueda-jo Castle (the second battle of Ueda).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eastern Camp, the Tokugawa side, split up and advanced along Tokai-do Road and Nakasen-do Road, while Masayuki and Shigenobu remained secluded in their stronghold, Ueda-jo Castle, to fight against Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s army, which belonged to the Eastern Camp and advanced along Nakasen-do Road at Ueda-jo Castle (the second battle of Ueda).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>寡兵の真田勢にてこずった秀忠軍は上田城攻略を諦めて去ったが、結果として主戦場となった美濃関ヶ原での決戦に間に合わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetada&apos;s army, which was bothered by outnumbered Sanada clan, gave up to capture Ueda-jo Castle and left, but as a result, they could not join the decisive engagement in Sekigahara, Mino, which was the main battle field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetada&apos;s army, which was bothered by the outnumbered Sanada clan, gave up on capturing Ueda-jo Castle and left, but as a result they could not join the decisive engagement in Sekigahara, Mino, which was the main battlefield.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetada&apos;s army, which was bothered by the outnumbered Sanada clan, gave up on capturing Ueda-jo Castle and left, but as a result they could not join the decisive engagement in Sekigahara, Mino, which was the main battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし三成率いる西軍は、9月15日に秀忠軍ぬきの徳川方に敗北を喫する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Western Camp led by Mitsunari was defeated by the Tokugawa side without Hidetada&apos;s army on October 21.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Western Camp led by Mitsunari was defeated by the Tokugawa side on October 21, without Hidetada&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Western Camp led by Mitsunari was defeated by the Tokugawa side on October 21, without Hidetada&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>昌幸と信繁は、本来なら敗軍の将として切腹を命じられるところだったが、信之の取り成しで紀伊国九度山町に配流を命じられるのみにとどまった（本来なら高野山配流であったが、信繁が竹林院を伴っていたため、女人禁制のかどで九度山に変わったと言われている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyuki and Shigenobu were supposed to be ordered Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), but thanks to plea by Nobuyuki, they were just ordered exile to Kudoyama Town, Kii Province (under normal circumstances, they would have been exiled to Koyasan, but it is said that they were exiled to Kudoyama because Nobushige was with Chikurin-in and Koyasan was prohibited to women).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyuki and Shigenobu were supposed to be ordered to commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), but thanks to a plea by Nobuyuki, they were ordered exiled to Kudoyama Town, Kii Province (under normal circumstances, they would have been exiled to Koyasan, but it is said that they were exiled to Kudoyama because Nobushige was with Chikurin-in and Koyasan was prohibited to women).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyuki and Shigenobu were supposed to be ordered to commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), but thanks to a plea by Nobuyuki, they were ordered exiled to Kudoyama Town, Kii Province (under normal circumstances, they would have been exiled to Koyasan, but it is said that they were exiled to Kudoyama because Nobushige was with Chikurin-in and Koyasan was prohibited to women).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>蟄居中の慶長16年（1611年）に父・昌幸は死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Masayuki died in 1611 during their stay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Masayuki, died in 1611 during their stay.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Masayuki, died in 1611 during their stay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>慶長17年（1612年）には信繁は出家、伝心月叟と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1612, Nobushige became a priest and called himself Denshin Gesso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1612, Nobushige became a priest and called himself Denshin Gesso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1612, Nobushige became a priest and called himself Denshin Gesso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>大坂城に入城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entrance to Osaka-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entrance to Osaka-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entrance to Osaka-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>慶長19年（1614年）「方広寺事件」をきっかけに徳川氏と豊臣氏の関係が悪化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1614, &quot;the Hoko-ji Temple Incident&quot; worsened the relation between the Tokugawa clan and Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1614, &quot;the Hoko-ji Temple Incident&quot; worsened the relations between the Tokugawa and Toyotomi clans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1614, &apos;the Hoko-ji Temple Incident&apos; worsened the relations between the Tokugawa and Toyotomi clans.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>大名の加勢が期待できない豊臣家は浪人 (武士)を集める策を採り、九度山の信繁の元にも使者を派遣し、黄金200枚、銀30貫を贈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Toyotomi family could not expect back up of daimyo (feudal lords), they collected ronin (masterless samurai) and sent an envoy to Nobushige in Kudoyama to give 200 pieces of gold and 30 Kan (a unit of weight, one kan is about 3.7 kg) of silver.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Toyotomi family could not expect the backup of daimyo (feudal lords), they collected ronin (masterless samurai) and sent an envoy to Nobushige in Kudoyama to give 200 pieces of gold and 30 kan (a unit of weight, with one kan equaling approximately 3.7 kg) of silver.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Toyotomi family could not expect the backup of daimyo (feudal lords), they collected ronin (masterless samurai) and sent an envoy to Nobushige in Kudoyama to give 200 pieces of gold and 30 kan (a unit of weight, with one kan equaling approximately 3.7 kg) of silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>信繁は国元にいる父・真田昌幸の旧臣たちに参戦を呼びかけ、九度山を脱出して子の大助幸昌とともに大坂城に入城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobushige called for former vassals of his father Nobuyuki Sanada to join the battle, escaped Kudoyama, and entered into Osaka-jo Castle with his child Daisuke Yukimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobushige called for former vassals of his father Nobuyuki Sanada to join the battle, escaped from Kudoyama and entered into Osaka-jo Castle with his child, Daisuke Yukimasa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobushige called for former vassals of his father Nobuyuki SANADA to join the battle, escaped from Kudoyama and entered into Osaka-jo Castle with his child, Daisuke YUKIMASA.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>しかし、入城の際の信繁の容姿は、歯は抜け落ち、白髪交じりで腰も曲がっていたため門番に山賊と勘違いされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that Nobushige was without teeth, with some gray hair, and stooped when he entered the castle and the gatekeeper mistook him for a bandit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that Nobushige was without teeth, had some gray hair and stooped when he entered the castle, so the gatekeeper mistook him for a bandit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that Nobushige was without teeth, had some gray hair and stooped when he entered the castle, so the gatekeeper mistook him for a bandit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>大坂で信繁の率いた軍は、鎧を赤で統一していたという（赤備え）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the army lead by Nobushige in Osaka all wore red armors (Akazonae (red arms)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the army led by Nobushige in Osaka wore red armor (Akazonae (red arms)).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the army led by Nobushige in Osaka wore red armor (Akazonae (red arms)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>しかし信繁自身については、それまで真田氏の次男坊として父・昌幸や兄・信之の名声に隠れていたために評価は低く、徳川家康も昌幸ではなく、その息子で無名の信繁が大坂に入ったと知り安堵の表情を浮かべたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Nobushige himself had been underestimated until then because he was hidden under fames of his father Masayuki and older brother Nobuyuki as a second son of the Sanada clan, so it is said that Ieyasu Tokugawa was relieved knowing that it was uncelebrated Nobushige, not Masayuki, who entered the Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nobushige himself had been underestimated until then because he had been overshadowed by his father Masayuki and older brother Nobuyuki as a second son of the Sanada clan, so it is said that Ieyasu Tokugawa was relieved knowing that it was the uncelebrated Nobushige, not Masayuki, who had entered Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nobushige himself had been underestimated until then because he had been overshadowed by his father Masayuki and older brother Nobuyuki as a second son of the Sanada clan, so it is said that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was relieved knowing that it was the uncelebrated Nobushige, not Masayuki, who had entered Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>大坂冬の陣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Fuyu no Jin (Winter Siege of Osaka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Fuyu no Jin (Winter Siege of Osaka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Fuyu no Jin (Winter Siege of Osaka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>慶長19年（1614年）に始まる大坂の役で信繁は、当初籠城に反対し、京を抑え、宇治・瀬田 (大津市)（宇治川の瀬田橋付近）で積極的に迎え撃つよう主張した（知将である父・昌幸の策とも言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka) started in 1614, Nobushige was against siege and insisted to aggressively fight at Seta in Uji (Otsu City) (around Seta Bridge over Uji-gawa River) at first (some say it was his father Nobuyuki who was a knowledgeable warrior).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Osaka no Eki (the Siege of Osaka), which started in 1614, Nobushige was against the siege and insisted on fighting aggressively at Seta in Uji (Otsu City) (around Seta Bridge, which spanned the Uji-gawa River) at first (some say it was his father Nobuyuki who was a knowledgeable warrior).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Osaka no Eki (the Siege of Osaka), which started in 1614, Nobushige was against the siege and insisted on fighting aggressively at Seta in Uji (Otsu City) (around Seta Bridge, which spanned the Uji-gawa River) at first (some say it was the strategy of his father Nobuyuki who was a knowledgeable warrior).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし籠城の策と決すると、信繁は大坂城の弱点であった三の丸南側、玉造口外に真田丸と呼ばれる土作りの出城（三日月形）を築き、鉄砲隊を用いて徳川方を挑発し先方隊に大打撃をあたえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when siege was decided, Nobushige built a (crescent-shaped) branch castle made of dirt called the Sanada-maru (Sanada Barbican) outside Tamatsukuriguchi, provoked the Tokugawa side using firearms troops, and gave a black eye to the advance party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the siege was decided Nobushige built a (crescent-shaped) branch castle made of dirt called the Sanada-maru (Sanada Barbican) outside Tamatsukuriguchi, provoked the Tokugawa side using troops with firearms, and gave the advance party a black eye.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the siege was decided Nobushige built a (crescent-shaped) branch castle made of dirt called the Sanada-maru (Sanada Barbican) outside Tamatsukuriguchi and the south of Sannomaru (outer part of the castle) which was the weak point of the Osaka-jo Castle, and provoked the Tokugawa side using troops with firearms, and gave the advance party a black eye.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>しかし、この真田丸を造る際、大坂方の他の武将は信繁が徳川方に寝返るための下準備と疑っており、少々ながらも警戒していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when he was building this Sanada-maru, other busho suspected that it might be a preparation for Nobushige to switch side to the Tokugawa side and were somewhat cautious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when he was building this Sanada-maru, other busho suspected that it might be a preparation for Nobushige to switch to the Tokugawa side and were somewhat cautious.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when he was building this Sanada-maru, other busho suspected that it might be a preparation for Nobushige to switch to the Tokugawa side and were somewhat cautious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>この時は越前松平家勢、加賀藩前田氏勢等を撃退し、真田昌幸の息子という扱いではなく、初めて“真田信繁”として、その武名を知らしめる事となる（信繁が主体的に戦闘の指揮を執った事が確認されるのは大坂の陣だけである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he defeated the armies of Echizen Matsudaira family and the Maeda clan of Kaga Domain, and introduce himself to as a commander &quot;Nobushige Sanada&quot; for the first time (It is confirmed only in Osaka no Jin that Nobushige took the initiative to hoist a flag).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, he defeated the armies of the Echizen Matsudaira family and the Maeda clan of the Kaga Domain, and introduced himself as a commander &quot;Nobushige Sanada&quot; for the first time (it is confirmed only in Osaka no Jin that Nobushige took the initiative in hoisting a flag).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, he defeated the armies of the Echizen Matsudaira family and the Maeda clan of the Kaga Domain, and introduced himself as a commander &quot;Nobushige SANADA&quot; for the first time (it is confirmed only in Osaka no Jin that Nobushige took the initiative in hoisting a flag).</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>冬の陣の講和後、この真田丸は両軍講和に伴う堀埋め立ての際に真っ先に取り壊されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After pacification of Fuyu no Jin, this Sanada-maru was destroyed first when filling in the moat due to the pacification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the pacification of Fuyu no Jin, this Sanada-maru was destroyed first when the moat was filled in.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the pacification of Fuyu no Jin, this Sanada-maru was destroyed first when the moat was filled in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>そして大坂方の弱体化を謀る家康は慶長20年2月に、使者として信繁の叔父である真田信尹を派遣し「信濃の中で一万石を与える」事を条件に寝返るよう説得している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu, who tried to weaken the Osaka side, sent Nobutada SANADA who was an uncle of Nobushige as an envoy to persuade to switch side based on the condition &apos;to give 10,000 koku in Shinano&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu, who tried to weaken the Osaka side, sent Nobutada SANADA, an uncle of Nobushige, as an envoy, hoping to persuade them to switch sides based on the condition of &apos;giving them 10,000 koku in Shinano.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu, who tried to weaken the Osaka side, sent Nobutada SANADA, an uncle of Nobushige in February 1615, as an envoy, hoping to persuade them to switch sides based on the condition of &apos;giving them 10,000 koku in Shinano.&apos;</e>
<cmt>日付補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし信繁はこれを断った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Nobushige refused this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nobushige refused this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nobushige refused this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>すると家康は再び信尹を使者として差し向け、今度は「信濃一国を与える」と説得に出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Ieyasu sent Nobutada as an envoy again, and tried to pursued saying &apos;to give the whole province of Shinano&apos; this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Ieyasu again sent Nobutada as an envoy, who tried to pursuade them, saying they&apos;d be given &apos;the whole province of Shinano.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Ieyasu again sent Nobutada as an envoy, who tried to persuade them, saying they&apos;d be given &apos;the whole province of Shinano.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>これを聞いた信繁は「この信繁、一万石では不忠者にならぬが、一国では不忠者になるとお思いか」と再びはねのけたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, when he heard this, Nobushige rejected it again saying &apos;Do you think I, Nobushige would not become disloyal for 10,000 koku but would be for a province?&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Nobushige, upon hearing this, rejected it again, saying, &apos;Do you think I, Nobushige, would not become disloyal for 10,000 koku but would be for a province?&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Nobushige, upon hearing this, rejected it again, saying, &apos;Do you think I, Nobushige, would not become disloyal for 10,000 koku but would be for a province?&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>大坂夏の陣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>翌年の大坂の役では、道明寺の戦いにおいて、伊達政宗隊の先鋒を銃撃戦の末に一時的に後退させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Siege of Osaka in the following year, he had an exchange of fire with the spearhead army of Masamune DATE and made them temporarily retreat in Domyoji War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Siege of Osaka the following year, he had an exchange of fire with the spearhead army of Masamune DATE and made them temporarily retreat in the Domyoji War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Siege of Osaka the following year, he had an exchange of fire with the spearhead army of Masamune DATE and made them temporarily retreat in the Domyoji War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>これら度々の勝ち戦により、次第に徳川軍も真田軍への攻撃を自重せざるを得なくなり、信繁はそれを見て堂々と大坂城に一時撤収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to these frequent triumphant battles, Tokugawa&apos;s army was gradually forced to hold attacks against Sanada&apos;s army, and Nobushige, seeing it, lordly withdrew to Osaka-jo Castle temporarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to these frequent triumphant battles, Tokugawa&apos;s army was gradually forced to hold attacks against Sanada&apos;s army, and Nobushige, seeing it, made a temporary but lordly withdrawal to Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to these frequent triumphant battles, Tokugawa&apos;s army was gradually forced to hold attacks against Sanada&apos;s army, and Nobushige, seeing it, made a temporary but lordly withdrawal to Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>その撤収の際には、「関東勢百万と候え、男はひとりもなく候」（「関東武者は百万あっても、男子は一人も居ないものだな」）と徳川軍を嘲笑しながら馬に乗り、悠然と撤収したといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the withdrawal, it is said that he rode a horse jeering Tokugawa&apos;s army saying &apos;Although there are a million warriors in Kanto, there are no men,&apos; and withdrew sedately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the withdrawal, it is said that as he rode a horse he jeered Tokugawa&apos;s army, saying, &apos;Although there are a million warriors in Kanto, there are no men,&apos; and calmly withdrew.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the withdrawal, it is said that as he rode a horse he jeered Tokugawa&apos;s army, saying, &apos;Although there are a million warriors in Kanto, there are no men,&apos; and calmly withdrew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>ただし道明寺の戦いでは先行した後藤基次勢が真田勢の援軍が駆けつける前に壊滅し、基次は討死している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Dokyoji War, however, the Mototsugu GOTO&apos;s spearhead army had been wiped out before reinforcement of Sanada&apos;s army came and Mototsugu died on the battle field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wowever, Mototsugu GOTO&apos;s spearhead army had been wiped out in the Dokyoji War, before the reinforcement of Sanada&apos;s army came, and Mototsugu died on the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Mototsugu GOTO&apos;s spearhead army had been wiped out in the Domyoji War, before the reinforcement of Sanada&apos;s army came, and Mototsugu died on the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この戦いの前に家康は基次に寝返りを打診していたため、基次に対して大坂城内では謀反の噂が流れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before this war, Ieyasu sounded Mototsugu for betrayal, so there was a rumor of Mototsugu&apos;s rebellion in Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before this war, Ieyasu sounded Mototsugu for betrayal, so there was a rumor of Mototsugu&apos;s rebellion in Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before this war, Ieyasu sounded Mototsugu for betrayal, so there was a rumor of Mototsugu&apos;s rebellion in Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>そのため基次は死を決して先鋒を勤めたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Mototsugu desperately volunteered the spearhead army for this reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Mototsugu had desperately volunteered the spearhead army for that reason.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Mototsugu had desperately volunteered the spearhead army for that reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>またこのときの指揮権は信繁にはなく、大野治長が持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Nobushige did not have the command authority at this time, but Harunaga ONO did.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Nobushige didn&apos;t have the command authority at the time but Harunaga ONO did.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Nobushige didn&apos;t have the command authority at the time but Harunaga ONO did.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>そのため基次の戦死の責任は信繁だけにあるとは言えないが、真田勢の行軍の遅れが後藤勢壊滅の一因であるとも、また基次の心情を察し敢えて救援を遅らせたとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Mototsugu&apos;s death cannot be attributed to Nobushige only, but it is said that delay of arrival of the Sanada army was one cause of annihilation of the Goto&apos;s army or he deliberately delayed reinforcement army understanding Mototsugu&apos;s feeling.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Mototsugu&apos;s death can&apos;t be attributed to Nobushige alone, but it is said that the delayed arrival of the Sanada army was one factor in the annihilation of Goto&apos;s army or that he deliberately delayed the reinforcement army, understanding Mototsugu&apos;s feelings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Mototsugu&apos;s death can&apos;t be attributed to Nobushige alone, but it is said that the delayed arrival of the Sanada army was one factor in the annihilation of Goto&apos;s army or that he deliberately delayed the reinforcement army, understanding Mototsugu&apos;s feelings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>本当は当日の濃霧のため道に迷い所定の時間に付く事ができず仕方なく後藤基次が戦いを始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, Nobushige was lost because of dense mist on that day and could not make it on time, and Mototsugu involuntarily started fighting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, Nobushige was lost because of dense mist on that day and could not make it on time, and reluctantly Mototsugu engaged the battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, Nobushige was lost because of dense mist on that day and could not make it on time, and reluctantly Mototsugu engaged the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="65">
<j>豊臣軍は後藤基次や木村重成などの主だった武将が討死し、疲弊していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyotomi&apos;s army was ravaged by deaths of major commanders including Mototsugu Goto and Shigenari KIMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyotomi&apos;s army was ravaged by the deaths of major commanders, including Mototsugu Goto and Shigenari KIMURA.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyotomi&apos;s army was ravaged by the deaths of major commanders, including Mototsugu GOTO and Shigenari KIMURA.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>信繁は士気を高める策として豊臣秀頼自身の出陣を求めたが、側近衆や母の淀殿に阻まれ失敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a strategy to lift spirit, Nobushige requested that Hideyori TOYOTOMI himself departure for the front, but prevented by Hideyori&apos;s close advisers and mother Yodo-dono (Lady Yodo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a strategy to lift the morale, Nobushige requested that Hideyori TOYOTOMI himself depart for the front, but he was prevented from doing so by Hideyori&apos;s close advisers and mother Yodo-dono (Lady Yodo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a strategy to lift the morale, Nobushige requested that Hideyori TOYOTOMI himself depart for the front, but he was prevented from doing so by Hideyori&apos;s close advisers and mother Yodo-dono (Lady Yodo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>豊臣氏の敗色が濃厚となる中、信繁は最後の作戦を立てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Toyotomi clan&apos;s defeat was likely, Nobushige made a last strategy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Toyotomi clan&apos;s defeat was likely, Nobushige made a last strategy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Toyotomi clan&apos;s defeat was likely, Nobushige made a last strategy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>それは豊臣方右翼として真田軍、左翼として毛利勝永軍を四天王寺・茶臼山古墳 (大阪市)付近に陣形し射撃戦と突撃を繰り返し家康の陣形に対し本陣を孤立させ、明石全登の軽騎兵団を迂回させ家康本陣を横撃させるというものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was to deploy Sanada&apos;s army as the right wing and Katsunaga MORI&apos;s army as the left wing of Toyotomi&apos;s side around Chausuyama Tumulus in Shitenno-ji Temple (Osaka City), repeat fire fight and offensive to isolate the headquarters of Tokugawa&apos;s army, have light cavalry troop of Takenori AKASHI get around to attack the headquarters of Ieyasu from the side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was to deploy Sanada&apos;s army as the right wing and Katsunaga MORI&apos;s army as the left wing of Toyotomi&apos;s side around Chausuyama Tumulus at Shitenno-ji Temple (Osaka City), repeat the firefight and offensive in order to isolate the headquarters of Tokugawa&apos;s army, and send light cavalry troops of Takenori AKASHI get around to attack the headquarters of Ieyasu from the side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was to deploy Sanada&apos;s army as the right wing and Katsunaga MORI&apos;s army as the left wing of Toyotomi&apos;s side around Chausuyama Tumulus at Shitenno-ji Temple (Osaka City), repeat the firefight and offensive in order to isolate the headquarters of Tokugawa&apos;s army, and send light cavalry troops of Takenori AKASHI get around to attack the headquarters of Ieyasu from the side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>しかし毛利隊の前面諸将が勝手に射撃を開始してしまったため、作戦を断念せざるを得なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because the warlords at the front of the Mori&apos;s army started fire without his order, he had to give up the strategy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the warlords at the front of Mori&apos;s army started fire without his order, he had to give up that strategy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the warlords at the front of Mori&apos;s army started fire without his order, he had to give up that strategy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>そして正面から徳川家康の本陣めがけて決死の突撃を敢行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he desperately started offensive to the headquarter of Ieyasu Tokugawa from the front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, in desperation he started an offensive upon the headquarters of Ieyasu Tokugawa from the front.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, in desperation he started an offensive upon the headquarters of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA from the front.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この突撃は真田勢のみではなく、左翼から攻める毛利勝永、明石全登らも奮闘し家康本営に肉薄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this offensive, not only Sanada&apos;s army, but also Katsunaga Mori and Takenori Akashi, etc. made a great effort and closed in on the headquarters of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this offensive, not only Sanada&apos;s army but also Katsunaga Mori, Takenori Akashi and others made a great effort and closed in on Ieyasu&apos;s headquarters.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this offensive, not only Sanada&apos;s army but also Katsunaga MORI, Takenori AKASHI and others made a great effort and closed in on Ieyasu&apos;s headquarters.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>勝永は本多勢を蹴散らし、何度か本営に突進したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Katsunaga defeated Honda&apos;s army and charged up to the headquarters several times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Katsunaga defeated Honda&apos;s army and made several charges up to the headquarters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Katsunaga defeated Honda&apos;s army and made several charges up to the headquarters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="73">
<j>真田勢は越前松平勢を突破し、家康の本陣まで攻め込み、屈強で鳴らす家康旗本勢を蹴散らした（ちなみに、本陣に攻め込まれ馬印が倒されたのは「三方ヶ原の戦い」以来二度目と言われ、真田勢の凄まじさに家康は自害を覚悟したほどだったという。これにより、奇しくも家康は武田家ゆかりの武将に二度馬印を倒されたこととなる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanada&apos;s army defeated Echizen Matsudaira&apos;s army, attacked the headquarters of Ieyasu, and defeated hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) of Ieyasu who were famous for their brawniness (it is said that it was the second time since &apos;the Battle of Mikatagahara&apos; when Ieyasu&apos;s headquarters was attacked and Uma-jirushi (massive flags used in Japan to identify a daimyo or equally important military commander on the field of battle) was brought down and Ieyasu prepared to kill himself seeing the fierceness of Sanada&apos;s army. By one of time&apos;s revenges, Ieyasu&apos;s uma-jirushi was brought down twice by commanders related to Takeda family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanada&apos;s army defeated Echizen Matsudaira&apos;s army, attacked the headquarters of Ieyasu and defeated hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) of Ieyasu, who were famous for their brawniness (it is said that it was the second time since &apos;the Battle of Mikatagahara&apos; when Ieyasu&apos;s headquarters was attacked and Uma-jirushi (massive flags used in Japan to identify a daimyo or equally important military commander on the field of battle) was brought down and Ieyasu prepared to kill himself, having seen the fierceness of Sanada&apos;s army; time was vengeful, and Ieyasu&apos;s uma-jirushi was brought down twice by commanders related to the Takeda family).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanada&apos;s army defeated Echizen Matsudaira&apos;s army, attacked the headquarters of Ieyasu and defeated hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) of Ieyasu, who were famous for their brawniness (it is said that it was the second time since &apos;the Battle of Mikatagahara&apos; when Ieyasu&apos;s headquarters was attacked and Uma-jirushi (massive flags used in Japan to identify a daimyo or equally important military commander on the field of battle) was brought down and Ieyasu prepared to kill himself, having seen the fierceness of Sanada&apos;s army; time was vengeful, and Ieyasu&apos;s uma-jirushi was brought down twice by commanders related to the Takeda family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="74">
<j>しかし、最終的には数で勝る徳川軍に追い詰められ、ついに四天王寺近くの安居神社（大阪市天王寺区）の境内で、味方の傷ついた兵士を看病していたところを襲われ、越前松平勢鉄砲組の西尾仁左衛門にその首を授けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, however, they were closed in by Tokugawa&apos;s army who outnumbered, and finally, he was attacked in Yasui-jinja Shrine near Shitenno-ji Temple (Tennoji Ward, Osaka City) when he was taking care of injured warriors and gave his head to Nizaemon NISHIO who belonged to the matchlock infantry of Echizen Matsudaira&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, however, they were closed in by Tokugawa&apos;s army, which was more numerous, and finally he was attacked at Yasui-jinja Shrine near Shitenno-ji Temple (Tennoji Ward, Osaka City) when he was taking care of injured warriors and gave up his head to Nizaemon NISHIO, who belonged to the matchlock infantry of Echizen Matsudaira&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, however, they were closed in by Tokugawa&apos;s army, which was more numerous, and finally he was attacked at Yasui-jinja Shrine near Shitenno-ji Temple (Tennoji Ward, Osaka City) when he was taking care of injured warriors and gave up his head to Nizaemon NISHIO, who belonged to the matchlock infantry of Echizen Matsudaira&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>享年49。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at 49.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus he died at age 49.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 49.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="76">
<j>信繁討死の翌5月8日、豊臣秀頼・淀殿母子は大坂城内で自害、太閤秀吉の誇った大坂城も落城し炎上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 4, the following day of Nobushige&apos;s death in the battle field, Hideyori Toyotomi and his mother Yodo-dono killed themselves in Osaka-jo Castle, and Osaka-jo Castle, of which Taiko (father of the Imperial adviser) Hideyoshi was proud, fell and went up in flames.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 4, the day after Nobushige&apos;s death in the field of battle, Hideyori Toyotomi and his mother Yodo-dono killed themselves in Osaka-jo Castle, and the castle, of which Taiko (father of the imperial advisor) Hideyoshi was so proud, fell and went up in flames.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 4, the day after Nobushige&apos;s death in the field of battle, Hideyori TOYOTOMI and his mother Yodo-dono killed themselves in Osaka-jo Castle, and the castle, of which Taiko (father of the imperial advisor) Hideyoshi was so proud, fell and went up in flames.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>ここに大坂夏の陣は徳川方の勝利に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this, Osaka Natsu no Jin ended with Tokugawa&apos;s victory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this, Osaka Natsu no Jin ended with Tokugawa&apos;s victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this, Osaka Natsu no Jin ended with Tokugawa&apos;s victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>その後大坂では、信繁は生きており、秀頼・淀殿を助け、紀州へと逃げ落ちたという噂が流れたと言われいるが、噂では薩摩の島津家領内に逃隠れし墓もある（子孫もありとの噂も）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, it is said that there was a rumor that Nobushige was still alive, helped Hideyori and Yodo-dono, and remained at large in Kishu, and there was another rumor that he fled to Shimazu Family&apos;s domain in Satsuma and there is his grave (another rumor sais he had descendants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that soon a rumor emerged that Nobushige was still alive, helped Hideyori and Yodo-dono, and remained at large in Kishu, and there was another rumor that he fled to the Shimazu Family&apos;s domain in Satsuma, where is grave is located (another rumor states that he had descendants).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that soon a rumor emerged that Nobushige was still alive, helped Hideyori and Yodo-dono, and remained at large in Kishu, and there was another rumor that he fled to the Shimazu family&apos;s domain in Satsuma, where is grave is located (another rumor states that he had descendants).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>実は秀頼と淀の方の遺体あったがどれが秀頼、淀の方の遺体（首）か分からず首実検が出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, they found bodies of Hideyori and Yodo-dono, but they could not distinguish which were Hideyori and Yodo-dono&apos;s heads and could not identify severed heads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, they found the bodies of Hideyori and Yodo-dono, but they couldn&apos;t distinguish which were Hideyori and Yodo-dono&apos;s heads and could not identify severed heads.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, they found the bodies of Hideyori and Yodo-dono, but they couldn&apos;t distinguish which were Hideyori and Yodo-dono&apos;s heads and could not identify severed heads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graveyard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graveyard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graveyard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>真田信繁の墓所（正確には供養墓・供養塔）は、以下の複数が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Nobushige Sanada&apos;s graveyards (to be precise, memorial tombs and towers), the following are identified:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Nobushige Sanada&apos;s graveyards (more precisely, memorial tombs and towers), the following are identified:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Nobushige SANADA&apos;s graveyards (more precisely, memorial tombs and towers), the following are identified:</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>龍安寺塔頭大珠院（京都府京都市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoan-ji Temple Tacchu daijuin (Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoan-ji Temple Tacchu daijuin (Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoan-ji Temple Tacchu daijuin (Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="82">
<j>信繁の七女おかねの夫石川貞清（宗林）は、竹林院を始めとする信繁の遺族を援助したことでも知られ、龍安寺に信繁夫妻の墓を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobushige&apos;s seventh daughter Okane&apos;s husband Sadakiyo ISHIKAWA (Sorin) is also known for supporting Nobushige&apos;s bereaved family including Chikurin-in and built a graveyard of Nobushige and his wife in Ryoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobushige&apos;s seventh daughter Okane&apos;s husband, Sadakiyo ISHIKAWA (Sorin), is also known for supporting Nobushige&apos;s bereaved family including Chikurin-in; he built a graveyard for Nobushige and his wife at Ryoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobushige&apos;s seventh daughter Okane&apos;s husband, Sadakiyo ISHIKAWA (Sorin), is also known for supporting Nobushige&apos;s bereaved family including Chikurin-in; he built a graveyard for Nobushige and his wife at Ryoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>この墓は鏡容池の弁天島に現存するとされるが、非公開となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this graveyard exists in Benten-jima Island in Kyoto-chi Pond, but it is not open to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this graveyard exists on Benten-jima Island in Kyoto-chi Pond, but it isn&apos;t open to the public.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this graveyard exists on Benten-jima Island in Kyoto-chi Pond, but it isn&apos;t open to the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="84">
<j>田村氏墓所（宮城県白石市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graveyard of the Tamura clan (Shiroishi City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graveyard of the Tamura clan (Shiroishi City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graveyard of the Tamura clan (Shiroishi City, Miyagi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="85">
<j>田村家出身の片倉定広（田村清顕の甥田村宗顕の子）に嫁いだ五女・阿昌蒲の縁で、田村家の墓所に墓が建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because his fifth daughter 阿昌蒲 married to Sadahiro KATAKURA (a child of Muneaki TAMURA who was a nephew of Kiyoaki TAMURA) from the Tamura family, his grave was built in the graveyard of the Tamura family.</e>
<cmt>「阿昌蒲」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because his fifth daughter 阿昌蒲 was married to Sadahiro KATAKURA (a child of Muneaki TAMURA, who was a nephew of Kiyoaki TAMURA) from the Tamura family, his grave was built in the graveyard of the Tamura family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his fifth daughter 阿昌蒲 was married to Sadahiro KATAKURA (a child of Muneaki TAMURA, who was a nephew of Kiyoaki TAMURA) from the Tamura family, his grave was built in the graveyard of the Tamura family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="86">
<j>長国寺（長野県長野市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chokoku-ji Temple (Nagano City, Nagano Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chokoku-ji Temple (Nagano City, Nagano Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chokoku-ji Temple (Nagano City, Nagano Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="87">
<j>松代藩真田家の菩提寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family temple of Sanada family in Matsushiro domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family temple of the Sanada family in the Matsushiro domain</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family temple of the Sanada family in the Matsushiro Domain</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>信繁や嫡男大介の供養塔がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are memorial towers of Nobushige and his legitimate son Daisuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are memorial towers of Nobushige and his legitimate son, Daisuke.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are memorial towers of Nobushige and his legitimate son, Daisuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="89">
<j>孝顕寺（福井県福井市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koken-ji temple (Fukui City, Fukui Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koken-ji temple (Fukui City, Fukui Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koken-ji temple (Fukui City, Fukui Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="90">
<j>信繁の首を取った越前松平家の家臣西尾仁左衛門が、自家の菩提寺に首塚を建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A vassal of Echizen Matsudaira family Nizaemon NISHIO, who killed Nobushige built a Kubi-zuka (burial mound for heads) in his family temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A vassal of the Echizen Matsudaira family, Nizaemon NISHIO, who killed Nobushige, built a Kubi-zuka (burial mound for heads) in his family temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A vassal of the Echizen Matsudaira family, Nizaemon NISHIO, who killed Nobushige, built a Kubi-zuka (burial mound for heads) in his family temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>実際に首が埋葬されたかは不明（真田一族の奪還を恐れ、別の場所ともいわれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown if Nobushige&apos;s head was actually buried (It is said that the head was placed in another place in fear of recapture by the Sanada clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It isn&apos;t known whether Nobushige&apos;s head was actually buried (it is said that the head was placed in another spot in fear of recapture by the Sanada clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It isn&apos;t known whether Nobushige&apos;s head was actually buried (it is said that the head was placed in another spot in fear of recapture by the Sanada clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="92">
<j>妙慶寺（秋田県由利本荘市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Myokei-ji Temple (Yurihonjo City, Akita Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myokei-ji Temple (Yurihonjo City, Akita Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myokei-ji Temple (Yurihonjo City, Akita Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="93">
<j>四女・御田姫（顕性院）が真田家（信繁系統）の菩提寺として建立した寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A temple built by his fourth daughter Onda-hime (Oden-hime) (Kensho-in) as a family temple of the Sanada family (Nobushige line).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A temple built by his fourth daughter, Onda-hime (Oden-hime) (Kensho-in), as a family temple of the Sanada family (Nobushige line).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A temple built by his fourth daughter, Onda-hime (Oden-hime) (Kensho-in), as a family temple of the Sanada family (Nobushige line).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>墓はないが位牌が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is not a grave, but ihai (ancestral tablets) remains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is not a grave, but ihai (ancestral tablets) remain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is not a grave, but ihai (ancestral tablets) remain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="95">
<j>一心院（秋田県大館市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isshin-in Temple (Odate City, Akita Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isshin-in Temple (Odate City, Akita Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isshin-in Temple (Odate City, Akita Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="96">
<j>大坂の陣では死なずに、島津氏を頼って鹿児島に落ち延びたとする伝説に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It derives from the legend that he did not die in Osaka no Jin, but fled to Kagoshima to seek help from the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It derives from the legend that he didn&apos;t die in Osaka no Jin but fled to Kagoshima in order to seek help from the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It derives from the legend that he didn&apos;t die in Osaka no Jin but fled to Kagoshima in order to seek help from the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>島津家が徳川に恭順したため、その後は各地を放浪、寛永2年（1625年）から四女御田姫の嫁ぎ先の実家佐竹氏に庇護され大館に住み、寛永18年（1641年）に75歳で没したと伝えられる（嫡男大介の墓もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the legend, he wandered around various places after Shimazu family obeyed Tokugawa, lived in Odate since 1625 under the patronage of Satake clan, to whom his fourth daughter Onda-hime (Oden-hime) married, and died in 1641 at age 75 (there is also a grave of his legitimate son Daisuke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the legend, he wandered around various places after the Shimazu family obeyed Tokugawa, lived in Odate from 1625 under the patronage of the Satake clan, into which his fourth daughter Onda-hime (Oden-hime) had married, and died in 1641 at age 75 (there is also a grave of his legitimate son Daisuke).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the legend, he wandered around various places after the Shimazu family obeyed Tokugawa, lived in Odate from 1625 under the patronage of the Satake clan, into which his fourth daughter Onda-hime (Oden-hime) had married, and died in 1641 at age 75 (there is also a grave of his legitimate son Daisuke).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>大坂夏の陣における信繁への評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluation of Shigenobu in Osaka Natsu no Jin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluation of Shigenobu in Osaka Natsu no Jin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluation of Shigenobu in Osaka Natsu no Jin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>島津忠恒（ただし、この戦いに島津氏は参加しておらず、伝聞から信繁の奮戦ぶりを推測して話した）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune SHIMAZU (Shimazu clan did not join this battle, but he told the following presuming Nobushige&apos;s hard fight based on hearsay).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune SHIMAZU (the Shimazu clan didn&apos;t join this battle, but he told the following, presuming Nobushige&apos;s hard fight based on hearsay).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune SHIMAZU (the Shimazu clan didn&apos;t join this battle, but he told the following, presuming Nobushige&apos;s hard fight based on hearsay).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="99">
<j>「五月七日に、御所様の御陣へ、真田左衛門仕かかり候て、御陣衆追いちらし、討ち捕り申し候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 3, Saemon SANADA attacked the headquarter of Gosho-sama (Ieyasu) and drove out or killed warriors. Warriors who broke away about three ri (a unit of length, one ri is about 500m) all survived. At the third time, Sanada also died on the battle field. Sanada is Japan&apos;s best soldier. Unheard-of in stories from ancient age. The Tokugawa side half lost. I say only this in general. &apos;</e>
<cmt>仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 3, Saemon SANADA attacked the headquarters of Gosho-sama (Ieyasu) and drove out or killed warriors; warriors who broke away about three ri (a unit of length, being about 500 meters) all survived; at the third time, Sanada also died on the battlefield; Sanada is Japan&apos;s best soldier; unheard-of in stories from an ancient age; the Tokugawa side half lost; I say only this in general.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 3, Saemon SANADA attacked the headquarters of Gosho-sama (Ieyasu) and drove out or killed warriors.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>「御陣衆、三里ほどずつ逃げ候衆は、皆みな生き残られ候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warriors who broke away about three ri (a unit of length, being about 500 meters) all survived.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>「三度目に真田も討死にて候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the third time, Sanada also died on the battlefield.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>「真田日本一の兵。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanada is Japan&apos;s best soldier.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>「古よりの物語にもこれなき由。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unheard-of in stories from an ancient age.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>「徳川方、半分敗北。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa side half lost.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>「惣別これのみ申す事に候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I say only this in general.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="106">
<j>細川忠興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="107">
<j>「左衛門佐、合戦場において討ち死に。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saemon no suke (assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) died on the battle field. It is the highest achievement in the history.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saemon no suke (assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) died on the battle field. It is the highest achievement in the history.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saemon no suke (assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) died on the battle field.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>「古今これなき大手柄。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the highest achievement in the history.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="109">
<j>大久保忠教（彦左衛門）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadataka OKUBO (Hikozaemon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadataka OKUBO (Hikozaemon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadataka OKUBO (Hikozaemon)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="110">
<j>「三方ヶ原にて一度御旗の崩れ申すより外、後先の陣にも御旗の崩れ申す事なし。いわんや七十に成らせられて、収めの御ほうどうの崩れては、何の世に恥をすすぎ成さるべきか」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except when the flag fell in Mikatagahara once, the flag never fell in battles. Even more, at age 70, ???&apos;</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except when the flag fell at Mikatagahara once, the flag never fell in battle; even more, at age 70... ?&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except in Mikatagahara, your flag never fell in battle; it would be ashame if you, the ruler, fell right now at the age of seventy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>この解釈であっているかは不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="111">
<j>「大坂御陣覚書」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osakagojinoboegaki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osakagojinoboegaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osakagojinoboegaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="112">
<j>「真田は味方の諸軍乱走るも機を屈せず、魚鱗に連なりて駆け破り、虎韜に別れては追い靡き、蜘蛛手十文字に掛け破らんと、馬の鼻を双べて駆け入り、其の速かなるは疾雷の耳を掩ふに及ばざるが如し。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanada was brave and his horse run like thunder so that people had to cover their ears.&apos;</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず、抄訳を試みました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="113">
<j>「翁草」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okina gusa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okina gusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okina gusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="114">
<j>「真田は、千載人口に残る奇策幾千百ぞや。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanada had thousands of tricky moves that would be told for one thousand years. Since when he was in Shinshu, he had fought against Tokugawa several times, and he never blundered. People say he is a venom insect for Tokugawa. Who would be a hero in this age but Sanada. Unrivaled and greatest of the age. Until now, even women and children know his name and beauty.&apos;</e>
<cmt>仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanada had thousands of tricky moves that would be told for a thousand years; since when he was in Shinshu he had fought against Tokugawa several times, and he never blundered; people say he is a venomous insect for Tokugawa; who would be a hero in this age but Sanada; unrivaled and the greatest of the age; until now, even women and children know his name and beauty.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanada had thousands of tricky moves that would be told for a thousand years.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>「そもそも信州以来、徳川に敵する事数回、一度も不覚の名を得ず、徳川の毒虫なりと世に沙汰せり、当世の英雄真田を非ずして誰ぞや。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since when he was in Shinshu he had fought against Tokugawa several times, and he never blundered; people say he is a venomous insect for Tokugawa; who would be a hero in this age but Sanada.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>「絶等離倫、一世の人物、今にいたりて女も童もその名を聞きてその美を知る。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unrivaled and the greatest of the age; until now, even women and children know his name and beauty.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="117">
<j>「北川覚書」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitagawa oboegaki&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitagawa oboegaki&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitagawa oboegaki&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="118">
<j>「車軸を流す雨の如く候へども、真田が備、一人も散らず真丸に堅り、とてものがれぬ処にて候間。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the battle which was like hard rain wiping out wheel axis, Sanada took command and no one run away but stayed there to protect robustly.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>「一寸も後をみせ候なと、皆々念仏を唱へ、死狂に懸り候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Everyone chanted mantra in desparation to take away their attention from the battlefield.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理意訳です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="120">
<j>「元和先鋒録」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genwa senporoku&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genwa senporoku&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genwa senporoku&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="121">
<j>「真田左衛門合戦の様子奇怪の節多し、此の日初めは茶臼山に出、夫より平野口に伏兵を引廻し、又岡山に出て戦ふ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many strange things about battles of Saemon SANADA. On this day, he first emerged in Mt. Chausu-yama, then led ambush in Hirano-guchi gateway, and then fought in Okayama. Later he died on the battle field in front of Tenno-ji Temple. The remains of cryptoporticus remains until now. Written in a very artificial way. &apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many strange things about the battles of Saemon SANADA; on this day he first emerged in Mt. Chausu-yama, then led an ambush in Hirano-guchi gateway, then fought in Okayama; later he died on the battlefield in front of Tenno-ji Temple; the remains of cryptoporticus are there to this day; written in a very artificial way.&apos;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many strange things about the battles of Saemon SANADA; on this day he first emerged in Mt. Chausu, then led an ambush in Hirano-guchi gateway, then fought in Okayama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>「後に天王寺表に討死す。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he died on the battlefield in front of Tenno-ji Temple.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>「其の往来抜け道の跡、今に相残り候旨、実にしやかに書き記し候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remains of cryptoporticus are there to this day; written in a very artificial way.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="124">
<j>「山下秘録」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamashita hiroku&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamashita hiroku&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamashita hiroku&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="125">
<j>「家康卿の御旗本さして、一文字にうちこむ、家康卿御馬印臥せさすること。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He stubbed hatamoto of Ieyasu and slashed. He brought down Ieyasu&apos;s uma-jirushi. Foreign countries aside, unprecedented brave in Japan. Mysterious bows killed all Sanada&apos;s soldiers. After the battle ended, there was no one who knew Sanada&apos;s command. They all died together on the battle field. &apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He stubbed the hatamoto of Ieyasu and slashed; he brought down Ieyasu&apos;s uma-jirushi; foreign countries aside, unprecedented bravery in Japan; mysterious bows killed all of Sanada&apos;s soldiers; after the battle ended, there was no one who knew Sanada&apos;s command; they all died together on the battlefield.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He stubbed the hatamoto of Ieyasu and slashed; he brought down Ieyasu&apos;s uma-jirushi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>「異国は知らず、日本にはためし少なき勇士なり、ふしぎなる弓取なり真田備居侍を一人も残さず討死させる也。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Foreign countries aside, unprecedented bravery in Japan; mysterious bows killed all of Sanada&apos;s soldiers.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>「合戦終わりて後に、真田下知を知りたる者、天下に是なし。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the battle ended, there was no one who knew Sanada&apos;s command.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>「一所に討死にせるなり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They all died together on the battlefield.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ文を分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="129">
<j>真田軍の名は不朽のものとなり、武勲にあやかろうとした諸将が信繁の首から遺髪をこぞって取り合いお守りにしたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Sanada&apos;s army became everlasting, and it is said that warlords who wanted to follow the example of his Bukun (deeds of arms) rushed to take his hair from Nobushige&apos;s head to make a charm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Sanada&apos;s army became everlasting, and it is said that warlords who wanted to follow the example of his Bukun (deeds of arms) rushed to take his hair from Nobushige&apos;s head in order to make charms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Sanada&apos;s army became everlasting, and it is said that warlords who wanted to follow the example of his Bukun (deeds of arms) rushed to take his hair from Nobushige&apos;s head in order to make charms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>旗印である六文銭は、六文銭を表しているといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His emblem on flag, six one-mon coins, is said to represent the money for the world of the dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emblem on his flag--six one-mon coins--is said to represent the money for the world of the dead.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emblem on his flag--six one-mon coins--is said to represent the money for the world of the dead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>六文銭とは、亡くなった人を葬る時、棺に入れる六文の銭の事で、三途の川の渡し賃のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six one-mon coins are put in the coffin when entomb a dead person for the fee of a boat to cross Sanzu-no-kawa (Sanzu River, or the River of Three Crossings).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Six one-mon coins are placed in the coffin when the deceased is entombed, as the fee for a boat to cross Sanzu-no-kawa (Sanzu River, or the River of Three Crossings).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six one-mon coins are placed in the coffin when the deceased is entombed, as the fee for a boat to cross Sanzu-no-kawa (Sanzu River, or the River of Three Crossings).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>これを旗印にすることは「不惜身命」（ふしゃくしんみょう：仏法のために身命をささげて惜しまないこと）を意味するといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that using them as the emblem on flag means &apos;fushakushinmyo&apos; (to generously devote one&apos;s body and life to the Buddhist law).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that using them as the emblem on a flag means &apos;fushakushinmyo&apos; (to generously devote one&apos;s body and life to the Buddhist law).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that using them as the emblem on a flag means &apos;fushakushinmyo&apos; (to generously devote one&apos;s body and life to the Buddhist law).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="133">
<j>信繁の人柄は、兄・信之の言葉によると柔和で辛抱強く、物静かで怒る様なことは無いという、およそ勇猛な武将のイメージとはかけ離れたものであったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to his older brother Nobuyuki, Nobushige was dovelike, patient, quiet, and rarely got angry, which is far from an image of a brave commander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to his older brother Nobuyuki, Nobushige was dovelike, patient, quiet and rarely angered, which is far from the image of a brave commander.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to his older brother Nobuyuki, Nobushige was dovelike, patient, quiet and rarely angered, which is far from the image of a brave commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>また、信之は『幸村君伝記』において「幸村は国郡を支配する本当の侍であり、それに対して我らは見かけを必死に繕い、肩をいからしている道具持ちという程の差がある。」とも語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Nobuyuki said in &quot;幸村君伝記,&quot; &apos;There is a huge difference between us: Yukimura is a real samurai (warrior) who governed Kokugun (provinces and counties), while we are tool holders who maintain a facade and try to look big.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Nobuyuki said in &quot;幸村君伝記,&quot; &apos;There is a huge difference between us: Yukimura is a real samurai (warrior) who governed Kokugun (provinces and counties), while we are tool holders who maintain a facade and try to look big.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Nobuyuki said in &quot;幸村君伝記,&quot; &apos;There is a huge difference between us: Yukimura is a real samurai (warrior) who governed Kokugun (provinces and counties), while we are tool holders who maintain a facade and try to look big.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>そのためか大坂の役大坂夏の陣では「浪人の分際で」と罵られたほど。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to that, he was landed on as &apos;you are just a ronin!&apos; in Osaka Natsu no Jin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, he was landed on as &apos;you are just a ronin!&apos; in Osaka Natsu no Jin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, he was landed on as &apos;you are just a ronin!&apos; in Osaka Natsu no Jin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="136">
<j>一般には江戸時代になってから、講談等でその名将ぶりが知られる事になるが、徳川に敵対したにも関わらず幕府側はそれを敢えて禁ずることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became to be known as a great commander in the Edo period to the public, but Bakufu did not prohibit that although he was against Tokugawa..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The public in the Edo period knew him as a great commander; the Bakufu didn&apos;t prohibit that, although he was against Tokugawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The public in the Edo period knew him as a great commander; the Bakufu didn&apos;t prohibit that, although he was against Tokugawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>これに関しては、「主君に最後まで忠義を尽くす」という筋立てが幕府に容認されたとする説の他に、二代将軍となった秀忠の関ヶ原での遅参を誤摩化すため、「真田親子が名将の方が都合が良かった」とする少々穿った見方なども存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for this, there are theories such as the story to &apos;cleave to the master until the last moment&apos; was accepted by bakufu, as well as a penetrating view that it was convenient to say &apos;the father and son of Sanada were great commanders&apos; to cover up delay of Hidetada, who became the second Shogun, for Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for this, there are theories such as the story that &apos;cleaving to the master until the last moment&apos; was accepted by the Bakufu, as well as a penetrating view that it was convenient to say &apos;the father and son of Sanada were great commanders&apos; in order to cover up the delay of Hidetada, who became the second shogun, for Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for this, there are theories such as the story that &apos;cleaving to the master until the last moment&apos; was accepted by the Bakufu, as well as a penetrating view that it was convenient to say &apos;the father and son of Sanada were great commanders&apos; in order to cover up the delay of Hidetada, who became the second shogun, for Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="138">
<j>家康は大坂方の諸将の中で最も活躍した信繁に脅威を覚え、大坂冬の陣の後には信繁の兄真田信之に命じて信濃一国40万石で彼を調略しようとしているが、この破格の条件に興味を微塵も見せず豊臣家への忠誠を最期まで貫き通している（一説には叔父真田信尹に命じて上田10万石とも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu felt Nobushige who was most active among warlords in the Osaka side was dangerous and ordered Nobushige&apos;s older brother Nobuyuki Sanada to pursued Nobushige to switch side for 400,000 koku of Shinano Province, but he was not interested in this preferential condition at all and persisted loyalty to the Toyotomi family (accordant to a theory, Ieyasu ordered Nobushige&apos;s uncle Nobutada SANADA and offered 100,000 koku of Ueda).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu felt that Nobushige, who was most active among warlords on the Osaka side, was dangerous and ordered Nobushige&apos;s older brother Nobuyuki Sanada to persuade Nobushige to switch sides for 400,000 koku of Shinano Province, but he wasn&apos;t interested in this preferential condition at all and persisted in his loyalty to the Toyotomi family (according to one theory, Ieyasu ordered Nobushige&apos;s uncle Nobutada SANADA and offered 100,000 koku of Ueda).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu felt that Nobushige, who was most active among warlords on the Osaka side, was dangerous and ordered Nobushige&apos;s older brother Nobuyuki SANADA to persuade Nobushige to switch sides for 400,000 koku of Shinano Province, but he wasn&apos;t interested in this preferential condition at all and persisted in his loyalty to the Toyotomi family (according to one theory, Ieyasu ordered Nobushige&apos;s uncle Nobutada SANADA and offered 100,000 koku of Ueda).</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="139">
<j>信繁の忠臣説には異を唱える者もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some disagree on loyalty of Nobushige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some disagree in regard to Nobushige&apos;s loyalty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some disagree in regard to Nobushige&apos;s loyalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="140">
<j>信繁と徳川氏は「不倶戴天の敵」であったといわれるが、これは後世の俗書や小説等による影響である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Nobushige and Tokugawa clan were &apos;inveterate enemies&apos;, but this is an effect of earthen books and novels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Nobushige and the Tokugawa clan were &apos;inveterate enemies,&apos; but this is an effect of earthen books and novels.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Nobushige and the Tokugawa clan were &apos;inveterate enemies,&apos; but this is an effect of earthen books and novels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="141">
<j>関ヶ原に西軍として参戦し、改易され、復活を遂げた数少ない大名である立花宗茂や丹羽長重も、本領に復帰する前に与えられた所領は宗茂が陸奥棚倉1万石、長重が常陸古渡1万石であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even for the few daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) who joined the Western Camp in Sekigahara, were punished by being deprived of their fief, and was restored, such as Muneshige TACHIBANA and Nagashige NIWA, given shoryo (territory) were Tanagura, Mutsu 10,000 koku for Muneshige and Futsuto, Hitachi 10,000 for Nagashige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even for the few daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) who joined the Western Camp in Sekigahara, they were punished by being deprived of their fiefs, but some were then restored, such as Muneshige TACHIBANA and Nagashige NIWA; those given shoryo (territories) were Tanagura, Mutsu 10,000 koku for Muneshige and Futsuto, and Hitachi 10,000 for Nagashige.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even for the few daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) who joined the Western Camp in Sekigahara, they were punished by being deprived of their fiefs, but some were then restored, such as Muneshige TACHIBANA and Nagashige NIWA; those given shoryo (territories) were Tanagura, Mutsu 10,000 koku for Muneshige and Futsuto, and Hitachi 10,000 for Nagashige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>宗茂や長重より知名度も実績も劣る信繁が信州40万石を与えられる可能性は低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unlikely that Nobushige who was less famous and had less achievements than Muneshige or Nagashige was given Shinshu 400,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unlikely that Nobushige, who was less famous and had fewer achievements than Muneshige or Nagashige, was given Shinshu 400,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unlikely that Nobushige, who was less famous and had fewer achievements than Muneshige or Nagashige, was given Shinshu 400,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>信繁本人も真に受けなかったと推察される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is inferable that Nobushige himself did not take it at face value.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is inferred that Nobushige didn&apos;t take it at face value.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is inferred that Nobushige didn&apos;t take it at face value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="144">
<j>家康からの破格の条件を断ったのが、豊臣家への忠誠のためであったかについては実証することはできず、逆に信繁の兄や叔父らが徳川家の臣下であることを根拠に「信繁は徳川方の間者である」という豊臣家臣からの誹謗中傷もあったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It cannot be proved that he refused the preferential condition proposed by Ieyasu because of loyalty to Toyotomi family, but adversely, based on the fact that Nobushige&apos;s older brother and uncle are vassals of Tokugawa family, it is said that there was defamation from vassals of Toyotomi that &apos;Shigenobu is a spy of the Tokugawa side&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can&apos;t be proved that he refused the preferential condition proposed by Ieyasu because of loyalty to the Toyotomi family, but adversely, based on the fact that Nobushige&apos;s older brother and uncle were vassals of the Tokugawa family, it is said that there was defamation from vassals of Toyotomi that &apos;Shigenobu is a spy of the Tokugawa side.&apos;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can&apos;t be proved that he refused the preferential condition proposed by Ieyasu because of loyalty to the Toyotomi family, but adversely, based on the fact that Nobushige&apos;s older brother and uncle were vassals of the Tokugawa family, it is said that there was defamation from vassals of Toyotomi that &apos;Shigenobu is a spy of the Tokugawa side.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="145">
<j>既に触れたように幸村は後の時代に創られた名前のため信之が“信繁”ではなく“幸村”と言う訳もなく、後世の脚色であると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, it is impossible that Nobushige said &apos;Yukimura&apos;, not &apos;Nobushige&apos; because Yukimura is a name created later, so it seems to be a dramatization in later generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, it is impossible that Nobushige said &apos;Yukimura&apos; instead of &apos;Nobushige&apos; because the Yukimura name was created later, so it seems to be a dramatization of later generations.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, it is impossible that Nobushige said &apos;Yukimura&apos; instead of &apos;Nobushige&apos; because the Yukimura name was created later, so it seems to be a dramatization of later generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>後世の真田関係の資料は信繁を「幸村」として神格化させる動きがあり、真田信繁関係の資料の信憑性には疑問がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a trend to deify Shigenobu as &apos;Yukimura&apos; in documents about Sanada in later generations, and credibility of documents about Nobushige Sanada opens to question.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a trend to deify Shigenobu as &apos;Yukimura&apos; in documents about Sanada in later generations, and the credibility of documents about Nobushige Sanada is open to question.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a trend to deify Shigenobu as &apos;Yukimura&apos; in documents about Sanada in later generations, and the credibility of documents about Nobushige SANADA is open to question.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="147">
<j>九度山に無名のまま朽ちる筈だった信繁を、将帥として召しだしてくれたことに感謝はあるだろうが、豊臣譜代の臣でもないのに、そこまで豊家に恩を感じていたか疑問である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Nobushige might have been thankful for the Toyotomi family for taking him as a commander when he had been supposed to die in Kudoyama obscurely, it is doubtful that he was so grateful for the Toyotomi family even though he was not a hereditary vassal of Toyotomi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Nobushige might have been grateful to the Toyotomi family for taking him as a commander when he was supposed to die in obscurity in Kudoyama, it is doubtful that he was so grateful to the Toyotomi family even though he wasn&apos;t a hereditary vassal of Toyotomi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Nobushige might have been grateful to the Toyotomi family for taking him as a commander when he was supposed to die in obscurity in Kudoyama, it is doubtful that he was so grateful to the Toyotomi family even though he wasn&apos;t a hereditary vassal of Toyotomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="148">
<j>真田信繁の方が実は長男で信之が実は次男なのだが、信繁の母の方が身分が低いので長男と次男を入れ換えられたという異説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another theory that Nobushige Sanada was actually the oldest son and Nobuyuki was the second son, but they were switched because Nobushige&apos;s mother was of lower birth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another theory that Nobushige Sanada was actually the oldest son and Nobuyuki was the second son, but they were switched because Nobushige&apos;s mother was of lower birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another theory that Nobushige SANADA was actually the oldest son and Nobuyuki was the second son, but they were switched because Nobushige&apos;s mother was of lower birth.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>源三郎、源二郎の順序入れ替わりの謎もその傍証の一つとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the mystery of switched order of Genzaburo and Genjiro is one of the collateral evidences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the mystery of the switched order of Genzaburo and Genjiro is an item of collateral evidence.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the mystery of the switched order of Genzaburo and Genjiro is an item of collateral evidence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="150">
<j>徳川家康があの世に行ったら酒を飲み交わしたい人物であると言ったと逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote that Ieyasu Tokugawa said that he wanted to drink with Nobushige in afterlife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote that Ieyasu Tokugawa said he wanted to drink with Nobushige in the afterlife.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA said he wanted to drink with Nobushige in the afterlife.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="151">
<j>信繁の愛槍は、「十文字槍」というもので、両鎌槍を強化してつくられた細めの槍であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobushige&apos;s favorite spear was a &apos;Jumonji Yari&apos; (a cross-shaped spear), a rather thin spear made by enhancing ryoukamayari (spear with two hooks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobushige&apos;s favorite spear was a &apos;Jumonji Yari&apos; (a cross-shaped spear), a relatively thin weapon made by enhancing ryoukamayari (a spear with two hooks).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobushige&apos;s favorite spear was a &apos;Jumonji Yari&apos; (a cross-shaped spear), a relatively thin weapon made by enhancing ryokamayari (a spear with two hooks).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>槍の柄は朱色に塗られ、真田の赤揃えに恥じぬ名槍だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hilt of the spear was painted bright red and it was an excellent spear that lived up to Sanada&apos;s Akazonae.</e>
<cmt>「赤揃え」は「赤備え」の誤植と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hilt of the spear was painted bright red, and it was an excellent weapon that lived up to Sanada&apos;s Akazonae.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hilt of the spear was painted bright red, and it was an excellent weapon that lived up to Sanada&apos;s Akazonae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="153">
<j>大阪の陣での信繁への高評価はやや不甲斐なかった徳川勢を遠まわしに擁護するためという、うがった見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a penetrating remark that appreciation of Nobushige in Osaka no Jin is to indirectly maintain rather poor achievement of Tokugawa&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a penetrating remark that the appreciation of Nobushige in Osaka no Jin indirectly implies a somewhat poor view regarding the achievements of Tokugawa&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a penetrating remark that the appreciation of Nobushige in Osaka no Jin indirectly implies a somewhat poor view regarding the achievements of Tokugawa&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family record</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family record</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family record</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="154">
<j>信繁には多くの子がいたが、真田氏における真田信繁家としては、嫡男の大助（真田幸昌）が生まれた時には既に九度山へ幽閉されており、幸昌は大坂城にて子を作らぬまま自害、この系統は絶えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobushige had many children, but as Nobushige Sanada&apos;s family in Sanada clan, he was already confined to Kudoyama when his legitimate son Daisuke (Yukimasa SANADA) was born and Yukimasa killed himself in Osaka-jo Castle without having a child, so this line failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobushige had many children, but as Nobushige Sanada&apos;s family in the Sanada clan he was already confined to Kudoyama when his legitimate son Daisuke (Yukimasa SANADA) was born; moreover, Yukimasa killed himself in Osaka-jo Castle without having a child, so this line failed.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobushige had many children, but as Nobushige SANADA&apos;s family in the Sanada clan he was already confined to Kudoyama when his legitimate son Daisuke (Yukimasa SANADA) was born; moreover, Yukimasa killed himself in Osaka-jo Castle without having a child, so this line failed.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="155">
<j>次男の大八（真田守信）は、伊達家重臣で後に三女阿梅の夫となる片倉重長の元で姉達とともに保護され、後に元服し片倉守信となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second son Daihachi (Morinobu SANADA) was protected with his older sisters under Shigenaga KATAKURA, a senior vassal of Date family and later married to his third daughter 阿梅, and later celebrated his attainment of manhood to become Morinobu KATAKURA.</e>
<cmt>「阿梅」読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second son Daihachi (Morinobu SANADA) was protected with his older sisters under Shigenaga KATAKURA, a senior vassal of the Date family; he later married his third daughter 阿梅 and subsequently celebrated his attainment of manhood to become Morinobu KATAKURA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second son Daihachi (Morinobu SANADA) was protected with his older sisters under Shigenaga KATAKURA, a senior vassal of the Date family; he later married his third daughter 阿梅 and subsequently celebrated his attainment of manhood to become Morinobu KATAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>以降、公式に残る信繁唯一の家系・仙台真田家として現在も続く事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the line remains until now as the only official line of Nobushige, the Sendai Sanada family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the line remains until now as the only official line of Nobushige, the Sendai Sanada family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the line remains until now as the only official line of Nobushige, the Sendai Sanada family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>なお、片倉氏姓から真田姓に復したのは守信の子・真田辰信の時である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family name was restored from Katakura to Sanada at the generation of Tatsunobu SANADA, Morinobu&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family name was restored from Katakura to Sanada at the generation of Tatsunobu SANADA, Morinobu&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family name was restored from Katakura to Sanada at the generation of Tatsunobu SANADA, Morinobu&apos;s child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>真田幸村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimura Sanada</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukimura Sanada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukimura SANADA</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="158">
<j>真田幸村（さなだ ゆきむら）とは江戸時代以降に流布した、小説や講談における真田信繁の通称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukimura Sanada is an ordinary name of Shigenobu Sanada in novels and kodan storytelling that were popular in and after the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukimura Sanada is an ordinary name for Shigenobu Sanada in the novels and kodan storytelling that were popular in and after the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukimura SANADA is an ordinary name for Shigenobu SANADA in the novels and kodan storytelling that were popular in and after the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>「第一次上田合戦」（真田信繁はこの戦いに参加した証拠が無く、上杉家に人質として入っていた可能性が高い）、「関ヶ原の戦い」の前哨戦である「第二次上田合戦」で、真田十勇士等の忍者軍団を使い大活躍し、その後「大坂の役」でも奮戦するが、大坂夏の陣で力尽き討死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He play outstandingly in &apos;the first battle of Ueda&apos; (there is no evidence that Nobushige Sanada joined this battle, but it is likely that he was at the Uesugi family as a hostage) and in &apos;the second battle of Ueda&apos; which was a preliminary skirmish of &apos;the Battle of Sekigahara&apos; leading ninja (professional spy in feudal Japan highly trained in stealth and secrecy) armies including Sanada Juyushi, and then fought hard in &apos;Osaka no Eki&apos;, but was at the end of his physical life and died on the battlefield of Osaka Natsu no Jin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served outstandingly in &apos;the first battle of Ueda&apos; (there is no evidence that Nobushige Sanada joined this battle, but it is likely that he was at the Uesugi family as a hostage) and in &apos;the second battle of Ueda,&apos; which was a preliminary skirmish of &apos;the Battle of Sekigahara&apos;s leading ninja (professional spies in feudal Japan, highly trained in stealth and secrecy) armies, including Sanada Juyushi; he then fought hard in &apos;Osaka no Eki,&apos; but was at the end of his physical life and died on the battlefield of Osaka Natsu no Jin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served outstandingly in &apos;the first battle of Ueda&apos; (there is no evidence that Nobushige SANADA joined this battle, but it is likely that he was at the Uesugi family as a hostage) and in &apos;the second battle of Ueda,&apos; which was a preliminary skirmish of &apos;the Battle of Sekigahara&apos; leading ninja (professional spies in feudal Japan, highly trained in stealth and secrecy) armies, including Sanada Juyushi; he then fought hard in &apos;Osaka no Eki,&apos; but was at the end of his physical life and died on the battlefield of Osaka Natsu no Jin.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legends</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legends</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legends</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="160">
<j>元和元年5月7日、享年49で死去したものとされるが、幸村には影武者が何人も居たとの伝承があり、そのため大坂城が落ちるのを眺めつつ、豊臣秀頼を守って城を脱出し、天寿を全うしたという俗説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said he died at age 49 in June 3, 1615, but there is a common theory that Yukimura had many Kagemusha (body doubles), so he protected Hideyori Toyotomi and escaped Osaka-jo Castle watching the castle fall, and die full of years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said he died at age 49 on June 3, 1615, but there is a common theory that Yukimura had many Kagemusha (body doubles), so he protected Hideyori Toyotomi and escaped from Osaka-jo Castle, watched the castle fall and ultimately died full of years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said he died at the age of 49 on June 3, 1615, but there is a common theory that Yukimura had many Kagemusha (body doubles), so he protected Hideyori TOYOTOMI and escaped from Osaka-jo Castle, watched the castle fall and ultimately died full of years.</e>
<cmt>用語統一人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="161">
<j>「花のようなる秀頼様を、鬼のようなる真田が連れて、退きも退いたり鹿児島へ」というわらべ歌が流行したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that a children&apos;s song &apos;Devilish Sanada takes flower-like Hideyori to retreat and retreat to Kagoshima&apos; became popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that a children&apos;s song with the words, &apos;Devilish Sanada takes flower-like Hideyori to retreat and retreat to Kagoshima,&apos; became popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that a children&apos;s song with the words, &apos;Devilish Sanada takes flower-like Hideyori to retreat and retreat to Kagoshima,&apos; became popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>「真田三代記」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanada Sandaiki&apos; (three generation of the Sanada family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanada Sandaiki&apos; (three generations of the Sanada family)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanada Sandaiki&apos; (three generations of the Sanada family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="162">
<j>『真田三代記』は江戸元禄期の歴史小説であり、真田昌幸・幸村・大助の三代、親・子・孫が徳川を相手に奮闘する物語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sanada Sandaiki&quot; is a historical novel in Genroku Period in Edo period and a story in which the three generations of Masayuki, Yukimura, and Daisuke Sanada fight hard against Tokugawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sanada Sandaiki,&quot; a historical novel from the Genroku era of the Edo period, is a story in which the three generations of Masayuki, Yukimura and Daisuke Sanada fight hard against Tokugawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sanada Sandaiki,&quot; a historical novel from the Genroku era of the Edo period, is a story in which the three generations of Masayuki, Yukimura and Daisuke SANADA fight hard against Tokugawa.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>後に生まれる真田十勇士中、猿飛佐助と望月六郎をのぞいた八勇士が登場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Sanada ten braves, eight braves except Sasuke SARUTOBI and Rokuro MOCHIZUKI are in the story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the ten Sanada braves, eight (excluding Sasuke SARUTOBI and Rokuro MOCHIZUKI) are in the story.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the ten Sanada braves, eight (excluding Sasuke SARUTOBI and Rokuro MOCHIZUKI) are in the story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>これが十勇士の原型とみられ、真田もの講談の流布とともに真田人気に繋がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is considered to be the prototype of ten braves and led to popularity of Sanada as well as circulation of kodan storytelling about Sanada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is considered to be the prototype of the ten braves and led to the popularity of Sanada as well as the circulation of kodan storytelling about Sanada.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is considered to be the prototype of the ten braves and led to the popularity of Sanada as well as the circulation of kodan storytelling about Sanada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="165">
<j>土橋 治重による現代語訳がPHP文庫から刊行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Translation to current Japanese by Jiju DOBASHI is published from PHP books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A translation into modern Japanese by Jiju DOBASHI is published by PHP Books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A translation into modern Japanese by Jiju DOBASHI is published by PHP Books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>真田十勇士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanada Juyushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanada Juyushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanada Juyushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="166">
<j>真田幸村の忍者として著名な「真田十勇士」は、「真田三代記」や「難波戦記」を底本として、大正時代に一世を風靡した立川文庫の中の一冊·「猿飛佐助」が大好評を博し、その総集編のタイトルとして使われたのが始まりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that &apos;Sanada Juyushi&apos; famous as ninja of Yukimura Sanada have their origin in the title of an omnibus of &apos;Sasuke Sarutobi&apos;, a book in &quot;Tachikawa Bunko&quot; Series, which was based on &apos;Sanada Sandaiki&apos; and &apos;Namba senki&apos; and lauded all over the world in Taisho era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that &apos;Sanada Juyushi,&apos; famous as ninja of Yukimura Sanada, have their origin in the title of an omnibus of &apos;Sasuke Sarutobi,&apos; a book in the &quot;Tachikawa Bunko&quot; series, which was based on &apos;Sanada Sandaiki&apos; and &apos;Namba senki&apos; and lauded throughout the world in the Taisho era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that &apos;Sanada Juyushi,&apos; famous as ninja of Yukimura SANADA, have their origin in the title of an omnibus of &apos;Sasuke SARUTOBI,&apos; a book in the &quot;Tachikawa Bunko&quot; series, which was based on &apos;Sanada Sandaiki&apos; and &apos;Nanba senki&apos; and lauded throughout the world in the Taisho era.</e>
<cmt>人名修正スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>類似ケースに「尼子十勇士」がある（但し、資料によって弱干のバラツキが見られる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a similar case &apos;ten brave warriors of the Amago clan&apos; (there are some differences among documents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a similar case of &apos;ten brave warriors of the Amago clan&apos; (there are some differences among documents).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a similar case of &apos;ten brave warriors of the Amago clan&apos; (there are some differences among documents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="168">
<j>主に上がる名前は猿飛佐助・霧隠才蔵・根津甚八・由利鎌之助・筧十蔵・三好政康・三好政勝・望月六郎・海野六郎・穴山小助（息子の真田大助を入れるケースもある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major names include Sasuke Sarutobi, Saizo KUMOGAKURE, Jinpachi Nezu, Kamanosuke YURI, Juzo KAKEI, Masayasu MIYOSHI, Masakatsu MIYOSHI, Rokuro MOCHIZUKI, Rokuro UNNO, and Kosuke ANAYAMA (in some cases, his son Daisuke Sanada is also included).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major names include Sasuke Sarutobi, Saizo KUMOGAKURE, Jinpachi Nezu, Kamanosuke YURI, Juzo KAKEI, Masayasu MIYOSHI, Masakatsu MIYOSHI, Rokuro MOCHIZUKI, Rokuro UNNO and Kosuke ANAYAMA (in some cases his son Daisuke Sanada is also included).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major names include Sasuke SARUTOBI, Saizo KUMOGAKURE, Jinpachi NEZU, Kamanosuke YURI, Juzo KAKEI, Masayasu MIYOSHI, Masakatsu MIYOSHI, Rokuro MOCHIZUKI, Rokuro UNNO and Kosuke ANAYAMA (in some cases his son Daisuke SANADA is also included).</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="169">
<j>いわゆる現在の幸村伝説と彼をとりまく十勇士の顔ぶれが確立したのは、明治末から大正初期にかけて子どもの人気を集めた『立川文庫』からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current so-called legend of Yukimura and the member of ten braves around him have been established since &quot;Tachikawa Bunko&quot; series that was popular among children from the end of Meiji to early Taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The current so-called legend of Yukimura and the members of the ten braves around him have been established since the &quot;Tachikawa Bunko&quot; series, which was popular among children from the end of the Meiji to the early Taisho.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The current so-called legend of Yukimura and the members of the ten braves around him have been established since the &quot;Tachikawa Bunko&quot; series, which was popular among children from the end of the Meiji to the early Taisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>猿飛佐助や霧隠才蔵は架空とも言われるが、海野六郎·根津甚八·望月六郎の姓のルーツは真田一族配下の滋野一党の姓と同一であり（根津に関しては、浅井長政の忘れ形見とされる浅井井頼がモデルという説もある）、また三好兄弟はそれぞれ三好政康・三好政勝がモデルと言われている（政勝は家康側として参陣していたが）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Sasuke Sarutobi and Saizo Kirigakure are fictional, the roots of family names of Rokuro Unno, Jinpachi Nezu, and Rokuro Mochizuki are same as family names of the Shigeno family under control of the Sanada family (for Nezu, there is a theory that Iyori ASAI who is said to be a bereaved child of Nagamasa AZAI was the model), and Masayasu MIYOSHI and Masakatsu MIYOSHI are said to be models of Mishoshi brothers respectively (however, Masakatsu joined the was in Ieyasu side).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Sasuke Sarutobi and Saizo Kirigakure are fictional, the roots of family names of Rokuro Unno, Jinpachi Nezu and Rokuro Mochizuki are the same as the family names of the Shigeno family under control of the Sanada family (for Nezu, there is a theory that Iyori ASAI, who is said to be a bereaved child of Nagamasa AZAI, was the model), and Masayasu MIYOSHI and Masakatsu MIYOSHI are said to be models of the Mishoshi brothers respectively (however, Masakatsu joined the war on the Ieyasu side).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Sasuke SARUTOBI and Saizo KIRIGAKURE are fictional, the roots of family names of Rokuro UNNO, Jinpachi NEZU and Rokuro MOCHIZUKI are the same as the family names of the Shigeno family under control of the Sanada family (for Nezu, there is a theory that Iyori ASAI, who is said to be a bereaved child of Nagamasa AZAI, was the model), and Masayasu MIYOSHI and Masakatsu MIYOSHI are said to be models of the Mishoshi brothers respectively (however, Masakatsu joined the war on the Ieyasu side).</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 1990+1997二世(id:133705), 模様砂漠(id:254067), 津軽為久(id:43478), 0null0(id:582), なみなみなみ(id:140780), Lupinoid(id:68), 久慈川(id:176153), バオール(id:139300), ブレイズマン(id:183852), でここ(id:9565), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), らりた(id:1327), 男梅(id:288554), カイの迷宮(id:72682), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), A-Taul(id:41790), Ryulong(id:92427), 日陰のコスモス(id:3802), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Point136(id:211299), OptimiEditor(id:183947), Shimoxx(id:9332), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Kouko0515(id:100370), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Ajax(id:11202), ゆず湯(id:190382), Moltke(id:17553), 松茸(id:27535), Seibuabina(id:37532), SMR(id:39987), おいかわ(id:55628), 樒(id:35770), Kagetudo(id:163875), 恢徳野人(id:50207), Interregnum(id:25269), Xqbot(id:273540), Ratsalad(id:61082), R2d2(id:48878), Junger(id:10282), Jmho(id:10472), ドルチェット(id:46458), Sheepech(id:111676), Yu-ki-na(id:115957), Harupri(id:133581), Chocoyoshi(id:170796), ひろっきー(id:87284), ＩＤＳ(id:49634), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Gussan01(id:91018), Loveless(id:129239), Kensyusou(id:73011), Yosemite(id:5808), Kz(id:18320), KASAGI(id:24405), LERK(id:4460), HidE(id:14357), ナガコマ(id:131900), 水野白楓(id:22811), Gori(id:13656), Anton21(id:158479), Aboshi(id:9318), Kaeruh(id:68419), Carkuni(id:79281), Newport8865(id:71168), Gazelle(id:54447), Noritada(id:687), Miya(id:1881), こいつぅ(id:2105), Kuma83(id:31177), っ(id:4481), T@ka(id:12814), Eskimbot(id:29676), HI(id:72996), 笹船団子(id:178738), Hyman-roth0512(id:48989), Taketa(id:64706), Jazzy(id:3202), 磯多申紋(id:36455), ファービィ(id:129184), 丁度氷(id:64000), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Blowback(id:173308), Revolução dos Cravos(id:220107), K3104(id:10350), Yas(id:739), Etoa(id:20987), Tinecici(id:192914), Calvero(id:38360), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), M-sho-gun(id:88956), 生涯一薩摩人(id:75048), ニコタマ二子多摩川(id:228848), Tears for Asia(id:61412), GoGoDoll(id:131511), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Tiyoringo(id:70026), モコ子(id:186830), Suppy99(id:306984), 小者(id:172526), Shota(id:10854), ルプス・サンフィッシュ・フヨウ(id:112117), Tietew(id:4054), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Koon16000(id:43615), LuckyStar Kid(id:79561), Wybot(id:81801), TT(id:46431), ちょーばみ(id:194335), Game-M(id:86301), Extrahitz(id:26245), 味っ子(id:17086), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Jason1208(id:101327), Uraios(id:72687), 難民(id:4644), Scchiang(id:27217), にゃ(id:89329), Lafen(id:307618), Izayohi(id:13095), Sat.K(id:3751), Beckia(id:273166), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kuro-hato(id:34041), ゐ(id:795), Fromm(id:71291), Nonnonba(id:124424), Yoshinba(id:49993), 663highland(id:18755), Safkan(id:423), オナガドリ(id:15179), Louperibot(id:128971), Machine gun(id:16921), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>