<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土御門泰重</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>土御門 泰重（つちみかど やすしげ、天正14年1月8日 (旧暦)（1586年2月26日）－寛文元年8月19日 (旧暦)（1661年9月12日））は、江戸時代初期の公卿・陰陽家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO (February 26th, 1586 ~ September 12th, 1661) is a Kugyo (a court noble of some rank) and Onmyoka (a diviner) of the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO (February 26th, 1586 ~ September 12th, 1661) is a Kugyo (a court noble of some rank) and Onmyoka (a diviner) of the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasushige TSUCHIMIKADO (February 26, 1586-September 12, 1661) is a Kugyo (Court noble) and Inyoka (the Yin and Yang school of philosophy) of the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>日付表記、記号を修正。「公卿、陰陽家」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストにより修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>土御門久脩の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A son of Hisanaga TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A son of Hisanaga TSUCHIMIKADO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Hisanaga TSUCHIMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>文章のスタイルに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は織田信重の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Nobushige ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Nobushige ODA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Nobushige ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に土御門泰広・土御門隆俊・土御門泰福らがいる（ただし、泰福の父については諸説あり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are Yasuhiro TSUCHIMIKADO, Takatoshi TSUCHIMIKADO, Yasutomi TSUCHIMIKADO among his children (however, the opinion is divided regarding the father of Yasutomi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are Yasuhiro TSUCHIMIKADO, Takatoshi TSUCHIMIKADO, Yasutomi TSUCHIMIKADO among his children (however, the opinion is divided regarding the father of Yasutomi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are Yasuhiro TSUCHIMIKADO, Takatoshi TSUCHIMIKADO, Yasutomi TSUCHIMIKADO among his children (however, the opinion is divided regarding the father of Yasutomi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>弟は倉橋家初代倉橋泰吉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brother is Yasuyoshi KURAHASHI, the founder of the Kurahashi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother was Yasuyoshi KURAHASHI, the founder of the Kurahashi family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother was Yasuyoshi KURAHASHI, the founder of the Kurahashi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>父は豊臣秀次の事件に連座して失脚したため、一時衰微していたが、豊臣秀吉死後の慶長8年（1603年）に元服して正六位上右近将監兼蔵人に任じられ、同17年（1612年）には中務大丞に転じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though his family was once fell on bad time as his father lost his position involved in intrigue of the incident of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, Yasushige passed Genpuku (ceremony of attaining manhood) in 1603 after the death of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and was designated as Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade, Ukonshogen and Kuraudo (keeper of imperial archives), and promoted to Nakatsukasa Taijo in 1612.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though his family was once fell on bad time as his father lost his position while involved in intrigue during the incident of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, Yasushige passed Genpuku (ceremony of attaining manhood) in 1603 after the death of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and was designated as Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade, Ukonshogen and Kuraudo (keeper of imperial archives), and promoted to Nakatsukasa Taijo in 1612.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though his family was once fell on bad time as his father lost his position while involved in intrigue during the incident of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, Yasushige passed genpuku (ceremony of attaining manhood) in 1603 after the death of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and was designated as Shorokuinojo Ukone no shogen and Kurodo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade, Lieutenant of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards and Chamberlain), and promoted to Nakatsukasa Taijo in 1612.</e>
<cmt>Genpukuを小文字に。スペースを削除。「正六位上右近将監兼蔵人」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、家業の暦学において失態があり、元和 (日本)2年（1616年）に賀茂氏系の幸徳井友景に暦学の権限を譲る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as he failed in his family business, the studies on the calendar system, he gave away the authority of the study to Tomokage KOTOKUI of the Kamo clan in 1616.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as he failed in his family business, the studies on the calendar system, he gave away the authority of the study to Tomokage KOTOKUI of the Kamo clan in 1616.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as he failed in his family business, the studies on the calendar system, he gave away the authority of the study to Tomokage KOTOKUI of the Kamo clan in 1616.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その結果、2年後には友景は陰陽頭に任じられ、泰重は後に天文博士から左兵衛督に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Tomokage was designated as Onmyo no kami (The head) and Yasushige was transferred from Tenmon no hakase (A scholar of astronomy) to Sahyoe no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Tomokage was designated as Onmyo no kami (The head) and Yasushige was transferred from Tenmon no hakase (A scholar of astronomy) to Sahyoe no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Tomokage was designated as Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Bureau of Divination) and Yasushige was transferred from Tenmon hakase (master of astronomy) to Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards), two years later.</e>
<cmt>「2年後」を追加。「陰陽頭、天文博士、左兵衛督」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、後に友景と不仲になり土御門家_(安倍氏)による陰陽道再興を志向したために、陰陽道の権限を巡って阿倍氏系土御門家と賀茂氏系幸徳井家の長期にわたる内紛の原因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as he got into bad terms with Tomokage later and he also tried to recover the status of Onmyodo (Japanese way of Yin-Yang principles) by the hand of Tsuchimikado clan (the Abe clan), it caused long conflicts between the Abe clan line Tsuchimikado family and the Kamo clan line Kotokui family over authenticity in Onmyodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as he got into bad terms with Tomokage later and he also tried to recover the status of Onmyodo (Japanese way of Yin-Yang principles) by the hand of the Tsuchimikado clan (the Abe clan), it caused a long conflict between the Abe clan line Tsuchimikado family and the Kamo clan line Kotokui family over authenticity in Onmyodo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as he got into bad terms with Tomokage later and he also tried to recover the status of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements) by the hand of the Tsuchimikado clan (the Abe clan), it caused a long conflict between the Abe clan line Tsuchimikado family and the Kamo clan line Kotokui family over authenticity in Onmyodo.</e>
<cmt>「陰陽道」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>寛永12年1月5日 (旧暦)（1635年2月22日）に従三位となり、慶安2年（1649年）に従二位まで昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) on February 22, 1635 and climb up to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 1649.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) on February 22, 1635 and climb up to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 1649.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) on February 22, 1635 and climb up to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 1649.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>69歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日記に『泰重卿記』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left Yasushige kyoki (Diary of Yasushige).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He left Yasushige kyoki (Diary of Yasushige).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He left &quot;Yasushige kyoki&quot; (Diary of Yasushige).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>