<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>斎藤利三</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimitsu SAITO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimitsu SAITO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimitsu SAITO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>斎藤 利三（さいとう としみつ）は、戦国時代 (日本)から安土桃山時代にかけての武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimitsu SAITO was a warlord who lived from the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) of Japanese history until the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimitsu SAITO was a warlord who lived from the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) of Japanese history until the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimitsu SAITO was a warlord who lived from the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States) of Japanese history until the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除、Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明智五宿老の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the five shukuro (dignitaries of samurai class) of Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>C列の「五宿老」は翻訳に使用しませんでした。不要であれば削除してください。代わりに、「宿老」の項目を追加しました。「明智五宿老」：「明智光秀の5人の宿老」と読み替えて訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the five shukuro (consular dignitaries of the samurai class) of Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>unclear as to what the role of the shukuro is, so difficult to render accurately in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the five shukuro (consular dignitaries of the samurai class) of Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>尾張国の織田信長の家臣である明智光秀の家老として有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimitsu SAITO is famous as the chief retainer of Mitsuhide AKECHI, a retainer of Nobunaga ODA, who ruled Owari Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimitsu SAITO is famous for having been the chief retainer of Nobunaga ODA&apos;s vassal Mitsuhide AKECHI, who ruled Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimitsu SAITO is famous for having been the chief retainer of Nobunaga ODA&apos;s vassal Mitsuhide AKECHI, who ruled Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>斎藤道三以前の美濃国斎藤氏の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was descended from the Saito clan in Mino Province, which was headed by Dosan SAITO when he was born.</e>
<cmt>「斎藤道三以前の美濃国斎藤氏」：「斉藤利三が生誕した時に斉藤道三が当主であった美濃国斉藤氏」と読み替えて訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family was descended from the Saito clan of Mino Province, which was headed by Dosan SAITO at the time he was born.</e>
<cmt>this entry uses 「美濃国」, while other sections use 「美濃地」.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family was descended from the Saito clan of Mino Province, which was headed by Dosan SAITO at the time he was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父は斎藤利賢、母は蜷川親順の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Toshikata SAITO, and his mother was a daughter of Chikakazu NINAGAWA (蜷川親順).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Toshikata SAITO, and his mother was a daughter of Chikakazu NINAGAWA (蜷川親順).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Toshikata SAITO, and his mother was a daughter of Chikakazu NINAGAWA (蜷川親順).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母を明智光秀の妹、光秀の姪にあたるとする説もあるが、光秀（1528年生れ）と利三（1534年生れ）の年齢差から生物学上ありえない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to other views, his mother was a younger sister or niece of Mitsuhide AKECHI; however, this is biologically impossible in light of the age difference between Mitsuhide (born in 1528) and Toshimitsu (born in 1534).</e>
<cmt>「母を明智光秀の妹、光秀の姪にあたるとする説」：原文の意味が不明です。「明智光秀の妹または姪にあたる」と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another version holds that his mother was a younger sister or niece of Mitsuhide AKECHI; however, this is biologically impossible in light of the age difference between Mitsuhide (born in 1528) and Toshimitsu (born in 1534).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another version holds that his mother was a younger sister or niece of Mitsuhide AKECHI; however, this is biologically impossible in light of the age difference between Mitsuhide (born in 1528) and Toshimitsu (born in 1534).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただし、明智光秀の生年（1528年）は有力な説であって、それより以前に生まれた可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Notwithstanding the above, the view that Mitsuhide AKECHI was born in 1528 is not decisive but merely prevails over other views; therefore, he might have been born earlier.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notwithstanding the above, although the view that Mitsuhide AKECHI was born in 1528 is the prevailing, not the definitive view, and there is the possibility that he might have been born earlier.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notwithstanding the above, although the view that Mitsuhide AKECHI was born in 1528 is the prevailing, not the definitive view, and there is the possibility that he might have been born earlier.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、年上の甥、姪は生物学的に存在するので光秀の姪という説は否定できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is biologically possible to have an elder nephew/niece; therefore, the view that Toshimitsu&apos;s mother was Mitsuhide&apos;s niece cannot be denied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, because it is biologically possible to have an elder nephew/niece, the version maintaining that Toshimitsu&apos;s mother was Mitsuhide&apos;s niece cannot be denied outright.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, because it is biologically possible to have an elder nephew/niece, the version maintaining that Toshimitsu&apos;s mother was Mitsuhide&apos;s niece cannot be denied outright.</e>
<cmt>Toshimitsu’s、Mitsuhide’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その母は、石谷光政に再嫁し、娘・菜々（長宗我部元親室）をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimitsu&apos;s mother married Mitsumasa ISHIGAI a second time and bore a daughter, Nana, who became the lawful wife of Motochika CHOSOKABE later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimitsu&apos;s mother remarried, to Mitsumasa ISHIGAI, and bore a daughter, Nana, who was to become the lawful wife of Motochika CHOSOKABE.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimitsu&apos;s mother remarried, to Mitsumasa ISHIGAI, and bore a daughter, Nana, who was to become the lawful wife of Motochika CHOSOKABE.</e>
<cmt>Toshimitsu’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>前室は斎藤道三の娘、後室は稲葉一鉄の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimitsu&apos;s first lawful wife was a daughter of Dosan SAITO, and his second lawful wife was a daughter of Ittetsu INABA.</e>
<cmt>「前室」、「後室」：それぞれ「最初の正室」、「二番目の正室」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimitsu&apos;s first lawful wife was a daughter of Dosan SAITO, and his second lawful wife was a daughter of Ittetsu INABA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimitsu&apos;s first lawful wife was a daughter of Dosan SAITO, and his second lawful wife was a daughter of Ittetsu INABA.</e>
<cmt>Toshimitsu’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>子に斎藤利宗、斎藤三存。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had two sons: Toshimune SAITO and Mitsunaka SAITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had two sons: Toshimune SAITO and Mitsunaka SAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had two sons: Toshimune SAITO and Mitsunaka SAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>娘の福（春日局）は稲葉重通の養女となり、江戸幕府の第3代将軍となる徳川家光の乳母となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughter Fuku, who assumed the name of Kasuga no Tubone later, was adopted by Shigemichi INABA, and served Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, who became the third shogun of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) later, as a wet nurse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughter, Fuku, who later assumed the name of Kasuga no Tubone, was adopted by Shigemichi INABA, and later served as a wet nurse for Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, who was to become the third shogun of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>assuming from the time frame that she was Iemitsu&apos;s wet nurse.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughter, Fuku, who later assumed the name of Kasuga no Tsubone, was adopted by Shigemichi INABA, and later served as a wet nurse for Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, who was to become the third shogun of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Kasuga no Tubone→Kasuga no Tsuboneに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>通称は斎藤内蔵助。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimitsu was commonly known as Kuranosuke SAITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimitsu was commonly known as Kuranosuke SAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimitsu was commonly known as Kuranosuke SAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lifelong History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lifelong History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>天文3年（1534年）、斎藤利賢の次男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimitsu SAITO was born in 1534 as the second son of Toshikata SAITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimitsu SAITO was born in 1534 as the second son of Toshikata SAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimitsu SAITO was born in 1534 as the second son of Toshikata SAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>はじめ斎藤義龍、次いで稲葉一鉄に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his early days, he served Yoshitatsu SAITO and then Ittetsu INABA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He first entered into the service of Yoshitatsu SAITO, and then Ittetsu INABA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He first entered into the service of Yoshitatsu SAITO, and then Ittetsu INABA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし天正8年（1580年）に稲葉一鉄と喧嘩別れし、明智光秀との縁戚関係から光秀に仕えるようになったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said, however, that he quarreled and parted ways with Ittetsu INABA in 1580, which resulted in him serving Mitsuhide AKECHI with whom he had kinship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said, however, that he quarreled and parted ways with Ittetsu INABA in 1580, which resulted in him going into the service of Mitsuhide AKECHI, owing to their shared relationship of kinship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said, however, that he quarreled and parted ways with Ittetsu INABA in 1580, which resulted in him going into the service of Mitsuhide AKECHI, owing to their shared relationship of kinship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>光秀には重用され、明智秀満と並ぶ明智氏筆頭家老として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was taken into Mitsuhide&apos;s confidence and held, along with Hidemitsu AKECHI, the office of the leading chief retainer of the Akechi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was taken into Mitsuhide&apos;s confidence and held, along with Hidemitsu AKECHI, the office of leading chief retainer of the Akechi clan.</e>
<cmt>unclear as to the retainer ranking system and roles.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was taken into Mitsuhide&apos;s confidence and held, along with Hidemitsu AKECHI, the office of leading chief retainer of the Akechi clan.</e>
<cmt>Mitsuhide’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>光秀の丹波平定後、1万石を与えられて丹波国黒井城主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Mitsuhide&apos;s subjugation of Tanba, Toshimitsu was given a fief of 10 thousand koku and became the lord of Kuroi Castle in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Mitsuhide&apos;s subjugation of Tanba, Toshimitsu was given a fief of 10 thousand koku, and became the lord of Kuroi Castle in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Mitsuhide&apos;s subjugation of Tanba, Toshimitsu was given a fief of 10 thousand koku, and became the lord of Kuroi-jo Castle in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>Mitsuhide’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正、Kuroi-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>天正10年（1582年）、光秀が織田信長に対する謀反（本能寺の変）を計画し、それを秀満と利三だけに打ち明けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, Mitsuhide plotted a rebellion against Nobunaga ODA, which led to the Honnoji Incident, and revealed this plot only to Hidemitsu and Toshimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, Mitsuhide hatched a plot against Nobunaga ODA, which resulted in the Honnoji Incident; he revealed his plot only to Hidemitsu and Toshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, Mitsuhide hatched a plot against Nobunaga ODA, which resulted in the Honno-ji Incident; he revealed his plot only to Hidemitsu and Toshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>the Honno-ji Incidentとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>秀満は賛成したが、利三はその無謀さから反対したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Hidemitsu was in favor of the plot but that Toshimitsu was against it because he considered it too reckless.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Hidemitsu was in favor of the plot but that Toshimitsu was opposed, considering it too reckless.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Hidemitsu was in favor of the plot but that Toshimitsu was opposed, considering it too reckless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし主君の命令には逆らえず、結局は本能寺の変に首謀者の一人として参加せざるを得なくなったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed, however, that he could not disobey the order of his lord and was finally forced to become involved in the Honnoji Incident as one of the masterminds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed, however, that he could not disobey the order of his lord, and was in the end compelled to take part in the Honnoji Incident as one of the principle co-conspirators.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed, however, that he could not disobey the order of his lord, and was in the end compelled to take part in the Honno-ji Incident as one of the principle co-conspirators.</e>
<cmt>the Honno-ji Incidentとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>本能寺にて信長を討った後、中国地方から引き返してきた豊臣秀吉との山崎の戦いでは先鋒として活躍するが、敗れて逃走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After killing Nobunaga at Honnoji Temple, he played a lively part in a battle against Hideyoshi Toyotomi, who had returned from the Chugoku Region, (the Battle of Yamazaki), serving as one of the vanguard; however, the forces led by him were defeated, which resulted in him fleeing.</e>
<cmt>「敗れて逃走した」：「敗れる」の主語は、「利三が率いた軍勢」としました。利三は参加者の一人であり、彼だけが敗れたわけではないので、利三を主語にすると不自然に感じられるからです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After succesfuly doing away with Nobunaga at Honnoji Temple, he took an active role in the Battle of Yamazaki, which was fought against Hideyoshi Toyotomi upon his return from the Chugoku Region; however, his forces were routed and he fled.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After succesfuly doing away with Nobunaga at Honno-ji Temple, he took an active role in the Battle of Yamazaki, which was fought against Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI upon his return from the Chugoku region; however, his forces were routed and he fled.</e>
<cmt>Honno-ji Templeとし、Hideyoshi Toyotomi→Hideyoshi TOYOTOMIに修正、Regionの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その後、秀吉の執拗な捜索により近江国堅田で捕縛され、六条河原で斬首となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he was arrested at Katata in Omi Province as a result of Hideyoshi&apos;s persistent manhunt and then beheaded at Rokujogawara (the execution ground that was located at Kamogawa River side).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi had him pursued, and was eventually arrested at Katata in Omi Province, and then beheaded at Rokujogawara (the execution ground located on the bank of the Kamogawa River).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi had him pursued, and was eventually arrested at Katata in Omi Province, and then beheaded at Rokujogawara (the execution ground located on the bank of the Kamo-gawa River).</e>
<cmt>Kamo-gawa Riverとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>享年49。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 49 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 49 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 49.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>磔刑にされたともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that he was crucified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that he was crucified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that he was crucified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>首もしくは胴体は光秀とともに本能寺に晒されたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his neck and body, along with Mitsuhide&apos;s ones, were gibbeted at Honnoji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his head and body, along with Mitsuhide&apos;s, were gibbeted at Honnoji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his head and body, along with Mitsuhide&apos;s, were gibbeted at Honno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Mitsuhide’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正、Honno-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>のち利三の首は彼と親交の深かった絵師の海北友松により京都市左京区浄土寺真如町の真正極楽寺へ葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Toshimitsu&apos;s neck was buried by a painter named Yusho KAIHOKU in Shinshogokurakuji Temple located at Jodojishinnyo-cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, as it is known today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimitsu&apos;s head was subsequently buried by a painter named Yusho KAIHOKU, within the precints of the Shinshogokurakuji Temple located in Jodojishinnyo-cho of Sakyo Ward in Kyoto City, as it is known today.</e>
<cmt>gammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimitsu&apos;s head was subsequently buried by a painter named Yusho KAIHOKU, within the precints of the Shinsho Gokuraku-ji Temple located in Jodojishinnyo-cho of Sakyo Ward in Kyoto City, as it is known today.</e>
<cmt>Toshimitsu’sのアポストロフィーを半角に修正、Shinshogokurakuji Temple→Shinsho Gokuraku-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality and anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality and anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile and Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>人物→統一リストの表記に修正、頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>明智光秀に仕えたのはわずか2年ほどであるにも関わらず、明智光秀古参の家臣より重用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimitsu served Mitsuhide AKECHI for as short as around two years, but held a more important position than other retainers who served Mitsuhide for a longer period did.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Toshimitsu served Mitsuhide AKECHI for a period of no longer than about two years, he held a more important position than other retainers who had been in the service of Mitsuhide for longer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Toshimitsu served Mitsuhide AKECHI for a period of no longer than about two years, he held a more important position than other retainers who had been in the service of Mitsuhide for longer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>これは単なる縁者関係だけではなく、斎藤利三が武将としての力量に優れていたことを示すものでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This indicates that Toshimitsu SAITO held such an important position not only because he had kinship with Mitsuhide AKECHI but also because he was sufficiently competent to act as a warlord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This indicates that Toshimitsu SAITO held such an important position not solely due to his kinship with Mitsuhide AKECHI, but because he had demonstrated the superior capabilities of a warlord.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This indicates that Toshimitsu SAITO held such an important position not solely due to his kinship with Mitsuhide AKECHI, but because he had demonstrated the superior capabilities of a warlord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>現在の歴史小説などでは明智光秀の忠臣として描かれ、本能寺の変でも積極的に賛意を示したとされることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is depicted as a loyal retainer of Mitsuhide Akechi in contemporary historical novels and many people assume that he actively expressed his approval of the plot to assassinate Nobunaga ODA at Honnoji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「本能寺の変でも積極的に賛意を示した」：「本能寺で織田信長を暗殺する計画に積極的に賛意を示した」と読み替えて訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is depicted as a loyal retainer of Mitsuhide Akechi in contemporary historical novels, and many people therefore assume that he actively supported the plot to attack Nobunaga ODA at Honnoji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is depicted as a loyal retainer of Mitsuhide AKECHI in contemporary historical novels, and many people therefore assume that he actively supported the plot to attack Nobunaga ODA at Honno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Mitsuhide Akechi→Mitsuhide AKECHIに修正、Honno-ji Templeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>だが、反対したともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, others say that he objected to that plot.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are those, however, who say that he opposed that plot.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are those, however, who say that he opposed that plot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>理由は明智光秀が後世に不忠不義の臣として残ること、織田信長を討てても他の諸大名がその方法から支持しないことを見抜いていたためとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is grounded on the view that Toshimitsu foresaw that, should the plot be set into action, Mitsuhide AKECHI would earn his place as a disloyal and immoral vassal in history and that, even if Mitsuhide succeeded in killing Nobunaga ODA, other feudal lords would criticize the means to kill Nobunaga and would not support Mitsuhide</e>
<cmt>「その方法から支持しない」：「その方法を批判し、明智光秀を支持しない」と読み替えて訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That view is grounded on the fact that Toshimitsu foresaw that, should the plot be set into action, Mitsuhide AKECHI would earn his place as a disloyal and immoral vassal in history, and that even if Mitsuhide succeeded in eliminating Nobunaga ODA, other feudal lords would not approve of the methods he employed, and would not offer him their support.</e>
<cmt>grammar, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That view is grounded on the fact that Toshimitsu foresaw that, should the plot be set into action, Mitsuhide AKECHI would earn his place as a disloyal and immoral vassal in history, and that even if Mitsuhide succeeded in eliminating Nobunaga ODA, other feudal lords would not approve of the methods he employed, and would not offer him their support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>稲葉氏から明智氏に鞍替えしたとき、稲葉一鉄は信長に対して斎藤利三の帰参を求め、織田信長も斎藤利三に稲葉氏への帰参を促した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Toshimitsu left the Inaba clan for the Akechi clan, Ittetsu INABA requested Nobunaga ODA to cause him to return to the service of Toshimitsu, and Nobunaga recommended Toshimitsu to do so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Toshimitsu left the Inaba clan for the Akechi clan, Ittetsu INABA requested that Nobunaga ODA intervene and have him returned to the service of the Inaba clan, a suggestion with wich Nobunaga was in agreement, and therefore recommended that Toshimitsu be returned to the service of the Inaba clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Toshimitsu left the Inaba clan for the Akechi clan, Ittetsu INABA requested that Nobunaga ODA intervene and have him returned to the service of the Inaba clan, a suggestion with wich Nobunaga was in agreement, and therefore recommended that Toshimitsu be returned to the service of the Inaba clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし明智光秀が「人がこだわるほどの良臣を蓄えなくては上様（織田信長）のもとで大功を挙げられませぬ」と述べて拒絶したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said, however, that Mitsuhide AKECHI, a retainer of Nobunaga ODA, rejected Nobunaga&apos;s recommendation, saying, &quot;I need to have such good retainers as to be persistently wanted by any lord so that I can render distinguished service to the Lord.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said, however, that Mitsuhide AKECHI rejected Nobunaga&apos;s recommendation, declaring, &quot;If I can&apos;t retain men of such calbier as to be persistently wanted by other lord&apos;s, I won&apos;t be capable of rendering distinguished service to my Lord (i.e., Nobunaga ODA).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said, however, that Mitsuhide AKECHI rejected Nobunaga&apos;s recommendation, declaring, &apos;If I can&apos;t retain men of such calbier as to be persistently wanted by other lord&apos;s, I won&apos;t be capable of rendering distinguished service to my Lord (i.e., Nobunaga ODA).&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをシングル・半角に修正、およびアポストロフィーを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nobunobunaga(id:117457), ドルチェット(id:46458), Nnh(id:474), Aotake(id:34929), Moltke(id:17553), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 小者(id:172526), Kagetudo(id:163875), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), YurikBot(id:18605), R28Bot(id:177951), 寂華(id:83725), けんち(id:5147), KASAGI(id:24405), Jmho(id:10472), Orihakat(id:99279), ToePeu.bot(id:157833), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>