<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原道雅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mishmasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Mishmasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michimasa</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原道雅（ふじわら の みちまさ、正暦三年（992年） - 天喜二年7月20日 (旧暦)（1054年8月25日））は平安時代の歌人・公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mishmasa (992 - August 25, 1054) was a court noble and a tank poet of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Mishmasa (992 - August 25, 1054) was a court noble and a tank poet of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michimasa (992 - August 31, 1054) was a court noble and a tanka poet of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Michimasaに訂正しました。グレゴリオ歴に訂正しました。tankaスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称は道雅三位、荒三位など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was more commonly known as &quot;Michimasa sanmi&quot; or &quot;Ara sanmi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was more commonly known as &quot;Michimasa sanmi&quot; or &quot;Ara sanmi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was more commonly known as Michimasa Sanmi or Ara Sanmi.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;削除しました。Sanmi大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>中関白藤原道隆、高階貴子の孫であり、一条帝皇后宮藤原定子の甥にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the grandson of FUJIWARA no Michitaka of the Naka no kanpaku family (literally, &quot;the second candidate family of Chief Advisor to the Emperor&quot;) and TAKASHINA no Kishi (a female poet), and the nephew of FUJIWARA no Teishi, the empress of Emperor Ichijiyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the grandson of FUJIWARA no Michitaka of the Naka no kanpaku family (literally, &quot;the second candidate family of Chief Advisor to the Emperor&quot;) and TAKASHINA no Kishi (a female poet), and the nephew of FUJIWARA no Teishi, the empress of Emperor Ichijiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the grandson of FUJIWARA no Michitaka of the Naka no kanpaku family (literally, &quot;the second candidate family of Chief Advisor to the Emperor&quot;) and TAKASHINA no Kishi (a female poet), and the nephew of FUJIWARA no Teishi, the empress of Emperor Ichijiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は儀同三司藤原伊周、母は大納言源重光女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Korechika, who was called &quot;Gidosanshi&quot;, and his mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Shigemitsu, who served as Dainagon (the chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was FUJIWARA no Korechika, who was called &quot;Gidosanshi&quot;, and his mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Shigemitsu, who served as Dainagon (the chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Korechika, who was Gido-sanshi minister, and his mother was a daughter of MINAMOTO no Shigemitsu, who served as Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>儀同三司→Gido-sanshi ministercalled削除しました。大納言→Dainagon (chief councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>妻は紫式部の夫山城守藤原宣孝の娘（紫式部の娘か否かは不明）で中古三十六歌仙のひとり上東門院中将をもうける（中古歌仙伝）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was married to a daughter of FUJIWARA no Nobutaka, who was Yamashiro no kami (the director of Yamashiro Province) and the husband of Shikibu MURASAKI (the author of the Tale of Genji) (although it is not known whether she was her mother), and had a child, Jotomonin no chujo, who was selected as one of Chuko sanjurokkasen (36 great waka poets, who had been not been chosen as 36 Great Poets by Fujiwara no kinto, or those of later times).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was married to a daughter of FUJIWARA no Nobutaka, who was Yamashiro no kami (the director of Yamashiro Province) and the husband of Shikibu MURASAKI (the author of the Tale of Genji) (although it is not known whether she was her mother), and had a child, Jotomonin no chujo, who was selected as one of Chuko sanjurokkasen (36 great waka poets, who had been not been chosen as 36 Great Poets by Fujiwara no kinto, or those of later times).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was married to a daughter of FUJIWARA no Nobutaka, who was Yamashiro no kami (the governer of Yamashiro Province) and the husband of Murasaki Shikibu (the author of the Tale of Genji) (although it is not known whether she was her mother), and had a child, Jotomonin no chujo, who was selected as one of Chuko sanjurokkasen (36 great waka poets, who had been not been chosen as 36 Great Poets by Fujiwara no kinto, or those of later times).</e>
<cmt>directorをgovernerに訂正しました。Murasaki Shikibuに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ほかに平惟仲女がいたが、離婚して皇藤原妍子に仕え、歌人として大和宣旨と号した（大鏡）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Okagami (literally, &quot;the Great Mirror&quot;, a historical writing), he had also been married to TAIRA no Korenaka and later divorced; then, his ex-wife served FUJIWARA no Kenshi, Emperor Sanjyo&apos;s second consort, and, as a tanka poet, she called herself &quot;Yamato no senji&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「皇藤原妍子」の表記にあるように、表記があいまいなため、調査し、説明を補っています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Okagami (literally, &quot;the Great Mirror&quot;, a historical writing), he had also been married to TAIRA no Korenaka and later divorced; then, his ex-wife served FUJIWARA no Kenshi, Emperor Sanjyo&apos;s second consort, and, as a tanka poet, she called herself &quot;Yamato no senji&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Okagami (the Great Mirror, a historical writing), he had also been married to a daughter of TAIRA no Korenaka and later divorced; then, his ex-wife served FUJIWARA no Kenshi, Emperor Sanjyo&apos;s second consort, and as a tanka poet, she called herself Yamato no senji.</e>
<cmt>括弧説明訂正しました。a daughter of 補足しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。コンマ削除しました。原文に『』がないので&quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子に僧覚助 (僧)がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a son named &quot;Kakujo&quot;, who became a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a son named &quot;Kakujo&quot;, who became a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a son named Kakujo, who was a Buddhist priest.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;削除しました。becameをwasに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>幼名を松君と言い、祖父道隆に溺愛されて育つが、長徳元年(995年)道隆は死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michimasa, who had been called &quot;Matsugimi&quot; as a child, grew up being doted on by his grandfather, Michitaka, who died in 995.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michimasa, who had been called &quot;Matsugimi&quot; as a child, grew up being doted on by his grandfather, Michitaka, who died in 995.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michimasa, who had been called Matsugimi as a child, grew up being doted on by his grandfather, Michitaka, who died in 995.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>翌年、父伊周が花山天皇に対し弓を射掛けると言う不敬事件で大宰権帥に左遷される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, his father, Korechika, was demoted to Dazaigonnosochi (vice commander of Dazaifu) as he attempted to frighten Emperor Kazan by shooting arrows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, his father, Korechika, was demoted to Dazaigonnosochi (vice commander of Dazaifu) as he attempted to frighten Emperor Kazan by shooting arrows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, his father, Korechika, was demoted to Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) as he attempted to frighten Emperor Kazan by shooting arrows.</e>
<cmt>大宰権帥→Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>長保六年(1004年)、14歳で従五位下に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1004, he was ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) when he was fourteen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1004, he was ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) when he was fourteen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1004, he was ranked Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) when he was fourteen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>寛弘八年（1011年）には東宮権亮となって敦成親王（後一条天皇）に仕え、長和五年(1016年)正月、後一条天皇践祚の際には蔵人頭に補せられ、翌月従三位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michimasa, who was designated as Togu gonnosuke (acting vice-minister who serves the imperial prince) in 1011, served Imperial Prince Atsuhira (who later became Emperor Ichijo), and in January 1016, he was appointed as Kurodo no to (the head of imperial archive keepers) when Emperor Goichijo ascended to the throne, and ranked Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in the next month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michimasa, who was designated as Togu gonnosuke (acting vice-minister who serves the imperial prince) in 1011, served Imperial Prince Atsuhira (who later became Emperor Ichijo), and in January 1016, he was appointed as Kurodo no to (the head of imperial archive keepers) when Emperor Goichijo ascended to the throne, and ranked Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in the next month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michimasa, who was designated as Togu gonnosuke (acting vice-minister who serves the imperial prince) in 1011, served Imperial Prince Atsuhira (who later became Emperor Ichijo), and in January 1016, he was appointed as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) when Emperor Goichijo ascended to the throne, and ranked Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in the next month.</e>
<cmt>東宮権亮→Togu Gon no suke (acting vice-minister who serves the imperial prince)蔵人頭→Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、同年九月に斎宮を退下し帰京した当子内親王と密通し、これを知った内親王の父三条天皇の怒りに触れて、勅勘を被った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Michimasa, who secretly had an affair with Imperial Princess Toshi, who had been back in Kyoto by September of this year after having served as Saigu (Ise shrine maiden), infuriated Emperor Sanjyo, her father, and was repudiated by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Michimasa, who secretly had an affair with Imperial Princess Toshi, who had been back in Kyoto by September of this year after having served as Saigu (Ise shrine maiden), infuriated Emperor Sanjyo, her father, and was repudiated by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Michimasa, who secretly had an affair with Imperial Princess Toshi, who had been back in Kyoto by September of this year after having served as Saigu (Ise-jingu Shrine maiden), infuriated Emperor Sanjyo, her father, and was repudiated by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Ise-jingu Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>万寿元年(1024年)12月6日に花山天皇の皇女が夜中の路上で殺され、翌朝、野犬に食われた酷たらしい姿で発見された（『小右記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (a diary of Sanesuke FUJIWARA), there was an incidence where a daughter of Emperor Kazan was murdered on a street in the midnight of December 6, 1024 and found miserably bitten up by homeless dogs in the next morning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (a diary of Sanesuke FUJIWARA), there was an incidence where a daughter of Emperor Kazan was murdered on a street the midnight of December 6, 1024 and found miserably bitten by homeless dogs the next morning.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shoyuki&quot; (a diary of Sanesuke FUJIWARA), there was an incidence where a daughter of Emperor Kazan was murdered on a street the midnight of January 14, 1025 and found miserably bitten by homeless dogs the next morning.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この事件は京の公家達を震撼させ、検非違使が捜査にあたり、翌万寿2年(1025年)7月25日に容疑者として法師隆範を捕縛、その法師隆範が藤原道雅の命で皇女を殺害したと自白する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This case frightened nobles in Kyoto and was investigated by Kebiishi (statutory office in the Heian and Kamakura periods); on July 25, 1025, the next year, Takanori, a bonze, was arrested, who confessed that he had murdered the princess as he had been ordered by Michimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This case frightened nobles in Kyoto and was investigated by Kebiishi (statutory office in the Heian and Kamakura periods); on July 25, 1025, the next year, Takanori, a bonze, was arrested, who confessed that he had murdered the princess as he had been ordered by Michimasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This case frightened court nobles in Kyoto and was investigated by kebiishi (a police and judicial chief); on August 27, 1025, Takanori, a bonze, was arrested, who confessed that he had murdered the princess as he had been ordered by Michimasa.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。the next year, 削除しました。検非違使→kebiishi (a police and judicial chief)court補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この事件は結局はうやむやにされるが、翌年の万寿三年(1026年)に左近衛中将を罷免され右京権大夫（正五位上相当官）に落とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the true murderer ended up undecided, but Michimasa was dismissed the post of Sakonenochujo (lieutenant general of Imperial Guards of the Left) and demoted to Ukyogonnodaibu (a post usually taken by nobles ranked Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the true murderer ended up undecided, Michimasa was dismissed from the post of Sakonenochujo (lieutenant general of Imperial Guards of the Left) and demoted to Ukyogonnodaibu (a post usually taken by nobles ranked Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the true murderer ended up undecided, Michimasa was dismissed from the post of Sakonenochujo (lieutenant general of Imperial Guards of the Left) and demoted to Ukyogonnodaibu (a post usually taken by nobles ranked Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、出世できぬまま天喜二年（1054年）七月、出家の直後薨ず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michimasa, who never had a chance to be promoted throughout the rest of his life, died in July 1054 immediately after he became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michimasa, who never had a chance to be promoted throughout the rest of his life, died in July 1054 immediately after he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michimasa, who never had a chance to be promoted throughout the rest of his life, died in July 1054 immediately after he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>『小右記』によると花山天皇の皇女を殺させた他、敦明親王の雑色長を凌辱した、博打場で乱行した、など乱行の噂が絶えなかったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shoyuki&quot;, rumors that he might have committed immoral, violent acts circulated one after another; besides the alleged murder of Emperor Kazan&apos;s princess, he might have humiliated the zoshikicho (the head of guards) of Imperial Prince Atsuakira, and made a scene at gambling houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shoyuki&quot;, rumors that he might have committed immoral, violent acts circulated one after another; besides the alleged murder of Emperor Kazan&apos;s princess, he might have humiliated the zoshikicho (the head of guards) of Imperial Prince Atsuakira, and made a scene at gambling houses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shoyuki&quot;, rumors that he might have committed immoral, violent acts circulated one after another; besides the alleged murder of Emperor Kazan&apos;s princess, he might have humiliated the zoshikicho (the head of guards) of Imperial Prince Atsuakira, and made a scene at gambling houses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このため、世上「荒三位」「悪三位」などと呼ばれたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That&apos;s why he was called &quot;Ara sanmi&quot; (literally, &quot;violent noble ranked Sanmi&quot;) or &quot;Aku-sanmi (&quot;bad noble ranked Sanmi&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This earned him the name &quot;Ara sanmi&quot; (literally, &quot;violent noble ranked Sanmi&quot;) or &quot;Aku-sanmi (&quot;bad noble ranked Sanmi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This earned him the name &apos;Ara sanmi&apos; (literally, &quot;violent noble ranked Sanmi&quot;) or &apos;Aku-sanmi&apos; (bad noble ranked Sanmi).</e>
<cmt>原文の『』に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。&quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>その一方和歌には巧みであり、中古三十六歌仙の1人としても知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he was good at making waka poems (31-syllable Japanese poems) and known as one of Chuko sanjurokkasen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he was good at making waka poems (31-syllable Japanese poems) and known as one of Chuko sanjurokkasen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he was good at making waka poems (31-syllable Japanese poems) and known as one of Chuko sanjurokkasen (the Medieval 36 Immortal Poets).</e>
<cmt>中古三十六歌仙、(the Medieval 36 Immortal Poets)説明補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>小倉百人一首には、次のようなの歌が取られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his waka poem has been selected in the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his waka poem has been selected in the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his waka poem has been selected in the Ogura Anthology of One Hundred Poems by One Hundred Poets:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>今はただ思ひ絶えなんとばかりを人づてならで言ふよしもがな</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now I am trying to give up on you, and I wish I could tell it to you directly, not through rumors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now I am trying to give up on you, and I wish I could tell it to you directly, not through rumors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now I am trying to give up on you, and I wish I could tell it to you directly, not through rumors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>後拾遺集の詞書には</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Goshuishu (an imperial anthology of Japanese waka, compiled in 1086 at the behest of Emperor Shirakawa), an explanatory note to his waka poem says:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Goshuishu (an imperial anthology of Japanese waka, compiled in 1086 at the behest of Emperor Shirakawa), an explanatory note to his waka poem says:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Goshuishu (an imperial anthology of Japanese waka, compiled in 1086 at the behest of Emperor Shirakawa), an explanatory note to his waka poem says:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>「伊勢の斎宮わたりよりまかり上りて侍りける人に、忍びて通ひけることを、おほやけも聞こしめして、守り女など付けさせ給ひて、忍びにも通はずなりにければ、詠み侍りける」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This waka was made when the Emperor, who came to know that a guy secretly had an affair with his daughter, the imperial princess who had served as Saigu at Ise Shrine, prevented him from seeing her again by guarding her with more of her aides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This waka was made when the Emperor, who came to know that a guy secretly had an affair with his daughter, the imperial princess who had served as Saigu at Ise Shrine, prevented him from seeing her again by guarding her with more of her aides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This waka was made when the Emperor, who came to know that a guy secretly had an affair with his daughter, the imperial princess who had served as Saigu at Ise-jingu Shrine, prevented him from seeing her again by guarding her with more of her aides.</e>
<cmt>Ise-jingu Shrineに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 桜井和人(id:19452), Masyu(id:31065), Ks8823(id:130146), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Ktmchi(id:113301), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>