<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>畠山勇子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuko HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuko HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuko HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>畠山 勇子（はたけやま ゆうこ、慶応元年（1865年）12月 - 明治24年（1891年）5月20日）は、1891年の大津事件で日露関係が緊張した際、被害者のロシア皇太子に謝罪の遺書を残して自殺した女性である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuko HATAKEYAMA (December, 1865 - May 20, 1891) is a woman who committed suicide leaving a suicide note to apologize to the victim, the Crown Prince of Russia when the relationship between Japan and Russia tensed at Otsu Incident of 1891.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuko HATAKEYAMA (December, 1865 - May 20, 1891) was a woman who committed suicide during the period the relationship between Japan and Russia became tense, leaving a suicide note to apologize to the crown prince of Russia who had been attacked by a Japanese in the Otsu Incident of 1891.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuko HATAKEYAMA (December, 1865 - May 20, 1891) was a woman who committed suicide during the period the relationship between Japan and Russia became tense, leaving a suicide note to apologize to the crown prince of Russia who had been attacked by a Japanese in the Otsu Incident of 1891.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1865年、安房国長狭郡鴨川町横渚（現・千葉県鴨川市）に畠山治平の長女として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born as the oldest daughter of Jihei HATAKEYAMA in Yokosuka, Kamogawa Town, Nagasa County, Awa Province (now Kamogawa City, Chiba Prefecture) in 1865.</e>
<cmt>「治平」を「治兵衛」とする資料もあった為読み方を「じへい」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born as the oldest daughter of Jihei HATAKEYAMA in Yokosuka, Kamogawa-cho, Nagasa County, Awa Province (present Kamogawa City, Chiba Prefecture) in 1865.</e>
<cmt>用語を統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born as the oldest daughter of Jihei HATAKEYAMA in Yokosuka, Kamogawa-cho, Nagasa County, Awa Province (present Kamogawa City, Chiba Prefecture) in 1865.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>畠山家は鴨川の農家で、かつては資産家であったが、明治維新のおりに私財を投じたため、生活は貧困であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Hatakeyama family was farming family in Kamogawa and formally capitalist, they gave all the money for the Meiji Restoration so they lived in poverty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatakeyama family had been farmer of Kamogawa and once very rich, however, at the Meiji Restoration they invested a lot of money, and later became very poor.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatakeyama family had been farmer of Kamogawa and once very rich, however, at the Meiji Restoration they invested a lot of money, and later became very poor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>5歳で父を失い、17歳で隣の千歳村（現南房総市）の平民に嫁いだが、うまくいかず23歳で離婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She lost her father at the age of 5 and married into the common people in a neighboring Chitose Village (now Minami Boso City) at the age of 17 but did not get along with it to get a divorce at the age of 23.</e>
<cmt>minamiboso</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She lost her father at the age of 5, and married a commoner in the neighboring Chitose Village (present Minamiboso City) at the age of 17, however she did not get along and divorced at the age of 23.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミス、固有名詞表記ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She lost her father at the age of 5, and married a commoner in the neighboring Chitose Village (present Minamiboso City) at the age of 17, however she did not get along and divorced at the age of 23.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>東京に出て華族の邸宅や横浜の銀行家宅の女中として働いた後、伯父の世話で日本橋区（現・中央区 (東京都)）室町の魚問屋にお針子として住み込みで奉公する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After moving to Tokyo to work as a maid at residences of the peerage and a banker in Yokohama, she served a fish wholesale store as a live-in hariko (woman doing needlework) to take care of her uncle in Nihombashi Ward (now Chuo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>お針子＝hariko (woman doing needlework)　としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After moving to Tokyo, she worked as maid at residences of the peerage and at a residence of a banker in Yokohama, and by the introduction of her uncle, she began to serve a fish wholesaler as a live-in hariko (woman doing needlework) in Muromachi, Nihonbashi Ward (present Chuo Ward, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>誤訳、訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After moving to Tokyo, she worked as maid at residences of the peerage and at a residence of a banker in Yokohama, and by the introduction of her uncle, she began to serve a fish wholesaler as a live-in hariko (woman doing needlework) in Muromachi, Nihonbashi Ward (present Chuo Ward, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>父や伯父の影響で、政治や歴史に興味を持ち、政治色の強い新聞などを熱心に読み、店の主人や同輩たちから変人とみなされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since she had interests in politics and history under the influence of her father and uncle, she read newspapers containing political elements enthusiastically so that a storekeeper and her peers considered her a freak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since she had interests in politics and history under the influence of her father and uncle, she read newspapers containing political elements enthusiastically so that a storekeeper and her peers considered her a freak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since she had interests in politics and history under the influence of her father and uncle, she read newspapers containing political elements enthusiastically so that a storekeeper and her peers considered her a freak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大津事件が起こるや、国家の有事としきりに嘆いたが、周囲は「またいつもの癖が始まった」と相手にもしなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As soon as Otsu Incident happened, she deplored a national emergency constantly but the people around her thought &apos;there&apos;s nothing unusual about her habit&apos; and paid no attention to her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as the Otsu Incident happened, she deplored and fussed that a national emergency had occurred, however, the close people ignored her fuss thinking &apos;there she goes again.&apos;</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as the Otsu Incident happened, she deplored and fussed that a national emergency had occurred, however, the close people ignored her fuss thinking &apos;there she goes again.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>5月11日来日中のロシア帝国のニコライ2世が暴漢に襲われて重傷を負う事件が発生（大津事件）、日本中が騒然となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 11, the Incident that the Russian Empire Nicholai II being in Japan was wounded seriously in the attack by a thug (Otsu Incident) happened and the whole of Japan was confused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 11, the crown prince of the Russian Empire (the Tsar&apos;s son, Tsarevich Nicholas) who would become Nicholai II (Tsarevich Nicholas II) was wounded seriously in the attack by a thug (Otsu Incident) during his visit to Japan, and people seethed in all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 11, the crown prince of the Russian Empire (the Tsar&apos;s son, Tsarevich Nicholas) who would become Nicholai II (Tsarevich Nicholas II) was wounded seriously in the attack by a thug (Otsu Incident) during his visit to Japan, and people seethed in all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そうした中、ロシア皇太子が本国からの命令で急遽神戸港から帰国の途につくことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that occasion, the Russian Empire started for home from Kobe Port in a hurry by the order from his country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such a situation, Russia decided and ordered that the crown prince of Russia should return to Russia from Kobe Port in a hurry.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a situation, Russia decided and ordered that the crown prince of Russia should return to Russia from Kobe Port in a hurry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それを知った勇子は、帰郷するからと奉公先の魚問屋を辞め、下谷の伯父の榎本六兵衛宅に押しかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuko, who knew that, quitted a fish wholesale store after coming home and went to the residence of her uncle Rokubei ENOMOTO in Shimotani uninvited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hearing that, Yuko left the fish wholesaler with an excuse that she would return to her hometown, and rushed to the residence of her uncle Rokubei ENOMOTO in Shitaya.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。固有名詞ミス、「下谷」は東京の「したや」のことです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hearing that, Yuko left the fish wholesaler with an excuse that she would return to her hometown, and rushed to the residence of her uncle Rokubei ENOMOTO in Shitaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>榎本は貿易商で、島津・毛利・山内・前田・蜂須賀ら大名家が幕府に内緒で銃を買い入れていた武器商人で、維新後は生糸の輸出で財をなしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enomoto was a trader and a weapon dealer that Daimyo (feudal lord) family such as Shimazu, Mori, Yamauchi, Maeda and Hachisuka purchased guns for the government secretly, and then he made a fortune in the exportation of raw silk thread after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enomoto was a trader and a weapon dealer from whom feudal lord families including Shimazu, Mori, Yamauchi, Maeda and Hachisuga had purchased guns secretly from the shogunate, and after the Meiji Restoration, he made a fortune by export of raw silk thread.</e>
<cmt>誤訳です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enomoto was a trader and a weapon dealer from whom feudal lord families including Shimazu, Mori, Yamauchi, Maeda and Hachisuga had purchased guns secretly from the shogunate, and after the Meiji Restoration, he made a fortune by export of raw silk thread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>勇子は伯父ならば自分の気持ちを理解してくれるだろうと考え、「このまま帰られたのでは、わざわざ京都まで行って謝罪した天皇陛下の面目が立たない」と口説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Yuko thought her uncle would understand her feelings, she urged him &apos;his Imperial Majesty who expressly went to Kyoto to apologize would lose face if the Crown Prince returns as it is.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「このまま帰られたのでは～」の文に主語「the Crown Prince」を補足してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Yuko thought her uncle would understand her thoughts, she asked him to do something, explaining &apos;if the crown prince returns like that, our Emperor who went all the way to Kyoto to apologize would lose face.&apos;</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Yuko thought her uncle would understand her thoughts, she asked him to do something, explaining &apos;if the crown prince returns like that, our Emperor who went all the way to Kyoto to apologize would lose face.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>伯父は一介の平民女性が国家の大事を案じてもどうなるものでもあるまいと諫めたが、思い詰めた勇子は汽車で京都へ旅立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although her uncle remonstrated there was no help for it even if a mere commoner concerned about a serious affair of the nation, Yuko obsessed and left for Kyoto by a train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although her uncle remonstrated with her explaining that there was no help for a mere common woman to concern about the nation&apos;s serious matters, the obsessed Yuko left for Kyoto by a train.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although her uncle remonstrated with her explaining that there was no help for a mere common woman to concern about the nation&apos;s serious matters, the obsessed Yuko left for Kyoto by a train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>勇子は京都で様々な寺を人力車で回った後、5月20日の午後7時過ぎ、「露国御官吏様」「日本政府様」「政府御中様」と書かれた嘆願書を京都府庁に投じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yuko made the rounds of the various temples in Kyoto by a rickshaw, she pitched a petition that said &apos;To the Russian Government Official&apos;, &apos;To the Japanese Government&apos; and &apos;To Government&apos; into Kyoto prefectural office after seven p.m. on May 20.</e>
<cmt>「政府御中様」の定訳不明。一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, after visiting a lot of temples by a rickshaw, Yuko presented petitions on which front were written &apos;Mr. Official of Russia,&apos; &apos;Messrs. Japanese Government&apos; and &apos;Messrs. Government&apos; to Kyoto prefectural office after seven p.m. on May 20.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。「投じた」は実際に投げたのではありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, after visiting a lot of temples by a rickshaw, Yuko presented petitions on which front were written &apos;Mr. Official of Russia,&apos; &apos;Messrs. Japanese Government&apos; and &apos;Messrs. Government&apos; to Kyoto prefectural office after seven p.m. on May 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>府庁前で死後見苦しからぬようにと両足を手拭で括って、剃刀で咽喉と胸部を深く切って自殺を謀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She tied her legs together with a towel so as not to be unsightly in front of the prefectural office and committed suicide by cutting her throat and chest with a razor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In front of the prefectural office, she tied her legs together with a towel to avoid appearing ugly after the suicide, and committed suicide by cutting her throat and chest deeply with a razor.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In front of the prefectural office, she tied her legs together with a towel to avoid appearing ugly after the suicide, and committed suicide by cutting her throat and chest deeply with a razor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかしすぐには死ぬことができず、すぐに病院に運ばれて治療が施されたが、傷の深さゆえ出血多量で絶命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since she could not die soon, she was taken to hospital to receive treatment; however, she died of a loss of blood with a deep cut.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since she could not die soon, she was taken to hospital to receive treatment; however, she died of a loss of blood with a deep cut.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since she could not die soon, she was taken to hospital to receive treatment; however, she died of a loss of blood with a deep cut.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>享年27。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age to death is 27.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>時制を直します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>当時の日本はまだ極東の弱小国であり、この事件を口実に大国ロシアに宣戦布告でもされたら国家滅亡さえ危ぶまれる、彼女はそう判断したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan was a Far Eastern lesser country in those days so that she judged there was great fear even for the fall of a nation if a big power Russia declared war on the pretext of this incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those years Japan was a lesser country of the Far East, so she thought that Japan might be destroyed if one of powers Russia declared war on the pretext of this incident.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those years Japan was a lesser country of the Far East, so she thought that Japan might be destroyed if one of powers Russia declared war on the pretext of this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>伯父や母、弟にあてた遺書は別に郵便で投函しており、総計10通を遺していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had mailed her suicide notes to her uncle, mother and younger brother separately and total 10 notes were left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had mailed her suicide notes to her uncle, mother and younger brother separately from the petitions, and the number of her letters brought the total to ten.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had mailed her suicide notes to her uncle, mother and younger brother separately from the petitions, and the number of her letters brought the total to ten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>その壮絶な死は「烈女勇子」と国家主義者が喧伝して世間に広まり、盛大な追悼式が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nationalists spread her heroic death as &apos;a chaste and strong-minded woman, Yuko&apos; to people and a grand memorial service was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The news about her brave death was spread among people by some nationalists praising her as &apos;the chaste and strong-minded woman Yuko&apos; and a grand memorial service for her was held.</e>
<cmt>文法ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The news about her brave death was spread among people by some nationalists praising her as &apos;the chaste and strong-minded woman Yuko&apos; and a grand memorial service for her was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>墓は末慶寺（京都市下京区万寿寺櫛筍上ガル）にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her grave is in Makkei-dera Temple (Kushige Agaru, Manju-ji Temple, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is in Makkei-ji Temple (Kushige-agaru, Manju-ji Temple, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>固有名詞読み間違いがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is in Makkei-ji Temple (Kushige-agaru, Manju-ji Temple, Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>彼女の墓にはラフカディオ・ハーン（小泉八雲）やポルトガル領事・ヴェンセスラウ・デ・モラエスも訪れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lafcadio Hearn (Yakumo KOIZUMI) and a Portuguese consul, Wenceslau José de Sousa de Moraes visited her grave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lafcadio Hearn (Yakumo KOIZUMI) and a Portuguese consul, Wenceslau José de Sousa de Moraes visited her grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lafcadio Hearn (Yakumo KOIZUMI) and a Portuguese consul, Wenceslau José de Sousa de Moraes visited her grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>モラエスはまた、リスボンの雑誌『セロエーズ』 Serões に彼女を紹介している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Moraes introduced her to the magazine &quot;Serões&quot; in Lisbon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Moraes introduced her to the magazine &quot;Serões&quot; in Lisbon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Moraes introduced her to the magazine &quot;Serões&quot; in Lisbon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>彼女の死は、ニコライ皇太子に宛てた遺書やセンセーショナルな新聞の報道などによって国際社会の同情をかい、ロシア側の寛容な態度（武力報復・賠償請求ともになし）につながったとの評価もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also estimated that Russian side took a generous attitude (no armed reprisal or a demand of reparation) because her death excited an international society&apos;s sympathy by her suicide note sent to the Crown Prince Nicholai and sensational newspaper reports.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say that the Russian side took a generous attitude (they did not carry out armed reprisals nor demand reparation) because her death had captured the international society&apos;s sympathy through her suicide note to the crown prince Nicholaii and sensational reports by newspapers.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say that the Russian side took a generous attitude (they did not carry out armed reprisals nor demand reparation) because her death had captured the international society&apos;s sympathy through her suicide note to the crown prince Nicholaii and sensational reports by newspapers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Udon-ya(id:48431), 貴亮(id:91813), Dr jimmy(id:111486), ZassouTori(id:136771), Greenland4(id:114494), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), ロロ(id:104252), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>