<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳大寺公胤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kimitane TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimitane TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintane TOKUDAIJI</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳大寺 公胤（とくだいじ きんたね、文明 (日本)19年1月27日 (旧暦)（1487年2月20日） - 大永6年10月12日 (旧暦)（1526年11月16日））は、室町時代の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kimitane TOKUDAIJI (February 20, 1487 - November 16 - 1526) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimitane TOKUDAIJI (February 20, 1487 - November 16 - 1526) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintane TOKUDAIJI (March 1, 1487 - November 26 - 1526) was a kugyo (court noble) who lived during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一February 20→March 116→26</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後土御門天皇（103代）・後柏原天皇（104代）の二帝にわたり仕え、官位は従一位左大臣まで昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served two emperors of Emperor Gotsuchimikado (the 103rd emperor) and Emperor Gokashiwabara (the 104th emperor), and advanced up to Sadaijin (minister of the left) at the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served two emperors, Emperor Gotsuchimikado (the 103rd emperor) and Emperor Gokashiwabara (the 104th emperor), and advanced to Sadaijin (minister of the left) at the rank of Juichii (Junior 1st Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served two emperors, Emperor Gotsuchimikado (the 103rd) and Emperor Gokashiwabara (the 104th), and advanced to Sadaijin (minister of the left) at the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>号は後野宮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He called himself Gononomiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called himself Gononomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called himself Gononomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は太政大臣徳大寺実淳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Saneatsu TOKUDAIJI, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Saneatsu TOKUDAIJI, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Saneatsu TOKUDAIJI, Daijo-daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に権大納言徳大寺実通がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanemichi TOKUDAIJI, Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor), was his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanemichi TOKUDAIJI, Gon Dainagon (a provisional major counselor), was his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanemichi TOKUDAIJI, Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state), was his son.</e>
<cmt>(a provisional major counselor)→ (a provisional chief councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>長享2年（1488年）従五位上に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1488, he was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1488, he was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior 5th Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1488, he was awarded Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以降累進して、侍従・近衛府・讃岐国・近衛府を経て、文亀元年（1501年）に従三位となり、公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, he continued being promoted, and was awarded Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1501, becoming a kugyo, after assuming a palace staff, a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards), a post at Sanuki Province and a post at Konoefu again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he continued being promoted, and was awarded Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank) in 1501, becoming a kugyo, after assuming a position as palace staff, a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards), a post at Sanuki Province, and a post at Konoefu again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he continued being promoted, and was awarded Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1501, becoming a kugyo, after assuming a position as palace staff, a post at Konoefu (the headquarters of the inner palace guards), a post at Sanuki Province, and a post at Konoefu again.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、参議と中納言を経て、永正11年（1514年）に従二位大納言となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1514 after that, he became Dainagon (a major counselor) at the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank) after assuming Sangi (a councilor) and Chunagon (a middle counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1514, he became Dainagon (a major counselor) at the rank of Junii (Junior 2nd Rank) after assuming Sangi (a councilor) and Chunagon (a middle counselor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1514, he became Dainagon (a chief councilor of state) at the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank) after assuming Sangi (a councilor) and Chunagon (a vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>翌年に辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He resigned the Dainagon post in the next year, or in 1515.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned the Dainagon post the next year, or in 1515.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned the Dainagon post the next year, or in 1515.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>永正14年（1517年）再度権大納言となり、右近衛大将・馬寮を兼務。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1517, he became Dainagon again, also assuming Ukone no daisho (the major captain of the right division of inner palace guards) and a post at Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses) additionally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1517, he became Dainagon again, also assuming the position as Ukone no daisho (major captain of the right division of inner palace guards) and additionally a post at Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1517, he became Gon Dainagon again, also assuming the position as Ukone no daisho (major captain of the right division of inner palace guards) and additionally a post at Meryo (the section taking care of imperial horses).</e>
<cmt>Dainagon →Gon Dainagon</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>永正16年（1519年）に近衛府となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1519, he was appointed to a post at Konoefu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1519, he was appointed to a post at Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1519, he was appointed to a post at Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>大永元年（1521年）には左近衛大将を辞し、内大臣に転じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1521, he resigned Sakone no daisho (the major captain of the left division of inner palace guards), and became Naidaijin (minister of the interior)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1521, he resigned Sakone no daisho (major captain of the left division of the inner palace guards), and became Naidaijin (minister of the interior)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1521, he resigned Sakone no daisho (major captain of the left division of the inner palace guards), and became Naidaijin (minister of the interior).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大永3年（1523年）には右大臣を経ずして異例の左大臣任命を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1523, he was appointed to Sadaijin (minister of the left) unprecedentedly without assuming Udaijin (minister of the right).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1523, he was appointed to Sadaijin (minister of the left) unprecedentedly without assuming Udaijin (minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1523, he was appointed to Sadaijin (minister of the left) unprecedentedly without assuming Udaijin (minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>大永6年（1526年）に従一位となるが、この年に病となり、左大臣を辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1526, he was awarded Juichii (Junior First Rank), but became ill and resigned Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1526, he was awarded Juichii (Junior 1st Rank), but became ill and resigned Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1526, he was awarded Juichii (Junior First Rank), but became ill and resigned Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>