<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>永倉新八</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpachi NAGAKURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpachi NAGAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpachi NAGAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>永倉 新八（ながくら しんぱち、天保10年4月11日 (旧暦)（1839年5月23日） - 大正4年（1915年1月5日）は、新撰組二番隊組長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpachi NAGAKURA (May 23, 1839 - January 5, 1915) was the leader of Nibantai (Second Unit) of the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpachi NAGAKURA (May 23, 1839 - January 5, 1915) was the leader of Nibantai (Second Unit) of the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpachi NAGAKURA (May 23, 1839 - January 5, 1915) was the leader of Nibantai (Second Unit) of the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>剣術師範。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an instructor of swordsmanship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an instructor of swordsmanship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an instructor of swordsmanship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本姓は「永倉」ではなく「長倉」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was written as &quot;長倉&quot; (長 means long), not &quot;永倉&quot;(永 means eternity), though both of which have the same reading.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was written as &quot;長倉&quot; (長 means long), not &quot;永倉&quot;(永 means eternity), though both have the same reading.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was written as &apos;長倉&apos; (長 means long), not &apos;永倉&apos; (永 means eternity), although both have the same reading.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。though →although</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名は栄吉、栄治。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood names were Eikichi and Eiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood names were Eikichi and Eiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood names were Eikichi and Eiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>諱は載之（のりゆき）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real personal name was Noriyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real personal name was Noriyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name is Noriyuki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>明治4年以降は杉村義衛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji 4, he changed his name to Sugimura Yoshie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Meiji 4, he changed his name to Sugimura Yoshie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, he changed his name to Yoshie SUGIMURA.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。西暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>試衛館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shieikan Training Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shieikan Training Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shieikan Training Hall</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>松前藩江戸定府取次役（150石）・長倉勘次の次男として誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the second son of Kanji NAGAKURA, who was 150 koku stipend, Edo Jofu Toritsugiyaku of the Matsumae clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the second son of Kanji NAGAKURA, who had a 150 koku stipend, Edo Jofu Toritsugiyaku of the Matsumae clan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the second son of Kanji NAGAKURA, who had a 150 koku stipend as the Edo Jofu Toritsugiyaku (Edo-based liaison) of the Matsumae Domain.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>弘化3年（1846年）、8歳のとき岡田十松（3代目）利章の神道無念流剣術道場「撃剣館」に入門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1846, at the age of eight, he entered Gekikenkan, the Shindo-Munen school swordsmanship training hall lead by Jumatsu OKADA III Toshiaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1846, at the age of eight, he entered Gekikenkan, the Shindo-Munen school swordsmanship training hall led by Jumatsu OKADA III Toshiaki.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered &apos;Gekikenkan,&apos; the Shindo-Munen school of swordsmanship training hall led by Jumatsu OKADA III Toshiaki in 1846 at the age of eight.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>松前藩上屋敷（現・東京都台東区小島二丁目付近）から通う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to the training hall from kamiyashiki (daimyo&apos;s regular residence) of the Matsumae clan (present, in the vicinity of 2 cho-me, Kojima, Taito Ward, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to the training hall from kamiyashiki (daimyo&apos;s regular residence) of the Matsumae clan (in the vicinity of 2 cho-me, Kojima, Taito Ward, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to the training hall from the Kamiyashiki (daimyo&apos;s regular residence) of the Matsumae Domain (near the current Kojima 2 chome, Taito Ward, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>4年目に師が死に、以後、岡田助右衛門に教わり15歳で切紙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the master died four years later, he trained under Sukeemon OKADA, and at the age of 15, he received Kirigami certificate (the lowest rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the master died four years later, he trained under Sukeemon OKADA, and at the age of 15, he received the Kirigami certificate (the lowest rank).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his master died four years later, he trained under Sukeemon OKADA and received the Kirigami certificate (the lowest rank) at the age of fifteen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>安政3年（1856年）、18歳で本目録。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1856, at the age of 18, he received Mokuroku certificate (second rank from the bottom).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1856, at the age of 18, he received the Mokuroku certificate (second rank from the bottom).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the Mokuroku certificate (second rank from the bottom) in 1856 at the age of eighteen.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>元服して新八と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He celebrated his coming of age, and changed his name to Shinpachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He celebrated his coming of age, and changed his name to Shinpachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He changed his name to Shinpachi upon coming of age.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>のち脱藩して剣術修行の旅にでる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he left the Matsumae clan and set out on a journey for training swordsmanship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he left the Matsumae clan and set out on a journey for training in swordsmanship.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he left the Matsumae Domain and set out on a journey for training in swordsmanship.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>武者修行中に、江戸市谷に道場試衛館を構え、武州多摩地方で門人を持っていた天然理心流の近藤勇に食客として入門する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his knight-errantry, he became a live-in apprentice of Isami KONDO who taught Tennenrishinryu school. Isami KONDO had a training hall Shieikan in Ichigaya in Edo and had disciples in Tama area in Bushu (Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his knight-training, he became a live-in apprentice of Isami KONDO who taught at Tennenrishinryu school. Isami KONDO had a training hall, Shieikan in Ichigaya in Edo, and had disciples in the Tama area in Bushu (Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his samurai training, he became a live-in apprentice of Isami KONDO of the Tennenrishin school who had a training hall, Shieikan in Ichigaya in Edo and had disciples in the Tama area in Bushu (Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>新撰組</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsengumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsengumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsengumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>近藤らとともに浪士組に参加し、新撰組結成後は二番隊組長を務めるなど新撰組草創期からの中心人物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He played a central role in Shinsengumi from the early period: He joined Roshigumi with Isami KONDO and others, and became the captain of the second unit when Shinsengumi was formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He played a central role in Shinsengumi from the early period. He joined Roshigumi with Isami KONDO and others, and became the captain of the second unit when Shinsengumi was formed.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in Roshigumi with Isami KONDO and others, and became the captain of the second unit when Shinsengumi was formed, playing a central role in Shinsengumi from its early days.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>芹沢鴨と同じ神道無念流の免許皆伝であり、芹沢とも親しく交わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had received Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency) certificate in the Shindo-Munen school as Kamo SERIZAWA did, and he kept on friendly terms with Kamo SERIZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had received a Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency) certificate in the Shindo-Munen school, as Kamo SERIZAWA had, and he kept on friendly terms with Kamo SERIZAWA.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAKURA had received a Menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency) certificate in the Shindo-Munen school, as with Kamo SERIZAWA, who he kept on friendly terms with.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1864年（元治元年）池田屋事件では、近藤勇、沖田総司らと共に奮戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, he fought bravely with Isami KONDO and Soji OKITA in the Ikedaya Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, he fought bravely with Isami KONDO and Soji OKITA in the Ikedaya Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought bravely with Isami KONDO and Soji OKITA during the Ikedaya Incident in 1864.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>沖田が倒れ、藤堂平助が負傷する中、永倉は獅子奮迅の働きをみせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Soji OKITA collapsed and Heisuke TODO was injured, NAGAKURA put on a display of furious activity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Soji OKITA collapsed and Heisuke TODO was injured, NAGAKURA put on a display of furious activity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAKURA put on a display of bravery while Soji OKITA fell and Heisuke TODO was injured.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>池田屋で一躍勇名を馳せた近藤には、一時、我儘な振る舞いが目立つようになったとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that once Isami KONDO became famous at a single bound for his bravery in the Ikedaya Incident, he noticeably have everything on his own way for a while.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that once Isami KONDO had become famous for his bravery in the Ikedaya Incident, it was noticeable that he had everything his own way for a while.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Isami KONDO, who had suddenly become famous for his bravery during the Ikedaya Incident, acted selfishly for a while.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>それを遺憾に思った永倉は、原田左之助、島田魁らと共に、脱退覚悟で近藤の非行五ヶ条を会津藩主松平容保へ訴え出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAKURA regretted that, and, together with Sanosuke HARADA, Kai SHIMADA and others at the risk of leaving Shinsengumi, reported Isami KONDO to the Lord of Aizu domain Katamori MATSUDAIRA for committing Hiko-go-kajo (five counts of misconduct).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAKURA regretted that, and, together with Sanosuke HARADA, Kai SHIMADA and others at the risk of leaving Shinsengumi, reported Isami KONDO to the Lord of the Aizu domain, Katamori MATSUDAIRA for committing Hiko-go-kajo (five counts of misconduct).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAKURA resented this and together with Sanosuke HARADA, Kai SHIMADA and others, reported Isami KONDO for committing Hiko-go-kajo (five counts of misconduct) to the Lord of the Aizu Domain, Katamori MATSUDAIRA under the risk of leaving Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これには、近藤を局長と認め従うが、我等は近藤の家臣ではなく同志だとする主張が込められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAKURA wrote the report with his belief that the members considered KONDO as the leader of Shinsengumi and intended to follow his instructions but they also considered themselves as his like-minded comrades, not vassals.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAKURA wrote the report with his belief that the members considered KONDO as the leader of Shinsengumi and intended to follow his instructions but they also considered themselves as his like-minded comrades, not vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAKURA expressed his belief in the report that the members considered KONDO as their leader and intended to follow his instructions but they also considered themselves as his comrades, not vassals.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>（この近藤の一時の増長は、武田観柳斎に隊士みな家臣として局長を慕っていると吹き込まれた為ともいわれている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is also said that the KONDO&apos;s temporary insolent behavior was incited by Kanryusai TAKEDA&apos;s misleading account that all members followed him as vassals.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is also said that the KONDO&apos;s temporary insolent behavior was incited by Kanryusai TAKEDA&apos;s misleading account that all members followed him as vassals.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is also said that KONDO&apos;s temporary insolent behavior was incited by Kanryusai TAKEDA&apos;s misleading account that all the members respected him and thought of themselves as his vassals.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この訴えを受けた容保のとりなしで近藤は身を改め、新選組は固い結束を取り戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mediated by Katamori MATSUDAIRA who had received the report, Isami KONDO mended his ways and Shinsengumi recovered its strong unity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mediated by Katamori MATSUDAIRA who had received the report, Isami KONDO mended his ways and Shinsengumi recovered its strong unity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katamori MATSUDAIRA, who had received the report, guided Isami KONDO into mending his ways and the Shinsengumi recovered its strong unity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>永倉はその後、幕府から見廻組格70俵3人扶持として取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, NAGAKURA was promoted by the shogunate government to the status of Mimawarigumi at 70 bales and a ration for three persons salary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, NAGAKURA was promoted by the shogunate government to the status of Mimawarigumi at 70 bales and a ration for three persons salary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, NAGAKURA was promoted by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to the status of Mimawarigumi with a salary of seventy bales and rations for three people.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>油小路事件では原田左之助らとともに御陵衛士の粛清に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Abura-no-koji Incident, NAGAKURA purged Goryo-eji (guards of Imperial mausoleums) with Sanosuke HARADA and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Abura-no-koji Incident, NAGAKURA purged Goryo-eji (guards of Imperial mausoleums) with Sanosuke HARADA and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Abura-no-koji Incident, NAGAKURA purged Goryo-eji (guards of Imperial mausoleums) with Sanosuke HARADA and others.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>御陵衛士には試衛館からの盟友であった藤堂平助がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heisuke TODO who had been NAGAKURA&apos;s sword friend since they met at Shieikan was included in the Goryo-eji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heisuke TODO who had been NAGAKURA&apos;s sword friend since they met at Shieikan was included in the Goryo-eji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heisuke TODO, who had been NAGAKURA&apos;s sword friend since they met at Shieikan, was a member of the Goryo-eji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>近藤の「藤堂だけは生かしておきたいものだ」という言葉もあり、永倉も平助を逃がそうと試みたが、平助は三浦常三郎の手によって討ち取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although KONDO said &quot;I want to save especially Todo&apos;s life.&quot; and NAGAKURA attempted to let Heisuke run away, Heisuke was killed by Tsunesaburo MIURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although KONDO said &quot;I want to save especially Todo&apos;s life.&quot; and NAGAKURA attempted to let Heisuke run away, Heisuke was killed by Tsunesaburo MIURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although KONDO said, &apos;I want to save Todo&apos;s life.&apos; and NAGAKURA attempted to let Heisuke run away, Heisuke was killed by Tsunesaburo MIURA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>沖田総司が病床に伏せると、沖田の一番隊も指揮し重要な任務を数々こなした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Soji OKITA was confined to his bed by illness, NAGAKURA also commanded OKITA&apos;s Ichibantai and fulfilled many great missions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Soji OKITA was confined to his bed by illness, NAGAKURA also commanded OKITA&apos;s Ichibantai and fulfilled many great missions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Soji OKITA fell ill, NAGAKURA also commanded OKITA&apos;s Ichibantai (first unit) and completed many important missions.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1868年（慶応4年）に新政府軍との戊辰戦争が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1868, the Boshin War broke out against the New governement army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1868, the Boshin War broke out against the New governement army.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Boshin War broke out against the army of the new government in 1868.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>京都の鳥羽伏見の戦いでは、決死隊を募り官軍の銃弾に対して刀一つで突撃する豪胆さも見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Toba-Fushimi in Kyoto, NAGAKURA showed his courage by collecting members of a suicide squid and charging with a sword at the firing imperial army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Toba-Fushimi in Kyoto, NAGAKURA showed his courage by collecting members of a suicide squad and charging with a sword at the firing imperial army.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Toba-Fushimi at Kyoto, NAGAKURA showed his courage by leading members of a suicide squad and charging with a sword against the bullet-firing imperial army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>江戸に退却後、新選組から名を改めた甲陽鎮撫隊に属して戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After retreated to Edo, he fought in the Koyo Chinbutai (a military unit formed specially for the campaign in Kai Province) which was a new name of Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After retreating to Edo, he fought in the Koyo Chinbutai (a military unit formed specially for the campaign in Kai Province) which was the new name of Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After retreating to Edo, he fought in the Koyo Chinbutai (a military unit formed specially for the campaign in the Kai Province), which was the new name for the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、敗れ官軍支配下の江戸に戻る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Koyo Chinbutai was defeated, however, and he returned to Edo which was under the control of the Imperial army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Koyo Chinbutai was defeated, however, and he returned to Edo which was under the control of the Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Koyo Chinbutai was defeated and he returned to Edo, which was under the control of the Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>江戸にて、近藤らと分離して結成した靖共隊（靖兵隊）に属して戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He separated from KONDO and others, and formed Seikyotai (or Seiheitai) in Edo and fought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He separated from KONDO and others, and formed Seikyotai (or Seiheitai) in Edo and fought.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Edo, he left Kondo and others to form the Seikyotai (or Seiheitai) and continued fighting.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>援軍を求め米沢藩に滞留中、会津藩の降伏を知り、その後江戸へ帰還。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He visited the Yonezawa clan for asking for reinforcement, and during that stay, he learned of surrender of the Aizu clan and returned to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He visited the Yonezawa clan asking for reinforcement, and during that stay, he learned of the surrender of the Aizu clan and returned to Edo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He visited the Yonezawa Domain to ask for reinforcement and learned of the surrender of the Aizu Domain during the stay and returned to Edo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>松前藩への帰藩が許され保護される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was permitted to back to the Matsumae domain and given protection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was permitted to go back to the Matsumae domain and given protection.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was permitted to return to the Matsumae Domain and was offered protection.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その後1871年（明治4年）藩医の杉村介庵の婿養子となり北海道松前町 (北海道)に渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in 1871, he became a son-in-law of Kaian SUGIMURA, Hani (Edo-period doctor working for his domain at a public clinic), and went over to Matsumae-cho town in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then in 1871, he became a son-in-law of Kaian SUGIMURA, Hani (Edo-period doctor working for his domain at a public clinic), and went over to Matsumae-cho town in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the son-in-law of Kaian SUGIMURA, who was a Hani (Edo-period doctor working for his domain at a public clinic) in 1871 and moved to Matsumae-cho in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>明治以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>明治6年（もしくは明治8年）、家督を継いで杉村治備（後に義衛）と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji 6 (or 8), he succeeded to a property and changed his name to Harunobu SUGIMURA (later to, Yoshie SUGIMURA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Meiji 6 (or 8), he succeeded to a property and changed his name to Harunobu SUGIMURA (later to, Yoshie SUGIMURA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1873 (or 1875), he succeeded as the family head and changed his name to Harunobu SUGIMURA (later to Yoshie SUGIMURA).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>その後北海道小樽市へ移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, in 1882, he moved to Otaru City in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, in 1882, he moved to Otaru City in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he moved to Otaru City in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>FB反映の上、文末の1882年を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>1882年（明治15年）、その苛烈さから鬼典獄（所長）と呼ばれた月形潔が管理する「地の果ての獄」樺戸集治監の剣術師範に招かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was invited to the post of instructor of swordsmanship by the Kabato Shujikan, or &quot;outland prison&quot;, (the predecessor of modern prison) and served there as an instructor until 1886.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was invited to the post of instructor of swordsmanship by the Kabato Shujikan, or &quot;outland prison&quot;, (the predecessor of modern prisons) and served there as an instructor until 1886.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1882, he was invited by Kiyoshi TSUKIGATA, who was known as the demon prison head because of his strictness, to become an instructor of swordsmanship at the Kabato Shujikan, or &apos;outland prison&apos; (the predecessor of modern prisons).</e>
<cmt>FB反映の上、冒頭に1882年を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>1886年（明治19年）までその職にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kabato Shujikan was managed by Kiyoshi TUKIGATA who was called a demon alcaide (warden) for his relentlessness.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kabato Shujikan was managed by Kiyoshi TUKIGATA who was called a demon alcaide (warden) for his relentlessness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served there as an instructor until 1886.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>退職後は東京へ再度戻り牛込にて剣術道場を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After retired, NAGAKURA returned to Tokyo and founded a swordsmanship training hall in Ushigome.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he retired, NAGAKURA returned to Tokyo and founded a swordsmanship training hall in Ushigome.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he retired, NAGAKURA returned to Tokyo again and founded a swordsmanship training hall at Ushigome.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>1891年（明治24年）、日清戦争開戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1891, the Sino-Japanese War started.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1891, the Sino-Japanese War started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sino-Japanese War broke out in 1891.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>57歳となった永倉は抜刀隊に志願する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAKURA, at the age of 57, volunteered for Battotai (drawn sword squad).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAKURA, at the age of 57, volunteered for Battotai (drawn sword squad).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAKURA volunteered for Battotai (drawn sword squad) at the age of 57.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし「お気持ちだけ……」と言われ断られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His offer was turned down with the reply &quot;We appreciate the offer, but…&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His offer was turned down with the reply &quot;We appreciate the offer, but…&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his offer was turned down with the reply &apos;We appreciate the offer, but...&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>永倉は「元新選組の手を借りたとあっては、薩摩の連中も面目丸つぶれというわけかい」と笑ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that NAGAKURA just laughed that away by the words &quot;Those from Satsuma cannot take me for fear of losing their face by being reinforced by the former Shinsengumi fighter.&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that NAGAKURA just laughed that away by the words &quot;Those from Satsuma cannot take me for fear of losing face by being reinforced by a former Shinsengumi fighter.&quot;.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that NAGAKURA just laughed and said, &apos;I guess those from Satsuma cannot accept the help of a former Shinsengumi fighter for fear of losing face.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>明治維新後、数少ない新選組幹部の生き残りとして、板橋に近藤勇、土方歳三の墓を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, as one of a few surviving senior members of Shinsengumi, he set up graves of Isami KONDO and Toshzo HIJIIKATA in Itabashi Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, as one of a few surviving senior members of Shinsengumi, he set up graves of Isami KONDO and Toshzo HIJIIKATA in Itabashi Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, as one of a few surviving senior members of Shinsengumi, he set up the graves of Isami KONDO and Toshizo HIJIKATA in Itabashi, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="50">
<j>1899年（明治32年）、妻と子供が北海道小樽色内で薬局を開局していた為に小樽へ再度移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For his wife and child had opened a pharmacy in Otaru Ironai in Hokkaido, he moved to Otaru again in 1899.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his wife and child had opened a pharmacy in Otaru Ironai in Hokkaido, he moved to Otaru again in 1899.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He moved backed to Otaru again in 1899 because his wife and child had opened a pharmacy in Otaru Ironai, Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>1905年（明治38年）から小樽緑1丁目（旧小樽少年科学館付近）に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1905, he lived in the vicinity of Otaru Midori 1-chome (near the former Otaru Shonen Kagakukan (Otaru Juvenile Science Museum)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1905, he lived in the vicinity of Otaru Midori 1-chome (near the former Otaru Shonen Kagakukan (Otaru Juvenile Science Museum)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lived in the vicinity of Otaru Midori 1-chome (near the former Otaru Shonen Kagakukan (Otaru Juvenile Science Museum)) from 1905.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>1909年（明治42年）7月に花園町に住む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From July, 1909, he lived in Hanazono-cho town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From July, 1909, he lived in Hanazono-cho town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lived in Hanazono-cho from July 1909.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>（旧小樽少年科学館の正面玄関を真正面に見て左の位置にある当時の建物名『小樽聯合(れんごう)衛生組合事務所』跡）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His house was at the site of the building named &quot;Otaru Rengo Eisei Kumiai Jimusho&quot;of those days which is on the left facing the front door of the former Otaru Shonen Kagakukan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His house was at the site of the building named &quot;Otaru Rengo Eisei Kumiai Jimusho&quot;in those days which is on the left facing the front door of the former Otaru Shonen Kagakukan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(His house was at the site of the building named &quot;Otaru Rengo Eisei Kumiai Jimusho&quot; (office of Otaru Union Health Association) in those days, which was to the left when facing the main front door of the former Otaru Shonen Kagakukan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="54">
<j>映画を好み孫を連れてよく映画館に通ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He loved movies and occasionally went to movie theaters taking his grandchild.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He loved movies and occasionally went to movie theaters taking his grandchild.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He loved movies and often went took his grandchildren to the movie theaters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>「近藤、土方は若くして死んでしまったが、自分は命永らえたおかげで、このような文明の不思議を見ることができた」と語っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he uttered, &quot;Kondo and Hijikata died young, but I survived so long that I can see such a wondedrful product of civilization.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he uttered, &quot;Kondo and Hijikata died young, but I survived so long so that I can see such wondedrful products of civilization.&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he said, &apos;Kondo and Hijikata died young, but I can experience such wonderful products of civilization because I survived.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>ある時、映画館の出口で地元のヤクザにからまれ、鋭い眼力と一喝で退散させたというエピソードもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an episode about him: He flashed back the yakuza accosting him and roared to dismiss the yakuza at the exit of a movie theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an episode about him; he flashed back to the yakuza accosting him and roared to dismiss the yakuza at the exit of a movie theater.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an episode about him that he was accosted by the local yakuza at the entrance of a movie theater, but sent them running with his sharp glare and loud yell.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>（実際は手拭で戦った、杖を持っていた、という説もある）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this episode, it is also said that he whipped the yakuza away with a Japanese cotton towel or he threatened the yakuza with a stick in his hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this episode, it is also said that he whipped the yakuza away with a Japanese cotton towel or he threatened the yakuza with a stick in his hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(There are also some who said that he fought the yakuza away with a Japanese cotton towel or he had a cane in his hand.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="58">
<j>1913年（大正2年）5月22日には近藤勇の娘、山田音羽と対面をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 22, 1913, he met a daughter of Isami KONDO, Otowa YAMADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 22, 1913, he met a daughter of Isami KONDO, Otowa YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He met the daughter of Isami KONDO, Otowa YAMADA on May 22, 1913.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="59">
<j>1915年(大正4年）1月5日に虫歯が原因の骨膜炎、敗血症で北海道小樽市にて死去、享年76。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 5, 1915, he died in Otaru City in Hokkaido at the age of 76.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5, 1915, he died in Otaru City in Hokkaido at the age of 76.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in Otaru City, Hokkaido at the age of seventy-six on January 5, 1915 due to blood poisoning from periostitis caused by a tooth cavity.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="60">
<j>墓所は分骨された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of his ashes were buried in separate places.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of his ashes were buried in separate places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His ashes were buried in separate places:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>東京都北区_(東京都)滝野川の寿徳寺境外墓地、札幌市清田区里塚霊園（一期三号762番）北海道小樽市中央墓地他。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some were buried in a grave out of the precincts of the Jutoku-ji Temple in Takinogawa, Kita Ward in Tokyo, and the other were buried in the Satozuka cemetery (1-ki, 3-go, No,762) in Kiyota Ward, Sapporo City in Hokkaido, and the central graveyard in Otaru City in Hokkaido, and other places.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some were buried in a grave out of the precincts of the Jutoku-ji Temple in Takinogawa, Kita Ward in Tokyo, and the others were buried in the Satozuka cemetery (1-ki, 3-go, No.762) in Kiyota Ward, Sapporo City in Hokkaido, and the central graveyard in Otaru City in Hokkaido, and other places.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jutoku-ji Temple in Takinogawa, Kita Ward in Tokyo, Satozuka cemetery (1-ki, 3-go, No.762) in Kiyota Ward, Sapporo City, Hokkaido and the central graveyard in Otaru City, Hokkaido, and other places.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="62">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>統一リストに従って修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>新撰組の隊長格でも屈指の剣腕を誇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpachi NAGAKURA was one of the most skillful swordsmen among the captains of Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpachi NAGAKURA was one of the most skillful swordsmen among the captains of Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpachi NAGAKURA was one of the most skillful swordsmen among the captains of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>阿部十郎は一に永倉、二に沖田、三に斎藤一の順であったと後年語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years, Juro Abe ranked NAGAKURA first, OKITA second, and SAITO third in swordsmanship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years, Juro Abe ranked NAGAKURA first, OKITA second, and SAITO third in swordsmanship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juro ABE later ranked NAGAKURA first, OKITA second, and SAITO third in order of swordsmanship.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>「龍飛剣」と称する下段の構えから上へ敵の剣を擦り上げながら下へ切り落とす技を得意としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was good at a feat called &quot;Ryuhiken&quot;. In that technique, he held his sword low, pushing up the opponent&apos;s sword and bring down his sword.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was good at a feat called &quot;Ryuhiken&quot;. In this technique, he held his sword low, pushing up the opponent&apos;s sword and bring down his sword.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was good at a technique called &apos;Ryuhiken,&apos; where you hold the sword low, push the opponent&apos;s sword up, and then strike the opponent by bringing the sword down.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>京都で島原亀屋の芸妓である小常を妻とし、小常は娘の磯子を産んだ後に他界している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He married Kotsune who had been a geisha at the geisha house Shimabara Kameya in Kyoto, and Kotsune died after giving birth to their daughter Isoko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He married Kotsune who had been a geisha at the geisha house Shimabara Kameya in Kyoto, and Kotsune died after giving birth to their daughter Isoko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He married Kotsune, who had been a geiko at Shimabara Kameya in Kyoto but Kotsune died after giving birth to their daughter, Isoko.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>磯子は永倉が京を去る際に小常の姉に預けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isoko was left in the care of Kotsune&apos;s elder sister when NAGAKURA left Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isoko was left in the care of Kotsune&apos;s elder sister when NAGAKURA left Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isoko was left in the care of Kotsune&apos;s elder sister when NAGAKURA left Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>1900年（明治33年）には関西で名を尾上小亀とした女役者になり、再会も果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1900, Isoko became an actress with a stage name Kogame ONOE in the Kansai Region, and later, she reunited with his father NAGAKURA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1900, Isoko became an actress with the stage name Kogame ONOE in the Kansai Region, and later, she reunited with her father NAGAKURA.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1900, Isoko became an actress called Kogame ONOE in the Kansai Region and was later reunited with her father.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="69">
<j>資料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Documents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>貴重な新選組の資料となる、『浪士文久報国記事』を書き残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAKURA wrote &quot;Roshi (masterless samurai) Bunkyu era patriotism articles&quot; which provides valuable data on Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAKURA wrote &quot;Roshi (masterless samurai) Bunkyu era patriotism articles&quot; which provide valuable data on Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAKURA wrote &quot;Roshi (masterless samurai) Bunkyu era patriotism articles&quot;, an important source on the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>また小樽新聞の記者に取材協力した『新選組顛末記』を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He cooperated with a newspaper reporter of the Otaru and left &quot;Shinsengumi Tenmatsuki (Detailed Report on Shinsengumi)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He cooperated with a newspaper reporter of the Otaru and left &quot;Shinsengumi Tenmatsuki (Detailed Report on Shinsengumi)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He cooperated with a newspaper reporter from Otaru Shinbun to produce &quot;Shinsengumi Tenmatsuki&quot; (Detailed Report on Shinsengumi).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>この永倉の一連の働きがその時までの「新選組は悪の人斬り集団、悪の使者」という人々の固定観念を突き崩し、現在に続く新選組再考のきっかけとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAGAKURA&apos;s those series of works broke the stereotyped idea of considering Shinsengumi &quot;a group of evil murderers, or a wicked envoy&quot;. Those documents triggered the second thought on Shinsengumi which is still on its way.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAGAKURA&apos;s series of works broke the stereotyped idea of considering Shinsengumi &quot;a group of evil murderers, or a wicked envoy&quot;. These documents triggered second thoughts regarding Shinsengumi, and these are still ongoing.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAGAKURA&apos;s series of works broke the stereotyped idea of considering Shinsengumi as &apos;a group of wicked murderers or evil envoy&apos; and triggered a reconsideration of the Shinsengumi that is still ongoing to this day.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田英(id:85936), パイク・ビショップ(id:114349), 経済準学士(id:22656), ブリキの太鼓叩き(id:3586), Tast(id:29478), Lupinoid(id:68), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Mintleaf(id:2216), 土方　誠(id:3651), 雲南(id:61460), 認定者(id:99098), ロココ(id:80572), 竜馬(id:14477), でここ(id:9565), ふんにゃらにゃ(id:27740), Goki(id:7107), Rei-bot(id:94097), Kahskydream(id:5116), Maakun(id:16735), FlaBot(id:30804), としぴい(id:161011), Izayohi(id:13095), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), TI(id:29132), Moltke(id:17553), Pica(id:9502), Oyoyoyo(id:196287), Ro-(id:36890), Javvy(id:22017), まいける西宮の沢(id:226396), 上田隼人(id:23104), 匿名内緒(id:266295), 青山光二(id:25291), NDR(id:5500), DoWhile(id:34638), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), Bokka7568(id:275377), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>