<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一色義貫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsura ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsura ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsura ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>一色 義貫（いっしき よしつら、1400年（応永7年） - 1440年6月14日（永享12年5月15日 (旧暦)））は、室町時代前期の守護大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsura ISSHIKI (1400 - June 14, 1440) was a shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsura ISSHIKI (1400 - June 14, 1440) was a shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsura ISSHIKI (1400 - June 14, 1440) was a shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) in the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一色満範の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Mitsunori ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Mitsunori ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Mitsunori ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>官位は兵部少輔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was Hyobu-shoyu (junior assistant minister of the Hyobusho Ministry of Military).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official rank was Hyobu-shoyu (junior assistant minister of the Hyobusho Ministry of Military).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official rank was Hyobu-shoyu (junior assistant minister of the Hyobusho Ministry of Military).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>左京大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>修理大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>スタイルを統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>初名は義範。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original name was Gihan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Yoshinori.</e>
<cmt>読みを直します。登録単語は他人のことか読み間違いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Yoshinori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>1409年、父・満範の死により家督を継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took over as head of the family after the death of his father Mitsunori ISSHIKI in 1409.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1409 he succeeded to the family head due to the death of his father Mitsunori.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1409 he succeeded to the family head due to the death of his father Mitsunori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>4代将軍足利義持時代から仕え、侍所を務め、1418年、1434年には山城国の守護にも任じられ、三河国・若狭国・丹後国、そして山城の4カ国（他に尾張国海東郡・知多郡分郡守護）を兼ねる有力守護大名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served the fourth Shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, served as Samurai-dokoro (the Board of Retainers), was assigned as shugo of the Yamashiro province in 1418 and 1434, and became a dominant Shugo Guardian Feudal Lord of four provinces (Mikawa, Wakasa, Tango and Yamashiro) (as well as Owari province Kaito District, Chita-gun Bungunshugo (a provincial constable of a specially given province in gun unit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had served the Ashikaga shogunate since the period of the fourth shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA; he served at Samurai-dokoro (the Board of Retainers), and was assigned as shugo of Yamashiro Province in 1418 and in 1434, and became a dominant shugo daimyo of four provinces, Mikawa, Wakasa, Tango and Yamashiro (besides those posts he was appointed bungun-shugo [provincial constable of specially given province] of Kaito County and Chita County of Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミス、誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had served the Ashikaga shogunate since the period of the fourth shogun Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA; he served at Samurai-dokoro (the Board of Retainers), and was assigned as shugo of Yamashiro Province in 1418 and in 1434, and became a dominant shugo daimyo of four provinces, Mikawa, Wakasa, Tango and Yamashiro (besides those posts he was appointed bungun-shugo [provincial constable of specially given province] of Kaito County and Chita County of Owari Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>武功においても伊勢国の北畠満雅を討ち、1427年に出奔した赤松満祐の討伐においても活躍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He performed great military exploits, subjugated Mitsumasa KITABATAKE in the Ise province, and subdued Mitsusuke AKAMATSU who ran away in 1427.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a military man, he performed great exploits, as he subjugated Mitsumasa KITABATAKE of Ise Province, and subdued the army of Mitsusuke AKAMATSU who had run away in 1427.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a military man, he performed great exploits, as he subjugated Mitsumasa KITABATAKE of Ise Province, and subdued the army of Mitsusuke AKAMATSU who had run away in 1427.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その功績により、四職の一人となって幕政に参与したが、6代将軍足利義教の代になると、供奉を放棄するなど次第に対立し、一時は幕政から遠ざけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated in the shogunate government as one of Shishiki, but when the sixth shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA assumed power, he abandoned attendance, was opposed to the shogun and was temporarily kept away from the shogunate government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For those achievements, he was appointed one of Shisiki (director generals of Samurai-dokoro) and participated in the government of the shogunate, however, in the period of the sixth shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, he gradually became opposed to the shogunate as he refused gubu (to attend shogun at events), and was even kept away from the government for some period.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。用語の説明を加えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For those achievements, he was appointed one of Shisiki (director generals of Samurai-dokoro) and participated in the government of the shogunate, however, in the period of the sixth shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, he gradually became opposed to the shogunate as he refused gubu (to attend shogun at events), and was even kept away from the government for some period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>管領の畠山満家らの仲介もあって、義貫は再び幕政に復帰している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsura returned to the shogunate government by the intermediation of kanrei (shogunal deputy) Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the good offices of Kanrei (shogunal deputy) Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA and others, Yoshitsura returned to the government.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the good offices of Kanrei (shogunal deputy) Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA and others, Yoshitsura returned to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1440年、関東で起こった結城合戦に際して、義教の命で大和国の越智氏を討伐のために出陣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He departed for the front to subdue the Ochi clan in the Yamato province by order of Yoshinori in the Yuki War in 1440.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1440, when the Yuki War started in the Kanto region, he departed for the front to subdue the Ochi clan of Yamato Province by order of Yoshinori.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1440, when the Yuki War started in the Kanto region, he departed for the front to subdue the Ochi clan of Yamato Province by order of Yoshinori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>義貫は永享の乱で幕府に対して挙兵した足利持氏の残党（一色時家等）を匿った罪を問われ、土岐持頼とともに義教から追討を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsura was charged with hiding the remnants (Tokiie ISSHIKI and so on) of Mochiuji ASHIKAGA who raised an army against the bakufu in the Eikyu War and Yoshiyuki and Mochiyori TOKI were hunted down by Yoshonori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsura was charged with hiding the remnants (Tokiie ISSHIKI and others) of Mochiuji ASHIKAGA who had raised an army against the bakufu in the Eikyo War, and he and Mochiyori TOKI were hunted by the army of Yoshonori.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsura was charged with hiding the remnants (Tokiie ISSHIKI and others) of Mochiuji ASHIKAGA who had raised an army against the bakufu in the Eikyo War, and he and Mochiyori TOKI were hunted by the army of Yoshonori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>武田信栄に腹背を攻められて敗北。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was attacked on the back by Nobuhide TAKEDA and was defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His troop was attacked from front and behind by Nobuhide TAKEDA, and was defeated.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。「腹背」は前と後ろ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His troop was attacked from front and behind by Nobuhide TAKEDA, and was defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同年5月15日、大和信貴山の竜門寺で一族と共に自害して果てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He and his family committed suicide at Ryumon-ji Temple on Mt. Shigi in the Yamato province on May 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 15 of the same year, he committed suicide together with his family at Ryumon-ji Temple on Mt. Shigi in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 15 of the same year, he committed suicide together with his family at Ryumon-ji Temple on Mt. Shigi in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>享年41。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 41.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at death was 41.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His age at death was 41.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>法号は安養寺泰雲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Anyo-ji Temple Taiun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Buddhist name was Anyoji-Taiun.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Anyoji-Taiun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>義貫は四ヶ国を兼ねる有力守護となり、そのために義教に警戒され、謀殺されたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsura became a dominant Shugo for four provinces, and it is said that he was bewared of by Yoshinori and murdered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that since Yoshitsura became a dominant shugo who governed four provinces, he was regarded as a threat by Yoshinori, and murdered deliberately.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that since Yoshitsura became a dominant shugo who governed four provinces, he was regarded as a threat by Yoshinori, and murdered deliberately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、一色氏内部でも家督をめぐり伯父である一色持範・甥である一色教親との抗争があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Isshiki clan, an uncle Mochinori ISSHIKI disputed with a nephew Norichika ISSHIKI regarding the reigns of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also inside the Isshiki clan, there was a fight between his uncle Mochinori ISSHIKI and his nephew Norichika ISSHIKI over the succession to the family head.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also inside the Isshiki clan, there was a fight between his uncle Mochinori ISSHIKI and his nephew Norichika ISSHIKI over the succession to the family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>一色氏の遺領地は分配され、一色氏は没落する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The property inheritance of the Isshiki clan was divided and the clan fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the family had killed themselves, their territory was divided and the Isshiki clan fell.</e>
<cmt>訳語選択ミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the family had killed themselves, their territory was divided and the Isshiki clan fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Point136(id:211299), NDR(id:5500), GAVVA(id:47103), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>