<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>赤沢朝経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomotsune AKAZAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomotsune AKAZAWA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomotsune AKAZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>赤沢 朝経（あかざわ ともつね）は、戦国時代 (日本)（室町時代後期）の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomotsune AKAZAWA was a Japanese military commander who lived during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), or the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomotsune AKAZAWA was a Japanese military commander who lived during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), or the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomotsune AKAZAWA was a Japanese military commander who lived during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), or the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His original surname was Minamoto.</e>
<cmt>ここで「源氏」は姓そのものを指しているため、&quot;the Minamoto clan&quot; ではなく &quot;Minamoto&quot;と訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original surname was Minamoto.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original surname was Minamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家系は清和源氏の一家系 河内源氏の傍系　甲斐源氏の流れを汲む信濃国守護家小笠原氏の庶家 赤沢氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Akazawa clan was from Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) and was also a collateral family of Kawachi-Genji, and additionally, the clan was a branch family of the Ogasawara clan, who served as the Military Governor of Shinano Province and who was descended from Kai-Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Akazawa clan originated from Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) and was also a collateral family of Kawachi-Genji, and additionally, the clan was a branch family of the Ogasawara clan, who served as the Military Governor of Shinano Province and descended from Kai-Genji.</e>
<cmt>was from → originated from. Who was descended →descended</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Akazawa clan originated from Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) and was also a collateral family of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), and additionally, the clan was a branch family of the Ogasawara clan, who served as the Military Governor of Shinano Province and descended from Kai-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>Genji に (Minamoto clan)　追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家督を譲った後は、入道宗益と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomotsune called himself Nyudosoeki after handing over the headship of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomotsune called himself Nyudosoeki after handing over the headship of the family.</e>
<cmt>OK.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomotsune called himself Nyudo Soeki after handing over the headship of the family.</e>
<cmt>Nyudosoeki→Nyudo Soeki</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>赤沢氏の本拠地は信濃国塩崎城で、朝経は家督を嫡子政経に譲って上洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Akazawa clan was based at Shiozaki-jo Castle in Shinano Province, and Tomotsune handed over the headship of the family to his heir Masatsune before going up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Akazawa clan was based at Shiozaki-jo Castle in Shinano Province, and Tomotsune handed over the headship of the family to his heir, Masatsune, before going up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>added commas before and after Masatsune.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Akazawa clan was based at Shiozaki-jo Castle in Shinano Province, and Tomotsune handed over the headship of the family to his heir, Masatsune, before going up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>本家小笠原氏に倣って「糾法（弓法）的伝」（小笠原流）を室町幕府の管領細川政元に伝授した縁で、将軍足利義政の弓道師範、更に武者所を兼任するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He taught kyuhotekiden (a generic term given to Japanese archery, horsemanship, and etiquette and formality) of the Ogasawara school to Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who was a kanrei (deputy to the shogun) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and this led him to serve the Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA as a teacher of Japanese archery and to take charge of the Mushadokoro (a division in charge of guard over a residence of a retired emperor or a cloistered emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He taught kyuhotekiden (a generic term given to Japanese archery, horsemanship, and etiquette and formal manners) of the Ogasawara school to Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who was a kanrei (deputy to the shogun) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and this led him to serve Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA as a teacher of Japanese archery and to take charge of the Mushadokoro (a division in charge of guarding over a residence of a retired emperor or a cloistered emperor).</e>
<cmt>formality → formal manners. The Shogun → Shogun.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He taught &apos;kyuhotekiden&apos; (a generic term given to Japanese archery, horsemanship, and etiquette and formal manners) of the Ogasawara school to Masamoto HOSOKAWA, who was a kanrei (deputy to the shogun) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and this led him to serve Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA as a teacher of Japanese archery and to take charge of the Mushadokoro (a division in charge of guarding over a residence of a retired emperor or a cloistered emperor).</e>
<cmt>「」に &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、細川政元の重臣として山城国・河内国・大和国など各地を転戦して武功を挙げ、山城上三郡守護代や幕府料所河内十七箇所の給人、近衛家領山城五ケ庄の代官などに任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, he rendered distinguished services in battles in various places such as Yamashiro Province, Kawachi Province, and Yamato Province as a chief vassal of Masamoto HOSOKAWA, and he was appointed a Shugodai (acting Military Governor) of Kamisangun (literally, &quot;upper three counties,&quot; which was a generic term given to Kuze County, Tuzuki County, and Soraku County) of Yamashiro Province, a kyujin (upper class samurai who has his own territory or who is given a territory by his lord) of 17 bakufu-ryosho (territories under the direct control of the bakufu) in Kawachi Province, and a daikan (local governor) of Gokasho, Yamashiro Province, which was a territory of the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he rendered distinguished services in battles in various places such as Yamashiro Province, Kawachi Province, and Yamato Province as a chief vassal of Masamoto HOSOKAWA, and he was appointed Shugodai (acting Military Governor) of Kamisangun (literally, &quot;upper three counties,&quot; which was a generic term given to Kuze County, Tuzuki County, and Soraku County) of Yamashiro Province, a kyujin (upper class samurai who has his own territory or who is given a territory by his lord) of 17 bakufu-ryosho (territories under the direct control of the bakufu) in Kawachi Province, and a daikan (local governor) of Gokasho, Yamashiro Province, which was a territory of the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt>appointed as → appointed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he rendered distinguished services in battles in various places such as Yamashiro Province, Kawachi Province, and Yamato Province as a chief vassal of Masamoto HOSOKAWA, and he was appointed Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Kamisangun (literally, &quot;upper three counties,&quot; which was a generic term given to Kuze County, Tsuzuki County, and Soraku County) of Yamashiro Province, a kyujin (upper class samurai who has his own territory or who is given a territory by his lord) of 17 bakufu-ryosho (territories under the direct control of the bakufu) in Kawachi Province, and a daikan (local governor) of Gokasho, Yamashiro Province, which was a territory of the Konoe family.</e>
<cmt>守護代の定訳Tuzuki→Tsuzuki</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>永正元年（1504年）、薬師寺元一と結託して主君・政元の廃立とその養子である細川澄元の擁立を企てたが、元一の弟・薬師寺長忠らによって鎮圧されて捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1504, he attempted to dethrone his lord Masamoto and enthrone Masamoto&apos;s adopted son Sumimoto HOSOKAWA in conspiracy with Motokazu YAKUSHIJI, but they were suppressed and arrested by Motokazu&apos;s younger brother Nagatada YAKUSHIJI and his team.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1504, he attempted to dethrone his lord Masamoto to enthrone Masamoto&apos;s adopted son Sumimoto HOSOKAWA in conspiracy with Motokazu YAKUSHIJI, but they were overcome and arrested by Motokazu&apos;s younger brother Nagatada YAKUSHIJI and his team.</e>
<cmt>and → to. Suppressed → over come.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1504, he attempted to dethrone his lord Masamoto to enthrone Masamoto&apos;s adopted son Sumimoto HOSOKAWA in conspiracy with Motokazu YAKUSHIJI, but they were overcome and arrested by Motokazu&apos;s younger brother Nagatada YAKUSHIJI and his team.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかしその豪勇を政元から惜しまれて助命され、永正2年（1505年）には罪を許されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto spared Tomotsune&apos;s life, however, because of his great bravery, and he was eventually forgiven in 1505.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamoto spared Tomotsune&apos;s life, however, because of his great bravery, he was eventually forgiven in 1505.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and&quot; was deleted.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamoto spared Tomotsune&apos;s life, however, because of his great bravery, he was eventually forgiven in 1505.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後は政元の家臣として永正3年（1506年）に大和に侵攻して畠山義英や畠山尚順らを破り、さらに大和の寺社勢力も破って大和を平定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in 1506, he invaded Yamato Province as a vassal of Masamoto and defeated Yoshihide HATAKEYAMA and Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA, and he also conquered military forces owned by temples and shrines, resulting in the establishment of peach in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in 1506, he invaded Yamato Province as a vassal of Masamoto and defeated Yoshihide HATAKEYAMA and Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA, and he also conquered the military forces owned by temples and shrines, resulting in the establishment of peach in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>conquered military forces → conquered the military forces.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in 1506, he invaded Yamato Province as a vassal of Masamoto and defeated Yoshihide HATAKEYAMA and Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA, and he also conquered the military forces owned by temples and shrines, resulting in the establishment of peach in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さらに三好之長と共に畿内各地に転戦して細川氏の勢力拡大に貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, he contributed to the expansion of the influence of the Hosokawa clan by taking part in a number of battles in various places within the Kinai (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) region with Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he contributed to the expansion of the influence of the Hosokawa clan by taking part in a number of battles in various places within the Kinai (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) region with Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he contributed to the expansion of the influence of the Hosokawa clan by taking part in a number of battles in various places within the Kinai (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) region with Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>永正4年（1507年）、政元の命令を受けて丹後国の一色義有を攻めるが、その戦いの最中である6月23日に政元が家臣の薬師寺長忠らによって暗殺された（永正の錯乱）ことを知った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1507, he attacked Yoshiari ISSHIKI, who was based in Tango Province, by order of Masamoto, but during the battle, he was informed of the assassination of Masamoto by his vassal Nagatada YAKUSHIJI on August 11 (the Eisho Disturbance).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1507, he attacked Yoshiari ISSHIKI, who was based in Tango Province, by order of Masamoto, but during the battle, he was informed of the assassination of Masamoto by his vassal Nagatada YAKUSHIJI on August 11 (the Eisho Disturbance).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1507, he attacked Yoshiari ISSHIKI, who was based in Tango Province, by order of Masamoto, but during the battle, he was informed of the assassination of Masamoto by his vassal Nagatada YAKUSHIJI on August 11 (the Eisho Disturbance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>軍を京都に撤退させようとしたが、一色義有や丹後の国人の反撃を受け、6月26日に自害に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attempted to withdraw troops to Kyoto, but Yoshiari ISSHIKI and local samurai in Tango Province made a counterattack, which led Tomotsune to commit suicide on August 14.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attempted to withdraw the troops from Kyoto, but Yoshiari ISSHIKI and the local samurai in Tango Province made a counterattack, which led Tomotsune to commit suicide on August 14.</e>
<cmt>withdraw the troops to Kyoto → withdraw the troops from Kyoto. Local samuari → the local samurai. 一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attempted to withdraw the troops to Kyoto, but Yoshiari ISSHIKI and the local samurai in Tango Province made a counterattack, which led Tomotsune to commit suicide on August 14.</e>
<cmt>from→to</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), ドルチェット(id:46458), ブレイズマン(id:183852), カイの迷宮(id:72682), 海衛士(id:19229), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>