<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原利仁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshihito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Toshihito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshihito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 利仁（ふじわら の としひと、生没年不詳）は、平安時代中期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshihito (year of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) lived in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Toshihito (years of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) lived in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>複数化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Toshihito (years of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) lived in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家藤原魚名流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Uona line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Uona line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Uona line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>祖父藤原高房は受領を歴任したほか盗賊の取締りで名を上げた人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grandfather FUJIWARA no Takafusa held Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors) and won fame for controlling of robbers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather FUJIWARA no Takafusa held Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors) and won fame for controlling of robbers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather FUJIWARA no Takafusa held Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors) and won fame for controlling of robbers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は民部卿藤原時長（中納言藤原山蔭の同母兄弟）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was FUJIWARA no Tokinaga, Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs) (maternal half-brother of FUJIWARA no Yamakage, Chunagon [middle counsellor]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs), FUJIWARA no Tokinaga (maternal half-brother of Chunagon [middle counsellor], FUJIWARA no Yamakage).</e>
<cmt>語順変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs), FUJIWARA no Tokinaga (maternal half-brother of Chunagon [middle counsellor], FUJIWARA no Yamakage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母は越前国出身の秦豊国女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of HATA no Toyokuni from Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of HATA no Toyokuni from Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of HATA no Toyokuni from Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>室に丹波国目伴統忠女、四品輔世王女などがあったほか、越前国敦賀の豪族藤原有仁の娘婿ともなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had wives such as a daughter of TOMO no Munetada titled sakan (the fourth rank govenment official under the Ritsuryo legal code) of Tanba Province and a daughter of Prince Sukeyo titled Shihon (the fourth rank of Imperial Princes&apos; rank); besides, became a son-in-law of FUJIWARA no Arihito who was from Gozoku (local ruling family) in Tsuruga, Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had wives such as a daughter of TOMO no Munetada titled sakan (the fourth rank govenment official under the Ritsuryo legal code) of Tanba Province and a daughter of Prince Sukeyo titled Shihon (the fourth rank of Imperial Princes&apos; rank); besides, became a son-in-law of FUJIWARA no Arihito who was Gozoku (local ruling family) in Tsuruga, Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>fromを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had wives such as a daughter of TOMO no Munetada titled sakan (the fourth rank govenment official under the Ritsuryo legal code) of Tanba Province and a daughter of Prince Sukeyo titled Shihon (the fourth rank of Imperial Princes&apos; rank); besides, became a son-in-law of FUJIWARA no Arihito who was Gozoku (local ruling family) in Tsuruga, Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>左近将監などを経て、延喜11年（911年）上野国介となり、翌12年（912年）に上総国介に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After experienced some posts including Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), he became Kozuke no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Kozuke) in 911 and was appointed to Kazusa no kuni no suke in 912.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After experienced some posts including Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), he became Kozuke no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Kozuke) in 911 and was appointed Kazusa no kuni no suke in 912.</e>
<cmt>to削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After experienced some posts including Sakon no shogen (Lieutenant the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), he became Kozuke no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Kozuke) in 911 and was appointed Kazusa no kuni no suke in 912.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのほか下総国介や武蔵国守など坂東の国司を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he held some posts of kokushi (provincial governors) in Bando region such as Shimosa no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Shimousa) and Musashi no kuni no kami (governor of Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he held some posts of kokushi (provincial governor) in Bando region such as Shimosa no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Shimousa) and Musashi no kuni no kami (governor of Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>単数化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he held some posts of kokushi (provincial governor) in Bando region such as Shimosa no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Shimousa) and Musashi no kuni no kami (governor of Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同15年（915年）には下野国高蔵山で貢調を略奪した群盗数千を鎮圧し武略を天下に知らしめたということが『鞍馬蓋寺縁起』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Anba Gaiji Engi&quot;(historical records book written in Muromachi period) tells that he suppressed a gang of several thousand robbers who had plundered tribute in Mt. Takakura of Shimotsuke Province and could show his strategy to the whole country in 915.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。「鞍馬蓋寺縁起」の定訳不明の為、ローマ字表記の後に括弧で補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Anba Gaiji Engi&quot;(historical records book written in the Muromachi period) tells that he suppressed a gang of several thousand robbers who had plundered of tribute in Mt.Takakura in Shimotsuke Province and could show his strategy to the whole country in 915.</e>
<cmt>冠詞挿入、of挿入、スペース削除、前置詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Anba Gaiji Engi&quot;(historical records book written in the Muromachi period) tells that he suppressed a gang of several thousand robbers who had plundered of tribute in Mt.Takakura in Shimotsuke Province and could show his strategy to the whole country in 915.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この年には鎮守府将軍となり、その最終位階は従四位下であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) in this year, whose last court rank was said to be Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) in the same year and his last court rank is said to have been Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>「この年」の表現変更、whoseを変更、時制変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Chinju-fu shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) in the same year and his last court rank is said to have been Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>後代、平安時代の代表的な武人として伝説化され多くの説話が残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many legendized stories as a typical warrior lived in Heian period have been handed down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many legendary stories in which he was a typical warrior lived in the Heian period have been handed down.</e>
<cmt>in which he was挿入、冠詞挿入、legendizeはあまり使われないので変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many legendary stories in which he was a typical warrior lived in the Heian period have been handed down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なかでも『今昔物語集』の中にある、五位の者に芋粥を食べさせようと京都から敦賀の舘へ連れ帰った話などが有名である（芥川龍之介はこの話を題材に小説『芋粥』を執筆している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among all those stories, the story written in &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (Tales of Times Now and Then collection) that he took back a man titled goi (Fifth Rank) from Kyoto to a residence in Tsuruga to let a man eat imogayu (sweet-potato broth) is famous (Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA wrote a novel &quot;Imogayu&quot; based on this story).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among all those stories, the story in &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (Tales of Times Now and Then collection) that he took a man titled goi (Fifth Rank) from Kyoto to his residence in Tsuruga to let a man eat imogayu (sweet-potato broth) is famous (Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA wrote a novel &quot;Imogayu&quot; based on this story).</e>
<cmt>written・back削除、his挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among all those stories, the story in &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (Tales of Times Now and Then collection) that he took a man titled goi (Fifth Rank) from Kyoto to his residence in Tsuruga to let a man eat imogayu (sweet-potato broth) is famous (Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA wrote a novel &quot;Imogayu&quot; based on this story).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>次男の藤原叙用が、斎宮頭となり、斎藤氏の祖となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second son FUJIWARA no Nobumochi became Saiku no kami (Director General of the High Priestess Office) and an ancestor of the Saito clan.</e>
<cmt>「斎宮頭」の定訳不明です。「斎宮寮の長官」として補足してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His second son FUJIWARA no Nobumochi became Saiku no kami (Director General of the High Priestess Office) and the ancestor of the Saito clan.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His second son FUJIWARA no Nobumochi became Saiku no kami (Director General of the High Priestess Office) and the ancestor of the Saito clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その孫の代では忠頼が加賀国介となり、加賀斎藤氏、弘岡斎藤氏、牧野氏の祖となり、加賀斎藤氏から堀氏、弘岡斎藤氏から富樫氏、林氏が出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his grandchild&apos;s time, Tadayori became Kaga no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Kaga) and an ancestor of the Kaga-Saito clan which originated the Hori clan, the Hirooka-Saito clan which originated the Togashi and the Hayashi clan, and the Makino clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his grandchild&apos;s time, Tadayori became Kaga no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Kaga) and the ancestor of the Kaga-Saito clan which was the origin of the Hori clan; the Hirooka-Saito clan which was the origin of the Togashi and the Hayashi clan; and the Makino clan.</e>
<cmt>セミコロン使用、動詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his grandchild&apos;s time, Tadayori became Kaga no kuni no suke (officer in charge of regional administration in Kaga) and the ancestor of the Kaga-Saito clan which was the origin of the Hori clan; the Hirooka-Saito clan which was the origin of the Togashi and the Hayashi clan; and the Makino clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>叙用の孫為時の家系からは吉田氏、前田氏、尚忠から吉原斎藤氏、河合斎藤氏、美濃斎藤氏が出たほか、重光から加藤氏、遠山氏が出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yoshida clan and the Maeda clan from a lineage of Nobumochi&apos;s grandson Tametoki, the Yoshiwara-Saito clan, the Kawai-Saito clan and the Mino-Saito clan from a lineage of Naotada, and besides the Kato clan and the Toyama clan from a lineage of Shigemitsu were generated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yoshida clan and the Maeda clan origined from a lineage of Nobumochi&apos;s grandson Tametoki, the Yoshiwara-Saito clan, the Kawai-Saito clan and the Mino-Saito clan originated from a lineage of Naotada, and the Kato clan and the Toyama clan originated from a lineage of Shigemitsu.</e>
<cmt>動詞変更、besides削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yoshida clan and the Maeda clan origined from a lineage of Nobumochi&apos;s grandson Tametoki, the Yoshiwara-Saito clan, the Kawai-Saito clan and the Mino-Saito clan originated from a lineage of Naotada, and the Kato clan and the Toyama clan originated from a lineage of Shigemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、一女は藤原秀郷の孫にあたる藤原文脩の室となり藤原文行、兼光らの母となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, his daughter married FUJIWARA no Fuminaga, a grandson of FUJIWARA no Hidesato, and became a mother of FUJIWARA no Fumiyuki and Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, his daughter married FUJIWARA no Fuminaga, a grandson of FUJIWARA no Hidesato, and became the mother of FUJIWARA no Fumiyuki and Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, his daughter married FUJIWARA no Fuminaga, a grandson of FUJIWARA no Hidesato, and became the mother of FUJIWARA no Fumiyuki and Kanemitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>利仁の後裔を称する氏族は多く仮冒は少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many families claim to be the descendants of Toshihito and those who give a false name are few.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many families claim to be the descendants of Toshihito without deceit.</e>
<cmt>「仮冒は少ない」の表現変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many families claim to be the descendants of Toshihito without deceit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また藤原秀郷と並んで藤原氏の武家社会への進出を象徴する人物と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that he was a symbolic man who made the Fujiwara clan&apos;s way into samurai society as well as FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that he was a symbolic man who made the Fujiwara clan&apos;s way into samurai society along with FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt>as well asを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that he was a symbolic man who made the Fujiwara clan&apos;s way into samurai society along with FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), ちちぶ(id:184715), Yanahan(id:2437), 味っ子(id:17086), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), BAKU(id:55205), 小者(id:172526), 堀五郎右衛門(id:84263), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>