<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原実政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanemasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sanemasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanemasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 実政（ふじわら の さねまさ、寛仁3年（1019年） - 寛治7年2月18日 (旧暦)（1093年3月23日））は平安時代中期の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanemasa (1019 - March 23, 1093) was a nobility in the middle period of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sanemasa (1019 - March 23, 1093) was a nobleman during the middle period of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanemasa (1019 - March 23, 1093) was a nobleman during the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>mid Heian period と他記事と表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>従三位藤原資業の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a child of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) FUJIWARA no Sukenari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the child of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) FUJIWARA no Sukenari.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the child of FUJIWARA no Sukenari, who had the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>従二位・参議。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His court rank was Junii (Junior Second Rank) Sangi (councillor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His court rank was Junii (Junior Second Rank) Sangi (councillor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His court rank was Junii (Junior Second Rank) and had the title of Sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>藤原北家日野流（藤原真夏流）、日野三位藤原資業の三男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the third son of Hino sanmi, FUJIWARA no Sukenari, of the Hino Line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (FUJIWARA no Manatsu line).</e>
<cmt>日野三位→定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the third son of Hino sanmi, FUJIWARA no Sukenari, of the Hino Line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (FUJIWARA no Manatsu line).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the third son of Hino sanmi, FUJIWARA no Sukenari, of the Hino Line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan (FUJIWARA no Manatsu line).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>文章博士であった父と同様に学問の道を歩み、長暦元年（1038年）文章得業生となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like his father, who was a Monjo hakase (professor of literature), he also learned literature and became as Monjo tokugosho (Distinguished Scholars of Letters) in 1038.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like his father, who was a Monjo hakase (professor of literature), he also learned literature and became as Monjo tokugosho (Distinguished Scholar of Letters) in 1038.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like his father, who was a Monjo hakase (professor of literature), he also learned literature and became as Monjo tokugosho (Distinguished Scholar of Letters) in 1038.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>次いで対策に及第し、長久2年（1041年）に六位蔵人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he passed taisaku (one of the examination for adopting government officials under the Ritsuryo legal codes) and became as Rokui no Kurodo (Chamberlain of Sixth Rank) in 1041.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, he passed taisaku (one of the examinations for adopting government officials under the Ritsuryo legal codes) and became Rokui no Kurodo (Chamberlain of Sixth Rank) in 1041.</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, he passed taisaku (one of the examinations for adopting government officials under the Ritsuryo legal codes) and became Rokui no Kurodo (Chamberlain of Sixth Rank) in 1041.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>長久3年（1042年）には後朱雀天皇の第二皇子尊仁親王（後の後三条天皇）読書始で尚復（侍読が読んだ内容を復唱する役割）を勤めた（『今鏡』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1042, he served as Shofuku (a person who repeats after what Jidoku (Imperial tutor) have read) in Dokushohajime (a ceremony when one starts to study) of the second Prince of Emperor Gosuzaku, Imperial Prince Takahito (later Emperor Gosanjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1042, he served as Shofuku (a person who repeats after what Jidoku (Imperial tutor has read) in Dokushohajime (a ceremony when one starts to study) of the second Prince of Emperor Gosuzaku, Imperial Prince Takahito (later Emperor Gosanjo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1042, he served as Shofuku (a person who repeats after what Jidoku [Imperial tutor] has read) in Dokushohajime (a ceremony when one starts to study) of the second Prince of Emperor Gosuzaku, Imperial Prince Takahito (later Emperor Gosanjo) (&quot;Imakagami&quot; [The Mirror of the Present]).</e>
<cmt>括弧の場所を一部修正しました。｢今鏡」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>永承5年（1050年）に東宮尊仁親王の東宮学士となり、敦成親王（後一条天皇）の侍読を勤めた父資業に続いて、親子二代で侍読となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1050, he bacame as Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics of the Crown Prince) of Togu (the Crown Prince), Imperial Prince Takahito, and with his father, who had bacame as Jidoku of Imperial Prince Atsuhira (Emperor Goichijo), they became as Jidoku in 2 generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1050, he bacame Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics for the Crown Prince) of Togu (the Crown Prince), Imperial Prince Takahito, and with his father, who had bacame Jidoku of Imperial Prince Atsuhira (Emperor Goichijo), they became as Jidoku in two generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1050, he became Togu gakushi (Teacher of the Classics for the Crown Prince) of Togu (the Crown Prince), Imperial Prince Takahito, and with his father, who had became Jidoku of Imperial Prince Atsuhira (Emperor Goichijo), they became as Jidoku in two generations.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>東宮学士実政に対する尊仁親王の信頼は厚く、天喜元年（1053年）、東宮御息所・藤原茂子 が第一皇子・貞仁親王を生んだ際には、実政の姉妹（藤原惟経の妻）が乳母の一人となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Takahito had deep trust against Togu gakushi Sanemasa, and when Togu Miyasudokoro (wife of Crown Prince) FUJIWARA no Moshi gave birth to his first Prince, Imperial Prince Sadahito, Sanemasa&apos;s sister (wife of FUJIWARA no Koretsune) became as one of Prince&apos;s wet nurse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Takahito had deep trust in Togu gakushi Sanemasa, and when Togu Miyasudokoro (wife of Crown Prince) FUJIWARA no Moshi gave birth to his first Prince, Imperial Prince Sadahito, Sanemasa&apos;s sister (wife of FUJIWARA no Koretsune) became as one of Prince&apos;s wet nurses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Takahito had deep trust in Togu gakushi Sanemasa, and when Togu Miyasudokoro (wife of Crown Prince) FUJIWARA no Moshi gave birth to his first Prince in 1053, Imperial Prince Sadahito, Sanemasa&apos;s sister (wife of FUJIWARA no Koretsune) became as one of Prince&apos;s wet nurses.</e>
<cmt>1053を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、康平7年（1064年）に実政が甲斐国国司に任じられ任国に下向する際、尊仁親王から、任国に行っても平安京のことひいては私のことを忘れないで欲しい、との趣旨の御製が贈られた（『今鏡』『十訓抄』等）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in 1064, when Sanemasa was appointed as Kai no kuni Kokushi (the provincial governor of Kai Province) and was going down to the place, a poem, with the general meaning that even when Sanemasa goes down to Kai Province, please do not forget about Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto) and myself, was sent from Imperial Prince Takahito (&quot;Imakagami,&quot; &quot;Jikkinsho,&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in 1064, when Sanemasa was appointed Kai no kuni Kokushi (the provincial governor of Kai Province) and was going down to the place, a poem, with the general meaning that even when Sanemasa goes down to Kai Province, please do not forget about Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto) and myself, was sent from Imperial Prince Takahito (&quot;Imakagami,&quot; &quot;Jikkinsho,&quot; and so on).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in 1064, when Sanemasa was appointed Kai no kuni Kokushi (Provincial Governor of Kai Province) and was going down to the place, a poem, with the general meaning that even when Sanemasa goes down to Kai Province, please do not forget about Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto) and myself, was sent from Imperial Prince Takahito (&quot;Imakagami,&quot; &quot;Jikkinsho&quot; [Miscellany of Ten Maxims], and so on).</e>
<cmt>十訓抄　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>治暦4年（1068年）、尊仁親王が後三条天皇として即位したことに伴い、実政は前東宮学士の労により正四位に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1068, following the enthronement of Imperial Prince Takahito as Emperor Gosanjo, Sanemasa was also advanced to Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), with his achievements as the former Togu gakushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1068, following the enthronement of Imperial Prince Takahito as Emperor Gosanjo, Sanemasa was also advanced to Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), because of his achievements as the former Togu gakushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1068, following the enthronement of Imperial Prince Takahito as Emperor Gosanjo, Sanemasa was also advanced to Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), because of his achievements as the former Togu gakushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>翌、治暦5年（1069年）には、同じく尊仁親王の学士であった大江匡房とともに新東宮貞仁親王（後の白河天皇）の学士に任じられ、尊仁・貞仁と二代続けて東宮学士を勤めることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, 1069, along with OE no Masafusa, who was also gakushi (teacher) of Imperial Prince Takahito, he was appointed as gakushi of new Togu Imperial Prince Sadahito (later Emperor Shirakawa), and became to serve as Togu gakushi to 2 generations, Takahito and Sadahito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, 1069, along with OE no Masafusa, who was also gakushi (teacher) of Imperial Prince Takahito, he was appointed as gakushi of new Togu Imperial Prince Sadahito (later Emperor Shirakawa), and came to serve as Togu gakushi for two generations, Takahito and Sadahito.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, 1069, along with OE no Masafusa, who was also gakushi (teacher) of Imperial Prince Takahito, he was appointed as gakushi of new Togu Imperial Prince Sadahito (later Emperor Shirakawa), and came to serve as Togu gakushi for two generations, Takahito and Sadahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>後三条天皇が即位してからも、その信頼は変わらず、延久4年12月（1073年）には弁官へ抜擢された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The trust against him was not changed even after the enthronement as Emperor Gosanjo, and in between January - February, 1073 (December 1072 in old lunar calendar), Sanemasa was selected as Benkan (officials of the Dajokan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trust in him did not change even after the enthronement as Emperor Gosanjo, and in between January - February, 1073 (December 1072 in old lunar calendar), Sanemasa was selected as Benkan (an official of the Dajokan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trust in him did not change even after the enthronement as Emperor Gosanjo, and in between January - February, 1073, Sanemasa was selected as Benkan (an official of the Dajokan).</e>
<cmt>旧暦の記載は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この人事について、本来なら権左中弁の藤原隆方を任命すべき所であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for this personnel affairs, Gon Sachuben (Provisional Middle Controller of the left) FUJIWARA no Takakata should have been the one to be selected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for personnel affairs, Gon Sachuben (Provisional Middle Controller of the Left) FUJIWARA no Takakata should have been the one selected.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for personnel affairs, Gon Sachuben (Provisional Middle Controller of the Left) FUJIWARA no Takakata should have been the one selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかしながら、以前木津の渡しで隆方が実政に対して、なかなか天皇になれない皇太子（尊仁親王）に当てこすった悪口を言ったことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the past at Kizu no Watashi (ferry at Kizu), Takakata slandered Sanemasa, relating to the Crown Prince (Imperial Prince Takahito) who could not become as the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the past at Kizu no Watashi (ferry at Kizu), Takakata slandered Sanemasa, relating to the Crown Prince (Imperial Prince Takahito) who could not become Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the past at Kizu no Watashi (ferry at Kizu), Takakata slandered Sanemasa, relating to the Crown Prince (Imperial Prince Takahito) who could not become Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>それを覚えていた後三条天皇は隆方を越えて敢えて実政を左中弁に任じたとされる（『今鏡』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo, remembering that, is said to have daringly selected Sanemasa as Sachuben (middle controller of the left), skipping Takakata (&quot;Imakagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosanjo, remembering that, is said to have daringly selected Sanemasa as Sachuben (middle controller of the left), skipping Takakata (&quot;Imakagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo, remembering that, is said to have daringly selected Sanemasa as Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left), skipping Takakata (&quot;Imakagami&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Middle Controller of the Left と大文字で統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>実政が左中弁となった直後、後三条天皇は貞仁親王（白河天皇）に譲位し院庁を開くと実政は院司となるが、まもなく後三条院は崩御した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Right after Sanemasa became as Sachuben, Emperor Gosanjo abdicated the throne to Imperial Prince Sadahito (Emperor Shirakawa) and opened In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) with Sanemasa as In no tsukasa (official of In no cho), but Gosanjoin (the retired Emperor Gosanjo) died soon after.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Right after Sanemasa became as Sachuben, Emperor Gosanjo abdicated the throne to Imperial Prince Sadahito (Emperor Shirakawa) and opened In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) with Sanemasa as In no tsukasa (official of In no cho), but Gosanjoin (the retired Emperor Gosanjo) died soon after.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Right after Sanemasa became as Sachuben, Emperor Gosanjo abdicated the throne to Imperial Prince Sadahito (Emperor Shirakawa) and opened In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) with Sanemasa as In no tsukasa (official of In no cho), but Gosanjo-in (the Retired Emperor Gosanjo) died soon after.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperorとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>次代の白河天皇も恩師である実政を厚遇し、承保4年（1077年）に蔵人頭、承暦4年（1080年）には参議・従三位と順調に昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next Emperor Shirakawa also treated his former teacher Sanemasa very well, and Sanemasa was smoothly advanced as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1077, and as Sangi (councillor) Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1080.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next Emperor Shirakawa also treated his former teacher Sanemasa very well, and Sanemasa was smoothly advanced as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1077, and as Sangi (councillor) Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1080.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next Emperor Shirakawa also treated his former teacher Sanemasa very well, and Sanemasa was smoothly advanced as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1077, and as Sangi (councilor) Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 1080.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>永保4年（1084年）実政は太宰大弐となり、大宰府へ下向する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1084, Sanemasa became as Dazai daini (senior assistant governor-general of Government Headquarters in Kyushu), and went down to Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1084, Sanemasa became as Dazai daini (senior assistant governor-general of Government Headquarters in Kyushu), and went to Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1084, Sanemasa became as Dazai daini (senior assistant governor-general of Government Headquarters in Kyushu), and went to Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>太宰府では九州最大の荘園領主であった宇佐八幡宮との間に紛争が発生したらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that a dispute broke out at Dazaifu between the largest lord of shoen (manor in medieval Japan) in Kyushu, Usa Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that a dispute broke out at Dazaifu between the largest lord of the shoen (manor in medieval Japan) in Kyushu, Usa Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that a dispute broke out at Dazaifu between the largest lord of the shoen (manor in medieval Japan) in Kyushu, Usa Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>寛治元年（1087年）、宇佐八幡宮の神人から白河院御所に対して、実政が正八幡宮神輿を射て毀損したとの訴えがあり、翌寛治2年（1088年）に実政は太宰大弐を辞して上洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1087, an invocation was made from jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) of Usa Hachimangu Shrine to Imperial palace of Shirakawa-in (retired Emperor Shirakawa), stating that Sanemasa shot mikoshi (portable shrine) of Sei Hachimangu with an arrow and has broken it, and Sanemasa resigned the position of Dazai daini and went up to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1087, an invocation was made from jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) of Usa Hachimangu Shrine to Imperial palace of Shirakawa-in (retired Emperor Shirakawa), stating that Sanemasa shot mikoshi (portable shrine) of Sei Hachimangu with an arrow and has broken it, and Sanemasa resigned the position of Dazai daini and went to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1087, an invocation was made from jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) of Usa Hachimangu Shrine to Imperial palace of Shirakawa-in (Retired Emperor Shirakawa), stating that Sanemasa shot mikoshi (portable shrine) of Sei Hachimangu with an arrow and has broken it, and Sanemasa resigned the position of Dazai daini and went to Kyoto in 1088.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperorとしました。1088を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>結局同年11月に実政は伊豆国への流罪と決定、併せて息子藤原敦宗も連座し左少弁を解官された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, in December of the same year, Sanemasa was decided to be banished to Izu Province, and his son FUJIWARA no Atsumune was also implicated and was made to resign from Sashoben (the third officer of department overseeing some major ministries).</e>
<cmt>11月を旧暦とみなして訳しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, in December of the same year, Sanemasa was banished to Izu Province, and his son FUJIWARA no Atsumune was also implicated and was made to resign from Sashoben (the third officer of department overseeing some major ministries).</e>
<cmt>grammar, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, in December of the same year, Sanemasa was banished to Izu Province, and his son FUJIWARA no Atsumune was also implicated and was made to resign from Sashoben (Minor Controller of the Left).</e>
<cmt>左少弁　補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その後実政は配流途中の近江国で出家したが許されず、寛治7年（1093年）伊豆国の配所で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Sanemasa became as a priest at Omi Province along the way to be banished but was not forgiven, an in 1093, he died at haisho (the place where a criminal is sent) in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Sanemasa became as a priest at Omi Province along the way to be banished but was not forgiven, an in 1093, he died at haisho (the place where a criminal is sent) in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Sanemasa became a priest at Omi Province along the way to be banished but was not forgiven, and in 1093, he died at haisho (the place where a criminal is sent) in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>官位・官職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Court ranks and court duties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Court ranks and court duties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of offices and ranks held</e>
<cmt>他記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>長暦元年（1038年） 文章得業生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1038 Monjo tokugosho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1038 Monjo tokugosho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1038: Monjo tokugosho</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>長暦2年（1039年） 美作国国司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1039 Mimasaka no kuni Kokushi (the provincial governor of Mimasaka Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1039 Mimasaka no kuni Kokushi (the provincial governor of Mimasaka Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1039: Mimasaka no kuni Kokushi (Provincial Governor of Mimasaka Province).</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>長久2年（1041年） 蔵人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1041 Kurodo (Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1041 Kurodo (Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1041: Kurodo (Chamberlain)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>長久4年（1043年） 式部省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1043 Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonial)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1043 Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonies)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1043: Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonies)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>長久5年（1044年） 従五位、宮内省</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1044 Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank), Kunaisho (Imperial Household Ministry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1044 Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank), Kunaisho (Imperial Household Ministry)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1044: Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank), Kunaisho (Imperial Household Ministry)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>永承5年（1050年） 大内記、従五位上、東宮学士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1050 Dainaiki (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade), Togu gakushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1050 Dainaiki (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade), Togu gakushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1050: Dainaiki (Senior Secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs), Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade), Togu gakushi</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>永承7年（1052年） 美濃国権介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1052 Mino no Gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Governor of Mino Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1052 Mino no Gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Governor of Mino Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1052: Mino no Gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Governor of Mino Province)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>天喜4年（1056年） 正五位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1056 Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1056 Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1056: Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>天喜6年（1058年） 加賀国権守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1058 Junior Governor of Kaga Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1058 Junior Governor of Kaga Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1058: Kaga no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Kaga Province)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>康平4年（1061年） 従四位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1061 Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1061 Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1061: Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>康平7年（1064年） 甲斐国守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1064 Governor of Kai Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1064 Governor of Kai Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1064: Kai no kuni no kami (Governor of Kai Province)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>治暦3年（1067年） 従四位上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1067 Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1067 Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1067: Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>治暦4年（1068年） 止東宮学士（尊仁親王踐祚による）、正四位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1068 Resigned from Togu gakushi (by Imperial succession of Imperial Prince Takahito), Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1068 Resigned from Togu gakushi (by Imperial succession of Imperial Prince Takahito), Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1068: Resigned from Togu gakushi (by Imperial succession of Imperial Prince Takahito), Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="37">
<j>治暦5年（1069年） 備中国守、文章博士、東宮学士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1069 Governor of Bicchu Province, Monjo hakase, Togu gakushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1069 Governor of Bicchu Province, Monjo hakase, Togu gakushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1069: Bicchu no kuni no kami (Governor of Bicchu Province), Monjo hakase, Togu gakushi</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="38">
<j>延久4年（1072年） 近江国守、弁官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1072 Governor of Omi Province, Benkan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1072 Governor of Omi Province, Benkan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1072: Oe no kuni no kami (Governor of Oe Province), Benkan</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="39">
<j>延久5年（1073年） 正四位上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1073 Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1073 Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1073: Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="40">
<j>承保2年（1075年） 修理左宮城使、右大弁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1075 Shuri sagujo shi (Secretary of the left Office of Palace Repairs), Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1075 Shuri sagujo shi (Secretary of the left Office of Palace Repairs), Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1075: Shuri sagujo shi (Secretary of the left Office of Palace Repairs), Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="41">
<j>承保4年（1077年） 蔵人頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1077 Kurodo no to</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1077 Kurodo no to</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1077: Kurodo no to</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="42">
<j>承暦元年（1078年） 京職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1078 Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1078 Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1078: Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="43">
<j>承暦2年（1078年） 但馬国権守、辞文章博士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1078 Junior Governor of Tajima Province, resigned from Monjo hakase</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1078 Junior Governor of Tajima Province, resigned from Monjo hakase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1078: Tajima no kuni Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Tajima Province), resigned from Monjo hakase</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="44">
<j>承暦4年（1080年） 参議、左大弁、従三位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1080 Sangi, Sadaiben (major controller of the left), Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1080 Sangi, Sadaiben (major controller of the left), Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1080: Sangi, Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left), Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="45">
<j>承暦5年（1081年） 勘解由使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1081 Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1081 Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1081: Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="46">
<j>永保2年（1082年） 正三位、讃岐国守、罷右京大夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1082 Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), Governor of Sanuki Province, removed as Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1082 Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), Governor of Sanuki Province, removed as Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1082: Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), Sanuki no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Sanuki Province), removed as Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="47">
<j>永保4年（1084年） 太宰府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1084 Dazaifu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1084 Dazaifu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1084: Dazaifu</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="48">
<j>応徳2年（1086年） 従二位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1063 Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1063 Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1086: Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>西暦＋コロン　の表現にしました。数字を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), Balmung0731(id:99201), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>