<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>毛利良勝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikatsu MORI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikatsu MORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikatsu MORI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>毛利 良勝（もうり よしかつ、生年不詳 - 天正10年6月2日 (旧暦)（1582年6月21日））は、織田信長の家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikatsu MORI (year of birth not known - June 21, 1582) was a Nobunaga ODA&apos;s retainer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikatsu MORI (year of birth not known - June 21, 1582) was Nobunaga ODA&apos;s retainer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikatsu MORI (year of birth not known - July 1, 1582) was Nobunaga ODA&apos;s retainer.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。Original記載の西暦はユリウス暦でした。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称は新助（新介とも）、新左衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Common name was Shinsuke (also written as &quot;新介&quot; instead of &quot;新助&quot;), and Shinzaemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Common name was Shinsuke (also written as &quot;新介&quot; instead of &quot;新助&quot;), and Shinzaemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Common name was Shinsuke (also written as &quot;新介&quot; instead of &quot;新助&quot;), and Shinzaemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>名は秀高とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had name of Hidetaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had name of Hidetaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had name of Hidetaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>身分は信長の馬廻であるが、小姓であったともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His status was Nobunaga&apos;s umamawari (general&apos;s mounted guard), but in another view, he was a kosho (page).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His status was Nobunaga&apos;s umamawari (general&apos;s mounted guard), but in another view, he was a kosho (page).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His status was Nobunaga&apos;s umamawari (general&apos;s mounted guard), but in another view, he was a kosho (page).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>出自については不明だが、織田信長に仕え、永禄3年（1560年）、桶狭間の戦いでは負傷した服部一忠を助け、今川義元の首を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His origin is not known, but he served Nobunaga ODA and, in 1560 in the Battle of Okehazama, he helped Kazutada HATTORI, who had been injured, and beheaded Yoshimoto IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His origin is not known, but he served Nobunaga ODA and, in 1560 in the Battle of Okehazama, he helped Kazutada HATTORI, who had been injured, and beheaded Yoshimoto IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his birthplace is not known, he served Nobunaga ODA and he helped Kazutada HATTORI who had been injured in the Battle of Okehazama in1560 and beheaded Yoshimoto IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その功により、のちに黒母衣衆のひとりとなったが、信長上洛後は大河内城攻め、甲州攻めなどでは名があるが、あまりぱっとせず、吏僚的な活躍が多いため、一隊の長に昇ることなく信長の側近として旗本部隊に属した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the reward for it, he was later promoted to a member of kurohoroshu (a group of selected warriors of Nobunaga ODA), but, after Nobunaga&apos;s visit to Kyoto, although his name was mentioned in records of the attack to Okochi-jo Castile and Invasion to Koshu, he did not have remarkable achievements and, because his worked mainly as an clerical staff, he was not promoted to a chief of a troop and belonged to a troop of the direct vassal to Nobunaga as close vassal.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the reward for it, he was later promoted to a member of kurohoroshu (a group of selected warriors of Nobunaga ODA), but, after Nobunaga&apos;s visit to Kyoto, although his name was mentioned in records of the attack on Okochi-jo Castile and the Invasion of Koshu, he did not have any remarkable achievements and, because he worked mainly as aclerical staff, he was not promoted to chief of troops and belonged to the troops of the direct vassal to Nobunaga, as a close vassal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the reward for that, he was later promoted to a member of kurohoroshu (a group of selected warriors of Nobunaga ODA), but after Nobunaga&apos;s visit to Kyoto, he did not have any remarkable achievements, so that although he made his name in the attack on Okochi-jo Castile and the Invasion of Koshu, he was not promoted to a chief of troops but he belonged to the troops of the direct vassal to Nobunaga as a close vassal because he worked mainly as a clerical staff.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天正10年（1582年）、本能寺の変の際は京都に随行しており、信長の長子織田信忠を守って二条城に篭り、最期に黒母衣衆としての意地を見せ、奮戦して壮絶に討死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582 on the occasion of the Honnoji Incident, he had following Nobunaga to Kyoto and he stayed in the Nijo-jo Castle to guard Nobutada ODA, who was the heir of Nobunaga, and showed his pride as a kurohoroshu and fought bravely and died a hero.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582 on the occasion of the Honnoji Incident, he had followed Nobunaga to Kyoto and stayed in Nijo-jo Castle to guard Nobutada ODA, who was the heir of Nobunaga, and showed his pride as a kurohoroshu and fought bravely and died a hero.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, on the occasion of the Honno-ji Temple Incident, he had followed Nobunaga to Kyoto and had stayed in the Nijo-jo Castle to guard Nobutada ODA who was the heir of Nobunaga and proved himself as a kurohoroshu and fought bravely and died in battle.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Loveless(id:129239), 難民(id:4644), Kotoito(id:21045), Safkan(id:423), Kamakura(id:472), Kouzuke1(id:2531), Suisui(id:69), Kagetudo(id:163875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>