<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>橘公業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kiminari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Kiminari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kiminari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>橘 公業（たちばな の きみなり、生没年未詳）は、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期の橘氏の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kiminari (years of birth and death unknown) was a general of the TACHIBANA family from the late Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Kiminari (公業) (years of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Tachibana family from the late Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記についての説明があるので原文を併記します。「武将」の訳出は用語集を参照しました。家名は頭文字のみ大文字で表記します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Kiminari (公業) (years of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Tachibana family from the late Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>公成とも表記される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was also written as Kiminari.</e>
<cmt>「公業」と「公成」の読み方は同じなので、英訳は同じ。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was also written as 公成.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記についての説明があるので原文を併記します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was also written as 公成.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>橘公長の次男であるため通称を橘次といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he was the second son of TACHIBANA no Kiminaga, he was commonly called Ji TACHIBANA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he was the second son of TACHIBANA no Kiminaga, he was commonly called Kitsuji, which literally meant &quot;Tachibana the second.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「橘次」は「きつじ」と読みます。そのまま英訳しても意味が通らないので説明を加えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he was the second son of TACHIBANA no Kiminaga, he was commonly called Kitsuji, which literally meant &quot;Tachibana the second.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法名を公蓮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legal name was Koren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legal name was Koren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legal name was Koren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>弓の名手であったと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was an excellent archer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was an excellent archer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was an excellent archer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>兄は橘公忠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His elder brother was TACHIBANA no Kimitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His elder brother was TACHIBANA no Kimitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His elder brother was TACHIBANA no Kimitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元々平知盛の家人であった父に従った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was originally following his father, who was a family member of TAIRA no Tomomori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was originally following his father, who was a Kenin (retainer) of TAIRA no Tomomori.</e>
<cmt>「家人」の訳出は用語集を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was originally following his father, who was a Kenin (retainer) of TAIRA no Tomomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>治承四年（1180年）に平家を見限って源氏の麾下に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1180, he gave up his position in the TAIRA family and entered the GENJI family as a direct retainer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1180, he gave up the Taira family and became a direct retainer of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>「平家を見限った」のですからhis positionは不要。「源家の一員となった」わけではありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1180, he gave up the Taira family and became a direct retainer of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>奥州合戦の論功で出羽国小鹿島（現秋田県男鹿市）の地頭に補された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a rewarding of his success during the battle in Oshu Region, he was appointed as the landlord of Sorokuto Island (present Akita Prefecture Oga-shi City) in the Dewano-kuni Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a reward for his success during the battle in the Oshu Region, he was appointed as the landlord of the Shorokuto Island in the Dewano-kuni Province (presently Oga City, Akita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>「～に対する報酬」はa reward for～。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a reward for his success during the battle in the Oshu Region, he was appointed as the landlord of the Shorokuto Island in the Dewano-kuni Province (presently Oga City, Akita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>文治5年（1189年）に起きた大河兼任の乱では敵前逃亡するなど一時は源頼朝の不興を買う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the outbreak of the Okawakaneto Riot in 1189, he escaped in front of the enemy and temporarily made MINAMOTO no Yoritomo mad.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the War of Kaneto OKAWA in 1189, he escaped in front of the enemy and temporarily made MINAMOTO no Yoritomo mad.</e>
<cmt>仕様に従い「乱」はwarと訳します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the War of Kaneto OKAWA in 1189, he escaped in front of the enemy and temporarily made MINAMOTO no Yoritomo mad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、結果として援軍を待ってから敵に当たった行為が適切であったとの評価を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after all, what his fighting back the enemy after waiting for the reinforcements was appraised as an appropriate act.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after all, his fighting back the enemy after waiting for the reinforcements was appraised as an appropriate act.</e>
<cmt>文法的にwhatは不要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after all, his fighting back the enemy after waiting for the reinforcements was appraised as an appropriate act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>乱後も小鹿島の所領を維持したほか、加えて出羽国秋田郡（現秋田県南秋田郡、潟上市、秋田市）を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the riot, not even could he keep his territory of Kojika-shima Island, he was also granted with Akita-gun County (present Minamiakita-gun County, Katagami-shi City, and Akita City of Akita Prefecture) in the Dewano-kuni Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, he not only retained his territory in the Shorokuto Island but also was granted Akita-gun County in the Dewano-kuni Province (presently Minamiakita-gun, Katagami City, and Akita City of Akita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>文構造がおかしいので修正しました。「小鹿島」の表記を修正しました。「～を付与される」はgrantedのみで可。Ｗｉｔｈは不要。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, he not only retained his territory in the Shorokuto Island but also was granted Akita-gun County in the Dewano-kuni Province (presently Minamiakita-gun, Katagami City, and Akita City of Akita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>承元3年（1209年）12月、御家人の美作朝親の妻と密通していたことから、朝親との間で合戦となり掛ける事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 1209, because he had some secret love affairs with the wife of the general Tomochi MIMASAKA of the noble family, it almost ended up in war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, 1209, he had some secret love affairs with the wife of the gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate)Tomochi MIMASAKA and almost ended up in a battle with Tomochi.</e>
<cmt>「御家人」の訳出は用語集に従いました。「朝親との間で」の訳漏れ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, 1209, he had some secret love affairs with the wife of the gokenin (an immediate vasal of the shogunate)Tomochi MIMASAKA and almost ended up in a battle with Tomochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>源実朝の命を受けた北条時房の仲介により事なきを得るという騒ぎにまで発展している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The commotion was calmed by the mediation from Tokifusa HOJO, who took the command from MINAMOTO no Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The commotion was such that it could be calmed only by the mediation by Tokifusa HOJO, who took the command from MINAMOTO no Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt>「騒ぎにまで発展」のニュアンスを出すため訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The commotion was such that it could be calmed only by the mediation by Tokifusa HOJO, who took the command from MINAMOTO no Sanetomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>嘉禎2年（1236年）に、本領であった伊予国宇和郡を西園寺公経に譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1236, his original territoy Uwa-gun County of Iyo-no-kuni Province was transferred to Kintsune SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1236, he transferred his original territoy Uwa-gun County of Iyo-no-kuni Province to Kintsune SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>能動態で訳す方が自然です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1236, he transferred his original territoy Uwa-gun County of Iyo-no-kuni Province to Kintsune SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>替地として肥前国杵島郡長島庄、大隅国種子島、豊前国副田庄、肥後国球磨郡久米郷を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In exchange, he was granted with Kishima-gun County of Hizen-no-kuni Province, Tanega-shima Island of Osumi-no-kuni Province, Soeda no sho estate of Buzen-no-kuni Province, and Kume-go Region in Kuma-gun County of Higo-no-kuni Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In exchange, he was granted Kishima-gun County of Hizen-no-kuni Province, Tanega-shima Island of Osumi-no-kuni Province, Soeda no sho estate of Buzen-no-kuni Province, and Kume-go Region in Kuma-gun County of Higo-no-kuni Province.</e>
<cmt>「～を付与される」はgrantedのみで可。Withは不要。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In exchange, he was granted Kishima-gun County of Hizen-no-kuni Province, Tanega-shima Island of Osumi-no-kuni Province, Soeda no sho estate of Buzen-no-kuni Province, and Kume-go Region in Kuma-gun County of Higo-no-kuni Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>子孫は肥前国を中心に広がることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendants became prosperous centering in Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants became prosperous in the wide area centering in Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>「を中心とする地域で」の意。Centering inだけでは不自然。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants became prosperous in the wide area centering in Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>かつて所領とした小鹿島の地名をとった小鹿島氏として繁栄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They took the name of their previous territory Sorokuto Island and prospered as the Sorokuto family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They took the name of their previous territory Sorokuto Island and prospered as the Sorokuto family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They took the name of their previous territory Sorokuto Island and prospered as the Sorokuto family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ちちぶ(id:184715), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>