<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>栄西</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>明菴 栄西（みんなんえいさい・ようさい、諡は千光国師、葉上（ようじょう）房とも称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minnan Eisai (also pronounce as Yosai) was also called Yojobo, and his shi (a posthumous name) was Senkokokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minnan Eisai (also pronounced Yosai) was also called Yojobo, and his shi (a posthumous name) was Senkokokushi.</e>
<cmt>verb form</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minnan Eisai (also pronounced Yosai) was also called Yojobo, and his shi (a posthumous name) was Senkokokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>永治元年4月20日 (旧暦)（1141年5月27日） - 建保3年7月5日 (旧暦)（1215年7月2日））は、仏教宗派・臨済宗の開祖、建仁寺の開山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He (May 27, 1141 - July 2, 1215) was the founder of Buddhism religious sect, Rinzai sect, and kaisan (a founder of temple as the first chief priest) of Kennin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He (May 27, 1141 - July 2, 1215) was the founder of a Buddhism religious sect, Rinzai sect, and kaisan (founder of a temple as the first chief priest) of Kennin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He (May 27, 1141 - July 2, 1215) was the founder of a Buddhism religious sect, Rinzai sect, and kaisan (founder of a temple as the first chief priest) of Kennin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>生年には異説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a heresy on the year of his birth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a heresy on the year of his birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a heresy on the year of his birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>天台宗葉上流の流祖でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also ryuso (a founder of school, an originator) of Yojo School of the Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also ryuso (founder of a school, an originator) of the Yojo School of the Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also ryuso (founder of a school, an originator) of the Yojo School of the Tendai Sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、喫茶の習慣を日本に伝えたことでも有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also famous for conveying the custom of tea drinking throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also famous for conveying the custom of tea drinking throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also famous for conveying the custom of tea drinking throughout Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>永治元年（1141年） 吉備津宮（現在の岡山県岡山市、吉備津神社 (岡山市)）の権禰宜賀陽貞遠の子として誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the child of Sadato KAYO, Gonnegi (general staff of a shrine) of Kibitsu no miya (present Kibitsu-jinja Shrine in Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture) in 1141.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1141, the child of Sadato KAYO, Gonnegi (general staff of a shrine) of Kibitsu no miya (present Kibitsu-jinja Shrine in Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1141, the child of Sadato KAYO, Gonnegi (general staff of a shrine) of Kibitsu no miya (present Kibitsu-jinja Shrine in Okayama City, Okayama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>『紀氏系図』（『続群書類従』本）には異説として紀季重の子・重源の弟とする説を載せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Kishi Kezu&quot;(a family tree of the Ki clan)(&quot;Zoku-Gunsho Ruiju&quot; Book (Book of The Library of Historical Documents, Continued)), the anecdote stated the heresy that he was the child of KI no Sueshige, the younger brother of Chogen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Kishi Kezu&quot;(a family tree of the Ki clan)(&quot;Zoku-Gunsho Ruiju&quot; Book (Book of The Library of Historical Documents, Continued)), an anecdote stated the heresy that he was the child of KI no Sueshige, the younger brother of Chogen.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Kishi Kezu&quot; (a family tree of the Ki clan) (&quot;Zoku-Gunsho Ruiju&quot; Book (Book of The Library of Historical Documents, Continued)), an anecdote stated the heresy that he was the child of KI no Sueshige, the younger brother of Chogen.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、これは重源が吉備津宮の再興に尽くしたことや重源が務めていた東大寺勧進職を栄西が継いだことから生じた説であり、史実ではないと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this anecdote raised because Chogen dedicated himself to reconstruct Kibitsu no miya and Eisai succeeded to the position of Daikanjin (priest to collect contributions) at Todai-ji Temple where Chogen worked for, so it was not considered as the historical fact.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this anecdote arose because Chogen dedicated himself to reconstructing Kibitsu no miya and Eisai succeeded to the position of Daikanjin (priest to collect contributions) at Todai-ji Temple where Chogen worked, so it was not considered an historical fact.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this anecdote arose because Chogen dedicated himself to reconstructing Kibitsu no miya and Eisai succeeded to the position of Daikanjin (priest to collect contributions) at Todai-ji Temple where Chogen worked, so it was not considered an historical fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>久安4年（1148年） 8歳で『倶舎論』、『婆沙論』を読んだと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was told that he read &quot;Kusharon&quot; (sutra of the Kusha sect) and &quot;Basharon&quot;(the Discourse on the Ten Stages) at the age of eight in 1148.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was told that he read &quot;Kusharon&quot; (sutra of the Kusha sect) and &quot;Basharon&quot;(the Discourse on the Ten Stages) at the age of eight in 1148.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was told that he read &quot;Kusharon&quot; (sutra of the Kusha sect) and &quot;Basharon&quot; (the Discourse on the Ten Stages) at the age of eight in 1148.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>久寿元年（1154年） 14歳で比叡山延暦寺にて出家得度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had shukke tokudo (entering the priesthood, becoming a monk) at Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei at the age of 14 in 1154.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He underwent shukke tokudo (entering the priesthood, becoming a monk) at Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei at the age of 14 in 1154.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He underwent shukke tokudo (entering the priesthood, becoming a monk) at Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei at the age of 14 in 1154.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>以後、延暦寺、吉備国安養寺、伯耆国大山寺 (鳥取県西伯郡大山町)などで天台宗の教学と密教を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he learned education and Esoteric Buddhism of Tendai Sect at Enryaku-ji Temple, Anyo-ji Temple in Kibi Province, and Daisen-ji Temple in Hoki Province (Daisen-cho, Saihaku District, Tottori Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he received his education and learned Esoteric Buddhism of the Tendai Sect at Enryaku-ji Temple, Anyo-ji Temple in Kibi Province, and Daisen-ji Temple in Hoki Province (Daisen-cho, Saihaku District, Tottori Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he received his education and learned Esoteric Buddhism of the Tendai Sect at Enryaku-ji Temple, Anyo-ji Temple in Kibi Province, and Daisen-ji Temple in Hoki Province (Daisen-cho, Saihaku-gun, Tottori Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>行法に優れ、自分の坊号を冠した葉上流を興す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was excel in gyoho (method of ascetic practices) and found Yojo School that his bogo (temple name) was crowned.</e>
<cmt>「坊号を冠した」の意味が明確に捉えられなかったため、直訳としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He excelled in gyoho (method of ascetic practices) and founded the Yojo School where he was awarded his bogo (temple name).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He excelled in gyoho (a method of ascetic practices) and founded the Yojo School named for his bogo (temple name).</e>
<cmt>原文の赤字部分は「自分の房号(priest title)を付けた」という意味に理解しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>仁安 (日本)3年（1168年） 形骸化した日本天台宗に嫌気し、南宋に留学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied in Southern Sung Dynasty in 1168 when he was tired of Nihon Tendai sect that lost substance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied in the Southern Sung Dynasty in 1168 when he became tired of the Nihon Tendai sect, which had lost substance.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied in the Southern Sung Dynasty in 1168 when he became tired of the Nihon Tendai sect, which had lost substance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天台山万年寺などを訪れ、『天台章疎』60巻を将来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He visited Mannen-ji Temple on Mt. Tendai and brought over &quot;Tendai Shozo&quot;60 Books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He visited Mannen-ji Temple on Mt. Tendai and brought over &quot;Tendai Shozo&quot;60 Books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He visited Mannen-ji Temple on Mt. Tendai and brought over &quot;Tendai Shozo&quot; 60 Books.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>当時、南宋では禅宗が繁栄し、それに大いに感化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen sect was flourished in Southern Sung Dynasty at that time, and he was significantly influenced by that.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Zen sect flourished in the Southern Sung Dynasty at that time, and he was significantly influenced by that.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Zen sect flourished in the Southern Sung Dynasty at that time, and he was significantly influenced by that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>仏法復興のために禅の重要性を感じたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He felt that Zen was important for revival of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He felt that Zen was important for revival of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He felt that Zen was important for revival of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>文治3年（1187年） 再び入宋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to Southern Sung Dynasty again in 1187.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to the Southern Sung Dynasty again in 1187.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to the Southern Sung Dynasty again in 1187.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>仏法辿流のためインド渡航を願い出るが許可されず、天台山万年寺の虚庵懐敞に師事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He requested to visit India to tell Buddhism but could not get permission, so he studied under Kian Ejo at Mannen-ji Temple at Mt. Tendai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He requested to visit India to preach Buddhism but could not get permission, so he studied under Kian Ejo at Mannen-ji Temple at Mt. Tendai.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He requested to visit India to preach Buddhism but could not get permission, so he studied under Kian Ejo at Mannen-ji Temple at Mt. Tendai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>建久2年（1191年） 虚庵懐敞より臨済宗の嗣法の印可を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received Inka (Certification of spiritual achievement) of shiho(to inherit the dharma from a priest master) for Rinzai sect from Kian Ejo in 1191.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received Inka (Certification of spiritual achievement) of shiho(to inherit the dharma from a priest master) for the Rinzai sect from Kian Ejo in 1191.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received Inka (Certification of spiritual achievement) of shiho(to inherit the dharma from a priest master) for the Rinzai sect from Kian Ejo in 1191.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>同年、帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned to Japan in 1191.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Japan in 1191.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Japan in 1191.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>福慧光寺、千光寺などを建立し、筑前国、肥後国を中心に布教に努める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He erected Fukueko-ji Temple and Senko-ji Temple and made effort to propagate mainly in Chikuzen Province and Higo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He erected Fukueko-ji Temple and Senko-ji Temple and made effort to propagate Buddhism, mainly in Chikuzen Province and Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Buddhism&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He erected Fukueko-ji Temple and Senko-ji Temple and made effort to propagate Buddhism, mainly in Chikuzen Province and Higo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="22">
<j>建久5年（1194年） 彼や大日房能忍の禅宗が盛んになり、天台宗からの排斥を受け、禅宗停止が宣下される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen sect by himself and Dainichibo Nonin was flourished in 1194, so he was rejected by Tendai sect and received imperial proclamation on prohibition of Zen sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Zen sect by himself and Dainichibo Nonin flourished in 1194, so he was rejected by the Tendai sect and an imperial proclamation was issued on prohibition of the Zen sect.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Zen sect by himself and Dainichibo Nonin flourished in 1194, so he was rejected by the Tendai sect and an imperial proclamation was issued on prohibition of the Zen sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="23">
<j>建久6年（1195年） 博多に聖福寺 (福岡市)を建立し、日本最初の禅道場とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He erected Shofuku-ji Temple (Fukuoka City) in Hakata in 1195 and made it the first Zen dojo (training hall) in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He erected Shofuku-ji Temple (Fukuoka City) in Hakata in 1195 and made it the first Zen dojo (training hall) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He erected Shofuku-ji Temple (Fukuoka City) in Hakata in 1195 and made it the first Zen dojo (training hall) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="24">
<j>同寺は後に後鳥羽天皇より「扶桑最初禅窟」の扁額を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This temple later received the framed motto saying &apos;Fuso Saisho Zenkutsu&apos; (Japan&apos;s first Zen place) by Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This temple later received a framed motto saying, &apos;Fuso Saisho Zenkutsu&apos; (Japan&apos;s first Zen place) by Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This temple later received a framed motto saying, &apos;Fuso Saisho Zenkutsu&apos; (Japan&apos;s first Zen place) by Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>栄西は自身が真言宗の印信を受けるなど、既存勢力との調和、牽制を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisai received Injin (mystagogy certificates a Buddhist priest awards his followers) of Shingon sect and blended in existing power and tried to make a feint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisai received Injin (mystagogy certificates a Buddhist priest awards his followers) of the Shingon sect and blended in existing power and tried to make a feint.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisai received Injin (mystagogy certificates a Buddhist priest awards his followers) of the Shingon sect and blended in existing power and tried to make a feint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="26">
<j>建久9年（1198年） 『興禅護国論』執筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Kozengokoku-ron&quot; in 1198.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote &quot;Kozengokoku-ron&quot; in 1198.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Kozengokoku-ron&quot; in 1198.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="27">
<j>禅が既存宗派を否定するものではなく、仏法復興に重要であることを説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It preached that Zen was not for denying the existing religious sects, it was important for revival of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It preached that Zen was not for denying the existing religious sects, and that it was important for revival of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;and that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It preached that Zen was not for denying the existing religious sects, and that it was important for revival of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="28">
<j>京都での布教に限界を感じて鎌倉に下向し、幕府の庇護を得ようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He felt his limitations to propagate in Kyoto, so he went down to Kamakura and tried to receive patronage of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He felt his limitations to propagate in Kyoto, so he went down to Kamakura and sought the patronage of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He felt his limitations to propagate in Kyoto, so he went down to Kamakura and sought the patronage of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="29">
<j>正治2年（1200年） 北条政子建立の寿福寺の住職に招聘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was invited to Jufuku-ji Temple erected by Masako HOJO as the chief priest in 1200.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was invited to Jufuku-ji Temple erected by Masako HOJO as the chief priest in 1200.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was invited to Jufuku-ji Temple erected by Masako HOJO as the chief priest in 1200.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="30">
<j>建仁2年（1202年） 源頼家の外護により京都に建仁寺を建立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He erected Kennin-ji Temple in Kyoto by the protection of MINAMOTO no Yoriie in 1202.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He erected Kennin-ji Temple in Kyoto by the protection of MINAMOTO no Yoriie in 1202.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He erected Kennin-ji Temple in Kyoto by the protection of MINAMOTO no Yoriie in 1202.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="31">
<j>建仁寺は禅・天台・真言の三宗兼学の寺であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kennin-ji Temple was the temple of Sanshu kengaku (learning the three sects) of Zen, Tendai, and Shingon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kennin-ji Temple was the temple of Sanshu kengaku (learning the three sects) of Zen, Tendai, and Shingon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kennin-ji Temple was the temple of Sanshu kengaku (learning the three sects) of Zen, Tendai, and Shingon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>以後、幕府や朝廷の権力に取り入り、それを利用して禅宗の振興に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, he was involved in the power of the bakufu and the Imperial Court and made effort to promote Zen sect by using the power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then, he was involved in the power of the bakufu and the Imperial Court and made efforts to promote the Zen sect by using this power.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then, he was involved in the power of the bakufu and the Imperial Court and made efforts to promote the Zen sect by using this power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="33">
<j>建永元年（1206年） 重源の後を受けて東大寺勧進職に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Daikanjin at Todai-ji Temple ceded by Chogen in 1206.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Daikanjin at Todai-ji Temple ceded by Chogen in 1206.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Daikanjin at Todai-ji Temple ceded by Chogen in 1206.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="34">
<j>建暦2年（1212年） 法印に叙任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) in 1212.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) in 1212.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) in 1212.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="35">
<j>建保元年（1213年） 権僧正に栄進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Gonsojo (the lowest grade that can be held by one who has reached the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) in 1213.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Gonsojo (the lowest grade that can be held by one who has reached the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) in 1213.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Gonsojo (the lowest grade that can be held by one who has reached the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests) in 1213.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="36">
<j>政治権力にひたすら追従する栄西には当時から多くの批判があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a lot of criticism about Eisai who intensely pursued the political power since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then, there was a lot of criticism about Eisai for his intense pursuit of political power.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then, there was a lot of criticism about Eisai for his intense pursuit of political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>特に栄西が幕府を動かし、大師猟号運動を行ったことは大きな非難を浴びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specially, Eisai drew stringent criticism for engaging in Daishi-go Ryo-go movement by steering the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, Eisai drew stringent criticism for engaging in the Daishi-go Ryo-go movement by steering the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, Eisai drew stringent criticism for engaging in the Daishi-go Ryo-go movement by steering the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>栄西の策動は生前授号の前例が無いことを理由に退けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His scheme was dismissed since there was no precedentof jugo (granted a pseudonym) in life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His scheme was dismissed since there was no precedentof jugo (granted a pseudonym) in one&apos;s lifetime.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His scheme was dismissed since there was no precedent of jugo (granted a pseudonym) in one&apos;s lifetime.</e>
<cmt>改行削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし、天台座主慈円は『愚管抄』で栄西を「増上慢の権化」と罵っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Jien of Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) insulted Eisai as &apos;the incarnation of conceit in Buddhism&apos; in &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Jien of Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) insulted Eisai as &apos;the incarnation of conceit in Buddhism&apos; in &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Jien of Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect) insulted Eisai as &apos;the incarnation of conceit in Buddhism&apos; in &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="40">
<j>建保3年（1215年） で病没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died of illness in 1215.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died of illness in 1215.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died of illness in 1215.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>終焉の地は鎌倉、京都の2説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two theories that the place of his death was either Kamakura or Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two theories about the place of his death, either Kamakura or Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two theories about the place of his death, either Kamakura or Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>他者からの栄西観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">View of Eisai from others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">View of Eisai from others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">View of Eisai from others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>日本曹洞宗の開祖である道元は、入宋前に建仁寺で修行しており、師の明全を通じて栄西とは孫弟子の関係になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dogen, the founder of Nihon Soto sect, practiced at Kennin-ji Temple before entering Southern Sung Dynasty and became magodeshi (disciple of disciple) relations with Eisai through Dogen&apos;s teacher Myozen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dogen, founder of the Nihon Soto sect, practiced at Kennin-ji Temple before entering the Southern Sung Dynasty and achieved magodeshi (disciple of disciple) relations with Eisai through Dogen&apos;s teacher Myozen.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dogen, founder of the Nihon Soto sect, practiced at Kennin-ji Temple before entering the Southern Sung Dynasty and achieved magodeshi (disciple of disciple) relations with Eisai through Dogen&apos;s teacher Myozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>栄西を非常に尊敬し、夜の説法を集めた『正法眼蔵随聞記』では、「なくなられた僧正様は…」と、彼に関するエピソードを数回も披露している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dogen respected Eisai very much and introduced the episodes about him many times as &apos;Sojo -sama (high-ranking Buddhist priest) who died...&apos; in &quot;Shobogenzo-zuimonki&quot; (collection of short talks, orations, comments on instruction and cautionary tales).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dogen respected Eisai very much and introduced the episodes about him many times as &apos;Sojo -sama (high-ranking Buddhist priest) who died...&apos; in &quot;Shobogenzo-zuimonki&quot; (collection of short talks, orations, comments on instruction and cautionary tales).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dogen respected Eisai very much and introduced the episodes about him many times as &apos;Sojo-sama (high-ranking Buddhist priest) who died...&apos; in &quot;Shobogenzo-zuimonki&quot; (collection of short talks, orations, comments on instruction and cautionary tales).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>なお、栄西と道元は直接会っていたかという問題は、最近の研究では会っていないとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, regarding the issue whether Eisai and Dogen have met in person or not, recent research reported they had not met in person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, regarding the issue of whether or not Eisai and Dogen had met in person, recent research has reported they did not met in person.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, regarding the issue of whether or not Eisai and Dogen had met in person, recent research has reported they did not met in person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>主な著作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major literary works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major literary works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major literary works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>『誓願寺盂蘭盆縁起』栄西唯一の肉筆文書で国宝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Seigan-ji Temple Urabon Engi&quot; (History of Urabon ritual at Seigan-ji Temple) was the only autograph document and the national treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Seigan-ji Temple Urabon Engi&quot; (History of Urabon ritual at Seigan-ji Temple) was the only autographed document and a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Seigan-ji Temple Urabon Engi&quot; (History of Urabon ritual at Seigan-ji Temple) was the only autographed document and a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>福岡市西区の誓願寺に滞在した折、書いたと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seemed that he wrote it when he stayed at Seigan-ji Temple in Nishi Ward, Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seemed that he wrote it when he stayed at Seigan-ji Temple in Nishi Ward, Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed that he wrote it when he stayed at Seigan-ji Temple in Nishi Ward, Fukuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>『喫茶養生記』（古田紹欽全訳注、講談社学術文庫、2000年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kissa-yojoki&quot; (Drink Tea and Prolong Life, A Note on Drinking Green Tea for Good Health)(All translator&apos;s notes by Shokin FURUTA, Academic paperback library, Kodansha Ltd. in 2000)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kissa-yojoki&quot; (Drink Tea and Prolong Life, A Note on Drinking Green Tea for Good Health)(All translator&apos;s notes by Shokin FURUTA, Academic paperback library, Kodansha Ltd. in 2000)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kissa-yojoki&quot; (Drink Tea and Prolong Life, A Note on Drinking Green Tea for Good Health) (All translator&apos;s notes by Shokin FURUTA, Academic paperback library, Kodansha Ltd. in 2000)</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="48">
<j>『喫茶養生記』は上下2巻からなり、上巻では茶の種類や抹茶の製法、身体を壮健にする喫茶の効用が説かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kissa-yojoki&quot;consisted of Volume 1 and 2, and it explained the variety of teas, manufacturing process of green tea, and the effectiveness of tea drinking that made a body healthy in the Volume 1.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kissa-yojoki&quot; consisted of Volume 1 and 2, and in Volume 1 it explained the variety of teas, the manufacturing process of green tea, and the effectiveness of tea drinking that made a body healthy.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kissa-yojoki&quot; consisted of Volume 1 and 2, and in Volume 1 it explained the variety of teas, the manufacturing process of green tea, and the effectiveness of tea drinking that made a body healthy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>下巻では飲水（現在の糖尿病）、中風、不食、瘡、脚気の五病に対する桑の効用と用法が説かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The effectiveness and directions of mulberry against five diseases, such as Insui (present diabetes), paralysis, summer lethargy, smallpox, and beriberi in the Volume 2.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 2 explained the effectiveness of and directions for use of mulberry against five diseases, Insui (present diabetes), paralysis, summer lethargy, smallpox, and beriberi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 2 explained the effectiveness of and directions for use of mulberry against five diseases, Insui (present diabetes), paralysis, summer lethargy, smallpox, and beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>このことから、茶桑経（ちゃそうきょう）という別称もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, another name of it was Chasokyo (written as 茶桑経, meaning tea, mulberry, and sutra).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of that, its alternative title was Chasokyo (written as 茶桑経, meaning tea, mulberry, and sutra).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of that, its alternative title was Chasokyo (written as 茶桑経, meaning tea, mulberry, and sutra).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>書かれた年代ははっきりせず、一般には建保2年（1214年）に源実朝に献上したという「茶徳を誉むる所の書」を完本の成立とするが、定説はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The written year was not certain, but it was generally considered &apos;The document to praise tea drinking&apos; presented to MINAMOTO no Sanetomo in 1214 to be Kanbon (complete edition), but there was no established theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year of its writing is not certain, and there is no established theory, but it was generally considered &apos;The document to praise tea drinking&apos; presented to MINAMOTO no Sanetomo in 1214 to be Kanbon (complete edition).</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year of its writing is not certain, and there is no established theory, but it was generally considered &apos;The document to praise tea drinking&apos; presented to MINAMOTO no Sanetomo in 1214 to be Kanbon (complete edition).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>『栄西-興禅護国論・喫茶養生記-』（古田紹欽著、講談社、1994年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Eisai-Kozengokoku-ron and Kissa-yojoki-&quot;(written by Shokin FURUTA, Kodansha Ltd. in 1994)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Eisai-Kozengokoku-ron and Kissa-yojoki-&quot;(written by Shokin FURUTA, Kodansha Ltd. in 1994)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Eisai-Kozengokoku-ron and Kissa-yojoki-&quot; (written by Shokin FURUTA, Kodansha Ltd. in 1994)</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), Tomzo(id:16777), Nnh(id:474), Reggaeman(id:6214), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), Wei Yuan(id:13342), 薩摩入道(id:199313), Sutou(id:32), Hybridtheorywaseda(id:258463), Ohura(id:5986), Auauauhouse(id:189325), Loveless(id:129239), Point136(id:211299), ＫＪ達磨(id:101625), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 無空(id:17049), Jpatokal(id:1566), Izayohi(id:13095), 果心居士(id:248111), STBot(id:137943), Dome2000(id:15142), YukkeBot(id:251107), 遠藤(id:30275), Escarbot(id:59151), Rusk(id:9895), Alecs.bot(id:194707), VolkovBot(id:105371), R28Bot(id:177951), Symauma(id:78765), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), Louperibot(id:128971), 机龍之介(id:61257), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>