<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>広橋兼仲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanenaka HIROHASHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanenaka HIROHASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanenaka HIROHASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>広橋 兼仲（ひろはし かねなか、 寛元2年（1244年） － 徳治3年1月20日 (旧暦)（1308年 2月12日））は鎌倉時代後期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanenaka HIROHASHI (1244 - February 12 (January 20, according to the old calendar), 1308) was Kugyo (a court noble) during the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanenaka HIROHASHI (1244 - February 12, 1308) was a kugyo (a court noble) during the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い旧暦は削除しました。「公卿」の訳部分が大文字、不定冠詞なしの状態で特定の人物を表すかのようになっていましたので、小文字化と不定冠詞を追加し修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanenaka HIROHASHI (1244 - February 12, 1308) was a kugyo (a court noble) during the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『民経記』の著者広橋経光の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of Tsunemitsu HIROHASHI, who was a writer of &quot;Minkeiki (the journal by Tsunemitsu HIROHASHI).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of Tsunemitsu HIROHASHI, who was the writer of &quot;Minkeiki (the journal by Tsunemitsu HIROHASHI).&quot;</e>
<cmt>著者は特定された人物ですので、不定冠詞ではなく定冠詞に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of Tsunemitsu HIROHASHI, who was the writer of &quot;Minkeiki (the journal by Tsunemitsu HIROHASHI).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は大宰大弐藤原親実の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Dazai no daini FUJIWARA no Chikazane (Senior Assistant Governor General of the Dazai-fu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of the Dazai-fu) FUJIWARA no Chikazane.</e>
<cmt>括弧内の説明文は太宰大弐についての説明ですので、その直後に説明が来るよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor General of the Dazai-fu) FUJIWARA no Chikazane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称である勘解由小路 兼仲の名で知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known in his common name, Kanenaka KADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, he is known in his common name, Kanenaka KADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt>訳文は過去形となっていますが、原文は「現在この通称で知られている」という意味ですので、現在形に修正し、また「今日」の意味のtodayを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, he is known in his common name, Kanenaka KADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日記『勘仲記』の著者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a writer of &quot;Kanchuki (Diary of Kanenaka HIROHASHI.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the writer of &quot;Kanchuki (Diary of Kanenaka HIROHASHI.&quot;</e>
<cmt>著者は特定された人物ですので、不定冠詞ではなく定冠詞に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the writer of &quot;Kanchuki (Diary of Kanenaka HIROHASHI.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>法号は兼寂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was 兼寂.</e>
<cmt>兼寂→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name was Kenjaku.</e>
<cmt>読みは法号ですので音読みとすると、「けんじゃく」でしょうか。特定はできないと思いますので、一応「けんじゃく」でお願いします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Kenjaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>建長4年（1252年）に元服、正嘉2年（1257年）に叙爵し、紀伝道（文章道）を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1252, he celebrated his coming of age, and was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1257, and he studied under Kidendo (Monjodo (Literature)).</e>
<cmt>叙爵→初めて従五位下に叙されること&lt;広辞苑→be appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)と訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1252, he celebrated his coming of age, and after he was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1257, he studied Kidendo (Monjodo (Literature)).</e>
<cmt>「紀伝道を学ぶ」を「studied under Kinendo」としていますが、この場合外国人には紀伝道が人物のように錯覚する可能性があります。間違いではないと思いますがunderを削除しました。叙爵したがために「紀伝道を学び始めた」と考えられますので、語順を変更して「and」による分割を減らしています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1252, he celebrated his coming of age, and after he was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1257, he studied Kidendo (Monjodo (Literature)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>正元元年に民部少輔に任じられ、近衛家・鷹司家の家司となり、弘安元年（1278年）より鷹司兼平・近衛家基の執事を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appointed to Minbu shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs) in 1259, he became Keishi (household superintendent) of the Konoe and the Takatsukasa family, and served as shitsuji (a steward) of Kanehira TAKATSUKASA and Iemoto KONOE in 1278.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointed to Minbu shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs) in 1259, he became Keishi (household superintendent) of the Konoe and the Takatsukasa family, and began to serve as shitsuji (a steward) of Kanehira TAKATSUKASA and Iemoto KONOE from 1278.</e>
<cmt>原文では「1278年より執事を務め始めた」の意味のところ、訳文では「1278年に執事を務めた」となっていましたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appointed to Minbu shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs) in 1259, he became Keishi (household superintendent) of the Konoe and the Takatsukasa family, and began to serve as shitsuji (a steward) of Kanehira TAKATSUKASA and Iemoto KONOE from 1278.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>弘安3年（1280年）に兄広橋兼頼が没すると嫡子として扱われ、弘安7年（1284年）に蔵人に任ぜられ、同10年に右少弁、正応元年（1288年）に左少弁、翌年には右中弁、左中弁に、その翌年には右大弁、左大弁に任じられ、春宮亮も兼任、正応4年には蔵人頭に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1280, he was treated as a legitimate child at the death of his elder brother, Kaneyori HIROHASHI, and in 1284, appointed to Kurodo (Chamberlain), and in 1287, Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right), and in 1288, Shashoben (Minor Controller of the Left), and in 1289, Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right), and Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left), and the next year, Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right), and Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left), and held the additional post, Togo no suke, and in 1291, was appointed to Karoo no to (Head Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanenaka became the legitimate successor of the family upon the death of his elder brother, Kaneyori HIROHASHI in 1280, then he was successively appointed to Kurodo (Chamberlain) in 1284, and Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1287, and Shashoben (Minor Controller of the Left) in 1288, and Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right) and Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left) in 1289, and Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) and Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left) in the next year with the additional post of Togo no suke, and to Karoo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1291.</e>
<cmt>原文の「嫡子として扱われる」はこの場合、訳にあるような単に「legitimate child」ではなく、「正当な後継」の意味が含まれています。その点留意して修正しました。青字は位置の変更をしめしています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanenaka became the legitimate successor of the family upon the death of his elder brother, Kaneyori HIROHASHI in 1280, then he was successively appointed to Kurodo (Chamberlain) in 1284, and Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1287, and Shashoben (Minor Controller of the Left) in 1288, and Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right) and Sachuben (Middle Controller of the Left) in 1289, and Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) and Sadaiben (Major Controller of the Left) in the next year with the additional post of Togo no suke, and to Karoo no to (Head Chamberlain) in 1291.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この間に左右宮城使や造興福寺長官（興福寺造寺司）や亀山上皇院司も兼ねている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that time, he also served as Ukyujoshi and Sayukyujoshi (Secretary of the left Office of Palace Repairs and Secretary of the right Office of Palace Repairs), Zo Kofuku-ji Temple chokan (Kofuku-ji Temple zojishi, the director for the construction of Kofuku-ji Temple), and Inshi (official of the retired emperor&apos;s office) of the Retired Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that time, he also served as Ukyujoshi and Sayukyujoshi (Secretary of the left Office of Palace Repairs and Secretary of the right Office of Palace Repairs), Zo Kofuku-ji Temple chokan (Kofuku-ji Temple zojishi, the director for the construction of Kofuku-ji Temple), and Inshi (official of the retired emperor&apos;s office) of the Retired Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that time, he also served as Ukyujoshi and Sayukyujoshi (Secretary of the left Office of Palace Repairs and Secretary of the right Office of Palace Repairs), Zo Kofuku-ji Temple chokan (Kofuku-ji Temple zojishi, the director for the construction of Kofuku-ji Temple), and Inshi (official of the retired emperor&apos;s office) of the Retired Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>正応5年（1292年）に日野資宣の死により日野流長者と任じられ、同年11月5日に蔵人頭から参議に任ぜられ、翌永仁元年（1293年）には従三位に叙せられて権中納言となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1292, he was appointed to Hinoryu choja (the head of the Hino family) at the death of Sukenobu HINO, and on November 5 of the same year, he was took an assignment of Sanji (Councilor) from Kurodo no to, and the next year, in 1293, was bestowed Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) to become Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1292, he was appointed to Hinoryu choja (the head of the Hino family) upon the death of Sukenobu HINO, and on November 5 of the same year, he was promoted to Sangi (Councilor) from Kurodo no to, and then he was bestowed Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) to become Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) the next year, in 1293.</e>
<cmt>前置詞用法について修正しています。「he was took an assignment」という部分の文法的誤りを修正し、昇進の意味を追加しました。「参議」が「Sanji」となっていましたので「Sangi」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1292, he was appointed to Hinoryu choja (the head of the Hino family) upon the death of Sukenobu HINO, and on November 5 of the same year, he was promoted to Sangi (Councilor) from Kurodo no to, and then he was bestowed Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) to become Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) the next year, in 1293.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>永仁2年（1294年）に権中納言を辞任するが正三位に叙され、正安元年（1299年）には従二位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1294, he resigned as Gon Chunagon, and was bestowed Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), and in 1299, Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1294, he resigned as Gon Chunagon, but his title was raised to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), and further raised to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 1299.</e>
<cmt>「辞任するが、正三位に叙され」の意味とするため、「and」を「but」としました。「叙する」をそのまま「bestow」の繰り返しで表現しても良いと思いますが、位が上がっていくことが主題ですので、そのように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1294, he resigned as Gon Chunagon, but his title was raised to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), and further raised to Junii (Junior Second Rank) in 1299.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>嘉元3年（1305年）に日野長者を日野俊光に譲り、徳治3年に出家して間もなく病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1305, he handed over Hino choja to Toshimitsu HINO, and passed away soon after he entered into priesthood in 1308.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1305, he handed over Hino choja status to Toshimitsu HINO and entered into priesthood in 1308, and soon after he died of an illness.</e>
<cmt>病死の意味が欠落していましたので修正しました。多少御純変更しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1305, he handed over Hino choja status to Toshimitsu HINO and entered into priesthood in 1308, and soon after he died of an illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>