<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原大津</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Otsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Otsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Otsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 大津（ふじわら の おおつ、延暦11年（792年） - 仁寿4年10月9日 (旧暦)（854年11月2日））は、平安時代前期の官人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Otsu (792-November 6, 854) was a government official (lower or middle ranked) in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>「仁寿4年10月9日 (旧暦)」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦854年11月6日」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Otsu (792-November 6, 854) was a government official in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Otsu (792-November 6, 854) was a government official in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a family member of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>「藤原北家」は、「統一用語」に従いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a member of the Northern House of the Fujiwara Clan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a member of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Clanの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原内麻呂の第9子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 9th child of FUJIWARA no Uchimaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the ninth child of FUJIWARA no Uchimaro.</e>
<cmt>&quot;9th&quot;→&quot;ninth&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the ninth child of FUJIWARA no Uchimaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>藤原真夏・藤原冬嗣らの異母弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was paternal half-brother of FUJIWARA no Manatsu and FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the paternal half-brother of FUJIWARA no Manatsu and FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the paternal half-brother of FUJIWARA no Manatsu and FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原良縄の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was father of FUJIWARA no Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of FUJIWARA no Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of FUJIWARA no Yoshitada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>18歳で大舎人大允となり、常陸大掾・右近将監を経て、天長3年（826年）従五位下備後守になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed Ootoneri no taijo (Senior Secretary of the Bureau of Royal Attendants) at the age of 18 and after he served as Hitachi no daijo (Senior Secretary of Hitachi Province) and Ukon no jo (Lieutenant of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Bingo no kami (provincial governor of Bingo) in 826.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed Ootoneri no Taijo (Senior Secretary of the Bureau of Royal Attendants) at the age of 18 and then served as Daijo (Senior Commissioner) of Hitachi Province and Ukon no Jo (Lieutenant of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), before being promoted to KAmi (Governor) of Bingo Province with the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 826.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed Ootoneri no Taijo (Senior Secretary of the Bureau of Royal Attendants) at the age of 18 and then served as Daijo (Senior Commissioner) of Hitachi Province and Ukon no Jo (Lieutenant of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), before being promoted to Kami (Governor) of Bingo Province with the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 826.</e>
<cmt>KAmi→Kamiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、大監物・散位頭・左馬助・信濃守・備前守などを歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, he successively filled the post of Daikenmotsu (a senior auditor in the ancient Ministry of Finance or Interior), Sani no to, Samanosuke (vice-minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses), Shinano no kami (Governor of Shinano Province), Bizen no kami (the governor of Bizen Province) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, he held various posts including Daikenmotsu (a senior government auditor), Sani no To (Head of the Bureau of Holders of Rank Without Portfolio), Samanosuke (Vice-Minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses), Kami (Governor) of Shinano Province, and Kami Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - unsure of the translation of &quot;散位頭&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, he held various posts including Daikenmotsu (a senior government auditor), Sani no To (Head of the Bureau of Holders of Rank Without Portfolio), Samanosuke (Vice-Minister of Left Division of Bureau of Horses), Governor of Shinano Province, and Governor of Bizen Province.</e>
<cmt>Kami (Governor) of Shinano Province, and Kami Bizen Province→Governor of Shinano Province, and Governor of Bizen Provincesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>承和 (日本)9年（842年）7月の承和の変では、山城国の宇治橋を守った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He defended Uji-bashi Bridge in Yamashiro Province in the Jowa Incident in August 842.</e>
<cmt>「承和 9年7月」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦842年8月」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Jowa Incident in August 842, he defended Uji-bashi Bridge in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>PrepopsitionWord order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Jowa Incident in August 842, he defended Uji-bashi Bridge in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>仁寿元年（851年）11月、正五位下になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in December 851.</e>
<cmt>「仁寿元年11月」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦851年12月」、　出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in December 851.</e>
<cmt>Prepostion</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in December 851.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同4年（854年）10月9日、63歳で卒去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on November 6, 854 at the age of 63.</e>
<cmt>「仁寿4年10月9日」＝グレゴリオ暦「西暦854年11月6日　」、出典：http://maechan.net/kanreki</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on November 6, 854 at the age of 63.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on November 6, 854 at the age of 63.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>身長が低かったが、意気が高く、歩射をよくした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was a short person, he was high-spirited and often performed shooting bows on foot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was a short person, he was out-going and enjoyed archery.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was a short person, he was out-going and enjoyed archery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また地方官としての優れた業績を残し、備後守・伊予守時代では民に慕われたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He left great achievements as a Chihokan (a local official) behind him and he is said to have been respected by people during his service as Bingo no kami and Iyo no kami (Governor of Iyo Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served with distinction as a local government official behind and is said to have been respected by local people during his time as the Kami of Bingo and Iyo Provinces.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served with distinction as a local government official behind and is said to have been respected by local people during his time as the Governor of Bingo and Iyo Provinces.</e>
<cmt>the Kami of Bingo and Iyo Provinces→the Governor of Bingo and Iyo Provincesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>