<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鷹司兼基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanemoto TAKATSUKASA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanemoto TAKATSUKASA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanemoto TAKATSUKASA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鷹司 兼基（たかつかさ かねもと、文治元年（1185年） - 没年不詳）は、鎌倉時代前期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanemoto TAKATSUKASA (鷹司 兼基, 1185 - year of death unknown) was a Kugyo (high court noble) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanemoto TAKATSUKASA (鷹司 兼基, 1185 - year of death unknown) was a Kugyo (high court noble) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanemoto TAKATSUKASA (鷹司 兼基, 1185 - year of death unknown) was a Kugyo (high court noble) in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>摂政近衛基通の4男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth son of Sessho (regent) Motomichi KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth son of Sessho (regent) Motomichi KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth son of Sessho (regent) Motomichi KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は寂舜法印の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Jakushun Hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Jakushun Hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>aをtheにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Jakushun Hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「室町」とも号したため、この系統の鷹司家は室町家とも称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As they used another name &quot;Muromachi&quot;, this lineage of the Takatsukasa family was called the Muromachi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As they used another surname &quot;Muromachi&quot;, this lineage of the Takatsukasa family was called the Muromachi family.</e>
<cmt>nameをsurnameにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As they used another surname &quot;Muromachi&quot;, this lineage of the Takatsukasa family was called the Muromachi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>建久8年（1197年）に元服して、従五位上侍従に任ぜられ、翌年には正五位下に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1197, after he had his genpuku (coming of age) celebrated, he was appointed as Jugoinojo Jiju (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, Chamberlain), and the next year, he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1197, after his genpuku (coming of age) ceremony, he was appointed as Jugoinojo Jiju (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, Chamberlain), and the next year, he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>「元服して」をafter his genpuku ceｒemonyにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1197, after his genpuku (coming of age) ceremony, he was appointed as Jugoinojo Jiju (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, Chamberlain), and the next year, he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>関白であった父のもとで急速な出世を遂げ、正治元年（1199年）に従四位下右近衛中将になると、翌2年には3度の叙階で10月26日には従三位に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He achieved rapid advancement in life under his father, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor): in 1199, he became Jushiinoge Ukone no chujo (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), and the next year 1200, after three time promotions, on December 11 he reached Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>原文は「従四位下近衛府」となっているが、Webに合わせて「従四位下右近衛中将」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He achieved rapid advancement in life under his father, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor); for example, in 1199, he became Jushiinoge Ukone no chujo (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), and the next year 1200, after three time promotions, on December 11 he reached Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>コロンをセミコロンに変え、transitionとしてfor exampleをつけくわえました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He achieved rapid advancement in life under his father, Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor); for example, in 1199, he became Jushiinoge Ukone no chujo (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), and the next year 1200, after three time promotions, on December 11 he reached Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>建仁2年（1202年）には正三位を経て従二位に叙され、元久元年（1204年）には20歳の若さで権中納言に任ぜられ、続いて翌年には正二位中納言に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1202, he was appointed as Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and then Junii (Junior Second Rank), and in 1204, he was appointed as Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) when he was as young as only 20 years old, and moreover the next year, he was appointed as Shonii Chunagon (Senior Second Rank, Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>原文は「20歳の若さで中納言」となっているが、Webに合わせて「20歳の若さで権中納言」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1202, he was appointed as Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and then Junii (Junior Second Rank), and in 1204, he was appointed as Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) when he was as young as only 20 years old, and moreover, he was appointed as Shonii Chunagon (Senior Second Rank, Middle Counselor) the next year.</e>
<cmt>moreoverのあとにカンマをつけ、the next yearの位置を後ろにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1202, he was appointed as Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and then Junii (Junior Second Rank), and in 1204, he was appointed as Gon Chunagon (Provisional Vice-Councilor of State) when he was as young as only 20 years old, and moreover, he was appointed as Shonii Chunagon (Senior Second Rank, Vice-Councilor of State) the next year.</e>
<cmt>Provisional Middle Counselor→Provisional Vice-Councilor of StateMiddle Counselor→Vice-Councilor of State(統一リストに合わせました）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>建永元年（1206年）に権大納言、建保3年（1215年）に大納言に任命され、建保6年（1218年）に大納言を辞任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1206, he was appointed as Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor), and in 1215, he was appointed as Dainagon (Major Counselor), but in 1218, he resigned his position as Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>原文は「建永元年（1206年）に大納言」となっているが、Webに合わせて「建永元年（1206年）に権大納言」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1206, he was appointed as Gon Dainagon (Provisional Major Counselor), and in 1215, he was appointed as Dainagon (Major Counselor), but in 1218, he resigned his position as Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1206, he was appointed as Gon Dainagon (Provisional Chief Councilor of State), and in 1215, he was appointed as Dainagon (Chief Councilor of State), but in 1218, he resigned his position as Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>Provisional Major Counselor→Provisional Chief Councilor of StateMajor Counselor→Chief Councilor of State(統一リストに合わせました）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>寛喜元年（1229年）には子の静基が実相院を創建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1229, his son Joki founded Jisso-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1229, his son Joki founded Jisso-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1229, his son Joki founded Jisso-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>建長3年（1251年）に出家して顕恵と名乗るが、没年は不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1251, he entered into priesthood and called him Kene (顕恵), but the year when he died is unknown.</e>
<cmt>「顕恵」の正式な読みは未確認です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1251, he entered into priesthood and called him Kene (顕恵), but the year when he died is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1251, he entered into priesthood and called him Kene (顕恵), but the year when he died is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>