<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>狩野永徳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eitoku KANO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eitoku KANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eitoku KANO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>狩野 永徳（かのう えいとく、天文 (元号)12年1月13日 (旧暦)（1543年2月16日） - 天正18年9月4日 (旧暦)（1590年10月12日））は、安土桃山時代の絵師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eitoku KANO (February 16, 1543-October 12, 1590) was a painter in the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eitoku KANO (February 16, 1543-October 12, 1590) was a painter who lived during the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eitoku KANO (February 16, 1543 - October 12, 1590) was a painter who lived during the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンの前後にスペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>狩野派（室町時代から江戸時代まで日本画壇の中心にあった画派）の代表的な画人であり、日本美術史上もっとも著名な画人の一人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a representative painter of Kano school (a principal painting school in Japan&apos;s artists&apos; circles from the Muromachi period through the Edo period) and one of the best-known painter in Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a leading painter of the Kano school (a painting school that served as a focal point for the art circles of Japan from the Muromachi period through to the Edo period) and remains one of the best-known painters in the history of Japanese art.</e>
<cmt>Translators should avoid automatically translating &quot;代表的&quot; as &quot;representative&quot; as there is often (though not always) a more suitable alternative.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a leading painter of the Kano school (a painting school that served as a focal point for the art circles of Japan from the Muromachi period through to the Edo period) and remains one of the best-known painters in the history of Japanese art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>現存する代表作に『唐獅子図屏風』、『洛中洛外図』、『聚光院障壁画』などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Karajishi-zu Byobu&quot; (folding screen with painting of Chinese lions, Karajishi), &quot;Rakuchu Rakugai-zu&quot; (Kyoto and its surroundings) and &quot;Juko-in Shohekiga&quot; (wall painting at Juko-in Temple) are his representative works in existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notable extant works of his include &quot;Karajishi-zu Byobu&quot; (a folding screen with a painting depicting karajishi, which is the Japanese word for Chinese lions), &quot;Rakuchu Rakugai-zu&quot; (a painting depicting Kyoto and its surroundings) and &quot;Juko-in Shohekiga&quot; (a wall painting at the Juko-in Temple).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notable extant works of his include &quot;Karajishi-zu Byobu&quot; (a folding screen with a painting depicting karajishi, which is the Japanese word for Chinese lions), &quot;Rakuchu Rakugai-zu&quot; (a painting depicting Kyoto and its surroundings) and &quot;Juko-in Shohekiga&quot; (a wall painting at the Juko-in Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>永徳は狩野松栄の息子で、狩野元信の孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eitoku was a son of Shoei KANO, also a grandson of Motonobu KANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eitoku was a son of Shoei KANO and was also a grandson of Motonobu KANO.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eitoku was a son of Shoei KANO and was also a grandson of Motonobu KANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>永徳は法号で、名は源四郎、諱は州信（くにのぶ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eitoku was a hogo (a Buddhist name), Genshiro and Kuninobu were his popular name and real name, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eitoku was his hogo (a Buddhist name), and Genshiro and Kuninobu were his popular name and real name, respectively.</e>
<cmt>I am not sure about the addition of &quot;a&quot; in the first clause. However I believe hogo is a general name (I.e. one of many hogos) so this is better. The second change is definitely correct, two independent clauses require a comma and coordinating conjunction to not be run-onNR: I agree that &quot;his&quot; seems a lot more natural than &quot;a,&quot; though I can&apos;t be 100% sure either.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eitoku was his hogo (a Buddhist name), and Genshiro and Kuninobu were his popular name and real name, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>狩野派の棟梁として、織田信長、豊臣秀吉という天下人に仕え、安土城、聚楽第、大坂城などの障壁画を制作した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the head of Kano school, he served Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who took control of the country, and created wall paintings for Azuchi Castle, Jurakudai residence and Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>「天下人」は「政権を掌握した人」という風に説明的に訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the head of Kano school, Eitoku served Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who took control of the country, and he created wall paintings for places such as Azuchi Castle, Jurakudai residence and Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>Consider restating &quot;etoku&quot; in first sentence instead of &quot;he&quot; などの omitted from translation.NR: I agree.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the head of Kano school, Eitoku served Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who took control of the country, and he created wall paintings for places such as Azuchi-jo Castle, Jurakudai residence and Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>城に-joを補足　他ファイルと合わせる</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>永徳が力を振るったこれらの代表的な事績は建物とともに滅びてしまったものが多く、真筆とされる現存作品は比較的少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of these representative achievements on which Eitoku displayed his talents were perished together with buildings and the existing works considered to be genuine are relatively few in number.</e>
<cmt>「力を振るった」は「才能を発揮した」と考えて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the representative achievements through which Eitoku displayed his talents perished together with the buildings that housed them, and the existing works considered to be genuine are relatively few in number.</e>
<cmt>I do not have the necessary background knowledge, but it would be nice to be able to say representative OF WHAT? Of Etoku&apos;s work or of the age in general? We are left to guess. NR: Very good point. on--&gt; through were--&gt; XNR: This is perhaps a minor point and I realize the Japanese says &quot;これら&quot;, but I think the sentence reads better if &quot;these&quot; is changed to &quot;the&quot;. Also, &quot;buildings&quot; seems to require an article and some hint as to the connection between the works of art and the buildings.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the representative achievements through which Eitoku displayed his talents perished together with the buildings that housed them, and the existing works considered to be genuine are relatively few in number.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>永徳といえば『唐獅子図』や『檜図』のような雄大なスケールの豪快な作品（大画）がよく知られるが、細部を緻密に描写した「細画」もよくしたとされる（『本朝画史』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eitoku is known for his magnificent and bold paintings (called &quot;Taiga&quot;) such as &quot;Karajishi-zu Byobu&quot; and &quot;Hinoki-zu&quot; (Japanese cypress tree), but he is considered to have created &quot;Saiga&quot; (detailed paintings) too (e.g. &quot;Honcho Gashi&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">RETURN TO TRANSLATOR, PLEASE --VL</e>
<cmt>It is odd to have a translation of hinoki-zu but not karajishi-zy byobu or honcho gashi… it would seem better to have them all translated or none of them, not just one.NR: Very good point. In such cases, could you leave a comment asking for the sentence in question to be returned to the translator?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eitoku is known for his magnificent and bold paintings (called &apos;Taiga&apos;) such as &quot;Karajishi-zu Byobu&quot; and &quot;Hinoki-zu&quot; (Japanese cypress tree), but he is considered to have created &apos;Saiga&apos; (detailed paintings) too (described in &quot;Honcho Gashi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>e.g. →described inこれは例ではなく出典原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にSaigaに合わせTaigaの&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>現存する代表作の一つである上杉本洛中洛外図は、彼が細密描写に秀でていたことを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his representative works in existence, &quot;Uesugi-bon Rakuchu Rakugai-zu&quot; shows that he excelled in detailed paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his representative works that is still extant, &quot;Uesugi-bon Rakuchu Rakugai-zu,&quot; shows that he excelled in detailed paintings.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his representative works that is still extant, &quot;Uesugi-bon Rakuchu Rakugai-zu,&quot; shows that he excelled in detailed paintings.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせる。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>天文 (元号)12年（1543年）、狩野松栄の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1543, he was born as the first son of Shoei KANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1543, Eitoku, the first son of Shoei KANO, was born.</e>
<cmt>天文 not translated… and I am not sure what to do with it because it means &quot;astronomy&quot; which is a non-sequitur here..NR: In this case, Tenbun or Temmon (?) is the name of a Japanese era. This would usually be written as &quot;1543 (Tenbun 12)&quot; but as we are only using the Western date we can ignore this information.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1543, Eitoku, the first son of Shoei KANO, was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>最初に永徳の事績が記録に現れるのは山科言継の日記『言継卿記』の天文21年（1552年）正月二十九日条で、この日に狩野法眼（狩野元信）が孫を連れて将軍足利義輝に拝謁したことが記録されており、この「孫」が当時10歳（数え年）の永徳と推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first record that described Eitoku&apos;s achievements was the chapter of January, 29, 1552 in &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA), according to that record, Hogen KANO (Motonobu KANO) took his grandson to have an audience with Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA and this &quot;grandson&quot; is supposed to be Eitoku at the age of 10 (by the traditional Japanese system).</e>
<cmt>「数え年」の訳語にある&quot;age&quot;は直前の&quot;at the age of&quot;の部分と重複するため、省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first record that described Eitoku&apos;s achievements was an entry in &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) written on January, 29, 1552; according to that record, Hogen KANO (Motonobu KANO) took his grandson to have an audience with Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, and this &quot;grandson&quot; is thought to be Eitoku at the age of 10 (by the traditional Japanese system).</e>
<cmt>Made more stylistic changes. Changed supposed --&gt; thought. Consider using &quot;traditional Japanese calendar&quot; instead of &quot;the traditional Japaense system&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first record that described Eitoku&apos;s achievements was an entry in &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) written on January 29, 1552; according to that record, Hogen KANO (Motonobu KANO) took his grandson to have an audience with Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, and this &apos;grandson&apos; is thought to be Eitoku at the age of 10 (by the traditional Japanese system).</e>
<cmt>日付表記スペース削除原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>永徳の代表作の一つと見なされている上杉本『洛中洛外図』は、その注文者、制作年代、景観年代について多くの説があるが、20世紀末の研究の進展により、永禄8年（1565年）の完成と見なされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for &quot;Uesugi-bon Rakuchu Rakugai-zu&quot;, one of his representative works, though there are various views on the customer, date of creation and date of depicted landscape, it came to be considered completed in 1565 thanks to the development of studies in the end of the 20th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for &quot;Uesugi-bon Rakuchu Rakugai-zu,&quot; one of his representative works, though there are various views on its patronage, date of creation, and the date of landscape it depicts, it is now considered to have been completed in 1565 according to scholarship that came about at the end of the 20th century.</e>
<cmt>comma inside quotation mark. Patron--&gt; patronage rephrased the last clause a bit.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for &quot;Uesugi-bon Rakuchu Rakugai-zu,&quot; one of his representative works, although there are various views on its patronage, date of creation, and the date of landscape it depicts, it is now considered to have been completed in 1565 according to scholarship at the end of the 20th century.</e>
<cmt>“that came about at” =&gt; “at”though→althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>当時永徳は23歳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eitoku was 23 years old at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eitoku was 23 years old at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eitoku was 23 years old at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この屏風は、天正2年（1574年）、織田信長から上杉謙信に贈られている（上杉年譜）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Uesugi Nenpu&quot; (Uesugi&apos;s chronological record), Nobunaga ODA gave this folding screen painting to Kenshin UESUGI in 1574.</e>
<cmt>（上杉年譜）の部分を「上杉年譜によれば」と文章にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Uesugi Nenpu&quot; (Uesugi&apos;s chronological record), Nobunaga ODA gave this folding screen painting to Kenshin UESUGI in 1574.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Uesugi Nenpu&quot; (Uesugi&apos;s chronological record), Nobunaga ODA gave this folding screen painting to Kenshin UESUGI in 1574.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>また、五摂家の筆頭である近衛家とも関係が深く、永禄10 - 11年（1567年 - 1568年）には近衛前久（さきひさ）邸の障壁画を描いている（言継卿記）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he was closely-linked to the Konoe family, the head of Gosekke (five families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku) and drew wall paintings for Sakihisa KONOE&apos;s residence in 1567 and 1568 (described in &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he was closely-linked to the Konoe family, the head of Gosekke (five families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku) and drew wall paintings for Sakihisa KONOE&apos;s residence in 1567 and 1568 (described in &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he was closely-linked to the Konoe family, the head of Gosekke (five families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku) and drew wall paintings for Sakihisa KONOE&apos;s residence in 1567 and 1568 (described in &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>天正4 - 7年（1576年 - 1579年）には安土城に障壁画を描き（信長公記）、天正11年（1583年）には大坂城、天正14年（1586年）には聚楽第の障壁画を担当するなど、織田信長や豊臣秀吉をはじめとする権力者に重く用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; (Biography of Nobunaga ODA), he drew wall paintings for Azuchi Castle from 1576 through 1579, then he did that for Osaka Castle and Jurakudai residence in 1583 and 1586 respectively, in this way, he was given important posts by lords such as Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; (in the biography of Nobunaga ODA), he drew wall paintings for Azuchi Castle from 1576 through 1579, then for Osaka Castle and Jurakudai residence as well in 1583 and 1586 respectively; in this way, he was given important posts by lords such as Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>This appeared once above as well, but is there a better term for &quot;wall paintings?&quot;added &quot;in the&quot; changed comma to semicolon.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shincho Koki&quot; (in the biography of Nobunaga ODA), he drew wall paintings for Azuchi-jo Castle from 1576 through 1579, then for Osaka-jo Castle and Jurakudai residence as well in 1583 and 1586 respectively; in this way, he was given important posts by lords such as Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>城に-joを補足他の時と合わせる。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>天正17年（1589年）には後陽成天皇の内裏の障壁画を担当し、天正18年（1590年）には桂宮の障壁画を描いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1589, he was in charge of wall painting of Emperor Goyozei&apos;s Imperial palace then in 1590, drew a wall painting of Katsuranomiya in 1590.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1589, he was commissioned to make a wall painting for Emperor Goyozei&apos;s Imperial palace, then in 1590, drew a wall painting of Katsuranomiya.</e>
<cmt>or &quot;in&quot; his imperial palace. 1590, 1590 … redundant.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1589, he was commissioned to make a wall painting for Emperor Goyozei&apos;s Imperial palace, then in 1590, drew a wall painting of Katsuranomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同年9月、永徳は東福寺法堂（はっとう）の天井画の龍図を制作中に病気になり、ほどなく死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of the same year, Eitoku got ill during creation of the ceiling painting of Tofuku-ji Hatto (Dharma Hall of Tofuku-ji Temple) and passed away shortly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of the same year, Eitoku became ill during the creation of the ceiling painting Tofuku-ji Hatto (Dharma Hall of Tofuku-ji Temple), and passed away shortly thereafter.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September of the same year, Eitoku became ill during the creation of the ceiling painting Tofuku-ji Hatto (Dharma Hall of Tofuku-ji Temple), and passed away shortly thereafter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>死因は、現代風に言えば過労死ではなかったかともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to be a death from overwork of today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cause of his death is what we would call overworking today.</e>
<cmt>More natural-sounding.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cause of his death is what we would call overworking today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、東福寺法堂の天井画は永徳の下絵を元に弟子の狩野山楽が完成させたが、現存しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ceiling painting of Tofuku-ji Hatto was completed by a disciple, Sanraku KANO, based on Eitoku&apos;s preliminary sketch, but it is not existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ceiling painting of Tofuku-ji Hatto was completed by a disciple, Sanraku KANO, based on Eitoku&apos;s preliminary sketch, but it is not extant.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ceiling painting of Tofuku-ji Hatto was completed by a disciple, Sanraku KANO, based on Eitoku&apos;s preliminary sketch, but it is not extant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>代表作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>聚光院障壁画（国宝） - 京都市・聚光院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juko-in Shohekiga (national treasure) - Juko-in, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juko-in Shohekiga (national treasure) - Juko-in, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juko-in Shohekiga (national treasure) - Juko-in, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>聚光院は大徳寺の塔頭で、永徳は方丈の障壁画を父松栄と共に描いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juko-in is a subtemple of Daitoku-ji Temple and Eitoku drew the wall painting of abbot&apos;s chamber with his father, Shoei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juko-in is a subtemple of Daitoku-ji Temple, and Eitoku drew the wall painting of the abbot&apos;s chamber together with his father, Shoei.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; hereadded comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juko-in is a subtemple of Daitoku-ji Temple, and Eitoku drew the wall painting of the abbot&apos;s chamber together with his father, Shoei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>永徳が担当したのは「花鳥図」16面および「琴棋書画図」8面から成る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eitoku was in charge of 16 panels of &quot;Kacho-zu&quot; (flowers and birds) and 8 panels of &quot;Kinki Shoga-zu&quot; (four accomplishments celebrated as pastimes of the elite-playing the instrument Kin, playing Chinese chess, practicing calligraphy and painting).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eitoku was commissioned to make 16 panels of &quot;Kacho-zu&quot; (flowers and birds) and 8 panels of &quot;Kinki Shoga-zu&quot; (four accomplishments celebrated as pastimes of the elite-playing the Kin, an instrument, playing Chinese chess, practicing calligraphy and painting).</e>
<cmt>Changed in charge of to &quot;commissioned&quot; againreprhased the clause relating to the instrument &quot;kin&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eitoku was commissioned to make 16 panels of &apos;Kacho-zu&apos; (depicting flowers and birds) and 8 panels of &apos;Kinki Shoga-zu&apos; (depicting the four accomplishments: the lute, the game of go, calligraphy, and painting).</e>
<cmt>I&apos;ve revised the explanation provided for Kinki Shoga-zu based on references such as the following. http://books.google.com/books?id=T2_5_W7UFXwC&amp;pg=PA93&amp;dq=%22the+four+accomplishments%22+calligraphy&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=3#v=onepage&amp;q=%22the%20four%20accomplishments%22%20calligraphy&amp;f=false</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>制作年代については従来聚光院創建の年である永禄9年（1566年）、24歳の作品とされていたが、画風の検討や、方丈自体の建立年代の見直しから、かなり後の天正11年（1583年）とする説も有力になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been considered to have been created in 1566 when Juko-in Temple was built and he was 24, but now it is reconsidered as 1583, much later than previous theory, due to the investigation of painting style and review of the age of abbot&apos;s chamber itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally it was considered to have been created in 1566 when Juko-in Temple was built and Eitoku was 24, but it is now considered to have been created in 1583, much later than was previously theorized, due to investigations into the painting style and inquiry into the age of abbot&apos;s chamber itself.</e>
<cmt>If &quot;abbot&apos;s chamber&quot; is the name of a work it needs to be captitalized. Otherwise add &quot;the&quot; this is true of row 40 as well. I am not sure which alternative is true.review of --&gt; inquiry into added &quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally it was considered to have been created in 1566 when Juko-in Temple was built and Eitoku was 24, but it is now considered to have been created in 1583, much later than was previously theorized, due to investigations into the painting style and inquiry into the age of abbot&apos;s chamber itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>2006年より順次複製が制作され、オリジナルは京都国立博物館に寄託される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reproduction paintings has been made sequentially since 2006 and the original paintings will be deposited with Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reproductions have been made at regular intervals since 2006, and the original paintings will be housed in Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>reproduction paintings --&gt; reproductions.Run-onsequentially --&gt; at regular intervalsdeposited -- &gt; housed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reproductions have been made at regular intervals since 2006, and the original paintings will be housed in Kyoto National Museum.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>洛中洛外図（国宝） - 上杉博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakuchu Rakugai-zu (national treasure) - Yonezawa City Uesugi Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakuchu Rakugai-zu (national treasure) - Yonezawa City Uesugi Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakuchu Rakugai-zu (national treasure) - Yonezawa City Uesugi Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>京都の中心部（洛中）と郊外（洛外）を鳥瞰的に描いた洛中洛外図の代表作で、永禄8年（1565年）までに永徳が描き、天正2年（1574年）（天正2年）に織田信長が上杉謙信に贈ったものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a representative Rakuchu Rakugai-zu portraying Rakuchu (center of Kyoto) and Rakugai (suburb) with bird&apos;s eye view and it is said that this painting was drawn by Eitoku before 1565 and given to Kenshin UESUGI by Nobunaga ODA in 1574.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a representative Rakuchu Rakugai-zu portraying Rakuchu (the center of Kyoto) and Rakugai (a suburb) from above, and it is said that this painting was drawn by Eitoku before 1565 and given to Kenshin UESUGI by Nobunaga ODA in 1574.</e>
<cmt>bird&apos;s eye view is too colloquial here. Comma and coordinating conjuction, again..</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a representative Rakuchu Rakugai-zu portraying Rakuchu (the center of Kyoto) and Rakugai (a suburb) from above, and it is said that this painting was drawn by Eitoku before 1565 and given to Kenshin UESUGI by Nobunaga ODA in 1574.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>歴史資料としても貴重で、この屏風に描かれた人物の数は約2,500人という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, this is important as a historical record and 2,500 people were portrayed in this screen painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, this is important as an historical record, and it is said that 2,500 people were portrayed in this screen painting.</e>
<cmt>historical demands &quot;an&quot; as indefinite article, not &quot;a&quot; added a comma againadded &quot;it is said&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, this is important as an historical record, and it is said that 2,500 people were portrayed in this screen painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この屏風については、描かれた都市景観から、制作年代についてさまざまに議論されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories about the date of creation because of the depicted city landscape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories about its date of creation because of the city landscape depicted.</e>
<cmt>the --&gt; itsword order improved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories about its date of creation because of the city landscape depicted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>屏風に描かれた景観年代を天文 (元号)16年（1547年、永徳5歳）のものと見なし「永徳筆ではない」とする説が発表されて論争を巻き起こしたこともあるが、絵画作品の景観年代と制作年代は必ずしも一致するものではなく、今日この説はほぼ否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the theory assuming that the landscape depicted on the screen was 1547 (when Eitoku was 5 years old) and concluding &quot;The painting is not a work of Eitoku&quot; caused controversy, but this theory is mostly denied today since the date of depicted landscape and the date of creation not always correspond with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once, a theory espousing that the landscape depicted on the screen was of 1547 (when Eitoku was 5 years old) and concluding that &quot;The painting is not a work of Eitoku&quot; caused controversy, but this theory is mostly disbelieved today since the date of the landscape depicted and the date of creation do not always correspond with each other.</e>
<cmt>assuming --&gt; espousing denied --&gt; disbelieved (consider discredited as an alternative)word order... Date of the landscape depicted.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once, a theory espousing that the landscape depicted on the screen was of 1547 (when Eitoku was 5 years old) and concluding that &apos;The painting is not a work of Eitoku&apos; caused controversy, but this theory is mostly discredited today since the date of the landscape depicted and the date of creation do not always correspond with each other.</e>
<cmt>“disbelieved”=&gt;”discredited”.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>その後歴史家の瀬田勝哉や黒田日出男の研究により、本作品は永徳の筆で、注文者は足利義輝、制作完成は永禄8年（1565年、永徳23歳）とする説がほぼ定説となっている（黒田日出男『謎解き洛中洛外図』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, a theory claiming that this painting was drawn by Eitoku, ordered by Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA and completed in 1565 (when Eitoku was 23 years old) became a dogma from studies of Katsuya SETA a historian, and Hideo KURODA who wrote &quot;Nazotoki Rakuchu Rakugaizu&quot; (Unraveling the mysteries of Rakuchu Rakugai-zu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, a theory claiming that this painting was drawn by Eitoku, ordered by Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA and completed in 1565 (when Eitoku was 23 years old) became dogmatic due to the research of the historian Katsuya SETA, and Hideo KURODA who wrote &quot;Nazotoki Rakuchu Rakugaizu&quot; (Unraveling the mysteries of Rakuchu Rakugai-zu).</e>
<cmt>assuming--&gt; claiming stuides --&gt; research a dogma--&gt; dogmatic word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, a theory claiming that this painting was drawn by Eitoku, ordered by Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA and completed in 1565 (when Eitoku was 23 years old) became dogmatic due to the research of the historian Katsuya SETA, and Hideo KURODA who wrote &quot;Nazotoki Rakuchu Rakugaizu&quot; (Unraveling the mysteries of Rakuchu Rakugai-zu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>唐獅子図屏風 - 宮内庁三の丸尚蔵館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karajishi-zu Byobu - Kunaicho Sannomaru Shozokan (The Museum of the Imperial Collections)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karajishi-zu Byobu - Kunaicho Sannomaru Shozokan (The Museum of the Imperial Collections)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karajishi-zu Byobu - Kunaicho Sannomaru Shozokan (The Museum of the Imperial Collections)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>天正10年（1582年、永徳40歳）に豊臣秀吉が毛利家に贈ったものと言われるが確証はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI gave this painting to the Mori family in 1582 (when Eitoku was 40 years old), but it is unconfirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI gave this painting to the Mori family in 1582 (when Eitoku was 40 years old), but this is unconfirmed.</e>
<cmt>it--&gt;thisconsider &quot;was not confirmed&quot; or &quot;has not been confirmed &quot; instead of &quot;unconfirmed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI gave this painting to the Mori family in 1582 (when Eitoku was 40 years old), but this has not been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>unconfirmed→has not been confirmed</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>明治期に皇室に献上された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was dedicated to the Imperial family during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was dedicated to the Imperial family during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was dedicated to the Imperial family during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>永徳筆である旨の狩野探幽（永徳の孫）の書入れがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a note written by Tanyu KANO (a grandson of Eitoku) explaining that it is a work of Eitoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a note written by Tanyu KANO (a grandson of Eitoku) explaining that it is a work of Eitoku&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>possessive</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a note written by Tanyu KANO (a grandson of Eitoku) explaining that it is a work of Eitoku&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>以上3件は従来から永徳筆とされてきたもので、美術史家の間には永徳作とすることについてほとんど異論はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These three paintings have been considered as works of Eitoku and that is accepted among art historians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These three paintings have come to be considered works of Eitoku, and there is little disagreement about this among art historians.</e>
<cmt>ほとんど異論はない this was poorly expressed in the English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These three paintings have come to be considered works of Eitoku, and there is little disagreement about this among art historians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="37">
<j>「特別展覧会 狩野永徳」（2007年、京都国立博物館）においては以下の作品を永徳作としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;KANO EITOKU Special Exhibition&quot; (Kyoto National Museum, 2007), the following paintings are treated as works of Eitoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;KANO EITOKU Special Exhibition&quot; (Kyoto National Museum, 2007), the following paintings are treated as works of Eitoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;KANO EITOKU Special Exhibition&quot; (Kyoto National Museum, 2007), the following paintings are treated as works of Eitoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>南禅寺大方丈障壁画（重要文化財） - 京都市・南禅寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wall painting at Ohojo of Nanzen-ji-Temple (important cultural property) - Nanzen-ji Temple, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wall painting at Ohojo of Nanzen-ji-Temple (important cultural property) - Nanzen-ji Temple, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>added &quot;A&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wall painting at Ohojo of Nanzen-ji Temple (important cultural property) - Nanzen-ji Temple, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="39">
<j>狩野派による共作（1586 - 91年頃）で、群仙図が永徳筆ではないかと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a collaborative work of Kano school (c. 1586-1591) and it is considered that Gunsen-zu was drawn by Eitoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a collaborative work of the Kano school (c. 1586-1591), and Gunsen-zu is said most likely to have been drawn by Eitoku.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;the&quot; and a comma, considered --&gt; believed, word order; added &quot;probably&quot;minor rephrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a collaborative work of the Kano school (c. 1586-1591), and Gunsen-zu is said most likely to have been drawn by Eitoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>檜図屏風（国宝） - 東京国立博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hinoki-zu Byobu - Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinoki-zu Byobu - Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinoki-zu Byobu (national treasure) - Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>(national treasure)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="41">
<j>伝永徳筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Said to be a work of Eitoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Said to be a work of Eitoku&apos;s</e>
<cmt>possessive</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A painting attributed to Eitoku.</e>
<cmt>表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>天正18年（1590年）? 桂宮家旧蔵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Painted around 1590. Former collection of the Katsuranomiya family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Painted around 1590. In the former collection of the Katsuranomiya family</e>
<cmt>added &quot;in the&quot;Is &quot;former&quot; the best word choice here?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Painted around 1590. In the former collection of the Katsuranomiya family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>元は八条宮邸の障壁画であったと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this painting was originally a wall painting of Hachijonomiya mansion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this painting was originally a wall painting of Hachijonomiya mansion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this painting was originally a wall painting in Hachijonomiya mansion.</e>
<cmt>of→in八条宮廷の中にあった障壁画です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>許由巣父図（重要文化財） - 東京国立博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoyu Soho-zu (Xuyou and Chaofu) - Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoyu Soho-zu (Xuyou and Chaofu) - Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoyu Soho-zu (Xuyou and Chaofu) (important cultural property) - Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>(important cultural property)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="45">
<j>伝永徳筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Said to be a work of Eitoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Said to be a work of Eitoku&apos;s</e>
<cmt>as above</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A painting attributed to Eitoku.</e>
<cmt>表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>2幅からなる紙本墨画。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihon Bokuga (ink painting on paper), consisted of 2 scroll paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shihon Bokuga (ink painting on paper), consisted of 2 scroll paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shihon Bokuga (monochrome ink painting on paper), consisted of 2 scroll paintings.</e>
<cmt>monochrome補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="47">
<j>仙人高士図屏風（重要文化財） - 京都国立博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sennin Koshi-zu Byobu (folding screen with painting of a hermit) - Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sennin Koshi-zu Byobu (folding screen with painting of a hermit) - Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sennin Koshi-zu Byobu (folding screen with painting of a hermit) (important cultural property) - Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt>(important cultural property)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="48">
<j>伝永徳筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Said to be a work of Eitoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Said to be a work of Eitoku&apos;s</e>
<cmt>ibid.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A painting attributed to Eitoku.</e>
<cmt>表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>元は建仁寺の塔頭の障壁画であったと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be originally a wall painting of the subtemple of Kennin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, it was said to be a wall painting of the subtemple of Kennin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>word order changedTenses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, it was said to be a wall painting of the subtemple of Kennin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="50">
<j>洛外名所遊楽図屏風 四曲一双 - 個人蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rakugai Meisho Yuraku-zu Byobu (folding screen with painting of amusements at notable locations around Kyoto), a pair of 4 fold screens - private collection</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rakugai Meisho Yuraku-zu Byobu (folding screen with painting of amusements at notable locations around Kyoto), a pair of 4 fold screens - private collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rakugai Meisho Yuraku-zu Byobu (folding screen with painting of amusements at notable locations around Kyoto), a pair of 4 fold screens - private collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="51">
<j>2005年7月、京都の古物商で発見された（2006年9月13日朝日新聞報道）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 2005, it was found in an antique dealer in Kyoto (reported on September 13, 2006 in The Asahi Shimbun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 2005, it was found in an antique dealer in Kyoto (reported on September 13, 2006 in The Asahi Shimbun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 2005, it was found in an antique dealer in Kyoto (reported on September 13, 2006 in The Asahi Shimbun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>落款等はないが上杉本洛中洛外図と描写法が良く似ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no seal and signature of the painter, but it is drawn in similar style as &quot;Uesugi-bon Rakuchu Rakugai-zu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neither the painter&apos;s seal nor his signature is present, but it is drawn in a style similar to that of &quot;Uesugi-bon Rakuchu Rakugai-zu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>phrasing, as -&gt; to that oftypographical error removed. Rephrased.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neither the painter&apos;s seal nor his signature is present, but it is drawn in a style similar to that of Uesugi-bon Rakuchu Rakugai-zu.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot; &quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="53">
<j>花鳥図押絵貼屏風 六曲一双 - 個人蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kacho-zu Oshiebari Byobu (folding screen pasted with pictures of flowers and birds), a pair of 6 fold screens - private collection</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kacho-zu Oshiebari Byobu (folding screen pasted with pictures of flowers and birds), a pair of 6 fold screens - private collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kacho-zu Oshiebari Byobu (folding screen pasted with pictures of flowers and birds), a pair of 6 fold screens - private collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="54">
<j>梔子に小禽図（墨画） - 個人蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ink painting of a small bird on Cape jasmine tree - private collection</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ink painting of a small bird on Cape jasmine tree - private collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ink painting of a small bird on Cape jasmine tree - private collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="55">
<j>老莱子図 - 山口・菊屋家住宅保存会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Picture of Roraishi - Yamaguchi Kikuyake Jutaku Hozonkai (Kikuyake Jutaku Preservation Foundation, Yamaguchi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Picture of Roraishi - Yamaguchi Kikuyake Jutaku Hozonkai (Kikuyake Jutaku Preservation Foundation, Yamaguchi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Picture of Roraishi - Yamaguchi Kikuyake Jutaku Hozonkai (Kikuyake Jutaku Preservation Foundation, Yamaguchi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="56">
<j>二十四孝図屏風 六曲一双 - 福岡市博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijushiko-zu Byobu (folding screen with painting depicting 24 filial figures), a pair of 6 fold screens - Fukuoka City Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijushiko-zu Byobu (folding screen with painting depicting 24 filial figures), a pair of 6 fold screens - Fukuoka City Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijushiko-zu Byobu (folding screen with painting depicting 24 filial figures), a pair of 6 fold screens - Fukuoka City Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="57">
<j>四季山水図 六曲一双 - 香雪美術館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiki Sansui-zu (Landscape of the four seasons), a pair of 6 fold screens - Kosetsu Museum of Art</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiki Sansui-zu (Landscape of the four seasons), a pair of 6 fold screens - Kosetsu Museum of Art</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiki Sansui-zu (Landscape of the four seasons), a pair of 6 fold screens - Kosetsu Museum of Art</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="58">
<j>伝永徳筆（左隻のみ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Said to be a work of Eitoku (left panel only)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Said to be a work of Eitoku&apos;s (left panel only)</e>
<cmt>possessive</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A painting attributed to Eitoku (left panel only).</e>
<cmt>表記を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="59">
<j>渡唐天神図 - 瀬戸市・定光寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toto Tenjin-zu (Tenjin who went over to China) - Joko-ji Temple, Seto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toto Tenjin-zu (Tenjin who went over to China) - Joko-ji Temple, Seto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toto Tenjin-zu (Tenjin who went to China) - Joko-ji Temple, Seto City</e>
<cmt>“Tenjin who went over to China” であれは戦う中国に加勢するような意味になる→“Tenjin who went to China”.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="60">
<j>柿本人麻呂図 - 群馬県立近代美術館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Portrait of KAKIMOTO no Hitomaro - The Museum of Modern Art, Gunma</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Portrait of KAKIMOTO no Hitomaro - The Museum of Modern Art, Gunma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Portrait of KAKIMOTO no Hitomaro - The Museum of Modern Art, Gunma</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="61">
<j>旧日光院客殿障壁画 - アルカンシエール美術財団</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wall painting at the former reception hall of Nikkoin Temple - Arc-en-Ciel Foundation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wall painting at the former reception hall of Nikkoin Temple - Arc-en-Ciel Foundation</e>
<cmt>added &quot;A&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wall painting at the former reception hall of Nikkoin Temple - Arc-en-Ciel Foundation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="62">
<j>織田信長像 - 大徳寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Portrait of Nobunaga ODA - Daitoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Portrait of Nobunaga ODA - Daitoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Portrait of Nobunaga ODA - Daitoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>現存しない作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Defunct works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lost works</e>
<cmt>defunct--&gt;lost</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lost works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>安土城障壁画 - 天正4年（1576年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wall painting at Azuchi Castle (painted in 1576)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wall painting at Azuchi Castle (painted in 1576)</e>
<cmt>added &quot;A&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wall painting at Azuchi-jo Castle (painted in 1576)</e>
<cmt>城に-joを補足他の記事と合わせる。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="64">
<j>大坂城障壁画 - 天正13年（1585年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wall painting at Osaka Castle (painted in 1585)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wall painting at Osaka Castle (painted in 1585)</e>
<cmt>added &quot;A&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wall painting at Osaka-jo Castle (painted in 1585)</e>
<cmt>城に-joを補足他の記事と合わせる。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="65">
<j>聚楽第障壁画 - 天正15年（1587年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wall painting at Jurakudai residence (painted in 1587)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wall painting at Jurakudai residence (painted in 1587)</e>
<cmt>added &quot;A&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wall painting at Jurakudai residence (painted in 1587)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="66">
<j>天瑞寺障壁画 - 天正16年（1588年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wall painting at Tenzui-ji Temple (painted in 1588)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A wall painting at Tenzui-ji Temple (painted in 1588)</e>
<cmt>added &quot;A&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A wall painting at Tenzui-ji Temple (painted in 1588)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>天瑞寺は大徳寺内に秀吉が創建したものだが、1874年、廃寺になった際、建物とともに障壁画も失われたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenzui-ji Temple was built by Hideyoshi on the grounds of Daitoku-ji Temple, in 1874, when Tenzui-ji Temple was closed, the wall painting was perished together with the building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenzui-ji Temple was built by Hideyoshi on the grounds of Daitoku-ji Temple in 1874, and when Tenzui-ji Temple was abandoned the wall painting perished together with the building.</e>
<cmt>closed---&gt; abandoned. I do not know if this temple was abandoned or destroyed. The best word choice depends on that distinction. Was perished --&gt; perished</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenzui-ji Temple was built by Hideyoshi on the grounds of Daitoku-ji Temple in 1874, and when Tenzui-ji Temple was abandoned the wall painting perished together with the building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>所在不明の作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Missing works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Missing works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Missing works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>安土城之図 - 天正9年（1581年）以前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azuchi-jo no zu (folding screen with painting of Azuchi Casle) (painted before 1581)</e>
<cmt>安土城之図→Azuchi-jo no zu (painting of Azuchi Castle)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azuchi-jo no zu (a folding screen with a painting of Azuchi Castle) (painted before 1581)</e>
<cmt>casle --&gt; castleadded &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azuchi-jo no zu (a folding screen with a painting of Azuchi-jo Castle) (painted before 1581)</e>
<cmt>城に-joを補足他の記事と合わせる。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="69">
<j>天正9年（1581年）、織田信長は安土を訪れた宣教師ヴァリニャーノに安土城之図屏風を贈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1581, Nobunaga ODA gave &quot;Azuchi-jo no zu Byobu&quot; to a missionary by the name of Alessandro Valignano who visited Azuchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1581, Nobunaga ODA gave &quot;Azuchi-jo no zu Byobu&quot; to a missionary by the name of Alessandro Valignano, who visited Azuchi Castle.</e>
<cmt>added commaAdded &quot;castle&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1581, Nobunaga ODA gave Azuchi-jo no zu Byobu to a missionary by the name of Alessandro Valignano, who visited Azuchi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>城に-joを補足他の記事と合わせる。原文に『』のない&quot; &quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>この屏風は永徳筆ではないかと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This folding screen painting is considered to be drawn by Eitoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This folding screen painting is considered to have been drawn by Eitoku.</e>
<cmt>be--&gt;have been</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This folding screen painting is considered to have been drawn by Eitoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この屏風は安土城下や京で展示され、後に天正遣欧使節の手によって渡欧し、バチカンにてローマ教皇に献納された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This folding screen painting was exhibited in the castle town of Azuchi and Kyo, Capital, then brought to Europe by envoy to Europe during the Tensho era and then dedicated to the Pope in Vatican.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This folding screen painting was exhibited in the castle town of Azuchi and Kyo, Capital, then brought to Europe by envoy to Europe during the Tensho era and then dedicated to the Pope in Vatican.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This folding screen painting was exhibited in the castle town of Azuchi and Kyo, Capital, then brought to Europe by envoy during the Tensho era and then dedicated to the Pope in the Vatican.</e>
<cmt>文法と重複問題。“ to Europe by envoy to Europe during the Tensho era and then dedicated to the Pope in Vatican.”=&gt;” to Europe by envoy during the Tensho era and then dedicated to the Pope in the Vatican.”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>教皇は住居と執務室を結ぶ廊下に屏風絵を飾ったといわれるが、教皇の死後に屏風は行方不明となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Pope displayed the folding screen painting in the hallway which connected his residence and office, but the painting went missing after the Pope passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Pope displayed the folding screen painting in the hallway that connected his residence and office, but the painting went missing after the Pope passed away.</e>
<cmt>which --&gt; that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Pope displayed the folding screen painting in the hallway that connected his residence and office, but the painting went missing after the Pope passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="73">
<j>1984年には滋賀県が、2005年には安土町が、それぞれバチカンを調査したが、いずれも発見には至らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiga Prefecture and Azuchi Town conducted investigation of Vatican in 1984 and 2005 respectively, but the painting was not found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiga Prefecture and Azuchi Town conducted investigation of Vatican in 1984 and 2005 respectively, but the painting was not found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiga Prefecture and Azuchi-cho conducted an investigation in the Vatica in 1984 and 2005 respectively, but the painting was not found.</e>
<cmt>文法間違い。 “investigation of Vatican”=&gt; “ an investigation in the Vatican”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kanejan(id:78613), ととりん(id:31982), Ceridwen(id:36889), Carbuncle(id:346), Cprobot(id:97843), Urania(id:7213), Eskimbot(id:29676), Kanoe(id:17203), 663highland(id:18755), Yas(id:739), Kouko0515(id:100370), Louperibot(id:128971), Kareha(id:36360), 行動で挽回するしかない(id:31799), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>