<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>千手の前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senju no Mae</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senju no Mae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senju no Mae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>千手の前（せんじゅのまえ　永万元年（1165年） - 文治4年（1188年）4月25日 (旧暦)）は平安時代末期の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senju no Mae (1165-April 25, 1188 (old calendar) was the lady, who lived in the end of Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senju no Mae (1165-April 25, 1188 (old calendar) was a lady, who lived during the end of Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senju no Mae (1165 - May 30, 1188) was a lady, who lived during the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『平家物語』によると駿河国手越長者の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), she was the daughter of Tegoshi choja (the chieftain of Tegoshi) of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), she was the daughter of Tegoshi choja (the chieftain of Tegoshi) of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), she was the daughter of Tegoshi choja (the chieftain of Tegoshi) in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>千手は源頼朝の官女となり、後に北条政子付きの女房となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senju became the Kanjo (court lady) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and the Nyobo (a lady-in-waiting) of Masako HOJO afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senju became the Kanjo (court lady) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and afterwards the Nyobo (a lady-in-waiting) of Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senju became the Kanjo (court lady) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and afterwards the Nyobo (a lady-in-waiting) of Masako HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>温和な性格の女性だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a lady with a warm personality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a lady with a warm personality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a lady with a warm personality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>寿永3年（1184年）3月27日、一ノ谷の戦いで捕虜になった平重衡が伊豆国国府に到着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Shigehira, who became a hostage during the Ichinotani no Tatakai (the Battle of Ichinotani), arrived to the Kokufu (ancient provincial offices, national government, provincial capital) of Izu Province on March 27, 1184.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Shigehira, who became a hostage during the Ichinotani no Tatakai (the Battle of Ichinotani), arrived to the Kokufu (ancient provincial offices, national government, provincial capital) of Izu Province on March 27, 1184.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Shigehira, who became a hostage during (the Battle of Ichinotani, arrived to the Kokufu (ancient provincial offices) of Izu Province on May 16, 1184.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>重衡は平清盛の五男で正三位近衛中将の位を持つ貴人であるが、治承4年（1180年）に南都（奈良）へ攻め込み興福寺、東大寺の尽くを焼き尽くした南都焼討を行った大将であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigehira was the fifth son of TAIRA no Kiyomori, the aristocrat with the ranks of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Konoe no chujo (middle captain of the palace guards), and the general who invaded and conquered Nanto (Nara) by burning down its Kofuku-ji Temple and Todai-ji Temple in 1180.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigehira was the fifth son of TAIRA no Kiyomori, the aristocrat with the ranks of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Konoe no chujo (middle captain of the palace guards), and the general who invaded and conquered Nanto (Nara) by burning down its Kofuku-ji Temple and Todai-ji Temple in 1180.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigehira was the fifth son of TAIRA no Kiyomori, the aristocrat with the ranks of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Konoe no chujo (middle captain of the palace guards), and the general who invaded and conquered Nanto (Nara) by burning down its Kofuku-ji Temple and Todai-ji Temple in 1180.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>翌28日、重衡と対面した頼朝が下記のように言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo, who clashed with Shigehira on the 28th of the following day stated, &quot;it is a happy occasion that I was able to mobilize the army to soften the anger of In (emperor) (Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa) and to carry out a vengeance for my late father (MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo) by defeating the Taira clan and meeting with you.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo, who clashed with Shigehira on the 28th of the following day stated, &quot;it is a happy occasion that I was able to mobilize the army to soften the anger of In (emperor) (Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa) and to carry out a vengeance for my late father (MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo) by defeating the Taira clan and meeting with you.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo clashed with Shigehira on 17 of the following day and stated as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。以下、一旦1文に戻してから分割しました。寿永3年3月28日としてグレゴリオ暦に直し表記し、」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「院（後白河法皇）の怒りを慰めるため、また亡き父（源義朝）の仇を討つために挙兵し、平氏を退治でき、こうして貴方と対面できたことは喜ばしいことだ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You could meet up with Lord TAIRA no Munemori eventually,&quot; to which Shigehira responded boldly, &quot;Mitamoto and Taira were people who were supposed to protect the imperial court together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You could meet up with Lord TAIRA no Munemori eventually,&quot; to which Shigehira responded boldly, &quot;Mitamoto and Taira were people who were supposed to protect the imperial court together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a happy occasion that I was able to mobilize the army to soften the anger of In (retired emperor) (Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa) and to carry out a vengeance for my late father (MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo) by defeating the Taira clan and meeting with you.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「いずれは平宗盛殿とも対面できるでしょう」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, only the Taira family defended the imperial court, and luck ran out at the end of twenty-something years of prosperity, and am captured like this now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, only the Taira family defended the imperial court, and luck ran out at the end of twenty-something years of prosperity, and am captured like this now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You could meet up with Lord TAIRA no Munemori eventually.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>重衡は下記のように堂々と言い放った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a member of the buke (samurai family), it is not disgraceful to lose one&apos;s life by the enemy hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a member of the buke (samurai family), it is not disgraceful to lose one&apos;s life by enemy hands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigehira responded boldly as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「そもそも源平は共に朝廷を守護する者であった。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I would like you to behead me now.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I would like you to behead me now.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minamoto and Taira were people who were supposed to protect the imperial court together.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「ところが近年は平家のみが朝廷を守護することになり、20余年の栄華を極めたるに、今は運尽きてこうして捕えられました。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, only the Taira family defended the imperial court, and luck ran out at the end of twenty-something years of prosperity, and am captured like this now.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「武家である以上は敵の手にかかって命を落とすのは恥ではない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a member of the buke (samurai family), it is not disgraceful to lose one&apos;s life by enemy hands.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「すぐにこの首をはねていただきたい」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I would like you to behead me now.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>頼朝は重衡の器量に感服して丁重に遇することとし、狩野宗茂に預けることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo was impressed with the capacity of Shigehira and decided to treat him with respect and passed his custody to Munemochi KANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo was impressed with the capacity of Shigehira and decided to treat him with respect and passed his custody to Munemochi KANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo was impressed with the capacity of Shigehira and decided to treat him with respect and passed his custody to Munemochi KANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>4月8日に重衡は鎌倉に移され、御所内に一室を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigehira was transferred to Kamakura on April 8 and was given a room within the gosho (palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigehira was transferred to Kamakura on April 8 and was given a room within the gosho (palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigehira was transferred to Kamakura on May 26 and was given a room within the gosho (palace).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>4月20日、沐浴を許され、夜になると頼朝のはからいで藤原邦通、工藤祐経そして官女の千手が遣わされ、徒然を慰めるために宴が催された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was permitted to bathe on April 20, and FUJIWARA no Kunimichi, Suketsune KUDO, and the Senju, who was the Kanjo (court lady), were dispatched to him by the arrangement of Yoritomo at the evening to hold a party to console the idleness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was permitted to bathe on April 20, and FUJIWARA no Kunimichi, Suketsune KUDO, and the Senju, who was the Kanjo (court lady), were dispatched to him by the arrangement of Yoritomo at the evening to hold a party to console the idleness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was permitted to bathe on June 7, and FUJIWARA no Kunimichi, Suketsune KUDO, and the Senju, who was the Kanjo (court lady), were dispatched to him by the arrangement of Yoritomo at the evening to hold a party to console the idleness.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>祐経が鼓を打ち、千手が琵琶を弾き、重衡が横笛を吹いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suketsune beat the drums, Senju played the biwa (Japanese lute), and Shigehira played the flute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suketsune beat the drums, Senju played the biwa (Japanese lute), and Shigehira played the flute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suketsune beat tsuzumi (hand drum), Senju played the biwa (Japanese lute), and Shigehira played oteki (transverse flute).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>雅楽の「五常楽」を吹くと、自分は解官された身だから後生楽と云うのだと洒落た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After performing the &quot;Gojoraku&quot; of the gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), he joked that since he was dismissed from the court official position, it was called Goshoraku (carefree and optimistic).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After performing the &quot;Gojoraku&quot; of the gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), he joked that since he was dismissed from the court official position, it was called Goshoraku (carefree and optimistic).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his performing the &apos;Goshoraku&apos; (also known as Gojoraku; literally, Gosho (five eternal virtues) composition) of the gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), he joked that since he was dismissed from the court official position, the tune was called &apos;Goshoraku&apos; (carefree and optimistic).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、「皇しょう急」を吹くと往生急（往生（死）を急ぐ）のだと興じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also amused himself that if he played &quot;Ojokyu (皇しょう急),&quot; it will be Ojokyu (往生急) (quickens death).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also amused himself that if he played &quot;Ojokyu (皇しょう急),&quot; it will be Ojokyu (往生急) (quickens death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he played &apos;Ojokyu&apos; (also known as Ojo no kyu, a tune of gagaku, performed by Kangen style (instruments style without dance)), he also amused himself that he would be &apos;Ojokyu&apos; (quicken death).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>夜が更けて、千手たちが帰ろうとすると、重衡はこれを引き留めて盃を進めさせ、朗詠し、前漢楚の故事をひいて燭が暗くなるのは虞美人（項羽の妻）の涙、夜が更けるのは四面楚歌の声さと言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became late at night and when Senju and others were about to leave, Shigehira stopped them and offered drink while recited, the candle dims due to the tears of Gubijin (Yu Meiren, who was the wife of Koseki Xiang Yu) and the night falls due to the voice of Shimensoka (being surrounded by enemies on all sides) taking after the historical event of the former Han and Chu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became late at night and when Senju and others were about to leave, Shigehira stopped them and offered drink while recited, the candle dims due to the tears of Gubijin (Yu Meiren, who was the wife of Koseki Xiang Yu) and the night falls due to the voice of Shimensoka (being surrounded by enemies on all sides) taking after the historical event of the former Han and Chu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became late at night and when Senju and others were about to leave, Shigehira stopped them and offered drink while recited and, taking after the historical event of the former Han and Chu, said as follows; the candle dims due to the tears of Gubijin (Yu Meiren, who was the wife of Koseki Xiang Yu) and the night falls due to the voice of Shimensoka (being surrounded by enemies on all sides).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>翌日、邦道は頼朝に宴の様子を「芸能、言動ともにとても優れた方でした」と報告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunimichi reported to Yoritomo about the atmosphere of the party on the following day as &quot;he was the one both excelled in art and use of words.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunimichi reported to Yoritomo about the atmosphere of the party on the following day as &quot;he was the one both excelled in art and use of words.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunimichi reported to Yoritomo about the atmosphere of the party on the following day as &apos;he was the one both excelled in art and use of words.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>頼朝は世間体を憚って宴に同席しなかったのを悔いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo regretted that he did not attend the party from being wary of receiving bad reputations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo regretted that he did not attend the party from being wary of receiving a bad reputation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo regretted that he did not attend the party from being wary of receiving a bad reputation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>頼朝は千手に夜具の着物を持たせて重衡のもとへ遣いさせ、祐経に「田舎の女もよいものですよ」と伝えさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo sent Senju to Shigehira with her night gown, saying to Suketsune, &quot;even a country woman is pleasing.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo sent Senju to Shigehira with her night gown, saying to Suketsune, &quot;even a country woman is pleasing.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo sent Senju to Shigehira with her night gown and Suketsune to say to him, &apos;even a country woman is pleasing.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>こうして、千手は虜囚の重衡に仕えることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Senju began to serve the hostage Shigehira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Senju began to serve the hostage Shigehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Senju began to serve the hostage Shigehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>重衡と千手との生活は長くは続かず、壇ノ浦の戦いで平家が滅亡した後の元暦2年（1185年）6月9日、重衡は南都大衆の強い要求により、引き渡されることになり鎌倉を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the life of Shigehira and Senju did not last long, and when the Taira clan fell due to the Dannoura Tatakai (the Battle of Dannoura) on June 9, 1185, Shigehira was handed over due to the demands of Nanto people and left Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the life of Shigehira and Senju did not last long, and when the Taira clan fell due to the Dannoura Tatakai (the Battle of Dannoura) on June 9, 1185, Shigehira was handed over due to the demands of Nanto people and left Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the life of Shigehira and Senju did not last long, and when the Taira family fell due to the Battle of Dannoura on July 14, 1185, Shigehira was handed over due to the demands of Nanto people and left Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>同月23日、重衡は木津川 (京都府)にて斬首された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigehira was beheaded at Kizu-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) on 23rd of the same month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigehira was beheaded at Kizu-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) on 23rd of the same month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigehira was beheaded at the Kizu-gawa River (Kyoto Prefecture) on 28 of the same month.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>その3年後の文治4年（1188年）4月22日、政子の女房として仕えていた千手は失神し、しばらくして蘇生するが、3日後の25日にわずか24歳で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senju, who was serving as the Nyobo of Masako, fainted on April 22, 1188, three years after that event, and recovered for a moment before dying at a young age of twenty-four on 25th which was three days after.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senju, who was serving as the Nyobo of Masako, fainted on April 22, 1188, three years after that event, and recovered for a moment before dying at a young age of twenty-four on 25th which was three days after.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senju, who was serving as the Nyobo of Masako, fainted on May 27, 1188, three years after that event, and recovered for a moment before dying at a young age of 24 on 30 which was three days after.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>鎌倉の人々は千手が亡き重衡を朝夕恋慕し、その嘆きが積み重なって病になったのだろうと噂した（『吾妻鏡』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People of Kamakura rumored that Senju continuously loved the late Shigehira that the grief build up and became ill (&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)).</e>
<cmt>『吾妻鏡』→&quot;Azumakagami&quot; (Mirror of my wife)と判断しました[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People of Kamakura rumored that Senju continuously loved the late Shigehira and that the grief built up and she became ill (&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; - The Mirror of the East).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People of Kamakura rumored that Senju continuously loved the late Shigehira and that the grief built up and she became ill (&quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East)).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="31">
<j>『平家物語』では、千手は出家して信濃国善光寺に入り、重衡の菩提を弔っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), Senju underwent shukke (became a Buddhist priest) and entered Zenko-ji Temple in Shinano Province to pray to Buddha for the happiness of the late Shigehira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), Senju underwent shukke (became a Buddhist priest) and entered Zenko-ji Temple in Shinano Province to pray to Buddha for the happiness of the late Shigehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heike Monogatari,&quot; Senju became a Buddhist priest and entered Zenko-ji Temple in Shinano Province to pray to Buddha for the happiness of the late Shigehira.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="32">
<j>鎌倉での重衡と千手との関わりは『平家物語』の一節になっており、これをもとに能の演目に重衡と千手の一夜を描く『千手』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relation between Shigehira and Senju in Kamakura is portrayed as a passage within the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; and the Noh (Japanese play) title of &quot;Senju&quot; which depicted the night between Shigehira and Senju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between Shigehira and Senju in Kamakura is portrayed as a passage within the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; and the Noh (Japanese play) title of &quot;Senju&quot; which depicted the night between Shigehira and Senju.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between Shigehira and Senju in Kamakura is portrayed as a passage within the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; and the Noh (Japanese play) title of &quot;Senju&quot; which depicted the night between Shigehira and Senju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また、静岡市駿河区手越の少将井神社には千手の像がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a statue of Senju present in Shoshoi-jinja Shrine in Tegoshi, Suruga Ward, Shizuoka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a statue of Senju present in Shoshoi-jinja Shrine in Tegoshi, Suruga Ward, Shizuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a statue of Senju present in Shoshoi-jinja Shrine in Tegoshi, Suruga Ward, Shizuoka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), 味っ子(id:17086), 地図帳(id:122587), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>