<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小山政光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamitsu OYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamitsu OYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamitsu OYAMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小山 政光（おやま まさみつ、生没年未詳）は、平安時代末期、鎌倉時代初期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamitsu OYAMA (dates of birth and death unknown) was a Bush (Japanese military commander) from the end of Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamitsu OYAMA (dates of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) lived over the end of Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>武将がBushとスペルミスです。時代の表現をlivedを加えて書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamitsu OYAMA (dates of birth and death unknown) was a busho (Japanese military commander) lived over the end of Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元の名は太田政光。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His former name was Masamitsu OTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Masamitsu OTA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;former&quot;だと一つ前の名前になるため&quot;original&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Masamitsu OTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>武蔵国の在庁官人で藤原秀郷の直系子孫とされる太田行政の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamitsu was a son of Yukimasa OTA, a Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) of Musashi Province, and who was called a direct descendant of FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamitsu was the son of Yukimasa OTA, a Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) of Musashi Province who was believed to be descended in a direct line from FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt>&quot;called&quot;では原文の意味と異なるので書き換えました。&quot;son&quot;の冠詞をtheに替えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamitsu was the son of Yukimasa OTA, a Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) of Musashi Province who was believed to be descended in a direct line from FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>太田政光は平安時代末期の1150年頃、下野国に移住して小山荘に住し、小山四郎、小山下野大椽と称し小山氏の祖となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamitsu OTA moved to Shimotsuke Province around 1150, the end of the Heian period, and settled in Oyama district, calling himself Shiro OYAMA or Shimotsukenodaiki OYAMA; thus, Masamitsu established the Oyama clan.</e>
<cmt>「小山荘」「小山下野大椽」の読み方が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamitsu OTA moved to Shimotsuke Province around 1150 in the end of the Heian period and settled in Oyama shoen (manor in medieval Japan), calling himself Shiro OYAMA or Shimotsukenodaiten OYAMA to be the founder of the Oyama family.</e>
<cmt>「小山荘」は荘園名とし訳しました。小山氏の祖はOyama familyと訳すべきと考えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamitsu OTA moved to Shimotsuke Province around 1150 in the end of the Heian period and settled in Oyama shoen (manor in medieval Japan), calling himself Shiro OYAMA or Shimotsukenodaiten OYAMA to be the founder of the Oyama family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>法名蓮西。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Homyo (a posthumous Buddhist name used in the Shin sect) was Rensai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Homyo (priest&apos;s name or posthumous Buddhist name) was Rensai.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Shin sect&quot;が真宗の意味と思いますが、Shinshu sectが正しいと思います。しかし法名は真宗に限られたものではないので法名の説明を用語集に従って変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Homyo (priest&apos;s name or posthumous Buddhist name) was Rensai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後妻として八田宗綱の娘で源頼朝の乳母を務めた寒河尼がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His second wife was SAMUKAWA no Ama, who was Munetsuna YATA&apos;s daughter and had worked as a Menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>「八田宗綱」の読み方が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAMUKAWA no Ama, the daughter of Munetsuna HATTA, who had been a Menoto (wet nurse) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was one of his wives.</e>
<cmt>原文から「本妻以外の妻の中に」と考えられるので書き換えました。乳母の説明を用語集に基づき変更し、わかりづらい箇所も変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAMUKAWA no Ama, the daughter of Munetsuna HATTA, who had been a Menoto (wet nurse) of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo was one of his wives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子に小山朝政、長沼宗政、結城朝光、宇都宮頼綱（猶子）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons were Tomomasa OYAMA, Tomomitsu YUKI, and Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA (an adopted child who was considered as Masmitsu&apos;s own).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons included Tomomasa OYAMA, Tomomitsu YUKI, and Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA (an adopted child).</e>
<cmt>猶子の説明がわかりづらいのでan adopted childだけにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons included Tomomasa OYAMA, Tomomitsu YUKI, and Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA (an adopted child).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>うち結城朝光のみが寒河尼の実子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomitsu YUKI was the only biological child of SAMUKAWA no Ama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, only Tomomitsu YUKI was a child born between he and SAMUKAWA no Ama.</e>
<cmt>「うち」が訳漏れです。&quot;the only biological child of SAMUKAWA no Ama&quot;では寒河尼の連れ子になってしまうと考え、書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, only Tomomitsu YUKI was a child born between he and SAMUKAWA no Ama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>官位は正七位下下野国椽。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masmitsu&apos;s official rank was Shoshichiinoge (Senior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade), Shimotsuke Province Ki.</e>
<cmt>「椽」の定訳がわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamitsu&apos;s official rank was Shoshichiinoge (Senior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade), the Ten (an official rank of provincial government) of Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>Masmitsu&apos;sにスペルミスがあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamitsu&apos;s official rank was Shoshichiinoge (Senior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade), the Ten (an official rank of provincial government) of Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>下野国の国府周辺に広大な所領を有し、下野最大の武士団を率いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masmitsu had a vast territory around Kokufu, Shimotsuke Province and led the largest armed group in Shimotsuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masmitsu had a vast territory around Kokufu, Shimotsuke Province and led the largest armed group in Shimotsuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masmitsu had a vast territory around Kokufu, Shimotsuke Province and led the largest armed group in Shimotsuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>治承4年（1180年）8月の源頼朝挙兵の際、政光と嫡子朝政は大番役として在京していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoritomo raised in August, 1180, Masahitsu and heir and son, Tomomasa, stayed in Kyoto as Obanyaku (guards in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoritomo raised an army in August 1180, Masamitsu and his son, Tomomasa were in Kyoto as Obanyaku (a job to guard Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Masahitsuがスペルミスです。「挙兵」、「政光と嫡子朝政」の訳が原文と異なります。Augustの後のコンマを除き、大番役の説明を単語調査に従い書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoritomo raised an army in August 1180, Masamitsu and his son, Tomomasa were in Kyoto as Obanyaku (a job to guard Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>が、頼朝の乳母であった後妻の寒河尼が元服前の朝光を伴って10月に房総で再起した頼朝の宿所を訪ねている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masahitsu&apos;s second wife, SAMUKAWA no Ama, accomanied with Tomomitsu, who hadn&apos;t reached the manhood yet, visited Yoritomo when he raised an army again in October, in Boso; SAMUKAWA no Ama was Yoritomo&apos;s Menoto in his childhood.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Masamitsu&apos;s wife SAMUKAWA no Ama, who had once been a Menoto of Yoritomo, visited Yoritomo&apos;s lodging with her son Tomomitsu who had not yet reached the manhood, when Yoritomo raised an army again in Boso in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt>「宿所」が訳漏れです。全体にわかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Masamitsu&apos;s wife SAMUKAWA no Ama, who had once been a Menoto of Yoritomo, visited Yoritomo&apos;s lodging with her son Tomomitsu who had not yet reached the manhood, when Yoritomo raised an army again in Boso in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>夫の不在中は妻が権限を持つのが慣習であり、これによって在地にあった小山氏の武士団は頼朝方に立つ事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was customary that while the leader of an armed group was away, his wife was in charge of them; SAMUKAWA no Ama&apos;s visit led to the Oyama group waiting on Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAMUKAWA no Ama&apos;s visit to Yoritomo led the armed groups belonging to the Oyama clan holding the fort to take Yoritomo&apos;s side because of the custom in those days: while the family head is away, his wife is authorized to handle all affairs of the clan.</e>
<cmt>全体的にわかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAMUKAWA no Ama&apos;s visit to Yoritomo led the armed groups belonging to the Oyama clan holding the fort to take Yoritomo&apos;s side because of the custom in those days: while the family head is away, his wife is authorized to handle all affairs of the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>以降、息子達と共に頼朝の御家人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, Masahitsu and his sons became Yoritomo&apos;s Gokenin (shogunal retainers of the Kamakura bakufu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, Masamitsu and his sons became Yoritomo&apos;s Gokenin (shogunal retainers of the Kamakura bakufu).</e>
<cmt>Masahitsuがスペルミスです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, Masamitsu and his sons became Yoritomo&apos;s Gokenin (shogunal retainers of the Kamakura bakufu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>文治5年（1189年）7月の奥州合戦で奥州へ向かう道中、下野の宿舎で政光が頼朝の接待をしていた時、頼朝の前に熊谷直実の子熊谷直家が祗候していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo and his vassal were on their way to Oshu, due to the battle of Oshu, in July 1189; when Masamitsu was working for Yoritomo, Naoie KUMAGAI, Naozane KUMAGAI&apos;s son, was sitting in front of Yoritomo as if he were Yoritomo&apos;s guest.</e>
<cmt>「祗候していた」の意味合いを確認仕切れていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masamitsu entertained Yoritomo who was on his way to Oshu for joining the Battle of Oshu broke out in July 1189 at the lodging in Shimotsuke Province, the Naozane KUMAGAI&apos;s son, Naoie KUMAGAI came to pay a visit to Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>全体的にわかりづらいので書き換えました。「下野の宿舎で」が訳漏れでしたので訳を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masamitsu entertained Yoritomo who was on his way to Oshu for joining the Battle of Oshu broke out in July 1189 at the lodging in Shimotsuke Province, the Naozane KUMAGAI&apos;s son, Naoie KUMAGAI came to pay a visit to Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>政光が何者か訪ねると、頼朝は「この者は本朝無双の勇士の熊谷小次郎直家である」と紹介した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masamitsu asked Yoritomo who that person was, Yoritomo introduced Naoie to Masamitsu as &apos;Naoie KUMAGAI, an incomparable warrior.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reply to the Masamitsu&apos;s question about the person, Yoritomo introduced Naoie by saying &apos;He is Kojiro Naoie KUMAGAI, the bravest warrior in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「本朝無双の勇士」の訳が原文と異なります。全体的にわかりづらいので書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reply to the Masamitsu&apos;s question about the person, Yoritomo introduced Naoie by saying &apos;He is Kojiro Naoie KUMAGAI, the bravest warrior in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>政光が何故無双と称するのか問うと、「一ノ谷の戦いをはじめとする平氏追討の戦場で父と共に度々命がけで戦ったからである」と褒めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Masamitsu asked Yoritomo why Naoie was called an incomparable warrior, Yoritomo praised Naoie, saying &apos;Naoie, together with his father, fought for life at the battles to kill the Heike clan, including the Battle of Ichinotani&apos;; Masamitsu laughed to hear that remark and said, &apos;Naoie is not the only warrior who fought and will fight for life for the sake of you (Yoritomo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Masamitsu asked Yoritomo the reason why Yoritomo called Naoie the bravest warrior, Yoritomo praised Naoie saying &apos;Because Naoie and his father desperately fought a series of battles to defeat the Heike clan, including the Battle of Ichinotani.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。わかりづらい箇所を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Masamitsu asked Yoritomo the reason why Yoritomo called Naoie the bravest warrior, Yoritomo praised Naoie saying &apos;Because Naoie and his father desperately fought a series of battles to defeat the Heike clan, including the Battle of Ichinotani.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>政光は大いに笑って「君（頼朝）のために命を捨てるのは、直家に限った事ではありません。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamitsu burst into a laugh at Yoritomo&apos;s remark and said, &apos;Naoie is not the only warrior to fight for our master (Yoritomo) at the cost of our own lives.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。わかりづらい箇所を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamitsu burst into a laugh at Yoritomo&apos;s remark and said, &apos;Naoie is not the only warrior to fight for our master (Yoritomo) at the cost of our own lives.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>「だたしこのような者はろくに郎党を持てないために自分で勲功をあげ、高名手柄にするしかないのでしょう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since such a fellow cannot have his own army, all he can do is distinguish himself and gain fame.</e>
<cmt>B欄の始まりが「だたし」が「ただし」だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since such a fellow like Naoie cannot afford to employ enough retainers of his own, there is nothing he can do but render distinguish services by himself and gain fame.</e>
<cmt>「ろくに郎党を」の原文の意味合いが足りないと思います。&quot;all he can do is distinguish himself and gain fame&quot;は文法上間違いがあると考え書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since such a fellow like Naoie cannot afford to employ enough retainers of his own, there is nothing he can do but render distinguish services by himself and gain fame.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>政光のごときは、だた郎党を派遣して忠を尽くすだけです。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All I can do is to be faithful by leading my army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to such a fellow, the likes of Masamitsu with lots of excellent retainers can show our devotion to our master only by dispatching part of retainers.&apos;</e>
<cmt>訳文と原文の意味が異なります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to such a fellow, the likes of Masamitsu with lots of excellent retainers can show our devotion to our master only by dispatching part of retainers.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>息子たちに「皆の者、今度の戦では先頭に進んで自分自身で手柄を立てて、本朝無双の勇士と褒めていただこうではないか。」と命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Everyone, let&apos;s push your way to the front of the line, win fame on the next battlefield to be praised as incomparable warriors.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, he sarcastically ordered his sons, &apos;Everyone, let&apos;s spearhead the next battle and render distinguish services by ourselves, otherwise we would not be praised as the bravest warriors in Japan by our master.&apos;</e>
<cmt>下のセルより移動し一文としました。わかりづらい箇所を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, he sarcastically ordered his sons, &apos;Everyone, let&apos;s spearhead the next battle and render distinguish services by ourselves, otherwise we would not be praised as the bravest warriors in Japan by our master.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>これは家人の高名がそのまま自己の戦功となる大領主の「大名」武士と、自身で戦功を立てるしかない「小名」武士の違いを示す例として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This episode is known as an example that shows the difference between &apos;Daimyo&apos; warrior and &apos;Shomyo&apos; warrior; &apos;Daimyo&apos; warrior, a feudal overlord, could gain fame when his vassal won fame while &apos;Shomyo&apos; warrior had to win fame by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This episode is known as an example showing the difference between &apos;Daimyo&apos; warrior and &apos;Shomyo&apos; warrior; the former, a feudal overlord, was allowed to regard his retainers&apos; fame as his feats, while the latter had to win fame by himself.</e>
<cmt>わかりづらい箇所を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This episode is known as an example showing the difference between &apos;Daimyo&apos; warrior and &apos;Shomyo&apos; warrior; the former, a feudal overlord, was allowed to regard his retainers&apos; fame as his feats, while the latter had to win fame by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>没年は不明だが、正治元年（1199年）以前に死去している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of his death is unknown but it is certain that he passed away before 1199.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year of his death is unknown, but it is certain that he passed away before 1199.</e>
<cmt>&quot;but&quot;の前にコンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year of his death is unknown, but it is certain that he passed away before 1199.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ちちぶ(id:184715), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>