<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>畠山義就</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro/Yoshinari HATAKEYAMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro HATAKEYAMA (his name can also be read as Yoshinari)</e>
<cmt>&quot;/Yoshinari&quot;→&quot;(his name can also be read as Yoshinari)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro HATAKEYAMA (his name can also be read as Yoshinari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>畠山 義就（はたけやま よしひろ（よしなり）、永享9年（1437年）？ - 延徳2年12月12日 (旧暦)（1491年1月21日））は、室町時代の武将である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro Hatakeyama (1437-January 21,1491) is a general of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro Hatakeyama (1437-January 21,1491) was a general of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro Hatakeyama (1437 - January 30, 1491) was a general of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足 グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>足利氏(足利将軍家)の一門にて室町幕府の三管領家のひとつである畠山氏出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He belonged to the Ashikaga family (Ashikaga Shogunate House) from the Hatakeyama family, one of the three Kanrei families, the shogunal deputies of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He belonged to the Hatakeyama Clan, a branch of the Ashikaga Clan (Ashikaga Shogunate House) and one of the three Kanrei families, the shogunal deputies of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&quot;family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;Added &quot;a branch of&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He belonged to the Hatakeyama clan, a branch of the Ashikaga clan (Ashikaga Shogunate House) and one of the three Kanrei families, the shogunal deputies of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>管領畠山持国の子で、母は側室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA, his mother was a concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA, his mother was a concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of Mochikuni HATAKEYAMA, his mother was a concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初名は義夏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first he was given the name Yosinatsu/Yoshika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first he was given the name Yosinatsu, which can also be read as Yoshika.</e>
<cmt>&quot;/Yoshika&quot;→&quot;which can also be read as Yoshika&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first he was given the name Yosinatsu, which can also be read as Yoshika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に畠山義豊がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a son, Yoshitoyo HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a son, Yoshitoyo HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a son, Yoshitoyo HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>畠山家の家督は養子に迎えた畠山持富（持国の弟）に決まっていたが、義就が出生すると48年に持富への相続を撤回し、室町幕府8代将軍の足利義政から裁可を得て義就が新たに後継者と定められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reigns of the HATAKEYAMA family were supposed to be given to Mochitoyo HATAKEYAMA (the younger brother of Mochikuni), who was his foster child, but when Yoshihiro/Yoshinari was born,the succession of Mochitoyo was withdrawn in the year 48, and Yoshihiro/Yoshinari was designated the new successor after earning the official approval of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the 8th Shogun of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reins of the HATAKEYAMA family were supposed to be given to Mochitoyo HATAKEYAMA (the younger brother of Mochikuni), who had been adopted into the family, but after Yoshihiro was born, Mochitoyo&apos;s succession was withdrawn in 1448 and Yoshihiro was designated the new successor after earning the official approval of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the 8th Shogun of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Spelling of &quot;reins&quot;&quot;his foster child&quot;→&quot;had been adopted into the family&quot;&quot;when&quot;→&quot;after&quot;Deleted &quot;/Yoshinari&quot;&quot;the succession of Mochitoyo&quot;→&quot;Mochitoyo&apos;s succession&quot;&quot;the year 48,&quot;→&quot;1448&quot;Deleted &quot;/Yoshinari&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reins of the HATAKEYAMA family were supposed to be given to Mochitoyo HATAKEYAMA (the younger brother of Mochikuni), who had been adopted into the family, but after Yoshihiro was born, Mochitoyo&apos;s succession was withdrawn in 1448 and Yoshihiro was designated the new successor after earning the official approval of Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the 8th Shogun of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>義就への相続には、守護代の神保氏や被官らが反対し、持富の子である畠山弥三郎を支持して抵抗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jimbo familiy, the Shugo-dai (Deputy Military Governor), and other vassals were opposed to the succession of Yoshihiro, and resisted by supporting Yasaburo HATAKEYAMA, the son of Mochitoyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jimbo Clan, who held the Shugo-dai (Deputy Military Governor) position, and other vassals were opposed to the succession of Yoshihiro, and resisted by supporting Yasaburo HATAKEYAMA, the son of Mochitoyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;Added &quot;who held&quot; and &quot;position&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jimbo clan, who held the Shugo-dai (Deputy Military Governor) position, and other vassals were opposed to the succession of Yoshihiro, and resisted by supporting Yasaburo HATAKEYAMA, the son of Mochitoyo.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1454年には弥三郎を没落させるが、細川氏や大和の国人である筒井氏らの支持を得て、義政から赦免された弥三郎は9月に再び上洛、義就は伊賀へ没落する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1454 Yoshihiro managed to defeat Yasaburo, but Yasaburo gaining the support of the Hosokawa family and the Tsutsui family, local bushi of the Province of Yamato, was pardonned by Yoshimasa and returned to Kyoto in September while Yoshihiro fled to Iga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1454 Yoshihiro managed to defeat Yasaburo, but Yasaburo, supported the Tsutsui Clan, local bushi from the Province of Yamato, and the Hosokawa Clan, was pardonned by Yoshimasa and returned to Kyoto in September while Yoshihiro fled to Iga.</e>
<cmt>&quot;family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;&quot;gaining the support of&quot;→&quot;, supported by&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;from&quot;Changed word order - original translation sounded like both clans were from Yamato</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1454 Yoshihiro managed to defeat Yasaburo, but Yasaburo, supported the Tsutsui clan, local bushi from the Province of Yamato, and the Hosokawa clan, was pardoned by Yoshimasa and returned to Kyoto in September while Yoshihiro fled to Iga.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clanスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>義就は12月に再び河内から上洛して弥三郎を追い、55年父の持国が死去すると３月には家督を継承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro returned to Kyoto in December from Kawachi and pursued Yasaburo and succeeded the reigns of the Hatakeyama family after the death of his father Mochikuni in 1455.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, Yoshihiro returned from Kawachi to Kyoto in pursuit of Yasaburo and, following the death of his father Mochikuni in 1455, took over as head of the Hatakeyama family.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;in December&quot; and &quot;from Kawachi&quot;&quot;and pursued&quot;→&quot;in pursuit of&quot;Moved &quot;after the death of his father Mochikuni in 1455&quot;&quot;after&quot;→&quot;following&quot;&quot;succeeded the reins&quot;→&quot;took over as head&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Yoshihiro returned from Kawachi to Kyoto in pursuit of Yasaburo and, following the death of his father Mochikuni in 1455, took over as head of the Hatakeyama family.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>59年に弥三郎が病死すると、弟の畠山政長が擁立され、引き続き義就と対立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1459 Yasaburo died from an illness, and his younger brother Masanaga HATAKEYAMA was put forward as a contender and continued the dispute with Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1459 Yasaburo died from illness, and his younger brother, Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, was put forward as a successor, continuing the dispute with Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;an&quot;&quot;contender and continued&quot;→&quot;successor, continuing&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1459 Yasaburo died from illness, and his younger brother, Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, was put forward as a successor, continuing the dispute with Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>60年9月には河内へ没落して、政長が家督を継承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1460, he fled to Kawachi and Masanaga succeed the reigns of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1460, Yoshihiro fled to Kawachi and Masanaga became head of the family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he&quot;→&quot;Yoshihiro&quot;&quot;succeed the reigns&quot;→&quot;became head&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1460, Yoshihiro fled to Kawachi and Masanaga became head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>義就には討伐の綸旨が下り、朝敵となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro was given the Imperial Order of subjugation and was designated the Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro was ordered subjugated by the Emperor and was designated the Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>&quot;given the Imperial Order of subjugation&quot;→&quot;ordered subjugated by the Emperor&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro was ordered subjugated by the Emperor and was designated the Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>義就は嶽山城(大阪府富田林市)に篭城し、討伐に下った畠山、細川、武田らの兵と戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro was besieged at Gakusanjo Castle (Tondabayashi City, Osaka Prefecture) and fought the armies of Hatakeyama, Hosokawa and Takeda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro was besieged at Gakusanjo Castle (Tondabayashi City, Osaka Prefecture) and fought the armies of the Hatakeyama, Hosokawa and Takeda.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro was besieged at Gakusan-jo Castle (Tondabayashi City, Osaka Prefecture) and fought the armies of the Hatakeyama, Hosokawa and Takeda.</e>
<cmt>Gakusanjo Castle→Gakusan-jo Castle</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>63年には嶽山城は陥落し、紀州から吉野へ逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1463, Gakusanjo Castle fell and Yoshihiro fled from Kishu to Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1463, Gakusanjo Castle fell and Yoshihiro fled from Kishu to Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1463, Gakusan-jo Castle fell and Yoshihiro fled from Kishu to Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>Gakusanjo Castle→Gakusan-jo Castle</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>義就は細川勝元と対抗する山名宗全(持豊)の支持を得て、66年12月には赦免されて河内から上洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro gained support from Sozen Yamana (Mochitoyo) who was opposed to Katsumoto Hosokawa, and returned to Kyoto from Kawachi, and was pardoned in December 1466.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro gained support from Sozen Yamana (Mochitoyo) who was fighting against Katsumoto Hosokawa, returned to Kyoto from Kawachi, and was pardoned in December 1466.</e>
<cmt>&quot;opposed to&quot;→&quot;fighting against&quot;deleted &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro gained support from Sozen YAMANA (Mochitoyo) who was fighting against Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, returned to Kyoto from Kawachi, and was pardoned in December 1466.</e>
<cmt>Yamana→YAMANAHosokawa→HOSOKAWA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>義政との拝謁も果たし、政長に畠山邸の明け渡しを要求させ、管領を辞任させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1467, the following year, he was granted an audience with Yoshimasa and was forced to leave Mochinaga the Hatakeyama residence and was also stripped of the position of Kanrei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was granted an audience with Yoshimasa, who ordered him to hand over the Hatakeyama residence to Mochinaga and stripped him of the position of Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;In 1467, the following year, &quot; - not in Japanese original&quot;and was forced&quot;→&quot;, who ordered him&quot;&quot;leave Mochinaga the Hatakeyama residence&quot;→&quot;, hand over the Hatakeyama residence to Mochinaga&quot;Deleted &quot;was also&quot;Added &quot;him&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was granted an audience with Yoshimasa, who ordered him to hand over the Hatakeyama residence to Mochinaga and stripped him of the position of Kanrei (shogunal deputy).</e>
<cmt>説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>翌67年には上御霊神社において衝突し、山名や斯波氏の協力を得て政長を破る(御霊合戦)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, 1467, they clashed at Kami-Mitama jinjya shrine, and Yoshinari with the help of Yamana and the Shibashi familiy managed to defeat Masanaga (the Battle of Mitama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, 1467, they clashed at Kami-Mitama-jinjya shrine and Yoshihiro, with the help of Yamana and the Shibashi Clan, managed to defeat Masanaga (the Battle of Mitama).</e>
<cmt>&quot;In the next&quot;→&quot;The following&quot;&quot;Yoshinari&quot;→&quot;Yoshihiro&quot; - for consistency&quot;family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;Moved commaAdded comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, 1467, they clashed at Kamigoryo-jinja Shrine and Yoshihiro, with the help of Yamana and the Shibashi clan, managed to defeat Masanaga (the Battle of Goryo).</e>
<cmt>上御霊神社→Kamigoryo-jinja Shrine [http://www.kyototsuu.jp/Jinjya/KamigoryouJinjya.html]Clan→clan御霊合戦→the Battle of Goryo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>御霊合戦により山名方が有利となったことにより、翌年には細川方が巻き返しを図り応仁の乱となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the side of Yamana had gained the upper hand because of the Battlle of Mitama, the Hosokawa side tried to recover its loses in the next year and started the Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the Battle of Mitama, Yamana had gained the upper hand and the following year, the Hosokawa side tried to recover its losses, leading to the start of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the side of&quot;&quot;because of the Battlle of Mitama&quot;→&quot;As a result of the Battle of Mitama&quot; and moved&quot;&quot;in the next year&quot;→&quot;the following year&quot;Spelling of &quot;losses&quot;&quot;and started&quot;→&quot;, leading to the start of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the Battle of Goryo, Yamana had gained the upper hand and the following year, the Hosokawa side tried to recover its losses, leading to the start of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>御霊合戦→the Battle of Goryo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>乱では宗全率いる西軍に属して政長と戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this war Yoshinari fought against Masanaga as part of the Western Forces led by Sozen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the war, Yoshihiro fought against Masanaga as part of the Western Forces led by Sozen.</e>
<cmt>&quot;this&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Added comma&quot;Yoshinari&quot;→&quot;Yoshihiro&quot; - for consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the war, Yoshihiro fought against Masanaga as part of the Western Forces led by Sozen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>77年9月に義就が政長討伐のために河内へ下り、遊佐氏を追い河内を制圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1477 Yoshinari moved into Kawachi in order to defeat Masanaga and brought Kawachi under his control after driving away the Yusa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1477, Yoshihiro moved into Kawachi in order to defeat Masanaga, bringing Kawachi under his control after driving away the Yusa Clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Yoshinari&quot;→&quot;Yoshihiro&quot; - for consistency&quot;and brought&quot;→&quot;, bringing&quot;&quot;family&quot;→&quot;Clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1477, Yoshihiro moved into Kawachi in order to defeat Masanaga, bringing Kawachi under his control after driving away the Yusa clan.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>両軍の間で講和が成立し、西軍諸将が相次いで帰国して解散、82年8月には細川政元と和睦するが、政長との抗争はその後も続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two armies arranged a peace and the Western generals dissolved their armies and returned to their domains, then in August 1482 Yoshinari made peace with Masamoto HOSOKAWA, but the dispute with Masanaga continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the two armies had made peace and the Western generals had dissolved their armies and returned to their domains, in August 1482 Yoshihiro made peace with Masamoto HOSOKAWA but the dispute with Masanaga continued.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;after&quot;&quot;arranged a&quot;→&quot;had made&quot;Added &quot;had&quot;Deleted &quot;then&quot;&quot;Yoshinari&quot;→&quot;Yoshihiro&quot; - for consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the two armies had made peace and the Western generals had dissolved their armies and returned to their domains, in August 1482 Yoshihiro made peace with Masamoto HOSOKAWA but the dispute with Masanaga continued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>主戦場となった山城国で国人らの一揆が起こり（山城国一揆）、撤退を要求される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Province of Yamashiro became the main battlegrounds and an uprising of the local people occurred (Yamashiro no kuniikki), and Yoshinari was asked to withdraw.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Province of Yamashiro, where the main fighting took place, there was an uprising of the local people (Yamashiro no kuniikki), who demanded that both sides withdraw.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;in&quot;&quot;became the main battlegrounds and&quot;→&quot;, where the main fighting took place,&quot;&quot;occurred&quot;→&quot;there was&quot;&quot;and Yoshinari was asked to&quot;→&quot;who demanded that both sides&quot; - I think they wanted both sides, not just Yoshihiro, to leave</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Province of Yamashiro, where the main fighting took place, there was an uprising of the local people (Yamashiro no kuniikki), who demanded that both sides withdraw.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Ittyon(id:1348), Tanuki Z(id:612), Nnh(id:474), YurikBot(id:18605), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Cprobot(id:97843), 海衛士(id:19229), Doskoi 8(id:1070), Shimoxx(id:9332), Ponsaku(id:31417), ずもも(id:40267), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>