<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今井兼平</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanehira IMAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanehira IMAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanehira IMAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>今井 兼平（いまい かねひら、仁平2年（1152年） - 元暦元年1月20日 (旧暦)（1184年3月4日））は平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanehira IMAI (1152-March 4, 1184) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanehira IMAI (1152 - March 4, 1184) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived at the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Added spacesin &gt; who lived at</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanehira IMAI (1152 - March 4, 1184) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived at the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称・四郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Shiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Shiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Shiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>よって今井四郎兼平ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he was also called Shiro Kanehira IMAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he was also called Shiro Kanehira IMAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he was also called Shiro Kanehira IMAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正式な名のりは中原兼平（なかはら の かねひら）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His formal name was NAKAHARA no Kanehira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His formal name was NAKAHARA no Kanehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His formal name was NAKAHARA no Kanehira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父は中原兼遠、兄弟に樋口兼光、巴御前、落合兼行がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was NAKAHARA no Kaneto, and his brothers were Kanemitsu HIGUCHI, Tomoe Gozen and Kaneyuki OCHIAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was NAKAHARA no Kaneto, and his brothers were Kanemitsu HIGUCHI, Tomoe Gozen and Kaneyuki OCHIAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was NAKAHARA no Kaneto, and his brothers were Kanemitsu HIGUCHI, Tomoe Gozen and Kaneyuki OCHIAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>義仲四天王の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of Yoshinaka Shitenno (four most loyal retainers of Yoshinaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the Yoshinaka Shitenno (four most loyal retainers of Yoshinaka).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the Yoshinaka Shitenno (four most loyal retainers of Yoshinaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>源義仲とは乳兄弟でもあり、最後まで義仲と共に戦い、『平家物語』の「木曾殿最期」の段の義仲と兼平の最期は、悲壮美に満ちている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka was a foster brother, he fought with him till the last, and the death of Yoshinaka and Kanehira at the stage of &apos;The Death of Kiso&apos; of &quot;Heike Monogatari (The tale of the Heike)&quot; was full of tragic beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanehira IMAI fought alongside his foster brother MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka until the last, and the death of Yoshinaka and Kanehira in the &apos;Death of Kiso&apos; section of &quot;Heike Monogatari (The tale of the Heike)&quot; is full of tragic beauty.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation.Completely retranslated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanehira IMAI fought alongside his foster brother MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka until the end, and the death of Yoshinaka and Kanehira in the &apos;Death of Kiso&apos; section of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike) is full of tragic beauty.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、この場面の兼平の矛盾した言い方や、「弓矢取りは、年頃日頃如何なる高名候へども、最後に不覚しぬれば、永き瑕（きず）にて候なり。」の武士たる心構えを伝える言に、その情況に応じての、兼平の義仲への苦しいいたわりの気持ち、美しい主従の絆が書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The contradictory words of Kanehira on this occasion and his bushi&apos;s attitude that &apos;a warrior faced disgrace for a long time if he made a mistake at the last even if he had been very famous before.&apos; shows sympathy of Kanehira to Yoshinaka in such situations and beautiful relationship between master and servant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The contradictory words of Kanehira on this occasion and his bushi&apos;s attitude that &apos;a warrior faced disgrace for a long time if he made a mistake at the last even if he had been very famous before.&apos; shows sympathy of Kanehira to Yoshinaka in such situations and beautiful relationship between master and servant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The way Kanehira contradicts himself in this scene and the samurai spirit he expresses when he says, &apos;If a warrior&apos;s last moments lack grace, he disgraces himself for a long time even if he was very prominent when alive&apos; demonstrate the painful sympathy Kanehira had for Yoshinaka in the situation he faced, as well as the beautifully strong relationship that existed between master and servant.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣのコメントを受けて書き直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>「日頃は何とも覚えぬ鎧が、今日は重うなったるぞや」と言う義仲に対し、次のように述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshinaka said &apos;my armor is heavy today, though I do not feel so at ordinary times&apos;, Kanehira said &apos;You feel so because you have lost your vigor and has grown timid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshinaka said &apos;my armor is heavy today, although it does not ordinarily feel so&apos;, Kanehira said &apos;You feel so because you have lost your vigor and have grown timid.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshinaka said &apos;my armor is heavy today, although it does not ordinarily feel so,&apos; Kanehira said as follows:</e>
<cmt>カンマ位置移動括弧内は原文、訳文ともに別にしました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「それは御方（みかた）に続く勢が候はねば、臆病でこそさは思し召し候らめ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You feel so because you have lost your vigor and have grown timid.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」で囲みました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「兼平一騎をば、余の武者千騎と思し召し候べし。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You should think that one horseman of Kanehira was a match for a thousand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You should think that one horseman of Kanehira was a match for a thousand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You should think that one horseman of Kanehira was a match for a thousand.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「ここに射残したる矢七つ八つ候へば、暫く防矢（ふせぎや）仕り候はん。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you have seven or right arrows, you can protect yourself against the enemy for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you have seven or eight arrows, you can protect yourself against the enemy for a while.</e>
<cmt>right &gt; eightFixed double space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you have seven or eight arrows, you can protect yourself against the enemy for a while.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「あれに見え候は、粟津の松原と申し候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You can see a pine grove of Matsubara over there.&apos;</e>
<cmt>粟津の松原は a pine grove of Matsubaraとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You can see a pine grove of Matsubara over there.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You can see a pine grove of Matsubara over there.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」で囲みました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「君はあの松の中へ入らせ給ひて、静に御自害候へ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go to the pine grove and kill yourself quietly&quot;. When Yoshinaka said &apos;I want to be killed at once rather than being defeated in several places&apos;, Kanehira said that &apos;a warrior faced disgrace for a long time if he made a mistake at the last even if he had been very famous before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go to the pine grove and kill yourself quietly&quot;. When Yoshinaka said &apos;I want to be killed at once rather than being defeated in several places&apos;, Kanehira said that &apos;a warrior faced disgrace for a long time if he made a mistake at the last even if he had been very famous before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Go to the pine grove and kill yourself quietly.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」で囲みました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>義仲が「所々で討たれんより、一所でこそ討死もせめ」と言うと、次のように述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshinaka said &apos;I want to be killed at once rather than being defeated in several places,&apos; Kanehira said as follows:</e>
<cmt>括弧内は原文、訳文ともに別にしました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「弓矢取りは、年頃日頃如何なる高名候へども、最後に不覚しぬれば、永き瑕（きず）にて候なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a warrior&apos;s last moments lack grace, he disgraces himself for a long time even if he was very prominent when alive&apos;</e>
<cmt>ＮＣのコメントを受けて書き直しました一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>「御身も労（つか）れさせ給ひ候ひぬ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You were very exhausted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You were very exhausted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You were very exhausted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「御馬も弱って候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Your horse also grew weak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Your horse also grew weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Your horse also grew weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>「云ふ甲斐なき人の郎等に組み落とされて、討たれさせ給ひ候ひなば、さしも日本国に鬼神と聞こえさせ給ひつる木曾殿をば、某が郎等の手に懸けて、討ち奉ったりなんぞ申されん事、口惜しかるべし。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you were defeated and killed by a nameless man and it was told that one of someone&apos;s retainers killed Kiso who was famous as a fierce god in Japan, it was very regrettable. Change your mind and go to the pine grove&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It would be regrettable if you were defeated and killed by a nameless man and it became told that Kiso, who was renowned throughout Japan as a fierce god, was killed a mere retainer, so I urge you change your mind and go to the pine grove&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Poor translation whih was in two senteces.Completely retranslated and addressed sentence issue.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It would be regrettable if you were defeated and killed by a nameless man and it became told that Kiso, who was renowned throughout Japan as a fierce god, was killed a mere retainer.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動「」内は一文ずつ分けました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「唯理を枉げて、あの松の中に入らせ給へ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So I urge you change your mind and go to the pine grove.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」で囲みました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>義仲が討たれると、次のように言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshinaka committed suicide, Kanehira said &apos;Then I must protect the army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshinaka committed suicide, Kanehira said &apos;Then I must protect the army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshinaka committed suicide, Kanehira said as follows:</e>
<cmt>「」内は別に分けました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>「今は誰をかかばはんとて、軍をばすべき。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then I must protect the army.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」内は別に分けました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>「これ見給へ、東国の殿ばら、日本一の剛の者の自害する手本よ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Look, my lord of the eastern provinces. This was a model of suicide of the Japan&apos;s strongest warrior&apos; and he put the tip of his sword into his mouth, jumped off his horse and killed himself with the sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Look, my lord of the eastern provinces, this was a model suicide by Japan&apos;s strongest warrior&apos; and he put the tip of his sword into his mouth, jumped off his horse and killed himself with the sword.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Look, my lord of the eastern provinces, this is a model suicide by Japan&apos;s strongest warrior.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」で囲みました。Was→is一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そして太刀の先を口の中に含み、馬上から飛び降り、太刀に貫かれ自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he put the tip of his sword into his mouth, jumped off his horse and killed himself with the sword.</e>
<cmt>「」内は別に分けました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>（現代語簡訳：戦前は義仲に「武士らしく強気になれ」と助言をし、戦中は死を共にしようとする義仲に「疲れているのだから潔く自害しなさい」と冷静にアドバイスをし、義仲が自害する時間稼ぎをした。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Brief translation in modern language: It was said before the last war that Kanehira told Yoshinaka that he should raise your spirits like a warrior&apos; and when Yoshinaka tried to die together in a battle, Kanehira advised him calmly that he should commit suicide bravely because he were exhausted&apos; to give him time to kill himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Brief translation in modern language: It was said before the last war that Kanehira told Yoshinaka that he should raise your spirits like a warrior&apos; and when Yoshinaka tried to die together in a battle, Kanehira advised him calmly that he should commit suicide bravely because he were exhausted&apos; to give him time to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Brief translation in modern Japanese: Before the battle, Kanehira advised Yoshinaka to &apos;raise his spirits like a warrior,&apos; but when Yoshinaka tried to continue fighting in the battle until his death, Kanehira calmly advised him that he should commit suicide bravely because he was too exhausted to fight any further, and gave Yoshinaka enough time to kill himself.)</e>
<cmt>ＮＣのコメントを受けて書き直しました一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>(義仲が討ち取られたと知った直後、「東国の方々、これが日本一の強者の自害する手本だ」と言った。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kanehira knew that Yoshinaka killed himself, he said &apos;Everybody in Kanto provinces, this is a model of suicide of the strongest man in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kanehira knew that Yoshinaka had killed himself, he said &apos;Everybody of the Kanto provinces, this is a model of suicide by the strongest man in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(When Kanehira found out that Yoshinaka had committed suicide, he said &apos;People of the Kanto provinces, this was a model suicide by the strongest man in Japan&apos;.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>伝承墓所：長野市川中島に兼平塚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditional tomb: Kanehira&apos;s tumulus in Kawanakajima, Nagano City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reputed burial place: Kanehira&apos;s tumulus in Kawanakajima, Nagano City</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to reflect source text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reputed burial place: Kanehira&apos;s tumulus in Kawanakajima, Nagano City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、滋賀県大津市晴嵐にも墓所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another tomb in Seiran, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a tomb in Seiran, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a tomb in Seiran, Otsu City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>奉斎神社：長野市川中島鎮座の今井神社や松本市今井 (松本市)鎮座の今井神社の主祭神として祀る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosai Shrine: He was enshrined as a chief god in Imai Shrine in Kawanakajima, Nagano City, and in Imai Shrine in Imai, Matsumoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosai Shrine: He was enshrined as a chief god in Imai Shrine in Kawanakajima, Nagano City, and in Imai Shrine in Imai, Matsumoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosai Shrine: He was enshrined as a chief god in Imai Shrine in Kawanakajima, Nagano City, and in Imai-jinja Shrine in Imai, Matsumoto City.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また群馬県渋川市北橘町の木曾三社神社などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also enshrined in Kisosansha Shrine, in Kitatachibanamachi, Shibukawa City, Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also enshrined in Kisosansha Shrine, in Kitatachibanamachi, Shibukawa City, Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also enshrined in Kisosansha-jinja Shrine, in Kitatachibana-machi, Shibukawa City, Gunma Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 赤井彗星(id:18381), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), Nnh(id:474), しるふぃ(id:11247), 由布(id:209183), 深志(id:34508), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), Tiyoringo(id:70026), 味っ子(id:17086), BAKU(id:55205), Cpro(id:28341), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>