<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>渋谷実</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minoru SHIBUYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minoru SHIBUYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minoru SHIBUYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>渋谷実（しぶやみのる、1907年1月2日 - 1980年12月20日）は、日本の映画監督である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minoru SHIBUYA (January 2, 1907 ~ December 20, 1980) is a Japanese movie director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minoru SHIBUYA (January 2, 1907 ~ December 20, 1980) was a Japanese movie director.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minoru SHIBUYA (January 2, 1907 - December 20, 1980) was a Japanese movie director.</e>
<cmt>~→-　他のトピックと合わせる。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>東京浅草区七軒町（現・台東区元浅草）に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born at Shichiken-cho, Asakusa-ku Ward (today&apos;s Motoasakusa, Taito-ku Ward), Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Shichiken-cho, Asakusa-ku Ward (today&apos;s Motoasakusa, Taito-ku Ward), Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Shichiken-cho, Asakusa Ward (today&apos;s Motoasakusa, Taito Ward), Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>-ku削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>慶應義塾大学文学部英語英文学科に入学するが、胸を病み療養生活を送る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Keio University, Faculty of Letters, Dept. of English and American Literature, however, he suffered from a disease of the chest and spent the days at hospital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered Keio University, Faculty of Letters, Dept. of English and American Literature, however, he suffered from a disease of the chest and spent days in the hospital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the Keio University Faculty of Letters Department of English Literature but developed a chest disease and spent time recuperating.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>回復後、松竹蒲田撮影所に出入りし、牛原虚彦監督の見習い助手を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his recuperation, he often visited Shochiku Kamata Studio, and became an apprentice of the director Kiyohiko USHIHARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After recuperating, he often visited Shochiku Kamata Studio, and became an apprentice of the director Kiyohiko USHIHARA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After recuperating, he often visited Shochiku Kamata Studio, and became an apprentice of the director Kiyohiko USHIHARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>1930年、松竹に助監督として正式入社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1930, he entered Shochiku Co., Ltd. officially as an assistant director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1930, he entered Shochiku Co., Ltd. officially as an assistant director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1930, he officially joined Shochiku Co., Ltd. as an assistant director.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>成瀬巳喜男、五所平之助両監督につく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked and practiced under both directors Mikio NARUSE and Heinosuke GOSHO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked and practiced under both directors Mikio NARUSE and Heinosuke GOSHO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked and practiced under both directors Mikio NARUSE and Heinosuke GOSHO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1937年、小津安二郎監督の『淑女は何を忘れたか』の助監督を務めた後、『奥様に知らすべからず』で監督デビュー。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1937, he worked as an assistant director of the film &quot;What Did the Lady Forget?&quot; of the director, Yasujiro OZU, and debuted as a director with the film &quot;Okusama ni Shirasu Bekarazu (Madame Shall Not Know).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1937, he worked as an assistant director of the film &quot;What Did the Lady Forget?&quot; directed by Yasujiro OZU, and debuted as a director with the film &quot;Okusama ni Shirasu Bekarazu&quot; (Madame Shall Not Know).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1937, he worked as an assistant director of the film &quot;What Did the Lady Forget?&quot; directed by Yasujiro OZU, and debuted as a director with the film &quot;Okusama ni Shirasu Bekarazu&quot; (Madame Shall Not Know).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>松竹蒲田らしいメロドラマに乾いた笑いを取り込んだ作品を次々と発表し、若手のホープとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a young white hope releasing movies one after another which contain an aspects of soap opera incorporated with cynical laughter typical in Shochiku Kamata Studio films..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a young white hope releasing movies one after another that contained aspects of a soap opera incorporated with cynical laughter typical in Shochiku Kamata Studio films..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a young hopeful, releasing successive Shochicu Kamata style films incorporating aspects of soap opera with a dry humor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>戦後になって、『自由学校』、『本日休診』など戦後風俗をコミカルに描いた作品で喜劇映画の復活を支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, he supported the revival of comedy movies by directing movies depicted the mode of life after the war in a comical way such as &quot;Jiyu Gakko (School of Freedom)&quot; and &quot;Honjitsu Kyushin (No Consultation Today),&quot;etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, he supported the revival of comedy movies by directing movies depicting the mode of life after the war in a comical way such as &quot;Jiyu Gakko&quot; (School of Freedom) and &quot;Honjitsu Kyushin&quot; (No Consultation Today),&quot;etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, he supported the comedy revival with films including &quot;Jiyu Gakko&quot; (lit. &quot;School of Freedom&quot;) and &quot;Honjitsu Kyushin&quot; (No Consultation Today) which were a comedic portrayal of post-war live.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションを補足し補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、『現代人』、『青銅の基督』などの作品では辛辣な社会風刺を盛り込み、存在感を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the works like &quot;Gendaijin (Moderns, The Postwar Japanese)&quot; and &quot;Seido no Kirisuto (Christ in Bronze),&quot; he took in harsh social satire and he showed his presence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In works like &quot;Gendaijin&quot; (Modern Postwar Japanese) and &quot;Seido no Kirisuto&quot; (Christ in Bronze), he took in harsh social satire and he made his presence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In works such as &quot;Gendai-jin&quot; (lit. &quot;Modern People&quot;) and &quot;Seido no Kirisuto&quot; (Christ in Bronze), he incorporated sharp social satire and made his presence felt.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その作風は門下の川島雄三に引き継がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The savor of his works were handed down to his descendant, Yuzo KAWASHIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The savor of his works were handed down to his descendant, Yuzo KAWASHIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His style was handed down to his student Yuzo KAWASHIMA.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>作風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The savor of his works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The savor of his works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Style</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>上述通り、正に松竹蒲田テイストと呼ぶべきエスプリの効いたドラマやシニカルな笑いの演出に優れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned in the above, he was good at direction of drama with esprit which should be called as the Shochiku Kamata Studio-taste and drama with cynical laughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, he was good at directing drama with spirit which should be called the Shochiku Kamata Studio-taste and drama with cynical laughter.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, he excelled when it came to creating what could be called typical Shochiku Kamata films which were cynical comedies incorporating wit.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これはフィルモグラフィーのほぼ全般に亘って言えることで、『勲章』（1954年）や『喜劇 仰げば尊し』（1966年）という松竹以外での作品にも見られる傾向である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above tendency can be said through almost all of his filmography, and it can be found in the works shot out of Shochiku Co., Ltd. such as &quot;Kunsho (Medal)&quot; (1954) and &quot;A comedy, Aogeba totoshi (respecting teachers)&quot; (1966).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above can be said about almost all of his films, and can be found in works shot out of Shochiku Co., Ltd. such as &quot;Kunsho&quot; (Medal) (1954) and &quot;A comedy, Aogeba totoshi&quot; (respecting teachers) (1966).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above can be said of almost all of his films and can also be found in works that he created outside of Shochiku such as &quot;Kunsho&quot; (Medal) (1954) and the comedy &quot;Aogeba Totoshi&quot;(respecting teachers) (1966).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この作風は当時の観客には非常に好評を博し、存命中は小津安二郎、木下惠介に並び称される高い観客動員力を誇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The savor of his works was much loved by the audience at the time and he was admired and had a similar drawing power to the theaters as Ysaujiro OZU and Keisuke KINOSHITA while he was alive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The savor of his works was much loved by the audience at the time and he was admired and had a drawing power to the theaters similar to Ysaujiro OZU and Keisuke KINOSHITA while he was alive.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This style was incredibly popular with audiences at the time and during his life, his ability to attract audiences was comparable to Yasujiro OZU and Keisuke KINOSHITA.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>小津が『秋刀魚の味』の次回作として温めていた企画『大根と人参』を監督するに至ったのも、そうした人気と実力を評価された故である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why he directed &quot;Daikon to Ninjin (Mr. Radish and Mr. Carrot)&quot; which was planed by director Ozu as the next project of &quot;Sanma no Aji (An Autumn Afternoon)&quot; is that his popularity and ability was appreciated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why he directed &quot;Daikon to Ninjin (Mr. Radish and Mr. Carrot)&quot; which was planed by director Ozu as the next project of &quot;Sanma no Aji&quot; (An Autumn Afternoon) is that his popularity and ability was appreciated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came to direct &quot;Daikon to Ninjin&quot; (Radishes and Carrots), which was originally planned by director Ozu as a project to follow &quot;Sanma no Aji&quot; (An Autumn Afternoon), due to an appreciation for his popularity and ability.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>また一方では『てんやわんや』で淡島千景を映画界に送り出したり、笠智衆を1962年の『酔っぱらい天国』などで小津、木下作品や「男はつらいよ」シリーズとは一線を画す役柄を演じさせたり、と俳優の潜在的な能力を引き出す手腕にも長けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, as he let Chikage AWASHIMA debut in the cinema world with the film &quot;Tenya Wanya (Crazy Uproar)&quot; and had Chishu RYU played a different character in the film &quot;Yopparai Tengoku (Heaven For A Drunkard)&quot; of 1962 from those characters of the works of Ozu and Kinoshita and of series of &quot;Otoko Wa Tsurai Yo (It&apos;s Tough Being a Man)&quot;, he had an ability to bring out the talent and potentials of actors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, as he let Chikage AWASHIMA debut in the cinema world with the film &quot;Tenya Wanya&quot; (Crazy Uproar) and had Chishu RYU played a different character in the film &quot;Yopparai Tengoku&quot; (Heaven For A Drunkard) of 1962, from those characters of the works of Ozu and Kinoshita and the series of &quot;Otoko Wa Tsurai Yo&quot; (It&apos;s Tough Being a Man), we can see that he had the ability to bring out the talent and potentials of actors.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, he launched Chikage AWASHIMA into the film industry with &quot;Tenya Wanya&quot; (Crazy Uproar) and had Chishu RYU play a completely different character in the 1962 film &quot;Yopparai Tengoku&quot; (lit. &quot;Heaven for the Drunk&quot;) from those characters in the works of Ozu and Kinoshita and the &apos;Otoko Wa Tsurai Yo&apos; (It&apos;s Tough Being a Man) series, indicating his ability to bring out the latent abilities of actors.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>池部良も、『現代人』（1952年）を通じて演技に開眼したと語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryo IKEBE also said he realized what an acting should be through the film &quot;Gendaijin&quot; (1952.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryo IKEBE also said he realized what acting should be like through the film &quot;Gendaijin&quot; (1952)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryo IKEBE said that his eyes were opened to acting by the film &quot;Gendai-jin&quot; (Postwar Japanese) (1952).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、『気違い部落』（1957年）はそのタイトルが主な原因となって、所謂封印作品となっている（ただしレトロスペクティヴなどで劇場上映される事はある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the film &quot;Kichigai Buraku (The Unbalanced Wheel) (1957) becomes a so-called Fuin sakuhin (banned and sealed work which should be avoided to put on the screen) mainly due to the title (literally, &quot;crackpot community,&quot;) however, it is sometimes put on the screen at the theaters at occasions of retrospectives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the film &quot;Kichigai Buraku&quot; (The Unbalanced Wheel) (1957) becomes a so-called Fuin sakuhin (banned and sealed work which should be prohibited from seen on the screen) mainly due to the title (literally, &quot;crackpot community,&quot;) however, it is sometimes shown at the theaters for the purpose of looking back.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The film &quot;Kichigai Buraku&quot; (The Unbalanced Wheel) (1957) was banned from release mainly due to its title (however, it is shown at theaters for retrospective screenings).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Geyogeyo(id:35444), Scanscan(id:201938), Cprobot(id:97843), 松木完之(id:26818), IwaimBot(id:190695), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>