<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>美田村顕教</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akinori MITAMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akinori MITAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akinori MITAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>美田村 顕教（みたむら あきのり、1850年1月16日（嘉永2年12月4日 (旧暦)） - 1931年（昭和6年）1月10日）は、旧丹波亀岡藩（丹波亀山藩）出身の武術家（天道流第14代）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akinori MITAMURA (January 16, 1850 - January 10, 1931) was a martial artist from the former Kameoka Domain in Tanba Province (Kameyama Domain of Tanba Province) and the fourteenth of the Tendo-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたため補足いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akinori MITAMURA (January 16, 1850 - January 10, 1931) was a martial artist from the former Kameoka Domain in Tanba Province (Kameyama Domain of Tanba Province) and the fourteenth Tendo-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akinori MITAMURA (January 16, 1850 - January 10, 1931) was a martial artist (the 14th head of Tendo school) from the former Kameoka Domain of Tanba Province (Kameyama Domain of Tanba Province).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>現在の天道流薙刀術が盛んとなる基を築いた人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A person who established the basis of today&apos;s popularity of the Tendo-ryu school naginata jutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A person who established the basis of today&apos;s popularity of the Tendo-ryu school naginata jutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A person who established the basis of today&apos;s popularity of naginata jutsu (art of Japanese halberd) of the Tendo school.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は岡之助、雅号は八重垣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Okanosuke, and his Gago (pseudonym) was Yaegaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Okanosuke, and his Gago (pseudonym) was Yaegaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Okanosuke, and his Gago (pseudonym) was Yaegaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1849年（嘉永2年）、丹波亀山藩士・美田村正明の孫として丹波国亀山（現 京都府亀岡市）に生まれ、1858年（安政5年）、藩の天道流剣術師範役・下河原一寧（天道流第12代）に入門する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1849, he was born in Kameyama, Tanba province (today&apos;s Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) as a grandson of Masaaki MITAMURA, who was a feudal retainer of Tanbakameyama, and became a disciple of the twelfth of the Tendo-ryu school, Kazune SHIMOGAWARA, who was a grandmaster of swordplay of the Tendo-ryu school of the domain in 1858.</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたため補足いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1849, he was born in Kameyama, Tanba province (today&apos;s Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) as the grandson of Masaaki MITAMURA, who was a feudal retainer of Tanbakameyama, and became a disciple of the twelfth Tendo-ryu school, Kazune SHIMOGAWARA, who was a grandmaster of swordplay of the Tendo-ryu school of the domain in 1858.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1849, he was born in Kameyama, Tanba Province (today&apos;s Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture) as the grandson of Masaaki MITAMURA, who was a feudal retainer of Kameyama Domain of Tanba Province, and became a disciple of the 12th Tendo school, Kazune SHIMOGAWARA, who was a grandmaster of swordplay of the Tendo school of the domain in 1858.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>翌1859年（安政6年）、11歳で家督を相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1859, he succeeded the family at the age of 11.</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたため補足いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1859, he succeeded the family at the age of eleven.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1859, the following year, he succeeded the family at the age of 11.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1860年（万延元年）より天道流のほかに、日置流大蔵派、大坪新流馬術、空伝流槍術、稲富流も学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1860, he also learned the Okura group of Heki-ryu school, Japanese horse-back archery technique by Otsubo new school, the art of spear by Kuden school, and the Inatomi school, in addition to the Tendo-ryu school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1860, he also learned from the Okura group at the Heki-ryu school, Japanese horse-back archery technique from the Otsubo new school, the art of spearing from the Kuden and the Inatomi schools, in addition to the Tendo-ryu school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1860, he also learned from the Okura group at the Heki school, Japanese horse-back archery technique from the Otsubo new school, the art of spearing from the Kuden and the Inatomi schools, in addition to the Tendo school.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>1863年（文久3年）の天誅組の変に際しては、御所の今出川御門外の警備に出陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Tenchu-gumi incident occurred in 1863, he guarded the outside of the Imadegawa Gomon of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたため補足いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Tenchu-gumi incident occurred in 1863, he guarded the outside of the Imadegawa Gomon of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Tenchu-gumi incident occurred in 1863, he guarded the outside of the Imadegawa Gomon of the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌1864年（元治元年）、藩が西洋式兵制を採用したことにより、西洋式砲術の高島流とオランダ式・イギリス式兵学を学び、1868年（慶応4年）、高島流砲術の免許を授かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, as the Domain employed a Western military style, he learned the Western gunnery of Takashima school and Dutch and British military sciences, and received a license of teaching the gunnery of Takashima school.</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたため補足いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, as the Domain employed a Western military style, he learned Western gunnery at the Takashima school and Dutch and British military sciences, and received a license to teach gunnery from the Takashima school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, the following year, as the Domain employed a Western military style, he learned Western gunnery at the Takashima school and Dutch and British military sciences, and received a license to teach gunnery from the Takashima school in 1868.</e>
<cmt>年号など補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>1871年1月（明治3年12月 (旧暦)）に結婚し、1871年8月（明治4年7月 (旧暦)）の廃藩置県後は、製紙業、材木商などの事業を始めたが事業は成功しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got married in January 1871, and after Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) in August 1871, he started business including paper production business and timber business, but was not successful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He got married in January 1871, and after Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) in August 1871, he started a business that included paper production and timber, but was not successful at it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He got married in January 1871, and after Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) in August 1871, he started a business that included paper production and timber, but was not successful at it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>同時期に写真術を修得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period, he mastered photography.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, he mastered photography.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, he mastered photography.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治維新以後、欧米の文物が流れ込み日本の伝統的な価値が忘れられていく風潮を嘆き、、一般子弟に古典や古武道を教育することを目的として、顕教を含む数人で亀岡（明治2年に亀山から改称）に生徳社を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lamented the tendency after the Meiji Restoration for the introduction of Western products of culture and fading of Japanese traditional values, and some people including Akinori established Seitokusha in Kameoka (the name was changed from Kameyama in 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lamented the tendency after the Meiji Restoration for the introduction of Western products of culture and the fading of Japanese traditional values, and some people including Akinori established Seitokusha in Kameoka (the name was changed from Kameyama in 1869.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lamented the tendency after the Meiji Restoration for the introduction of Western products of culture and the fading of Japanese traditional values, and some people including Akinori established Seitokusha in Kameoka (the name was changed from Kameyama in 1869).</e>
<cmt>かっこを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>顕教は生徳社の剣術教師となり生徳社の武道場・偃修館で剣術を教えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akinori became a swordplay teacher, and instructed swordplay at Enshukan, a martial arts school of Seitokusha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akinori became a sword teacher, and instructed sword fencing at Enshukan, a martial arts school of Seitokusha.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akinori became a sword teacher, and instructed sword fencing at Enshukan, a martial arts school of Seitokusha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>（偃修館は1903年（明治36年）に大日本武徳会南桑支所に統合される）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Enshukan was incorporated into the Minamikuwa (南桑) branch of Dainihon butoku kai.</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたため補足いたしました。　南桑→Minamikuwa [定訳不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Enshukan was incorporated into the Minamikuwa (南桑) branch of Dainihon butoku kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Enshukan was incorporated into the Nanso branch of the Dai Nippon Butoku Kai (Greater Japan Martial Virtue Society) in 1903.)</e>
<cmt>年号など補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>1891年（明治24年）、天道流第13代・下河原一霍より流儀を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1891, he inherited the style from the thirteenth of the Tendo-ryu Ikkaku SHIMOGAWARA.</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたため補足いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1891, he inherited the style from the thirteenth Tendo-ryu Ikkaku SHIMOGAWARA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1891, he inherited the style from the 13th Tendo school Ikkaku SHIMOGAWARA.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>顕教は天道流の諸術の中で薙刀術を得意としたこともあり薙刀術の指導者としての活動が多くなり、、皇族の御前で天道流薙刀術を演武したほか、西洞院子爵家の道場で薙刀術を指導した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Akinori was good at naginata jutsu among all techniques of the Tendo-ryu school, his activity as a naginata teacher increased, and he not only performed the naginata jutsu of the Tendo-ryu school in front of Imperial families but also instructed at a training hall of the House of Viscount Nishinotoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Akinori was good at naginata jutsu among all the techniques of the Tendo-ryu school, his activity as a naginata teacher increased, and he not only performed the naginata jutsu of the Tendo-ryu school in front of the Imperial family, but also instructed at a training hall of the House of Viscount Nishinotoin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Akinori was good at naginata jutsu among all the techniques of the Tendo school, his activity as a naginata teacher increased, and he not only performed the naginata jutsu of the Tendo school in front of the Imperial family, but also instructed at a training hall of the House of Viscount Nishinotoin.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、同志社女学校（現 同志社女子大学）、京都府立第一・第二高等女学校、滋賀県女子師範学校等の薙刀教師を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he successively held the positions of naginata teacher at Doshisha Girls&apos; School (today&apos;s Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts), Kyoto Prefectural First and Second Girls&apos; High School, Shiga Prefectural Women&apos;s Normal School, and other schools.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he successively held the positions of naginata teacher at Doshisha Girls&apos; School (today&apos;s Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts), Kyoto Prefectural First and Second Girls&apos; High School, Shiga Prefectural Women&apos;s Normal School, and other schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he successively held the positions of naginata teacher at Doshisha Girls&apos; School (today&apos;s Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts), Kyoto Prefectural First and Second Girls&apos; High Schools, Shiga Prefectural Women&apos;s Normal School, and other schools.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、小西酒造創業家の小西家の道場・修武館でも薙刀術を指導した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also instructed naginatajutsu at Shubukan (修武館), a training hall of the Konishi family who founded the Konishi Shuzo brewery.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理　修武館→Shubukan [定訳不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also instructed naginatajutsu at Shubukan (修武館), a training hall of the Konishi family who also founded the Konishi Shuzo brewery.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also instructed naginata at Shubukan, a training hall of the Konishi family who also founded the Konishi Shuzo brewery.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>（修武館で定められた剣術形「修武館奥之形」のうちの1本に顕教の伝えた天道流剣術の技が採用されている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The technique of the swordplay of the Tendo-ryu school taught by Akinori is employed in one of the determined swordplay forms &quot;Shubukan oku no kata&quot; (修武館奥之形) of Shubukan (修武館).</e>
<cmt>修武館奥之形→Shubukan oku no kata [読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The technique of the sword taught at the Tendo-ryu school by Akinori is employed in one of the determined sword fencing forms &quot;Shubukan oku no kata&quot; (修武館奥之形) of Shubukan (修武館).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The technique of the sword taught at the Tendo school by Akinori is employed in &apos;Shubukan Oku no kata&apos; (combination arts and deep arts of Shubukan Training Hall), one of the determined sword fencing forms by Shubukan.)</e>
<cmt>かっこ、クォーテーションなどを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>1904年（明治37年）、大日本武徳会本部の剣術と薙刀術の助教授に任命されたので、武徳会本部のある京都市に移住する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1904, he was appointed to assistant professor of swordplay and naginata jutsu (art of Japanese halberd) at the Kyoto Dai-nihon-butoku-kai honbu (Kyoto Great Japan Federation of martial arts Headquarter), so he moved to Kyoto City where there is the headquarter.</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたので補足いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1904, he was appointed to assistant professor of sword fencing and naginata jutsu (art of Japanese halberd) at the Kyoto Dai-nihon-butoku-kai honbu (Kyoto Great Japan Federation of martial arts Headquarter), so he moved to Kyoto City where the headquarters are.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1904, he was appointed to assistant professor of sword fencing and naginata jutsu (art of Japanese halberd) at the headquarters of the Dai Nippon Butoku Kai, so he moved to Kyoto City where the headquarters are.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>1924年（大正13年）、薙刀術範士を授与される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1924, he received naginata jutsu Hanshi (the top rank).</e>
<cmt>年号が抜けていたので補足いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1924, he received naginata jutsu Hanshi (the top rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1924, he received naginata jutsu Hanshi (the top rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>1931年（昭和6年）1月10日没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died on January 10, 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Died on January 10, 1931.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died on January 10, 1931.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>享年83。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Died at the age of eighty-three.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>流儀は養女（血縁上は姪）の美田村千代が継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The style was inherited by his adopted daughter Chiyo MITAMURA, who was his biological niece.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The style was inherited by his adopted daughter Chiyo MITAMURA, who was his biological niece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The style was inherited by his adopted daughter Chiyo MITAMURA, who was his biological niece.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Himazin(id:22034), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>