<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳川綱吉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳川 綱吉（とくがわ つなよし、正保3年1月8日 (旧暦)（1646年2月23日） - 宝永6年1月10日 (旧暦)（1709年2月19日）、在職延宝8年(1680年)-宝永6年(1709年）は江戸幕府の第5代征夷大将軍である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA (February 23, 1646 - February 19, 1709, reigning from 1680 to 1709) was the fifth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Edo bakufu (feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA (February 23, 1646 - February 19, 1709, reigning from 1680 to 1709) was the fifth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues barbarians&quot;) of the Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA (February 23, 1646 - February 19, 1709, reigning from 1680 to 1709) was the fifth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues barbarians&quot;) of the Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>3代将軍徳川家光の4男、幼名は徳松。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was the fourth son of the third shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, and his childhood name was Tokumatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi, whose childhood name was Tokumatsu, was the fourth son of the third shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi, whose childhood name was Tokumatsu, was the fourth son of the third shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は桂昌院（お玉）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Keishoin (a.k.a Otama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Keishoin (who was also known as Otama).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Keishoin (who was also known as Otama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正室は鷹司教平の娘鷹司信子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s lawful wife was Nobuko TAKATSUKASA, daughter of Norihira TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s lawful wife was Nobuko TAKATSUKASA, the daughter of Norihira TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s lawful wife was Nobuko TAKATSUKASA, the daughter of Norihira TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>側室に瑞春院（お伝）、寿光院、清心院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuishunin (a.k.a Otsuta), Jukoin and Seishinin were his concubines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His concubines were Zuishunin (who was also known as Otsuta), Jukoin and Seishinin.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His concubines were Zuishunin (who was also known as Otsuta), Jukoin and Seishinin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>お手つきに牧野成貞の妻の阿久里とその娘の安などがいたという俗説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is popularly said that Tsunayoshi violated Narisada MAKINO&apos;s wife, Aguri, and also her daughter, Yasu, amongst others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are stories that Tsunayoshi had affairs with several women, including Narisada MAKINO&apos;s wife, Aguri, and daughter, Yasu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are stories that Tsunayoshi had affairs with several women, including Narisada MAKINO&apos;s wife, Aguri, and daughter, Yasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、後世の創作と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it is regarded as fiction made in the later age.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these are believed to be tales invented at a later date.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these are believed to be tales invented at a later date.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>子は、徳川徳松、鶴姫 (徳川家)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s children were Tokumatsu TOKUGAWA and Tsuruhime (the Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s children were Tokumatsu TOKUGAWA and Tsuruhime.</e>
<cmt>*I presume &quot;(徳川家)&quot; is part of the wikipedia link and not actually part of the sentence so I left it out as they are obviously part of the Tokugawa family</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s children were Tokumatsu TOKUGAWA and Tsuruhime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>俗に、柳沢吉里が綱吉の落胤であるといわれるが、実際には疑わしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly believed that Yoshisato YANAGISAWA was Tsunayoshi&apos;s illegitimate child, but this is doubtful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly believed that Yoshisato YANAGISAWA was Tsunayoshi&apos;s illegitimate child, but this is doubtful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly believed that Yoshisato YANAGISAWA was Tsunayoshi&apos;s illegitimate child, but this is doubtful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸城に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was born in Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi was born in Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was born in Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>幕府創業に尽力した2代将軍・徳川秀忠は祖父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, who devoted himself to establishing the bakufu was Tsunayoshi&apos;s grandfather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grandfather was Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the second shogun, who devoted himself to establishing the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grandfather was Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the second shogun, who devoted himself to establishing the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>初代将軍・徳川家康は曾祖父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first shogun, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, was Tsunayoshi&apos;s great-grandfather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the first shogun, was his great-grandfather.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the first shogun, was his great-grandfather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>慶安4年（1651年）4月、兄の長松（徳川綱重）とともに賄領として近江、美濃、信濃、駿河、上野から15万石を拝領し家臣団を付けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1651 Tsunayoshi, together with his elder brother Nagamatsu (Tsunashige TOKUGAWA), was presented with 150,000 koku (koku is a unit of volume, 1 koku corresponds to the land which yields approximately 180 liters of crops) from the provinces of Omi, Mino, Shinano, Suruga and Kozuke and was also given his vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1651, Tsunayoshi and his elder brother, Nagamatsu (Tsunashige TOKUGAWA), were presented with 150,000 koku (a unit of measurement for rice volume, used to asses wealth) from the provinces of Omi, Mino, Shinano, Suruga and Kozuke, and were also given some retainers.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1651, Tsunayoshi and his elder brother, Nagamatsu (Tsunashige TOKUGAWA), were presented with 150,000 koku (a unit of measurement for rice volume, used to asses wealth, 1 koku is 180.39 liter) from the provinces of Omi, Mino, Shinano, Suruga and Kozuke, and were also given some retainers.</e>
<cmt>｢兄」、 「石」を用語集の通りに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同月には将軍徳川家光が死去し、8月に兄の徳川家綱が将軍宣下を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same month the shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA died, and in August Tsunayoshi&apos;s older brother, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, was appointed shogun by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same month, Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA died, and in August, Tsunayoshi&apos;s older brother, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, was appointed shogun by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same month, Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA died, and in August, Tsunayoshi&apos;s older brother, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, was appointed shogun by the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>綱吉は将軍弟となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently Tsunayoshi became a younger brother of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Tsunayoshi became the brother of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - I don&apos;t think the fact that he was a younger brother is that relevant as it states that the Shogun was his older brother in the previous sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Tsunayoshi became the brother of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>承応2年（1653年）に元服し、従三位中将に叙任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1653 Tsunayoshi cerebrated his attainment of adulthood and was installed as Chujo of Jusanmi (Middle Captain, Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1653, Tsunayoshi celebrated his coming-of-age and was made Middle Captain, Junior Third Rank.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1653, Tsunayoshi celebrated his coming-of-age and was conferred Jusanmi Chujo (Middle Captain, Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>「叙任」を用語集の通りに修正しました。また役職に補足をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>将軍家綱から偏諱を受け名を「綱吉」と改め、。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was granted the right to use a portion of the real name of the shogun, Ietsuna, and changed his name to Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was granted the right to use a portion of the name of the shogun, Ietsuna, and changed his name to Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was granted the right to use a portion of the name of the shogun, Ietsuna, and changed his name to Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>明暦3年（1657年）、明暦の大火で竹橋の自邸が焼失したために9月に神田へ移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1657 Tsunayoshi&apos;s residence in Takebashi was destroyed by the Great Fire of Meireki and therefore he moved to Kanda in September.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1657, after Tsunayoshi&apos;s residence in Takebashi was destroyed in the Great Fire of Meireki, he moved to Kanda in September.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1657, after Tsunayoshi&apos;s residence in Takebashi was destroyed in the Great Fire of Meireki, he moved to Kanda in September.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>寛文元年（1661年）8月、上野国館林藩藩主として城持ちとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1661 Tsunayoshi became a &quot;shiro-mochi&quot; (literally, a castle holder) to be the lord of Tatebayashi Domain in Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1661, he became a &quot;shiro-mochi&quot; (literally, a castle holder) when he was made Lord of Tatebayashi Domain in Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1661, he became a &quot;shiromochi&quot; (literally, a castle holder) when he was made Lord of Tatebayashi Domain in Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;shiro-mochi&quot;→shiromochi としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>所領は25万石となる（館林徳川家）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently his territory became 250,000 koku (the Tatebayashi Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently his territory grew to be worth 250,000 koku (the Tatebayashi Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently his territory grew to be worth 250,000 koku (the Tatebayashi Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>が創設12月には参議に叙任され、この頃「館林宰相」と通称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Tatebayashi Tokugawa family was founded, in December Tsunayoshi was appointed a councilor and was then commonly known as &quot;Tatebayashi prime minister.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the December after the Tatebayashi Tokugawa family was founded, Tsunayoshi was appointed a councilor and came to be known popularly as &quot;the Tatebayashi Prime Minister.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the December after the Tatebayashi Tokugawa family was founded, Tsunayoshi was appointed Sangi (a councilor) and came to be known popularly as &quot;the Tatebayashi Prime Minister.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Sangi を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>寛文10年（1670年）に牧野成貞を館林藩家老3,000石に抜擢する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1670 Tsunayoshi promoted Narisada MAKINO to the post of karo (chief retainer) to the Tatebayashi clan and presented him with 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1670, he promoted Narisada MAKINO to the post of karo (chief retainer) of the Tatebayashi Clan and presented him with 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1670, he promoted Narisada MAKINO to the post of karo (chief retainer) of the Tatebayashi Clan and presented him with 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>延宝8年（1680年）5月、将軍家綱に継嗣がなかったことからその養嗣子として江戸城二の丸に迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1680 Tsunayoshi was installed in Ninomaru (outer citadel) of the Edo-jo Castle as Ietsugu&apos;s adopted heir, because the shogun Ietsuna didn&apos;t have an heir.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1680, Tsunayoshi was installed in Ninomaru (the outer citadel) of Edo-jo Castle as Ietsuna&apos;s adopted heir, since Ietsuna, the shogun, didn&apos;t have an heir.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1680, Tsunayoshi was installed in Ninomaru (the outer citadel) of Edo-jo Castle as Ietsuna&apos;s adopted heir, since Ietsuna, the shogun, didn&apos;t have an heir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>同月、家綱が40歳で死去したために将軍宣下を受け内大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Ietsuna died age 40 in the same month, Tsunayoshi was appointed shogun by the emperor and also received the court rank of Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same month, Ietsuna died at the age of 40 and Tsunayoshi was appointed Shogun by the Emperor and made Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same month, Ietsuna died at the age of 40 and Tsunayoshi was appointed Shogun by the Emperor and made Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>家綱時代の大老酒井忠清を廃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi dismissed Tadakiyo SAKAI, who had been tairo (chief minister) in the time of Ietsuna.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi dismissed Tadakiyo SAKAI, who had been Ietsuna&apos;s tairo (chief minister) and replaced him with Masatoshi HOTTA, who had worked hard to get Tsunayoshi installed as shogun.</e>
<cmt>*I think this sentence is better rejoined to the next one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi dismissed Tadakiyo SAKAI, who had been Ietsuna&apos;s tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt>二文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>自己の将軍職就任に功労があった堀田正俊を大老とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead Tsunayoshi installed Masatoshi HOTTA as tairo, who contributed a great deal to install him in the post of shogun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead Tsunayoshi installed Masatoshi HOTTA as tairo, who contributed a great deal to install him in the post of shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He replaced Sasaki with Masatoshi HOTTA, who had worked hard to get Tsunayoshi installed as shogun.</e>
<cmt>二文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その後忠清は病死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, Tadakiyo died of illness.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, Tadakiyo died of illness.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, Tadakiyo died of illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし、酒井家を改易にしたい綱吉は大目付に「墓から掘り起こせ」などと命じて病死かどうかを異常なまでに詮議させたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi, who wanted to rob the Sakai family of their social standing and expropriate their properties, obsessively requested an investigation to determine if Tadakiyo truly died of illness, for example by ordering ometsuke (chief inspector of the Edo shogunate) to dig up his grave.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi, hoping to deprive the Sakai family of their social standing and property, obsessively requested an investigation to determine if Tadakiyo had truly died of illness by ordering, for example, the ometsuke (chief inspector) to dig up Tadakiyo&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi, hoping to deprive the Sakai family of their social standing and property, obsessively requested an investigation to determine if Tadakiyo had truly died of illness by ordering, for example, the ometsuke (chief inspector) to dig up Tadakiyo&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし証拠は出せず、結局酒井忠清の弟酒井忠能が言いがかりをつけられて改易されるにとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However no evidence was found and finally it just ended up that Tadayoshi SAKAI, younger brother of Tadakiyo SAKAI, was robbed of his rank and properties on a false charge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, no evidence was found, with the result that only Tadayoshi SAKAI, Tadakiyo&apos;s younger brother, lost his rank and property on trumped up charges.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, no evidence was found, with the result that only Tadayoshi SAKAI, Tadakiyo&apos;s younger brother, lost his rank and property on trumped up charges.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>綱吉は大老堀田正俊を片腕に処分が確定していた越後国高田藩の継承問題（越後騒動）を裁定し直したり、諸藩の政治を監査するなどして積極的な政治に乗り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi, with the considerable assistance of the tairo Masatoshi HOTTA, actively went into politics such as re-ruling on the matter of succession to the Takada clan in Echigo Province (called Echigo Sodo) even though this matter had already been settled, and inspecting politics in domains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi, with the considerable assistance of the tairo, Masatoshi HOTTA, actively involved himself in politics, re-ruling on the matter of succession in Takada Domain in Echigo Province (known as the Echigo Quarrel) even though it had already been settled, and inspecting the politics of several domains.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi, with the considerable assistance of the tairo, Masatoshi HOTTA, actively involved himself in politics, re-ruling on the matter of succession in Takada Domain in Echigo Province (known as the Echigo Quarrel) even though it had already been settled, and inspecting the politics of several domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>「左様せい様」と陰口された家綱時代に没落した将軍権威の向上に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi strived to increase the prestige of the shogun, which had been lost in the reign of Ietsuna, who was run down as &quot;Mr. Do-so.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi worked hard to increase the shogun&apos;s authority, which had been lost under Ietsuna, who had been known behind his back as &quot;Sir Make it so.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi worked hard to increase the shogun&apos;s authority, which had been lost under Ietsuna, who had been known behind his back as &quot;Sir Make it so.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また幕府の会計監査のために勘定吟味役を設置して、有能な小身旗本の登用をねらった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Tsunayoshi set up the post of Kanjoginmiyaku (post in the Edo bakufu to support commissioners in the finance ministry) to audit accounts in the bakufu aiming to promote the talented lower rank hatamoto (direct retainer to a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Tsunayoshi set up the post of Kanjoginmiyaku to audit the government&apos;s accounts, aiming to promote talented low-ranking hatamoto (direct retainers to the shogun).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Tsunayoshi set up the post of Kanjoginmiyaku to audit the government&apos;s accounts, aiming to promote talented low-ranking hatamoto (direct retainers to the shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>荻原重秀もここから登用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigehide OGIWARA was promoted through this line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigehide OGIWARA was promoted from this post.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigehide OGIWARA was promoted from this post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また外様大名からも一部幕閣への登用がみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also some of tozama daimyo (a feudal lord who was non-hereditary retainer of the Tokugawa family) were promoted to the position of cabinet officials of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also some &apos;tozama daimyo&apos; (feudal lords who were non-hereditary retainers of the Tokugawa family) were promoted to become cabinet officials.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also some &apos;tozama daimyo&apos; (feudal lords who were non-hereditary retainers of the Tokugawa family) were promoted to become cabinet officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="35">
<j>また戦国の殺伐とした気風を排除して徳を重んずる文治政治を推進。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Tsunayoshi eliminated the savage atmosphere of the warring period and pushed forward with the politics of civilian government, which valued virtue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Tsunayoshi eliminated the savage atmosphere of the warring period and promoted civil government, which valued virtue.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Tsunayoshi eliminated the savage atmosphere of the warring period and promoted civil government, which valued virtue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>これは父家光が綱吉に儒学を叩き込んだことに影響している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because Tsunayoshi&apos;s father, Iemitsu, drummed Confucianism into him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because Tsunayoshi&apos;s father, Iemitsu, drummed Confucianism into him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because Tsunayoshi&apos;s father, Iemitsu, drummed Confucianism into him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>（弟としての分をわきまえさせ、家綱に無礼を働かないようにするためだったという）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it was aiming to get Tsunayoshi to learn his place as younger brother and not to act disrespectfully to Ietsuna.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（）は除いて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this was to get Tsunayoshi to learn his place as a younger brother and not to act disrespectfully to Ietsuna.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is said that this was to get Tsunayoshi to learn his place as a younger brother and not to act disrespectfully to Ietsuna.)</e>
<cmt>括弧をつけたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>綱吉は林信篤をしばしば召しては経書の討論を行い、また四書や易経を幕臣に講義したほか、学問の中心地として湯島大聖堂を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi often called Nobuatsu HAYASHI to discuss Keisho (the most important documents in Confucianism), gave lectures on The Four Books of Confucianism and I Ching (The Book of Changes) to his retainers in the bakufu, and built Yushima Daiseido as the center of scholarship.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi often called Nobuatsu HAYASHI to discuss the Confucian Classics, gave lectures on The Four Books of Confucianism and the &quot;I Ching&quot; (The Book of Changes) to retainers in the government, and built Yushima Daiseido as the center of scholarship.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi often called Nobuatsu HAYASHI to discuss the Confucian Classics, gave lectures on The Four Books of Confucianism and the &quot;I Ching&quot; (The Book of Changes) to retainers in the government, and built Yushima Daiseido as the center of scholarship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>たいへん学問好きな将軍であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a study-loving shogun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a study-loving shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a study-loving shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>儒学の影響で歴代将軍の中でももっとも尊皇心が厚かった将軍としても知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all the shoguns, Tsunayoshi is also known as the shogun who revered the emperor the most due to the influence of Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all the shoguns, Tsunayoshi is also known as the one who, due to the influence of Confucianism, revered the emperor the most.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all the shoguns, Tsunayoshi is also known as the one who, due to the influence of Confucianism, revered the emperor the most.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>御料（皇室領）を1万石から3万石に増額して献上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi increased &quot;goryo&quot; (estate of Imperial family) from 10,000 koku to 30,000 koku and presented it to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi increased the &quot;goryo&quot; (Imperial family&apos;s estate) from 10,000 koku to 30,000 koku and presented it to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi increased the &quot;goryo&quot; (Imperial family&apos;s estate) from 10,000 koku to 30,000 koku and presented it to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また大和国と河内国一帯の御陵を調査のうえに修復が必要なものに巨額な資金をかけて計66陵を修復させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also he had the Imperial mausoleums throughout Yamato and Kawachi Provinces investigated, and had 66 of them which needed repairing restored, spending a huge amount of money.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had Imperial mausoleums throughout Yamato and Kawachi Provinces investigated, spending a huge amount of money to restore 66 of them which were in need of repair.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had Imperial mausoleums throughout Yamato and Kawachi Provinces investigated, spending a huge amount of money to restore 66 of them which were in need of repair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>公家達の所領についても概ね綱吉時代に倍増している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the feudal land of court nobles was also doubled in the time of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the court nobles&apos; territory of also doubled during Tsunayoshi&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the court nobles&apos; territory of also doubled during Tsunayoshi&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="44">
<j>また、のちに赤穂藩主浅野長矩を大名としては異例の即日切腹に処した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Tsunayoshi condemned the lord of the Ako domain, Naganori ASANO, to death (seppuku) and had him executed on the same day, which was an unusual treatment to the daimyo (feudal lord) rank.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi also condemned the Lord of Ako Domain, Naganori ASANO, to commit seppuku and had him carry it out on the same day, which was unusual treatment for a daimyo.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi also condemned the Lord of Ako Domain, Naganori ASANO, to commit seppuku and had him carry it out on the same day, which was unusual treatment for a daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>それも朝廷との儀式を台無しにされたことへの綱吉の激怒が大きな原因であったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main reason for this seems to be that Tsunayoshi became angry because ASANO disrupted a ceremony with the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main reason for this seems to be that Tsunayoshi was angry at ASANO for making a mess of a ceremony with the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main reason for this seems to be that Tsunayoshi was angry at Asano for making a mess of a ceremony with the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>苗字のみなので小文字に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>綱吉のこうした儒学を重んじる姿勢は、新井白石・室鳩巣・荻生徂徠・雨森芳州・山鹿素行らの学者を輩出するきっかけにもなり、この時代、儒学が隆盛を極めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This attitude of Tsunayoshi to value Confucianism encouraged the growth of scholars such as Hakuseki ARAI, Kyuso MURO, Sorai OGYU, Hoshu AMENOMORI and Soko YAMAGA, and Confucianism reached the peak of its prosperity at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s attitude of valuing Confucianism encouraged an increase in scholars such as Hakuseki ARAI, Kyuso MURO, Sorai OGYU, Hoshu AMENOMORI and Soko YAMAGA, with Confucianism reaching the peak of its prosperity at this time.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s attitude of valuing Confucianism encouraged an increase in scholars such as Hakuseki ARAI, Kyuso MURO, Sorai OGYU, Hoshu AMENOMORI and Soko YAMAGA, with Confucianism reaching the peak of its prosperity at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="47">
<j>綱吉の治世の前半は基本的には善政として天和の治と称えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi is admired because he basically conducted good government (called &quot;Government in the Tenna Era&quot;) in the first half of his reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi is admired because he was basically a good ruler in the first half of his rule (known as the &quot;Tenna Government&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi is admired because he was basically a good ruler in the first half of his rule (known as the &quot;Tenna Government&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="48">
<j>しかしながら、貞享元年（1684年）堀田正俊が若年寄稲葉正休に刺殺されると、綱吉は以後大老を置かず側用人の牧野成貞、柳沢吉保らを重用して老中などを遠ざけるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However after Masatoshi HOTTA was stabbed to death by a wakadoshiyori (subordinate to tairo), Masayasu INABA, in 1684, Tsunayoshi didn&apos;t have tairo anymore and took sobayonin (lord chamberlain) such as Narisada MAKINO and Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA into his confidence instead, keeping his distance from roju (subordinate to tairo, higher than wakadoshiyori).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Masatoshi HOTTA was stabbed to death by Masayasu INABA, a junior councilor, in 1684, Tsunayoshi no longer had a tairo, instead relying on sobayonin (lord chamberlains) such as Narisada MAKINO and Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA, and kept his distance from the roju (the most senior officials in the government).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Masatoshi HOTTA was stabbed to death by Masayasu INABA, a junior councilor, in 1684, Tsunayoshi no longer had a tairo, instead relying on sobayonin (lord chamberlains) such as Narisada MAKINO and Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA, and kept his distance from the roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders).</e>
<cmt>「老中」を用語集の通りに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>また綱吉は儒学の孝に影響されて、母桂昌院に従一位という前例のない高官を朝廷より賜るなど特別な処遇をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Tsunayoshi was influenced by the notion of filial duty in Confucianism and treated his mother, Keishoin, in a very special way such as receiving an unprecedented high rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) on her behalf her from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi was also influenced by the Confucian notion of filial piety and treated his mother, Keishoin, in a very special way, such as having her awarded the unprecedented high rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was also influenced by the Confucian notion of filial piety and treated his mother, Keishoin, in a very special way, such as having her awarded the unprecedented high rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>桂昌院とゆかりの深い本庄家・牧野家（小諸藩主）などに特別な計らいがあったともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that Tsunayoshi arranged special things for the Honjo family and the Makino family (the lord of Komoro Domain) which had a close association with Keishoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that Tsunayoshi gave special treatment to the Honjo family and the Makino family (the lords of Komoro Domain), who had a close association with Keishoin.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that Tsunayoshi gave special treatment to the Honjo family and the Makino family (the lords of Komoro Domain), who had a close association with Keishoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="51">
<j>この頃から有名な生類憐れみの令をはじめとする後世に“悪政”といわれる政治を次々とおこなうようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At around this time Tsunayoshi started to conduct successive policies which in later times were labeled &quot;maladministration,&quot; including the famous Shorui Awaremi no Rei (ordinances of animal protection).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, Tsunayoshi introduced successive policies which would later be labeled &quot;maladministration,&quot; including the famous Shorui Awaremi no Rei (prohibiting the killing of animals).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, Tsunayoshi introduced successive policies which would later be labeled &quot;maladministration,&quot; including the famous Shorui Awaremi no Rei (prohibiting the killing of animals).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>（生類憐れみの令については、母の寵愛していた隆光僧正の言を採用して発布したものであるとする説があった。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an opinion that Shorui Awaremi no Rei was promulgated following the advice of sojo (a Buddhist priest ranked in the highest managerial position) Ryuko who was favored by Tsunayoshi&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（は除いて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an opinion that Shorui Awaremi no Rei was promulgated following the advice of the sojo (a high-ranking Buddhist priest), Ryuko, who was favored by Tsunayoshi&apos;s mother.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(There was an opinion that Shorui Awaremi no Rei was promulgated following the advice of the sojo [a high-ranking Buddhist priest], Ryuko, who was favored by Tsunayoshi&apos;s mother.)</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正、余分なスペースを除き、「僧正」を用語集の通りに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>(しかし、現在では、隆光や桂昌院と生類憐みの令の関係は否定されている。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However now the relationship between Ryuko, Keishoin and Shorui Awaremi no Rei is denied.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at present the relationship between Ryuko, Keishoin and Shorui Awaremi no Rei is rejected.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, at present the relationship between Ryuko, Keishoin and Shorui Awaremi no Rei is rejected.)</e>
<cmt>括弧を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>(また、一般的に信じられている「過酷な悪法」とする説は、江戸時代史見直しの中で再考されつつある。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the common belief that it was an &apos;evil and severe law&apos; is reflected in the current review of Edo period history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the common belief that it was an &apos;evil and severe law&apos; is a reflection of the current revision of Edo period history.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Also, the common belief that it was an &apos;evil and severe law&apos; is a reflection of the current revision of Edo period history.)</e>
<cmt>括弧を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>(詳しくは同項目を参照のこと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For more details, refer to the Shorui Awaremi no Rei section.</e>
<cmt>）は除いて訳しました。同項目→生類憐みの令の項目として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For more details, refer to the Shorui Awaremi no Rei section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For more details, refer to the Shorui Awaremi no Rei section.)</e>
<cmt>括弧を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これらが幕府の財政を悪化させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These worsened the financial condition of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These policies worsened the financial condition of the government.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These policies worsened the financial condition of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>勘定奉行荻原重秀の献策による貨幣の改鋳を実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the suggestion of Kanjobugyo (commissioner of finance) Shigehide OGIWARA Tsunayoshi re-minted the currency.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the suggestion of Kanjobugyo (Commissioner of Finance) Shigehide OGIWARA, the currency was re-minted.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the suggestion of Kanjobugyo (Commissioner of Finance) Shigehide OGIWARA, the currency was re-minted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし、本来改鋳すべき時期をやや逸していたこともありかえって経済を混乱させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead it was disruptive to the economy, partly because the timing had been slightly overdue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead it caused chaos in the economy, partly because it was slightly overdue.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead it caused chaos in the economy, partly because it was slightly overdue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="59">
<j>嫡男の徳松が死去した後の将軍後継問題が発生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The issue of a successor to the shogun arose after Tsunayoshi&apos;s legitimate son, Tokumatsu, died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The issue of a successor to the shogun arose after Tsunayoshi&apos;s legitimate son, Tokumatsu, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The issue of a successor to the shogun arose after Tsunayoshi&apos;s legitimate son, Tokumatsu, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>娘の鶴姫を嫁がせていた徳川御三家の紀州徳川家の徳川綱教が候補に上がったが徳川光圀が反対したという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Tsunanori TOKUGAWA to whom Tsunayoshi&apos;s daughter, Tsuruhime, got married was nominated as the successor but Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA objected to it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Tsunanori TOKUGAWA, who was married to Tsunayoshi&apos;s daughter, Tsuruhime, was nominated as the successor but Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA objected.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Tsunanori TOKUGAWA, who was married to Tsunayoshi&apos;s daughter, Tsuruhime, was nominated as the successor but Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA objected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>宝永元年（1704年）、6代将軍は甥で甲斐国甲府藩の徳川家宣（綱豊）に決定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1704, it was decided that Ienobu (a.k.a Tsunatoyo) TOKUGAWA, who was Tsunayoshi&apos;s nephew and from Kofu Domain, Kai Province, become the sixth shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1704, it was decided that Ienobu (originally Tsunatoyo) TOKUGAWA, who was Tsunayoshi&apos;s nephew and from Kofu Domain, Kai Province, would become the sixth shogun.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1704, it was decided that Ienobu (originally Tsunatoyo) TOKUGAWA, who was Tsunayoshi&apos;s nephew and from Kofu Domain, Kai Province, would become the sixth shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>綱吉は宝永6年（1709年）に死去、享年63。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi died in 1709, at the age of 63.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi died in 1709, at the age of 63.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi died in 1709, at the age of 63.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="63">
<j>家宣が将軍になると「生類憐みの令」はすぐに廃止されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the &apos;Shorui Awaremi no Rei&apos; was abolished immediately after Ienobu became the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shorui Awaremi no Rei&apos; was abolished immediately after Ienobu became shogun.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shorui Awaremi no Rei&apos; was abolished immediately after Ienobu became shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>しかし殺生である鷹狩りは、徳川吉宗が8代将軍になったのちまで復活することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However falconry, which involved destruction of life, didn&apos;t revive until Yoshimune TOKUGAWA became the eighth shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However falconry, which involved the destruction of life, was not revived until Yoshimune TOKUGAWA became the eighth shogun.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However falconry, which involved the destruction of life, was not revived until Yoshimune TOKUGAWA became the eighth shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>ちなみに吉宗は天和の治をおこなった綱吉に対して敬愛の念を抱き、吉宗の享保の改革の中にもその影響がみられるといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally it is said that Yoshimune respected Tsunayoshi for conducting good &quot;Government in the Tenna era&quot; and its influences can be seen in the Kyoho Reforms (the reforms made in the Kyoho era) led by Yoshimune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, it is said that Yoshimune respected Tsunayoshi for his &quot;Tenna Government&quot; and its influences can be seen in the Yoshimune&apos;s Kyoho Reforms.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, it is said that Yoshimune respected Tsunayoshi for his &quot;Tenna Government&quot; and its influences can be seen in the Yoshimune&apos;s Kyoho Reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="66">
<j>7代将軍・徳川家継の大叔父で松平清武の叔父に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was the grand uncle to the seventh shogun Ietsugu TOKUGAWA, and the uncle to Kiyotake MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi was great uncle to the seventh shogun, Ietsugu TOKUGAWA, and uncle to Kiyotake MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was great uncle to the seventh shogun, Ietsugu TOKUGAWA, and uncle to Kiyotake MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>8代将軍徳川吉宗とははとこにあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was the second cousin to the eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was second cousin to the eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was second cousin to the eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="68">
<j>柳沢吉保の側室飯塚染子は綱吉からの拝領妻であるという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA&apos;s concubine, Someko IIZUKA, was given to him by Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA&apos;s concubine, Someko IIZUKA, was given to him by Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA&apos;s concubine, Someko IIZUKA, was given to him by Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>その妻の出産した男子である柳沢吉里は綱吉の実子であるとの噂が当時からあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even at that time there was a rumor that Yoshisato YANAGISAWA, who his wife, Someko, gave birth to, was Tsunayoshi&apos;s biological son.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even at that time there was a rumor that the father of Someko&apos;s child, Yoshisato YANAGISAWA, was Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even at that time there was a rumor that the father of Someko&apos;s child, Yoshisato YANAGISAWA, was Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>綱吉は柳沢家に、松平姓を与えて特に連枝の待遇としたが、これがその事情を雄弁に物語っているという指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some point out the fact that Tsunayoshi especially gave the Yanagisawa family the Matsudaira cognomen and treated them as honorable siblings eloquently explains the story behind it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is pointed out that this neatly explains why Tsunayoshi conferred the Matsudaira name on the Yanagisawa family and treated them as siblings.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is pointed out that this neatly explains why Tsunayoshi conferred the Matsudaira name on the Yanagisawa family and treated them as siblings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>しかし、現在ではこの説は否定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However this view is now dismissed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this view is now dismissed.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this view is now dismissed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="72">
<j>墓所は東京都台東区上野桜木一丁目の寛永寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s graveyard is in the Kanei-ji Temple in Sakuragi 1chome, Ueno, Taito Ward, Tokyo Metropolitan area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s grave is in Kanei-ji Temple in Sakuragi 1-chome, Ueno, Taito Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s grave is in Kanei-ji Temple in Sakuragi 1-chome, Ueno, Taito Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Record of offices and ranks held</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Record of Offices and Ranks Held</e>
<cmt>Capital letters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of Offices and Ranks Held</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>1653年（承応2年）　8月12日元服。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 3, 1653 Tsunayoshi cerebrated his attainment of adulthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 12, 1653, celebrated coming-of-age.</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 12, 1653, celebrated coming-of-age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>同日従四位下右近衛権中将兼右馬頭に叙任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the same day, Tsunayoshi was appointed Ukone no Gon no Chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and also Umanokami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the same day, appointed Ukone no Gon no Chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) with the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and also Umanokami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the same day, appointed Ukone no Gon no Chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) with the rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and also Umanokami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>さらに、同月17日には正三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, on the 8th of the month he was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, on the 17th of the month, promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, on the 17th of the month, promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="76">
<j>1661年（寛文元年）　12月28日、参議補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 16, 1662 Tsunayoshi was appointed Sangi (Councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 28, 1661, appointed Sangi (Councilor).</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 28, 1661, appointed Sangi (Councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="77">
<j>1680年（延宝8年）　5月7日、将軍後継者となり、同日、従二位権大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 3, 1680 Tsunayoshi became the successor to the shogun and on the same day was appointed Gon Dainagon (Provisional Chief Councilor of State) of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 7, 1680, made successor to the shogun and on the same day, appointed Gon Dainagon (Provisional Chief Councilor of State) with the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 7, 1680, made successor to the shogun and on the same day, appointed Gon Dainagon (Provisional Chief Councilor of State) with the rank of Junii Gon Dainagon (Junior Second Rank, Provisional Chief Councilor of State).</e>
<cmt>「従二位権大納言」の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>ついで、8月21日、正二位内大臣兼右近衛大将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently on September 13, he was appointed Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior) and Ukone no Daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, on August 21, appointed Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior) and Ukone no Daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) with the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, on August 21, appointed Shonii Naidaijin (Senior Second Rank, Inner Minister) and Ukone no Daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) with the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>「正二位内大臣」の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>征夷大将軍・源氏長者宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi received the proclamation of his appointment as seii taishogun and Genji no Choja (Chief of the Minamoto Clan) from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s appointment as seii taishogun and Genji no Choja (Chief of the Minamoto Clan) proclaimed by the Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s appointment as seii taishogun and Genji no Choja (Chief of the Minamoto Clan) proclaimed by the Imperial Court</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="80">
<j>1705年（宝永2年）　3月5日、右大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 29, 1705 he was appointed Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 5, 1705, appointed Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 5, 1705, appointed Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="81">
<j>1709年（宝永6年）　1月10日、薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 19, 1709 Tsunayoshi died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 10, 1709, Tsunayoshi died.</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 10, 1709, Tsunayoshi died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>ついで、同月23日、贈正一位太政大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently on March 4, Zo Shoichii (Senior First Rank, posthumously conferred) and Daijo Daijin (Grand Minister) were conferred on him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, on January 23, posthumously made Shoichii (Senior First Rank) and Daijo Daijin (Grand Minister).</e>
<cmt>Revised to better reflect the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, on January 23, posthumously made Zo Shoichii Daijo Daijin (Senior First Rank posthumously conferred, Grand minister of state) and Daijo Daijin (Grand Minister).</e>
<cmt>「贈正一位太政大臣」の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>綱吉の評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluation of Tsunayoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluation of Tsunayoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluation of Tsunayoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="83">
<j>綱吉の行状については価値の低い資料による報告が誇張されて伝えられている部分もあり、近年では綱吉の政治に対する評価の再検討が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Partly, some exaggerated reports about Tsunayoshi&apos;s behaviors in less valuable documents were spread.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are some exaggerated reports about Tsunayoshi&apos;s behavior in documents with little value, in recent years, Tsunayoshi&apos;s politics have undergone a reevaluation.</e>
<cmt>*I think these two sentences read better as one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are some exaggerated reports about Tsunayoshi&apos;s behavior in documents with little value, in recent years, Tsunayoshi&apos;s politics have undergone a reevaluation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="84">
<j>綱吉は「側近の寵臣以外の意見を軽視し、悪法で民衆を苦しめた」という否定的評価がなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On one hand Tsunayoshi is evaluated negatively because he listened little to the opinions of others, except those of his close advisors and favorite retainers and because he plagued his people with evil laws.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On one hand, there is the negative assessment that Tsunayoshi &quot;ignored the opinions of anyone except his close advisors and favorite retainers and burdened the people with evil laws.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On one hand, there is the negative assessment that Tsunayoshi &quot;ignored the opinions of anyone except his close advisors and favorite retainers and burdened the people with evil laws.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>一方で、元禄4年（1691年）と同5年（1692年）に江戸で綱吉に謁見したドイツ人医師エンゲルベルト・ケンペルの「非常に英邁な君主であるという印象を受けた」といった評価も受けている（ケンペル著『日本誌』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand a German doctor, Engelbert Kaempfer, who had an audience with Tsunayoshi evaluated him highly in his book &quot;Nihonshi&quot; (The History of Japan), saying &quot;I had the impression that he was a great monarch.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Engelbert Kaempfer, a German doctor who had an audience with Tsunayoshi, rated him highly in his book &quot;The History of Japan,&quot; saying, &quot;I had the impression that he was a great monarch.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Engelbert KAEMPFER, a German doctor who had an audience with Tsunayoshi in 1691 and in 1692, rated him highly in his book &quot;The History of Japan,&quot; saying, &quot;I had the impression that he was a great monarch.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Kaempferを大文字にしました。年の訳漏れを加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>ケンペルの綱吉観や両者の交流については中公新書刊行『ケンペルと徳川綱吉』（ベアトリス・M. ボダルト・ベイリー・1994年　ISBN 4-12-101168-6）に詳しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaempfer&apos;s view of Tsunayoshi and interaction between them are written in detail in &quot;Kaempfer and Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA&quot; (Beatrice M Bodart-Bailey, 1994, ISBN 4-12-101168-6) published by Chuko Shinsho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaempfer&apos;s view of Tsunayoshi and the interaction between them are described in detail in &quot;Kenperu to Tokugawa Tsunayoshi&quot; (Beatrice M. Bodart-Bailey, 1994, ISBN 4-12-101168-6) published by Chuko Shinsho.</e>
<cmt>*I&apos;m not sure there is an English version of this book, and since the ISBN code is for the Japanese book, I changed the title to a romanization of the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaempfer&apos;s view of Tsunayoshi and the interaction between them are described in detail in &quot;Kenperu to Tokugawa Tsunayoshi&quot; (Beatrice M. Bodart-Bailey, 1994, ISBN 4-12-101168-6) published by Chuko Shinsho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="87">
<j>綱吉の治世下は、近松門左衛門、井原西鶴、松尾芭蕉といった文化人を生んだ元禄期であり、好景気の時代だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the reign of Tsunayoshi, the Genroku period, men of culture such as Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU, Saikaku IHARA and Basho MATSUO appeared and the economy boomed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s rule covered the Genroku period, which saw the appearance of men of culture such as Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU, Saikaku IHARA and Basho MATSUO and a booming economy.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s rule covered the Genroku period, which saw the appearance of men of culture such as Monzaemon CHIKAMATSU, Saikaku IHARA and Basho MATSUO and a booming economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>このため優れた経済政策を執っていたという評価もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus some evaluate Tsunayoshi as having conducted sound economic policy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus some evaluate Tsunayoshi as having conducted sound economic policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus some evaluate Tsunayoshi as having conducted sound economic policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>また、治世の前期と後期の評価を分けて考えるべきだという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also some say that the first and the final halves of Tsunayoshi&apos;s reign must be evaluated separately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also some say that the first and second halves of Tsunayoshi&apos;s reign must be evaluated separately.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also some say that the first and second halves of Tsunayoshi&apos;s reign must be evaluated separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>前期における幕政刷新の試みはある程度成功している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s attempt to reform the bakufu government in the first half of his reign was successful to some degree.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s attempt to reform the military government during the first half of his reign was successful to some degree.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s attempt to reform the military government during the first half of his reign was successful to some degree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>享保の改革を行った8代将軍徳川吉宗も綱吉の定めた武家諸法度をそのまま「武家諸法度」として採用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, who conducted the Kyoho Reform (the reforms in the Kyoho period) directly adopted Tsunayoshi&apos;s version of Buke Shohatto (a code for the warrior households).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, who carried out the Kyoho Reforms, directly adopted Tsunayoshi&apos;s version of the Buke Shohatto (a code for warrior households).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, who carried out the Kyoho Reforms, directly adopted Tsunayoshi&apos;s version of the Buke Shohatto (Laws for the Military Houses).</e>
<cmt>「武家諸法度」を用語集の通りに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>その施政には綱吉前期の治世を範とした政策が多いと指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some point out that many of Yoshimune&apos;s policies were modeled after the government of the first half of Tsunayoshi&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been pointed out that many of Yoshimune&apos;s policies were modeled after the first half of Tsunayoshi&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been pointed out that many of Yoshimune&apos;s policies were modeled after the first half of Tsunayoshi&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="93">
<j>綱吉の治世の評価が低いことについては、不幸な偶然もいくつかあると指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the reason for the low evaluation of Tsunayoshi&apos;s reign, some unlucky coincidences are pointed out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several unlucky coincidences are often given as the reason for the low evaluation of Tsunayoshi&apos;s rule.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several unlucky coincidences are often given as the reason for the low evaluation of Tsunayoshi&apos;s rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>具体的には、元禄11年（1698年）の勅額大火（数寄屋橋門外より出火し上野を経て千住まで300町余を焼失、死者3,000人以上）や宝永4年（1707年）の宝永大噴火などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, there was the Great Fire of Chokugaku in 1698 (&apos;chokugaku&apos; means the imperial votive tablet), which started outside Sukiyabashi-mon Gate, and continued through Ueno to Senju burning down about 300 towns and causing more than 3,000 deaths and in addition in 1710 there was the Great Eruption of the Hoei Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, there was the Great Chokugaku Fire of 1698, which started outside the Sukiyabashi-mon Gate, and continued through Ueno to Senju, burning down about three square kilometers and causing more than 3,000 deaths and, in addition, in 1710 there was the Hoei Eruption of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>* -I don&apos;t think a definition of chokugaku is relevant here. -I think &quot;町&quot; refers to the 尺貫法, rather than towns in this case, though I may be wrong</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, there was the Great Chokugaku Fire of 1698, which started outside the Sukiyabashi-mon Gate, and continued through Ueno to Senju, burning down about three square kilometers and causing more than 3,000 deaths and, in addition, in 1710 there was the Hoei Eruption of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>それらは、現代では治世の評価を左右するものとは考えにくいが、当時は「天罰」と受け止められてもいたしかたないものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this modern age it is hard to believe that these events influenced the evaluation of his reign, but at the time people naturally presumed he was being punished by Heaven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this modern age it is hard to believe that these events influenced the evaluation of his reign, but at the time, people naturally presumed he was being punished by Heaven.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this modern age it is hard to believe that these events influenced the evaluation of his reign, but at the time, people naturally presumed he was being punished by Heaven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="96">
<j>また、現代においての評価の低さはドラマによるところが最も大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the low evaluation of Tsunayoshi&apos;s reign in the present is mainly attributable to dramas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the current low evaluation of Tsunayoshi&apos;s rule is mainly attributable to dramas.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the current low evaluation of Tsunayoshi&apos;s rule is mainly attributable to dramas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>というのも徳川綱吉がドラマに登場するのは基本的に忠臣蔵関連か水戸黄門関連のドラマのどちらかであることが多いためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the dramas in which Tsunayoshi appears are mostly related to either &quot;Chushingura&quot; (The treasury of Loyal Retainers) or to &quot;Mito Komon.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because the dramas in which Tsunayoshi appears are mostly related to either &quot;Chushingura&quot; or &quot;Mito Komon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because the dramas in which Tsunayoshi appears are mostly related to either &quot;Chushingura&quot; or &quot;Mito Komon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>（そのためか歴代徳川将軍の中でも知名度の高い部類に入る）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore Tsunayoshi is one of the best known of all the shoguns.</e>
<cmt>（）は除いて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Tsunayoshi is one of the best known of all the shoguns.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Therefore, Tsunayoshi is one of the best known of all the shoguns.)</e>
<cmt>括弧をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="99">
<j>忠臣蔵（元禄赤穂事件）では大抵の場合高家吉良上野介が浅野内匠頭をいじめる姿が描かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most Chushingura (a.k.a. Genroku Ako Incident) dramas include the depiction that Kira Kozuke no Suke, a master of ceremonies, bullies Asano Takumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most versions of Chushingura (also known as the Genroku Ako Incident) depict Kira Kozuke no Suke, the master of ceremonies, bullying Asano Takumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most versions of Chushingura (The treasury of Loyal Retainers, also known as Genroku Ako Incident) depict Kira Kozuke no Suke, the master of ceremonies, bullying Asano Takumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>「忠臣蔵」に補足を加え、名前の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>その結果、浅野にのみ切腹を命じて吉良の罪をとわなかった将軍徳川綱吉には「いじめっ子」に加担したかのような否定的イメージが付きまとってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the shogun Tsunayoshi who sentenced only Asano to suicide by disembowelment without accusing Kira is often associated with the negative image that he supported a &apos;bully.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Tsunayoshi, who sentenced only Asano to death by seppuku without accusing Kira, is often associated with the negative image of him supporting a &apos;bully.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Tsunayoshi, who sentenced only Asano to death by seppuku without accusing Kira, is often associated with the negative image of him supporting a &apos;bully.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>このことも、綱吉の評価を実際以上に低めていると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is one of the reasons for the underestimation of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is one of the reasons for the low opinion of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is one of the reasons for the low opinion of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="102">
<j>そして綱吉のもう一つの不運は水戸黄門（徳川光圀）の存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another piece of bad luck for Tsunayoshi is the existence of Mito Komon (Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another piece of bad luck for Tsunayoshi is the existence of Mito Komon (Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another piece of bad luck for Tsunayoshi is the existence of Mito Komon (Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>光圀は生類憐みの令に抗議して犬の毛皮を送ったという逸話を中心に綱吉に直言したという記録がいくつかある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdotes about Mitsukuni that he sent Tsunayoshi dogs&apos; fur to protest against Shorui Awaremi no Rei. There are some records, including this anecdote, that Mitsukuni spoke without reserve to Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are records, including an anecdote about Mitsukuni sending dogs&apos; fur to Tsunayoshi to protest against the Shorui Awaremi no Rei, showing that Mitsukuni spoke frankly to Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>I think these two sentences read better as one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are records, including an anecdote about Mitsukuni sending dogs&apos; fur to Tsunayoshi to protest against the Shorui Awaremi no Rei, showing that Mitsukuni spoke frankly to Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>そのため、光圀の物語水戸黄門の中では悪役を割り当てられてしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently Tsunayoshi plays an evil role in the story about Mitsukuni, &quot;Mito Komon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Tsunayoshi plays an evil role in &quot;Mito Komon,&quot; the story about Mitsukuni.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Tsunayoshi plays an evil role in &quot;Mito Komon,&quot; the story about Mitsukuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>また、光圀が大日本史を編纂し、綱吉が自ら易経を講じるなど、類似した方向性を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally they had similar tastes, for example Mitsukuni compiled &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great History of Japan) and Tsunayoshi gave lectures on &quot;I Ching&quot; (The Book of Changes).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, they had similar tastes, for example Mitsukuni compiled &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great History of Japan) and Tsunayoshi gave lectures on the &quot;I Ching.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, they had similar tastes, for example Mitsukuni compiled &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great History of Japan) and Tsunayoshi gave lectures on the &quot;I Ching.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>そのため、水戸黄門ファンの中には、黄門を持ち上げるためにことさらに綱吉をけなすという風潮もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore some fans of Mito Komon have a tendency to unnecessarily disparage Tsunayoshi in order to flatter Komon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, some fans of Mito Komon have a tendency to unnecessarily disparage Tsunayoshi in order to flatter Komon.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, some fans of Mito Komon have a tendency to unnecessarily disparage Tsunayoshi in order to flatter Komon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="107">
<j>綱吉再評価に関する文献として、代表的で入手が容易なものとして、吉川弘文館『徳川綱吉』（塚本学・1998年）、文春新書『黄門さまと犬公方』（山室恭子・1998年 ISBN 4-16-660010-9）が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA&quot; (Manabu TSUKAMOTO, 1998, published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan) and &quot;Komon and the Dog Shogun&quot; (Kyoko YAMAMURO, 1998, published by Bunshun Shinsho, ISBN 4-16-660010-9) can be mentioned as representative and readily available literature on the re-evaluation of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tokugawa Tsunayoshi&quot; (Manabu TSUKAMOTO, 1998, published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan) and &quot;Komon-sama to Inu-Kubo&quot; (Kyoko YAMAMURO, 1998, published by Bunshun Shinsho, ISBN 4-16-660010-9) are easy to obtain examples of works on Tsunayoshi&apos;s re-evaluation.</e>
<cmt>*Since the publisher and ISBN number are given, I think the Japanese title is better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tokugawa Tsunayoshi&quot; (Manabu TSUKAMOTO, 1998, published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan) and &quot;Komon-sama to Inu-Kubo&quot; (Kyoko YAMAMURO, 1998, published by Bunshun Shinsho, ISBN 4-16-660010-9) are easy to obtain examples of works on Tsunayoshi&apos;s re-evaluation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>また、2004年12月28日にフジテレビ系列で放送されたドラマ「徳川綱吉 イヌと呼ばれた男」も、この再評価に連なる系列のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also a TV drama aired on the Fuji TV network on December 28, 2004 &quot;Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA - man called a dog&quot; is in line with this movement of re-evaluation of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, a TV drama aired on the Fuji TV network on December 28, 2004, &quot;Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA - a man called dog&quot; is in line with this movement of the re-evaluation of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity but I wonder if the name of the TV show shouldn&apos;t be kept in Japanese.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, a TV drama aired on the Fuji TV network on December 28, 2004, &apos;Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA - a man called dog&apos; is in line with this movement of the re-evaluation of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>井沢元彦も「逆説の日本史」中で、非常に高く評価している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohiko IZAWA also rates him very highly in his book &quot;Gyakusetsu no Nihonshi&quot; (Paradoxical Japanese History).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohiko IZAWA also rates him very highly in his book &quot;Gyakusetsu no Nihonshi&quot; (Paradoxical Japanese History).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohiko IZAWA also rates him very highly in his book &apos;Gyakusetsu no Nihonshi&apos; (Paradoxical Japanese History).</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>綱吉と能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi and Noh</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi and Noh</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi and Noh (traditional masked dance-drama)</e>
<cmt>｢能」を用語集の通りに修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="110">
<j>家康以来、代々の将軍は能を愛好してきたが、綱吉はその中でも「能狂」と言われるほどの執着を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Ieyasu, successive shoguns liked Noh and Tsunayoshi especially showed a deep attachment to it; so much so that he was called &apos;Noh crazy&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Ieyasu onwards, the shoguns appreciated Noh, especially Tsunayoshi, who had such a deep attachment to it that he was called &apos;Noh crazy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Ieyasu onwards, the shoguns appreciated Noh, especially Tsunayoshi, who had such a deep attachment to it that he was called &apos;Noh crazy.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>綱吉の能狂の特徴として、能楽研究者の表章は以下の5点を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akira OMOTE, a researcher of Nogaku (the art of Noh), cites the following five points to characteristically show Tsunayoshi&apos;s affection for Noh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akira OMOTE, a researcher of Nogaku (the art of Noh), cites the following five characteristics of Tsunayoshi&apos;s affection for Noh.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akira OMOTE, a researcher of Nogaku (the art of Noh), cites the following five characteristics of Tsunayoshi&apos;s affection for Noh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="112">
<j>自ら能を舞い、それを人に見せることを好んだこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Performing Noh plays for himself and being happy to show his performance to others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Performing Noh plays himself and being happy to show his performance to others.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Performing Noh plays himself and being happy to show his performance to others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="113">
<j>側近・諸大名に能を舞うことを強制したこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forcing his close advisors and daimyo (feudal lords) to perform Noh plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forcing his close advisors and the daimyo to perform Noh plays.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forcing his close advisors and the daimyo to perform Noh plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="114">
<j>能役者の追放・登用、また流派を超えての移籍などを繰り返したこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repeatedly ousting and appointing Noh performers, and also trading them regardless of their school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Repeatedly ousting and appointing Noh performers, and moving them from school to school.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Repeatedly ousting and appointing Noh performers, and moving them from school to school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="115">
<j>能役者を士分に取り立てたこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Promoting Noh performers to the class of samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Promoting Noh performers to the class of samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Promoting Noh performers to the class of samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="116">
<j>稀曲・珍曲を見ることを好んで、廃曲となっていたものをも多く復活させたこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Liking to watch rare, uncommon plays and even reviving many abandoned plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fondness for rare and unusual plays and even reviving many abandoned plays.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fondness for rare and unusual plays and even reviving many abandoned plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="117">
<j>まず1については、将軍就任後間もない延宝9年2月、桂昌院のために催した能で、自ら「船弁慶」、「猩々 (能)」を舞うなど、早い時期から見られる傾向である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the first point, in March 1681 not long after the inauguration of the shogun, Tsunayoshi performed &apos;Funabenkei&apos; and &apos;Shojo&apos; in the Noh held for Keishoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the first point, this was a tendency that can be seen early on in his reign, for example, in March 1681, not long after his inauguration as shogun, Tsunayoshi performed &apos;Funabenkei&apos; and &apos;Shojo&apos; in the Noh held for Keishoin.</e>
<cmt>I think these two sentences read better as one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the first point, this was a tendency that can be seen early on in his reign, for example, in March 1681, not long after his inauguration as shogun, Tsunayoshi performed &apos;Funabenkei&apos; and &apos;Shojo&apos; in the Noh held for Keishoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>これは年を追うごとに頻度を増し、江戸城内のみならず、寵臣邸や寺社へ赴く際には、儒学の講義に続いて綱吉が能を舞うことが常であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It became more frequent year by year and Tsunayoshi always performed Noh plays following the lecture of Confucianism not only in the Edo-jo Castle but also when he visited his favorite retainers&apos; residences, temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It became more frequent year by year and Tsunayoshi always performed Noh plays following his lectures on Confucianism not only in Edo-jo Castle, but also when he visited his favorite retainers&apos; residences, temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became more frequent year by year and Tsunayoshi always performed Noh plays following his lectures on Confucianism not only in Edo-jo Castle, but also when he visited his favorite retainers&apos; residences, temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>元禄10年には71番の能、150番以上の舞囃子を舞っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1697 he performed 71 Noh plays and danced more than 150 Maibayashi (dance performance accompanied by music).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1697, he performed 71 Noh plays and danced more than 150 Maibayashi (abbreviated Noh dances).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1697, he performed 71 Noh plays and danced more than 150 Maibayashi (abbreviated Noh dances).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>諸大名や公家もまた、追従としてその拙い能を所望せねばならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently daimyo and kuge (court nobles) had to flatter him by requesting his poor Noh performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, daimyo and kuge (court nobles) had to request his inept Noh performances to flatter him.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, daimyo and kuge (court nobles) had to request his inept Noh performances to flatter him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="121">
<j>2についても、将軍就任当初から小姓に能を舞わせるなどしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the second point, Tsunayoshi had been forcing his pages to perform since the beginning of his inauguration of the shogun post.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the second point, Tsunayoshi had forced his pages to perform he was inaugurated as shogun.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the second point, Tsunayoshi had forced his pages to perform he was inaugurated as shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>しかし、後には側近ばかりか大大名にもこれを強制した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he even forced not only his close advisors but also daidaimyo (feudal lords having a greater stipend) to do so.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he even forced not only his close advisors but also the more powerful daimyo to perform.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he even forced not only his close advisors but also the more powerful daimyo to perform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>貞享3年4月、徳川綱教・前田綱紀・徳川光友・徳川綱豊・徳川光貞・徳川光圀・徳川綱誠・徳川綱条といった御三家・前田氏による能が催されているのがその好例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One good example of this is a Noh performance held by members of Gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa clan) and the Maeda clan such as Tsunanori TOKUGAWA, Tsunanori MAEDA, Mitsutomo TOKUGAWA, Tsunatoyo TOKUGAWA, Mitsusada TOKUGAWA, Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, Tsunanari TOKUGAWA, and Tsunaeda TOKUGAWA in May 1686.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One good example of this is a Noh performance held by members of Gosanke (the three branches of the Tokugawa Clan) and the Maeda Clan such as Tsunanori TOKUGAWA, Tsunanori MAEDA, Mitsutomo TOKUGAWA, Tsunatoyo TOKUGAWA, Mitsusada TOKUGAWA, Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, Tsunanari TOKUGAWA, and Tsunaeda TOKUGAWA in May 1686.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One good example of this is a Noh performance held by members of Gosanke (the three branches of the Tokugawa Clan) and the Maeda Clan such as Tsunanori TOKUGAWA, Tsunanori MAEDA, Mitsutomo TOKUGAWA, Tsunatoyo TOKUGAWA, Mitsusada TOKUGAWA, Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, Tsunanari TOKUGAWA, and Tsunaeda TOKUGAWA in May 1686.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>この場合も彼らは直前になって綱吉の命を受け、慌てて稽古をせねばならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, as with the others, they had to rush into the practice following the last minute order of Tsunayoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, as with the others, they had to rush through practice following Tsunayoshi&apos;s last minute order.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, as with the others, they had to rush through practice following Tsunayoshi&apos;s last minute order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>綱吉が宝生流を好んだため、諸大名も宝生流を取り立てたことが、現在まで加賀などで宝生流が盛んな一因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi preferred the Hosho school, and consequently daimyo also favored this school, which is one of the reasons that the Hosho school has thrived up to the present day in Kaga region and elsewhere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi preferred the Hosho school, and consequently daimyo also favored this school, which is one of the reasons why the Hosho school has thrived up to the present day in the Kaga region and elsewhere.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi preferred the Hosho school, and consequently daimyo also favored this school, which is one of the reasons why the Hosho school has thrived up to the present day in the Kaga region and elsewhere.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="126">
<j>3の例となるのは、宝生大夫による「道成寺」の小鼓を打つことを命じられた観世流小鼓方当主・観世新九郎が、流派が違うことを理由にこれを拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exemplifying the third point Tsunayoshi ordered Shinkuro KANZE, who was the family head of kotsuzumi-kata (family in charge of small hand drum) of Kanze school, to play the drum for &quot;Dojo-ji Temple&quot; performed by Hoshodayu (top performer of Hosho school), but Shinkuro refused because he belonged to a different school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exemplifying the third point, Tsunayoshi ordered Shinkuro KANZE, who was the head of the family in charge of the small hand drum of the Kanze school, to play the drum in &quot;Dojo-ji Temple,&quot; performed by the leading actors of the Hosho school, but Shinkuro refused because he belonged to a different school.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exemplifying the third point, Tsunayoshi ordered Shinkuro KANZE, who was the head of the family in charge of the small hand drum of the Kanze school, to play the drum in &apos;Dojo-ji Temple,&apos; performed by the leading actors of the Hosho school, but Shinkuro refused because he belonged to a different school.</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>これに対し、天和3年2月に新九郎父子を追放、翌3月、宝生座に移籍させ姓まで宝生に返させて呼び戻した一件がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reacting to this, in February 1683 Tsunayoshi banished Shinkuro and his son and the following March forced them to transfer to Hosho-za group and even to transfer their family name before summoning them back.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, in February 1683, Tsunayoshi banished Shinkuro and his son and, the following March, forced them to transfer to Hosho-za company and even to change their family name to Hosho before summoning them back.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, in February 1683, Tsunayoshi banished Shinkuro and his son and, the following March, forced them to transfer to Hosho-za company and even to change their family name to Hosho before summoning them back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>他にも甲府時代のお抱え役者の登用、さらに貞享3年には喜多流三世喜多七太夫を追放し、喜多座を解体するという「能界を震撼させる大事件」を起こしている（翌年赦免）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally Tsunayoshi raised an in-house performer, who was hired in his Kofu district period, and further in 1686 he caused a big incident by banishing Shichidayu KITA III of Kita school and dissolving Kita-za group which &apos;shook the Noh industry&apos; (pardoned the following year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Tsunayoshi promoted performers from his Kofu days and, in 1686, he caused a big incident by banishing Shichidayu KITA III of the Kita school and dissolving the Kita-za company, an act which &apos;shook the Noh world&apos; (he was pardoned the following year).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Tsunayoshi promoted performers from his Kofu days and, in 1686, he caused a big incident by banishing Shichidayu KITA III of the Kita school and dissolving the Kita-za company, an act which &apos;shook the Noh world&apos; (he was pardoned the following year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="129">
<j>4については、『徳川実紀』にも批判する文章が載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the forth point, the text criticizing it is in &quot;Tokugawa Jikki&quot; (The True Tokugawa Records).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the fourth point, the section criticizing it is in &quot;Tokugawa Jikki&quot; (The True Tokugawa Records).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the fourth point, the section criticizing it is in &quot;Tokugawa Jikki&quot; (The True Tokugawa Records).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>士分に取り立てられた役者は、特に貞享以後はこのために新設された廊下番のポストにつけられて表向き能役者を廃業し、綱吉が城中で私的に催す能に出演させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Performers promoted to samurai were, especially in and after the Jokyo era, conferred the newly set post of rokaban (a kind of officer in the Edo-jo Castle) and officially retired from the stage but were made to perform Noh plays privately held by Tsunayoshi in the Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Performers promoted to samurai were, especially in and after the Jokyo era, conferred the newly-created post of rokaban (a kind of officer in Edo-jo Castle) and officially retired from the stage but were made to perform Noh plays privately held by Tsunayoshi in the castle.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Performers promoted to samurai were, especially in and after the Jokyo era, conferred the newly-created post of rokaban (a kind of officer in Edo-jo Castle) and officially retired from the stage but were made to perform Noh plays privately held by Tsunayoshi in the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>当初は能流派以外の役者を士分としていたが、次第に諸座の大夫・家元クラスがその対象となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning performers who didn&apos;t belong to the main Noh schools were promoted to the samurai class, but gradually performers of tayu and iemoto (head or chief) classes of each school were targeted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning, the performers promoted were those who didn&apos;t belong to the main Noh schools, but gradually leading actors and the heads of each company were targeted.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning, the performers promoted were those who didn&apos;t belong to the main Noh schools, but gradually leading actors and the heads of each company were targeted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>これを断ればやはり追放が待っており、当主・後継者を奪われた各家は大きく混乱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Turning down the offer of course ends up with punishment and the families of several schools which were robbed of their chief or successor were hugely disrupted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course, turning down the offer resulted in punishment and several families who lost their head or successor were hugely disrupted.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course, turning down the offer resulted in punishment and several families who lost their head or successor were hugely disrupted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>特に大夫を2度に渡って取り立てられた喜多座では、分家の権左衛門家が断絶を余儀なくされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in Kita school, where two tayu were promoted, one of its branch families - the Gonzaemon family - was forced to disband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the Kita-za company, where two leading actors were promoted, one of its branch families, the Gonzaemon family, was forced to disband.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the Kita-za company, where two leading actors were promoted, one of its branch families, the Gonzaemon family, was forced to disband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>登用された役者たちは、三世喜多七太夫宗能改め中条直景のように九百石取りにまで出世するものもいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the performers who were promoted highly, such as Naokage NAKAJO (transformed from Shichidayu KITA III, Sono), received 900 koku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the promoted performers, such as Naokage NAKAJO (whose stage name was Shichidayu KITA III, Sono), received 900 koku.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the promoted performers, such as Naokage NAKAJO whose stage name was Shichidayu Muneyoshi KITA III, received 900 koku.</e>
<cmt>括弧を除き、名前の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>しかし、五世喜多七太夫恒能のように綱吉の男色の相手を断り切腹させられるなど、多くは過酷な運命をたどることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However many of them suffered a severe fate, including Shichidayu KITA IV, Kono, who refused to play a homosexual partner for Tsunayoshi and was forced to commit suicide by disembowelment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処恒能：読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many of them suffered a harsher fate, such as Shichidayu KITA IV, Kono, who refused to play a homosexual partner for Tsunayoshi and was forced to commit suicide by disembowelment.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many of them suffered a harsher fate, such as Shichidayu Kono KITA IV, who refused to play a homosexual partner for Tsunayoshi and was forced to commit suicide by disembowelment.</e>
<cmt>IV→V、名前の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="136">
<j>5であるが、綱吉は日頃演じられない珍しい曲を観ることを好み、廃絶されていた古曲を積極的に復曲させて上演させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the fifth point, Tsunayoshi liked to see rare pieces which were not usually performed, and willingly revived and performed old plays which had been abandoned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the fifth point, Tsunayoshi liked to see rare pieces which were not usually performed, and willingly revived and performed old plays which had been abandoned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the fifth point, Tsunayoshi liked to see rare pieces which were not usually performed, and willingly revived and performed old plays which had been abandoned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>それまで長く演じられなかったにもかかわらず、綱吉の時代に復活した曲は実に41番にも及ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As many as 41 plays were revived in the time of Tsunayoshi even though they hadn&apos;t been performed for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As many as 41 plays that hadn&apos;t been performed for a long time were revived during Tsunayoshi&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As many as 41 plays that hadn&apos;t been performed for a long time were revived during Tsunayoshi&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>もっともこれも、6日ほど前に急に命じられ、慌てて間に合わせたものがほとんどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However most of them were revived in a hurry to be able to be completed in time after the performers received sudden orders about six days before the performance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the performers received sudden orders about six days before the performance, most of the plays were revived in a hurry.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the performers received sudden orders about six days before the performance, most of the plays were revived in a hurry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>そのうち20番は現在まで各流派で演じられており、中には「雨月」・「大原御幸」・「蝉丸 (能)」など現在でも高く評価されている曲が含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">20 of these revived plays have been performed by each school until the present day including &quot;Ugetsu&quot; (Rain and the Moon), &quot;Ohara Goko&quot; (Visiting Ohara) and &quot;Semimaru&quot; (Prince Semimaru), which are highly evaluated even to this day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">20 of these revived plays have been performed by each school until the present day, including &quot;Ugetsu&quot; (Rain and the Moon), &quot;Ohara Goko&quot; (Visiting Ohara) and &quot;Semimaru&quot; (Prince Semimaru), which are highly regarded even to this day.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">20 of these revived plays have been performed by each school until the present day, including &apos;Ugetsu&apos; (Rain and the Moon), &apos;Ohara Goko&apos; (Visiting Ohara) and &apos;Semimaru&apos; (Prince Semimaru), which are highly regarded even to this day.</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>同様の傾向のあった家宣による復曲と合わせ、「怪我の功名」ながら、これは後世に残る業績となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with the revived pieces by Ienobu, who had the same tendency as Tsunayoshi, these revived Noh plays are considered to be a great lasting achievement although resulting from retainers&apos; misfortune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with the pieces revived by Ienobu, who was similarly inclined, these Noh plays are considered to be great lasting achievements, notwithstanding the fact they were &quot;something good coming from something bad.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with the pieces revived by Ienobu, who was similarly inclined, these Noh plays are considered to be great lasting achievements, notwithstanding the fact they were &quot;something good coming from something bad.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="141">
<j>生類憐れみの令により民を苦しめたとの説により有名な綱吉であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi is notorious for plaguing the public with Shorui Awaremi no Rei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi is notorious for burdening the public with the Shorui Awaremi no Rei.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi is notorious for burdening the public with the Shorui Awaremi no Rei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>しかし、まだ将軍宣下を受ける前から天領の代官たちに対し諭したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it is said that Tsunayoshi admonished local governors in tenryo (shogunal demesnes) before receiving the Imperial appointment to shogun, saying as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処&quot;諭したとされる&quot;は本来「」の後にありますが、「」内が長文になるため最初に訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that Tsunayoshi was already warning local governors in shogunal fiefs even before being proclaimed shogun by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that Tsunayoshi was already warning local governors in shogunal fiefs even before being proclaimed shogun by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>｢天領」を用語集の通りに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>「支配者が寛やかに民を扱うと、民は奢りに走り本業を怠る。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;If a ruler treats his people leniently they will indulge in luxury and neglect their primary role.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;If a ruler treats his people leniently, they will indulge in luxury and neglect their primary role.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a ruler treats his people leniently they will indulge in luxury and neglect their primary role.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>「奢侈を許してはいけない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Do not allow them luxury.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Do not allow them luxury.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Do not allow them luxury.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>「民は為政者を信用していない 為政者もまた民を疑っている このようなことが起こらないように意思の疎通に心がけよ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Try and communicate well with your people to avoid the situation that the public don&apos;t trust statesman and the statesman is doubtful about the public.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Try and communicate well with your people to avoid a situation where the public don&apos;t trust statesmen and statesmen are doubtful about the public.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Try and communicate well with your people to avoid a situation where the public don&apos;t trust statesmen and statesmen are doubtful about the public.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>「代官等は率先して身を慎み、職務をよく理解し、年貢の収納に努め、下役に任せ切りにせず、自らが先に立って職務に精励することが肝要である。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is important for local governors to be the first to abstain from extravagance, clearly understand their own duty, make an effort to collect and pay nengu (land tax), not to leave their duties completely to subordinates, and to take the lead in working hard on their duties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is important for local governors to be the first to abstain from extravagance, to clearly understand their own duty, to make an effort to collect and pay land tax, not to leave their duties completely to subordinates, and to take the lead in working hard on their duties.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is important for local governors to be the first to abstain from extravagance, to clearly understand their own duty, to make an effort to collect and pay land tax, not to leave their duties completely to subordinates, and to take the lead in working hard on their duties.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="147">
<j>生類憐みの令や福祉政策が目立つ綱吉であるが。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s prominent achievements are Shorui Awaremi no Rei and welfare policies.</e>
<cmt>文章が中途で終わっているように見えます。現在のWikiのページに、相当する部分がないようなのですが、一応一文として訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s prominent achievements are the Shorui Awaremi no Rei and welfare policies.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s prominent achievements are the Shorui Awaremi no Rei and welfare policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="148">
<j>「大樹寺に収められている歴代将軍の位牌は、将軍の身長にあわせて作られている」という説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a belief that the height of the mortuary tablets of the shoguns, which are kept in Daiju-ji Temple, is based on their body height.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a belief that the height of the shoguns&apos; mortuary tablets, which are kept in Daiju-ji Temple, is based on how tall they were.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a belief that the height of the shoguns&apos; mortuary tablets, which are kept in Daiju-ji Temple, is based on how tall they were.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>そこから「身長が130センチ強しかなかった」という『内分泌学説』が出てきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this opinion, some propose the theory that Tsunayoshi was only a little more than 130 centimeter tall because of an internal secretion disorder.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this opinion, there is a theory that Tsunayoshi was only a little more than 130 centimeters tall because of a hormone disorder.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this opinion, there is a theory that Tsunayoshi was only a little more than 130 centimeters tall because of a hormone disorder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>綱吉の位牌の高さは124センチである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The height of Tsunayoshi&apos;s mortuary tablet is 124 centimeters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The height of Tsunayoshi&apos;s mortuary tablet is 124 centimeters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The height of Tsunayoshi&apos;s mortuary tablet is 124 centimeters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>増上寺に葬られ改葬の際に遺骨の身長が計測された5人の将軍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cremains of five shoguns who were buried in Zojo-ji Temple were measured when they were reburied.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remains of five shoguns who were buried in Zojo-ji Temple were measured when they were reburied.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remains of five shoguns who were buried in Zojo-ji Temple were measured when they were reburied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>5人の将軍については遺骨と位牌のサイズの差は5センチ以内に収まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The difference in the length between their cremains and the mortuary tables was all within five centimeters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The differences in the length between their remains and the mortuary tables were all within five centimeters.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The differences in the length between their remains and the mortuary tables were all within five centimeters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>綱吉は低身長症（軟骨無形成症）であったことが考えられる、という説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This fact leads to the opinion that Tsunayoshi had a short stature (achondrogenesis).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This fact has led to the opinion that Tsunayoshi was of short stature (achondrogenesis).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This fact has led to the opinion that Tsunayoshi was of short stature (achondrogenesis).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="154">
<j>「七五三」は徳松の健康を願ったのが始まりの一つとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One opinion about the origin of &quot;Shichi-go-san&quot; (a day of prayer for the healthy growth of young children) is that it was started to hope for the health of Tsunayoshi&apos;s child, Tokumatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One opinion about the origin of &quot;Shichi-go-san&quot; (a day of prayer for the healthy growth of young children) is that it was started to pray for the health of Tsunayoshi&apos;s child, Tokumatsu.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One opinion about the origin of &apos;Shichi-go-san&apos; (a day of prayer for the healthy growth of young children) is that it was started to pray for the health of Tsunayoshi&apos;s child, Tokumatsu.</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>しかし、その当の徳松が夭折したのは何とも皮肉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However ironically enough, Tokumatsu himself died young.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, ironically enough, Tokumatsu himself died young.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, ironically enough, Tokumatsu himself died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="156">
<j>たいへんな猿楽（能）好きであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was a big fan of sarugaku noh (a form of theatre popular during the 11th to 14th centuries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi was a big fan of sarugaku Noh (a form of theatre popular during the 11th to 14th centuries).</e>
<cmt>Capital letter</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi was a big fan of sarugaku Noh (a form of theatre popular during the 11th to 14th centuries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>例えば元禄4年3月22日（1691年）に初めて神田橋門の柳沢吉保邸に行った際自ら五番舞った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Tsunayoshi himself performed five sarugaku plays when he first visited the residence of Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA in Kandabashi-mon Gate on April 20, 1691.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Tsunayoshi himself performed five sarugaku plays when he first visited Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA&apos;s residence at the Kandabashi-mon Gate on April 20, 1691.</e>
<cmt>*Left dates in the Gregorian calendar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Tsunayoshi himself performed five sarugaku plays when he first visited Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA&apos;s residence at the Kandabashi-mon Gate on April 20, 1691.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>以降、宝永5年10月5日（1708年）まで（計58回）柳沢邸で能曲を楽しんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then Tsunayoshi enjoyed Noh performances in Yanagisawa&apos;s residence a total of 58 times until November 16, 1708.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Tsunayoshi enjoyed Noh performances in Yanagisawa&apos;s residence a total of 58 times until November 16, 1708.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Tsunayoshi enjoyed Noh performances in Yanagisawa&apos;s residence a total of 58 times until November 16, 1708.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="159">
<j>『三王外記』には、娘・安を犯された牧野成貞は、自身の代で牧野家を断絶させると言ったと書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Sanno Gaiki&quot; (The Secret History of the Three Rulers) it is written that Narisada MAKINO, whose daughter Yasu was raped by Tsunayoshi, said he would wipe out the Makino family in his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Sanno Gaiki&quot; (The Secret History of the Three Rulers) it is written that Narisada MAKINO, whose daughter Yasu was raped by Tsunayoshi, said he would wipe out the Makino family in his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Sanno Gaiki&quot; (The Secret History of the Three Rulers) it is written that Narisada MAKINO, whose daughter Yasu was raped by Tsunayoshi, said he would wipe out the Makino family in his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>更にこれを敷衍した三田村鳶魚は、牧野成貞の妻・阿久里までも綱吉に献上されたとさえ言い、綱吉を罵った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further Engyo MITAMURA expanded the story to say even Narisada MAKINO&apos;s wife, Aguri was given to Tsunayoshi and vilified him for this.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Engyo MITAMURA elaborated on this to say even Narisada MAKINO&apos;s wife, Aguri, was given to Tsunayoshi and vilified him for this.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Engyo MITAMURA elaborated on this to say even Narisada MAKINO&apos;s wife, Aguri, was given to Tsunayoshi and vilified him for this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>池波正太郎がこれを小説化したため人口に膾炙している説であるが、『三王外記』そのものの史料価値が現在では疑われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is widely known as Shotaro IKENAMI wrote a novel about the story but currently the value of &quot;Sanno Gaiki&quot; itself as a historical material is questionable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became widely known due to Shotaro IKENAMI&apos;s novel based on the story, but currently the value of &quot;Sanno Gaiki&quot; itself as a historical material is questionable.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became widely known due to Shotaro IKENAMI&apos;s novel based on the story, but currently the value of &quot;Sanno Gaiki&quot; itself as a historical material is questionable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="162">
<j>俗説ではあるが、柳沢吉保が送り込んだ女と綱吉が交合中に「吉保に甲斐一国を与える」と確約した（綱吉の死によって反故になる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is popularly believed that Tsunayoshi confirmed that he would give Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA the whole province of Kai while having intercourse with a woman whom Yoshiyasu sent (although the promise was broken due to Tsunayoshi&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is popularly believed that Tsunayoshi, while having intercourse with a woman sent by Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA, promised to give Yoshiyasu the whole province of Kai (although this was voided by Tsunayoshi&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is popularly believed that Tsunayoshi, while having intercourse with a woman sent by Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA, promised to give Yoshiyasu the whole province of Kai (although this was voided by Tsunayoshi&apos;s death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>このことから、以後将軍が女人と交合する時には、屏風の後ろに監“聴”役二人を置き、二人の証言が一致し御年寄（大奥の最高権力者）が承認するまで徹底的に話し合ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that since this incident, two people to keep a close ear on it were put behind a screen when a shogun has intercourse with a woman and thorough discussion was held until these two people&apos;s testimonies were consistent with each other and the person in paramount authority in Ooku (the inner halls of the Edo-jo Castle where the wife and concubines of the Shogun and their servants resided) called Otoshiyori approved it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that because of this incident, two people were stationed behind a screen to listen carefully when the shogun was having intercourse with a woman and thorough discussions held until the Otoshiyori (the most powerful person in the shogun&apos;s harem) acknowledged that their testimonies agreed.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that because of this incident, two people were stationed behind a screen to listen carefully when the shogun was having intercourse with a woman and thorough discussions held until the Otoshiyori (the most powerful person in the shogun&apos;s harem) acknowledged that their testimonies agreed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>（御台所には監聴は付かなかったとされる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that hearing witnesses were not used for a legitimate wife of a shogun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（）は除いて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that these &quot;hearing witnesses&quot; were not used for the shogun&apos;s legitimate wife.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is believed that hearing witnesses were not used for a legitimate wife of a shogun.)</e>
<cmt>括弧を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>更に異説として、綱吉は当時の男性の多くと同様に少年愛日本をたしなみ、吉保に命じて少年を送り込ませ男色を楽しんだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further it is believed that Tsunayoshi had a taste for homosexual relationships with boys, ordering Yoshiyasu to send them, and enjoyed intercourse with them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also an opinion that Tsunayoshi, like many men of his time, practiced pederasty and ordered Yoshiyasu to bring young boys to him for his pleasure.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also an opinion that Tsunayoshi, like many men of his time, practiced pederasty and ordered Yoshiyasu to bring young boys to him for his pleasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>（大河ドラマ「八代将軍吉宗」では綱吉の男色好みを彷彿とさせるシーンが随所に登場した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the taiga (literally big river) drama &quot;The Eighth Shogun Yoshimune,&quot; there were many scenes suggesting Tsunayoshi&apos;s homosexuality.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（）は除いて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the historical drama &quot;The Eighth Shogun, Yoshimune,&quot; there were many scenes suggesting Tsunayoshi&apos;s homosexuality.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In the historical drama &apos;The Eighth Shogun, Yoshimune,&apos; there were many scenes suggesting Tsunayoshi&apos;s homosexuality.)</e>
<cmt>括弧を加え、クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="167">
<j>将軍職に就いて、まだ日も浅い頃、4代将軍家綱の治世に決着がついていた越前松平家のお家騒動について、当事者の小栗美作と永見大蔵を呼び寄せた上で綱吉自身が家綱の決定を覆す採決をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after Tsunayoshi was inaugurated as shogun, he summoned the parties involved in the family feud of the Echizen Matsudaira family, Mimasaka OGURI and Okura NAGAMI, although the dispute had already been settled in the reign of the forth shogun, Ietsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after Tsunayoshi was inaugurated as shogun, he summoned the parties involved in the Echizen Matsudaira family feud, Mimasaka OGURI and Okura NAGAMI, and although the dispute had already been settled during the rule of the fourth shogun, Ietsuna, and Tsunayoshi reversed Ietsuna&apos;s verdict.</e>
<cmt>I think these two sentences read better as one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after Tsunayoshi was inaugurated as shogun, he summoned the parties involved in the Echizen Matsudaira family feud, Mimasaka OGURI and Okura NAGAMI, and although the dispute had already been settled during the rule of the fourth shogun, Ietsuna, and Tsunayoshi reversed Ietsuna&apos;s verdict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>すなわち、松平光長は領地没収、小栗美作父子に切腹を命じ、永見大蔵に島流しと決定したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, he decided to confiscate the feudal land of Mitsunaga MATSUDAIRA, ordered Mimasaka OGURI father and son to commit suicide by disembowelment, and sentenced Okura NAGAMI. to banishment to an island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, he decided to confiscate Mitsunaga MATSUDAIRA&apos;s land, ordered Mimasaka OGURI and his son to commit seppuku, and banished Okura NAGAMI to an island.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, he decided to confiscate Mitsunaga MATSUDAIRA&apos;s land, ordered Mimasaka OGURI and his son to commit seppuku, and banished Okura NAGAMI to an island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>このとき、老中の堀田正俊が決定を言い渡した後、綱吉は「これにて決裁す、はやまかり立て」と大音声で言ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Tsunayoshi said in a thunderous voice after a roju (senior councilor), Masatoshi HOTTA had announced the sentences, &quot;Now the case is closed. Get out right now.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the roju Masatoshi HOTTA had announced the sentences, Tsunayoshi said in a thunderous voice, &quot;Now the case is closed. Get out right now.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the roju Masatoshi HOTTA had announced the sentences, Tsunayoshi said in a thunderous voice, &quot;Now the case is closed. Get out right now.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Sat666(id:127263), Bletchingly(id:21356), Nnh(id:474), Ojigiri(id:329), DragonBot(id:161936), Cprobot(id:97843), Lupinoid(id:68), 飲んでも飲まれるな(id:120588), Tribot(id:186681), Alex K(id:86829), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), 代言人(id:33675), IwaimBot(id:190695), Tamago915(id:11009), 百楽天(id:5266), 麦塚ほとり(id:54917), Maakun(id:16735), Kzhr(id:131), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Tosiho(id:73924), つね(id:123605), Carbuncle(id:346), たね(id:10372), Project(id:11782), 松茸(id:27535), Tomos(id:10), Seibuabina(id:37532), Viamedia(id:109883), 前図書頭(id:134750), YukkeBot(id:251107), Kagetudo(id:163875), はるひ(id:59079), 彩華1226(id:64711), Sanmari(id:1707), Xqbot(id:273540), Tietew(id:4054), 博物学博士(id:33603), Nekosuki600(id:21263), N7a-n7a(id:133436), Richknight(id:141069), Suisui(id:69), 立志堂(id:132177), 小太刀(id:18154), ちょーばみ(id:194335), Omaemona1982(id:298245), Reggaeman(id:6214), ブリキの太鼓叩き(id:3586), Charenji(id:7908), Doskoi 8(id:1070), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Rai koku(id:1661), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Johncapistrano(id:969), Hhst(id:13720), DNCAL(id:120593), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 下総大納言(id:43461), UMBRO(id:100484), Loveless(id:129239), Chobot(id:20846), こぶまき(id:38278), YOUJI(id:172173), LERK(id:4460), Izayohi(id:13095), やりたこ(id:113528), Aifjiofjioejafaewra(id:189619), 水野白楓(id:22811), Soulbot(id:72267), Carkuni(id:79281), 鉈上じゃ乱(id:193027), VolkovBot(id:105371), Touryuuuan(id:89696), Miya.m(id:4662), きまま(id:183217), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>