<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>洞院実世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saneyo TOIN</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saneyo TOIN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saneyo TOIN</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>洞院 実世（とういん さねよ、延慶 (日本)元年（1308年） - 正平 (日本)13年/延文3年8月19日 (旧暦)（1358年9月22日））は、南北朝時代 (日本)の南朝 (日本)に仕えた公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saneyo TOIN (1308-September 22, 1358) was a Court noble who served the Southern Court (Japan) in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saneyo TOIN (1308-September 22, 1358) was a Court noble who served the Southern Court (Japan) in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saneyo TOIN (1308-September 22, 1358) was a Court noble who served the Southern Court (Japan) in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は洞院公賢。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Kinkata TOIN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Kinkata TOIN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Kinkata TOIN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>洞院実夏の庶兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was illegitimate elder brother of Sanenatsu TOIN.</e>
<cmt>「庶兄」は、広辞苑、和英大辞典にも見当たらす、「庶子」を参考に訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the illegitimate elder brother of Sanenatsu TOIN.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the illegitimate elder brother of Sanenatsu TOIN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に洞院公行・近衛兼嗣母（実夏の養女となる）・尼尊悟・尼理摘がいる（『尊卑分脈』・『摂政家伝』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children included Kinko TOIN, mother of Kanetsugu KONOE (became an adopted daughter of Sanenatsu), 尼尊悟 and 尼理摘 (&quot;Sonpibunmyaku&quot;/&quot;Sesshokaden&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included Kinko TOIN, mother of Kanetsugu KONOE (became an adopted daughter of Sanenatsu), 尼尊悟 and 尼理摘 (&quot;Sonpibunmyaku&quot;/&quot;Sesshokaden&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included Kinko TOIN, mother of Kanetsugu KONOE (became an adopted daughter of Sanenatsu), 尼尊悟 and 尼理摘 (&quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy)/&quot;Sesshokaden&quot;).</e>
<cmt>尊卑分脈の定訳摂政家伝と日本語部分は不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「与喜左大臣」と呼ばれた（『新葉和歌集』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called &apos;Yoki no sadaijin&apos; (&quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; (Collection of New Pages).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called &apos;Yoki no sadaijin&apos; (&quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; (Collection of New Pages).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called &apos;Yoki no sadaijin&apos; (&quot;Shinyo Wakashu&quot; (Collection of New Pages).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>二条師基・北畠親房・四条隆資とともに南朝の重鎮として政務を指導した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He, as a leader of the Southern Court, administered affairs of state with Moromoto NIJO, Chikafusa KITABATAKE and Takasuke SHIJO.</e>
<cmt>「Southern Court (Japan)」の「(Japan)」はこれより省略いたします。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He, as a leader of the Southern Court, administered affairs of state with Moromoto NIJO, Chikafusa KITABATAKE, and Takasuke SHIJO.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He, as a leader of the Southern Court, administered affairs of state with Moromoto NIJO, Chikafusa KITABATAKE, and Takasuke SHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1358（正平13年/延文3）年8月19日、「水腫」のため南朝で死去（『園太暦』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died of hydrops in the Southern Court on August 19, 1358 (&quot;Entairyaku&quot;(Diary of Kinkata TOIN).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died of hydrops in the Southern Court on August 19, 1358 (&quot;Entairyaku&quot;(Diary of Kinkata TOIN)).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died of &apos;hydrops&apos; in the Southern Court on September 22, 1358 (&quot;Entairyaku&quot;(Diary of Kinkata TOIN)).</e>
<cmt>in の前のスペース短縮括弧に &apos; &apos;年月日、Ｂ４どおりに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>事績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>後醍醐天皇の側近として無礼講（破仏講）に参加する（『太平記』）など、早くから倒幕運動で指導的役割を務め、元弘の乱でも同じく倒幕を指揮したため六波羅探題に捕われ、まもなく官職を剥奪された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He, from early on, took the leadership role in the movement to overthrow the Shogunate including his participation in the unrestricted binge (unrestricted binge) as a close aide of Emperor Godaigo (&quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace)) and also led the overthrow of the Shogunate in the Genko War, and, thus, captured by the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) and shortly deprived of his government posts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From early on, he took a leadership role in the movement to overthrow the Shogunate, including his participation in the unrestricted binge (unrestricted binge) as a close aide of Emperor Godaigo (&quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace)) and also led the overthrow of the Shogunate in the Genko War, and, thus, shortly after being captured by the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) he was deprived of his government posts.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From early on, he took a leadership role in the movement to overthrow the Shogunate, including his participation in the unrestricted binge as a close aide of Emperor Godaigo (&quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace)) and also led the overthrow of the Shogunate in the Genko War, and, thus, shortly after being captured by the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) he was deprived of his government posts.</e>
<cmt>unrestricted binge (unrestricted binge)　同じなので括弧書きを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>加えて1332年（元弘2年/正慶元年）4月10日 (旧暦)には幕府の意向により父・公賢邸預かりの処分が下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, on April 10, 1332, with the intention of the Shogunate, he was penalized to become in custody of his father, Kinkata at his residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, on April 10, 1332, with the intention of the Shogunate, he was penalized to be put in the custody of his father, Kinkata at his residence.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, on April 10, 1332 (old calendar), with the intention of the Shogunate, he was penalized to be put in the custody of his father, Kinkata at his residence.</e>
<cmt>「旧暦」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>建武の新政が始まると本職に復帰し、1334年（建武元年）8月 (旧暦)、雑訴決断所二番（東海道を担当）に就任、政権の中枢幹部として威を振るった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He regained his government posts upon the start of the Kemmu Restoration, and in August 1334 assumed the office of Second Zasso-Ketsudansho (agency of Kemmu government to file lawsuits) (in charge of Tokai-do Road) and displayed his power as one of the top officials of the Government.</e>
<cmt>「建武」は、「Kemmu」で統一いたします（「Kenmu」ではなく）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He regained his government posts upon the start of the Kemmu Restoration, and in August 1334 assumed the office of Second Zasso-Ketsudansho (agency of Kemmu government to file lawsuits) (in charge of Tokai-do Road) and displayed his power as one of the top officials of the Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He regained his government posts upon the start of the Kenmu Restoration, and in August 1334 (old calendar) assumed the office of Second Zasso-Ketsudansho (agency of Kenmu government to file lawsuits) (in charge of Tokai-do Road) and displayed his power as one of the top officials of the Government.</e>
<cmt>「旧暦」　訳漏れ対応しました。Kemmu→Kenmu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>足利尊氏が関東地方において反旗を翻すと「大将軍」として東海道を進軍して戦う（『忽那家文書』）が、敗れて西走。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takauji ASHIKAGA rose in revolt in the Kanto region, he charged forward through Tokai-do Road and fought (&quot;Kutsuna Family&apos;s notes&quot;), but defeated and escaped to Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Takauji ASHIKAGA rose in revolt in the Kanto region, he charged forward through Tokai-do Road and fought (&quot;Kutsuna Family&apos;s notes&quot;), but was defeated and escaped to Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)).</e>
<cmt>added &quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Takauji ASHIKAGA rose in revolt in the Kanto region, he charged forward through Tokai-do Road and fought (&quot;Kutsuna Family&apos;s notes&quot;), but was defeated and escaped to Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天皇が山門に避難すると、二条師基とともに洛中に兵を進めて再び足利軍と戦うが、この時もまもなく撤退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Emperor Sanmon gate (temple gate) took refuge in the Sanmon gate (temple gate), he led troops into Rakuchu (inside the capital Kyoto) and fought against the Ashikaga side again, but shortly drew off this time also,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Emperor Sanmon gate (temple gate) took refuge in the Sanmon gate (temple gate), he led troops into Rakuchu (inside the capital Kyoto) and fought against the Ashikaga side again, but shortly drew off this time also,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Emperor took refuge in the Sanmon gate (temple gate), he led troops into Rakuchu (inside the capital Kyoto) and fought against the Ashikaga side again, but shortly drew off this time also,</e>
<cmt>初めの　Sanmon gate (temple gate)　削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天皇の京都還幸の際、密命を受けて恒良親王・新田義貞・脇屋義助らとともに北陸地方に赴き宮方の再挙を謀った（『神皇正統記』）が、ここでも戦況は芳しくなく、結局途中で戦地を離れて吉野に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of Kyoto Kanko (the Emperor coming back to Kyoto), he received a secret order, went to the Hokuriku District with Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi, Yoshisada NITTA and Yoshisuke WAKIYA and tried to find another chance for court&apos;s side (&quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns)), but, here again, the war situation was not favorable and eventually left the battlefield giving up halfway and entered into Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of Kyoto Kanko (the Emperor coming back to Kyoto), he received a secret order, went to the Hokuriku District with Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi, Yoshisada NITTA, and Yoshisuke WAKIYA and tried to find another chance for the court&apos;s side (&quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns)), but, here again, the war situation was not favorable and he eventually left the battlefield giving up halfway and entered Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of Kyoto Kanko (the Emperor coming back to Kyoto), he received a secret order, went to the Hokuriku region with Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi, Yoshisada NITTA, and Yoshisuke WAKIYA and tried to find another chance for the court&apos;s side (&quot;Jinno Shotoki&quot; (A Chronicle of Gods and Sovereigns)), but, here again, the war situation was not favorable and he eventually left the battlefield giving up halfway and entered Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>District→region</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>後村上天皇即位後は、親房・隆資とともに幼い新帝を支え南朝の柱石となる（『太平記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the enthronement of Emperor Gomurakami, he became a pillar of the Southern Court supporting the infant new emperor with Chikafusa and Takasuke (&quot;Taiheiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the enthronement of Emperor Gomurakami, he became a pillar of the Southern Court supporting the infant new emperor with Chikafusa and Takasuke (&quot;Taiheiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the enthronement of Emperor Gomurakami, he became a pillar of the Southern Court supporting the infant new emperor with Chikafusa and Takasuke (&quot;Taiheiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>実際、1349年（正平4年/貞和5年）秋には、伊賀国に入って現地の南朝方勢力を指導し（『阿蘇家文書』）、また1351年（正平6年/観応2年）頃にも九州への下向を命じられる（『阿蘇家文書』）など、縦横に活動している（ただし下向は結局中止となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He actually took such an active part as, in fall of 1349, he entered into the Iga Province where he trained the local Southern Court forces (&quot;Documents of the Aso family&quot;) and around 1351, he was ordered to go down to Kyushu (&quot;Documents of the Aso family&quot;) (but, eventually the going down to Kyushu was cancelled).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He actually took such an active part as, in fall of 1349, he entered Iga Province where he trained the local Southern Court forces (&quot;Documents of the Aso family&quot;) and around 1351, he was ordered to go down to Kyushu (&quot;Documents of the Aso family&quot;) (but, eventually his going down to Kyushu was cancelled).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He actually took such an active part as, in fall of 1349, he entered Iga Province where he trained the local Southern Court forces (&quot;Documents of the Aso family&quot;) and around 1351, he was ordered to go down to Kyushu (&quot;Documents of the Aso family&quot;) (but, eventually his going down to Kyushu was cancelled).</e>
<cmt>actually →in fact</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>正平の一統が成ると隆資とともに京都の統治をするのではないかという風聞も流れた（『園太暦』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the Shohei no itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts), a rumor went around that he would govern Kyoto with Takasuke (&quot;Entairyaku&quot;(Diary of Kinkata TOIN)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the Shohei no itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts), a rumor went around that he would govern Kyoto with Takasuke (&quot;Entairyaku&quot;(Diary of Kinkata TOIN)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the Shohei no itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts), a rumor went around that he would govern Kyoto with Takasuke (&quot;Entairyaku&quot;(Diary of Kinkata TOIN)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>男山の戦いにも従軍したが南朝軍は総崩れとなり、「子」（公行か?）とともに河内国東条に敗走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he went to the front in the Battle of Otokoyama, the Southern Court forces collapsed completely and he escaped down to Tojo, Kawachi Province with &apos;Son&apos; (Kinko?).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he went to the front in the Battle of Otokoyama, the Southern Court forces collapsed completely and he escaped to Tojo, Kawachi Province with &apos;Son&apos; (Kinko?).</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;down&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he went to the front in the Battle of Otokoyama, the Southern Court forces collapsed completely and he escaped to Tojo, Kawachi Province with &apos;Son&apos; (Kinko?).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>南朝の武者所の構成員であり（『壺井八幡及通法寺文書』。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a member of Mushadokoro (place where Samurai of guard of the Imperial Palace is staffed) of the Southern Court (&quot;壺井八幡及通法寺文書&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a member of Mushadokoro (place where Samurai of guard of the Imperial Palace is staffed) of the Southern Court (&quot;壺井八幡及通法寺文書&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a member of Mushadokoro (place where Samurai of guard of the Imperial Palace is staffed) of the Southern Court (&quot;Documents of Tsuboi Hachiman Shrine and Tsuho-ji Temple&quot;.</e>
<cmt>壺井八幡及通法寺文書は定訳不明ですが、訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>署名は「権中納言兼左衛門督藤原朝臣」）、訴訟関係の事務に携わっていたことが確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">signed by &apos;Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), FUJIWARA no Asomi&apos;), and engaged in lawsuit office work, which can be confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned &apos;Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), FUJIWARA no Asomi&apos;), and engaged in lawsuit office work, which can be confirmed.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He signed his name as &apos;Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards), FUJIWARA no Asomi&apos;), and engaged in lawsuit office work, which can be confirmed.</e>
<cmt>「署名は」の訳を変更しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また1357年（正平12年/延文2年）9月17日 (旧暦)付「聴断」目録（『久米田寺文書』）に見える「参仕人々」の「左大臣」は実世だとする説もある（『大日本史料』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an opinion that &apos;Minister of the Left&apos; of &apos;People in service&apos; appearing in &apos;Chodan&apos; Mokuroku (&quot;Kumeta-dera Monjo&quot;) dated September 17, 1357 was Saneyo (&quot;Dai Nihon Shiryo&quot; (the Historical Materials of Japan) and so on)).</e>
<cmt>「参仕人々」は、広辞苑の「さん‐し【参仕】参上して仕えること」を参考に仮訳しました。読み方も不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an opinion that &apos;Minister of the Left&apos; of &apos;People in service&apos; appearing in &apos;Chodan&apos; Mokuroku (&quot;Kumeta-dera Monjo&quot;) dated September 17, 1357 was Saneyo (&quot;Dai Nihon Shiryo&quot; (the Historical Materials of Japan) and so on)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an opinion that &apos;Minister of the Left&apos; of &apos;People in service&apos; appearing in &apos;Chodan&apos; Mokuroku (&quot;Kumeta-dera Monjo&quot;(written materials of Kumeta-dera Temple)) dated September 17 (old calendar), 1357 was Saneyo (&quot;Dai Nihon Shiryo&quot; (the Historical Materials of Japan) and so on)).</e>
<cmt>「旧暦」　訳漏れ対応しました。「久米田寺文書」定訳不明ですが説明補足しました。「聴断」は定訳不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>人物像とその評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality and reputation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality and reputation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality and reputation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>一般には対室町幕府強硬論者だといわれる（佐藤進一など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is generally said to have been a hard-liner against the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (Shinichi SATO and so on).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is generally said to have been a hard-liner against the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (Shinichi SATO and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is generally said to have been a hard-liner against the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (Shinichi SATO and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>『太平記』によると、北陸で幕府軍に敗北し吉野に戻った脇屋義助に、後村上天皇が恩賞を与えたことについて、富士川の戦いで敗走した平維盛を昇進させた平清盛の故事を引き合いに出して、強く反発したが、四条隆資にその発言のつたなさを指摘されると、一言も反論できず部屋を出ていったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Taiheiki,&quot; he deeply opposed the Onsho (reward grants) Emperor Gomurakami granted to Yoshisuke WAKIYA who had returned to Yoshino after defeated by the army of bakufu in Hokuriku region, referring to the historical event of TAIRA no Kiyomori who promoted TAIRA no Koremori having been defeated and routed in Battle of Fujigawa, but, when Takasuke SHIJO pointed out the awkwardness of his remarks, he got out of the room without a word of refutation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Taiheiki,&quot; he deeply opposed the Onsho (reward grants) Emperor Gomurakami granted to Yoshisuke WAKIYA who had returned to Yoshino after being defeated by the army of bakufu in Hokuriku region, referring to the historical event of TAIRA no Kiyomori who promoted TAIRA no Koremori having been defeated and routed in the Battle of Fujigawa, but, when Takasuke SHIJO pointed out the awkwardness of his remarks, he left the room without a word of refutation.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Taiheiki,&quot; he deeply opposed the Onsho (reward grants) Emperor Gomurakami granted to Yoshisuke WAKIYA who had returned to Yoshino after being defeated by the army of bakufu in Hokuriku region, referring to the historical event of TAIRA no Kiyomori who promoted TAIRA no Koremori having been defeated and routed in the Battle of Fujigawa, but, when Takasuke SHIJO pointed out the awkwardness of his remarks, he left the room without a word of refutation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また同じく『太平記』によると、観応の擾乱の影響で南朝に降伏してきた足利直義の処遇を巡って議論になった際、二条師基が即時赦免を進言したのに対し、実世は誅殺を主張したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Taiheiki&quot; again, in debate over the treatment of Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA who surrendered to the Southern Court influenced by the Kanno Disturbance, while Moromoto NIJO suggested an immediate pardon, Saneyo insisted on death penalty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Taiheiki&quot; again, in debate over the treatment of Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA who surrendered to the Southern Court influenced by the Kanno Disturbance, while Moromoto NIJO suggested an immediate pardon, Saneyo insisted on the death penalty.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Taiheiki&quot; again, in debate over the treatment of Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA who surrendered to the Southern Court influenced by the Kanno Disturbance, while Moromoto NIJO suggested an immediate pardon, Saneyo insisted on the death penalty.</e>
<cmt>treatment の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>さらに正平の一統破綻後における楠木氏の縁者を仲介とする公武の和平交渉にも反対であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he is said to have opposed to negotiations between the imperial court and the shogunate which was arranged by the relatives of the Kusunoki clan after the failure of the Shohei no itto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he is said to have opposed negotiations between the imperial court and the shogunate which was arranged by the relatives of the Kusunoki clan after the failure of the Shohei no itto.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he is said to have opposed negotiations between the imperial court and the shogunate which was arranged by the relatives of the Kusunoki clan after the failure of the Shohei no itto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これらの逸話を総合すると、やや硬直した思想の持ち主であったようであるが、その一方で『太平記』の作者は実世を「大才」と賞し、中厳円月も彼を「賢臣」と称える詩を残している（『東海一漚集』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering all of these anecdotes together, he seems to have had rigid way of thinking, but on the other hand, the author of &quot;Taiheiki&quot; praised Saneyo as &apos;Capable person&apos; and Engetsu CHUGAN wrote a poem describing him as &apos;Subject of wisdom&apos; (&quot;Tokai ichioshu&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering all of these anecdotes together, he seems to have hada rigid way of thinking, but on the other hand, the author of &quot;Taiheiki&quot; praised Saneyo as a &apos;Capable person&apos; and Engetsu CHUGAN wrote a poem describing him as a &apos;Subject of wisdom&apos; (&quot;Tokai ichioshu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering all of these anecdotes together, he seems to have had a rigid way of thinking, but on the other hand, the author of &quot;Taiheiki&quot; praised Saneyo as a &apos;Capable person&apos; and Chugan Engetsu wrote a poem describing him as a &apos;Subject of wisdom&apos; (&quot;Tokai ichioshu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>hada→had a「中厳円月」は姓名ではないので表記を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of offices and ranks held</e>
<cmt>表記を変更しました</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="28">
<j>日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date according to old lunar calendar</e>
<cmt>日付＝旧暦を追記しました。統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>1313年（正和2年）9月6日 (旧暦)、叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 6, 1313, he was raised to the peerage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 6, 1313, he was raised to the peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 6, 1313: He was raised to the peerage.</e>
<cmt>On September 6, 1313, he→September 6, 1313: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>1314年（正和3年）9月21日 (旧暦)、従五位上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 21, 1314, he was promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 21, 1314, he was promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 21, 1314: He was promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>On September 21, 1314, he→September 21, 1314: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>1317年（正和6年）1月5日 (旧暦)、正五位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 5, 1317, he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 5, 1317, he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5, 1317: He was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>On January 5, 1317, he→January 5, 1317: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>1318年（文保2年）1月22日 (旧暦)、侍従。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 22, 1318, he was appointed Chamberlain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 22, 1318, he was appointed Chamberlain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 22, 1318: He was appointed Chamberlain.</e>
<cmt>On January 22, 1318, he→January 22, 1318: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>同年11月21日 (旧暦)、従四位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 21, 1318, he was promoted to jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 21, 1318, he was promoted to jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 21, 1318: He was promoted to jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>On November 21, 1318, he→November 21, 1318: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>1322年（元亨2年）1月2日 (旧暦)、従四位上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 2, 1322, he was promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 2, 1322, he was promoted to Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 2, 1322: He was promoted to Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>Jushiijo→JushiinojoOn January 2, 1322, he→January 2, 1322: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>同年6月17日 (旧暦)、右少将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 17, 1322, he was appointed Ushosho (major general of the institution for guarding the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 17, 1322, he was appointed Ushosho (major general of the institution for guarding the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 17, 1322: He was appointed Ushosho (major general of the institution for guarding the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>On June 17, 1322, he→June 17, 1322: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>1327年（嘉暦2年）7月23日 (旧暦)、故あって四位を失い位記を収公されるが、同時に蔵人に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 23, 1327, he was deprived of Fourth Rank and the Iki (court rank diploma) was confiscated for some reason, but, at the same time, he was appointed Kurodo (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 23, 1327, he was deprived of Fourth Rank and the Iki (court rank diploma) was confiscated for some reason, but, at the same time, he was appointed Kurodo (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 23, 1327: He was deprived of Fourth Rank and the Iki (court rank diploma) was confiscated for some reason, but, at the same time, he was appointed Kurodo (Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>On July 23, 1327, he→July 23, 1327: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>同年11月10日 (旧暦)、権左中弁。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 10, he was appointed Gon Sachuben (Provisional Middle Controller of the left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 10, he was appointed Gon Sachuben (Provisional Middle Controller of the left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 10, 1327: He was appointed Gon Sachuben (Provisional Middle Controller of the left).</e>
<cmt>「同年」　訳漏れ対応しました。On November 10, 1327, he→ November 10, 1327: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="38">
<j>1328年（嘉暦3年）9月26日 (旧暦)、正四位上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 26, 1328, he was promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 26, 1328, he was promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 26, 1328: He was promoted to Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>On September 26, 1328, he→September 26, 1328: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="39">
<j>同年11月9日 (旧暦)、従三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 9, 1328, he was promoted to jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 9, 1328, he was promoted to jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 9, 1328: He was promoted to jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>On November 9, 1328, he→November 9, 1328: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="40">
<j>1330年（元徳2年）1月13日 (旧暦)、造東大寺長官（3月後醍醐天皇、東大寺に行幸）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 13, 1330, he was appointed Zo-Todaiji-chokan (the Director for the Construction of Todai-ji Temple) (Three months later, Emperor Godaigo visited Todai-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 13, 1330, he was appointed Zo-Todaiji-chokan (the Director for the Construction of Todai-ji Temple) (Three months later, Emperor Godaigo visited Todai-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 13, 1330: He was appointed Zo-Todaiji-chokan (the Director for the Construction of Todai-ji Temple) (In March, Emperor Godaigo visited Todai-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>「3月後醍醐天皇」　誤訳と考え訂正しました。On January 13, 1330, he→January 13, 1330: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="41">
<j>同年3月 (旧暦)、権中納言・正三位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1330, he was appointed and promoted to Gon Chunagon and Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1330, he was appointed and promoted to Gon Chunagon and Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 1330: He was appointed and promoted to Gon Chunagon and Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>In March 1330, he→March 1330: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="42">
<j>同年12月14日 (旧暦)、検非違使別当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 14, 1330, he was appointed Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 14, 1330, he was appointed Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 14, 1330: He was appointed Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police).</e>
<cmt>On December 14, 1330, he→December 14, 1330: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="43">
<j>1331年（元弘元年/元徳3年）10月5日 (旧暦)、元弘の乱に参与したため官職剥奪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 5, 1331, he was deprived of the government posts due to his participation in the Genko War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 5, 1331, he was deprived of his government posts due to his participation in the Genko War.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 5, 1331: He was deprived of his government posts due to his participation in the Genko War.</e>
<cmt>On October 5, 1331, he→October 5, 1331: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="44">
<j>1333年（元弘3年/正慶2年）9月23日 (旧暦)、修理大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 23, 1333, he was appointed Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 23, 1333, he was appointed Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 23, 1333: He was appointed Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>On September 23, 1333, he→September 23, 1333: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="45">
<j>1334年（建武 (日本)元年）12月17日 (旧暦)、大学頭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 17, 1334, he was appointed Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 17, 1334, he was appointed Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 17, 1334: He was appointed Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education).</e>
<cmt>On December 17, 1334, he→December 17, 1334: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="46">
<j>1336年（延元元年/建武3年）3月2日 (旧暦)、正二位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 2, 1336, he was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 2, 1336, he was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 2, 1336: He was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>On March 2, 1336, he→March 2, 1336: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="47">
<j>1339年（延元4年/暦応2年）、南朝において権大納言（『系図纂要』。以下同じ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1339, he was appointed Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1339, he was appointed Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1339: He was appointed Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) in the Southern Court (&quot;Keizu sanyo&quot; (pedigree charts of Edo period), which also includes the following descriptions).</e>
<cmt>『系図纂要』　訳漏れ対応しました。大納言の定訳In 1339, he→1339: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="48">
<j>1347年（正平 (日本)2年/貞和3年）、南朝において右大将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1347, he was appointed Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1347, he was appointed Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1347: He was appointed Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>In 1347, he→1347: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="49">
<j>1348年（正平3年/貞和4年）10月 (旧暦)、南朝において従一位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1348, he was promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1348, he was promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1348: He was promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>In October 1348, he→October 1348: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="50">
<j>1353年（正平8年/文和2年）、南朝において右大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1353, he was appointed udaijin (minister of the right) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1353, he was appointed udaijin (minister of the right) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1353: He was appointed udaijin (minister of the right) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>In 1353, he→1353: He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="51">
<j>1355年（正平10年/文和4年）3月7日 (旧暦)、南朝において左大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 7, 1355, he was appointed sadaijin (Minister of the left) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 7, 1355, he was appointed sadaijin (Minister of the left) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 7, 1355: He was appointed sadaijin (minister of the left) in the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>On March 7, 1355, he→March 7, 1355: HeMinister of the left→minister of the left（minister of the rightにあわせました）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), Oxhop(id:2551), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>