<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>加藤嘉明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki KATO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki KATO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki KATO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>加藤 嘉明（かとう よしあき）は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代にかけての武将・大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki KATO is the busho (general) and daimyo during the Azuchi-Momoyama and Edo Periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki KATO was a busho (general) and daimyo during the Azuchi-Momoyama and Edo Periods.</e>
<cmt>is the&apos;→&apos;was a&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki KATO was a busho (general) and daimyo during the Azuchi-Momoyama and Edo Periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伊予国伊予松山藩主、のち陸奥国会津藩初代藩主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the leader of Iyo-Matsuyama Han of Iyo no Kuni (Iyo Province) and eventually became the leader of Aizu Han of Mutsu no Kuni (Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the leader of the Iyo-Matsuyama Han (or fief) in Iyo no Kuni (Iyo Province) and eventually became the leader of Aizu Han in Mutsu no Kuni (Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>of&apos;→&apos;in&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the lord of the Iyo-Matsuyama Domain (or fief) in Iyo no Kuni (Iyo Province) and eventually became the lord of Aizu Domain in Mutsu no Kuni (Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>leader→lordHan→Domain</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>水口藩加藤家初代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the first generation of the KATO Family of Minakuchi Han.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first generation of the KATO family of the Minakuchi Han.</e>
<cmt>is&apos;→&apos;was&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first generation of the KATO family of the Minakuchi Domain.</e>
<cmt>Han→Domain</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>よしあきらと読む説も存在し、松山市の文献や説明、坊っちゃん列車でのガイドなどにおいても散見され、愛媛新聞でもたびたび話題となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that his name is also pronounced as Akira YOSHI and is mentioned in Matsuyama City&apos;s literatures and descriptions, the guide for Bocchan Ressha (train), and occasionally in Ehime Shinbun (newspaper).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that his name is also pronounced as Yoshiakira and he is mentioned in literature and descriptions of Matsuyama City, the guide for Bocchan Ressha train, and occasionally in the Ehime Shinbun newspaper.</e>
<cmt>I think the pronunciation is just his given name.&apos;is&apos;→&apos;was&apos;Changed word orderDeleted brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that his name is also pronounced as Yoshiakira and he is mentioned in literature and descriptions of Matsuyama City, the guide for Bocchan Ressha train, and occasionally in the Ehime Shinbun newspaper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>父は徳川氏（松平氏）に仕えていた徳川譜代の武士である加藤教明（岸教明）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Noriaki KATO (Noriaki KISHI), the bushi (samurai) of TOKUGAWA fudai that served TOKUGAWA Family (Matsuyama Family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Noriaki KATO (also known as Noriaki KISHI), a bushi, or samurai, who served several generations of the TOKUGAWA Family (MATSUYAMA Family).</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;also known as&apos;&apos;the&apos;→&apos;a&apos;&apos;fudai&apos;→&apos;several generations&apos;&apos;that&apos;→&apos;who&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Noriaki KATO (also known as Noriaki KISHI), a bushi, or samurai, who served several generations of the TOKUGAWA Clan (MATSUDAIRA Clan).</e>
<cmt>Matsuyama→MATSUDAIRAFamily→Clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>賤ヶ岳の戦い賤ヶ岳の七本槍の1人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the Shichihonyari in Shizugatake of the Battle of Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the Shichihonyari (Seven Spears) of Shizugatake during the Battle of Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt>Added translation of &apos;Shichihonyari&apos;&apos;in&apos;→&apos;of&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the Shichihonyari (Seven Spears) of Shizugatake during the Battle of Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>通称は孫六。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His alias was Magoroku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as Magoroku.</e>
<cmt>His alias was&apos;→&apos;He was also known as&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as Magoroku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一ルール</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>秀吉時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>永禄6年（1563年）、三河国（愛知県）の徳川家康の家臣である加藤教明の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the eldest son of Noriaki KATO, the handsman of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in Mikawa no Kuni (Mikawa Province) in 1563.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Mikawa no Kuni (Mikawa Province) in 1563, the eldest son of Noriaki KATO, a retainer of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order.&apos;the handsman&apos;→&apos;a retainer&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Mikawa no Kuni (Mikawa Province) in 1563, the eldest son of Noriaki KATO, a retainer of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>生まれた年の三河一向一揆で父の教明が、一揆側に属して徳川家康に背き、流浪の身となったため、嘉明も放浪する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his father, Noriaki, was exiled for siding with the revolts in Mikawa Ikko Ikki opposing TOKUGAWA Ieyasu in the same year he was born, he also led the life of a wanderer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since his father, Noriaki, was exiled for siding with anti-Ieyasu TOKUGAWA Mikawa Ikko Ikki revolts in the same year he was born, he grew up leading the life of a wanderer.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&apos;opposing&apos;→&apos;anti-&apos;deleted &apos;in&apos;&apos;also led&apos;→&apos;grew up leading&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since his father, Noriaki, was exiled for siding with anti-Ieyasu TOKUGAWA Mikawa Ikko Ikki revolts in the same year he was born, he grew up leading the life of a wanderer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>やがて尾張国（愛知県）で、加藤景泰の推挙を受けて豊臣秀吉（豊臣秀吉）に見出され、その小姓として仕えるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, he received the recommendation of Kageyasu KATO and was discovered by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI to begin serving him as a page.</e>
<cmt>豊臣秀吉（豊臣秀吉)→Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, on the recommendation of Kageyasu KATO, he was selected to serve as a page to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>he received&apos;→&apos;on&apos;&apos;and...page&apos;→&apos;, he was selected to serve as a page to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, on the recommendation of Kageyasu KATO, he was selected to serve as a page to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>織田信長死後の天正11年（1583年）には、秀吉と織田家筆頭家老の柴田勝家との間で行われた賤ヶ岳の戦いで、福島正則、加藤清正らと共に活躍し、『賤ヶ岳七本槍』の一人に数えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He performed along with Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Kiyomasa KATO in the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583 that occurred between Hideyoshi and Katsuie SHIBATA, the Hitto Garo (high serving samurai of daimyo) of Oda Family and was counted as on of the &quot;Shichihonyari of the Battle of Shizugatake.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1583, he fought alongside Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Kiyomasa KATO at the Battle of Shizugatake, between Hideyoshi and Katsuie SHIBATA, a Hitto-Garo (or high-ranking samurai) of the Oda Family, and was counted as one of the &quot;Shichihonyari of Shizugatake.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Nobunaga ODA, in 1583, he fought alongside Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Kiyomasa KATO at the Battle of Shizugatake, between Hideyoshi and Katsuie SHIBATA, a Hitto-Garo (or high-ranking samurai) of the Oda Family, and was counted as one of the &quot;Shichihonyari of Shizugatake.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「after the death of Nobunaga ODA」を追加。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>秀吉は信長の統一政策を継承し、嘉明は天正13年（1585年）の四国征伐、天正15年（1587年）の九州征伐、天正18年（1590年）の小田原の役などに水軍を率いて参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi inherited Nobunaga&apos;s unification policy and Yoshiaki conquested Shikoku in 1585, Kyushu in 1587, and participated in the Odawara no Eki (Odawara Campaign) with his navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi continued Nobunaga&apos;s unification policy and Yoshiaki conquered Shikoku in 1585, Kyushu in 1587, and his navy participated in the Odawara Campaign.</e>
<cmt>inherited&apos;→&apos;continued&apos;&apos;conquested&apos;→&apos;conquered&apos;Moved &apos;his navy&apos;Deleted &apos;Odawara no Eki&apos; and brackets.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi continued Nobunaga&apos;s unification policy and Yoshiaki conquered Shikoku in 1585, Kyushu in 1587, and his navy participated in the Odawara Campaign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それらの武功から、天正14年（1586年）には淡路国志智において1万5000石を与えられ、大名となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From these battle achievements, he was granted with 15,000 koku Shichi of Awaji no Kuni and became its daimyo in 1586.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to these successes, in 1586 he was granted the 15,000 koku Shichi in Awaji no Kuni, becoming its daimyo.</e>
<cmt>From these battle achievements&apos;→&apos;Due to these successes&apos;&apos;with&apos;→&apos;the&apos;&apos;of&apos;→&apos;in&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to these successes, in 1586 he was granted the 15,000 koku Shichi in Awaji no Kuni, becoming its daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>文禄元年（1592年）からの秀吉の朝鮮出兵である文禄・慶長の役では、水軍を統率して李舜臣指揮の朝鮮水軍と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lead the navy in Hideyoshi&apos;s dispatch of soldiers to Korea in Buncho-Keicho no Eki (Korean invasions) and fought against the Korean navy led by Yi Sun-sin from 1592.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1592, he led the navy during Hideyoshi&apos;s Buncho-Keicho Korean invasions and fought against the Korean navy led by Yi Sun-sin.</e>
<cmt>Moved &apos;from1592&apos; to beginning&apos;lead&apos;→&apos;led&apos;Deleted &apos;no Eki&apos; and brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1592, he led the navy during Hideyoshi&apos;s Buncho-Keicho Korean invasions and fought against the Korean navy led by Yi Sun-sin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その功績により、文禄4年（1595年）には、伊予国（愛媛県）正木（松前町 (愛媛県)）に6万石を与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this achievement, he was given 60,000 koku of Masaki (Masaki-cho, Ehime Prefecture) of Iyo no Kuni (Iyo Province)(Ehime Prefecture) in 1595.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afer this success, in 1595, he was given Masaki in the province of Iyo no Kuni (present day Masaki-cho, Ehime Prefecture) with an income of 60,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>Due to this achievement&apos;→&apos;After this success&apos;Changed word order.Added &apos;with an income of&apos;Deleted &apos;(Ehime Prefecture)&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afer this success, in 1595, he was given Masaki in the province of Iyo no Kuni (present day Masaki-cho, Ehime Prefecture) with an income of 60,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、文禄・慶長の役においては、明の水軍の包囲で篭城し、食糧の欠乏に苦しんだ蔚山倭城（倭城）の清正を救援する武功も立て、10万石に加増されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he was granted additionally with 10,000 koku for his deeds in rescuing Kiyomasa in Ulsan Japanese Castle (Ulsan) who suffered from food shortage during the battle while being surrounded by Ming navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was granted an additional 10,000 koku for rescuing Kiyomasa during the Ming navy&apos;s seige of the Japanese castle at Ulsan.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, his domain was expanded to 100,000 koku for rescuing Kiyomasa who suffered from food shortage during the Ming navy&apos;s seige of the Japanese castle at Ulsan.</e>
<cmt>桁が違う（「10,000 koku」→「100,000 koku」）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）8月に秀吉が死去すると帰国し、豊臣政権における五奉行の石田三成らと五大老の徳川家康の争いでは家康派に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned to Japan in August 1598 upon the death of Hideyoshi and belonged to Ieyasu side during the conflict between TOYOTOMI Administration&apos;s Go bugyo Mitsunari Ishida and Gotairo Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death in August 1598, he returned to Japan and joined Ieyasu&apos;s side during the conflict between the TOYOTOMI Administration&apos;s Go-Bugyo, (member of Five Commissioners), Mitsunari Ishida, and the Go-Tairo (Member of the Five Elders), Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderDeleted &apos;the&apos;&apos;belonged to&apos;→&apos;joined&apos;Added &apos;the&apos;Added definition of Japanese terms.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death in August 1598, he returned to Japan and joined Ieyasu&apos;s side during the conflict between the TOYOTOMI Administration&apos;s Gobugyo, (member of Five Major Magistrates), Mitsunari Ishida, and the Gotairo (Member of the Council of Five Elders), Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>用語統一(Gobugyo, Gotairo)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>慶長4年（1599年）、五大老の前田利家の死後に加藤清正らが三成殺害を企てた事件には、嘉明も襲撃メンバーに参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated as the assault member in the attempted Mitsunari assassination incident in 1599 planned by Kiyomasa KATO after the death of Godairo Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in the attempted Mitsunari assassination incident in 1599, planned by Kiyomasa KATO after the death of the Go-Tairo, Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;as the assault member&apos;Added commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in the attempted Mitsunari assassination incident in 1599, planned by Kiyomasa KATO after the death of the Gotairo, Toshiie MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>用語統一(Gotairo)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）、家康が会津の上杉景勝の謀反を主張し、討伐を発令すると嘉明も従軍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ieyasu declared the revolt of Kagekatsu UESUGI in Aizu and ordered his suppression, Yoshiaki participated in the army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1600, Yoshiaki participated in the campaign against Kagekatsu UESUGI of Aizu, whom Ieyasu had declared to be plotting a revolt.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1600, Yoshiaki participated in the campaign against Kagekatsu UESUGI of Aizu, whom Ieyasu had declared to be plotting a revolt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>家康らの大坂留守中に三成らが挙兵し、引き返した東軍（徳川方）と美濃（岐阜県）で衝突して関ヶ原の戦いに至ると、嘉明は前哨戦である岐阜城攻めや、大垣城攻めにおいて戦い、本戦では石田三成の軍勢と戦って武功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Ieyasu was absent from Osaka Castle, Mitsunari gathered his army and clashed with the returning Eastern Army (TOKUGAWA side) in Mino (present day Gifu Prefecture), to lead to the Battle of Sekigahara, Yoshiaki sucessfully attacked the frontal base Gifu Castle, Oogaki Castle, and fought against Mitsunari Ishida forces in the main battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Ieyasu was away from Osaka Castle, Mitsunari gathered his army and clashed with the returning Eastern Army (TOKUGAWA side) at Mino (Gifu Prefecture), leading to the Battle of Sekigahara, where Yoshiaki attacked Gifu and Oogaki Castles in skirmishes, and fought against Mitsunari ISHIDA&apos;s forces in the main battle.</e>
<cmt>absent&apos;→&apos;was away&apos;&apos;in&apos;→&apos;at&apos;&apos;to lead&apos;→&apos;leading to&apos;Added &apos;where&apos;&apos;the frontal base&apos;→&apos;in skirmishes&apos;―mistranslation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Ieyasu was away from Osaka, Mitsunari gathered his army and clashed with the returning Eastern Army (TOKUGAWA side) at Mino (Gifu Prefecture), leading to the Battle of Sekigahara, where Yoshiaki attacked Gifu and Oogaki Castles in early skirmishes, and fought against Mitsunari ISHIDA&apos;s forces in the main battle.</e>
<cmt>大阪城ではない（「Osaka Castle」→「Osaka」）。前哨戦→「early skirmishes」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>戦後、その功績により伊予松山20万石に加増移封され、松山城 (伊予国)を建築するが、完成する前に会津藩40万石に転封された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to these achievements, 20,000 koku was added to Iyo Matsuyama to begin building Matsuyama Castle (Iyo no Kuni (Iyo Province)) but its 400,000 koku was shifted back to Aizu Han before its completion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to these achievements, the income from Iyo Matsuyama was increased to 200,000 koku, and work was begun on building Matsuyama Castle (Iyo no Kuni (Iyo Province)) but, before it could be completed, he was moved to the 400,000 koku Aizu Han.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence- mistranslation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to these achievements, the income from Iyo Matsuyama was increased to 200,000 koku, and work was begun on building Matsuyama Castle (Iyo no Kuni (Iyo Province)) but, before it could be completed, he was moved to the 400,000 koku Aizu Domain.</e>
<cmt>「Han」→「Domain」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>城が完成するのは蒲生忠知の時代のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle finished its construction in Tadatomo GAMO&apos;s period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle was completed by Tadatomo GAMO.</e>
<cmt>finished its construction in Tadatomo GAMO&apos;s period&apos;→&apos;was completed by Tadatomo GAMO&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle was completed by Tadatomo GAMO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>その後は豊臣恩顧の大名であったが、家康に危険視されることを恐れて、慶長19年（1614年）からの豊臣氏との戦いである大坂冬の陣では江戸城留守居を務め、慶長20年（1615年）の大坂夏の陣では2代将軍・徳川秀忠に従って徳川方として参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later became the daimyo who was favored by TOYOTOMI, but fearing Ieyasu to consider him dangerous, he stayed and guarded Edo Castle during Osaka Fuyu no Jin (the Winter War in Osaka) from 1614 and served under the second generation Hidetada TOKUNAGA during Osaka Natsu no Jin (the Summer War in Osaka) in 1615.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later became a favored daimyo of TOYOTOMI, but fearing that Ieyasu considered him dangerous, he stayed and guarded Edo Castle during the Fuyu no Jin (the Winter War in Osaka) from 1614 and served the second Shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA during the Natsu no Jin (the Summer War in Osaka) in 1615.</e>
<cmt>the daimyo who was favored by&apos;→&apos;a favored daimyo of&apos;&apos;Ieyasu to consider&apos;→&apos;that Ieyasu considered&apos;Added &apos;the&apos;Deleted &apos;Osaka&apos;Deleted &apos;under&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since being a favored daimyo of TOYOTOMI, then he feared that Ieyasu considered him dangerous, he stayed and guarded Edo Castle during the Fuyu no Jin (the Winter War in Osaka) from 1614 and served the second Shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA during the Natsu no Jin (the Summer War in Osaka) in 1615.</e>
<cmt>「豊臣恩顧の大名」だったのは従来のこと。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>元和 (日本)5年（1619年）には福島正則の改易で広島城の接収を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He takes over Hiroshima Castle during the dismissal of Masanori FUKUSHIMA in 1619.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1619, he took over Hiroshima Castle following the dismissal of Masanori FUKUSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>Moved date&apos;takes over&apos;→&apos;took over&apos;&apos;during&apos;→&apos;following&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1619, he took over Hiroshima Castle following the dismissal of Masanori FUKUSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>寛永4年（1627年）、会津の蒲生忠郷死後の騒動で蒲生氏が減転封された後を受けて、会津藩40万石に加増移封された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The additional 400,000 koku was added to Aizu Han by lessened estate of the Gamo Family due to the feud that rose after the death of Tadasato GAMO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1627, in the turmoil following Tadasato GAMO&apos;s death, the Gamo family lost control of the 400,000 koku Aizu Han, which was given to Yoshiaki.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence- mistranslation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1627, in the turmoil following Tadasato GAMO&apos;s death, the Gamo Clan lost control of the 400,000 koku Aizu Domain, which was given to Yoshiaki.</e>
<cmt>「Han」→「Domain」「family」→「Clan」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>寛永8年（1631年）9月12日に江戸で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on September 12, 1631 in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in Edo on September 12, 1631.</e>
<cmt>Moved &apos;in Edo&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in Edo on September 12, 1631.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>享年69。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at 69.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 69 years old.</e>
<cmt>died at 69&apos;→&apos;was 69 years old&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 69 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>嘉明の死後、家督は嫡男の加藤明成が継いだが、明成が暗愚なために家中で堀主水立ち退き事件が起こって幕府の介入を招き、減封、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legitamate son, Akinari KATO, inherited the family property after Yoshiaki&apos;s death, but his estate lessened when the Leaving of Hori Mondo Incidence which involved shogunate occurred.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legitimate son, Akinari KATO, inherited the family property after Yoshiaki&apos;s death but, after the Hori Mondo Incident provoked the involvement of the shogunate, his property was confiscated and</e>
<cmt>Joined sentences back together</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legitimate son, Akinari KATO, inherited the family property after Yoshiaki&apos;s death but, after the Hori Mondo Incident provoked the involvement of the shogunate, his property was confiscated and</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>嗣子を立てて家名存続との裁定となるが、明成が正室をはばかって子息はないと頑固に主張したため改易され、庶子の加藤明友に近江国水口藩2万石に減移封されることで名跡が保たれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was dismissed from the post when he vehemently denied the presence of a son (in fear of his formal wife) when questioned about who will continue the family name, and his illegitimate child Akitomo KATO received 20,000 koku Minakuchi Han in Omi no Kuni to continue the surname.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">he was reduced in rank after vehemently denying the presence of a son (in fear of his formal wife) when questioned about who will continue the family name, resulting in his illegitimate child, Akitomo KATO, receiving the 20,000 koku Minakuchi Han in Omi no Kuni and continuing the surname.</e>
<cmt>Not sure if the illegitimate child is Yoshiaki&apos;s or Akinari&apos;s, though probably the former</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">he was reduced in rank after vehemently denying the presence of a son (in fear of his formal wife) when questioned about who will continue the family name, resulting in his illegitimate child, Akitomo KATO, receiving the 20,000 koku Minakuchi Domain in Omi no Kuni and continuing the surname.</e>
<cmt>「Han」→「Domain」</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>Person&apos;→&apos;Character&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>統一ルール</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>賤ヶ岳七本槍の一人として名を馳せた武勇に優れた名将であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the great commander who spread his name as one of the Shichihonyari of Shizugatake known for his bravery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a great commander who, as one of the Shichihonyari of Shizugatake, was known for his military prowess.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a great commander who, as one of the Shichihonyari of Shizugatake, was known for his military prowess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>武勇だけではなく、築城や城下町の建設などにも力量を発揮した政治家でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He excelled not only in bravery but was also a politician who showed his strength in the construction of a castle and its castle town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was not only brave, but was also a capable politician as shown by his construction of the castle and surrounding town.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was not only brave, but was also a capable politician as shown by his construction of the castle and surrounding town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>愛媛県においては、現在でも松山城築城の評価は高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsuyama Castle&apos;s castle formation is regarded highly even now in Ehime Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsuyama Castle&apos;s fortifications are still highly regarded in Ehime Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>castle formation is regarded highly even now&apos;→&apos;fortification sare still highly regarded&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsuyama Castle&apos;s fortifications are still highly regarded in Ehime Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Flamelai(id:34490), Mnd(id:15140), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), ドルチェット(id:46458), Πrate(id:11329), Reggaeman(id:6214), 松茸(id:27535), HI(id:72996), Николай Булганин(id:196360), Lupinoid(id:68), 小者(id:172526), Jyo81(id:180101), でここ(id:9565), Yonoemon(id:55450), NoriBeat(id:2074), ＩＤＳ(id:49634), YurikBot(id:18605), Qje(id:160294), Shiro4873(id:109602), KASAGI(id:24405), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>