<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原明子 (染殿后)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akirakeiko (Somedono no kisaki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Akirakeiko (Somedono no kisaki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akirakeiko (Somedono no kisaki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 明子（ふじわら の あきらけいこ/めいし、天長6年（829年） - 昌泰3年5月23日 (旧暦)（900年6月22日））は、藤原良房と源潔姫の娘で文徳天皇の女御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akirakeiko (A.D.829 ~ June 22nd, 900) was a daughter between FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and his wife, MINAMOTO no Kiyohime, and Nyogo (a court lady-next in the rank to the Chugu or Second Consort of the Emperor) of the Emperor Montoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Akirakeiko (A.D.829 ~ June 22nd, 900) was the daughter between FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and his wife, MINAMOTO no Kiyohime, and Nyogo (a court lady-next in the rank to the Chugu or Second Consort of the Emperor) of the Emperor Montoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Akirakeiko (829-June 27, 900) was the daughter between FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and his wife, MINAMOTO no Kiyohime, and nyogo (a high-ranking lady in the court (a consort of an emperor)) of the Emperor Montoku.</e>
<cmt>日付、記号を修正。「女御」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大変な美貌の持ち主だったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is said to be very beautiful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was said to be very beautiful.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was said to be very beautiful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>清和院（通称染殿）が里邸であったため、染殿后（そめどののきさき）とよばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As her family home was the Seiwa-in temple (commonly called &quot;Somedono&quot;, she was called Somedono no kisaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As her family home was the Seiwa-in temple (commonly called &quot;Somedono,&quot; she was called Somedono no kisaki.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As her family home was the Seiwa-in Temple (commonly called &quot;Somedono,&quot;) she was called Somedono no kisaki.</e>
<cmt>temple を大文字に。かっこを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>文徳天皇が東宮であったとき、入内。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She married into the Imperial Court when Emperor Montoku was a Togu (The Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She married into the Imperial Court when Emperor Montoku was a Togu (The Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She married into the Imperial Court when Emperor Montoku was a Togu (the Crown Prince).</e>
<cmt>The を小文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>夫が即位するとまもなく女御になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after her husband acceded to the throne, she became a nyogo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after her husband acceded to the throne, she became a nyogo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after her husband acceded to the throne, she became a nyogo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、その年（850年）のうちに惟仁親王（のちの清和天皇）を出産する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within the year she became a nyogo (850), she gave a birth to Imperial Prince Korehito, the later Emperor Seiwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the year she became a nyogo (850), she gave birth to Imperial Prince Korehito, the later Emperor Seiwa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the year she became a nyogo (850), she gave birth to Imperial Prince Korehito, the later Emperor Seiwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>惟仁親王はすぐ立太子した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official investiture of the Crown Prince was made to the Imperial Prince Korehito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official investiture of the Crown Prince was made toImperial Prince Korehito.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Official investiture of the Crown Prince was made to Imperial Prince Korehito.</e>
<cmt>スペースを挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仁寿3年（853年）に従三位、天安 (日本)2年（858年）には従一位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was ranked as Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 853 and promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 858.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was ranked as Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 853 and promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 858.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was ranked as Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 853 and promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) in 858.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、子の清和天皇からは「皇太后」、孫の陽成天皇からは「太皇太后」の号を贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was entitled to the &quot;Empress&quot; by her own son, the Emperor Seiwa, and also the &quot;Grand Empress&quot; by her grand son, the Emperor Yozei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was given the title &quot;Empress&quot; by her own son, the Emperor Seiwa, and also the &quot;Grand Empress&quot; by her grand son, the Emperor Yozei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was given the title &quot;Empress Dowager&quot; by her own son, the Emperor Seiwa, and also the &quot;Grand Empress Dowager&quot; by her grand son, the Emperor Yozei.</e>
<cmt>「皇太后、太皇太后」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>子は、前述した清和天皇と賀茂斎院になった儀子内親王がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among her children were aforementioned emperor Seiwa and Imperial Princess Gishi who later became a Kamo no saiin (maiden princess or queen served as high priestess at the Kamo Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among her children were aforementioned emperor Seiwa and Imperial Princess Gishi who later became a Kamo no saiin (maiden princess or queen served as high priestess at the Kamo Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among her children were aforementioned Emperor Seiwa and Imperial Princess Gishi who later became a Kamo Saiin (Imperial Princess appointed to serve the deities of the Kamo-jinja Shrines).</e>
<cmt>emperor　を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>また、貞観 (日本)7年（865年）ごろから一種のうつ病のようなものにかかっていたらしく、それらしき記述（物の怪に悩まされる）が『今昔物語集』などに見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that she suffered from a kind of depression from around 865, which was implied in &quot;Konjaku Monogatarishuu&quot; (Tales of Times Now Past) as she was annoyed by mononoke (evil spirits).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that she suffered from a kind of depression from around 865, which was implied in &quot;Konjaku Monogatarishuu&quot; (Tales of Times Now Past) as she was annoyed by mononoke (evil spirits).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that she suffered from a kind of depression from around 865, which was implied in &quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu)&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past) as she was annoyed by mononoke (evil spirits).</e>
<cmt>『今昔物語集』を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>彼女は、叔母である藤原順子、従妹の藤原高子とともに良房の（ひいては藤原家の）摂関政治の礎を築いたともいえるが、自ら表に出ようとはしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it can be said that she established with her aunt FUJIWARA no Nobuko and a cousin FUJIWARA no Takaiko as well the cornerstone of the administration by regents and advisers of Yoshifusa, namely the Fujiwara family, she never wanted to go mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it can be said that she was established with her aunt FUJIWARA no Nobuko and a cousin FUJIWARA no Takaiko as well the cornerstone of the administration by regents and advisers of Yoshifusa, namely the Fujiwara family, she never wanted to go mainstream.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it can be said that she was established with her aunt FUJIWARA no Nobuko and a cousin FUJIWARA no Takaiko as well the cornerstone of Sekkan (regent to the emperor) government of Yoshifusa, namely the Fujiwara family, she never wanted to go mainstream.</e>
<cmt>「摂関政治」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>72歳と当時では珍しい長命で崩御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She demised at the age of 72, which was a rare longevity at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died at the age of 72, which was a rare longevity at the time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died at the age of 72, which was a rare longevity at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>女御宣下を受けてからでも文徳を含め6代の天皇が交代している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After she received an imperial proclamation to become a nyogo, six emperors reigned one after another including Montoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After she received an imperial proclamation to become a nyogo, six emperors reigned one after another including Montoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after she received an Imperial letter of appointment as nyogo, six emperors reigned one after another including Montoku.</e>
<cmt>「女御宣下を受けてからでも」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Andee(id:20421), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 渡辺茜(id:136156), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>