<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>豊臣秀次</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>豊臣 秀次（とよとみ の ひでつぐ、とよとみ ひでつぐ）／羽柴 秀次（はしば ひでつぐ）は、戦国時代 (日本)（室町時代末期）から天正時代の武将・大名・関白である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI/Hedetsugu HASHIBA was Busho (Japanese military commander), daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) from the Sengoku period (Japan) (the end of Muromachi period) to Tensho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI/Hedetsugu HASHIBA was a busho (Japanese military commander), daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) from the Sengoku period (Japan) (the end of the Muromachi period) to Tensho period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI/Hidetsugu HASHIBA was a busho (Japanese military commander), daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) from the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan) (the end of the Muromachi period) to Tensho period.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>豊臣秀吉の姉・日秀の子で、秀吉の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Nisshu, the elder sister of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and became his adopted son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Nisshu, the elder sister of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and became his adopted son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Nisshu, the elder sister of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and became his adopted son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は孫七郎（まごしちろう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Magoshichiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Magoshichiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Magoshichiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名は治兵衛（じへえ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Jihee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Jihe-e.</e>
<cmt>Maybe Jihe-e is better.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Jihe-e.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>はじめ、戦国大名・三好氏の一族・三好康長に養子入りして三好信吉（みよし のぶよし）と名乗っていたが、後に羽柴 秀次と改名する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted to Yasunaga MIYOSHI who was a family of warring lord MIYOSHI clan, and named Nobuyoshi MIYOSHI, but he changed his name to Hidetsugu HASHIBA later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by Yasunaga MIYOSHI who was a member of the warring-lord family, the MIYOSHI clan, and named Nobuyoshi MIYOSHI, but he later changed his name to Hidetsugu HASHIBA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by Yasunaga MIYOSHI who was a member of the MIYOSHI clan, a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period), and named Nobuyoshi MIYOSHI, but he later changed his name to Hidetsugu HASHIBA.</e>
<cmt>戦国大名　追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお「豊臣秀次」の読み方については、豊臣氏を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the reading of &apos;Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI&apos;, refer to the TOYOTOMI clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the Toyotomi clan for the way of reading &quot;Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the article on the Toyotomi clan for the way of reading &apos;Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>正室は池田恒興の娘、継室は右大臣・菊亭晴季の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Tsuneoki IKEDA, his second wife was a daughter of Minister of Right, Harusue KIKUTEI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was a daughter of Tsuneoki IKEDA, and his second wife was a daughter of a Minister of the Right, Harusue KIKUTEI.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Tsuneoki IKEDA, and his second wife was a daughter of a Udaijin (minister of the right), Harusue KIKUTEI.</e>
<cmt>右大臣　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>側室は、最上義光の娘・駒姫、淡輪徹斎隆重の娘・小督局、大島新左衛門の娘・お国など、ほか多数いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had many concubines who were Komahime, a daughter of Yoshimitsu MOGAMI, Kogo-no-tsubone, a daughter of Tessai Takashige TANNOWA, Okuni, a daughter of Shinzaemon OSHIMA and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had many concubines including Komahime, a daughter of Yoshimitsu MOGAMI, Kogo-no-tsubone, a daughter of Tessai Takashige TANNOWA, and Okuni, a daughter of Shinzaemon OSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had many concubines including Komahime, a daughter of Yoshimitsu MOGAMI, Kogo-no-tsubone, a daughter of Tessai Takashige TANNOWA, and Okuni, a daughter of Shinzaemon OSHIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>前半生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first half of his life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first half of his life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first half of his life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）、豊臣秀吉の姉・とも（瑞竜院日秀）と三好吉房（当時は木下弥助）の長男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in 1568 as the first son of Tomo (Zuiryu-in Nisshu) who was the elder sister of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Yoshifusa MIYOSHI (Yasuke KINOSHITA then).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born the first son of Tomo (Zuiryu-in Nisshu) (the elder sister of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) and Yoshifusa MIYOSHI (then known as Yasuke KINOSHITA) in 1568.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born the first son of Tomo (Zuiryu-in Nisshu) (the elder sister of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) and Yoshifusa MIYOSHI (then known as Yasuke KINOSHITA) in 1568.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>織田信長の浅井氏攻めに際し、宮部継潤に養子として送り込まれた（浅井氏滅亡後に返還）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nobunaga ODA attacked AZAI clan, Hidetsugu was sent to Keijun MIYABE as his adopted son (then he was returned after the fall of AZAI clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nobunaga ODA attacked the AZAI clan, Hidetsugu was sent to Keijun MIYABE as his adopted son (he was then returned after the fall of the AZAI clan).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nobunaga ODA attacked the Azai clan, Hidetsugu was sent to Keijun MIYABE as his adopted son (he was then returned after the fall of the Azai clan).</e>
<cmt>Azai clan としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、信長が開始した四国征伐において、秀吉が四国に対する影響力を強めるため、当時阿波国で勢力を誇っていた三好康長に養子として送り込まれ、三好信吉と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when Nobunaga started the Conquest of Shikoku Hideyoshi was going to strengthen the clout in Shikoku, so Hidetsugu was sent to become the adopted child of Yasunaga MIYOSHI who had a strong power in Awa Province then, he gave his name Nobuyoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, when Nobunaga started the Conquest of Shikoku, Hideyoshi was going to strengthen his clout in Shikoku, thus Hidetsugu was sent to become the adopted child of Yasunaga MIYOSHI who had strong power in Awa Province at the time. He was given the name Nobuyoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>Wording. I think a better translation of 影響力 is &quot;influence&quot; rather than &quot;clout&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, when Nobunaga started the Conquest of Shikoku, Hideyoshi was going to strengthen his clout in Shikoku, thus Hidetsugu was sent to become the adopted child of Yasunaga MIYOSHI who had strong power in Awa Province at the time, where he was given the name Nobuyoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天正10年（1582年）6月の信長の死後、秀吉が信長の後継者としての地位を確立する過程において、秀吉の数少ない縁者として重用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga died in June 1582, Hideyoshi was establishing his status as his successor, and Hidetsugu was given important posts to Hideyoshi as one of a few relatives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga died in June 1582, Hideyoshi was establishing his status as his successor, and Hidetsugu was given important posts to Hideyoshi as one of a few relatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga died in July 1582, Hideyoshi was establishing his status as his successor, and Hidetsugu was given important posts by Hideyoshi as one of a few relatives.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>天正11年（1583年）の賤ヶ岳の戦いに参戦して武功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu attended the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583, achieved military exploits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu took part in the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583, achieving military exploits.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu took part in the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583, achieving military exploits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天正12年（1584年）の小牧・長久手の戦いにも参加し、このとき「中入り」のため三河国別働奇襲隊の総指揮を執ったが、逆に徳川家康軍の奇襲を受けて惨敗し、舅である池田恒興や森長可らを失い、命からがら敗走する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attended the Battle of Komaki Nagakute in 1584, then he was a general commander of Betsudo Surprise Attack Troops in Mikawa Province for the intermission, but they suffered terrible defeat by a surprise attack of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA army, so Hidetsugu lost Tsuneoki IKEDA, a father-in-law, and Nagayoshi MORI and escaped with his bare life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took part in the Battle of Komaki Nagakute in 1584, where he was a general commander of the Betsudo Surprise Attack of Troops in Mikawa Province for &quot;intermission&quot;, but they suffered terrible defeat by a surprise attack by the Ieyasu TOKUGAWA army. Hidetsugu lost Tsuneoki IKEDA, his father-in-law along with Nagayoshi MORI, and escaped with his bare life.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took part in the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584, where he was a general commander of the detached surprise attack force in Mikawa Province for &apos;intermission,&apos; but they suffered terrible defeat by a surprise attack by the Ieyasu TOKUGAWA army; Hidetsugu lost Tsuneoki IKEDA, his father-in-law along with Nagayoshi MORI, and escaped with his bare life.</e>
<cmt>別働→detached force としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このため、秀吉から激しく叱責された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So that he was reproached severely by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, he was severely repremanded by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, he was severely repremanded by Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この時期、羽柴秀次と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gave his name as Hidetsugu HASHIBA in this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gave himself the name Hidetsugu HASHIBA in this period.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Please check that this translation is correct.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gave himself the name Hidetsugu HASHIBA in this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>天正13年（1585年）の紀伊国紀州征伐、四国征伐では軍功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He achieved military exploits at the Conquest of Kishu in Kii Province and the Conquest of Shikoku in 1585.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He achieved military exploits at the Conquest of Kishu in Kii Province and the Conquest of Shikoku in 1585.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He achieved military exploits at the Conquest of Kishu in Kii Province and the Conquest of Shikoku in 1585.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このため、近江国八幡山城に43万石を与えられた（うち、23万石は御年寄り衆分）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So that he was given 430,000 koku in Hachimann-yama Castle in Omi Province (230,000 koku out of them were for Otoshiyori [chief retainers].)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given 430,000 koku (crop yields) in Hachiman-yama Castle in Omi Province (of which 230,000 were for Otoshiyori (chief retainers) as a reward).</e>
<cmt>Wording. I also added &quot;as a reward&quot; as I think this reflects the meaning better.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given 430,000 koku (crop yields) in Hachimanyama-jo Castle in Omi Province (of which 230,000 were for Otoshiyori [chief retainers] as a reward).</e>
<cmt>Hachimanyama-jo Castle としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>領内の統治でも善政を布いたと言われ、近江八幡市には「水争い裁きの像」などが残り逸話が語り継がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to be a good governor for inside of the territory, a &apos;Statue of Justice for the fight over water&apos; was remained in Hachiman City, Omi Province, and the anecdote has been handed down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to be a good governor for the inside of the territory, a &quot;Statue of Justice for the Fight Over Water&quot; remains in Hachiman City, Omi Province, and such anecdote have been handed down.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to be a good governor for the inside of the territory; a &apos;Statue of Justice for the Fight Over Water&apos; remains in Omihachiman City, and his anecdotes have been handed down.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これは田中吉政など家臣の功績が大きいとも言われているが、悪政を敷いた代官を自ら成敗したり名代を任せた父の三好吉房について「頼りない」と評価するなど主体性を発揮した面も伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This might be due to a great achievement of his vassals, Yoshimasa TANAKA and others, but the another face of Hidetsugu showed his independence, such that he himself punished the local governors who operated maladministration and judged his father Yoshifusa MIYOSHI, who was in charge of Myodai (a substitute), &apos;unreliable&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This might be due to the great achievement of his vassals, Yoshimasa TANAKA and others, but another face of Hidetsugu showed his independence, such that he himself punished the local governors who misgoverned and judged his father Yoshifusa MIYOSHI, who was in charge of Myodai (a substitute), &quot;unreliable&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This might be due to the great achievement of his vassals, Yoshimasa TANAKA and others, but another face of Hidetsugu showed his independence, such that he himself punished the local governors who misgoverned and judged his father Yoshifusa MIYOSHI, who was in charge of Myodai (a substitute), &apos;unreliable.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>吉政らの補佐を受けつつ、徐々に彼らを使いこなすに至ったというのが実像であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So that the real image is that he gradually controlled them supported by Yoshimasa and other vassels.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The real image is that he gradually controlled them while being supported by Yoshimasa and other vassels.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The real image is that he gradually controlled them while being supported by Yoshimasa and other vassels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>天正18年（1590年）の小田原の役にも参加し、戦後、移封を拒否して改易された織田信雄の旧領である尾張国、伊勢国北部5郡などに100万石の大領を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attended the Battle of Odawara in 1590, and a large territory of 1 million koku was given in Owari Province and 5 Counties in the north of Ise Province where were the former territory of Nobuo ODA who was dismissed after the war because of refusal of changing territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attended the Battle of Odawara in 1590, and was given a large territory of one million koku (crop yields) was given in Owari Province and five districts in the north of Ise Province in the former territory of Nobuo ODA who was dismissed after the war because of refusal of changing territory.</e>
<cmt>Wording. I also added &quot;(crop yields)&quot; after koku, but as it has been explained already, is it necessary? Please check.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attended the Battle of Odawara in 1590, and was given a large territory of one million koku in Owari Province and five districts in the north of Ise Province in the former territory of Nobukatsu ODA who was dismissed after the war because of refusal of changing territory.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>葛西・大崎一揆においても鎮圧で武功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He achieved military exploits to suppress Kasai Osaki riot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He achieved military exploits to suppress the Kasai Osaki riot.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He achieved military exploits to suppress the Kasai and Osaki riot.</e>
<cmt>Kasai and Osaki としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last moment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Final Days</e>
<cmt>I think this phrase will vary greatly depending on the context it is used.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>天正19年（1591年）8月に秀吉の嫡男・豊臣鶴松が死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsurumatsu TOYOTOMI, a legitimate son of Hideyoshi died in August 1591.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsurumatsu TOYOTOMI, a legitimate son of Hideyoshi, died in August 1591.</e>
<cmt>Added a comma.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsurumatsu TOYOTOMI, a legitimate son of Hideyoshi, died in September 1591.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そのため、11月に秀吉の養子となり、12月には秀吉の後継者として、豊臣姓を贈られ、関白職を譲られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly Hidetsugu was adopted to Hideyoshi in November, given TOYOTOMI cognomen as a successor of Hideyoshi in December, and was passed over the post of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, Hidetsugu was adopted by Hideyoshi in November and was given TOYOTOMI cognomen as a successor of Hideyoshi in December, and was passed over for the post of Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, Hidetsugu was adopted by Hideyoshi in December and was given TOYOTOMI cognomen as a successor of Hideyoshi in January of the next year, and was passed over for the post of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。関白　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>そして聚楽第に居住して政務を執ったが、秀吉は全権を譲ったわけではなく、二元政治となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He moved to Jurakudai residence to live and operated the government affairs, but as Hideyoshi did not give full powers, dual government existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He moved to the Jurakudai residence to live and operated government affairs, but as Hideyoshi did not turn over full powers, a dual government existed.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He moved to the Jurakudai residence to live and operated government affairs, but as Hideyoshi did not turn over full powers, a dual government existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その後、文禄・慶長の役に専念する秀吉の代わりに内政を司ることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, he controlled domestic administration substituted for Hideyoshi who dedicated to the Battle of Bunroku Keicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, he controlled domestic administrations for Hideyoshi who was dedicating himself to the Battle of Bunroku Keicho.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, he controlled domestic administrations for Hideyoshi who was dedicating himself to the Battle of Bunroku and Keicho.</e>
<cmt>Bunroku and Keicho としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし文禄2年（1593年）に秀吉に実子・豊臣秀頼が生まれると、秀吉から次第に疎まれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However when a biological child of Hideyoshi, Hideyori TOYOTOMI was born in 1593, Hidetsugu got on the wrong side of Hideyoshi gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when a biological child of Hideyoshi, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, was born in 1593, Hidetsugu gradually got on the wrong side of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when a biological child of Hideyoshi, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, was born in 1593, Hidetsugu gradually got on the wrong side of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>秀頼と秀次の娘を婚約させるなど互いに譲歩も試みられたが、けっきょく文禄4年（1595年）7月8日、秀吉の命令で高野山に追放され、出家した（これ以降、出家した関白＝禅閤となり、豊臣の姓から豊禅閤〈ほうぜんこう〉と呼ばれた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They tried to compromise by affiancing Hideyori and a daughter of Hidetsugu, but after all he was expelled to Koyasan by the order of Hideyoshi in July 8, 1595, then he became a priest, (he became a priest chief adviser to the Emperor called Zenko, and called Hozenko related to the name of TOYOTOMI.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They tried to compromise by affiancing Hideyori and a daughter of Hidetsugu, but in the end he was expelled to Koyasan by the order of Hideyoshi on July 8, 1595. He then he became a priest (he became a priest chief adviser to the Emperor (Zenko), and called was Hozenko, a name related to Toyotomi).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They tried to compromise by affiancing Hideyori and a daughter of Hidetsugu, but in the end he was expelled to Mt. Koya by the order of Hideyoshi on August 13, 1595; subsequently he became a priest (he became a priest Kanpaku [Zenko], and was called Hozenko, a name related to Toyotomi).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。高野山→Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>同年7月15日に切腹を命じられ青巌寺・柳の間にて死亡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was ordered Seppuku on July 15, he died at Willow room at Seigan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ordered committ seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) on July 15, and he died in the Willow room at Seigan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Wording. I added &quot;(suicide by disembowelment)&quot; as a description of seppuku as this is the first sentence in the document where seppuku is mentioned. Please check that this is OK as I am not sure if an explanation is necessary or not. I have not added the explanation anywhere else in the document where seppuku is mentioned.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was ordered to commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) on August 20, and he died in the Willow room at Seigan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>享年28。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at age of 28.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at age of 28.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>死後、秀次の一族・妻妾・息子・娘・家臣の多くが粛清され、秀次の首は秀吉によって京都の三条河原に曝された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death, the family of Hidetsugu, his wives and concubines, sons and daughters and many of vassals were purged, and the head of Hidetsugu was exposed by Hideyoshi at SANJOGAWARA in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his death, the family of Hidetsugu, his wives and concubines, sons and daughters along with many of his vassals, were purged, and the head of Hidetsugu was exposed by Hideyoshi at Sanjogawara in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death, the family of Hidetsugu, his wives and concubines, sons and daughters along with many of his vassals, were purged, and the head of Hidetsugu was exposed by Hideyoshi at Sanjogawara in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>秀吉により、新たに秀頼が後継者へ指名され、秀吉の死後、秀頼が家督を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyori was appointed by Hideyoshi to be a successor and succeeded the family estate after Hideyoshi died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyori was appointed by Hideyoshi to be a successor and succeeded the family estate after Hideyoshi died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyori was appointed by Hideyoshi to be a successor and succeeded the family estate after Hideyoshi died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>秀次事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hidetsugu Incident</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hidetsugu Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>秀次であったが、文禄元年（1593年）、秀吉に新たな子豊臣秀頼が生まれると関係が決定的に悪化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi had a new son Hideyori TOYOTOMI in 1593, the relation between Hidetsugu and Hideyoshi was deteriorated decisively.</e>
<cmt>秀次であったが、の部分の前文が不明のため、この部分は訳していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi had a new son, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, in 1593, and the relationship between Hidetsugu and Hideyoshi decisively deteriorated.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi had a new son, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, in 1593, and the relationship between Hidetsugu and Hideyoshi decisively deteriorated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）に秀吉によって謀反の疑いをかけられることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was put under suspicion of a rebellion by Hideyoshi in 1595.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was put under suspicion of a rebellion by Hideyoshi in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was put under suspicion of a rebellion by Hideyoshi in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>同年7月3日、聚楽第に居た秀次のもとへ石田三成ら五奉行のうち4名が訪れ、秀次に対し高野山へ行くように促された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 3, 1595, 4 out of 5 magistrates including Mitsunari ISHIDA visited Hidetsugu at Jurakudai residence, urged him to go to Koyasan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 3, 1595, four out of five magistrates including Mitsunari ISHIDA visited Hidetsugu at the Jurakudai residence and urged him to go to Koyasan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 8, 1595, four out of five magistrates including Mitsunari ISHIDA visited Hidetsugu at the Jurakudai residence and urged him to go to Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。高野山→Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>同月8日に秀次は謀反についての釈明の為に、秀吉の居る伏見城へ赴くが、対面することが出来ず、同日高野山へ入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 8 Hidetsugu visited Hideyoshi in Fushimi-jo Castle to explain about the rebellion, but he could not meet him, and went to Koyasan on the same day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 8, Hidetsugu visited Hideyoshi in Fushimi-jo Castle to explain the rebellion, but he could not meet him, and went to Koyasan on the same day.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 13, Hidetsugu visited Hideyoshi in Fushimi-jo Castle to explain the rebellion, but he could not meet him, and went to Mt. Koya on the same day.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。高野山→Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>それから1週間後の15日に秀次のもとへ福島正則らが訪れ、秀次に対し秀吉から切腹の命令が下ったことを伝えられ、同日、秀次及び秀次の小姓らを含めた嫌疑をかけられた人々が切腹することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A week later on 15, Masanori FUKUSHIMA and some others visited Hidetsugu to tell the order of Seppuku given by Hideyoshi, finally Hidetsugu and others under suspicion including his pages committed suicide by disembowelment on that day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A week later on July 15, Masanori FUKUSHIMA and some others visited Hidetsugu to pass on the order of committing seppuku given by Hideyoshi. Hidetsugu and others under suspicion including his pages committed seppuku that day.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A week later on August 20, Masanori FUKUSHIMA and some others visited Hidetsugu to pass on the order of committing seppuku given by Hideyoshi; Hidetsugu and others under suspicion including his pages committed seppuku that day.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>秀次は雀部重政の介錯により切腹し、そして重政と東福寺の僧侶玄隆西堂も切腹した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu did Seppuku with a support of Shigemasa SASABE who assisted Hidetsugu in committing hara-kiri by beheading him, then Shigemasa and a Buddhist monk of Tofuku-ji Temple Genryuseido also committed suicide by disembowelment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu committed seppuku with the support of Shigemasa SASABE who assisted Hidetsugu in committing seppuku by beheading him. Shigemasa and a Buddhist monk of Tofuku-ji Temple Genryuseido also committed seppuku.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu committed seppuku with the support of Shigemasa SASABE who assisted Hidetsugu by beheading him, while Shigemasa and a Buddhist monk of Tofuku-ji Temple Genryuseido also committed seppuku.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>秀次及び同日切腹した関係者らの遺体は金剛峰寺に葬られ、秀次の首は三条河原へ送られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">he corpses of Hidetsugu and the persons concerned to Seppuku were buried at Kongobuji Temple, and the head of Hidetsugu was sent to Sanjogawara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The corpses of Hidetsugu along with those associated with seppuku were buried at Kongobuji Temple, and the head of Hidetsugu was sent to Sanjogawara.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Please check the translation of &quot;関係者&quot;. Is &quot;those associated&quot; appropriate?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The corpses of Hidetsugu along with those who committed seppuku were buried at Kongobu-ji Temple, and the head of Hidetsugu was sent to Sanjogawara.</e>
<cmt>associated with seppuku →committed seppuku としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>そして、同年8月2日 (旧暦)（9月5日）には三条河原において、秀次の家族及び女人らも処刑されることになり、秀次の首が据えられた塚の前で、遺児（4男1女）及び正室・側室・侍女ら併せて39名が処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 2, 1595, the family of Hidetsugu and females were put to death at Sanjogawara, 39 people in total including the bereaved child (4 boys and 1 girl), a lawful wife, concubines, and waiting women were put to death in front of the tumulus where the head of Hidetsugu was laid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 2, 1595, the family of Hidetsugu including the women were executed at Sanjogawara. A total of 39 people including the bereaved children (four boys and one girl), a lawful wife, concubines, and waiting women were executed in front of the tumulus where the head of Hidetsugu was laid.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 5, 1595, the family of Hidetsugu including the women were executed at Sanjogawara; a total of 39 people including the bereaved children (four boys and one girl), a lawful wife, concubines, and waiting women were executed in front of the tumulus where the head of Hidetsugu was laid.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>約5時間かけて行われた秀次の家族らの処刑後、その遺体は一箇所に埋葬され、その埋葬地には秀次の首を収めた石櫃が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the execution of the family of Hidetsugu which took about 5 hours, those corpses were buried in one place, a cist which the head of Hidetsugu was in it placed at the burial ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the execution of the family of Hidetsugu which took about five hours, the corpses were buried in the one place. A cist (a box-shaped funerary urn made of stone) in which the head of Hidetsugu was put, was placed at the burial ground.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the execution of the family of Hidetsugu which took about five hours, the corpses were buried in one place, and a cist (a box-shaped funerary urn made of stone) in which the head of Hidetsugu was put, was placed at the burial ground.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>その後、秀次ら一族の埋葬地は慶長16年(1611年)、豪商の角倉了以によって再建されるまで、誰にも顧みられることなく放置されていた（畜生塚）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on the burial place had been neglected and left there until a wealthy merchant Ryoi SUMINOKURA reconstructed it. (Chikushozuka [Mound of Beasts])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The burial place was neglected until a wealthy merchant named Ryoi SUMINOKURA reconstructed it (Chikushozuka (Mound of Beasts)).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The burial place was neglected until a wealthy merchant named Ryoi SUMINOKURA reconstructed it (Chikusho-zuka [Mound of Beasts]) in 1611.</e>
<cmt>1611年　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>なお、秀次に関連した大名は監禁させられ聚楽第も破却された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) who were related to Hidetsugu were confined, and Jurakudai residence was destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) who were related to Hidetsugu were confined, and the Jurakudai residence was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimyo who were related to Hidetsugu were confined, and the Jurakudai residence was also destroyed.</e>
<cmt>既出の単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>ただし、秀次の妻子が皆殺しにされたわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it does not mean that all of wives and children of Hidetsugu were killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this does not mean that all of the wives and children of Hidetsugu were killed.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this does not mean that all of the wives and children of Hidetsugu were killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>淡輪徹斎隆重の娘・小督の局との娘のお菊は女児であり尚且つ生後一ヶ月の幼さであったためか助命され、お菊の祖父の弟の子の後藤興義に預けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okiku, a daughter between Kogo-no-tsubone who was a daughter of Tessai Takashige TANNOWA was spared as she was a girl and only 1 month old, so she was left to Okiyoshi GOTO who was a son of the younger brother of Okiku&apos;s grandfather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okiku, a daughter of Kogo-no-tsubone (who was a daughter of Tessai Takashige TANNOWA) was spared as she was a girl and only one month old. She was left to Okiyoshi GOTO who was a son of the younger brother of Okiku&apos;s grandfather.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okiku, a daughter of Kogo-no-tsubone (who was a daughter of Tessai Takashige TANNOWA) was spared as she was a girl and only one month old; she was left to Okiyoshi GOTO who was a son of the younger brother of Okiku&apos;s grandfather.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、のちの真田信繁の側室・隆精院、梅小路家に嫁いだ娘の二人も難を逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, 2 other daughters who became a concubine of Nobushige SANADA, Ryuseiin later, and one who married into Umenokoji family could get out of trouble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, two other daughters who became concubines of Nobushige SANADA (later Ryuseiin), and one who married into the Umenokoji family were able to get themselves out of trouble.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Please check that &quot;(later Ryuseiin)&quot; is appropriate.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, a daughter named Ryuseiin, who later became a concubine of Nobushige SANADA, and two other daughters who married into the Umenokoji family were able to get themselves out of trouble.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>他にも正室である池田恒興の娘・若御前も助命され、兄・池田輝政のもとに送り返されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakagozen who was a lawful wife and a daughter of Tsuneoki IKEDA was also spared and sent back to his elder brother Terumasa IKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakagozen, who was a lawful wife and daughter of Tsuneoki IKEDA, was also spared and sent back to his elder brother Terumasa IKEDA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakagozen, who was a lawful wife and daughter of Tsuneoki IKEDA, was also spared and sent back to his elder brother Terumasa IKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="49">
<j>この秀次ら一族処刑に関して、その経緯を記した絵巻「瑞泉寺縁起」が京都の瑞泉寺 (京都市)に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emaki (picture scroll) &apos;Zuisen-ji Temple engi (writing about the history)&apos;written about the process of the execute of Hidetsugu and his family has been kept in Zuisen-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emaki (picture scroll) &quot;Zuisen-ji Temple Engi&quot; (writing of history) written about the process of the execution of Hidetsugu and his family is kept in Zuisen-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emaki (picture scroll) &apos;Zuisen-ji Temple Engi&apos; (writing of history) written about the process of the execution of Hidetsugu and his family is kept in Zuisen-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>粛清の理由</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason of purge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Reasons for Purging</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons for purging</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>秀次粛清の理由において、次のような説が上げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following theories are given as the reason of the purge of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following theories are given as reasons for the purging of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following theories are given as reasons for the purging of Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>実子である秀頼の後継を確実なものとし、秀次の子孫を根絶やしにして直系継承を守るため</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to ensure that the successors wase the real son Hideyori and to eradicate the descendants of Hidetsugu to secure the succession of the direct line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to ensure that the successors were the real sons of Hideyori and to eradicate the descendants of Hidetsugu to secure the succession of the direct line.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to ensure the succession by the real son Hideyori and to eradicate the descendants of Hidetsugu to secure the succession of the direct line.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>秀頼誕生後から酒色に溺れ、女狂いになったなどの奇行説（→「殺生関白」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A theory of eccentric behavior after Hideyori was born such as addiction to alcohol and being crazy for woman. (Sessho Kanpaku [life-killing kanpaku])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A theory of eccentric behavior after Hideyori was born such as addiction to alcohol and being crazy for women (Sessho Kanpaku (life-killing kanpaku)).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A theory of eccentric behavior after Hideyori was born such as addiction to alcohol and being crazy for women (Sessho Kanpaku [life-killing kanpaku]).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>秀頼の生母・淀殿と「近江派」の吏僚・石田三成らによる陰謀説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A conspiracy theory by a real mother of Hideyori, Yodo-dono and an executive officer of &apos;Omi group&apos; Mitsunari ISHIDA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A conspiracy theory by the real mother of Hideyori, Yodo-dono, and an executive officer of &quot;Omi group&quot;, Mitsunari ISHIDA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A conspiracy theory by the real mother of Hideyori, Yodo-dono, and an executive officer of &apos;Omi group,&apos; Mitsunari ISHIDA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>（ただし、武功夜話によると、三成は秀次の無罪を主張していたという。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(However according to Bukoyawa [one of the family genealogies], Mitsunari insisted the innocence of Hidetsugu.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(However, according to Bukoyawa (one of the family genealogies), Mitsunari insisted on the innocence of Hidetsugu.)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, according to Bukoyawa (one of the family genealogies), Mitsunari insisted on the innocence of Hidetsugu.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>秀次切腹の主な連座者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main persons of complicity of Hidetsugu&apos;s seppuku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main persons of complicity of Hidetsugu&apos;s seppuku.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main persons of complicity of Hidetsugu&apos;s seppuku</e>
<cmt>二バイト文字を修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>切腹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seppuku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seppuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seppuku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>木村重茲（助命後自裁）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigekore KIMURA (committed suicide after spared)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigekore KIMURA (committed suicide after being spared)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigekore KIMURA (committed suicide after being spared)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>木村志摩守（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KIMURA Shima no kami (Governor of Shima Province) (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KIMURA Shima no kami (Governor of Shima Province) (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Despite the set terminology, I changed &quot;Granting death&quot; to &quot;sentenced to death&quot; throughout the document.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KIMURA Shima no kami (Governor of Shima Province) (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>前野長康（助命後自裁）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayasu MAENO (committed suicide after spared)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayasu MAENO (committed suicide after being spared)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayasu MAENO (committed suicide after being spared)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>前野景定（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagesada MAENO (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagesada MAENO (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagesada MAENO (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>羽田正親（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masachika HANEDA (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masachika HANEDA (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masachika HANEDA (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>服部一忠（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazutada HATTORI (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazutada HATTORI (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazutada HATTORI (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>渡瀬繁詮（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeaki WATARASE (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeaki WATARASE (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeaki WATARASE (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>明石則実（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norizane AKASHI (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norizane AKASHI (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norizane AKASHI (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>一柳可遊（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kayu HITOTSUYANAGI (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kayu HITOTSUYANAGI (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kayu HITOTSUYANAGI (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>粟野秀用（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidemochi AWANO (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidemochi AWANO (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidemochi AWANO (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>白江成定（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narisada SHIRAE (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narisada SHIRAE (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narisada SHIRAE (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>熊谷直澄（熊谷直之）（賜死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naosumi KUMAGAI (Naoyuki KUMAGAI) (Granting death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naosumi KUMAGAI (Naoyuki KUMAGAI) (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naosumi KUMAGAI (Naoyuki KUMAGAI) (sentenced to death)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>三好吉房（改易・流罪）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshifusa MIYOSHI (Kaieki [forfeit rank of Samurai and properties], Deportation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshifusa MIYOSHI (kaieki (stripping of rank of Samurai and properties) and deported)</e>
<cmt>I changed the explanation to kaieki to make it easier to understand.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshifusa MIYOSHI (kaieki [stripping of rank of samurai and properties] and deported)</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>六角義郷（改易）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshisato ROKKAKU (Kaieki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshisato ROKKAKU (kaieki (stripping of rank of Samurai and properties))</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshisato ROKKAKU (kaieki)</e>
<cmt>改易　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>木下吉隆（改易・流罪）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka KINOSHITA (Kaieki, Deportation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka KINOSHITA (kaieki (stripping of rank of Samurai and properties) and deported)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka KINOSHITA (kaieki and deported)</e>
<cmt>改易　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>里村紹巴（蟄居）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joha SATOMURA (House arrest)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joha SATOMURA (house arrest)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joha SATOMURA (house arrest)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>浅野幸長（流罪→のちに復帰）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaga ASANO (Deportation, Returned later)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaga ASANO (deported, but later returned)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaga ASANO (deported, but later returned)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>前野忠康（浪人）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayasu MAENO (Ronin [masterless samurai])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayasu MAENO (Ronin (masterless samurai))</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayasu MAENO (Ronin [masterless samurai])</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>滝川雄利（除封）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsutoshi TAKIGAWA (Johou [the same as Kaieki])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsutoshi TAKIGAWA (joho (the same as Kaieki))</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsutoshi TAKIGAWA (joho [the same as Kaieki])</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>荒木元清（追放）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motokiyo ARAKI (Banishment)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motokiyo ARAKI (banished)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motokiyo ARAKI (banished)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>菊亭晴季（流罪）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harusue KIKUTEI (Deportation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harusue KIKUTEI (deported)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harusue KIKUTEI (deported)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>土御門有脩（流罪）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arinaga TSUCHIMIKADO (Deportation)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arinaga TSUCHIMIKADO (deported)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arinaga TSUCHIMIKADO (deported)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>難を逃れた主な人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profiles who were saved from trouble</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who evaded trouble</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who evaded trouble</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>藤堂高虎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatora TODO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatora TODO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatora TODO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>中村一氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazuuji NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazuuji NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazuuji NAKAMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>堀尾吉晴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu HORIO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu HORIO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu HORIO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>山内一豊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>伊達政宗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamune DATE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamune DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamune DATE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>最上義光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki MOGAMI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki MOGAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki MOGAMI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>田中吉政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimasa TANAKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimasa TANAKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimasa TANAKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>細川忠興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>最上、細川、伊達らは徳川家康の取り成しで事なきを得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MOGAMI, HOSOKAWA, DATE were saved from trouble through the good offices of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mogami, Hosokawa, and Date were saved from trouble through mediation of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mogami, Hosokawa, and Date were saved from trouble through mediation of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>「殺生関白」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sessho Kanpaku (life-killing kanpaku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sessho Kanpaku (life-killing kanpaku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sessho Kanpaku (life-killing kanpaku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="86">
<j>事件直前の秀次は嗜好殺人などの非道行為（盲人を辻斬りにした）を繰り返したとも言われ、「殺生関白」（「摂政関白」の韻に掛けた創作）の異名をとったという話は有名であるが、実情は不明であり疑わしい点も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu was said that he repeated villainy actions such as preference murder (he killed a blind man on the street.) so it is famous that he got another name &apos;Sessho Kanpaku (life-killing Kanapku)&apos; (a homonym of Sessho Kanpaku [regent and chief adviser to the Emperor]), but the actual circumstances are unknown and a lot of points are doubtful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Hidetsugu repeated villainies such as preference murder (he killed a blind man on the street), thus he famously was given the name &quot;Sessho Kanpaku&quot; (life-killing kanapku), a homonym of Sessho Kanpaku (Regent and Chief Adviser to the Emperor), but the actual circumstances are unknown and a lot of points are doubtful.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Hidetsugu repeated villainies such as preference murder (he killed a blind man on the street), thus he famously was given the name &apos;Sessho Kanpaku,&apos; a homonym of Sessho Kanpaku (Regent and Chief Adviser to the Emperor), but the actual circumstances are unknown and a lot of points are doubtful.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>秀次事件の影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence of Hidetsugu Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence of the Hidetsugu Incident</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence of the Hidetsugu Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>秀次は秀吉晩年の豊臣家の中では唯一とも言ってもよい成人した親族であったため、彼が存命していたなら、後の家康の覇権奪取に抵抗した可能性もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu could be the only adult relative in the TOYOTOMI family in Hideyoshi&apos;s later years, so if Hidetsugu was alive he might have resisted the takeover of hegemony done by Ieyasu later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu could be the only adult relative in the Toyotomi family in Hideyoshi&apos;s later years, so if Hidetsugu was alive he might have resisted the takeover of hegemony later carried out by Ieyasu later.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu could be the only adult relative in the Toyotomi family in Hideyoshi&apos;s later years, so if Hidetsugu was alive he might have resisted the takeover of hegemony later carried out by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>later ダブりを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>秀次とその子をほぼ殺し尽くしたことは、数少ない豊臣家の親族をさらに弱める結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The massacre of Hidetsugu and his children resulted to make the small TOYOTOMI family much weaker.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The massacre of Hidetsugu and his children resulted in making the small Toyotomi family much weaker.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The massacre of Hidetsugu and his children resulted in making the small Toyotomi family much weaker.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>また、秀次事件に関係し秀吉の不興を買った大名は総じて関ヶ原の戦いで徳川方である東軍に属することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) who got displeasure by Hideyoshi relating to the Hidetsugu Incident belonged to the East army as Tokugawa side at the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) who incurred Hideyoshi&apos;s displeasure in regards to the Hidetsugu Incident belonged to the East Army of the Tokugawa side at the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, daimyo who incurred Hideyoshi&apos;s displeasure in regards to the Hidetsugu Incident belonged to the East camp of the Tokugawa side at the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="90">
<j>笠谷和比古は、朝鮮出兵をめぐる吏僚派と武断派の対立などとともに、秀次事件が豊臣家及び豊臣家臣団の亀裂を決定的にした豊臣政権の政治的矛盾のひとつであり、関ヶ原の戦いの一因と指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazuhiko KASAYA pointed that as well as the confliction between a civilian party and a military government group over the dispatch troops to Korea, Hidetsugu Incident was one of the political contradiction of the TOYOTOMI government that decided the crack in the vassals of the TOYOTOMI clan and the TOYOTOMI family, and it was one of the reasons of the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazuhiko KASAYA pointed out that as well as the confliction between civilian parties and military government groups over the dispatch of troops to Korea, the Hidetsugu Incident was one of the political contradictions of the Toyotomi government that determined the cracks in the vassals of the Toyotomi clan and the Toyotomi family, and it was one of the causes of the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazuhiko KASAYA pointed out that as well as the confliction between civilian parties and military government groups over the dispatch of troops to Korea, the Hidetsugu Incident was one of the political contradictions of the Toyotomi government that determined the cracks within the Toyotomi family and the Toyotomi vassals, and it was one of the causes of the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="91">
<j>秀次は通説として凡庸・無能な武将として評価されることが多いが、秀次の失敗は小牧・長久手の戦いの敗戦の一度だけであり、その後の紀伊・四国征伐、小田原征伐での山中城攻め、奥州仕置などでは武功を発揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a popular theory, Hidetsugu was evaluated often as a Japanese military commander of mediocre and incapable, but his failure was only the defeat of the Battle of Komaki Nagakute, and later he achieved the military exploits at the Kii Shikoku Conquest, the Siege of Yamanaka-jo Castle at the Conquest and Siege of Odawara, and the punishment in Oshu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a popular theory, Hidetsugu was evaluated often as a mediocre and incapable Japanese military commander, but his failure was only the defeat of the Battle of Komaki Nagakute. He later achieved military exploits at the Kii Shikoku Conquest, the Siege of Yamanaka-jo Castle at the Conquest and Siege of Odawara, and the executions in Oshu.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a popular theory, Hidetsugu was evaluated often as a mediocre and incapable Japanese military commander, but his failure was only the defeat of the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute; he later achieved military exploits at the Kii and Shikoku Conquests, the Siege of Yamanaka-jo Castle at the Conquest and Siege of Odawara, and the executions in Oshu.</e>
<cmt>Komaki and Nagakute としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>政務においても山内一豊、堀尾吉晴らの補佐もあって無難にこなしていることを考慮すると、そこそこの力量はあったものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering his performance of the affairs of state was fairly well with an assistant of Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI and Yoshiharu HORIO, he might have been a person with moderate ability.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering his performance of state affairs was quite good with the assistance of Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI and Yoshiharu HORIO, he might have been a person with moderate ability.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering his performance of state affairs was quite good with the assistance of Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI and Yoshiharu HORIO, he might have been a person with moderate ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>下記にも書かれてあるとおり文武両道の人物だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had the ability of both the literary and martial arts as described bellow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had the ability of both the literary and martial arts as described below.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the ability of both the literary and martial arts as described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="94">
<j>秀次事件のとき、秀吉譜代の家臣である前野長康、さらには木村重茲、渡瀬繁詮、先に陰謀説で名前の挙がっている石田三成など多くの人物たちが秀次の無罪を主張して弁護していることから、秀次は諸大名から人望があったものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hidetsugu Incident occurred many persons such as Nagayasu MAENO, Shigekore KIMURA, Shigeaki WATARASE who were hereditary vassals of Hideyoshi, and Mitsunari ISHIDA who was known by the conspiracy theory, and many others insisted a innocence of Hidetsugu and protected him, so that it is understandable that Hidetsugu was a respected person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Hidetsugu Incident, many people such as Nagayasu MAENO, Shigekore KIMURA, Shigeaki WATARASE who were hereditary vassals of Hideyoshi, and Mitsunari ISHIDA who was known through conspiracy theories and many others insisted on the innocence of Hidetsugu and protected him, so that it is understandable that Hidetsugu was a respected person.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Hidetsugu Incident occurred, many people such as Nagayasu MAENO, Shigekore KIMURA, Shigeaki WATARASE who were hereditary vassals of Hideyoshi, and Mitsunari ISHIDA who was known through conspiracy theories and many others insisted on the innocence of Hidetsugu and protected him, so that it is understandable that Hidetsugu was a respected person.</e>
<cmt>After →When the Hidetsugu Incident occurred　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="95">
<j>秀次はキリシタンではないにも関わらず、宣教師からは穏やかで思慮深い性質であると賞賛の言葉をもらっている（ルイス・フロイス「日本史」など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of not being a Christian, Hidetsugu was praised by a missionary that he was a gentle and considerable person. (Luis FROIS &apos;History of Japan&apos; etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of not being a Christian, Hidetsugu was praised by a missionary that he was a gentle and considerable person (Luis FROIS &quot;History of Japan&quot;, etc.).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of not being a Christian, Hidetsugu was praised by a missionary that he was a gentle and considerable person (Luis FROIS &apos;History of Japan,&apos; etc.).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>この点からも巷説の「殺生関白」は実像だったか疑問がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this point, it is doubtful whether the gossip of &apos;Sessho Kanpaku (life-killing kanpaku) was his real image or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this point, it is doubtful whether the gossip of &quot;Sessho Kanpaku&quot; (life-killing kanpaku) was his real image or not.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this point, it is doubtful whether the gossip of &apos;Sessho Kanpaku&apos; was his real image or not.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>キリスト教についても理解を示し、キリシタンであったのではないかとする研究者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he understood Christianity, some researchers consider that he might have been a Christian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he understood Christianity, some researchers consider that he might have been a Christian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he understood Christianity, some researchers consider that he might have been a Christian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="98">
<j>秀次は古筆を愛し、多くの公家とも交流を持つ当代一流の教養人でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu was a first-rank educated person of the day who loved ancient Japanese writings and held cultural exchanges with many Court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu was a first-rank educated person of the day who loved ancient Japanese writings and held cultural exchanges with many court nobles.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu was a first-rank educated person of the day who loved ancient Japanese writings and held cultural exchanges with many court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>学問の上達ぶりを賞賛する公家の手記も現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collections of notes written by Court of nobles exist, in which they admired his improvement of learning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collections of notes written by court nobles exist, in which they admired his improvement of learning.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collections of notes written by court nobles exist, in which they admired his improvement of learning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>一方、在野の学者である藤原惺窩などは秀次を低く評価し、「学問が穢れる」と相手にしなかったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, scholars who were out of power such as Seika FUJIWARA were known that they devaluated Hidetsugu and ignored him saying &apos; Learning become corrupt&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, scholars who were out of power such as Seika FUJIWARA were known to devaluate Hidetsugu and ignored him, saying &quot;Learning becomes corrupt&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Please check the translation of &quot;学問が穢れる&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, scholars who were out of power such as Seika FUJIWARA were known to devaluate Hidetsugu and ignored him, saying &apos;Learning becomes corrupt.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>ただし藤原惺窩の父・冷泉為純は秀吉によって見殺しにされているため、秀吉の養子である秀次をあえて酷評した可能性も否定できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Seika FUJIWARA&apos;s father Tamezumi REIZEI was left in the lurch by Hideyoshi, a possibility cannot be denied that he dared criticize Hidetsugu severely as he was an adopted son of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Seika FUJIWARA&apos;s father, Tamezumi REIZEI, was left in the lurch by Hideyoshi, the possibility cannot be denied that he dared criticize Hidetsugu severely as he was an adopted son of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Seika FUJIWARA&apos;s father, Tamezumi REIZEI, was left in the lurch by Hideyoshi, the possibility cannot be denied that he dared criticize Hidetsugu severely as he was an adopted son of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="102">
<j>武術については、疋田景兼より剣術と槍術を学んだほか、長谷川宗喜や片山久安からも剣術を学んだとされ、切腹の際の介錯ができるだけの腕前があったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for martial arts, he learned swordplay and the art of the spearman from Kagekane HIKITA, and also learned swordplay from Munenobu HASEGAWA and Hisayasu KATAYAMA, so that he had the ability of Kaishaku (to assist someone in committing hara-kiri by beheading him) at the scene of Seppuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for martial arts, he learned swordplay and the art of spearmanship from Kagekane HIKITA, and also learned swordplay from Munenobu HASEGAWA and Hisayasu KATAYAMA, and thus had the ability of kaishaku (to assist someone in committing seppuku by beheading him) at during the act of seppuku.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for martial arts, he learned swordplay and the art of spearmanship from Kagekane HIKITA, and also learned swordplay from Munenobu HASEGAWA and Hisayasu KATAYAMA, and thus had the ability of kaishaku (to assist someone in committing seppuku by beheading him) during the act of seppuku.</e>
<cmt>at を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>刀剣の鑑定も行っていた形跡もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is evidence that he authenticated swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is evidence that he authenticated swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is evidence that he authenticated swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>このほか日置流、荒木流馬術も学んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also learned Heki-ryu (a school of Japanese archery) and Araki-ryu Japanese horsemanship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also learned Heki-ryu (a school of Japanese archery) and Araki-ryu (Japanese horse-back archery technique).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also learned Heki-ryu school of Japanese archery and Araki-ryu school of horse-back archery.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>秀次の特殊な偏諱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu&apos;s Specific Henki (granting subordinates the use of a Chinese character from the superior&apos;s real name)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu&apos;s Specific Henki (granting subordinates the use of a Japanese character from the superior&apos;s real name).</e>
<cmt>I changed &quot;Chinese character&quot; to &quot;Japanese character&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu&apos;s specific henki (granting subordinates the use of a Japanese character from the superior&apos;s real name).</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="105">
<j>大名の常として、秀次も有力な家臣の子などに偏諱（へんき）を授けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), Hidetsugu granted the children of strong vassals the use of a Chinese character of his name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), Hidetsugu granted the children of strong vassals the use of a Japanese character of his name.</e>
<cmt>I changed &quot;Chinese character&quot; to &quot;Japanese character&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a daimyo, Hidetsugu granted the children of strong vassals the use of a Japanese character of his name.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>偏諱を受けたと思しき武将には田中吉次、織田長次、増田盛次らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The military commanders who might have been granted a Chinese character were Yoshitsugu TANAKA, Nagatsugu ODA, and Moritsugu MASUDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The military commanders who might have been granted a Japanese character were Yoshitsugu TANAKA, Nagatsugu ODA, and Moritsugu MASUDA.</e>
<cmt>I changed &quot;Chinese character&quot; to &quot;Japanese character&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The military commanders who might have been granted a Japanese character from his name were Yoshitsugu TANAKA, Nagatsugu ODA, and Moritsugu MASUDA.</e>
<cmt>from his name を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>秀次の偏諱は他の武将と異なり、下偏諱を諱の下の字として与えるという変わった形態を取っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu granted his name in a different way from others that he gave the latter Chinese character of his name for the second portion of the name of subordinates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu granted his name in a different way from others in that he gave the latter Japanese character of his name for the second portion of the name of subordinates.</e>
<cmt>I changed &quot;Chinese character&quot; to &quot;Japanese character&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu granted his name in a different way from others in that he gave the latter Japanese character of his name for the second portion of the name of subordinates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="108">
<j>※日付＝旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dates are written by the old lunar calendar</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dates are written in the form of the old lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dates are written in the form of the old lunar calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>天正13年（1585年）10月、従四位下右近衛権少将に叙任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1585, he was ordained to Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, Ukonoe gonno shosho (major general).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1585, he was ordained to Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, Ukonoe gonno shosho (Major General).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1585, he was ordained to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Ukone no Gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>右近衛権少将　補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="110">
<j>天正14年（1586年）右近衛権中将に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He transferred to Ukonoe gonno chujo (lieutenant general) in 1586.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He transferred to Ukonoe gonno chujo (Lieutenant General) in 1586.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1586, he was transferred to Ukone no Gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>右近衛権中将 補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>11月25日、参議に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Sangi, Councilor on November 25.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Sangi (Councilor) on November 25.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 25, he was appointed to Sangi (Councilor).</e>
<cmt>文章表現を日付から開始するように統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>右近衛権中将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He remained in the position of Ukonoe gonno chujo (lieutenant general).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He remained in the position of Ukonoe gonno chujo (Lieutenant General).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained his position of Ukone no Gon no chujo.</e>
<cmt>如元　表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="113">
<j>天正15年（1587年）11月22日、従三位に昇叙し、権中納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Junior Third Rank, and transferred to Gon Chunagon in November 22, 1587.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Junior Third Rank, and transferred to Gon Chunagon on November 22, 1587.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 22, 1587, he was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), and transferred to Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>文章表現を日付から開始するように統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>新中納言と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Shin-Chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Shin-Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Shin-Chunagon (new Chunagon).</e>
<cmt>新中納言　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>その後、近江中納言あるいは、江州中納言とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he was also called Omi Chunagon or Goshu Chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was later also called Omi Chunagon or Goshu Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was later also called Omi Chunagon or Goshu Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="116">
<j>天正16年（1588年）4月19日、従二位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Junior Second Rank in April 19, 1588.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Junior Second Rank on April 19, 1588.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 19, 1588, he was promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>文章表現を日付から開始するように統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>権中納言如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He remained in the position of Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He remained in the position of Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained his position of Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>如元　表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>この時期、清華家の家格に列す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He joined the family lineage of Seiga family during this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined the family lineage of the Seiga family during this period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He joined the family lineage of the Seiga family (one of the highest court noble families in Japan at that time) during this period.</e>
<cmt>清華家　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="119">
<j>天正19年（1591年）2月11日、正二位に昇叙し、権大納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Senior Second Rank and transferred to Gon Dainagon in February 11, 1591.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Senior Second Rank and transferred to Gon Dainagon on February 11, 1591.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 11, 1591, he was promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank) and transferred to Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>文章表現を日付から開始するように統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>12月4日、内大臣に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He transferred to Naidaijin on December 4.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He transferred to Naidaijin on December 4.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 4, he was transferred to Naidaijin (minister of the center).</e>
<cmt>文章表現を日付から開始するように統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>12月28日、関白宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accepted the imperial proclamation to become Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) on December 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accepted the imperial proclamation to become Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) on December 28.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 28, he accepted the imperial proclamation to become Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>文章表現を日付から開始するように統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>内覧宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received the imperial proclamation to nairan (private inspection).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the imperial proclamation of nairan (private inspection).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the imperial proclamation of nairan (a preliminary inspection of official documents submitted from the daijokan [Great Council of State] to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>内覧　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>豊臣氏長者宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TOYOTOMI clan accepted the imperial proclamation of Chieftain of family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Toyotomi clan accepted the imperial proclamation of Chieftain of the Family</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was proclaimed as the Chieftain of the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>秀次が「豊臣氏長者」の宣下を受けた、と解釈し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>内大臣如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He remained in the present position, Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He remained in the present position of Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained his position of Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>如元　表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="125">
<j>文禄元年（1592年）1月29日、左大臣に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He transferred to the minister of the left in January 29, 1592.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He transferred to Minister of the Left on January 29, 1592.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 29, 1592, he was transferred to Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>文章表現を日付から開始するように統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>関白・内覧・豊臣氏長者如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Chief adviser to the Emperor, Private inspector, he remained in the present position of the TOYOTOMI clan chieftain of family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Chief Adviser to the Emperor, Nairan (one who inspected documents submitted to the Emperor), and remained in the position of Chieftan of the Family of Toyotomi&apos;s clan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained his positions as Kanpaku, Nairan, and Chieftain of the Toyotomi&apos;s clan.</e>
<cmt>既出の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="127">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）7月8日、出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered into priesthood in July 8, 1595.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered the priesthood on July 8, 1595.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 8, 1595, he entered the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>文章表現を日付から開始するように統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>7月15日、没す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in July 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on July 15.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 15, he passed away.</e>
<cmt>文章表現を日付から開始するように統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>墓所と供養</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His graveyard and memorial service for the dead</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His graveyard and memorial service.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His graveyard and memorial service</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graveyard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graveyard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graveyard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="129">
<j>京都市の瑞泉寺 (京都市)に豊臣秀次の五輪の塔と、処刑された者の墓がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gorin Tower (a memorial gravestone for the dead) of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI and the graveyards of executed peoples are in Zuisen-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gorin Tower (a memorial gravestone for the dead) of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI and the graveyards of those executed are in Zuisen-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gorin Tower (a memorial gravestone for the dead) of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI and the graveyards of those executed are in Zuisen-ji Temple (Kyoto City) in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>（京都市）を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>墓所は善正寺 (京都市)にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His graveyard is in Zensho-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His graveyard is in Zensho-ji Temple in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His graveyard is in Zensho-ji Temple (Kyoto City) in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>（京都市）を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="131">
<j>また秀次が切腹した高野山にも墓所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also another graveyard is in Koyasan where Hidetsugu did Seppuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also another graveyard in Koyasan where Hidetsugu committed seppuku.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also another graveyard in Mt. Koya where Hidetsugu committed seppuku.</e>
<cmt>高野山→Mt. Koya としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>供養</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuyo (a memorial service for the dead)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuyo (a memorial service for the dead)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Memorial service</e>
<cmt>小タイトルと統一し、英語の表現にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="132">
<j>豊臣秀次の命日の7月15日には、瑞龍寺 (近江八幡市)住職により、八幡山（滋賀県近江八幡市）で供養が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the anniversary of the death of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI on July 15, a memorial service for him is held at Hachimanyama (Omihachiman city, Shiga Prefecture) by the chief priest of Zuiryu-ji Temple (Omi Hachiman City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the anniversary of the death of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI on July 15, a memorial service for him is held at Hachimanyama (Omihachiman City, Shiga Prefecture) by the chief priest of Zuiryu-ji Temple (Omi Hachiman City).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the anniversary of the death of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI on July 15, a memorial service for him is held at Hachimanyama (Omihachiman City, Shiga Prefecture) by the chief priest of Zuiryu-ji Temple (Omihachiman City).</e>
<cmt>Omihachiman City としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田英(id:85936), いいすく(id:136753), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Arufu(id:733), Sat666(id:127263), ドルチェット(id:46458), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), HI(id:72996), Hyman-roth0512(id:48989), Extrahitz(id:26245), Andee(id:20421), Kamakura(id:472), 猫者(id:206449), Gombe(id:27), Kurz(id:1601), ピノキオ(id:245510), Fumipon(id:46816), ＩＤＳ(id:49634), Azusayumi7(id:21082), A-Taul(id:41790), 蠍(id:93080), TheM(id:47266), Knua(id:66861), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), Chacmool(id:202970), 越中掾(id:149423), Klesha(id:203751), ５１６(id:45205), Kouko0515(id:100370), Sea of Japan(id:3230), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Ach(id:5408), ゆず湯(id:190382), 漬けマグロ(id:145695), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Shinyafortune(id:42940), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), Iwacchi(id:31193), Y.o-ji-nn(id:39866), Bakira(id:184047), 立つのかよ(id:111350), 小者(id:172526), 彩華1226(id:64711), Kagetudo(id:163875), Carkuni(id:79281), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), Kanjy(id:36859), Ksgk(id:276633), Little tree(id:43251), Iriakan PK(id:294640), Nekosuki600(id:21263), 伏儀(id:142093), Safkan(id:423), 満月(id:82772), Mameneko(id:785), Jmho(id:10472), 歴史研究家(id:108842), Sokyo(id:55425), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>