<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>重野安繹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsugu SHIGENO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsugu SHIGENO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsugu SHIGENO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>重野 安繹（しげの やすつぐ、文政10年10月6日 (旧暦)（1827年11月24日） - 明治43年（1910年）12月6日）は江戸末期から明治初期に活躍した漢学者、歴史家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutsugu SHIGENO (November 24, 1827 - December 6, 1910) was a scholar of Chinese classics and a historian, who played an active role during the end of Edo period to the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsugu SHIGENO (November 24, 1827 - December 6, 1910) was a scholar of Chinese classics and a historian, who played an active role during the end of Edo period to the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsugu SHIGENO (November 24, 1827 - December 6, 1910) was a scholar of Chinese classics and a historian, who played an active role during the end of Edo period to the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本で最初に実証主義を提唱した日本歴史学研究の泰斗、また日本最初の文学博士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a person of authority in Japanese history studies, who advocated the positivism for the first time in Japan, and the first PhD in literature.</e>
<cmt>泰斗→person of authorityとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a person of authority in Japanese history studies, who advocated positivism for the first time in Japan, and the first PhD in literature in Japan.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。「日本最初の文学博士」の部分の”日本”を補いました。the positivism→positivism と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a person of authority in Japanese history studies, who advocated positivism for the first time in Japan, and the first PhD in literature in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は厚之丞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Atsunojo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Atsunojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Atsunojo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>字は子徳、号は成斎、曙戒軒鞭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His azana (Chinese courtesy name which was, historically, the name formerly given to adult Chinese men, used in place of their given name in formal situations; scholars and the literati of Japan adopted this custom of courtesy name) was Shitoku, and his pseudonyms were Seisai and Shokaikenben (曙戒軒鞭).</e>
<cmt>曙戒軒鞭→正式な読み方が不明です：Shokaikenben (曙戒軒鞭) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His azana (Chinese courtesy name which was, historically, the name formerly given to adult Chinese men, used in place of their given name in formal situations; scholars and the literati of Japan adopted this custom of courtesy name) was Shitoku, and his pseudonyms were Seisai and Shokaikenben (曙戒軒鞭).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His azana (Chinese courtesy name which was, historically, the name formerly given to adult Chinese men, used in place of their given name in formal situations; scholars and the literati of Japan adopted this custom of courtesy name) was Shitoku, and his pseudonyms were Seisai and Shokaikenben (曙戒軒鞭).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>薩摩国鹿児島郡坂元村生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Sakamoto-mura Village, Kashima Country, Satsuma Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Sakamoto-mura Village, Kasgohima Country, Satsuma Province.</e>
<cmt>Kashima→Kagoshima と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Sakamoto-mura Village, Kasgohima Country, Satsuma Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>元治元年（1864年）に藩校・造士館の講師となり、薩摩藩国父・島津久光の命により『皇朝世鑑』を著す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1865, he became an instructor at hanko (a domain school) of Satsuma Domain, Zoshikan school, and by the order of so called &apos;father of Satsuma Domain,&apos; Hisamitsu SHIMAZU, he wrote &quot;Kochoseikan&quot; (Imperial court almanac).</e>
<cmt>薩摩藩国父→定訳不明：so called &apos;father of Satsuma Domain&apos; としました。『皇朝世鑑』→定訳不明：&quot;Kochoseikan&quot; (Imperial court almanac) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, he became an instructor at hanko (a domain school) of the Satsuma Domain, Zoshikan school, and by the order of the so called &apos;adored leader as father of the Satsuma Domain,&apos; Hisamitsu SHIMAZU, he wrote &quot;Kochoseikan&quot; (imperial court almanac).</e>
<cmt>「薩摩藩国府」については、”国府＝父のように敬愛される指導者”ということで修正しました。1865→1864,Imperial→imperial と修正しました。the を補いました。『皇朝世鑑』の定訳は確認出来ておりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, he became an instructor at hanko (a domain school) of the Satsuma Domain, Zoshikan school, and by the order of the so called &apos;adored leader as father of the Satsuma Domain,&apos; Hisamitsu SHIMAZU, he wrote &quot;Kochoseikan&quot; (imperial court almanac).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、昌平黌の生徒にもなり、塩谷宕陰、安井息軒などの教えを受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also became a student of Shoheiko (a school run by Edo bakufu) and learned from Toin SHIONOYA and Sokken YASUI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also became a student of Shoheiko (a school run by Edo bakufu) and learned from Toin SHIONOYA and Sokken YASUI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also became a student of Shoheiko (a school run by Edo bakufu) and learned from Toin SHIONOYA and Sokken YASUI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この頃、同僚の金の使い込みにより、遠島処分にされ、その先で西郷隆盛と出会った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this period, accused guilty upon his colleague&apos;s peculation, he was exiled to a remote island, where he met Takamori SAIGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this period, accused guilty upon his colleague&apos;s peculation, he was exiled to a remote island, where he met Takamori SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this period, accused guilty upon his colleague&apos;s peculation, he was exiled to a remote island, where he met Takamori SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>岩下方平らとともに薩英戦争の戦後処理を担当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took charge of the postwar process of the Anglo-Satsuma War, together with Michihira IWASHITA and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took charge of the postwar process of the Anglo-Satsuma War, together with Michihira IWASHITA and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took charge of the postwar process of the Anglo-Satsuma War, together with Michihira IWASHITA and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治4年（1871年）に上京し、明治8年（1875年）以降太政官正院修史局・修史館にて明治政府の修史事業に関わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, he went up to Tokyo, and since 1875, he was involved the historiography project carried out by the Meiji government at Shushikan affiliated to the Bureau of Historiography, Dajokan-Seiin (the Grand Council of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, he went up to Tokyo, and from 1875, he was involved the historiography project carried out by the Meiji government at Shushikan affiliated to the Bureau of Historiography, Dajokan-Seiin (the Grand Council of state).</e>
<cmt>since→from と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, he went up to Tokyo, and from 1875, he was involved the historiography project carried out by the Meiji government at Shushikan affiliated to the Bureau of Historiography, Dajokan-Seiin (the Grand Council of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>明治11年（1879年）、帝国学士院会員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1879, he became a member of the Imperial Academy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1879, he became a member of the Imperial Academy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1879, he became a member of the Imperial Academy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>明治14年（1881年）、『大日本編年史』編纂に参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1881, he participated in the compilation of &quot;Dainihon hennenshi&quot; (Great Japanese Chronological History).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1881, he participated in the compilation of &quot;Dainihon hennenshi&quot; (Great Japanese Chronological History).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1881, he participated in the compilation of &quot;Dainihon hennenshi&quot; (Great Japanese Chronological History).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>清考証学派に範をとる歴史学方法論を主張、これに基づき児島高徳の実在や楠木正成の逸話を否定し「抹殺博士」の異名をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He insisted the historical science methodology, which modeled its methodology for the Qing-style study of old documents, and based on this, he denied the existence of Takanori KOJIMA (a personage appears in &quot;Taiheiki&quot; story) as a real figure as well as the anecdotes related to Masashige KUSUNOKI, and thus, he was dubbed &apos;Doctor elimination.&apos;</e>
<cmt>清考証学派→定訳不明：Qing-style study of old documents としました。歴史学方法論→定訳不明：historical science methodology としました。「抹殺博士」→定訳不明：&apos;Doctor elimination&apos; としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He advocated the historical science methodology, which modeled its methodology for the Qing-style study of old documents, and based on this, he denied the existence of Takanori KOJIMA (a personage appears in &quot;Taiheiki&quot; story) as a real figure as well as the anecdotes related to Masashige KUSUNOKI, and thus, he was dubbed &apos;the doctor elimination.&apos;</e>
<cmt>insisted→advocated,Doctor elimination→the doctor elimination と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He advocated the historical science methodology, which modeled its methodology for the Qing-style study of old documents, and based on this, he denied the existence of Takanori KOJIMA (a personage appears in &quot;Taiheiki&quot; story) as a real figure as well as the anecdotes related to Masashige KUSUNOKI, and thus, he was dubbed &apos;the doctor elimination.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかしこのような主張は川田甕江ら国学系・水戸学系歴史学者との対立を激化させ、のちの久米邦武筆禍事件の原因の一つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his such an argument intensified the confrontation with the scalars of Kokugaku (the study of Japanese classical literature and culture) like Oko KAWADA, and historians of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain), and later this confrontation resulted in one of the causes of Kunitake KUME&apos;s Hikka-jiken Incident (troubles brought on by what Kunitake KUME&apos;s has written).</e>
<cmt>久米邦武筆禍事件→定訳不明：Kunitake KUME&apos;s Hikka-jiken Incident (troubles brought on by what Kunitake KUME&apos;s has written) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these arguments intensified the confrontation with the scalars of Kokugaku (the study of Japanese classical literature and culture) such as Oko KAWADA, and historians of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain), and later this confrontation resulted in one of the causes of the Kume Kunitake Incident (troubles brought on by what Kunitake KUME&apos;s has written).</e>
<cmt>his such an argument→these arguments,like→such as と修正しました。「久米邦武筆禍事件」については、&quot;Kume Kunitake Incident&quot;との表記を確認しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these arguments intensified the confrontation with the scalars of Kokugaku (the study of Japanese classical literature and culture) such as Oko KAWADA, and historians of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain), and later this confrontation resulted in one of the causes of the Kume Kunitake Incident (troubles brought on by what Kunitake KUME&apos;s has written).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>明治21年（1888年）、帝国大学文科大学（のちの東京大学文学部）教授に就任、その翌年には「史学会」初代会長に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1888, he assumed the post of professor at Imperial University (later Faculty of Literature, The University of Tokyo), and the next year he became the first president of &apos;Shigakukai&apos; (The Historical Society of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1888, he assumed the post of professor at Imperial University (later Faculty of Literature, The University of Tokyo), and the following year he became the first president of &apos;Shigakukai&apos; (The Historical Society of Japan).</e>
<cmt>next→following と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1888, he assumed the post of professor at Imperial University (later Faculty of Literature, The University of Tokyo), and the following year he became the first president of &apos;Shigakukai&apos; (The Historical Society of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>この間、明治12年（1879年）の東京学士会院創設とともに会員となり、漢文訓読を廃し音読による中国語教育の水準向上を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period, he also became a member of the Tokyo Academy from the outset of its foundation, and he insisted abolition of the Japanese reading of a Chinese character in the kanbun (Chinese classics) and improve the level of Chinese language education by exclusively using original Chinese reading.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, he also became a member of the Tokyo Academy as it was founded, and he insisted abolition of the Japanese reading of Chinese characters in the kanbun (Chinese classics), and improving the level of Chinese language education by exclusively using original Chinese reading.</e>
<cmt>from the outset of its foundation→as it was founded,a Chinese character→Chinese characters,improve→improving と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, he also became a member of the Tokyo Academy as it was founded, and he insisted abolition of the Japanese reading of Chinese characters in the kanbun (Chinese classics), and improving the level of Chinese language education by exclusively using original Chinese reading.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また同年来日した清国の洋務運動知識人の王韜との交遊を契機に、翌年結成された日本最初の本格的アジア主義団体・興亜会に参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He formed a friendship with Wang Tao, a Qing&apos;s intellectual involved in the Western Affaire Movement, who came to Japan in the same year (1879), and influenced by the association with Wang, he took part in Koakai group, the first organization of full-blown Asianism in Japan founded the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He formed a friendship with Wang Tao, a Qing&apos;s intellectual involved in the Western Affairs Movement, who came to Japan in the same year (1879), and influenced by the association with Wang, he took part in Koakai group, the first organization of full-blown Asianism in Japan founded the following year.</e>
<cmt>Affaire→Affairs,next→following と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He formed a friendship with Wang Tao, a Qing&apos;s intellectual involved in the Western Affairs Movement, who came to Japan in the same year (1879), and influenced by the association with Wang, he took part in Koakai group, the first organization of full-blown Asianism in Japan founded the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>明治22年（1889年）近代実証史学の立場から『赤穂義士実話』を著す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Ako-gishi Jitsuwa&quot; (The real story of loyal retainers of Ako) from the standpoint of the modern positivist history.</e>
<cmt>近代実証史学→定訳不明： the modern positivist history としました。『赤穂義士実話』→定訳不明： &quot;Ako-gishi Jitsuwa&quot; (The real story of loyal retainers of Ako) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote &quot;Ako-gishi Jitsuwa&quot; (The real story of loyal retainers of Ako) from the standpoint of the modern positivist study of history in 1889.</e>
<cmt>「1889年」を補いました。modern positivist history→modern positivist study of history と修正しました。『赤穂義士実話』、「近代実証史学」の定訳は確認出来ておりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Ako-gishi Jitsuwa&quot; (The real story of loyal retainers of Ako) from the standpoint of the modern positivist study of history in 1889.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>それまであった赤穂浪士寺坂信行逃亡説の証拠を論破し、逆に彼が討入に参加した証となる史料を提示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He refuted the conventional evidences used in order to support the runaway story of Ako Roshi (lordless samurai of Ako domain) Nobuyuki TERASAKA, and in turn, he presented some historical materials to testify Terasaka&apos;s participation in the raid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He refuted the conventional evidences used in order to support the runaway story of the Ako Roshi (lordless samurai of Ako Domain) Nobuyuki TERASAKA, and in turn, he presented some historical materials to testify Terasaka&apos;s participation in the raid.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。domain→Domain と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He refuted the conventional evidences used in order to support the runaway story of the Ako Roshi (lordless samurai of Ako Domain) Nobuyuki TERASAKA, and in turn, he presented some historical materials to testify Terasaka&apos;s participation in the raid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>それ以来、寺坂逃亡説は口にする者が減ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that since then, the Terasaka&apos;s runaway story came to be less talked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that since then, the Terasaka&apos;s runaway story came to be less mentioned.</e>
<cmt>talked→mentioned と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that since then, the Terasaka&apos;s runaway story came to be less mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>明治23年（1890年）、星野恒・久米邦武と共に『国史眼』を執筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1890, he wrote &quot;Kokushigan&quot; (a vision on the national history), together with Hisashi HOSHINO and Kunitake KUME.</e>
<cmt>『国史眼』→定訳不明：&quot;Kokushigan&quot; (a vision on the national history) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1890, he wrote &quot;Kokushigan&quot; (a vision on the national history), together with Hisashi HOSHINO and Kunitake KUME.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1890, he wrote &quot;Kokushigan&quot; (a vision on the national history), together with Hisashi HOSHINO and Kunitake KUME.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>同年には貴族院 (日本)勅撰議員となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he was appointed a member of the House of Peers by the Imperial command.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he was appointed a member of the House of Peers (Japan) by the imperial command.</e>
<cmt>（日本）を補いました。Imperial→imperial と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he was appointed a member of the House of Peers (Japan) by the imperial command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし明治25年（1892年）の久米邦武筆禍事件の影響で重野は翌年に帝大教授を辞職、修史事業も中止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was involved in the troubles brought on by what Kunitake KUME had written (the Kunitake KUME&apos;s Hikka-jiken Incident) in 1892, and next year he resigned his post of professor at Imperial University, and consequently the historiography project was suspended.</e>
<cmt>久米邦武筆禍事件→定訳不明：the troubles brought on by what Kunitake KUME had written (the Kunitake KUME&apos;s Hikka-jiken Incident) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was involved in the troubles brought on by what Kunitake KUME had written (the Kume Kunitake Incident) in 1892, and the following year he resigned his post of professor at Imperial University, and consequently the historiography project was halted.</e>
<cmt>「久米邦武筆禍事件」については、&quot;Kume Kunitake Incident&quot;との表記を確認しています。next→the following,suspended→halted と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was involved in the troubles brought on by what Kunitake KUME had written (the Kume Kunitake Incident) in 1892, and the following year he resigned his post of professor at Imperial University, and consequently the historiography project was halted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>明治43年（1910年）、83歳で没。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1910, he died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1910, he died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1910, he died at the age of 83.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>墓所は東京都台東区の谷中霊園。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is located in Yanaka Cemetery in Taito Ward, Tokyo,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is located in Yanaka Cemetery in Taito Ward, Tokyo Metropolis.</e>
<cmt>Tokyo→Tokyo Metropolis と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is located in Yanaka Cemetery in Taito Ward, Tokyo Metropolis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>養子縁組の尚は大久保利通の長男・大久保利和に嫁ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His adoptive daughter Nao (尚) married into the first son of Toshimichi OKUBO, Toshikazu OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>養子縁組→adopted daughter としました。尚→正式な読み方が不明です：Nao (尚) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His adoptive daughter Nao (尚) married into the first son of Toshimichi OKUBO, Toshikazu OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His adoptive daughter Nao (尚) married into the first son of Toshimichi OKUBO, Toshikazu OKUBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="27">
<j>著書に、『成斎文初集』『成斎文二集』『成斎先生遺稿』があり、『重野博士史学論文集』全3巻補巻1冊も刊行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Seisai Bunshu&quot; (Seisai&apos;s writings), &quot;Seisai Bunnishu&quot; (Seisai&apos;s writings II), &quot;Seisai-sensei Ikoshu&quot; (Professor Seisai&apos;s literary remains), and his collection of papers, &quot;Shigeno Hakase Shigaku Ronbunshu&quot; (Collection of history papers of Dr. Shige) consisting of three volumes and an appendix was also published.</e>
<cmt>『成斎文初集』→定訳不明：&quot;Seisai Bunshu&quot; (Seisai&apos;s writings) としました。 『成斎文二集』→定訳不明：&quot;Seisai Bunnishu&quot; (Seisai&apos;s writings II) としました。 『成斎先生遺稿』→定訳不明：&quot;Seisai-sensei Ikoshu&quot; (Professor Seisai&apos;s literary remains) としました。『重野博士史学論文集』→定訳不明：&quot;Shigeno Hakase Shigaku Ronbunshu&quot; (Collection of history papers of Dr. Shige) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote &quot;Seisai Bunshu&quot; (Seisai&apos;s writings), &quot;Seisai Bunnishu&quot; (Seisai&apos;s writings II), &quot;Seisai-sensei Ikoshu&quot; (Professor Seisai&apos;s literary remains), and his collection of papers, &quot;Shigeno Hakase Shigaku Ronbunshu&quot; (Collection of history papers of Dr. Shigeno) consisting of three volumes and an appendix was also published.</e>
<cmt>Dr. Shie→Dr. Shigeno と修正しました。なお、『成斎文初集』、『成斎文二集』、『成斎先生遺稿』、『重野博士史学論文集』の定訳については確認出来ておりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Seisai Bunshu&quot; (Seisai&apos;s writings), &quot;Seisai Bunnishu&quot; (Seisai&apos;s writings II), &quot;Seisai-sensei Ikoshu&quot; (Professor Seisai&apos;s literary remains), and his collection of papers, &quot;Shigeno Hakase Shigaku Ronbunshu&quot; (Collection of history papers of Dr. Shigeno) consisting of three volumes and an appendix was also published.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、書状等が坂口筑母によって『重野成斎宛諸家書状』『稿本・重野成斎伝』としてまとめられ、国立国会図書館に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His letters and other written materials were compiled by Tsukumo SAKAGUCHI as &quot;Shigeno Seisai-ate Shoke Shojo&quot; (Letters directed to Seisai SHIGENO from various scholars) and &quot;Kohon: Shigeno Seisai-den&quot; (Manuscript: biography of Seisai SHIGENO), and these books are housed in the National Diet Library.</e>
<cmt>『重野成斎宛諸家書状』→定訳不明：&quot;Shigeno Seisai-ate Shoke Shojo&quot; (Letters directed to Seisai SHIGENO from various scholars) としました。『稿本・重野成斎伝』→定訳不明：&quot;Kohon: Shigeno Seisai-den&quot; (Manuscript: biography of Seisai SHIGENO) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His letters and other written materials were compiled by Tsukumo SAKAGUCHI as &quot;Shigeno Seisai-ate Shoke Shojo&quot; (Letters directed to Seisai SHIGENO from various scholars) and &quot;Kohon: Shigeno Seisai-den&quot; (Manuscript: biography of Seisai SHIGENO), and these are housed in the National Diet Library.</e>
<cmt>these books are→these are と修正しました。なお、『重野成斎宛諸家書状』、『稿本・重野成斎伝』の定訳については確認出来ておりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His letters and other written materials were compiled by Tsukumo SAKAGUCHI as &quot;Shigeno Seisai-ate Shoke Shojo&quot; (Letters directed to Seisai SHIGENO from various scholars) and &quot;Kohon: Shigeno Seisai-den&quot; (Manuscript: biography of Seisai SHIGENO), and these are housed in the National Diet Library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 生涯一薩摩人(id:75048), Tomzo(id:16777), Straysheep(id:42448), 宗純(id:232846), Moltke(id:17553), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 兵庫大将(id:129966), Tamago915(id:11009), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), 栄華(id:123663), YukkeBot2(id:251491), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>