<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>瀧廉太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rentaro TAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rentaro TAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rentaro TAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>瀧 廉太郎（たき れんたろう、1879年8月24日 - 1903年6月29日）は、日本の音楽家・作曲家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rentaro TAKI (August 24, 1879 - June 29, 1903) was a Japanese musician and composer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rentaro TAKI (August 24, 1879 - June 29, 1903) was a Japanese musician and composer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rentaro TAKI (August 24, 1879 - June 29, 1903) was a Japanese musician and composer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明治の西洋音楽黎明期における代表的な音楽家の一人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of leading musicians who lived at the early stage of the development of Western music in Japan in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lived during the early stages of the development of Western music in Japan in the Meiji era, and was one of the leading musicians of the period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lived during the early stages of the development of Western music in Japan in the Meiji era, and was one of the leading musicians of the period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>1879年（明治12年）東京生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Tokyo in 1879.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Tokyo in 1879.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Tokyo in 1879.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>瀧家は江戸時代、日出藩（現・大分県日出町）の家老職をつとめた上級武士の家柄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taki family was from such a high-ranking warrior class that they served as a karo (chief retainer) at the Hiji Domain (present-day Hiji-machi, Oita Prefecture) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taki family was from the warrior class, and of such a high rank that they had served as a karo (chief retainer) in Hiji Domain (present-day Hiji-machi, Oita Prefecture) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taki family was from the warrior class, and of such a high rank that they had served as a karo (chief retainer) in Hiji Domain (present-day Hiji-machi, Oita Prefecture) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>父・吉弘は大蔵省に勤務後内務省 (日本)に転じ大久保利通､伊藤博文らのもとで中央の官吏として務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Yoshihiro was transferred to the Ministry of Interior after the Ministry of Finance, and he worked as an official of the central government under the supervision of Toshimichi OKUBO and Hirofumi ITO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処原文に「内務省 (日本)」とありますがリンク先の用語と混ざっているようです。ウェブを確認し「内務省」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Yoshihiro was transferred to the Ministry of Interior from the Ministry of Finance, and worked as a central government official under the supervision of Toshimichi OKUBO and Hirofumi ITO.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Yoshihiro was transferred to the Ministry of Interior from the Ministry of Finance, and worked as a central government official under the supervision of Toshimichi OKUBO and Hirofumi ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後地方官として神奈川県､富山県富山市、大分県竹田市等を移り住んだため、瀧も生後間もなくから各地を回ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he lived in several places such as Kanagawa Prefecture, Toyama City in Toyama Prefecture, and Taketa City in Oita Prefecture as he worked as a local official, and accordingly, Taki also had to go from place to place soon after his birth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He subsequently worked as a local official, which involved moves to several places, among them Kanagawa Prefecture, Toyama City in Toyama Prefecture, and Taketa City in Oita Prefecture; accordingly, soon after his birth, Taki also had to go from place to place.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He subsequently worked as a local official, which involved moves to several places, among them Kanagawa Prefecture, Toyama City in Toyama Prefecture, and Taketa City in Oita Prefecture; accordingly, soon after his birth, Taki also had to go from place to place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1894年（明治27年）に15歳で東京音楽学校（現・東京芸術大学）に入学する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered Tokyo Music School (present-day Tokyo University of the Arts) in 1894 at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taki entered Tokyo Music School (present-day Tokyo University of the Arts) in 1894 at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>Replaced pronoun with proper noun.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taki entered Tokyo Music School (present-day Tokyo University of the Arts) in 1894 at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1898年に本科を卒業し、研究科に進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He finished the regular course in 1898, and then he went to the graduate school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He finished the regular courses in 1898, then went to the graduate school.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He finished the regular courses in 1898, then went to the graduate school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>こうして彼は作曲とピアノ演奏でめきめきと才能を伸ばしていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He developed his talents for music composition and piano performance with remarkable speed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He developed his talents for music composition and piano performance with remarkable speed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He developed his talents for music composition and piano performance with remarkable speed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1900年10月7日には、東京にあった聖公会博愛教会で洗礼を受けてキリスト教徒になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 7, 1900, he was baptized into the Christian faith at the Grace Episcopal Church, which belonged to the Anglican-Episcopal Church, in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 7, 1900, he was baptized into the Christian faith at Grace Episcopal Church, which was affiliated with the Anglican-Episcopal Church, in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 7, 1900, he was baptized into the Christian faith at Grace Episcopal Church, which was affiliated with the Anglican-Episcopal Church, in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>10月28日に堅信礼を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had confirmation on October 28.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was confirmed on October 28.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was confirmed on October 28.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>明治時代の前半に多くの翻訳唱歌ができたが、日本語訳詞を&quot;無理にはめこんだ&quot;ぎこちない歌が多く、日本人作曲家によるオリジナルの歌を望む声が高まっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although many foreign songs were translated for school music classes in the early Meiji period, most of them were awkward as translated lyrics were forcibly set to the music, and accordingly, there was high demand for Japanese songs composed by Japanese composers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although many foreign songs were translated for school music classes in the early Meiji period, most of them were awkward, with translated lyrics forcibly set to the music; accordingly, there was high demand for Japanese songs composed by Japanese composers.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although many foreign songs were translated for school music classes in the early Meiji period, most of them were awkward, with translated lyrics forcibly set to the music; accordingly, there was high demand for Japanese songs composed by Japanese composers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>瀧は最も早く、その要望に応えた作曲家と言えるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taki can be said to have been the first composer who responded to that demand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taki can be said to have been the first composer to respond to that demand.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taki can be said to have been the first composer to respond to that demand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>彼の代表作である「荒城の月」は、「箱根八里」と並んで文部省編纂の「中学唱歌」に掲載された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his most important pieces &apos;Kojo no Tsuki&apos; (The Moon over the Deserted Castle) was adopted into the music book for junior high schools, which was compiled by the Ministry of Education, along with his another song called &apos;Hakone Hachiri.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「箱根八里」について、ここでは用語集の「Traditional local folk song in the Hakone district」という説明はふさわしくないため（地方の歌ではなく、瀧廉太郎による作曲ということが明らかなため）省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojo no Tsuki&apos; (The Moon over the Deserted Castle), one of his most important pieces, was adopted into the music book compiled by the Ministry of Education for junior high schools, along with another of his songs, &apos;Hakone Hachiri.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojo no Tsuki&apos; (The Moon over the Deserted Castle), one of his most important pieces, was adopted into the music book compiled by the Ministry of Education for junior high schools, along with another of his songs, &apos;Hakone Hachiri.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、人気の高い曲のひとつである「花 (滝廉太郎)」は1900年（明治33年）8月に作曲された、4曲からなる組曲『四季』の第1曲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his popular songs &apos;Hana&apos; (Flowers) is the first song of his suite &quot;Shiki&quot; (Four Seasons) consisting of four songs, which was composed in August 1900.</e>
<cmt>原文に「花 (滝廉太郎)」とありますがリンク先の用語と混ざっているようです。ウェブを確認し「花」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hana&apos; (Flowers), one of his popular songs, is the first song of his suite &quot;Shiki&quot; (Four Seasons), which consists of four songs and was composed in August 1900.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hana&apos; (Flowers), one of his popular songs, is the first song of his suite &quot;Shiki&quot; (Four Seasons), which consists of four songs and was composed in August 1900.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「お正月」、「鳩ぽっぽ」、「雪やこんこ」などは、日本生まれの最も古い童謡作品として知られるが、これらは1900年に編纂された幼稚園唱歌に収められた名曲である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His songs such as &apos;Oshogatsu&apos; (New Year&apos;s Day), &apos;Hato Poppo&apos; (Pigeons), and &apos;Yuki Ya Konko&apos; (Japanese Snow Song) are known as the oldest nursery songs which were composed in Japan, and these songs are such excellent pieces that were included in the music book for kindergarten students compiled in 1900.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His songs &apos;Oshogatsu&apos; (New Year&apos;s Day), &apos;Hato Poppo&apos; (Pigeons), and &apos;Yuki Ya Konko&apos; (Japanese Snow Song) are known as the oldest nursery songs to be composed in Japan, and are such excellent pieces that they were included in the music book compiled in 1900 for kindergarten students.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His songs &apos;Oshogatsu&apos; (New Year&apos;s Day), &apos;Hato Poppo&apos; (Pigeons), and &apos;Yuki Ya Konko&apos; (Japanese Snow Song) are known as the oldest nursery songs to be composed in Japan, and are such excellent pieces that they were included in the music book compiled in 1900 for kindergarten students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また「荒城の月」は、ベルギーで讃美歌になったことも判明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it has become known that some Belgians sang &apos;Kojo no Tsuki&apos; as a hymn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it has become known that &apos;Kojo no Tsuki&apos; was converted into a hymn in Belgium.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it has become known that &apos;Kojo no Tsuki&apos; was converted into a hymn in Belgium.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>1901年（明治34年）4月、日本人の音楽家として2人目にヨーロッパ（ドイツ）のフェリックス・メンデルスゾーン音楽演劇大学（フェリックス・メンデルスゾーン設立）に留学する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered the University of Music and Theatre &quot;Felix Mendelssohn Bartholdy&quot; Leipzig (established by Felix Mendelssohn) in Europe (Germany) in April 1901, and he was the second Japanese composer who entered this school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1901, Taki entered the European University of Music and Theatre &quot;Felix Mendelssohn Bartholdy&quot; Leipzig (established by Felix Mendelssohn) in Germany, becoming the second Japanese composer to attend this school.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1901, Taki entered the European University of Music and Theatre &quot;Felix Mendelssohn Bartholdy&quot; Leipzig (established by Felix Mendelssohn) in Germany, becoming the second Japanese composer to attend this school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>文部省外国留学生として入学、ピアノや対位法などを学ぶが、わずか2ヶ月後に肺結核を発病し、1年で帰国を余儀なくされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was sent abroad to this school by the Ministry of Education and he took piano lessons and learned counterpoint, but only two months later, he caught tuberculosis and had to return to Japan one year after he entered the school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He entered the school as a Ministry of Education exchange student; he took piano lessons and learned counterpoint, but after only two months, he caught tuberculosis and had to return to Japan one year after entering the school.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He entered the school as a Ministry of Education exchange student; he took piano lessons and learned counterpoint, but after only two months, he caught tuberculosis and had to return to Japan one year after entering the school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後父親の故郷である大分県で療養していたが、1903年（明治36年）6月29日に23歳の若さで死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received medical treatment in Oita Prefecture, which was his father&apos;s hometown, but he died on June 29, 1903 at the premature age of 23.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received medical treatment in Oita Prefecture, his father&apos;s home prefecture, but on June 29, 1903, he died at the young age of 23.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received medical treatment in Oita Prefecture, his father&apos;s home prefecture, but on June 29, 1903, he died at the young age of 23.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>墓所は大分市の熊野寺にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His graveyard is at Kumano-ji (熊野寺) Temple in Oita City.</e>
<cmt>熊野寺の正式な読み方が不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is at Kumano-ji (熊野寺) Temple in Oita City.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is at Kumano-ji (熊野寺) Temple in Oita City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Works of Taki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works</e>
<cmt>Removed words absent in original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>歌曲に有名な作品が多い瀧だが、1900年には日本人作曲家による初めてのピアノ独奏曲メヌエット (滝廉太郎)を作曲している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Taki made many popular songs, he also composed a piano solo called Minuet in 1900, and this was the first piano solo made by a Japanese composer.</e>
<cmt>原文に「メヌエット (滝廉太郎)」とありますがリンク先の用語と混ざっているようです。ウェブを確認し「メヌエット」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Taki wrote many popular songs, he also composed a piano solo called Minuet in 1900, which became the first piano solo by a Japanese composer.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Taki wrote many popular songs, he also composed a piano solo called Minuet in 1900, which became the first piano solo by a Japanese composer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>肺結核が悪化して、死期が近いことを悟った時、死の4ヶ月前に作曲したピアノ曲「憾 (滝廉太郎)（うらみ）」が最後の作品として残された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he realized he would die soon due to the worsening of his pulmonary tuberculosis, he composed a piece of music for the piano named &apos;Urami&apos; (regret) four months before his death, and this became his last work.</e>
<cmt>原文に「憾 (滝廉太郎)」とありますがリンク先の用語と混ざっているようです。ウェブを確認し「憾」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pulmonary tuberculosis worsened, and when he realized he would soon die, he composed a piano piece titled &apos;Urami&apos; (Regret) four months before his death; this became his last work.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pulmonary tuberculosis worsened, and when he realized he would soon die, he composed a piano piece titled &apos;Urami&apos; (Regret) four months before his death; this became his last work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>また、後に、「箱根八里」は、箱根登山鉄道の発車メロディーになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, his song &apos;Hakone Hachri&apos; became a departure song of trains of Hakone Tozan Railway afterward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His song &apos;Hakone Hachiri&apos; later became the departure song for Hakone Tozan Railway trains.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His song &apos;Hakone Hachiri&apos; later became the departure song for Hakone Tozan Railway trains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>「花」は、東北新幹線・上越新幹線の上野駅到着・発車時の車内チャイム（通称「ふるさとチャイム」）として使われていたが、東京駅開業後は使用されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His song &apos;Hana&apos; used to be used as an alarm within a train (generally known as Furusato Chime [literally, &quot;Hometown Chime&quot;]) for a departure and an arrival at Ueno Station for Tohoku Shinkansen and Joetsu Shinkansen, but they stopped using that song when Tokyo Station opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His song &apos;Hana&apos; was formerly used as an onboard alert (generally known as the Furusato Chime [literally, &quot;Hometown Chime&quot;]) for Tohoku and Joetsu Shinkansen departures and arrivals at Ueno Station, but they stopped using the song after the opening of Tokyo Station.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His song &apos;Hana&apos; was formerly used as an onboard alert (generally known as the Furusato Chime [literally, &quot;Hometown Chime&quot;]) for Tohoku and Joetsu Shinkansen departures and arrivals at Ueno Station, but they stopped using the song after the opening of Tokyo Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>メヌエット・「憾」を除いて、全て声楽作品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All his works are songs except for Minuet and Urami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All his works are written to be sung, except for Minuet and Urami.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All his works are written to be sung, except for Minuet and Urami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>1896年（明治29年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1896</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1896</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1896</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>日本男児 （詞・東郊。独唱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nippon Danji (literally, &quot;a son of Japan,&quot; lyrics by Ko TO [東郊], a solo piece)</e>
<cmt>東郊の正式な読みが不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nippon Danji (literally &quot;A Son of Japan,&quot; a solo piece with lyrics by Ko TO [東郊])</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nippon Danji (literally &quot;A Son of Japan,&quot; a solo piece with lyrics by Ko TO [東郊])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>1897年（明治30年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1897</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1897</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1897</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>春の海 （詞・東くめ。独唱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haru no Umi (literally, &quot;spring sea,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, a solo piece)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haru no Umi (literally &quot;Spring Sea,&quot; a solo piece with lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haru no Umi (literally &quot;Spring Sea,&quot; a solo piece with lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>散歩 （詞・中村秋香。独唱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanpo (literally, &quot;a walk,&quot; lyrics by Akika NAKAMURA, a solo piece)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanpo (literally &quot;A Walk,&quot; a solo piece with lyrics by Akika NAKAMURA)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanpo (literally &quot;A Walk,&quot; a solo piece with lyrics by Akika NAKAMURA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>命を捨てて （詞・不詳。独唱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inochi o Sutete (literally, &quot;giving up my life,&quot; a write of the lyrics unknown, a solo piece)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inochi o Sutete (literally &quot;Giving Up My Life,&quot; a solo piece, lyricist unknown)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inochi o Sutete (literally &quot;Giving Up My Life,&quot; a solo piece, lyricist unknown)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>1899年（明治32年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1899</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1899</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1899</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>我神州 （詞・砂沢丙喜治。独唱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waga Shinshu (literally, &quot;our land of gods,&quot; lyrics by Hekiji SUNASAWA [砂沢丙喜治], a solo piece)</e>
<cmt>砂沢丙喜治の正式な読みが不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Waga Shinshu (literally &quot;Our Land of Gods,&quot; a solo piece with lyrics by Hekiji SUNASAWA [砂沢丙喜治])</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Waga Shinshu (literally &quot;Our Land of Gods,&quot; a solo piece with lyrics by Hekiji SUNASAWA [砂沢丙喜治])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>四季の瀧 （詞・東くめ。ソプラノ・アルト・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiki no Taki (literally, &quot;a fall of four seasons,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, soprano and alto accompanied with piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiki no Taki (literally &quot;A Waterfall of Four Seasons,&quot; for soprano and alto with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiki no Taki (literally &quot;A Waterfall of Four Seasons,&quot; for soprano and alto with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>1900年（明治33年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1900</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1900</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1900</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="37">
<j>メヌエット（ピアノ曲）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minuet (a piece for piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minuet (piano piece)</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minuet (piano piece)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="38">
<j>組歌『四季』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suite &quot;Shiki&quot; (literally, &quot;four seasons&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Shiki&quot; (literally &quot;Four Seasons&quot;) suite</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Shiki&quot; (literally &quot;Four Seasons&quot;) suite</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="39">
<j>1　花 (滝廉太郎) （詞・武島羽衣。ソプラノ・アルト・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 Hana (lyrics by Hagoromo TAKESHIMA, soprano and alto accompanied with piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 Hana (for soprano and alto with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Hagoromo TAKESHIMA)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 Hana (for soprano and alto with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Hagoromo TAKESHIMA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="40">
<j>2　納涼 （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2. Noryo (literally, &quot;the cool of a summer evening,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2. Noryo (literally &quot;The Cool of a Summer Evening,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2. Noryo (literally &quot;The Cool of a Summer Evening,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="41">
<j>3　月 （詞・瀧廉太郎。ソプラノ・アルト・テノール・バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3 Tsuki (literally, &quot;the moon,&quot; lyrics by Rentaro TAKI, soprano, alto, tenor, and bass)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3 Tsuki (literally &quot;The Moon,&quot; for soprano, alto, tenor, and bass, lyrics by Rentaro TAKI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3 Tsuki (literally &quot;The Moon,&quot; for soprano, alto, tenor, and bass, lyrics by Rentaro TAKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="42">
<j>4　雪 （詞・中村秋香。ソプラノ・アルト・テノール・バス・ピアノとオルガン伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4 Yuki (literally, &quot;snow,&quot; lyrics by Akika NAKAMURA, soprano, alto, tenor, and bass accompanied with the piano and the organ)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4 Yuki (literally, &quot;snow,&quot; for soprano, alto, tenor, and bass with piano and organ accompaniment, lyrics by Akika NAKAMURA,)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4 Yuki (literally, &quot;snow,&quot; for soprano, alto, tenor, and bass with piano and organ accompaniment, lyrics by Akika NAKAMURA,)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="43">
<j>中学唱歌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Songs for music classes at junior high schools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Songs for junior high school music classes</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Songs for junior high school music classes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="44">
<j>箱根八里 （詞・鳥居忱。独唱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakone Hachiri (lyrics by Makoto TORII, a solo piece)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakone Hachiri (a solo piece, lyrics by Makoto TORII)</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakone Hachiri (a solo piece, lyrics by Makoto TORII)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="45">
<j>荒城の月 （詞・土井晩翠。独唱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojo no Tsuki (lyrics by Bansui DOI, a solo piece)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kojo no Tsuki (a solo piece, lyrics by Bansui DOI)</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kojo no Tsuki (a solo piece, lyrics by Bansui DOI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="46">
<j>豊太閤 （詞・外山正一。独唱）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hotaiko (lyrics by Masakazu TOYAMA, a solo piece)</e>
<cmt>豊太閤が用語集ではHodaikoになっておりますが、正しい読みは「ほうたいこう」です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hotaiko (a solo piece, lyrics by Masakazu TOYAMA)</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hotaiko (a solo piece, lyrics by Masakazu TOYAMA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="47">
<j>1901年（明治34年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1901</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1901</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1901</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="48">
<j>幼稚園唱歌（作曲は1900年から）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Songs for students at kindergartens (Taki started to compose these songs in 1900)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Songs for kindergarten students (Taki began to compose these songs in 1900)</e>
<cmt>Word order, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Songs for kindergarten students (Taki began to compose these songs in 1900)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="49">
<j>ほうほけきょ （詞・瀧廉太郎。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hohokekyo (lyrics by Rentaro TAKI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hohokekyo (solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Rentaro TAKI)</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hohokekyo (solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Rentaro TAKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="50">
<j>ひばりはうたひ （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hibari wa Utai (literally, &quot;a lark trills,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hibari wa Utai (literally &quot;A Lark Trills,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hibari wa Utai (literally &quot;A Lark Trills,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="51">
<j>鯉幟 （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koinobori (literally, &quot;a carp streamer,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koinobori (literally &quot;A Carp Streamer,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koinobori (literally &quot;A Carp Streamer,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="52">
<j>海のうへ （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umi no Ue (literally, &quot;above the sea,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umi no Ue (literally &quot;Above the Sea,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umi no Ue (literally &quot;Above the Sea,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="53">
<j>桃太郎 （詞・瀧廉太郎。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momotaro (lyrics by Rentaro TAKI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momotaro (solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Rentaro TAKI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momotaro (solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Rentaro TAKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="54">
<j>お池の蛙 （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oike no Kaeru (literally, &quot;frogs in a pond&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oike no Kaeru (literally &quot;Frogs in a Pond,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oike no Kaeru (literally &quot;Frogs in a Pond,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="55">
<j>夕立 （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yudachi (literally, &quot;an evening shower,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yudachi (literally &quot;An Evening Shower,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yudachi (literally &quot;An Evening Shower,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="56">
<j>かちかち山 （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kachikachi Yama (literally, &quot;Mt. Kachikachi,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kachikachi Yama (literally &quot;Mt. Kachikachi,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kachikachi Yama (literally &quot;Mt. Kachikachi,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="57">
<j>水あそび （詞・瀧廉太郎。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizuasobi (literally, &quot;playing in the water,&quot; lyrics by Rentaro TAKI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizuasobi (literally &quot;Playing in the Water,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Rentaro TAKI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizuasobi (literally &quot;Playing in the Water,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Rentaro TAKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="58">
<j>鳩ぽっぽ （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hato Poppo (lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hato Poppo (solo vocal with piano accompaniment,lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hato Poppo (solo vocal with piano accompaniment,lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="59">
<j>菊 （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiku (literally, &quot;a chrysanthemum,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiku (literally &quot;A Chrysanthemum,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiku (literally &quot;A Chrysanthemum,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="60">
<j>軍ごっこ （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gun Gokko (literally, &quot;playing soldiers,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gun Gokko (literally &quot;Playing Soldiers,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gun Gokko (literally &quot;Playing Soldiers,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="61">
<j>雀 （詞・佐佐木信綱。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzume (literally, &quot;sparrows,&quot; lyrics by Nobutsuna SASAKI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suzume (literally &quot;Sparrows,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Nobutsuna SASAKI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suzume (literally &quot;Sparrows,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Nobutsuna SASAKI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="62">
<j>雪やこんこ （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuki ya Konko (lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuki ya Konko (solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuki ya Konko (solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="63">
<j>お正月 (歌曲) （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oshogatsu (lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oshogatsu (solo vocal with piano accompaniment,lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oshogatsu (solo vocal with piano accompaniment,lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="64">
<j>さようなら （詞・東くめ。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sayonara (literally, &quot;good-bye,&quot; lyrics by Kume HIGASHI, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sayonara (literally &quot;Goodbye,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sayonara (literally &quot;Goodbye,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Kume HIGASHI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="65">
<j>1902年（明治35年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1902</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1902</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1902</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="66">
<j>別れの歌 （詞・不詳。ソプラノ・アルト・テノール・バス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakare no Uta (literally, &quot;a farewell song,&quot; a writer of the lyrics unknown, soprano, alto, tenor, and bass)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakare no Uta (literally &quot;A Farewell Song,&quot; for soprano, alto, tenor, and bass, lyricist unknown)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakare no Uta (literally &quot;A Farewell Song,&quot; for soprano, alto, tenor, and bass, lyricist unknown)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="67">
<j>水のゆくへ （詞・不詳。2ソプラノ・アルト・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizu no Yukue (literally, &quot;the flow of water,&quot; a writer of the lyrics unknown, two sopranos and an alto accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizu no Yukue (literally &quot;The Water&apos;s Flow,&quot; for two sopranos and alto with piano accompaniment, lyricist unknown)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizu no Yukue (literally &quot;The Water&apos;s Flow,&quot; for two sopranos and alto with piano accompaniment, lyricist unknown)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="68">
<j>荒磯の波 （詞・徳川光圀。独唱・ピアノ伴奏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Araiso no Nami (literally, &quot;waves at a rocky shore,&quot; lyrics by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, solo vocal accompanied with the piano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Araiso no Nami (literally &quot;Waves at a Rocky Shore,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA)</e>
<cmt>Word order, capitalization, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Araiso no Nami (literally &quot;Waves at a Rocky Shore,&quot; solo vocal with piano accompaniment, lyrics by Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="69">
<j>1903年（明治36年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1903</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1903</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1903</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="70">
<j>憾 (滝廉太郎)（ピアノ曲）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Urami (a piece for piano)</e>
<cmt>原文に「憾 (滝廉太郎)」とありますがリンク先の用語と混ざっているようです。ウェブを確認し「憾」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Urami (a piece for piano)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Urami (a piece for piano)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="71">
<j>そのほか他の作曲家の作品の編曲も存在</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Taki arranged other composers&apos; pieces of music.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Taki arranged music by other composers.</e>
<cmt>Word order, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Taki arranged music by other composers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Okapia2(id:98589), Charlesy(id:137799), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Yuichiokubo(id:88759), Bellcricket(id:37640), Tarosan(id:330), GAVVA(id:47103), Uraios(id:72687), 寒漁夫(id:99134), Hhst(id:13720), Evangelical(id:117841), Goki(id:7107), Loveless(id:129239), Tamago915(id:11009), Korokoro(id:42329), Yas(id:739), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Kzhr(id:131), Mark-zero(id:48822), Belle Equipe(id:39537), Izayohi(id:13095), Carbuncle(id:346), Openup(id:211756), なめこ汁(id:128895), 松茸(id:27535), Complex01(id:10454), PixelBot(id:166734), 磯キリン(id:64770), Shigeruko(id:160087), Artfan(id:15278), グラタン(id:94405), 間久部緑郎(id:22345), 大分帰省中(id:180882), VolkovBot(id:105371), Ribbon(id:172), 663highland(id:18755), けんち(id:5147), Akimoto(id:6951), WikiFlier(id:31951), いわしぐも(id:93607), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>