<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三条の方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo no Kata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo no Kata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo no kata</e>
<cmt>kata は小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三条の方（さんじょうのかた、大永元年（1521年）? - 元亀元年7月28日 (旧暦)（1570年8月29日））は、戦国時代 (日本)の女性、甲斐国の守護大名である武田信玄の継室である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo no kata (1521 - August 29, 1570) was a women in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) and the second wife of Shingen TAKEDA, who was</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo no kata (1521 - August 29, 1570) was a women who lived during the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States), and the second wife of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization, elaboration. Deleted &quot;who was&quot; to eliminate sentence fragment.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo no kata (c. 1521 - August 29, 1570) was a woman who lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan), and was the second wife of Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>The edited version reads much more naturally than the original translation but &quot;women&quot; should be &quot;woman&quot; and I think &quot;was&quot; is required between &quot;and&quot; and &quot;the&quot;.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>左大臣・転法輪三条公頼の2女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the second daughter of Kinyori TENPORIN-SANJO, who was the Sadaijin(minister of the left)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the second daughter of Kinyori TENPORIN-SANJO, who was the Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>inserted space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the second daughter of Kinyori TENPORIN-SANJO, who was the Sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>姉には細川晴元夫人、妹には本願寺顕如夫人の如春尼がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wife of Harumoto HOSOKAWA was her elder sister and Nyoshunni, who was the wfie of Kennyo HONGANJI, was her younger sister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her elder sister was the wife of Harumoto HOSOKAWA, and Nyoshunni, her younger sister, was the wife of Kennyo HONGANJI.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her elder sister was the wife of Harumoto HOSOKAWA, and Nyoshunni, her younger sister, was the wife of Kennyo HONGANJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子には武田義信、黄梅院 (人名)（北条氏政夫人）、海野信親（龍宝）、武田信之、見性院 (穴山梅雪正室)（穴山信君夫人）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had children as follows: Yoshinobu TAKEDA, Obaiin (or, Kobaiin) (wife of Ujimasa HOJO), Nobuchika UNNO (Ryuho), Nobuyuki TAKEDA and Kenshoin (legitimate wife of Baisetsu ANAYAMA)(wife of Nobukimi ANAYAMA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had children as follows: Yoshinobu TAKEDA, Obaiin (or Kobaiin) (wife of Ujimasa HOJO), Nobuchika UNNO (Ryuho), Nobuyuki TAKEDA, and Kenshoin (legitimate wife of Baisetsu ANAYAMA) (wife of Nobukimi ANAYAMA).</e>
<cmt>punctuation, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her children included the following: Yoshinobu TAKEDA, Obaiin (or Kobaiin) (wife of Ujimasa HOJO), Nobuchika UNNO (also known as Ryuho), Nobuyuki TAKEDA, and Kenshoin (legitimate wife of Baisetsu ANAYAMA) (wife of Nobukimi ANAYAMA).</e>
<cmt>punctuation, spacing&quot;She had children as follows&quot; sounds a bit unnatural to me. Also, I don&apos;t think the average reader will know what the information provided in parentheses is supposed to mean. So I added some explanation.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>本名は不明で一般には、三条の方、三条夫人などと称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her real name was not known and she is usually called Sanjo no kata or Sanjo fujin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her real name is not known, and she is usually called Sanjo no kata or Sanjo fujin.</e>
<cmt>present tense, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real name is not known, and she is usually called Sanjo no kata or Sanjo fujin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>京都の三条邸で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born in the mansion of the Sanjo family in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born in the mansion of the Sanjo family in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born in the mansion of the Sanjo family in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>三条家は清華家の一つで、摂関家に次ぐ家柄であり極官は太政大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjo family was one of Seiga-ke, which was the social standing of a family next to Sekkan-ke (the highest social standing for noble families) and its highest attainable position was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjo family belonged to Seiga-ke, the family social standing next to Sekkan-ke (the highest social standing for noble families), and its highest attainable position was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjo family belonged to the Seiga family, which was second in terms of social standing only to the Sekkan families (the five families of the Fujiwara clan who were entitled to hold the position of Sekkan [regent]), and the highest position a member of this family could attain was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>This reads to me as if &quot;Seiga-ke&quot; is Japanese for a type of family social standing, but I don&apos;t think that is the case, is it? I think the use of &quot;its&quot; is incorrect in that presumably only a member of the family could attain that position, not the family itself.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>笛と装束の家として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjo family was known as the family for fue (Japanese flute) and shozoku (ritual accouterments).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjo family was known for the fue (Japanese flute) and shozoku (ritual accouterments).</e>
<cmt>omitted unnecessary words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjo family was known for the fue (Japanese flute) and shozoku (ritual accouterments).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>分家の三条西家には、当代随一の文化人として名高い三条西実隆がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sanjonishi family, which was a branch family, there was Sanetaka SANJONISHI, who was famous as the greatest man of culture of the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjonishi family, which was a branch family, included Sanetaka SANJONISHI, who was famous as the greatest man of culture of the day.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjonishi family, which was a branch family, included Sanetaka SANJONISHI, who was famous as the greatest man of culture of the day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>駿河国の今川氏の仲介で天文 (元号)5年（1536年）7月、武田晴信に嫁す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, 1536, she married Harunobu TAKEDA through intermediation by the Imagawa clan in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, 1536, Sanjo no kata married Harunobu TAKEDA through the intermediation of the Imagawa clan in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;she&quot; to &quot;Sanjo no kata&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, 1536, Sanjo no kata married Harunobu TAKEDA through the intermediation of the Imagawa clan in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>義信、黄梅院、信親、信之、見性院と、晴信との間に次々と3男2女をもうける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Harunobu, she successively gave birth to three sons and two daughters as follows: Yoshinobu, Obaiin, Nobuchika, Nobuyuki and Kenshoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Harunobu, she successively gave birth to three sons and two daughters as follows: Yoshinobu, Obaiin, Nobuchika, Nobuyuki, and Kenshoin.</e>
<cmt>inserted serial comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Harunobu, she successively gave birth to three sons and two daughters as follows: Yoshinobu, Obaiin, Nobuchika, Nobuyuki, and Kenshoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>武田家の近習衆のなかには警護等を務めていたと思われる御料人衆がおり、五味新右衛門をはじめ10人が付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were Goryoninshu (close aides), who seems to have guarded her among Kinjushu (personal attendant) of the Takeda family and ten starting with Shinemon GOMI were attached to her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among Kinjushu (personal attendants) of the Takeda family, Goryoninshu (close aides) seem to have guarded her; ten of them, starting with Shinemon GOMI, were attached to her.</e>
<cmt>word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among Kinjushu (personal attendants) of the Takeda family, Goryoninshu (close aides) seem to have guarded her; ten of them, starting with Shinemon GOMI, were attached to her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>父・三条公頼の斬殺、義信の謀反、信親の盲目、信之の夭折、黄梅院の離縁と27歳にしての病死など、度重なる不運に見舞われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She successively had a stroke of bad luck, such as her father, Kinyori SANJO&apos;s death being killed with a sword, revolt of Yoshinobu, Nobuchika&apos;s loss of eyesight, Nobuyuki&apos;s young death and divorce and death at the age of twenty-seven of Obaiin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She experienced a series of misfortunes, including the death of her father, Kinyori SANJO, by the sword; the revolt of Yoshinobu; Nobuchika&apos;s loss of eyesight; Nobuyuki&apos;s early death; and Obaiin&apos;s divorce and death at the age of twenty-seven.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She experienced a series of misfortunes, including the death of her father, Kinyori SANJO, by the sword; the revolt of Yoshinobu; Nobuchika&apos;s loss of eyesight; Nobuyuki&apos;s early death; and Obaiin&apos;s divorce and death at the age of twenty-seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>元亀元年（1570年）7月28日に死去、享年50。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died on July 28, 1570 at the age of fifty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo died on July 28, 1570 at the age of fifty.</e>
<cmt>&quot;she&quot; to &quot;Sanjo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo no kata died on August 29, 1570 at the age of fifty.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>墓所は甲府市の円光院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her graveyard exists in the Enko-in Temple in Kofu City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave sits in Enko-in Temple in Kofu City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;graveyard&quot; to &quot;grave.&quot; I know that the term given here is &quot;graveyard,&quot; but &quot;grave&quot; seems more appropriate.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave sits in Enko-in Temple in Kofu City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>円光院の葬儀記録には、快川紹喜の三条の方の人柄を称賛する「大変にお美しく、仏への信仰が篤く、周りにいる人々を包み込む、春の陽光のように温かくておだやかなお人柄で、信玄さまとの夫婦仲も、むつまじいご様子でした」と記された記録が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the record of funeral ceremonies of the Enko-in Temple, Joki KAISEN&apos;s compliment on Sanjo no kata&apos;s personality is recorded as &quot;She is very beautiful and a person of strong faith to Buddha, warm-hearted and genial like the spring sun that encompassing those around her. Also she had a happy married life with Shingen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the record of funeral ceremonies of Enko-in Temple, Joki KAISEN&apos;s compliment on Sanjo no kata&apos;s personality is recorded as &quot;She is very beautiful and a person of strong faith in Buddha, warm-hearted and genial like the spring sun encompassing those around her. In addition, she lived a happy married life with Shingen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the record of funeral ceremonies of Enko-in Temple, Joki KAISEN&apos;s compliment on Sanjo no kata&apos;s personality is recorded as &apos;She is very beautiful and a person of strong faith in Buddha, warm-hearted and genial like the spring sun encompassing those around her. In addition, she lived a happy married life with Shingen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>信仰に関しては、武田家に嫁ぐ時､持参したと伝えられている三条家に伝わる木造釈迦如来坐像が現存して円光院に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to religious matters, there exists wooden shakanyorai zazo (wooden seated statue of Shaka Nyorai (Shakamuni)), which was handed down in the Sanjo family and brought by her when she married into the Takeda family and kept in the Enko-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to religious matters, Sanjo inherited a wooden shakanyorai zazo (wooden seated statue of Shaka Nyorai (Shakamuni)) which had been handed down in the Sanjo family; she brought it with her when she married into the Takeda family and it was kept in the Enko-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to religious matters, Sanjo no kata inherited a wooden shakanyorai zazo (wooden seated statue of Shaka Nyorai (Shakamuni)) which had been handed down in the Sanjo family; she brought it with her when she married into the Takeda family and it was kept in the Enko-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>sanjo no kata としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>彼女が向嶽寺に新寄進をしている記録が『甲斐国志』に残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kaikokushi (history of Kai Province), there is a record that she made new donation to the Kogaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kaikokushi (history of Kai Province), there is a record that she made a new donation to the Kogaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>inserted article. Please check &quot;new donation&quot;; meaning is unclear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Kaikokushi&quot; (history of Kai Province), there is a record that she made a new donation to the Kogaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>本願寺の顕如の正室は、三条の方の妹、如春尼であり、本願寺と信玄との同盟の裏には、三条の方の尽力があったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legitimate wife of Kennyo of the Hongan-ji Temple was Sanjo no kata&apos;s younger sister, Nyoshunni, and it seems that, in the background of alliance between the Hongan-ji Temple and Shingen, there was efforts of Sanjo no kata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo&apos;s younger sister, Nyoshunni, was the legitimate wife of Kennyo of the Hongan-ji Temple, and it seems that Sanjo no kata made background efforts in forging the alliance between Hongan-ji Temple and Shingen.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo no kata&apos;s younger sister, Nyoshunni, was the legitimate wife of Kennyo of the Hongan-ji Temple, and it seems that Sanjo no kata made background efforts in forging the alliance between Hongan-ji Temple and Shingen.</e>
<cmt>sanjo no kata としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、武田氏の家紋と､彼女が皇室から使用を許された菊花紋と桐紋が彫られた愛用の鏡が円光院に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A mirror used by her engraved with the crest of the Takeda clan and Kikukamon (the Imperial crest of the chrysanthemum) and Kirimon(the crest of the paulownia) which she was allowed to use by the Imperial family is kept in the Enko-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Enko-in Temple, there is a mirror used by Sanjo engraved with the crest of the Takeda clan, Kikukamon (the Imperial crest of the chrysanthemum), and Kirimon (the crest of the paulownia), which the Imperial family allowed her to use.</e>
<cmt>word order, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Enko-in Temple, there is a mirror used by Sanjo no kata engraved with the crest of the Takeda clan, as well as Kikukamon crest (the Imperial crest of the chrysanthemum), and Kirimon crest (the crest of the paulownia) which the Imperial family allowed her to use.</e>
<cmt>as well as を追加し、武田氏の家紋、菊花紋、桐紋の３つが彫られている、としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>さらに、円光院に伝わる当時の史料・『円光院寺伝』によると、信玄が信濃国駒場で臨終間近の時、病の床に馬場信春を呼び寄せ、（安土桃山時代の高名な仏師）宮内卿法印康清に彫らせた、自分が日頃から信仰していた陣中守り本尊、刀八毘沙門・勝軍地蔵を託し、説三和尚に送り、円光院に納めてくれるように遺言したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Enko-in Jiden (history of Enko-in Temple)&quot;, which is a historical materials at that time kept by the Enko-in Temple, just before Shingen&apos;s death at Komaba in Shinano Province, he called Ｎobuharu BABA to his bedside and left his Jinchu Mamorihonzon (guardian deity at the front, Tohachi-bishamon and Shogun-jizo, which Shingen had carved by Kunaikyo hoin Yasukiyo ([宮内卿法印 定訳不明])(famous busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues) in the Azuchi-Momoyama Period)and worshipped very much, and left a will to give it to Sessan-osho to dedicate it to the Enko-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, according to &quot;Enko-in Jiden (history of Enko-in Temple),&quot; which is historical material kept by Enko-in Temple at that time, just before Shingen&apos;s death at Komaba in Shinano Province, he called Ｎobuharu BABA to his bedside and left to Sessan-osho, for dedication to Enko-in Temple, his Jinchu Mamorihonzon (guardian deity at the front, Tohachi-bishamon and Shogun-jizo, carved at Shingen&apos;s order by Kunaikyo hoin Yasukiyo ([宮内卿法印 定訳不明])(famous busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues) in the Azuchi-Momoyama Period and worshipped very much.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Enko-in Jiden&quot; (history of Enko-in Temple), which is historical material kept by Enko-in Temple at that time, just before Shingen&apos;s death at Komaba in Shinano Province, he called Nobuharu BABA to his bedside and left his will to send to Sessan-osho (a priest), for dedication to Enko-in Temple, his Jinchu Mamorihonzon (guardian deity at the front), Tohachi-bishamon (a statue of Bishamoten) and Shogun-jizo (Jizo that brings victory), carved at Shingen&apos;s order by Kunaikyo hoin Yasukiyo ([宮内卿法印 定訳不明])(famous busshi (sculptor of Buddhist Statues) in the Azuchi-Momoyama period and worshipped very much).</e>
<cmt>一部補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに自分の遺体も、円光院に3年間密葬させるよう遺言したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also left a will to bury his body secretly for three years in the Enko-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingen also willed that his body be buried secretly for three years in Enko-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>rewording, please confirm (do we need to use &quot;private funeral&quot;?)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingen also willed that his body be buried secretly for three years in Enko-in Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>この2体の仏像はその遺言通り、現在も円光院に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two statues were still kept in the Enko-ji Temple even today according to the will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two statues are still kept in the Enko-ji Temple even today, in accordance with Shingen&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>change to present tense, rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two statues are still kept in the Enko-ji Temple even today, in accordance with Shingen&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>笛吹市にある二宮美和神社 (笛吹市)に、永禄9年（1566年）11月25日に奉納された赤皮具足は信玄の物だという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a view that akagawa gusoku (armor made with red leather) dedicated to the Ninomiya Miwa-jinja Shrine in Fuefuki City on November 25, 1566 belonged to Shingen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many believe that akagawa gusoku (armor made with red leather) dedicated to Ninomiya Miwa-jinja Shrine in Fuefuki City on November 25, 1566 belonged to Shingen.</e>
<cmt>changed to more active &quot;many believe&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many believe that akagawa gusoku (armor made with red leather) dedicated to Ninomiya Miwa-jinja Shrine in Fuefuki City on January 15, 1567 (November 25, 1566 in old lunar calendar) belonged to Shingen.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>義信の東光寺 (山梨県)幽閉の時期である事などから、三条の方が義信の赤皮具足を奉納したとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it was the time when Yoshinobu was confined in Toko-ji Temple (Yamanashi Prefecture), there is a view that Sanjo no kata dedicated Yoshinobu&apos;s akagawa gusoku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it was the time when Yoshinobu was confined in Toko-ji Temple (Yamanashi Prefecture), there is a view that Sanjo no kata dedicated Yoshinobu&apos;s akagawa gusoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it was the time when Yoshinobu was confined in Toko-ji Temple (Yamanashi Prefecture), there is a view that Sanjo no kata dedicated Yoshinobu&apos;s akagawa gusoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>ドラマ、小説の影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influences of dramas and novels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influences of dramas and novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influences of dramas and novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>息子の義信の謀反、諏訪氏の出身の側室、諏訪御料人（諏訪御寮人）の子の武田勝頼が武田氏の家督を継いだ史実や、TVドラマや小説などの創作物の影響により信玄との不仲説や悪妻説などが流布。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of historical facts that revolt of her son, Yoshinobu, concubine from the Suwa family and that Katsuyori TAKEDA, who was a son of Suwa goryonin, inherited the position of the family head and influences of fictions such as TV dramas and novels, a view of bad blood with Shingen and a view that she was a bad wife have been disseminated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some believe that there was bad blood between Sanjo and Shingen and that Sanjo was a bad wife, because of the historical facts of a revolt by her son, Yoshinobu, and the inheritance of the position of family head by Katsuyori TAKEDA, who was a son of Suwa goryonin, a concubine from the Suwa family, as well as influences of works of fiction such as TV dramas and novels.</e>
<cmt>word order; please check, as I made drastic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some believe that there was bad blood between Sanjo no kata and Shingen and that Sanjo no kata was a bad wife, because of the historical facts of a revolt by her son, Yoshinobu, and the inheritance of the position of family head by Katsuyori TAKEDA, who was a son of Suwa goryonin, a concubine from the Suwa family, as well as influences of works of fiction such as TV dramas and novels.</e>
<cmt>sanjo no kata としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>不器量で暗愚な上に公家の家柄を鼻にかけ、高慢で嫉妬深い悪妻という否定的イメージを持たれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She has been given negative image of a bad wife who, in addition to being ill-favored and benighted, was proud of her blood of noble and overproud and jealous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She has been given the negative image of a bad wife who, in addition to being ill-favored and benighted, was proud of her noble blood and overproud and jealous.</e>
<cmt>inserted &quot;the,&quot; word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She has been given the negative image of a bad wife who, in addition to being ill-favored and benighted, was proud of her noble blood and overproud and jealous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>これらのイメージはほぼ全て新田次郎原作の小説『武田信玄』によって作られたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of such images were caused by the novel &quot;Tekeda Shingen (Shingen TAKEDA)&quot; by Jiro NITTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most such images arise from the novel &quot;Tekeda Shingen (Shingen TAKEDA)&quot; by Jiro NITTA.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most such images arise from the novel &quot;Takeda Shingen&quot; (Shingen TAKEDA) by Jiro NITTA.</e>
<cmt>&quot; の位置を移動しました。Takeda と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>邦画『風林火山 (映画)（1969年）』（井上靖原作）では久我美子が演じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Japanese movie &quot;Furin Kazan&quot; (originally written by Yasushi INOUE), Yoshiko KUGA starred as her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Japanese movie &quot;Furin Kazan&quot; (originally written by Yasushi INOUE), Yoshiko KUGA starred as Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;her&quot; to &quot;Sanjo.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Japanese movie &quot;Furin Kazan (movie) (1969)&quot; (originally written by Yasushi INOUE), Yoshiko KUGA starred as Sanjo no kata.</e>
<cmt>(movie) (1969)を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>ただし、1988年に映像化された日本放送協会大河ドラマでは、紺野美沙子が演じる三条夫人自身は信玄を慕うあまりの側室（諏訪御寮人）への嫉妬心からの、敵としての役回りという感が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the taiga drama series screened by NHK (Japan Broadcasting Corporation), we felt that Sanjo fujin herself, performed by Misako KONNO, played a role of enemy of concubine (Suwa goryonin) because of her love to Shingen resulting in jealousy against the concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the taiga drama series screened by NHK (Japan Broadcasting Corporation), we felt that Sanjo fujin herself, performed by Misako KONNO, played the role of an enemy of a concubine (Suwa goryonin), because of her jealous love for Shingen.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the taiga drama series screened by NHK (Japan Broadcasting Corporation) in 1988, we felt that Sanjo fujin herself, performed by Misako KONNO, played the role of an enemy of a concubine (Suwa goryonin), because of her jealous love for Shingen.</e>
<cmt>in 1988 を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>小説内の悪女要素は侍女の八重が演じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The element of wicked woman seen in the novel was performed by her maid, Yae.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The element of wicked woman in the novel was performed by her maid, Yae.</e>
<cmt>omitted &apos;seen&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The element of wicked woman in the novel was performed by her maid, Yae.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、悪妻説や信玄との不仲説を裏付ける当時の史料は存在していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no historical material of that time that supports the view of bad wife or the view of bad blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no historical material of that time that supports the view of bad wife or the view of bad blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no historical material of that time that supports the view of bad wife or the view of bad blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>信玄との間に5人の子供をもうけていることから、出自や性格の理由で不仲であったとは言い切れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As she gave birth to five children with Shingen, we cannot pronounce that they were not in good relation because of origin or personality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As she gave birth to five children with Shingen, we cannot pronounce that Sanjo&apos;s origin or personality caused a poor relation between them.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As she gave birth to five children with Shingen, we cannot pronounce that Sanjo no kata&apos;s origin or personality caused a poor relation between them.</e>
<cmt>sanjo no kataとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>最近では、彼女と信玄の夫婦仲は決して悪くはなかったとする見方が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, the view that the relation between Shingen and her as a married couple was not bad has been becoming more dominant.</e>
<cmt>（途中に、読点はありますが、もともとは一つの文として書かれたと思われる）二つの文を一緒にして、再度二つの文に分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, the view that the relation of married couple between Shingen and Sanjo was not bad has been becoming more dominant.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, the view that the relation of married couple between Shingen and Sanjo no kata was not bad has been becoming more dominant.</e>
<cmt>sanjo no kataとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>おそらく、諏訪御料人が武田家最後の当主勝頼の母になった事から、信玄と諏訪御料人との関係を美化し、強調するため、三条夫人が悪妻として描かれるようになったと考えられる（不当貶めの法則）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This view surmises that because Suwa goryonin became the mother of the last family head of the Takeda family, in order to romanticize the relation between Shingen and Suwa goryonin and put stress on it, Sanjo fujin became to be described as a bad wise (rule of unfair diminishing).</e>
<cmt>（途中に、読点はありますが、もともとは一つの文として書かれたと思われる）二つの文を一緒にして、再度二つの文に分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This view surmises that because Suwa goryonin became the mother of the last family head of the Takeda family, in order to romanticize and put emphasis on the relation between Shingen and Suwa goryonin, Sanjo fujin came to be described as a bad wife (rule of unfair diminishing).</e>
<cmt>spelling, rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This view surmises that because Suwa goryonin became the mother of Katsuyori, the last family head of the Takeda family, in order to romanticize and put emphasis on the relation between Shingen and Suwa goryonin, Sanjo fujin came to be described as a bad wife (rule of unfair diminishing).</e>
<cmt>勝頼　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>これを受けて、2007年NHK大河ドラマの『風林火山 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（井上靖原作）では、原作とは違い、可憐で繊細な少女というイメージに転換。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to it, in the taiga drama series of NHK for 2007 &quot;Furin Kazan (NHK taiga drama)&quot; (originally, written by Yasushi INOUE), her image was changed to a pretty and fragile little girl departed from the original.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to the prevailing view, in the taiga drama series of NHK for 2007 &quot;Furin Kazan (NHK taiga drama)&quot; (originally written by Yasushi INOUE), Sanjo&apos;s image was changed to a pretty and fragile little girl, in a significant departure from the original.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to the prevailing view, in the taiga drama series of NHK for 2007 &quot;Furin Kazan (NHK taiga drama)&quot; (originally written by Yasushi INOUE), Sanjo no kata&apos;s image was changed to a pretty and fragile little girl, in a significant departure from the original.</e>
<cmt>sanjo no kataとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>池脇千鶴が演じる三条夫人は全く高慢なところがなく、ひたすらに晴信を慕いながらも芯の強い女性を演じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo fujin performed by Chizu IKEWAKI was not overproud and acted as a lady who loved Harunobu and had a stalwart heart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo fujin, performed by Chizu IKEWAKI, was not overproud and acted as a lady who loved Harunobu and had a stalwart heart.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo fujin, performed by Chizu IKEWAKI, was not overproud and acted as a lady who loved Harunobu and had a stalwart heart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>唯一、偶然に晴信からの諏訪御料人（由布姫）への恋歌を目にしてしまい、女心から嫌味を言うシーンがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was only one scene in which she happened to see Harunobu&apos;s koiuta (waka of love) to Suwa goryonin (Yuhime) and, because of woman&apos;s mind, said terrible thins..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was only one scene in which she happened to see Harunobu&apos;s koiuta (love poem) to Suwa goryonin (Yuhime) and, because she had a woman&apos;s mind, said terrible things.</e>
<cmt>spelling, changed &quot;waka of love&quot; to &quot;love poem&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was only one scene in which she happened to see Harunobu&apos;s koiuta (love poem) to Suwa goryonin (Yuhime) and, because she had a woman&apos;s mind, said terrible things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>その直後に目に涙を浮かべるなど一貫して純情な乙女として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, she was consistently described as a pure-hearted young lady to make a misty gaze immediately after that.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otherwise, she was consistently described as a pure-hearted young lady who made a misty gaze immediately after that.</e>
<cmt>rewording, changed &quot;however&quot; to &quot;otherwise,&quot; in order to avoid confusion in the next sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otherwise, she was consistently described as a pure-hearted young lady who made a misty gaze immediately after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また一方では諏訪御料人のイメージも「軟」から「硬」へ180度転換していることから、一般的に浸透してしまった歴史通念に対する、制作側の意図的な挑戦であると言えよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, as the image of Suwa goryonin was 180 degree shifted from &quot;soft&quot; to &quot;hard,&quot; we can say that is was intentional challenge from the producer side against popular belief on history which has been widely penetrated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, as the image of Suwa goryonin was shifted 180 degrees from &quot;soft&quot; to &quot;hard,&quot; we can say that the producer intentionally challenged a popular historical belief that had penetrated widely.</e>
<cmt>rewording, word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, as the image of Suwa goryonin was shifted 180 degrees from &apos;soft&apos; to &apos;hard,&apos; we can say that the producer intentionally challenged a popular historical belief that had penetrated widely.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 諏訪太郎頼光(id:98476), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 建長(id:119884), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), 鈴木康文(id:97280), 小者(id:172526), でここ(id:9565), MDR-SK(id:192066), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Iganin(id:80282), 代言人(id:33675), Kanoe(id:17203), こぶまき(id:38278), Bellenion(id:22635), Nzero(id:18138), Bankokuya(id:91191), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>