<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>稲垣浩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshi INAGAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshi INAGAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshi INAGAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>稲垣 浩（いながき ひろし、1905年12月30日 - 1980年5月21日）は、日本の映画監督。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshi INAGAKI (born December 30, 1905, died May 21, 1980) was a Japanese film director.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshi INAGAKI (born December 30, 1905, died May 21, 1980) was a Japanese film director.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshi INAGAKI (December 30, 1905 - May 21, 1980) was a Japanese film director.</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本映画の基礎を作った名監督の一人であり、海外での評価も極めて高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He helped lay the foundations of the film industry in Japan, and as such he was one of Japan&apos;s most famous directors; his films are also very popular with overseas audiences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He helped lay the foundations of the film industry in Japan, and as such he was one of Japan&apos;s most famous directors; his films are also very popular with overseas audiences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He helped lay the foundations of the film industry in Japan, and as such he was one of Japan&apos;s most famous directors; his films are also very popular with overseas audiences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal profile and career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal profile and career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile and career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>東京本郷区駒込千駄木町（現・文京区千駄木1丁目）に、父は新派俳優・東明二郎の息子として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Komagome Sendagi Town in Tokyo&apos;s Hongo ward (today the first district of Sendagi in Bunkyo ward) to his father Jiro TOMEI, an actor of the new acting school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Komagome Sendagi Town in Tokyo&apos;s Hongo ward (today the first district of Sendagi in Bunkyo ward) to his father Jiro TOMEI, an actor of the new acting school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Komagome Sendagi Town in Tokyo&apos;s Hongo ward (today 1-chome, Sendagi, Bunkyo Ward) to his father Jiro TOMEI, an actor of the new acting school.</e>
<cmt>住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母の病気のために小学校を一年でやめ、7歳から東明浩の芸名で子役となり舞台に立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He stopping going to elementary school in his first year because his mother was ill, and starting when he was seven with his debut, he appeared on stage as a child actor under the name Hiroshi TOMEI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He stopping going to elementary school in his first year because his mother was ill, and starting when he was seven with his debut, he appeared on stage as a child actor under the name Hiroshi TOMEI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He stopping going to elementary school in his first year because his mother was ill, and starting when he was seven with his debut, he appeared on stage as a child actor under the name Hiroshi TOMEI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>8歳の時に母が亡くなり、父と共に旅公演に出たが、この間に独学で読み書きを覚え、小説家、劇作家を目指すほどの読書家となり、戯曲の執筆をはじめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother passed away when he was eight, and so he went on tour with his father, giving performances around Japan; during this period, he also taught himself to read and write, becoming quite a bookworm in an effort to become a novelist or playwright; he soon began writing his own plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother passed away when he was eight, and so he went on tour with his father, giving performances around Japan; during this period, he also taught himself to read and write, becoming quite a bookworm in an effort to become a novelist or playwright; he soon began writing his own plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother passed away when he was eight, and so he went on tour with his father, giving performances around Japan; during this period, he also taught himself to read and write, becoming quite a bookworm in an effort to become a novelist or playwright; he soon began writing his own plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>それを父の一座にかけたところ意外にも好評を博したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These plays were well-received not only among his father&apos;s acting troupe but among a larger audience as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These plays were well-received not only among his father&apos;s acting troupe but among a larger audience as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These plays were well-received not only among his father&apos;s acting troupe but among a larger audience as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>大正11年、日活向島撮影所に俳優として入社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1922, he joined the Nikkatsu Mukojima film studio as an actor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1922, he joined the Nikkatsu Mukojima film studio as an actor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1922, he joined the Nikkatsu Mukojima film studio as an actor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>12年、溝口健二監督の「夜」などで銀幕での親子出演を果たすが、やがて監督を志すようになり、伊藤大輔の伊藤映画研究所に参加し、シナリオを学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1923, Inagaki&apos;s father-son performances (with his father Jiro) began to appear on the silver screen, including in such works as director Kenji MIZOGUCHI&apos;s film &quot;Yoru&quot; (Night), but as time passed Inagaki set his sights on becoming a director himself, leading him to take part in Daisuke ITO&apos;s Ito Film Study Group studying scenarios.</e>
<cmt>I noticed the online database has &quot;Ito film laboratory&quot; but I think that&apos;s a poor word choice in this case.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1923, Inagaki&apos;s father-son performances (with his father Jiro) began to appear on the silver screen, including in such works as director Kenji MIZOGUCHI&apos;s film &quot;Yoru&quot; (Night), but as time passed Inagaki set his sights on becoming a director himself, leading him to take part in Daisuke ITO&apos;s Ito Film Study Group studying scenarios.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1923, Inagaki&apos;s father-son performances (with his father Jiro) began to appear on the silver screen, including in such works as director Kenji MIZOGUCHI&apos;s film &apos;Yoru&apos; (Night), but as time passed Inagaki set his sights on becoming a director himself, leading him to take part in Daisuke ITO&apos;s Ito Film Study Group studying scenarios.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>15年の伊藤監督・父出演の「日輪」では助監督を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inagaki worked as assistant director on the 1925 film &quot;Nichirin&quot; (The Sun), starring his father Jiro and directed by Ito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inagaki worked as assistant director on the 1925 film &quot;Nichirin&quot; (The Sun), starring his father Jiro and directed by Ito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inagaki worked as assistant director on the 1925 film &apos;Nichirin&apos; (The Sun), starring his father Jiro and directed by Ito.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>のち衣笠貞之助の助監督を経て、昭和3年伊藤の紹介で伊丹万作とともに片岡千恵蔵プロの創設に参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later switched to working as assistant director to Teinosuke KINUGASA, and in 1928, through the good offices of Ito, he, along with Mansaku ITAMI, was invited to participate in the founding of the Chiezo KATAOKA Productions film company.</e>
<cmt>The meaning of &quot;sousetsu&quot; is very unclear.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later switched to working as assistant director to Teinosuke KINUGASA, and in 1928, through the good offices of Ito, he, along with Mansaku ITAMI, was invited to participate in the founding of the Chiezo KATAOKA Productions film company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later switched to working as assistant director to Teinosuke KINUGASA, and in 1928, through the good offices of Ito, he, along with Mansaku ITAMI, was invited to participate in the founding of the Chiezo KATAOKA Productions film company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同年千恵蔵主演、伊丹脚本の「天下太平記」で監督としてデビューし、以後、「放蕩三昧」「源氏小僧」「絵本武者修行」「元禄十三年」といった千恵蔵主演の明朗にして陽気な時代劇を多数手がけ、伊丹と共に千恵蔵プロの二本柱と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That same year, Inagaki made his directorial debut on the film &quot;Tenka Taiheiki&quot; (Record of the Great Peace Under Heaven), which starred Chiezo and whose screenplay was written by Itami; thereafter, he made a great number of cheerful period dramas showing Chiezo&apos;s merrier side, including &quot;Hoto zanmai&quot; (Drowning in the Three Pleasures), &quot;Genji kozo&quot; (The Young Priest Genji), &quot;Ehon musha shugyo&quot; (Picture Book of a Warrior Traveling to Hone His Martial Skills), and &quot;Genroku Ju-san nen&quot; (Year Thirteen of the Genroku Era (about the year 1700)), leading to Inagaki and Itami being called the &quot;two supporting pillars&quot; of Chiezo Productions.</e>
<cmt>I do not think it is a good idea to say &quot;Knight Errant&quot; or &quot;Knight Errantry&quot; for this title, as that has a strong Western context that is not necessarily appropriate to the context of this film/story.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That same year, Inagaki made his directorial debut on the film &quot;Tenka Taiheiki&quot; (Record of the Great Peace Under Heaven), which starred Chiezo and whose screenplay was written by Itami; thereafter, he made a great number of cheerful period dramas showing Chiezo&apos;s merrier side, including &quot;Hoto zanmai&quot; (Drowning in the Three Pleasures), &quot;Genji kozo&quot; (The Young Priest Genji), &quot;Ehon musha shugyo&quot; (Picture Book of a Warrior Traveling to Hone His Martial Skills), and &quot;Genroku Ju-san nen&quot; (Year Thirteen of the Genroku Era (about the year 1700)), leading to Inagaki and Itami being called the &quot;two supporting pillars&quot; of Chiezo Productions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That same year, Inagaki made his directorial debut on the film &apos;Tenka Taiheiki&apos; (Record of the Great Peace Under Heaven), which starred Chiezo and whose screenplay was written by Itami; thereafter, he made a great number of cheerful period dramas showing Chiezo&apos;s merrier side, including &apos;Hoto zanmai&apos; (Drowning in the Three Pleasures), &apos;Genji kozo&apos; (The Young Priest Genji), &apos;Ehon musha shugyo&apos; (Picture Book of a Warrior Traveling to Hone His Martial Skills), and &apos;Genroku Ju-san nen&apos; (Year Thirteen of the Genroku Era (about the year 1700)), leading to Inagaki and Itami being called the &apos;two supporting pillars&apos; of Chiezo Productions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また長谷川川伸の「瞼の母」「一本刀土俵入り」、子母沢寛原作「弥太郎笠」などのまた旅物も好評で、のちにたびたびリメイクされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inagaki&apos;s adaptations to the silver screen of stories by Shin HASEGAWA like &quot;Mabuta no haha&quot; (Mother of my Eyelids) and &quot;Ippongatana dohyo iri&quot; (Ippongatana (One-sword) enters the ring) as well as Kan Shimozawa&apos;s work &quot;Yataro kasa&quot; (Yataro&apos;s kasa (a type of conical hat)), of the wandering warrior genre, also garnered rave reviews; in later years such films by Inagaki were repeatedly remade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inagaki&apos;s adaptations to the silver screen of stories by Shin HASEGAWA like &quot;Mabuta no haha&quot; (Mother of my Eyelids) and &quot;Ippongatana dohyo iri&quot; (Ippongatana (One-sword) enters the ring) as well as Kan Shimozawa&apos;s work &quot;Yataro kasa&quot; (Yataro&apos;s kasa (a type of conical hat)), of the wandering warrior genre, also garnered rave reviews; in later years such films by Inagaki were repeatedly remade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inagaki&apos;s adaptations to the silver screen of stories by Shin HASEGAWA like &apos;Mabuta no haha&apos; (Mother of my Eyelids) and &apos;Ippongatana dohyo iri&apos; (Ippongatana (One-sword) enters the ring) as well as Kan Shimozawa&apos;s work &apos;Yataro kasa&apos; (Yataro&apos;s kasa (a type of conical hat)), of the wandering warrior genre, also garnered rave reviews; in later years such films by Inagaki were repeatedly remade.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>9年には三村伸太郎、山中貞雄、滝沢英輔、八尋不二ら京都の鳴滝に住んでいた若手映画人らと映画会社の垣根を超えた脚本執筆集団を結成し、「梶原金八」の合同筆名で山中監督「百万両の壺」「河内山宗俊」、滝沢監督「太閤記」「宮本武蔵」のシナリオを執筆し、それぞれヒットを飛ばした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1934, he formed a screenplay writing group that managed to establish a presence in the film world with other young filmmakers living in Kyoto&apos;s Narutaki area, including Shintaro MIMURA, Sadao YAMANAKA, Eisuke TAKIZAWA, and Fuji YAHIRO; under the combined pen-name &quot;Kinpachi KAJIWARA,&quot; this group wrote the scenarios for &quot;Hyakuman ryo no ko&quot; (The Million-Dollar Vase) and &quot;Soshun Kouchiyama,&quot; both directed by Yamannaka, and for &quot;Taikoki&quot; (Chronicle of Hideyoshi) and &quot;Miyamoto Musashi&quot; (Musashi Miyamoto), both directed by Takizawa, and every one of these films written by the group became smash hits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1934, he formed a screenplay writing group that managed to establish a presence in the film world with other young filmmakers living in Kyoto&apos;s Narutaki area, including Shintaro MIMURA, Sadao YAMANAKA, Eisuke TAKIZAWA, and Fuji YAHIRO; under the combined pen-name &quot;Kinpachi KAJIWARA,&quot; this group wrote the scenarios for &quot;Hyakuman ryo no ko&quot; (The Million-Dollar Vase) and &quot;Soshun Kouchiyama,&quot; both directed by Yamannaka, and for &quot;Taikoki&quot; (Chronicle of Hideyoshi) and &quot;Miyamoto Musashi&quot; (Musashi Miyamoto), both directed by Takizawa, and every one of these films written by the group became smash hits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1934, he formed a screenplay writing group that managed to establish a presence in the film world with other young filmmakers living in Kyoto&apos;s Narutaki area, including Shintaro MIMURA, Sadao YAMANAKA, Eisuke TAKIZAWA, and Fuji YAHIRO; under the combined pen-name &apos;Kinpachi KAJIWARA,&apos; this group wrote the scenarios for &apos;Hyakuman ryo no ko&apos; (The Million-Dollar Vase) and &apos;Soshun Kouchiyama,&apos; both directed by Yamannaka, and for &apos;Taikoki&apos; (Chronicle of Hideyoshi) and &apos;Miyamoto Musashi&apos; (Musashi Miyamoto), both directed by Takizawa, and every one of these films written by the group became smash hits.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>その後は日活太秦や太秦京都を中心に映画を撮影し、10年山中と共同監督した「関の弥太ッぺ」、中里介山原作の「大菩薩峠」、11年前進座出演の「股旅千一夜」、16年「海を渡る祭礼」などといった時代劇の大作や話題作を製作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this, Inagaki continued to shoot films, mainly around Nikkatsu Uzumasa and Uzumasa Kyoto, and in 1935 he co-directed &quot;Seki no Yatappe&quot; with Yamanaka; Inagaki also independently crafted some of his most celebrated epic and period films during this period, including his 1935 film &quot;Daibosatsu toge&quot; (literally &quot;The Bodhisattva&apos;s Pass&quot; but sometimes credited as &quot;The Sword of Doom&quot; in English) based on the original novel by Kaizan NAKAZATO, his 1936 film &quot;Matatabi sen-ichi ya&quot; (A Thousand and One Nights in a Gambler&apos;s Wandering Life) starring the actors of the Zenshin troupe, and the film &quot;Umi wo wataru sairei&quot; (The Ocean-Crossing Festival) in 1941.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, Inagaki continued to shoot films, mainly around Nikkatsu Uzumasa and Uzumasa Kyoto, and in 1935 he co-directed &quot;Seki no Yatappe&quot; with Yamanaka; Inagaki also independently crafted some of his most celebrated epic and period films during this period, including his 1935 film &quot;Daibosatsu toge&quot; (literally &quot;The Bodhisattva&apos;s Pass&quot; but sometimes credited as &quot;The Sword of Doom&quot; in English) based on the original novel by Kaizan NAKAZATO, his 1936 film &quot;Matatabi sen-ichi ya&quot; (A Thousand and One Nights in a Gambler&apos;s Wandering Life) starring the actors of the Zenshin troupe, and the film &quot;Umi wo wataru sairei&quot; (The Ocean-Crossing Festival) in 1941.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, Inagaki continued to shoot films, mainly around Nikkatsu Uzumasa and Uzumasa Kyoto, and in 1935 he co-directed &apos;Seki no Yatappe&apos; with Yamanaka; Inagaki also independently crafted some of his most celebrated epic and period films during this period, including his 1935 film &apos;Daibosatsu toge&apos; (literally &apos;The Bodhisattva&apos;s Pass&apos; but sometimes credited as &apos;The Sword of Doom&apos; in English) based on the original novel by Kaizan NAKAZATO, his 1936 film &apos;Matatabi sen-ichi ya&apos; (A Thousand and One Nights in a Gambler&apos;s Wandering Life) starring the actors of the Zenshin troupe, and the film &apos;Umi wo wataru sairei&apos; (The Ocean-Crossing Festival) in 1941.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>18年には阪東妻三郎を主演に迎え、病床の伊丹が脚本を担当した「無法松の一生」は戦前の日本映画を代表する名作といわれるが、人力車夫・無法松が軍人の未亡人に愛の告白をするという場面が時局に合わないとして、検閲でカットされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1943 he welcomed Tsumasaburo BANDO as his new star, and Inagaki&apos;s &quot;Muhomatsu no issei&quot; (Life of Muhomatsu), whose screenplay was written by Itami from his sickbed, is hailed as a pre-1945 masterpiece of Japanese film, but the scene where Muhomatsu the rickshaw driver confesses his love to a soldier&apos;s widow was considered unacceptable given the wartime situation and was cut by the censors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1943 he welcomed Tsumasaburo BANDO as his new star, and Inagaki&apos;s &quot;Muhomatsu no issei&quot; (Life of Muhomatsu), whose screenplay was written by Itami from his sickbed, is hailed as a pre-1945 masterpiece of Japanese film, but the scene where Muhomatsu the rickshaw driver confesses his love to a soldier&apos;s widow was considered unacceptable given the wartime situation and was cut by the censors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1943 he welcomed Tsumasaburo BANDO as his new star, and Inagaki&apos;s &apos;Muhomatsu no issei&apos; (Life of Muhomatsu), whose screenplay was written by Itami from his sickbed, is hailed as a pre-1945 masterpiece of Japanese film, but the scene where Muhomatsu the rickshaw driver confesses his love to a soldier&apos;s widow was considered unacceptable given the wartime situation and was cut by the censors.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>戦後は20年の「最後の攘夷党」でいち早く活動を開始し、22年東横映画(現・東映)の第一作となった現代劇「こころ月の如く」を監督。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inagaki resumed making films very soon after the war ended with his 1945 &quot;Saigo no joi to&quot; (The Final &apos;Expel the Foreigners&apos; Group), and in 1947 directed the period drama that is now recognized as the finest film produced by To-Yoko Eiga (today&apos;s Toei Company, Ltd.): &quot;Kokoro tsuki no gotoku&quot; (A Heart Like the Moon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inagaki resumed making films very soon after the war ended with his 1945 &quot;Saigo no joi to&quot; (The Final &apos;Expel the Foreigners&apos; Group), and in 1947 directed the period drama that is now recognized as the finest film produced by To-Yoko Eiga (today&apos;s Toei Company, Ltd.): &quot;Kokoro tsuki no gotoku&quot; (A Heart Like the Moon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inagaki resumed making films very soon after the war ended with his 1945 &apos;Saigo no joi to&apos; (The Final &apos;Expel the Foreigners&apos; Group), and in 1947 directed the period drama that is now recognized as the finest film produced by To-Yoko Eiga (today&apos;s Toei Company, Ltd.): &apos;Kokoro tsuki no gotoku&apos; (A Heart Like the Moon).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>25年からは主に東宝で活躍し、31年三船敏郎の「宮本武蔵」がアカデミー賞外国語映画賞を受賞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting in 1950, he began working mainly for Toho; his film &quot;Miyamoto Musashi&quot;, starring Toshiro Mifune as Musashi, won the 1955 Academy Award for Best Foreign Language Film.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting in 1950, he began working mainly for Toho; his film &quot;Miyamoto Musashi&quot;, starring Toshiro Mifune as Musashi, won the 1955 Academy Award for Best Foreign Language Film.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting in 1950, he began working mainly for Toho; his film &apos;Miyamoto Musashi,&apos; starring Toshiro Mifune as Musashi, won the 1955 Academy Award for Best Foreign Language Film.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>さらに33年には自作「無法松の一生」を戦時中にカットされた箇所を元に戻して再度映画化し、ベネチア国際映画祭グランプリに輝く、このときに本国に「トリマシタ　ナキマシタ」の電報を打ったという話は有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1957, he re-released his own film &quot;Muhomatsu no issei&quot; with the scenes that had been cut by the wartime censors restored; the complete version then went on to win the Grand Prix at the Venice International Film Festival, and the story of the brief telegram he sent to Japan just after receiving the reward, &quot;won, cried,&quot; is quite famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1957, he re-released his own film &quot;Muhomatsu no issei&quot; with the scenes that had been cut by the wartime censors restored; the complete version then went on to win the Grand Prix at the Venice International Film Festival, and the story of the brief telegram he sent to Japan just after receiving the reward, &quot;won, cried,&quot; is quite famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1957, he re-released his own film &apos;Muhomatsu no issei&apos; with the scenes that had been cut by the wartime censors restored; the complete version then went on to win the Grand Prix at the Venice International Film Festival, and the story of the brief telegram he sent to Japan just after receiving the reward, &apos;won, cried,&apos; is quite famous.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>昭和30年代以降は黒澤明とともに東宝の大作及び時代劇路線の代表的な監督とされ、34年三船出演・円谷英二特撮の東宝1000本記念映画「日本誕生」を、37年東宝30周年記念映画「忠臣蔵」を製作し、それぞれ興行的に成功を収めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beginning in 1955, he was recognized, along with Akira KUROSAWA, as being one of Toho&apos;s two great master directors of epics and period dramas; in 1959 he created &quot;Nihon tanjo&quot; (The Birth of Japan), Toho&apos;s commemorative 1000th film, starring Mifune and featuring special effects by Eiji TSUBURAYA, as well as the 1962 commemorative film &quot;Chushingura&quot; (sometimes credited as &quot;The Forty-Seven Ronin&quot; in English) celebrating the 30th anniversary of Toho&apos;s founding in 1932, both of which achieved success as entertainment films.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beginning in 1955, he was recognized, along with Akira KUROSAWA, as being one of Toho&apos;s two great master directors of epics and period dramas; in 1959 he created &quot;Nihon tanjo&quot; (The Birth of Japan), Toho&apos;s commemorative 1000th film, starring Mifune and featuring special effects by Eiji TSUBURAYA, as well as the 1962 commemorative film &quot;Chushingura&quot; (sometimes credited as &quot;The Forty-Seven Ronin&quot; in English) celebrating the 30th anniversary of Toho&apos;s founding in 1932, both of which achieved success as entertainment films.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beginning in 1955, he was recognized, along with Akira KUROSAWA, as being one of Toho&apos;s two great master directors of epics and period dramas; in 1959 he created &apos;Nihon tanjo&apos; (The Birth of Japan), Toho&apos;s commemorative 1000th film, starring Mifune and featuring special effects by Eiji TSUBURAYA, as well as the 1962 commemorative film &apos;Chushingura&apos; (sometimes credited as &apos;The Forty-Seven Ronin&apos; in English) celebrating the 30th anniversary of Toho&apos;s founding in 1932, both of which achieved success as entertainment films.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>のち東京宝映プロの代表に就任、タレントの指導や演劇活動を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he began working as a representative of Tokyo Hoei Productions, providing guidance to the company&apos;s stars and running them through on-stage acting exercises.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he began working as a representative of Tokyo Hoei Productions, providing guidance to the company&apos;s stars and running them through on-stage acting exercises.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he began working as a representative of Tokyo Hoei Productions, providing guidance to the company&apos;s stars and running them through on-stage acting exercises.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>晩年は「日刊スポーツ」に劇画「ナンセンス三浪士」を連載した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his final years, he had the story called &quot;Nonsense Miroshi&quot; (Three Nonsensical Ronin) serialized as a comic strip in Nikkan Sports (a daily newspaper).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his final years, he had the story called &quot;Nonsense Miroshi&quot; (Three Nonsensical Ronin) serialized as a comic strip in Nikkan Sports (a daily newspaper).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his final years, he had the story called &apos;Nonsense Miroshi&apos; (Three Nonsensical Ronin) serialized as a comic strip in Nikkan Sports (a daily newspaper).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>1980年5月21日、逝去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inagaki passed away on May 21, 1981.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inagaki passed away on May 21, 1981.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inagaki passed away on May 21, 1980.</e>
<cmt>数字修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>享年74。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 74.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 74.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Genba(id:20640), Cprobot(id:97843), 松木完之(id:26818), Hatsune(id:26654), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), 平凡児朗(id:23570), VolkovBot(id:105371), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Azucar(id:20348), 武蔵野明日香(id:20176), Tiroru(id:233517), 桃の木(id:90241), Point136(id:211299), Yukida-R(id:293280), Yas(id:739), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>