<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>禅海</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenkai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenkai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenkai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>禅海（ぜんかい、元禄4年（1691年） - 安永3年（1774年））は、江戸時代中期の曹洞宗の僧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenkai (1691 - 1774) was a Buddhist priest of Soto Sect of Zen Buddhism in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenkai (1691 - 1774) was a Buddhist priest of the Sotoshu sect of Zen Buddhism in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>articlereference for 宗: 用語統一リスト</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenkai (1691 - 1774) was a Buddhist priest of the Sotoshu sect of Zen Buddhism in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>越前国高田藩士の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Son of a feudal retainer of Takada Domain in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of a feudal retainer of Takada Domain in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of a feudal retainer of Takada Domain in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本名は福原市九郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name is Ichikuro FUKUHARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Ichikuro FUKUHARA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Ichikuro FUKUHARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>生年については貞享4年（1687年）説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some record says his birth was in 1687.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some record says his birth was in 1687.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some record says his birth was in 1687.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>詳しくは真如庵禅海といい、江戸浅草の住人、祖先は越後高田の福原氏であるといい、もと籍を曹洞宗に置く六十六部であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His full Buddhist name is Shinnyoan Zenkai; he lived in Asakusa, Edo; his ancestors were said to be the Fukuhara clan of Takada Domain in Echigo Province; and he was a member of rokuju-rokubu (Buddhist pilgrim carrying 66 copies of the Lotus Sutra to be left at sites across Japan) of the Soto Sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His full Buddhist name was Shinnyoan Zenkai; he lived in Asakusa, Edo; his ancestors were said to be the Fukuhara clan of Takada Domain in Echigo Province; and he was a member of rokuju-rokubu (Buddhist pilgrim carrying 66 copies of the Lotus Sutra to be left at sites across Japan) of the Sotoshu sect.</e>
<cmt>grammarreference for 宗: 用語統一リスト</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His full Buddhist name was Shinnyoan Zenkai; he lived in Asakusa, Edo; his ancestors were said to be the Fukuhara clan of Takada Domain in Echigo Province; and he was a member of rokuju-rokubu (Buddhist pilgrim carrying 66 copies of the Lotus Sutra to be left at sites across Japan) of the Sotoshu sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>両親が亡くなった事から世の無常を感じて出家し、諸国を行脚、正徳 (日本)5年（1715年）に得度して禅海と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He felt absence of absolutes upon the death of his parents, went into priesthood, pilgrimed various parts of the country and had a Buddhist name Zenkai.</e>
<cmt>出家も得度も辞書を見るとまったく同じで、違いがわかりません。ただYahoo Q&amp;Ahttp://detail.chiebukuro.yahoo.co.jp/qa/question_detail/q1238340087　で「出家とは世俗を離れ、家庭生活を捨てて仏門に入ること。得度とは僧侶となるための出家の儀式」という回答があり、これが正しければ、違いがよくわかります。しかし、具体的にはどういう儀式かわからないので、左記の日本語文については「得度」のところは略しました。また「禅海と称した」というのは「自分で称した」のか「そういう名前をもらったのか」がわかりません。自分で称するということはないと思うので、「禅海という仏教名を持った」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He felt the absence of absolutes upon the death of his parents, entered the priesthood, went on pilgrimages to various parts of the country and obtained the Buddhist name, Zenkai, when he experienced tokudo (a rite to become a monk) in 1715.</e>
<cmt>一部訳漏れ: 1715年にarticle, rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He felt the absence of absolutes upon the death of his parents, entered the priesthood, went on pilgrimages to various parts of the country and obtained the Buddhist name, Zenkai, when he experienced tokudo (a rite to become a monk) in 1715.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>豊前国（今の大分県）耶馬渓の青の洞門を開削したものとして知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known as the creator of the Blue Tunnel in Yabakei Valley, Fuzen Province (today&apos;s Oita prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known as the creator of the Blue Tunnel in Yabakei Valley, Fuzen Province (today&apos;s Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>capital</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known as the creator of the Blue Tunnel in Yabakei Valley, Fuzen Province (today&apos;s Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>回国の途中、豊後国羅漢寺 (中津市)を参詣した時、川沿いの断崖にかけられた桟橋、青野渡が危険で、人馬のしばしば覆没することを知り、これを哀れみ、鑿道の誓願を発し、陸道の掘削を思いついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he paid a homage to Rakan-ji Temple, Bungo Province (today&apos;s Nakatsu city) during his pilgrimage, he learned that Aono-watari, a pier built on a cliff along a river, was so fragile and shaky that people and horses often fell down in the river, felt so sorry, made his profession of building a path and came up with an idea of excavating a path in the rock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he paid a homage to Rakan-ji Temple, Bungo Province (today&apos;s Nakatsu City) during his pilgrimage, he learned that Aono-watari, a pier built on a cliff along a river, was so fragile and shaky that people and horses often fell down into the river and felt so sorry that he made a vow of building a path and came up with the idea of excavating for the path.</e>
<cmt>「青野渡」の読み不明preposition/article/wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he paid a homage to Rakan-ji Temple, Bungo Province (today&apos;s Nakatsu City) during his pilgrimage, he learned that Aono-watari, a pier built on a cliff along a river, was so fragile and shaky that people and horses often fell down into the river and felt so sorry that he made a vow of building a path and came up with the idea of excavating for the path.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1730年（享保15年）頃、豊前国中津藩主の許可を得て掘削を始めたが、その後周辺の村民や九州諸藩の領主の援助を得て30年余りの歳月をかけて、1763年（宝暦13年）に完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around 1730, he started excavation with the approval of the head of Nakatsu Domain in Buzen Province and completed the work in 1763, in about 30 years, with the help of local residents and the support of local domain lords in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In around 1730, he started excavation with the approval of the head of Nakatsu Domain in Buzen Province and completed the work in 1763, in about 30 years, with the help of local residents and the support of local domain lords in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In around 1730, he started excavation with the approval of the head of Nakatsu Domain in Buzen Province and completed the work in 1763, in about 30 years, with the help of local residents and the support of local domain lords in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>高さ2丈、径3丈、長さ308歩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tunnel was about 2 jo (about 6 m) in height, 3 jo (about 9 m) in width and 308 bu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tunnel was 6.06 meters in height, 9.09 meters in diameter and 308 bu (560 meters) in length.</e>
<cmt>words addedconversion rule: 用語統一リストI converted 1歩 = 6尺 according to the URL below: http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%AD%A9</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tunnel was 6.06 meters in height, 9.09 meters in diameter and 308 bu (560 meters) in length.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>開通後、通行人から通行料を徴収したという話が伝わっており、この洞門は日本最古の有料道路とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a legend, after the tunnel was opened, people who used this tunnel paid the fee, and therefore this tunnel is said to be Japan&apos;s oldest toll road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a legend, after the tunnel was opened, people who used this tunnel paid a fee, and therefore this tunnel is said to be Japan&apos;s oldest toll road.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a legend, after the tunnel was opened, people who used this tunnel paid a fee, and therefore this tunnel is said to be Japan&apos;s oldest toll road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>菊池寛の小説『恩讐の彼方に』のモデルとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This story became a model of one of the works of Japanese novelist Kan KIKUCHI, &quot;Onshu no Kanata ni&quot; (Beyond the Revenge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This story became a model of one of the works of Japanese novelist Kan KIKUCHI, &quot;Onshu no Kanata ni&quot; (Beyond Love and Hate).</e>
<cmt>reference for 恩讐の彼方に: http://dic.search.yahoo.co.jp/search?ei=UTF-8&amp;fr=top_ga1_sa&amp;p=%E6%81%A9%E8%AE%90</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This story became a model of one of the works of Japanese novelist Kan KIKUCHI, &quot;Onshu no Kanata ni&quot; (Beyond Love and Hate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>作中では主である旗本中川三郎兵衛を殺害してその妾と出奔、鳥居峠 (長野県)で茶屋経営の裏で強盗を働いていたが、己の罪業を感じて出家、主殺しの罪滅ぼしのために青の洞門の開削を始め、後に仇とつけ狙った三郎兵衛の息子と共に鑿ったものとされるが、主殺しなどのエピソードは菊池の創作である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The murder episode depicted in this novel is a fiction created by the author Kikuchi; according to the novel, the main character killed his master, a direct retainer of the Tokugawa Shogunate, Saburobei NAKAGAWA, ran away with his master&apos;s concubine, became a robber while running a rest house at Torii Pass (Nagano prefecture), but when he felt his sin, he went into priesthood, started excavation of a tunnel in expiation for his sin, and ended up working together with a son of Saburobei, who looked after him for revenge, to complete the excavation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The murder episode depicted in this novel is a fiction created by the author Kikuchi; according to the novel, the main character killed his master, a direct retainer of the Tokugawa Shogunate, Saburobei NAKAGAWA, ran away with his master&apos;s concubine, became a robber while running a rest house at Torii Pass (Nagano Prefecture), but when he felt his sin, he went into priesthood, started excavation of a tunnel in expiation for his sin, and ended up working together with a son of Saburobei, who followed him seeking revenge, to complete the excavation.</e>
<cmt>capital/ wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The murder episode depicted in this novel is a fiction created by the author Kikuchi; according to the novel, the main character killed his master, a direct retainer of the Tokugawa Shogunate, Saburobei NAKAGAWA, ran away with his master&apos;s concubine, became a robber while running a rest house at Torii Pass (Nagano Prefecture), but when he felt his sin, he went into priesthood, started excavation of a tunnel in expiation for his sin, and ended up working together with a son of Saburobei, who followed him seeking revenge, to complete the excavation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Mooko(id:36162), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), Shinkansen(id:13703), Musashino(id:51342), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>