<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小野蘭山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranzan ONO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小野 蘭山（おの らんざん、享保14年8月21日 (旧暦)（1729年9月13日） - 文化 (元号)7年3月2日 (旧暦)（1810年4月5日））は、江戸時代の大本草学者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ranzan ONO (September 13, 1729 - April 5, 1810) was a great scholar of herbalism in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan ONO (September 13, 1729 - April 5, 1810) was a great scholar of herbalism in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan ONO (September 13, 1729 - April 5, 1810) was a great scholar of herbalism in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は識博（もとひろ）、通称は喜内、字は以文、号 (称号)は蘭山、朽匏子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was Motohiro, common name was Kinai, azana (Chinese courtesy name) was Ibun and second names were Ranzan and Kyuhoshi.</e>
<cmt>「朽匏子」＝「きゅうほうし」の読みは、下記サイトから引用いたしました。　「小野蘭山年表　磯野直秀」(PDF)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Motohiro, common name was Kinai, azana (Chinese courtesy name) was Ibun, and pen names were Ranzan and Kyuhoshi.</e>
<cmt>・「名」を「本名（real name）」とし、「号」をpen nameとしました（second nameは名字の意になり得るため）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Motohiro, common name was Kinai, azana (Chinese courtesy name) was Ibun, and pen names were Ranzan and Kyuhoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しばしば「日本のカール・フォン・リンネ」と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has frequently been called &apos;Carl von Linné of Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is frequently called the Japanese Carl von Linné.</e>
<cmt>・簡潔化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is frequently called the Japanese Carl von Linné.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>京都出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He came from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He came from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He came from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>門弟に杉田玄白、木村兼葭堂、飯沼慾斎、谷文晁、桜田欽斎、水谷豊文、三谷公器、狩谷エキ斎、吉田立仙、山本盛備（大正年間の総理大臣山本権兵衛の養曽祖父）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His disciples included Genpaku SUGITA, Kenkado KIMURA, Yokusai IINUMA, Buncho TANI, Kinsai SAKURADA, Toyobumi MIZUTANI, Koki MITANI, Ekisai KARIYA, Rissen YOSHIDA and Morinae YAMAMOTO (the adoptive great-grandfather of Gombei YAMAMOTO, a Prime Minister in the Taisho period).</e>
<cmt>「飯沼慾斎（いいぬま　よくさい）」「水谷豊文（みずたに　とよぶみ）」は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://www.ndl.go.jp/nature/varie/varie_1.html  「桜田欽斎(さくらだ　きんさい）」は、下記から引用いたしました。　　http://www.google.co.jp/search?hl=ja&amp;rlz=1T4RNWE 「三谷公器(みたに　こうき）」「吉田立仙（よしだ　りっせん」は、サイトでも読み方は見つからず、定かではありません。   　 「山本 盛備（やまもと もりなえ）」は、下記サイトから引用しました。http://keyword.auone.jp/Result/?sysid=K001&amp;serviceid=0001001001&amp;devcd=2&amp;keyword=%E5%B1%B1%E6%9C%AC%E7%9B%9B%E5%82%99&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;maxResults=5&amp;start=0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His disciples included Genpaku SUGITA, Kenkado KIMURA, Yokusai IINUMA, Buncho TANI, Kinsai SAKURADA, Toyobumi MIZUTANI, Koki MITANI, Ekisai KARIYA, Rissen YOSHIDA, and Morinae YAMAMOTO (the adoptive great-grandfather of Gombei YAMAMOTO, Prime Minister in the Taisho period).</e>
<cmt>・コンマをandの前に付け、Prime Ministerの前のaを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His disciples included Genpaku SUGITA, Kenkado KIMURA, Yokusai IINUMA, Buncho TANI, Kinsai SAKURADA, Toyobumi MIZUTANI, Koki MITANI, Ekisai KARIYA, Rissen YOSHIDA, and Morinae YAMAMOTO (the adoptive great-grandfather of Gombei YAMAMOTO, Prime Minister in the Taisho period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>本姓は佐伯氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His main name was the Saeki clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real surname was Saeki.</e>
<cmt>・「本姓」の訳を変更しました。・この場合、「氏」の訳出は不要と判断し、clanを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real surname was Saeki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>16歳の時から父の師であった松岡恕庵に本草学を学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started studying herbalism at the age of 16 under Joan MATSUOKA, his father&apos;s teacher.</e>
<cmt>「松岡恕庵（まつお　じょあん）」は、下記サイトから引用しました。http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E6%9D%BE%E5%B2%A1&amp;dtype=0&amp;stype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=20258417346400</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started studying herbalism at the age of 16 under Joan MATSUOKA, his father&apos;s teacher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started studying herbalism at the age of 16 under Joan MATSUOKA, his father&apos;s teacher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>非常に記憶力がよく一度聞いたことは一生忘れなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he had a good memory and never forget for a lifetime what he once heard of.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he had an excellent memory and never forgot what he once heard of.</e>
<cmt>・goodをexcellent（非常によい）に変更しました。・forgetの時制を過去形に修正しました。・neverがあるので、「一生」を直訳している部分は不要と判断し、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he had an excellent memory and never forgot what he once heard of.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ところが2年と経たず恕庵が死去、以後は独学で本草学を学ぶことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, less than two years later, Joan died and after that he ended up studying herbalism by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unexpectedly, less than two years later, Joan died, and after that he ended up studying herbalism by himself.</e>
<cmt>・Howeverが合わないように思われますので変更しました。・コンマをandの前に追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unexpectedly, less than two years later, Joan died, and after that he ended up studying herbalism by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そんな中、蘭山は一つの壁に突き当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such a situation, Ranzan was confronted with a difficulty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Ranzan was confronted with a difficulty.</e>
<cmt>・「そんな中」の訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Ranzan was confronted with a difficulty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>実はそれまでの本草学は中華人民共和国から伝わった李時珍の著書『本草綱目』を元に作られたもので日本固有の動植物、鉱物などに適した形をもっていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, herbalism up to that time had been based on &quot;Compendium of Materia Medica,&quot; a book written by LI Shizhen which was introduced from China, not suitable for the indigenous animals, plants and minerals of Japan.</e>
<cmt>江戸時代の中国は、「清」で「中華人民共和国」は太平洋戦争後成立しました。訳はあえて、「中国」＝「China」といたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The problem was that until then herbalism in Japan had been based on a book called &quot;Compendium of Materia Medica&quot; written by Shizhen LI, which was introduced from China, and the theory was inapplicable to some animals, plants and minerals indigenous to Japan.</e>
<cmt>・文脈に合っていないと思われるIn realityなどの表現を変更しました。・中国人の名である「李時珍」を、翻訳仕様指示書に従って、名＋姓の順にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The problem was that until then herbalism in Japan had been based on a book called &quot;Compendium of Materia Medica&quot; written by Shizhen LI, which was introduced from China, and the theory was inapplicable to some animals, plants and minerals indigenous to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その事から、蘭山は積極的に山や森に分け入り日本の本草学作りを志した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above fact, Ranzan tried to establish Japanese herbalism by actively penetrating deep into the mountains and woods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Ranzan tried to establish Japanese herbalism by actively going into mountains and woods to observe life there.</e>
<cmt>・「その事から」の訳を変更しました。・「分け入り」の訳をより適切と思われるものに変更し、文意が通じやすくなるよう「生き物を観察する」という意味を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Ranzan tried to establish Japanese herbalism by actively going into mountains and woods to observe life there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>25歳で京都丸太町に私塾・衆芳軒を開塾、多くの門人を教えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 25, he opened a private school, Shuhoken in Marutamachi, Kyoto, where he educated many disciples.</e>
<cmt>「衆芳軒」は、サイトでも見つからず、定かではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of 25, he opened a private school, Shuhoken, in Marutamachi, Kyoto, where he taught many students.</e>
<cmt>・Shuhokenの後ろにコンマが必要なため、加えました。・educateの使い方が適切か判断しかねましたので、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of 25, he opened a private school, Shuhoken, in Marutamachi, Kyoto, where he taught many students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>蘭山が研究した本草学は広く知られる事になり日本中から生徒が集まり千人を越える人間が巣立って行ったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the herbalism Ranzan studied came to be extensively known, his school collected pupils from all over Japan and over 1000 pupils graduated from the school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the herbalism Ranzan developed came to be extensively known, which attracted pupils from all over Japan, and more than 1,000 people graduated from his school.</e>
<cmt>・「研究した」は、蘭山が「発展させた」と解釈し、訳を変更しました。・文のつながりがよくなかったのを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the herbalism Ranzan developed came to be extensively known, which attracted pupils from all over Japan, and more than 1,000 people graduated from his school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>天明8年1月30日 (旧暦)（1788年3月7日）、蘭山60歳の時、天明の京都大火が発生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 7, 1788 when Ranzan was at the age of 60, the Great Kyoto Fire of the Tenmei era occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 7, 1788, when Ranzan was 60 years old, the Great Kyoto Fire of the Tenmei period occurred.</e>
<cmt>・年の前に必要なコンマを付けました。・「60歳」を簡潔にしました。・「天明」を用語統一リスト通りに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 7, 1788, when Ranzan was 60 years old, the Great Kyoto Fire of the Tenmei period occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>私塾・衆芳軒も大火にやかれ蘭山も門人の吉田立仙の家に避難。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his private school, Shuhoken was destroyed by fire, Ranzan and his disciples escaped to the house of Rissen YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his private school, Shuhoken, was destroyed by fire, Ranzan escaped to the house of his student, Rissen YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>・Shuhokenの後に必要なコンマを加えました。・「蘭山と門人が吉田立仙の家に避難」という訳になっていたので、原文通りの意味になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his private school, Shuhoken, was destroyed by fire, Ranzan escaped to the house of his student, Rissen YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この大火で門弟達は散り散りとなり、しばらくの暇ができた蘭山は、自身の研究をまとめる著作の執筆をして過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to that great fire, his disciples were scattered and Ranzan who had time to spare for a while spent his time to write literary works on his own study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to that great fire, his students were scattered, and Ranzan, having some time to spare, spent his time writing literary works on his study.</e>
<cmt>・コンマや関係代名詞などの不適切な使い方を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to that great fire, his students were scattered, and Ranzan, having some time to spare, spent his time writing literary works on his study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>71歳の時、幕命により江戸に移り医学校教授方となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the age of 71, he moved to Edo by an order of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to become an instructor in the medical science school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the age of 71, he moved to Edo by the order of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to become an instructor in the medical science school.</e>
<cmt>・an orderのanをtheとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the age of 71, he moved to Edo by the order of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to become an instructor in the medical science school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>享和元年（1801年） - 文化2年(1805年)にかけて、諸国をめぐり植物の採集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1801 to 1805, he gathered herbs travelling around many provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1801 to 1805, he gathered herbs traveling around many provinces.</e>
<cmt>・翻訳仕様指示書に従い、travellingのスペルをアメリカ式にl（エル）１つとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1801 to 1805, he gathered herbs traveling around many provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>享和3年（1803年）75歳の時に研究をまとめた著書『本草綱目啓蒙』脱稿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1803 at the age of 75, he completed his book, &quot;Compendium of Materia Medica Enlightenment&quot; on his study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1803, at the age of 75, he completed a series of books on his study, &quot;Compendium of Materia Medica Enlightenment.&quot;</e>
<cmt>・年の後にコンマを加え、on his studyの位置を変えました。・48巻あるということですので、a bookではなくa series of booksとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1803, at the age of 75, he completed a series of books on his study, &quot;Compendium of Materia Medica Enlightenment.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>本草1882種を書き表す大著で3年にかけて全48巻が刊行され、日本最大の本草学書になった（この著書はのちにフィリップ・フランツ・フォン・シーボルトが手に入れ、蘭山を東洋のカール・フォン・リンネと賞賛している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a great work describing 1,882 kinds of herbs which were published in the 48 volumes in total taking three years and ended up as a largest herbalism book in Japan (Philipp Franz von Siebold later obtained this book and praised Ranzan as Carl von Linné of the East).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a great 48-volume work describing 1,882 kinds of herbs published separately over three years, and ended up the largest herbalism book in Japan (Philipp Franz von Siebold later obtained this series and praised Ranzan as Carl von Linné of the East).</e>
<cmt>・多少整理し、前カッコの後ろにあった余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a great 48-volume work describing 1,882 kinds of herbs published separately over three years, and ended up the largest herbalism book in Japan (Philipp Franz von Siebold later obtained this series and praised Ranzan as Carl von Linné of the East).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>文化7年（1810年）1月27日死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on January 27, 1810.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on January 27, 1810.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on January 27, 1810.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>享年82。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 82.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 82 then.</e>
<cmt>・前の文とのつながりをよくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 82 then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>エピソード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>蘭山が残したものにホタルの語源について述べたものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among what he left behind him, there is a writing about the origin of the word, Hotaru (firefly).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan left behind writing about the origin of the word, Hotaru (firefly).</e>
<cmt>・余分と思われる部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan left behind writing about the origin of the word, Hotaru (firefly).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>蛍は日本書紀の記述からすでに「蛍」、「保多留」などと書かれていて語源については諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hotaru appeared in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) written as &apos;Hotaru&apos; and &apos;Hotaru&apos; (The two are pronounced in the same way but written by different Chinese characters), but as for the origin of the word, there are various theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hotaru appeared as early as the time of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), written in a few different characters in the book, but the origin of the word is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>・「すでに」を訳出し、全体的に簡潔化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hotaru appeared as early as the time of Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan), written in a few different characters in the book, but the origin of the word is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>貝原益軒は火が垂る（垂れる、流れる、こぼれ落ちる）から「火垂る」とし蘭山は星が垂るから「星垂る」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ekiken KAIBARA referred to &apos;Hitaru&apos; (Fire drips) as coming from a fire dripping (dropping, flowing and spilling out), while Ranzan referred to &apos;Hoshitaru (Star drips) as coming from a star dripping.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ekiken KAIBARA suggested that &apos;Hotaru&apos; came from &apos;Hi-ga-taru&apos; (Sparks fly off), while Ranzan wrote that its origin was &apos;Hoshi-ga-taru&apos; (Stars fall).</e>
<cmt>・原文は、ホタルを漢字でどのように書くかという違いから両者の主張の違いを説明しようとしているのだと思いますが、そのまま訳すと混乱を招くかと思いますので、もっと簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ekiken KAIBARA suggested that &apos;Hotaru&apos; came from &apos;Hi-ga-taru&apos; (Sparks fly off), while Ranzan wrote that its origin was &apos;Hoshi-ga-taru&apos; (Stars fall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dr jimmy(id:111486), 星組背番号10(id:19983), Papamaruchan22(id:71152), Kaznov17(id:68122), Humpty Dumpty書記官(id:155033), Dream100(id:41924), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>