<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宮簀媛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyazu-hime (princess Miyazu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyazu-hime</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyazu-hime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宮簀媛（ミヤズヒメ）は、日本神話に登場する尾張国造の乎止与命（オトヨ）の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyazu-hime is a Japanese mythology figure who is a daughter of Owarinokuni-no-miyatsuko Totoyo (Otoyo)-no-mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyazu-hime (Princess Miyazu) was a Japanese mythology figure who was a daughter of Otoyo no Mikoto of Owari no kuni no Miyakko (governor of Owari Province before the ritsuryo system [a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code]).</e>
<cmt>過去形にし、用語集・原文に読みを合わせ、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyazu-hime (Princess Miyazu) was a Japanese mythology figure who was a daughter of Otoyo no Mikoto of Owari no kuni no Miyakko (governor of Owari Province before the ritsuryo system [a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『日本書紀』では宮簀媛、『古事記』では美夜受比売。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her name is written as 宮簀媛 in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and 美夜受比売 in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>漢字そのものが問題となっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her name is written as 宮簀媛 in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and 美夜受比売 in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name is written as 宮簀媛 in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and 美夜受比売 in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父の乎止与命は天火明命（アメノホアカリ）の子孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Totoyo-no-mikoto, who was her father, was a descendant of Ame no Hoakari (one of the gods in Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otoyo no Mikoto, who was her father, was a descendant of Ame no Hoakari (one of the gods in Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt>読みを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otoyo no Mikoto, who was her father, was a descendant of Ame no Hoakari (one of the gods in Japanese mythology).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本武尊（ヤマトタケル）の東征の帰路、尾張滞在の際に娶られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On his way home from his expedition to the east, YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto married Miyazu-hime during his stay in Owari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his way home from his expedition to the east, YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto married Miyazu-hime during his stay in Owari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On his way home from his expedition to the east, YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto married Miyazu-hime during his stay in Owari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本武尊が能褒野で亡くなると、日本武尊より預けられた天叢雲剣（草薙の剣、三種の神器の一）を奉斉鎮守するため熱田神宮を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto died in Nobono, Miyazu-hime built Atsuta-jingu Shrine to enshrine Ame no Murakumo no Tsurugi (or Kusanagi no Tsurugi, the sword of the Imperial regalia and one of the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family), which was left by YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto died in Nobono, Miyazu-hime built Atsuta-jingu Shrine to enshrine Ame no Murakumo no Tsurugi (also known as Kusanagi no Tsurugi, the sword of the Imperial regalia and one of the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family), which was left by YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto died in Nobono, Miyazu-hime built Atsuta-jingu Shrine to enshrine Ame no Murakumo no Tsurugi (also known as Kusanagi no Tsurugi, the sword of the Imperial regalia and one of the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family), which was left by YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>『日本書紀』によれば、日本武尊は東征の帰途、尾張へ入り尾張氏の娘宮簀媛を娶って滞在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto married Miyazu-hime, who was a daughter of the Owari clan, in Owari on his way home from his expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto married Miyazu-hime, who was a daughter of the Owari clan, in Owari on his way home from his expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto married Miyazu-hime, who was a daughter of the Owari clan, in Owari on his way home from his expedition to the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>やがて近江国の伊吹山に荒ぶる神がいると聞いて、天叢雲剣を媛の家に残し素手で退治に出かけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he heard about the violent god in Mt. Ibuki in Omi Province, and went off to exterminate the god unarmed, leaving behind the Ame no Murakumo no Tsurugi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he heard about the violent god in Mt. Ibuki in Omi Province, and went off to exterminate the god unarmed, leaving behind the Ame no Murakumo no Tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he heard about the violent god in Mt. Ibuki in Omi Province, and went off to exterminate the god unarmed, leaving behind the Ame no Murakumo no Tsurugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、山道で神が大蛇に化して出現したのを無視したところ、神は氷を降らせて尊を迷わした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he ignored a giant snake he encountered on the mountain road, which was in fact the god in disguise, the god sent hailstones to annoy Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he ignored a giant snake he encountered on the mountain road, which was in fact the god in disguise, the god sent hailstones to annoy Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he ignored a giant snake he encountered on the mountain road, which was in fact the god in disguise, the god sent hailstones to annoy Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このため尊は失神し、山下の泉でようやく正気を取り戻したが、病の身となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It made Mikoto faint, and when he finally came to at Yamashita no Izumi (spring), he found himself ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It made Mikoto faint, and when he finally came to at Yamashita no Izumi (spring in Yamashita), he found himself ill.</e>
<cmt>用語補足を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It made Mikoto faint, and when he finally came to at Yamashita no Izumi (spring in Yamashita), he found himself ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして尊は尾張へ戻るが、媛の家には寄らず、そのまま伊勢に向かったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikoto returned to Owari, but headed to Ise without visiting the house of Miyazu-hime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikoto returned to Owari, but headed to Ise without visiting the house of Miyazu-hime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikoto returned to Owari, but headed to Ise without visiting the house of Miyazu-hime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>『古事記』にも同様の話を記載するが、美夜受比売を尾張国造の祖とし、倭建命は比売の月経をおして交わったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;Kojiki&quot; describes a similar story, it states that Miyazu-hime was the ancestor of Owarinokuni-no-miyatsuko, and that YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto made love to Miyazu-hime during her menstruation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;Kojiki&quot; describes a similar story, it states that Miyazu-hime was the ancestor of Owari no kuni no Miyakko, and that YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto made love to Miyazu-hime during her menstruation.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &quot;Kojiki&quot; describes a similar story, it states that Miyazu-hime was the ancestor of Owari no kuni no Miyakko, and that YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto made love to Miyazu-hime during her menstruation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>またその結婚は東国へ向かう途中に尾張を通った時に約束がしてあったとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also states that they were engaged on Mikoto&apos;s way to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region), when he was in Owari.</e>
<cmt>東国へ向かう途中に尾張を通った時：こちらの主語は尊として訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also states that they were engaged on Mikoto&apos;s way to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region), when he visited Owari.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also states that they were engaged on Mikoto&apos;s way to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region), when he visited Owari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『尾張国風土記』逸文の熱田社由来および『熱田大神宮縁起』には、日本武尊が尾張連らの遠祖である宮酢媛命を娶って宿泊した時、剣が神々しく光り輝いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the origin of Atsuta-yashiro Shrine, which is an itsubun (unknown or lost writings) in &quot;Owari no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (records of the culture and geography of the Owari Province), and &quot;Atsuta daijingu Engi&quot; (History of Atsuta-daijingu Shrine), when YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto married Miyazuhime no mikoto, who was a forefather of the Owari Muraji group, and stayed with her, the sword produced a divine light.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the origin of Atsuta-yashiro Shrine, which is an itsubun (unknown or lost writings) in &quot;Owari no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (records of the culture and geography of the Owari Province), and &quot;Atsuta daijingu Engi&quot; (History of Atsuta-daijingu Shrine), when YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto married Miyazu-hime no Mikoto, who was a primitive ancestor of the Owari Muraji group, and stayed with her, the sword produced a divine light.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the origin of Atsuta-yashiro Shrine, which is an itsubun (unknown or lost writings) in &quot;Owari no Kuni Fudoki&quot; (records of the culture and geography of the Owari Province), and &quot;Atsuta daijingu Engi&quot; (History of Atsuta-daijingu Shrine), when YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto married Miyazu-hime no Mikoto, who was a primitive ancestor of the Owari Muraji group, and stayed with her, the sword produced a divine light.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このため、宮酢媛命にその剣を奉斎することを命じ、そこで建てたのが熱田神宮であるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing the light, YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto ordered Miyazuhime no mikoto to enshrine the sword, on which occasion Atsuta-jingu Shrine was built.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処このため：ここでは光を見たため、と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto ordered Miyazu-hime no Mikoto to enshrine the sword, on which occasion Atsuta-jingu Shrine was built.</e>
<cmt>表現を原文に合わせ、用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, YAMATO Takeru no Mikoto ordered Miyazu-hime no Mikoto to enshrine the sword, on which occasion Atsuta-jingu Shrine was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 YOSHI438(id:174755), KAMUI(id:9330), Hayashix(id:32691), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>