<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>賀茂保憲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KAMO no Yasunori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KAMO no Yasunori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KAMO no Yasunori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>賀茂 保憲（かも の やすのり、延喜17年（917年） - 貞元 (日本)2年2月22日 (旧暦)（977年3月14日））は、平安時代中期の陰陽師、陰陽家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KAMO no Yasunori (917-March 14, 977) was the Onmyoji (diviner) and Inyoka (the Yin and Yang school of philosophy) of the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KAMO no Yasunori (917-March 14, 977) was the Onmyoji (diviner) and Inyoka (the Yin and Yang school of philosophy) of the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KAMO no Yasunori (917-March 14, 977) was the Onmyoji (diviner) and Inyoka (the Yin and Yang school of philosophy) of the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>賀茂忠行の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eldest son of KAMO no Tadayuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of KAMO no Tadayuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of KAMO no Tadayuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>安倍晴明の師とも、また彼の兄弟子とも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was said to be the master of ABE no Seimei or his anideshi (senior apprentice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was said to be the master of ABE no Seimei or his anideshi (senior apprentice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was said to be the master of ABE no Seimei or his senior apprentice.</e>
<cmt>「anideshi (senior apprentice)」→「senior apprentice」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>弟には内記上人こと慶滋保胤、息子には賀茂光栄と権天文博士に任じられた賀茂光国、娘に歌人の賀茂保憲女がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, who had the rank of the Naiki Shonin (Imperial Secretary who was allowed to enter the imperial court), as his younger brother, KAMO no Mitsuyoshi and KAMO no Mitsukuni, who was assigned to be the Gonno tenmon hakase (Assistant Master of Astronomy) as his sons, and had KAMO no Yasunori no Musume (daughter of KAMO no Yasunori), who was the kajin (waka (Japanese poem) poet), as his daughter.</e>
<cmt>内記上人→ Naiki Shonin (Imperial Secretary who was allowed to enter the imperial court), 賀茂光国→KAMO no Mitsusukeと判断しました。[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, who had the rank of Naiki Shonin (Imperial Secretary who was allowed to enter the imperial court), as his younger brother, KAMO no Mitsuyoshi and KAMO no Mitsukuni, who was assigned to be the Gonno tenmon hakase (Assistant Master of Astronomy) as his sons, and KAMO no Yasunori no Musume (daughter of KAMO no Yasunori), who was the kajin (waka (Japanese poem) poet), as his daughter.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, who had the rank of Naiki Shonin (Imperial Secretary who was allowed to enter the imperial court), as his younger brother, KAMO no Mitsuyoshi and KAMO no Mitsukuni, who was assigned to be the Gon no tenmon hakase (Assistant Master of Astronomy) as his sons, and KAMO no Yasunori no Musume (daughter of KAMO no Yasunori), who was the waka (Japanese poem) poet, as his daughter.</e>
<cmt>「Gonno tenmon hakase」→「Gon no tenmon hakase」「kajin (waka (Japanese poem) poet)」→「waka (Japanese poem) poet」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>父である賀茂忠行と同じく陰陽道の達人で、確証はないが陰陽頭を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the master of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements) similar to his father, KAMO no Tadayuki, and although there was no confirmation, he successively held the post of the Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Buereau of Divination).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the master of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements) similar to his father, KAMO no Tadayuki, and although there was no confirmation, he successively held the post of the Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Buereau of Divination).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the master of Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements) similar to his father, KAMO no Tadayuki, and although there was no confirmation, he successively held the post of the Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Bureau of Divination).</e>
<cmt>「Buereau」→「Bureau」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また暦道を究めて、著書「暦林」を記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied Rekido (study of almanac from the use of astronomy) and wrote &quot;Rekirin&quot; (the forest of Almanac).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied Rekido (study of almanacs from the use of astronomy) and wrote &quot;Rekirin&quot; (the forest of Almanac).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied Rekido (study of almanacs from the use of astronomy) and wrote &quot;Rekirin&quot; (the forest of Almanac).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「今昔物語集」によれば、幼少時に父が祓いを依頼されたので付いていき、その祓いの最中に供物に無数の鬼が集っているのを見て、父・忠行に告げたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past), he accompanied the exorcism his father was asked to do, and told his father, Tadayuki, that he saw numerous oni (Japanese ogre) gather around the offering at the time of exorcism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past), he accompanied the exorcism that his father was asked to do, and told his father, Tadayuki, that he saw numerous oni (Japanese ogre) gather around the offering at the time of the exorcism.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Konjaku monogatari shu&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past), he accompanied the exorcism that his father was asked to do, and told his father, Tadayuki, that he saw numerous oni (Japanese ogre) gather around the offering at the time of the exorcism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>忠行は、我が子が修行を積まなくても見鬼（鬼を見る能力）の才を身に着けていることに驚きいり、以後陰陽道を指南したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayuki was surprised that his own child had the talent of Kenki (the ability to see spirits) without a training, and instructed him Onmyodo from that time hence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayuki was surprised that his own child had the talent of Kenki (the ability to see spirits) without training, and instructed him Onmyodo from that time hence.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayuki was surprised that his own child had the talent of Kenki (the ability to see spirits) without training, and instructed him Onmyodo from that time hence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>陰陽頭・天文博士・暦博士・主計頭・穀倉院別当を歴任、造暦宣旨、従四位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He consecutively held the posts of Onmyoto, tenmon hakase (master of astronomy), reki hakase (master of reki (calendar)), Kazue no kami (the head of budget bureau), Kokuso-in betto (Chief of Grain warehouse) and declared Senji (Imperial decree) of creating a calendar, and was given the Jo rank (imperial court rank) of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He consecutively held the posts of Onmyoto, tenmon hakase (master of astronomy), reki hakase (master of reki (calendar)), Kazue no kami (the head of the budget bureau), Kokuso-in betto (Chief of the Grain warehouse) and declared a Senji (Imperial decree) for creating a calendar, and was given the Jo rank (imperial court rank) of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He consecutively held the posts of Onmyoto, tenmon hakase (master of astronomy), reki hakase (master of reki (calendar)), Kazue no kami (the head of the budget bureau), Kokuso-in betto (Chief of the Grain warehouse) and declared a Senji (Imperial decree) for creating a calendar, and was given the Jo rank (imperial court rank) of Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼は父よりも官位が上になったことに申し訳なさを感じ、父・忠行の昇進を願い出たこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he felt apologetic for having the official court rank higher than his father, there was an occasion where he asked for the promotion of his father, Tadayuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he felt apologetic for having an official court rank higher than his father, there was an occasion where he asked for the promotion of his father, Tadayuki.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he felt apologetic for having an official court rank higher than his father, there was an occasion where he asked for the promotion of his father, Tadayuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>彼の残した「暦林」は現代においてもいわゆる旧暦を読む際の重要な資料となっており、後の暦法の発展は彼がいなければなかったことであるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Rekirin&quot; that he left is used as the valuable resource in order to read various old calendar even now that it could be said that there was no later development of rekiho (method of making calendars) if he was absent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Rekirin&quot; that he left is used as a valuable resource in order to read various old calendars even though it could now be said that there was no later development of rekiho (method of making calendars) after he was absent.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Rekirin&apos; that he left is used as a valuable source even now in reading what is called the old calendar and it can be said that there have been no later development of rekiho (method of making calendars) without him.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>陰陽道の暦道をその子の賀茂光栄に、また天文道を安倍晴明に継がせて、これから陰陽道宗家を二分にすることが有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed down the Rekido of Onmyodo to his son, KAMO no Mitsuyoshi, and passed down tenmondo (ancient horoscopy) to Seimei ABE, and was famous for dividing the head of Onmyodo family into two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed down the Rekido of Onmyodo to his son, KAMO no Mitsuyoshi, and passed down tenmondo (ancient horoscopy) to Seimei ABE, and was famous for dividing the head of the Onmyodo family into two.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed down the Rekido of Onmyodo to his son, KAMO no Mitsuyoshi, and passed down Tenmondo (ancient horoscopy) to ABE no Seimei, and was famous for dividing the head of the Onmyodo family into two.</e>
<cmt>「tenmondo」→「Tenmondo」「Seimei ABE」→「ABE no Seimei」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『続古事談』によれば、安倍晴明と賀茂光栄がどちらが師匠の賀茂保憲に気重されたについての論争をしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Zokukojidan&quot; (Tales of the early Kamakura Period), Seimei ABE and KAMO no Mistuyoshi debated on who their master KAMO no Yasunori wasn&apos;t looking forward to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Zokukojidan&quot; (Tales of the early Kamakura Period), Seimei ABE and KAMO no Mistuyoshi debated on who their master KAMO no Yasunori was not looking forward to.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Zoku kojidan&quot; (Tales of Antiquity Continued), ABE no Seimei and KAMO no Mitsuyoshi debated on which of them their master KAMO no Yasunori was not looking forward to.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), ととりん(id:31982), 可怜(id:206074), Cprobot(id:97843), Korokoro(id:42329), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Point136(id:211299), Mi-no(id:64590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>