<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平忠房</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadafusa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tadafusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadafusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 忠房（たいら の ただふさ、生年未詳 - 文治元年12月16日 (旧暦)（1186年1月8日））は平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadafusa (? ~ January 8, 1186) is a busho (Japanese military commander) of the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tadafusa (? ~ January 8, 1186) was a busho (Japanese military commander) during the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadafusa (year of birth unknown - January 15, 1186) was a busho (Japanese military commander) who lived during the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。統一グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平重盛の六男（五男という説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the 6th son of TAIRA no Shigemori (there is an opinion that he is the 5th son.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 6th son of TAIRA no Shigemori (there is an opinion that he could have been the 5th son.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 6th son of TAIRA no Shigemori (there is an opinion that he could have been the 5th son).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原経子 (藤原家成の四女)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother is FUJIWARA no Keishi (the 4th daughter of FUJIWARA no Ienari.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was FUJIWARA no Keishi (the 4th daughter of FUJIWARA no Ienari.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Keishi (the 4th daughter of FUJIWARA no Ienari).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正妻は藤原信西の五男藤原脩範の娘で1179年1月に忠房の元に嫁ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His legal wife is a daughter of FUJIWARA no Naganori, the 5th son of FUJIWARA no Shinzei, and she married Tadafusa in January 1179.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His legal wife was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Naganori, the 5th son of FUJIWARA no Shinzei, and she married Tadafusa in January 1179.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legal wife was a daughter of FUJIWARA no Naganori - the fifth son of FUJIWARA no Shinzei, and she married Tadafusa in January 1179.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>官位は従五位侍従兼丹後国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank is jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank), jiju (a chamberlain) and the Governor of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>丹後国での地位が不明で、仮に左記のようにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official rank is jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank), jiju (a chamberlain) and the Governor of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official rank was Jugoi Jiju (Junior Fifth Rank Chamberlain) and Governor of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため「丹後侍従」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus he was called &quot;Tango-jiju.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus he was called &quot;Tango-jiju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus he was called &quot;Tango-jiju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>平家公達草紙によると、安元2年（1176年）3月の後白河法皇50歳の祝賀の催し「安元の賀」に兄達四人と共に彼の名前が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Heike-kindachi Soshi (a book on Taira clan nobles), his name was shown among participants with his 4 elder brothers at the 50th birthday celebration of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, &quot;Angen no ga (Celebration of Angen Year)&quot; in March (lunar calendar) 1176.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Heike-kindachi Soshi (a book on Taira clan nobles), his name was shown among participants with his 4 elder brothers at the 50th birthday celebration of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, &quot;Angen no ga (Celebration of Angen Year)&quot; in March (lunar calendar) 1176.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Heike-kindachi Soshi (a book on Taira clan nobles), his name was shown among participants with his 4 elder brothers at the 50th birthday celebration of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, &apos;Angen no ga (Celebration of Angen Year)&apos; in March (lunar calendar) 1176.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除スペース削除原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（当時の役職は兵衛佐）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His post at the time was Hyoe no suke (the assistant captain of the Headquarters of the Middle Palace Guard.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His post at the time was Hyoe no suke (the assistant captain of the Headquarters of the Middle Palace Guard.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The post he held at the time was Hyoe no suke (assistant captain of the Headquarters of the Middle Palace Guard).)</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。かっこ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>『平家物語』の「六代被斬」によると、忠房は平氏が屋島の戦いで敗れた後、ひそかに陣を抜け出し、紀伊国の豪族湯浅宗重の庇護を受けて同地に潜伏する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the part of Rokudai kirare in &quot;Heike Monogatari (The tale of the Heike),&quot; Tadafusa escaped in secrecy from the armed camp of Taira clan when they were defeated at the Battle of Yashima, and concealed himself under the protection of a powerful regional clan of Muneshige YUASA in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>「六代被斬」が分かりません。左記のようにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the part of the Rokudai kirare in &quot;Heike Monogatari (The tale of the Heike),&quot; Tadafusa escaped in secrecy from the armed camp of the Taira clan when they were defeated at the Battle of Yashima, and he concealed himself under the protection of a powerful regional clan of Muneshige YUASA in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Rokudai Kirare&apos; in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike), Tadafusa escaped in secrecy from the camp of the Taira clan after being defeated at the Battle of Yashima, and he hid under the protection of the powerful Muneshige YUASA in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>壇ノ浦の戦いで平家一門が滅亡した後、源頼朝による追討を受けるも、宗重や平景清ら平家の残党が忠房の元に集い、3ヶ月の篭城という徹底抗戦する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Heike clan ruined at the Battle of Dannoura, though Tadafusa was chased by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, the remnants of the Heike clan such as Muneshige and TAIRA no Kagekiyo got together at Tadafusa and they made a do-or-die resistance, holding castle for 3 months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Heike clan was destroyed at the Battle of Dannoura, though Tadafusa was pursued by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, the remnants of the Heike clan such as Muneshige and TAIRA no Kagekiyo got together at Tadafusa and they made a do-or-die resistance, holding the castle for 3 months.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the downfall of the Taira clan at the Battle of Dannoura, Tadafusa was pursued by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo but the remnants of the Taira clan including Muneshige and TAIRA no Kagekiyo banded around Tadafusa and mounted a do-or-die resistance in which it is said that they hold the castle for three months.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし「重盛には旧恩があり、その息子は助命する」という頼朝の偽りの誘いを受けて降人となり、鎌倉に出頭する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tadafusa took Yoritomo&apos;s words seriously that Yoritomo had an old favor from Shigemori and Yoritomo would help his son Tadafusa, thus Tadafusa surrendered to Yoritomo and appeared at Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tadafusa took Yoritomo&apos;s words seriously that Yoritomo had an old favor from Shigemori and Yoritomo would help his son Tadafusa, thus Tadafusa surrendered to Yoritomo and appeared at Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tadafusa believed Yoritomo&apos;s lie that &apos;he owed Shigemori an old favor and would spare his son&apos;s life,&apos; so surrendered and turned himself in at Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>頼朝に面会した後、京に送還されるが、その途上頼朝の命を受けた後藤基清によって斬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tadafusa met Yoritomo, he was sent back to Kyo (the capital), however, he was killed on the way by Motokiyo GOTO who was ordered by Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tadafusa met Yoritomo, he was sent back to Kyo (the capital), however, he was killed on the way by Motokiyo GOTO who was ordered by Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tadafusa met Yoritomo, he was sent back to the capital but he was killed on the way by Motokiyo GOTO who was acting under the orders of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>『吉記』には文治元年（1185年）12月8日の項に、「同日、小松内府息忠房招引関東事」とあり、16日に「忠房被切首事」との記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the entry of December 8, 1185 (lunar calendar date) of Kikki (a diary of Tunefusa YOSHIDA), &quot;On the day Tadafusa, the son of Komatsu-naifu (the title of his father) was brought to Kanto&quot; and on the 16th, &quot;Tadafusa was cut by his neck.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「小松内府息忠房」は、「小松内府の子息、忠房」と読みましたが不明です。左記の様にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the entry of December 8, 1185 (lunar calendar date) of Kikki (a diary of Tunefusa YOSHIDA), &quot;On the day Tadafusa, the son of Komatsu-naifu (the title of his father) was brought to Kanto&quot; and on the 16th, &quot;Tadafusa&apos;s neck was cut.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The January 7, 1186 entry in Kikki (a diary of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA) reads &apos;On this day, Tadafusa, the son of Komatsu-naifu (the title of his father) was summoned to the Kanto region&apos; and on the entry for the 16th state that &apos;Tadafusa was beheaded.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に直し、スペル修正、クォーテーションの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>涙ヶ磯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Namida ga iso (rocky shore of tears)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Namida ga iso (rocky shore of tears)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Namida ga iso (rocky shore of tears)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>丹後の伝承によると、忠房には白拍子花松との間との間に遺児がおり、平家滅亡を聞いた彼女は丹後に潜んでいたが源氏の捜索が及ぶのを恐れ、子供を道連れとみせかけて自ら岩から身投げをしたという話も残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to tradition of Tango Province, there was a child of between Tadafusa and Hanamatsu, a dancing girl, and though Hanamatsu concealed herself in Tango when she heard the ruin of the Heike clan, a day she jumped to her death from the rock as if she were with her child fearing the hunting down by Genji clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a tradition in Tango Province, there was a child between Tadafusa and Hanamatsu, a dancing girl, and though Hanamatsu concealed herself in Tango, when she heard about the Heike clan being destoyed, she purposely jumped to her death making it appear that she took her child with her being afraid that the Genji clan would hunt down her child if they thought the child was still alive..</e>
<cmt>punctuation, revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Tango Province legend, stories remain that Tadafusa had a child with a prostitute named Hanamatsu who hid in Tango upon hearing about the downfall of the Taira family, but she feared that she would be discovered by the Minamoto clan so threw herself from a rock, making it appear as if she had taken her child with her with her.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Masyu(id:31065), Enosi(id:19649), Azusayumi7(id:21082), ゐ(id:795), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Kouko0515(id:100370), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>