<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>赤松則村</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norimura AKAMATSU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norimura AKAMATSU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norimura AKAMATSU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>赤松 則村（あかまつ のりむら、建治3年（1277年） - 正平 (日本)5年/観応元年1月11日 (旧暦)（1350年2月18日））は、日本の南北朝時代 (日本)の武将である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norimura AKAMATSU (born 1277, died January 11, 1350 (old lunar calendar) (February 18, 1350)) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Nanbokucho Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norimura AKAMATSU (born 1277, died January 11, 1350 (old lunar calendar) (February 18, 1350)) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Nanbokucho Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norimura AKAMATSU (born 1277, died February 26, 1350) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除南北朝時代の定訳February 18→February 26に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>法名は円心。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Enshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Enshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His homyo (a name given to a person who enters the Buddhist priesthood) was Enshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は赤松茂則。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Shigenori AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Shigenori AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Shigenori AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に赤松範資、赤松貞範、赤松則祐、赤松氏範、赤松氏康らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children included Norisuke AKAMATSU, Sadanori AKAMATSU, Norisuke AKAMATSU, Ujinori AKAMATSU and Ujiyasu AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included Norisuke AKAMATSU, Sadanori AKAMATSU, Norisuke AKAMATSU, Ujinori AKAMATSU and Ujiyasu AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included Norisuke AKAMATSU, Sadanori AKAMATSU, Norisuke AKAMATSU, Ujinori AKAMATSU and Ujiyasu AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>赤松氏4代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the fourth head of the Akamatsu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the fourth head of the Akamatsu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the fourth head of the Akamatsu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>挙兵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rising</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rising</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rising</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>後醍醐天皇が鎌倉幕府打倒を掲げて挙兵した元弘の乱において、元弘3年（1333年）、後醍醐の皇子護良親王の令旨を受けて反幕府勢力として挙兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Genko Rebellion, in which Emperor Godaigo raised an army to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu, he took up arms against the shogunate at ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses, etc.) of Imperial Prince Moriyoshi, the son of Godaigo, in 1333.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Genko Rebellion, in which Emperor Godaigo raised an army to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu, Norimura took up arms against the shogunate at ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses, etc.) of Imperial Prince Moriyoshi, the son of Godaigo, in 1333.</e>
<cmt>substituted name for &quot;he&quot;confirm that &quot;he&quot; indicates Norimura</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Genko War, in which Emperor Godaigo raised an army to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu, Norimura took up arms against the shogunate at ryoji (orders issued by princes, empresses, etc.) of Imperial Prince Moriyoshi, the son of Godaigo, in 1333.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣがＨ欄にコメントを残しているため、訂正文を入れられません。&quot;he&quot;はNorimura です。Rebellion は War に訂正する必要があります。→Gのコメント欄に移し、上記の訂正を行った訳をH欄に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>初め、一族の高田氏が内通しようとしたため兵を動かし、西条山城にて戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He first used his army to fight against the Takada clan, a member of his family, which attempted naitsu (engagement in secret communication), at Nishijoyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He first used his army to fight against the Takada clan, members of his family, which attempted naitsu (engagement in secret communication), at Nishijoyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He first used his army to fight against the Takada clan, members of his family, which attempted naitsu (engagement in secret communication), at Nishijoyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その菩提寺である了宅庵にて自害に追い込む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later forced the Takada clan to suicide himself at Ryotaku-an, which was his Bodai-ji Temple (a Buddhist temple that houses one&apos;s family grave).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later forced the Takada clan to commit suicide at Ryotaku-an, which was his Bodai-ji Temple (a Buddhist temple that houses one&apos;s family grave).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later forced the Takada clan to commit suicide at Ryotaku-an, which was his Bodai-ji Temple (a Buddhist temple that houses one&apos;s family grave).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、六波羅探題の命を受けた備前（岡山県）の守護加持氏が兵を出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, the Kaji clan serving as Shugo (guard) in Bizen Province (Okayama Prefecture) raised an army at the order of rokuharatandai (Kyoto branch of the Kamakura bakufu).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the Kaji clan, serving as Shugo (guard) in Bizen Province (Okayama Prefecture), raised an army at the order of rokuharatandai (Kyoto branch of the Kamakura bakufu).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the Kaji clan, serving as Shugo (provincial constable) in Bizen Province (Okayama Prefecture), raised an army at the order of Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>守護の訳、変更六波羅探題の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、その先発隊である伊東氏と三石城で戦いその盟主である伊藤惟群を服従させ、これを西国幕府軍の備えとして三石城に残し東上を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin fought against its advance team composed of the Ito clan at Mitsuishi-jo Castle; the leader Koremure ITO, who came to heel, remained at Mitsuishi-jo Castle as the reserve force of Saigoku bakufu; Enshin started to go to the east capital, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin fought against its advance team composed of the Ito clan at Mitsuishi-jo Castle; the leader Koremure ITO, who came to heel, remained at Mitsuishi-jo Castle as the reserve force of Saigoku bakufu; Enshin started toward the east capital, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin fought against its advance team composed of the Ito clan at Mitsuishi-jo Castle; the leader Koremure ITO, who came to heel, remained at Mitsuishi-jo Castle as the reserve force of Saigoku bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun); Enshin started toward the east.</e>
<cmt>幕府の定訳capital Tokyo 削除　（当時、東京ではないし、原文にないので削除しました。）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>この後円心は室山に陣を築き、諸豪族の参集を待った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin established his armed camp in Muroyama, where he waited for various Gozoku (local ruling families) to join.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin established his armed camp in Muroyama, where he waited for various Gozoku (local ruling families) to join.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin established his armed camp in Muroyama, where he waited for various Gozoku (local ruling families) to join.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しばらくの後、白川郷・山田村小部郷・石南花山で経た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, he stayed in Shirakawago, Obu-go, Yamada-mura and Mt Shakunage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, he stayed in Shirakawago, Obu-go, Yamada-mura and Mt Shakunage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while, he stayed in Shirakawago, Obu-go, Yamada-mura and Mt. Shakunage.</e>
<cmt>Mt→Mt.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>布引谷沿いに南に向かい、あらかじめ長男範資に築かせておいた摩耶山城へ入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went south along Nunobikidani, and entered Mayasan-jo Castle that had been founded in advance by his oldest son, Norisuke.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went south along Nunobikidani, and entered Mayasan-jo Castle, which had been founded by his oldest son, Norisuke.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went south along Nunobikidani, and entered Mayasan-jo Castle, which had been founded by his oldest son, Norisuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>元弘3年（1333年）2月11日には、早くも六波羅軍2万が攻め寄せてくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 11, 1333, as many as 20,000 Rokuhara warriors invaded.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 11, 1333, as many as 20,000 Rokuhara warriors invaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 5, 1333, as many as 20,000 Rokuhara warriors invaded.</e>
<cmt>February 11→March 5に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、赤松軍得意の野伏り戦を展開し、これを撃退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Akamatsu&apos;s forces conducted its specialty nobuserisen (war by unofficial warriors) to repel the enemy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Akamatsu&apos;s forces conducted their specialty, nobuserisen (war by unofficial warriors) to repel the enemy.</e>
<cmt>pronoun, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Akamatsu&apos;s forces conducted their specialty, nobuserisen (war by unofficial warriors) to repel the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>六波羅攻略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conquering Rokuhara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conquering Rokuhara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conquering Rokuhara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>円心は勢いを買って久々知に陣取り、24日には酒部に進出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fueled by the victory, Enshin established an armed camp in Kukuchi, and debounched into Sakebe on the 24th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fueled by the victory, Enshin established an armed camp in Kukuchi, and advanced into Sakebe on the 24th.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fueled by the victory, Enshin established an armed camp in Kukuchi, and advanced into Sakebe on the 18th.</e>
<cmt>the 24th→the 18thに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>3月10日に六波羅軍1万が瀬川に布陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 10, 10,000 Rokuhara worriers were deployed in Segawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 10, 10,000 Rokuhara worriers were deployed in Segawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 2, 10,000 Rokuhara worriers were deployed in Segawa.</e>
<cmt>March 10→May 2に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その日の夜、円心の陣に尼崎から上陸した四国の小笠原勢が奇襲をかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ambush Ogasawara forces, which came ashore in Amagasaki from Shikoku, attacked the Enshin&apos;s armed camp that evening.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogasawara ambush forces, which came ashore in Amagasaki from Shikoku, attacked Enshin&apos;s armed camp that evening.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogasawara ambush forces, which came ashore in Amagasaki from Shikoku, attacked Enshin&apos;s armed camp that evening.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>円心は僅か50騎で敵を突破し久々知に帰陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin defeated the enemy with only 50 soldiers, and returned to Kukuchi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin defeated the enemy with only 50 soldiers, and returned to Kukuchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin defeated the enemy with only 50 soldiers, and returned to Kukuchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そこで兵の集合を待ち、則祐の進言を聞き入れ3,000騎を率いて敵陣に夜襲をかけ敵は敗走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He waited for his army to turn out, took Norisuke&apos;s advise, and entered the enemy line in a night raid with 3,000 soldiers; the enemy was put to fight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He waited for his army to turn out, took Norisuke&apos;s advice, and entered the enemy line in a night raid with 3,000 soldiers; the enemy was put to flight.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He waited for his army to turn out, took Norisuke&apos;s advice, and entered the enemy line in a night raid with 3,000 soldiers; the enemy was put to flight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ここでまた、則祐が追撃案を出し12日には山崎に侵攻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norisuke once again advised him to chase the enemy, and his forces invaded Yamazaki on the 12th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norisuke once again advised him to chase the enemy, and his forces invaded Yamazaki on the 12th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norisuke once again advised him to chase the enemy, and his forces invaded Yamazaki on the 4th.</e>
<cmt>12th→4thに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>京都淀・赤井・西岡付近に放火を敢行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He pressed ahead with torching the neighborhood areas of Kyoto Yodo, Akai and Nishioka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He pressed ahead with torching the neighborhood areas of Kyoto Yodo, Akai and Nishioka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He pressed ahead with torching the neighborhood areas of Kyoto Yodo, Akai and Nishioka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これに対して六波羅軍は、高橋・隅田両検断に2万を預け出陣させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a countermeasure, the Rokuhara forces delegated 20,000 worriers to two kendan officials: TAKAHASHI and SUMIDA; the two troops departed for the front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a countermeasure, the Rokuhara forces delegated 20,000 worriers to two kendan officials: TAKAHASHI and SUMIDA; the two troops departed for the front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a countermeasure, the Rokuhara forces delegated 20,000 warriors to two kendan (official in charge of judicial administration), Takahashi and Sumida, after which the Rokuhara forces departed for the front.</e>
<cmt>TAKAHASHI→TakahashiSUMIDA→Sumida「検断」の説明：検断は、official in charge of judicial administrationにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これを知った円心は、軍を二つに分け一方を久我縄手へ差し向け、自らは六波羅軍が陣取る桂へ進軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin was informed of their move; he separated his army into two, making one group to go to Koganawate and the other including himself to go to Katsura occupied by the Rokuhara forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin was informed of their move; he separated his army into two, making one group go to Koganawate and the other, including himself, go to Katsura occupied by the Rokuhara forces.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin was informed of their move; he separated his army into two, making one group go to Koganawate and the other, including himself, go to Katsura occupied by the Rokuhara forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>両軍は桂川を挟んで対峙した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two forces confronted across the Katsura River.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two forces confronted each other across the Katsura River.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;each other&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two forces confronted each other across the Katsura-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Katsura→Katsura-gawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この時川は増水しとても渡れそうになかったが則祐が先陣を切り押し渡り敵を蹴散らした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The river was swollen and looked impossible to go over; however, Norisuke led the troop across the river and defeated the enemy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The river was swollen and looked uncrossable; however, Norisuke led the troop across the river and defeated the enemy.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The river was swollen and looked uncrossable; however, Norisuke led the troop across the river and defeated the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>そのまま大宮・猪熊・堀川・油小路に放火しつつ六波羅を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The troop set afire in Omiya, Inokuma, Horikawa and Aburakoji, heading to Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The troop set fire in Omiya, Inokuma, Horikawa and Aburakoji, heading to Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troop set fire in Omiya, Inokuma, Horikawa and Aburakoji, heading to Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>危機感を覚えたのか六波羅は、時の天皇光厳帝を六波羅に迎え六波羅を仮御所とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In sense of crisis, Rokuhara invited the then Emperor Kogen, and designated Rokuhara as the makeshift palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a sense of crisis, Rokuhara invited the then-Emperor Kogen, and designated Rokuhara the makeshift palace.</e>
<cmt>wordingRokuhara given as both name of person and place name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a sense of crisis, Rokuhara Tandai invited the then-Emperor Kogon to Rokuhara, which he had designated as a makeshift palace.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣがＨ欄にコメントを入れています。Kogen→Kogon に訂正お願いします。→コメントをコメント欄に入れて、下記の訂正を行った訳をH欄に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、新手の河野・陶山をはじめ兵を大量に投入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many worriers including rockies, KONO and SUYAMA, joined the forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many warriers, including rockies, KONO and SUYAMA, joined the forces.</e>
<cmt>&quot;rockies&quot; incorrect, but intended meaning unclear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many warriers, including rookies, Kono and Suyama, joined the forces.</e>
<cmt>ＮＣがＨ欄にコメントを入れています。&quot;rockies&quot; は &quot;rookies&quot; だと思います。人名がすべて大文字になっているのも訂正が必要です。ご確認願います。→コメントをコメント欄に入れ、上記の訂正を行った訳をH欄に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>これまで、破竹の進撃をしていた円心軍は総崩れとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Enshin&apos;s forces that had invaded in full career, suffered a debacle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Enshin&apos;s forces, which had invaded in full career, suffered a debacle.</e>
<cmt>&quot;that&quot; to &quot;which&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Enshin&apos;s forces, which had invaded in full career, suffered a debacle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>円心と則祐は、急ぎ男山まで逃れたがここで円心は自刃すると従者に告げたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin and Norisuke immediately escaped to Otokoyama, where Enshin was believed to have told his servant that he would commit suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin and Norisuke immediately escaped to Otokoyama, where Enshin was believed to have told his servant that he would commit suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin and Norisuke immediately escaped to Otokoyama, where Enshin was believed to have told his servant that he would commit suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし円心は、自分の旗印である左三つ巴の旗の上に大龍を描き八万菩薩のお告げとし再度京へ攻め込むと告げたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Enshin drew a big dragon on his flag marked with the hidari mitsudomoe crest; the dragon was a prophecy of hachiman bosatsu (hachiman Bodhisattva), reflecting his determination to once again invade Kyo (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Enshin drew a big dragon on his flag marked with the hidari mitsudomoe crest; the dragon was a prophecy of hachiman bosatsu (hachiman Bodhisattva), reflecting his determination to once again invade Kyo (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Enshin drew a big dragon on his flag marked with the hidari mitsudomoe crest; the dragon was a prophecy of hachiman bosatsu (hachiman Bodhisattva), reflecting his determination to once again invade Kyo (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>その後、山崎の戦で快勝したが次の洛中戦で敗北した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a sweeping victory in the Battle of Yamazaki, he was defeated in the following battle of Rakuchu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a sweeping victory in the Battle of Yamazaki, he was defeated in the following battle of Rakuchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a sweeping victory in the Battle of Yamazaki, he was defeated in the following battle of Rakuchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>それから円心はしばらく山崎の陣に居た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin stayed at the army camp in Yamazaki for a while.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin stayed at the army camp in Yamazaki for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin stayed at the army camp in Yamazaki for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>名越高家・足利尊氏（尊氏）の出陣を知ると迎撃に出て名越高家を佐用頼家が討ち取り戦は終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lay in wait for Takaie NAGOE and Takauji ASHIKAGA, who he was informed had departed; Yoriie SAYO killed Takaie NAGOE to end the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lay in wait for Takaie NAGOE and Takauji ASHIKAGA, who he was informed had departed; Yoriie SAYO killed Takaie NAGOE to end the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lay in wait for Takaie NAGOE and Takauji ASHIKAGA, who he was informed had departed; Yoriie SAYO killed Takaie NAGOE to end the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この戦の後高氏は領地である丹波篠村へ向かい兵を集め2万3,000騎で挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, the Ko clan went to their terrirory, Shinomura, Tanba, to recruit 23,000 soldiers for raising an army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, the Ko clan went to their terrirory, Shinomura, Tanba, to recruit 23,000 soldiers for raising an army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, the Ko clan went to their terrirory, Shinomura, Tanba, to recruit 23,000 soldiers for raising an army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>勢いを増した帝方の諸将は京を包囲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The robust warlords on the Emperor side besieged Kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The robust warlords on the Emperor&apos;s side besieged Kyo.</e>
<cmt>possessive</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The robust warlords on the Emperor&apos;s side besieged Kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>これを見た六波羅探題は鎌倉へ落ち延び、六波羅は陥落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) escaped to Kamakura; this was the fall of Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) escaped to Kamakura; this was the fall of Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuhara Tandai escaped to Kamakura; this was the fall of Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>六波羅探題の説明、既出のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>一方関東では新田義貞が奮戦して鎌倉を落とし、元弘の乱は終結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kanto region, Yoshitada NITTA fought brively with Kamakura to end the Genko War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kanto region, Yoshitada NITTA fought bravely with Kamakura to end the Genko War.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kanto region, Yoshisada NITTA fought bravely with Kamakura to end the Genko War.</e>
<cmt>Yoshitada→Yoshisada</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>建武の新政下の円心</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin during Kemmu Restoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin during the Kemmu Restoration</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin during the Kemmu Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>鎌倉幕府滅亡後の建武の新政では、それまでの播磨国守護職を没収されるなど優遇されなかった事が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Kemmu Restoration after the fall of the Kamakura bakufu, Enshin was dismissed from the military governor of Harima Province that he had assumed; it is known that he was not given favorable treatment during the period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kemmu Restoration after the fall of the Kamakura bakufu, Enshin was dismissed from the military governorship of Harima Province that he had assumed; it is known that he was not given favorable treatment during this period.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kemmu Restoration after the fall of the Kamakura bakufu, Enshin was dismissed from the governor of Harima Province that he had assumed; it is known that he was not given favorable treatment during this period.</e>
<cmt>military governorship→governor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>これは朝廷内の権力争いの結果、護良親王派が三位局（阿野廉子）派に敗れた結果といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed to be because the Imperial Prince Moriyoshi&apos;s side lost to the sanmi no tsubone (Yasuko ANO)&apos;s side as a result of an internal power struggle within the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is believed to have happened because Imperial Prince Moriyoshi&apos;s side lost to the sanmi no tsubone (Yasuko ANO)&apos;s side as a result of an internal power struggle within the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is believed to have happened because Imperial Prince Moriyoshi&apos;s side lost to the sanmi no tsubone (Yasuko ANO)&apos;s side as a result of an internal power struggle within the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>同じく護良派といわれる楠木正成も（後世においては多大な名声を得たが）当時は戦功に比べ不遇であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly, Masashige KUSUNOKI, who is believed to have been on the Moriyoshi&apos;s side, was in obscurity despite his contributions during the war (Masashige gained a reputation in future generations).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, Masashige KUSUNOKI, who is believed to have been on Moriyoshi&apos;s side, was in obscurity despite his contributions during the war (Masashige gained a reputation in future generations).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, Masashige KUSUNOKI, who is believed to have been on Moriyoshi&apos;s side, was in obscurity despite his contributions during the war (Masashige gained a reputation in future generations).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>逆に三位局派の名和長年、千種忠顕等は新政の恩賞で厚く遇されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, Nagatoshi NAWA and Tadaaki CHIGUSA, both belonging to the sanmi no tsubone&apos;s side, were given rewards and treated favorably during Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, Nagatoshi NAWA and Tadaaki CHIGUSA, both belonging to sanmi no tsubone&apos;s side, were given rewards and treated favorably during the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, Nagatoshi NAWA and Tadaaki CHIGUSA, both belonging to sanmi no tsubone&apos;s side, were given rewards and treated favorably during the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、ともに倒幕戦争を戦った護良親王が建武 (日本)元年（1334年）に失脚すると則村の新政における立場は失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1334, Imperial Prince Moriyoshi, with whom Enshin had fought with during the anti-bakufu war, fell from power; This made the end of Enshin&apos;s career in Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1334, Imperial Prince Moriyoshi, with whom Enshin had fought during the anti-bakufu war, fell from power; this marked the end of Enshin&apos;s career in the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1334, Imperial Prince Moriyoshi, with whom Enshin had fought during the anti-bakufu war, fell from power; this marked the end of Enshin&apos;s career in the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>怒った円心は、赤松へ帰っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Infuriated Enshin returned to Akamatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The infuriated Enshin returned to Akamatsu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The infuriated Enshin returned to Akamatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>白旗城合戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle at Shirahata-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle at Shirahata-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle at Shirahata-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>建武2年（1335年）に足利尊氏が中前代の乱を平定する軍に、則村は次男貞範を従軍させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1335, Enshin made his second son Sadanori join the army that Takauji ASHIKAGA formed to suppress the Nakasendai Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1335, Enshin made his second son, Sadanori, join the army that Takauji ASHIKAGA formed to suppress the Nakasendai Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1335, Enshin made his second son, Sadanori, join the army that Takauji ASHIKAGA formed to suppress the Nakasendai War.</e>
<cmt>Disturbance→War</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>その平定後鎌倉で建武政権から離反して京都に進攻した尊氏が、翌年、北畠顕家、新田義貞、楠木正成らの宮方に敗れて九州へ逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the suppression, Takauji seceded from the Kenmu government in Kamakura and invaded Kyoto; in the following year, Takauji was defeated by the court&apos;s side including Akiie KITABATAKE, Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI, and escapted to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the suppression, Takauji seceded from the Kenmu government in Kamakura and invaded Kyoto; in the following year, Takauji was defeated by the court&apos;s side, including Akiie KITABATAKE, Yoshisada NITTA, and Masashige KUSUNOKI, and escapted to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the suppression, Takauji seceded from the Kenmu government in Kamakura and invaded Kyoto; in the following year, Takauji was defeated by the court&apos;s side, including Akiie KITABATAKE, Yoshisada NITTA, and Masashige KUSUNOKI, and escapted to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>足利方に味方して、尊氏から改めて播磨国守護職を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin took sides with ASHIKAGA, and was reappointed to the military governor of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin took sides with ASHIKAGA, and was reappointed the military governor of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin took sides with ASHIKAGA, and was reappointed the governor of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>military 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>以後は足利方として戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, he took sides with ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he took sides with ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he took sides with Ashikaga.</e>
<cmt>ASHIKAGA→Ashikaga</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>京都方面から進撃してきた新田義貞を総大将とする尊氏討伐軍6万騎を播磨国赤松の白旗城（兵庫県赤穂郡上郡町）で迎え撃った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">60,000 soldiers marched from Kyoto as the troop aiming at subjugation of Takauji; the troop was headed by Yoshisada NITTA; Enshin lay in wait for the soldiers at Shirahata-jo Castle in Akamatsu, Harima Province (Kamigori Town, Ako County, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">60,000 soldiers marched from Kyoto as the troop aiming at subjugation of Takauji; the troop was headed by Yoshisada NITTA; Enshin lay in wait for the soldiers at Shirahata-jo Castle in Akamatsu, Harima Province (Kamigori Town, Ako County, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">60,000 soldiers marched from Kyoto as the troop aiming at subjugation of Takauji; the troop was headed by Yoshisada NITTA; Enshin lay in wait for the soldiers at Shirahata-jo Castle in Akamatsu, Harima Province (Kamigori Town, Ako County, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これに対し、丹波国氷上郡の久下時重は、仁木頼章の一手も加えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokishige KUGE of Hikami County, Tanba Province added Yoriaki NIKI&apos;s forces to fight back.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokishige KUGE of Hikami County, Tanba Province added Yoriaki NIKI&apos;s forces to fight back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokishige KUGE of Hikami County, Tanba Province added Yoriaki NIKI&apos;s forces to fight back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>氷上の高山寺城から加古川沿いに下ってきては新田軍の補給路を絶えず脅かした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descending along Kako River from Kosanji-jo Castle in Hikami, the enemy repeatedly threatened to cut Nitta forces&apos; supply lines.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descending along the Kako River from Kosanji-jo Castle in Hikami, the enemy repeatedly threatened to cut Nitta forces&apos; supply lines.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descending along the Kako-gawa River from Kosanji-jo Castle in Hikami, the enemy repeatedly threatened to cut Nitta forces&apos; supply lines.</e>
<cmt>Kako→Kako-gawa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>また、白旗城は、地理的に北方の美作、但馬方面からいくらでも支援が可能という強みも持ち合わせていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shirahata-jo Castle had another geographical advantage; it could receive as many supplies as they wished from the Northern Mimasaka and Tajima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shirahata-jo Castle had another geographical advantage; it could receive as many supplies as they wished from the Northern Mimasaka and Tajima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shirahata-jo Castle had another geographical advantage; it could receive as many supplies as they wished from the Northern Mimasaka and Tajima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>そのため、則村以下2千の兵が立て籠る白旗城を義貞は圧倒的な兵力を持ちながら攻めあぐね、50日以上釘付けにされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite the overwhelming troop size, Yoshisada struggled to tear apart Shirahata-jo Castle, in which Norimura and his 2,000 worriers cloistered themselves; Yoshisada was tied up for more than 50 days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite the overwhelming number of troops, Yoshisada struggled to tear apart Shirahata-jo Castle, in which Norimura and his 2,000 warriers cloistered themselves; Yoshisada was tied up for more than 50 days.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite the overwhelming number of troops, Yoshisada struggled to tear apart Shirahata-jo Castle, in which Norimura and his 2,000 warriors cloistered themselves; Yoshisada was tied up for more than 50 days.</e>
<cmt>warriers→warriors</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>その間、尊氏は多々良浜の戦いで菊池武敏を破り、九州を制圧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Takauji defeated Taketoshi KIKUCHI in the Tatarahama War and conquered Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Takauji defeated Taketoshi KIKUCHI in the Tatarahama War and conquered Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Takauji defeated Taketoshi KIKUCHI in the Tatarahama War and conquered Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>西国の武士を軒並み味方に加えながら、軍勢を海と陸の二手に分け、東上を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gaining over almost all worriers in Saigoku (western part of Japan), Takauji started to go to the east capital, Tokyo, with his two troops; one by the sea and the other by the ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gaining over almost all warriers in Saigoku (the western part of Japan), Takauji started to go to the east capital, Tokyo, with his two troops; one by the sea and the other by land.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gaining over almost all warriors in Saigoku (the western part of Japan), Takauji started to go to the east with his two troops; one by the sea and the other by land.</e>
<cmt>warriers→warriorscapital, Tokyo 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>足利軍東上の知らせに新田軍は撤退を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nitta&apos;s forces started to withdraw when they were informed of Takauji&apos;s forces heading east.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nitta&apos;s forces started to withdraw when they were informed of Takauji&apos;s forces heading east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nitta&apos;s forces started to withdraw when they were informed of Takauji&apos;s forces heading east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>しかし、士気は極端に低下し、寝返りや足利軍への投降者が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With extreme moral corruption, many worriers switched to or surrendered to Ashikaga&apos;s forces.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With extreme moral corruption, many warriers switched to or surrendered to Ashikaga&apos;s forces.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With extreme moral corruption, many warriors switched to or surrendered to Ashikaga&apos;s forces.</e>
<cmt>warriers→warriors</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>さらに、白旗城を出てきた赤松軍の追撃も受け、総崩れとなって兵庫まで逃げ延びた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nitta&apos;s forces suffered a debacle with the pursuit of Akamatsu&apos;s forces that came out from Shirahata-jo Castle; Nitta managed to escape to Hyogo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nitta&apos;s forces suffered a debacle with the pursuit of Akamatsu&apos;s forces that came out from Shirahata-jo Castle; Nitta managed to escape to Hyogo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nitta&apos;s forces suffered a debacle with the pursuit of Akamatsu&apos;s forces that came out from Shirahata-jo Castle; Nitta managed to escape to Hyogo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>この後、尊氏は湊川の戦いで勝利した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji later won the Minatogawa War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji later won the Minatogawa War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji later won the Minatogawa War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Later Years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Later Years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Later Years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>足利尊氏と弟の足利直義が対立した観応の擾乱においても尊氏に従った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He followed Takauji in the the Kanno Riot, in which Takauji ASHIKAGA confronted with his younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin followed Takauji in the Kanno Riot, in which Takauji ASHIKAGA confronted his younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;with&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin followed Takauji in the Kanno Riot, in which Takauji ASHIKAGA confronted his younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>直義方についた尊氏の庶子で直義の養子の足利直冬を追討するため軍を編成している最中に京都で急死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He suddenly died in Kyoto while he was organizing an army to hunt down Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, who took sides with Tadayoshi; Tadafuyu was born a son of Takauji by his concubine and was later adopted to Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He suddenly died in Kyoto while he was organizing an army to hunt down Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, who took sides with Tadayoshi; Tadafuyu was born a son of Takauji by his concubine and was later adopted by Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He suddenly died in Kyoto while he was organizing an army to hunt down Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, who took sides with Tadayoshi; Tadafuyu was born a son of Takauji by his concubine and was later adopted by Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>法名は法雲寺月潭円心。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Hounji Gettan Enshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name was Hounji Gettan Enshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Hounji Gettan Enshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>墓所は京都市東区の東山建仁寺の塔頭寺院久昌院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried at Tacchujiin Kyushoin of Higashiyama Kennin-ji Temple in Higashi-ku Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried at Tacchujiin Kyushoin of Higashiyama Kennin-ji Temple in Higashi-ku Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried at Kyushoin, tatchu (sub-temples in the site of main temple) of Higashiyama Kennin-ji Temple in Higashi Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>塔頭の定訳Higashi-ku→Higashi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>供養塔が兵庫県赤穂郡上郡町の金華山法雲寺 (上郡町)（法雲昌国禅寺）にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His memorial tower was constructed at Kinkazan Houn-ji Temple (Kamigori Town) (Houn Shokoku Zenji-Temple) in Kamigori Town, Ako-gun County, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His memorial tower was constructed at Kinkazan Houn-ji Temple (Kamigori Town) (Houn Shokoku Zenji-Temple) in Kamigori Town, Ako-gun County, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His memorial tower was constructed at Kinkazan Houn-ji Temple (Kamigori Town) (Houn Shokoku Zenji-Temple) in Kamigori Town, Ako County, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Ako-gun→Ako</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="68">
<j>また、木像が兵庫県赤穂郡上郡町の宝林寺にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wooden statue is kept at Horin-ji Temple in Kamigori Town, Ako-gun County, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wooden statue is kept at Horin-ji Temple in Kamigori Town, Ako-gun County, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wooden statue is kept at Horin-ji Temple in Kamigori Town, Ako County, Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Ako-gun→Ako</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>楠木正成との関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship with Masashige KUSUNOKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship with Masashige KUSUNOKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship with Masashige KUSUNOKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>円心は、楠木正成の親類にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin was a relative of Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin was a relative of Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin was a relative of Masashige KUSUNOKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>円心には、出家した円光という弟がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enshin had a younger brother named Enko, who became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enshin had a younger brother named Enko, who became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enshin had a younger brother named Enko, who became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この円光のもと正成の姉が嫁いでおり、正成から見れば円心は義理の兄弟ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enko married Masashige&apos;s eldery sister; Enshin is Masashige&apos;s brother in law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enko married Masashige&apos;s eldery sister; Enshin is Masashige&apos;s brother in law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enko married Masashige&apos;s eldery sister; Enshin is Masashige&apos;s brother in law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>登場作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works that feather Enshin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works that feature Enshin</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works that feature Enshin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>北方謙三『悪党の裔』（中央公論社／中公文庫）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Akuto no sue&quot; authored by Kenzo KITAKATA (Chuo Koronsha/Chuko Bunko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Akuto no sue&quot; authored by Kenzo KITAKATA (Chuo Koronsha/Chuko Bunko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Akuto no sue&quot; authored by Kenzo KITAKATA (Chuo Koronsha/Chuko Bunko)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>『太平記 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（NHK大河ドラマ）演：渡辺哲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Taiheiki&quot; (NHK historical drama) produced by Tetsu WATANABE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Taiheiki&quot; (NHK historical drama) produced by Tetsu WATANABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Taiheiki&quot; (NHK historical drama) produced by Tetsu WATANABE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), Carbuncle(id:346), 与左衛門(id:159462), H-shige(id:19751), Cprobot(id:97843), 夏が来た具合(id:68083), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Cave cattum(id:41235), Shota(id:10854), Kurz(id:1601), かなべえコバトン(id:15491), でここ(id:9565), Carkuni(id:79281), Yonoemon(id:55450), Unknowns(id:68123), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), Junger(id:10282), オナガドリ(id:15179), ５１６(id:45205), Suisui(id:69), Kzhr(id:131), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>