<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>荷田春満</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KADA no Azumamaro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KADA no Azumamaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KADA no Azumamaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>荷田春満（かだのあずままろ、寛文9年1月3日 (旧暦)（1669年2月3日） － 元文元年7月2日 (旧暦)（1736年8月8日））は、江戸時代中期の国学者・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KADA no Azumamaro (February 3rd, 1669-August 8th, 1736) was a scholar of Japanese classical literature and a waka poet in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KADA no Azumamaro (February 3rd, 1669-August 8th, 1736) was a scholar of Japanese classical literature and a waka poet in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KADA no Azumamaro (February 3, 1669 - August 8, 1736) was a scholar of Japanese classical literature and a waka poet in the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>rd, th削除しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都の生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称斎宮（いつき）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also popularly known as Itsuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also popularly known as Itsuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also popularly known as Itsuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初名は信盛と称し、のちに東丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first childhood name was Nobumori, later changed to Azumamaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first childhood name was Nobumori, later changed to Azumamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first childhood name was Nobumori, later changed to Azumamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父は伏見稲荷神社（現在の伏見稲荷大社）の社家で御殿預職の羽倉信詮（はくらのぶあき）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Nobuaki HAKURA came from the shake (family of Shinto priests serving a shrine on a hereditary basis) of Fushimi Inari-jinja Shrine (present Fushimi Inari Taisha Shrine) and assumed the post of administrator of the shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Nobuaki HAKURA came from the shake (family of Shinto priests serving a shrine on a hereditary basis) of Fushimi Inari-jinja Shrine (present Fushimi Inari Taisha Shrine) and assumed the post of administrator of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Nobuaki HAKURA came from the shake (family of Shinto priests serving a shrine on a hereditary basis) of Fushimi Inari-jinja Shrine (present Fushimi Inari-taisha Shrine) and assumed the post of administrator of the shrine.</e>
<cmt>Fushimi Inari-taisha Shrineに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>母は細川忠興の家臣深尾氏の娘貝子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother Kaiko was a daughter of Mr. Fukao, a retainer of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother Kaiko was a daughter of Mr. Fukao, a retainer of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother Kaiko was a daughter of Fukao, a retainer of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>Mr.削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>古典・日本史を研究して復古神道を提唱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Studying Japanese classics and history, he advocated the fukko shinto (reform shinto (prominent 18th century form of Shinto, based on the classics, and free from Confucian and Buddhist influences)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Studying Japanese classics and history, he advocated the fukko shinto (reform shinto (prominent 18th century form of Shinto, based on the classics, and free from Confucian and Buddhist influences)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Studying Japanese classics and history, he advocated the fukko shinto (reform shinto (prominent 18th century form of Shinto, based on the classics, and free from Confucian and Buddhist influences)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>『万葉集』・『古事記』・『日本書紀』の研究の基礎を築き、賀茂真淵・本居宣長・平田篤胤とともに国学の四大人の一人に数えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he laid the foundation of the study of &quot;Manyoshu (collection of poetries)&quot;, &quot;Kojiki (Japanese oldest history book)&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)&quot;, he was respected as one of four savants in the study of Japanese classical literature along with KAMO no Mabuchi, Norinaga MOTOORI and Atsutane HIRATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he laid the foundation of the study of &quot;Manyoshu (collection of poetries)&quot;, &quot;Kojiki (Japanese oldest history book)&quot; and &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)&quot;, he was respected as one of four savants in the study of Japanese classical literature along with KAMO no Mabuchi, Norinaga MOTOORI and Atsutane HIRATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he laid the foundation of the study of &quot;Manyoshu&quot; (collection of poetries), &quot;Kojiki&quot; (Japanese oldest history book) and &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), he was respected as one of four savants in the study of Japanese classical literature along with KAMO no Mabuchi, Norinaga MOTOORI and Atsutane HIRATA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>著述は、業半ばで倒れたため未定稿のものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of his writings were left unfinished because he broke down halfway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of his writings were left unfinished because he fell ill halfway.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of his writings were left unfinished because he fell ill halfway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>主な著書に『万葉集僻案抄』『春葉集』などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His main work includes &quot;Manyoshu hekiansho (an annotated edition of the Manyoshu) &quot;and &quot;Shunyoshu (an anthology)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His main work includes &quot;Manyoshu hekiansho (an annotated edition of the Manyoshu) &quot;and &quot;Shunyoshu (an anthology)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His main work includes &quot;Manyoshu hekiansho&quot; (an annotated edition of the Manyoshu) and &quot;Shunyoshu&quot; (an anthology).</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1928年から1932年にかけて稲荷神社により『荷田全集』全7巻が、1944年に同じく稲荷神社の編になる『荷田春満全集』全10巻が企画されるが、いずれも当時の情勢により中止となってしまっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Fushimi Inari-jinja Shrine planned to compile &quot;Kada zenshu (collection of the writings of KADA no Azumamaro) &quot;of seven volumes from 1928 to 1932 and &quot;KADA no Azumamaro zenshu (collection of writings of KADA no Azumamaro) &quot;of ten volumes in 1944, these plans were cancelled due to the circumstances at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Fushimi Inari-jinja Shrine planned to compile &quot;Kada zenshu (collection of the writings of KADA no Azumamaro) &quot;of seven volumes from 1928 to 1932 and &quot;KADA no Azumamaro zenshu (collection of writings of KADA no Azumamaro) &quot;of ten volumes in 1944, these plans were cancelled due to the circumstances at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Fushimi Inari-jinja Shrine planned to compile &quot;Kada zenshu&quot; (collection of the writings of KADA no Azumamaro) of seven volumes from 1928 to 1932 and &quot;KADA no Azumamaro zenshu&quot; (collection of writings of KADA no Azumamaro) of ten volumes in 1944, these plans were cancelled due to the circumstances at that time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;の位置を訂正しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>近年新たに、國學院大學の百二十周年記念事業の一環として「近世国学の展開と荷田春満の史料的研究」プロジェクトが立ち上がり、『新編荷田春満全集』全12巻が刊行されつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, as part of the memorial work for the 120th anniversary of Kokugakuin University, a project was started aiming to research the modern development in the study of Japanese classical literature and Kada no Azumamaro based on the historical sources, with the result that &quot;Shinpen KADA no Azumamaro zenshu (new collection of the writings of KADA no Azumamaro) of twelve volumes has been publishing.</e>
<cmt>近世国学の意味がわかりません。国学は古典文学の研究なので，近世が何を修飾しているのか不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, as part of the memorial work for the 120th anniversary of Kokugakuin University, a project was started aiming to research the modern development in the study of Japanese classical literature and Kada no Azumamaro based on the historical sources, with the result that &quot;Shinpen KADA no Azumamaro zenshu (new collection of the writings of KADA no Azumamaro) of twelve volumes has been publishing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, as part of the memorial work for the 120th anniversary of Kokugakuin University, a project was started aiming to research the modern development in the study of Japanese classical literature and KADA no Azumamaro based on the historical sources, with the result that &quot;Shinpen KADA no Azumamaro zenshu&quot; (new collection of the writings of KADA no Azumamaro) of twelve volumes has been publishing.</e>
<cmt>KADA大文字にしました。&quot;の位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>弟子に賀茂真淵がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KAMO no Mabuchi was his disciple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KAMO no Mabuchi was his disciple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KAMO no Mabuchi was his disciple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>養子は荷田在満。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KADA no Arimaro was his adopted son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KADA no Arimaro was his adopted son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KADA no Arimaro was his adopted son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>京都市伏見区の伏見稲荷大社境内に隣接する東丸神社は学問の神様で知られ、合格祈願の絵馬や折鶴が奉納されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azumamaro-jinja Shrine in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, adjacent to the precincts of Fushimi Inari Taisha Shrine is known by a god of studies, therefore Ema (a votive horse tablet) for praying the success in examination and folded-paper cranes are dedicated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azumamaro-jinja Shrine in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, adjacent to the precincts of Fushimi Inari Taisha Shrine is known by a god of studies, therefore Ema (a votive horse tablet) for praying the success in examination and folded-paper cranes are dedicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azumamaro-jinja Shrine in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, adjacent to the precincts of Fushimi Inari-taisha Shrine is known by a god of studies, therefore Ema (a votive horse tablet) for praying the success in examination and folded-paper cranes are dedicated.</e>
<cmt>Fushimi Inari-taisha Shrineに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ucheniitza(id:32811), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Nnh(id:474), Kokokugoji(id:93628), Cprobot(id:97843), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>