<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>北条早雲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun HOJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>北條 早雲 / 伊勢 盛時（ほうじょう そううん / いせ もりとき）は、室町時代中後期（戦国時代 (日本)初期）の武将で、戦国大名となった後北条氏の祖である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun HOJO (AKA Moritoki ISE) was a military commander during the mid to late Muromachi Period in the Age of Civil Wars, and he was the patriarch of warring lord of Go-Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun HOJO (also known as Moritoki ISE) was a military commander during the mid to late Muromachi Period, and the patriarch of the Go-Hojo (or Late Hojo) Clan, a powerful warrior clan of the Warring States Period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;AKA&quot;→&quot;also known as&quot;&quot;Age of Civil Wars&quot;→&quot;Warring States Period&quot;Deleted &quot;he was&quot;Added &quot;(or Late Hojo)&quot;Capitalized &quot;c&quot;Deleted &quot;warring lord &quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun HOJO (also known as Moritoki ISE) was a military commander during the mid to late Muromachi Period, and the patriarch of the Gohojo clan (or Late Hojo), a powerful warrior clan of the Warring States Period.</e>
<cmt>後北条氏→the Gohojo clan (or Late Hojo)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伊勢 宗瑞（いせ そうずい）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called Sozui ISE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Sozui ISE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Sozui ISE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>北條早雲は戦国大名の嚆矢であり、早雲の活動は東国の戦国時代の端緒として歴史的意義がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun HOJO was a leading figure among the warring lords, and his achievements are historically meaningful in that they triggered the warring period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun HOJO was a leading figure among the warring lords, and his achievements are historically significant in that they triggered the Warring States Period in the eastern provinces.</e>
<cmt>&quot;meaningful&quot;→&quot;significant&quot;&quot;warring period&quot;→&quot;Warring States Period in the eastern provinces&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun HOJO was a leading figure among the warring lords, and his achievements are historically significant in that they triggered the Warring States Period in the eastern provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>諱は長らく長氏（ながうじ）と伝えられてきたが、現在では盛時（もりとき）が定説となっている（出自節を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his real name was Nagauji, which was rarely used, and today, Moritoki is the commonly accepted name (see section on Place of Birth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was long said to be Nagauji but today, Moritoki is the commonly accepted name (see section on Place of Birth).</e>
<cmt>Reworded first part of sentenceDeleted &quot;which was rarely used&quot; - not in original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was long said to be Nagauji but today, Moritoki is the commonly accepted name (see section on Origins).</e>
<cmt>下記の「出自」節表記に合わせて「Place of Birth」→「Origins」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>通称は新九郎（しんくろう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun was called Shinkuro as a boy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Shinkuro.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Shinkuro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>戒名は早雲庵宗瑞（そううんあんそうずい）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name is Soun-An-Sozui.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name was Soun-An-Sozui.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was&quot; - although &quot;is&quot; is literally correct, &quot;was&quot; sounds more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name was Sounan Sozui.</e>
<cmt>早雲庵宗瑞→Sounan Sozui</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>生年は長らく永享4年（1432年）が定説とされてきたが、近年新たに康正2年（1456年）説が提唱されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was long believed that his year of birth was 1432; however, recent studies advocates his birth year to be 1456.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it has long been believed that he was born in 1432, recent theories have suggested the year 1456.</e>
<cmt>&quot;his year of birth was&quot;→&quot;he was born in&quot;&quot;studies advocates his birth year to be&quot;→&quot;theories have suggested the year&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it has long been believed that he was born in 1432, recent theories have suggested the year 1456.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>伊勢家が北条姓を称したのは盛時の嫡男・氏綱のときであるが、通例では伊勢盛時も遡って「北条早雲」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ise family changed its last name to HOJO during the time Moritoki&apos;s son Ujitsuna was active; and, Soun HOJO is commonly used retroactive to the time he was called Moritoki ISE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ISE family name was changed to HOJO by Moritoki&apos;s son, Ujitsuna, and Soun HOJO, rather than Moritoki ISE, is the name commonly used.</e>
<cmt>&quot;changed its last name to HOJO during the time&quot;→&quot;name was changed to HOJO by&quot;Deleted &quot;was active&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ise family name was changed to Hojo by Moritoki&apos;s son, Ujitsuna, and Soun HOJO, rather than Moritoki ISE, is the name commonly used.</e>
<cmt>ISE→IseHOJO→Hojo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>従って、盛時の存命中に「北条早雲」の名が使われたことは無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Moritoki never used the name Soun HOJO during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Moritoki never used the name Soun HOJO during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Therefore&quot;→&quot;However&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Moritoki never used the name Soun HOJO during his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>Life→Biographyに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Place of birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origins</e>
<cmt>&quot;Place of birth&quot;→&quot;Origins&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>一介の素浪人から戦国大名にのし上がった下剋上の典型とするのが長く通説とされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has long been believed that Soun was a classic example of one a master-less samurai, climbing up the ladder to warlord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun has long been seen as a classic example of a ronin (masterless samurai) climbing up the ladder to become a daimyo.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderAdded &quot;ronin&quot;, bracketsDeleted hyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun has long been seen as a classic example of a ronin (masterless samurai) climbing up the ladder to become a daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、実際には室町幕府の政所執事を務めた伊勢氏の出自とみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is also believed that he was a member of the Ise clan holding public office in the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is also believed that he was a member of the Ise Clan that held public office in the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &quot;c&quot;&quot;holding&quot;→&quot;that held&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is also believed that he was a member of the Ise clan that held public office in the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1950年代に発表された藤井論文以降、伊勢氏のうちで備中国に居住した支流で、備中国荏原庄（現井原市）で生まれたという説が有力となり、その後の資料検証によって備中荏原荘の半分を領する領主（300貫といわれる）であることがほぼ確定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Fujii Theory was published in 1950, the most popular theory states that Soun was in the Ise faction residing in the Province of Bitchu, born in the village of Ebara (currently Ihara City), and a study of other documents has basically determined that he was a feudal lord owning half of Bitchu Ebara (300 kan, a unit of rice weight before the koku system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Fujii Theory was published in the 1950s, the most popular theory states that Soun was born in the village of Ebara (modern day Ihara City) into a branch of the Ise Clan residing in the Province of Bitchu, and the study of other documents has basically determined that he was a feudal lord owning half of Bitchu Ebara (worth 300 kan, a unit of rice weight used before the koku system).</e>
<cmt>&quot;1950&quot;→&quot;the 1950s&quot;Capitalized &quot;c&quot;Reworded mid-section&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Added &quot;used</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Fujii Theory was published in the 1950s, the most popular theory states that Soun was born in the village of Ebara (modern day Ihara City) into a branch of the Ise clan residing in the Province of Bitchu, and the study of other documents has basically determined that he was a feudal lord owning half of Bitchu Ebara (worth 300 kan, a unit of rice weight used before the koku system).</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>室町幕府申次衆の書状と駿河国関連の書状において照らし合わせたところ、記載された史料の「伊勢新九郎盛時」なる人物が同一である事も決め手となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When checking with the documents left by the civil servants in the Muromachi Shogunate and the document related to the Province of Suruga, it has been confirmed that both of these historical document listed Ise-Shinkuro-Moritoki, which supports the above theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documents left by the civil servants of the Muromachi Shogunate and documents related to the Province of Suruga both mention a certain &quot;Ise-Shinkuro-Moritoki&quot;, which supports the above theory.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;When checking with the&quot; and &quot;the&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;of&quot;Made 2nd &quot;document&quot; pluralReworded 2nd part of sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents left by the civil servants of the Muromachi Shogunate and documents related to the Province of Suruga both mention a certain &apos;Shinkuro Moritoki ISE,&apos; which supports the above theory.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にIse-Shinkuro-Moritoki→Shinkuro Moritoki ISE</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>従来の説は文献の解釈の違いによるところが大きく、さらに「備中伊勢氏」説は史料が最も豊富で多岐にわたる事も出自解明に寄与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conventionally accepted theory differed due to how documents were interpreted; however, the theory that Soun was in the Ise clan of Bitchu is noted in the majority of historical documents, leading it to being accepted as his origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theories differed depending on how documents were interpreted but since the majority of them note that Soun was from the Ise Clan of Bitchu, this has become an accepted fact.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theories differed depending on how documents were interpreted but since the majority of them note that Soun was from the Ise clan of Bitchu, this has become an accepted fact.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>近年の研究で早雲の父・伊勢盛定が幕府政所執事伊勢貞親と共に八代将軍足利義政の申次衆として重要な位置にいた事も明らかになってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the recent studies, it has become clear that Soun&apos;s father, Morisada ISE, and Sadachika ISE held important positions in the Muromachi Shogunate fulfilling the duty of announcing the arrival of visitors to the 8th Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent studies have shown that Soun&apos;s father, Morisada ISE, and Sadachika ISE held important positions in the Muromachi Shogunate, fulfilling the duty of announcing the arrival of visitors to the 8th Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;In the recent studies, it has become clear&quot;→&quot;Recent studies have shown&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent studies have shown that Soun&apos;s father, Morisada ISE, and Sadachika ISE held important positions in the Muromachi Shogunate, fulfilling the duty of announcing the arrival of visitors to the 8th Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>早雲は伊勢盛定と京都伊勢氏当主で政所執事の伊勢貞国の娘との間に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun was born the son of Morisada ISE and the daughter of Sadachika ISE, the head of Ise clan in Kyoto who held an upper-ranking post in the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun was born between Morisada ISE and the daughter of Sadakuni ISE, the head of Ise Clan in Kyoto who held an upper-ranking post in the government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the son of&quot;→&quot;born between&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun was born between Morisada ISE and the daughter of Sadakuni ISE, the head of Ise clan in Kyoto who held an upper-ranking post in the government.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>決して身分の低い素浪人ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he was not a lowly master-less samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he was not a lowly ronin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;masterless samurai&quot;→&quot;ronin&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he was not a lowly ronin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>早雲は盛定の所領、備中荏原荘で生まれ、若年時はここに居住したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun was born in Bitchu Ebara area, owned by Morisada, and was known to have been raised there as a young boy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun was born in the Bitchu Ebara area, owned by Morisada, and is thought to have been raised there as a young boy.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;was known&quot;→&quot;is thought&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun was born in the Bitchu Ebara area, owned by Morisada, and is thought to have been raised there as a young boy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>荏原荘には文明 (日本)3年（1471年）付けの「平盛時」の署名の禁制が残されている（ただし、花押が後のものとは異なる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Ebara, there remains prohibition laws signed by Kiyomori TAIRA dated 1471 (The Kao Code signature is different to ones found later).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Ebara, there remain prohibition laws signed by Moritoki TAIRA dated 1471 (The Kao Code signature is different to ones found later).</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;s&apos;&quot;Kiyomori&quot;→&quot;Moritoki&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Ebara, there remain prohibition laws signed by Moritoki TAIRA dated 1471 (The Kao Code signature is different to ones found later).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>さらに、備中国からは大道寺氏、内藤氏、笠原氏など、後北条氏の家臣が出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Daidoji, Naito and Kasahara clans that served the Go-Hojo clan also originated in Bitchu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Daidoji, Naito and Kasahara clans that served the Go-Hojo clan also originated in Bitchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Daidoji, Naito and Kasahara clans that served the Gohojo clan also originated in Bitchu.</e>
<cmt>後北条氏→the Gohojo clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>幕府申次衆・奉公衆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Civil Servant and Military Posts in Muromachi Shogunate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Civil Servant and Military Posts in the Muromachi Shogunate</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Civil Servant and Military Posts in the Muromachi Shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>応仁元年（1467年）応仁の乱が起こり、駿河守護今川義忠が上洛して東軍に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1467, the Onin War broke out, and Yoshitada IMAGAWA, in the post of guard at Suruga, came to Kyoto to join the force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1467, the Onin War broke out, and Yoshitada IMAGAWA, the Shugo (Governor) of Suruga, came to Kyoto to join the eastern army.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in the post of guard at&quot;→&quot;the Shugo (Governor) of&quot;&quot;force&quot;→&quot;eastern army&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1467, the Onin War broke out, and Yoshitada IMAGAWA, the Shugo (Governor) of Suruga, came to Kyoto to join the eastern army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>義忠はしばしば伊勢貞親を訪れており、その申次を早雲の父盛定が務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitada had often visited Sadachika ISE, and it was Soun&apos;s father, Morisada, who had received and announced his arrival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitada had often visited Sadachika ISE, and it was Soun&apos;s father, Morisada, who had received and announced his arrival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitada had often visited Sadachika ISE, and it was Soun&apos;s father, Morisada, who had received and announced his arrival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その縁で早雲の姉（または妹）の北川殿が義忠と結婚したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was these meetings that led to the marriage of Yoshitada and Soun&apos;s sister, Kitagawa-Dono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was these meetings that led to the marriage of Yoshitada and Soun&apos;s sister, Kitagawa-Dono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was these meetings that led to the marriage of Yoshitada and Soun&apos;s sister, Kitagawa-dono.</e>
<cmt>Dono→dono</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>早雲が素浪人とされていた頃は北川殿は側室であろうとされていたが、備中伊勢氏は今川氏と家格的に遜色なく、近年では正室であると見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Soun was thought to be a master-less samurai, Kitagawa-Dono was said to be Yoshitada&apos;s mistress; however, ranks of the Ise and Imagawa clans were equivalent, and so recently, the theory has been revised to state that Kitagawa-Dono was Yoshitada&apos;s legal wife, not his mistress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Soun was thought to be a ronin, Kitagawa-Dono was said to be Yoshitada&apos;s mistress; however, the Ise and Imagawa Clans were of equivalent rank and so recently, the theory has been revised to state that Kitagawa-Dono was Yoshitada&apos;s legal wife, not his mistress.</e>
<cmt>&quot;masterless samurai&quot;→&quot;ronin&quot;&quot;ranks of the Ise and Imagawa clans were equivalent&quot;→&quot;the Ise and Imagawa Clans were of equivalent rank&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Soun was thought to be a ronin, Kitagawa-dono was said to be Yoshitada&apos;s mistress; however, the Ise and Imagawa clans were of equivalent rank and so recently, the theory has been revised to state that Kitagawa-dono was Yoshitada&apos;s legal wife, not his mistress.</e>
<cmt>Dono→donoClan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>文明5年（1473年）に北川殿は嫡男龍王丸（後の今川氏親）を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 14673, Kitagawa-Dono gave birth to a son, Tatsu-o-maru (later the name was changed to Ujichika IMAGAWA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1473, Kitagawa-Dono gave birth to a son, Tatsu-o-maru (who later took the name Ujichika IMAGAWA)</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;6&apos;&quot;later the name was changed to&quot;→&quot;who later took the name&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1473, Kitagawa-dono gave birth to a son, Tatsuomaru (who later took the name Ujichika IMAGAWA).</e>
<cmt>Dono→dono-削除ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>京都で早雲は将軍義政の弟の足利義視に仕えたとされるが、近年有力視される康正2年（1456年）生まれとすると、義視が将軍後継者と擬されていた時期（1464年-1467年）には10歳前後で幼すぎ、応仁元年（1467年）以降、義視は西軍に走っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, Soun is said to have served Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, younger brother to Shogun Yoshimasa; however, if Soun had been born in 1456, the recent theory considered most popular today, he would have been only 10 years old during the period Yoshimi was considered to be the next Shogun (1464-1467), and Yoshimi had changed sides to the East force after 1467.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, Soun is said to have served Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, the younger brother of Shogun Yoshimasa, though if Soun had been born in 1456, as the most popular recent theories contend, he would have been only 10 years old during the period Yoshimi was in line to be the next Shogun (1464-1467), and Yoshimi had changed sides to the western army after 1467.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;, &quot;of&quot;&quot;; however,&quot;→&quot;, though&quot;&quot;the recent theory considered most popular today&quot;→&quot;as the most popular recent theories contend&quot;&quot;considered to be the next Shogun&quot;→&quot;in line to be the next Shogun&quot;&quot;East force&quot;→&quot;western army&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, Soun is said to have served Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, the younger brother of Shogun Yoshimasa, although if Soun had been born in 1456, as the most popular recent theories contend, he would have been only 10 years old during the period Yoshimi was in line to be the next shogun (1464-1467), and Yoshimi had changed sides to the western army after 1467.</e>
<cmt>next Shogun→next shogunthough→although に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>このため、これを疑問視する見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering this fact, some view the theory as questionable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering this fact, some view this date as questionable.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the theory&quot;→&quot;this date&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering this fact, some view this date as questionable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>「伊勢新九郎盛時」の名は文明13年（1481年）から文書に現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name Ise-Shinkuro-Moritoki comes out in documents written in 1481 and thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Ise-Shinkuro-Moritoki appears in documents from 1481 onwards.</e>
<cmt>&quot;comes out&quot;→&quot;appears&quot;&quot;written in&quot;→&quot;from&quot;&quot;and thereafter&quot;→&quot;onwards&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Shinkuro Moritoki ISE appears in documents from 1481 onwards.</e>
<cmt>Ise-Shinkuro-Moritoki→Shinkuro Moritoki ISE</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>文明15年（1481年）に将軍足利義尚の申次衆に任命されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1481, Soun was appointed civil servant to Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1483, Soun was appointed civil servant to Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>Although Japanese original has &quot;文明15年（1481年）&quot;, 文明15年 was actually 1483, so changed accordingly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1483, Soun was appointed civil servant to Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>長享元年（1487年）奉公衆となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to a military post in 1481.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to a military post in 1487.</e>
<cmt>&quot;1481&quot;→&quot;1487&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to a military post in 1487.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>京で幕府に出仕している間、早雲は建仁寺と大徳寺で禅を学んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Soun was working for the Bakufu government in Kyoto, he studied zen at Kennin-ji Temple and Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Soun was working for the Bakufu government in Kyoto, he studied Zen at Kennin-ji Temple and Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;z&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Soun was working for the bakufu government in Kyoto, he studied Zen at Kennin-ji Temple and Daitoku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Bakufu→bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>駿河下向</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Return to Province of Suruga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Return to the Province of Suruga</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Return to the Province of Suruga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>文明8年（1476年）今川義忠は遠江国の塩売坂の戦いで西軍の遠江守護斯波義廉方の国人横地氏、勝間田氏の襲撃を受けて討ち死にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1476, Yoshitada IMAGAWA was attacked and killed by the West Force led by the Yokichi and Katsumata clans, guards of the Province of Totoumi serving Yoshikado SHIBA, at the Battle of Shiouri-zaka in Totoumi.</e>
<cmt>遠江国等Province of Totoumiとすると同じ事の繰り返しで邪魔なので、初出のみProvinceを入れてその後は臨機応変にＰｒｏvince を入れたり、Totoumiだけ使用してます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1476, at the Battle of Shiouri-zaka in the Province of Totoumi, Yoshitada IMAGAWA was attacked and killed by the western army&apos;s Yokichi and Katsumata Clans, who served the Governor of Totoumi, Yoshikado SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the Province of&quot;Changed word orderDeleted &quot;guards&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1476, at the Battle of Shiouri-zaka in Totomi Province, Yoshitada IMAGAWA was attacked and killed by the western army&apos;s Yokichi and Katsumata clans, who served the Governor of Totomi, Yoshikado SHIBA.</e>
<cmt>遠江国→Totomi ProvinceClan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、遠江国の政情は複雑で、近年の研究ではこれらの国人は東軍の斯波義良に属するものだと考察されており、義忠は同じ東軍と戦っていたことになってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The governing status of Totoumi was complicated and recent study has revealed that clans serving Totoumi actually belonged to Yoshinaga SHIBA in the East Force, which meant that Yoshitada was fighting the East Force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the political situation in Totoumi was complicated and recent studies have shown that these clans were actually under the command of Yoshinaga SHIBA of the eastern army, which means that Yoshitada was fighting the eastern, not the western, army.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;However,&quot;&quot;governing status of&quot;→&quot;political situation in&quot;Made &quot;study&quot; and verb plural&quot;revealed&quot;→&quot;shown&quot;Added &quot;these&quot;Deleted &quot;serving Totoumi&quot;&quot;belonged to&quot;→&quot;under the command of&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;of&quot;&quot;East Force&quot;→&quot;eastern army&quot;&quot;meant&quot;→&quot;means&quot;Added &quot;, not the western,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the political situation in Totomi Province was complicated and recent studies have shown that these clans were in fact under the command of Yoshinaga SHIBA of the eastern army, which means that Yoshitada was fighting the eastern, not the western, army.</e>
<cmt>遠江国→Totomi Provinceactually→in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>残された嫡男龍王丸は幼少であり（異説あり）、このため今川氏の家臣三浦氏、朝比奈氏などが一族の小鹿範満（義忠の従兄弟）を擁立して、家中が二分される家督争いとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitada died, his son, Tatsu-o-maru was still young (other theories exist), and the retainers Miura clan and Asahina clan tried to bring Norimitsu OSHIKA (Yoshitada&apos;s cousin) to their side, dividing the Imagawa clan in two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitada died, his son, Tatsu-o-maru, was still young (other theories exist), so retainers such as the Miura and Asahina Clans backed Norimitsu OSHIKA (Yoshitada&apos;s cousin), dividing the Imagawa clan in two.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and&quot;→&quot;so&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;such as the&quot;Deleted &quot;clan&quot;&quot;tried to bring Norimitsu OSHIKA (Yoshitada&apos;s cousin) to their side&quot;→&quot;backed Norimitsu OSHIKA (Yoshitada&apos;s cousin)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitada died, his son, Tatsuomaru, was still young (other theories exist), so retainers such as the Miura and Asahina clans backed Norimitsu OSHIKA (Yoshitada&apos;s cousin), dividing the Imagawa clan in two.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan-削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これに堀越公方と扇谷上杉氏が介入し、それぞれ執事の上杉政憲と家宰の太田道灌を駿河国へ兵を率いて派遣させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horigoe Kubo and the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan intervened and dispatched forces led by their higher-ranking officers, Masanori UESUGI and Dokan OTA, to the Province of Suruga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horigoe Kubo and the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi Clan intervened and dispatched forces led by their higher-ranking officers, Masanori UESUGI and Dokan OTA, to the Province of Suruga.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horigoe Kubo and the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan intervened and dispatched forces led by their higher-ranking officers, Masanori UESUGI and Dokan OTA, to the Province of Suruga.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>範満と上杉政憲は血縁があり、また太田道灌も史料に範満の「合力」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norimitsu and Masanori UESUGI were related by blood, and Dokan OTA has also noted in historical documents that he was on the side of Norimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norimitsu and Masanori UESUGI were related by blood, and Dokan OTA is also recorded as having supported Norimitsu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;has also noted in historical documents that he was on the side of&quot;→&quot;is also recorded as having supported&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norimitsu and Masanori UESUGI were related by blood, and Dokan OTA is also recorded as having supported Norimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>龍王丸派にとって情勢は不利であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatsu-o-maru was at the disadvantage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatsu-o-maru&apos;s supporters was at the disadvantage.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;&apos;s supporters&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatsuomaru&apos;s supporters was at the disadvantage.</e>
<cmt>-削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>北川殿の弟（または兄）である早雲は駿河国へ下り、調停を行い龍王丸が成人するまで範満を家督代行とすることで決着させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being Kitagawa-Dono&apos;s brother, Soun went to Suruga to mediate between the two forces and worked it out so that Norimitsu would reign over the family on Tatsu-o-maru&apos;s behalf until Tatsu-o-maru came of age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being Kitagawa-Dono&apos;s brother, Soun went to Suruga to mediate between the two forces and worked it out so that Norimitsu would reign over the family on Tatsu-o-maru&apos;s behalf until Tatsu-o-maru came of age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being Kitagawa-dono&apos;s brother, Soun went to Suruga to mediate between the two forces and worked it out so that Norimitsu would reign over the family on Tatsuomaru&apos;s behalf until Tatsuomaru came of age.</e>
<cmt>Dono→dono</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>上杉政憲と太田道灌も撤兵させた（この時に道灌と会談したという話もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he had Masanori UESUGI and Dokan OTA&apos;s forces withdrew (One theory states that at this time, Soun had a meeting with Dokan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, he had Masanori UESUGI and Dokan OTA&apos;s forces withdraw (there is a story that Soun met with Dokan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;withdrew&quot;→&quot;withdraw&quot;&quot;One theory states that at this time, Soun had a meeting&quot;→&quot;there is a story that Soun met&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, he had Masanori UESUGI and Dokan OTA&apos;s forces withdraw (there is a story that Soun met with Dokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>旧来の説なら、早雲と道灌は同年齢であった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conventional theory holds that Soun and Dokan were of the same age.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conventional theory holds that Soun and Dokan were of the same age.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conventional theory holds that Soun and Dokan were of the same age.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>両派は浅間神社で神水を酌み交わして和議を誓った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two sects exchanged vows of peace drinking sacred water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two sides exchanged vows of peace by drinking sacred water at Asamajinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>&quot;sects&quot;→&quot;sides&quot;Added &quot;by&quot; and &quot;at Asamajinja Shrine&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two sides exchanged vows of peace by drinking sacred water at Asama-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>家督を代行した範満が駿府城に入り、龍王丸は母北川殿と小川の法永長者（長谷川政宣）の屋敷（小川城（焼津市））に身を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norimitsu, acting as the head of the clan, came to live in Suruga Castle and Tatsu-o-maru and his mother Kitagawa-Dono went to the residence of Kogawa-no-hoei-Choja (Masanobu HASEGAWA) (Today, it is Kogawa-jo Castle in Yaizu City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norimitsu, acting as the head of the clan, went to live in Sumpu Castle and Tatsu-o-maru and his mother, Kitagawa-Dono, went to the residence (present-day Kogawa-jo Castle in Yaizu City) of Choja HOEI of Kogawa (also known as Masanobu HASEGAWA).</e>
<cmt>&quot;came&quot;→&quot;went&quot;&quot;Suruga&quot;→&quot;Sumpu&quot;&quot;Kogawa-no-hoei-Choja&quot;→&quot;Choja HOEI of Kogawa&quot;Added &quot;also known as&quot;&quot;Today, it is&quot;&quot;→&quot;present-day&quot;Moved &quot;(present-day Kogawa-jo Castle in Yaizu City)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norimitsu, acting as the head of the clan, went to live in Sumpu Castle and Tatsuomaru and his mother, Kitagawa-dono, went to the residence (present-day Kogawa-jo Castle in Yaizu City) of Hoei Choja (also known as Masanobu HASEGAWA) of Kogawa.</e>
<cmt>Dono→dono-削除法永長者→Hoei Choja</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>従来、この調停成功は早雲の抜群の知略による立身出世の第一歩とされるが、これは貞親・盛定の命により駿河守護家・今川氏の家督相続介入の為に下向したものであるとの説が有力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that the success of this mediation was due to Soun&apos;s outstanding maneuver, which became his first step of his social climb; however, prevailing theory holds that he came to Suruga to intervene with the inheritance of the reigns of the Imagawa clan under the order of Sadachika and Morisada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The success of Soun&apos;s arbitration due to his exceptional resourcefulness has been said to be the first step of his social climb; however, prevailing theory holds that he was ordered by Sadachika and Morisada to go to Suruga to intervene in the Imagawa Clan&apos;s inheritance dispute.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The success of Soun&apos;s arbitration due to his exceptional resourcefulness has been said to be the first step of his social climb; however, prevailing theory holds that he was ordered by Sadachika and Morisada to go to Suruga to intervene in the Imagawa clan&apos;s inheritance dispute.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="44">
<j>今川氏の家督争いが収まると早雲は京へ戻り、上述のとおり将軍義尚に仕えて奉公衆になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the contest for family rule was settled, Soun returned to Kyoto and served Shogun Yoshinao and was appointed to a military post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the contest for family rule was settled, Soun returned to Kyoto and served Shogun Yoshinao, being appointed to a military post.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and was&quot;→&quot;, being&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the contest for family rule was settled, Soun returned to Kyoto and served Shogun Yoshinao, being appointed to a military post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="45">
<j>この最初の駿河下向と家督争い調停については、黒田基樹は新説による早雲の推定年齢の若さ（20歳）と、事件に付いて記している『鎌倉大草紙』には早雲の名が見えないことから考えて、このエピソードの実在に疑問を呈している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the entering Suruga and mediation for family rule, Motoki KURODA&apos;s new theory states that at the time Soun was estimated to be 20 years old and his name does not come up in the &quot;Kamakura Ozoshi (Document on battles during Muromachi Period), &quot; undermining the credibility of the episode.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding his journey to Suruga and mediation over the family succession, Motoki KURODA&apos;s new theory states that at the time Soun was estimated to be 20 years old and his name does not appear in the &quot;Kamakura Ozoshi (Document on battles during the Muromachi Period), &quot; undermining the credibility of the episode.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the entering&quot;→&quot;his journey to&quot;&quot;for&quot;→&quot;over the&quot;&quot;rule&quot;→&quot;succession&quot;&quot;come up&quot;→&quot;appear&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding his journey to Suruga and mediation over the family succession, Motoki KURODA&apos;s new theory states that at the time Soun was estimated to be 20 years old and his name does not appear in the &quot;Kamakura Ozoshi (Document on battles during the Muromachi Period),&quot; undermining the credibility of the episode.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="46">
<j>早雲の駿河下向については以下のようなエピソードが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following episode is known about Soun&apos;s travel to Suruga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following episodes is known about Soun&apos;s travel to Suruga.</e>
<cmt>Made &quot;episode&quot; plural&quot;travel&quot;→&quot;journey&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following episodes is known about Soun&apos;s travel to Suruga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="47">
<j>『北条記』に見える早雲駿河下向時の一節には、大道寺重時、荒木兵庫、多目権兵衛・山中才四郎・荒川又次郎・在竹兵衛らの仲間6人と、伊勢国で神水を酌み交わして、一人が大名になったら他の者は家臣になろうと誓い合ったという、三国志の桃園の誓いのような話が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is states in the &quot;Hojoki&quot; that Soun drank sake with Shigetoki DAIDOJI, Hyogo ARAKI, Gonbee TAME, Saishiro YAMANAKA, Matajiro ARAKAWA and Hyoe ARITAKE in Ise and that they vowed that should one of them become a feudal lord, the others would become his retainers, which is similar to the story of Toen-no-chikai in &quot;Sangokushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is stated in the &quot;Hojoki&quot; that Soun drank sake with Shigetoki DAIDOJI, Hyogo ARAKI, Gonbee TAME, Saishiro YAMANAKA, Matajiro ARAKAWA and Hyoe ARITAKE in Ise and that they vowed that should one of them become a feudal lord, the others would become his retainers, which is similar to the story of Toen-no-chikai in &quot;Sangokushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;states&quot;→&quot;stated&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is stated in the &quot;Hojoki&quot; that Soun drank sake with Shigetoki DAIDOJI, Hyogo ARAKI, Gonbee TAME, Saishiro YAMANAKA, Matajiro ARAKAWA and Hyoe ARITAKE in Ise and that they vowed that should one of them become a feudal lord, the others would become his retainers, which is similar to the story of Toen-no-chikai in &quot;Sangokushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="48">
<j>『公方両将記』には、陸奥国へ下ろうとしていた早雲は駿河国の薩埵峠で盗賊に遭い身ぐるみはがれて難渋していたところを守護の奥方の輿と出会い衣服を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is stated in &quot;Kuboryoshoki&quot; that on his way to the Province of Mutsu, he was robbed of all things by bandits at the Satta Pass in Suruga, when the provincial constables&apos; wife&apos;s traveling group found him, they gave him clothes to wear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is stated in the &quot;Kuboryoshoki&quot; that, on his way to the Province of Mutsu, he was robbed of all his possessions by bandits at the Satta Pass in Suruga, and when the Governor&apos;s wife&apos;s traveling group found him, they gave him clothes to wear.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;things&quot;→&quot;his possessions&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;&quot;provincial constables&apos;&quot;→&quot;Governor&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is stated in the &quot;Kuboryoshoki&quot; that, on his way to the Province of Mutsu, he was robbed of all his possessions by bandits at the Satta Pass in Suruga, and when the Governor&apos;s wife&apos;s traveling group found him, they gave him clothes to wear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>それが「叔母」の北川殿であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was his &apos;aunt&apos;, Kitagawa-Dono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was his &apos;aunt&apos;, Kitagawa-Dono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was his &apos;aunt&apos;, Kitagawa-Dono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>その縁で、今川氏に仕えるようになったという話になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, he served Imagawa clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, he served Imagawa clan</e>
<cmt>&quot;served&quot;→&quot;came to serve&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, he served Imagawa clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>このエピソードは司馬遼太郎の小説『箱根の坂』でも使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This episode is also noted in Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s &quot;Hakone no Saka&quot; (Hakone Hill Road)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This episode is also noted in Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s &quot;Hakone no Saka&quot; (Hakone Hill Road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This episode is also noted in Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s &quot;Hakone no Saka&quot; (Hakone Hill Road)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="52">
<j>いずれも、いかにも大志を抱く素浪人にふさわしい話であり、創作であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of these episodes seen to suggest that he had been a poor samurai with great ambition, however they are most likely fictions..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although all of these episodes seen to suggest that he had been a poor samurai with great ambition, they are most likely fiction.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;Although&quot;Deleted &quot;however&quot; and &quot;s.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although all of these episodes seen to suggest that he had been a poor samurai with great ambition, they are most likely fiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="53">
<j>文明11年（1479年）前将軍義政は龍王丸の家督継承を認めて本領を安堵する内書を出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1479, the previous Shogun Yoshimasa had sent a Naisho or a confidential letter approving Tatsu-o-maru&apos;s inheritance of family rule, allowing for Tatsu-o-maru to inherit family property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1479, the former Shogun, Yoshimasa, sent a Naisho, or confidential letter, approving Tatsu-o-maru&apos;s inheritance of the family headship.</e>
<cmt>&quot;previous&quot;→&quot;former&quot;Deleted &quot;had&quot;&quot;rule&quot;→&quot;headship&quot;Deleted &quot;allowing for Tatsu-o-maru to inherit family property&quot; - adds nothing to previous clause.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1479, the former Shogun, Yoshimasa, sent a Naisho, or confidential letter, approving Tatsuomaru&apos;s inheritance of the family headship.</e>
<cmt>-削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>ところが、龍王丸が15歳を過ぎて成人しても範満は家督を戻そうとはしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Norimitsu would not return the family rule to Tatsu-o-maru even after Tatsu-o-maru reached his adulthood at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Norimitsu would not return the family rule to Tatsu-o-maru even after Tatsu-o-maru became an adult at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>&quot;reached his adulthood&quot;→&quot;became an adult&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Norimitsu would not return the family rule to Tatsuomaru even after Tatsuomaru became an adult at the age of 15.</e>
<cmt>-削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="55">
<j>長享元年（1487年）早雲は再び駿河国へ下り、龍王丸を補佐すると共に石脇城（焼津市）に入って同志を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1487, Soun went to Suruga once again to assist Tatsu-o-maru, and at the same time gathered allies at Ishiwaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1487, Soun went to Suruga once again to assist Tatsu-o-maru, at the same time gathering allies at Ishiwaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;and&quot;&quot;gathered&quot;→&quot;gathering&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1487, Soun went to Suruga once again to assist Tatsuomaru, at the same time gathering allies at Ishiwaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>-削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>同年11月、早雲は兵を起こし、駿河館を襲撃して範満とその弟小鹿孫五郎を殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of the same year, Soun formed an army, attacked Suruga House and killed Norimitsu and his younger brother, Magogoro OSHIKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, Soun formed an army, attacked Suruga House and killed Norimitsu and his younger brother, Magogoro OSHIKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the same year, Soun formed an army, attacked Suruga House and killed Norimitsu and his younger brother, Magogoro OSHIKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>龍王丸は駿河館に入り、2年後に元服して氏親を名乗り正式に今川家当主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatsu-o-maru moved into Suruga House, 2 years later celebrated coming of age, became the head of Imagawa family with the name Ujichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatsu-o-maru moved into Suruga House, 2 years later celebrated coming of age and became the head of the Imagawa family, taking the name Ujichika.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;and&quot;, &quot;the&quot;&quot;with&quot;→&quot;, taking&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatsuomaru moved into Suruga House, 2 years later celebrated coming of age and became the head of the Imagawa family, taking the name Ujichika.</e>
<cmt>-削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="58">
<j>早雲は伊豆国との国境に近い興国寺城（現沼津市）と所領を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun was granted Kokuji-jo Castle and some land (Numazu City today) near the border of the Province of Izu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun was granted Kokuji-jo Castle and some land (present-day Numazu City near the border of the Province of Izu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;today&quot;→&quot;present-day&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun was granted Kokuji-jo Castle and some land (present-day Numazu City near the border of the Province of Izu).</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>駿河へ留まり、今川氏の家臣となった早雲は氏親を補佐、守護代の出す「打渡状」を発行していることから駿河守護代の地位にあったとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun who remained in Suruga to serve the Imagawa clan, issued a Uchiwatashi Letter, a letter written by Shugodai local magistrate, which suggests that he may have been in the position of Shugodai at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun, who remained in Suruga to serve the Imagawa clan, issued a Uchiwatashi Letter, a letter written by the Shugodai local magistrate, which suggests that he may have been in the position of Shugodai at the time.</e>
<cmt>Added comma and &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun, who remained in Suruga to serve the Imagawa clan, issued a &apos;Uchiwatashi&apos; Letter, a letter written by the Shugodai local magistrate, which suggests that he may have been in the position of Shugodai at the time.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="60">
<j>この頃に早雲は伊勢家と同格である平氏一門の幕府奉公衆小笠原政清の娘（南陽院殿）と結婚し、嫡男氏綱が生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At about this time Soun married a daughter of Masakiyo OGASAWARA (Nanyoin-Dono), a family belonging to Taira clan of the same social rank as the Ise family, and had a son, Ujitsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At about this time Soun married Nanyoin-Dono, a daughter of Masakiyo OGASAWARA, a Taira Clan branch family with the same social rank as the Ise family, and had a son, Ujitsuna.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;Nanyoin-Dono&quot;&quot;family belonging to Taira clan of&quot;→&quot;family belonging to Taira clan of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At about this time Soun married Nanyoin-dono, a daughter of Masakiyo OGASAWARA, a Taira clan branch family with the same social rank as the Ise family, and had a son, Ujitsuna.</e>
<cmt>Dono→donoClan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>伊豆討入り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raid on Izu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Raid on Izu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raid on Izu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>早雲が堀越公方の子足利茶々丸を襲撃して滅ぼし、伊豆国を奪った事件は、旧勢力が滅び、新興勢力が勃興する下克上の嚆矢とされ、戦国時代の幕開けとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun&apos;s attack on and overthrow of Chachamaru ASHIKAGA to take control over Izu is said to have triggered other attacks on higher powers and the opening of the Warring Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun&apos;s attack on and overthrow of Chachamaru ASHIKAGA to take control over Izu is said to have triggered other attacks on those in power and the opening of the Warring Period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;higher powers&quot;→&quot;those in power&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun&apos;s attack on and overthrow of Chachamaru ASHIKAGA to take control over Izu is said to have triggered other attacks on those in power and the opening of the Warring Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>政治が腐敗した京を捨てて、関東の沃野に志を立てたように描かれてきた早雲だが、中央の政治と連動した動きを取っていることが近年になって家永遵嗣などの研究で分ってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun had been depicted as a samurai who had abandoned the corrupt government in Kyoto for the Kanto area; however, a recent study by Junji IENAGA reveals that he had taken action in collaboration with the central government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun had been depicted as a samurai who had abandoned the corrupt government in Kyoto for the Kanto area; however, a recent study by Junji IENAGA reveals that he acted in collaboration with the central government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;had taken action&quot;→&quot;acted&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun had been depicted as a samurai who had abandoned the corrupt government in Kyoto for the Kanto area; however, a recent study by Junji IENAGA reveals that he acted in collaboration with the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>享徳の乱で関東公方足利成氏が幕府に叛き、将軍の命を受けた今川氏が鎌倉市を攻めて占領。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kyotoku War, Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, a Kanto Kubo, disobeyed the Bakufu administration, and the Imagawa clan was ordered by the Shogun to attack and capture Kamakura City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kyotoku War, Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, a Kanto Kubo, disobeyed the Bakufu administration, and the Imagawa Clan was ordered by the Shogun to attack and capture Kamakura City.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kyotoku War, Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, a Kanto Kubo, disobeyed the Bakufu administration, and the Imagawa clan was ordered by the Shogun to attack and capture Kamakura City.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>成氏は古河城に逃れて古河公方と呼ばれる反対勢力となり、幕府方の関東管領上杉氏と激しく戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeuji escaped to Kago-jo Castle joining the opposition to the Bakufu administration, called the Koga Kubo, and fought fiercely against the Uesugi clan, the Bakufu force in Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeuji escaped to Koga-jo Castle, joining the opposition to the Bakufu administration, called the Koga Kubo, and fought fiercely against the Uesugi clan, the Bakufu force in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kago-jo&quot;→&quot;Koga-jo&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeuji escaped to Koga-jo Castle, joining the opposition to the Bakufu administration, called the Koga Kubo, and fought fiercely against the Uesugi clan, the Bakufu force in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>将軍義政は成氏に代る関東公方として、弟の足利政知を送るが、成氏方の力が強く、鎌倉に入ることもできず伊豆国北条に本拠に留まって堀越公方と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun Yoshimasa sent his brother Masatomo ASHIKAGA to replace Shigeuji; however, Shigeuji&apos;s force was strong, hindering Masatomo&apos;s advances on Kamakura, which left him stuck at Hojo fort in Izu, what was later called the Horikoshi-Kubo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun Yoshimasa sent his brother Masatomo ASHIKAGA to replace Shigeuji; however, Shigeuji&apos;s army was strong, hindering Masatomo&apos;s advances on Kamakura, which left him stuck at Hojo fort in Izu and subsequently he became known as the Horikoshi-Kubo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;force&quot;→&quot;army&quot;&quot;what was later called&quot;→&quot;and subsequently he became known as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogun Yoshimasa sent his brother Masatomo ASHIKAGA to replace Shigeuji; however, Shigeuji&apos;s army was strong, hindering Masatomo&apos;s advances on Kamakura, which left him stuck at Hojo fort in Izu and subsequently he became known as Horigoe Kubo.</e>
<cmt>上記に合わせて、Horikoshi→Ｈｏｒigoeｔｈｅ削除-削除,　スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>文明14年（1483年）古河公方成氏と関東管領上杉氏との和睦が成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1483, peace was settled between Koga-Kobo Shigeuji and the Kanto official Uesugi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1483, peace was established between the Koga-Kubo, Shigeuji, and the Kanto Kanrei (Shogun&apos;s deputy), Uesugi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;settled&quot;→&quot;established&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;Kobo&quot;→&quot;Kubo&quot;&quot;official&quot;→&quot;Kanrei (Shogun&apos;s deputy)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1483, peace was established between the Koga Kubo, Shigeuji, and the Kanto Kanrei (Shogun&apos;s deputy), Uesugi.</e>
<cmt>-削除, スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>堀越公方の存在は宙に浮いてしまい、伊豆一国のみを支配する存在となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This peace left Horikoshi-Kobo on the limb, and he came to rule only the land of Izu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This peace made the Horikoshi-Kubo&apos;s position uncertain and he was left in control of only the Province of Izu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;left Horikoshi-Kobo on the limb&quot;→&quot;made the Horikoshi-Kubo&apos;s position uncertain&quot;&quot;came to rule&quot;→&quot;left in control&quot;&quot;land&quot;→&quot;Province&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This peace made Horigoe Kubo&apos;s position uncertain and he was left in control of only the Province of Izu.</e>
<cmt>上記に合わせて、Horikoshi→Ｈｏｒigoeｔｈｅ削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>政知には長男に茶々丸がいたが、正室の円満院との間に潤童子と清晃をもうけていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatomo&apos;s eldest son was Chachamaru, and he also had Jundoji and Seiko with his wife Enmanin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatomo&apos;s eldest son was Chachamaru, and he also had Jundoji and Seiko with his wife, Enmanin.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatomo&apos;s eldest son was Chachamaru, and he also had Jundoji and Seiko with his wife, Enmanin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>清晃は出家して京にいたが、政知は勢力挽回のために日野富子や管領細川政元と連絡してこの清晃を将軍に擁立しようと図っていたとの噂があったと長享元年（1487年）の大乗院尋尊の日記に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in the 1487 diary of Jinson DAIJOIN that Seiko was at a temple in Kyoto to join priesthood, but there was a rumor that Masatomo tried to back up Seiko to become a Shogun together with Tomiko HINO and Masamoto HOSOKAWA, in order to recover his power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the 1487 diary of Jinson DAIJOIN, although Seiko was in Kyoto to join the priesthood, there was a rumor that Masatomo, together with Tomiko HINO and Masamoto HOSOKAWA, was planning to make Seiko Shogun in order to recover his power.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It is written in&quot;→&quot;According to&quot;&quot;that&quot;→&quot;, although&quot;Deleted &quot;at a temple&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;but&quot;Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the 1487 diary of Jinson DAIJOIN, although Seiko was in Kyoto to join the priesthood, there was a rumor that Masatomo, together with Tomiko HINO and Masamoto HOSOKAWA, was planning to make Seiko Shogun in order to recover his power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>中世史の研究者の下山治久はこの計画に早雲と氏親が関与していたのではないかと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A researcher of medieval history, Haruhisa SHIMOYAMA, states that Soun and Ujichika were involved in this plan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A researcher of medieval history, Haruhisa SHIMOYAMA, states that Soun and Ujichika were involved in this plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A researcher of medieval history, Haruhisa SHIMOYAMA, states that Soun and Ujichika were involved in this plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="71">
<j>延徳3年（1491年）に政知が没すると、茶々丸は円満院とその子の潤童子を殺害して強引に跡目を継ぐという事件が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1491, after the death of Masatomo, Chachamaru killed Enmanin and her child Jundoji and forced his way to power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1491, after the death of Masatomo, Chachamaru killed Enmanin and her child Jundoji and forced his way to power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1491, after the death of Masatomo, Chachamaru killed Enmanin and her child Jundoji and forced his way to power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="72">
<j>早雲は延徳3年（1491年）5月までは「伊勢新九郎」の文書が残っているが、明応3年（1494年）の史料では「早雲庵宗瑞」と法名になっており、この間に出家したようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun&apos;s name appears until May of 1491 as Shinkuro ISE, but in a 1494 document, he appears under his priesthood name, Soun-An-Sozui, suggesting that he entered the priesthood between these years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun&apos;s name appears until May of 1491 as Shinkuro ISE, but in a 1494 document, he appears under his priesthood name, Soun-An-Sozui, suggesting that he entered the priesthood between these years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun&apos;s name appears until June of 1491 as Shinkuro ISE, but in a 1494 document, he appears under his priesthood name, Sounan Sozui, suggesting that he entered the priesthood between these years.</e>
<cmt>早雲庵宗瑞→Sounan Sozuiグレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>この時代の武士の出家には政治的な意味があることが多く、家永遵嗣は清晃の母の円満院の横死が理由ではないかと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When samurai entered the priesthood during this age, there was often political meaning behind it, and researcher Junji IENAGA states that Soun joined the priesthood because of the unnatural death of Seiko&apos;s mother, Enmanin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When samurai entered the priesthood during this age, there was often political meaning behind it, and researcher Junji IENAGA states that Soun joined the priesthood because of the unnatural death of Seiko&apos;s mother, Enmanin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When samurai entered the priesthood during this age, there was often political meaning behind it, and researcher Junji IENAGA states that Soun joined the priesthood because of the unnatural death of Seiko&apos;s mother, Enmanin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="74">
<j>明応2年（1493年）4月、管領細川政元が明応の政変を起こして将軍足利義稙を追放。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1493, Masatomo HOSOKAWA authored political change in Meio and deported Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1493, Masatomo HOSOKAWA organized the &quot;Meio Coup&quot; and exiled Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;authored political change in Meio&quot;→&quot;organized the &quot;Meio Coup&quot;&quot;&quot;deported&quot;→&quot;exiled&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1493, Masatomo HOSOKAWA organized the Meio Coup and exiled Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;　&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>清晃を室町殿（実質上の将軍）に擁立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attempted to place Seiko in the position of Muromachi Dono, which, in reality is the position of Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attempted to place Seiko in the position of Muromachi Dono, which in reality was equivalent to Shogun.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is the position of&quot;→&quot;was equivalent to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attempted to place Seiko in the position of Muromachi-dono, which in reality was equivalent to Shogun.</e>
<cmt>-dono</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>清晃は還俗して足利義澄を名乗る（後に義澄と改名）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiko returned to secular life under the name Yoshito ASHIKAGA (Later changed to Yoshizumi).</e>
<cmt>カッコに後に義澄と改名とあり、その前の足利義澄で意味が通りませんので調べたところ足利義遐でないかと思います。訳もそのようにしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiko returned to secular life under the name Yoshito ASHIKAGA (Later changed to Yoshizumi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiko returned to secular life under the name Yoshito ASHIKAGA (Later changed to Yoshizumi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>権力の座に就いた義遐は母と兄の敵討ちを幕府官僚の経歴を持ち、茶々丸の近隣に城を持つ早雲へ命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Placed in power, Yoshito vowed revenge for his mother and brother&apos;s death, and ordered Soun, an official in the Bakufu with a castle near Chachamaru&apos;s residence, to carry out the attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Placed in power, Yoshito vowed revenge for his mother and brother&apos;s death, and ordered Soun, an official in the Bakufu with a castle near Chachamaru&apos;s residence, to carry out the attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Placed in power, Yoshito vowed revenge for his mother and brother&apos;s death, and ordered Soun, an official in the Bakufu with a castle near Chachamaru&apos;s residence, to carry out the attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>これを受けて早雲は、同年夏か秋ごろに伊豆堀越御所の茶々丸を攻撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this, Soun attacked the Imperial palace of Izu-Horikoshi in the summer or fall of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun attacked the Imperial palace of Izu-Horikoshi in the summer or fall of the same year.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;with this&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun attacked the Imperial palace of Izu-Horigoe in the summer or fall of the same year.</e>
<cmt>上記に合わせて、Horikoshi→Ｈｏｒigoe</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>この事件を伊豆討入りといい、東国戦国期の幕開けと評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident is called the Izu Raid, and considered the opening the Warring States Period of the East</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident is called the Izu Raid, and considered the opening the Warring States Period of the East.</e>
<cmt>Added full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident is called the Izu Raid, and considered the opening the Warring States Period of the East.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="80">
<j>後世の軍記物には、この伊豆討入りに際して、早雲が修善寺に湯治と称して自ら密偵となり伊豆の世情を調べたとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is stated in the war chronicles that in preparation for the Izu Raid, Soun went to Shuzen-ji Temple, claiming to be going for a hot spring cure, and spied on Izu himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is stated in the war chronicles that in preparation for the Izu Raid, Soun went to Shuzen-ji Temple, claiming to be going for a hot spring cure, and spied on Izu himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is stated in the war chronicles that in preparation for the Izu Raid, Soun went to Shuzen-ji Temple, claiming to be going for a hot spring cure, and spied on Izu himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>また、「討入りは、伊豆国の兵の多くが山内上杉氏に動員され上野国の合戦に出て手薄になったのを好機とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also stated that &quot;The raid took place when many samurai from Izu were recruited by Yamanouchi-Uesugi clan to fight in the battle at the Province of Kozuke, leaving Izu with a small number of samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also stated that &quot;The raid took place when many samurai from Izu were away fighting for the Yamanouchi-Uesugi Clan in the Province of Kozuke, leaving Izu with a small number of samurai.</e>
<cmt>&quot;recruited by Yamanouchi-Uesugi clan to fight in the battle at&quot;→&quot;away fighting for the Yamanouchi-Uesugi Clan in the Province of Kozuke&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also stated that &apos;the raid took place when many samurai from Izu were away fighting for the Yamanouchi-Uesugi Clan in the Province of Kozuke, leaving Izu with a small number of samurai.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>早雲の手勢200人と氏親に頼んで借りた300人の合わせて500人が、10艘の船に乗って清水港を出港。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Soun&apos;s force of 200 worriers and the 300 borrowed from Ujichika, the force of 500 boarded 10 ships and left Shimizu Harbor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A force of 500, made up of 200 of Soun&apos;s warriors and 300 borrowed from Ujichika, boarded 10 ships and left Shimizu Harbor.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&quot;With Soun&apos;s force of 200 worriers and the&quot;→&quot;made up of 200 of Soun&apos;s warriors and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A force of 500, made up of 200 of Soun&apos;s warriors and 300 borrowed from Ujichika, boarded 10 ships and left Shimizu Harbor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>駿河湾を渡って西伊豆の海岸に上陸すると、住民は海賊の襲来と恐れて家財道具を持って山へ逃げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After crossing Suruga Bay and landing on the beach at West Izu, all the local people thought they were pirates, so they escaped into the mountains with their belongings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After crossing Suruga Bay and landing on the beach at West Izu, all the local people thought they were piratesand fled into the mountains with their belongings.</e>
<cmt>&quot;, so they escaped&quot;→&quot;and fled&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After crossing Suruga Bay and landing on the beach at West Izu, all the local people thought they were pirates and fled into the mountains with their belongings.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>早雲の兵は一挙に堀越御所を急襲して火を放ち、茶々丸は山中に逃げ自害に追い込まれた」と書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun&apos;s force made a sweeping attack of Horigoe Palace and Chachamaru was forced into the mountains where he then committed suicide.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun&apos;s force made a sweeping attack of Horigoe Palace and Chachamaru was forced into the mountains where he then committed suicide.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun&apos;s force made a sweeping attack of Horigoe Palace and Chachamaru was forced into the mountains where he then committed suicide.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>しかし、どこまで真実か分らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not known how much of this is truth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not known how much of this is fact.</e>
<cmt>&quot;truth&quot;→&quot;fact&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known how much of this is fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="86">
<j>この他「早雲は伊豆国韮山城（現伊豆の国市）を新たな居城として伊豆国の統治を始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another document states that &quot;Soun began ruling the Province of Izu residing in the Nirayama-jo Castle (currently Izunokuni City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another document states that &quot;Soun began ruling the Province of Izu from Nirayama-jo Castle (currently Izunokuni City).</e>
<cmt>&quot;residing in the&quot;→&quot;from&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another document states that &apos;Soun began ruling the Province of Izu from Nirayama-jo Castle (currently Izunokuni City).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>高札を立てて味方に参じれば本領を安堵すると約束し、一方で参じなければ作物を荒らして住居を破壊すると布告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He proclaimed to all that if they set up a Kosatsu (a notice board) and become allies, their lands would be secured; if not, he would destroy their crops and houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He proclaimed to all that if they set up a Kosatsu (a notice board) and became allies, their lands would be secured; if not, he would destroy their crops and houses.</e>
<cmt>&quot;become&quot;→&quot;became&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He proclaimed to all that if they set up a Kosatsu (a notice board) and became allies, their lands would be secured; if not, he would destroy their crops and houses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>また、兵の乱暴狼藉を厳重に禁止し、病人を看護するなど善政を施し、茶々丸の悪政に苦しんでいた伊豆の武士や領民はたちまち早雲に従った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He prohibited violent acts by his arm forces and established laws protecting and nursing the ill, which resulted in all samurai and residents who had suffered from the misgovernment of Chachamaru to follow his leadership.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He prohibited violent acts by his armed forces and established laws protecting and nursing the ill, which resulted in all samurai and residents who had suffered from the misgovernment of Chachamaru to follow his leadership.</e>
<cmt>&quot;arm&quot;→&quot;armed&quot;&quot;to follow&quot;→&quot;following&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He prohibited violent acts by his armed forces and established laws protecting and nursing the ill, which resulted in all samurai and residents who had suffered from the misgovernment of Chachamaru to follow his leadership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>抵抗する関戸吉信の深根城（下田市）を落として皆殺しにして力を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He exhibited his power by attacking Yoshinobu SEKIDO, who resisted Soun, took over Fukane-jo Castle (Shimoda City) and killed all his followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He exhibited his power by attacking Yoshinobu SEKIDO, who resisted Soun, took over Fukane-jo Castle (Shimoda City) and killed all his followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He exhibited his power by attacking Yoshinobu SEKIDO, who resisted Soun, took over Fukane-jo Castle (Shimoda City) and killed all his followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>そして、それまでの煩瑣で重い税制を廃して四公六民の租税を定め領民は歓喜し、伊豆一国は30日で平定された」と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He abolished the complicated and heavy tax system and replaced it with the Shiko-Rokumin system, which pleased the residents and brought peace to Land of Izu in 30 days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He abolished the complicated and heavy tax system and replaced it with the Shiko-Rokumin system (which allowed farmers to keep 60% of their crop) which pleased the residents and brought peace to the Province of Izu in 30 days.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;Land&quot;→&quot;the Province&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He abolished the complicated and heavy tax system and replaced it with the Shiko-Rokumin system (which allowed farmers to keep 60% of their crop) which pleased the residents and brought peace to the Province of Izu in 30 days.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="91">
<j>軍記物語などでは自害したと言われる茶々丸は史書においては堀越御所から逃亡しており、武田氏、関戸氏、狩野氏、土肥氏らに擁せられて早雲に数年に渡って抵抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chachamaru committed suicide according to the war chronicles, but other historical document claim that he had escaped from Horigoe Palace and resisted Soun for a period of several years followed by the Takeda, Sekido, Kano and Dohi clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chachamaru committed suicide according to the war chronicles, but other historical document claim that he had escaped from Horigoe Palace and resisted Soun for a period of several years followed by the Takeda, Sekido, Kano and Dohi clans.</e>
<cmt>Added explanation of &quot;Shiko-Rokumin system&quot; and quote marks</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chachamaru committed suicide according to the war chronicles, but other historical document claim that he had escaped from Horigoe Palace and resisted Soun for a period of several years followed by the Takeda, Sekido, Kano and Dohi clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>早雲は伊豆の国人を味方につけながら茶々丸方を徐々に追い込み、明応7年（1497年）に南伊豆の深根城を落として、5年かかってようやく伊豆国を平定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While gathering allies from Izu, Soun slowly drove Chachamaru into a corner, and five years later in 1497, he took over Fukane-jo Castle in South Izu, finally bringing peace to the land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While gathering allies from Izu, Soun slowly drove Chachamaru into a corner, and five years later in 1497, he took over Fukane-jo Castle in South Izu, finally bringing peace to the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While gathering allies from Izu, Soun slowly drove Chachamaru into a corner, and five years later in 1497, he took over Fukane-jo Castle in South Izu, finally bringing peace to the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="93">
<j>伊豆国の平定をする一方で、早雲は今川氏の武将としての活動も行っており、明応3年（1494年）頃から今川氏の兵を指揮して遠江国へ侵攻して、中遠まで制圧している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While working for peace in Izu, Soun was active as a war lord for the Imagawa clan, commanding the Imagawa force in the invasion of Totoumi, conquering land as far as the Chuen area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While working for peace in Izu, Soun was active as a war lord for the Imagawa clan, commanding the Imagawa forces during the invasion of Totoumi and conquering land as far as the Chuen area.</e>
<cmt>&quot;force in&quot;→&quot;forces during&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While working for peace in Izu, Soun was active as a war lord for the Imagawa clan, commanding the Imagawa forces during the invasion of Totomi and conquering land as far as the Chuen area.</e>
<cmt>Totoumi→Totomi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>早雲と氏親は連携して領国を拡大していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Soun and Ujichika allied themselves and expanded their lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Soun and Ujichika allied themselves and continued expanding their territories.</e>
<cmt>&quot;expanded their lands&quot;→&quot;continued expanding their territories&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Soun and Ujichika allied themselves and continued expanding their territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>小田原城奪取</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Capture of Odawara-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Capture of Odawara-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Capture of Odawara-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>二本の大きな杉の木を鼠が根本から食い倒し、やがて鼠は虎に変じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two large cedar trees are eaten at the root by a rat, and the rat turns into a tiger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two large cedar trees are eaten at the root by a rat, and the rat turns into a tiger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two large cedar trees are eaten at the root by a rat, and the rat turns into a tiger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>という霊夢を早雲が見たという話が『北条記』に書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is written in the &quot;Hojoki&quot; that Soun dreamt such a strange dream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Hojoki&quot; records that Soun dreamt such a strange dream.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;It is written in&quot;Added &quot;records&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Hojoki&quot; records that Soun dreamt such a strange dream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>二本の杉とは関東管領の山内上杉氏と扇谷上杉氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two cedar trees signified Yamauchi-Uesugi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi, government officials in Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two cedar trees signified Yamauchi-Uesugi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi, government officials in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two cedar trees signified Yamauchi-Uesugi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi, government officials in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>鼠とは子の年生まれの早雲のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rat was Soun who was born in the year of the rat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rat was Soun, who was born in the Year of the Rat.</e>
<cmt>Added commaCapitalized &apos;y&apos; and &apos;r&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rat was Soun, who was born in the Year of the Rat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="99">
<j>明応3年（1494年）関東では山内上杉氏と扇谷上杉氏の抗争（長享の乱）が再燃し、上杉定正は早雲に援軍を依頼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1494, a battle took place between Yamauchi-Uesugi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clans, and Sadamasa UESUGI requested reinforcement from Soun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1494, a battle took place between the Yamauchi-Uesugi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi Clans, and Sadamasa UESUGI requested reinforcement from Soun.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1494, a battle took place between the Yamauchi-Uesugi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clans, and Sadamasa UESUGI requested reinforcement from Soun.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>定正と早雲は荒川 (関東)で上杉顕定の軍と対峙するが、定正が落馬して死去したことにより、早雲は兵を返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadamasa and Soun fought Akisada UESUGI&apos;s troops at the Ara-kawa River (Kanto), where Sadamasa fell off his horse and died, and Soun returned with his troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadamasa and Soun fought Akisada UESUGI&apos;s troops at the Ara-kawa River (Kanto) but when Sadamasa fell off his horse and died, Soun returned with his troops.</e>
<cmt>&quot;, where&quot;→&quot;but when&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadamasa and Soun fought Akisada UESUGI&apos;s troops at the Ara-kawa River (Kanto) but when Sadamasa fell off his horse and died, Soun returned with his troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="101">
<j>扇谷上杉氏は相模国の三浦氏と大森氏を支柱としていたが、この年に、それぞれの当主である扇谷上杉定正、三浦時高、大森氏頼の三人が死去するという不運に見舞われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan had allied itself with the Miura and Omori clans of Sagami; and in this year, misfortune struck.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogigayatsu-Uesugi Clan had allied itself with the Miura and Omori Clans of Sagami but</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Deleted &quot;; and in this year, misfortune struck.&quot; - this clause comes at the end of the Japanese sentence so moved it to next cell.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan had allied itself with the Miura and Omori clans of Sagami but in the same year, misfortune struck when the heads of the three clans, Sadamasa OGIGAYATSU-UESUGI, Tokitaka MIURA and Ujiyori OMORI all passed away.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan一文にまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="102">
<j>早雲は茶々丸の討伐・捜索を大義名分として、明応4年（1495年）に甲斐国に攻め込み、守護武田信縄と戦っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using the search for Chachamaru as cover, Soun attacked the Province of Kai and fought against Nobutsuna TAKEDA, the guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using the search for Chachamaru as cover, Soun attacked the Province of Kai and fought against the governor, Nobutsuna TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;the governor&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using the search for Chachamaru as cover, Soun attacked the Province of Kai and fought against the governor, Nobutsuna TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>同年9月、相模国小田原市の大森藤頼を討ち小田原城を奪取した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of the same year, he subjugated Fujiyori OMORI in Odawara City, the Province of Sugami, and captured Odawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of the same year, he defeated Fujiyori OMORI at Odawara City in the Province of Sugami, and captured Odawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot;→&quot;at&quot;&quot;,&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;subjugated&quot;→&quot;defeated&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September of the same year, he defeated Fujiyori OMORI at Odawara City in the Province of Sugami, and captured Odawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="104">
<j>『北条記』によれば、早雲は大森藤頼にたびたび進物を贈るようになり、最初は警戒していた藤頼も心を許して早雲と親しく歓談するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hojoki,&quot; Soun sent gifts to Fujiyori OMORI from time to time, and the Fujimori who was at first on guard became cordial and held friendly talks with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Hojoki,&quot; Soun sent gifts to Fujiyori OMORI from time to time and Fujimori, who was at first on guard, became cordial and held friendly talks with him.</e>
<cmt>Deleted comma and &quot;the&quot;Added commas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Hojoki,&quot; Soun sent gifts to Fujiyori OMORI from time to time and Fujiyori, who was at first on guard, became cordial and held friendly talks with him.</e>
<cmt>Fujimori→Fujiyori</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>ある日、早雲は箱根山での鹿狩りのために領内に勢子を入れさせて欲しいと願い、藤頼は快く許した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, Soun requested to bring in beaters to Fujiyori&apos;s land for deer hunting at Mt. Hakone, which Fujiyori graciously agreed to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, Soun requested to bring in beaters to Fujiyori&apos;s land for deer hunting at Mt. Hakone, which Fujiyori graciously agreed to.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, Soun requested to bring in beaters to Fujiyori&apos;s land for deer hunting at Mt. Hakone, which Fujiyori graciously agreed to.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>早雲は屈強の兵を勢子に仕立てて箱根山に入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun brought his strongest troops to Mt. Hakone and dispatched them as beaters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun brought his strongest troops to Mt. Hakone and dispatched them as beaters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun brought his strongest troops to Mt. Hakone and dispatched them as beaters.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>その夜、千頭の牛の角に松明を灯した早雲の兵が小田原城へ迫り、勢子に扮して背後の箱根山に伏せていた兵たちが鬨の声を上げて火を放つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That night, Soun&apos;s troops attached torches to the horns of 1,000 cows and attacked Odawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That night, Soun&apos;s troops, who had dressed as beaters and hidden on Mt. Hakone, attached torches to the horns of 1,000 cows and, as they neared Odawara-jo Castle,</e>
<cmt>Mixed this sentence and next one to remake one sentence.Added &quot;who had dressed as beaters and hidden on Mt. Hakone&quot;&quot;attacked&quot;→&quot;as they neared&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That night, Soun&apos;s troops, who had dressed as beaters and hidden on Mt. Hakone, attached torches to the horns of 1,000 cows and, as they neared Odawara-jo Castle, they let out a battle cry and set fire to the castle.</e>
<cmt>OK一文にまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>数万の兵が攻め寄せてきたと、おびえた小田原城は大混乱になり、藤頼は命からがら逃げ出して、早雲は易々と小田原城を手に入れたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thinking that an army of tens of thousands of soldiers came to attack Odawara-jo Castle, the castle was thrown into chaos, Fujiyori abandoned the castle and Soun easily captured it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thinking that an army of tens of thousands of soldiers was attacking, the castle was thrown into chaos, Fujiyori barely escaped with his life and Soun easily captured it.</e>
<cmt>&quot;came to attack&quot;→&quot;was attacking&quot;Deleted &quot;Odawara-jo Castle&quot;&quot;abandoned the castle&quot;→&quot;barely escaped with his life&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thinking that an army of tens of thousands of soldiers was attacking, the castle was thrown into chaos, Fujiyori barely escaped with his life and Soun easily captured it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>典型的な城盗りの物語で、似たような話は織田信秀の那古野城奪取、尼子経久の月山富田城奪取にもあり、どこまで真実か分らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is typical of the stories told about capturing castles, and similar stories exist including Nobuhide ODA&apos;s capture of Nagoya-jo Castle and Tsunehisa AMAGO&apos;s capture of Gassantoda-jo Castle, though it remains unknown whether these incidents actually occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is typical of the stories told about capturing castles, and similar stories exist about Nobuhide ODA&apos;s capture of Nagoya-jo Castle and Tsunehisa AMAGO&apos;s capture of Gassantoda-jo Castle, though how much is true remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>&quot;including&quot;→&quot;about&quot;&quot;whether these incidents actually occurred&quot;→&quot;how much is true&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is typical of the stories told about capturing castles, and similar stories exist about Nobuhide ODA&apos;s capture of Nagoya-jo Castle and Tsunehisa AMAGO&apos;s capture of Gassantoda-jo Castle, although how much is true remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>though→althoughに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="110">
<j>この小田原城奪取は明応4年（1495年）9月とされているが、史料によって年月が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The capture of Odawara-jo Castle is commonly known to have taken place in September of 1495, but the date differs according to different historical documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The capture of Odawara-jo Castle is commonly thought to have taken place in September of 1495, but the date differs according to different historical documents.</e>
<cmt>&quot;known &quot;→&quot;thought&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The capture of Odawara-jo Castle is commonly thought to have taken place in September of 1495, but the date differs according to different historical documents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>黒田基樹は明応5年（1496年）に山内上杉氏が小田原城と思われる要害を攻撃し、扇谷上杉方の守備側の名に大森藤頼と早雲の弟伊勢弥次郎の名が山内上杉顕定の書状にあったことを根拠に年次に疑問を呈し、それ以降のことではないかとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historian Motoki KURODA questions the date on account of Akisada Yamauchi-Uesugi&apos;s letter, in which it is written that Yamauchi-Uesugi clan attacked a stronghold thought to be the Odawara-jo Castle in 1496, and listed among the forces with Ogigayatsu-Uesugi were Fujiyori OMORI and Soun&apos;s younger brother Yajiro ISE; therefore, Soun&apos;s capture of Odawara-jo Castle must have occurred thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historian Motoki KURODA questions the date on account of Akisada YAMAUCHI-UESUGI&apos;s letter, in which it is written that the Yamauchi-Uesugi Clan attacked a stronghold thought to be Odawara-jo Castle in 1496, and listed among the forces with the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi were Fujiyori OMORI and Soun&apos;s younger brother Yajiro ISE; therefore, Soun&apos;s capture of Odawara-jo Castle must have occurred thereafter.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &quot;Yamauchi-Uesugi&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &quot;c&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historian Motoki KURODA questions the date on account of Akisada YAMAUCHI-UESUGI&apos;s letter, in which it is written that the Yamauchi-Uesugi clan attacked a stronghold thought to be Odawara-jo Castle in 1496, and listed among the forces with the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi were Fujiyori OMORI and Soun&apos;s younger brother Yajiro ISE; therefore, Soun&apos;s capture of Odawara-jo Castle must have occurred thereafter.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>また、明応10年3月28日_(旧暦)（文亀元年/1501年）に早雲が小田原城下にあった伊豆山神社の所有地を自領の1ヶ村と交換した文書が残されており、この時点では早雲が小田原城を既に領有していたとみられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a document stating that on March 28, 1501, Soun exchanged one of the villages he ruled for the land on which Izusan-jinja Shrine stood and which was under the jurisdiction of Odawara-jo Castle, meaning that Soun was already ruling over Odawara-jo Castle at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a document stating that on March 28, 1501, Soun exchanged one of the villages he ruled for the land on which Izusan-jinja Shrine stood and which was under the jurisdiction of Odawara-jo Castle, meaning that Soun was already ruling over Odawara-jo Castle at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a document stating that on April 25, 1501, Soun exchanged one of the villages he ruled for the land on which Izusan-jinja Shrine stood and which was under the jurisdiction of Odawara-jo Castle, meaning that Soun was already ruling over Odawara-jo Castle at that time.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="113">
<j>小田原城は後に後北条氏の本城となるが、早雲は終生、伊豆国の韮山城を居城としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Odawara-jo Castle later became the Go-Hojo clan&apos;s main castle, and Soun lived in Nirayama-jo Castle in Izu throughout his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Odawara-jo Castle later became the Go-Hojo clan&apos;s main castle but Soun lived in Nirayama-jo Castle in Izu throughout his life.</e>
<cmt>&quot;, and&quot;→&quot;but&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Odawara-jo Castle later became the Go-Hojo clan&apos;s main castle but Soun lived in Nirayama-jo Castle in Izu throughout his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="114">
<j>小田原城奪取など、早雲の一連の行動は、茶々丸討伐という目的だけでなく、自らの勢力範囲を拡大しようとする意図もあったと見られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun&apos;s actions, including the capture of Odawara-jo Castle, were taken not only for the objective of subjugating Chachamaru, but also to expand his own power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun&apos;s actions, including the capture of Odawara-jo Castle, were taken not only to defeat Chachamaru, but also to expand his own power.</e>
<cmt>&quot;for the objective of subjugating&quot;→&quot;to defeat&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun&apos;s actions, including the capture of Odawara-jo Castle, were taken not only to defeat Chachamaru, but also to expand his own power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>だが近年の研究では義澄-細川政元-今川氏親-早雲のラインと、足利義稙-大内政弘-足利茶々丸-武田信虎のライン、即ち明応の政変による対立構図の中での軍事行動であることが明らかになってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent studies, it has become clear that they were military measures that took advantage of the conflicting structure of Yoshizumi-Masamoto HOSOKAWA-Ujichika IMAGAWA- Soun line and Yoshitane ASHIKAGA-Chachamaru ASHIKAGA-Nobutora TAKEDA from political changes in Meio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent studies, it has become clear that they were part of military maneuvering between the two sides involved in the Meio Coup.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence and deleted the lists of names, which were a bit confusing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent studies, it has become clear that they were part of military maneuvering between the two sides involved in the Meio Coup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>小田原城奪取も、藤頼が義稙ラインの山内上杉氏に寝返った為のものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The capture of Odawara-jo Castle, too, was thought to be the result of Fujiyori selling out to the Yamauchi-Uesugi clan in the Yoshitane line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The capture of Odawara-jo Castle, too, was thought to be the result of Fujiyori selling out to the Yamauchi-Uesugi Clan, who were backing Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &quot;c&quot;&quot;in the Yoshitane line&quot;→&quot;who were backing Yoshitane&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The capture of Odawara-jo Castle, too, was thought to be the result of Fujiyori selling out to the Yamauchi-Uesugi clan, who were backing Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>最終的に、明応8年（1498年）、早雲は甲斐国で茶々丸を捕捉し、殺害することに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, in 1498, Soun succeeded in capturing and killing Chachamaru in the Province of Kai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, in 1498, Soun succeeded in capturing and killing Chachamaru in the Province of Kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, in 1498, Soun succeeded in capturing and killing Chachamaru in the Province of Kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>討った場所については、伊豆国の深根城とする説も有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another popular theory is that Soun killed Chachamaru at Fukane-jo Castle in Izu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another popular theory is that Soun killed Chachamaru at Fukane-jo Castle in Izu.</e>
<cmt>Added full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another popular theory is that Soun killed Chachamaru at Fukane-jo Castle in Izu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="119">
<j>今川氏の武将としての活動も続き、文亀年間（1501年-1504年）には三河国にまで進んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warlord Imagawa continued advancing as far as the Province of Mikawa between the years 1501 and 1504.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an Imagawa Clan commander, Soun continued advancing as far as the Province of Mikawa between the years 1501 and 1504.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Warlord Imagawa&quot;→&quot;As an Imagawa Clan commander, Soun&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an Imagawa clan commander, Soun continued advancing as far as the Province of Mikawa between the years 1501 and 1504.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>『柳営秘鑑』によると文亀元年（1501年）9月、岩津城下にて松平長親（徳川家康の先祖）と戦って敗北し、三河侵攻は失敗に終わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Ryuei Hikan (Historical record of Edo Bakufu)&quot; Imagawa fought against Nagachika MATSUDAIRA near Iwadu-jo Castle and lost, and his attempt to invade Mikawa ended in failure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Ryuei Hikan (Historical record of the Edo Bakufu),&quot; in September, 1501, he was defeated by Nagachika MATSUDAIRA near Iwadu-jo Castle and his attempt to invade Mikawa ended in failure.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; and &quot;in September, 1501&quot;&quot;Imagawa&quot;→&quot;he&quot;&quot;fought against&quot;,&quot;and lost&quot;→&quot;was defeated by&quot;Deleted comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Ryuei Hikan&quot; (Historical record of the Edo Bakufu), in October 1501, he was defeated by Nagachika MATSUDAIRA near Iwadu-jo Castle and his attempt to invade Mikawa ended in failure.</e>
<cmt>書物の説明を移動グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>松平方の先陣の酒井氏、本多氏、大久保氏の働きがあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsudaira&apos;s successful defense was due to the support of the Sakai, Honda and Okubo clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsudaira&apos;s successful defense was due to the support of the Sakai, Honda and Okubo Clans.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &quot;c&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsudaira&apos;s successful defense was due to the support of the Sakai, Honda and Okubo clans.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>ただし、徳川実紀では、永正3年（1506年）8月20日のこととされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the historical record of Tokugawa, the incident took place on August 20, 1506.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to the historical records of the Tokugawa, the incident took place on August 20, 1506.</e>
<cmt>&quot;In&quot;→&quot;However, according to&quot;Made &quot;record&quot; pluralAdded &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to the historical records of the Tokugawa, the incident took place on September 17, 1506.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>相模平定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subjugation of Sagami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subjugation of Sagami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subjugation of Sagami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="123">
<j>その後、早雲は相模方面へ本格的に転進し、関東南部の制圧に乗り出したが、茶々丸討伐の名目を失ったため、この後の軍事行動には多大な困難が伴った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Soun changed his direction toward Sagami aiming for control of the South Kanto area; however because he had lost his pretext of subjugating Chachamaru, his military actions involved much hardship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Soun changed his direction and headed toward Sagami, aiming for control of the South Kanto area but struggled in his campaigns because he had lost his pretext of subjugating Chachamaru, his military actions involved much hardship.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;and headed&quot;&quot;; however&quot;→&quot;but&quot;&quot;his military actions involved much hardship&quot;→&quot;struggled in his campaigns&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Soun changed his direction and headed toward Sagami, aiming for control of the South Kanto area but struggled in his campaigns because he had lost his pretext of subjugating Chachamaru, his military actions involved much hardship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>更に、伊豆・西相模を失った山内上杉顕定による離間策により氏親・早雲は義澄・政元と断絶されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Akisada Yamauchi-Uesugi, who had lost his land of Izu and West Sagami, schemed to cut Ujichika and Soun&apos;s ties with Yoshizumi and Masamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Akisada YAMAUCHI-UESUGI, who had lost his land of Izu and West Sagami, schemed to cut Ujichika and Soun&apos;s ties with Yoshizumi and Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &quot;Yamauchi-Uesugi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Akisada YAMAUCHI-UESUGI, who had lost his land of Izu and West Sagami, schemed to cut Ujichika and Soun&apos;s ties with Yoshizumi and Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>この事によって政治的な立場が弱くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence his political power stood on shaky ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was therefore in a politically weak position.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was therefore in a politically weak position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="126">
<j>それでも早雲は今川氏の援助を受けながら、今度は義稙-大内ラインに与し、徐々に相模に勢力を拡大していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of this, Soun then connected himself to the Yoshitane-Ouchi line, expanding his power with support from the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of this, Soun, with support from the Imagawa Clan, aligned himself with the Yoshitane-Ouchi faction, and slowly expanded his power in Sagami.</e>
<cmt>&quot;connected himself to&quot;→&quot;aligned himself with&quot;&quot;line&quot;→&quot;faction&quot;&quot;expanding his power&quot;→&quot;slowly expanded his power in Sagami&quot;Moved &quot;with support from the Imagawa Clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of this, Soun, with support from the Imagawa clan, aligned himself with the Yoshitane-Ouchi faction, and slowly expanded his power in Sagami.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>こうした関東進出の大きな画期となったのは、永正元（1504年）8月の武蔵国立河原の戦いであり、上杉朝良に味方した早雲は、今川氏親とともに出陣して山内上杉顕定に勝利した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The event that triggered his movement to the Kanto area was the Battle of the Province of Musashi in August of 1504, in which Soun, on the side of Tomoyoshi UESUGI, fought with Ujichika IMAGAWA and defeated Akisada Yamauchi-Uesugi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The event that triggered his movement to the Kanto area was the Battle of Tachigawara in the Province of Musashi in August of 1504, in which Soun, on the side of Tomoyoshi UESUGI, fought with Ujichika IMAGAWA and defeated Akisada YAMAUCHI-UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;Tachigawara in&quot; Capitalized &quot;Yamauchi-Uesugi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The event that triggered his movement to the Kanto area was the Battle of Tachigawara in the Province of Musashi in September of 1504, in which Soun, on the side of Tomoyoshi UESUGI, fought with Ujichika IMAGAWA and defeated Akisada YAMAUCHI-UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="128">
<j>この敗戦後に山内上杉顕定は越後上杉氏の来援を得て反撃に出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the defeat, Akisada gained support from the Echigo-Uesugi clan and rebelled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the defeat, Akisada, with support from the Echigo-Uesugi Clan, launched a counterattack.</e>
<cmt>&quot;gained&quot;→&quot;, with&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;&quot;and rebelled&quot;→&quot;launched a counterattack&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the defeat, Akisada, with support from the Echigo-Uesugi clan, launched a counterattack.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>相模国へ乱入して、扇谷上杉氏の諸城を攻略。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He broke into Sagami and captured Yamauchi-Uesugi&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He invaded Sagami and captured several of the Ougigayatsu-Uesugi Clan&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt>&quot;broke into&quot;→&quot;invaded&quot;&quot;Yamauchi&quot;→&quot;Ougigayatsu&quot;Added &quot;several of the&quot;, &quot;Clan&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He invaded Sagami and captured several of the Ougigayatsu-Uesugi clan&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>翌永正2年（1505年）、河越城に追い込まれた上杉朝良は降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1502, Tomoyoshi UESUGI was driven to Kawagoe-jo Castle, where he announced his surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1502, Tomoyoshi UESUGI was driven to Kawagoe-jo Castle, where he announced his surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1502, Tomoyoshi UESUGI was driven to Kawagoe-jo Castle, where he announced his surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>これにより、早雲は山内上杉氏、扇谷上杉氏の両上杉と敵対することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this, Soun became the enemy of both the Yamauchi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this, Soun became the enemy of both the Yamauchi-Uesugi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi Clans.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;-Uesugi&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this, Soun became the enemy of both the Yamauchi-Uesugi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clans.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="132">
<j>（1509年）以降は早雲の今川氏の武将としての活動はほとんど見られなくなり、早雲は相模進出に集中する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1509 and thereafter, Soun&apos;s activity as Imagawa clan warlord quieted down, and he concentrating on his move into Sagami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1509 onwards, Soun&apos;s activity as an Imagawa commander quietened down, and he concentrated on his move into Sagami.</e>
<cmt>&quot;In 1509 and thereafter&quot;→&quot;From 1509 onwards&quot;Added &quot;an&quot;&quot;clan warlord&quot;→&quot;commander&quot;&quot;concentrating&quot;→&quot;concentrated&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1509 onwards, Soun&apos;s activity as an Imagawa commander quietened down, and he concentrated on his move into Sagami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>永正3年（1506年）に相模国で検地を初めて実施して支配の強化を図っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1506, he surveyed Sagami for the first time aiming to exhibit the strength of his authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1506, he carried out the first survey of Sagami, aiming to strengthen his authority.</e>
<cmt>&quot;surveyed Sagami for the first time&quot;→&quot;carried out he first survey of Sagami,&quot;&quot;to exhibit the strength of&quot;→&quot;to strengthen&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1506, he carried out the first survey of Sagami, aiming to strengthen his authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="134">
<j>永正4年（1505年）、管領細川政元が暗殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1505, Official Masamoto Hosokawa was assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1505, Kanrei Masamoto Hosokawa was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>&quot;official&quot;→&quot;Kanrei&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1505, Kanrei Masamoto HOSOKAWA was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>Hosokawa→HOSOKAWA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>同年、顕定の弟で越後守護上杉房能が守護代の長尾為景（上杉謙信の父）に殺される事件が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Akisada&apos;s younger brother Fusayoshi UESUGI, who was the guard in Echigo, was killed by deputy guard Tamekage NAGAO (the father of Kenshin UESUGI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Akisada&apos;s younger brother, Fusayoshi UESUGI, who was the Shugo of Echigo, was killed by the deputy Shugo, Tamekage NAGAO (the father of Kenshin UESUGI).</e>
<cmt>Added comma&quot;guard in&quot;→&quot;Shugo of&quot;&quot;guard&quot;→&quot;Shugo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Akisada&apos;s younger brother, Fusayoshi UESUGI, who was the Shugo of Echigo, was killed by the deputy Shugo, Tamekage NAGAO (the father of Kenshin UESUGI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>早雲は為景と結んで顕定を牽制した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together Soun and Tamekage restrained Akisada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together Soun and Tamekage restrained Akisada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together Soun and Tamekage restrained Akisada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="137">
<j>永正6年（1509年）7月、顕定は大軍を率いて越後国へ出陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July of 1509, Akisada went into a battle in the Province of Echigo leading a huge force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July of 1509, Akisada led a huge force into battle in the Province of Echigo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;leading&quot;→&quot;led&quot;&quot;went&quot;→&quot;led a huge force&quot;Deleted &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July of 1509, Akisada led a huge force into battle in the Province of Echigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>同年8月、この隙を突いて早雲は扇谷上杉朝良の本拠江戸城に迫った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August of the same year, while Akisada was in Echigo, Soun attacked Tomoyoshi Ogigayatsu-Uesugi&apos;s home ground Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August of the same year, while Akisada was in Echigo, Soun attacked Tomoyoshi OGIGAYATSU-UESUGI&apos;s base, Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &quot;Ogigayatsu-Uesugi&quot;&quot;home ground&quot;→&quot;base&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August of the same year, while Akisada was in Echigo, Soun attacked Tomoyoshi OGIGAYATSU-UESUGI&apos;s base, Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>上野国に出陣していた朝良は兵を返して反撃に出て、翌永正7年（1510年）まで早雲と武蔵国、相模国で戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoyoshi, who had been fighting in the Province of Ueno, returned and revolted, and Tomoyoshi and Soun&apos;s troops fought against each other in Sagami until 1510.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoyoshi, who had been fighting in the Province of Ueno, returned and counterattacked, fighting against Soun in Sagami until 1510.</e>
<cmt>&quot;revolted&quot;→&quot;counterattacked&quot;&quot;and Tomoyoshi and Soun&apos;s troops fought against each other&quot;→&quot;fighting against Soun&apos;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoyoshi, who had been fighting in the Province of Ueno, returned and counterattacked, fighting against Soun in Sagami until 1510.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>早雲は権現山城（横浜市）の上田政盛を扇谷上杉氏から離反させ攻勢に出るが、同年7月になって山内上杉氏と扇谷上杉氏が反撃に出て、権現山城は落城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun alienated Masamori UEDA, at Gongenyama-jo Castle, from the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan and attacked the castle; and in July of the same year, the forces of the Uesugi clans of Yamauchi and Ogigayatsu captured Gongenyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun cut off Masamori UEDA, at Gongenyama-jo Castle, from the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi Clan and attacked the castle but in July of the same year, the forces of the Yamauchi and Ogigayatsu Uesugi Clans captured Gongenyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>&quot;alienated&quot;→&quot;cut off&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;&quot;; and&quot;→&quot;but&quot;Moved &quot;Yamauchi and Ogigayatsu&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun cut off Masamori UEDA, at Gongenyama-jo Castle, from the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan and attacked the castle but in August of the same year, the forces of the Yamauchi and Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clans captured Gongenyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan-補足グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>三浦義同（道寸）が早雲方の住吉要害（平塚市）を攻略して小田原城まで迫る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiatsu (Dosan) MIURA captured Sumiyoshi fortress (Hiratsuka City) and advanced on Odawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiatsu (Dosan) MIURA captured Sumiyoshi fortress (Hiratsuka City) and advanced on Odawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiatsu (Dosan) MIURA captured Sumiyoshi fortress (Hiratsuka City) and advanced on Odawara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>早雲は手痛い敗北を喫し、扇谷上杉氏との和睦をして切り抜けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun experienced a severe defeat, getting out of this ordeal by making peace with the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun experienced a severe defeat, getting out of this ordeal by making peace with the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun experienced a severe defeat, getting out of this ordeal by making peace with the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>一方、同年6月には越後国に出陣していた顕定は長尾為景の逆襲を受けて敗死してしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June of the same year, Akisada, who had been in the Province of Echigo, was attacked and killed by Tamekage NAGAO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year, Akisada, who had been in the Province of Echigo, was attacked and killed by Tamekage NAGAO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July of the same year, Akisada, who had been in the Province of Echigo, was attacked and killed by Tamekage NAGAO.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="144">
<j>三浦氏は相模国の名族で源頼朝の挙兵に参じ、鎌倉幕府創立の功臣として大きな勢力を有していたが、嫡流は執権の北条氏に宝治合戦で滅ぼされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Miura clan was a powerful family in Sagami, who joined Yoritomo MINAMOTO force and given the power as a meritorious retainer for the establishment of Kamakura Shogunate; however, the direct line of Minamoto had been overthrown by the Hojo clan in the battle of Hoji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Miura Clan had been a powerful family in Sagami, fighting for Yoritomo MINAMOTO and becoming extremely powerful retainers of the early Kamukura Shogunate but the direct line had been overthrown by the Hojo Clan in the Battle of Hoji.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was&quot;→&quot;had been&quot;&quot;who joined Yoritomo MINAMOTO force&quot;→&quot;fighting for Yoritomo MINAMOTO&quot;&quot;given the power as a meritorious retainer for the establishment of Kamakura Shogunate&quot;→&quot;becoming extremely powerful retainers of the early Kamukura Shogunate&quot;&quot;; however&quot;→&quot;but&quot;Deleted &quot;of Minamoto&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos; and &apos;b&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miura clan had been a powerful family in Sagami, fighting for MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and becoming extremely powerful retainers of the early Kamukura Shogunate but the direct line had been overthrown by the Hojo clan in the Battle of Hoji.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan源頼朝→MINAMOTO no Yoritomo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>しかし、傍流は相模国の豪族として続き、相模国で大きな力を持っていた（相模三浦氏）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the indirect line maintained its power in Sagami (Sagami-Miura clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the indirect line maintained its power in Sagami (Sagami-Miura clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the indirect line maintained its power in Sagami (Sagami-Miura clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="146">
<j>この頃の三浦氏は扇谷上杉氏に属し、同氏の出身で当主の三浦義同（道寸）が相模中央部の岡崎城 (相模国)（現伊勢原市）を本拠とし、三浦半島の三崎城（現三浦市（軍記物などには新井城とある）を子の三浦義意が守っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At about this time, the Miura clan belonged to the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi group, Yoshiatsu (Dosan) MIURA based himself at the Okazaki-jo Castle (Province of Sagami) located in the central area of Sagami, and Yoshioki MIURA, the son of Yoshiatsu, based himself at the Misaki-jo Castle (present day Miura City (also called Arai-jo Castle in a war chronicle)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At about this time, the Miura clan belonged to the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi group, with Yoshiatsu (Dosan) MIURA based at Okazaki-jo Castle in central Sagami, and Yoshioki MIURA, the son of Yoshiatsu, based at Misaki-jo Castle (also called Arai-jo Castle in the war chronicles) in present-day Miura City.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;with&quot;Deleted &quot;himself&quot;, &quot;the&quot;, &quot;(Province of Sagami)&quot;, &quot;located&quot;, &quot;the&quot;, &quot;area of&quot;Moved &quot;(also called Arai-jo Castle in a war chronicle)&quot;&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;Made &quot;chronicle&quot; pluralRemoved bracketsAdded &quot;in&quot; and hyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At about this time, the Miura clan belonged to the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi group, with Yoshiatsu (Dosan) MIURA based at Okazaki-jo Castle in central Sagami, and Yoshioki MIURA, the son of Yoshiatsu, based at Misaki-jo Castle (also called Arai-jo Castle in the war chronicles) in present-day Miura City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>早雲の相模平定のためには、どうしても三浦氏を滅ぼさねばならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the subjugation of Sagami, Soun had destroyed the Miura clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to control Sagami, Soun had to destroy the Miura Clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;For the subjugation of &quot;→&quot;In order to control&quot;&quot;had destroyed&quot;→&quot;had to destroyl&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to control Sagami, Soun had to destroy the Miura clan.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="148">
<j>敗戦から体勢を立て直した早雲は、永正9年（1512年）8月に岡崎城を攻略し、三浦義同を住吉城（逗子市）に敗走させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the defeat, Soun regrouped his forces and captured Okazaki-jo Castle in August 1512, driving Yoshiatsu MIURA to Sumiyoshi-jo Castle (Zushi City).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his defeat, Soun regrouped his forces and captured Okazaki-jo Castle in August 1512, driving Yoshiatsu MIURA to Sumiyoshi-jo Castle (Zushi City).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his defeat, Soun regrouped his forces and captured Okazaki-jo Castle in September 1512, driving Yoshiatsu MIURA to Sumiyoshi-jo Castle (Zushi City).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除グレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>勢いに乗って住吉城も落とし、義同は義意の守る三崎城に逃げ込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of this momentum, Soun also captured Sumiyoshi-jo Castle, and Yoshiatsu escaped to Misaki-jo Castle, where Yoshioki resided.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of this momentum, Soun also captured Sumiyoshi-jo Castle, and Yoshiatsu escaped to Misaki-jo Castle, where Yoshioki resided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of this momentum, Soun also captured Sumiyoshi-jo Castle, and Yoshiatsu escaped to Misaki-jo Castle, where Yoshioki resided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>早雲は鎌倉に入り、相模の支配権をほぼ掌握する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun went to Kamakura, and assumed virtually all of the ruling authority over Sagami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun entered Kamakura and seized control of virtually all of Sagami.</e>
<cmt>&quot;went to&quot;→&quot;entered&quot;Deleted comma&quot;assumed virtually all of the ruling authority over&quot;→&quot;seized control of virtually all of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun entered Kamakura and seized control of virtually all of Sagami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>上杉朝興が江戸城から救援に駆けつけるが、早雲はこれを撃破する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomooki UESUGI led his troops to the rescue from Edo-jo Castle, and Soun counterattacked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomooki UESUGI led a relief force from Edo-jo Castle but was crushed by Soun.</e>
<cmt>&quot;his troops to the rescue&quot;→&quot;a relief force&quot;&quot;, and Soun counterattacked&quot;→&quot;but was crushed by Soun&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomooki UESUGI led a relief force from Edo-jo Castle but was crushed by Soun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>さらに三浦氏を攻略するため、同年10月、鎌倉に玉縄城を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to subjugate the MIURA clan, Soun built Tamanawa-jo Castle in Kamakura in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to subjugate the MIURA clan, Soun built Tamanawa-jo Castle in Kamakura in October of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to subjugate the Miura clan, Soun built Tamanawa-jo Castle in Kamakura in November of the same year.</e>
<cmt>MIURA→Miuraグレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="153">
<j>義同はしばしば兵を繰り出して早雲と戦火を交えるが、次第に圧迫され三浦半島に封じ込められてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiatsu attempted several times to defeat Soun, to no avail, gradually lost his power and was finally contained within the boundaries of the Miura Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiatsu led several unsuccessful attacks against Soun and was gradually pushed back until finally contained within the boundaries of the Miura Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>&quot;attempted&quot;→&quot;led&quot;&quot;times to defeat Soun, to no avail&quot;→&quot;unsuccessful attacks against Soun&quot;&quot;, gradually lost his power and was&quot;→&quot;and was gradually pushed back until&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiatsu led several unsuccessful attacks against Soun and was gradually pushed back until finally contained within the boundaries of the Miura Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>扇谷上杉氏も救援の兵を送るがことごとく撃退された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogigayatsu-Uesugi also sent rescue missions, which returned in defeat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogigayatsu-Uesugi Clan also sent relief forces, which returned in defeat.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;, &quot;Clan&quot;&quot;rescue missions&quot;→&quot;relief forces&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan also sent relief forces, which returned in defeat.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="155">
<j>永正13年（1516年）7月、扇谷上杉朝興が三浦氏救援のため玉縄城を攻めるが早雲はこれを打ち破り、義同・義意父子の篭る三崎城に攻め寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July of 1516, Tomooki Ogigayatsu-Uesugi attacked Tamanawa-jo Castle in support of the MIURA clan; however, Soun won and turned around to attack Misaki-jo Castle where Yoshiatsu and Yoshioki were hiding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July of 1516, Tomooki OGIGAYATSU-UESUGI attacked Tamanawa-jo Castle in support of the MIURA Clan but Soun crushed the assault and attacked Misaki-jo Castle, where Yoshiatsu and Yoshioki were hiding.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &quot;Ogigayatsu-Uesugi&quot;, &apos;c&apos;&quot;; however, Soun won and turned around to attack&quot;→&quot;but Soun crushed the assault and attacked&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August of 1516, Tomooki OGIGAYATSU-UESUGI attacked Tamanawa-jo Castle in support of the Miura clan but Soun crushed the assault and attacked Misaki-jo Castle, where Yoshiatsu and Yoshioki were hiding.</e>
<cmt>MIURA→MiuraClan→clanグレゴリオ歴に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>激戦の末に義同・義意父子は討ち死にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both father and son, Yoshiatsu and Yoshioki, died fighting in the fierce battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both father and son, Yoshiatsu and Yoshioki, died fighting in the fierce battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both father and son, Yoshiatsu and Yoshioki, died fighting in the fierce battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>名族三浦氏は滅び、早雲は相模全域を平定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the powerful Miura clan fell, Soun subjugated all of Sagami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the fall of the powerful Miura Clan, Soun controlled all of Sagami.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Once the powerful Miura clan fell&quot;→&quot;With the fall of the powerful Miura Clan&quot;&quot;&quot;subjugated&quot;→&quot;controlled&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the fall of the powerful Miura clan, Soun controlled all of Sagami.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="158">
<j>その後、早雲は上総国の小弓公方足利義明と武田氏を支援して、房総半島に渡り、翌永正14年（1517年）まで転戦している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Soun supported Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the Oyumi-kubo clan of the Province of Kazusa, and the Takeda clan, leading his troops to the Boso Peninsula and joining the battle until 1517.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Soun supported the Oyumi Kubo, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, of the Province of Kazusa and the Takeda clan, fighting on the Boso Peninsula until 1517.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;the Oyumi-kubo&quot;Deleted &quot;clan&quot; and comma&quot;leading his troops to the Boso Peninsula and joining the battle&quot;→&quot;fighting on the Boso Peninsula&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Soun supported the Oyumi Kubo, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, of the Province of Kazusa and the Takeda clan, fighting on the Boso Peninsula until 1517.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="159">
<j>永正15年（1518年）、家督を嫡男氏綱に譲り、翌永正16年（1519年）に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1518, Soun retired and put his son Ujitsuna at the head of the family, and he died in 1519.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1518, Soun retired, putting his son Ujitsuna at the head of the family, and he died in 1519.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and put&quot;→&quot;, putting&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1518, Soun retired, putting his son Ujitsuna at the head of the family, and he died in 1519.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>享年64または享年88。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was either 64 or 88 years old at the time of his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was either 64 or 88 years old at the time of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was either 64 or 88 years old at the time of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="161">
<j>早雲は、領国支配の強化を積極的に進めた最初期の大名であり、かつ伊豆一国を支配しながら室町幕府から正式な伊豆の守護として任じられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun is one of the first feudal lords who actively strengthened the rule of regional territories. He also ruled over Izu, yet he was never officially appointed to serve as the Muromachi Shogunate&apos;s representative..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun was one of the first feudal lords who actively strengthened the rule of regional territories and ruled over Izu, although he was never officially appointed to serve as the Muromachi Shogunate&apos;s representative..</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;was&quot;&quot;. He also&quot;→&quot;and&quot;&quot;yet&quot;→&quot;although&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun was one of the first feudal lords who actively strengthened the rule of regional territories and ruled over Izu, although he was never officially appointed to serve as the Muromachi Shogunate&apos;s representative..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>その点から、最初の戦国大名とも呼ばれている（当然、守護大名ではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this perspective, he is also known as the first warlord (not a lord of the guard).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this perspective, he is also known as the first Sengoku daimyo (as opposed to a Shugo daimyo).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Sengoku daimyo&quot;&quot;not a lord of the guard&quot;→&quot;as opposed to a Shugo daimyo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this perspective, he is also known as the first Sengoku daimyo (as opposed to a Shugo daimyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>『早雲寺殿廿一箇条』（そううんじどのにじゅういちかじょう）という家法を定め、これは分国法の祖形となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun established a family code known as the &quot;Sounjidono Nijuichikaijo&quot; which became the foundation for regional law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun established a family code known as the &quot;Sounjidono Nijuichikaijo,&quot; which became the foundation for regional law.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun established a family code known as the &quot;Sounjidono Nijuichikaijo,&quot; which became the foundation for regional law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>永正3年（1506年）に小田原周辺で指出検地（在地領主に土地面積・年貢量を申告させる検地）を実施しているが、これは、戦国大名による検地として最古の事例とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1506, Soun ordered an inspection of the land around Odawara (to determine the land area and for the declaration of taxes paid to regional ruling lords paid in rice and produce), and Soun&apos;s land inspection is considered to be the first performed by the warring lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1506, Soun ordered an inspection of the land around Odawara in order to determine its size and to decide land taxes paid by peasants, considered to be the first such inspection performed by a Sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt>Removed bracketsAdded &quot;in order&quot;&quot;the land area&quot;→&quot;its size&quot;&quot;for the declaration&quot;→&quot;to decide&quot;&quot;to regional ruling lords paid in rice and produce→&quot;paid by peasants&quot;Reworded last part of sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1506, Soun ordered an inspection of the land around Odawara in order to determine its size and to decide land taxes paid by peasants, considered to be the first such inspection performed by a Sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="165">
<j>また、死の前年から虎の印判状を用いるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About a year before his death, he started using Inbanjo (name stamps) instead of Kao (signatures)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About a year before his death, he started using Inbanjo (name stamps) instead of Kao (signatures).</e>
<cmt>Added full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About a year before his death, he started using Inbanjo (name stamps) instead of Kao (signatures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="166">
<j>早雲の後を継いだ氏綱は北条氏（後北条氏）を称して武蔵国へ領国を拡大。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujitsuna, who inherited Soun&apos;s land used the name Hojo (Go-hojo) and expanded his rule to the Province of Musashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujitsuna, who inherited Soun&apos;s land, used the name Hojo (Go-Hojo) and expanded his rule to the Province of Musashi.</e>
<cmt>Added commaCapitalized &apos;h&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujitsuna, who inherited Soun&apos;s land, used the name Hojo (Gohojo) and expanded his rule to the Province of Musashi.</e>
<cmt>Go-Hojo→Gohojo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>以後、北条氏康、北条氏政、北条氏直と勢力を伸ばし、五代に渡って関東に覇を唱えることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, together with Ujiyasu HOJO, Ujimasa HOJO and Ujinao HOJO, the Hojo clan increased its power and gained supremacy over the Kanto area for the subsequent five generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, under the leadership of Ujiyasu HOJO, Ujimasa HOJO and Ujinao HOJO, the Hojo Clan increased its power, dominating the Kanto area for five generations.</e>
<cmt>&quot;together with&quot;→&quot;under the leadership of&quot;&quot;and gained supremacy over&quot;→&quot;dominating&quot;Deleted &quot;the subsequent&quot; - it&apos;s 5 in total: Soun, his son and these 3</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, under the leadership of Ujiyasu HOJO, Ujimasa HOJO and Ujinao HOJO, the Hojo clan increased its power, dominating the Kanto area for five generations.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>早雲の出自と生年の論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Debate over the date and place of Soun&apos;s birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Debate over the date and place of Soun&apos;s birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Debate over the date and place of Soun&apos;s birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="168">
<j>既に老いの境に入った一介の伊勢国の浪人 (武士)が、妹が守護の愛妾となっていたのを頼りに駿河へ下って身を興し、後に関東を切り取る一代の梟雄北条早雲となる、というストーリーが従来小説などでよく描かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical novels often include the story of Soun HOJO as a master-less samurai in his later life who went to Suruga seeking help from his younger sister, a mistress to a Shogun guard, and rose to become the ruler of the Kanto area</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical novels often include the story of Soun HOJO as a masterless samurai in his later life, who went to Suruga seeking help from his younger sister, the governor&apos;s mistress, and rose to become the ruler of the Kanto area</e>
<cmt>Deleted hyphen&quot;a mistress to a Shogun guard&quot;→&quot;the governor&apos;s mistress&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical novels often include the story of Soun HOJO as a masterless samurai in his later life, who went to Suruga seeking help from his younger sister, the governor&apos;s mistress, and rose to become the ruler of the Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="169">
<j>江戸時代前期までは後北条氏は名門伊勢氏の出と考えられていた様子だが、江戸時代中期以降、『太閤記』の影響で戦国時代を身分の低い者が実力で身を興す「下克上の時代」ととらえる史観が民衆の願望もあいまって形成され,明治時代になって定着し、戦後まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apparently, the Go-hojo clan was thought to have originated from the Ise clan until the beginning of Edo Period; however, from Mid-Edo Period, a novel &quot;Taikoki&quot; came out, which revised Soun as a lowly samurai in the Warring State Period, who came to power through his achievements in the so called &quot;Gekokujo Period.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apparently, until the beginning of the Edo Period, the Go-Hojo Clan was thought to have originated from the Ise clan but from the mid-Edo Period, influenced by the &quot;Taikoki,&quot; a biography of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, the view of Soun as a lowly samurai in the Warring States Period, who came to power through his achievements in the so called &quot;Gekokujo Period&quot; caught the public&apos;s imagination,</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderCapitalized &apos;h&apos;, &apos;c&apos;&quot;; however&quot;→&quot;but&quot;&quot;Mid-Edo&quot;→&quot;the mid-Edo&quot;Rewrote sentence in order to remake it one with the next sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apparently, until the beginning of the Edo Period, the Gohojo clan was thought to have originated from the Ise clan but from the mid-Edo Period, influenced by the &quot;Taikoki,&quot; a biography of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, the view of Soun as a lowly samurai in the Warring States Period, who came to power through his achievements in the so called &apos;Gekokujo Period&apos; caught the public&apos;s imagination, becoming well-established in the Meiji Period and prevailing until the end of WWII.</e>
<cmt>Go-Hojo→GohojoClan→clan原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に一文にまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>その下克上の代表として北条早雲、斎藤道三、豊臣秀吉が語られ、早雲は身分の低い素浪人とすることが通説となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the historical figures presented as lowly samurai climbing up the social ladder are Soun HOJO, Dosan SAITO and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI; and Soun born as a lowly samurai became the conventional theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With stories told about lowly samurai, such as Soun HOJO, Dosan SAITO and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, climbing up the social ladder, it became common opinion that Soun was a low-born ronin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Some of the historical figures presented as&quot;→&quot;With stories told about&quot;&quot;are&quot;→&quot;such as&quot;Changed word order&quot;and Soun born as a lowly samurai became the conventional theory&quot;→&quot;it became common opinion that Soun was a low-born ronin&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With stories told about lowly samurai, such as Soun HOJO, Dosan SAITO and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, climbing up the social ladder, it became common opinion that Soun was a low-born ronin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>出自に関する論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Debate over place of birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Debate over place of birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Debate over place of birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="171">
<j>早雲の出自については長年明らかにならず、主なものに、大和国在原説、山城国宇治説、伊勢説、京都説、備中説があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun&apos;s place of birth remained unknown for a long time and some of the most accepted theories are that he came from Ariwara of the Province of Yamato, Uji in the Province of Yamashiro, Ise, Kyoto or Bitchu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun&apos;s place of birth remained unknown for a long time and some of the most accepted theories were that he came from Ariwara in Yamato Province, Uji in Yamashiro Province, Ise, Kyoto or Bitchu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;are&quot;→&quot;were&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;in&quot;Moved &quot;Province&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun&apos;s place of birth remained unknown for a long time and some of the most accepted theories were that he came from Ariwara in Yamato Province, Uji in Yamashiro Province, Ise, Kyoto or Bitchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="172">
<j>大和在原説と山城宇治説は『北条五代記』に異説として紹介されたもので有力視はされなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aiwara in Yamato Province and Uji in Yamashiro Province were two candidates introduced as divergent views in the &quot;Hojo Godaiki (History of 5 generations of the Hojo clan)&quot; but did not become prevailing theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aiwara in Yamato Province and Uji in Yamashiro Province were two candidates introduced as divergent views in the &quot;Hojo Godaiki (History of 5 generations of the Hojo clan)&quot; but did not become prevailing theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ariwara in Yamato Province and Uji in Yamashiro Province were two candidates introduced as divergent views in the &quot;Hojo Godaiki&quot; (History of 5 generations of the Hojo clan) but did not become prevailing theories.</e>
<cmt>書物の説明移動在原→Ａｒｉｗａｒａ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>伊勢説は『北条記』『相州兵乱記』に書かれており、早雲が信濃国守護小笠原定基に宛てた書状で「伊勢の関氏と同族である」と書いていたことを根拠に1901年に藤井継平が主張し、田中義成がこれを支持した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ise theory comes from the &quot;Hojoki&quot; and &quot;Soshu Heiranki,&quot; and asserted by a scholar, Tsugihei FUJII, with the reasoning that Soun sent a letter to Sadamoto OGASAWARA, guard for the Province of Shinano, that &quot;I belong to the same family as the Seki clan of Ise,&quot; which won the support of the historian, Yoshinari TANAKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ise theory, based on a letter Soun sent to Sadamoto OGASAWARA, Governor of Shinano Province, stating &quot;I belong to the same family as the Seki Clan of Ise,&quot; that appears in the &quot;Hojoki&quot; and the &quot;Soshu Heiranki,&quot; was advocated in 1901 by the scholar, Tsugihei FUJII, and supported by the historian, Yoshinari TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderDeleted &quot;and&quot;&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;&quot;asserted&quot;→&quot;advocated&quot;&quot;with the reasoning that Soun sent a letter&quot;→&quot;based on a letter Soun sent&quot;&quot;guard for the Province of Shinano&quot;→&quot;Governor of Shinano Province&quot;&quot;that&quot;→&quot;stating&quot;Added &quot;in 1901&quot;&quot;which won the support of&quot;→&quot;and supported by&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ise theory, based on a letter Soun sent to Sadamoto OGASAWARA, Governor of Shinano Province, stating &apos;I belong to the same family as the Seki Clan of Ise,&apos; that appears in the &quot;Hojoki&quot; and the &quot;Soshu Heiranki,&quot; was advocated in 1901 by the scholar, Tsugihei FUJII, and supported by the historian, Yoshinari TANAKA.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>これに対して渡辺世祐は『寛政重修諸家譜』などにある幕府政所執事の京都伊勢氏の出身で、伊勢貞親の弟伊勢貞藤またはその子供であろうとする京都説を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, another historian, Yosuke WATANABE, asserted that Soun originated from Kyoto-Ise clan, a steward for the Bakufu government as stated in the &quot;Kansei Choshushokafu,&quot; and Soun was the same person as Sadafuji ISE, Sadachika ISE&apos;s younger brother, or his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, another historian, Yosuke WATANABE, asserted that Soun originated from the Kyoto-Ise Clan, was a steward for the Bakufu government as stated in the &quot;Kansei Choshushokafu,&quot; and that Soun was either the same person as Sadafuji ISE, Sadachika ISE&apos;s younger brother, or his son.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added &quot;was&quot;, that&quot;, &quot;either&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, another historian, Yosuke WATANABE, asserted that Soun originated from the Kyoto-Ise clan, was a steward for the Bakufu government as stated in the &quot;Kansei Choshushokafu,&quot; and that Soun was either the same person as Sadafuji ISE, Sadachika ISE&apos;s younger brother, or his son.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>一般には伊勢説が定着して上記のような「伊勢素浪人」という早雲像ができあがる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, Soun is mostly known as the master-less samurai from Ise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, Soun is mostly known as the masterless samurai from Ise.</e>
<cmt>Deleted hyphen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, Soun is mostly known as the &apos;masterless samurai from Ise.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>一方、研究者の間では京都説が有力視されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Still other researchers considered the Kyoto theory the most reliable..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Still other researchers considered the Kyoto theory the most reliable.</e>
<cmt>Deleted full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Still other researchers considered the Kyoto theory the most reliable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="177">
<j>備中説は『今川記』および『太閤記』に書かれており、井原市法泉寺の古文書を調査した藤井駿が1956年に早雲を備中伊勢氏で将軍足利義尚の側近であった「伊勢新九郎盛時」とする論文を発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bitchu theory is written in the &quot;Imagawa-ki &quot;and &quot;Taikoki,&quot; and Shun FUJII who had researched the old documents at Hosen-ji Temple in Ihara City, published a paper in 1956 stating that Soun had been the Shinkuro Moritoki ISE, who was an attendant to Shogun Yoshinao Ashikaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bitchu theory comes from the &quot;Imagawa-ki &quot;and &quot;Taikoki,&quot; when Shun FUJII, who had researched the old documents at Hosen-ji Temple in Ihara City, published a paper in 1956 stating that Soun had been the Shinkuro Moritoki ISE who was an attendant to Shogun Yoshinao Ashikaga.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is written in&quot;→&quot;comes from&quot;&quot;and&quot;→&quot;when&quot;Added commaDeleted comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bitchu theory comes from the &quot;Imagawa-ki &quot;and &quot;Taikoki,&quot; when Shun FUJII, who had researched the old documents at Hosen-ji Temple in Ihara City, published a paper in 1956 stating that Soun had been the Shinkuro Moritoki ISE who was an attendant to Shogun Yoshinao ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>Ashikaga→ASHIKAGA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>1980年前後に奥野高広、今谷明、小和田哲男が史料調査の結果として「伊勢新九郎盛時」を後の北条早雲とする論文を発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some time around 1980, Takahiro OKUNO, Akira IMATANI and Tetsuo OWADA published a paper stating that as a result of historical research, Shinkuro Moritoki ISE later became Soun HOJO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some time around 1980, Takahiro OKUNO, Akira IMATANI and Tetsuo OWADA, after examing historical archives, published a paper stating that Shinkuro Moritoki ISE later became Soun HOJO.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as a result of historical research&quot;→&quot;after examing historical archives&quot;Changed word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some time around 1980, Takahiro OKUNO, Akira IMATANI and Tetsuo OWADA, after examining historical archives, published a paper stating that Shinkuro Moritoki ISE later became Soun HOJO.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>その後、有効な反論も出ず、家永遵嗣などの研究の進展もあって、ほぼ定説化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No counterargument was proposed, and because this was also supported by a study published by Junji IENAGA, this has become the accepted fact.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No counterargument was proposed, and because this was also supported by a study published by Junji IENAGA, it has become the accepted theory.</e>
<cmt>&quot;this&quot;→&quot;it&quot;&quot;fact&quot;→&quot;theory&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No counterargument was proposed, and because this was also supported by a study published by Junji IENAGA, it has become the accepted theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>江戸時代前期成立の『今川記』に戻った訳で「本卦返り」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the translation of the &quot;Imagawa-ki&quot; it is called the &apos;Honkegaeri.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the version of the &quot;Imagawa-ki&quot; produced in the early Edo period, it is called the &apos;Honkegaeri,&apos; literally &apos;returning to the main family&apos;</e>
<cmt>I　think &quot;訳&quot; is &apos;version&apos; rather than &apos;translation&apos;Added explantion of &quot;Honkegaeri&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the version of the &quot;Imagawa-ki&quot; produced in the early Edo period, it is called the &apos;Honkegaeri,&apos; literally &apos;returning to the main family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>早雲は氏素性のない素浪人ではなく、将軍に直接仕える名門の出であったことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this Soun is now considered not a master-less samurai but a samurai from a distinguished family that served directly under the Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this, Soun is now considered not a masterless samurai but one from a distinguished family that served directly under the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>Added commaDeleted hyphen&quot;samurai&quot;→&quot;one&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this, Soun is now considered not a masterless samurai but one from a distinguished family that served directly under the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>生年に関する論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Debate over his date of birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Debate over his date of birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Debate over his date of birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="182">
<j>早雲の年齢については江戸時代以来、享年88（永享4年（1432年）生）とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been believed from the Edo Period that Soun was born in 1432 and died at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been believed from the Edo Period that Soun was born in 1432 and died at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been believed from the Edo Period that Soun was born in 1432 and died at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>当時としては非常に長命である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eighty-eight would have been a very long life for a man of that period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This would have been a very long life for a man of that period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Eighty-eight&quot;→&quot;This&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This would have been a very long life for a man of that period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>これだと、駿河に下向して興国寺城主となり、長男氏綱が生まれた時点で数え年で56歳、伊豆討ち入りの時点で62歳となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the above date, he would have been 56 years old when he went to Suruga and became lord of Kokokuji-jo Castle and had his oldest son Ujitsuna, and 62 years old when he led his troops into battle at Izu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the above date, he would have been 56 years old when he went to Suruga and became lord of Kokokuji-jo Castle and had his oldest son Ujitsuna, and 62 years old when he led his troops into battle at Izu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the above date, he would have been 56 years old when he went to Suruga and became lord of Kokokuji-jo Castle and had his oldest son Ujitsuna, and 62 years old when he led his troops into battle at Izu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>江戸時代前期の史料で姉とされる北川殿が今川義忠と結婚した応仁元年（1467年）で早雲は36歳になっており、姉だと当時の女性としては晩婚に過ぎる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitagawa-Dono, listed as Soun&apos;s older sister in documents from the early Edo Period, married Yoshitada IMAGAWA in 1467, when Soun would have been 36 years old, which would make her marriage too late in her life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitagawa-Dono, listed as Soun&apos;s older sister in documents from the early Edo Period, married Yoshitada IMAGAWA in 1467, when Soun would have been 36 years old, which would make her marriage too late in her life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitagawa-dono, listed as Soun&apos;s older sister in documents from the early Edo Period, married Yoshitada IMAGAWA in 1467, when Soun would have been 36 years old, which would make her marriage too late in her life.</e>
<cmt>Dono→donoスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>そこで歳の離れた妹とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory was revised to make Kitagawa-Dono Soun&apos;s very young sister.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory was revised to make Kitagawa-Dono Soun&apos;s very young sister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory was revised to make Kitagawa-dono Soun&apos;s very young sister.</e>
<cmt>Dono→dono</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="187">
<j>早雲は小説家や評論家から「大器晩成」の典型としてよく取り上げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun is often depicted by novelists and critics as person who bloomed late in life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun is often depicted by novelists and critics as a person who bloomed late in life.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun is often depicted by novelists and critics as &apos;a person who bloomed late in life.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>しかしながら、早雲が歴史上に登場するのが50歳近く、本格的に活動するのが60歳を過ぎてから、最晩年の80歳をすぎても自ら兵を率いて戦っており、いかに矍鑠としていても少々異様であり、疑問に感じる者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, appearance of Soun in history near the age of 50, coming into full bloom after 60 and still leading a battle after 80 would be quite odd, which brings this theory into question..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the appearance of Soun in history near the age of 50, coming into full bloom after 60 and still leading a battle after 80 would be quite odd, which brings this theory into question..</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the appearance of Soun in history near the age of 50, coming into full bloom after 60 and still leading a battle after 80 would be quite odd, which brings this theory into question..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>（下山治久も著書で疑問を述べている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Haruhisa SHIMOYAMA also expressed his doubts in his book.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Haruhisa SHIMOYAMA also expressed his doubts in his book.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Haruhisa SHIMOYAMA also expressed his doubts in his book.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="190">
<j>近年になって黒田基樹は享年88は江戸時代中期以降の系図類から出たものであり江戸時代前期の史料には存在しないことを明らかにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, Motoki KURODA has pointed out that the idea that Soun was 88 years old at the time of his death comes from a family tree created in the Mid Edo Period, and that such data does not exist in documents from the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, Motoki KURODA has pointed out that the idea that Soun was 88 years old at the time of his death comes from a family tree created in the mid-Edo Period, and that such data does not exist in documents from the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Mid Edo&quot;→&quot;mid-Edo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, Motoki KURODA has pointed out that the idea that Soun was 88 years old at the time of his death comes from a family tree created in the mid-Edo Period, and that such data does not exist in documents from the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>永享4年（1432年）生れだと近年有力視された幕臣伊勢盛時の父盛定の活動時期とも伊勢貞親（盛時の母の兄弟）の甥という系譜関係も成り立たなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If he had been born in 1423, the theories about the active period of Morisada, father of Moritoki ISE, retainer to the Shogun&apos;s or that he was the nephew of Sadachika ISE (Moritoki&apos;s mother&apos;s brother) would not stand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If he had been born in 1423, the theories about the active period of Morisada, father of the shogunate retainer Moritoki ISE, or about his being the nephew of Sadachika ISE (Moritoki&apos;s mother&apos;s brother) would not stand.</e>
<cmt>&quot;retainer to the Shogun&apos;s&quot;→&quot;the shogunate retainer&quot;&quot;that he was&quot;→&quot;about his being&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If he had been born in 1432, the theories about the active period of Morisada, father of the shogunate retainer Moritoki ISE, or about his being the nephew of Sadachika ISE (Moritoki&apos;s mother&apos;s brother) would not stand.</e>
<cmt>1423→1432</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>これは長年、早雲と思われた伊勢貞藤の生年と混同されてしまった結果であるとし、江戸時代前期成立の軍記物で「子の年」生まれと記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The discrepancy resulted from confusion with the date of birth of Sadafuji ISE, who was once thought to be Soun, and from a war chronicles written at the beginning of Edo Period, in which Soun was described as having been born in the year of Rat.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The discrepancy resulted from confusion over the date of birth of Sadafuji ISE, who was once thought to be Soun, and from war chronicles written at the beginning of Edo Period, in which Soun was described as having been born in the year of Rat.</e>
<cmt>&quot;with&quot;→&quot;over&quot;Deleted &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The discrepancy resulted from confusion over the date of birth of Sadafuji ISE, who was once thought to be Soun, and from war chronicles written at the beginning of Edo Period, in which Soun was described as having been born in the year of Rat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>姉の北川殿の結婚時期と考え合わせて、24歳若い康正2年（1456年）生まれであろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering the date of his sister Kitagawa-Dono&apos;s marriage, he must have been 24 years younger than the conventional theory holds(born 1456).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the date of his sister Kitagawa-Dono&apos;s marriage, he must have been 24 years younger (born 1456) than the conventional theory holds.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;(born 1456)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the date of his sister Kitagawa-dono&apos;s marriage, he must have been 24 years younger (born 1456) than the conventional theory holds.</e>
<cmt>Dono→dono</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>これだと、姉の北川殿の結婚の時期に11歳頃、駿河下向時点で32歳、享年は64歳となり、当時の人間の活動としては妥当な年齢であることから、有力視されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this age, Soun would have been 11 when Kitagawa-Dono got married, 32 when he went to Suruga and 64 at the time of his death, common for the man of that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this age, Soun would have been 11 when Kitagawa-Dono got married, 32 when he went to Suruga and 64 at the time of his death, common for the man of that time.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this age, Soun would have been 11 when Kitagawa-dono got married, 32 when he went to Suruga and 64 at the time of his death, common for the man of that time.</e>
<cmt>Dono→dono</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="195">
<j>しかしながら、この説については未だ検討中の段階で、これを採らず享年88説を採る研究者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this theory is still being examined, and there are researchers who still insist that Soun died at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this theory is still being examined, and there are researchers who still insist that Soun died at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this theory is still being examined, and there are researchers who still insist that Soun died at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>最近の小説や評論の類それにインターネットのホームページも早雲を「大器晩成」の典型として享年88説を採っているものが多く、必ずしも一般に定着した訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent novels, reviews and postings on the Internet still maintain that Soun was a man who bloomed late in life and died at the age of 88, and neither of the above theories have been established among the general public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent novels, reviews and postings on the Internet still maintain that Soun was a man who bloomed late in life and died at the age of 88, and neither of the above theories have been established among the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent novels, reviews and postings on the Internet still maintain that Soun was a man who &apos;bloomed late in life&apos; and died at the age of 88, and neither of the above theories have been established among the general public.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>(ちなみに、近世以前の平均寿命の短さは乳幼児死亡率の高さが主な原因であり、成人男子の平均余命だけを考えれば現代人より著しく短い訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(As a reference, the average life expectancy in that period was lower than today, not because the people then died at an earlier age but because of the high infant mortality rate and the average life of an adult male was not significantly shorter than that of today.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(As a reference, the average life expectancy in that period was lower than today, not because the people then died at an earlier age but because of the high infant mortality rate; the average life of an adult male was not significantly shorter than that of today.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and&quot;→&quot;;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(As a reference, the average life expectancy in that period was lower than today, not because the people then died at an earlier age but because of the high infant mortality rate; the average life of an adult male was not significantly shorter than that of today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>他の戦国大名では武田信虎(享年81歳)など80代まで生きた著名な人物は多い。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many famous people who lived into their 80s such as the war lord Nobutora TAKEDA, who lived to 81.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many famous people who lived into their 80s, such as the war lord Nobutora TAKEDA, who lived to 81.)</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many famous people who lived into their 80s, such as the war lord Nobutora TAKEDA, who lived to 81.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>現況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current status</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Current status</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Current status</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="199">
<j>作家などは身分が低く人生の辛酸を舐め、十分に老成した人間でなければ早雲のような活躍はできまいと長年論じてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some writers have long argued that only a fully mature man who have been born low and had lived a hard life would be able to win the success that Soun did.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some writers have long argued that only a fully mature man who had been born low and had lived a hard life would be able to win the success that Soun did.</e>
<cmt>&quot;have&quot;→&quot;had&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some writers have long argued that only a fully mature man who had been born low and had lived a hard life would be able to win the success that Soun did.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>近年の研究を反映した早雲像は全く別であり、将軍に直接仕える名門一族の青年が幕府の命を帯びて駿河に下り、中央の政治と連動しながら関東で活躍して、後北条氏の祖となったことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The image of Soun reflecting studies made in recent years is completely different; a man who had served the Shogun received order from the Bakufu to go to Suruga, and ruled over Kanto in collaboration with the central government, and later became a member of the Go-Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image of Soun seen in recent studies is completely different; a young man from a noted family who served the Shogun received an order from the Bakufu to go to Suruga, ruled over Kanto in collaboration with the central government and later became a member of the Go-Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;reflecting studies made in recent years&quot;→&quot;seen in recent studies&quot;Added &quot;young&quot;, &quot;a noted family&quot;, &quot;a&quot;Deleted &quot;and&quot;, comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image of Soun seen in recent studies is completely different; a young man from a noted family who served the Shogun received an order from the Bakufu to go to Suruga, ruled over Kanto in collaboration with the central government and later became a member of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>Go-Hojo→Ｇｏｈojo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="201">
<j>これらの新説が、主な小説やメディアでは以下のように扱われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new theories as treated in major novels and media as described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new theories as treated in major novels and media are described below.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as&quot;→&quot;are&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new theories as treated in major novels and media are described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="202">
<j>司馬遼太郎の『箱根の坂』（1984年）では、その時期の研究を反映して単純な伊勢素浪人とせず、備中伊勢氏とし、政所執事伊勢貞親の屋敷に寄宿しながら京で足利義視に仕える設定である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Ryotaro Shiba&apos;s novel &quot;Hakone-no-saka (The Slopes of Hakone)&quot; (1984), he reflects the studies of time and is presented not as simple master-less samurai of Ise, but as a samurai of the Bitchu-Ise clan serving Yoshimi AHIKAGA while residing in the residence of Sadachika ISE, a steward of the Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s novel, &quot;Hakone-no-saka (The Slopes of Hakone)&quot; (1984), reflects the studies of time and Soun is presented not as a simple ronin of Ise, but as a samurai of the Bitchu-Ise clan, serving Yoshimi AHIKAGA while residing in the residence of Sadachika ISE, a steward of the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &quot;Shiba&quot;Deleted &quot;in&quot;, &quot;he&quot;Added &quot;Soun&quot;, &quot;a&quot;&quot;master-less samurai&quot;→&quot;ronin&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryotaro SHIBA&apos;s novel, &quot;Hakone-no-saka&quot; (The Slopes of Hakone) (1984), reflects the studies of time and Soun is presented not as a simple ronin of Ise, but as a samurai of the Bitchu-Ise clan, serving Yoshimi AHIKAGA while residing in the residence of Sadachika ISE, a steward of the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>書物の説明移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>しかしながら、大衆小説として「身分の低い素浪人」のイメージを守り、早雲を伊勢氏の末流とし、鞍作りを業にする職人的人物として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he maintained the image held by the general public of his being a lowly samurai, by presenting him as the descendent of the Ise clan and a saddle maker.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, to maintain the image held by the general public of Soun being a lowly samurai, Shiba presented him as the descendent of the Ise clan and a saddle maker.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he maintained&quot;→&quot;to maintain&quot;&quot;his&quot;→&quot;Soun&quot;&quot;by presenting&quot;→&quot;Shiba presented&quot;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, to maintain the image held by the general public of Soun being a lowly samurai, Shiba presented him as the descendent of the Ise clan and a saddle maker.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>年齢については当時の通説の享年88説で「大器晩成」として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He kept the conventional version of the theory with Soun&apos;s as a later bloomer who died at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He kept the conventional version of the theory with Soun as a later bloomer who died at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;&apos;s&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He kept the conventional version of the theory with Soun as &apos;a later bloomer&apos; who died at the age of 88.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>北川殿は血のつながらない妹とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitagawa-Dono is depicted as a younger sister with no blood relations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitagawa-Dono is depicted as a younger sister with no blood connection.</e>
<cmt>&quot;relations&quot;→&quot;connection&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitagawa-dono is depicted as a younger sister with no blood connection.</e>
<cmt>Dono→dono</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="206">
<j>南原幹雄 の『謀将 北条早雲』（2002年）では、近年の研究を反映して康正2年生まれ説を採り、北川殿は姉となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Bosho Soun Hojo&quot;(2002) by Mikio NAMBARA, he reflects the new theory that has him being born in 1456, with Kitagawa-Dono depicted as his older sister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikio NAMBARA&apos;s &quot;Bosho Soun Hojo&quot;(2002) reflects the recent theory that he was born in 1456, with Kitagawa-Dono depicted as his older sister.</e>
<cmt>&quot;new&quot;→&quot;recent&quot;&quot;has him being&quot;→&quot;he was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikio NAMBARA&apos;s &quot;Bosho Soun Hojo&quot; (2002) reflects the recent theory that he was born in 1456, with Kitagawa-dono depicted as his older sister.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足Dono→dono</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="207">
<j>2005年放送の「その時歴史が動いた：戦国をひらいた男～北条早雲　56才からの挑戦～」（日本放送協会、ゲスト：小和田哲男静岡大学教授）では、早雲を幕府の高級官僚としているが、年齢については享年88説を採り「大器晩成」として描いている（諸説を検討の結果一般的な説を採用したとのこと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the documentary, &quot;Movement of History: The Man that started the Warring States Period - Soun HOJO, Challenge from the age of 56&quot; (NHK, Guest: Tetsuo OWADA, Professor of Shizuoka University), broadcasted in 2005, Soun is described as a late bloomer who became of a high ranking officer in the Bakufu government and who died at the age of 88 (a generally accepted theory that was adopted after reviewing various theories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the documentary, &quot;Movement of History: The Man that started the Warring States Period - Soun HOJO, Challenge from the age of 56&quot; (NHK, Guest: Tetsuo OWADA, Professor of Shizuoka University), broadcast in 2005, Soun is described as a late bloomer who became a high ranking officer in the Bakufu government and who died at the age of 88 (a generally accepted theory that was adopted after reviewing various theories).</e>
<cmt>&quot;broadcasted&quot;→&quot;broadcast&quot;Deleted &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the documentary, &quot;Movement of History: The Man that started the Warring States Period - Soun HOJO, Challenge from the age of 56&quot; (NHK, Guest: Tetsuo OWADA, Professor of Shizuoka University), broadcast in 2005, Soun is described as &apos;a late bloomer&apos; who became a high ranking officer in the Bakufu government and who died at the age of 88 (a generally accepted theory that was adopted after reviewing various theories).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&apos;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="208">
<j>1980年代以前の小説や一般向け書籍では、早雲を「非常に長命な大器晩成」「徒手空拳の素浪人」として書かれているものが多く、海音寺潮五郎の早雲の史伝などは典型である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of novels and books for general public published during and after 1980s describe Soun as &quot;a man who bloomed late and lived a long life&quot; and as &quot;a master-less samurai who had built himself up from nothing,&quot; with Chogoro KAIONJI&apos;s historical legend being the typical.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most novels and books for the general public published during and after the 1980s describe Soun as &quot;a man who bloomed late and lived a long life&quot; and as &quot;a masterless samurai who had built himself up from nothing,&quot; with Chogoro KAIONJI&apos;s historical legend being typical.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;of&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted hyphen and &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most novels and books for the general public published during and after the 1980s describe Soun as &apos;a man who bloomed late and lived a long life&apos; and as &apos;a masterless samurai who had built himself up from nothing,&apos; with Chogoro KAIONJI&apos;s historical legend being typical.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>現在でもそのイメージで高齢者の再チャレンジの見本のように早雲を語る作家が少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, this image still prevails, and many writers use Soun as an example to encourage people to take on new challenges late in life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, this image still prevails, and many writers use Soun as an example to encourage people to take on new challenges late in life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, this image still prevails, and many writers use Soun as an example to encourage people to take on new challenges late in life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), JAnDbot(id:66507), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), PATMAN(id:145791), 味っ子(id:17086), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kogane(id:28186), Ultratomio(id:1090), 百人(id:16483), Kurz(id:1601), でここ(id:9565), Tomo suzuki(id:11928), クマー(id:114361), MioUzaki(id:89034), 玄史生(id:43670), Yukimura.S(id:2138), UMBRO(id:100484), 埴○(id:40977), Shimoxx(id:9332), Maakun(id:16735), Kouko0515(id:100370), KASAGI(id:24405), Bankokuya(id:91191), Kentin(id:6768), 漬けマグロ(id:145695), SINOBU(id:28887), 時空の旅人(id:120663), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 富樫仁(TOGASHI Jin)(id:53524), 大和魂(id:156556), Yanahan(id:2437), Clen(id:100642), 梁山泊智多星呉用(id:127114), Aboshi(id:9318), Carkuni(id:79281), Tietew(id:4054), Boca samba(id:137526), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), R28Bot(id:177951), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), Shikai shaw(id:14306), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Mipu(id:5360), Safkan(id:423), けんち(id:5147), Junger(id:10282), Suisui(id:69), 歴史研究家(id:108842), Wwwq9999(id:178176), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>