<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉良義央</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa KIRA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa KIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa KIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉良 義央（きら よしひさ）は、江戸時代前期の高家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa KIRA was a koke (master of ceremony) in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa KIRA was a koke (master of ceremony) in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa KIRA was a koke (master of ceremony) in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『忠臣蔵』の敵役として有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is known as a villain&apos;s part of &quot;Chusingura&quot; (the title of a Kabuki drama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is known through the villain&apos;s role in &quot;Chusingura&quot; (the title of a Kabuki drama).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is known through the villain&apos;s role in &quot;Chusingura&quot; (the title of a Kabuki drama).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>幼名は三郎、通称は左近。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Saburo, and went by the name of Sakon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Saburo, and he went by the name Sakon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Saburo, and he went by the name Sakon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>従四位上左近衛権少将、上野介（こうずけのすけ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) Sakone gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Kozuke no Suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) Sakone gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Kozuke no Suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) Sakonoe gon no shosho (Provisional Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), Kozuke no Suke.</e>
<cmt>「左近衛権少将」の読みはsakonoe gon no shoshoであると思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>吉良上野介と呼ばれることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is often called Kozuke no Suke KIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is often called Kozuke no Suke KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is often called Kozuke no Suke KIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>本姓は源氏（清和源氏）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real family name was Genji (Seiwa-Genji, or Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real family name was Genji (Seiwa-Genji, or Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real family name was Genji (Seiwa-Genji, or Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>家紋は丸に二つ引・五三桐。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family crest was maruni futasu biki (two lines in a circle) and gosan no kiri (literally, five three paulownia).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family crest was maruni futatsu biki (two lines in a circle) and gosan no kiri (literally, &quot;five three paulownia&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family crest was maruni futatsu biki (two lines in a circle) and gosan no kiri (literally, &quot;five three paulownia&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>なお、義央の読みは従来「よしなか」とされていたが、愛知県吉良町の華蔵寺に収められる古文書の花押などから、現在では「よしひさ」と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, his name was conventionally pronounced &apos;Yoshinaka,&apos; but now it is considered &apos;Yoshihisa&apos; from a written seal of old documents which were collected in Kezo-ji Temple in Kira-cho, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, his name was conventionally pronounced &apos;Yoshinaka,&apos; but now it is considered &apos;Yoshihisa&apos; based on a written seal of old documents assembled at Kezo-ji Temple in Kira-cho, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, his name was conventionally pronounced &apos;Yoshinaka,&apos; but now it is considered &apos;Yoshihisa&apos; based on a written seal of old documents assembled at Kezo-ji Temple in Kira-cho, Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Place of origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Place of origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Place of origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>寛永18年（1641年）9月2日、高家旗本吉良義冬（4200石）と酒井忠勝の姪（酒井忠吉の娘）の嫡男として、江戸鍛冶橋通りの吉良邸にて生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 2, 1641, he was born the eldest legitimate son of Yoshifuyu KIRA (4200 koku), koke hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu), and a niece of Tadakatsu SAKAI (a daughter of Tadakichi SAKAI) at the residence of Kira on the street of Edo Kajibashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 2, 1641, he was born the eldest legitimate son of Yoshifuyu KIRA (4200 koku), koke hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu), and a niece of Tadakatsu SAKAI (a daughter of Tadakichi SAKAI) at the residence of Kira on the street of Edo Kajibashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 6, 1641, he was born the eldest legitimate son of Yoshifuyu KIRA (4200 koku), koke hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu), and a niece of Tadakatsu SAKAI (a daughter of Tadayoshi SAKAI) at the residence of Kira on the street of Edo Kajibashi.</e>
<cmt>①「寛永18年（1641年）9月2日」は、グレゴリオ暦で1641年10月6日なので訳を訂正しました。②「酒井忠吉」の読みはTadayoshi SAKAIであると思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一説によれば、陣屋があった群馬県藤岡市白石の生まれともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to another account, he was born at Shiroishi, Fujioka City, Gunma Prefecture, where jinya (regional government office) was located.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to another account, he was born at Shiroishi, Fujioka City, Gunma Prefecture, where the jinya (regional government office) was located.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to another account, he was born at Shiroishi, Fujioka City, Gunma Prefecture, where the jinya (regional government office) was located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>義冬の母が高家今川家出身であるため、今川氏真の続柄にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshifuyu&apos;s mother was from koke Imagawa family, so he was related to Ujizane IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshifuyu&apos;s mother was from the koke Imagawa family, so he was related to Ujizane IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshifuyu&apos;s mother was from the koke Imagawa family, so he was related to Ujizane IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>母は大身旗本酒井忠吉（大老酒井忠勝 (若狭国小浜藩主)の実弟）の長女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the eldest daughter of taishin hatamoto (greater vassal) Tadakichi SAKAI (a biological younger brother of tairo (chief minister) Tadakatsu SAKAI (the lord of Obama domain of Wakasa Province)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the eldest daughter of the taishin hatamoto (greater vassal) Tadakichi SAKAI (a biological younger brother of tairo (chief minister) Tadakatsu SAKAI (the lord of the Obama domain of Wakasa Province)).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the eldest daughter of the taishin hatamoto (greater vassal) Tadayoshi SAKAI (a biological younger brother of tairo (chief minister) Tadakatsu SAKAI (the lord of the Obama domain of Wakasa Province)).</e>
<cmt>「酒井忠吉」の読みはTadayoshi SAKAIであると思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>継母は母の妹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His stepmother was a younger daughter of his mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His stepmother was a younger daughter of his mother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His stepmother was a younger sister of his mother.</e>
<cmt>「母の妹」であることから、a younger sister of his motherへ変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>弟に東条義叔（500石の旗本）・東条義孝（切米300俵の旗本）・東条冬貞（義叔養子）・東条冬重（義孝養子）・孝証（山城国石清水八幡宮の僧侶・豊蔵坊孝雄の弟子）の5人がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had five younger brothers: Yoshisue TOJO (hatamoto with 500 koku), Yoshitaka TOJO (hatamoto with 300 bags of kirimai (an allowance in rice), Fuyusada TOJO (an adopted son of Yoshisue), Fuyushige TOJO (an adopted son of Yoshitaka), and Kosho (a disciple of Hozobo Koyu, a Buddhist monk of Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine in Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt>孝証と豊蔵坊孝雄の正しい読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had five younger brothers: Yoshisue TOJO (hatamoto with 500 koku), Yoshitaka TOJO (hatamoto with 300 bags of kirimai (an allowance in rice), Fuyusada TOJO (an adopted son of Yoshisue), Fuyushige TOJO (an adopted son of Yoshitaka), and Kosho (a disciple of Hozobo Koyu, a Buddhist monk of Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine in Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had five younger brothers: Yoshisue TOJO (hatamoto with 500 koku), Yoshitaka TOJO (hatamoto with 300 bags of kirimai (an allowance in rice), Fuyusada TOJO (an adopted son of Yoshisue), Fuyushige TOJO (an adopted son of Yoshitaka), and Kosho (a disciple of Hozobo Koyu, a Buddhist monk of Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine in Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>妹も2人おり、うち1人は安藤氏に嫁いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had two younger sisters, and one of them was married to a man of Ando clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had two younger sisters, and one of them was married to a man of the Ando clan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had two younger sisters, and one of them was married to a man of the Ando clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>承応2年（1653年）3月16日、将軍徳川家綱に拝謁。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 16, 1653, he was granted an audience with Shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 16, 1653, he was granted an audience with the shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 13, 1653, he was granted an audience with the shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>「承応2年（1653年）3月16日」はグレゴリオ暦で、1653年4月13日であるため訳を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>明暦3年（1657年）12月27日、従四位侍従兼上野国に叙任（位階が高いにもかかわらず、上野守でなく上野介である事については、親王任国を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 27, 1657, he was invested with Jushiino jiju (Junior Forth Rank Chamberlain) of Kozuke Province. (See also shinno ninkoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes) for the reason why he was not Kozuke no kami (Governor of Kozuke Province) but Kozuke no suke (assistant governor of Kozuke Province) in spite of his high-court ranking..)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 27, 1657, he was invested with Jushiino jiju (Junior Fourth Rank Chamberlain) of Kozuke Province (see also shinno ninkoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes) for the reason he was not Kozuke no kami (the governor of Kozuke Province) but Kozuke no suke (the assistant governor of Kozuke Province) despite his high court ranking).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 30, 1658, he was invested with Jushiino jiju (Junior Fourth Rank Chamberlain) of Kozuke Province (see also shinno ninkoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes) for the reason he was not Kozuke no kami (the governor of Kozuke Province) but Kozuke no suke (the assistant governor of Kozuke Province) despite his high court ranking).</e>
<cmt>「明暦3年（1657年）12月27日」はグレゴリオ暦で、1658年1月30日であるため訳を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>万治元年（1658年）4月、出羽国米沢藩主上杉綱勝の妹・梅嶺院（後の富子）と結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1658, he was married to Baireiin (later known as Tomiko), a younger sister of Tsunakatsu UESUGI, the lord of the Yonezawa domain in Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1658, he was married to Baireiin (later known as Tomiko), a younger sister of Tsunakatsu UESUGI, the lord of the Yonezawa domain in Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1658, he was married to Baireiin (later known as Tomiko), a younger sister of Tsunakatsu UESUGI, the lord of the Yonezawa domain in Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>「万治元年4月」はグレゴリオ暦で1658年5月にあたるため、訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この婚儀は美男子であった義央を、富子が見初めたとの逸話もあるが、確実な資料からは見出せない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote about his marriage, which says that Tomiko fell in love with beautiful Yoshihisa at first sight, but we cannot find the evidence in the reliable materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote about his marriage, which states that Tomiko fell in love with the beautiful Yoshihisa at first sight, but no such evidence can be found in reliable materials.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote about his marriage, which states that Tomiko fell in love with the beautiful Yoshihisa at first sight, but no such evidence can be found in reliable materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>『上杉年譜』は「万治元年3月5日、柳営において老中酒井忠清・松平信綱・阿部忠秋列座のなか、保科正之から三姫を吉良上野介へ嫁がせるべき旨を命じられたことを千坂兵部が（綱勝に）言上した」と幕命による婚儀と記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Uesugi Nenpu&quot; (Uesugi&apos;s chronological record), it was a marriage ordered by bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun): &apos;On March 5, 1658, Hyobu CHISAKA told (Tsunakatsu) that he was ordered to marry Sanhime to Kozuke no Suke KIRA by Masayuki HOSHINA in front of the assembled company such as roju (senior councilor) Tadakiyo SAKAI, Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA, and Tadaaki ABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Uesugi Nenpu&quot; (Uesugi&apos;s chronological record), it was a marriage ordered by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun): &apos;On March 5, 1658, Hyobu CHISAKA told (Tsunakatsu) that he had been ordered to marry Sanhime to Kozuke no Suke KIRA by Masayuki HOSHINA in front of the assembled company such as the roju (senior councilor) Tadakiyo SAKAI, Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA and Tadaaki ABE.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Uesugi Nenpu&quot; (Uesugi&apos;s chronological record), it was a marriage ordered by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun): &apos;On April 7, 1658, Hyobu CHISAKA told (Tsunakatsu) that he had been ordered to marry Sanhime to Kozuke no Suke KIRA by Masayuki HOSHINA in front of the assembled company such as the roju (senior councilor) Tadakiyo SAKAI, Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA and Tadaaki ABE.</e>
<cmt>「万治元年3月5日」はグレゴリオ暦で、1658年4月7日であることから訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、吉良氏が古くからの婚姻関係によって扇谷上杉氏の血を引いており、二男四女（長男上杉綱憲、次男吉良三郎、長女鶴姫、次女振姫、三女阿久利姫、四女菊姫）に恵まれた（ただし次男・三郎と次女・振姫は夭折）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kira clan was related to the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan by old marital relations, and he had two sons and four daughters (the eldest son Tsunanori UESUGI, the second son Saburo KIRA, the eldest daughter Tsruhime, the second daughter Furihime, the third daughter Kurihime, the fourth daughter Kikuhime). (However, the second and third sons and the second daughter Furihime died young.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kira clan was related to the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan by old marriage connections, and he had two sons and four daughters (the eldest son Tsunanori UESUGI, the second son Saburo KIRA, the eldest daughter Tsruhime, the second daughter Furihime, the third daughter Kurihime, and the fourth daughter Kikuhime) (however, the second and third sons and the second daughter Furihime died young).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kira clan was related to the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan by old marriage connections, and he had two sons and four daughters (the eldest son Tsunanori UESUGI, the second son Saburo KIRA, the eldest daughter Tsuruhime, the second daughter Furihime, the third daughter Akurihime, and the fourth daughter Kikuhime) (however, the second son Saburo and the second daughter Furihime died young).</e>
<cmt>①「長女鶴姫」のスペルをthe eldest daughter Tsuruhimeへ訂正しました。②「三女阿久利姫」の読みを訂正し、the third daughter Akurihimeに変更しました。③「（ただし次男・三郎と～）」の訳を、however, the second son Saburo and ~へ変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>名門の家柄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">High lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">High lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">High lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>万治2年（1659年）から父とともに出仕する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1659, he started to attend at the court with his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1659, he began attending the court with his father.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1659, he began attending the court with his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>部屋住みの身分ながら、家禄とは別に庇蔭料1000俵が支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was a dependent, he got 1000 bags of rice as hiinryo (allowance for the person who does not succeed to a property) in addition to karoku (hereditary stipend).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was a dependent, he got 1000 bags of rice as a hiinryo (an allowance for the person who doesn&apos;t succeed to a property) in addition to a karoku (hereditary stipend).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was a dependent, he got 1000 bags of rice as a hiinryo (an allowance for the person who doesn&apos;t succeed to a property) in addition to a karoku (hereditary stipend).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>寛文2年（1662年）8月には、大内仙洞御所造営の御存問の使として初めて京都へ赴き、後西天皇の謁見を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1662, he first went to Kyoto as an envoy of gozonmon built by Ouchi Sento Imperial Palace, and was granted an audience with Emperor Gosai.</e>
<cmt>「御存問」の意味、正しい読み方ともに不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1662, he first went to Kyoto as an envoy of the gozonmon built by Ouchi Sento Imperial Palace, and was granted an audience with Emperor Gosai.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1662, he first went to Kyoto as an envoy of the gozonmon built by Ouchi Sento Imperial Palace, and was granted an audience with Emperor Gosai.</e>
<cmt>①「寛文2年8月」はグレゴリオ暦で1662年9月ですので、訳を変更しました。②「御存問」の意味と「大内仙洞御所造営」の関係が不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>以降、生涯を通じて年賀使15回、幕府の使者9回の計24回上洛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, he went to the capital (Kyoto) for twenty-four times throughout his life: fifteen times as an envoy of New Year&apos;s greetings, and nine times as an envoy of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, he went to the capital (Kyoto) 24 times throughout his life: 15 times as an envoy of New Year&apos;s greetings and nine times as an envoy of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he went to the capital (Kyoto) 24 times throughout his life: 15 times as an envoy of New Year&apos;s greetings and nine times as an envoy of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>寛文3年（1663年）1月19日、後西上皇の院政の開始に対する賀使としての2度目の上洛の際、22歳にして従四位に昇進している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 19, 1663, when he went up to the capital for the second time as kashi (ambassador) for the retired Emperor Gosai&apos;s newly started cloister government, he got promoted to Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) at the age of 22.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 19, 1663, when he went up to the capital for the second time as kashi (ambassador) for the retired Emperor Gosai&apos;s newly estabished cloister government, he was promoted to Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) at the age of 22.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 26, 1663, when he went up to the capital for the second time as kashi (ambassador) for the retired Emperor Gosai&apos;s newly established cloister government, he was promoted to Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank) at the age of 22.</e>
<cmt>①「寛文3年（1663年）1月19日」はグレゴリオ暦で、1663年2月26日のため訳を訂正しました。②establishedのスペルを訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>24回もの上洛は高家の中でも群を抜いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to the capital as many as twenty-four times, which stood out among the koke.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went to the capital as many as 24 times, which was significant among the koke.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went to the capital as many as 24 times, which was significant among the koke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>さらに部屋住みの身でありながら使者職を行っていた事は、高家としての技倆が卓越していた事を表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he worked as an envoy although he was a dependent, which suggests that his ability as koke was outstanding.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he worked as an envoy although he was a dependent, which suggests that his ability as a koke was outstanding.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he worked as an envoy although he was a dependent, which suggests that his ability as a koke was outstanding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>優秀な技倆を綱吉が寵愛した為ともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that because Tsunayoshi favored his excellent ability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said to be because Tsunayoshi admired his excellent ability.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said to be because Tsunayoshi admired his excellent ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>寛文4年（1664年）閏5月、米沢藩主上杉綱勝が嗣子なきまま急死したために改易の危機に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In intercalary fifth month of 1664, Tsunakatsu UESUGI, the lord of the Yonezawa domain, died suddenly without having his heir, so the family plunged into a crisis of being deprived of samurai status and forfeited the family territories.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the intercalary fifth month of 1664, Tsunakatsu UESUGI, the lord of the Yonezawa domain, died suddenly without an heir, so the family plunged into a crisis of being deprived of samurai status and forfeited its territories.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the intercalary fifth month of 1664, Tsunakatsu UESUGI, the lord of the Yonezawa domain, died suddenly without an heir, so the family plunged into a crisis of being deprived of samurai status and forfeited its territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、保科正之（上杉綱勝の岳父）の斡旋を受け、長男三之助を上杉家の養子（のち上杉綱憲）とした結果、上杉家は改易を免れ、30万石から15万石への減知で危機を収束させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, by the good offices of Masayuki HOSHINA (father-in-law of Tsunakatsu UESUGI), the eldest son, Sannosuke (later known as Tsunanori UESUGI), was adopted by the Uesugi family, therefore the Uesugi family could avoid the crisis, and their fief was decreased from 300 thousand to 15 thousand in the end.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to the good offices of Masayuki HOSHINA (father-in-law of Tsunakatsu UESUGI), the eldest son, Sannosuke (later known as Tsunanori UESUGI), was adopted by the Uesugi family, and therefore the Uesugi family was able to avoid the crisis, but ultimately its fief was decreased from 300,000 to 15,000.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to the good offices of Masayuki HOSHINA (father-in-law of Tsunakatsu UESUGI), the eldest son, Sannosuke (later known as Tsunanori UESUGI), was adopted by the Uesugi family, and therefore the Uesugi family was able to avoid the crisis, but ultimately its fief was decreased from 300,000 to 150,000.</e>
<cmt>「15万石」の数字の表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>綱勝急死は義央による毒殺説が存在するが、これは上杉家江戸家老千坂兵部らと対立して失脚した米沢藩士福王子八弥の流言飛語で、信憑性は乏しいとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a view that Tsunakatsu died suddenly because Yoshihisa killed him with poison, but this is considered a groundless rumor spread by Hachiya FUKUOJI, a feudal retainer of Yonezawa domain, who lost his position in conflict with Hyobu CHISAKA, Edo-garo (one of the highest ranking vassals of a daimyo during the Edo period) of the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a view that Tsunakatsu died suddenly because Yoshihisa poisoned him, but this is considered a groundless rumor spread by Hachiya FUKUOJI, a feudal retainer of the Yonezawa domain, who lost his position in conflict with Hyobu CHISAKA, Edo-garo (one of the highest-ranking vassals of a daimyo during the Edo period) of the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a view that Tsunakatsu died suddenly because Yoshihisa poisoned him, but this is considered a groundless rumor spread by Hachiya FUKUOJI, a feudal retainer of the Yonezawa domain, who lost his position in conflict with Hyobu CHISAKA, Edo-garo (one of the highest-ranking vassals of a daimyo during the Edo period) of the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>以後、義央は上杉家との関係を積極的に利用するようになり、たびたび財政支援をさせたほか、3人の娘達を綱憲の養女として縁組を有利に進めようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then Yoshihisa came to use relationship with the Uesugi family positively, and not only made them support him financially, but also tried to make his three daughters adopted by Tsunanori profitably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Yoshihisa came to use the relationship with the Uesugi family positively; he not only made them support him financially but also tried to have his three daughters profitably adopted by Tsunanori.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Yoshihisa came to use the relationship with the Uesugi family positively; he not only made them support him financially but also tried to have his three daughters profitably adopted by Tsunanori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>長女上杉鶴は薩摩藩主島津綱貴の室、次女上杉阿久利は交代寄合旗本津軽政たけの室、3女上杉菊も旗本酒井忠平の室となっている（鶴姫は綱貴に離縁され、菊姫も死別するが、のちに公家大炊御門経音の室となって1男1女を産む）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eldest daughter, Tsuru UESUGI, became a wife of Tsunataka SHIMAZU, the lord of Satsuma domain, second daughter, Akuri UESUGI, got married to Masatake TSUGARU, kotaiyoriai (landholding liege vassals with alternate attendance obligations) hatamoto, and third daughter, Kiku UESUGI, also became a wife of Tadahira SAKAI, a hatamoto. (Princess Tsuru was divorced from Tsunataka, and princess Kiku lost her husband, but later she became a wife of Tsunenari OINOMIKADO, a court noble, and gave birth to a son and a daughter.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His eldest daughter, Tsuru UESUGI, became a wife of Tsunataka SHIMAZU, the lord of the Satsuma domain, the second daughter, Akuri UESUGI, married Masatake TSUGARU, a kotaiyoriai (landholding liege vassals with alternate attendance obligations) hatamoto, and the third daughter, Kiku UESUGI, also became a wife of Tadahira SAKAI, a hatamoto (Princess Tsuru was divorced from Tsunataka, and Princess Kiku had lost her husband, but later she became a wife of Tsunenari OINOMIKADO, a court noble, and gave birth to a son and a daughter).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His eldest daughter, Tsuru UESUGI, became a wife of Tsunataka SHIMAZU, the lord of the Satsuma domain, the second daughter, Akuri UESUGI, married Masatake TSUGARU, a kotaiyoriai (landholding liege vassals with alternate attendance obligations) hatamoto, and the third daughter, Kiku UESUGI, also became a wife of Tadahira SAKAI, a hatamoto (Princess Tsuru was divorced from Tsunataka, and Princess Kiku had lost her husband, but later she became a wife of Tsunenari OINOMIKADO, a court noble, and gave birth to a son and a daughter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="35">
<j>寛文8年（1668年）5月、父義冬の死去により家督を相続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, 1668, he succeeded to a property because of the death of his father Yoshifuyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1668, he succeeded to a property due to the death of his father Yoshifuyu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1668, he succeeded to a property due to the death of his father Yoshifuyu.</e>
<cmt>「寛文8年5月」はグレゴリオ暦で1668年6月であるため、訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>時に28歳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 28 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 28 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 28 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="37">
<j>延宝8年（1680年）閏9月、高家の極官である左近衛少将に任官し、天和 (日本)3年（1683年）3月には大沢基恒、畠山義里とともに高家に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In intercalary ninth month of 1680, he was appointed as Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), which was the highest rank for koke, and in March 1683, he was installed as koke together with Mototsune OSAWA and Yoshisato HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the intercalary ninth month of 1680, he was appointed Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), which was the highest rank for a koke, and in March 1683 he was installed as a koke together with Mototsune OSAWA and Yoshisato HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the intercalary ninth month of 1680, he was appointed Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), which was the highest rank for a koke, and in March 1683 he was installed as a koke together with Mototsune OSAWA and Yoshisato HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>また、長男綱憲の上杉家入り以後、嫡男は次男三郎だったが、貞享2年（1685年）9月1日に夭折。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, after Tsunenori, the eldest son, was adopted by the Uesugi family, his heir was Saburo, the second son, but he died young on September 1, 1685.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, after Tsunenori, the eldest son, was adopted by the Uesugi family, his heir was Saburo, the second son, but he died young on September 1, 1685.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, after Tsunenori, the eldest son, was adopted by the Uesugi family, his heir was Saburo, the second son, but he died young on September 28, 1685.</e>
<cmt>「貞享2年（1685年）9月1日」はグレゴリオ暦で、1685年9月28日であることから訳を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>綱憲や幕府とも協議の末、綱憲次男の春千代を吉良義周と改名させて養子とし、元禄3年（1690年）4月16日に江戸鍛冶橋の邸宅へ迎え入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he consulted with Tsunanori and bakufu, they adopted Haruchiyo, the second son of Tsunanori, changing his name into Yoshimasa KIRA, and on April 16, 1690, they took him in to the residence at Edo Kajibashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once he had consulted with Tsunanori and the bakufu, they adopted Haruchiyo, the second son of Tsunanori, changing his name into Yoshimasa KIRA, and on April 16, 1690 they took him into the residence at Edo Kajibashi.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once he had consulted with Tsunanori and the bakufu, they adopted Haruchiyo, the second son of Tsunanori, changing his name into Yoshimasa KIRA, and on May 24, 1690, they took him into the residence at Edo Kajibashi.</e>
<cmt>「元禄3年（1690年）4月16日」はグレゴリオ暦で、1690年5月24日であることから訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="40">
<j>元禄11年（1698年）9月6日、江戸の大火により鍛冶橋邸を焼失し、のち八重洲にて再建する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 6, 1698, he lost his residence at Kajibashi because of the great fire of Edo, and later he rebuilt his residence at Yaesu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 6, 1698, he lost his residence at Kajibashi because of the great fire of Edo, but later he rebuilt his residence at Yaesu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 9, 1698, he lost his residence at Kajibashi because of the great fire of Edo, but later he rebuilt his residence at Yaesu.</e>
<cmt>「元禄11年（1698年）9月6日」はグレゴリオ暦で、1698年10月9日であることから訳を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>皮肉であるが、この大火で消防の指揮をとっていたのは浅野であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ironically it was Asano who was in charge of firefighting in this fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ironically, it was Asano who was in charge of firefighting in that catastrophic event.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ironically, it was Asano who was in charge of firefighting in that catastrophic event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>松の廊下の事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsu no roka (literally, a corridor of pine trees) incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsu no roka (literally, a corridor of pine trees) incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsu no roka (literally, a corridor of pine trees) incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>元禄14年（1701年）2月4日、播磨国赤穂藩主浅野長矩と伊予国宇和島藩伊予吉田藩主伊達村豊両名は、東山天皇の勅使である柳原資廉・高野保春・霊元天皇の院使である清閑寺熈定らの饗応役に命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 4, 1701, both Naganori ASANO, the lord of Ako domain in Harima Province, and Muratoyo DATE, the lord of Iyo-Yoshida domain, were appointed as receptionist for Imperial envoys of Emperor Higashiyama such as Sukekado YANAGIWARA, Yasuharu TAKANO, and Hirosada SEIKANJI, inshi (a messenger from the retired Emperor) of Emperor Reigen.</e>
<cmt>文末の表現が意味をなさなかったため、ウェブを参照して、後列の冒頭の箇所に貼り付けました。「伊予国宇和島藩伊予吉田藩主伊達村豊」の箇所ですが、リンク先の言葉が混在しているようです。ウェブを参照したところ、「伊予吉田藩主伊達村豊」となっていました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 4, 1701, both Naganori ASANO, the lord of the Ako domain in Harima Province, and Muratoyo DATE, the lord of the Iyo-Yoshida domain, were appointed as receptionists for the Imperial envoys of Emperor Higashiyama such as Sukekado YANAGIWARA, Yasuharu TAKANO and Hirosada SEIKANJI, an inshi (messenger from the retired Emperor) of Emperor Reigen.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 13, 1701, both Naganori ASANO, the lord of the Ako domain in Harima Province, and Muratoyo DATE, the lord of the Iyo-Yoshida domain in Iyo Province, were appointed as receptionists for the Imperial envoys of Emperor Higashiyama such as Sukekado YANAGIWARA, Yasuharu TAKANO and Hirosada SEIKANJI, an inshi (messenger from the retired Emperor) of Emperor Reigen.</e>
<cmt>①「元禄14年（1701年）2月4日」はグレゴリオ暦で、1701年3月13日であることから訳を変更しました。②翻訳者さんの指摘通り、「伊予国宇和島藩伊予吉田藩主伊達村豊」の箇所の混在部分ですが、補足で「伊予国」を訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>その際、義央は指南役に任命されたが、義央は朝廷への年賀の使者として京都におり、帰途に体調を崩して2月29日まで江戸に戻らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this occasion, Yoshihisa was ordered to be an instructor, but he was in Kyoto as an envoy to tell New Year&apos;s greetings for Imperial court, and got out of condition on his way home, so did not return to Edo until February 29.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, Yoshihisa was ordered to be an instructor, but he was in Kyoto as an envoy to convey New Year&apos;s greetings for the Imperial Court; but his condition diminished on the way home so he didn&apos;t return to Edo until February 29.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Yoshihisa was ordered to be an instructor, but he was in Kyoto as an envoy to convey New Year&apos;s greetings for the Imperial Court; but his condition diminished on the way home so he didn&apos;t return to Edo until April 7.</e>
<cmt>原文では単に「2月29日」となってますが、前文からの流れで「元禄14年2月29日」であると思われ、グレゴリオ暦の4月7日使用して訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>この間、2度目の饗応役であった浅野は過去の経験をもとに饗応準備をしていたが、かつてとは変更になっていることもあって手違いを生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Asano, whose work as a receptionist was his second time, prepared for treat based on his past experience, but a mistake occurred because some processes in the last time were changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Asano, whose was working as a receptionist for the second time, prepared for treatment based on his past experience, a mistake occurred because some of the processes had been changed since the last time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Asano, who was working as a receptionist for the second time, prepared for banquet based on his past experience, a mistake occurred because some of the processes had been changed since the last time.</e>
<cmt>①Asanoを受ける関係代名詞はwhoであると思います。②「饗応」の訳が原文から離れてしまってますので、banquetに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>ここに擦れ違いが生じた、と見る向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people think that a discrepancy arose here.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people believe a discrepancy arose here.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people believe a discrepancy arose here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="46">
<j>3月14日午前10時頃、城内大廊下にて浅野から額と背中を斬りつけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around ten o&apos;clock in the morning on March 14, ASANO slashed at him with a sword in a great corridor of the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At about ten o&apos;clock on the morning of March 14, ASANO slashed at him with a sword in a great corridor of the castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At about ten o&apos;clock on the morning of April 21, ASANO slashed at him with a sword in a great corridor of the castle.</e>
<cmt>原文の「3月14日」は「元禄14年3月14日」であると思われ、グレゴリオ暦の4月21日を使用して訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>浅野は旗本梶川頼照らに取り押さえられ、義央は高家品川伊氏・畠山義寧らによって蘇鉄の間へ運ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ASANO was arrested by Yoriteru KAJIKAWA, hatamoto, and others, then Yoshihisa was carried to the sotetsu no ma (a room of cycad) by Koreuji SHINAGAWA, koke, and Yoshiyasu HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ASANO was arrested by Yoriteru KAJIKAWA, hatamoto, and others, whereupon Yoshihisa was carried to the sotetsu no ma (a room of cycad) by Koreuji SHINAGAWA, koke, and Yoshiyasu HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ASANO was arrested by Yoriteru KAJIKAWA, hatamoto, and others, whereupon Yoshihisa was carried to the sotetsu no ma (a room of cycad) by Koreuji SHINAGAWA, koke, and Yoshiyasu HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>外科医栗崎道有の治療のおかげで命は助かり、額の傷は残らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to Douu KURISAKI, a surgeon, he was saved and a sword injury on his forehead disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to Douu KURISAKI, a surgeon, he was saved, and eventually the sword wound on his forehead disappeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to Douu KURISAKI, a surgeon, he was saved, and eventually the sword wound on his forehead disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>その後、目付大久保忠鎮らの取り調べを受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he was examined by Tadashige OKUBO, a metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was examined by Tadashige OKUBO, a metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was examined by Tadashige OKUBO, a metsuke (inspector of foot soldiers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>浅野を取り調べた目付多門重共の「多門筆記」によると、吉良は｢拙者何の恨うけ候覚えこれ無く、全く内匠頭乱心と相見へ申し候。且つ老体の事ゆえ何を恨み申し候や万々覚えこれ無き由｣と答えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;A Record by Okado,&apos; which was written by Shigetomo OKADO, a metsuke who examined ASANO, KIRA answered that &apos; I haven&apos;t done anything to deserve his enmity, and takumi-no-kami (the head of Bureau of Skilled Artisans) seems to have just become insane. Besides, I&apos;m so old that I don&apos;t remember why he had hard feelings against me.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;A Record by Okado,&apos; which was written by Shigetomo OKADO, a metsuke who had examined ASANO, KIRA answered, &apos;I haven&apos;t done anything to deserve his enmity, and takumi-no-kami (the head of the Bureau of Skilled Artisans) seems to have just become insane; besides, I&apos;m so old that I don&apos;t remember why he could have hard feelings against me.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;A Record by Okado,&apos; which was written by Shigetomo OKADO, a metsuke who had examined ASANO, KIRA answered, &apos;I haven&apos;t done anything to deserve his enmity, and takumi-no-kami (the head of the Bureau of Skilled Artisans) seems to have just become insane; besides, I&apos;m so old that I don&apos;t remember why he could have hard feelings against me.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>浅野は激怒した将軍徳川綱吉の命により、即日切腹となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ASANO was ordered to commit hara-kiri by Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, a shogun who got angry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ASANO was ordered to commit hara-kiri by the shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, whom the situation had angered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ASANO was ordered to commit hara-kiri by the shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, whom the situation had angered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="52">
<j>3月26日、高家肝煎職の御役御免願いを提出したが、旧赤穂藩士との確執が噂され、近所の阿波国徳島藩富田藩蜂須賀氏などからも懸念されたため、8月、幕命により吉良家は松平信望（5000石の旗本）の本所 (墨田区)の屋敷に移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 26, he asked to be released from a position of Koke-kimoiri (performing good offices for nobles), but there was a rumor that he had conflict with retainers of old Ako domain, and his neighbor Hachisuka clan who was from Tomida domain in Awa Province also worried, so the Kira family was ordered to move to a residence of Nobumochi MATSUDAIRA (hatamoto with 5000 koku) in Honjo (Sumida Ward) by bakufu in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 26, he asked to be released from a position of Koke-kimoiri (performing good offices for nobles), but there was a rumor that he was in conflict with retainers of the old Ako domain, and his neighbor the Hachisuka clan, from the Tomida domain in Awa Province, also worried, so in August the bakufu order the Kira family to move to a residence of Nobumochi MATSUDAIRA (hatamoto with 5,000 koku) in Honjo (Sumida Ward).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 3, he asked to be released from a position of Koke-kimoiri (performing good offices for nobles), but there was a rumor that he was in conflict with retainers of the old Ako domain, and his neighbor the Hachisuka clan, from the Tomida domain in Awa Province, also worried, so in September the bakufu order the Kira family to move to a residence of Nobumochi MATSUDAIRA (hatamoto with 5,000 koku) in Honjo (Sumida Ward).</e>
<cmt>①原文の「3月26日」は「元禄14年3月26日」であると思われ、グレゴリオ暦の5月3日を使用して訳を変更しました。②また、「8月」も「元禄14年8月」ですので、グレゴリオ暦では9月になるため、訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>当時の本所は江戸の郊外とされる辺鄙な所であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honjo in those days was located in an out-of-the-way place in the suburbs of Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honjo in those days was located in an out-of-the-way place in the suburbs of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honjo in those days was located in an out-of-the-way place in the suburbs of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>名門の吉良家がこのような辺鄙な所への屋敷換えされたことで、幕府は吉良家を見捨てた、もしくは逆に討ち入りをさせたかったという説が根強くある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also those who argue tenaciously that bakufu deserted him because the distinguished Kira family was ordered to move to such an inconvenient place by bakufu, or bakufu wanted the family to be attacked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also those who argue tenaciously that the bakufu deserted him because the distinguished Kira family was ordered to move to such an inconvenient place by the bakufu, or that the bakufu wanted the family to be attacked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also those who argue tenaciously that the bakufu deserted him because the distinguished Kira family was ordered to move to such an inconvenient place by the bakufu, or that the bakufu wanted the family to be attacked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="55">
<j>また、この屋敷替えに合わせるように、8月21日、大目付の庄田安利（浅野長矩は罪人であるとして庭先で切腹させた人物）・高家肝煎の大友義孝（吉良義央腹心の部下）・書院番士の東条冬重（義央の実弟）など、義央に近いと見られた人物が「勤めがよくない」として罷免されて小普請編入となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, on August 21, around the same time of his move, those who seemed to be close friends of Yoshihisa such as Yasutoshi SHODA, a Ometsuke, (a man who told that Naganori ASANO was a criminal and made him commit hara-kiri in the garden), and Fuyushige TOJO (Yoshihisa&apos;s real younger brother), shoinhanshi (the shogun&apos;s body guard or the castle guard), were relieved of thier posts because &apos;they were not doing well&apos; and they were put into kobushin (samurai without official appointments who receive small salaries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, on August 21, around the time of his move, those who seemed to be close friends of Yoshihisa, such as Yasutoshi SHODA, a Ometsuke, (the man who said that Naganori ASANO was a criminal and made him commit hara-kiri in the garden), and Fuyushige TOJO (Yoshihisa&apos;s younger blood brother), shoinhanshi (the shogun&apos;s bodyguard or the castle guard), were relieved of their posts because &apos;they were not doing well&apos; and they were made kobushin (samurai without official appointments who received small salaries).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, on September 23, around the time of his move, those who seemed to be close friends of Yoshihisa, such as Yasutoshi SHODA, a Ometsuke, (the man who said that Naganori ASANO was a criminal and made him commit hara-kiri in the garden), and Fuyushige TOJO (Yoshihisa&apos;s younger blood brother), shoinhanshi (the shogun&apos;s bodyguard or the castle guard), were relieved of their posts because &apos;they were not doing well&apos; and they were made kobushin (samurai without official appointments who received small salaries).</e>
<cmt>原文の「8月21日」は「元禄14年8月21日」のことであると思われますので、ゴレゴリオ暦の9月23日を使い訳し変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="56">
<j>一方、作家井沢元彦は、｢浅野のような男を饗応役として推薦・承認した責任を取らされたのではないか｣と、人事選考の失敗が原因で吉良一派が懲罰的処分を受けたとの見解を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Motohiko IZAWA, a writer, said, &apos;he might have been placed the responsibility for having recommended and approved a man like Asano as a receptionist,&apos; and suggested a view that the Kira family received a punishment because of a failure of selecting a person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Motohiko IZAWA, a writer, said, &apos;he might have been held responsible for having recommended and approved a man like Asano as a receptionist,&apos; and suggested a view that the Kira family receive a punishment due to the failure in selecting a person.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Motohiko IZAWA, a writer, said, &apos;he might have been held responsible for having recommended and approved a man like Asano as a receptionist,&apos; and suggested a view that the Kira family receive a punishment due to the failure in selecting a person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="57">
<j>さらに、屋敷替えに梅嶺院は同道せず、上杉家の芝白金の下屋敷へ移っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Baireiin did not accompany him when he moved, but she moved to a suburban residence of the Uesugi family in Shiba-Shirogane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Baireiin did not accompany him when he moved but instead moved to a suburban residence of the Uesugi family in Shiba-Shirogane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Baireiin did not accompany him when he moved but instead moved to a suburban residence of the Uesugi family in Shiba-Shirogane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>討ち入りを懸念して妻の身を案じたため、また、富子が「浅野も腹を切ったのだからあなたも切ったらどうです？」と言ったため不仲になった、新屋敷が狭くて大勢の女中を連れることができないため等、諸説があって定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories about it as follows but none of them are assured: he worried about being attacked and was anxious about his wife; they got to be on bad terms because Tomiko said, &apos;Asano committed hara-kiri, so why don&apos;t you do that, too?&apos;; because the new residence was small, he could not take a lot of maidservants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories about it (as follows), but none is certain: he worried about being attacked and was anxious about his wife; they came to be on bad terms because Tomiko said, &apos;Asano committed hara-kiri, so why don&apos;t you do that too?&apos;; or, because the new residence was small, he could not take a lot of maid-servants.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories about it (as follows), but none is certain: he worried about being attacked and was anxious about his wife; they came to be on bad terms because Tomiko said, &apos;Asano committed hara-kiri, so why don&apos;t you do that too?&apos;; or, because the new residence was small, he could not take a lot of maid-servants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="59">
<j>12月11日、義央は隠居願いを提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 11, Yoshihisa submitted a request of retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 11, Yoshihisa submitted a request for retirement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 8, 1702, Yoshihisa submitted a request for retirement.</e>
<cmt>原文の「12月11日」は「元禄14年12月11日」であると思われますので、グレゴリオ暦の1702年1月8日を使用し訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>高家肝煎に復帰できる見込みもなく、世論に押された幕府から処罰が下る前に先手を打ったものとも見られ、即座に受理された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that there was no hope of making a comeback to koke-kimoiri, so he took the initiative before he was punished by bakufu, which was supported by popular opinion, and his request was accepted immediately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apparently there was no hope of making a comeback to koke-kimoiri, so he took the initiative before he was punished by the bakufu, which was supported by popular opinion, and his request was immediately accepted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apparently there was no hope of making a comeback to koke-kimoiri, so he took the initiative before he was punished by the bakufu, which was supported by popular opinion, and his request was immediately accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>養嗣子吉良義周が家督を相続。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimasa KIRA, an adopted heir, succeeded to a property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimasa KIRA, an adopted heir, succeeded to a property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimasa KIRA, an adopted heir, succeeded to a property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>義央は隠居となり表高家に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa retired and took his place among omote-koke (koke without a title).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa retired and took his place among omote-koke (koke without a title).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa retired and took his place among omote-koke (koke without a title).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="63">
<j>元禄15年（1702年）7月に浅野長広が浅野本家に預かりとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, 1702, Nagahiro ASANO became a custody of the main family of Asano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1702, Nagahiro ASANO came into the custody of the main family of Asano.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1702, Nagahiro ASANO came into the custody of the main family of Asano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>吉良は茶会を12月4日に計画していたが、当日は将軍綱吉が柳沢吉保邸に訪問するために14日になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kira planned a tea party held on December 4, but shogun Tsunayoshi was going to visit a residence of Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA on the day, so it was rescheduled for 14th.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kira planned a tea party to be held on December 4, but the shogun Tsunayoshi was going to visit the residence of Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA on the day, so it was rescheduled for the 14th.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kira planned a tea party to be held on January 20, 1703, but the shogun Tsunayoshi was going to visit the residence of Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA on the day, so it was rescheduled for the 30th.</e>
<cmt>原文の「12月4日」は「元禄15年12月4日」と思われ、グレゴリオ暦の1703年1月20日を使用し訳し変えました。また、「（12月）14日」も同様に、グレゴリオ暦では30日となるため、訳し変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>この情報は茶人山田宗偏を通じて、宗偏の弟子脇屋新兵衛（その正体は47士の1人大高源五）につかまれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This information was conveyed to Shinbei WAKIYA (actually, he was Gengo OTAKA, one of the 47 retainers), a disciple of Sohen YAMADA, a master of tea ceremony through him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This information was conveyed to Shinbei WAKIYA (actually, he was Gengo OTAKA, one of the 47 retainers), a disciple of Sohen YAMADA, a master of tea ceremony through him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through Sohen YAMADA, a master of tea ceremony, this information was conveyed to Shinbei WAKIYA (actually, he was Gengo OTAKA, one of the 47 retainers), who was a disciple of Sohen.</e>
<cmt>翻訳文の最後のthrough himの部分が文全体と接続できないため、文頭にもっていき文の流れを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>元筆頭家老大石良雄は討ち入り日に決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshio OISHI, the former hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) decided the date of raid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshio OISHI, the former hitto karo (head of chief retainers) decided on the date of the raid.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshio OISHI, the former hitto karo (head of chief retainers) decided on the date of the raid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of his life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The end of his life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The end of his life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>15日深夜、大石を始めとする赤穂浪士四十七士が吉良邸に討ち入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 15th at midnight, 47 Ako Roshi (lordless samurai of Ako domain) such as Oishi attacked the residence of Kira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At midnight on the 15th, 47 Ako Roshi (lordless samurai of the Ako domain), including Oishi, attacked the residence of Kira.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At midnight on the 31th, 47 Ako Roshi (lordless samurai of the Ako domain), including Oishi, attacked the residence of Kira.</e>
<cmt>原文「15日｣は「元禄15年12月15日」のことで、グレゴリオ暦では1703年1月31日のことであるため、訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>義周はじめ吉良家臣らは防戦にあたるも、義央自身は炭小屋に隠れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimasa and his retainers fought in defense, while Yoshihisa hid himself in a charcoal cabin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimasa and his retainers fought in defense, and Yoshihisa hid in a charcoal shed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimasa and his retainers fought in defense, and Yoshihisa hid in a charcoal shed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>赤穂浪士たちは吉良の捜索にあたったものの、容易に見つけることはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ako Roshi tried to search Kira, but they could not find him easily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ako Roshi searched in vain for Kira, but he wasn&apos;t so easily found.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ako Roshi searched in vain for Kira, but he wasn&apos;t so easily found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>吉田忠左衛門や間十次郎らが、台所横の炭小屋から話し声がしたため、中へ入ろうとするや、皿鉢や炭などが投げつけられ、2人の吉良家臣たちが斬りかかってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chuzaemon YOSHIDA and Jujiro HAZAMA heard somebody talking in the charcoal cabin beside the kitchen, so they tried to go into it, but bowls and charcoal were thrown to them, and two retainers of Kira family was attacking them with swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuzaemon YOSHIDA and Jujiro HAZAMA heard somebody talking in the charcoal shed beside the kitchen, so they tried to enter it, but bowls and charcoal were thrown at them, and two retainers of the Kira family attacked them with swords.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuzaemon YOSHIDA and Jujiro HAZAMA heard somebody talking in the charcoal shed beside the kitchen, so they tried to enter it, but bowls and charcoal were thrown at them, and two retainers of the Kira family attacked them with swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>切り伏せたあと、奥で動くものがあったため、間十次郎に槍で突いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After they defeated the retainers, Jujiro HAZAMA lanced something with that moved in the back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they defeated the retainers, Jujiro HAZAMA lanced something that moved in the back.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they defeated the retainers, Jujiro HAZAMA lanced something that moved in the back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>義央は脇差で抵抗しようとするも、武林唯七に斬り捨てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa tried to resist with his short sword, but he was cut down by Tadashichi TAKEBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa tried to resist with his short sword, but he was cut down by Tadashichi TAKEBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa tried to resist with his short sword, but he was cut down by Tadashichi TAKEBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>なお、吉良家の戦死者は小林平八郎・清水一学・新貝弥七郎・鳥居利右衛門・須藤与一右衛門・左右田源八郎ら17名（一説に16名）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, 17 people of the Kira family were killed such as Heihachiro KOBAYASHI, Ichigaku SHIMIZU, Yashichiro SHINKAI, Riemon TORII, Yoichiemon SUDO, and Genpachiro SODA. (according to another account, 16 people were killed.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, 17 people of the Kira family were killed, including Heihachiro KOBAYASHI, Ichigaku SHIMIZU, Yashichiro SHINKAI, Riemon TORII, Yoichiemon SUDO and Genpachiro SODA (according to another account, 16 people were killed).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, 17 people of the Kira family were killed, including Heihachiro KOBAYASHI, Ichigaku SHIMIZU, Yashichiro SHINKAI, Riemon TORII, Yoichiemon SUDO and Genpachiro SODA (according to another account, 16 people were killed).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>重傷者は山吉新八郎ら23名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">23 people including Shinpachiro YAMAYOSHI were Severely wounded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twenty-three people, including Shinpachiro YAMAYOSHI, were severely wounded.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Twenty-three people, including Shinpachiro YAMAYOSHI, were severely wounded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>それ以外の家臣は戦意を喪失して戦わなかったようである（討ち入った浪士たちは口々に「五十人組、百人組」等と叫び、大人数での討ち入りであると見せかけようとしており、米沢藩邸に急を知らせた吉良邸近所の豆腐屋も、「赤穂の浪人およそ百五十人ほど討ち入り」と伝えていたという）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other retainers seem to have lost their fighting spirit and did not fight. (Roshi who raid Kira&apos;s residence cried respectively, &apos;a group of fifty people, a group of one hundred people, trying to pretend to be a raid by many people, so a tofu (bean-curd) dealer living in Kira&apos;s neighbor told the people in the residence of Yonezawa domain about this attack, saying &apos;around 150 Ako ronin made a raid.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other retainers seemed to lose their fighting spirit and did not fight (Roshi, who raided Kira&apos;s residence, cried, &apos;a group of 50 people, a group of 100 people, trying to pretend to be a raid by many people, so a tofu (bean-curd) dealer living in Kira&apos;s neighborhood told the people in the residence of the Yonezawa domain about this attack, saying that &apos;about 150 Ako ronin had conducted a raid).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other retainers seemed to lose their fighting spirit and did not fight (Roshi, who raided Kira&apos;s residence, cried, &apos;a group of 50 people, a group of 100 people, trying to pretend to be a raid by many people, so a tofu (bean-curd) dealer living in Kira&apos;s neighborhood told the people in the residence of the Yonezawa domain about this attack, saying that &apos;about 150 Ako ronin had conducted a raid).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="76">
<j>吉良家臣たちは幕命により上杉家が管理するが、綱憲は勇戦が認められた7名のみを召抱え、戦わなかった家臣はすべて追い払っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakufu ordered the Uesugi family to supervise the retainers of Kira, but Tsunanori took only seven people who fought bravely, and drove away all retainers who did not fight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu ordered the Uesugi family to supervise the retainers of Kira, but Tsunanori took only seven brave fighters and drove away all the retainers who did not resist.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu ordered the Uesugi family to supervise the retainers of Kira, but Tsunanori took only seven brave fighters and drove away all the retainers who did not resist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>奮戦者としては小林と清水が有名だが、「大河内文書」によると大した活躍はしておらず、一番活躍したのは山吉新八郎や新貝弥七郎など上杉家派遣の家臣達であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobayashi and Shimizu are known as retainers who fought hard, but according to &apos;Okochi document,&apos; they did not work so much, and the best fighters were retainers who were sent by the Uesugi family such as Shinpachiro YAMAYOSHI and Yashichiro SHINKAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobayashi and Shimizu are known as retainers who fought hard, but according to the &apos;Okochi document&apos; they did not work so much; it goes on to state that the best fighters were retainers who had been sent by the Uesugi family, such as Shinpachiro YAMAYOSHI and Yashichiro SHINKAI.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobayashi and Shimizu are known as retainers who fought hard, but according to the &apos;Okochi document&apos; they did not work so much; it goes on to state that the best fighters were retainers who had been sent by the Uesugi family, such as Shinpachiro YAMAYOSHI and Yashichiro SHINKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>なお、近松行重が池に斬り落とされているが、この近松の相手をしたのも山吉新八郎であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that it was Shinpachiro YAMAYOSHI who cut Yukichige CHIKAMATSU down into the pond.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it was Shinpachiro YAMAYOSHI who cut Yukichige CHIKAMATSU down into the pond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it was Shinpachiro YAMAYOSHI who cut Yukichige CHIKAMATSU down into the pond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="79">
<j>吉良の首は泉岳寺の浅野長矩の墓前に捧げられたあと、箱に詰めて同寺に預けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of Kira was dedicated in front of the grave of Naganori ASANO in Sengaku-ji Temple, then they put it into a box and asked the temple to look after it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of Kira was dedicated in front of the grave of Naganori ASANO at Sengaku-ji Temple, after which they put it into a box and asked the temple to look after it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of Kira was dedicated in front of the grave of Naganori ASANO at Sengaku-ji Temple, after which they put it into a box and asked the temple to look after it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>寺では僧二人にこれを持たせて吉良家へ送り返し、家老左右田孫兵衛と斎藤宮内がこれを受け取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple made two monks take it back to the Kira family, and Magobe SODA, a chief retainer, and Kunai SAITO accepted it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple made two monks take it back to the Kira family, and Magobe SODA, a chief retainer, and accepted it together with Kunai SAITO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple made two monks take it back to the Kira family, and Magobe SODA, a chief retainer, and accepted it together with Kunai SAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>二人の連署の署名がある吉良の首の領収書を泉岳寺が残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sengaku-ji Temple keeps an acknowledgment of Kira&apos;s head jointly signed by them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengaku-ji Temple keeps an acknowledgment of Kira&apos;s head jointly signed by them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengaku-ji Temple keeps an acknowledgment of Kira&apos;s head jointly signed by them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>先の刃傷時に治療にあたった栗崎道有が首と胴体をつなぎ合わせたあと、菩提寺の万昌寺に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Douu KURISAKI, who treated Yoshihisa when he got a sword injury, connected his head to the body, and then he was buried in Kira&apos;s family temple, Mansho-ji.</e>
<cmt>万昌寺の正しい読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Douu KURISAKI, who treated Yoshihisa when he got a sword injury, connected his head to the body, and then he was buried in Kira&apos;s family temple, Mansho-ji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Douu KURISAKI, who treated Yoshihisa when he got a sword injury, connected his head to the body, and then he was buried in Kira&apos;s family temple, Mansho-ji.</e>
<cmt>「万昌寺」の正しい読み方不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>戒名「霊性寺殿実山相公大居士」、享年62。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name is &apos;Reishojidenjitsuzanshokodaikoji,&apos; and he died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>戒名の意味はわからなかったため、ローマ字表記のみです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous Buddhist name is &apos;Reishojidenjitsuzanshokodaikoji,&apos; and he died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous Buddhist name is &apos;Reishojidenjitsuzanshokodaikoji,&apos; and he died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="84">
<j>この当時の万昌寺は市ヶ谷にあったが、大正期に万昌院と改めて中野に移転に伴って墓も移動し、現在は史跡に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mansho-ji Temple in those days was located at Ichigaya, but it was renamed Mansho-in during the Taisho period and moved to Nakano, so his grave was also relocated and it is now designated as a historic site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mansho-ji Temple in those days was located at Ichigaya, but it was renamed Mansho-in during the Taisho period and moved to Nakano, so his grave was also relocated and is now designated as a historic site.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mansho-ji Temple in those days was located at Ichigaya, but it was renamed Mansho-in during the Taisho period and moved to Nakano, so his grave was also relocated and is now designated as a historic site.</e>
<cmt>「万昌寺」の正しい読み方不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public estimation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The public&apos;s assessment</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The public&apos;s assessment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>忠臣蔵の「悪役」として有名な義央の評価は芳しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa is not so popular because he is known as &apos;the villain&apos; in Chusingura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa isn&apos;t very popular because he&apos;s known as &apos;the villain&apos; in Chusingura.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa isn&apos;t very popular because he&apos;s known as &apos;the villain&apos; in Chusingura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>しかし、領地三河国幡豆郡では、貞享3年（1686年）に築いた黄金堤による治水事業や富好新田をはじめとする新田開拓や人柄から名君とされ、地元では慕われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in his territory, Hazu District of Mikawa Province, he is considered a wise ruler and still liked due to the golden bank which he made in 1686, flood prevention projects, and a development of new rice fields such as Tomiyoshi Shinden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in his territory--Hazu District of Mikawa Province--he&apos;s considered a wise ruler and is still liked due to the golden bank that he built in 1686, as well as flood-prevention projects and the development of new rice fields such as Tomiyoshi Shinden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in his territory--Hazu District of Mikawa Province--he&apos;s considered a wise ruler and is still liked due to the golden bank that he built in 1686, as well as flood-prevention projects and the development of new rice fields such as Tomiyoshi Shinden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>吉良町には赤馬という郷土玩具が存在するが、これは義央が赤馬に乗って領内を視察したのを機に作られた玩具だとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a folk toy called Akauma (a red horse) in Kira town, and it is said to have been made when Yoshihisa inspected his territory on the back of his red horse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a folk toy called Akauma (a red horse) in Kira Town, and it is said to have been made when Yoshihisa inspected his territory on the back of his red horse.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a folk toy called Akauma (a red horse) in Kira Town, and it is said to have been made when Yoshihisa inspected his territory on the back of his red horse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="88">
<j>もっとも、義央は領地を殆ど訪れた形跡がないことから（領地に入ったことが確認されているのは僅か一度のみ）、地元での評価は汚名を着せられた領主に対する同情によるところが大きいと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there was no trace of Yoshihisa&apos;s visit to his territory (it was confirmed that Yoshihisa went to his territory only once), so it is considered that he was appreciated in the place he came from mainly because the people seem to have sympathized with thier lord, who was slurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there was no trace of Yoshihisa&apos;s visit to his territory (it was confirmed that Yoshihisa went to his territory only once), so it is considered that he was appreciated in the place he came from mainly because the people seemed to have sympathized with their lord, who had been slain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there was no trace of Yoshihisa&apos;s visit to his territory (it was confirmed that Yoshihisa went to his territory only once), so it is considered that he was appreciated in the place he came from mainly because the people seemed to have sympathized with their lord, who had been slain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="89">
<j>吉良には浅野内匠頭以外の饗応役にも、いわゆるいじめを行っていたという逸話が多く残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many anecdotes about Kira&apos;s what is called ill-treatment to the receptionists other than Asano Takumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many anecdotes regarding Kira&apos;s so-called ill-treatment of receptionists other than Asano Takumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many anecdotes regarding Kira&apos;s so-called ill-treatment of receptionists other than Asano Takumi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>しかし物語としての『忠臣蔵』が成立した後に、物語のイメージから後世に創作された可能性も高いので、注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, we have to be careful about treating these anecdotes because after &quot;Chusingura&quot; as a tale was completed, people could have made up these stories under the influence of tale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, one must be cautious in regard to such anecdotes because, after &quot;Chusingura&quot; as a tale was completed, people could have made up such stories under the influence of the tale.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, one must be cautious in regard to such anecdotes because, after &quot;Chusingura&quot; as a tale was completed, people could have made up such stories under the influence of the tale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="91">
<j>元禄11年（1698年）、勅使饗応役となった亀井茲親は義央からいじめを受け、耐えかねた茲親は家老の多胡真蔭にもらしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in 1698, Korechika KAMEI, who became a receptionist for Imperial envoys, was treated harshly by Yoshihisa, and Korechika could not stand it any more and revealed it to chief retainer Sanekake TAKO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in 1698 Korechika KAMEI, who became a receptionist for Imperial envoys, was treated harshly by Yoshihisa, but Korechika could no longer stand it and therefore notified the chief retainer, Sanekake TAKO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in 1698 Korechika KAMEI, who became a receptionist for Imperial envoys, was treated harshly by Yoshihisa, but Korechika could no longer stand it and therefore notified the chief retainer, Sanekake TAKO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>真蔭は主君を諫める一方で、密かに金遣役を呼んで納戸金一箱を取り出させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Sanekake protested against his lord, he secretly called a person who was in charge of supervising money, and made him take a box of money in a storage room.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Sanekake protested against his lord, he secretly called a person who was in charge of supervising money and made him take a box of money from a storage room.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Sanekake protested against his lord, he secretly called a person who was in charge of supervising money and made him take a box of money from a storage room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>彼はそれを茶菓子のなかに入れて手土産として吉良邸へ持参した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He put it into a refreshment served with tea and brought it to the residence of Kira as a gift.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He put it into a refreshment served with tea and brought it to the residence of Kira as a gift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He put it into a refreshment served with tea and brought it to the residence of Kira as a gift.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>主君の無礼を詫びたうえ、指導引き回しを懇願して帰邸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He apologized for his lord&apos;s impoliteness, begged earnestly him to lead his lord, and went home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He apologized for his lord&apos;s impoliteness, begged him earnestly him to forgive his lord, and went home.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He apologized for his lord&apos;s impoliteness, begged him earnestly to forgive his lord, and went home.</e>
<cmt>himが二重に使用されてましたので、不要な語を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>翌日より茲親への態度が急に優しくなったので事なきをえた、という話が津和野名産の茶菓子源氏巻誕生の逸話として残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the following day, he suddenly came to treat Korechika gently, so the situation didn&apos;t become serious, which has been handed down as an anecdote about the origin of a noted confection called Genjimaki made in Tsuwano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the following day, he suddenly came to treat Korechika gently, so the situation didn&apos;t become serious; this has been handed down as an anecdote about the origin of a noted confection called Genjimaki, made in Tsuwano.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the following day, he suddenly came to treat Korechika gently, so the situation didn&apos;t become serious; this has been handed down as an anecdote about the origin of a noted confection called Genjimaki, made in Tsuwano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>その逸話の初出は、大田南畝（蜀山人）の「半日閑話」(1749年)であり、さらに桃井若狭之助（亀井玆親）と加古川本蔵（多胡真蔭）のエピソードが登場する『仮名手本忠臣蔵』(1748年初上演)の後に書かれているので、後世の創作の可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The anecdote first appeared in &apos;Hannichi kanwa&apos; (A half-day of leisurely talk) (1749) by Nanbo OTA (Shokusanjin), and it was written after &quot;Kanatehon Chusingura&quot; (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers) (first performed in 1748), which contains an episode of Wakasanosuke MOMOI (Korechika KAMEI) and Honzo KAKOGAWA (Sanekake TAKO), so there is a strong possibility that it was made by the posterity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The anecdote first appeared in &apos;Hannichi kanwa (A Half-Day of Leisurely Talk)&apos; (1749) by Nanbo OTA (Shokusanjin), and it was written after &quot;Kanatehon Chusingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers)&quot; (first performed in 1748), which contains an episode of Wakasanosuke MOMOI (Korechika KAMEI) and Honzo KAKOGAWA (Sanekake TAKO), so there is a strong possibility that it was created through posterity.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The anecdote first appeared in &apos;Hannichi kanwa (A Half-Day of Leisurely Talk)&apos; (1749) by Nanbo OTA (Shokusanjin), and it was written after &quot;Kanatehon Chusingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers)&quot; (first performed in 1748), which contains an episode of Wakasanosuke MOMOI (Korechika KAMEI) and Honzo KAKOGAWA (Sanekake TAKO), so there is a strong possibility that it was created through posterity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="97">
<j>なお、浅野が刃傷に及ぶ前、加藤泰恒（伊予大洲藩主）や戸沢正庸（出羽新庄藩主）が日光法会中に受けた義央のいじめを浅野に伝え、お役目を終えるまで耐えよと諭した逸話が、冷光君御伝記（誠尽忠臣記よりの情報としている）や義人録（広島藩士御牧武大夫信久の証言として）などに記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Record of Reikogimi (information that is Seijin Chushinki-friendly) and A Record of Gijin (as an evidence of Mimaki Budayu Nobuhisa, a retainer of Hiroshima domain) contain an anecdote about Yasutsune KATO (the lord of Ozu domain in Iyo Province) and Masatsune TOZAWA (the lord of Shinjo domain in Dewa Province), who told Asano about Yoshihisa&apos;s ill-treatment during the Nikko Buddhist religious service, and were persuaded to stand until the end of their services.</e>
<cmt>「誠尽忠臣記」、「御牧武大夫信久」の正しい読み方不明です。冷光君御伝記、義人録の定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Record of Reikogimi (information that is Seijin Chushinki-friendly) and A Record of Gijin (as evidence of Mimaki Budayu Nobuhisa, a retainer of the Hiroshima domain) contain an anecdote about Yasutsune KATO (lord of the Ozu domain in Iyo Province) and Masatsune TOZAWA (lord of the Shinjo domain in Dewa Province), who told Asano about Yoshihisa&apos;s ill-treatment during the Nikko Buddhist religious service but were persuaded to stand until the end of their services.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Record of Reikogimi (information that is Seijin Chushinki-friendly) and A Record of Gijin (as evidence of Mimaki Budayu Nobuhisa, a retainer of the Hiroshima domain) contain an anecdote about Yasutsune KATO (lord of the Ozu domain in Iyo Province) and Masatsune TOZAWA (lord of the Shinjo domain in Dewa Province), who told Asano about Yoshihisa&apos;s ill-treatment during the Nikko Buddhist religious service but were persuaded to stand until the end of their services.</e>
<cmt>「誠尽忠臣記」、「御牧武大夫信久」の正しい読み方不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="98">
<j>上杉家家臣たちからの評価も芳しくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retainers of Uesugi family did not appreciate him very much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retainers of the Uesugi family did not appreciate him very much.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retainers of the Uesugi family did not appreciate him very much.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>出納帳には「上野介殿江」という項目が設けられ、吉良家の買掛金や普請は上杉家が持つのが恒例となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The account book had a category like &apos;to Kozuke no Suke&apos; and it was customary for the Uesugi family to adjust accounts payable and paid for construction of the Kira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The account book had a category such as &apos;to Kozuke no Suke,&apos; and it was customary for the Uesugi family to adjust accounts payable and pay the costs of construction for the Kira family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The account book had a category such as &apos;to Kozuke no Suke,&apos; and it was customary for the Uesugi family to adjust accounts payable and pay the costs of construction for the Kira family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>呉服橋の新邸も上杉家から支出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new residence in Gofukubashi was also paid by the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new residence in Gofukubashi was also paid for by the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new residence in Gofukubashi was also paid for by the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>江戸勘定須田右近は米沢の重臣にあてた書状の中で「当方もやがて吉良家同然にならん」と書き遺している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukon SUDA, Edo kanjo (an official), left a letter to a chief retainer of Yonezawa, in which he wrote that &apos;before long we will be like the Kira family.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukon SUDA, Edo kanjo (an official), left a letter to a chief retainer of Yonezawa, in which he wrote that &apos;before long we will be like the Kira family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukon SUDA, Edo kanjo (an official), left a letter to a chief retainer of Yonezawa, in which he wrote that &apos;before long we will be like the Kira family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>そのため、近年の忠臣蔵を扱ったドラマの中には上杉家江戸家老の色部安長が「金食い虫」吉良を消すため策動したものであるかのように描くものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore among the dramas concerning Chusingura in recent years, some of the describe the incident as if Yasunaga IROBE, Edo-garo of the Uesugi family, maneuvered for killing Kira, &apos;a money-eater.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, among the dramas concerning Chusingura in recent years, some describe the incident as if Yasunaga IROBE, Edo-garo of the Uesugi family, who maneuvered for the killing of Kira, was &apos;a money-eater.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, among the dramas concerning Chusingura in recent years, some describe the incident as if Yasunaga IROBE, Edo-garo of the Uesugi family, maneuvered for the killing of Kira, &apos;a money-eater.&apos;</e>
<cmt>as if 以降の文におけるNCの解釈が間違っているため、翻訳者さんの訳に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>真偽は不明だが、上杉家にとって吉良の存在は、上杉鷹山による藩政改革まで藩財政を窮乏させる要因のひとつになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not certain whether it is true or not, but the Uesugi family was painfully hard up for money partly due to Kira until the reformation of domain duties by Yozan UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not certain whether it is true or not, but the Uesugi family was painfully hard up for money--partly due to Kira--until the reformation of domain duties by Yozan UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not certain whether it is true or not, but the Uesugi family was painfully hard up for money--partly due to Kira--until the reformation of domain duties by Yozan UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="104">
<j>更に事件が朝廷に伝わった時、東山天皇の嬉々としていた様子が関白近衛基熙の日記に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, when the incident was reported to the Imperial court, Emperor Higashiyama was so glad, which was recorded in the diary of Chancellor Motohiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, when the incident was reported to the Imperial Court, Emperor Higashiyama was very glad; this was recorded in the diary of Chancellor Motohiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, when the incident was reported to the Imperial Court, Emperor Higashiyama was very glad; this was recorded in the diary of Chancellor Motohiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>幕府の方針を忠実に実行しただけとはいえ、吉良は幕府による朝廷抑制政策の通達役に立つことが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kira carried out faithfully what bakufu decided, he often played a role of telling policies of repressing Imperial court by order of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kira had faithfully carried out the decisions of the bakufu, he often served to convey policies that repressed the Imperial Court under order of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kira had faithfully carried out the decisions of the bakufu, he often served to convey policies that repressed the Imperial Court under order of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>そのため、天皇もまた吉良に含むところがあった事が推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it is conjectured that the Emperor also had something against Kira on his mind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is conjectured that the Emperor also had something against Kira on his mind.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is conjectured that the Emperor also had something against Kira on his mind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="107">
<j>茶道としての義央は、茶匠千宗旦の晩年の弟子の一人であり、『茶道便蒙抄』を著した茶人山田宗偏などとも親交を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa was one of the disciples of a tea master, SEN no Sotan, who was in his later years, and had also a friendship with tea masters such as Sohen YAMADA, who wrote &quot;Chado benmosho&quot; (a manual of tea ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa was one of the disciples of a tea master, SEN no Sotan, who was in his later years, and had a friendship with tea masters such as Sohen YAMADA, who wrote &quot;Chado benmosho&quot; (a tea-ceremony manual).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa was one of the disciples of a tea master, SEN no Sotan, who was in his later years, and had a friendship with tea masters such as Sohen YAMADA, who wrote &quot;Chado benmosho&quot; (a tea-ceremony manual).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>「卜一（ぼくいち・上野介の上の字を二分したもの）」という茶の号を持ち、卜一流を興していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a name of &apos;Bokuichi&apos; (the first letter of his name, Kozuke no Suke, was divided into two), and began Bokuichi School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had the name &apos;Bokuichi&apos; (the first letter of his name, Kozuke no Suke, was divided into two), and established the Bokuichi School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the name &apos;Bokuichi&apos; (the first letter of his name, Kozuke no Suke, was divided into two), and established the Bokuichi School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Notes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>義央以外の高家衆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koke members excluding Yoshihisa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koke members, excluding Yoshihisa</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koke members, excluding Yoshihisa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="109">
<j>刃傷事件があった元禄14年（1701年）、吉良は高家肝煎の地位にあったが、当時高家肝煎は吉良を含めて9人いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1701, when the sword fight occurred, Kira was in a position of Koke-kimoiri, and there were nine people who were in that position then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1701, when the swordfight occurred, Kira was in the position of Koke-kimoiri, and at the time there were nine people in such a position.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1701, when the swordfight occurred, Kira was in the position of Koke-kimoiri, and at the time there were nine people in such a position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>吉良以外では畠山基玄（従四位上侍従）・大友義孝（従四位下侍従）・品川伊氏（従四位下侍従）・京極高規（従四位下侍従）・戸田氏興 (旗本)（従四位下侍従）・織田信門（従五位下侍従）・畠山義寧（従五位下侍従）・横瀬貞顕（従五位下侍従）である（元禄14年当時）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than Kira, they were Motokuro HATAKEYAMA (Jushiijo jiju (a chamberlain)), Yoshitaka OTOMO (Jushiinoge jiju (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade Chamberlain)), Koreuji SHINAGAWA (Jushiinoge jiju), Takatsuki KYOGOKU (Jushiinoge jiju), Ujioki TODA (hatamoto) (Jushiinoge jiju), Nobukado ODA (Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) jiju), Yoshiyasu HATAKEYAMA (Jugoinoge jiju), and Sadaakira YOKOSE (Jugoinoge jiju). (as of 1702)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than Kira, they were Motokuro HATAKEYAMA (Jushiijo jiju (a chamberlain)), Yoshitaka OTOMO (Jushiinoge jiju (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade Chamberlain)), Koreuji SHINAGAWA (Jushiinoge jiju), Takatsuki KYOGOKU (Jushiinoge jiju), Ujioki TODA (hatamoto) (Jushiinoge jiju), Nobukado ODA (Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) jiju), Yoshiyasu HATAKEYAMA (Jugoinoge jiju), and Sadaakira YOKOSE (Jugoinoge jiju) (as of 1702).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than Kira, they were Motokuro HATAKEYAMA (Jushiijo jiju (a chamberlain)), Yoshitaka OTOMO (Jushiinoge jiju (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade Chamberlain)), Koreuji SHINAGAWA (Jushiinoge jiju), Takatsuki KYOGOKU (Jushiinoge jiju), Ujioki TODA (hatamoto) (Jushiinoge jiju), Nobukado ODA (Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) jiju), Yoshiyasu HATAKEYAMA (Jugoinoge jiju), and Sadaakira YOKOSE (Jugoinoge jiju) (as of 1701).</e>
<cmt>「元禄14年」は西暦1701年であるため、訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>吉良・畠山・大友の三人が高家肝煎職だが、なかでも吉良は高家肝煎職の最古参であり、且つ唯一の左少将であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kira, Hatakeyama, and Otomo were Koke-kimoiri, and Kira was the oldest and the only Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kira, Hatakeyama, and Otomo were Koke-kimoiri, and Kira was the oldest and the only Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kira, Hatakeyama, and Otomo were Koke-kimoiri, and Kira was the oldest and the only Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>高家筆頭と呼ばれているのはこのためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why he was called Koke hitto (highest rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why he was called Koke hitto (highest rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why he was called Koke hitto (highest rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>江戸っ子と田舎大名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A person born in Edo and rustic daimyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A person born in Edo and a rustic daimyo</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A person born in Edo and a rustic daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="113">
<j>吉良が浅野に「田舎大名」などと言った根拠はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no evidence for Kira&apos;s telling Asano &apos;rustic daimyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no evidence that Kira had described Asano as a &apos;rustic daimyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no evidence that Kira had described Asano as a &apos;rustic daimyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>ただ、吉良も三河国（愛知県）に領地を持つ旗本である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kira was also a hatamoto who had territory in Mikawa Province (Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kira was also a hatamoto who had territory in Mikawa Province (Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kira was also a hatamoto who had territory in Mikawa Province (Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>両者の違いは、旗本と大名の問題に起因している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The difference between them had its origin in a problem of hatamoto and daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The difference between them had its origin in the problem of hatamoto and daimyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The difference between them had its origin in the problem of hatamoto and daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>旗本は自らの領地に入ることがほとんどなく、家臣を代官に任命して派遣し、すべてを任せている場合がほとんどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hatamoto hardly visited his own territory, and sent thier retainers, appointing them as deputy, and most of hatamoto entrusted everything to the deputies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatamoto hardly visited his own territory but instead sent their retainers, appointing them as deputies, and most of the hatamoto entrusted everything to the deputies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatamoto hardly visited his own territory but instead sent their retainers, appointing them as deputies, and most of the hatamoto entrusted everything to the deputies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>吉良も領地三河国幡豆郡吉良町に入ったのは一度のみで、上野国緑野郡白石村と碓氷郡人見村に至っては一度も行ったことがない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kira also visited his territory, Kira-cho, Hazu District in Mikawa Province, only once, and had never visited Shiraishi village, Midono District in Kozuke Province and Hitomi village in Usui District.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kira also visited his territory (Kira-cho, Hazu District, Mikawa Province) only once but had never visited Shiraishi Village, Midono District, Kozuke Province; or Hitomi Village, in Usui District.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kira also visited his territory (Kira-cho, Hazu District, Mikawa Province) only once but had never visited Shiraishi Village, Midono District, Kozuke Province; or Hitomi Village, in Usui District.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>そのため、旗本が領地にアイデンティティを持つことはほとんどない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore hatamoto hardly had a sense of identity in his territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, hatamoto hardly had a sense of identity within his territory.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, hatamoto hardly had a sense of identity within his territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>一方、大名（特に外様大名）は参勤交代で隔年に領地に入るので、領地にアイデンティティを持つ傾向が強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, daimyo (especially tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord)) tended to have a sense of identity in their lands because they visited the places due to sankinkotai (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo) every other year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the daimyo (especially the tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lords)) tended to have a sense of identity in their lands because they visited the places due to sankinkotai (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo) every other year.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the daimyo (especially the tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lords)) tended to have a sense of identity in their lands because they visited the places due to sankinkotai (daimyo&apos;s alternate-year residence in Edo) every other year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>旗本や譜代大名からは「田舎大名」と失笑を買うことがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were sometimes laughed at by hatamoto and fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), saying &apos;rustic daimyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were sometimes laughed at by the hatamoto and fudai daimyo (a daimyo in a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), who called them &apos;rustic daimyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were sometimes laughed at by the hatamoto and fudai daimyo (a daimyo in a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), who called them &apos;rustic daimyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>吉良と大石の親戚関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A kinship relation between Kira and Oishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A kinship relation between Kira and Oishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kinship relation between Kira and Oishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>吉良と大石の二人は、近衛家諸大夫進藤家と斎藤家を通じる形で遠縁がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kira and Oishi were distantly related through Konoe family shodaibu (fourth and fifth-rank officials) Shindo family and Saito family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kira and Oishi were distantly related through the Konoe family shodaibu (fourth- and fifth-rank officials), the Shindo and Saito families.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kira and Oishi were distantly related through the Konoe family shodaibu (fourth- and fifth-rank officials), the Shindo and Saito families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>吉良から見れば、妻の母親の実家を継いだ者が大石家の血の流れる者だったということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To Kira, the one who succeeded to a family home of his wife&apos;s mother was somebody who was related to the Oishi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To Kira, the one who succeeded to the family home of his wife&apos;s mother was related to the Oishi family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To Kira, the one who succeeded to the family home of his wife&apos;s mother was related to the Oishi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>しかし、事件前から面識があったかどうかは不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is not clear whether they had known each other before the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is not clear whether they had known each other before the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is not clear whether they had known each other before the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="124">
<j>太線は実子、細線は夫婦、二重線は養子、点線は養子入り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thick lines indicate biological child; thin lines indicate husband and wife: double lines indicate adopted child; dot lines indicate received child for adoption.</e>
<cmt>「養子」と「養子入り」の違いがわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The thick lines indicate biological children, the thin lines indicate husband and wife, the double lines indicate adopted children; and the dotted lines indicate children received for adoption.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The thick lines indicate biological children, the thin lines indicate husband and wife, the double lines indicate adopted children; and the dotted lines indicate children adopted by another family.</e>
<cmt>翻訳者さんの指摘した「養子入り」ですが、「他の家に養子に入る」ことではないかと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), 二八(id:10408), Charlesy(id:137799), Extrahitz(id:26245), Ykosub(id:2877), おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), 味っ子(id:17086), Kouzuke1(id:2531), 0太郎(id:7375), GAVVA(id:47103), Aki4(id:229124), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), 玄史生(id:43670), Nagira(id:98130), A-Taul(id:41790), Kadzuwo(id:3701), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), 東京大仏(id:226493), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Kouko0515(id:100370), KASAGI(id:24405), 諸星団(id:72202), LERK(id:4460), Anchnavi(id:266280), ZERO(id:3727), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Thomo(id:169717), Onaonan(id:147861), ととりん(id:31982), Raff(id:14006), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Jt noSke(id:32855), Seibuabina(id:37532), YukkeBot(id:251107), Shinkansen(id:13703), Kagetudo(id:163875), MDR-SK(id:192066), Carkuni(id:79281), くまたろう(id:46892), ゐ(id:795), 博物学博士(id:33603), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Junger(id:10282), 富田幸群(id:146723), MiraModreno(id:212669), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>