<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原定子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Teishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Teishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Teishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 定子（ふじわら の ていし/さだこ）、貞元 (日本)2年（977年）―長保2年12月16日 (旧暦)（ユリウス暦1001年1月13日））は、平安時代、第66代一条天皇の中宮、のち皇后（享年は同時代の公卿藤原行成の日記『権記』による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Teishi (Sadako) (977-January 13, 1001) was Chugu and later Empress to 66th Emperor Ichijo during Heian Period (The age of her death is from Kugyo FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary, &quot;Gonki&quot; from the same period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Teishi (her name can alo be read as Sadako) (977-January 13, 1001) was Chugu and later Empress to the 66th Emperor, Ichijo during the Heian Period (The date of her death is taken from Kugyo FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary, &quot;Gonki&quot; of the same period.</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;her name can alo be read as&apos;Added commaAdded &apos;the&apos;&apos;Age&apos;→&apos;date&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Teishi (her name can alo be read as Sadako) (977-January 13, 1001) was Chugu and later Empress to the sixty-sixth Emperor, Ichijo, during the Heian period (The date of her death is taken from Kugyo FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary, &quot;Gonki&quot; of the same period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一により、66thをスペルアウトする。Period→period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『日本紀略』『栄花物語』は25とする）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihongiryaku&quot; and &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; stated her as 25.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihongiryaku&quot; and &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; claim she died at the age of 25.)</e>
<cmt>stated her as 25&apos;→&apos;claim she died at the age of 25&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihongiryaku&quot; and &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; claim she died at the age of 25.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>脩子内親王（996年―1049年）・敦康親王（999年―1018年）・び子内親王（1000年―1008年、び＝女偏に美）らの生母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She mothered Princess Shushi (996-1049), Prince Atsuyasu (999-1018), and Princess Bishi (1000-1008).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the mother of Princess Shushi (996-1049), Prince Atsuyasu (999-1018), and Princess Bishi (1000-1008).</e>
<cmt>mothered&apos;→&apos;was the mother of&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the mother of Princess Shushi (996-1049), Prince Atsuyasu (999-1018), and Princess Bishi (1000-1008).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>通称は「一条院皇后宮」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her alias was &apos;Ichijoin Kogogu (Ichijoin Empress).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was also known as &apos;Ichijoin Kogogu (Ichijoin Empress).&apos;</e>
<cmt>Her alias was&apos;→&apos;She was also known as&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was also known as &apos;Ichijoin Kogogu (Ichijoin Empress).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『枕草子』の作者清少納言が仕えた后として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She is known as the empress served by &quot;The Pillow Book (Makura no Soshi)&quot; author, Sei Shonagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She is known for being the empress served by &quot;The Pillow Book (Makura no Soshi)&quot; author, Sei Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>as&apos;→&apos;for being&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She is known for being the empress served by &quot;The Pillow Book (Makura no Soshi)&quot; author, Sei Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>関白内大臣正二位藤原道隆の長女、母は式部大輔高階成忠の女・正三位高階貴子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was the eldest daughter of Kanpaku Naidaijin Shonii FUJIWARA no Michitaka and the daughter of Shikibu no Taifu (appointed Confucius scribe who reads to the emperor) TAKASHINA no Naritada, Shosanmi TAKASHINA no Kishi.</e>
<cmt>式部大輔→Shikibu no Taifu (Confucius scribe) [http://www.sol.dti.ne.jp/~hiromi/kansei/o_shou_shikibu.html]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was the eldest daughter of Kanpaku Naidaijin Shonii (Advisor and Minister of the Centre) FUJIWARA no Michitaka and TAKASHINA no Kishi, the daughter of TAKASHINA no Naritada, the Shikibu no Taifu (or Chief Judge at the Ministry of Civil Affairs).</e>
<cmt>Added explanation of Japanese terms</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was the eldest daughter of FUJIWARA no Michitaka, who was Kanpaku Naidaijin (Advisor and Minister of the Centre), Shonii (Senior Second Rank), and TAKASHINA no Kishi, who was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and a daughter of TAKASHINA no Naritada, the Shikibu no Taifu (or Chief Judge at the Ministry of Civil Affairs).</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に合わせて訳文を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>正二位内大臣藤原伊周（974年―1010年）、正二位中納言藤原隆家（979年―1044年）は同母兄弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her maternal brothers were Shonii Naidaijin FUJIWARA no Korechika (974-1010) and Shonii Chunagon FUJIWARA no Takaie (979-1044).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her maternal brothers were Shonii Naidaijin FUJIWARA no Korechika (974-1010) and Shonii Chunagon (or Middle Counsellor) FUJIWARA no Takaie (979-1044).</e>
<cmt>Added explanation of Japanese terms, though not sure of &apos;Shonii Naidaijin&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her maternal brothers were Shonii Naidaijin FUJIWARA no Korechika (974-1010) and Shonii Chunagon (or Middle Counsellor) FUJIWARA no Takaie (979-1044).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>略伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>正暦元年（990年）1月25日 (旧暦)、数え14歳の春に、3歳年下の一条天皇に入内し、まもなく従四位下に叙せられ、ついで女御となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She married three years younger Emperor Ichijo on the spring of her 14th year on January 25, 990 (old lunar calendar) to enter the imperial court and eventually received the title of Jushiige and also became his Nyogo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She entered the imperial court in the spring of her 14th year when she married Emperor Ichijo, who was three years younger, on January 25, 990 (old lunar calendar) and eventually received the title of Jushiige and also became his Nyogo (or consort).</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She entered the imperial court in the spring of her 14th year when she married Emperor Ichijo, who was three years younger, on January 25, 990 (old lunar calendar) and eventually received the title of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and also became his Nyogo (or consort).</e>
<cmt>Jushiige→JushiinogeJushiinoge　の英訳を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>局は登華殿（一説に凝華舎、または両方とも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She resided in Tokaden (one theory stated Gyokasha and/or both).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She resided in the Tokaden or, according to one theory the Gyokasha parts of the palace, or both.</e>
<cmt>(one theory stated Gyokasha and/or both)&apos;→&apos;or, according to one theory the Gyokasha parts of the palace, or both&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She resided in the Tokaden or, according to one theory the Gyokasha parts of the palace, or both.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>同年10月5日 (旧暦)、皇后に冊立され「中宮」を号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 5 (old lunar calendar) of the same year, she was designated as empress and gained the title of &apos;Chugu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 5 (old lunar calendar) of the same year, she was named empress and given the title of &apos;Chugu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>designated as&apos;→&apos;named&apos;&apos;gained&apos;→&apos;given&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 5 (old lunar calendar) of the same year, she was named empress and given the title of &apos;Chugu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同じ年の5月には、父・道隆が祖父藤原兼家の亡き後を継いで摂政・氏長者に就任しており、道隆一族は輝かしい栄華を謳歌した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 990, her father Michitaka took after the late FUJIWARA no Kaneie to be assigned to Sessho and Uji no choja positions, and Michitaka Family sang praise of this glory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 990, with her father Michitaka assuming the Sessho (or regency) and the leadership of the clan when his grandfather FUJIWARA no Kaneie died, the family entered a golden period.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 990, with her father Michitaka assuming the Sessho (or regency) and the leadership of the clan when his grandfather FUJIWARA no Kaneie died, the family entered a golden period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>定子の母貴子は円融天皇朝に掌侍を勤めて高内侍と称された人で、女ながらに漢文を能くし、殿上の詩宴にもに招かれるほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teishi&apos;s mother Kishi served as Naisho no jo of Emperor Enyu to be called as Ko no naishi due to her profound master in Classical Chinese even as a female and was even invited to the poetry parties of the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teishi&apos;s mother, Kishi, served as Naisho no jo (looking after the sacred sword and jewels) of Emperor Enyu and was known as Ko no naishi due to her mastery of Classical Chinese, which was rare for a woman and led to her being invited to the poetry parties at the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>Added commaAdded explanation of &apos;Naisho no jo&apos;&apos;profound master&apos;→&apos;mastery&apos;&apos;even...palace&apos;→&apos;which was rare for a woman and led to her being invited to the poetry parties at the imperial palace&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teishi&apos;s mother, Kishi, served as Naishi no jo (looking after the sacred sword and jewels) of Emperor Enyu and was known as Ko no naishi due to her mastery of Classical Chinese, which was rare for a woman and led to her being invited to the poetry parties at the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>Naisho no jo→Naishi no jo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、定子の父道隆は、「猿楽言」（冗談）を好み酒を愛した陽気な性格の人だという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teishi&apos;s father, Michitaka, seemed to have an optimistic personality who loved sake and say &apos;Sarugogoto (jokes).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teishi&apos;s father, Michitaka, is said to have had a jovial personality, who loved sake and telling jokes, or &apos;Sarugogoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>seemed to have an optimistic&apos;→&apos;is said to have had a jovial&apos; say &apos;Sarugogoto (jokes).&apos;&apos;→&apos;telling jokes, or &apos;Sarugogoto.&apos;&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teishi&apos;s father, Michitaka, is said to have had a jovial personality, who loved sake and telling jokes, or &apos;Sarugogoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>こうした父母の血を享けて、定子は聡明な資質を持ち、和漢の才に通暁したばかりでなく、明朗快活な性格に育ったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having inherited the blood of such parents, Teishi grew up to be wise and well-versed in both Japanese and Chinese as well as having bright and cheerful personality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having the blood of such parents in her veins, Teishi grew up to be wise and well-versed in both Japanese and Chinese, with a bright and cheerful personality.</e>
<cmt>inherited the blood of such parents&apos;→&apos;the blood of such parents in her veins&apos;&apos;as well as having&apos;→&apos;, with a &apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having the blood of such parents in her veins, Teishi grew up to be wise and well-versed in both Japanese and Chinese, with a bright and cheerful personality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>正暦四年頃から定子の死去まで彼女に仕えた女房・清少納言が著した随筆『枕草子』は、生き生きとした筆致で、彼女の人格的魅力を今日に伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sei Shonagon, who served Teishi as lady-in-waiting, lively told Teishi&apos;s personal attractiveness in her essay, &quot;The Pillow Book&quot; even to the present day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teishi&apos;s attractive personality can be felt even today through the lively description in the &quot;The Pillow Book,&quot; written by her lady-in-waiting, Sei Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teishi&apos;s attractive personality can be felt even today through the lively description in the &quot;The Pillow Book,&quot; written by her lady-in-waiting (993-Teishi&apos;s death), Sei Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>「正暦四年頃から定子の死去まで」の訳を追加。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>負うにあたる夫・一条天皇との仲も至極良好で、機知を愛し風雅を重んじる一条朝の宮廷の風潮は定子に負うところが大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had an extremely good relationship with her cousin and husband Emperor Ichijo, and the trend of Ichijo era&apos;s court to focus its importance on wit and elegance owed greatly to Teishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had an extremely good relationship with her husband, Emperor Ichijo, and the trend of Ichijo&apos;s court to focus on the importance of wit and elegance owed a lot to Teishi.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;cousin&apos;&apos;its importance on&apos;→&apos;on the importance of&apos;&apos;greatly&apos;→&apos;a lot&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had an extremely good relationship with her husband, Emperor Ichijo, and the trend of Ichijo&apos;s court to focus on the importance of wit and elegance owed a lot to Teishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、長徳元年（995年）4月10日、関白であった定子の父道隆が死去すると、政権は国母・藤原詮子の介入により定子の叔父藤原道兼、ついで藤原道兼が急死するとその弟藤原道長の手に渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Teishi&apos;s position was endangered when she lost her strong supporters first from the death of her Kanpaku father, Michitaka, on April 10, 995, and the political power shifted to her uncle FUJIWARA no Michikane by emperor&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Senshi, and then to his younger brother FUJIWARA no Michinaga upon his sudden death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Teishi&apos;s position became precarious when she lost her main supporters. First, her father, who was the Kanpaku, died on April 10, 995 and, through the intervention of the Emperor&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Senshi, the political power shifted to her uncle, FUJIWARA no Michikane, and then, upon his sudden death, to his younger brother FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>Split into two sentences</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, her father Michitaka, who was the Kanpaku, died on April 10, 995 and, through the intervention of the Emperor&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Senshi, the political power shifted to her uncle, FUJIWARA no Michikane, and then, upon his sudden death, to his younger brother FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処原文が。で終わるように修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>有力な後盾を失った定子の立場は危ういものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teishi&apos;s position became precarious when she lost her main supporters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>さらに、翌年4月には定子の兄・内大臣伊周、弟・中納言隆家らが花山天皇奉射事件を起こして左遷された。（長徳の変）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Teishi&apos;s older brother Naidaijin Korechika and younger brother Chunagon Takaie were demoted (The Chotoku Conspiracy) in following April by their attempted assasicination of Emperor Kazan by arrows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the following April, Teishi&apos;s brothers Naidaijin Korechika and Chunagon Takaie were demoted after their involvement in the The Chotoku Conspiracy, an attempted assasination of former Emperor, Kazan.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the following April, Teishi&apos;s brothers Naidaijin Korechika and Chunagon Takaie were demoted after their involvement in the The Chotoku Conspiracy, an attempted assasination by arrows of former EmperorKazan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処原文が。で終わるように修正。by arrows　を追加原文は「花山天皇」ですが、実際は法皇であるため、チェッカーの解釈（former Emperor)を採用しますが、原文とは食い違っています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>定子も内裏を退出し里第二条宮に還御するが、目の前で邸に逃げ込んだ兄弟が検非違使に捕らえられることを見て、あまりの衝撃に自ら鋏を取り落飾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teishi also escaped from the imperial palace to return to her parents&apos; home of Nijo Palace, but she shaved off the head with her scissors to enter monastery from the shock of witnessing the arrest of her brothers by Kebiishi as they ran into the palace before her very eyes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teishi also left the imperial palace and returned to her parents&apos; home of Nijo Palace, but after the shock of witnessing the Imperial police (or Kebiishi) arrest her brothers, who were in hiding at the house, she cut off her hair in preparation for entry into a monastery.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&apos;escaped&apos;→&apos;left&apos;&apos;head&apos;→&apos;hair&apos;added explanation of Keibi</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teishi also left the imperial palace and returned to her parents&apos; home of Nijo Palace, but after the shock of witnessing the Imperial police (or Kebiishi) arrest her brothers, who were in hiding at the house, she cut off her hair in preparation for entry into a monastery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>中宮はこの時身重であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugu was pregnant at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was pregnant at the time.</e>
<cmt>Chugu&apos;→&apos;she&apos;&apos;this&apos;→&apos;the&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was pregnant at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>中宮の出家は5月1日 (旧暦)のことで、この後、同年夏に二条宮が全焼し、10月には母・貴子も没するなど、不幸は続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugu entered monastery on May 1, but misfortune continued as Nijo Palace burnt down during summer and her mother Kishi passed away in October.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She entered the monastery on May 1, but her misfortune continued as Nijo Palace burnt down that summer and her mother, Kishi, died in October.</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;her&apos;Added commas&apos;passed away&apos;→&apos;died&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She entered the monastery on May 1, but her misfortune continued as Nijo Palace burnt down that summer and her mother, Kishi, died in October.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>その後、長徳三年（997年）4月になって伊周らの罪は赦され、また一条天皇は誕生した皇女・脩子内親王との対面を望み、周囲の反対を押し退け、同年6月、再び定子を宮中に迎え入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the Korechika and others were pardoned in April 997, and Emperor Ichijo invited Teishi back into the court against other&apos;s opposition in his wish to see the newly born crown princess, Princess Shushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in April 997, Korechika and the others were pardoned and, despite opposition, Emperor Ichijo invited Teishi back to the court because he wished to see the newly born crown princess, Princess Shushi.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order&apos;against other&apos;s&apos;→&apos;despite&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in April 997, Korechika and the others were pardoned and, despite opposition, Emperor Ichijo invited Teishi back to the court because he wished to see the newly born daughter, Imperial Princess Shushi.</e>
<cmt>crown princess　は原文の意に合わないので daughter　としました。また、内親王は Imperial Princess</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>中宮御所は清涼殿からほど遠い中宮職の御曹司と決められたが、それでも定子が出家の身で禁裏へ入った事への公卿の顰蹙を反映して、藤原実資はその日記『小右記』長徳三年六月二十二日条に、「天下不甘心」の語を記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Government administrators such as FUJIWARA no Sanesuke reflected on his &quot;Shoyuki&quot;diary, &apos;Emperor not reconciled &apos; on June 22, 997, showing their disapproval of Teishi who managed to move into the emperor&apos;s residence despite residence for Chugu candidates were located far apart from Seiryoden and after she entered monastery.</e>
<cmt>不甘心-&gt; not reconciled to　(中国語→英語） [http://translate.google.co.jp]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nobles at court were shocked that Teishi had moved into the palace when the Chugu residence was some way away, leading FUJIWARA no Sanesuke to write in his diary &quot;Shoyuki&quot; on June 22, 997, that &quot;the Emperor was displeased.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Changed word orderChanged translation of quote</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chugu residence was decided to be a room of Chugu Office which was far from Seiryoden(Emperor&apos;s residence), however, the nobles at court frowned upon the fact that Teishi had moved into the palace after she became a nun, leading FUJIWARA no Sanesuke to write in his diary &quot;Shoyuki&quot; on June 22, 997, that &quot;people are displeased&quot;</e>
<cmt>trans 1,2　ともに、原文の意味からはずれていたため、訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>この再入内で定子は実質的に還俗し、長保元年（999年）11月7日 (旧暦)、一条天皇の第一皇子・敦康親王を出産。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to re-entering of court, she gave birth to Emperor Ichijo&apos;s first crown prince, Prince Atsuyasu on November 7, 999.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After re-entering the court, she gave birth to Emperor Ichijo&apos;s first crown prince, Prince Atsuyasu, on November 7, 999.</e>
<cmt>Due to&apos;→&apos;after&apos;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After re-entering the court, she gave birth to Emperor Ichijo&apos;s first son, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, on November 7, 999.</e>
<cmt>crown prince→son親王→Imperial Prince</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>天皇の喜びは大きかったが、先に長女藤原彰子を入内させていた道長はこのことで焦慮し、彰子の立后を謀るようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor was overjoyed, but Michinaga whose eldest daughter, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, first entered imperial court was upset over the news and schemed to promote Shoshi as the empress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was overjoyed, but FUJIWARA no Michinaga, whose eldest daughter, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, had entered the imperial court before Teishi, was upset over the news and schemed to promote Shoshi as the empress.</e>
<cmt>Added &apos;the&apos;added &apos;FUJIWARA no&apos;&apos;first entered imperial court&apos;→&apos;had entered the imperial court before Teishi&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was overjoyed, but FUJIWARA no Michinaga, whose eldest daughter, FUJIWARA no Shoshi, had entered the imperial court, was upset over the news and schemed to promote Shoshi as the empress.</e>
<cmt>before Teishi　を省く（「先に」は、「定子の出産より以前に」の意味だと思うので</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>東三条院詮子の支持もあって、長保二年（1000年）2月25日 (旧暦)、女御彰子が新たに皇后に冊立され「中宮」を号し、先に「中宮」を号していた皇后定子は「皇后宮」に号され、史上はじめての「一帝二后」となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the support of Higashi Sanjoin Senshi, Nyogo Shoshi was promoted to &apos;Chugu&apos; on February 25, 1000, and the first &apos;Chugu&apos; Teishi&apos; was titled as &apos;Empress Consort,&apos; creating the first &apos;One Emperor, Two Empresses&apos; on a recorded history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the support of Higashi Sanjoin Senshi, Nyogo Shoshi was made &apos;Chugu&apos; on February 25, 1000, and Teishi, the previous &apos;Chugu,&apos; was named &apos;Empress Consort,&apos; creating the first &apos;One Emperor, Two Empresses&apos; in recorded history.</e>
<cmt>Couldn&apos;t find translation of Higashi Sanjoin Senshi&apos;first &apos;Chugu&apos; Teishi&apos;&apos;→&apos;Teishi, the previous &apos;Chugu,&apos;&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the support of Higashi Sanjoin Senshi, Nyogo Shoshi was installed as Empress and given the title of &apos;Chugu&apos; on February 25, 1000, and Teishi, the previous &apos;Chugu,&apos; was named &apos;Empress Consort,&apos; creating the first &apos;One Emperor, Two Empresses&apos; in recorded history.</e>
<cmt>「皇后に冊立され」の訳が抜けていたので補う。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>同年の暮れ、定子は第二皇女・び子内親王を出産して崩じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of same year, Teishi delivered second crown princess, Princess Bishi, and passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of same year, Teishi died after giving birth to the second crown princess, Princess Bishi.</e>
<cmt>Teishi delivered second crown princess, Princess Bishi, and passed away&apos;→&apos;Teishi died after giving birth to the second crown princess, Princess Bishi&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of same year, Teishi died after giving birth to the second daughter of the Emperor, Imperial Princess Bishi.</e>
<cmt>crown princess　は原文の意に合わないので daughter of the Emperor　としました。また、内親王は Imperial Princess</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>生前の希望から鳥辺野の南のあたりに土葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was buried on the southern side of Toribeno from her living wish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was buried on the southern side of Toribeno in accordance with her wishes.</e>
<cmt>from her living wish→&apos;in accordance with her wishes&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was buried on the southern side of Toribeno in accordance with her wishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>陵墓は今、京都市東山区今熊野泉山町にある鳥辺野陵（とりべののみささぎ）がそれとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mausoleum is considered to be Toribeno no Misasagi in Imagumanosenzan-cho, Higashiyama-ku, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mausoleum is the Toribeno no Misasagi mausoleum in Imagumanosenzan-cho, Higashiyama-ku, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;is considered to be&apos;added &apos;the&apos;Added &apos;mausoleum&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mausoleum is the Toribeno no Misasagi mausoleum in Imagumanosenzan-cho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>ku→Ward</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>死に臨んで定子が書き残した遺詠「夜もすがら契りし事を忘れずは　こひむ涙の色ぞゆかしき」は、『後拾遺和歌集』に哀傷巻頭歌として収められ、また、鎌倉時代初めに編まれた小倉百人一首の原撰本「百人秀歌」にも採られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poem she left on her dying bed, &apos;Yomosugara Chigirishi Koto o Wasurezuba Koin Namida no Irozo Yukashiki (Please do not forget our all-night bonding/I wonder what colored tears you will shed after my death) &apos; was collected as the first elegy within &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; and used within Ogura Hyakunin Isshu&apos;s original anthology, &apos;Hyakunin Shuka.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poem she left on her death bed, &apos;Yomosugara Chigirishi Koto o Wasurezuba Koin Namida no Irozo Yukashiki (Please do not forget our all-night bonding/I wonder what color tears you will shed after my death) &apos; was included as an elegy in &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; and used in OGURA Hyakunin Isshu&apos;s original anthology, &apos;Hyakunin Shuka.&apos;</e>
<cmt>dying bed&apos;→&apos;death bed&apos;&apos;colored&apos;→&apos;color&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poem she left on her death bed, &apos;Yomosugara Chigirishi Koto o Wasurezuba Koin Namida no Irozo Yukashiki (Please do not forget our all-night bonding/I wonder what color tears you will shed after my death) &apos; was included as an elegy in &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; and used in OGURA Hyakunin Isshu&apos;s original anthology, &apos;Hyakunin Shuka.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="34">
<j>定子の死後、中関白家（父と弟の間にあって関白になった道隆家の呼称）は没落の一途をたどった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Teishi&apos;s death, Naka no Kanpaku family (name of Michitaka who became Kanpaku between her father and younger brother) fell to ruins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Teishi&apos;s death, the Naka no Kanpaku family (the name used when her father and brother were the kanpaku) fell into decline.</e>
<cmt>Added&apos; the&apos;&apos;name of Michitaka who became Kanpaku between her father and younger brother) fell to ruins&apos;→&apos;he name used when her father and brother were the kanpaku) fell into decline&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Teishi&apos;s death, the Naka no Kanpaku family (the family name of Michitaka&apos;s, who became Kanpaku after his father and before his younger brother) fell into decline.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に合わせて訳文を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>定子が儲けた敦康親王が、后腹の第一皇子でありながら即位できなかったのも、それゆえである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the reason why Prince Atsuyasu could not accede to the throne despite the fact that he was the first crown prince born from the empress&apos;s womb.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this the reason, Prince Atsuyasu, despite being the son of an empress, was unable to ascend the throne.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this the reason, Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, despite being the first son of an empress, was unable to ascend the throne.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に合わせて訳文を修正。親王→Imperial Prince</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), Show-ichi(id:10061), MIO(id:31681), 青山コロハ(id:118527), BAKU(id:55205), Mois(id:30596), Masyu(id:31065), 代言人(id:33675), Yume149(id:17504), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), YOSHI438(id:174755), トホホ川(id:50502), けんち(id:5147), Kzhr(id:131), 小太刀(id:18154), LERK(id:4460), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>