<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平重盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Shigemori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Shigemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Shigemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 重盛（たいら の しげもり）は、平安時代末期の武将、公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Shigemori was a military commander and a kugyo at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Shigemori was a military commander and a kugyo at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Shigemori was a military commander and a kugyo (the top court officials) at the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>公卿の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平清盛の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first, true son of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first, true son of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first, true son of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>保元の乱・平治の乱で若き武将として父平清盛を助けて相次いで戦功を上げ、父の立身とともに累進し、最終的には近衛府、正二位内大臣にまで出世した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was noted for his distinguished war service as a young military commander while assisting his father, TAIRA no Kiyomori, in the Hogen as well as Heiji Disturbances and was promoted as his father became successful, and in the end, he became an Inner Minister of the Sho ni-i rank of a konoefu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was noted for his distinguished war service as a young military commander while assisting his father, TAIRA no Kiyomori, in the Hogen as well as Heiji Disturbances. He was promoted as his father became successful, and in the end, he became an Inner Minister of the Sho ni-i rank of a konoefu.</e>
<cmt>run-on sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was noted for his distinguished war service as a young military commander while assisting his father, TAIRA no Kiyomori, in the Hogen as well as Heiji Wars. He was promoted as his father became successful, and in the end, he became an Inner Minister of the Shonii (Senior Second Rank) rank of the Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、Disturbances→Warsに修正、「正二位」「近衛府」の表記を修正、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>嫡男ではあったが正妻の平時子の子である平宗盛や平徳子とは母が異なり有力な外戚の庇護はなく、室が藤原成親の妹・経子であったため、成親失脚後は一門のなかでは孤立気味であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Shigemori was the first and real son of TAIRA no Kiyomori, he was not the son of the legal wife TAIRA no Tokiko who gave birth to TAIRA no Munemori and TAIRA no Tokuko, and he therefore did not have any powerful support of any of his maternal relatives, and furthermore, since his wife was Keishi who was a sister of FUJIWARA no Narichika, he became somehow isolated within the clan after Narichika fell from power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shigemori was the first and real son of TAIRA no Kiyomori, he was not the son of the legal wife TAIRA no Tokiko who gave birth to TAIRA no Munemori and TAIRA no Tokuko. Therefore, he lacked any powerful support from his maternal relatives; since his wife was Keishi, a sister of FUJIWARA no Narichika, he became somehow isolated within the clan after the Narichika fell from power.</e>
<cmt>run-on sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shigemori was the first and real son of TAIRA no Kiyomori, he was not the son of the legal wife TAIRA no Tokiko who gave birth to TAIRA no Munemori and TAIRA no Tokuko, and therefore, he lacked any powerful support from his maternal relatives; since his wife was Keishi, a sister of FUJIWARA no Narichika, he became somehow isolated within the clan after the Narichika fell from power.</e>
<cmt>訳文が二文にわかれているため、一文になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>鹿ケ谷の陰謀の際には清盛の後白河天皇幽閉を身をもって制止するなど、政治的には後白河法皇に近い立場だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Shishigatani Incident occurred, Shigemori stood up to Kiyomori&apos;s attempt to incarcerate Emperor Goshirakawa; therefore, politically speaking, Shigemori was close to the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Shishigatani Incident occurred, Shigemori stood up to Kiyomori&apos;s attempt to incarcerate Emperor Goshirakawa; therefore, politically speaking, Shigemori was close to the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Shishigatani Incident occurred, Shigemori stood up to Kiyomori&apos;s attempt to incarcerate Emperor Goshirakawa; therefore, politically speaking, Shigemori was close to the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>清盛の後継者として期待されながらも、清盛と後白河法皇の対立では有効な対策をとることができないまま、父に先立ち病没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was expected to become the successor of his father, Kiyomori, but ended up dying of illness before him, unable to implement any effective measures to solve the conflict between his father and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was expected to succeed his father, Kiyomori, but he died of illness before he could do this. He was unable to implement any effective measures to solve the conflict between his father and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was expected to succeed his father, Kiyomori, but he died of illness before he could do this, unable to implement any effective measures to solve the conflict between his father and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>訳文が二文にわかれているため、一文になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>六波羅小松第に居を構えていたことから、小松殿ないし小松内大臣とも、またその邸宅に48の灯篭を建てていたことから灯篭大臣とも称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Komatsu-dono or Komatsu Naidaijin because he had a house in Rokuhara Komatsudai, and he was also called the Lantern Minister since he had built 48 lantern towers at his house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Komatsu-dono or Komatsu Naidaijin because he had a house in Rokuhara Komatsudai. He was also called the Lantern Minister since he had built 48 lantern towers at his house.</e>
<cmt>run-on sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Komatsu-dono or Komatsu Naidaijin because he had a house in Rokuhara Komatsudai, and he was also called the Lantern Minister since he had built 48 lantern towers at his house.</e>
<cmt>訳文が二文にわかれているため、一文になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>wording consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>保元の乱、平治の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hogen and Heiji Disturbances</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hogen and Heiji Disturbances</e>
<cmt>article needed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hogen and Heiji Wars</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>保延4年（1138年）、清盛の長男として誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori was born in 1138 as the first son of Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori was born in 1138 as the first son of Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori was born in 1138 as the first son of Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>母は右近将監高階基章の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Motoaki TAKASHINA who was an ukon no jo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Motoaki TAKASHINA who was an ukon no jo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Motoaki TAKASHINA who was Ukon no jo (Lieutenant of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>an ukon no jo→Ukon no joとし、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>久安6年（1150年）12月、鳥羽法皇の蔵人に補される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 1150, he was appointed to be a kurodo of the Cloistered Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, 1150, he was appointed to be a kurodo of the Cloistered Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, 1150, he was appointed to be Kurodo (Chamberlain) of the Cloistered Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>「蔵人」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>翌年正月に従五位下になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January of the following year, he was assigned to the Ju go-i no ge rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January of the following year, he was assigned to the Ju go-i no ge rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January of the following year, he was assigned to the Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) rank.</e>
<cmt>Ju go-i no ge→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱に父に従って参戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1156, he followed his father&apos;s order and fought in the Hogen Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1156, he followed his father&apos;s order and fought in the Hogen Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1156, he followed his father&apos;s order and fought in the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt>Hogen Warに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>『兵範記』には中務少輔・重盛の名が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s name was mentioned in the &quot;Heihanki&quot; as a nakatsukasa sunaisuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori&apos;s name was mentioned in the Heihanki as a nakatsukasa sunaisuke.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s name was mentioned in the &quot;Heihanki&quot; (diary of TAIRA no Nobunori) as a nakatsukasa no shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>『兵範記』→原文に合わせクォーテーションを入れ、補足を追加、「中務少輔」→読みを修正、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>清盛の軍勢は源為朝との戦闘で大きな被害を出し、形勢不利と見た清盛は撤退を指示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s force was seriously damaged in the battle against MINAMOTO no Tametomo, and concluding that the he was losing, Kiyomori ordered his force to withdraw.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori&apos;s force was seriously damaged in the battle against MINAMOTO no Tametomo. Anticipating his loss, Kiyomori ordered his forces to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s force was seriously damaged in the battle against MINAMOTO no Tametomo. Anticipating his loss, Kiyomori ordered his forces to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この時に重盛は父の制止を振り切って、為朝と戦うため出陣しようとするなど血気盛んなところを見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori, however, being hot-blooded, tried to enter the war against Tametomo in defiance of his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori, however, being hot-blooded, tried to enter the war against Tametomo in defiance of his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori, however, being hot-blooded, tried to enter the war against Tametomo in defiance of his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>保元の乱は清盛の属す天皇方の勝利に終わり、保元2年（1157年）正月、重盛はその功績により19歳で従五位上に昇叙した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor&apos;s side to which Kiyomori belonged won the Hogen Disturbance, and in January, 1157, Shigemori at the age of 19 was promoted to the Ju go-i no jo rank for his outstanding performance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor&apos;s side, to which Kiyomori belonged, won the Hogen Disturbance, and in January of 1157 Shigemori at the age of 19 was promoted to the Ju go-i no jo rank for his outstanding performance.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor&apos;s side, to which Kiyomori belonged, won the Hogen War, and in January of 1157 Shigemori at the age of 19 was promoted to the Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) rank for his outstanding performance.</e>
<cmt>Hogen War, Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同年10月22日に大内裏が再建され、清盛は仁寿殿を造営した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 22 of the same year, the Daidairi was reconstructed and Kiyomori built the Jijuden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 22 of the same year, the Daidairi was reconstructed and Kiyomori built the Jijuden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 22 of the same year, the Daidairi (the Greater Imperial Palace) was reconstructed and Kiyomori built the Jijuden (literally, &quot;hall of benevolence and longevity,&quot; which is the Emperor&apos;s residence).</e>
<cmt>「大内裏」「仁寿殿」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>父から造営の賞を譲られた重盛は、正五位下となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a prize from his father for building the Jijuden, Shigemori was assigned to the Sho go-i no ge rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a prize from his father for building the Jijuden, Shigemori was assigned to the Sho go-i no ge rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a prize from his father for building the Jijuden, Shigemori was assigned to the Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) rank.</e>
<cmt>Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>保元3年（1158年）年8月、清盛は知行国を安芸国から遠江国に移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1158, Kiyomori&apos;s chigyokoku changed from Aki Province to Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, 1158, Kiyomori&apos;s chigyokoku changed from Aki Province to Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, 1158, Kiyomori&apos;s chigyokoku (provincial fiefdom) changed from Aki Province to Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>「知行国」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>自らは大宰大弐であったため、重盛が代わりに遠江守となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kiyomori was serving as a Dazai no daini, Shigemori became the Totomi no kami on behalf of Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kiyomori was serving as a Dazai no daini, Shigemori became the Totomi no kami on behalf of Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kiyomori was serving as a Dazai no daini (Senior Assistant Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices), Shigemori became the Govenor of Totomi Province on behalf of Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>「大宰大弐」の補足を追加、Totomi no kami→Governor of Totomi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>平治元年（1159年）12月9日、平治の乱の勃発の時、清盛は熊野参詣のため紀伊国にいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Heiji Disturbance broke out on December 9, 1159, Kiyomori was on a pilgrimage to Kumano Sanzan in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>「熊野参詣」は「熊野三山詣で」を意味すると解釈し訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Heiji Disturbance broke out on December 9, 1159, Kiyomori was on a pilgrimage to Kumano Sanzan in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Heiji War broke out on December 9, 1159, Kiyomori was on a pilgrimage to Kumano Sanzan in Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>Heiji Warに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>『平治物語』では重盛は動揺する父を励ましたとするが、『愚管抄』によれば清盛と一緒にいたのは基盛・宗盛と侍15人で、重盛は同道していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Tale of Heiji&quot; had that Shigemori comforted his upset father, but according to &quot;Gukansho,&quot; Kiyomori was with Motomori, Munemori, and 15 samurais, and Shigemori was not in the party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tale of Heiji told of Shigemori comforting his upset father, but according to the Gukansho, Kiyomori was with Motomori, Munemori, and 15 samurai, and Shigemori was present.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Heiji&quot; told of Shigemori comforting his upset father, but according to the &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), Kiyomori was with Motomori, Munemori, and 15 samurai, and Shigemori was present.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせクォーテーションを入れ、『愚管抄』の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>京都に戻った清盛は二条天皇を内裏から六波羅に脱出させ、藤原信頼・源義朝の追討宣旨を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon returning to Kyoto, Kiyomori helped Emperor Nijo escape from the Dairi to Rokuhara, and then received from the Emperor a written order to hunt down and kill FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon returning to Kyoto, Kiyomori helped Emperor Nijo escape from the Dairi to Rokuhara. He then received from the Emperor a written order to hunt down and kill FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon returning to Kyoto, Kiyomori helped Emperor Nijo escape from the Dairi (Imperial Palace) to Rokuhara. He then received from the Emperor a written order to hunt down and kill FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>「内裏」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>重盛は叔父・頼盛とともに出陣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori went to the battle with his uncle, Yorimori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori went to battle with his uncle, Yorimori.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori went to battle with his uncle, Yorimori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この戦いで重盛は「年号は平治、都は平安、我らは平氏、三つ同じ（平）だ、ならば敵を平らげよう」と味方の士気を鼓舞し、源義平と御所の右近の橘・左近の桜の間で激戦を繰り広げ、堀河の合戦では馬を射られながらも材木の上に立ち上がって新たな馬に乗り換えるなど獅子奮迅の活躍をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori raised the morale of the members of his army saying that &apos;we are in the era of Heiji, the capital is Heian, and we are the Taira clan, all having the same character (with different sounds such as Hei and Taira), and so we shall flatten (also the same character as Hei/Taira) our enemy out,&apos; and engaged in fierce battles against MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, between mandarin orange trees of the Ukon and cherry trees of the Sakon at the Imperial Palace, and then in the Battle of Horikawa, he performed heroically with irresistible force as he, after getting his own horse shot by arrows, stood up on logs and then climbed upon a new horse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori raised the morale of the members of his army saying that &apos;we are in the era of Heiji, the capital is Heian, and we are the Taira clan, all having the same character (the character can be read as both Hei and Taira), and so we shall flatten (also the same character as Hei/Taira) our enemy out&apos;. He engaged in fierce battles against MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, between mandarin orange trees of the Ukon and cherry trees of the Sakon at the Imperial Palace. He performed heroically in the Battle of Horikawa with irresistible force as he--after losing his own horse to a volley of arrows--stood up on logs and then climbed upon a new horse.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori raised the morale of the members of his army saying that &apos;we are in the era of Heiji, the capital is Heian, and we are the Taira clan, all having the same character (the character can be read as both Hei and Taira), and so we shall flatten (also the same character as Hei/Taira) our enemy out,&apos; and he engaged in fierce battles against MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, between mandarin orange trees of the Ukon and cherry trees of the Sakon at the Imperial Palace, and then he performed heroically in the Battle of Horikawa with irresistible force as he - after losing his own horse to a volley of arrows - stood up on logs and then climbed upon a new horse.</e>
<cmt>複数文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、ハイフンを削除、スペースを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>もっとも『愚管抄』によれば義朝はすぐに内裏を出撃して六波羅に迫ったとあるので、内裏で戦闘が行われたかどうかは定かでなく、話を盛り上げるための創作の可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Gukansho,&apos; Yoshitomo immediately left the Dairi for Rokuhara, however it is not certain that there were in fact any battles at the Dairi, and therefore, this could be a fiction to make the story more thrilling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &apos;Gukansho,&apos; Yoshitomo immediately left the Dairi for Rokuhara; however, it is not certain that there were in fact any battles at the Dairi, and therefore, this could be an embellishment to make the story more thrilling.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Gukansho,&quot; Yoshitomo immediately left the Dairi for Rokuhara; however, it is not certain that there were in fact any battles at the Dairi, and therefore, this could be an embellishment to make the story more thrilling.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>この合戦で信頼と行動した成親は助命されるが、成親の妹・経子を妻にしていた重盛の嘆願が背景にあったと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narichika had his life spared since he joined Nobuyori in this battle, but this may in fact be attributed to a plea by Shigemori, whose wife was a younger sister of Narichika, Keishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narichika had his life spared since he joined Nobuyori in this battle, but this may in fact be attributed to a plea by Shigemori, whose wife was a younger sister of Narichika, Keishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narichika had his life spared since he joined Nobuyori in this battle, but this may in fact be attributed to a plea by Shigemori, whose wife was a younger sister of Narichika, Keishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>乱の終結後に合戦の恩賞の除目があり、重盛は勲功賞として伊予国に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rewards were granted after the disturbance was over, and Shigemori was appointed to be in charge of Iyo Province as a reward for his distinguished service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rewards were granted after the disturbance was over, and Shigemori was appointed to be in charge of Iyo Province as a reward for his distinguished service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rewards were granted after the war was over, and Shigemori was appointed to be in charge of Iyo Province as a reward for his distinguished service.</e>
<cmt>disturbance→warに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>年が明けてすぐに従四位下となり、左馬頭も兼任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early in the new year, he was assigned to the Ju shi-i no ge rank and also to sama no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early in the new year, he was assigned to the Ju shi-i no ge rank and also to sama no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early in the new year, he was assigned to the Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) rank and also to Sama no kami (Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) とし、「左馬頭」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>順調な昇進（二条親政期）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Smooth Promotion (during the Period of Emperor Nijo&apos;s Control)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Smooth Promotion (during the Period of Emperor Nijo&apos;s Control)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Smooth Promotion (during the Period of Emperor Nijo&apos;s Control)</e>
<cmt>全角スペースを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>応保元年（1161年）9月、後白河と建春門院の間に生まれた皇子（高倉天皇親王）を皇太子にしようとする陰謀が発覚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, 1161, a conspiracy to make the prince born of Goshirakawa and Kenshunmonin, (Imperial Prince Takakura), become the crown prince was revealed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, 1161, a conspiracy to make the prince born of Goshirakawa and Kenshunmonin, (Imperial Prince Takakura), become the crown prince was revealed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, 1161, a conspiracy to make the prince born of Goshirakawa and Kenshunmonin, (Imperial Prince Norihito), become the crown prince was revealed.</e>
<cmt>「高倉天皇親王」→ウェブで確認したところ「憲仁親王」となっていたため (憲仁親王→後の高倉天皇、バグと思われます)、Imperial Prince Takakura→Imperial Prince Norihitoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この事件では平時忠・平教盛・成親らが二条天皇によって解官されるが、清盛は同調せず二条を支援したため、その信任を確固たるものにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitada, TAIRA no Norimori, and Narichika were removed from their posts by Emperor Nijo in this incident, but Kiyomori supported Nijo instead of them, and this resulted in establishment of Kiyomori&apos;s trusworthiness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tokitada, TAIRA no Norimori, and Narichika were removed from their posts by Emperor Nijo in this incident. However, Kiyomori supported Nijo instead of them, and this resulted in the establishment of Kiyomori&apos;s trusworthiness.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tokitada, TAIRA no Norimori, and Narichika were removed from their posts by Emperor Nijo in this incident. However, Kiyomori supported Nijo instead of them, and this resulted in the establishment of Kiyomori&apos;s trusworthiness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>重盛の昇進も目覚ましく、応保2年（1161年）正月に正四位下、10月に右兵衛督、翌年正月には26歳の若さで、従三位に叙せられ公卿となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Shigemori was promoted rapidly, and was assigned to the Sho shi-i no ge rank in 1161, to be an ukone no kami in October, and to the Ju sanmi rank to become a kugyo in January of the next year when he was only 26 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Shigemori was promoted rapidly, and was assigned to the Sho shi-i no ge rank in 1161, to be an ukone no kami in October, and to the Ju sanmi rank to become a kugyo in January of the next year when he was only 26 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Shigemori was promoted rapidly, and was assigned to the Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) rank in 1161, to be Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards) in October, and to the Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) rank to become a kugyo in January of the next year when he was only 26 years old.</e>
<cmt>Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) とし、a ukone no kami→Uhyoe no kamiに訂正、補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>清盛は二条の親政を支える一方で後白河に対しても配慮を怠らず、後白河のために蓮華王院を造営した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While supporting the political control by Nijo, Kiyomori at the same time never forgot to show consideration for Goshirakawa, and built the Rengeo-in Temple for him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While supporting the political control by Nijo, Kiyomori at the same time never forgot to show consideration for Goshirakawa, and built the Rengeo-in Temple for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While supporting the political control by Nijo, Kiyomori at the same time never forgot to show consideration for Goshirakawa, and built the Rengeo-in Temple for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>長寛2年（1164年）2月、父から造営の賞を譲られた重盛は、正三位に叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1164, as a prize from his father for building the Rengeo-in temple, Shigemori was assigned to the Sho sanmi rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1164, as a prize from his father for building the Rengeo-in temple, Shigemori was assigned to the Sho sanmi rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1164, as a prize from his father for building the Rengeo-in Temple, Shigemori was assigned to the Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) rank.</e>
<cmt>temple→Temple、およびSho sanmi→Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>9月、清盛は一門の繁栄を祈願して、厳島神社に装飾経33巻（平家納経）を寄進するが、重盛も一門・家人とともに製作に携わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, in the hope for prosperity of his clan, he donated 33 volumes of Decorated Sutras (Heike nokyo) to the Itsukushima Jinja Shrine, and for this, Shigemori also participated in its creation with other clan and family members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, in hopes for the prosperity of his clan, he donated 33 volumes of the Decorated Sutras (Heike nokyo) to the Itsukushima Jinja Shrine. For this, Shigemori also participated in its creation with other clan and family members.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, in hopes for the prosperity of his clan, he donated 33 volumes of the Decorated Sutras (Heike nokyo) to the Itsukushima-jinja Shrine, and for this, Shigemori also participated in its creation with other clan and family members.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、およびItsukushima-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>長寛3年（1165年）4月、二条天皇は病に倒れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, 1165, Emperor Nijo was taken with illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, 1165, Emperor Nijo was taken ill.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, 1165, Emperor Nijo was taken ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>重態となった二条天皇は5月に重盛を参議に任じ、6月に皇子・六条天皇に譲位、院庁を開設して執事別当に重盛を指名するなど最期まで執念を見せるが、7月に崩御した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being in serious condition, Emperor Nijo appointed Shigemori to be a sangi in May, abdicated the throne to his son Emperor Rokujo and also established an administrative organization under direct control of the emperor in June, and appointed Shigemori to Shitsuji betto, through these acts showing his persistent spirit, but finally passed away in July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being in serious condition, Emperor Nijo appointed Shigemori to be a sangi in May, abdicated the throne to his son Emperor Rokujo and also established an administrative organization under direct control of the emperor in June, and appointed Shigemori to Shitsuji betto. He showed his tenacity of purpose through these acts, but he finally passed away in July.</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being in serious condition, Emperor Nijo appointed Shigemori to be Sangi (Royal Advisor) in May, abdicated the throne to his son Emperor Rokujo and also established an administrative organization under direct control of the emperor in June, and appointed Shigemori to Shitsuji betto (chief officer), showing his tenacity of purpose through these acts, but he finally passed away in July.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、および「参議」「執事別当」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>六条天皇を平氏と摂関家が支える体制が成立し、重盛は永万2年（1166年）4月に左兵衛督、7月には権中納言・右衛門督となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, a system was established wherein the Taira clan and the Sekkan family supported Emperor Rokujo, and Shigemori was appointed to Sahyoe no kami in April, 1166, and was appointed to be a gon chunagon and uemon no kami at the same time in July.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, a system was established wherein the Taira clan and the Sekkan family supported Emperor Rokujo, and Shigemori was appointed to Sahyoe no kami in April, 1166, and was appointed to be a gon chunagon and uemon no kami at the same time in July.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, a system was established wherein the Taira clan and the Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) supported Emperor Rokujo, and Shigemori was appointed to Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards) in April, 1166, and was appointed to be Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) and Uemon no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) at the same time in July.</e>
<cmt>Sekkan family →Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) とし、「左兵衛督」「権中納言」「右衛門督」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし天皇が幼少のため、政局は著しく不安定だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The political condition however was extremely unstable as the emperor was still quite young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The political condition however was extremely unstable as the emperor was still quite young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The political condition however was extremely unstable as the emperor was still quite young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>7月に近衛基実が死去すると、六条天皇の政権は瓦解する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, when Motozane KONOE died in July, the Emperor Rokujo administration collapsed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, when Motozane KONOE died in July, the Emperor Rokujo regime collapsed.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, when Motozane KONOE died in July, the Emperor Rokujo regime collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="43">
<j>清盛の後継者（後白河院政期）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successor of Kiyomori (period of the Goshirakawa cloister government)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Successor of Kiyomori (period of the Goshirakawa cloister government)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successor of Kiyomori (period of the Goshirakawa cloister government)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="44">
<j>平氏が二条親政派から離脱して後白河上皇を支持したことにより、仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）10月に憲仁親王の立太子が実現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan removed itself from the Nijo political sect and supported the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, and this contributed to investiture of Imperial Prince Norihito in October, 1166.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan removed itself from the Nijo political sect and supported the retired Emperor Goshirakawa. This contributed to the investiture of Imperial Prince Norihito in October 1166.</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan removed itself from the Nijo political sect and supported the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa, which contributed to the investiture of Imperial Prince Norihito in October 1166.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、およびthe Retired Emperor Goshirakawaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>憲仁親王の乳母には重盛の室・経子と藤原邦綱の女・綱子が選ばれ、重盛は乳父（めのと）になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s wife, Keishi, and a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna, Tsunako, were selected as nannies of Prince Norihito, and so Shigemori was a husband of a nanny.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori&apos;s wife, Keishi, and a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna, Tsunako, were selected as nannies of Prince Norihito, and so Shigemori was the husband of a nanny.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s wife, Keishi, and a daughter of FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna, Tsunako, were selected as nannies of Imperial Prince Norihito, and so Shigemori was the husband of a nanny.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince Norihitoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>12月には清盛の後任として春宮大夫となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, Shigemori became Togu no daibu as Kiyomori&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, Shigemori became Togu no daibu as Kiyomori&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Shigemori became Togu no daibu (Master of the Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) as Kiyomori&apos;s successor.</e>
<cmt>「春宮大夫」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>仁安2年（1167年）2月には、権大納言となり帯剣を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 1167, Shigemori became Gon dainagon and was allowed to be armed with a sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1167, Shigemori became Gon dainagon and was allowed to be armed with a sword.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1167, Shigemori became Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state) and was allowed to be armed with a sword.</e>
<cmt>「権大納言」の表記統一リストに基づき修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>清盛は5月17日に太政大臣を辞任するが、それに先立つ5月10日、重盛に対して東山・東海・山陽・南海道の山賊・海賊追討宣旨が下された（『兵範記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori resigned as Chancellor of the State on May 17, but before his resignation, on May 10, Shigemori received a written imperial order to hunt down and kill bandits and pirates in Higashiyama, Tokai, Sanyo, and Nankai-do (&quot;Heihanki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori resigned as Chancellor of the State on May 17. However, before his resignation, on May 10 Shigemori received a written imperial order to hunt down and kill bandits and pirates in Higashiyama, Tokai, Sanyo, and Nankai-do (Heihanki).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori resigned as Chancellor of the State on May 17; however, before his resignation, on May 10 Shigemori received a written imperial order to hunt down and kill bandits and pirates in Higashiyama, Tokai, Sanyo, and Nankai-do (&quot;Heihanki&quot; (diary of TAIRA no Nobunori)).</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、『兵範記』→原文に合わせクォーテーションをいれ、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>これにより、重盛は国家的軍事・警察権を正式に委任され、清盛の後継者としての地位を名実ともに確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This event marked an official transfer of the rights associated with national military and police affairs to Shigemori, and he therefore established his position as a successor of Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This event marked an official transfer of the rights associated with national military and police affairs to Shigemori, and he therefore established his position as a successor to Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This event marked an official transfer of the rights associated with national military and police affairs to Shigemori, and he therefore established his position as a successor to Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>さらに重盛は丹後国・越前国を知行国として、経済的にも一門の中で優位にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Shigemori was the most powerful economically within his clan as he had Tango and Echizen Provinces as his chigyokoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Shigemori was the most powerful economically within his clan as he had Tango and Echizen Provinces as his chigyokoku (provinces under his control).</e>
<cmt>The word &quot;chigyokoku&quot; required the explanation in parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Shigemori was the most powerful economically within his clan as he had Tango and Echizen Provinces as his chigyokoku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;chigyokoku&quot;の補足説明は既出のため(29行目)、ローマ字表記のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="51">
<j>後継者となった重盛だが健康を害したらしく、「日来所労」「昨今不快」により12月の東宮の御書始を欠席し、大乗会の上卿も交替する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the succession, Shigemori most likely fell in ill health, and he therefore failed to attend the Dokushohajime held at the Togu in December since, as he put it, he &apos;has been ill&apos; and &apos; has been feeling discomfort,&apos; and also, he let someone else assume the shokei post at the Daijoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the succession, Shigemori most likely fell ill, and he therefore failed to attend the Dokushohajime (ceremony to learn how to read under the guidance of professors) held at the Togu in December since, as he put it, he &apos;has been ill&apos; and &apos;has been feeling uncomfortable,&apos; and also, he let someone else assume the shokei post at the Daijoe (commemoration of the five major Mahayana Buddhist sutras).</e>
<cmt>wordingThe words &quot;Dokushohajime&quot; and &quot;Daijoe&quot; required the explanation in parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the succession, Shigemori most likely fell ill, and he therefore failed to attend the Goshohajime (ceremony to learn how to read under the guidance of professors) held at the Togu (Crown Prince&apos;s Quarters) in December since, as he put it, he &apos;has been ill&apos; and &apos;has been feeling uncomfortable,&apos; and also, he let someone else assume the shokei (master of ceremony) post at the Daijoe (commemoration of the five major Mahayana Buddhist sutras).</e>
<cmt>Dokushohajime→Goshohajimeに修正、「東宮」「上卿」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>仁安3年（1168年）2月、清盛が病のため出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 1168, Kiyomori entered the priesthood because of his illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1168, Kiyomori entered the priesthood due to illness.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1168, Kiyomori entered the priesthood due to illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>政情不安を危惧した後白河は憲仁を即位させ（高倉天皇）、体制の安定を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerned about unstable political conditions, Goshirakawa made Norihito (Emperor Takakura) ascend the throne in the hope of stabilizing the regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerned about unstable political conditions, Goshirakawa made Norihito (Emperor Takakura) ascend the throne in the hope of stabilizing the regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerned about unstable political conditions, Goshirakawa made Norihito (Emperor Takakura) ascend the throne in the hope of stabilizing the regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>重盛は体調不良が続いたらしく、12月に権大納言を辞任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to persistent poor physical condition, Shigemori resigned as Gon dainagon in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to his persistent poor physical condition, Shigemori resigned as Gon dainagon in December.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to his persistent poor physical condition, Shigemori resigned as Gon Dainagon in December.</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>出家後の清盛は福原に退隠し、六波羅には重盛が残って一門の統率にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After entering the priesthood, Kiyomori secluded himself from the world in Fukuhara, and Shigemori remained in Rokuhara to lead the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After entering the priesthood, Kiyomori secluded himself from the world in Fukuhara, while Shigemori remained in Rokuhara to lead the clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After entering the priesthood, Kiyomori secluded himself from the world in Fukuhara, while Shigemori remained in Rokuhara to lead the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>嘉応元年（1169年）11月の八十嶋祭で高倉天皇は重盛の六波羅邸から出立し、重盛室の経子が勅使役を勤めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Yasoshima-sai in November, 1169, Emperor Takakura left Shigemori&apos;s residence in Rokuhara, and Shigemori&apos;s wife Keishi served as an imperial messenger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Yasoshima-sai in November 1169, Emperor Takakura left Shigemori&apos;s residence in Rokuhara, and Shigemori&apos;s wife Keishi served as an imperial messenger.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Yasoshima-sai festival in November 1169, Emperor Takakura left Shigemori&apos;s residence in Rokuhara, and Shigemori&apos;s wife Keishi served as an imperial messenger.</e>
<cmt>Yasoshima-sai→Yasoshima-sai festivalとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>嘉応の強訴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Direct Petition in Kao</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Direct Petition in Kao</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Direct Petition in Kao</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>嘉応元年（1169年）12月、延暦寺の大衆が、重盛の義兄で尾張国の知行国主・藤原成親の流罪を求めて強訴を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1169, armed priests of the Enryaku-ji Temple made a petition for deportation of FUJIWARA no Narichika who was an older brother-in-law of Shigemori and also the head of his own chigyokoku, Owari Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1169, armed priests of the Enryaku-ji Temple made a petition for deportation of FUJIWARA no Narichika, who was an older brother-in-law of Shigemori and also the head of his own chigyokoku, Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1169, armed priests of the Enryaku-ji Temple made a petition for deportation of FUJIWARA no Narichika, who was an older brother-in-law of Shigemori and also the head of his own chigyokoku, Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>大衆は内裏を取り囲んで気勢を上げ、検非違使別当・時忠は官兵の派遣など早急な対策をとることを進言する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The armed priests boosted their morale by surrounding the Dairi, and advised Kebiishi betto Tokitada to take an immediate action such as dispatch of the imperial army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The armed priests boosted their morale by surrounding the Dairi, and advised Kebiishi betto Tokitada to take immediate action, such as dispatching the imperial army.</e>
<cmt>punctuation; verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The armed priests boosted their morale by surrounding the Dairi, and advised Kebiishi betto (superintendent of the Imperial Police) Tokitada to take immediate action, such as dispatching the imperial army.</e>
<cmt>「検非違使別当」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>この時、重盛は官兵300騎を率いて宗盛・頼盛とともに待機していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Shigemori was already leading 300 imperial horse soldiers and stood by together with Munemori and Yorimori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Shigemori was already leading 300 imperial horse soldiers and stood together with Munemori and Yorimori.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Shigemori was already leading 300 imperial horse soldiers and stood together with Munemori and Yorimori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>公卿の議定では慎重論が大勢を占め、重盛も後白河の三度に渡る出動命令を拒否したため、やむを得ず後白河院は成親の流罪を認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the majority of kugyo agreed that they were against risking a battle, and also, because Shigemori refused to follow the operation order that was issued three times by Goshirakawa, Goshirakawa-in agreed to deportation of Narichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the majority of kugyo (court nobles) agreed that they were against risking a battle, and also, because Shigemori refused to follow the operation order that was issued three times by Goshirakawa, Goshirakawa-in agreed to deport Narichika.</e>
<cmt>The word &quot;kugyo&quot; required the explanation in parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the majority of kugyo agreed that they were against risking a battle, and also, because Shigemori refused to follow the operation order that was issued three times by Goshirakawa, Goshirakawain agreed to deport Narichika.</e>
<cmt>&quot;kugyo&quot;の補足説明は既出のため(4行目)、ローマ字表記のみとしました。Goshirakawa-in→Goshirakawainとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="61">
<j>しかし、すぐに巻き返しに転じて成親を検非違使別当に任命、時忠は解任され身代わりに配流とされてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa-in, however, quickly executed a comeback operation and assigned Narichika to Kebiishi betto, resulting in removal of Tokitada from his post and then in deportation of him instead of Narichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa-in, however, quickly executed a comeback operation and assigned Narichika to Kebiishi betto, resulting in the removal of Tokitada from his post and then his deportation instead of Narichika.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawain, however, quickly executed a comeback operation and assigned Narichika to Kebiishi betto, resulting in the removal of Tokitada from his post and then his deportation instead of Narichika.</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawainとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>後白河院と延暦寺の対立は悪化の一途をたどり、事態を憂慮した清盛は正月14日、重盛を福原に呼び寄せて状況を報告させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conflict between Goshirakawa-in and the Enryaku-ji Temple went from bad to worse, and being concerned about the situation, on January 14, Kiyomori called Shigemori over to Fukuhara and demanded a report of the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conflict between Goshirakawa-in and the Enryaku-ji Temple worsened; and, concerned over the situation Kiyomori called Shigemori over to Fukuhara on January 14 and demanded a report of the situation.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conflict between Goshirakawain and the Enryaku-ji Temple worsened; and, concerned over the situation Kiyomori called Shigemori over to Fukuhara on January 14 and demanded a report of the situation.</e>
<cmt>Goshirakawainとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>このように重盛は一門の代表とはいえ、重要案件については清盛の判断が優先していて、自らの意思・行動はかなり制約されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, although Shigemori was the leader of the clan, Kiyomori&apos;s decisions were prioritized for important matters; therefore Shigemori&apos;s desires and actions were very much limited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, although Shigemori was the leader of the clan, Kiyomori&apos;s decisions were prioritized for important matters; therefore, Shigemori&apos;s desires and actions were very much limited.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, although Shigemori was the leader of the clan, Kiyomori&apos;s decisions were prioritized for important matters; therefore, Shigemori&apos;s desires and actions were very much limited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>結局、成親の解官で延暦寺は引き下がり事態は沈静化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, Narichika was removed from the post, the Enryaku-ji Temple community members withdrew themselves, and the situation was once again under control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Narichika was removed from the post, the Enryaku-ji Temple community members withdrew themselves, and the situation was once again under control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Narichika was removed from the post, the Enryaku-ji Temple community members withdrew themselves, and the situation was once again under control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>同年4月、重盛は権大納言に復帰し、成親も検非違使別当に返り咲いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April of the same year, Shigemori once again became Gon dainagon, and Narichika also came back as Kebiishi betto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April of the same year, Shigemori once again became Gon dainagon, and Narichika also came back as Kebiishi betto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of the same year, Shigemori once again became Gon Dainagon, and Narichika also came back as Kebiishi betto.</e>
<cmt>Ｇon Dainagonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>殿下乗合事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenga no Noriai Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenga no Noriai Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenga no Noriai Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>嘉応2年（1170年）7月3日、法勝寺八講の初日、摂政・松殿基房の従者が参詣途中で出会った平資盛の車の無礼をとがめて恥辱を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 3, 1170, which was the first day of the hakko event at the Hossho-ji Temple, a servant of the regent Motofusa MATSUDONO reproached the TAIRA no Sukemori party for their impolite behavior and humiliated them on the way to the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 3 1170, which was the first day of the hakko event at the Hossho-ji Temple, a servant of the regent Motofusa MATSUDONO reproached TAIRA no Sukemori&apos;s party for their impolite behavior and humiliated them on the way to the temple.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 3 1170, which was the first day of the hakko event (eight lectures on the Lotus Sutra) at the Hossho-ji Temple, a servant of the regent Motofusa MATSUDONO reproached TAIRA no Sukemori&apos;s party for their impolite behavior and humiliated them on the way to the temple.</e>
<cmt>「八講」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>その後、重盛の子の車と知った基房は震え上がり、ただちに下手人を重盛のもとに引き渡して謝罪するが、重盛は申し出を拒絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motofusa later on came to know that it was the party of the son of Shigemori and therefore became horrified, and so he immediately made apologies by sending a servant to Shigemori, but Shigemori declined the offer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motofusa later came to know that it was the party of the son of Shigemori and was horrified. So, he immediately made apologies by sending a servant to Shigemori, but Shigemori declined the offer.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motofusa later came to know that it was the party of the son of Shigemori and was horrified; so, he immediately made apologies by sending a servant to Shigemori, but Shigemori declined the offer.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>基房は報復を恐れて、しばらく外出を止める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being afraid of retaliation, Motofusa stayed inside for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being afraid of retaliation, Motofusa refused to leave his residence for a while.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being afraid of retaliation, Motofusa refused to leave his residence for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>ほとぼりが冷めたと思われた10月21日、天皇の元服定のため基房が参内する途中、重盛の武者が基房の従者を襲い乱暴を働いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 21, after things seemed to have calmed down, a warrier serving Shigemori attacked and assaulted Motofusa&apos;s servant when Motofusa was on his way to the Imperial Palace to celebrate the Emperor&apos;s reaching the age of maturity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 21, after things seemed to have calmed down, a warrior serving Shigemori attacked and assaulted Motofusa&apos;s servant when Motofusa was on his way to the Imperial Palace to celebrate the Emperor reaching the age of maturity.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 21, after things seemed to have calmed down, a warrior serving Shigemori attacked and assaulted Motofusa&apos;s servant when Motofusa was on his way to the Imperial Palace to celebrate the Emperor reaching the age of maturity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="70">
<j>この事件のため、天皇の元服定は延引となってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this incident, the ceremony of the Emperor&apos;s reaching the age of maturity was postponed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this incident, the ceremony of the Emperor reaching the age of maturity was postponed.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this incident, the ceremony of the Emperor reaching the age of maturity was postponed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>重盛は天皇の乳父の立場にあり、その行為は許されるものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori was the husband of a nanny of the Emperor, and that incident was therefore unforgivable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori was the husband of a nanny to the Emperor, which made this incident unforgivable.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori was the husband of a nanny to the Emperor, which made this incident unforgivable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>重盛を高く評価する慈円も、さすがにこの事件に関しては「不可思議ノ事ヲ一ツシタリシナリ」（『愚管抄』）と困惑している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jien, who highly praised Shigemori, felt confused about this incident saying &apos;that was something that went beyond my understanding&apos; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jien, who highly praised Shigemori, felt confused about this incident saying &apos;that was something that went beyond my understanding&apos; (Gukansho).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jien, who highly praised Shigemori, felt confused about this incident saying &apos;that was something that went beyond my understanding&apos; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを入れ&quot;Gukansho&quot;としました。(既出のため補足は省略)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>この事件の影響からか、12月に重盛は再び権大納言を辞任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, Shigemori resigned from Gon dainagon yet again, and this could have been due to that incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, Shigemori resigned from Gon dainagon yet again--this could have resulted from that incident.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Shigemori resigned from Gon Dainagon yet again - this could have resulted from that incident.</e>
<cmt>Gon dainagon→Gon Dainagonとし、ハイフン削除、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>翌年正月3日の天皇元服の儀式に、重盛は欠席した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori did not attend the coming-of-the age ceremony of the Emperor held on January 3 in the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori did not attend the coming-of-age ceremony of the Emperor held on January 3 in the following year.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori did not attend the coming-of-age ceremony of the Emperor held on January 3 in the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>この儀式の進行に携わったのは、建春門院の兄弟・平親宗と中納言に昇進していた異母弟・宗盛だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Chinamune, a brother of Kenshunmonin, and Munemori, who had been promoted to a chunagon by then and who also was a younger half brother of Shigemori, conducted the ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Chinamune, a brother of Kenshunmonin, and Munemori, who had been promoted to chunagon (Middle Counselor) by then and who also was a younger half brother of Shigemori, conducted the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>The word &quot;chunagon&quot; required the explanation in parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Chinamune, a brother of Kenshunmonin, and Munemori, who had been promoted to Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) by then and who also was a younger half brother of Shigemori, conducted the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに基づき、Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>宗盛の台頭は、重盛の後継者としての地位を脅かすものとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munemori was gaining power, and this later threatened Shigemori&apos;s post as a successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munemori was gaining power, and this later threatened Shigemori&apos;s post as a successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munemori was gaining power, and this later threatened Shigemori&apos;s post as a successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>右大将、内大臣就任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Becoming the Udaisho and the Inner Minister</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Becoming the Udaisho and the Inner Minister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Becoming the Udaisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) and the Inner Minister</e>
<cmt>「右大将」の補足を追加</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>承安 (日本)元年（1171年）12月、清盛の女・徳子が高倉天皇に入内したのを機に、重盛は権大納言に復帰する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 1171, taking the marriage of Tokuko, a daughter of Kiyomori, and Emperor Takakura, Shigemori returned to the Gon dainagon post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, 1171, taking the marriage of Tokuko, a daughter of Kiyomori, and Emperor Takakura, Shigemori returned to the Gon dainagon post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, 1171, taking the marriage of Tokuko, a daughter of Kiyomori, and Emperor Takakura, Shigemori returned to the Gon Dainagon post.</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>復帰後の重盛は、朝廷の公事を精力的に勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returning to the post, Shigemori actively engaged himself in Imperial affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning to the post, Shigemori actively engaged himself in Imperial affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning to the post, Shigemori actively engaged himself in Imperial affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>承安3年（1173年）4月、法住寺殿の萱御所の火災ではいち早く駆けつけて消火活動にあたり、後白河から称えられた（『建春門院中納言日記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, 1173, when there was a fire at the Kaya gosho in the Hojyu-ji Temple, Shigemori quickly came to the scene to put out the fire and was then praised by Goshirakawa (&quot;Kenshomonin Chunagon&apos;s Diary&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1173, when there was a fire at the Kaya gosho in Hojyu-ji Temple, Shigemori quickly came to the scene to put out the fire and was then praised by Goshirakawa (Kenshomonin Chunagon&apos;s Diary).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1173, when there was a fire at the Kaya gosho palace in Hojyu-ji Temple, Shigemori quickly came to the scene to put out the fire and was then praised by Goshirakawa (&quot;Kenshomonin Chunagon&apos;s Diary&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Kaya gosho→Kaya gosho palaceとし、原文にあわせクォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>同年冬の南都大衆の強訴に対しては、院宣により家人・平貞能を宇治に派遣して防備に当たらせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there was a petition by armed priests of the Nanto sect in the winter of the same year, Shigemori, following the imperial order, sent one of his family members, TAIRA no Sadayoshi, to Uji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there was a petition by armed priests of the Nanto sect in the winter of the same year, Shigemori, following the imperial order, sent one of his family members, TAIRA no Sadayoshi, to Uji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there was a petition by armed priests of the Nanto sect in the winter of the same year, Shigemori, following the imperial order, sent one of his family members, TAIRA no Sadayoshi, to Uji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>承安4年（1174年）7月、重盛は空席となっていた右近衛大将に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, Shigemori was assigned to the Ukone no daisho post which was at the time vacant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, Shigemori was assigned to the Ukone no daisho post which was at the time vacant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, Shigemori was assigned to the Ukone no daisho Ukone no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) post which was at the time vacant.</e>
<cmt>「右近衛大将」の補足を追加 (=右大将)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>この任官に対して清盛の喜びは大きく、21日の拝賀の儀式には邦綱以下公卿10人、殿上人27人が付き従った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori was greatly pleased by this appointment, and Kunitsuna, 10 kugyo, and 27 tenjo-bito therefore attended the celebration held on the 21st.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori was greatly pleased by this appointment, and Kunitsuna, 10 kugyo, and 27 tenjo-bito therefore attended the celebration held on the 21st.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori was greatly pleased by this appointment, and Kunitsuna, 10 kugyo, and 27 tenjo-bito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) therefore attended the celebration held on the 21st.</e>
<cmt>「殿上人」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="83">
<j>安元2年（1176年）正月、後白河の50歳の賀には重盛も一門の筆頭として出席、平氏と後白河法皇の蜜月ぶりを示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, 1176, Shigemori as the head of the clan, attended the celebration of Goshirakawa&apos;s 50th birthday, showing a close and favorable relationship between the Taira clan and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January, 1176, Shigemori as the head of the clan, attended the celebration of Goshirakawa&apos;s 50th birthday, showing a close and favorable relationship between the Taira clan and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, 1176, Shigemori as the head of the clan, attended the celebration of Goshirakawa&apos;s 50th birthday, showing a close and favorable relationship between the Taira clan and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>5月に重盛は改めて海賊追討宣旨を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, Shigemori again received an imperial order to hunt down and kill pirates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, Shigemori again received an imperial order to hunt down and kill pirates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, Shigemori again received an imperial order to hunt down and kill pirates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>しかし、7月に建春門院が死去したことで平氏と後白河法皇の対立はしだいに顕在化することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Kenshomonin in July, however, conflicts between the Taira clan and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa gradually surfaced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Kenshomonin in July, however, conflicts between the Taira clan and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa gradually surfaced.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Kenshomonin in July, however, conflicts between the Taira clan and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa gradually surfaced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>それでも翌年正月には重盛が左近衛大将、宗盛が右近衛大将となり、両大将を平氏が独占する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, in January next year, Shigemori was assigned to Sakone no daisho and Munemori was assigned to Ukone no daisho, resulting in the Taira clan dominating both daisho posts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, in January next year, Shigemori was assigned to the Sakone no daisho and Munemori was assigned to Ukone no daisho, resulting in the Taira clan dominating both daisho posts.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, in January next year, Shigemori was assigned to the Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and Munemori was assigned to Ukone no daisho, resulting in the Taira clan dominating both daisho posts.</e>
<cmt>「左近衛大将」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>3月には藤原師長が太政大臣となったことで空席となった内大臣に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Inner Minister post became vacant as FUJIWARA no Moronaga was assigned to Chancellor of the State, and in March, Shigemori was assigned to Inner Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Inner Minister post became vacant as FUJIWARA no Moronaga was assigned to Chancellor of the State, and in March, Shigemori was assigned to Inner Minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Inner Minister post became vacant as FUJIWARA no Moronaga was assigned to Chancellor of the State, and in March, Shigemori was assigned to Inner Minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>後白河法皇も福原を訪れるなど、表面的には何事もなく時は過ぎていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time passed as if nothing of concern was happening, as for example represented by the visit to Fukuhara by Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The time passed as if nothing of concern was happening--this is represented by the visit to Fukuhara by the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The time passed as if nothing of concern was happening - this is represented by the visit to Fukuhara by the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除、スペースを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>安元の強訴と鹿ケ谷事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Direct Petition in Angen and the Shishigatani Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Direct Petition in Angen and the Shishigatani Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Direct Petition in Angen and the Shishigatani Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>しかし、4月になると延暦寺が加賀国・藤原師高の流罪を要求して強訴を起こす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in April, members of the Enryaku-ji Temple made a direct petition for deportation of FUJIWARA no Morotaka of Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in April, members of the Enryaku-ji Temple made a direct petition to deport FUJIWARA no Morotaka of Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in April, members of the Enryaku-ji Temple made a direct petition to deport FUJIWARA no Morotaka of Kaga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>発端は延暦寺の末寺・白山と現地の目代の紛争で、中央に波及して院と延暦寺の全面衝突となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The outset of the direct petition was a dispute between one of the branch temples called the Shirayama-ji Temple and a local agent, and the impact of this dispute expanded into a full conflict between the Emperor and the Enryaku-ji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The outset of the direct petition was a dispute between one of the branch temples called Shirayama-ji Temple and a local agent; and, the impact of this dispute expanded into a full conflict between the Emperor and Enryaku-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation; wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The outset of the direct petition was a dispute between one of the branch temples called Shirayama-ji Temple and a local agent; and, the impact of this dispute expanded into a full conflict between the Emperor and Enryaku-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>この時、官兵を率いた重盛は閑院内裏を警護して大衆と対峙していたが、家人の放った矢が神輿の当たるという不祥事を引き起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori, leading the imperial army, guarded the Kanin dairi and fought against the armed priests, but he accidentally created a scandal when an arrow shot by one of his family members hit the portable shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori, leading the imperial army, guarded the Kanin dairi and fought against the armed priests, but he accidentally created a scandal when an arrow shot by one of his family members hit the portable shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori, leading the imperial army, guarded the Kanin dairi palace and fought against the armed priests, but he accidentally created a scandal when an arrow shot by one of his family members hit the portable shrine.</e>
<cmt>Kanin dairi→Kanin dairi palaceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>高倉天皇は法住寺殿に避難し、後白河は大衆を実力で排除しようとするが、京都が戦場になる可能性があると反対の声が上がり、実際に出動する平氏一門も、延暦寺との衝突には極めて消極的な態度をとったために断念、大衆の要求を受諾して師高の配流・神輿を射た重盛の家人の投獄を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Emperor Takakura was evacuated to the Hoju-ji-den and Goshirakawa attempted to eliminate the armed priests by force, Goshirakawa faced an opposition saying that Kyoto may become a war zone, and also, the Taira clan, those that would actually fight the battle, were quite hesitant to be in a conflict with the Enryaku-ji Temple; therefore, Goshirakawa abandoned his attempt, accepted the request and deported Morotaka, and imprisoned Shigemori&apos;s family member who had shot at the portable shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Emperor Takakura was evacuated to the Hoju-ji-den and Goshirakawa attempted to eliminate the armed priests by force, Goshirakawa faced an opposition saying that Kyoto may become a war zone. Also, the Taira clan, those that would actually fight the battle, were quite hesitant to be in a conflict with Enryaku-ji Temple; therefore, Goshirakawa abandoned his attempt, accepted the request and deported Morotaka, and imprisoned Shigemori&apos;s family member who had shot the portable shrine.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Emperor Takakura was evacuated to the Hojuji-dono palace and Goshirakawa attempted to eliminate the armed priests by force, Goshirakawa faced an opposition saying that Kyoto may become a war zone, and also, the Taira clan, those that would actually fight the battle, were quite hesitant to be in a conflict with Enryaku-ji Temple; therefore, Goshirakawa abandoned his attempt, accepted the request and deported Morotaka, and imprisoned Shigemori&apos;s family member who had shot the portable shrine.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、およびHoju-ji-den→Hojuji-dono palaceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="93">
<j>その後、「太郎焼亡」と呼ばれる大火が発生し、太極殿・関白以下13人の公卿の邸宅が焼失する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, an extensive fire called &apos;Taro shobo&apos; occurred, and the Daigokuden and a total of 13 kanpaku and kugyo residences were burned down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the &apos;Taro shobo&apos; conflagration occurred, and the Daigokuden and a total of 13 kanpaku and kugyo residences were burned down.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the &apos;Taro shobo&apos; conflagration occurred, and the Daigokuden and a total of 13 kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and kugyo residences were burned down.</e>
<cmt>「関白」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>その中には重盛の邸宅も含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s house was one of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori&apos;s house was one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s house was one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>5月、後白河は延暦寺に報復を決意すると、天台座主・明雲を解任、所領を没収して伊豆国への配流を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, upon deciding to retaliate against the Enryaku-ji Temple, Goshirakawa dismissed Myoun who was tendai zasu, seized his land, and issued an order to deport him to Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, upon deciding to retaliate against the Enryaku-ji Temple, Goshirakawa dismissed Myoun who was Tendai zasu (a chief priest of the Tendai sect of Buddhism), seized his land, and issued an order to deport him to Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>The word &quot;Tendai zasu&quot; required the explanation in parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, upon deciding to retaliate against the Enryaku-ji Temple, Goshirakawa dismissed Myoun who was Tendai zasu (a chief priest of the Tendai sect of Buddhism), seized his land, and issued an order to deport him to Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>しかし明雲の身柄は大衆に奪還されたため、後白河は重盛・宗盛を呼び出して延暦寺への攻撃を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoun was however rescued by armed priests, and Goshirakawa therefore called for Shigemori and Munemori and ordered an attack against the Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoun was however rescued by armed priests, and Goshirakawa therefore summoned Shigemori and Munemori and ordered an attack against Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoun was however rescued by armed priests, and Goshirakawa therefore summoned Shigemori and Munemori and ordered an attack against Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>重盛らは「清盛の指示がなければ動かない」と返答したため、話にならないと見た後白河法皇は、清盛を福原から呼び出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kiyomori responded that he &apos;would not make any actions unless ordered by Kiyomori,&apos; Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa thought conversation with Shigemori would be a waste of time and therefore called Kyomori over from Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kiyomori responded that he &apos;would not make any actions unless ordered by Kiyomori,&apos; the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa thought a conversation with Shigemori would be a waste of time and therefore called Kyomori over from Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kiyomori responded that he &apos;would not make any actions unless ordered by Kiyomori,&apos; the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa thought a conversation with Shigemori would be a waste of time and therefore called Kiyomori over from Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>Kyomori→Kiyomoriに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>清盛も出兵には消極的だったが後白河法皇は強硬姿勢を崩さず、やむを得ず出兵を承諾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori also was reluctant to dispatch troops, but since Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa maintained a hard-line stance, Kiyomori approved dispatch of troops against his will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori also was reluctant to dispatch troops, but since the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa maintained a hard-line stance, Kiyomori approved the dispatch of troops against his will.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori also was reluctant to dispatch troops, but since the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa maintained a hard-line stance, Kiyomori approved the dispatch of troops against his will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="99">
<j>6月1日、多田行綱が平氏打倒の陰謀を密告したことで状況は激変した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 1, Yukitsuna TADA tipped off Kiyomori that there was a conspiracy to bring down the Taira clan, and this dramatically changed the situation.</e>
<cmt>多田行綱が「清盛に対して」密告したと解釈し訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 1, Yukitsuna TADA secretly informed Kiyomori that there was a conspiracy to bring down the Taira clan, and this dramatically changed the situation.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 1, Yukitsuna TADA secretly informed Kiyomori that there was a conspiracy to bring down the Taira clan, and this dramatically changed the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>この事件では重盛の義兄・成親も関与していて、重盛は捕らえられた成親に「命だけは助かるようにする」と励ましたという（『愚管抄』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s older brother-in-law Narichika was involved in this incident, and Shigemori cheered up the captured Narichika saying that he &apos;would not let him die&apos; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori&apos;s older brother-in-law Narichika was involved in this incident, and Shigemori cheered up the captured Narichika saying that he &apos;would not let him die&apos; (Gukansho).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s older brother-in-law Narichika was involved in this incident, and Shigemori cheered up the captured Narichika saying that he &apos;would not let him die&apos; (&quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせクォーテーションを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>清盛の怒りは凄まじく、成親は備前国へ配流され関係者も一網打尽に検挙された（鹿ケ谷の陰謀）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori was outraged, and as a result, Narichika was deported to Bizen Province, and those who took part in the incident were all arrested (Shishigatani Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori was outraged, and as a result, Narichika was deported to Bizen Province, and those who took part in the incident were all arrested (Shishigatani Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori was outraged, and as a result, Narichika was deported to Bizen Province, and those who took part in the incident were all arrested (Shishigatani Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>重盛は左大将を辞任して抗議の姿勢を見せ、配流された成親に密かに衣類を送るなど必死の努力をするが、7月に成親は殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori resigned from sadaisho to show his resistance and tried hard to save deported Narichika by for example secretly sending clothes to him, but in July, Narichika was killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori resigned from the position of sadaisho to show his resistance and tried hard to save deported Narichika by, for example, secretly sending clothes to him; however, in July, Narichika was killed.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori resigned from the position of sadaisho (Major Captain the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) to show his resistance and tried hard to save deported Narichika by, for example, secretly sending clothes to him; however, in July, Narichika was killed.</e>
<cmt>「左大将」の補足を追加 (=左近衛大将)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="103">
<j>重盛は嫡子・維盛の妻に成親の女を迎えるなど、成親と親密な関係だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori and Narichika had a close relationship; for example, Shigemori married his son Koremori off to a daughter of Narichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori and Narichika had a close relationship; for example, Shigemori married his son Koremori off to a daughter of Narichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori and Narichika had a close relationship; for example, Shigemori married his son Koremori off to a daughter of Narichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>重盛は成親を、後白河に対する交渉窓口・パイプ役として重視し、後白河法皇に平氏の要望を取り次ぐ役割を期待していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori valued Narichika as a negotiator and a connection to Goshirakawa and expected him to tell Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa the requests of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori valued Narichika as a negotiator and a connection to Goshirakawa and expected him to inform the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa of the requests of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori valued Narichika as a negotiator and a connection to Goshirakawa and expected him to inform the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa of the requests of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>その成親が平氏打倒の首謀者であったことで、重盛の面目は丸潰れとなり政治的地位を失墜させることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the fact that Narichika actually was the leader of the conspiracy to bring down the Taira clan, Shigemori was greatly ashamed and lost his political standing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the fact that Narichika actually was the leader of the conspiracy to bring down the Taira clan, Shigemori was greatly ashamed and lost his political standing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the fact that Narichika actually was the leader of the conspiracy to bring down the Taira clan, Shigemori was greatly ashamed and lost his political standing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>終焉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End of His Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Final Days</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Final Days</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>この事件により重盛は無気力となり、政治の表舞台にはほとんど姿を見せなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident dispirited Shigemori and since then he hardly made appearances in political scenes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident dispirited Shigemori, and caused him to hardly make appearances on the political stage.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident dispirited Shigemori, and caused him to hardly make appearances on the political stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>治承2年（1178年）2月には内大臣の辞任を申し出るが、中宮・徳子が懐妊したため、中宮の父とされていた重盛の辞任は認められなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1178, Shigemori offered his resignation as Inner Minister, but his offer was declined because chugu Tokuko became pregnant and Shigemori was the father of the chugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1178, Shigemori offered his resignation as Inner Minister, but his offer was declined because chugu Tokuko became pregnant and Shigemori was the father of the chugu (the second consort of an emperor).</e>
<cmt>The word &quot;chugu&quot; required the explanation in parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1178, Shigemori offered his resignation as Inner Minister, but his offer was declined because chugu (the second consort of an emperor) Tokuko became pregnant and Shigemori was the father of the chugu.</e>
<cmt>「中宮」の補足の位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>6月、重盛は着帯の儀式に出席する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, Shigemori attended the obi-ceremony to pray for safe delivery of the baby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, Shigemori attended the obi-ceremony to pray for the safe delivery of his baby.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, Shigemori attended the obi-ceremony to pray for the safe delivery of his baby.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>徳子は11月に皇子を出産（安徳天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokuko gave birth to a son in November (Emperor Antoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokuko gave birth to a son in November (Emperor Antoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokuko gave birth to a son in November (Emperor Antoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>翌月には「言仁」の名字が定められ、立太子した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following month, Emperor Antoku was given a family name &apos;Tokihito&apos; and became a crown prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following month, Emperor Antoku was given the family name &apos;Tokihito&apos; and became a crown prince.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following month, Emperor Antoku was given the family name &apos;Tokihito&apos; and became a crown prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="111">
<j>治承3年（1179年）2月、重盛は東宮の百日（ももか）の祝に出席するが、病により家に籠もるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 1179, Shigemori attended the celebration for the 100th day from the birth of Togu, but he often stayed home due to illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1179, Shigemori attended the celebration for the 100th day since the birth of Togu, but he often stayed home due to illness.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1179, Shigemori attended the celebration for the 100th day since the birth of Togu (the Crown Prince), but he often stayed home due to illness.</e>
<cmt>「東宮」の補足を追加 (既出の「東宮」の意味とは別のため)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>3月には熊野に参詣して後世のことを祈ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, Shigemori supposedly visited Kumano to pray for a good future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, Shigemori supposedly visited Kumano to pray for a good future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, Shigemori supposedly visited Kumano to pray for a good future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>やがて不食に陥り、5月25日出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he started permanent fasting, and entered the priesthood on May 25.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he started permanent fasting, and entered the priesthood on May 25.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he started permanent fasting, and entered the priesthood on May 25.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>法名は浄蓮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Joren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Buddhist name was Joren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Buddhist name was Joren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>6月21日には後白河が、六波羅の小松殿を訪れて重盛を見舞った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 21, Goshirakawa visited Shigemori at the Komatsu-dono in Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 21, Goshirakawa visited Shigemori at the Komatsu-dono in Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 21, Goshirakawa visited Shigemori at the Komatsu-dono in Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>時を同じくして清盛の女・盛子も亡くなっているが、後白河は盛子の相続していた摂関家領を自らの管理下に置き、平氏への圧力を強めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the same time, Moriko, a daughter of Kiyomori, died, and Goshirakawa started to control the land of the sekkan family that Moriko inherited and increased pressure on the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the same time, Moriko, a daughter of Kiyomori, died, and Goshirakawa started to control the land of the sekkan family that Moriko inherited and increased pressure on the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the same time, Moriko, a daughter of Kiyomori, died, and Goshirakawa started to control the land of the Sekkan-ke that Moriko inherited and increased pressure on the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>「摂関家」→前出の表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>7月29日、42歳で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 29, Shigemori died at the age of 42.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 29, Shigemori died at the age of 42.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 29, Shigemori died at the age of 42.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>死因については、胃潰瘍、背中にできた腫瘍、脚気などの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a number of theories about the cause of his death such as a stomach ulcer, tumor on his back, and beriberi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are a number of theories about the cause of his death such as a stomach ulcer, tumor on his back, and beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a number of theories about the cause of his death such as a stomach ulcer, tumor on his back, and beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>10月、仁安 (日本)元年（1166年）以来の重盛の知行国・越前が、後白河法皇によって没収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa seized Echizen, the chigyokoku that Shigemori had controlled since 1166.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa seized Echizen, the chigyokoku that Shigemori had controlled since 1166.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa seized Echizen, the chigyokoku that Shigemori had controlled since 1166.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>翌月、清盛と後白河法皇の関係は完全に破綻、治承三年の政変によって後白河院政は停止される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following month, the relationship between Kiyomori and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa completely fell part, and the Goshirakawa cloister government ended by the Coup of the Third Year of Jisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following month, the relationship between Kiyomori and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa completely fell part, and the Goshirakawa cloister government ended by Coup in the Third Year of Jisho.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following month, the relationship between Kiyomori and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa completely fell part, and the Goshirakawa cloister government ended by Coup in the Third Year of Jisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Reputation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Reputation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Reputation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>重盛に対する同時代人の評価は、「かくの如きの時、必ず使を送られ殊に芳心（親切な心）を致されるなり」（『山槐記』）、「イミジク心ウルハシク」（『愚管抄』）、「武勇時輩にすぐると雖も、心懆甚だ穏やかなり」（『百錬抄』）など好意的なものが多く、優れた武人であると同時に穏和で気配りのできる人物だった（ただし九条兼実は重盛を嫌っていて、非難の言葉を日記に記している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who lived in the same time period as Shigemori often regarded him as a &apos;kind person who sent his messenger when something occurred (&quot;Sankaiki&quot;),&apos; &apos;a person of a very beautiful mind (&quot;Gukansho&quot;),&apos; and &apos;a very calm person even though he was braver than anyone (&quot;Hyakurensho&quot;),&apos; and therefore, he was an excellent warrior and at the same time calm and considerate (however, Kanezane KUJO disliked Shigemori and scorned him in his personal diary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who lived in the same time period as Shigemori often regarded him as a &apos;kind person who sent his messenger when something occurred (Sankaiki),&apos; &apos;a person of a very beautiful mind (Gukansho),&apos; and &apos;a very calm person even though he was braver than anyone (Hyakurensho),&apos; and therefore, he was an excellent warrior yet at the same time calm and considerate (however, Kanezane KUJO disliked Shigemori and scorned him in his personal diary).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who lived in the same time period as Shigemori often regarded him as a &apos;kind person who sent his messenger when something occurred (&quot;Sankaiki&quot; (diary by Tadachika NAKAYAMA)),&apos; &apos;a person of a very beautiful mind (&quot;Gukansho&quot;),&apos; and &apos;a very calm person even though he was braver than anyone (&quot;Hyakurensho&quot; (History book from the Kamakura period)),&apos; and therefore, he was an excellent warrior yet at the same time calm and considerate (however, Kanezane KUJO disliked Shigemori and scorned him in his personal diary).</e>
<cmt>作品名→原文に合わせすべてクォーテーションを入れ、『山槐記』『百錬抄』は初出のため補足説明を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>中山忠親の送った見舞いの使者に対しても「年来の素懐、障りなく遂げおはんぬ。喜悦きはまりなし」と返礼を述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To the messenger that Tadachika NAKAYAMA sent, Shigemori expressed his gratitude saying that &apos;my long-time desire came true and I was extremely pleased.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To the messenger that Tadachika NAKAYAMA sent, Shigemori expressed his gratitude saying that &apos;my long-time desire came true and I was extremely pleased.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To the messenger that Tadachika NAKAYAMA sent, Shigemori expressed his gratitude saying that &apos;my long-time desire came true and I was extremely pleased.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>その温厚・誠実な人柄で後白河の信任も厚く、『平家物語』において平氏一門の良識派的な存在とされていることも、その人柄が後世に伝わっていたことによると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of his warm and sincere personality, he was very much trusted by Goshirakawa, and the fact that he was portrayed as the reasonable one of the Taira clan in &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot; was because information on his personality was passed down to later generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of his warm and sincere personality, he was very much trusted by Goshirakawa. The fact that he was portrayed as the reasonable one of the Taira clan in the Tale of the Heike was because information on his personality was passed down to later generations.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of his warm and sincere personality, he was very much trusted by Goshirakawa, and the fact that he was portrayed as the reasonable one of the Taira clan in the &quot;Tale of the Heike&quot; was because information on his personality was passed down to later generations.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、および原文に基づきTale of the Heikeにクォーテーションを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="124">
<j>しかし、清盛と後白河の間に立たされた重盛は、平氏の棟梁とはいっても全権を掌握していたわけではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shigemori, who was forced to stand between Kiyomori and Goshirakawa, did not necessarily have total control even though he was the leader of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shigemori, who was forced to stand between Kiyomori and Goshirakawa, did not necessarily have total control even though he was the leader of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shigemori, who was forced to stand between Kiyomori and Goshirakawa, did not necessarily have total control even though he was the leader of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>自らの意思を封じ込め調整役に回らざるを得ない立場が、彼の温厚な性格を形成したといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had to contain himself and served as a coordinator, and this probably contributed to formation of the mild and quiet personality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had to contain himself and served as a coordinator, and this probably contributed to the formation of his mild and quiet personality.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had to contain himself and served as a coordinator, and this probably contributed to the formation of his mild and quiet personality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>しかし、その性格は本来のものではなく、努力と自己抑制による後天的なものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note that this personality was not the one that he was born with; it is believed that he developed it through effort and self-control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note that this personality was not the one that he was born with; it is believed that he developed it through effort and self-control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that this personality was not the one that he was born with; it is believed that he developed it through effort and self-control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>保元・平治の乱での勇猛で生き生きとした姿は影を潜めるが、殿下乗合事件を見ると、激しい感情を心の底に隠していたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His valiant and lively self shown in the Hogen and Heiji Disturbances disappeared, but how he acted in the Tenga no noriai incident suggests that he was in fact hiding his intense emotions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The valiant and lively personality seen in the Hogen and Heiji Disturbances disappeared. But how he acted in the Tenga no noriai incident suggests that he was in fact hiding his intense emotions.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The valiant and lively personality seen in the Hogen and Heiji Wars disappeared, but how he acted in the Tenga no noriai incident suggests that he was in fact hiding his intense emotions.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正、およびthe Hogen and Heiji Warsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>重盛がつぶやいたという「忠ならんと欲すれば孝ならず、孝ならんとすれば欲すれば忠ならず」（『日本外史』）の言葉も史実かどうかは不明だが、『愚管抄』でも重盛は「トク死ナバヤ（早く死にたいものだ）」と生きることに望みを失った言葉を残しており、清盛と後白河の対立の中で無力であった状況を考えれば、あり得ない話ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori supposedly mumbled that &apos;if I try to be faithful to the Emperor, I cannot be a good son. If I try to be a good son, then I cannot be faithful to the Emperor (&quot;Nihon gaishi&quot;),&apos; but it is not certain if this is historical fact; however, since in &quot;Gukansho&quot; he also left words of hopelessness saying that &apos;I want to die early,&apos; he may have actually said it considering the fact that he was powerless standing between Kiyomori and Goshirakawa who were in conflict with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori supposedly mumbled that &apos;if I try to be faithful to the Emperor, I cannot be a good son. If I try to be a good son, then I cannot be faithful to the Emperor (Nihon gaishi),&apos; but it is not certain if this is historical fact. However, since in Gukansho he also left words of hopelessness saying that &apos;I want to die early,&apos; he may have actually said it considering the fact that he was powerless standing between Kiyomori and Goshirakawa who were in conflict with each other.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori supposedly mumbled that &apos;if I try to be faithful to the Emperor, I cannot be a good son, and if I try to be a good son, then I cannot be faithful to the Emperor (Nihon gaishi),&apos; but it is not certain if this is historical fact. However, since in Gukansho he also left words of hopelessness saying that &apos;I want to die early,&apos; he may have actually said it considering the fact that he was powerless standing between Kiyomori and Goshirakawa who were in conflict with each other.</e>
<cmt>文中にピリオドが入っているため、一文になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>重盛の母は身分が低かったため、支えてくれる有力な親族を持たず、同母弟の基盛が早くに死去していたことも、重盛の孤立感を深めたと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s mother was of low birth and he therefore did not have any powerful relatives that could support him, and also, his younger brother by the same mother, Motomori, died young, and these facts are believed to have deepened Shigemori&apos;s loneliness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemori&apos;s mother was of low birth and he therefore did not have any powerful relatives that could support him. Also, his younger brother by the same mother, Motomori, died young. These facts are believed to have deepened Shigemori&apos;s loneliness.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemori&apos;s mother was of low birth and he therefore did not have any powerful relatives that could support him, and also, his younger brother by the same mother, Motomori, died young, and these facts are believed to have deepened Shigemori&apos;s loneliness.</e>
<cmt>複数文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="130">
<j>重盛の死は、清盛と後白河法皇の対立を抑えていた最後の歯止めが失われたことを意味し、両者の同盟関係を完全に崩壊させることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The death of Shigemori meant the loss of the last defense against a conflict between Kiyomori and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and as a result, the alliance between them completely fell apart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The death of Shigemori meant the loss of the last defense against a conflict between Kiyomori and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and as a result, the alliance between them completely fell apart.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The death of Shigemori meant the loss of the last defense against a conflict between Kiyomori and the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and as a result, the alliance between them completely fell apart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>肖像画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Portrait</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Portrait</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Portrait</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="131">
<j>重盛の肖像画は京都神護寺所蔵の神護寺三像伝平重盛像である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The portrait of Shigemori is one of the three portraits owned by the Jingo-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The portrait of Shigemori is one of the three portraits owned by Jingo-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The portrait of Shigemori is one of the three portraits owned by Jingo-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>だが、近年、足利尊氏の肖像画ではないかという説が有力となってきているため、論争となっている（神護寺三像）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, however, the theory that the portrait was actually Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s portrait has been widely accepted, causing debates (three portraits at the Jingo-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, however, the theory that the portrait was actually Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s portrait has been widely accepted, causing debates (three portraits at Jingo-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, however, the theory that the portrait was actually Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s portrait has been widely accepted, causing debates (three portraits at Jingo-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Record of Office and Rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Record of Office and Rank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of Office and Rank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="133">
<j>久安6年（1150年）（13歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1150, at the age of 13</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1150, at the age of 13</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1150 (13 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>12月30日蔵人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 30: kurodo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 30: kurodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 30: Kurodo</e>
<cmt>Kurodoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="135">
<j>久安7年のち改元して仁平元年（1151年）（14歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1151, at the age of 14</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1151, at the age of 14</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1151 (14 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>正月1日従五位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 1: Ju go-i no ge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 1: Ju go-i no ge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 1: Jugoinoge</e>
<cmt>Jugoinogeとしました。(補足説明は既出のため省略)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="137">
<j>久寿2年（1155年）（18歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1155, at the age of 18</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1155, at the age of 18</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1155 (18 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>7月22日中務少輔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 22: Nakatsukasa sunaisuke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 22: Nakatsukasa sunaisuke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 22: Nakatsukasa no shoyu</e>
<cmt>Nakatsukasa sunaisuke→Nakatsukasa no shoyuに修正 (補足説明は既出のため省略)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="139">
<j>保元2年（1157年）（20歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1157, at the age of 20</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1157, at the age of 20</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1157 (20 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>正月24日従五位上（保元の乱での功績）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 24: Ju go-i no jo (for his performance in the Hogen Disturbance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 24: Ju go-i no jo (for his performance in the Hogen Disturbance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 24: Jugoinojo (for his performance in the Hogen War)</e>
<cmt>Jugoinojo, Hogen Warに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>9月19日中務権大輔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 19: Nakatsukasa no gon no taifu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 19: Nakatsukasa no gon no taifu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 19: Nakatsukasa no gon no taifu (provisional Senior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs)</e>
<cmt>Nakatsukasa no gon no taifu→初出のため補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>10月22日正五位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 22: Sho go-i no ge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 22: Sho go-i no ge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 22: Shogoinoge</e>
<cmt>Shogoinogeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>10月27日左衛門佐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 27: saemon no suke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 27: saemon no suke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 27: Saemon no suke (assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>Saemon no sukeとし、初出のため補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="144">
<j>保元3年（1158年）（21歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1158, at the age of 21</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1158, at the age of 21</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1158 (21 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>8月10日遠江守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 10: Totomi no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 10: Totomi no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 10: Governor of Totomi Province</e>
<cmt>Totomi no kami→Governor of Totomi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="146">
<j>保元4年のち改元して平治元年（1159年）（22歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1159, at the age of 22</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1159, at the age of 22</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1159 (22 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>12月27日伊予守（平治の乱での功績）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 27: Iyo no kami (for his performance in the Heiji Disturbance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 27: Iyo no kami (for his performance in the Heiji Disturbance)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 27: Governor of Iyo Province (for his performance in the Heiji War)</e>
<cmt>Iyo no kami→Governor of Iyo Provinceとし、Heiji Disturbance→Heiji Warに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="148">
<j>平治2年のち改元して永暦元年（1160年）（23歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1160, at the age of 23</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1160, at the age of 23</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1160 (23 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>正月6日従四位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 6: Ju shi-i no ge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 6: Ju shi-i no ge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 6: Jushiinoge</e>
<cmt>Jushiinogeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>正月27日左馬頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 27: sama no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 27: sama no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 27: Sama no kami</e>
<cmt>Sama no kamiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>10月11日従四位上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 11: Ju shi-i no jo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 11: Ju shi-i no jo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 11: Jushiinojo</e>
<cmt>Jushiinojoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>11月30日内蔵頭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 30: kura no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 30: kura no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 30: Kura no kami (Chief of Kuraryo, Bureau of Palace Storehouses).</e>
<cmt>Kura no kamiとし、初出のため補足説明を入れ、原文に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>左衛門佐・伊予守両官を止む</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resigned from both sama no kami and iyo no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He resigned from both sama no kami and iyo no kami.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He resigned from both Saemon no suke and Governor of Iyo Province</e>
<cmt>sama no kami→Saemon no suke、およびiyo no kami→Governor of Iyo Provinceに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="154">
<j>応保2年（1162年）（25歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1162, at the age of 25</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1162, at the age of 25</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1162 (25 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>正月5日正四位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5: Sho shi-i no ge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5: Sho shi-i no ge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5: Shoshiinoge</e>
<cmt>Shoshiinogeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>正月27日内蔵頭を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 27: resigned from kura no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 27: resigned from kura no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 27: resigned from Kura no kami</e>
<cmt>Kura no kamiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>10月28日右兵衛督</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 28: ukone no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 28: ukone no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 28: Uhyoe no kami</e>
<cmt>ukone no kami→Uhyoe no kamiに訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="158">
<j>応保3年のち改元して長寛元年（1163年）（26歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1163, at the age of 26</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1163, at the age of 26</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1163 (26 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>正月5日従三位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5: Ju sanmi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5: Ju sanmi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5: Jusanmi</e>
<cmt>Jusanmiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="160">
<j>長寛2年（1164年）（27歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1164, at the age of 27</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1164, at the age of 27</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1164 (27 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>2月17日正三位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 17: Sho sanmi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 17: Sho sanmi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 17: Shosanmi</e>
<cmt>Shosanmiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="162">
<j>長寛3年のち改元して永万元年（1165年）（28歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1165, at the age of 28</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1165, at the age of 28</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1165 (28 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>参議</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sangi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sangi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="164">
<j>永万2年のち改元して仁安元年（1166年）（29歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1166, at the age of 29</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1166, at the age of 29</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1166 (29 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>正月12日近江権守を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 12: Omi no go no kami as a concurrent post</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 12: Omi no go no kami as a concurrent post</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 12: Provisional Governor of Omi Province as a concurrent post</e>
<cmt>Omi no go no kami→Provisional Governor of Omi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>4月6日左兵衛督</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 6: Sahyoe no kami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 6: Sahyoe no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 6: Sahyoe no kami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>7月15日権中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 15: gon chunagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 15: gon chunagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 15: Gon Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>Gon Chunagonとし、原文に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>右衛門督を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uemon no kami as a concurrent post</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uemon no kami as a concurrent post</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uemon no kami as a concurrent post</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="169">
<j>12月2日春宮大夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 2: Togu no daibu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 2: Togu no daibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 2: Togu no daibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="170">
<j>仁安2年（1167年）（30歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1167, at the age of 30</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1167, at the age of 30</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1167 (30 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>正月28日従二位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 28: Ju ni-i</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 28: Ju ni-i</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 28: Junii (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>Juniiとし、初出のため補足を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>2月11日権大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 11: Gon dainagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 11: Gon dainagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 11: Gon Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagonとし、原文に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>春宮大夫を兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Togu no daibu as a concurrent post</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as togu no daibu concurrently.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Served as Togu no daibu concurrently</e>
<cmt>Togu no daibuとし、ピリオド削除、一部文章修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="174">
<j>仁安3年（1168年）（31歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1168, at the age of 31</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1168, at the age of 31</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1168 (31 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>2月19日春宮大夫を辞任（高倉天皇践祚のため）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 19: resigned from Togu no daibu (as Emperor Takakura ascended the throne)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 19: resigned from Togu no daibu (as Emperor Takakura ascended the throne)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 19: resigned from Togu no daibu (as Emperor Takakura ascended the throne)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>12月13日権大納言を辞任（病のため）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 13: resigned from Gon dainagon (due to illness)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 13: resigned from Gon dainagon (due to illness)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 13: resigned from Gon Dainagon (due to illness)</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="177">
<j>仁安4年のち改元して嘉応元年（1169年）（32歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1169, at the age of 32</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1169, at the age of 32</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1169 (32 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>正月5日正二位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 5: Sho ni-i</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 5: Sho ni-i</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 5: Shonii</e>
<cmt>Shoniiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="179">
<j>嘉応2年（1170年）（33歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1170, at the age of 33</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1170, at the age of 33</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1170 (33 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>4月21日権大納言に還任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 21: returned to the Gon dainagon post</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 21: returned to the Gon dainagon post</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 21: returned to the Gon Dainagon post</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>12月30日権大納言を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 30: resigned as Gon dainagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 30: resigned as Gon dainagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 30: resigned as Gon Dainagon</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="182">
<j>嘉応3年のち改元して承安元年（1171年）（34歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1171, at the age of 34</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1171, at the age of 34</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1171 (34 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>12月8日権大納言に還任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 8: returned to the Gon dainagon post</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 8: returned to the Gon dainagon post</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 8: returned to the Gon Dainagon post</e>
<cmt>Gon Dainagonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="184">
<j>承安4年（1174年）（37歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1174, at the age of 37</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1174, at the age of 37</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1174 (37 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>7月8日右近衛大将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 8: Ukone no daisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 8: Ukone no daisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 8: Ukone no daisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="186">
<j>承安5年のち改元して安元元年（1175年）（38歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1175, at the age of 38</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1175, at the age of 38</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1175 (38 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>11月28日大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 28: dainagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 28: dainagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 28: Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに基づき、Dainagon (chief councilor of state)とし、原文に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>右近衛大将も兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukone no daisho as a concurrent post</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as ukone no daisho concurrently.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Served as Ukone no daisho concurrently</e>
<cmt>Ukone no daishoとし、ピリオド削除、一部文章修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="189">
<j>安元3年のち改元して治承元年（1177年）（40歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1177, at the age of 40</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1177, at the age of 40</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1177 (40 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>正月24日左近衛大将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 24: Sakone no daisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 24: Sakone no daisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 24: Sakone no daisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>3月5日内大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 5: Inner Minister</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 5: Inner Minister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 5: Inner Minister.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>左近衛大将も兼任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakone no daisho as a concurrent post</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as sakone no daisho concurrently.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Served as Sakone no daisho concurrently</e>
<cmt>Sakone no daishoとし、ピリオド削除、一部文章修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="193">
<j>6月5日左近衛大将を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 5: resigned from Sakone no daisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 5: resigned from Sakone no daisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 5: resigned from Sakone no daisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="194">
<j>治承2年（1178年）（41歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1178, at the age of 41</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1178, at the age of 41</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1178 (41 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>2月8日内大臣の辞表を提出</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 8: submission of a letter of resignation as Inner Minister</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 8: submission of a letter of resignation as Inner Minister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 8: submission of a letter of resignation as Inner Minister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>6月辞表返却。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June: the letter was returned as unaccepted</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June: the letter was returned as unaccepted</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June: The letter was returned as unaccepted.</e>
<cmt>the→Theとし、ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>内大臣留任（徳子懐妊のため）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stayed at the Inner Minister post (as Tokuko became pregnant)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He stayed at his Inner Minister post (as Tokuko became pregnant).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stayed at his Inner Minister post (as Tokuko became pregnant)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、一部文章修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="198">
<j>治承3年（1179年）（42歳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1179, at the age of 42</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1179, at the age of 42</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1179 (42 years old)</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>3月11日内大臣を辞任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 11: resigned as Inner Minister</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 11: resigned as Inner Minister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 11: resigned as Inner Minister</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>登場作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Media Programs that Shigemori was Featured in</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Media Programs Featuring Shigemori</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Media Programs Featuring Shigemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="200">
<j>平治物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tale of Heiji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tale of Heiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tale of Heiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>平家物語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tale of the Heike</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tale of the Heike</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tale of the Heike</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>源平盛衰記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genpei seisuiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genpei seisuiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genpei Seisuiki (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans)</e>
<cmt>seisuiki→Seisuikiとし、補足説明を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>『地獄門』（1953年 大映、監督：衣笠貞之助、演：黒川弥太郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jikokumon&quot; (directed by Teinosuke KINUGASA, starring Yataro KUROSAWA, Daiei, 1953)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jikokumon (directed by Teinosuke KINUGASA, starring Yataro KUROSAWA, Daiei, 1953)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jigokumon&quot; (directed by Teinosuke KINUGASA, starring Yataro KUROSAWA, Daiei, 1953)</e>
<cmt>Jikokumon→Jigokumonに修正、および原文にあわせクォーテーションを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>『好色源平絵巻』（1977年 東映、監督：深尾道典、演：須田黒冬）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koshoku Genpei Emaki&quot; (directed by Michinori FUKAO, starring Kurofuyu SUDA, Toei, 1977)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshoku Genpei Emaki (directed by Michinori FUKAO, starring Kurofuyu SUDA, Toei, 1977)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Koshoku Genpei Emaki&quot; (directed by Michinori FUKAO, starring Kurofuyu SUDA, Toei, 1977)</e>
<cmt>原文にあわせクォーテーションを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>『新・平家物語 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（1972年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：原田大二郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zoku Heike Monogatari (NHK taiga drama)&quot; (starring Daijiro HARADA, 1972 NHK taiga drama)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoku Heike Monogatari (NHK taiga drama) (starring Daijiro HARADA, 1972 NHK taiga drama)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shin Heike Monogatari&quot; (starring Daijiro HARADA, 1972 NHK taiga drama)</e>
<cmt>Zoku Heike Monogatari→Shin Heike Monogatariに修正、および原文にあわせクォーテーションを追加、&quot;NHK taiga drama&quot;が重複しているため、前の表記を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>『平清盛 (TBSドラマ)』（1992年 TBS、演：渡部篤郎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Taira no Kiyomori (TBS drama)&quot; (starring Atsuro WATABE, 1992 TBS)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taira no Kiyomori (TBS drama) (starring Atsuro WATABE, 1992 TBS)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Taira no Kiyomori&quot; (TBS drama) (starring Atsuro WATABE, 1992 TBS)</e>
<cmt>原文にあわせクォーテーションを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>『義経 (NHK大河ドラマ)』（2005年 NHK大河ドラマ、演：勝村政信）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yoshitsune (NHK taiga drama)&quot; (starring Masanobu KATSUMURA, 2005 NHK taiga drama)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsune (NHK taiga drama) (starring Masanobu KATSUMURA, 2005 NHK taiga drama)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yoshitsune&quot; (starring Masanobu KATSUMURA, 2005 NHK taiga drama)</e>
<cmt>原文にあわせクォーテーションを追加、&quot;NHK taiga drama&quot;が重複しているため、前の表記を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Nnh(id:474), 霧木諒二(id:9795), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), 三浦大輔(id:93377), Juyukichi(id:16958), PATMAN(id:145791), 味っ子(id:17086), Kareha(id:36360), 小者(id:172526), Dwy(id:13375), OMBX(id:35852), Azusayumi7(id:21082), ゐ(id:795), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), 海衛士(id:19229), Point136(id:211299), Bit(id:2197), Ponsaku(id:31417), Richknight(id:141069), Kouko0515(id:100370), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>