<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>甘露寺親長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikanaga KANROJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikanaga KANROJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikanaga KANROJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>甘露寺 親長（かんろじ ちかなが、応永31年（1425年） - 明応9年8月17日 (旧暦)（1500年8月31日））は、室町時代中期から戦国時代 (日本)にかけての公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born in 1425 and gone in 1500, - in detail, the date he was gone is August 17 by the lunar calendar (August 31 by the solar calendar) - Chikanaga KANROJI was a &quot;kuge&quot; (court noble) living from the middle of the Muromachi period to the Sengoku period (the Warring States period in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born in 1425, died in 1500, - in detail, the date he died was August 17 by the lunar calendar (August 31 by the solar calendar) - Chikanaga KANROJI was a &quot;kuge&quot; (court noble) living from the middle of the Muromachi period to the Sengoku period (the Warring States period in Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikanaga KANROJI (1424 - September 20, 1500) was a kuge (court noble) living from the middle of the Muromachi period to the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>実務家公卿を輩出した藤原北家勧修寺流甘露寺家の当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the head of the Kanroji family which belonged to the Kaju-ji line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and the Kaju-ji line produced many practical &quot;kugyo&quot; (top court officials).</e>
<cmt>※「流」は「血筋」の意味で&quot;line&quot;と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the head of the Kanroji family which belonged to the Kaju-ji line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and the Kaju-ji line produced many practical &quot;kugyo&quot; (top court officials).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the head of the Kanroji family which was Kajuji line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan and produced many practical kugyo (a Court noble).</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>出家後は蓮空。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After becoming a priest, he was called &quot;Renku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After becoming a priest, he was called &quot;Renku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After becoming a priest, he was called Renku.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一字名は鬼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His one character name was &quot;鬼,&quot; which reads &quot;ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His one character name was &quot;鬼,&quot; which reads &quot;ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His one character name was &apos;ki&apos; (鬼).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>甥に三条西実隆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanetaka SANJONISHI was his nephew.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanetaka SANJONISHI was his nephew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanetaka SANJONISHI was his nephew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>娘婿に中御門宣胤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutane NAKANOMIKADO was his son-in-law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutane NAKANOMIKADO was his son-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutane NAKANOMIKADO was his son-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>応永31年（1425年）頭弁（蔵人頭左大弁）甘露寺房長の子として生まれる（応永32年説もあり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikanaga KANROJI was born in 1425 (some say in 1426) as a child of Fusanaga KANROJI, the then &quot;To no ben,&quot; or &quot;Kurodo no to Benkan,&quot; (Chief Secretary of the Palace Officer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikanaga KANROJI was born in 1425 (some say in 1426) as a child of Fusanaga KANROJI, the then &quot;To no ben,&quot; or &quot;Kurodo no to Benkan,&quot; (Chief Secretary of the Palace Officer).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1425 (some say in 1426): Chikanaga KANROJI was born as a child of Fusanaga KANROJI, then To no ben (a chief of officials of the dajokan (Grand Council of State)), also referred as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) Sadaiben (major controller of the left).</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し、ウェブに合わせて原文訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>嘉吉元年（1441年）昇殿、従五位下に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1441, he was permitted to enter &quot;Tenjo no ma&quot; (the station within the Imperial Palace only available to a limited number of high-ranking court nobles), and he got the investiture to &quot;Jugoinoge&quot; (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>※「昇殿」とは「殿上の間（限られた高官のみ出入りを許された宮廷内の詰所）への伺候を許されること」（集英社・国語辞典参照）なので、そう変えて訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1441, he was permitted to enter &quot;Tenjo no ma&quot; (the station within the Imperial Palace only available to a limited number of high-ranking court nobles), and he got the investiture to &quot;Jugoinoge&quot; (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1441: Permitted to access to the imperial court, and got the rank Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>嘉吉3年（1443年）、南朝 (日本)の遺臣が内裏の中に侵入し、三種の神器を奪おうとした事件（禁闕の変）が起きた際、自ら太刀を振るって後花園天皇を守護した逸話が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a known story that he guarded Emperor Gohanazono with his own sword when &quot;Kinketsu no hen&quot; (the incident at the Gate at of the Imperial Palace) occurred in 1443, in which a surviving retainer of the Southern Court intruded into &quot;Dairi&quot; (the Inner Palace) and tried to rob &quot;Sanshu no Jingi&quot; (the three sacred emblems for the Imperial Family).</e>
<cmt>※「禁闕」とは「皇居の門」のこと(集英社・国語辞典）なので、その解説部分でもそのように変えて訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a well known story that he guarded Emperor Gohanazono with his own sword when &quot;Kinketsu no hen&quot; (the incident at the Gate at of the Imperial Palace) occurred in 1443, in which a surviving retainer of the Southern Court intruded into &quot;Dairi&quot; (the Inner Palace) and tried to rob &quot;Sanshu no Jingi&quot; (the three sacred emblems for the Imperial Family).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1443: There is a well known story that he guarded Emperor Gohanazono with his own sword when a surviving retainer of the Southern Court intruded into Dairi (the Inner Palace) and tried to rob the Three Sacred Treasures of the Imperial Family (Kinketsu Incident).</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>文安元年（1444年）右少弁、同3年（1446年）蔵人・権右中弁となり正五位上。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1444, the title of &quot;Ushoben&quot; (Minor Controller of the Right) was given to him, and then in 1446, &quot;Kurodo&quot; (the Palace Officer) &amp; &quot;Gon no uchuben&quot; (Deputy Middle Controller of the Right) were given, and his rank was promoted to &quot;Shogoinojo&quot; (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1444, the title of &quot;Ushoben&quot; (Minor Controller of the Right) was given to him, and then in 1446, &quot;Kurodo&quot; (the Palace Officer) &amp; &quot;Gon no uchuben&quot; (Deputy Middle Controller of the Right) were given, and he was promoted to &quot;Shogoinojo&quot; (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1444: The title of Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) was given to him; in 1446, Kurodo (Chamberlain) and Gon Uchuben (provisional Middle Controller of the right) were given, and he was promoted to Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後も累進し従三位権中納言となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he got promoted even higher to &quot;Jusanmi&quot; (Junior Third Rank) and the title of &quot;Gon no chunagon&quot; (Deputy Midddle Councilor) was given to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he got promoted even higher to &quot;Jusanmi&quot; (Junior Third Rank) and the title of &quot;Gon no chunagon&quot; (Deputy Midddle Councilor) was given to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he got promoted even higher to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and the title of Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) was given to him.</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>康正2年（1456年）正三位に進み、陸奥国出羽国按察使に任ぜられ、以後明応2年（1493年）まで同職にとどまったため按察使中納言の名で呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1456, he was promoted to &quot;Shosanmi&quot; (Senior Third Rank) and was appointed &quot;Mutsu no kuni Dewa no kuni Azechi&quot; (Provincial Inspector of Mutsu and Dewa Province), and he remained in the post until 1493, so he was called &quot;Azechi no chunagon.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1456, he was promoted to &quot;Shosanmi&quot; (Senior Third Rank) and was appointed &quot;Mutsu no kuni Dewa no kuni Azechi&quot; (Provincial Inspector of Mutsu and Dewa Province), and he remained in the post until 1493, so he was called &quot;Azechi no chunagon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1456: Promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and was appointed Mutsu no kuni and Dewa no kuni Azechi (local inspector of Mutsu and Dewa Province), and he remained in the post until 1493, so he was called Azechi no chunagon.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また長年賀茂伝奏も務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he served for long as &quot;Kamo Tenso&quot; (the post to transmit the entreaty of Kamo Shrine to the in or the emperor).</e>
<cmt>※「（寺社）伝奏」とは「特定寺社からの奏請を院・天皇へ取り次ぐ役職」のことであり（Wiki 「寺社伝奏」参照）左でもそれを踏まえて訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he served for long as &quot;Kamo Tenso&quot; (the post to transmit the entreaty of Kamo Shrine to the in or the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he served for long as Kamo-denso (Kamo-jinja shrine messenger to Emperor).</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>応仁の乱による戦火で自邸が焼失したため、文明 (日本)2年（1470年）に勧修寺・鞍馬寺等へ避難するが、それらも焼け出され、家蔵の文書・日記類も焼失した（甘露寺家を嫡流とする勧修寺流は実務の家柄であり、必要上から記録を克明につけており「日記の家」とも称された）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fires of &quot;Onin no ran&quot; (Onin War) burned down his house, so he evacuated to Kaju-ji Temple, Kurama-dera Temple, or somewhere else, but he was burned out of even those places by the fires, and his family collection of documents and diaries was also burned away; incidentally, the Kaju-ji line, whose direct descendant is the KANROJI family, was a line that many family members assumed practical work, and they put the documents and diaries on record in detail out of necessity, so people called them &quot;Family of Diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fires of &quot;Onin no ran&quot; (Onin War) burned down his house, so he evacuated to Kaju-ji Temple, Kurama-dera Temple, or somewhere else, but he was burned out of even those places by the fires, and his family collection of documents and diaries was also lost in the fire; incidentally, the Kaju-ji line, whose direct descendant is the KANROJI family, was a line that many family members assumed practical work, and they put the documents and diaries on record in detail out of necessity, so people called them &quot;Family of the Diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fires of the Onin War burned down his house, so he evacuated to Kaju-ji Temple, Kurama-dera Temple, or somewhere else in 1470, but he was burned out of even those places by the fires, and his family collection of documents and diaries was also lost in the fire (incidentally, the Kajuji line, whose direct descendant is the KANROJI family, was a line that many family members assumed practical work, and they put the documents and diaries on record in detail out of necessity, so people called them &apos;Family of the Diary.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>年号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同年9月には帰京し、再出仕。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of the same year, he returned to Kyoto and went to work at court again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of the same year, he returned to Kyoto and went to work at court again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October of the same year, he returned to Kyoto and went to work at court again.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>すでに前年には官位は正二位に昇っていたが、官職は寛正6年（1465年）に権中納言を辞して以来、就任を固辞している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the year before, his rank became as high as &quot;Shonii&quot; (Senior Second Rank), but after he resigned from &quot;Gon no chunagon&quot; in 1465, he firmly refused to assume the new title.</e>
<cmt>※セル17・18にあるように、陸奥国出羽国按察使や賀茂伝奏は続けているわけですから、ここも「就任を固辞した」とあるのは、それ以外の「新たな官職」への就任のことであると解して訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the year before, his rank became as high as &quot;Shonii&quot; (Senior Second Rank), but later he resigned from &quot;Gon no chunagon&quot; in 1465, he firmly refused to assume the new title.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the year before, his rank became as high as Shonii (Senior Second Rank), but later he resigned from Gon Chunagon in 1465, he firmly refused to assume the new title.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>有職故実に通じていたことから、多くの公卿から指導を依頼され、たびたび官に推挙されたが、「高官無益なり」とかたくなに断ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an expert of &quot;yusoku kojitsu&quot; (ancient practices and usages in the court), so many top court officials asked him for advice and they often recommended him for a higher rank, but he firmly refused it and said, &quot;It is futile to be an officer of a higher rank.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an expert of &quot;yusoku kojitsu&quot; (ancient practices and usages in the court), so many top court officials asked him for advice and they often recommended him for a higher rank, but he firmly refused it and said, &quot;It is futile to be an officer of a higher rank.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an expert of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette), so many top court officials asked him for advice and they often recommended him for a higher rank, but he firmly refused it and said, &apos;it is futile to be an officer of a higher rank.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語集より補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>文明9年（1477年）には後土御門天皇の命によって洞院公賢の年代記『皇代暦』を増補して天皇に献上している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1477, under the order of Emperor Gotsuchimikado, he enlarged the chronicle &quot;Kodaireki&quot; written by Kinkata TOIN, and presented it to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1477, under the order of Emperor Gotsuchimikado, he enlarged the chronicle &quot;Kodaireki&quot; written by Kinkata TOIN, and presented it to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1477: Under the order of Emperor Gotsuchimikado, he enlarged the chronicle &quot;Kodaireki&quot; (a chronicle from the period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties till the Muromachi period) written by Kinkata TOIN, and presented it to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>明応元年（1492年）嫡子甘露寺元長ら周囲の強い薦めにより権大納言への就任を受けたが、翌年、明応の政変に憤慨した後土御門天皇が退位を決意するとこれを諌め、その直後にすべての官を辞して出家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1492, Chikanaga agreed to assume &quot;Gon no dainagon&quot; (Deputy Major Councilor) on the strong recommendation of the people around him including his heir Motonaga KANROJI, but in 1493, when Emperor Gotsuchimikado determined to abdicate from the throne because the emperor resented &quot;Meio no seihen&quot; (Rebellion in Meio), Chikanaga remonstrated with the emperor, and right after that, Chikanaga himself resigned from all his posts and became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1492, Chikanaga agreed to assume &quot;Gon no dainagon&quot; (Deputy Major Councilor) on the strong recommendation of the people around him including his heir Motonaga KANROJI, but in 1493, when Emperor Gotsuchimikado determined to abdicate from the throne because the emperor resented &quot;Meio no seihen&quot; (Rebellion in Meio), Chikanaga remonstrated with the emperor, and right after that, Chikanaga himself resigned from all his posts and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1492: Chikanaga agreed to assume Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state) on the strong recommendation of the people around him including his heir Motonaga KANROJI, but in the following year, when Emperor Gotsuchimikado determined to abdicate from the throne because the emperor resented Meio Coup, Chikanaga remonstrated with the emperor, and right after that, Chikanaga himself resigned from all his posts and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>法名・蓮空を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His &quot;Homyo&quot; (Buddhist name) was &quot;Renku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His &quot;Homyo&quot; (Buddhist name) was &quot;Renku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Homyo (Buddhist name) was Renku.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>明応9年（1500年）、美濃国で没す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1500, he died in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1500, he died in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1500: Died in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>享年77。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 77.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 77.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 77.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>子は元長の他に万里小路春房がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides Motonaga, he has another child Harufusa MADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides Motonaga, he had another child Harufusa MADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides Motonaga, he had another child Harufusa MADENOKOJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>日記として『親長卿記』があり、同時代の貴重な史料となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His diary &quot;Chikanaga kyoki&quot; still exists today and serves as the valuable historical material of that age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His diary &quot;Chikanaga kyoki&quot; still exists today and serves as valuable historical material from that age.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His diary &quot;Chikanaga kyo ki&quot; still exists today and serves as valuable historical material from that age.</e>
<cmt>用語集の表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>またそれまでの諸記録の写本も多く残し、特に吉田経房の日記『吉記』や洞院公賢の日記『園太暦』の現存する写本の大部分は、親長の手によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also left many manuscripts of documents, and among others, the existent manuscripts of &quot;Kitsuki&quot; (the diary written by Tsunefusa YOSHIDA) &amp; &quot;Entairyaku&quot; (the diary written by Kinkata TOIN) were both mostly handwritten by Chikanaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also left many manuscripts of documents, and among others, the existent manuscripts of &quot;Kitsuki&quot; (the diary written by Tsunefusa YOSHIDA) and &quot;Entairyaku&quot; (the diary written by Kinkata TOIN) were both mostly handwritten by Chikanaga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also left many manuscripts of documents, and among others, the existent manuscripts of &quot;Kikki,&quot; the diary of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, and &quot;Entairyaku,&quot; the diary of Kinkata TOIN, were both mostly handwritten by Chikanaga.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career of title &amp; rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career title and rank</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Official Record</e>
<cmt>他ファイルに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1441年（嘉吉元年）　従五位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1441 - &quot;Jugoinoge&quot; (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1441 - &quot;Jugoinoge&quot; (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1441: Jugoinoge</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>1444年（文安元年）　右少弁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1444 - &quot;Ushoben&quot; (Minor Cntroller of the Right)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1444 - &quot;Ushoben&quot; (Minor Cntroller of the Right)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1444: Ushoben</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1446年（文安3年）　蔵人、権右中弁、正五位上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1446 - &quot;Kurodo&quot; (The Palace Officer), &quot;Gon no uchuben&quot; (Deputy Middle Controller of the Right), &quot;Shogoinojo&quot; (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1446 - &quot;Kurodo&quot; (The Palace Officer), &quot;Gon no uchuben&quot; (Deputy Middle Controller of the Right), &quot;Shogoinojo&quot; (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1446: Kurodo, Gon no Uchuben, Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1448年（文安5年）　従四位下、従四位上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1448 - &quot;Jushiinoge&quot; (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), &quot;Jushiinojo&quot; (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1448 - &quot;Jushiinoge&quot; (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), &quot;Jushiinojo&quot; (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1448: Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), then Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1450年（宝徳2年）　権左中弁、左中弁、蔵人頭、正四位下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1450 - &quot;Gon no sachuben&quot; (Deputy Middle Controller of the Left), &quot;Sachuben&quot; (Middle Controller of the Left), &quot;Kurodo no to&quot; (Chief Secretary of the Palace Officer), &quot;Shosiinoge&quot; (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1450 - &quot;Gon no sachuben&quot; (Deputy Middle Controller of the Left), &quot;Sachuben&quot; (Middle Controller of the Left), &quot;Kurodo no to&quot; (Chief Secretary of the Palace Officer), &quot;Shosiinoge&quot; (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1450: Gon Sachuben (Provisional Middle Controller of the left), Sachuben (middle controller of the left), Kurodo no to, Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>1451年（宝徳3年）　正四位上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1451 - &quot;Shoshiinojo&quot; (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1451 - &quot;Shoshiinojo&quot; (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1451: Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>1452年（享徳元年）　右大弁、参議、従三位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1452 - &quot;Udaiben&quot; (Major Controller of the Right), &quot;Sangi&quot; (Royal Adviser), &quot;Jusanmi&quot; (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1452 - &quot;Udaiben&quot; (Major Controller of the Right), &quot;Sangi&quot; (Royal Adviser), &quot;Jusanmi&quot; (Junior Third Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1452: Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right), Sangi (councilor), Jusanmi</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1453年（享徳2年）　権中納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1453 - &quot;Gon no chunagon&quot; (Deputy Middle Councilor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1453 - &quot;Gon no chunagon&quot; (Deputy Middle Councilor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1453: Gon Chunagon</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1456年（康正2年）　正三位、陸奥国出羽国按察使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1456 - &quot;Shosanmi&quot; (Senior Third Rank), &quot;Mutsu no kuni Dewa no kuni Azechi&quot; (Provincial Inspector of Mutsu &amp; Dewa Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1456 - &quot;Shosanmi&quot; (Senior Third Rank), &quot;Mutsu no kuni Dewa no kuni Azechi&quot; (Provincial Inspector of Mutsu and Dewa Province)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1456: Shosanmi, Mutsu no kuni Dewa no kuni Azechi</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>1465年（寛正6年）　従二位、権中納言を辞す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1465 - Departure from &quot;Junii&quot; (Junior Second Rank) &amp; &quot;Gon no chunagon&quot; (Deputy Middle Councilor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1465 - Departure from &quot;Junii&quot; (Junior Second Rank) and &quot;Gon no chunagon&quot; (Deputy Middle Councilor)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1465: Junii (Junior Second Rank), resigned Gon Chunagon</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>1469年（文明元年）　正二位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1469 - &quot;Shonii&quot; (Senior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1469 - &quot;Shonii&quot; (Senior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1469: Shonii</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>1492年（明応元年）　権大納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1492 - &quot;Gon no dainagon&quot; (Deputy Major Councilor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1492 - &quot;Gon no dainagon&quot; (Deputy Major Councilor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1492: Gon Dainagon</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>1493年（明応2年）　権大納言、按察使を辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1493 - Departure from &quot;Gon no dainagon&quot; &amp; &quot;Mutsu no kuni Dewa no kuni Azechi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1493 - Departure from &quot;Gon no dainagon&quot; and &quot;Mutsu no kuni Dewa no kuni Azechi&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1493: Resigned Gon Dainagon and Mutsu no kuni Dewa no kuni Azechi</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用し表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>出家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Becoming a priest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Becoming a priest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Became a priest.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Oxhop(id:2551), トホホ川(id:50502), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>