<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>春香院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunmoji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunmoji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunmoji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>春香院（しゅんもじ、天正8年5月7日 (旧暦)（1580年6月18日） - 寛永18年11月20日 (旧暦)（1641年12月22日））は、前田利家と芳春院夫妻の六女で前田利長の実妹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunmoji (June 18, 1580 - December 22, 1641) was the sixth daughter of Toshiie MAEDA and Hoshunin, and the biological younger sister of Toshinaga MAEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunmoji (June 18, 1580 - December 22, 1641) was the sixth daughter of Toshiie MAEDA and Hoshunin, and the biological younger sister of Toshinaga MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunmoji (June 18, 1580 - December 22, 1641) was the sixth daughter of Toshiie MAEDA and Hoshunin, and the biological younger sister of Toshinaga MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名はおちよ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her first name was Ochiyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her first name was Ochiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her first name was Ochiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>前田 千世（まえだ ちよ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiyo MAEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiyo MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiyo MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>春香院は、1597年に細川忠興の嫡男細川忠隆と結婚するが、「故あって（義母細川ガラシャとともに自害しなかったことを指す）、慶長五年（1600年）に細川家から離縁。」（細川家記綿考輯録より）され、のち前田加賀八家のひとつでまつ（芳春院）の信頼が深い村井長頼の子村井長次に再嫁した（時期には異説がある。再婚時期の謎。）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunmoji married Tadataka HOSOKAWA, the legitimate son of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, in 1597, but was &apos;divorced from the Hosokawa family in 1600 for a reason (she did not commit suicide with the mother-in-law, Garasha HOSOKAWA)&apos; (according to Hosokawakeki menkoshuroku), and later remarried Nagatsugu MURAI, the son of Nagayori MURAI, who was one of the Maeda Kaga eight families, and deeply trusted by Matsu (Hoshunin) (There are different theories on the timing. Described later.).</e>
<cmt>「再婚時期の謎。」はWebにしたがい「後述。」として訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunmoji married Tadataka HOSOKAWA, the legitimate son of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, in 1597, but was &apos;divorced from the Hosokawa family in 1600 for a reason (she did not commit suicide with the mother-in-law, Garasha HOSOKAWA)&apos; (according to Hosokawakeki menkoshuroku), and later remarried Nagatsugu MURAI, the son of Nagayori MURAI, who was one of the Maeda Kaga eight families, and deeply trusted by Matsu (Hoshunin) (There are different theories on the timing. Described later.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunmoji married Tadataka HOSOKAWA, the legitimate son of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, in 1597, but was &apos;divorced from the Hosokawa family in 1600 for a certain reason (which was she did not commit suicide with the mother-in-law, Garasha HOSOKAWA)&apos; (according to &quot;Hosokawakeki menkoshuroku&quot; (Records of the Hosokawa family)), and later remarried Nagatsugu MURAI, the son of Nagayori MURAI, who was from one of the eight Maeda Kaga families, and deeply trusted by Matsu (Hoshunin) (There are different theories on the timing: see &apos;Mystery about the timing of remarriage&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>再嫁後の春香院と村井長次との間に実子はなかったものの、養子長光（実は織田長孝の子で、織田有楽斎の孫にあたる）をとり、1613年に長次が死去したあとは、落飾して村井家で春香院となり、穏やかな後半生を過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After remarrying, Shunmoji did not have a biological child with Nagatsugu MURAI, but adopted Nagamitsu (who was in fact, the child of Nagataka ODA and grandchild of Urakusai ODA), and after the death of Nagatsugu in 1613, she went on to rakushoku (to take the tonsure and enter the priesthood) and became Shunmoji in the Murai family, and had a peaceful latter half of life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After remarrying, Shunmoji did not have a biological child with Nagatsugu MURAI, but adopted Nagamitsu (who was in fact, the child of Nagataka ODA and grandchild of Urakusai ODA), and after the death of Nagatsugu in 1613, she went on to rakushoku (to take the tonsure and enter the priesthood) and became Shunmoji in the Murai family, and had a peaceful life in the latter half.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After remarrying, Shunmoji did not have a biological child with Nagatsugu MURAI, but adopted Nagamitsu (who was in fact, the child of Nagataka ODA, and the grandchild of Urakusai ODA), and after the death of Nagatsugu in 1613, she took the tonsure and entered the priesthood, and had a peaceful life in the Murai family under the Buddhist name Shunmoji for the latter half of her life.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、村井家石高は16,500石余で経済的にも恵まれており、春香院は村井長次死後に能登領熊甲神社の再建などもしている（岩沢愿彦著『前田利家』など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Murai family was financially well off, with a kokudaka (assessed yield) of around 16,500 koku, and Shunmoji worked on the reconstruction of Kumakabuto-jinja Shrine in the Noto territory after the death of Nagatsugu MURAI (&quot;Toshiie MAEDA&quot; by Yoshihiko IWASAWA etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Murai family was financially well off, with a kokudaka (assessed yield) of around 16,500 koku, and Shunmoji worked on the reconstruction of Kumakabuto-jinja Shrine in the Noto territory after the death of Nagatsugu MURAI (&quot;Toshiie MAEDA&quot; by Yoshihiko IWASAWA etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Murai family was financially well off, with a kokudaka (assessed yield) of around 16,500 koku, and Shunmoji worked on the reconstruction of the Kumakabuto-jinja Shrine in the Noto territory after the death of Nagatsugu MURAI (according to &quot;Toshiie MAEDA&quot; by Yoshihiko IWASAWA etc.).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>1641年金沢で死去、享年62。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died in 1641 in Kanazawa, at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died in 1641 in Kanazawa, at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died in 1641 in Kanazawa, at the age of sixty-two.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>墓地は野田山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her grave is in Mount Noda.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is on Mount Noda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is located on Mount Noda.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>春香院はまつ（芳春院）34歳の末子でもあり、子供のうちで最もかわいがられたようで、春香院（おちよ：忠隆妻など、かもじ：村井妻、しゅんもじ：春香院）宛の芳春院自筆状が金沢市の加越能文庫や前田土佐守家資料館などに多く現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunmoji was the youngest child of Matsu (Hoshunin) at age 34 and the most loved among her children, and many notes by Hoshunin in her own handwriting addressed to Shunmoji (Ochiyo: wife of Tadataka, etc., Kamoji: wife of Murai, Shunmoji) exist in the Kaetsuno Bunko (Kaetsuno collection) and Maeda Tosanokamike Shiryokan (Museum of the Maeda family, governor of Tosa Province) in Kanazawa City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunmoji was the youngest child of Matsu (Hoshunin) at age 34 and the most loved among her children, and many notes by Hoshunin in her own handwriting addressed to Shunmoji (Ochiyo: wife of Tadataka, etc., Kamoji: wife of Murai, Shunmoji) exist in the Kaetsuno Bunko (Kaetsuno collection) and Maeda Tosanokamike Shiryokan (Museum of the Maeda family, governor of Tosa Province) in Kanazawa City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunmoji was the youngest child of Matsu (Hoshunin) born at the age of thirty-four and the most beloved among the siblings, and quite a few notes by Hoshunin in her own handwriting addressed to Shunmoji (Ochiyo: wife of Tadataka, etc., Kamoji: wife of Murai, Shunmoji) exist in the Kaetsuno Bunko (Kaetsuno collection) and Maeda Tosanokamike Shiryokan (Museum of the Maeda family, governor of Tosa Province) in Kanazawa City.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>〔前田家家譜より〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[From the genealogical table of the Maeda family]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[From the genealogical table of the Maeda family]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[From the genealogical table of the Maeda family]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>千世姫、千代姫又は長姫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiyohime (千世姫), Chiyohime (千代姫), or Nagahime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiyohime (千世姫), Chiyohime (千代姫), or Nagahime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiyohime (千世姫), Chiyohime (千代姫), or Nagahime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>初め肥後侯細川忠興の男忠隆に嫁し、後藩臣村井長次の室となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She first married Tadataka HOSOKAWA, the legitimate son of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, a feudal lord in Higo, and later became the wife of Nagatsugu MURAI, a retainer of a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>「男忠隆」は「嫡男忠隆」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She first married Tadataka HOSOKAWA, the legitimate son of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, a feudal lord in Higo, and later became the wife of Nagatsugu MURAI, a retainer of a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She first married Tadataka HOSOKAWA, the legitimate son of a feudal lord in Higo, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA; and later became the wife of Nagatsugu MURAI, a retainer of a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>天正八年五月七日生る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born on June 18, 1580.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born on June 18, 1580.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born on June 18, 1580.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>母は芳春院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her mother was Hoshunin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her mother was Hoshunin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her mother was Hoshunin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>寛永十八年十一月二十日没す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died on December 22, 1641.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died on December 22, 1641.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died on December 22, 1641.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>享年六十二。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>法号は春香院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her hogo (a Buddhist name) was Shunmoji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her hogo (a Buddhist name) was Shunmoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her Buddhist name was Shunmoji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>野田山に葬る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was buried in Mount Noda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was buried on Mount Noda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was buried in the ground on Mount Noda.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>再婚時期の謎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mystery about the timing of remarriage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mystery about the timing of remarriage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mystery about the timing of remarriage</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>春香院の再嫁は1605年とされる（『前田氏戦記集』中の「村井家伝」）が、実際に加賀の村井家に入った時期は1611年頃であった可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Shunmoji remarried in 1605 (&apos;Records of the Murai family&apos; in the &quot;Maedashi senkishu&quot; (War records of the Maeda clan)), but it is likely that the actual time that she joined the Murai family in Kaga was around 1611.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Shunmoji remarried in 1605 (&apos;Records of the Murai family&apos; in the &quot;Maedashi senkishu&quot; - War records of the Maeda clan), but it is likely that the actual time that she joined the Murai family in Kaga was around 1611.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Shunmoji remarried in 1605 (&apos;Records of the Murai family&apos; in the &quot;Maedashi senkishu&quot; - War records of the Maeda clan), but it is likely that the actual time that she joined the Murai family in Kaga was around 1611.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>1600年に細川氏から離縁された後も、金沢に帰るまでは春香院は廃嫡された忠隆に付き添って京都で暮らしており、夭折した男子熊千代のほかに、徳姫（のちに左大臣西園寺実晴御台所）、吉姫、福姫（のちに京都公家・久世家初代の久世通式室）、萬姫（夭折）を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being divorced from the Hosokawa clan in 1600, Shunmoji lived together with disinherited Tadataka in Kyoto, and gave birth to a boy, Kumachiyo, who died young, as well as Tokuhime (later Midaidokoro (shogun or minister&apos;s wife) of Sadaijin (minister of the left), Saneharu SAIONJI), Yoshihime, Fukuhime (later wife of Michishiki KUZE, the first of the Kuze family, a kuge (court noble) in Kyoto), and Marihime (died young).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being divorced from the Hosokawa clan in 1600, Shunmoji lived together with disinherited Tadataka in Kyoto, and gave birth to a boy, Kumachiyo, who died young, as well as Tokuhime (later Midaidokoro (shogun or minister&apos;s wife) of Sadaijin (minister of the left), Saneharu SAIONJI), Yoshihime, Fukuhime (later wife of Michishiki KUZE, the first of the Kuze family, a kuge (court noble) in Kyoto), and Marihime (died young).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being divorced from the Hosokawa clan in 1600, Shunmoji lived together with disinherited Tadataka in Kyoto, and gave birth to a boy Kumachiyo, who died young, as well as Tokuhime (later, a wife of the minister of the left Saneharu SAIONJI), Yoshihime, Fukuhime (later, a wife of Michinori KUZE, the first generation of the Kuze family, a court noble in Kyoto), and Marihime (died young).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>すなわち、春香院は細川家からは離縁されても、1611年までは忠隆（細川家を1604年廃嫡された後は長岡休無と称す）とは別れていなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, despite being divorced from the Hosokawa family, Shunmoji did not separate from Tadataka (called Kyumu NAGAOKA after being disinherited from the Hosokawa family in 1604) until 1611.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, despite being divorced from the Hosokawa family, Shunmoji did not separate from Tadataka (called Kyumu NAGAOKA after being disinherited from the Hosokawa family in 1604) until 1611.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, in spite of being divorced from the Hosokawa family, Shunmoji did not separate from Tadataka (who was called Kyumu NAGAOKA, after being disinherited from the Hosokawa family in 1604) until 1611.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Nnh(id:474), NISYAN(id:169936), 松茸(id:27535), Hosokawajun(id:72875), Mongol(id:42517), 寂華(id:83725), こぶまき(id:38278), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>