<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上杉憲顕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noriaki UESUGI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noriaki UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noriaki UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>上杉 憲顕（うえすぎ のりあき、1306年（徳治元年） - 1368年10月31日（正平 (日本)23年/応安元年9月19日 (旧暦)））は、鎌倉時代末期から南北朝時代 (日本)にかけての武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noriaki UESUGI (1306-1368 October 31) was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the end of Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noriaki UESUGI (1306 - October 31, 1368) was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the end of Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>1368 October 31--&gt; October 31, 1368</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noriaki UESUGI (1306 - October 31, 1368) was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the end of Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>初代関東管領。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Kanto Kanrei (A shogunal deputy for the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Kanto Kanrei (A shogunal deputy for the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Kanto Kanrei (A shogunal deputy for the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>山内上杉家の始祖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>上杉憲房の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Son of Norifusa UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Son of Norifusa UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Son of Norifusa UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>兄弟に上杉憲藤（犬懸上杉家）ほか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has Norifuji UESUGI (Inukake Uesugi Family) and others as his brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He has Norifuji UESUGI (Inukake Uesugi Family) and others as his brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He has Norifuji UESUGI (Inukake Uesugi Family) and others as his brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>子に上杉能憲、上杉憲将、上杉憲賢、上杉憲春、上杉憲方、上杉憲栄（越後上杉家）、上杉憲英（庁鼻和上杉家）、岩松直国室、上杉朝房室がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children areYoshinori UESUGI, Norimasa UESUGI, Norikata UESUGI, Noriharu UESUGI, Norikata UESUGI, Noriyoshi UESUGI (Echigo Uesugi Family), Norifusa UESUGI (Kobanawa Uesugi Family), Naokuni IWAMATSU&apos;s lawful wife, and Tomofusa UESUGI&apos;s lawful wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children areYoshinori UESUGI, Norimasa UESUGI, Norikata UESUGI, Noriharu UESUGI, Norikata UESUGI, Noriyoshi UESUGI (Echigo Uesugi Family), Norifusa UESUGI (Kobanawa Uesugi Family), Naokuni IWAMATSU&apos;s lawful wife, and Tomofusa UESUGI&apos;s lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children areYoshinori UESUGI, Norimasa UESUGI, Norikata UESUGI, Noriharu UESUGI, Norikata UESUGI, Noriyoshi UESUGI (Echigo Uesugi Family), Norifusa UESUGI (Kobanawa Uesugi Family), Naokuni IWAMATSU&apos;s lawful wife, and Tomofusa UESUGI&apos;s lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>足利尊氏・足利直義兄弟の母上杉清子は父憲房の妹であり、従って憲顕と尊氏・直義とは従兄弟の関係であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA&apos;s mother, Kiyoko UESUGI was also the sister of Noriaki&apos;s father Norifusa, Takuji and Tadayoshi were his cousins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mother Kiyoko UESUGI of Takauji ASHIKAGA and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA was a younger sister of Noriaki&apos;s father Norifusa, therefore, Takuji and Tadayoshi were Noriaki&apos;s male cousins.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mother Kiyoko UESUGI of Takauji ASHIKAGA and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA was a younger sister of Noriaki&apos;s father Norifusa, therefore, Takuji and Tadayoshi were Noriaki&apos;s male cousins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>早くから尊氏に仕え、関東廂番に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served for Takauji from his early years, and was appointed as hisashi ban (a person who keeps the night watch staying under the eaves of building) of the Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served for Takauji from his early years, and was appointed as hisashi ban (a person who keeps the night watch staying under the eaves of building) of the Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served for Takauji from his early years, and was appointed as hisashi ban (a person who keeps the night watch staying under the eaves of building) of the Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1335年（建武 (日本)2年）に尊氏が後醍醐天皇に叛くと、直義の部隊に属した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takauji disobeyed the Emperor Godaigo in 1335 (Japan), he joined Tadayoshi&apos;s troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Takauji disobeyed the Emperor Godaigo in 1335, he joined Tadayoshi&apos;s troop.</e>
<cmt>(Japan)を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Takauji disobeyed the Emperor Godaigo in 1335, he joined Tadayoshi&apos;s troop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>尊氏が九州に落ちると石見国に派遣されたと太平記にあるが、これは後に石見守護となった上野頼兼と書き間違えられたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &apos;Taiheiki&apos; (The Record of the Great Peace), it mentions that he was sent to Iwami Province when Takauji fell to Kyushu, but it seems that there was a mistake in writing which really meant to mention Norikane UENO who became Iwami no Shugo (the provincial constable of Iwami Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described in &apos;Taiheiki&apos; (The Record of the Great Peace) that he was dispatched to Iwami Province when Takauji fled to Kyushu, but it seems that he was mistaken in writing for Norikane UENO, who later became Iwami no Shugo (the provincial constable of Iwami Province).</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is described in &apos;Taiheiki&apos; (The Record of the Great Peace) that he was dispatched to Iwami Province when Takauji fled to Kyushu, but it seems that he was mistaken in writing for Norikane UENO, who later became Iwami no Shugo (the provincial constable of Iwami Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1336年（建武3年）、父の憲房は尊氏を京から西へ逃がすため京都四条河原で南朝方の北畠顕家・新田義貞と戦って戦死、また長兄の上杉憲藤も1338年（暦応元年）に摂津国で顕家と戦って戦死したため、憲房の跡を憲顕が継ぐところとなった（山内上杉家）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336, his father Norifusa dies in a battle in Shijo Gawara Kyoto when fighting against Yoshitada NITTA and Akiie KITABATAKE from the Southern Court trying to flee Takauji from Kyoto to the west, and also his oldest brother, Norifuji UESUGI dies in a battle against Akiie in 1338 in Settsu Province, therefore he had to take over after his father&apos;s place (Yamanouchi-Uesugi Family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336, his father Norifusa died in a battle at Shijo Gawara in Kyoto when fighting against Yoshitada NITTA and Akiie KITABATAKE of the Southern Court so as to make Takauji flee from Kyoto to the west, in addition, his oldest brother, Norifuji UESUGI died in a battle against Akiie in 1338 in Settsu Province; therefore he had to take over his father&apos;s place (Yamanouchi-Uesugi Family).</e>
<cmt>diesを diedに変更（２箇所）、その他表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336, his father Norifusa died in a battle at Shijo Gawara in Kyoto when fighting against Yoshitada NITTA and Akiie KITABATAKE of the Southern Court so as to make Takauji flee from Kyoto to the west, in addition, his oldest brother, Norifuji UESUGI died in a battle against Akiie in 1338 in Settsu Province; therefore he had to take over his father&apos;s place (Yamanouchi-Uesugi Family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>上杉氏はもともと公家であったが、武家の足利氏と結び付いて関東の新興勢力となり、従兄弟の上杉重能（詫間上杉家）や上杉朝定（二橋上杉家、後の扇谷上杉家）、それに兄弟の上杉憲藤（犬懸上杉家）などを祖とする上杉諸家が、将軍家・足利氏との姻戚関係を背景として、室町時代を通し関東で勢力抗争を展開することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uesugi clan was a court noble from the beginning, but then became a emerging power of Kanto region after uniting with the samurai family, Ashikaga clan, and along with the background of Uesugi family founded by his cousins, Shigeyoshi UESUGI (Takuma-Uesugi family) and Tomosada UESUGI (Futahashi-Uesugi family, later Ogigayatsu Uesugi family), and his brother Norifuji UESUGI (Inukake-Uesugi family) having matrimonial relations with Ashikaga clan who were the shogun family developing power struggles in the kanto region throughout the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uesugi clan was a court noble at the beginning, and became an emerging power in Kanto region through having a relationship with the samurai family, Ashikaga clan; then the Uesugi families founded by his male cousins, Shigeyoshi UESUGI (Takuma-Uesugi family), Tomosada UESUGI (Futahashi-Uesugi family, later Ogigayatsu Uesugi family), and his brother Norifuji UESUGI (Inukake-Uesugi family) underwent power conflicts to expand its influence in the Kanto region while taking advantage of matrimonial relations with Ashikaga clan of the shogun family throughout the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uesugi clan was a court noble at the beginning, and became an emerging power in Kanto region through having a relationship with the samurai family, Ashikaga clan; then the Uesugi families founded by his male cousins, Shigeyoshi UESUGI (Takuma-Uesugi family), Tomosada UESUGI (Futahashi-Uesugi family, later Ogigayatsu Uesugi family), and his brother Norifuji UESUGI (Inukake-Uesugi family) underwent power conflicts to expand its influence in the Kanto region while taking advantage of matrimonial relations with Ashikaga clan of the shogun family throughout the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>尊氏の命により、憲顕は戦死した長兄・上杉憲藤の後任として鎌倉府（足利義詮が首長）の執事に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the order from Takauji, Noriaki gets appointed as steward of Kamakura Government (Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA is the chief) after his oldest brother Norifuji UESUGI who died in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under orders from Takauji, Noriaki was appointed as steward of Kamakura Government (Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA was the chief) succeeding to his oldest brother Norifuji UESUGI who had died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>時制の調整および表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under orders from Takauji, Noriaki was appointed as steward of Kamakura Government (Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA was the chief) succeeding to his oldest brother Norifuji UESUGI who had died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同じく斯波義長の後任として執事に命ぜられた高師冬が常陸国の南朝勢と戦ったのに対し、1341年（暦応4年）に守護国となった越後国には憲顕配下で守護代の長尾景忠が入国し、その平定に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KO no Morofuyu, who was also appointed to be a steward after Yoshinaga SHIBA, fought against Southern Court force of Hitachi Province, and in 1341 Kagetaka NAGAO who was ruled under Noriaki entered the Echigo Province which became Shugo&apos;s territory, and made an effort to suppress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KO no Morofuyu, who was also appointed to be a steward after Yoshinaga SHIBA, fought against the Southern Court forces of Hitachi Province, whereas Kagetaka NAGAO, who was shudodai (deputy military governor) under Noriaki, entered the Echigo Province, which had become Shugo&apos;s territory in 1341, and made efforts to suppress the province.</e>
<cmt>「守護代の」の部分の訳を追加、その他表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KO no Morofuyu, who was also appointed to be a steward after Yoshinaga SHIBA, fought against the Southern Court forces of Hitachi Province, whereas Kagetaka NAGAO, who was shudodai (deputy military governor) under Noriaki, entered the Echigo Province, which had become Shugo&apos;s territory in 1341, and made efforts to suppress the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1349年（貞和5年）、観応の擾乱が起きると、隠棲した直義に代わって義詮が鎌倉から京に呼ばれ、義詮に代わって足利基氏が鎌倉公方となって京から鎌倉に下向した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Kanno Disturbance took place in 1349, Yoshiakira was called to Kyo (Kyoto) from Kamakura instead of Tadayoshi who lived in seclusion, and Motouji ASHIKAGA went to Kamakura from Kyo as Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) to take Yoshiakira&apos;s place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kanno Disturbance took place in 1349, Yoshiakira was called to Kyo (Kyoto) from Kamakura instead of Tadayoshi who lived in seclusion, and Motouji ASHIKAGA went to Kamakura from Kyo as Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) to take over Yoshiakira&apos;s position.</e>
<cmt>take Yoshiakira&apos;s place --&gt; take over Yoshiakira&apos;s position</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kanno Disturbance took place in 1349, Yoshiakira was called to Kyo (Kyoto) from Kamakura instead of Tadayoshi who lived in seclusion, and Motouji ASHIKAGA went to Kamakura from Kyo as Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) to take over Yoshiakira&apos;s position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>憲顕は師冬と共に基氏を補佐するが、直義方の上杉重能が高師直の配下に暗殺されると、直義方の憲顕は師冬と拮抗するところとなり、養子の上杉能憲と共に尊氏に敵対し、1351年（観応2年）には師冬を鎌倉から追放して諏訪氏に攻めさせこれを自害に追い込み、さらに直義を鎌倉に招こうとしたため、尊氏の怒りを買って上野・越後における守護職を剥奪された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noriaki assists Motouji together with Morofuyu, but when Shigeyoshi UESUGI of Tadayoshi troop gets murdered by the samurai under the command of KO no Moronao, Noriaki who is also from the Tadayoshi troop, countervailed against Morofuyu, and together with Yoshinori UESUGI who is an adopted child, opposed with Takauji exiled Morofuyu from Kamakura in 1352, and had Suwa clan attack him which made him commit suicide, and tried to invite Tadayoshi to Kamakura, which lead to Takauji&apos;s anger, and due to this, his shugoshiki (military governor) was deprived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noriaki assisted Motouji together with Morofuyu, but when Shigeyoshi UESUGI of Tadayoshi troop was assassinated by the samurai under the command of KO no Moronao, Noriaki who was also from the Tadayoshi troop, came to countervail against Morofuyu, then he and his adopted son Yoshinori UESUGI together became in conflict with Takauji; in 1351, Noriaki exiled Morofuyu from Kamakura and had Suwa clan attack him, which made Morofuyu commit suicide, and further tried to invite Tadayoshi to Kamakura, at which Takauji got furious and deprived him of the post of shugoshiki (military governor) of Kazusa and Echigo Provinces.</e>
<cmt>時制の調整および表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noriaki assisted Motouji together with Morofuyu, but when Shigeyoshi UESUGI of Tadayoshi troop was assassinated by the samurai under the command of KO no Moronao, Noriaki who was also from the Tadayoshi troop, came to countervail against Morofuyu, then he and his adopted son Yoshinori UESUGI together became in conflict with Takauji; in 1351, Noriaki exiled Morofuyu from Kamakura and had Suwa clan attack him, which made Morofuyu commit suicide, and further tried to invite Tadayoshi to Kamakura, at which Takauji got furious and deprived him of the post of shugoshiki (military governor) of Kazusa and Echigo Provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>翌1352年（正平7年）、直義が死去して観応の擾乱は終結するが、国内の諸将は憲顕から離反し、憲顕は信濃国に追放された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanno Disturbance comes to an end after the death of Tadayoshi in 1352, but the warlords in the country defected from Noriaki, and he gets sent off to Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi died in 1352 and the Kanno Disturbance came to an end, however warlords in the country defected from Noriaki, and he was eventually exiled to Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>時制の調整および表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi died in 1352 and the Kanno Disturbance came to an end, however warlords in the country defected from Noriaki, and he was eventually exiled to Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このとき、剃髪して道昌と号している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time he becomes a monk, and is named Dosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time he became a monk and was named Dosho.</e>
<cmt>becomes をbecame に、is をwasに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time he became a monk and was named Dosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、尊氏が没し2代将軍となった足利義詮および鎌倉公方となった足利基氏兄弟は、幼少時に執事として補佐した叔父の憲顕を密かに越後守護に再任し、1362年（貞治2年）には関東管領畠山国清を罷免しこれに抵抗して領国の伊豆に籠った国清を討伐、翌年、憲顕を国清の後釜として鎌倉に召還しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after Takauji died, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who became the 2nd shogun and Motouji ASHIKAGA who became a Kamakura kubo, secretly made their uncle Noriaki who they assisted as steward in their childhood, to be reassigned as Echigo Shugo (provincial constable), and in 1362 they dismissed the Kanto Kanrei, Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA, and put him down when he resisted when he barricaded himself in the territory of Izu, and a year later, they tried to bring Noriaki back to Kamakura as Kunikiyo&apos;s replacement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Takauji died, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who had become the 2nd shogun and Motouji ASHIKAGA who had become a Kamakura kubo, secretly made their uncle Noriaki, who had assisted them as steward in their childhood, be reassigned as Echigo Shugo (provincial constable), and in 1362 they dismissed Kanto Kanrei, Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA, who made resistance against the treatment and barricaded himself in the territory of Izu but was eventually suppressed; and a year later, they tried to bring Noriaki back to Kamakura as Kunikiyo&apos;s replacement.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Takauji died, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who had become the 2nd shogun and Motouji ASHIKAGA who had become a Kamakura kubo, secretly made their uncle Noriaki, who had assisted them as steward in their childhood, be reassigned as Echigo Shugo (provincial constable), and in 1362 they dismissed Kanto Kanrei, Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA, who made resistance against the treatment and barricaded himself in the territory of Izu but was eventually suppressed; and a year later, they tried to bring Noriaki back to Kamakura as Kunikiyo&apos;s replacement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この動きを知った上野・越後守護代の芳賀禅可（宇都宮氏綱の重臣）は鎌倉に上る憲顕を上野で迎え撃とうとするが逆に武蔵国苦林野で基氏の軍勢に敗退、これに口実を得た基氏軍は討伐軍を宇都宮城に差し向けるが、途中の祇園城で小山義政の仲介の下、宇都宮氏綱の弁明を入れて討伐は中止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenka HAGA (a senior vassal of Utsunomiya clan) who was a Echigo no Sugodai (deputy of Shugo of Echigo Province) of Ueno, suspected this movement, tries to engage Noriaki headed for Kamakura in Ueno, but gets defeated by Motouji&apos;s troop in Nigabayashino, Musashi Province using this as an excuse the Motouji troop sends punitive force to Utsunomiya-jo Castle, but on their way in Gion-jo Castle, under the auspices of Yoshimasa OYAMA, they canceled the subjugation due to the explanation of Ujitsuna UTSUNOMIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenka HAGA (a senior vassal of Utsunomiya clan) who was Sugodai (provincial constable) of Echigo and Kazusa Provinces, being aware of this movement, planned to intercept Noriaki, heading for Kamakura, in Ueno, but was defeated by Motouji&apos;s troops at Nigabayashino, Musashi Province; making use of this incident as a reason, Motouji sent punitive forces to Utsunomiya-jo Castle, but on their way to Utsunomiya, the sending of troops for subjugation was cancelled because Motouji accepted an exucuse of Ujitsuna UTSUNOMIYA in Gion-jo Castle under mediation by Yoshimasa OYAMA.</e>
<cmt>上野をUenoからKazusa Provinceに変更するなど、用語、動詞、冠詞、時制、その他表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenka HAGA (a senior vassal of Utsunomiya clan) who was Sugodai (provincial constable) of Echigo and Kazusa Provinces, being aware of this movement, planned to intercept Noriaki, heading for Kamakura, in Ueno, but was defeated by Motouji&apos;s troops at Nigabayashino, Musashi Province; making use of this incident as a reason, Motouji sent punitive forces to Utsunomiya-jo Castle, but on their way to Utsunomiya, the sending of troops for subjugation was cancelled because Motouji accepted an exucuse of Ujitsuna UTSUNOMIYA in Gion-jo Castle under mediation by Yoshimasa OYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>こうして、尊氏亡き後の幕府・鎌倉府によって代々の東国武家の畠山国清および宇都宮氏綱が務めていた関東管領職および越後・上野守護職は公式に剥奪され、新興勢力の上杉憲顕がその後釜に座り、上杉氏は代々その職に就くこととなった（関東の政変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Takauji, Togoku (eastern country) samurai family, Ujitsuna UTSUNOMIYA&apos;s Kanto Kanrei, and Ueno shugoshiki (provincial constables of Ueno Province) was officially deprived by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun), Kamakura government, and emerging power of Noriaki UESUGI took over after that, and Uesugi clan kept that position for generations (political changes of the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Takauji, the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun), i.e., the Kamakura government officially took away the posts of Kanto Kanreishiki (shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) and shugoshiki (provincial constables) of Echigo and Kazusa Provinces, which had been served by persons from Togoku (eastern provincies) samurai families for generations, such as Ujitsuna UTSUNOMIYA and Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA; instead, an emerging power of Noriaki UESUGI took over them, and Uesugi clan became capable of serving these posts for generations (political changes of the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>「越後・上野守護職」をUeno shugoshiki (provincial constables of Ueno Province)からshugoshiki (provincial constables) of Echigo and Kazusa Provincesに変更するなど、用語、表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Takauji, the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun), i.e., the Kamakura government officially took away the posts of Kanto Kanreishiki (shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) and shugoshiki (provincial constables) of Echigo and Kazusa Provinces, which had been served by persons from Togoku (eastern provincies) samurai families for generations, such as Ujitsuna UTSUNOMIYA and Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA; instead, an emerging power of Noriaki UESUGI took over them, and Uesugi clan became capable of serving these posts for generations (political changes of the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>1367年に基氏が死去、翌年、憲顕が上洛した隙に蜂起した河越直重らの武蔵平一揆武蔵平一揆の乱に対しては政治工作で対抗、関東管領を継いだ犬懸上杉家上杉朝房が幼少の足利氏満を擁して川越城に出陣し鎮圧するのを助けた（1368年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motouji dies in 1367, and a year later when Noriaki proceeded to the capital in the Musashi hei ikki Riot by Naoshige KAWAGOE who uprose, he opposed against with political maneuver, and Tomofusa UESUGI of Inukake-Uesugi family who took over Kanto Kanrei and had the young Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA at his head, take off to Kawagoe-jo Castle and helped with the suppression..</e>
<cmt>原文に誤り有り。武蔵平一揆が二重記載されています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motouji died in 1367, and a year later when Noriaki proceeded to the capital, the Musashi hei ikki Riot led by Naoshige KAWAGOE took place; Noriaki dealt with the riot in a very political way, i.e., he helped Tomofusa UESUGI of Inukake-Uesugi family, who had taken over Kanto Kanrei, take off to Kawagoe-jo Castle for suppression having young Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA as a nominal leader.</e>
<cmt>時制の調整、表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motouji died in 1367, and a year later when Noriaki proceeded to the capital, the Musashi hei ikki Riot led by Naoshige KAWAGOE took place; Noriaki dealt with the riot in a very political way, i.e., he helped Tomofusa UESUGI of Inukake-Uesugi family, who had taken over Kanto Kanrei, take off to Kawagoe-jo Castle for suppression having young Ujimitsu ASHIKAGA as a nominal leader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これにより、武蔵国など鎌倉公方の直轄領をも、上杉氏が代々守護職を世襲することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this, the Uesugi clan made success as the shugoshiki (military governor) for generations including the direct control territory of Kamakura kubo such as Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, the Uesugi clan came to serve by heredity the posts of shugoshiki (military governor) including the direct control territory of Kamakura kubo such as Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, the Uesugi clan came to serve by heredity the posts of shugoshiki (military governor) including the direct control territory of Kamakura kubo such as Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>引き続き、新田義宗や脇屋義治などの南朝 (日本)勢力の鎮圧に後陣で当たったが、老齢のために9月19日、足利の陣中にて死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued to suppress the Southern Court (Japan) power such as Yoshimune NITTA and Yoshiharu WAKIYA as a reserve troop, but died in the Ashikaga camp on September 19, due to his old age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to suppress the Southern Court (Japan) power such as Yoshimune NITTA and Yoshiharu WAKIYA as a reserve troop, but died in the Ashikaga camp on September 19, due to his old age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to suppress the Southern Court (Japan) power such as Yoshimune NITTA and Yoshiharu WAKIYA as a reserve troop, but died in the Ashikaga camp on September 19, due to his old age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>法号は国清寺桂山道昌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hogo (a Buddhist name) is Kokusei-ji Temple Katsurayama Dosho.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hogo (a Buddhist name) is 国清寺桂山道昌 (Kokusei-ji Temple Katsurayama Dosho).</e>
<cmt>「国清寺桂山道昌」を追記（読み方不明のための措置）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hogo (a Buddhist name) is 国清寺桂山道昌 (Kokusei-ji Temple Katsurayama Dosho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>墓所は伊豆の国市奈古屋の国清寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave is at the Kokusei-ji Temple in Nagoya, Izunokuni City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is at the Kokusei-ji Temple in Nagoya, Izunokuni City.</e>
<cmt>Grave --&gt; His grave</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is at the Kokusei-ji Temple in Nagoya, Izunokuni City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), FCTR2(id:213046), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Lem(id:9112), UMBRO(id:100484), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Suisui(id:69), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>