<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>川端家長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaga KAWABATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaga KAWABATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>川端　家長 （かわばた　いえなが、生没年不詳）は、宇喜多氏家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaga KAWABATA (the year of birth and death unknown) was a vassal of the Ukita clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaga KAWABATA (year of birth and death unknown) was a vassal of the Ukita clan.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>官位は丹後守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was Tango no kami (the governor of Tango Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official rank was Tango no kami (the governor of Tango Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>元浦上氏（浦上宗景）家臣であり、主家滅亡後に宇喜多家に仕え、佐良山城・室尾城の守備に就く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had been a vassal of the Uragami clan (Munekage URAGAMI), and after the downfall of the Uragami clan, he served the Ukita clan and guarded Sarayama Castle and Muroo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had been a vassal of the Uragami clan (Munekage URAGAMI), and after the downfall of the Uragami clan, he served the Ukita clan and guarded Sarayama Castle and Muroo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had been a vassal of the Uragami clan (Munekage URAGAMI), and after the downfall of the Uragami clan, he served the Ukita clan and guarded Sarayama-jo Castle and Muroo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>城名に -jo 追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>天正11年（1583年）、草刈重継との戦に負けて城を離れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1538, he left the castles after defeating the battle with Shigetsugu KUSAKARI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1538, he left the castles after defeat in a battle against Shigetsugu KUSAKARI.</e>
<cmt>defeating the &gt; derfeat in awith &gt; against</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後、知行1600石・本丸御番衆並びに鉄砲頭を務めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that afterwards, he was given the chigyo (enfeoffment) of 1,600 koku and appointed as the guard of Honmaru (the keep of a castle) and the head of the artillery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that afterwards, he was given a chigyo (enfeoffment) of 1,600 koku, appointed guard of the honmaru (the keep of a castle) and the head of the artillery.</e>
<cmt>the &gt; aand &gt;,Deleted &quot;as the&quot;Honmaru &gt; the honmaru</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>