<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高島秋帆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuhan TAKASHIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuhan TAKASHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuhan TAKASHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高島 秋帆（たかしま しゅうはん、1798年9月24日（寛政10年8月15日 (旧暦)） - 1866年2月28日（慶応2年1月14日 (旧暦)））は、江戸時代後期・幕末期の砲術家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuhan TAKASHIMA (September 24, 1798 - February 28, 1866) was a hojutsuka (ballistic specialist) during the late Edo period and the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuhan TAKASHIMA (September 24, 1798 - February 28, 1866) was a hojutsuka (ballistic specialist) during the late Edo period and the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuhan TAKASHIMA (September 24, 1798 - February 28, 1866) was a hojutsuka (ballistic specialist) during the late Edo period and the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>名は茂敦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name was Shigeyoshi.</e>
<cmt>諱・通称・号の慣わしを考え、「名」をnicknameにすることや、茂敦が字であったこと（『高島秋帆』/有馬成甫・吉川弘文館、『豆州幕末物語』/高遠敦・望月五洋）からcourtesy nameまたはname received upon reaching adulthoodなども検討致しましたが、原文に近いものに致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name was Shigeyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name was Shigeyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は糾之丞、四郎大夫、喜平。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Tadanojo, Shirodayu, and Kihei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Tadanojo, Shirodayu, and Kihei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Tadanojo, Shirodayu, and Kihei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は秋帆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name he called himself was Shuhan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name he called himself was Shuhan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name he called himself was Shuhan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>高島流砲術の創始者（流祖）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder (ryuso, an originator) of Takashima ryu hojutsu (the Takashima School of Gunnery).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the founder (ryuso, an originator) of Takashima ryu hojutsu (the Takashima School of Gunnery).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the founder (ryuso, an originator) of Takashima ryu hojutsu (the Takashima School of Gunnery).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「火技之中興洋兵之開祖」と号すことを認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gained acceptance in calling himself as &apos;kagi chukoyohei kaiso&apos; (the originator who introduced Western gunnery and military science to Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gained recognition calling himself &apos;kagi chukoyohei kaiso&apos; (the originator who introduced Western gunnery and military science to Japan).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gained recognition calling himself &apos;kagi chukoyohei kaiso&apos; (the originator who introduced Western gunnery and military science to Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>1798年（寛政10年）、長崎町年寄の高島茂起（四郎兵衛）の三男として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in 1798 as the third son of Shigeki (Shirobe) TAKASHIMA, a Nagasaki machi toshiyori (an important local officer under the Tokugawa Shogunate of Nagasaki-machi Town).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1798 as the third son of Shigeki (Shirobe) TAKASHIMA, a Nagasaki machi toshiyori (an important local officer under the Tokugawa Shogunate of Nagasaki-machi Town).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1798 as the third son of Shigeki (Shirobe) TAKASHIMA, a Nagasaki machi toshiyori (an important local officer under the Tokugawa Shogunate of Nagasaki-machi Town).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>当時、長崎は日本で唯一の海外と通じた都市であったため、そこで育った秋帆は、日本砲術と西洋砲術の格差を知って愕然とし、自らオランダ語や洋式砲術を学んで、私費で銃器等を揃え1834年（天保5年）に高島流砲術を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time, since Nagasaki was the only city in Japan open to overseas, Shuhan who grew up there was astonished to find the gap between Japanese gunnery and Western gunnery, and he studied Dutch and foreign gunnery on his own, gathered firearms and so on by his private expense, and in 1834, consummated the Takashima ryu hojutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, since Nagasaki was the only city in Japan open to overseas, Shuhan, who grew up there, was astonished to find such a large gap between Japanese gunnery and Western gunnery, so he studied Dutch and foreign gunnery on his own, gathered firearms and so on with his private money, and in 1834, completed the Takashima ryu hojutsu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, since Nagasaki was the only city in Japan open to overseas, Shuhan, who grew up there, was astonished to find such a large gap between Japanese gunnery and Western gunnery, so he studied Dutch and foreign gunnery on his own, gathered firearms and so on with his private money, and in 1834, completed the Takashima ryu hojutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、この年には、佐賀藩武雄領主鍋島茂義が入門、翌1835年（天保6年）免許皆伝を与えるとともに、自作第一号の大砲（青銅製モルチール砲）を献上している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in this year, Shigeyoshi NABESHIMA, the feudal lord of Takeo in the Saga Domain, became his disciple, and a year after in 1835, along with granting menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency), he presented his first original cannon (a bronze mortar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in this year, Shigeyoshi NABESHIMA, the feudal lord of Takeo in the Saga Domain, became his disciple, and a year after in 1835, along with granting menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency), he presented his first original cannon (a bronze mortar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in this year, Shigeyoshi NABESHIMA, the feudal lord of Takeo in the Saga Domain, became his disciple, and a year after in 1835, along with granting menkyo-kaiden (full proficiency), he presented his first original cannon (a bronze mortar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、清がイギリスとの戦争であるアヘン戦争に敗れたことを知ると、秋帆は幕府に意見書を提出して1841年6月27日（天保12年5月9日）、武州徳丸ヶ原（現東京都板橋区高島平）で日本初となる洋式砲術と洋式銃陣の公開演習を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, on learning Qing&apos;s defeat against England in the Opium War, Shuhan submitted a written report to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and on June 27, 1841, conducted Japan&apos;s first public exercise of foreign gunnery and western armed camp at Bushu Tokumarugahara (the area including current Tokyo, Saitama Prefecture and the western part of Kanagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, upon learning of Qing&apos;s defeat in the Opium War with England, Shuhan submitted a written report to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and on June 27, 1841, conducted Japan&apos;s first public exercise of foreign gunnery and western armed encampment at Bushu Tokumarugahara (the area including current Tokyo, Saitama Prefecture and the western part of Kanagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, upon learning of Qing&apos;s defeat in the Opium War with England, Shuhan submitted a written report to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and on June 27, 1841, conducted Japan&apos;s first public exercise of foreign gunnery and western armed encampment at Bushu Tokumarugahara (at present Takashimadaira, Itabashi-Ward, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>（現東京都板橋区高島平)を補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この時の兵装束は筒袖上衣に裁着袴（たっつけばかま）、頭に黒塗円錐形の銃陣笠であり、特に銃陣笠は見分に来ていた幕府役人が「異様之冠物」と批判するような斬新なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The heishozoku (military costume) at this time was tsutsusode joi (straight-sleeved jacket) with tatsutsuke bakama (man&apos;s formal divided skirt), black lacquered conical jujingasa (a conical headpiece for armed soldiers) on the head, and the jujingasa, particularly, was such a novelty that officers of the feudal government who came for field surveying criticized as &apos;iyo no kaburimono&apos; (an eccentric headgear).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The heishozoku (military costume) at this time was tsutsusode joi (straight-sleeved jacket) with tatsutsuke bakama (man&apos;s formal divided skirt), and a black lacquered conical jujingasa (a conical headpiece for armed soldiers) on the head; this jujingasa, particularly, was such a novelty that officers of the feudal government who came for field surveying criticized it as &apos;iyo no kaburimono&apos; (an eccentric headgear).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The heishozoku (military costume) at this time was tsutsusode joi (straight-sleeved jacket) with tatsutsuke bakama (man&apos;s formal divided skirt), and a black lacquered conical jujingasa (a conical headpiece for armed soldiers) on the head; this jujingasa, particularly, was such a novelty that officers of the feudal government who came for field surveying criticized it as &apos;iyo no kaburimono&apos; (an eccentric headgear).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この演習の結果、幕府からは砲術の専門家として重用され、江川英龍や下曽根金三郎らに師匠として砲術を伝授していたが、幕府から重用されることを妬んだ鳥居耀蔵の讒訴により翌1842年（天保13年）に投獄され、高島家は断絶となってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this exercise, he was given an important post from the bakufu as an expert on gunnery, and as an instructor, he initiated Hidetatsu EGAWA and Kinsaburo SHIMOZONE into gunnery, but was imprisoned in 1842 on false charges raised by Yozo TORII who was jealous of Shuhan being taken into bakufu&apos;s confidence, and the Takashima family line ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this exercise, he was given an important post from the bakufu as an expert on gunnery, and as an instructor, he initiated Hidetatsu EGAWA and Kinsaburo SHIMOZONE into gunnery, but was imprisoned in 1842 on false charges raised by Yozo TORII who was jealous of Shuhan being taken into the bakufu&apos;s confidence, and the Takashima family line ended.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this exercise, he was given an important post from the bakufu as an expert on gunnery, and as an instructor, he initiated Hidetatsu EGAWA and Kinsaburo SHIMOZONE into gunnery, but was imprisoned in 1842 on false charges raised by Yozo TORII who was jealous of Shuhan being taken into the bakufu&apos;s confidence, and the Takashima family line ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>武蔵国岡部藩にて幽閉されたが、洋式兵学の必要を感じた諸藩は秘密裏に高島秋帆に接触し教わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was in confinement at the Okabe Domain of Musashi Province, but the domains that felt the need for the Western military science secretly contacted ShuhanTAKASHIMA and were given lessons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was in confinement at the Okabe Domain of Musashi Province, but the domains that felt the need for the Western military science secretly contacted Shuhan TAKASHIMA and were given lessons.</e>
<cmt>Added space.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was in confinement at the Okabe Domain of Musashi Province, but the domains that felt the need for the Western military science secretly contacted Shuhan TAKASHIMA and were given lessons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>1853年（嘉永6年）、ペリー来航による社会情勢の変化により赦免されて出獄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1853, from the changes of social conditions due to the arrival of Commodore Perry, he was pardoned and discharged from prison.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1853, due to the changes of social conditions caused by the arrival of Commodore Perry, he was pardoned and discharged from prison.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1853, due to the changes of social conditions caused by the arrival of Commodore Perry, he was pardoned and discharged from prison.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後は幕府の講武所支配及び師範となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, he became Kobusho Shihai (an executive of Kobusho, a military training institute) of the bakufu and a grand master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, he became Kobusho Shihai (an executive of Kobusho, a military training institute) of the bakufu and a grand master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, he became Kobusho Shihai (an executive of Kobusho, a military training institute) of the bakufu and a grand master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そして、幕府の砲術訓練の指導に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he made efforts in directing bakufu&apos;s gunnery training.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he assisted in directing the bakufu&apos;s gunnery training.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he assisted in directing the bakufu&apos;s gunnery training.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1866年（慶應2年）、69歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1866, he died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1866, he died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1866, he died at the age of 69.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>慶応元年に『歩操新式』等の教練書を「秋帆高島敦」名で編纂した（著者は本間弘武で秋帆は監修）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1865, military drill manual such as &apos;Hoso Shinshiki&apos; (a book on military drill completed by Shuhan TAKASHIMA) was compiled by the name &apos;Shuhan TAKASHIMA Yoshi&apos; (Hirotake HONMA was the author, and Shuhan was the editor.)</e>
<cmt>「秋帆高島敦」の「敦」の読み方を見つけることができず、名前の読みを充てております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1865, a manual for military drills named &apos;Hoso Shinshiki&apos; (a book on military drills completed by Shuhan TAKASHIMA) was compiled under the name &apos;Shuhan TAKASHIMA Yoshi&apos; (Hirotake HONMA was the author, and Shuhan was the editor.)</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1865, a manual for military drills named &apos;Hoso Shinshiki&apos; (a book on military drills completed by Shuhan TAKASHIMA) was compiled under the name &apos;Shuhan TAKASHIMA Yoshi&apos; (Hirotake HONMA was the author, and Shuhan was the editor.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>尚、そのときの「号令」が今日、学校や自衛隊にも受け継がれていると思われているが、「気をつけ」（当時は「気を着け」と表記された）、「休め」、「前へ進め」、「立て銃（たてつつ）」、「担え銃（になえつつ）」等は安政五年に元岡舎圭人なる人物が作った言葉であり高島秋帆が作ったというのは間違いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is believed that &apos;Gourei&apos; (words of command) of those times has lived on till the present day in schools and the self-defense forces; however, &apos;ki o tsuke&apos; (stand to attention!) (it was written to mean &quot;wear or put on attention&quot;), &apos;yasume&apos; (at ease!), &apos;mae e susume&apos; (get up!), &apos;tatetsutsu&apos; (order arms!), &apos;ninaetsutsu&apos; (shoulder arms!) and so on were made in 1858 by a man named 元岡圭人, and to consider that Shuhan made them is incorrect.</e>
<cmt>「気をつけ」（当時は「気を着け」と表記された）については、表記についての言及のため&quot;written to mean&quot;を用いて、「着け」の意味を表現するように致しました。また、元岡圭人の定訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it is believed that the &apos;Gourei&apos; (words of command) of those times have lived on to the present day in schools and the self-defense forces; however, &apos;ki o tsuke&apos; (stand at attention!) (it was written to mean &quot;wear or put on attention&quot;), &apos;yasume&apos; (at ease!), &apos;mae e susume&apos; (get up!), &apos;tatetsutsu&apos; (order arms!), &apos;ninaetsutsu&apos; (shoulder arms!) and so on were made in 1858 by a man named 元岡圭人, and to consider that Shuhan made them is incorrect.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it is believed that the &apos;Gourei&apos; (words of command) of those times have lived on to the present day in schools and the self-defense forces; however, &apos;ki o tsuke&apos; (stand at attention!) (it was written to mean &quot;wear or put on attention&quot;), &apos;yasume&apos; (at ease!), &apos;mae e susume&apos; (get up!), &apos;tatetsutsu&apos; (order arms!), &apos;ninaetsutsu&apos; (shoulder arms!) and so on were made in 1858 by a man named 元岡舎圭人, and to consider that Shuhan made them is incorrect.</e>
<cmt>読み不明（元岡舎圭人）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>但し元岡舎圭人が何者かは未だ判明していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it is still unknown who 元岡圭人 was.</e>
<cmt>元岡圭人の定訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it is still unknown who 元岡圭人 was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it is still unknown who 元岡舎圭人 was.</e>
<cmt>読み不明（元岡舎圭人）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>歩兵が背負った背嚢は当時「ランドセル」と呼ばれ、これが後の世に「小学生」のシンボルとなって親しまれることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rucksacks that foot soldiers carried were called &apos;randoseru&apos; (a school rucksack) at the time, and they became the symbol for &apos;elementary school students&apos; in the following generations and became familiarized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rucksacks that foot soldiers carried at the time were called &apos;randoseru&apos; (a school rucksack), and they became a symbol for &apos;elementary school students&apos; in the following generations and became a familiar site.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rucksacks that foot soldiers carried at the time were called &apos;randoseru&apos; (a school rucksack), and they became a symbol for &apos;elementary school students&apos; in the following generations and became a familiar sight.</e>
<cmt>site→sight</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、現代の褐色包装用紙である「ハトロン紙」は当時の紙早合（かみはやごう＝紙製弾薬包）の意のオランダ語「パトロン」用紙の系譜を引くもので、当時の「銃文化」が今日の日本人の生活にもかかわっていることが、これらの語からわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, &apos;Sulfate paper,&apos; the brown wrapping paper of the present-day, is derived from the Dutch &apos;patroon&apos; paper which at the time meant kamihayago (an ammunition cartridge made with paper), and that &apos;custom of firearms&apos; of those times also takes part in today&apos;s Japanese lives can be discerned from these words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, &apos;Sulfate paper,&apos; the brown wrapping paper used today, is derived from the Dutch &apos;patroon&apos; paper which at the time meant kamihayago (an ammunition cartridge made with paper), and the &apos;custom of firearms&apos; of those times that continue to be used in the every day lives of Japan today can be discerned from these words.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, &apos;Sulfate paper,&apos; the brown wrapping paper used today, is derived from the Dutch &apos;patroon&apos; paper which at the time meant kamihayago (an ammunition cartridge made with paper), and the &apos;custom of firearms&apos; of those times that continue to be used in the every day lives of Japan today can be discerned from these words.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、東京都板橋区「高島平」は、高島秋帆によって初めて洋式砲術と洋式銃陣の公開演習が行われたことに因んで名づけられたものであり昔からの地名ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, &apos;Takashimadaira&apos; in Itabashi Ward, Tokyo is named after the public exercise of foreign gunnery and western armed camp by Shuhan TAKASHIMA, and it is not a place name from old times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, &apos;Takashimadaira&apos; in Itabashi Ward, Tokyo is named after the public exercise of foreign gunnery and western armed military camps by Shuhan TAKASHIMA, and it is not a historical name for a place.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, &apos;Takashimadaira&apos; in Itabashi Ward, Tokyo is named after the public exercise of foreign gunnery and western armed military camps by Shuhan TAKASHIMA, and it is not a historical name for a place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>秋帆の洋式砲術は、幕末の志士である吉田松陰や坂本龍馬、河井継之助らも大きな影響を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuhan&apos;s western gunnery has greatly influenced the patriots in the end of Edo period such as Shoin YOSHIDA, Ryoma SAKAMOTO, and Tsugunosuke KAWAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuhan&apos;s western gunnery greatly influenced patriots in the end of Edo period such as Shoin YOSHIDA, Ryoma SAKAMOTO, and Tsugunosuke KAWAI.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuhan&apos;s western gunnery greatly influenced patriots in the end of Edo period such as Shoin YOSHIDA, Ryoma SAKAMOTO, and Tsugunosuke KAWAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 松浸史(id:78240), Artskcr(id:50298), Goki(id:7107), 松茸(id:27535), Cprobot(id:97843), 吉閥(id:24594), Maakun(id:16735), Oh!wenka(id:53059), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>