<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平政連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Masatsura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Masatsura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Masatsura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 政連（たいら の まさつら、生没年不詳）は、鎌倉時代末期の幕府官僚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Masatsura (dates of birth and death unknown) was a bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) bureaucrat in the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Masatsura (dates of birth and death unknown) was a bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) bureaucrat during the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Masatsura (year of birth and death unknown) was a bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) bureaucrat during the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>一説によれば、1308年（徳治3年）北条得宗家内管領長崎宗綱に宛てに書かれた『平政連諫草』の筆者だとされているが、確証はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory says that he is the author of &quot;TAIRA no Masatsura isamegusa&quot; (Remonstration by TAIRA no Masatsura) written in 1308 and addressed to Uchi-Kanrei (head of the Tokuso Family) Munetsuka NAGASAKI of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan, but this is not confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory says that he is the author of &quot;TAIRA no Masatsura isamegusa&quot; (Remonstration by TAIRA no Masatsura) written in 1308 and addressed to Uchi-Kanrei (head of the Tokuso Family) Munetsuka NAGASAKI of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan, but this is not confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory says that he was the author of &quot;TAIRA no Masatsura isamegusa&quot; (Remonstration by TAIRA no Masatsura) written in 1308 and addressed to Uchi-Kanrei (head of the Tokuso Family) Munetsuka NAGASAKI of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan, but this is not confirmed.</e>
<cmt>一部過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ちなみに、同文書は北条貞時への諫言を目的として作られたものとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The document was prepared to remonstrate Sadatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The document was prepared to remonstrate Sadatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The document was prepared to remonstrate Sadatoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>その前後の経歴および家系は不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His background around the occasion and family lineage are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His background and family lineage are unknown.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His background and family lineage are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>