<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山田重忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada YAMADA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada YAMADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada YAMADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山田 重忠（やまだ　しげただ）は、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけての武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada YAMADA was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Heian and early Kamakura periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada YAMADA was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Heian and early Kamakura periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada YAMADA was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the late Heian and early Kamakura periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山田重満の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Son of Shigemitsu YAMADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Shigemitsu YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Shigemitsu YAMADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>仮名 (通称)は二郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His alias (common name) was Jiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His alias (common name) was Jiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His alias (common name) was Jiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>史料によっては重広、重定、重貞と記されるほか、泉重忠とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Depending on the historical materials, his name was recorded as Shigehiro or Shigesada (Chinese character for Shigesada were 重定 or 重貞), or Shigetada IZUMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending on the historical materials, his name 重忠 was recorded as 重広, 重定 or 重貞 in Chinese characters, or called Shigetada IZUMI.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on the historical materials, his name 重忠 was recorded as 重広, 重定 or 重貞 in Chinese characters, or called Shigetada IZUMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>承久の乱で宮方の武将として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He played an important role in the Jokyu War as a busho on the court&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active in the Jokyu War as a busho on the court&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active in the Jokyu War as a busho on the court&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>治承・寿永の乱では重忠の父の重満が墨俣川の戦いで源行家の軍勢に加わり討死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Jisho-Juei Civil War, his father Shigemitsu joined the army of MINAMOTO no Yukiie in the Battle of Sunomatagawa and died on the battle field.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Jisho-Juei War, Shigetada&apos;s father Shigemitsu joined the army of MINAMOTO no Yukiie in the Battle of Sunomatagawa and died on the battle field.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Jisho-Juei War, Shigetada&apos;s father Shigemitsu joined the army of MINAMOTO no Yukiie in the Battle of Sunomatagawa and died on the battle field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>重忠はその後の源義仲入京に際して上洛し、一族の高田重家や葦敷重隆らと共に京中の守護の任に就くなどした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada went to Kyoto afterward following MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and assumed positions of Shugo (a provincial military governor) in the capital along with his relatives such as Shigeie TAKADA and Shigetaka AJIKI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada went to Kyoto afterward following MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and assumed positions of Shugo (military governor) in the capital along with his relatives such as Shigeie TAKADA and Shigetaka AJIKI.</e>
<cmt>用語補足を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada went to Kyoto afterward following MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and assumed positions of Shugo (military governor) in the capital along with his relatives such as Shigeie TAKADA and Shigetaka AJIKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>義仲の滅亡後、源頼朝が鎌倉幕府を創設すると重忠は尾張国山田庄（名古屋市北西部、瀬戸市、長久手町の一帯）の地頭に任じられ御家人に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Yoshinaka, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo founded the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Shigetada was appointed as the jito (manager and lord of manor) of Yamada-sho Manor, Owari Province (northwestern area of Nagoya City, Seto City and Nagakute-cho region) and became a member of gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Yoshinaka, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo founded the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Shigetada was appointed as the jito (manager and lord of manor) of Yamada no sho Manor, Owari Province (northwestern area of Nagoya City, Seto City and Nagakute Town region) and became a member of gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Yoshinaka, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo founded the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Shigetada was appointed as the jito (manager and lord of manor) of Yamada no sho Manor, Owari Province (northwestern area of Nagoya City, Seto City and Nagakute Town region) and became a member of gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、朝廷との繋がりも深く京で後鳥羽上皇に近侍し、健保元年（1213年）には上皇の法勝寺供養に供奉するなどしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he had a close connection with the Imperial Court and served the retired Emperor Gotoba in Kyoto, and in 1213, he attended the Hossho-ji kuyo (memorial service for Hossho-ji Temple) for the retired Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he had a close connection with the Imperial Court and served the Retired Emperor Gotoba in Kyoto, and in 1213, he attended the Hossho-ji kuyo (memorial service for Hossho-ji Temple) for the Retired Emperor.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he had a close connection with the Imperial Court and served the Retired Emperor Gotoba in Kyoto, and in 1213, he attended the Hossho-ji kuyo (memorial service for Hossho-ji Temple) for the Retired Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>承久3年（1221年）5月、後鳥羽上皇が討幕の挙兵をすると重忠は水野左近（水野氏の祖）ら一族とともにこれに参じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1221, when the retired Emperor Gotoba raised an army to attack the shogunate, Shigetada joined it along with his relatives including Sakon MIZUNO (the founder of the Mizuno clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1221, when the Retired Emperor Gotoba raised an army to attack the shogunate, Shigetada joined it along with his relatives including Sakon MIZUNO (the founder of the Mizuno clan).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1221, when the Retired Emperor Gotoba raised an army to attack the shogunate, Shigetada joined it along with his relatives including Sakon MIZUNO (the founder of the Mizuno clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年6月、京方は幕府軍を美濃と尾張の国境の尾張川で迎え撃つことになり、重忠は墨俣町に陣を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June same year, kyogata (the Kyoto side or supporters of the Imperial court in Kyoto) waited for the army of bakufu at Owari-gawa River, which was the border or Mino and Owari, and Shigetada had his army ready in Sunomata-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June same year, kyogata (the Kyoto side or supporters of the Imperial Court in Kyoto) waited for the army of bakufu at the Owari-gawa River, which was the border or Mino and Owari, and Shigetada had his army ready in Sunomata Town.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June same year, kyogata (the Kyoto side or supporters of the Imperial Court in Kyoto) waited for the army of bakufu at the Owari-gawa River, which was the border or Mino and Owari, and Shigetada had his army ready in Sunomata Town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>京方の大将の河内判官藤原秀澄（京方の首謀者・藤原秀康の弟）は少ない兵力を分散する愚策をとっており、重忠は兵力を集中して機制を制して尾張国府を襲い、幕府軍を打ち破って鎌倉まで押し寄せる積極策を進言するが、臆病な秀澄はこれを取り上げなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daisho (Major Captain) of kyogata, Kawachi hangan (judge, magistrate) FUJIWARA no Hidezumi (younger brother of FUJIWARA no Hideyasu, the ringleader of kyogata had a stupid stunt of dispersing their army with a small number of soldiers, and Shigetada advised an aggressive strategy to gather the force, control the situation, attack the provincial capital of Owari province, defeat the army of bakufu and go to Kamakura, but coward Hidezumi did not adopt that strategy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daisho (Major Captain) of kyogata, Kawachi no jo (judge, magistrate) FUJIWARA no Hidezumi (younger brother of FUJIWARA no Hideyasu, the ringleader of kyogata) had a stupid stunt of dispersing their army with a small number of soldiers, and Shigetada advised an aggressive strategy to gather the force, control the situation, attack the provincial capital of Owari Province, defeat the army of bakufu and go to Kamakura, but coward Hidezumi did not adopt that strategy.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daisho (Major Captain) of kyogata, Kawachi no jo (judge, magistrate) FUJIWARA no Hidezumi (younger brother of FUJIWARA no Hideyasu, the ringleader of kyogata) had a stupid stunt of dispersing their army with a small number of soldiers, and Shigetada advised an aggressive strategy to gather the force, control the situation, attack the provincial capital of Owari Province, defeat the army of bakufu and go to Kamakura, but coward Hidezumi did not adopt that strategy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>京方の美濃の防御線は幕府軍によってたちまち打ち破られ、早々に退却を始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyogata&apos;s control line in Mino was defeated by the army of bakufu quickly and soon they began to withdraw.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyogata&apos;s defense line in Mino was defeated by the army of bakufu quickly and soon they began to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyogata&apos;s defense line in Mino was defeated by the army of bakufu quickly and soon they began to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>重忠はこのまま退却しては武士の名折れと、300余騎で杭瀬川に陣をしき待ちかまえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada, on the other hand, thought that it would be a shame as a samurai to withdraw, and had his army of 300 horsemen ready at the Kuise-gawa River and waited for his enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada, on the other hand, thought that it would be a shame as a samurai to withdraw, and had his army of 300 horsemen ready at the Kuise-gawa River and waited for his enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada, on the other hand, thought that it would be a shame as a samurai to withdraw, and had his army of 300 horsemen ready at the Kuise-gawa River and waited for his enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>武蔵国児玉党3000余騎が押し寄せ重忠はさんざんに戦い、児玉党100余騎を討ち取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three thousand horsemen of the Kodama Party of the Musashi Province attacked and Shigetada fought back hard, and beat 100 horsemen of the Kodama Party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3000 horsemen of the Kodama Party of the Musashi Province attacked and Shigetada fought back hard, and beat 100 horsemen of the Kodama Party.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3000 horsemen of the Kodama Party of the Musashi Province attacked and Shigetada fought back hard, and beat 100 horsemen of the Kodama Party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>重忠の奮戦があったものの京方は総崩れになり、重忠も京へ退却した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Shigetada fought well in the battle, kyogata lost control and he went back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shigetada fought well in the battle, kyogata lost control and he went back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shigetada fought well in the battle, kyogata lost control and he went back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>京方は淀川を頼りに京都の防衛を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyogata tried to protect Kyoto by utilizing Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyogata tried to protect Kyoto by utilizing the Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyogata tried to protect Kyoto by utilizing the Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>重忠は比叡山の僧兵と勢多に陣を置き、橋げたを落として楯を並べて幕府軍を迎え撃った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada had the armed priests of Mt.Hiei-zan ready in Seta, dropped the bridge beam, lined up shields and waited for the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada had the armed priests of Mt. Hiei ready in Seta, dropped the bridge beam, lined up shields and waited for the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada had the armed priests of Mt. Hiei ready in Seta, dropped the bridge beam, lined up shields and waited for the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>重忠と山法師は奮戦して熊谷直国（熊谷直実の孫）を討ち取るが、幕府軍の大軍には敵わず京方の防御陣は突破された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada and Yamahoshi (armed priests) fought well and killed Naokuni KUMAGAI (grandson of Naozane KUMAGAI); however, couldn&apos;t beat the huge army of bakufu and the defense of the kyogata was defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada and Yamahoshi (armed priests) fought well and killed Naokuni KUMAGAI (grandson of Naozane KUMAGAI); however, couldn&apos;t beat the huge army of bakufu and the defense of the kyogata was defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada and Yamahoshi (armed priests) fought well and killed Naokuni KUMAGAI (grandson of Naozane KUMAGAI); however, couldn&apos;t beat the huge army of bakufu and the defense of the kyogata was defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>幕府軍が都へ乱入する中で、重忠は藤原秀康、三浦胤義らと最後の一戦をすべく御所へ駆けつけるが、御所の門は固く閉じられ、上皇は彼らを文字どおり門前払いした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the army of bakufu invaded in Kyoto, Shigetada hurried to the Imperial Palace along with FUJIWARA no Hideyasu and Taneyoshi MIURA for the last battle, but the gate of the Imperial Palace was firmly closed and the retired Emperor Gotoba literally turned them away at the door.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the army of bakufu invaded in Kyoto, Shigetada hurried to the Imperial Palace along with FUJIWARA no Hideyasu and Taneyoshi MIURA and others for the last battle, but the gate of the Imperial Palace was firmly closed and the Retired Emperor Gotoba literally turned them away at the door.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the army of bakufu invaded in Kyoto, Shigetada hurried to the Imperial Palace along with FUJIWARA no Hideyasu and Taneyoshi MIURA and others for the last battle, but the gate of the Imperial Palace was firmly closed and the Retired Emperor Gotoba literally turned them away at the door.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>重忠は「大臆病の君に騙られて、無駄死にするわ」と門を叩いて悲憤した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada cried with anger and sadness and beat the door saying &apos;I was deceived by a coward Emperor and would die for nothing.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada cried with anger and sadness and beat the door saying &apos;I was deceived by a coward Emperor and would die for nothing.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada cried with anger and sadness and beat the door saying &apos;I was deceived by a coward Emperor and would die for nothing.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>重忠は藤原秀康、三浦胤義ら京方武士の残党と東寺に立て篭もり、これに幕府軍の大軍が押し寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada, along with other remaining samurai of kyogata, including FUJIWARA no Hideyasu and Taneyoshi MIURA, barricaded himself in the Toji Temple, where the army of bakufu attacked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada, along with other remaining samurai of kyogata, including FUJIWARA no Hideyasu and Taneyoshi MIURA, barricaded himself in the To-ji Temple, where the army of bakufu attacked.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada, along with other remaining samurai of kyogata, including FUJIWARA no Hideyasu and Taneyoshi MIURA, barricaded himself in the To-ji Temple, where the army of bakufu attacked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>重忠は敵15騎を討ち取る奮戦をしたが手勢のほとんどが討ち取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigetada killed 15 horsemen of the enemy but most of the samurai on his side were killed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigetada killed 15 horsemen of the enemy but most of the samurai on his side were killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigetada killed 15 horsemen of the enemy but most of the samurai on his side were killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>嵯峨般若寺山（京都市右京区）に落ちのび、ここで自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He escaped to Sagahannyaji-yama Mountain (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) and killed himself there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He escaped to Mt. Sagahannyaji (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) and killed himself there.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He escaped to Mt. Sagahannyaji (Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City) and killed himself there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>子の重継も幕府軍に捕らえられ殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son Shigetsugu was captured and killed by the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son Shigetsugu was captured and killed by the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son Shigetsugu was captured and killed by the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>『沙石集』は重忠を「弓箭の道に優れ、心猛く、器量の勝った者である。心優しく、民の煩いを知り、優れた人物であった」と称賛している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shasekishu&quot; (collection of Buddhist stories) praises Shigetada as &apos;a man who was good at Kyusen (Bow and arrow), brave, and good-looking; he was also sweet and understood the problems of the people, and was a very good man.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shasekishu&quot; (collection of Buddhist stories) praises Shigetada as &apos;a man who was good at Kyusen (Bow and arrow), brave, and good-looking; he was also sweet and understood the problems of the people, and was a very good man.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shasekishu&quot; (collection of Buddhist stories) praises Shigetada as &apos;a man who was good at Kyusen (Bow and arrow), brave, and good-looking; he was also sweet and understood the problems of the people, and was a very good man.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), 味っ子(id:17086), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), 樒(id:35770), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>