<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上杉景勝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagekatsu UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>上杉 景勝（うえすぎ かげかつ）/長尾 顕景（ながお あきかげ）または長尾 景勝（ながお かげかつ）は、戦国時代 (日本)から江戸時代前期にかけての大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI/Akikage NAGAO or Kagekatsu NAGAO was a feudal lord who lived from the Warring States period (of Japanese history) until the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagekatsu UESUGI/Akikage NAGAO or Kagekatsu NAGAO was a feudal lord who lived from the Warring States period (of Japanese history) until the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI/Akikage NAGAO or Kagekatsu NAGAO was a feudal lord who lived from the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) until the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代を統一ルール</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>豊臣政権の五大老の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the five chief ministers of the Toyotomi administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the five chief ministers of the Toyotomi administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the five chief ministers of the Toyotomi administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>出羽国米沢藩初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as the first lord of the Yonezawa domain in Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as the first lord of the Yonezawa domain in Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as the first lord of the Yonezawa domain in Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一ルール</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出生から家督争いまで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Birth until the Feud of Succession to the Headship of the Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>「家督争い」：何家の家督をめぐる争いなのかを明記した方が、明確な訳文になり、英語として自然なので、文脈より、「上杉家の家督をめぐる争い」を意味するものと想定して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Birth until the Feud of Succession of the Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Birth until the Feud of Succession of the Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>弘治元年（1555年）、越後国（現・新潟県）に上田長尾氏当主・長尾政景の次男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI was born in 1555 in Echigo Province (Niigata Prefecture as it is known today) as the second son of Masakage NAGAO, who was the head of the UEDA NAGAO clan at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagekatsu UESUGI was born in 1555 in Echigo Province (Niigata Prefecture as it is known today) as the second son of Masakage NAGAO, who was the head of the UEDA NAGAO clan at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI was born in 1555 in Echigo Province (Niigata Prefecture as it is known today) as the second son of Masakage NAGAO, who was the head of the UEDA NAGAO clan at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>生母は上杉謙信の実姉・仙桃院で、景虎の甥に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real mother was Sentoin, who was a real sister of Kenshin UESUGI and a nephew of Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>「景虎の甥に当たる」：この記述の主語が明記されていないので、あるいはこの記述に誤りがあるため、原文の語句に従って訳出（主語を「生母」として訳出）すると、左記のように意味不明の訳文になります。もし、正しい記述が「景虎は甥に当たる」であれば、訳文は次のようになります。His real mother was Sentoin, who was a real sister of Kenshin UESUGI; accordingly, Kagetora was her nephew.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real mother was Sentoin, who was a real sister of Kenshin UESUGI and a nephew of Kagetora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real mother was Sentoin, who was a real sister of Kenshin UESUGI, therefore Kagekatsu was a nephew of Kenshin (Kagetora).</e>
<cmt>上杉謙信は、虎千代（幼名）→長尾景虎→上杉政虎→輝虎→不識庵謙信と変わったようです。原文の書き方が奇妙ですが、「（長尾）景虎」は「上杉謙信」の初名、つまり同一人物です。とりあえず原文どおりにしています。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>早世した兄に代わり、世子となるが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the heir in place of his elder brother, who died young.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the heir in place of his elder brother, who died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the heir in place of his elder brother, who died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>永禄7年（1564年）、父の政景が死去し、春日山城に入って叔父の上杉輝虎（謙信）の養子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of his father (Masakage) in 1564, however, Kagekatsu moved to Kasugayama Castle to be adopted by his uncle (Terutora (Kenshin) UESUGI).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of his father (Masakage) in 1564, however, Kagekatsu moved to Kasugayama Castle to be adopted by his uncle (Terutora (Kenshin) UESUGI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of his father (Masakage) in 1564, however, Kagekatsu moved to Kasugayama Castle to be adopted by his uncle (Terutora (Kenshin) UESUGI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>永禄9年（1566年）の関東出兵が初陣であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His first campaign is supposed to be the dispatch of an expeditionary force to Kanto in 1566.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first campaign was intended to be the dispatch of an expeditionary force to Kanto in 1566.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposed that his first campaign was the dispatch of an expeditionary force to Kanto in 1566.</e>
<cmt>現実には出兵したかどうか明確でないので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>景勝は、越中の将椎名康胤の取成や謙信旗本の吉江資堅の軍役を定めるなど、謙信政権下で重要な役割を担っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Kagekatsu played a key role under Kenshin&apos;s administration: for example, he acted as mediator between Yasutane SHIINA, an official of the Ecchu domain, and Kenshin, as well as assigned a military duty to Suketaka YOSHIE, a direct retainer of Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>「越中の将」：辞書の定訳を使って文字どおりに訳出すると「the leader of Ecchu」となりますが、これは原文が真に意味するものと異なるのではないかと思います（上記の訳は越中藩主を意味するものと解釈されかねません）。インターネット検索により、椎名康胤は越中藩の守護代であったことが判明し、この事実に基づき、「an official of the Ecchu domain」と訳出しました。「取成」：原文には、誰と誰の間を取り成すのかが明記されていませんが、訳文中では、これを明記した方が英語として自然であると判断し、「椎名康胤と謙信の間を取り成すこと」として訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Kagekatsu played a key role under Kenshin&apos;s administration; he acted as a mediator between Yasutane SHIINA, an official of the Ecchu domain, and Kenshin. He also assigned military duties to Suketaka YOSHIE, a direct retainer of Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Kagekatsu played a key role under Kenshin&apos;s administration; he acted as a mediator between Yasutane SHIINA, an official of the Ecchu domain, and Kenshin; he also assigned military duties to Suketaka YOSHIE, a direct retainer of Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>「, He」→「; he」</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>天正3年（1575年）、名を長尾顕景から上杉景勝（一説では長尾景勝）に改めると共に、謙信から弾正少弼の位を譲られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1575, he changed his name from Akikage NAGAO to Kagekatsu UESUGI (or Kagekatsu NAGAO, according to another view) and inherited the rank of Danjo-no-shosuke (a vice minister of the Ministry of Justice) from Kenshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1575, he changed his name from Akikage NAGAO to Kagekatsu UESUGI (or Kagekatsu NAGAO, according to another view) and inherited the rank of Danjo-no-shosuke (a vice minister of the Ministry of Justice) from Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1575, he changed his name from Akikage NAGAO to Kagekatsu UESUGI (or Kagekatsu NAGAO, according to another view) and inherited the rank of Danjo-Shohitsu (junior assistant President of the Board of Censors) from Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>「弾正少弼」→「danjo-shohitsu (junior assistant President of the Board of Censors)」</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>天正6年（1578年）、謙信が死去すると、北条家からの人質として送られてきた謙信の養子で義兄（または義弟）上杉景虎との相続争いが勃発する（御館の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Kenshin in 1578, there broke out a dispute with Kagetora UESUGI, who was Kenshin&apos;s adopted son sent from the Hojo clan as a hostage and was Kagekatsu&apos;s elder (or younger) brother, over the succession (the Otate Disturbance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Kenshin in 1578, a dispute over the line of succession broke out--Kagetora UESUGI, who was Kenshin&apos;s adopted son sent from the Hojo clan as a hostage and was Kagekatsu&apos;s elder (or younger) brother (the Otate Disturbance).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Kenshin in 1578, a dispute over the line of succession broke out--Kagetora UESUGI, who was Kenshin&apos;s adopted son sent from the Hojo clan as a hostage and was Kagekatsu&apos;s elder (or younger) brother (the Otate Disturbance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これは謙信が後継体制を整えないうちに急死してしまったことや、越後の長尾諸家を中心とした、何代にも渡る権力争いなどの複雑な事情が背後に絡んでいるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that complicated circumstances, such as Kenshin&apos;s sudden death before the completion of arrangements for the succession as well as struggles for power which continued for generations mainly among the Nagao families in Echigo, were involved in this dispute behind the scenes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There appears to have been a series of complicated circumstances underlying this dispute; such as Kenshin&apos;s sudden death before the completion of arrangements for the succession, as well as struggles for power which continued for generations mainly among the Nagao families in Echigo.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There appears to have been a series of complicated circumstances underlying this dispute; such as Kenshin&apos;s sudden death before the completion of arrangements for the succession, as well as struggles for power which continued for generations mainly among the Nagao families in Echigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>御館の乱において、景勝は謙信の死の直後に謙信の遺言と詐称して春日山城本丸と金蔵を占拠し、春日山城城下の御館（上杉憲政の屋敷）に立て籠もった景虎と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Otate Disturbance, Kagekatsu occupied the donjon and treasure-house of Kasugayama Castle immediately after Kenshin&apos;s death on the false pretext that he was bequeathed them by Kenshin and fought against Kagetora who holed up in Otate (the residence of Norimasa UESUGI) located outside the walls of Kasugayama Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Otate Disturbance, Kagekatsu occupied the donjon and treasure-house of Kasugayama Castle immediately after Kenshin&apos;s death on the false premise that it was bequeathed to him Kenshin. He fought against Kagetora, who holed up in Otate (the residence of Norimasa UESUGI) located outside the walls of Kasugayama Castle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Otate Disturbance, Kagekatsu occupied the donjon and treasure-house of Kasugayama Castle immediately after Kenshin&apos;s death on the false premise that it was bequeathed to him by Kenshin, and then he fought against Kagetora, who holed up in Otate (the residence of Norimasa UESUGI) located outside the walls of Kasugayama Castle.</e>
<cmt>byを追加。「. He」→「, and then he」</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>乱中において、景虎正室である実姉（妹）華渓院は景勝の降伏命令を拒んで自害、和議を申し出ようとした養祖父の憲政が景虎の嫡男上杉道満丸（信濃国豪族市川氏に庇護され、生存していた説あり）とともに景勝の兵によって討たれるなど、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Otate Disturbance, Kekeiin, who was Kagetora&apos;s lawful wife and Kagekatsu&apos;s real elder (or younger) sister, refused Kagekatsu&apos;s order for surrender and killed herself, and Norimasa, Kagetora&apos;s adoptive grandfather, attempting to make overtures for peace was killed by a Kagekatsu&apos;s soldier along with Domanmaru UESUGI, Kagetora&apos;s eldest son, (he is supposed by those who have a different view to have been sheltered by the Ichikawa clan, a powerful clan in Shinano Province and have survived thereafter).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「実姉（妹）華渓院」：「景勝の実姉（妹）華渓院」として訳出しました。「養祖父の憲政」：「景虎の養祖父の憲政」として訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Otate Disturbance, Kekeiin, who was Kagetora&apos;s wife and Kagekatsu&apos;s elder (or younger) sister, refused Kagekatsu&apos;s order for surrender and killed herself. Norimasa, Kagetora&apos;s adoptive grandfather, attempting to make overtures for peace was killed by a Kagekatsu soldier along with Domanmaru UESUGI, Kagetora&apos;s eldest son (alternative accounts have them surviving after receiving shelter from the Ichikawa clan, a powerful clan in Shinano Province).</e>
<cmt>wording; note to translator--please avoid run-on sentences.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Otate Disturbance, Kekeiin, who was Kagetora&apos;s wife and Kagekatsu&apos;s elder (or younger) sister, refused Kagekatsu&apos;s order for surrender and killed herself. Norimasa, Kagetora&apos;s adoptive grandfather, attempting to make overtures for peace was killed by a Kagekatsu soldier along with Domanmaru UESUGI, Kagetora&apos;s eldest son (alternative accounts have them surviving after receiving shelter from the Ichikawa clan, a powerful clan in Shinano Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>徐々に立場を悪くした景虎は天正7年（1579年）3月に自害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to circumstances such as the above, Kagetora&apos;s position gradually got undermined, and Kagetora killed himself in March 1579.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to circumstances such as the above, Kagetora&apos;s position was gradually undermined, and Kagetora killed himself in March 1579.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to circumstances such as the above, Kagetora&apos;s position was gradually undermined, and Kagetora killed himself in March 1579.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、乱においては当初、戦局は不利であったため、甲相同盟に基づき調停のため越後へ出兵した甲斐国の武田勝頼に接触し、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Kagekatsu made contact with Katsuyori TAKEDA in Kai Province, who dispatched an expedition force to Echigo for the purpose of mediation in accordance with the Koso Alliance (an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Hojo clan in Sagami Province) at the early stage of the Disturbance where the tide of the Disturbance was against Kagekatsu&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（3センテンスに分割）この原文は景勝に言及するものと判断し、訳文を作成しました。「同年12月」：文字どおりに&quot;in December of the same year&quot;と訳出しましたが、訳文が長いため、何年のことなのかが分かり難いと感じました。&quot;in December 1579&quot;とした方が、読者にとって分かりやすいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Kagekatsu made contact with Katsuyori TAKEDA in Kai Province, who dispatched an expedition force to Echigo for the purpose of mediation in accordance with the Koso Alliance (an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Hojo clan in Sagami Province) at the early stage of the Disturbance where the tide of the Disturbance was against Kagekatsu&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Kagekatsu made contact with Katsuyori TAKEDA in Kai Province, who dispatched an expedition force to Echigo for the purpose of mediation in accordance with the Koso Alliance (an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Hojo clan in Sagami Province) at the early stage of the Disturbance where the tide of the Disturbance was against Kagekatsu&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>同年12月に勝頼の異母妹菊姫 (大儀院)を正室に迎えて甲越同盟を結び、武田家との関係を強化した</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Kagekatsu took Kikuhime (Daigiin), Katsuyori&apos;s half sister by a different mother, as his lawful wife in December of the same year and concluded the Koetsu Alliance (an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Uesugi clan in Echigo Province), so that the relationship with the Takeda clan would be reinforced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（3センテンスに分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Kagekatsu took Kikuhime (Daigiin), Katsuyori&apos;s half sister by a different mother, as his lawful wife in December and concluded the Koetsu Alliance (an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Uesugi clan in Echigo Province), so that the relationship with the Takeda clan would be strengthened.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Kagekatsu took Kikuhime (Daigiin), Katsuyori&apos;s half sister by a different mother, as his lawful wife in December and concluded the Koetsu Alliance (an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Uesugi clan in Echigo Province), so that the relationship with the Takeda clan would be strengthened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>（上杉家当主が武田家から正室を迎えたのは上杉禅秀以来）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Kagekatsu was the second incumbent head of the Uesugi family, after Zenshu UESUGI, to take a woman born to the Takeda family as lawful wife).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（3センテンスに分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kagekatsu was the second incumbent head of the Uesugi family, after Zenshu UESUGI, to take a woman born to the Takeda family as a lawful wife).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kagekatsu was the second incumbent head of the Uesugi family, after Zenshu UESUGI, to take a woman born to the Takeda family as a lawful wife).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これにより、武田氏の支援を得て戦局を覆した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Kagekatsu obtained support from the Takeda clan and caused the tide of the Disturbance to turn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Kagekatsu obtained support from the Takeda clan and turned the tide of the Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Kagekatsu obtained support from the Takeda clan and turned the tide of the Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>翌年天正8年（1580年）には越後の豪族も追従し、景勝は事実上の上杉家当主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following 1580, Kagekatsu caused powerful clans in Echigo to follow him and became the de facto head of the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>「越後の豪族も追従し」：日本語として不適切ではないかと思われます。「越後の豪族も追従させ」とすべきと判断し、そのように訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, 1580, Kagekatsu caused powerful clans in Echigo to follow him and became the de facto head of the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, 1580, Kagekatsu caused powerful clans in Echigo to follow him and became the de facto head of the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>織田家との戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fight against the Oda Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fight against the Oda Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fight against the Oda Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>御館の乱の混乱が続く天正9年（1581年）、乱の恩賞問題により対立状態にあった北越後の新発田重家が織田信長と通じて造反した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1581, amid the disorder caused by the Otate Disturbance, the issue of rewards for the feats in the Disturbance caused Shigeie SHIBATA, who resided in northern Echigo and was confronted with the Uesugi family, to come to be in touch with Nobunaga ODA and rebel agaubst the Uesugi family</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（3センテンスに分割）「乱の恩賞問題」：「乱での手柄に対する恩賞の問題」として訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1581, amid the disorder caused by the Otate Disturbance, those circumstances brought the Uesugi family to the brink of extinction. Shigeie SHIBATA, who resided in northern Echigo and was confronted with the Uesugi family, was raised by being in touch with Nobunaga ODA because of the issue of rewards for the feats in the Disturbance--the invasion into Ecchu Province by the Oda forces led by Katsuie SHIBATA, a hereditary vassal of the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1581, amid the disorder caused by the Otate Disturbance, the issue of rewards for the feats in the Disturbance caused Shigeie SHIBATA, who resided in northern Echigo and was confronted with the Uesugi family, to come to be in touch with Nobunaga ODA and rebel against the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>エディット時の文章が原文対応となっていなかったため、修正しました。agaubst→against</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その上、織田家譜代柴田勝家率いる織田軍に越中国にまで侵攻される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Uesgi family had Ecchu Province invaded and attacked by the Oda forces led by Katsuie SHIBATA, a hereditary vassal of the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（3センテンスに分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Uesgi family had Ecchu Province invaded and attacked by the Oda forces led by Katsuie SHIBATA, a hereditary vassal of the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Uesgi family had Ecchu Province invaded and attacked by the Oda forces led by Katsuie SHIBATA, a hereditary vassal of the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>上杉家は滅亡の危機に立たされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those circumstances and other circumstances brought the Uesugi family to the brink of extinction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（3センテンスに分割）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those circumstances and other circumstances brought the Uesugi family to the brink of extinction.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those circumstances and other circumstances brought the Uesugi family to the brink of extinction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>天正10年（1582年）、侵攻する織田軍は越中を完全に制圧し、上杉家はまさに窮地に立たされるが、6月2日、織田信長が本能寺にて自害したため（本能寺の変）織田軍の北征は頓挫し、上杉家は九死に一生を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, the Oda forces having invaded Ecchu brought the whole area of Ecchu under their control, which resulted in the Uesugi family being in an exactly difficult situation; however, the Uesugi family narrowly escaped death because the expedition of the Oda forces to the provinces located to the north of Ecchu suffered a setback on account of Nobunaga ODA&apos;s suicide at Honnoji Temple (the Honnoji Incident) on June 2.</e>
<cmt>「北征」：「越中よりも北側に位置する諸国の征伐」と解釈して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, the Oda forces having invaded Ecchu brought the whole area of Ecchu under their control. This resulted in the Uesugi family being placed in a difficult situation. However, on June 2 Nobunaga ODA committed suicide at at Honnoji Temple (the Honnoji Incident) causing the Oda expeditionary forces in the provinces located to the north of Ecchu to suffer a setback; this allowed the Uesugi family to narrowly escape death.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, when the Oda forces&apos;s complete seizure of the Ecchu made the Uesugi family in a difficult situation, Nobunaga ODA committed suicide at Honnoji Temple (the Honnoji Incident) on June 2, as a result, the Oda expeditionary forces had to renounce aggression, allowing the Uesugi family to survive narrowly.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻して簡潔にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、織田氏の侵攻に加え、御館の乱後の混乱が長期化し、自力のみによる沈静化ができなくなったことから、謙信が一代で拡大した上杉氏の国力は著しく衰退し、上杉家の力は急激に凋落の一途を辿った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, the prolonged disorder after the Otate Disturbance, along with the invasion by the Oda forces, made it impossible for the Uesugi family to calm down the situation through its own efforts, which resulted in the provincial power of the Uesugi family, which was expanded in the course of Kenshin&apos;s lifetime, being markedly declined and in the power of the Uesugi family following a path of sudden decline.</e>
<cmt>「沈静化」：原文には、何を沈静化するのかが明記されておりませんが、「事態を沈静化すること」と解釈して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, the prolonged disorder after the Otate Disturbance along with the invasion by the Oda forces, made it impossible for the Uesugi family to pacify the situation by themselves. This resulted in Uesugi&apos;s provincial power, which had expanded over the course of Kenshin&apos;s lifetime, to markedly declined and in the power of the whole Uesugi family to suddenly go down the path of decline.</e>
<cmt>wording; mistranslation (上杉氏と上杉家の違い)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, the prolonged disorder after the Otate Disturbance along with the invasion by the Oda forces, made it impossible for the Uesugi family to pacify the situation by themselves, this resulted in Uesugi&apos;s provincial power, which had expanded over the course of Kenshin&apos;s lifetime, and the Uesugi family&apos;s prestige to decline markedly.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>豊臣政権時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of the Toyotomi Administration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period of the Toyotomi Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period of the Toyotomi Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>信長の死後、北信濃国に侵攻し、一部を支配下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Nobunaga, Kagekatsu invaded northern Shinano Province and put a part thereof under his control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Nobunaga, Kagekatsu invaded northern Shinano Province and placed a portion under his control.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Nobunaga, Kagekatsu invaded northern Shinano Province and placed a portion under his control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、天正13年（1585年）には真田昌幸を一時的に従属下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he temporarily subordinated Masayuki SANADA to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he temporarily subordinated Masayuki SANADA to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he temporarily subordinated Masayuki SANADA to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>信長の死後に台頭した羽柴秀吉（豊臣秀吉）に天正14年（1586年）6月、秀吉に養子であった甥の畠山義真（当時は上杉義真）を人質として差し出し、臣従して命脈を保った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To survive after the rise of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) following Nobunaga&apos;s death, Kagekatsu had Yoshizane HATAKEYAMA (assuming the name of Yoshizane UESUGI at that time), Kagetora&apos;s adopted son and nephew, taken by Hideyoshi as a hostage in June 1586, and rendered homage and service to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To survive after the rise of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) following Nobunaga&apos;s death, Kagekatsu had Yoshizane HATAKEYAMA (he had assumed the name of Yoshizane UESUGI at that time), Kagetora&apos;s adopted son and nephew, taken by Hideyoshi as a hostage in June 1586, and rendered homage and service to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To survive after the rise of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) following Nobunaga&apos;s death, Kagekatsu had Yoshizane HATAKEYAMA (he had assumed the name of Yoshizane UESUGI at that time), Kagetora&apos;s adopted son and nephew, taken by Hideyoshi as a hostage in June 1586, and rendered homage and service to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その際に、越中と上野（真田氏の大名としての独立）の領有を放棄、換わりに佐渡・出羽の切り取りを許可される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, he gave up the possession of the fief of Ecchu and Kozuke (his giving up of the possession of the fief of Kozuke resulted in the Sanada clan becoming independent to act as a feudal lord), and was permitted to occupy Sado and Dewa instead thereof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, he surrendered the fief of Ecchu and Kozuke (the surrendering of Kozuke resulted in the Sanada clan becoming independent to act as a feudal lord), and he was permitted to occupy Sado and Dewa instead.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, he surrendered the fief of Ecchu and Kozuke (the surrendering of Kozuke resulted in the Sanada clan becoming independent to act as a feudal lord), and he was permitted to occupy Sado and Dewa instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>このとき、景勝は正親町天皇に拝謁して右近衛少将に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concurrently, Kagekatsu had an audience with the Emperor Ogimachi and was appointed to the post of Ukonne no Shosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concurrently, Kagekatsu had an audience with the Emperor Ogimachi and was appointed to the post of Ukonne no Shosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concurrently, Kagekatsu had an audience with the Emperor Ogimachi and was appointed to the post of Ukone no Shosho (Minor Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>天正11年（1583年）の賤ヶ岳の戦いでは秀吉に味方し、越中侵攻を命ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Shizugatake, which occurred in 1583, Kagekatsu took the side of Hideyoshi and was ordered to invade Ecchu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Shizugatake, which occurred in 1583, Kagekatsu took the side of Hideyoshi and was ordered to invade Ecchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Shizugatake, which occurred in 1583, Kagekatsu took the side of Hideyoshi and was ordered to invade Ecchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、本国から動けず合戦には参加できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he could not participate in the Battle because he could not leave his province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he could not participate in the battle because he could not leave his province.</e>
<cmt>capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he could not participate in the battle because he could not leave his province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>天正12年（1584年）、小牧・長久手の戦いと天正13年（1585年）、富山の役では佐々成政を牽制した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute and the Battle of Toyama (Siege of Toyama Castle), which occurred in 1584 and 1585, respectively, he contained Narimasa SASSA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute and the Battle of Toyama (Siege of Toyama Castle), which occurred in 1584 and 1585, he contained Narimasa SASSA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute and the Battle of Toyama (Siege of Toyama Castle), which occurred in 1584 and 1585, he contained Narimasa SASSA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>天正16年（1588年）にも上洛し、従三位・参議・中将に昇叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1588, he went up to Kyoto again and was promoted to Sangi (state councilor) and Chujo (lieutenant general) at Jusanmi (the Junior Third Court Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1588, he once again travelled to Kyoto and was promoted to Sangi (state councilor) and Chujo (lieutenant general) at Jusanmi (the Junior Third Court Rank).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1588, he once again travelled to Kyoto and was promoted to Sangi (state councilor), Chujo (Middle Captain) and Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)、Chujo (Middle Captain)に用語統一。at→and</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この時、羽柴姓を許され、越後中納言と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, he was permitted to assume the surname of Hashiba and came to be called Echigo Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>「越後中納言」：呼称であるので、ローマ字に音訳するにとどめました。「中納言」についての訳注が必要であれば、&quot;Echigo Chunagon&quot;の直後に&quot;(Chunagon refers to a councilor ranking after dainagon (chief councilor of state) and before shonagon)&quot;という文言を追記してください。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, he was permitted to assume the surname of Hashiba and came to be called Echigo Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, he was permitted to assume the surname of Hashiba and came to be called Echigo Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>天正15年（1587年）、秀吉の後ろ盾と協力を得た景勝は、長年にわたり抗争状態にあった新発田重家を討ち、天正17年（1589年）には佐渡国の本間氏を討伐し、佐渡を平定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1587, Kagekatsu defeated Shigeie SHIBATA, with whom he had been in conflict for years, with the backing and cooperation of Hideyoshi; thereafter, in 1589, he subjugated the Homma clan and established peace in Sado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1587, Kagekatsu defeated Shigeie SHIBATA, with whom he had been in conflict for years, with the backing and cooperation of Hideyoshi. Thereafter in 1589, he subjugated the Homma clan and established peace in Sado.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1587, Kagekatsu defeated Shigeie SHIBATA, with whom he had been in conflict for years, with the backing and cooperation of Hideyoshi, thereafter in 1589, he subjugated the Homma clan and established peace in Sado.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>天正18年（1590年）、後北条氏との小田原合戦にも、山浦景国を先鋒として出兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also dispatched an expeditionary force to the Odawara Campaign against the Gohojo clan in 1590 with Kagekuni YAMAURA being in the vanguard thereof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also dispatched an expeditionary force to the Odawara Campaign against the Gohojo clan in 1590 with Kagekuni YAMAURA in the vanguard.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also dispatched an expeditionary force to the Odawara Campaign against the Gohojo clan in 1590 with Kagekuni YAMAURA in the vanguard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="38">
<j>天正20年（1592年）の6月6日から9月8日まで、家臣の高梨頼親らを伴って秀吉の文禄・慶長の役に参加し、渡鮮する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He participated in Bunroku Keicho no Eki (Japan&apos;s invasions of Korea) along with Yorichika TAKANASHI, his retainer, over the period from June 6, 1592 to September 8 of the same year, and went to Korea.</e>
<cmt>「文禄・慶長の役に参加し、渡鮮する」：出来事が時間の流れと逆に記述されているのではないでしょうか。一応、原文どおりに訳出しましたが、不自然です。時間の流れに従って、下記のように訳出した方が良いと思います。He went to Korea and participated in Bunroku Keicho no Eki (Japan&apos;s invasions of Korea) along with Yorichika TAKANASHI, his retainer over the period from June 6, 1592 to September 8 of the same year.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He participated in Bunroku Keicho no Eki (Japan&apos;s invasions of Korea) along with Yorichika TAKANASHI, his retainer, between the period of June 6 to September 8, 1592.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He participated in Bunroku Keicho no Eki (Japan&apos;s invasions of Korea) along with Yorichika TAKANASHI, his retainer, between the period of June 6 to September 8, 1592.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>このとき朝鮮における日本軍最前線基地として熊川に城（倭城）を築城している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, he built a castle (Wajo, namely, Japanese-style castle) in Ungchon so that it would be used as a base at the forefront of the Japanese armed forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, he built a castle (Wajo, or a Japanese-style castle) in Ungchon so that it would be used as a base at the front of the Japanese armed forces.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, he built a castle (Wajo, or a Japanese-style castle) in Ungchon so that it would be used as a base at the front of the Japanese armed forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="40">
<j>慶長2年（1597年）、小早川隆景が死去した後を受けて、豊臣氏五大老の一人に列せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1597, he was raised to one of the five chief ministers of the administration of the Toyotomi clan to replace Takakage KOBAYAKAWA who had died.</e>
<cmt>「小早川隆景が死去した後を受けて」：「死去下小早川隆景の後任として」と読み替えて訳出しました。「豊臣氏五大老」：「豊臣氏の政権の五大老」と解釈し、左記のように訳出しましたが、&quot;the five chief ministers of the Toyotomi administration&quot;とした方がすっきりすると思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1597, he was raised to one of the five chief ministers of the administration of the Toyotomi clan to replace Takakage KOBAYAKAWA who had died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1597, he was raised to one of the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) of the administration of the Toyotomi clan to replace Takakage KOBAYAKAWA who had died.</e>
<cmt>五大老→Gotairo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）、秀吉の命により会津120万石に加増移封された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1598, he was awarded an increase of 1.2 million koku with some of his fief transferred to Aizu under the orders of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>「会津120万石に加増移封された」：「120万石に加増され、会津に移封された」と読み替えて訳出しました。尚、この場合の移封ですが、後続の原文より、「領地の一部が会津に移された」と解釈できるので、&quot;with some of his fief transferred to Aizu&quot;と訳出しました。&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1598, under the orders of Hideyoshi, he was awarded an increase of 1.2 million koku with some of his fief transferred to Aizu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1598, under the orders of Hideyoshi, he was awarded an increase of 1.2 million koku with some of his fief transferred to Aizu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>旧領地から引き続き統治が認められたのは、佐渡一国及び越後のごく一部（東蒲原）と本庄繁長が最上義光と激しい争奪戦をして奪った出羽国庄内地方のみで、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among his former fief, he was only allowed to continue to govern the whole Sado Province, a small part of Echigo (Higashikanbara) and Shonai Region in Dewa Province of which Shigenaga HONJO had deprived Yoshiaki MOGAMI after a fierce scramble.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his former fief, he was only allowed to continue to govern the whole Sado Province, a small part of Echigo (Higashikanbara) and Shonai Region in Dewa Province, of which Shigenaga HONJO had deprived Yoshiaki MOGAMI after a fierce scramble.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among his former fief, he was only allowed to continue to govern the whole Sado Province, a small part of Echigo (Higashikanbara) and Shonai Region in Dewa Province, of which Shigenaga HONJO had deprived Yoshiaki MOGAMI after a fierce scramble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>後は戦国時代_(日本)伊達氏の領地だった出羽置賜地方、陸奥国伊達郡、信夫郡、刈田郡と伊達政宗が征服した会津地方であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides the above, he was allowed to govern Okitama Region in Dewa, and Date-gun, Shinobu-gun and Katta-gun in Mutsu Province, all of which had been the fief of the Date clan in the Warring States period (of Japans history), as well as Aizu Region which had been conquered by Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「戦国時代_(日本)伊達氏の領地だった」：「戦国時代_(日本)に伊達氏の領地だった」のか「戦国時代_(日本)以降伊達氏の領地だった」のかを判断できませんでした。文字どおりに前者を意味するものと仮定して訳出してあります。後者が正しければ、&quot;in&quot;を&quot;since&quot;に変更してください。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides the above, he was allowed to govern Okitama Region in Dewa, and Date-gun, Shinobu-gun and Katta-gun in Mutsu Province. All of these had been the fief of the Date clan in the Warring States period (Japan), as well as the Aizu Region which had been conquered by Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides the above, he was allowed to govern Okitama Region in Dewa, and Date-gun, Shinobu-gun and Katta-gun in Mutsu Province, all of these had been the fief of the Date clan in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), as well as the Aizu Region which had been conquered by Masamune DATE.</e>
<cmt>一文に変更。用語統一、the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また、各地は山地で隔絶され、現在でも交通の難所と呼ばれる峠道で結ばれているだけであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of the above areas was isolated from one another by mountains, and is, even now, only connected with one another by so-called &apos;the most difficult part of traffic&apos;, that is, a road over a mountain pass.</e>
<cmt>「また」：訳出すると訳文の流れが悪くなるので、あえて訳出しておりません。「現在でも～であった」：時制が一致していませんが、現在のことに言及しているので、現在形で訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of the above areas were isolated from one another by mountains. Even now they are only connected to one another by trecherous mountain passes.</e>
<cmt>verb tense, wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of the above areas were isolated from one another by mountains, and is, even now they are only connected to one another by trecherous mountain passes.</e>
<cmt>一文に変更。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>常に北側に境を接する最上義光、伊達政宗と衝突の危険性が有り、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were always dangers of conflicts with Yoshimitsu MOGAMI and Masamune DATE whose fiefs bordered the northern edge of Kagekatsu&apos;s fief.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「常に北側に境を接する最上義光、伊達政宗」：言葉が足りないと思います。これは、「最上義光、伊達正宗の領土が景勝の領土の北側で接すること」を意味するものと解釈し、そのように訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were always dangers of conflicts with Yoshimitsu MOGAMI and Masamune DATE whose fiefs bordered the northern edge of the Kagekatsu&apos;s fief.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were always dangers of conflicts with Yoshimitsu MOGAMI and Masamune DATE whose fiefs bordered the northern edge of the Kagekatsu&apos;s fief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>改易された蒲生氏に代わり東北諸大名の監視と牽制のための配置であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Kagekatsu was stationed there to monitor and check feudal lords in Tohoku in place of the Gamo clan which had forfeited the fief located there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Kagekatsu was stationed there to monitor and check feudal lords in Tohoku in place of the Gamo clan, which had forfeited the fief located there.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Kagekatsu was stationed there to monitor and check feudal lords in Tohoku in place of the Gamo clan, which had forfeited the fief located there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="47">
<j>景勝は要となる米沢城に直江兼続に30万石（与力を含む、直江本領は6万石との説あり）を与えて配置させ、対伊達氏最前線の白石城の甘糟景継、福島城の本庄繁長、梁川城の須田長義、東禅寺城の志田義秀を指揮させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagekatsu caused Kanetsugu NAOE to be stationed at Yonezawa Castle, which played a pivotal role, with 300 thousand koku (including foot soldiers) given to Kanetsugu NAOE(however, some say that the yield of Naoe&apos;s fief was 60 thousand koku), thereby causing Kanetsugu to supervise Kagetsugu AMAKASU stationed at Shiraishi Castle located at the forefront against the Date clan, Shigenaga HONJO stationed at Fukushima Castle, Nagayoshi SUDA stationed at Yanagawa Castle and Yoshihide SHIDA stationed at Tozenji Castle.</e>
<cmt>「配置させ」、「指揮させた」：使役形で表現されているので、&quot;caused Kanetsugu NAOE to ～&quot;と訳出しましたが、下記のように訳出する方が英語として自然ではないかと思います。Kagekatsu stationed Kanetsugu NAOE at Yonezawa Castle playing a pivotal role with 300 thousand koku (including foot soldiers; in this connection, some say that the yield of Naoe&apos;s fief was 60 thousand koku) given to Kanetsugu, so that he would supervise Kagetsugu AMAKASU stationed at Shiraishi Castle located at the forefront against the Date clan, Shigenaga HONJO stationed at Fukushima Castle, Nagayoshi SUDA stationed at Yanagawa Castle and Yoshihide SHIDA stationed at Tozenji Castle.「直江本領」：文字どおりに&quot;Naoe&apos;s fief&quot;と訳出しましたが、不自然に感じられます。&quot;the fief of the Naoe family&quot;または&quot;the fief of the Naoe clan&quot;とした方が自然だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagekatsu stationed Kanetsugu NAOE at Yonezawa Castle to play a pivotal role with 300 thousand koku (including foot soldiers; in this connection, some say that the yield of Naoe&apos;s fief was 60 thousand koku) to Kanetsugu; he was also to supervise Kagetsugu AMAKASU stationed at Shiraishi Castle located at the forefront against the Date clan, Shigenaga HONJO stationed at Fukushima Castle, Nagayoshi SUDA stationed at Yanagawa Castle and Yoshihide SHIDA stationed at Tozenji Castle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagekatsu stationed Kanetsugu NAOE at Yonezawa Castle to play a pivotal role with 300 thousand koku (including foot soldiers; in this connection, some say that the yield of Naoe&apos;s fief was 60 thousand koku) to Kanetsugu; he was also to supervise Kagetsugu AMAKASU stationed at Shiraishi Castle located at the forefront against the Date clan, Shigenaga HONJO stationed at Fukushima Castle, Nagayoshi SUDA stationed at Yanagawa Castle and Yoshihide SHIDA stationed at Tozenji Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>会津征伐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subjugation of Aizu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subjugation of Aizu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subjugation of Aizu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）8月、秀吉が死去すると、家老の直江兼続が五奉行の石田三成と懇意にあった事などの経緯から徳川家康と対立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Hideyoshi in August 1598, due to circumstances such as intimacy of Kanetsugu NAOE, a principal retainer of Kagekatsu, with Mitsunari ISHIDA, one of the Five Magistrates, Kagekatsu became opposed to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Hideyoshi in August 1598, Kagekatsu, one of the Five Magistrates, opposed Ieyasu TOKUGAWA due to various circumstances, such as the intimacy of Mitsunari ISHIDA with Kanetsugu NAOE, a principal retainer of Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Hideyoshi in August 1598, Kagekatsu, one of the Gobugyo (Five Major Magistrates), opposed Ieyasu TOKUGAWA due to various circumstances, such as the intimacy of Mitsunari ISHIDA with Kanetsugu NAOE, a principal retainer of Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）2月になると、景勝は夏までに領内諸城の補修を命ずる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1600, Kagekatsu ordered that the castles in his fief be repaired by the summer of the same year.</e>
<cmt>「夏までに」：「同年の夏までに」と解釈して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1600, Kagekatsu ordered that the castles in his fief be repaired by the summer of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1600, Kagekatsu ordered that the castles in his fief be repaired by the summer of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>3月になると若松城が将来手狭になると考え、会津盆地のほぼ中央に位置する神指に新城の建築を命ずる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, he expected that the capacity of Wakamatsu Castle would become insufficient later and ordered that a new castle be constructed at Kozashi positioned roughly in the center of Aizu Basin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, he anticipated that Wakamatsu Castle would become cramped in the future and ordered that a new castle be constructed at Kozashi, positioned roughly in the center of Aizu Basin.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he anticipated that Wakamatsu Castle would become cramped in the future and ordered that a new castle be constructed at Kozashi, positioned roughly in the center of Aizu Basin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>4月、家康から上洛して領内諸城改修の申し開きをするように召還命令が出るがこれを拒否する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, Ieyasu issued a recall order so that Kagekatsu would go up to Kyoto to give an explanation for the repair of the castles in his fief, but Kagekatsu refused this order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, Ieyasu issued a recall order so that Kagekatsu would go up to Kyoto to give an explanation for the repair of the castles in his fief, but Kagekatsu refused this order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, Ieyasu issued a recall order so that Kagekatsu would go up to Kyoto to give an explanation for the repair of the castles in his fief, but Kagekatsu refused this order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この召還命令は景勝を排除するための策だと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This recall order is assumed to have been a means to remove Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This recall order is assumed to have been a means to remove Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This recall order is assumed to have been a means to remove Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>この際、直江兼続による挑発的な返答が、家康の会津征伐を煽ったとされる（直江状）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Kanetsugu NAOE wrote a sensational reply (the Naoe Letter), which incited Ieyasu to subjugate Aizu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Kanetsugu NAOE wrote a sensational reply (the Naoe Letter), which incited Ieyasu to subjugate Aizu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Kanetsugu NAOE wrote a sensational reply (the Naoe Letter), which incited Ieyasu to subjugate Aizu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>ともあれ、家康は大軍を率いて景勝討伐に出陣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyway, Ieyasu went to the front leading vast forces to subjugate Kagekatsu..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu went to the front leading vast forces to subjugate Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu went to the front leading vast forces to subjugate Kagekatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>景勝は神指城の突貫工事を命ずるが、6月になると普請を中断して家康軍の対応にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagekatsu ordered that Kozashi Castle be constructed at full speed, but suspended the construction in June to respond to Ieyasu&apos;s forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagekatsu ordered that Kozashi Castle be constructed as quickly as possible, but suspended the construction in June to respond to Ieyasu&apos;s forces.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagekatsu ordered that Kozashi Castle be constructed as quickly as possible, but suspended the construction in June to respond to Ieyasu&apos;s forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>7月、討伐に向かった家康の留守中に三成らが挙兵（関ヶ原の戦い）し、家康が西上するとなると会津から出兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, Mitsunari, etc. took up arms during the absence of Ieyasu, who had gone on an expedition, (the Battle of Sekigahara); thereafter, when Ieyasu decided to go westward, Kagekatsu dispatched expeditionary forces from Aizu.</e>
<cmt>「家康が西上するとなると会津から出兵」：この記述には、誰が出兵したのかが明記されておりませんが、暫定的に景勝が出兵したものと想定して訳文を作成しました。これでよいかご確認ください。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, Mitsunari, among others, took up arms during the absence of Ieyasu, who had gone on an expedition (the Battle of Sekigahara). Later, when Ieyasu decided to go westward, Kagekatsu dispatched expeditionary forces from Aizu.</e>
<cmt>wording, sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, Mitsunari, among others, took up arms (the Battle of Sekigahara) during the absence of Ieyasu, who had gone on an expedition, and as Ieyasu decided to go westward, Kagekatsu dispatched expeditionary forces from Aizu.</e>
<cmt>1文に戻しました。(the Battle of Sekigahara)の位置を変えました。ご確認ください。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>東軍に与した伊達政宗や最上義光らと戦った（慶長出羽合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagekatsu fought against Masamune DATE and Yoshiaki MOGAMI, who joined up with the East squad (the Battle of Dewa in the Keicho Era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagekatsu fought against Masamune DATE and Yoshiaki MOGAMI, who joined the East squad (the Battle of Dewa in the Keicho Era).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagekatsu fought against Masamune DATE and Yoshiaki MOGAMI, who joined the East squad (the Battle of Dewa in the Keicho Era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし、9月15日の本戦で三成ら西軍が敗れたため、12月に家康に降伏することを余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kagekatsu was forced in December to surrender to Ieyasu because the West squad including Mitsunari was defeated in the final battle on September 15.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kagekatsu was forced in December to surrender to Ieyasu because the West squad including Mitsunari was defeated in the final battle on September 15.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kagekatsu was forced to surrender to Ieyasu in December, because the West squad including Mitsunari was defeated in the final battle on September 15.</e>
<cmt>in Decemberの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="59">
<j>慶長6年（1601年）、直江兼続と共に上洛して家康に謝罪し、また正室菊姫を人質として家康へ差し出したことにより、上杉氏の存続は許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1601, Kagekatsu went up to Kyoto with Kanetsugu NAOE to apologize to Ieyasu as well as had Kikuhime, his lawful wife, taken by Ieyasu as a hostage, which resulted in Ieyasu permitting the survival of the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1601, Kagekatsu travelled to Kyoto with Kanetsugu NAOE to apologize to Ieyasu. He also had Kikuhime, his wife, taken by Ieyasu as a hostage; this allowed for the survival of the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1601, Kagekatsu travelled to Kyoto with Kanetsugu NAOE to apologize to Ieyasu, as well as had Kikuhime, his wife, taken by Ieyasu as a hostage; this allowed for the survival of the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>1文に戻しました。ご確認ください。文法的に問題ないかご確認ください。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>景勝直轄の所領は尽く没収され、唯一安堵された兼続直轄の所領は置賜地方、信夫郡、伊達郡であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kagekatsu forfeited the entire fief under the direct control of himself and was authorized to exclusively possess the fief under the direct control of Kanetsugu, that is, Okitama Region, Shinobu-gun and Date-gun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「安堵」：この場合は、所領の領有に対する承認を意味するものとして訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kagekatsu surrendered all of the fiefs under his direct control and was authorized to exclusively possess the fief under the direct control of Kanetsugu--Okitama Region, Shinobu-gun and Date-gun.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of the fiefs under Kagekatu&apos;s direct control were forfeited and the only three fiefs such as in Okitama Region, Shinobu-gun and Date-gun remained in Kanetsugu&apos;s direct control.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすく修正しましたが、文法的に問題ないかご確認ください。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>この3郡からなる出羽国米沢藩30万石藩主として減移封され、景勝一代において上杉家は信越の強大な大大名から出羽半国の一大名へと没落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, he was transferred to the Yonezawa domain (consisting of the above three areas and yielding 300 thousand koku) in Dewa Province as the lord thereof with his fief decreased, which led to the fall of the Uesugi family from the powerful Daidaimyo (a feudal lord having a greater stipend) in Shinnetsu down to one feudal lord of half of Dewa Province in the course of Kagekatsu&apos;s lifetime.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「3郡」：「置賜地方」が郡に相当するか否かを判断できなかったため、&quot;three areas&quot;と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, he was transferred to the Yonezawa domain (consisting of the above three areas and yielding 300 thousand koku) in Dewa Province as the lord of a smaller fief. This led to the fall of the Uesugi family from the powerful Daidaimyo (a feudal lord having a greater stipend) in Shinnetsu down to one feudal lord of half of Dewa Province over the course of Kagekatsu&apos;s lifetime.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, he was transferred to the Yonezawa domain (consisting of the above three areas and yielding 300 thousand koku) in Dewa Province as the lord of a smaller fief in which led to the fall of the Uesugi family from the powerful Daidaimyo (a feudal lord having a greater power) in Shinetsu down to one feudal lord of half of Dewa Province over the course of Kagekatsu&apos;s lifetime.</e>
<cmt>1文に戻しました。ご確認ください。文法的に問題ないかご確認ください。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>減封後、家臣の直江兼続・清野長範らが米沢藩の藩政確立に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the curtailment of Kagekatsu&apos;s fief, his retainers, including Kanetsugu NAOE and Naganori KIYONO, strove for the establishment of government of the Yonezawa domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the curtailment of Kagekatsu&apos;s fief, his retainers, including Kanetsugu NAOE and Naganori KIYONO, strove to establish a government for the Yonezawa domain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the curtailment of Kagekatsu&apos;s fief, his retainers, including Kanetsugu NAOE and Naganori KIYONO, strove to establish a government for the Yonezawa domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>慶長19年（1614年）からの大坂の役大坂冬の陣では徳川方について先鋒として鴫野の戦いなどで大功を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Winter Siege of Osaka Castle of Osaka no Eki (the Sieges of Osaka Castle), which started in 1614, Kagekatsu took Tokugawa&apos;s side and rendered distinguished services in the Battle of Kamono, etc., acting as leader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the 1614 Winter Siege of Osaka Castle in Osaka no Eki (the Sieges of Osaka Castle), Kagekatsu took Tokugawa&apos;s side and served as a distinguish leader in the Battle of Kamono, among other times.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1614 Winter Siege of Osaka, Kagekatsu took Tokugawa&apos;s side and served successfully as a vanguard in the Battle of Kamono, among other times.</e>
<cmt>単に「winter siege of osaka」（大阪冬の陣）として整理しました。先鋒は意味がずれてしまっているので「vanguard」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>翌慶長20年（1615年）、大坂夏の陣大坂夏の陣では京都警備を担当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Summer Siege of Osaka Castle, which occurred in in the following 1615, he took charge of keeping watch over Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1615 Summer Siege of Osaka Castle, he kept watch over Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1615 Summer Siege of Osaka, he kept watch over Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>「summer siege of osaka」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="65">
<j>元和9年（1623年）3月20日、米沢で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 20, 1623, Kagekatsu died in Yonezawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 20, 1623, Kagekatsu died in Yonezawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 20, 1623, Kagekatsu died in Yonezawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>享年69。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 69 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 69 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 69 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>後を庶子定勝が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was succeeded by Sadakatsu, his illegitimate son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was succeeded by Sadakatsu, his illegitimate son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was succeeded by Sadakatsu, his illegitimate son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="68">
<j>墓所：遺骨は和歌山県高野町の高野山清浄心院、遺灰と衣冠は山形県米沢市の御廟の上杉家御廟所に、それぞれ納められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Grave sites: Kagekatsu&apos;s remains were laid at Shojoshin-in Temple, Mt. Koyasan, located in Koya Town, Wakayama Prefecture while his ashes and court dress and crown were at the mausoleum of the Uesugi family located in Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>「御廟の上杉家御廟所」：左記原文の意味が不明です。「御廟の」は不要ではないでしょうか。訳文では訳出しておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Grave sites: Kagekatsu&apos;s remains were laid at Shojoshin-in Temple, Mt. Koyasan, located in Koya Town, Wakayama Prefecture while his ashes and court dress and crown were kept at the mausoleum of the Uesugi family located in Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Grave sites: Kagekatsu&apos;s remains were laid at Shojoshin-in Temple, Mt. Koyasan, located in Koya Town, Wakayama Prefecture while his ashes and court dress and crown were kept at the mausoleum of the Uesugi family located in Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="69">
<j>人物 ・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality/anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character/Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile/Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>統一ルール</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="70">
<j>養父の謙信を戦国武将として尊敬していたといわれる景勝は、それゆえに自分は謙信に及ばないとの想いが強く、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kagekatsu respected Kenshin, his adoptive father, as a civil war commander and therefore strongly believed that he was inferior to Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kagekatsu respected Kenshin, his adoptive father, as a civil war commander, and had a strong inferiority complex regarding Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kagekatsu respected Kenshin, his adoptive father, as a Sengoku Busho (Military Commnader in the Warring States Period), and had a strong inferiority complex regarding Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>常に謙信のようにありたいと考えて行動していたため、感情を表に出すことがほとんどなかったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that he always acted in the hope of being a match for Kenshin and therefore rarely displayed his emotion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that he always acted in the hope of being a match for Kenshin, and, therefore, rarely displayed his emotion.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that he always acted in the hope of being a match for Kenshin, and, therefore, rarely displayed his emotion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>ある時、飼っていた猿が景勝の座に座って、もっともらしくうなずいたり、部下に指図したりといった自分の物まねをしていたのを目にした景勝は、そのあまりの可笑しさに思わず笑みをこぼしたが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once, Kagekatsu saw his pet monkey sitting at his seat and doing imitations of him (for example, nodding and giving directions to his subordinates with a perfectly straight face), and those imitations were so funny that a smile broke out on his face.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been told that on one occassion Kagekatsu saw his pet monkey sitting at his seat and imitating him (nodding and giving directions to his subordinates with a perfectly straight face), and he found this so amusing that he couldn&apos;t help but smile.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been told that on one occassion Kagekatsu saw his pet monkey sitting at his seat and imitating him (nodding and giving directions to his subordinates with a perfectly straight face), and he found this so amusing that he couldn&apos;t help but smile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>これが彼が生涯でただ一度家臣たちの目前で見せた笑顔であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this was the only time his retainers saw him smiling in his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this was the only time his retainers saw him smile in his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this was the only time his retainers saw him smile in his lifetime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="74">
<j>かなりの愛刀家であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is assumed to have been considerably fond of collecting swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is assumed to have been considerably fond of collecting swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is assumed to have been considerably fond of collecting swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>卓越した鑑定眼を持ち、特に気に入ったものから選抜した「上杉景勝御手選三十五腰」と呼ばれるコレクションには国宝や重要文化財が多数含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had prominent connoisseurship, and the collection of swords selected from among those particularly striking his fancy, which is called &apos;上杉景勝御手選三十五腰&apos;, includes many national treasures and important cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had prominent connoisseurship, and the collection of swords selected from among those particularly striking his fancy, which is called &apos;上杉景勝御手選三十五腰&apos;, includes many national treasures and important cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>red lettering needs translation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had prominent connoisseurship, and the collection of swords selected from among those particularly striking his fancy, which is called &apos;上杉景勝御手選三十五腰&apos;, includes many national treasures and important cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="76">
<j>ある時、豊臣秀吉が京都・伏見城（もしくは大坂城）に各大名を招き宴が開かれたが、この宴の会場に前田利益が紛れ込んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI invited each feudal lord to a banquet held at Fushimi Castle in Kyoto (or Osaka Castle), and Toshimasu MAEDA slipped in the site of this banquet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI invited each feudal lord to a banquet held at Fushimi Castle in Kyoto (or Osaka Castle). Toshimasu MAEDA snuck into this banquet.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI invited each feudal lord to a banquet held at Fushimi Castle in Kyoto (or Osaka Castle), and Toshimasu MAEDA snuck into this banquet.</e>
<cmt>1文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>宴もたけなわになった頃、慶次郎は末席から猿面をつけ手拭いで頬被りをし、扇を振りながら身振り手振り面白おかしく踊り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the height of the banquet, Keijiro, wearing a monkey mask with a cloth wrapped over his head and cheeks and tied under his chin, started dancing comically with gestures at the seat farthest from the front while shaking a fan, and finally became so reckless as to do imitations of a monkey while sitting on the knees of the feudal lords, but none of the feudal lords blamed him or got angry because his behavior was an entertainment for the banquet.</e>
<cmt>「慶次郎」：「前田利益」を指すようですが、原文では、この事実への言及がありません。そのため、状況を把握するのが困難ではないかと思いました。「慶次郎」と「前田利益」が同一人物であるという記述を原文の然るべき個所に挿入した方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the height of the banquet, Keijiro, wearing a monkey mask with a cloth wrapped over his head and cheeks and tied under his chin, started dancing in a comical manner with gestures at the seat farthest from the front while manipulating a fan.</e>
<cmt>wording一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the height of the banquet, Keijiro, wearing a monkey mask with a cloth wrapped over his head and cheeks and tied under his chin, started dancing in a comical manner with gestures at the seat farthest from the front while manipulating a fan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>ついには列席している大名達の膝の上に座っては猿真似をやるという暴挙にまで至ったが、大名達は宴の余興ゆえに咎める者も怒り出す者もいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became so daring as to continue his monkey imitation on the laps of the feudal lords, but he was never censured because his behavior was so entertaining for all of the banquet attendees.</e>
<cmt>wording一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became so daring as to continue his monkey imitation on the laps of the feudal lords, but he was never censured because his behavior was so entertaining for all of the banquet attendees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>しかし、上杉景勝の前に来ると慶次郎は膝に乗ることを避けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When coming to the seat in front of Kagekatsu UESUGI, however, Keijiro did not try to sit on Kagekatsu&apos;s knees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he came to Kagekatsu UESUGI, however, Keijiro made no attempt to sit on Kagekatsu&apos;s lap.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he came to Kagekatsu UESUGI, however, Keijiro made no attempt to sit on Kagekatsu&apos;s lap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>その理由について尋ねられた慶次郎は、「景勝の前に出ると威風凛然としていてどうしても座ることが出来なかった」と語ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When being asked why not, Keijiro replied, &quot;When I was at the seat in front of Kagekatsu, he looked so majestic that I could never sit on his knees.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When asked why not, Keijiro replied, &quot;When I was in front of Kagekatsu, he looked so majestic that I could never sit on his lap.&quot;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When asked why not, Keijiro replied, &quot;When I was in front of Kagekatsu, he looked so majestic that I could never sit on his lap.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>また「天下広しといえども、真に我が主と頼むは会津の景勝殿をおいて外にあるまい」と慶次郎が後に語ったということから、義を貫く人物は景勝をおいて他にはいないと見込んでの、慶次郎なりの敬意を示した行動だったともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, based on the fact that Keijiro said later, &quot;I would never rely on anyone other than the lord Kagekatsu of Aizu as my master in all the wide world, some say that Keijiro&apos;s behavior represents his respect for Kagekatsu, whom he trusted as the only person adhering to justice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, based on the fact that Keijiro said later, &quot;I would never rely on anyone else in all the world but lord Kagekatsu of Aizu to be my master,&quot; some say that Keijiro&apos;s behavior represents his respect for Kagekatsu, whom he trusted as the only just person.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, based on the fact that Keijiro said later, &quot;I would never rely on anyone else in all the world but lord Kagekatsu of Aizu to be my master,&quot; some say that Keijiro&apos;s behavior represents his respect for Kagekatsu, whom he trusted as the only just person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="82">
<j>叔父であり義父である上杉謙信との仲については諸説あり、尊敬、思慕の対象であったという見かたから、実は険悪であったという説まで様々である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With regard to the relations with Kenshin UESUGI, Kagekatsu&apos;s uncle and adoptive father, there are various views, ranging from one that Kagekatsu respected and longed for Kenshin to one that such relations were tense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various views regarding relations with Kenshin UESUGI, Kagekatsu&apos;s uncle and adoptive father. These views ranged from Kagekatsu respecting and longing for Kenshin to one that such relations were tense.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various views regarding relations with Kenshin UESUGI, Kagekatsu&apos;s uncle and adoptive father, ranging from Kagekatsu respecting and longing for Kenshin to one that such relations were tense.</e>
<cmt>1文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>これは謙信が後継体制を築く前に急死したことが影響しているともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say that Kenshin&apos;s sudden death before the establishment of arrangements for the succession affected the relations between them.</e>
<cmt>「これ」：謙信と景勝の関係を指すものと解釈し、&quot;the relations between them&quot;と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say that Kenshin&apos;s sudden death before the establishment of arrangements for the succession affected relations between them.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say that Kenshin&apos;s sudden death before the establishment of arrangements for the succession affected relations between them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>また父の政景が謙信と対立していたことから謙信による政景暗殺説が存在するが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, others say, based on the fact that Masakage, Kagekatsu&apos;s father, was confronted with Kenshin, that Kenshin assassinated Masakage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another account states that Masakage, Kagekatsu&apos;s father, was confronted and assassinated by Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another account states that Masakage, Kagekatsu&apos;s father, was confronted and assassinated by Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>これらの影響か景勝による謙信暗殺説も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These views might have given rise to a view that Kagekatsu assassinated Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These views might have also given rise to the view that Kagekatsu assassinated Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These views might have also given rise to the view that Kagekatsu assassinated Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>しかしその一方、景勝は晩年病床に臥したとき、宗心という法名を名乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, however, Kagekatsu assumed the Buddhist name of Soshin when he was ill in bed in his closing years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, however, Kagekatsu assumed the Buddhist name of Soshin when he was ill in bed near the end of his life.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, however, Kagekatsu assumed the Buddhist name of Soshin when he was ill in bed near the end of his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>これは養父の謙信がかつて京都で名乗ったことがある法名であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kenshin had previously assumed this Buddhist name while having been in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is told that Kenshin had previously assumed this Buddhist name while he was in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is told that Kenshin had previously assumed this Buddhist name while he was in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="88">
<j>景勝が弾正少弼を謙信から譲り受けた際の2通の書状が、景勝自身の筆跡と同じであるとし、景勝が自己を正当化する為、偽作したとの説（「新潟県史」「上越市史 通史編2 中世」）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the ground that two letters that were written when Kagekatsu inherited the rank of Danjo-no-shosuke (a vice minister of the Ministry of Justice) from Kenshin were in the same handwriting as Kagekatsu&apos;s, some say that Kagekatsu forged those letters in order to justify himself (&quot;The History of Niigata Prefecture&quot;, &quot;The History of Joetsu City: Complete History I: The Mediaeval Period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two letters were written in Kagekatsu&apos;s handwriting when Kagekatsu inherited the rank of Danjo-no-shosuke (a vice minister of the Ministry of Justice) from Kenshin. Some say that Kagekatsu forged those letters in order to justify himself (The History of Niigata Prefecture, The History of Joetsu City: Complete History I: The Medieval Period).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kagekatsu inherited the rank of Danjo-Shohitsu from Kenshin, some say that the two relevant letters were written in Kagekatsu&apos;s handwriting; that is to say Kagekatsu forged those letters in order to justify himself (The History of Niigata Prefecture, The History of Joetsu City: Complete History I: The Medieval Period).</e>
<cmt>1文に戻しました。弾正少弼→danjo-shohitsu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>しかし、上杉景虎が蘆名盛氏にあてた書状には「先日申入れ候如く、少弼曲なきからいゆえ」と景勝を少弼と呼んでいる処をみると、景勝官途は上杉家中において、公の事実と見て間違いないであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, considering the fact that Kagetora UESUGI referred to Kagekatsu as the vice minister in his letter to Moriuji ASHINA, as shown in the statement, &quot;Because the vice minister is uninteresting and strict as I told you the other day,.....&quot;, it would be safe to bet that Kagekatsu&apos;s government service was widely known in the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>「先日申入れ候如く、少弼曲なきからいゆえ」：この原文についての解釈及びこれに対応する訳に確信を持つことができません。仮訳とさせてください（特に「曲なきからい」の部分）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, considering the fact that Kagetora UESUGI referred to Kagekatsu as the vice minister in his letter to Moriuji ASHINA, as shown in the statement, &quot;Because the vice minister is uninteresting and strict, as I told you the other day,.....&quot;, it would be a safe assumption that Kagekatsu&apos;s government service was widely known in the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, considering the fact that Kagetora UESUGI referred to Kagekatsu as the vice minister in his letter to Moriuji ASHINA, as shown in the statement, &quot;Because the vice minister is uninteresting and strict, as I told you the other day,.....&quot;, it would be a safe assumption that Kagekatsu&apos;s government service was widely known in the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="90">
<j>「奥羽永慶軍記」には、景勝は大変な女嫌いで身辺に女を一切近づけず、また正室の菊姫 (大儀院)と非常に不仲であると共に、極めて衆道を好み、身辺にはもっぱら美貌の少年達のみを侍らせていたという話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A war chronicle titled &quot;Ouu Eikei Gunki&quot; contains a tale saying that Kagekatsu extraordinarily hated women and kept any woman away from him, that he was on extraordinarily bad terms with his lawful wife, Kikuhime (Daigiin), and that he had a liking for male homosexuality and had only good-looking boys beside him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A war chronicle entitled Ouu Eikei Gunki contains a tale of Kagekatsu having extraordinary hatred for women, that he actively kept women away from him, and that he did not get along with his wife, Kikuhime (Daigiin). Instead, it has been told that he had an affinity for men, and often kept good-looking boys close to him.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A war chronicle entitled Ouu Eikei Gunki contains a tale of Kagekatsu having extraordinary hatred for women, that he actively kept women away from him, and that he did not get along with his wife, Kikuhime (Daigiin); instead it has been told that he had an affinity for men, and often kept good-looking boys close to him.</e>
<cmt>1文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>しかし、この書物には側室の桂岩院の出自を遊女とし、直江兼続が世継ぎを生ませる為、この遊女を男装させて景勝に引き合わせて定勝を生ませたが、この女は自分が女だと景勝に知られて怒りを買い、その寵愛を失ったことを悲観して自殺したとし、それを恨みとした定勝が兼続を自らの手で殺害するという明らかに史実と異なる記述や考証がされており、信憑性には問題がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the credibility of this book is problematic because it contains statements and documentation obviously inconsistent with historical facts, which are as follows: Keigannin, Kagekatsu&apos;s concubine, was a descendent of a harlot; Kanetsugu NAOE caused this harlot to disguise herself as a man and introduced her to Kagekatsu so that she would bear an heir to Kagekatsu; She bore Sadakatsu, but she incurred Kagekatsu&apos;s anger because of being found by Kagekatsu to be a woman; This woman was disappointed by the loss of Kagekatsu&apos;s favor and killed herself; Her suicide caused Sadakatsu to have hard feelings against Kanetsugu and kill Kanetsugu in person.</e>
<cmt>「桂岩院の出自を遊女とし」、「この遊女を」：前者の記述を文字どおりに訳出すると、&quot;Keigannin was a descendent of a harlt&quot;となります（出自＝生まれと解釈しました）。これに対し、後者の記述を文字どおりに訳出すると&quot;this harlot&quot;となり、桂岩院自身が遊女であることになり、前者の記述と矛盾します。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the credibility of this book is problematic because it contains statements and documentation obviously inconsistent with historical facts. Some of these inconsistencies follow: Keigannin, Kagekatsu&apos;s concubine, was a descendent of a prostitute; Kanetsugu NAOE forced this prostitute to disguise herself as a man and introduced her to Kagekatsu so that she would bear an heir to Kagekatsu; she bore Sadakatsu, but she incurred Kagekatsu&apos;s anger because he found out that she was a woman; this woman was disappointed by the loss of Kagekatsu&apos;s favor and killed herself; her suicide caused Sadakatsu to harbor ill will against Kanetsugu, and he killed Kanetsugu in person.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the credibility of this book is problematic because it contains statements and documentation obviously inconsistent with historical facts; some of these inconsistencies follow: Keigannin, Kagekatsu&apos;s concubine, was a descendent of a prostitute; Kanetsugu NAOE forced this prostitute to disguise herself as a man and introduced her to Kagekatsu so that she would bear an heir to Kagekatsu; she bore Sadakatsu, but she incurred Kagekatsu&apos;s anger because he found out that she was a woman; this woman was disappointed by the loss of Kagekatsu&apos;s favor and killed herself; her suicide caused Sadakatsu to harbor ill will against Kanetsugu, and he killed Kanetsugu in person.</e>
<cmt>1文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>景勝は慶長17年（1612年）8月に衆道禁止令を発布しており（「三重年表」）、これを根拠として男色家ではないとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another view that Kagekatsu was not a male homosexual, which is grounded on the fact that Kagekatsu issued an order forbidding male homosexuality in 1612 (&apos;Chronological Table of Mie&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another view that Kagekatsu was not homosexual, which is based on the fact that Kagekatsu issued an order forbidding male homosexuality in 1612 (&apos;Chronological Table of Mie&apos;).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another view that Kagekatsu was not homosexual, which is based on the fact that Kagekatsu issued an order forbidding male homosexuality in 1612 (&apos;Chronological Table of Mie&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="93">
<j>米沢への減移封の際、景勝は所領を大幅に減らされたにも関わらず、家臣の召し放ちを行わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When being transferred to Yonezawa, Kagekatsu&apos;s fief was considerably decreased; however, he brought all his retainers to Yonezawa.</e>
<cmt>「召し放ちを行わなかった」：「すべての家臣を米沢に連れて行った」と読み替えて訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When being transferred to Yonezawa, Kagekatsu&apos;s fiefdom was considerably decreased; however, he brought all of his retainers to Yonezawa.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When being transferred to Yonezawa, Kagekatsu&apos;s fiefdom was considerably decreased; however, he brought all of his retainers to Yonezawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>この事が後世の米沢藩の財政難の元凶になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became the main cause of financial difficulties of the later Yonezawa domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became the main cause of the financial difficulties of the later Yonezawa domain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became the main cause of the financial difficulties of the later Yonezawa domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="95">
<j>京都府京都市伏見区にある景勝町の地名の由来は、かつてこの地に景勝の伏見の下屋敷があったことに基づく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the name of Kagekatsu-cho, which is located in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is Kagekatsu&apos;s suburban residence (called Fushimi no Shimoyashiki) that existed there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the name Kagekatsu-cho, located in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, was the location of Kagekatsu&apos;s suburban residence (called Fushimi no Shimoyashiki).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the name Kagekatsu-cho, located in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, was the location of Kagekatsu&apos;s suburban residence (called Fushimi no Shimoyashiki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), ドルチェット(id:46458), ちょーばみ(id:194335), Nnh(id:474), Reggaeman(id:6214), デュオ(id:40933), Lupinoid(id:68), Tokyosampo00(id:140349), 味っ子(id:17086), Harupri(id:133581), Revth(id:12179), Gedz(id:14192), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), 堀五郎右衛門(id:84263), ひろっきー(id:87284), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), Azusayumi7(id:21082), A-Taul(id:41790), Rei-bot(id:94097), 怪蘇(id:45514), Sho-gun(id:74168), Knua(id:66861), Chobot(id:20846), Nubolari(id:69933), Funhouse(id:169027), こぶまき(id:38278), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Maakun(id:16735), Kz(id:18320), シェーラ(id:17988), 常陸介(id:176100), Mnd(id:15140), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Thomo(id:169717), Mondayprecioustime(id:119374), たね(id:10372), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), 表現等規制委員会(id:61918), Agira(id:109845), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Kagetudo(id:163875), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), M1991A1(id:111171), Yonoemon(id:55450), Hungugu(id:20858), ゐ(id:795), Tveye505(id:163789), KSKS(id:97637), 上(id:14148), けんち(id:5147), Louperibot(id:128971), 人造人間だみゃ～ん(id:119413), Hadrianvs et antinovs(id:187552), King-wise(id:19033), Mtdhryk(id:106423), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>