<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原敦信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Atsunobu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Atsunobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Atsunobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 敦信（ふじわら の あつのぶ。生没年不詳）は、平安時代中期の歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Atsunobu (date of birth and death unknown) is a poet in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Atsunobu (date of birth and death unknown) was a poet in the mid Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Tense, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Atsunobu (year of birth and death unknown) was a poet in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>概ね10世紀末頃から11世紀中頃までにかけて活動していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active from about the end of the tenth century to about the middle of the eleventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active from about the end of the tenth century to about the middle of the eleventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active from about the end of the 10th century to about the middle of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原式家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is from the Fujiwara Shikike (a sub branch of Fujiwara family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Fujiwara Shikike (a sub branch of the Fujiwara family).</e>
<cmt>Tense, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was in the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>因幡国国司藤原合茂の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is a son of Inaba no kuni Kokushi (provincial governor) FUJIWARA no Aishige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Inaba no kuni Kokushi (Provincial Governor of Inaba) FUJIWARA no Aishige.</e>
<cmt>Tense, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Inaba no kuni Kokushi (Provincial Governor of Inaba Province) FUJIWARA no Aishige.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>正五位（または正四位）・山城国守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank), or Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), and Yamashiro no kuni no kami (governor of Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the position of Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank), and Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), and was Yamashiro no kuni no kami (Governor of Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the position of Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank), and Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank), and was Yamashiro no kuni no kami (Governor of Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>円融天皇の時文章生となり、敦良親王の読書始に列席するなどの活動を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial University) at the time of Emperor Enyu, and attended Dokushohajime, a ceremony when one starts to study, of Imperial Prince Atsunaga and performed other activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial University) at the time of Emperor Enyu, and attended the Dokushohajime (a ceremony to mark when an individual starts to study) of Imperial Prince Atsunaga among other activities.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial University) at the time of Emperor Enyu, and attended the Dokushohajime (a ceremony to mark when an individual starts to study) of Imperial Prince Atsunaga among other activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>藤原式家の院政期における儒文確立の礎を築くなどの活躍をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active and built the foundation for establishing 儒文 during the insei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor) of Fujiwara Shikike.</e>
<cmt>読み方、定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active in building the foundation for establishing 儒文 during the insei period (the period of government by the retired Emperor) of Fujiwara Shikike.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active in building the foundation for Confucianism academically during the insei period (the period of government by the retired Emperor) of the Ceremonial House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>「儒文」の意味が確認できなかったため、「学問としての儒教」として訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>晩年の様子については不詳であるが、不遇で出家したようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His life in his later years is unknown, but it is said that he was unhappy and entered into priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details of his life in later years are few, but it is said that he was unhappy and entered into the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details of his life in later years are few, but it is said that he was unhappy and entered into the priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hajimari(id:205606), Snap55(id:89773), Namimakura0115(id:292875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>