<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>安倍晴明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ABE no Seimei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ABE no Seimei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ABE no Seimei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>安倍 晴明（あべの せいめい/はるあきら/はれあき、延喜21年（921年）? - 寛弘2年9月26日 (旧暦)（1005年10月31日））は、平安時代の最も有名な陰陽師の一人であり、鎌倉時代から明治時代初めまで陰陽寮を統括した阿倍氏（土御門家）の祖である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ABE no Seimei (Haruaki, Hareaki, 921? to October 31, 1005) was one of the most famous Ommyoji (Ommyo diviner), and he is the ancestor of Abe clan (Tsuchimikado family) who was responsible for Ommyo-ryo (Bureau of Yin and Yang) from Kamakura Period to early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>陰陽寮 = Bureau of Yin and Yang, &quot;Key to Japanese Heart and Soul&quot;, published by Kodansha International Ltd.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ABE no Seimei (Haruakira, Hareaki, 921? to October 31, 1005) was one of the most famous Ommyoji (Ommyo diviner), and he is the ancestor of the Abe clan (Tsuchimikado family) who was responsible for Ommyo-ryo (Bureau of Yin and Yang) from the Kamakura Period to the early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>Haruaki→Haruakiraとしました。the Abe clanに訂正しました。Kamakura Period to early Meiji Period→the Kamakura Period to the early Meiji Periodとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ABE no Seimei (Haruakira, Hareaki, 921? to October 31, 1005) was one of the most famous Ommyoji (Ommyo diviner), and he is the ancestor of the Abe clan (Tsuchimikado family) who was responsible for Ommyo-ryo (Bureau of Yin and Yang) from the Kamakura Period to the early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>当時最先端の呪術・科学であった「天文道」や占いなどの陰陽道の技術に関して卓越した知識を持ったエキスパートであり、平安貴族たちの信頼を受けた大陰陽師で、その事跡は神秘化されて数多くの伝説的逸話を生んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a great Ommyoji who was trusted by aristocrats during Heian Period, and he was also an expert who had a remarkable knowledge of the art of Ommyodo (the Way of Yin and Yang), such as divination and &quot;ancient astrology&quot;, which was the most advanced form of magic and science at the time, and many legendary anecdotes have been created based on mystified stories about him.</e>
<cmt>天文道 = ancient astrology陰陽道 = the Way of Yin and Yang陰陽道 = occult divination system based on Taoist theory of the five elements/cosmic dual force system</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a great Ommyoji who was trusted by aristocrats during the Heian Period, and he was also an expert who had a remarkable knowledge of the art of Ommyodo (the Way of Yin and Yang), such as divination and &apos;ancient astrology,&apos; which was the most advanced form of magic and science at the time, and many legendary anecdotes have been created based on mystified stories about him.</e>
<cmt>the Heian Period, &apos;ancient astrology&apos;に訂正しました。コンマを&apos;&apos; 内に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a great Ommyoji who was trusted by aristocrats during the Heian Period, and he was also an expert who had a remarkable knowledge of the art of Ommyodo (the Way of Yin and Yang), such as divination and &apos;ancient astrology,&apos; which was the most advanced form of magic and science at the time, and many legendary anecdotes have been created based on mystified stories about him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>道摩法師（蘆屋道満）とはライバル関係にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Priest Doma (Doman ASHIYA) was his rival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Priest Doma (Doman ASHIYA) was his rival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Priest Doma (Doman ASHIYA) was his rival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、平将門の子の平将国が安倍晴明ではないかという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is a view that states that TAIRA no Masakuni, a son of TAIRA no Masakado, might have been Seimei ABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is a view that states that TAIRA no Masakuni, a son of TAIRA no Masakado, might have been Seimei ABE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is a view that states that TAIRA no Masakuni, a son of TAIRA no Masakado, might have been Seimei ABE..</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>後世に陰陽道の経典となる秘伝書『ほき内伝』（ほきないでん、別名『金烏玉兎集』）の著者に仮託されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His name is used as the author of &quot;Hoki-Naiden&quot; (also known as &quot;Kin&apos;u-Gyokuto shu&quot;), a book of secrets which later became the canon in Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His name is used as the author of &quot;Hoki-Naiden&quot; (also known as &quot;Kin&apos;u-Gyokuto shu&quot;), a book of secrets which later became the canon in Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name is used as the author of &quot;Hoki-Naiden&quot; (also known as &quot;Kinu-Gyokuto shu&quot;), a book of secrets which later became the canon in Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt>Kin&apos;u→Kinuに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>実際の晴明の著作としては土御門家に伝わった『占事略决』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The actual work Seimei authored is Senji-Ryakketsu, which has been passed down in Tuschimikado family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The actual work Seimei authored is &quot;Senji-Ryakketsu,&quot; which has been passed down in the Tuschimikado family.</e>
<cmt>本のタイトルなので、原文に『』を補足、英訳を&quot;Senji-Ryakketsu,&quot;に修正しました。the Tuschimikado familyに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The actual work Seimei authored is &quot;Senji-Ryakketsu,&quot; which has been passed down in the Tuschimikado family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>特に近年では夢枕獏の小説（のち漫画・映画化）のヒットにより、京都にある晴明神社が人であふれかえるほどの大ブームとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, because a novel by Baku YUMEMAKURA (later made into a manga and a movie) recently became a big hit, Seimei-jinja Shrine in Kyoto became so popular that it has been full of visitors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, because a novel by Baku YUMEMAKURA (later made into a manga and a movie) recently became a big hit, Seimei-jinja Shrine in Kyoto became so popular that it has been full of visitors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, because a novel by Baku YUMEMAKURA (later made into a manga and a movie) recently became a big hit, Seimei-jinja Shrine in Kyoto became so popular that it has been full of visitors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>史実上の晴明</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seimei in Historical Facts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seimei in Historical Facts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seimei in Historical Facts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>安倍晴明は、阿倍氏の伝える系図によると、大膳職の官にある下級貴族安倍益材（あべのますき）の子として摂津国阿倍野（現・大阪市阿倍野区）に生まれた（奈良県桜井市安倍を生誕の地とする伝承もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the family tree of Abe clan, Seimei ABE was born in Abeno, Settsu Province (present day Abeno Ward, Osaka City), as a son of ABE no Masuki, a low-ranking aristocrat who had the rank of Daizenshiki (there is also a lore that places Abe, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture as his birth place).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the family tree of the Abe clan, Seimei ABE was born in Abeno, Settsu Province (present day Abeno Ward, Osaka City), as a son of ABE no Masuki, a low-ranking aristocrat who had the rank of Daizenshiki (there is also a lore that places Abe, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture as his birth place).</e>
<cmt>the Abe clanに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the family tree of the Abe clan, ABE no Seimei was born in Abeno, Settsu Province (present day Abeno Ward, Osaka City), as a son of ABE no Masuki, a low-ranking aristocrat who had the rank of Daizenshiki (there is also a lore that places Abe, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture as his birth place).</e>
<cmt>Seimei ABE→ABE no Seimeiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>阿倍仲麻呂の子孫を称するが、系図では『竹取物語』にもその名が登場する右大臣阿倍御主人の直系の子孫であるという説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known as a descendant of ABE no Nakamaro, but the view that considers him as a direct descendant of Minister of the Right, ABE no Miushi, whose name also appears in &quot;The Tale of Bamboo-Cutter&quot;, is dominant,</e>
<cmt>竹取物語 = The Tale of Bamboo-Cutter</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known as a descendant of ABE no Nakamaro, but the view that considers him as a direct descendant of the Minister of the Right, ABE no Miushi, whose name also appears in &quot;The Tale of Bamboo-Cutter,&quot; is dominant.</e>
<cmt>Minister→the Minister 竹取物語は本のタイトルなので、原文に『』を補足しました。コンマを&quot;&quot;内に移動、文末をピリオドに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also known as a descendant of ABE no Nakamaro, but the view that considers him as a direct descendant of Udaijin (Minister of the Right), ABE no Miushi, whose name also appears in &quot;The Tale of Bamboo-Cutter,&quot; is dominant.</e>
<cmt>the Minister of the Right→Udaijin (Minister of the Right)に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、一部の古文書では安倍朝臣晴明ではなく安倍宿禰晴明と記載されるものが散見されるため、「朝臣」を「宿禰」の上位に厳格に位置づける当時の慣習から考えて、安倍御主人からの安倍朝臣姓の家系ではなく、難波吉士族の難波忌寸（のち宿禰）の末裔ではないかとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because ABE no Sukune Seimei, instead of ABE no Ason Seimei, appears often in a group of ancient documents, and based on the practice at that time of strictly placing &quot;Ason&quot; above &quot;Sukune&quot;, there is a view that considers him as a descendant of NANIWA no Imiki (later sukune) of NANIWA no Kishi clan instead of a family that bears the ABE no Ason family name that originates from ABE no Miushi.</e>
<cmt>朝臣 = &quot;ason&quot;, 定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because ABE no Sukune Seimei, instead of ABE no Ason Seimei, appears often in a group of ancient documents, and based on the practice at that time of strictly placing &quot;Ason&quot; above &quot;Sukune,&quot; there is a view that considers him as a descendant of NANIWA no Imiki (later sukune) of the NANIWA no Kishi clan instead of a family that bears the ABE no Ason family name that originates from ABE no Miushi.</e>
<cmt>(※朝臣→a high-ranking Court noble)コンマを&quot;&quot;内に移動しました。NANIWA no Kishi clan→the NANIWA no Kishi clan</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because ABE no Sukune Seimei, instead of ABE no Ason Seimei, appears often in a group of ancient documents, and based on the practice at that time of strictly placing &quot;Ason&quot; above &quot;Sukune,&quot; there is a view that considers him as a descendant of NANIWA no Imiki (later sukune) of the NANIWA no Kishi clan instead of a family that bears the ABE no Ason family name that originates from ABE no Miushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>いずれにしても古代から続く名門の家柄に生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any case, he was born to a distinguished family that had continued since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, he was born to a distinguished family that had continued since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, he was born to a distinguished family that had continued since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>生年は定かではないが、寛弘二年九月（1005年）に85歳で亡くなったと記録されていることから逆算して延喜二十一年（921年）生まれと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of his birth is uncertain, but because it has been recorded that he passed away at the age of 85 in 1005, it can be estimated that he was born in 921 by counting backwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year of his birth is uncertain, but because it has been recorded that he passed away at the age of 85 in 1005, it can be estimated that he was born in 921 by counting backwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year of his birth is uncertain, but because it has been recorded that he passed away at the age of 85 in 1005, it can be estimated that he was born in 921 by counting backwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>幼少の頃については確かな記録がないが、陰陽師賀茂忠行・賀茂保憲父子に陰陽道を学び、天文道を伝授されたということになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are no reliable records of his childhood, but it is said that he learned Ommyodo and was initiated into the ancient astrology from the Ommyoji father-and-son pair, KAMO no Tadayuki and KAMO no Yasunori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no reliable records of his childhood, but it is said that he learned Ommyodo and was initiated into the ancient astrology from the Ommyoji father-and-son pair, KAMO no Tadayuki and KAMO no Yasunori.</e>
<cmt>KAMOの前のスペースを調整しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no reliable records of his childhood, but it is said that he learned Ommyodo and was initiated into the ancient astrology from the Ommyoji father-and-son pair, KAMO no Tadayuki and KAMO no Yasunori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>確かな記録に現れるのは960年で、当時天文得業生（陰陽寮に所属し天文博士から天文道を学ぶ学生の職）であった晴明は村上天皇に占いを命ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reliable records appear from 960, and Seimei, who was a student of ancient astrology (the studenthood belonging to the Office of Ommyo to learn ancient astrology from the scholar of ancient astrology), was ordered by Emperor Murakami to perform a divinatory reading.</e>
<cmt>天文得業生 = astrology learner (the studenthood belonging to the office of Ommyo to learn astrology from the astrologist), 訳文には用語集の learner を student にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reliable records appear from 960, and Seimei, who was a student of ancient astrology (the studenthood belonging to the Office of Ommyo to learn ancient astrology from the scholar of ancient astrology), was ordered by Emperor Murakami to perform a divinatory reading.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reliable records appear from 960, and Seimei, who was a student of ancient astrology (the studenthood belonging to the Office of Ommyo to learn ancient astrology from the scholar of ancient astrology), was ordered by Emperor Murakami to perform a divinatory reading.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>出世は遅れていたが占いの才能は既に貴族社会で認められていたことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His career advancement occurred late, but it can be seen that his talent in divinatory reading had already been acknowledged in the aristocratic circles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His career advancement occurred late, but it can be seen that his talent in divinatory reading had already been acknowledged in the aristocratic circles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His career advancement occurred late, but it can be seen that his talent in divinatory reading had already been acknowledged in the aristocratic circles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、天文博士の官に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he was assigned to the rank of a scholar of ancient astrology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was assigned to the rank of a scholar of ancient astrology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was assigned to the rank of a scholar of ancient astrology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>979年、59歳の晴明は当時の皇太子（後の花山天皇）の命で那智山 (山)の天狗を封ずる儀式を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 979, by the order of the heir to the throne then (later Emperor Kazan), Seimei, at the age of 59, conducted a ritual to suppress the tengu (long-nosed goblins) of Mt. Nachi-san.</e>
<cmt>天狗 = tengu (long-nosed goblin)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 979, by the order of the heir to the throne then (later Emperor Kazan), Seimei, at the age of 59, conducted a ritual to suppress the tengu (long-nosed goblins) of Mt. Nachi-san.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 979, by the order of the heir to the throne then (later Emperor Kazan), Seimei, at the age of 59, conducted a ritual to suppress the tengu (long-nosed goblins) of Mt. Nachi-san.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このころから花山天皇の信頼を受けるようになったようで、記録にしばしば晴明が占いや陰陽道の儀式を行った様子が見られるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that he began to gain Emperor Kazan&apos;s trust from around this time, and records begin to show that Seimei often performed divinatory readings and Ommyodo rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that he began to gain Emperor Kazan&apos;s trust from around this time, and records begin to show that Seimei often performed divinatory readings and Ommyodo rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that he began to gain Emperor Kazan&apos;s trust from around this time, and records begin to show that Seimei often performed divinatory readings and Ommyodo rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>花山天皇の退位後は、一条天皇や藤原道長の信頼を集めるようになったことが、道長の日記『御堂関白記』などの当時の貴族の日記から分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Kazan stepped down he began to gain trust from Emperor Ichijo and FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and this fact can be seen from the diaries of aristocrats from that time, such as Michinaga&apos;s diary, &quot;Mido Kampaku ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Kazan stepped down he began to gain trust from Emperor Ichijo and FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and this fact can be seen from the diaries of aristocrats from that time, such as Michinaga&apos;s diary, &quot;Mido Kampaku ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Kazan stepped down he began to gain trust from Emperor Ichijo and FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and this fact can be seen from the diaries of aristocrats from that time, such as Michinaga&apos;s diary, &quot;Mido Kampaku ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>陰陽師として名声を極めた晴明は、天文道で培った計算能力をかわれて主計寮に異動し主計権助を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seimei, who became very famous as an Ommyoji, was recognized for his talent in calculation, which he gained through ancient astrology, and he moved to Kazue-ryo (Office of Accounting) and worked as Kazue no Gon-no-suke (Deputy Director of Office of Accounting).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seimei, who became very famous as an Ommyoji, was recognized for his talent in calculation, which he gained through ancient astrology, and he moved to Kazue-ryo (Office of Accounting) and worked as Kazue no Gon-no-suke (Deputy Director of Office of Accounting).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seimei, who became very famous as an Ommyoji, was recognized for his talent in calculation, which he gained through ancient astrology, and he moved to Kazue-ryo (Office of Accounting) and worked as Kazue no Gon-no-suke (Deputy Director of Office of Accounting).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その後、京職、穀倉院、播磨国などの官を歴任し、位は従四位下にのぼった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he held positions in Kyoshiki (Kyoto Police Office), Kokuso-in (Grain Warehouse), Harima Province and so on, and his courtly rank was elevated to jushi-i ge (Junior Fourth Court Rank Low).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he held positions in Kyoshiki (Kyoto Police Office), Kokuso-in (Grain Warehouse), Harima Province and so on, and his courtly rank was elevated to Jushii-ge (Junior Fourth Court Rank Low).</e>
<cmt>jushi-i ge→Jushii-geとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he held positions in Kyoshiki (Kyoto Police Office), Kokuso-in (Grain Warehouse), Harima Province and so on, and his courtly rank was elevated to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>Jushii-ge (Junior Fourth Court Rank Low)→Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに天文博士や陰陽助（陰陽寮の次官）に晴明の二人の息子安倍吉昌と安倍吉平が任ぜられ、安倍氏は晴明一代の間に師忠行の賀茂氏と並ぶ陰陽道の家となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Seimei&apos;s two sons, ABE no Yoshimasa and ABE no Yoshihira, were assigned as the scholar of the ancient astrology and Ommyojo (Deputy Minister of Ommyo-ryo), and during Seimei&apos;s generation alone the Abe clan became an Ommyodo family, just like Tadayuki MORO of Kamo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Seimei&apos;s two sons, ABE no Yoshimasa and ABE no Yoshihira, were assigned as the scholar of the ancient astrology and Ommyojo (Deputy Minister of Ommyo-ryo), and during Seimei&apos;s generation alone the Abe clan became an Ommyodo family, just like Tadayuki MORO of the Kamo clan.</e>
<cmt>the Kamo clanに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Seimei&apos;s two sons, ABE no Yoshimasa and ABE no Yoshihira, were assigned as the scholar of the ancient astrology and Ommyojo (Deputy Minister of Ommyo-ryo), and during Seimei&apos;s generation alone the Abe clan became an Ommyodo family, just like Tadayuki MORO of the Kamo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>墓所・霊廟・神社・末裔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Grave, Mausoleum, Shrines and Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Grave, Mausoleum, Shrines and Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Grave, Mausoleum, Shrines and Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>墓所は京都嵯峨野にあり、渡月橋の近くにひっそりと眠っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is located in Sagano, Kyoto, and he is resting quietly near Togetsu-kyo Bridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is located in Sagano, Kyoto, and he is resting quietly near Togetsu-kyo Bridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is located in Sagano, Kyoto, and he is resting quietly near Togetsu-kyo Bridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>安倍晴明を祀る神社は、屋敷跡に建てられたという一条戻橋近くの晴明神社や、生誕地の大阪市阿倍野区に建てられたとされる安倍晴明神社など全国各地に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines that enshrine ABE no Seimei exist in various locations throughout the country such as Seimei-jinja Shrine near Ichijo-modori-bashi Bridge, which is said to have been constructed on the former grounds of his mansion, and ABE no Seimei-jinja Shrine which is said to have been constructed in his birth place of Abeno Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines that enshrine ABE no Seimei exist in various locations throughout the country such as Seimei-jinja Shrine near Ichijo-modori-bashi Bridge, which is said to have been constructed on the former grounds of his mansion, and ABE no Seimei-jinja Shrine which is said to have been constructed in his birth place of Abeno Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines that enshrine ABE no Seimei exist in various locations throughout the country such as Seimei-jinja Shrine near Ichijo-modori-bashi Bridge, which is said to have been constructed on the former grounds of his mansion, and ABE no Seimei-jinja Shrine which is said to have been constructed in his birth place of Abeno Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>また子孫では平安時代末期の安倍泰親と室町時代初期の安倍有世が優れた陰陽師であったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among his descendants, it is said that Yasuchika ABE at the end of Heian Period and ABE no Ariyo from early Muromachi Period were very talented Ommyoji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among his descendants, it is said that Yasuchika ABE at the end of the Heian Period and ABE no Ariyo from the early Muromachi Period were very talented Ommyoji.</e>
<cmt>the Heian Period, the early Muromachi Periodに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among his descendants, it is said that Yasuchika ABE at the end of the Heian Period and ABE no Ariyo from the early Muromachi Period were very talented Ommyoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>有世は足利義満から信頼され、その推挙で陰陽師では初めて公卿となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ariyo was highly trusted by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, and upon his recommendation he became the very first Ommyoji to be a noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ariyo was highly trusted by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, and upon his recommendation he became the very first Ommyoji to be a noble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ariyo was highly trusted by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, and upon his recommendation he became the very first Ommyoji to be a noble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>有世の子孫は室町時代後期頃から土御門家を名乗り陰陽道のみならず神道や暦などの分野にも大きな影響力を持つ事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ariyo&apos;s descendants began to use the name Tsuchimikado from the latter part of Muromachi Period, and they cast a strong influence not only in Ommyodo but also in Shintoism and in the field of almanacs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ariyo&apos;s descendants began to use the name Tsuchimikado from the latter part of the Muromachi Period, and they cast a strong influence not only in Ommyodo but also in Shintoism and in the field of almanacs.</e>
<cmt>the Muromachi Periodに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ariyo&apos;s descendants began to use the name Tsuchimikado from the latter part of the Muromachi Period, and they cast a strong influence not only in Ommyodo but also in Shintoism and in the field of almanacs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>土御門家は以後江戸時代まで幕府の天文職と朝廷の陰陽寮の要職を累代に継承して家門の格を高めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From then on until Edo Period, the Tsuchimikado family elevated the family&apos;s rank by passing down the key positions in astrology in the Shogunate and Ommyo-ryo in the Imperial Court to the successive generations within the family.</e>
<cmt>原文にはありませんが、 &quot;within the family&quot; を訳文に追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then on until the Edo Period, the Tsuchimikado family elevated the family&apos;s rank by passing down the key positions in astrology in the Shogunate and Ommyo-ryo in the Imperial Court to the successive generations within the family.</e>
<cmt>the Edo Periodに訂正。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then on until the Edo Period, the Tsuchimikado family elevated the family&apos;s rank by passing down the key positions in astrology in the Shogunate and Ommyo-ryo in the Imperial Court to the successive generations within the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>土御門家最後の陰陽寮関連人物は幕末に活動した土御門晴雄の息子で、明治初期に陰陽寮の最後を見守った土御門晴栄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last person associated with Ommyo-ryo from the Tsuchimikado family was Harue TSUCHIMIKADO, who saw through the end of Ommyo-ryo during the early part of Meiji Period, and who was also a son of Haruo (Hareo, Haretaka) TSUCHIMIKADO, who worked during the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last person associated with Ommyo-ryo from the Tsuchimikado family was Harue TSUCHIMIKADO, who saw through the end of Ommyo-ryo during the early part of the Meiji Period, and who was also a son of Haruo (Hareo, Haretake) TSUCHIMIKADO, who worked during the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>the Meiji, the Edoに訂正しました。Haretaka→ Haretake 用語集その他より</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last person associated with Ommyo-ryo from the Tsuchimikado family was Harue TSUCHIMIKADO, who saw through the end of Ommyo-ryo during the early part of the Meiji Period, and who was also a son of Haruo (Hareo, Haretake) TSUCHIMIKADO, who worked during the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>安倍晴明が登場する作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works in Which ABE no Seimei Appear</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works in Which ABE no Seimei Appear</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works in Which ABE no Seimei Appear</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>平安・中世文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian and medieval Literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian and medieval Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian and Medieval Literature</e>
<cmt>medieval→Medievalとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>晴明が死んだ11世紀のうちに、早くも晴明は神秘化されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seimei had already been mystified during the 11th century, when he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seimei had already been mystified during the 11th century, when he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seimei had already been mystified during the 11th century, when he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>歴史物語の『大鏡』や説話集の『今昔物語』『宇治拾遺物語』『十訓抄』はいくつかの晴明に関する神秘的な逸話を載せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical tale of &quot;Okagami&quot; and collections of narratives such as &quot;The Tale of Times Now Past&quot;, &quot;The Tale of Ujishui&quot; and &quot;Jukkinsho&quot; contain several mysterious anecdotes related to Seimei.</e>
<cmt>『今昔物語』 = &quot;The Tale of Times Now Past&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical tale of &quot;Okagami&quot; and collections of narratives such as &quot;The Tale of Times Now Past,&quot; &quot;The Tale of Ujishui&quot; and &quot;Jukkinsho&quot; contain several mysterious anecdotes related to Seimei.</e>
<cmt>指示書に従い、コンマを&quot;&quot;内に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical tale of &quot;Okagami&quot; and collections of narratives such as &quot;The Tale of Times Now Past,&quot; &quot;The Tale of Ujishui&quot; and &quot;Jukkinsho&quot; contain several mysterious anecdotes related to Seimei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>『大鏡』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Okagami&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Okagami&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Okagami&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>帝紀『花山天皇』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teiki (History of Emperors) &quot;Emperor Kazan&quot;</e>
<cmt>定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teiki (History of Emperors) &quot;Emperor Kazan&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teiki (History of Emperors) &quot;Emperor Kazan&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>花山天皇が帝位を捨てて出家しようとした時、晴明は天文を見てそれを察知し、式神を使って朝廷に急報しようとしたが、ちょうどその時天皇は寺に向かっているところだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Kazan was about to give up his crown and to become an ordained monk, Seimei detected that through astrology, and as he tried to send an urgent message to the Imperial Court using Shikishin (a form of magic or divination) the Emperor was just heading toward the temple at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Kazan was about to give up his crown and to become an ordained monk, Seimei detected that through astrology, and as he tried to send an urgent message to the Imperial Court using Shikishin (a form of magic or divination) the Emperor was just heading toward the temple at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Kazan was about to give up his crown and to become an ordained monk, Seimei detected that through astrology, and as he tried to send an urgent message to the Imperial Court using Shikishin (a form of magic or divination) the Emperor was just heading toward the temple at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>『今昔物語』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Times Now Past&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Tale of Times Now Past&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Times Now Past&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>『安部晴明随忠行習道語』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Abe no Seimei Zuichu-Gyoshu Dogo&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Abe no Seimei Zuichu-Gyoshu Dogo&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Abe no Seimei Zuichu-Gyoshu Dogo&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>晴明が幼少の頃、賀茂忠行の夜行に供をしている時、夜道に鬼の姿を見て忠行に知らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his childhood, when Seimei was accompanying KAMO no Tadayuki during his night duty, he saw an image of a demon and he notified Tadayuki about it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his childhood, when Seimei was accompanying KAMO no Tadayuki during his night duty, he saw an image of a demon and he notified Tadayuki about it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his childhood, when Seimei was accompanying KAMO no Tadayuki during his night duty, he saw an image of a demon and he notified Tadayuki about it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>忠行は晴明が優れた才能をもつことを悟り、陰陽道のすべてを教え込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayuki realized that Seimei had an extraordinary talent, and he taught him everything about Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayuki realized that Seimei had an extraordinary talent, and he taught him everything about Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayuki realized that Seimei had an extraordinary talent, and he taught him everything about Ommyodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>陰陽道の大家となった晴明は、ある時播磨国から来た陰陽師に術比べを挑まれたが、いともたやすく懲らしめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seimei, who became an authority in Ommyodo, was once challenged to compete in magic by an Ommyoji who came from Harima Province, but he easily chastised the challenger.</e>
<cmt>原文にはありませんが、 &quot;challenger&quot; を訳文に追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seimei, who became an authority in Ommyodo, was once challenged to compete in magic by an Ommyoji who came from Harima Province, but he easily chastised the challenger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seimei, who became an authority in Ommyodo, was once challenged to compete in magic by an Ommyoji who came from Harima Province, but he easily chastised the challenger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="38">
<j>仁和寺の寛朝僧正のところで、同席した公卿達に陰陽道の技でカエルを殺してみせるようにせがまれ、術を用いて手を触れずにカエルを真平らに潰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was asked by the nobles, who were also in attendance in front of the high Buddhist priest Kancho of Nin&apos;na-ji Temple, to use Ommyodo techniques to kill a frog, and he used his magic to smash and flatten the frog without touching it with his hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was asked by the nobles, who were also in attendance in front of the high Buddhist priest Kancho of Nin&apos;na-ji Temple, to use Ommyodo techniques to kill a frog, and he used his magic to smash and flatten the frog without touching it with his hands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was asked by the nobles, who were also in attendance in front of the high Buddhist priest Kancho of Ninna-ji Temple, to use Ommyodo techniques to kill a frog, and he used his magic to smash and flatten the frog without touching it with his hands.</e>
<cmt>Nin&apos;na→Ninnaに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="39">
<j>晴明の家では式神を家事に使っており、人もいないのに勝手に門が開閉していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Seimei&apos;s house, they used Shikishin for household chores, and even though there was nobody the gate used to open and close on its own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Seimei&apos;s house, they used Shikishin for household chores, and even though there was nobody the gate used to open and close on its own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Seimei&apos;s house, they used Shikishin for household chores, and even though there was nobody the gate used to open and close on its own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="40">
<j>『播磨国陰陽師智徳法師語』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Buddhist priest Chitoku, the Ommyo diviner, of the Province of Harima&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Tale of Buddhist priest Chitoku, the Ommyo diviner, of the Province of Harima&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Buddhist priest Chitoku, the Ommyo diviner, of the Province of Harima&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>播磨国の陰陽師、智徳法師が方術で海賊を捕らえた物語だが、末尾に「智徳はこれほど優れた陰陽師でありながら晴明にはかなわなかった」と記されているので、前の物語に登場した播磨の陰陽師は彼のことだとわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a story of Buddhist Priest Chitoku, an Ommyoji from Harima Province, who caught the pirates using his magic, but at the end it is noted that &quot;Even though Chitoku was a very talented ommyoji, he was no match for Seimei,&quot; and it can be said that he was the Ommyoji from Harima Province in the previous story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a story of Buddhist Priest Chitoku, an Ommyoji from Harima Province, who caught the pirates using his magic, but at the end it is noted that &apos;Even though Chitoku was a very talented ommyoji, he was no match for Seimei,&apos; and it can be said that he was the Ommyoji from Harima Province in the previous story.</e>
<cmt>&quot;&quot;→ &apos;&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a story of Buddhist Priest Chitoku, an Ommyoji from Harima Province, who caught the pirates using his magic, but at the end it is noted that &apos;Even though Chitoku was a very talented ommyoji, he was no match for Seimei,&apos; and it can be said that he was the Ommyoji from Harima Province in the previous story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>『宇治拾遺物語』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Ujishui&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Tale of Ujishui&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Tale of Ujishui&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>『晴明蔵人少将封ずる事』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Seimei Sealed a Major General and Keeper of Imperial Archives&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Seimei Sealed a Major General and Keeper of Imperial Archives&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Seimei Sealed a Major General and Keeper of Imperial Archives&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>晴明がある時、カラスに糞をかけられた蔵人少将を見て、カラスの正体が式神であることを見破り、少将の呪いをといてやった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One time, Seimei saw a crow dropping its excrements on a major general who was also a keeper of Imperial archives, he saw through that the crow was really a Shikishin, and he removed the curse that was put on the major general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One time, Seimei saw a crow dropping its excrements on a major general who was also a keeper of Imperial archives, he saw through that the crow was really a Shikishin, and he removed the curse that was put on the major general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One time, Seimei saw a crow dropping its excrements on a major general who was also a keeper of Imperial archives, he saw through that the crow was really a Shikishin, and he removed the curse that was put on the major general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>『御堂関白の御犬晴明等奇特の事』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The Miraculous Deed of the Dog of Mido-Kanpaku and Seimei&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The Miraculous Deed of the Dog of Mido-Kanpaku and Seimei&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Miraculous Deed of the Dog of Mido-Kanpaku and Seimei&quot;</e>
<cmt>Kanpaku→Kampaku ヘボン式にしました。Kampaku→Kanpakuに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>藤原道長が可愛がっていた犬が、ある時主人の外出を止めようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One time, FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s beloved dog tried to stop his master from going outside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One time, FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s beloved dog tried to stop his master from going outside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One time, FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s beloved dog tried to stop his master from going outside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>驚いた道長が晴明に占わせると、晴明は式神の呪いがかけられそうになっていたのを犬が察知したのだと告げ、式神を使って呪いをかけた陰陽師を見つけ出して捕らえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surprised, Michinaga let Seimei take a divinatory reading, and Seimei said that he was about to be cursed with a Shikishin and that the dog noticed that, and he found the Ommyoji who used Shikishin to put a curse and arrested him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surprised, Michinaga let Seimei take a divinatory reading, and Seimei said that he was about to be cursed with a Shikishin and that the dog noticed that, and he found the Ommyoji who used Shikishin to put a curse and arrested him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surprised, Michinaga let Seimei take a divinatory reading, and Seimei said that he was about to be cursed with a Shikishin and that the dog noticed that, and he found the Ommyoji who used Shikishin to put a curse and arrested him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>『十訓抄』にも同様の記述あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same description can also be found in &quot;Jukkinsho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same description can also be found in &quot;Jukkinsho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same description can also be found in &quot;Jukkinsho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>近世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>文楽・歌舞伎 『蘆屋道満大内鑑』 （通称「葛の葉」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunraku and Kabuki, &quot;Ashiya-doman Ouchikagami&quot; (also known as &quot;Kuzu no Ha&quot; (Arrowroot Leaves))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunraku and Kabuki, &quot;Ashiya-doman Ouchikagami&quot; (also known as &quot;Kuzu no Ha&quot; (Arrowroot Leaves))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunraku and Kabuki, &quot;Ashiya-doman Ouchikagami&quot; (also known as &quot;Kuzu no Ha&quot; (Arrowroot Leaves))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>『蘆屋道満大内鑑』を始めとして、葛の葉伝承を題材とする作品には、多くの場合安倍晴明が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting with &quot;Ashiya-doman Ouchikagami&quot;, ABE no Seimei often appears in works that use the Legend of Arrowroot Leaves as their themes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting with &quot;Ashiya-doman Ouchikagami,&quot; ABE no Seimei often appears in works that use the Legend of Arrowroot Leaves as their themes.</e>
<cmt>コンマを&quot;&quot;内に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting with &quot;Ashiya-doman Ouchikagami,&quot; ABE no Seimei often appears in works that use the Legend of Arrowroot Leaves as their themes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>『蘆屋道満大内鑑』では、晴明は父、安倍保名と母、葛葉明神の化身である白狐との間に生まれた子供とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Ashiya-doman Ouchikagami&quot;, Seimei is set up as a child born between his father, ABE no Yasuna, and his mother, who was a white fox, that was an avatar of Kuzuha Myojin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Ashiya-doman Ouchikagami,&quot; Seimei is set up as a child born between his father, ABE no Yasuna, and his mother, who was a white fox, that was an avatar of Kuzuha Myojin.</e>
<cmt>コンマを&quot;&quot;内に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Ashiya-doman Ouchikagami,&quot; Seimei is set up as a child born between his father, ABE no Yasuna, and his mother, who was a white fox, that was an avatar of Kuzuha Myojin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>また晴明は最終的には清浄を意味する「清明」への改名を帝に願い出て聞き届けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seimei, in the end, requests the Emperor to change his name to &quot;Seimei&quot; which implies purity, and his request is granted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seimei (晴明), in the end, requests the Emperor to change his name to &quot;Seimei (清明)&quot; which implies purity, and his request is granted.</e>
<cmt>漢字を記載しなければ、原文の意味が伝わらないので漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seimei (晴明), in the end, requests the Emperor to change his name to &apos;Seimei (清明)&apos; which implies purity, and his request is granted.</e>
<cmt>原文の｢｣に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>葛の葉を題材とする作品を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to works that use the Arrowroot Leaves as their themes.</e>
<cmt>原文に「葛の葉」が２回繰り返されて書かれてます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to works that use the Arrowroot Leaves as their themes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to works that use the Arrowroot Leaves as their themes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Avanzare(id:34657), Kanejan(id:78613), Tommy6-bot(id:171289), Vini 175(id:164051), Nnh(id:474), MIsogi(id:20599), Hokuto-hei(id:68481), Ideal(id:236), Sheepech(id:111676), 三竹修二郎(id:88082), 春野秋葉(id:36725), Sutou(id:32), 石原充士(id:87840), Uraios(id:72687), KAWASAKI Hiroyuki(id:1514), Gombe(id:27), Ukyo(id:28757), Masyu(id:31065), A-Taul(id:41790), K-Phil(id:53114), 代言人(id:33675), Loveless(id:129239), 豊臣浩勝(id:96439), Bankokuya(id:91191), Japanese Boy(id:96234), 華宮 真白(id:108847), Kkkdc(id:32227), ととりん(id:31982), Stanislaus(id:1806), Hvn0413(id:38818), 水野白楓(id:22811), TS(id:481), Authority(id:10737), MIO(id:31681), 莞爾帝(id:37986), 黒百合紫(id:142439), Kamitani(id:30757), Rusk(id:9895), RoboDick(id:34097), 陳君(id:131566), GOAT(id:13684), Shouden(id:38327), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Mitty(id:36615), Ikedat76(id:34218), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), 西＠東(id:32113), Safkan(id:423), Junger(id:10282), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>