<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>英勝院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisho-in</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisho-in</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eishoin</e>
<cmt>指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>英勝院（えいしょういん、天正5年11月9日 (旧暦)（1578年12月7日） - 寛永19年8月23日 (旧暦)（1642年9月17日））は、徳川家康の側室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisho-in (December 7, 1578-September 17, 1642) was Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s Sokushitsu (concubine.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisho-in (December 7, 1578-September 17, 1642) was Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s Sokushitsu (concubine.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eishoin (December 17, 1578 - September 17, 1642) was Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s concubine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は里見氏の旧臣で太田道灌のひ孫にあたる太田康資とされる説と、江戸城代の遠山直景 (左衛門大夫)（遠山政景の子）とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are beliefs that his father was Yasusuke OTA who was the Satomi clan&apos;s old retainer and was a grandson of Dokan OTA, and his father was Naokage TOYAMA (Saemon no taifu) (Masakage TOYAMA&apos;s son,) the keeper of Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is belived that his father was Yasusuke OTA who was the Satomi clan&apos;s old retainer and was a grandson of Dokan OTA, and his father was Naokage TOYAMA (Saemon no taifu) (Masakage TOYAMA&apos;s son,) the keeper of Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that his father was Yasusuke OTA who was the Satomi clan&apos;s old retainer and was a grandson of Dokan OTA; and his father was Naokage TOYAMA (the Left Gate Watch, the son of Masakage TOYAMA,) the keeper of Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>常陸国の戦国大名で豊臣秀吉により支配地を失い、結城氏の元に身をよせていた江戸重通の娘が太田康資の養女になったという説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another belief that Yasusuke OTA adopted a daughter of Shigemichi EDO, Hitachi Province daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period who lost his territories in control because of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and was staying with the Yuki clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another belief that Yasusuke OTA adopted a daughter of Shigemichi EDO, Hitachi Province daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period who lost his territories in control because of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and was staying with the Yuki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another belief that Yasusuke OTA adopted a daughter of Shigemichi EDO, the territorial lord in the Warring States period in Hitachi Province, who lost his territories in control because of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and was staying with the Yuki clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>兄として太田重正があげられるが、重正は遠山氏の系図に含まれており（武家家伝の武蔵遠山氏参照）、父の死後その母方（遠山氏）で英勝院と兄妹のようにして育てられた可能性が考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemasa OTA was one of his older brothers, and is included in the Toyama clan&apos;s family trees (refer to the Musashi-Toyama clan in &quot;Record of Family Trees&quot;) and may have been raised on the mother side of his family (the Toyama clan) with Eisho-in after his father&apos;s death like as if the both had been a brother and sister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemasa OTA was one of his older brothers, and is included in the Toyama clan&apos;s family trees (refer to the Musashi-Toyama clan in &quot;Record of Family Trees&quot;) and may have been raised on the mother side of his family (the Toyama clan) with Eisho-in after his father&apos;s death like as if the both had been a brother and sister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemasa OTA was one of her elder brothers, who is included in the Toyama clan&apos;s family trees (refer to the Musashi-Toyama clan in &quot;Record of Family Trees&quot;) and may have been raised on the mother side of his family (the Toyama clan) with Eishoin after his father&apos;s death like as if the both had been a brother and sister.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>重正の母は、遠山綱景の娘の法性院（太田康資室）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigemasa&apos;s mother was Hossho-in (Yasusuke OTA&apos;s wife), a daughter of Tsunakage TOYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigemasa&apos;s mother was Hossho-in (Yasusuke OTA&apos;s wife), a daughter of Tsunakage TOYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigemasa&apos;s mother was Hosshoin (a wife of Yasusuke OTA), a daughter of Tsunakage TOYAMA.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>英勝院が重正の妹を称するのは、それほど早い時期ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time when Eisho-in identified herself as Shigemasa&apos;s younger sister was not so early.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The time when Eisho-in identified herself as Shigemasa&apos;s younger sister was not so early.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The time when Eishoin identified herself as Shigemasa&apos;s younger sister was not so much early.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>いずれにしても、前述の通り多くの説があり、その出自は定かなものとはされていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any case, there are several beliefs as mentioned before, and her origin (roots) is not considered certain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case her origin (roots) are not considered to be certain due to the multiple theories floating around as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case her origin are not considered to be certain due to the multiple theories are being around as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幼名は「於八」か。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her name in her childhood may be &apos;Ohatsu&apos; (於八.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her name in her childhood may have been &apos;Ohatsu&apos; (於八.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name during childhood may have been &apos;Ohatsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後に「梶」「（勝」、落飾後は「英勝院」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, she was called &apos;Okaru&apos; and &apos;Sho&apos; and after rakushoku (to take the tonsure and enter the priesthood,) she identified herself as &apos;Eisho-in.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「（勝」の”（”　は間違って付けた可能性があるので英訳では削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, she was called &apos;Okaru&apos; and &apos;Sho&apos; and after rakushoku (to take the tonsure and enter the priesthood,) she identified herself as &apos;Eisho-in.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, she was called &apos;Okaru&apos; and &apos;Sho&apos;, and after took the tonsure and enter the priesthood, she identified herself as &apos;Eishoin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>豊臣秀吉によって江戸に移封された徳川家康は積極的に関東の名門の末裔を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was transferred to Edo by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and was proactively engaged in recruiting the scions of old reputable families in Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was transferred to Edo by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and was proactively engaged in recruiting the scions of old reputable families in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was transferred to Edo by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and was proactively engaged in recruiting the descendants of old reputable families in Kanto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのなかに江戸城代であった遠山氏（道灌の流れを引く太田氏という説もある）も含まれており、早くに（13歳頃）家康に仕えたと考えられている（年齢的にも、最初から側室だったというのは推測の域を出ない。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The TOYAMA clan (according to another belief, it was the Ota clan who was connected with Dogan,) the keeper of Edo-jo Castle was included in such scions, and she is thought to have served for Ieyasu at her young age (around thirteen) (based on her age, it is a matter for speculation that she would have served Ieyasu as his concubine from the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The TOYAMA clan (according to another belief, it was the Ota clan who was connected with Dogan,) the keeper of Edo-jo Castle was included in such scions, and she is thought to have served for Ieyasu at her young age (around thirteen) (based on her age, it is a matter for speculation that she would have served Ieyasu as his concubine from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Toyama clan (according to another belief, it was the Ota clan who was connected with Dokan), who was the keeper of Edo-jo Castle, was included in the descendants, and she is thought to have served for Ieyasu at her young age (around thirteen) (based on her age, it is pure supposition that she would have served Ieyasu as his concubine from the beginning.)</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文・訳文に閉じ括弧を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>(少なくとも、女性官僚側室ではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At least, she was not a female office concubine.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At least, is is certain she was not a female office concubine.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is certain she was not at least a female office concubine).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文・訳文に開き括弧を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>同じ遠山氏（武蔵遠山氏はもとは明知遠山氏、遠山直景参照）で徳川譜代の旗本となっていた遠山利景（明知遠山）あるいはその兄とも一部で推測されている天海（同じ遠山氏の家紋を用いている）の推挙によるものともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that her serving for Ieyasu was recommended by Toshikage TOYAMA (the Akechi-Toyama) who was from the same Toyama clan (the Musashi-Toyama clan was originally the Akechi-Toyama clan; refer to Naokage TOYAMA.) and was Hatamoto (a direct vassal of the shogun) under Tokugawa Fudai (daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) or by Tenkai who was assumed to be her older brother (he used the same family crest as the one used by the Toyama clan) by some groups of people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that her serving for Ieyasu was recommended by Toshikage TOYAMA (the Akechi-Toyama) who was from the same Toyama clan (the Musashi-Toyama clan was originally the Akechi-Toyama clan; refer to Naokage TOYAMA.) and was Hatamoto (a direct vassal of the shogun) under Tokugawa Fudai (daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) or by Tenkai who was assumed to be her older brother (he used the same family crest as the one used by the Toyama clan) by some groups of people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say that her serving for Ieyasu was recommended by Toshikage TOYAMA (the Akechi-Toyama) who was from the same Toyama clan (the Musashi-Toyama clan was originally the Akechi-Toyama clan; refer to &quot;Naokage TOYAMA&quot;) and was a hereditary direct vassal to the Tokugawa shogunate, or by Tenkai who was assumed to be her older brother (he used the same family crest as that used by the Toyama clan).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「梶（八）」と呼ばれ、非常に聡明だったことから寵愛を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was called &apos;Okaru (Hatsu)&apos; and was so smart that she got affection from Ieyasu very much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was called &apos;Okaru (Hatsu)&apos; and her intelligence won Ieyasu&apos;s affection.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was called &apos;Okaru (Hatsu),&apos; and her intelligence won Ieyasu&apos;s affection.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。コンマの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一時松平正綱に嫁されていたが、すぐに家康の元に戻されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although she was married with Masatsuna MATSUDAIRA for a while, she was taken back to Ieyasu soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although she was married with Masatsuna MATSUDAIRA for a while, she was soon taken back to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although she was married to Masatsuna MATSUDAIRA for a while, she was soon taken back to Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>家康の子を懐妊していることがわかったからともいわれるが、推測の域を出ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the reason was because she was found to be pregnant with Ieyasu&apos;s child, but it is a matter for speculation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the reason was because she was found to be pregnant with Ieyasu&apos;s child, but this is a matter for speculation.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the reason was because she was found to be pregnant with Ieyasu&apos;s child, but this is pure supposition.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>慶長12年（1607年）1月に家康最後の子である6女市姫を30歳で産む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gave birth to the last sixth daughter of Ieyasu, Ichihime in January 1607 at the age of thirty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gave birth to the sixth and last daughter of Ieyasu, Ichihime in January 1607 at the age of thirty.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gave birth to the sixth and the last daughter of Ieyasu, Ichihime in January 1607, at the age of thirty.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>市姫は伊達政宗の嫡男・虎菊丸（のちの伊達忠宗）と婚約するが、4歳で夭折する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichihime was engaged with Toragikumaru (虎菊丸) (later, Tadamune DATE,) a son of Masamune DATE, but she died very young at the age of four.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichihime was engaged with Toragikumaru (虎菊丸) (later, Tadamune DATE,) a son of Masamune DATE, but she died very young at the age of four.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichihime was engaged with Toragikumaru (later, Tadamune DATE), a son of Masamune DATE, but she died very young at the age of four.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>不憫に思った家康は養珠院（万）の産んだ徳川頼房と結城秀康の次男である松平忠昌、外孫であった振姫（池田輝政の娘）らの養母とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu felt sorry for Okaru and arranged her to adopt Yorifusa TOKUGAWA who was born from Yojuin (Man,) Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA, the second son of Hideyasu YUKI and Furihime (a daughter of Terumasa IKEDA) who was Sotomago (a grandchild from a daughter married into another family.)</e>
<cmt>　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu felt sorry for Okaru and arranged her to adopt Yorifusa TOKUGAWA who was born from Yojuin (Man,) Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA, the second son of Hideyasu YUKI and Furihime (a daughter of Terumasa IKEDA) who was Sotomago (a grandchild from a daughter married into another family.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu felt sorry for Okaru and arranged her to adopt Yorifusa TOKUGAWA who was born from Yojuin (also known as Man), Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA, the second son of Hideyasu YUKI and Furihime (a daughter of Terumasa IKEDA) who was a grandchild from a daughter married into another family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>家康の死後は落飾して「英勝院」と称し、江戸田安の比丘尼屋敷に在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Ieyasu&apos;s death, she entered into priesthood and was called &apos;Eisho-in,&apos; and lived in Bikuni residence in Edo Tayasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Ieyasu&apos;s death, she entered into priesthood and was called &apos;Eisho-in,&apos; and lived in Bikuni residence in Edo Tayasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Ieyasu&apos;s death, she entered into priesthood and was called &apos;Eishoin,&apos; and lived in the female Buddhist disciple residence in Edo Tayasu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>のち寛永11年（1634年）に太田道灌の旧領で以前は屋敷のあった相模国鎌倉扇谷（神奈川県鎌倉市）の地を徳川家光より賜り、菩提所として英勝寺を建立して住持。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She got a piece of land located in Ogigayatsu, Kamakura, Sagami Province (Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture) from Iemitsu TOKUGAWA in 1634, that was Dogan OTA&apos;s old territory where his house existed before, and built Eisho-ji Temple there as a family temple and became the chief priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She recieved a piece of land located in Ogigayatsu, Kamakura, Sagami Province (Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture) from Iemitsu TOKUGAWA in 1634, that was Dogan OTA&apos;s old territory where his house existed before, and built Eisho-ji Temple there as a family temple and became the chief priest.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She received a piece of land located in Ogigayatsu, Kamakura, Sagami Province (Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture) from Iemitsu TOKUGAWA in 1634, that was Dokan OTA&apos;s old territory where his house existed before, and built Eisho-ji Temple there as a family temple and became the chief priest.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>65歳で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She died at the age of sixty five.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She died at the age of sixty five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She died at the age of 65.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>法号は英勝院殿長誉清春大禅定尼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Buddhist name was 英勝院殿長誉清春大禅定尼.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Buddhist name was 英勝院殿長誉清春大禅定尼.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her Buddhist name was Eishoinden Choyo Seishun Daizenjoni (英勝院殿長誉清春大禅定尼).</e>
<cmt>読みを補足しました（参考サイト：http://www2.ocn.ne.jp/~so-sweet/pedigree/eishoji/index.htm）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>墓所は英勝寺である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her grave is at Eisho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is at Eisho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her graveyard is at Eisho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>梶の聡明さを知らしめる逸話は数多く残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remain a lot of anecdotes telling how smart Okaru was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There remain many anecdotes which reminice on her intelligence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a lot of episodes which reminisce on her intelligence.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>後に創作され尾ひれがついたもの、あるいは他の側室の話と混同されているものなどあるが、いずれも家康がいかに寵愛していたかを証明するものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some anecdotes were created and exaggerated in later years, and others were mixed up with anecdotes related to other concubines, but they are all thought to prove how much Ieyasu loved her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some anecdotes were created and exaggerated in later years, and others were mixed up with anecdotes related to other concubines, but they are all thought to prove how much Ieyasu loved her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some episodes were created and exaggerated in later years, and others were mixed up with episodes related to other concubines, but they are all thought to prove how much Ieyasu loved her.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>うまいものも塩、まずいものも塩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What tastes good is salt and what tastes bad is salt, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What tastes good is salt and what tastes bad is salt, too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What Tastes Good Is Salt but What Tastes Bad Is Salt.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>家康が家臣たちを集めた時に突然「一番美味い食べ物とは何か」と尋ねた際に、他の者たちがそれぞれが答えをならべたのが、家康がそばで控えていた梶にも尋ねると、「それは塩です」と答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ieyasu abruptly asked his retainers in a gathering &apos;What is the most delicious food?,&apos; each of the retainers answered, and when he also asked Okaru who was attending by Ieyasu, she answered, &apos;It&apos;s salt.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ieyasu abruptly asked his retainers in a gathering &apos;What is the most delicious food?,&apos; each of the retainers answered, and when he also asked Okaru who was attending by Ieyasu, she answered, &apos;It&apos;s salt.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ieyasu abruptly asked his retainers at a party &apos;What is the most delicious food?,&apos; each of the retainers answered; then, Ieyasu also asked Okaru who was attending by Ieyasu, she answered, &apos;It&apos;s salt.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>「塩がなければ味を調えられません」という意外な理由に一同が感心した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As she said &apos;It is impossible to adjust the taste without salt,&apos; all the people got impressed with the unexpected reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As she said &apos;It is impossible to adjust the taste without salt,&apos; eveyone was impressed by her unexpected reasoning.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As she said &apos;It is impossible to adjust the taste without salt,&apos; everyone was impressed by her unique explanation.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>「では一番不味いものは何か」と梶に尋ねると、彼女は迷わずに「それも塩です。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he asked Okaru, &apos;What is the worst food?&apos;, she answered without hesitation, &apos;It&apos;s also salt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he asked Okaru, &apos;What is the worst food?&apos;, she answered without hesitation, &apos;It&apos;s also salt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he asked Okaru, &apos;What is the worst food?,&apos; without hesitation, she said &apos;It&apos;s also salt.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>どれほど美味しきものでも、塩を入れすぎれば食べられません」と答えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However delicious the food is, it can&apos;t be eaten with too much salt in it&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However delicious the food is, it can&apos;t be eaten with too much salt in it&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However delicious the food is, it is not good for eating with too much salt in it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>戦への同行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accompanying for wars</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accompanying Ieyasu during wartime</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accompanying Ieyasu during wartime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>梶は関ヶ原の戦いおよび大坂の役にも男装して騎馬にて同行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okaru accompanied Ieyasu on horseback wearing a male outfit at the time the Battle of Sekigahara and the Siege of Osaka broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okaru accompanied Ieyasu on horseback wearing a male outfit at the time the Battle of Sekigahara and the Siege of Osaka broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okaru in a male outfit went on horseback to accompany Ieyasu at the time the Battle of Sekigahara and the Siege of Osaka broke out.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>関ヶ原にて勝利した際にはそれを祝って「勝」と改名させたほどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he won the Battle of Sekigahara, he even made her to change her name to &apos;Sho (勝.)&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his victory at the Battle of Sekigahara, he even made her to change her name to &apos;Sho (勝.)&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his victory at the Battle of Sekigahara, Ieyasu even made her change her name to &apos;Sho (literally, victory).&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また、豊臣秀吉存命中に人質として大坂城に捕らわれたが、単独で脱出し騎馬にて家康の元に帰ったという逸話もあるが、これはさすがに創作であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote that when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was alive, Eisho-in who was held hostage in Osaka Castle got out of the castle without other people&apos;s support and went back to Ieyasu on horseback, but obviously, this will be a fiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote that when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was alive, Eisho-in who was held hostage in Osaka Castle got out of the castle without other people&apos;s support and went back to Ieyasu on horseback, but obviously, this will be a fiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an episode that when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was alive, Okaru who was held hostage in Osaka-jo Castle got out of the castle without other people&apos;s support and went back to Ieyasu on horseback, but obviously, this will be a fiction.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>倹約家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">frugal person</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">frugal person</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frugal Person</e>
<cmt>タイトル表記にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>梶が家康に寵愛された理由の一つに、その倹約家ぶりがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the reasons why Okaru got affection from Ieyasu was her economical lifestyle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the reasons why Okaru received Ieyasu&apos;s affection was her economical lifestyle.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the reasons why Okaru received Ieyasu&apos;s affection was her economical lifestyle.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>小袖をこまめに洗濯させて、新しいものを着ようとはしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosode (a kimono with short sleeves worn as underclothing by the upper classes) she used to wear was repeatedly washed and cleaned and she would hardly have put on a new one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosode (a kimono with short sleeves worn as underclothing by the upper classes) she used to wear was repeatedly washed and cleaned and she would hardly have put on a new one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A kimono with short sleeves she used to wear was repeatedly washed and cleaned, and she would hardly have put on a new one.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>倹約して富を蓄えることこそ大切であり、それは天下の人に施すため、また子々孫々まで国の富が不足しないようにするためであると日頃から言い含めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She regularly insisted that to save wealth was very important because it should be distributed to the people of the country and the saving would prevent country&apos;s wealth from running short through the generations of their offspring.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She regularly insisted that to save wealth was very important because it should be distributed to the people of the country and that this would prevent a country&apos;s wealth from running short through the generations of their offspring.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She regularly insisted that to save wealth was very important because it should be distributed to the people of the country, and that this would prevent a country&apos;s wealth from running short through the generations of their offspring.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>家康は駿府城の奥向きの大半を彼女に任せ、また金蔵の鍵すら預けていたとさえ伝えられるほどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the old anecdotes, Ieyasu entrusted her to manage the most part of the inner affairs of Sunpu Castle, including even allowing her to take a key of a cashbox.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to old anecdotes, Ieyasu entrusted her with the management of most of the inner affairs of Sunpu Castle, even allowing her to take a cashbox key.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to episodses, Ieyasu entrusted her with the management of most of the inner affairs of Sunpu-jo Castle, even leaving her a cashbox key.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>春日局との関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relation with Kasuga no Tsubone</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relation with Kasuga no Tsubone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relation with Kasuga no Tsubone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>春日局との関係では、駿府にいた家康に会わせ、家光が秀忠の後継となることを助けたという話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the relations with Kasuga no Tsubone, there is an anecdote that Eisho-in set up an occasion for Kasuga no Tsubone to meet Ieyasu who was staying in Sunpu to assist her in Iemitsu becoming a successor of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt>”英勝院が春日局を家康に会わせた”と理解して英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding her relations with Kasuga no Tsubone, there is an anecdote that Eisho-in set up an occasion for Kasuga no Tsubone to meet Ieyasu who was staying in Sunpu to assist her in Iemitsu becoming a successor of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding her relations with Kasuga no Tsubone, an episode states that Eishoin set up an occasion for Kasuga no Tsubone to meet Ieyasu who was staying in Sunpu to assist her in Iemitsu becoming a successor of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>家康没後において、女性官僚として春日局と並んで最上位を占めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Ieyasu&apos;s death, Eisho-in rose to the highest post of a female officer as well as Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Ieyasu&apos;s death, Eisho-in rose to the highest post of a female officer as well as Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Ieyasu&apos;s death, Eishoin reached the highest post of a female officer as well as Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>婚姻の際の籠の順序は英勝院が春日局より先であり、徳川内でいかに丁重に扱われていたかががわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the wedding ceremony, the order of the basket which carried Eisho-in was ahead of Kasuga no Tsubone&apos;s basket, which tells how politely and importantly Eisho-in was treated in the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the wedding ceremony, the order of the basket which carried Eisho-in was ahead of Kasuga no Tsubone&apos;s basket, which tells how politely and importantly Eisho-in was treated in the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the wedding ceremony, the basket which carried Eishoin was ahead of Kasuga no Tsubone&apos;s basket, which tells how politely and importantly Eishoin was treated in the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>太田氏中興の祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originator of restoration of the Ota clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originator of restoration of the Ota clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originator of the Restoration of the Ota Clan</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>梶は兄とされる重正の子である太田資宗を養子とし、譜代格として徳川秀忠に出仕させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okaru adopted Sukemune OTA, a son of Shigemasa who was believed to be her older brother, and arranged him to serve for Hidetada TOKUGAWA when he was in the rank of Fudai (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family.)</e>
<cmt>”譜代格として”をどのように英訳すればよいのか定かでありませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okaru adopted Sukemune OTA, a son of Shigemasa who was believed to be her older brother, and arranged him to serve for Hidetada TOKUGAWA when he was in the rank of Fudai (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okaru adopted Sukemune OTA, a son of Shigemasa, who was believed to be her older brother, and arranged him to serve for Hidetada TOKUGAWA as in the rank of a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>資宗は順調に出世し、徳川家光からの覚えも良く、六人衆（のちの若年寄）となり、さらには下野国山川藩15600石の藩主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukemune who had been smoothly promoted and favored by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA was assigned for Rokuninshu (later, Wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun))) and became a head of Yamakawa Domain, Shimotsuke Province which yielded 15,600 koku in rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukemune who had been smoothly promoted and favored by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA was assigned for Rokuninshu (later, Wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun))) and became a head of Yamakawa Domain, Shimotsuke Province which yielded 15,600 koku in rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukemune who had been favorably promoted and favored by Iemitsu TOKUGAWA was assigned for a managerial position in Edo bakufu initially called &apos;Rokuninshu&apos; later called &apos;Wakadoshiyori,&apos; and became a lord of the Yamakawa Domain, Shimotsuke Province which yielded 15,600 koku in rice.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。コンマの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>奏者番などを歴任し、最終的には遠江国浜松藩35000石まで登りつめ、子孫は幕府の要職を歴任し、老中も出し、明治維新後には子爵となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sukemune continued to take the posts of Sojaban (an official in charge of ceremonies,) etc., he finally rose to the head of Totoumi Domain, Hamamatsu Province which yielded 35,000 koku in rice, and his offspring continued to take important posts in the bakufu such as Roju (a member of shogun&apos;s council of elders) and became a viscount after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Sukemune continued to take the posts of Sojaban (an official in charge of ceremonies,) etc., he finally rose to the head of Totoumi Domain, Hamamatsu Province which yielded 35,000 koku in rice, and his offspring continued to take important posts in the bakufu such as Roju (a member of shogun&apos;s council of elders) and became a viscount after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Sukemune continued to take the posts including an official in charge of ceremonies, he finally rose to the lord of the Hamamatsu Domain, Totoumi Province which yielded 35,000 koku in rice, and his offspring continued to take important posts in the bakufu such as a member of shogun&apos;s council of elders and became a viscount after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>彼女は没落寸前であった太田氏を近世大名として、明治の世まで生き残らせたといえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that thanks to Eisho-in, the Ota clan which was about to die survived through the Meiji Period, being kinsei (early modern) daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that thanks to Eisho-in, the Ota clan which was about to die survived through the Meiji Period, being kinsei (early modern) daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that thanks to Eishoin, the Ota clan which was about to fall, survived through the Meiji period, being the early modern feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="47">
<j>英勝寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>英勝寺は神奈川県鎌倉市にある浄土宗の寺院で、山号は東光山。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eisho-ji Temple is a Jodo (Pure Land) sect temple in Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture and its Sango (temple&apos;s title) is Mt. Tokozan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eisho-ji Temple is a Jodo (Pure Land) sect temple in Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture and its Sango (temple&apos;s title) is Mt. Tokozan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eisho-ji Temple is a Jodo sect temple in Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture and its title prefixed to the temple name is Mt. Tokozan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>現在も鎌倉唯一の尼寺である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is still a sole nunnery temple in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is still a sole nunnery temple in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is still the only nunnery temple in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>徳川頼房や、徳川家光から庇護をうけ、はじめ玉峰清因（徳川頼房の娘小良姫）を門主に迎えて開基したこともあり、代々水戸徳川家の子女を門主に迎えていため、「水戸御殿」や「水戸の尼寺」ともいわれたいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The temple, which had been under the aegis of Yorifusa TOKUGAWA and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA and initially founded with 玉蜂清因 (Sarahime, a daughter of Yorifusa TOKUGAWA) in the post of chief priest, continued to invite daughters from Mito Tokugawa family for the chief priest post, and therefore it seemed to be called &apos;Mito Goten Palace&apos; or &apos;nunnery temple in Mito.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple, which had been under the aegis of Yorifusa TOKUGAWA and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA and initially founded with 玉蜂清因 (Sarahime, a daughter of Yorifusa TOKUGAWA) in the post of chief priest, continued to invite daughters from Mito Tokugawa family for the chief priest post, and therefore it seemed to be called &apos;Mito Goten Palace&apos; or &apos;nunnery temple in Mito.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple, which had been under the aegis of Yorifusa TOKUGAWA and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, and founded with Gyokuho Seiin (Sarahime, a daughter of Yorifusa TOKUGAWA) in the post of the chief priest, continued to invite daughters from Mito Tokugawa family for the chief priest post, which seemed to be why it called &apos;Mito Goten Palace&apos; or &apos;nunnery temple of Mito.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>仏殿、祠堂、唐門、鐘楼などには葵の紋が見られ、いずれも神奈川県指定の重要文化財に選定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family crest of Hollyhock is seen on Buddhist sanctum, Shidosen (money donated to a temple,) Kara-mon gate (Chinese-style gate) and Shoro (a bell tower) and all those items are Prefecture designated important cultural properties for Kanagawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family crest of Hollyhock is seen on Buddhist sanctum, Shidosen (money donated to a temple,) Kara-mon gate (Chinese-style gate) and Shoro (a bell tower) and all those items are Prefecture designated important cultural properties for Kanagawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest of Hollyhock is seen on the Buddhist sanctum, the hall dedicated to the souls of ancestors, the Chinese-style gate and the bell tower, all of which are Prefecture designated important cultural properties for Kanagawa Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 前田左衛門佐(id:194701), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Koon16000(id:43615), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Point136(id:211299), Kuma83(id:31177), Sorrysorry(id:102591), Choihei(id:122228), Jmho(id:10472), 彩華1226(id:64711), Jade0416(id:104181), CooZone(id:42589), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>