<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原家隆 (従二位)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Ietaka (Junii rank (Junior Second Rank))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Ietaka (Junii rank (Junior Second Rank))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Ietaka (Junii rank (Junior Second Rank))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 家隆（ふじわら の いえたか、保元3年（1158年） - 嘉禎3年4月9日 (旧暦)（1237年5月5日））は、鎌倉時代初期の公卿、歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Ietaka (1158-May 5, 1237) was the Kugyo (the top court official) and Kajin poet in early Kamakura era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Ietaka (1158-May 5, 1237) was a Kugyo (top court official) and Kajin poet in the early Kamakura era.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Ietaka (1158 - May 5, 1237) was a court noble and Kajin poet in the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Kamakura period としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>有職読みで「かりゅう」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called as &quot;Karyu&quot; under Yusoku-yomi (expression of respect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called &quot;Karyu,&quot; under Yusoku-yomi (an expression of respect).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called &apos;Karyu,&apos; under Yusoku-yomi (an expression of respect).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初名、顕隆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name he had at the beginning was Akitaka (顕隆).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His original name was Akitaka (顕隆).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His original name was Akitaka (顕隆).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法名、仏性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His homyo (Buddhist name) was Bussho (仏性).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His homyo (Buddhist name) was Bussho (仏性).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His homyo (Buddhist name) was Bussho (仏性).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>権中納言藤原光隆の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of FUJIWARA no Mitsutaka, who had a title of Gon no chunagon (Provisional Middle Councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ietaka was the son of FUJIWARA no Mitsutaka, who held the title of Gon no chunagon (Provisional Middle Councilor).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ietaka was the son of FUJIWARA no Mitsutaka, who held the title of Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>権中納言→Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原兼輔の末裔であり、紫式部の遠縁に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the descendant of FUJIWARA no Kanesuke and was distantly-related to Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a descendant of FUJIWARA no Kanesuke and a distant relative of Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a descendant of FUJIWARA no Kanesuke and a distant relative of Murasaki Shikibu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>『新古今和歌集』の撰者の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the senja (author) for &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Japanese Poems of Ancient and Modern Times).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the senja (authors) of &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Japanese Poems of Ancient and Modern Times).</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the senja (authors) of &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Japanese Poems of Ancient and Modern Times).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>安元元年（1175年）、叙爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1175: He went under Joshaku (conferred a peerage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1175: Joshaku (conferred a peerage).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1175, he was conferred a peerage.</e>
<cmt>文章での表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1177年、侍従。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1177: He became a Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1177: Became a Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1177, he became a Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>文章での表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>各国の国司を併任し、建久4年（1193年）正月、侍従を辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held an additional post as Kokushi (lord) of each province and retired from Jiju position in January 1193.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 1193: Assigned additional post as Kokushi (provincial lord) and retired from Jiju position.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1193, he was assigned additional post as Kokushi (provincial lord) in various provinces and retired from Jiju position.</e>
<cmt>各国の　を追加しました。グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>正治3年（1201年）正月、従四位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 1201: He became a Jushii no ge rank (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 1201: Attained Jushii no ge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1201, he was promoted to Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt>Jushii としました。グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>元久3年（1206年）、宮内省律令制度下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1206: He became the Kunaisho (the Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) under the Ritsuryo Ranks and Position.</e>
<cmt>宮内省→Kunaisho(the Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household)[http://forums.samurai-archives.com/viewtopic.php?t=3397]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1206: Became a member of the Kunaisho (the Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) under the Ritsuryo Ranks and Position.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1206, he was appointed as Kunaikyo (Minister of the Sovereign&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>原文のwikiを参照し、「宮内省律令制度下」の部分が「宮内卿」とありましたので、左記のようにいたしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>承久3年（1220年）まで宮内卿を務め、止めたのちに正三位に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as Kunaikyo until 1220 and was given Jo rank of Shosanmi rank (Senior Third Rank) once retired from that position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ietaka served as Kunaikyo until 1220, and once retired from that position was given the Jo rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>word order, rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ietaka served as Kunaikyo until 1220, and once retired from that position, he was given the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>嘉禎元年（1235年）、参議従二位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1235: He became the Sangi (Consultant) with a Junii rank (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1235: Became a Sangi (Consultant) with a rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1235, he became a Sangi (councilor) with a rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>参議→Sangi (councilor)　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1237年、病を得て79歳で出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1237: He fell ill and became a priest at 79.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1237: Fell ill and became a priest at 79.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1237, he fell ill and became a priest at the age of 79.</e>
<cmt>文章での表現にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>出家後は摂津国四天王寺に入り、夕陽丘より見える「ちぬの海（大阪湾）」に沈む夕日を好み、その彼方にある極楽へいくことを望んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He entered the Shitenno-ji Temple of Settsu no kuni (Settsu Province) and liked the sunset above &quot;Chinu no umi (Osaka Bay)&quot; seen from Yuhigaoka and wished to travel to Gokuraku (Land of Ultimate Bliss) beyond that place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ietake entered the Shitenno-ji Temple of Settsu no kuni (Settsu Province) and liked the sunset view above &quot;Chinu no umi (Osaka Bay)&quot; as seen from Yuhigaoka and wished to travel beyond there to Gokuraku (Land of Ultimate Bliss).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ietake entered the Shitenno-ji Temple of Settsu Province and liked the sunset view above &apos;Chinu no umi (Osaka Bay)&apos; as seen from Yuhigaoka and wished to travel beyond there to Gokuraku (Land of Ultimate Bliss).</e>
<cmt>Settsu Province としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>現在、大阪市天王寺区夕陽丘町5に家隆塚（伝藤原家隆墓）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a tumulus of Ietaka in 5 Yuhigaoka-cho, Tennoji-ku, Osaka City (allegedly a tomb of FUJIWARA no Ietada) present day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the present day, there is a tumulus of Ietaka in 5 Yuhigaoka-cho, Tennoji-ku, Osaka City (allegedly the tomb of FUJIWARA no Ietaka).</e>
<cmt>word order, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the present day, there is a tumulus of Ietaka in 5 Yuhigaoka-cho, Tennoji-ku, Osaka City (allegedly the tomb of FUJIWARA no Ietaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>和歌を藤原俊成に学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He learned Waka (Japanese poem) under FUJWIARA no Toshinari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned Waka (Japanese poetry) under FUJWIARA no Toshinari.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned Waka (Japanese poetry) under FUJIWARA no Toshinari.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA　と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>寂蓮の婿だったという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a theory that he was the groom of Jakuren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a theory that he was the groom of Jakuren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a theory that he was the groom of Jakuren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>歌人としては、晩成型であったが、『六百番歌合』、『正治百首』などに参加して、やがて藤原定家と並び称される歌人として評価されるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded late for a Kajin poet, but he participated in &quot;Ropyakuban Utaawase&quot; and &quot;Shoji-Hyakushu&quot; and became a Kajin poet reputated to be the one that stood on equal grounds as FUJIWARA no Teika (Sadaie).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded late for a Kajin poet, but he participated in &quot;Ropyakuban Utaawase&quot; and &quot;Shoji-Hyakushu&quot; and gained a reputaiton as a Kajin poet standing on equal ground with FUJIWARA no Teika (Sadaie).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded late for a Kajin poet, but he participated in &quot;Roppyakuban utaawase&quot; (The Poetry Match in 600 Rounds) and &quot;Shoji Hyakushu&quot; (Hundred-Poem Sequence of the Shoji Era) and gained a reputation as a Kajin poet standing on equal ground with FUJIWARA no Teika (Sadaie).</e>
<cmt>歌集の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>承久の乱で隠岐に流された後鳥羽天皇を慰めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He comforted Emperor Gotoba who was exiled to Oki from Jokyu no ran (Rebellion of Jokyu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ietaka gave comfort to Emperor Gotoba, who was exiled to Oki from Jokyu no ran (Rebellion of Jokyu).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ietaka gave comfort to Emperor Gotoba, who was exiled to Oki in the Jokyu War.</e>
<cmt>Jokyu War　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>歌風は平明で幽寂な趣きと評価される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His poetic style was pointed out as transpicuous and Yujaku (solitude).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His poetic style has been characterized as transparent and reflecting on the theme of Yujaku (solitude).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His poetic style has been characterized as transpicuous and reflecting on the theme of Yujaku (solitude).</e>
<cmt>平明→transpicuous　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>『新勅撰和歌集』には、最高の35首が収められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirty five of his best poems were collected within &quot;Shin Chokusen Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirty-five of his best poems were collected within &quot;Shin Chokusen Wakashu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirty-five of his best poems were collected within &quot;Shin chokusen wakashu&quot; (New Imperial Anthology of Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>歌集の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>歌集の『壬二集（みにしゅう）』は六家集の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kashu (Collection of Japanese poems) called &quot;Minishu&quot; was one of the Rokkashu (the six great Kashu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kashu (Collection of Japanese poems) called &quot;Minishu&quot; was one of the Rokkashu (the six great Kashu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kashu (Collection of Japanese poems) called &quot;Minishu&quot; was one of the Rokkashu (the six great Kashu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>息子の藤原隆祐と娘の承明門院小宰相も歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son, FUJIWARA no Takasue and daughter, Kozaisho, who had a title of Shomeimonin, were also Kajin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son, FUJIWARA no Takasue, and daughter, Kozaisho, who had the title of Shomeimonin, were also Kajin.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son, FUJIWARA no Takasuke, and daughter, Kozaisho, who had the title of Shomeimonin, were also Kajin.</e>
<cmt>Takasuke に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Lonicera(id:20638), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 翠碧晶(id:68524), Ks8823(id:130146), Kaustuv(id:64800), MIsogi(id:20599), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), Andee(id:20421), Aphaia(id:3132), 葉月(id:25674), Yuming(id:17854), Hatsune(id:26654), さららゆら(id:12274), Kenpei(id:11349), 代言人(id:33675), Point136(id:211299), Yas(id:739), 伏儀(id:142093), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>