<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>巴御前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoe Gozen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoe Gozen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lady Tomoe</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>巴御前（ともえごぜん／ともゑごぜん、生没年不詳）は、平安時代末期の信濃国の武将とされる女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoe Gozen (years of birth and death not known) was a women who is deemed a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Shinano Province who lived the last days of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoe Gozen (years of birth and death not known) was a women who is deemed a busho (Japanese military commander) of the Shinano Province who lived during the last days of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lady Tomoe (years of birth and death not known) was a lady who was deemed a military commander in the Shinano Province and lived during the last days of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>字は鞆、鞆絵とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her name is sometimes expressed with characters &quot;鞆&quot; or &quot;鞆絵.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her name is sometimes expressed with characters &quot;鞆&quot; or &quot;鞆絵.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name Tomoe (巴) is sometimes expressed with the characters &quot;鞆&quot; or &quot;鞆絵.&quot;</e>
<cmt>漢字の違いを表すために、漢字を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>信濃国の豪族・中原兼遠（中三権頭）の娘で、源義仲の愛妾。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a daughter of Kaneto NAKAHARA (Chuza gon no kami), who was the gozoku (local ruling family) in the Shinano Province and a MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka&apos;s favorite concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a daughter of Kaneto NAKAHARA (Chuza gon no kami), who was the gozoku (local ruling family) in the Shinano Province and MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka&apos;s favorite concubine.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a daughter of Kaneto NAKAHARA (Chuza gon no kami), who was a local ruling family in the Shinano Province, and MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka&apos;s favorite concubine.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>樋口兼光・今井兼平の妹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was a younger sister of Kanemitsu HIGUCHI and Kanehira IMAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was a younger sister of Kanemitsu HIGUCHI and Kanehira IMAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was a younger sister of Kanemitsu HIGUCHI and Kanehira IMAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>軍記物語である『平家物語』で「木曾最期」の章段だけに登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), which is a war chronicle, she appears in the chapter of &quot;Kiso no saigo&quot; (The Death of Kiso).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), which is a war chronicle, she appears in the chapter of &quot;Kiso no saigo&quot; (The Death of Kiso).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the war chronicle titled &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;, she appears in the chapter of &apos;Kiso no saigo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>義仲四天王とともに義仲の平氏討伐に従軍し、治承・寿永の乱で戦う大刀と強弓の女武者として描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was described as a female warrior with a long sword and a strong bow who, together with Yoshinaka shitenno (four most loyal retainers of Yoshinaka, she joined Yoshinaka&apos;s subjugation of the Taira family and fought in the Jisho-Juei War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was described as a female warrior with a long sword and a strong bow who, together with Yoshinaka shitenno (four most loyal retainers of Yoshinaka, joined Yoshinaka&apos;s subjugation of the Taira family and fought in the Jisho-Juei War.</e>
<cmt>She was described as a female warrior with a long sword and a strong bow who, together with Yoshinaka shitenno (four most loyal retainers of Yoshinaka, joined Yoshinaka&apos;s subjugation of the Taira family and fought in the Jisho-Juei War).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was described as a female warrior fighting with a long sword and a strong bow who, together with Yoshinaka shitenno (the four most loyal retainers to Yoshinaka), joined Yoshinaka&apos;s subjugation of the Taira family and fought in the Jisho-Juei War.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「木曾殿は信濃国より､巴・山吹とて､二人の便女 を具せられたり。山吹はいたはりあって､都にとどまりぬ。中にも巴は色白く髪長く､容顔まことに優れたり。強弓精兵、一人当千の兵者（つわもの）なり」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described as &quot;Kiso-dono brought two binjo (beautiful maid) named Tomoe and Yamabuki form the Shinano Province. For consolation purpose, Yamabuki stayed in the capital. In particular, Tomoe is fair-skinned and has long hairs and she was really beautiful. Shi is a very strong warrior and a match for a thousand.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置三つの文を一緒にし、ふたつに再分割しました。(引用箇所に脱落があるおそれがあります。)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described as &quot;Kiso-dono brought two binjo (beautiful maid) named Tomoe and Yamabuki form the Shinano Province. For consolation purpose, Yamabuki stayed in the capital. In particular, Tomoe was fair-skinned and had long hairs and was very beautiful. She was very strong and could match a thousand warriors.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chronicle describes &apos;Kiso-dono brought two beautiful maids named Tomoe and Yamabuki from the Shinano Province. For some reasons, Yamabuki stayed in the capital. In particular, Tomoe was fair-skinned and had long hair and was very beautiful. She was very strong, having the strength of a thousand warriors.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、宇治川の戦いで敗れ落ち延びる義仲に従い、最後の七騎、五騎になっても討たれなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also told that she followed Yoshinaka, who was defeated in the Ujigawa War and tried to run away and she was not killed even the total number of the party decreased to seven or five.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置三つの文を一緒にし、ふたつに再分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also told that she followed Yoshinaka, who was defeated in the Ujigawa War and tried to run away. and was not killed even though the total number of men remaining were 5 or 7.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that when she followed Yoshinaka, who Yoshinaka was defeated in the Battle of Uji-gawa River and tried to run away, she was not killed even though only five to seven men remained.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>義仲は「お前は女であるからどこへでも逃れて行け。自分は討ち死にする覚悟だから、最後に女を連れていたなどと言われるのはよろしくない」と巴を落ち延びさせようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka tried to let Tomoe run away by telling her, &quot;Since you are a women, run away to any place. I have made my mind to fight and die. It is not good that I have a women with me to the last. &quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka tried to let Tomoe run away by telling her, &quot;Since you are a women, run away to any place. I have made my mind to fight and die. It is not good that I have a woman with me to the last. &quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka tried to let Tomoe run away by telling her, &apos;Since you are a woman, run away anywhere you can. I have made my mind to fight and die. It is not good that I have a woman by my side to the last.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>巴はなおも落ちようとしなかったが、再三言われたので「最後のいくさしてみせ奉らん（最後の奉公でございます）」と言い、大力と評判の敵将が現れると、馬を押し並べて引き落とし、首をねじ切って捨てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoe did not agree to run away, but as she was ordered repeatedly, she said &quot;This is my last service.&quot; and, when an enemy general who was famous for his strong power, appeared she placed horses side by side and brought down him and wrenched off his neck and threw the head away..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoe did not agree to run away, but as she was ordered repeatedly, she said &quot;This is my last service.&quot; and, when an enemy general who was famous for his strength appeared she placed horses side by side and brought him down, wrenching his neck off and threw the head away..</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoe did not agree to the Yoshinaka&apos;s order, but as she was ordered repeatedly, she said, &apos;This is my last service.&apos; and when the enemy general who was famous for his strength appeared, she rode her hose side by side with the general&apos;s horse and brought him down, wrenching his neck off and throwing the head away.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後巴は鎧・甲を脱ぎ捨てて東国の方へ落ち延びた所で物語から姿を消す（覚一本）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Tomoe too off her armor and helmet and ran away toward the eastern country and disappears from the story (Kakuichi-bon text).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Tomoe too off her armor and helmet and ran away toward the eastern country and disappears from the story (Kakuichi-bon text).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Tomoe took off her armor and helmet and ran away toward the eastern country and disappeared from the tale (Kakuichi-bon text).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>八坂本では、巴を追ってきた敵将を返り討ちにした後、義仲に落ちるように言われ、後世を弔うことが最後の奉公であると諭されて東へ向かい行方知れずとなったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yasaka-bon text, after Tomoe killed an enemy general who chased after her, she was told by Yoshinaka to run away and convinced that the last service should be to moan, and she moved to the east and she was lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yasaka-bon text, after Tomoe killed an enemy general who chased after her, she was told by Yoshinaka to run away and convinced that the last service should be to moan, and she moved to the east and she was lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Yasaka-bon text, after Tomoe killed an enemy general who had chased after her, she was told by Yoshinaka to run away and convinced that her last service should be to mourn him, and she headed eastward and she was lost.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>『源平盛衰記』では、倶利伽羅峠の戦いにも大将の一人として登場し、この時28歳としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans), she appeared in the Battle of the Kurikara Pass as one of generals and it was said that she was twenty-eight years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans), she appeared in the Battle of the Kurikara Pass as one of generals and it was said that she was twenty-eight years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot;, she appeared in the Battle of the Kurikara Pass as one of generals, and it was said that she was twenty-eight years old at that time.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>宇治川の戦いでは畠山重忠との戦いも描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to the Battle of Uji-gawa River, the battle with Shigetada HATAKEYAMA is described.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to the Battle of Uji-gawa River, the battle with Shigetada HATAKEYAMA is described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the scenes of the Battle of Uji-gawa River, the battle against Shigetada HATAKEYAMA is described.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>半沢六郎は、重忠に巴が何者か問われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuro HANZAWA was asked by Shigetada what Tomoe was.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuro HANZAWA was asked by Shigetada what Tomoe was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuro HANZAWA was asked by Shigetada who was Tomoe.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「木曽殿の御乳母に、中三権頭が娘巴といふ女なり。強弓の手練れ、荒馬乗りの上手。乳母子ながら妾（おもひもの）にして、内には童を仕ふ様にもてなし、軍には一方の大将軍して、更に不覚の名を取らず。今井・樋口と兄弟にて、怖ろしき者にて候」と答えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He replied, &quot;She is a daughter between the wet nurse of Kiso-dono and Chuza gon no kami and called Tomoe. She is good at using a strong bow and taming a wild horse. Although she is a daughter of the wet nurse, she is a concubine, and she entertain him like a boy at home and, in the army, she if a general and she has never been defeated. She is a sister of IMAI and HIGUCHI and she is a terrible person.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He replied, &quot;She is a daughter between the wet nurse of Kiso-dono and Chuza gon no kami and called Tomoe. She is good at using a strong bow and taming a wild horse. Although she is a daughter of the wet nurse, she is a concubine, and she entertains him like a boy at home and, in the army, she is a general and she has never been defeated. She is a sister of IMAI and HIGUCHI and she is a terrible person.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He replied, &apos;She is a daughter between the wet nurse of Kiso-dono and Chuza gon no kami and called Tomoe. She is good at using a strong bow and taming a wild horse. Although she is a daughter of the wet nurse, she became a concubine, and she entertains him like entertaining a boy at home and, in the army, she is a commander in chief and she has never been defeated. She is a sister of IMAI and HIGUCHI and she is a terrible person.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>敵将との組合いや義仲との別れがより詳しく描写されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Struggling with an enemy general and farewell with Yoshinaka were described in more details.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Struggling with an enemy general and the farewell with Yoshinaka were described in more details.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot;, her struggling with an enemy general and farewell to Yoshinaka were described in more details.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>落ち延びた後に頼朝から鎌倉へ召され、和田義盛の妻となって朝比奈義秀 を生み、和田合戦ののち出家して主・親・子の菩提を弔い、91歳で生涯を終えたという後日談が語られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the later development that, after having run away, she was called by Yoritomo to Kamakura and married Yoshimori WADA and gave birth of Yoshihide ASAHINA, and that, after Wada gassen (battle of Wada), he became a priestess and mourned her master, parents and child and died at the age of ninety-one.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, after having run away, she was called by Yoritomo to Kamakura and married Yoshimori WADA and gave birth to Yoshihide ASAHINA, and after Wada gassen (battle of Wada), he became a priestess and mourned her master, parents and child and died at the age of ninety-one.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having run away, she was called by Yoritomo to Kamakura and married Yoshimori WADA, giving birth to Yoshihide ASAHINA, and after the battle of Wada, she became a priestess and mourned her master, parents and child and died at the age of ninety-one.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>海音寺潮五郎は金刺氏の持ち城に山吹城という城があることから、巴と山吹は義仲の支持勢力である中原氏と金刺氏が一族の中でも優秀な娘を副官・秘書官として派遣したと推察している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Kanasashi clan had a castle called Yamabuki-jo castle, Chogoro KAIONJI surmised that Tomoe and Yamabuki were dispatched as aides-de-camp or secretaries by the Nakahara clan and Kanasashi clan, who were supporters of Yoshinaka, choosing capable daughters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Kanasashi clan had a castle called Yamabuki-jo castle, Chogoro KAIONJI surmised that Tomoe and Yamabuki were dispatched as aides-de-camp or secretaries by the Nakahara clan and Kanasashi clan, who were supporters of Yoshinaka, choosing capable daughters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Kanasashi clan had a castle called Yamabuki-jo Castle, Chogoro KAIONJI surmised that Tomoe and Yamabuki were dispatched as aides-de-camp or secretaries by the Nakahara clan and Kanasashi clan, who were supporters of Yoshinaka, choosing capable daughters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>女武将であるという『平家物語』や『源平盛衰記』の記述は史実としては疑問があり、文学的脚色である可能性も高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The description in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; and &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; that she was a busho is doubtful as a historical fact and the possibility that it is a literary fiction is high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The description in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; and &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; that she was a busho is doubtful as a historical fact and the possibility that it is literary fiction is high.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The description in &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; and &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; that she was a military commander is doubtful as a historical fact and it is highly possible that it is literary fiction.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ただし、鎌倉幕府の公式記録である『吾妻鏡』に越後の城氏の一族である坂額御前の健闘により討伐軍に大被害が生じたとの記事がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), which is the official record of the Kamakura shogunate, has an article that, brave and good fight of Hangaku Gozen, who was a family member of the Jo clan in Echigo, caused the punitive force serious damages.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), which is the official record of the Kamakura shogunate, has an article that, brave and good fight of Hangaku Gozen, who was a family member of the Jo clan in Echigo, caused the punitive force serious damages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot;, which is the official record of the Kamakura shogunate, has an article that, brave and good fight of Hangaku Gozen, who was a family member of the Jo clan in Echigo, caused the punitive force serious damages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>なおかつ戦後に彼女が結婚した甲斐源氏の浅利義遠もその強さに惚れ込んで求婚しているため、当時の甲信越地方の武士の家庭では女性も第一線級として通用する戦闘訓練を受けている例があることは事実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, as Yoshito ASARI of Kai-Genji (Minamoto clan) with whom she married after the war proposed her because of her braveness, it is a fact that, in samurai&apos;s family in Koshinetsu district at that time, there is an example that even women were received a training for fighting that was sufficient to fight the top class warrior.,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, as Yoshito ASARI of Kai-Genji (Minamoto clan) with whom she married after the war proposed to her because of her braveness, it is a fact that, in samurai&apos;s family in Koshinetsu district at that time, there is an example that even women were received a training for fighting that was sufficient to fight the top class warrior.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, as Yoshito ASARI of Kai-Genji (Minamoto clan) with whom she married after the war had proposed to her because of her braveness, it is a fact that, in a samurai&apos;s family in Koshinetsu district at that time, there existed examples of women receiving training that would allow them to stand toe-to-toe with top class warriors.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>神奈川県横須賀市、長野県木曽郡木曽町、新潟県上越市など各地に巴御前の墓とされるものが現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There actually exist graves that are said to be Tomoe Gozen&apos;s grave in various places such as Yokosuka City in Kanagawa Prefecture, Kiso Town in Kiso County in Nagano Prefecture and Joetsu City in Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There actually exist graves that are said to be Tomoe Gozen&apos;s grave in various places such as Yokosuka City in Kanagawa Prefecture, Kiso Town in Kiso County in Nagano Prefecture and Joetsu City in Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There actually exist graves that are said to be Tomoe Gozen&apos;s grave in various places such as Yokosuka City in Kanagawa Prefecture, Kiso-cho, Kiso-gun in Nagano Prefecture and Joetsu City in Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 PC-777(id:109818), Los688(id:12316), Bakkai(id:7233), Tomzo(id:16777), Suguri F(id:11127), Zen(id:9573), アイザール(id:133157), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Charenji(id:7908), PixelBot(id:166734), PATMAN(id:145791), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), ふたりはGoki鰤MaxHeart(id:19635), 味っ子(id:17086), Ash Crow(id:26765), 小者(id:172526), Luna plena(id:23904), Hatsune(id:26654), でここ(id:9565), Sakura minami 8080(id:244567), A6M4(id:14155), 由布(id:209183), ゐ(id:795), Isepo(id:14382), Kinori(id:443), 代言人(id:33675), R28Bot(id:177951), 福太郎(id:132415), Point136(id:211299), SPQR(id:39044), Hoistsail(id:149433), Sakura2008(id:182339), 豊田充(id:58694), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>