<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今川氏親</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujichika IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujichika IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujichika IMAGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>今川 氏親（いまがわ うじちか）は戦国時代の武将・守護大名・戦国大名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujichika IMAGAWA was a warlord and provincial military governor in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>「武将・守護大名・戦国大名」→合わせて&quot;a warlord and provincial military governor&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujichika IMAGAWA was a warlord and provincial military governor in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujichika IMAGAWA was a warlord, Shugo Daimyo (Provincial Daimyo), and Sengoku Daimyo (Daimyo in Sengoku period) in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>「武将・守護大名・戦国大名」を原文通り分けて訳出しました。(後列でも守護大名と戦国大名の両方の記載が出てくることも考慮しました。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real family name was Minamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real family name was Minamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real family name was Minamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家系は清和源氏の一家系　河内源氏の棟梁　鎮守府将軍源義家の子　源義国を祖とする足利氏の一門　吉良氏の庶家　今川氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Imagawa clan, which was a branch family of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan originated from the Emperor Seiwa), the head family of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan based in Kawachi Province), a relative family of the Ashikaga clan originated from MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni who was a son of Chinju-fu Shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, and a branch family of the Kira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He descended from the line of Seiwa-Genji, the head family of the Kawachi-Genji clan, which was in turn a cadet family of the Ashikaga clan,the latter being a descendant of Minamoto no Yoshikuni, son of Chinju-fu Shogun (Commander-in-chief of the Defense of the North), Minamoto no Yoshie. The Kira clan came next in line followed by his clan, the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>This sentence is quite difficult to put in one sentence as it is a bit confusing.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the Imagawa clan, a branch family of the Kira clan which was a cadet family of the Ashikaga clan whose ancestor was MINAMOTO no Yoshikuni, a son of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie who was Chinju-fu Shogun (Commander-in-Chief of the Defense of the North) and the head of the Kawachi-Genji clan (Minamoto clan), a branch family of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>「清和源氏の一家系」、「足利市の一門吉良氏の庶家」のかかりうけが異なっていたため全体を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>駿河国今川氏7代当主である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the seventh head of the Imagawa clan in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the seventh head of the Imagawa clan in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the seventh head of the Imagawa clan in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>駿河守護。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo (military governor) of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as Shugo (military governor) for Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>sentence necesssary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as Shugo (military governor) for Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>官位は従四位修理大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His court rank was Jushii Shuri no Daibu (Junior Fourth Rank, Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His court rank was Jushii Shuri no Daibu (Junior Fourth Rank, Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His court rank was Jushii Shuri no Daibu (Junior Fourth Rank, Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>父は今川義忠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Yoshitada IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Yoshitada IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Yoshitada IMAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>出生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>父の駿河国守護義忠が応仁の乱で東軍に味方して上洛していたときに、母の北川殿と結婚したと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father Shugo of Suruga Province Yoshitada seems to have married his mother Kitagawa-dono, when he was in Kyoto joining the Eastern Army during the Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father Yoshitada, Shugo of Suruga Province, is believed to have married his mother, Kitagawa-dono, when he joined forces with the Eastern Army in Kyoto during the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father Yoshitada, Shugo of Suruga Province, is believed to have married his mother, Kitagawa-dono, when he joined forces with the Eastern Army in Kyoto during the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>北川殿は伊勢新九郎盛時（北条早雲）の姉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitagawa-dono was an older sister of Shinkuro Moritoki ISE (Soun HOJO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitagawa-dono was the older sister of Shinkuro Moritoki ISE (also known as Soun HOJO).</e>
<cmt>&quot;The&quot; is better than &quot;an&quot; and I put &quot;also known as to make it clear that Soun HOJO is a name.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitagawa-dono was the older sister of Shinkuro Moritoki ISE (also known as Soun HOJO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>伊勢新九郎が素浪人と考えられていた頃は側室とされていたが、近年の研究で室町幕府政所執事の名門伊勢氏の一族であることがほぼ明らかになっており、北川殿は正室だったと考えられてる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was considered as a concubine when Shinkuro ISE was considered to have been a mere masterless samurai, but recent studies have almost confirmed that he was from the Ise clan, a distinguished family holding the position of head of Mandokoro (Administrative Board) of the Muromachi shogunate, and thus she has come to be considered as lawful wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was considered a concubine when Shinkuro ISE was thought to have been a mere masterless samurai, but recent studies have almost confirmed that he was from the Ise clan, a distinguished family who was head of the Muromachi shogunate&apos;s Administrative Board, and thus she has come to be considered a lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think it is necessary to include the Japanese Mandokoro as it makes the sentence sound awkward.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was considered a concubine when Shinkuro ISE was thought to have been a mere masterless samurai, but recent studies have almost confirmed that he was from the Ise clan, a distinguished family who was the head of the Muromachi shogunate&apos;s Administrative Board, and thus she has come to be considered a lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>head of → the head of</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>文明5年（1473年）（文明3年（1471年）とも）に北川殿の子として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujichika was born in 1473 (1471 according to another theory) as a son of Kitagawa-dono.</e>
<cmt>主語（Ujichika）を補足して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujichika was born the son of Kitagawa-dono in 1473 (1471 according to another theory).</e>
<cmt>more natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujichika was born the son of Kitagawa-dono in 1473 (1471 according to another theory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>幼名は龍王丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Ryuo-maru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Ryuo-maru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Tatsuo-maru.</e>
<cmt>Ryuo-maru → Tatsuo-maru</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>北川殿の弟（兄とも）が後の北条早雲であったことが、氏親の生涯に大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The life of Ujichika was greatly influenced by the fact that a younger brother (older brother according to another theory) of Kitagawa-dono was later Soun HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujichika&apos;s life was greatly influenced by the fact that Kitagawa-dono&apos;s younger brother (older brother according to another theory) would later become Soun HOJO.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujichika&apos;s life was greatly influenced by the fact that Kitagawa-dono&apos;s younger brother (older brother according to another theory) would later become Soun HOJO.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>家督争い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succession Dispute</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succession Dispute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succession Dispute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>文明8年（1476年）に父義忠が遠江国で一揆に襲われ戦死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1476, his father Yoshitada was killed by rebels in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1476, his father Yoshitada was killed by rebels in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1476, his father Yoshitada was attacked and killed during riots in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>killed by rebels → attacked and killed during riots</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>龍王丸はまだ幼少だったため、家臣の三浦氏、朝比奈氏らが一族の小鹿範満（義忠の従兄弟）を擁立してお家騒動が起こり、龍王丸派と範満派が分かれて数度の合戦に及ぶ事態になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Ryuo-maru was very young then, vassals including the Miura clan and Asahina clan supported relative Norimitsu OSHIKA (cousin of Yoshitada), and it led to a succession dispute, causing several battles between Ryuo-maru party and Norimitsu party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Ryuo-maru was very young then, vassals from the Miura clan and Asahina clan supported relative Norimitsu OSHIKA (cousin of Yoshitada) as successor, and this led to a succession dispute involving several battles between the Ryuo-maru faction and the Norimitsu faction.</e>
<cmt>I think it is necessary to state clearly what the asahina clan&apos;s support was for, ahead of mentioning &quot;sucession dispute&quot;. Also, &quot;faction&quot; is better than party.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Tatsuo-maru was very young then, vassals from the Miura clan and Asahina clan supported relative Norimitsu OSHIKA (cousin of Yoshitada) as successor, and this led to a succession dispute involving several battles between the Tatsuo-maru faction and the Norimitsu faction.</e>
<cmt>Ryuo-maru → Tatsuo-maru</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>堀越公方執事の上杉政憲と扇谷上杉家家宰の太田道灌が兵を率いて駿河国へ進駐して家督争いに介入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanori UESUGI who was the head of Horikoshi Kubo (also called Horigoe Kubo, which was the shogunal deputy based in Horigoe, Izu Province) and Dokan OTA who was the chief retainer of the Uesugi clan intervened in the succession dispute by leading forces into Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanori UESUGI, who was the head of Horikoshi Kubo (also called Horigoe Kubo, shogunal deputy based in Horigoe, Izu Province) and Dokan OTA, chief retainer of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan, intervened in the succession dispute by leading forces into Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>Why isn&apos;t Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan used in the translation?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanori UESUGI, who was the head of Horikoshi Kubo (also called Horigoe Kubo, shogunal deputy based in Horigoe, Izu Province) and Dokan OTA, the chief retainer of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan, intervened in the succession dispute by leading forces into Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>chief retainer → the chief retainer</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これを叔父の伊勢新九郎が仲裁に入り、範満が龍王丸の後見人として家督を代行することで決着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His uncle Shinkuro ISE arbitrated the dispute and they agreed that Norimitsu would head the family on behalf of Ryuo-maru as his guardian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His uncle Shinkuro ISE arbitrated the dispute and they agreed that Norimitsu would act as guardian to Ryuo-maru and head the family on his behalf.</e>
<cmt>order of original sentence sounds awkward</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His uncle Shinkuro ISE arbitrated the dispute and they agreed that Norimitsu would act as guardian to Tatsuo-maru and head the family on his behalf.</e>
<cmt>Ryuo-maru → Tatsuo-maru</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>伊勢新九郎が素浪人と考えられていた頃は、抜群の知略による後の北条早雲の出世の第一歩のように語られていたが、近年の研究で名門伊勢氏の一族の幕臣伊勢盛時であることがほぼ明らかになっており、これは室町幕府の意向を受けて伊勢盛時が駿河国へ下向して今川家の内紛を調停したようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time Shinkuro ISE was considered to have been a mere masterless samurai, it was told as if it had been the first step for the success of later Soun HOJO who was very smart, but recent studies have almost confirmed that he was Moritoki ISE, who was a retainer of the Muromachi shogunate from the distinguished Ise clan, and in fact, Moritoki ISE seems to have went to Suruga Province and arbitrated the Imagawa family&apos;s dispute in accordance with the desire of the Muromachi shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Shinkuro ISE was thought to have been a mere masterless samurai, his actions were conveyed as the first step in a mastermind plan to succeed as the future Soun HOJO, but recent studies have almost confirmed that he was Moritoki ISE, member of the distinguished Ise clan and retainer of the Muromachi shogunate, and that he had in fact gone to Suruga Province to arbitrate the Imagawa family dispute in accordance with the wishes of the Muromachi shogunate.</e>
<cmt>While I understand the basic point of the sentence, some word usage is inappropriate in some cases and the structure needed to be changed a bit.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Shinkuro ISE was thought to have been a mere masterless samurai, his actions were conveyed as the first step in a mastermind plan to succeed as the future Soun HOJO, but recent studies have almost confirmed that he was Moritoki ISE, a member of the distinguished Ise clan and a retainer of the Muromachi shogunate, and that he had in fact gone to Suruga Province to arbitrate the Imagawa family dispute in accordance with the wishes of the Muromachi shogunate.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>家督を代行した範満が今川館に入り、龍王丸は母北川殿と小川の法永長者（長谷川政宣）の屋敷である小川城 (駿河国)（焼津市）に身を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norimitsu, who held the family headship on behalf of Ryuo-maru, came to live in Imagawa Mansion, and Ryuo-maru stayed with his mother Kitagawa-dono in Kogawa-jo Castle (in Suruga Province, now Yaizu City), which was the residence of Kogawa no Hoei Choja (Millionaire Hoei of Kogawa, who was Masanobu HASEGAWA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norimitsu, who held the family headship on behalf of Ryuo-maru, moved into Imagawa Mansion, and Ryuo-maru stayed with his mother, Kitagawa-dono, in Kogawa-jo Castle (in Suruga Province, now Yaizu City), which was the residence of Kogawa no Hoei Choja (Millionaire Hoei of Kogawa, Masanobu HASEGAWA).</e>
<cmt>word usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norimitsu, who held the family headship on behalf of Tatsuo-maru, moved into the Imagawa residence, and Tatsuo-maru stayed with his mother, Kitagawa-dono, in Kogawa-jo Castle (in Suruga Province, now Yaizu City), which was the residence of Kogawa no Hoei Choja (Millionaire Hoei of Kogawa, Masanobu HASEGAWA).</e>
<cmt>Imagawa Mansion → the Imagawa residenceRyuo-maru → Tatsuo-maru</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>文明11年（1479年）伊勢盛時は幕府に申請して前征夷大将軍足利義政の名による龍王丸の家督継承の内書を得ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1479, Moritoki ISE asked the shogunate for a permission for Ryuo-maru&apos;s succession to the family headship, which was given in the name of former Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1479, at the request of Moritoki ISE, the shogunate granted permission for Ryuo-maru&apos;s succession to the family headship, in the name of the former Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1479, at the request of Moritoki ISE, the shogunate handed a confidential letter directly to Moritoki, granted permission for Tatsuo-maru&apos;s succession to the family headship, in the name of the former Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>「内書」の訳を追加しました。Ryuo-maru → Tatsuo-maruスペースの追加と削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>だが、龍王丸が15歳を過ぎて成人しても範満は家督を返そうとはせず、家督奪取の動きを見せて龍王丸を圧迫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Norimitsu did not return the family headship to Ryuo-maru, who was then over 15 and had reached the age of manhood, and suppressed him with the intention of seizing the headship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, rather than returning the family headship to Ryuo-maru, Norimitsu suppressed him with the intention of seizing the headship, even after Ryuo-maru had passed the age of 15 and become an adult.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, rather than returning the family headship to Tatsuo-maru, Norimitsu suppressed him with the intention of seizing the headship, even after Tatsuo-maru had passed the age of 15 and become an adult.</e>
<cmt>Ryuo-maru → Tatsuo-maruスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>文明19年（1487年）北川殿と龍王丸は京都で将軍足利義尚に仕えていた伊勢新九郎盛時に助けを求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1487, Kitagawa-dono and Ryuo-maru asked Shinkuro Moritoki ISE for help, who was then serving Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1487, Kitagawa-dono and Ryuo-maru asked Shinkuro Moritoki ISE, who was then serving Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA in Kyoto, for help.</e>
<cmt>sentence structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1487, Kitagawa-dono and Tatsuo-maru asked Shinkuro Moritoki ISE, who was then serving Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA in Kyoto, for help.</e>
<cmt>Ryuo-maru → Tatsuo-maru</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>盛時は再び駿河国へ下向。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moritoki went to Suruga Province again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moritoki went to Suruga Province again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moritoki went to Suruga Province again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>同年11月、盛時は石脇城（焼津市）を拠点に兵を集めて駿河館を襲撃して範満を殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of the same year, Moritoki organized an army based in Ishiwaki-jo Castle (in Yaizu City), and attacked Suruga Mansion and killed Norimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, Moritoki organized an army based at Ishiwaki-jo Castle (in Yaizu City), attacking Suruga Mansion and killing Norimitsu.</e>
<cmt>The &quot;and&quot; before attack is not needed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the same year, Moritoki organized an army based at Ishiwaki-jo Castle (in Yaizu City), attacking the Suruga residence and killing Norimitsu.</e>
<cmt>Suruga Mansion → the Suruga residence</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>龍王丸は駿河館に入って元服して氏親と名乗り、今川家の当主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuo-maru entered into Suruga Mansion and took the name of Ujichika after attending the ceremony of attaining manhood, and thus became the head of the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuo-maru entered Suruga Mansion and took the name Ujichika after attending his coming-of-age ceremony,thereby becoming the head of the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatsuo-maru entered the Suruga residence and took the name Ujichika after celebrating his coming-of-age, thereby becoming the head of the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>Ryuo-maru → Tatsuo-maruSuruga Mansion → the Suruga residenceattending his coming-of-age ceremony → celebrating his coming-of-ageスペースの追加と削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>伊勢盛時には興国寺城が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moritoki ISE was awarded Kokokuji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moritoki ISE was awarded Kokokuji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moritoki ISE was awarded Kokokuji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>これより前、同年10月に龍王丸は大名で初めての印判状の文書を発給している（定着はせず、後に通常の花押を用いるようになっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to this event, in October of the same year, Ryuo-maru became the first daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) to use a stamp seal to issue a document (though did not continue it and later used normal written seal).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to this, in October of the same year, Ryuo-maru became the first daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) to use a stamp seal to issue a document (though this did not last and he later used the normal written seal).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to this, in October of the same year, Tatsuo-maru became the first daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) to use a stamp seal to issue a document (though this did not last and he later used the normal written seal).</e>
<cmt>Ryuo-maru → Tatsuo-maru</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>今川家当主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Head of the Imagawa Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Head of the Imagawa Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Head of the Imagawa Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>堀越公方に内紛が起き、明応2年（1493年）将軍足利義澄の命により、伊勢盛時（以後、早雲とする）は足利茶々丸を討伐して、伊豆国を手中にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A disturbance occurred in Horikoshi Kubo, and Moritoki ISE (hereinafter referred to as Soun), on the order of Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, destroyed Chachamaru ASHIKAGA in 1493 and conquered Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An internal conflict occurred in Horikoshi Kubo, and Moritoki ISE (hereinafter referred to as Soun), on the order of Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, destroyed Chachamaru ASHIKAGA and conquered Izu Province in 1493.</e>
<cmt>There&apos;s no need to substitute internal conflict for disturbance.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An internal conflict occurred in Horikoshi Kubo, and Moritoki ISE (hereinafter referred to as Soun), on the order of Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA, destroyed Chachamaru ASHIKAGA and conquered Izu Province in 1493.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>氏親も早雲に兵を貸してこれを助けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujichika also supported it by lending his soldiers to Soun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujichika also supported Soun by lending him his soldiers.</e>
<cmt>The &apos;it&quot; in original sentence doesn&apos;t make sense.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujichika also supported Soun by lending him his soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これは管領細川政元が起こした明応の政変に連動した動きであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was an action taken in response to the Meio Coup led by Shogunal Deputy Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their actions were in response to the Meio Coup led by Shogunal Deputy Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>The subject of &apos;it&apos; is not clear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their actions were in response to the Meio Coup led by Shogunal Deputy Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>以後、氏親と早雲は密接な協力関係を持って支配領域の拡大を行うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Ujichika and Soun closely cooperated with each other to expand their territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then onwards, Ujichika and Soun cooperated closely with each other to expand their territories.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then onwards, Ujichika and Soun cooperated closely with each other to expand their territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="35">
<j>駿河国の隣国遠江国は元は今川家が守護職を継承していたが、後に斯波氏に守護職を奪われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The position of shugo of Totomi Province, a neighboring province of Suruga, used to be inherited by the Imagawa family but later the Shiba clan replaced it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position of shugo of Suruga&apos;s neighboring province, Totomi, which had originally been handed down in the Imagawa family, was later taken over by the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position of shugo of Suruga&apos;s neighboring province, Totomi, which had originally been handed down in the Imagawa family, was later taken over by the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>遠江国奪還は今川家の悲願となり父義忠は遠江国での戦いで命を失っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imagawa family ardently desired to regain Totomi Province, and his father Yoshitada died in the battle there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imagawa family wanted desperately to regain Totomi Province and Ujichika&apos;s father, Yoshitada, died there in battle.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Ardently desired&quot; doesn&apos;t sound appropriate here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imagawa family wanted desperately to regain Totomi Province and Ujichika&apos;s father, Yoshitada, died there in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>当主となった氏親も積極的に遠江国への進出を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having become the head of the family, Ujichika also attempted to invade Totomi Province aggressively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having become the head of the family, Ujichika also made aggressive attempts at invading Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having become the head of the family, Ujichika also made aggressive attempts at invading Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="38">
<j>遠江国への侵攻の兵を率いたのは早雲で、明応3年（1494年）頃から始まり、遠江国中部まで勢力下に収めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Soun who led the army to invade Totomi Province from around 1494 and got up to the middle part of the province under its control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was, however, Soun who led an army into Totomi Province from around 1494, gaining control of up to the midsection of the province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was, however, Soun who led an army into Totomi Province from around 1494, gaining control of up to the midsection of the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この時には氏親は未だに遠江守護ではなかったものの、独自の立場で検地を行って守護斯波氏による支配体制を否認した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Ujichika was not yet shugo of Totomi Province at that time, he carried out land survey on his own authority, denying the Shiba clan&apos;s authority there as shugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ujichika had not yet become shugo of Totomi Province, he carried out his own independent land surveys, undermining the Shiba clan&apos;s authority as shugo.</e>
<cmt>word usageDid he do one survey or surveys?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ujichika had not yet become shugo of Totomi Province, he carried out his own independent land surveys, undermining the Shiba clan&apos;s authority as shugo.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>これによって今川家は事実上室町幕府からの統制を離れて守護大名から戦国大名の段階へ移ったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, it is said to have transformed the Imagawa family into a warlord from a feudal lord holding the position of shugo under the control of the Muromachi shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is said to have essentially signified a break away by the Imagawa family from the control of the Muromachi shogunate and a change in their position from Shugo Daimyo(Provincial Daimyo) to Sengoku Daimyo(Daimyo in Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>original sentence is quite confusing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is said to have essentially signified a break away by the Imagawa family from the control of the Muromachi shogunate and a change in their position from Shugo Daimyo (Provincial Daimyo) to Sengoku Daimyo (Daimyo in Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>スペースの追加と削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、氏親は駿河本国内においても検地を実施して、領国の一円支配を推し進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujichika also carried out land survey in his home Suruga Province and promoted an integrated administration of his territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujichika also carried out land surveys in his home of Suruga Province and promoted an integrated administration of his territory.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujichika also carried out land surveys in his home of Suruga Province and promoted an integrated administration of his territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また、安倍金山を開発して財力を増した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he developed Abe Gold Mine, which increased his financial power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he developed Abe Gold Mine, which increased his financial power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he developed Abe Gold Mine, which increased his financial power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="43">
<j>早雲は更に兵を進めて文亀年間（1501年-1504年）には三河国岩津城の松平氏を攻めているほか、甲斐国都留郡にも出兵して郡内領主小山田氏や守護武田氏と戦っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun advanced his army further and attacked the Matsudaira clan at Iwatsu-jo Castle in Mikawa Province during Bunki era (1501 - 1504), in addition to sending an army to Tsuru County in Kai Province and fighting against the Oyamada clan who was the feudal lord of Gunnai and the Takeda clan who was shugo there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun advanced his army further, attacking the Matsudaira clan at Iwatsu-jo Castle in Mikawa Province during the Bunki era (1501 - 1504) and sending an army to Tsuru County in Kai Province where they fought against the Oyamada clan, feudal lord of Gunnai, and the Takeda clan who was shugo there.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun advanced his army further, attacking the Matsudaira clan at Iwatsu-jo Castle in Mikawa Province during the Bunki era (1501 - 1504) and sending an army to Tsuru County in Kai Province where they fought against the Oyamada clan, feudal lord of Gunnai, and the Takeda clan who was shugo there.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>一方、氏親は早雲の関東進出にも協力して長享の乱に介入、扇谷上杉氏に味方して山内上杉家と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Ujichika supported Soun who was advancing to Kanto region, and intervened in the Chokyo Rebellion by fighting against the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family in favor of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Ujichika supported Soun&apos;s advance to the Kanto region, intervening in the Chokyo Rebellion and siding with the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan in battle against the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Ujichika supported Soun&apos;s advance to the Kanto region, intervening in the Chokyo Rebellion and siding with the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan in battle against the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>永正元年（1504年）の武蔵国立河原の戦いに早雲とともに出陣して関東管領上杉顕定を破っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1504, he fought in the battle of Tachikawanohara in Musashi Province, together with Soun, and defeated Shogunal Deputy for Kanto Region Akisada UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1504, he fought in the battle of Tachikawanohara in Musashi Province together with Soun, and defeated Shogunal Deputy for Kanto Region, Akisada UESUGI..</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1504, he fought in the battle of Tachikawanohara in Musashi Province together with Soun, and defeated Shogunal Deputy for Kanto Region, Akisada UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="46">
<j>永正2年（1505年）頃に中御門宣胤の娘（後の寿桂尼）を正室に迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1505, a daughter of Nobutane NAKAMIKADO became his lawful wife (later Jukei-ni).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1505, Nobutane NAKAMIKADO&apos;s daughter (the future Jukei-ni) became his lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1505, Nobutane NAKAMIKADO&apos;s daughter (the future Jukei-ni) became his lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="47">
<j>永正3年-5年（1506年-1508年）には再び早雲率いる今川軍が三河国へ侵攻して、松平長親と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1506 to 1508, the Imagawa army led by Soun invaded Mikawa Province again and fought against Nagachika MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1506 to 1508, the Imagawa army, led by Soun, invaded Mikawa Province again and fought against Nagachika MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>Basically OK. Just inserted commas.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1506 to 1508, the Imagawa army, led by Soun, invaded Mikawa Province again and fought against Nagachika MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="48">
<j>永正6年（1509年）以降は早雲の今川家の武将として活動がなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 1509, Soun ceased to work as a military commander of the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After 1509, Soun no longer worked as military commander of the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>I think &apos;cease&apos; doesn&apos;t reflect the Japanese correctly.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 1509, Soun no longer worked as military commander of the Imagawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>この頃に早雲は政治的に今川家から独立したようで、以後は関東進出を本格化させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soun seems to have become independent from the Imagawa family around that time, and later seriously started to advance to Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soun had apparently become independent of the Imagawa family and, from this time onwards, he shifted his advance to the Kanto region into full swing.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soun had apparently become independent of the Imagawa family and, from this time onwards, he shifted his advance to the Kanto region into full swing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="50">
<j>永正5年（1508年）、氏親は幕府に願い正式に遠江守護に任じられ、遠江国支配の大義名分を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1508, Ujichika asked the shogunate to officially appoint him as shugo of Totomi Province, which was granted, and thus he obtained a legitimate reason to rule the province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1508, the shogunate granted Ujichika&apos;s request, officially appointing him shugo of Totomi Province, and thereby giving him a legitimate reason to rule the province.</e>
<cmt>original sentence awkward</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1508, the shogunate granted Ujichika&apos;s request, officially appointing him shugo of Totomi Province, and thereby giving him a legitimate reason to rule the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>永正8年（1511年）に尾張国守護斯波義達が今川方の刑部城（浜松市）を攻め、氏親が出陣してこれを退けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1511, when Shugo of Owari Province Yoshitatsu SHIBA attacked Osakabe-jo Castle owned by the Imagawa family (in Hamamatsu City), Ujichika fought it off by leading his army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1511, when Owari Province Shugo, Yoshitatsu SHIBA, attacked Osakabe-jo Castle, owned by the Imagawa family (in Hamamatsu City), Ujichiki mobilized his army and fought off the attack.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1511, when Owari Province Shugo, Yoshitatsu SHIBA, attacked Osakabe-jo Castle, owned by the Imagawa family (in Hamamatsu City), Ujichiki mobilized his army and fought off the attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>斯波義達はなおも攻撃を続け、遠江国での斯波氏との戦いが激化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitatsu SHIBA continued the attack, which led to fierce battles with the Shiba clan in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitatsu SHIBA continued the attack, which led to fierce battles with the Shiba clan in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitatsu SHIBA continued the attack, which led to fierce battles with the Shiba clan in Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="53">
<j>永正13年（1516年）に引馬城（浜松市）の大河内貞綱が今川家に背き、斯波義達も加わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1516, Sadatsuna OKOCHI holding Hikuma-jo Castle (in Hamamatsu City) betrayed the Imagawa family, and Yoshitatsu SHIBA also joined it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1516, Sadatsuna OKOCHI of Hikuma-jo Castle (Hamamatsu City) betrayed the Imagawa family, and Yoshitatsu SHIBA joined him.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1516, Sadatsuna OKOCHI of Hikuma-jo Castle (Hamamatsu City) betrayed the Imagawa family, and Yoshitatsu SHIBA joined him.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>氏親は出陣して引馬城を包囲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujichika led the army and surrounded Hikuma-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujichika led his army and surrounded Hikuma-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujichika led his army and surrounded Hikuma-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>安倍金山の鉱夫を用いて坑道を掘って水の手を絶って降伏させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made miners of Abe Gold Mine to dig a tunnel to cut off water supply, and it forced the enemies to surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had the miners of Abe Gold Mine dig a tunnel, cutting off the water supply and forcing the enemies to surrender.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had the miners of Abe Gold Mine dig a tunnel, cutting off the water supply and forcing the enemies to surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>大河内貞綱は討ち死にし、斯波義達は出家して降伏し、尾張国へ送り返された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadatsuna OKOCHI was killed in the battle, and Yoshitatsu SHIBA surrendered by entering into the priesthood and was sent back to Owari Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadatsuna OKOCHI was killed in this battle, and Yoshitatsu SHIBA, who surrendered by entering into the priesthood, was sent back to Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadatsuna OKOCHI was killed in this battle, and Yoshitatsu SHIBA, who surrendered by entering into the priesthood, was sent back to Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>これにより、遠江国が平定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus Totomi Province was conquered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus Totomi Province was conquered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus Totomi Province was conquered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="58">
<j>また、永正12年（1515年）には、甲斐西郡の国人領主である大井信達に味方して守護武田信虎と争い、中道往還沿いの勝山城 (甲斐国)を一時占拠している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, he fought against Shugo Nobutora TAKEDA in favor of Nobusato OI who was a local lord in Nishigoori, Kai Province, and temporarily occupied Katsuyama-jo Castle (in Kai Province) located along Nakamichi Okan Road in 1515.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, in 1515, he joined forces with Nobusato Oi, local lord of Nishigori in Kai Province, in battle against Shugo Nobutora TAKEDA, temporarily occupying Katsuyama-jo Castle (in Kai Province) located along Nakamichi Okan Road in 1515.</e>
<cmt>word usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, in 1515, he joined forces with Nobusato Oi, local lord of Nishigori in Kai Province, in battle against Shugo Nobutora TAKEDA, temporarily occupying Katsuyama-jo Castle (in Kai Province) located along Nakamichi Okan Road in 1515.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>永正14年（1517年）氏親は信虎と和議を結び撤兵し、大井信達は信虎に降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1517, Ujichika concluded a peace agreement with Nobutora and withdrew his army, and Nobusato OI surrendered to Nobutora.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1517, Ujichika concluded a peace agreement with Nobutora and withdrew his army, while Nobusato OI surrendered to Nobutora.</e>
<cmt>unnecessary use of and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1517, Ujichika concluded a peace agreement with Nobutora and withdrew his army, while Nobusato OI surrendered to Nobutora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>その後も、氏親後期に甲駿同盟が成立するまでたびたび甲斐国への侵攻を行い、武田氏との対立が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confrontation with the Takeda clan continued after that, and Ujichika often invaded Kai Province until an alliance between Suruga Province and Kai Province was concluded in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confrontation with the Takeda clan continued after that, and Ujichika often invaded Kai Province until an alliance between Suruga Province and Kai Province was concluded in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confrontation with the Takeda clan continued after that, and Ujichika often invaded Kai Province until an alliance between Suruga Province and Kai Province was concluded in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="61">
<j>公家の娘の寿桂尼との結婚によって京とのつながりが強まり、京の文化を駿府に取り入れたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His marriage with Jukei-ni, who was a daughter of a court noble, is said to have strengthened his connection with Kyoto and led Kyoto culture to be adopted into Sunpu (the capital of Suruga Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His marriage to Jukei-ni, the daughter of a court noble, is said to have strengthened his connection with Kyoto and led to Kyoto&apos;s culture being adopted in Sunpu (the capital of Suruga Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His marriage to Jukei-ni, the daughter of a court noble, is said to have strengthened his connection with Kyoto and led to Kyoto&apos;s culture being adopted in Sunpu (the capital of Suruga Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>氏親も和歌と連歌を特に好んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujichika also liked waka (traditional Japanese poetry consisting of thirty-one syllables) and renga (collaborative poetry) among others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujichika especially liked waka (traditional Japanese poetry consisting of thirty-one syllables) and renga (collaborative poetry).</e>
<cmt>There is nothing to suggest &apos;among others&apos; in the Japanese sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujichika especially liked waka (traditional Japanese poetry consisting of thirty-one syllables) and renga (collaborative poetry).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>晩年は中風にかかって寝たきりになり、寿桂尼が政治を補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was confined to bed in his later years due to a stroke, and Jukei-ni supported him to deal with political matters.</e>
<cmt>「中風」→脳卒中。（http://www.nmh.or.jp/nousotsu/nousotu.html）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was confined to bed in his later years due to a stroke, and Jukei-ni assisted him with political matters.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was confined to bed in his later years due to a stroke, and Jukei-ni assisted him with political matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>死の2ヶ月前の大永6年（1526年）4月に戦国時代の代表的な分国法『今川仮名目録』を制定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1526, two months before his death, he established &quot;Imagawa Kana Mokuroku&quot; (Imagawa House Laws), typical provincial laws that warlords enforced in their territories in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1526, two months before his death, he established the &quot;Imagawa Kana Mokuroku&quot; (Imagawa House Laws), typical provincial laws that warlords enforced in their territories in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1526, two months before his death, he established the &quot;Imagawa Kana Mokuroku&quot; (Imagawa House Laws), typical provincial laws that warlords enforced in their territories in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>嫡男氏輝がまだ成人していないため、家臣の争いを抑える目的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its aim was to prevent a dispute between vassals, because his heir Ujiteru had not yet reached the age of manhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was aimed at preventing a dispute between vassals, because his heir Ujiteru had not yet come of age.</e>
<cmt>It is not clear what &apos;its&apos; refers to.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was aimed at preventing a dispute between vassals, because his heir Ujiteru had not yet come of age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="66">
<j>大永6年（1526年）6月23日駿府の今川館で息を引き取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 23, 1526, he died at Imagawa Mansion in Sunpu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 23, 1526, he died at Imagawa Mansion in Sunpu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 23, 1526, he died at the Imagawa residence in Sunpu.</e>
<cmt>Imagawa Mansion → the Imagawa residence</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>氏親の葬儀は増善寺で執行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The funeral ceremony for Ujichika was held at Zozen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The funeral ceremony for Ujichika was held at Zozen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The funeral ceremony for Ujichika was held at Zozen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>「葬儀記」によると7,000人の僧侶が参加し、かくして葬儀の喪主である長男氏輝が祭文を読み、棺のつなは善徳寺の御曹司義元、御位牌は花倉の御曹司良真がもって曹洞宗最高の法式で行われ、戦国大名の歴史の上でも例をみない大葬儀であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Sogiki&apos; (Records of Funeral), it was an exceptionally grand funeral in the history of warlords, held in the supreme ceremonial style of the Sotoshu sect, with 7,000 priests participating in, his oldest son Ujiteru reading prayers as the host, son Yoshimoto at Zentoku-ji Temple holding a rope of coffin and son Ryoshin in Hanakura holding a Buddhist mortuary tablet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「善徳寺の御曹司義元」→氏親の息子の義元のこと。&quot;son Yoshimoto at Zentoku-ji Temple&quot;と訳しました。「花倉の御曹司良真」→氏親の息子良真のこと。&quot;son Ryoshin in Hanakura&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &apos;Sogiki&apos; (Funeral Records), it was an exceptionally grand funeral in the history of warlord funerals, held in the supreme ceremonial style of the Sotoshu sect, with 7,000 priests participating, his oldest son Ujiteru reading prayers as the host, son Yoshimoto of Zentoku-ji Temple holding the rope of the coffin and son Ryoshin from Hanakura holding the Buddhist mortuary tablet.</e>
<cmt>use of &apos;the&apos; and &apos;a&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &apos;Sogiki&apos; (Funeral Records), it was an exceptionally grand funeral in the history of warlord funerals, held in the supreme ceremonial style of the Sotoshu sect, with 7,000 priests participating, his oldest son Ujiteru reading prayers as the host, a son Yoshimoto of Zentoku-ji Temple holding the rope of the coffin and a son Ryoshin from Hanakura holding the Buddhist mortuary tablet.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), ナポレオン(id:212346), Takatsuki(id:28491), Novo(id:87875), S.S.Exp.Hashimoto(id:4001), Aotake(id:34929), Cprobot(id:97843), Extrahitz(id:26245), Yanahan(id:2437), 味っ子(id:17086), Mop(id:12061), Kagetudo(id:163875), 彩華1226(id:64711), でここ(id:9565), 五郎兵衛(id:25423), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), 松平蔵人(id:229480), 平惣衛門(id:99387), Miyachi(id:70658), Oplkiuy7654322(id:188089), Suisui(id:69), Louperibot(id:128971), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 常陸介(id:176100), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>