<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蜂屋頼隆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritaka HACHIYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritaka HACHIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritaka HACHIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蜂屋 頼隆（はちや よりたか、1534年（天文 (元号)3年）- 1589年11月3日（天正17年9月25日 (旧暦)））は、戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritaka HACHIYA (1534-November 3, 1589) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritaka HACHIYA (1534 - November 3, 1589) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritaka HACHIYA (1534 - November 3, 1589) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>官位は兵庫頭、出羽守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official court rank was a Hyogo no kami (Head of Hyogo), Dewa no kami (the governor of Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The official court rank was a Hyogo no kami (Head of Hyogo), Dewa no kami (Governor of Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The official court rank was a Hyogo no kami (Head of Hyogo), Dewa no kami (Governor of Dewa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>侍従。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正室は丹羽長秀の妹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was a younger sister of Nagahide NIWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was a younger sister of Nagahide NIWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was a younger sister of Nagahide NIWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>はじめ土岐氏、次いで斎藤氏に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first he served the Toki clan and after that he served the Saito clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first he served the Toki clan and then the Saito clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first he served the Toki clan and then the Saito clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>織田信長が美濃国攻めを開始した頃、信長の家臣となり、黒母衣衆に名を連ね、信長の上洛における諸合戦や一向一揆討伐戦などにおいて活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nobunaga ODA started the attack on Mino Province, he became a vassal of Nobunaga as a member of Kurohoroshu group and played an active role at various battles for Nobunaga&apos;s going to Kyoto and putting down Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nobunaga ODA started the attack on Mino Province, he became a vassal of Nobunaga as a member of Kuro horo shu (an elite bodyguard unit in black) and played an active role at various battles for Nobunaga&apos;s going to Kyoto and putting down Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers).</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにし、用語等を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nobunaga ODA started the attack on Mino Province, he became a vassal of Nobunaga as a member of Kuro horo shu (an elite bodyguard unit in black) and played an active role at various battles for Nobunaga&apos;s going to Kyoto and putting down Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>信長の上洛後は、京洛の政務にも関わっており、信長の上洛前後には部隊長クラスの扱いを受け、一軍を率いていたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritaka who was involved in the affairs of capital Kyoto after Nobunaga went to Kyoto, was treated as a commanding officer heading a troop around Nobunaga&apos;s going to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the fact that Yoritaka was involved in the affairs of capital Kyoto after Nobunaga went to Kyoto, he was treated as a commanding officer heading a troop around Nobunaga&apos;s going to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにし、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the fact that Yoritaka was involved in the affairs of capital Kyoto after Nobunaga went to Kyoto, he was treated as a commanding officer heading a troop around Nobunaga&apos;s going to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>また、信長の命により、謀反を起こした（有岡城の戦い）荒木村重の一族の処刑も行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the order of Nobunaga, he also conducted the execution of the Murashige ARAKI family who rose in revolt against Nobunaga (the battle of Arioka-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the order of Nobunaga, he also conducted the execution of the Murashige ARAKI family who rose in revolt against Nobunaga (the battle of Arioka-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the order of Nobunaga, he also conducted the execution of the Murashige ARAKI family who rose in revolt against Nobunaga (the battle of Arioka-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>その後も諸戦に参戦し、軍功を重ねたが、主だった武将が各方面侵攻の国主として任命された頃も、遊撃軍扱いであり、他の主力家臣よりは一歩出世が遅れた形となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that he participated in various battles and made some military glories, but his troop was still treated as a corps of rangers, even after major bushos were appointed lords to go into various directions, which meant his career was taking a step back from the other major vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that he participated in various battles and made some military glories, but his troop was still treated as a corps of rangers, even after major busho warriors were appointed lords to go into various directions, which meant his career was taking a step back from the other major vassals.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that he participated in various battles and made some military glories, but his troop was still treated as a corps of rangers, even after major busho warriors were appointed lords to go into various directions, which meant his career was taking a step back from the other major vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、天正8年（1580年）、佐久間信盛親子の追放後に、丹羽長秀・津田信澄らと共に、織田信孝の配下として付けられ、和泉国一国の支配権をほぼ任されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1580, after Nobumori SAKUMA and his son were banished, Yoritaka was regarded as vassals of Nobutaka ODA, together with Nagahide NIWA and Nobusumi TSUDA, and was given most of the control of Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1580, after Nobumori SAKUMA and his son were banished, Yoritaka was given most of the control of Izumi Province as vassals of Nobutaka ODA, together with Nagahide NIWA and Nobusumi TSUDA, and so on.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1580, after Nobumori SAKUMA and his son were banished, Yoritaka was given most of the control of Izumi Province as vassals of Nobutaka ODA, together with Nagahide NIWA and Nobusumi TSUDA, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>1582年の本能寺の変によって信長が死去した後、津田信澄は織田信孝・丹羽長秀に殺害されるが、これには関与せず静観。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga died by Honnoji Incident in 1582, when Nobusumi TSUDA was killed by Nobuta oda and Nagahide NIWA, Yoritaka had no involvement in it observing calmly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga died by Honnoji Incident in 1582, when Nobusumi TSUDA was killed by Nobutaka ODA and Nagahide NIWA, Yoritaka had no involvement in it observing calmly.</e>
<cmt>読み、表記を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga died by Honnoji Incident in 1582, when Nobusumi TSUDA was killed by Nobutaka ODA and Nagahide NIWA, Yoritaka had no involvement in it observing calmly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>山崎の合戦には、信孝に従い参戦しているが、光秀が死に柴田勝家・織田信孝が秀吉と敵対すると、豊臣秀吉に属し、織田信孝の岐阜城攻めに加わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Battle of Yamasaki in which Yoritaka participated following Nomutaka, when Mitsuhide died and consequently Katsuie SHIBATA and Nomutaka ODA fought against Hideyoshi, Yoritaka served Hideyoshi ODA and participated in the attack on Gifu-jo Castle of Nobutaka ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Yamasaki in which Yoritaka participated following Nobutaka, when Mitsuhide died and consequently Katsuie SHIBATA and Nobutaka ODA fought against Hideyoshi, Yoritaka served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and participated in the attack on Gifu-jo Castle of Nobutaka ODA.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Yamasaki in which Yoritaka participated following Nobutaka, when Mitsuhide died and consequently Katsuie SHIBATA and Nobutaka ODA fought against Hideyoshi, Yoritaka served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and participated in the attack on Gifu-jo Castle of Nobutaka ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>戦後、越前国敦賀に所領4万石を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war he was given 40,000 koku in Tsuruga-jo Castle in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the battle, he was given 40,000 koku in Tsuruga of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>原文には 「敦賀城」とありましたが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「敦賀」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出し、原文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the battle, he was given 40,000 koku in Tsuruga of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>羽柴の姓を授けられたことから、羽柴敦賀侍従と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he was given the family name Hashiba, he was called Hashibatsuruga jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he was given the family name Hashiba, he was called Hashiba Tsuruga Jiju (literally, chamberlain of Hashiba in Tsuruga).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he was given the family name Hashiba, he was called Hashiba Tsuruga Jiju (literally, chamberlain of Hashiba in Tsuruga).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後も佐々成政攻めや、九州征伐に秀吉配下として従軍したが、1589年、56歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that he also joined the attack to Narimasa SASSA and the Kyushu Conquest serving under Hideyoshi and died at 56 in 1589.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that he also joined the attack on Narimasa SASSA and the Kyushu Conquest serving under Hideyoshi and died at the age of 56 in 1589.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that he also joined the attack on Narimasa SASSA and the Kyushu Conquest serving under Hideyoshi and died at the age of 56 in 1589.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>丹羽長秀の四男、直政(1580年生まれ)が養子に居たがその頃にはおそらく亡くなっていた為に嗣子無く、蜂屋氏は断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, his adopted son who was the forth son of Nagahide NIWA (born in 1580), seemed to be already dead, so he had no heir and the Hachiya clan ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, Nagamasa, Yoritaka&apos;s adopted son who was the fourth son of Nagahide NIWA (born in 1580), seemed to be already dead, and so he had no heir and the Hachiya clan ended.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「直政」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, Naomasa, Yoritaka&apos;s adopted son who was the fourth son of Nagahide NIWA (born in 1580), seemed to be already dead, and so he had no heir and the Hachiya clan ended.</e>
<cmt>Nagamasa→Naomasa</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Cprobot(id:97843), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), High and low(id:122810), Point136(id:211299), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Kotoito(id:21045), 春秋君(id:174988), Bakira(id:184047), 蚯蚓(id:254651), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Sea of Japan(id:3230), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>