<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上野清信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyonobu UENO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyonobu UENO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyonobu UENO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>上野 清信（うえの きよのぶ、生没年不詳）は、戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyonobu UENO (year of birth and death unknown) was a Busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyonobu UENO (year of birth and death unknown) was a Busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyonobu UENO (year of birth and death unknown) was a Busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real family name was Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real family name was the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>Genji→the Minamoto clanに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real family name was the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家系は清和源氏の一家系　河内源氏の流れを汲む足利氏の傍流　上野氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His family line was the Ueno clan, a branch of the Ashikaga clan following Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), one of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His family line was the Ueno clan, a branch of the Ashikaga clan following Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), one of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>one of Seiwa-Genji→one of the Seiwa-Genjiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His family line was the Ueno clan, a branch of the Ashikaga clan following Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), one of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は幕臣にて旧備中国鬼邑山城城主　上野信孝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Nobutaka UENO, a Shogun&apos;s retainer and the lord of the Kimurayama-jo Castle in old Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Nobutaka UENO, a Shogun&apos;s retainer and the lord of the Kimurayama-jo Castle in old Bitchu Province.</e>
<cmt>Bicchu→Bitchuに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Nobutaka UENO, a Shogun&apos;s retainer and the lord of the Kimurayama-jo Castle in old Bitchu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>弟は上野頼久、上野右衛門尉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His brother included Yorihisa UENO and Uemon no jo UENO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His brother included Yorihisa UENO and Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) UENO.</e>
<cmt>Uemon no joの補足追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His brother included Yorihisa UENO and Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) UENO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>官位は中務少輔従五位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official rank was Nakatsukasa no Shoyu, Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official rank was Nakatsukasa no Shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs), Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>Nakatsukasa no Shoyuの補足追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official rank was Nakatsukasa no Shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs), Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>父　上野信孝は足利義稙の近臣として、明応の政変において征夷大将軍を追われた義稙に随行して西国に下り、備中国鬼邑山城主に任ぜられた武将であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, Nobutaka UENO was a Busho, who, as a trusted vassal of Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, went down to Saigoku (western part of Japan (especially Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)) with Yoshitane being driven out of his position of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Coup of Meio and was appointed the lord of the Kimurayama-jo Castle in Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, Nobutaka UENO was a Busho, who, as a trusted vassal of Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, went down to Saigoku (western part of Japan [especially Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki]) with Yoshitane being driven out of his position of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Coup of Meio and was appointed the lord of the Kimurayama-jo Castle in Bitchu Province.</e>
<cmt>Bicchu→Bitchuに修正、カッコ表記修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, Nobutaka UENO was a Busho, who, as a trusted vassal of Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, went down to Saigoku (western part of Japan [especially Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki]) with Yoshitane being driven out of his position of Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) in the Coup of Meio and was appointed the lord of the Kimurayama-jo Castle in Bitchu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>父は一門の上野高直を鬼邑山城主とし、次男　上野頼久を備中国松山城 (備中国)に任じて、嫡男　清信を伴い、京都帰洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father made Takanao UENO of his family the lord of the Kimurayama-jo Castle in Bicchu Province, made his second son, Yorihisa UENO the lord of the Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bicchu Province) and went back to Kyoto with his eldest legitimate son, Kiyonobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father made Takanao UENO of his family the lord of the Kimurayama-jo Castle in Bitchu Province, made his second son, Yorihisa UENO the lord of the Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bitchu Province) and went back to Kyoto with his eldest legitimate son, Kiyonobu.</e>
<cmt>Bicchu→Bitchuに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father made Takanao UENO of his family the lord of the Kimurayama-jo Castle in Bitchu Province, made his second son, Yorihisa UENO the lord of the Matsuyama-jo Castle (Bitchu Province) and went back to Kyoto with his eldest legitimate son, Kiyonobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>以後、清信は父とともに室町幕府に出仕し足利将軍家に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, Kiyonobu worked with his father at Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) serving the Ashikaga Shogun Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, Kiyonobu worked with his father at Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) serving the Ashikaga Shogun Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, Kiyonobu worked with his father at Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) serving the Ashikaga Shogun Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>清信は、13代将軍　足利義輝が従弟 足利義栄を奉じる三好義継、三好三人衆・松永久秀の軍勢に討たれ、義輝の実弟　足利義昭に追跡の手が及ぶと、義昭に随行し越前国の朝倉義景の下に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the 13th Shogun, Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was killed by the army of Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI, Miyoshi sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan) and Hisahide MATSUNAGA having Yoshihide ASHIKAGA, his younger cousin, at their head and then Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, Yoshiteru&apos;s real younger brother was pursued, Kiyonobu followed Yoshiaki to escape to Echizen Province for help of Yoshikage ASAKURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the 13th Shogun, Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was killed by the army of Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI, Miyoshi sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan) and Hisahide MATSUNAGA having Yoshihide ASHIKAGA, Yoshiteru&apos;s younger cousin, at their head and then Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, Yoshiteru&apos;s real younger brother was pursued, Kiyonobu followed Yoshiaki to escape to Echizen Province for help of Yoshikage ASAKURA.</e>
<cmt>his younger cousin→Yoshiteru&apos;s younger cousinとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the 13th Shogun, Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA was killed by the army of Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI, Miyoshi sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan) and Hisahide MATSUNAGA having Yoshihide ASHIKAGA, Yoshiteru&apos;s younger cousin, at their head and then Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, Yoshiteru&apos;s real younger brother was pursued, Kiyonobu followed Yoshiaki to escape to Echizen Province for help of Yoshikage ASAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>朝倉氏の膝元　一乗谷城に逗留後、義昭をして将軍義栄討伐の兵を挙げることを求めるものの、朝倉義景が一向に動かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After staying at Ichijodani Castle, the headquarters of Asakura clan, Kiyonobu asked Yoshikage ASAKURA to raise an army with Yoshiaki as its head to attack Shogun Yoshihide, but Yoshikage did not act at all.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After staying at Ichijodani-jo Castle, the headquarters of Asakura clan, Kiyonobu asked Yoshikage ASAKURA to raise an army with Yoshiaki as its head to attack Shogun Yoshihide, but Yoshikage did not act at all.</e>
<cmt>Ichijodani Castle→Ichijodani-jo Castleとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After staying at Ichijodani-jo Castle, the headquarters of Asakura clan, Kiyonobu asked Yoshikage ASAKURA to raise an army with Yoshiaki as its head to attack Shogun Yoshihide, but Yoshikage did not act at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>義昭は尾張国の織田信長の保護を受け、織田軍の加勢により将軍職を奪還、京都に入洛し清信はこれに随行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki came to be protected by Nobunaga ODA of Owari Province, received reinforcements by the Oda army, recaptured Shogunate and when he entered into Kyoto, Kiyonobu followed him.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki came to be protected by Nobunaga ODA of Owari Province, received reinforcements by the Oda army, recaptured Shogunate and when he entered Kyoto, Kiyonobu followed him.</e>
<cmt>entered into Kyoto→entered Kyotoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki came to be protected by Nobunaga ODA of Owari Province, received reinforcements by the Oda army, recaptured Shogunate and when he entered Kyoto, Kiyonobu followed him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、信長と義昭の対立が深め、幕命によって形成された信長包囲網が信長の手によって崩された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, due to the confrontation between Nobunaga and Yoshiaki intensifying, anti-Nobunaga network was formed by the order of the Bakufu, but it was destroyed by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, due to the confrontation between Nobunaga and Yoshiaki intensifying, anti-Nobunaga network was formed by the order of the bakufu, but it was destroyed by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>the Bakufu→the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, due to the confrontation between Nobunaga and Yoshiaki intensifying, anti-Nobunaga network was formed by the order of the bakufu, but it was destroyed by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>幕府に迫る織田軍を前に、清信は義昭の面前で徹底抗戦を訴え、降伏を唱える細川幽斎と口論に及んだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Oda army was closing in on the Bakufu, Kiyonobu insisted on all-out resistance and reportedly got into a quarrel in spite of the presence of Yoshiaki with Yusai HOSOKAWA who advocated surrender.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Oda army was closing in on the bakufu, Kiyonobu insisted on all-out resistance and reportedly got into a quarrel in spite of the presence of Yoshiaki with Yusai HOSOKAWA who advocated surrender.</e>
<cmt>the Bakufu→the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Oda army was closing in on the bakufu, Kiyonobu insisted on all-out resistance and reportedly got into a quarrel in spite of the presence of Yoshiaki with Yusai HOSOKAWA who advocated surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、1573年（天正元年）年に室町幕府が滅び、義昭が毛利氏を頼ると清信は義昭と離れ、そのまま信長に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Muromachi bakufu was overthrown in 1573 and Yoshiaki came under the protection of the Mori clan, Kiyonobu left him and started to serve Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Muromachi bakufu was overthrown in 1573 and Yoshiaki came under the protection of the Mori clan, Kiyonobu left him and started to serve Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Muromachi bakufu was overthrown in 1573 and Yoshiaki came under the protection of the Mori clan, Kiyonobu left him and started to serve Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>本能寺の変において信長が亡くなった後、その事実上の後継となった豊臣秀吉に仕え、馬廻となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga was killed in the Honnoji Incident, he came to serve Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, the virtual successor of Nobunaga and became Umamawari (horse guards).</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga was killed in the Honnoji Incident, Kiyonobu came to serve Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, the virtual successor of Nobunaga and became Umamawari (horse guards).</e>
<cmt>he came to→Kiyonobu came toとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga was killed in the Honnoji Incident, Kiyonobu came to serve Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, the virtual successor of Nobunaga and became Umamawari (horse guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>文禄・慶長の役では秀吉に随行して肥前国名護屋城にあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have followed Hideyoshi and stayed at Hizen Province Nagoya-jo Castle in the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have followed Hideyoshi and stayed at Nagoya-jo Castle in Hizen Province during the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>at Hizen Province Nagoya-jo Castle in the Bunroku-Keicho War→at Nagoya-jo Castle in Hizen Province during the Buroku-Keicho Warとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to have followed Hideyoshi and stayed at Nagoya-jo Castle in Hizen Province during the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後の消息は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His whereabouts after that was unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His whereabouts after that was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His whereabouts after that was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>