<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上杉謙信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>上杉 謙信／上杉 輝虎（うえすぎ けんしん／うえすぎ てるとら）は、戦国時代 (日本)における越後国の戦国大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI (or Terutora UESUGI) was a warring lord in Echigo Province during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin UESUGI (or Terutora UESUGI) was a warring lord in Echigo Province during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI (or Terutora UESUGI) was a warring lord in Echigo Province during the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後世、越後の虎とも越後の龍とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In future generations, he was also called Echigo no Tora (Tiger in Echigo Province) or Echigo no Ryu (dragon in Echigo Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In future generations, he was called Echigo no Tora (Tiger of Echigo Province) or Echigo nor Ryu (Dragon of Echigo Province).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In future generations, he was called Echigo no Tora (Tiger of Echigo Province) or Echigo no Ryu (Dragon of Echigo Province.)</e>
<cmt>&quot;nor&quot;を&quot;no&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>上杉氏の下で越後国の守護代を務めた長尾氏出身で、初名は長尾景虎（ながお かげとら）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI was from the Nagao clan who served as shugodai (deputy military governor) of Echigo Province under the Uesugi clan, and his original name was Kagetora NAGAO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin UESUGI, whose original name was Kagetora NAGAO and initially from the Nagao clan, served as Shugodai (deputy military governor) in Echigo Province under the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI, whose original name was Kagetora NAGAO, was from the Nagao clan that served as Shugodai (deputy military governor) in Echigo Province under the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;served as&quot;が&quot;the Nagao clan&quot;に掛かるよう掛かり受けを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>兄である晴景の養子となって長尾氏の家督を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by his older brother, Harukage, and succeeded to the family headship of Nagao clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by his older brother, Harukage, and took over reigns of the family of Nagao clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by his older brother, Harukage, and took over reigns of the family of Nagao clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>主君・上杉定実から見て「正妻の甥」且つ「婿の弟」にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For his lord, Sadazane UESUGI, Kenshin was a &apos;nephew of legal wife&apos; and &apos;younger brother of daughter&apos;s husband.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For his lord, Sadazane UESUGI, Kenshin was the &apos;nephew of lawful wife&apos; and &apos;younger brother of son-in-law&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For his lord, Sadazane UESUGI, Kenshin was the &apos;nephew of lawful wife&apos; and &apos;younger brother of son-in-law&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>のちに関東管領上杉憲政から上杉氏の家督を譲られ、上杉政虎と名を変えて上杉氏が世襲する室町幕府の重職関東管領に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin who took over the family headship of the Uesugi clan from Norimasa UESUGI, Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), thereafter changed his name to Masatora UESUGI, and was appointed to Kanto Kanrei, an important post in the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) which was inherited by the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin took over the family headship of the Uesugi clan from Norimasa UESUGI, who was a Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), he thereafter changed his name to Masatora UESUGI, and was later appointed to Kanto Kanrei, an important post in the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) which is inherited by the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin took over the family headship of the Uesugi clan from Norimasa UESUGI, who was a Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), he thereafter changed his name to Masatora UESUGI, and was later appointed to Kanto Kanrei, an important post in the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) which is inherited by the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後に将軍足利義輝より偏諱（へんき）を受けて最終的には上杉輝虎と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Kenshin received Henki (a portion of the name of a person in high rank, which is given to a retainer to show the subordination) from Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, and used Terutora UESUGI as his ultimate name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Kenshin was granted Henki (a portion of the name of a person in the high rank, which is given to a retainer to show the subordination) from Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, and ultimately he was named Terutora UESUGI..</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Kenshin was granted Henki (a portion of the name of a person in the high rank, which is given to a retainer to show the subordination) from Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, and ultimately he was named Terutora UESUGI..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>周辺の武田信玄、北条氏康、織田信長、佐野昌綱らと合戦を繰り広げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He repeatedly fought with Shingen TAKEDA, Ujiyasu HOJO, Nobunaga ODA and Masatsuna SANO in surrounding provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He repeatedly fought battles with Shingen TAKEDA, Ujiyasu HOJO, Nobunaga ODA and Masatsuna SANO from the surrounding provinces.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He repeatedly fought battles with Shingen TAKEDA, Ujiyasu HOJO, Nobunaga ODA and Masatsuna SANO from the surrounding provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>特に五回に及んだとされる武田信玄との川中島の合戦は、後世たびたび物語として描かれており、よく知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, the Battle of Kawanakajima which was implemented five times is often used as a subject matter of story in future generations, and is well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, the Battle of Kawanakajima which was implemented five times, and is often a subject matter of well known stories in future generations.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, the Battle of Kawanakajima, which was implemented five times, is well known since it is often a subject matter of stories in future generations.</e>
<cmt>コンマを追加、well_ knownをBattle_of_Kawanakajimaの述部とし、その説明としてoften以下をsinceｓで繋ぎました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>自ら毘沙門天の転生であると信じていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Kenshin believed that he himself was a reincarnation of Bishamonten (Vaisravana).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin believed that he was a reincarnation of Bishamonten (Vaisravana, guardian god of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Kenshin believed that he was a reincarnation of Bishamonten (Vaisravana, guardian god of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>「とされる」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、上杉謙信女性説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, there is a theory that Kenshin UESUGI was female.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there is a theory that Kensin Uesugi was a female.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there is a theory that Kensin Uesugi was a female.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>家督相続</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succession to family headship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succession to family headship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succession to Family Headship</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>享禄3年（1530年）1月21日、越後国守護代・長尾為景の四男（または三男）・虎千代として春日山城に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 28, 1530, he was born at Kasugayama-jo Castle as Torachiyo, the fourth (or third) son of Tamekage NAGAO, shugodai of Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>享禄3年（1530年）1月21日→February 28, 1530[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 28, 1530, he was born as Torachiyo, the fourth (or third) son of Tamekage NAGAO, shugodai of Echigo Province, at Kasugayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 28, 1530, he was born as Torachiyo, the fourth (or third) son of Tamekage NAGAO, Shugodai of Echigo Province, at Kasugayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>shugodaiの頭文字を大文字に変更。しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>天文 (元号)5年（1536年）に兄の長尾晴景が家督を継ぎ、虎千代は城下の林泉寺 (上越市)に入門して住職の天室光育の教えを受けたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that his older brother, Harukage NAGAO, succeeded to the family headship in 1536, and Torachiyo became a disciple of Rinsen-ji Temple (Joetsu City) in the castle town, and received teachings from a priest, Koiku TENSHITSU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that his older brother, Harukage NAGAO, took over the reigns of the family in 1536, Torachiyo entered Rinsen-ji Temple (Joetsu City) a castle town, and received teachings from the chief priest Koiku TENSHITSU.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that his older brother, Harukage NAGAO, took over the reigns of the family in 1536 and that Torachiyo became a disciple of Rinsen-ji Temple (Joetsu City) in the town around the castle and received teachings from the chief priest Koiku TENSHITSU.</e>
<cmt>「寺に入門した」はTorachiyo was left in custody of Rinsen-ji Temple →Torachiyo became a disciple of Rinsen-ji Temple としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>実父と仲が良くなかったため、為景から避けられる形で寺に入れられたこととされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been believed that Torachiyo was put into a temple in the form of distancing him from Tamekage because he was on outs with his natural father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Torachiyo did not have good relations with his natural father, he was distanced by entering the temple.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that since Torachiyo did not have good relations with his natural father Tamekage, he was distanced by becoming a disciple of the temple.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れのTamekageを追加。「とされている」を訳出しました。leaving in custody →becoming a discipleとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>天文12年（1543年）8月15日に元服して長尾景虎と名乗り、中越の長尾家領統治のため栃尾城に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torachiyo who reached the manhood on September 23, 1543 changed his name to Kagetora NAGAO, and entered Tochio-jo Castle to rule the territory of the Nagao family in Chuetsu.</e>
<cmt>天文12年（1543年）8月15日→September 23, 1543[こよみのページより]長尾家→the Nagao family[対訳では、the Nagao Family と &quot;family&quot;を大文字にて表記しておりますが、用語統一リストに従い、小文字に変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torachiyo, on attaining manhood on September 23, 1543 changed his name to Kagetora NAGAO, and entered Tochio-jo Castle to rule the territory of the Nagao family in Chuetsu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torachiyo, on attaining manhood on September 23, 1543 changed his name to Kagetora NAGAO, and entered Tochio-jo Castle to rule the territory of the Nagao family in Chuetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>当時、越後では守護上杉定実が伊達稙宗の子・伊達実元（伊達実元）を婿養子に迎える件で天文の乱が起こっており、越後の国人衆も養子縁組に賛成派と反対派に二分されていたが、兄の晴景は病弱なこともあって内紛を治めることはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, although the Tenbun War occurred in Echigo Province over an adoption of Sanemoto DATE, son of Tanemune DATE, as daughter&apos;s husband by Sadazane UESUGI, shugo (a provincial military governor), and kokujin-shu (powerful families in a province) were divided into two groups of approving of and disapproving of such adoption, Kenshin&apos;s older brother, Harukage, could not settle the internal conflict because he was sickly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that time, the Tenbun War broke out in Echigo Province when Sadazane UESUGI was to adopt Sanemoto DATE, son of Tanemune DATE, as a son-in-law, two groups comprising shugo (a provincial military governer) and Kokujin-shu (powerful families in a province) were divided in favor or opposing such an adoption, Kenshin&apos;s brother, Harukage, could not settle this internal conflict due to his illness.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that time, the Tenbun War broke out in Echigo Province when Sadazane UESUGI, Shugo (a provincial military governer), was to adopt Sanemoto DATE, son of Tanemune DATE, as a son-in-law, and Kokujin-shu (powerful families in a province) in the province were divided in favor or opposing such an adoption, but Kenshin&apos;s brother, Harukage, could not settle this internal conflict due to his illness.</e>
<cmt>shugoの頭文字を大文字に変更し、移動しました。訳漏れのin the provinceを追加しました。アポストロフィーを半角に変更しました。butを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>景虎は元服した同年、病弱な晴景を侮り反乱を起こした越後の豪族を討伐することで初陣を飾った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year as reaching the manhood, Kagetora played an active role in his uijin (first battle) by subduing Gozoku (powerful families) in Echigo who despised sickly Harukage and caused a rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, on attaining manhood, Kagetora was decorated for his active role in uijin (first battle) for subduing Gozoku (powerful families) in Echigo, who had rebelled against the sickly Harukage.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, on attaining manhood, Kagetora won a victory in his first campaign for subduing local ruling families in Echigo Province who had rebelled against the sickly Harukage.</e>
<cmt>decorated forで「初陣を飾る」は「最初の戦いに勝利した」と修正しました。Provinceを追加しました。豪族をlocal ruling familiesに修正し、カンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>天文15年（1546年）には黒滝城城主の黒田秀忠が長尾氏に対して謀反を起こすと、景虎は、兄に代わって上杉定実から討伐を命じられ、総大将として黒田氏を滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hidetada KURODA, lord of Kurotaki-jo Castle, caused a rebellion against the Nagao clan, Kagetora was ordered by Sanezane UESUGI to subdue Hidetada on behalf of his older brother, and ruined the Kuroda clan as a supreme commander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hidetada KURODA, lord of Kurotaki-jo Castle, rebelled against the Nagao clan, Kagetora was ordered by Sadazane UESUGI to subdue Hidetada on behalf of his older brother as supreme commander eventually he destroyed the Kuroda clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hidetada KURODA, lord of Kurotaki-jo Castle, rebelled against the Nagao clan in 1546, Kagetora was ordered by Sadazane UESUGI to subdue Hidetada on behalf of his older brother as supreme commander and eventually destroyed the Kuroda clan.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れのin 1546を追加しました。andを追加し、heを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>するとかねてから晴景に不満をもっていた越後の国人の一部は景虎を擁立し晴景に退陣を迫るようになり、晴景と景虎との関係は険悪なものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, some local lords in Echigo Province who had been dissatisfied with Harukage backed up Kagetora and forced Harukage to withdraw, and as a result, relations between Harukage and Kagetora were aggravated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some local lords in Echigo Province were dissatisfied with Harukage, backed Kagetora and forced Harukage to withdraw, as a result, relations between Harukage and Kagetora was aggravated.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some local lords in Echigo Province, who had been dissatisfied with Harukage, backed Kagetora and forced Harukage to withdraw; as a result, relations between Harukage and Kagetora was aggravated.</e>
<cmt>「かねてから」を訳出しました。カンマをセミコロンに変更しました。relationsに呼応するbe動詞を複数に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>天文17年（1548年）、定実の調停のもと、12月30日、晴景は景虎を養子とした上で家督を譲って隠退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 30, 1548 in old lunar calendar, Harukage who adopted Kagetora transferred the family headship to him, and withdrew, through the mediation of Sanezane.</e>
<cmt>12月30日→December 30, 1548 in old lunar calendar[新暦に換算すると、翌年の2月7日となり、後述の「2年後の天文19年（1550年）と整合しなくなるので、旧暦にて表記しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 30, 1548 of the old lunar calendar, through the mediation of Sadazane, Harukage, who had adopted Kagetora, transferred the family headship to him and retired.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Feburary 7, 1549, through the mediation of Sadazane, Harukage adopted Kagetora, then transferred the family headship to him and retired.</e>
<cmt>日付はグレゴリオ暦で表記し、後述の「２年後」は「旧暦で２年後」である旨を明記して対応しました。,_who_hadを削除しthenを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>景虎は長尾氏の本拠である春日山城に入り、19歳で家督を相続し、越後守護代となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagetora entered Kasugayama-jo Castle which was a headquarter of Nagao clan, succeeded to the family headship at the age of 19, and became shugodai (deputy military governor) of Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagetora entered Kasugayama-jo Castle which was a headquarter of Nagao clan, succeeded to the family headship at the age of 19, and became shugodai (deputy military governor) of Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagetora entered Kasugayama-jo Castle which was a headquarter of Nagao clan, and at the age of 19, succeeded to the family headship and became Shugodai of Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>shugodaiの頭文字を大文字に変更し、既出の為、説明を削除しました。at the age of 19,を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>2年後の天文19年（1550年）には、定実が後継者を遺さずに死去したため、将軍・足利義輝は景虎の越後国主の地位を認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1550 two years after that, Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA recognized a social status of Kagetora as lord of Echigo Province because Sanezane had no successors when he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1550, two years later, Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA recognized the social status of Kagatora as lord of Echigo Province, as Sadazane died with no successors.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1550, two years later in the old lunar calender, Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA recognized the social status of Kagatora as lord of Echigo Province, as Sadazane died with no successors.</e>
<cmt>in the old lunar calenderを追加して「旧暦で２年後」である旨を明記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>同年、一族の坂戸城主・長尾政景（上田長尾家）が景虎の家督相続に不満を持って反乱を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Masakage NAGAO (Ueda Nagao family) who was a member of the family and a lord of Sakato-jo Castle caused a rebellion because he was dissatisfied with Kagetora&apos;s succession to the family headship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Masakage NAGAO (Ueda Nagao family), a member of the family and lord of Sakato-jo Castle rebelled, as he was dissatisfied with Kagetora&apos;s succession to the family headship.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Masakage NAGAO (Ueda Nagao family), a member of the family and lord of Sakato-jo Castle rebelled, as he was dissatisfied with Kagetora&apos;s succession to the family headship.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを半角に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし景虎は、翌年天文20年（1551年）に鎮圧している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kagetora settled it in the following year, 1551.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1551, the following year Kagetora suppressed the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1551, the following year Kagetora suppressed the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>川中島の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Kawanakajima</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Kawanakajima</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Kawanakajima</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>天文年間には甲相駿三国同盟を背景とした甲斐の武田信玄による信濃侵攻と相模の北条氏康による北関東侵攻が本格化しており、甲相同盟により相互に出兵した両者の侵攻により、景虎は二正面作戦を余儀なくされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tenbun era, the invasion of Shinano by Shingen TAKEDA in Kai Province and the invasion of Kita Kanto (Northern Kanto) by Ujiyasu HOJO were implemented on a full-scale basis against a backdrop of Ko So Sun Sangoku Domei (tripartite of Kai-Sagami-Suruga alliance), and due to invasion by both parties mutually dispatching troops under the Koso Alliance (an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Hojo clan in Sagami Province), Kagetora was forced to take a double front strategy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tenbun era, invasions of Shinano by Shingen TAKEDA, Kai Province, and of Kita Kanto (Northern Kanto) by Ujiyasu HOJO were implemented full-scale against a backdrop of Ko So Sun Sangoku Domei (tripartite of Kai-Sagami- Suruga alliance), due to these invasions both parties under the Koso Alliance (an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Hojo clan in Sagami Province), Kagetora was forced to take a double front strategy.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tenbun era, invasions of Shinano by Shingen TAKEDA, Kai Province, and of Kita Kanto (Northern Kanto) by Ujiyasu HOJO, Sagami Province, were implemented full-scale against a backdrop of Ko So Sun Sangoku Domei (tripartite of Kai-Sagami- Suruga alliance), and due to these invasions by both parties which dispatched troops to each other under the Koso Alliance (an alliance between the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Hojo clan in Sagami Province), Kagetora was forced to take a double front strategy.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れのSagami Provinceを追加しました。andを追加しました。ｂyを追加しました。whichを追加しました。dispatched troops to each other を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>氏康による攻勢を受けていた上野国平井城に拠る関東管領の上杉憲政が、越後に対して救援を求めると景虎はただちに出兵して北条軍を破り、憲政を平井城へ戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Norimasa UESUGI, Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), based at Hirai-jo Castle in Kozuke Province, was attacked by Ujiyasu and asked the Uesugi clan in Echigo Province for help, Kagetora immediately dispatched troops and defeated the Hojo army, and then returned Norimasa to Hirai-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>越後→the Uesugi clan in Echigo Province[上記の甲相同盟の説明において、&quot;the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Hojo clan in Sagami Province&quot;と記載しており、また越後という地名だけでは意味不明と解釈し、『越後の上杉氏』として英訳しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ujiyasu attacked Norimasa UESUGI, Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), at Hirai-jo Castle in Kozuke Province, he seeked the help of the Uesugi clan in Echigo province, Kagetora immediately dispatched troops and defeated the Hojo army, and returned Hirai-jo Castle to Norimasa.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Norimasa UESUGI, Kanto Kanrei, based at Hirai-jo Castle in Kozuke Province, was attacked by Ujiyasu and seeked the help of the Uesugi clan in Echigo Province, Kagetora immediately dispatched troops and defeated the Hojo army, and let Norimasa to go back to Hirai-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>主節の主語をNorimasaに変更しました。既出の「関東管領」の説明を削除しました。「拠る」を訳出し、atをbased atに変更しました。provinceの頭文字を大文字に変更しました。andを追加しました。「憲政を平井城へ戻した」をlet Norimasa to go back toHirai-jo Castleに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>越後の隣国・上野へ力を伸ばす北条氏は、越後の安全を確保する上でも脅威だったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because the Hojo clan who extended his power to Kozuke Province, neighboring province of Echigo, was also a threat in securing the safety of Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan extended their power to Kozuke Province, a neighboring province of Echigo Province, which was a threat to secure the safety of Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo clan, who extended their power to Kozuke Province, a neighboring province of Echigo Province, was also a threat to Kagetora in securing the safety of Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>「北条氏」に掛かる部分を, whoで括り、「脅威だった」の意味上の目的語としてKagetoraを訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>天文21年（1552年）1月、上杉憲政を越後に迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1552, Kagetora received Norimasa UESUGI into Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>天文21年（1552年）1月→February 1552[新暦に換算すると、1月1日が2月5日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1552, Kagetora received Norimasa UESUGI into Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1552, Kagetora received Norimasa UESUGI into Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>4月23日、従五位下弾正少弼に叙任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 26, 1552, Kagetora was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) danjo-shohitsu (Associate Deputy Minister of Justice).</e>
<cmt>4月23日→May 26[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 26, 1552, Kagetora was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) danjo-shohitsu (Associate Deputy Minister of Justice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 26, 1552, Kagetora was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) danjo-shohitsu (Associate Deputy Minister of Justice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>天文22年（1553年）9月、上洛して後奈良天皇および室町幕府第13代将軍・足利義輝に謁見している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1553, Kagetora went up to Kyoto, and had an audience with Emperor Gonara and the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>天文22年（1553年）9月→October 1553[新暦に換算すると、9月1日は10月18日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1553, Kagetora proceeded to Kyoto to have an audience with Emperor Gonara and the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1553, Kagetora proceeded to Kyoto to have an audience with Emperor Gonara and the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA of the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>同年、甲斐国の武田晴信の信濃侵攻によって領地を追われた村上義清・高梨政頼（景虎の叔父）らの信濃国人が領地復権を望んで景虎のもとへ逃亡してくると、8月にはこれに応じて信濃に出兵し、川中島（長野市南郊）で晴信と対峙する（第1次川中島の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, when local lords in Shinano Province such as Yoshikiyo MURAKAMI, Masayori TAKANASHI (Kagetora&apos;s uncle) and so on who got kicked out of their territories due to the invasion of Shinano by Harunobu TAKEDA in Kai Province escaped to Kagetora with the hope of reinstatement of territories, Kagetora dispatched troops to Shinano Province in response to such request in September of the same year, and confronted Harunobu at Kawanakajima (southern suburb of Nagano City) (the first Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>8月→September[新暦に換算すると、8月1日は9月18日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Harunobu TAKEDA in Kai Province, deposed from their territories local lords in Shinano Province such as Yoshikiyo MURAKAMI, Masayori TAKANASHI (Kagetora&apos;s uncle) and so on who all escaped and went to Kagetora with the hope of reinstating their territories, Kagetora dispatched troops to Shinano Province in response to the request in September and confronted Harunobu at Kawanakajima (southern surburb of Nagano City) (the first Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, when local lords in Shinano Province such as Yoshikiyo MURAKAMI, Masayori TAKANASHI (Kagetora&apos;s uncle) and so on who were disposed of their territories due to the invasion of Shinano Province by Harunobu TAKEDA in Kai Province and escaped to Kagetora with the hope of reinstatement of their territories, Kagetora dispatched troops to Shinano Province in response to the request in September and confronted Harunobu at Kawanakajima (southern surburb of Nagano City) (the first Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>「村上義清・高梨政頼」を主語に変更。しましたアポストロフィーを全角に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>天文23年（1554年）、家臣の北条高広（きたじょう たかひろ）が武田と通じて謀反を起こしたが、天文24年（1555年）には自らが出陣してこれを鎮圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Takahiro KITAJO, Kagetora&apos;s vassal, trafficked with the Takeda clan and caused a rebellion in 1554, Kagetora himself departed for the front and settled this rebellion in 1555.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Takahiro KITAJO, Kagetora&apos;s vassal, trafficked with the Takeda clan and initiated a rebellion in 1554, Kagetora himself departed for the front and suppressed the rebellion in 1555.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Takahiro KITAJO, Kagetora&apos;s vassal, trafficked with the Takeda clan and initiated a rebellion in 1554, Kagetora himself departed for the front and suppressed the rebellion in 1555.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを全角に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>4月、晴信と川中島で再び対峙したが（第2次川中島の戦い）、決着はつかず対陣5ヶ月に及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kagetora confronted Harunobu at Kawanakajima again (the second Battle of Kawanakajima) in May 1555, the battle was still unsettled, and they were encamped facing each other for five months.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処4月→May 1555[新暦に換算すると、4月1日は5月1日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kagetora confronted Harunobu at Kawanakajima again (the second Battle of Kawanakajima) in May 1555, the battle was still unsettled, and they were encamped facing each other for five months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kagetora confronted Harunobu at Kawanakajima again (the second Battle of Kawanakajima) in May 1555, the battle was still unsettled, and they were encamped facing each other for five months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>最終的には駿河国の今川義元の仲介のもとに和睦して撤退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They finally made peace through under the auspices of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA in Suruga Province and withdrew.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They finally made peace and withdrew under the mediation of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They finally made peace and withdrew under the mediation of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA in Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>ところが弘治_(日本)2年（1556年）6月、出家すると宣言して高野山（一説に比叡山）に向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in July 1556, Kagetora declared that he would enter into priesthood, and left for Mt. Koya (or Mt. Hiei according to another theory).</e>
<cmt>弘治_(日本)2年（1556年）6月→July 1556[新暦に換算すると、6月1日は7月17日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in July 1556, Kagetora declared that he would enter into priesthood, and left for Mt. Koya (or Mt. Hiei according to a theory).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in July 1556, Kagetora declared that he would enter into priesthood, and left for Mt. Koya (or Mt. Hiei according to a theory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この頃、武田氏との抗争や家臣同士の領土争いの調停で心身が疲れきっていたとも言われているが、天室光育、長尾政景らの説得で出家を断念した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it has been said that Kagetora was physically and mentally fatigued with mediation of dispute with the Takeda clan and of dispute among vassals over territories around this time, he gave up entering into priesthood by persuasions of Koiku TENSHITSU, Masakage NAGAO and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is said that Kagetora was physically and mentally fatigued by disputes with the Takeda clan and other vassals over territories, he gave up entering priesthood by persuasions of Koiku TENSHITSU, Masakage NAGAO and so on.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is said that Kagetora was physically and mentally fatigued by dispute with the Takeda clan and by mediation of dispute among vassals over territories, he gave up entering priesthood by persuasions of Koiku TENSHITSU, Masakage NAGAO and so on.</e>
<cmt>disputesを単数にしました。訳詞漏れの「調停」を「家臣同士の領土争い」に掛けて訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>弘治3年（1557年）4月、川中島に出陣する（第三次川中島の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1557, Kagetora departed for the front at Kawanakajima (the third Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>弘治3年（1557年）4月→May 1557[新暦に換算すると、4月1日は5月9日になるので(こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1557, Kagetora departed for the front at Kawanakajima (the third Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1557, Kagetora departed for the front at Kawanakajima (the third Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし武田軍とは睨み合いに終始し、さらに越中で一向一揆が起こったため、撤退を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since he was entirely-focused on face-off with the Takeda army, and moreover an uprising of Ikko sect followers occurred in Ecchu Province, Kagetora was forced to withdraw.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when he was preoccupied face to face with the Takeda army, an uprising of the Ikko sect followers occurred in Ecchu Province, thus Kagetora was forced to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Kagetora was preoccupied face to face with the Takeda army, an uprising of the Ikko sect followers occurred in Ecchu Province, thus he was forced to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>Kagetoraとheを移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>関東管領就任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assumption of Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assumption of Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assumption of Kanto Kanrei</e>
<cmt>既出の「関東管領」の説明を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>永禄2年（1559年）4月、再度上洛して正親町天皇や将軍・足利義輝に拝謁する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1559, Kagetora went up to Kyoto again, and had an audience with the Emperor Ogimachi and Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>永禄2年（1559年）4月→May 1559[新暦に換算すると、4月1日は5月17日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1559, Kageotra went up to Kyoto again, to have an audience with the Emperor Ogimachi and Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1559, Kagetora went up to Kyoto again to have an audience with the Emperor Ogimachi and Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>KageotraをKagetoraに修正。カンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>このとき、義輝から管領並の待遇を与えられた（上杉の七免許）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he received treatments at the same level as kanrei (shogunal deputy) from Yoshiteru (Uesugi&apos;s seven licenses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This time, he received the same treatment as a kanrei (shogunal deputy) from Yoshiteru (Uesugi&apos;s seven licenses).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This time, he received the same treatment as a kanrei (shogunal deputy) from Yoshiteru (Uesugi&apos;s seven licenses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>景虎と義輝との関係は親密なものであったが、義輝が幕府の重臣である大舘晴光を派遣して景虎・晴信・氏康の三者の和睦を斡旋し三好長慶の勢力を駆逐するために協力するよう説得した際には、三者の考え方の溝は大きく実現しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kagetora had a close relationship with Yoshiteru, when Yoshiteru dispatched Harumitsu ODACHI, a chief retainer of bakufu, to mediate a settlement among three persons of Kagetora, Harunobu and Ujiyasu, and persuaded them to cooperate in driving out the force of Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, such cooperation was not realized because their ideas differed largely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inspite of a close relationship between Kagetora and Yoshiteru, when Yoshiteru dispatched Harumitsu ODACHI, a chief retainer of bakufu, to mediate an alliance among Kagetora, Harunobu and Ujiyasu and to persuade them to cooperate in expelling the force of Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, the alliance was not realized due to the large differences in ideas.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inspite of a close relationship between Kagetora and Yoshiteru, when Yoshiteru dispatched Harumitsu ODACHI, a chief retainer of bakufu, to mediate an alliance among Kagetora, Harunobu and Ujiyasu and to persuade them to cooperate in expelling the force of Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, the alliance was not realized due to the large differences in ideas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>永禄3年（1560年）3月、越中に出陣し、神保長職を破って椎名康胤を援けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1560, Kagetora departed for the front in Ecchu Province, and helped Yasutane SHIINA by defeating Nagamoto JINBO.</e>
<cmt>永禄3年（1560年）3月→April 1560[新暦に換算すると、3月1日は4月6日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1560, Kagetora departed for the front in Ecchu Province, and helped Yasutane SHIINA by defeating Nagamoto JINBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1560, Kagetora departed for the front in Ecchu Province, and helped Yasutane SHIINA by defeating Nagamoto JINBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>5月、関東に出陣して厩橋城で越年する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1560, Kagetora departed for the front in the Kanto region, and kept over the winter at Umayabashi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>5月→June 1560[新暦に換算すると、5月1日は6月4日となるので（こよみのページより）]厩橋城→Umayabashi-jo Castle[対訳では、Umayabashi Castle と表記されておりますが、他の城の表記に合わせ、変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1560, Kagetora departed for the front in the Kanto region, and remained at Umayabashi-jo Castle for the rest of the year.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1560, Kagetora departed for the front in the Kanto region, and remained at Umayabashi-jo Castle for the rest of the year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>武蔵松山城 (武蔵国)を攻め落とし、永禄4年（1561年）3月に関東管領・上杉憲政を擁して長野業正、小山秀綱、小田氏治、那須資胤、佐竹義重 (十八代当主)、太田資正、三田綱秀、成田長泰ら旧上杉家家臣団10万の大軍で小田原城を包囲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagetora who captured Musashi Matsuyama-jo Castle (Musashi Province) supported Norimasa UESUGI, Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) in March 1561, and besieged Odawara-jo Castle with a large force consisting of 100,000 vassals of old Uesugi clan such as Narimasa NAGANO, Hidetsuna OYAMA, Ujiharu ODA, Suketane NASU, Yoshishige SATAKE (the 18th family head), Sukemasa OTA, Tsunahide MITA, Nagayasu NARITA and so on.</e>
<cmt>永禄4年（1561年）3月→March 1561[新暦に換算すると、3月1日は3月26日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagetora captured Musashi Matsuyama-jo Castle (Musashi Province) supported Norimasa UESUGI, Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) in March 1561, and besieged Odawara-jo Castle with a large force consisting of 100,000 vassals of old Uesugi clan such as Narimasa NAGANO, Hidetsuna OYAMA, Ujiharu ODA, Suketane NASU, Yoshishige SATAKE (the 18th family head), Sukemasa OTA, Tsunahide MITA, Nagayasu NARITA and so on.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagetora captured Musashi Matsuyama-jo Castle (Musashi Province), and in March 1561, supported Norimasa UESUGI, Kanto Kanrei, and besieged Odawara-jo Castle with a large force consisting of 100,000 vassals of old Uesugi clan such as Narimasa NAGANO, Hidetsuna OYAMA, Ujiharu ODA, Suketane NASU, Yoshishige SATAKE (the 18th family head), Sukemasa OTA, Tsunahide MITA, Nagayasu NARITA and so on.</e>
<cmt>既出の「関東管領」の説明を削除しました。In March 1561を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>また小田原へ向かう途上には、関東公方の在所で当時は関東の中心と目されていた古河御所を制圧し、北条氏の傀儡であった足利義氏 (古河公方)を放逐のうえ足利藤氏（本来の正統な古河公方）を替りに古河御所内に迎え入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, on the way to Odawara, Kagetora took Kogagosho (residence of Koga-kubo) in control, which was regarded as a hometown of Kanto-kubo and as a center of Kanto region at that time, and after expelling Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (Kogakubo (descendants of one of the Ashikaga families that held the office of the Kanto district administrator) who was a puppet of the Hojo clan, he received Fujiuji ASHIKAGA (originally legitimate Kogakubo) in the Kogagosho instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the way to Odawara, Kagetora took over Kogagosho(residence of Koga-kubo) a hometown of Kanot-kubo and center of Kanto region, later expelling Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (Kogakubo (descendants of one of the Ashikaga families that held the office of the Kanto district administrator)), who was a puppet of the Hojo clan, and instead reinstated Fujiuji ASHIKAGA (original legitimate Kogakubo).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way to Odawara, Kagetora took over Kogagosho(residence of Koga-kubo), which was a hometown of Kanto-kubo and regarded as the center of Kanto region, later expelling Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (Kogakubo (descendants of one of the Ashikaga families that held the office of the Kanto district administrator)), who was a puppet of the Hojo clan, and instead reinstated Fujiuji ASHIKAGA (original legitimate Kogakubo).</e>
<cmt>Kanot-kuboを修正しました。, which wasを追加しました。「目されていた」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし小田原城自体は、落城させることができず、1ヶ月後に鎌倉に兵を引いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he failed to have Odawara-jo Castle itself fall, and withdrew his soldiers to Kamakura one month later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he failed to take over Odawara-jo Castle and so withdrew his soldiers to Kamakura a month later.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he failed to take over Odawara-jo Castle and so withdrew his soldiers to Kamakura a month later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし、この間に景虎は、上杉憲政の要請もあって鎌倉府の鶴岡八幡宮において閏3月16日、山内上杉家の家督と関東管領職を相続、名を上杉政虎（うえすぎ まさとら）と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, during this period, Kagetora succeeded to the family headship of Yamanouchi-Uesugi family and the post of Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) at Kamakura Hachimangu Shrine of Kamakura bakufu on May 10, 1561 also at the request of Norimasa UESUGI, and changed his name to Masatora UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>閏3月16日→May 10, 1561[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, Kagetora succeeded to the family headship of Yamanouchi-Uesugi family and the post of Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) at Kamakura Hachimangu Shrine of Kamakura bakufu on May 10, 1561, also at the request of Norimasa UESUGI, he changed his name to Masatora UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, Kagetora succeeded to the family headship of Yamanouchi-Uesugi family and the post of Kanto Kanrei at Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine of Kamakura Government on May 10, 1561, also at the request of Norimasa UESUGI, he changed his name to Masatora UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>既出の「関東管領」の説明を削除しました。Kamakura Hachimangu をTsurugaoka Hachiman-guに修正しました。Kamakura bakufuをKamakura Governmentに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="49">
<j>関東管領の職は本来、古河公方（鎌倉公方）を助けることが職務であるため、北条に侵略されていた古河御所の奪還と、本来の正統な相続者である足利藤氏を古河公方に擁立することに成功した景虎は朝廷および幕府からも関東の諸大名からも認められた上杉氏の家督相続と関東管領就任であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the duty of Kanto Kanrei was originally to assist Kogakubo (Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region), it was also recognized by the Imperial court, bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and territorial lords in the Kanto region that Kagetora who succeeded in regaining control of Kogagosho (residence of Koga-kubo) invaded by the Hojo clan and in putting Fujiuji ASHIKAGA, originally legitimate successor, forward as Kogakubo inherited the family headship of Uesugi clan and assumed Kanto kanrei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The duty of Kanto Kanrei was originally to assist the Kogakubo (Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region), it was also recognized by the Imperial court, bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and territorial lords in the Kanto region that Kagetora succeeded in regaining control of Kogagosho (residence of Koga-kubo) which was invaded by the Hojo clan, he put forward Fujiuji ASHIKAGA, original legitimate successor, as Kogakubo, thus Kagetora inherited the family headship of Uesugi clan and assumed Kanto Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The duty of Kanto Kanrei was originally to assist the Kogakubo (Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region)), and since Kagetora succeeded in regaining control of Kogagosho which was invaded by the Hojo clan and put forward Fujiuji ASHIKAGA, original legitimate successor, as Kogakubo, it was also recognized by the Imperial court, bakufu and territorial lords in the Kanto region that Kagetora inherited the family headship of Uesugi clan and assumed Kanto Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>「奪還と、・・・擁立に成功した」を移動しました。「括弧閉じ」を追加しました。既出の「古河御所」の説明を削除しました。既出の幕府の説明を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="50">
<j>もともと上杉家は足利氏の外戚として名門の地位にあり、関東管領職はその縁で代々任じられてきた役職であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally the Uesugi family was in the position of family of pedigree as a maternal relative of Ashikaga clan, and had been appointed to Kanto Kanrei for generations due to such relationship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally the Uesugi family inherited the family pedigree of a maternal relative of the Ashikaga clan, and has been appointed to Kanto Kanrei for generations due to such a relationship.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally the Uesugi family inherited the family pedigree of a maternal relative of the Ashikaga clan, and had been appointed to Kanto Kanrei for generations due to such a relationship.</e>
<cmt>hasをhadに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>長尾家は上杉家の家臣筋であり、しかも上杉家の本姓が藤原氏なのに対して長尾家は桓武平氏であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nagao family was a vassal of Uesugi family, and furthermore, the real family name of Uesugi family was the Fujiwara clan while that of Nagao family was Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nagao family was a vassal of the Uesugi family, furthermore the real family name of the Uesugi family was Fujiwara while that of Nagao family was Kammu-Heishi (Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nagao family was a vassal of the Uesugi family, furthermore, the real family name of the Uesugi family was Fujiwara while that of Nagao family was Kammu-Heishi (Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>読み易さの為、カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>異姓にして家臣筋の長尾景虎が上杉氏の名跡を継承するに至った背景には、かねてから上杉家に養子を招くことを望んでいた上杉憲政が、上杉家から養子を出したことのある佐竹氏からの養子を断られ、苦悩の末に越後国の実力者である長尾景虎に継がせたという経緯がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a background to succession to the family name of Uesugi clan by Kagetora NAGAO whose real family name was different and who was a vassal, there was a history that Norimasa UESUGI who had always desired to adopt a child from the Uesugi family received a refusal of adoption from the Satake clan who had adopted a child from the Uesugi family, and made a tough decision to have Kagetora NAGAO, influential person in Echigo Province, succeed to the family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The circumstance to the inheritance to a family name of Uesugi clan by Kagetora NAGAO who was a vassal with a different real name, Norimasa UESUGI always desired to adopt a child from the Uesugi family, was refused adoption from the Satake clan who in turn had adopted a child from the Uesugi family, then Norimasa made a tough decision to adopt Kagetora NAGAO, an influential person in Echigo Province who succeed to the family name.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The circumstance to the inheritance to a family name of Uesugi clan by Kagetora NAGAO who was a vassal with a different real name was that Norimasa UESUGI always desired to adopt a child to the Uesugi family but was refused from the Satake clan who had adopted a child from the Uesugi family, then made a tough decision to have Kagetora NAGAO, an influential person in Echigo Province, succeed to the family name.</e>
<cmt>背景説明を加える為、was thatを追加しました。Fromをtoに変更しました。In turnを削除しました。カンマを追加し、adoptをhave…succeed toに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="53">
<j>ただし、藩翰譜によると、政虎自身が上杉頼成の男系子孫であるという記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &apos;Hankanpu&apos; (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) had a description that Masatora himself was a descendant in the male line of Yorinari UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is an account in the &apos;Hankanpu&apos; (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) that Masatora was a male descendant of Yorinari UESUGI..</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is an account in the &apos;Hankanpu&apos; (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) that Masatora was a male descendant of Yorinari UESUGI..</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィーを全角に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>応仁武鑑や萩原家譜案にも、上杉頼成の男子（長尾藤景）が長尾氏へ入嗣した旨が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oninbukan (a book of heraldry in the Onin era) and Hakiwara-kafuan (proposed genealogical table of the Hagiwara family) also had a description to the effect that a son (Fujikage NAGAO) of Yorinari UESUGI was adopted by the Nagao clan as an heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onin Bukan(a book of heraldy in the Onin era) and Hagiwara-kafun (proposed genealogical table of the Hagiwara family) also has a description to the effect that a son (Fujikage NAGAO) of Yorinari UESUGI was adopted by the Nagao clan as an heir.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onin Bukan(a book of heraldry in the Onin era) and Hagiwara-kafuan (proposed genealogical table of the Hagiwara family) also has a description to the effect that a son (Fujikage NAGAO) of Yorinari UESUGI was adopted by the Nagao clan as an heir.</e>
<cmt>heraldryをheraldryに修正。Hagiwara-kafunをHagiwara-kafuanに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>しかし、他の系図では上杉家から養子を迎えたのは下総に分家した長尾であって、越後長尾氏には直接関係無いとする系図がほとんど（長尾景為或いは長尾景能の流れ）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, most of other family trees showed that the Nagao family established in Shimousa Province as a branch family adopted a child from the Uesugi family, and the Echigo Nagao clan had no direct relationship (a line of Kagetame NAGAO or Kageyoshi NAGAO).</e>
<cmt>長尾影能→Kageyoshi NAGAO[影能の読み方は、仮表記です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, most of the other family trees show that the Nagao family established in Shimousa Province as a branch family adopted a child from the Uesugi family, and the Echigo Nagao clan had almost no direct relationship (a line of Kagetame NAGAO or Kageyoshi NAGAO).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, most of the other family trees show that the Nagao family established in Shimousa Province as a branch family adopted a child from the Uesugi family, and the Echigo Nagao clan had almost no direct relationship (a line of Kagetame NAGAO or Kageyoshi NAGAO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>実際の血統が繋がっていなくとも、長尾家も佐竹家と同じく上杉家からの養子を迎えた家系ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that as well as the Satake family, the Nagao family belonged to a line of family adopting a child from the Uesugi family even though a blood line was not connected actually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both the Satake and the Nagao families belonged to a line of family by adopting a child from the Uesugi family, although there was no direct blood line.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the Satake and the Nagao families belonged to a line of family by adopting a child from the Uesugi family, although there was no direct blood line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>武田信玄・北条氏康との戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle with Shingen TAKEDA and Ujiyasu HOJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle with Shingen TAKEDA and Ujiyasu HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle with Shingen TAKEDA and Ujiyasu HOJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>帰国後の永禄4年（1561年）8月、1万3000の兵を率いて川中島に出陣する（第4次川中島の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1561 after coming back to own Province, Masatora UESUGI led 13,000 soldiers and departed for the front at Kawanakajima (the fourth Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>永禄4年（1561年）8月→September 1561[新暦に換算すると、8月1日は9月20日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1561, after returning to their own Province, Masatora UESUGI led 13,000 soldiers and departed for the front at Kawanakajima (the fourth Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1561, after returning to their own Province, Masatora UESUGI led 13,000 soldiers and departed for the front at Kawanakajima (the fourth Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>このとき、武田軍と大決戦に及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, a battle with the Takeda army developed to a mighty one.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, a battle with the Takeda army developed to a mighty one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, a battle with the Takeda army developed to a mighty one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>信玄の実弟である武田信繁・武田軍軍師山本勘助らを討ち取ったが、上杉軍の死傷者も甚大で、結局痛み分けに終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it killed Nobushige TAKEDA, Shingen&apos;s own younger brother, and Kansuke YAMAMOTO, strategist of Takeda army, the Uesugi army also had an enormous number of casualties and this Battle ended up in a draw due to damage to both armies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although, Nobushige TAKEDA, Shingen&apos;s younger brother, and Kansuke YAMAMOTO, strategist of Takeda army were killed, the Uesugi army also had an enormous number of casualties and the Battle ended in a draw due to damage to both armies.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although, Nobushige TAKEDA, Shingen&apos;s younger brother, and Kansuke YAMAMOTO, strategist of Takeda army were killed, the Uesugi army also had an enormous number of casualties and the Battle ended in a draw due to damage to both armies.</e>
<cmt>記号の修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>11月、再び関東に出て氏康と戦う（生野山合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1561, Masatora went to the Kanto region again, and fought with Ujiyasu (the Battle of Mt. Ikuno).</e>
<cmt>11月→December 1561[新暦に換算すると、11月1日は12月17日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1561, Masatora returned to the Kanto region, and fought with Ujiyasu (the Battle of Mt. Ikuno).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1561, Masatora returned to the Kanto region, and fought with Ujiyasu (the Battle of Mt. Ikuno).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>しかし川中島における軍勢の被害が甚大であり積極的に戦うことができず撤退する（内閣文庫所蔵・小幡家文書）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Masatora withdrew by reason that he could not fight actively due to great damage to the troops at the Battle of Kawanakajima (Obatake Monjo (documents of the Obata family) possessed in the Cabinet Library).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Masatora could not fight actively due to heavy damage to the troops at the Battle of Kawanakajima and had to withdraw (Obatake Monjo (documents of the Obata family) in the Cabinet Library).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Masatora could not fight actively due to heavy damage to the troops at the Battle of Kawanakajima and had to withdraw (Obatake Monjo (documents of the Obata family) in the Cabinet Library).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>その後は成田長泰や佐野昌綱を始め、武蔵国の同族上杉憲盛までもが北条方に降る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, not only Nagayasu NARITA and Masatsuna SANO but also Norimori UESUGI of kin in Musashi Province surrendered to the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, not only Nagayasu NARITA and Masatsuna SANO but also Norimori UESUGI of Musashi Province surrendered to the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, not only Nagayasu NARITA and Masatsuna SANO but also Norimori UESUGI of Musashi Province surrendered to the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>政虎は上野・武蔵・常陸・下野・下総などで転戦したが、関東における領土は主に東上野にとどまった（但し謙信没時、上野・下野・常陸の豪族の一部は上杉方）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Masatora moved from place to place to fight in the provinces of Kozuke, Musashi, Hitachi, Shimotsuke and Shimousa, his territories in the Kanto region remained mainly in the eastern part of Kozuke Province (however, some powerful families in the provinces of Kozuke, Shimotsuke and Hitachi took the side of Uesugi clan when Kenshin died).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Masatora moved from place to place to fight in the provinces of Kozuke, Musashi, Hitachi, Shimotsuke and Shimousa, his territories in the Kanto region remained mainly in the eastern part of Kozuke Province (however, some powerful families in the provinces of Kozuke, Shimotsuke and Hitachi took the side of Uesugi clan when Kenshin died).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Masatora moved from place to place to fight in the provinces of Kozuke, Musashi, Hitachi, Shimotsuke and Shimousa, his territories in the Kanto region remained mainly in the eastern part of Kozuke Province (however, some powerful families in the provinces of Kozuke, Shimotsuke and Hitachi took the side of Uesugi clan when Kenshin died).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>12月、将軍義輝の一字を賜り、諱を輝虎（てるとら）と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1562, Masatora was granted one letter (輝)from the name of Shogun Yoshiteru (義輝), and changed his imina (personal name) to Terutora (輝虎).</e>
<cmt>12月→January 1562[新暦に換算すると、12月1日は翌年の1月15日となるので（こよみのページより）]「輝」の一字を賜ったので、これを説明するため、漢字も併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1562, Masatora was granted one letter (輝)from the name of Shogun Yoshiteru (義輝), and changed his imina (personal name) to Terutora (輝虎).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1562, Masatora was granted one letter (輝)from the name of Shogun Yoshiteru (義輝), and changed his imina (personal name) to Terutora (輝虎).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="65">
<j>武田信玄と北信濃をめぐって川中島の戦いを行うが決着は着かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetutora conducted the Battle of Kawanakajima with Shingen TAKEDA over Kitashinano (northern part of Shinano Province), but the battle was unsettled.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terutora conducted the Battle of Kawanakajima with Shingen TAKEDA over Kitashinano (northern part of Shinano Province), but the battle was unsettled.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terutora conducted the Battle of Kawanakajima with Shingen TAKEDA over Kitashinano (northern part of Shinano Province), but the battle was unsettled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>結局のところ信濃の北辺の一部を掌握したのみで、村上氏、高梨氏らの旧領を回復することはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it turned out, Terutora only gained control of part of northern edge of Shinano Province, and failed to regain old territories of Murakami clan and Takanashi clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it turned out, Terutora only gained control of a part of the northern edge of Shinano Province, and failed to regain former territories of Murakami clan and Takanashi clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it turned out, Terutora only gained control of a part of the northern edge of Shinano Province, and failed to regain former territories of Murakami clan and Takanashi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>永禄5年（1562年）7月と9月、越中に出陣して椎名康胤を圧迫する神保長職を降伏させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August and October 1562, Masatora departed for the front in Ecchu Province, and forced Nagamoto JINBO oppressing Yasutane SHIINA to surrender.</e>
<cmt>永禄5年（1562年）７月と9月→August and October 1562[新暦に換算すると、7月1日は8月10日と、また9月1日は10月8日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August and October 1562, Terutora departed for the front in Ecchu Province, and forced Nagamoto JINBO who was oppressing Yasutane SHIINA to surrender.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August and October 1562, Terutora departed for the front in Ecchu Province, and forced Nagamoto JINBO who was oppressing Yasutane SHIINA to surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>永禄7年（1564年）、信玄と手を結んで越後へ攻め込んだ蘆名盛氏軍を撃破。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1564, he obliterated the army headed by Moriuji ASHINA which invaded Echigo Province under an alliance with Shingen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1564, he obliterated the army headed by Moriuji ASHINA which invaded Echigo Province under an alliance with Shingen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1564, he obliterated the army headed by Moriuji ASHINA which invaded Echigo Province under an alliance with Shingen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>その間に信玄が信濃野尻城 (信濃国)を攻略したが奪還し、後に川中島で再び対峙した（第5次川中島の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that time, Terutora regained Shinano Nojiri-jo Castle (Shinano Province) conquered by Shingen, but thereafter, he confronted Shingen at Kawanakajima again (the fifth Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meanwhile, Terutora captured Shinano Nojiri-jo Castle (Shinano Province) conquered by Shingen, thereafter, he again confronted Shingen at Kawanakajima again (the fifth Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meanwhile, Terutora captured Shinano Nojiri-jo Castle (Shinano Province) conquered by Shingen, thereafter, he again confronted Shingen at Kawanakajima again (the fifth Battle of Kawanakajima).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>しかし60日に及ぶ対峙の末に撤退し、決着は着かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Terutora withdrew after confronting Shingen for 60 days, and the Battle was unsettled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Terutora withdrew after confronting Shingen for 60 days, and the Battle was unsettled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Terutora withdrew after confronting Shingen for 60 days, and the Battle was unsettled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="71">
<j>関東の戦線では輝虎が永禄5年（1562年）に上野館林城主の赤井氏を滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the front line in the Kanto region, Tetutora ruined the Akai clan, lord of Kozuke Tatebayashi-jo Castle, in 1562.</e>
<cmt>館林城→Tatebayashi-jo Castle[対訳では、Tatebayashi Castle と表記されておりますが、他の城の表記に合わせ、変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1562, at the front in Kanto region, Terutora destroyed the Akai clan, lord of Kozuke Tatebayashi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1562, at the front in Kanto region, Terutora destroyed the Akai clan, lord of Kozuke Tatebayashi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>その後は武蔵の成田氏、下野の小山氏、下総の結城氏を降伏させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Terutora succeeded in having the Narita clan in Musashi Province, the Oyama clan in Shimotsuke Province and the Yuki clan in Shimousa Province surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Terutora succeeded in having the Narita clan in Musashi Province, the Oyama clan in Shimotsuke Province and the Yuki clan in Shimousa Province to surrender.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Terutora succeeded in having the Narita clan in Musashi Province, the Oyama clan in Shimotsuke Province and the Yuki clan in Shimousa Province to surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>永禄7年（1564年）には下野の佐野氏を数度降伏させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1564, he succeeded in having the Sano clan in Shimotsuke Province surrender several times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1564, he succeeded in having the Sano clan in Shimotsuke Province to surrender several times.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1564, he succeeded in having the Sano clan in Shimotsuke Province to surrender several times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>永禄9年（1566年）には常陸の小田氏を再び降伏させ、下総の千葉氏の拠点である臼井城へ攻め寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1566, he succeeded in having the Oda clan in Hitachi Province surrender again, and attacked Usui-jo Castle which was a foothold of Chiba clan in Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1566, he succeeded in having the Oda clan in Hitachi Province to surrender again, and attacked Usui-jo Castle which was a foothold of the Chiba clan in Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1566, he succeeded in having the Oda clan in Hitachi Province to surrender again, and attacked Usui-jo Castle which was a foothold of the Chiba clan in Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>だが、城自体は陥落寸前まで追い詰めたものの結果的には撤退することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Terutora cornered the castle to the extent of almost falling, but eventually, he had to withdraw.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Terutora cornered the castle to the extent of almost taking over, but eventually, he had to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Terutora cornered the castle to the extent of almost taking over, but eventually, he had to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="76">
<j>さらにちょうどその頃、武田信玄が上杉方の西上野を次々と平定し、長野氏や倉賀野氏を滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, at around that time, Shingen TAKEDA suppressed territories of Uesugi clan in the western part of Kozuke one after another, and ruined the Nagano clan and the Kuragano clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, around the time, Shingen TAKEDA suppressed territories of the Uesugi clan in western part of Kozuke one after another, and destroyed the Nagano and Kuragano clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, around the time, Shingen TAKEDA suppressed territories of the Uesugi clan in western part of Kozuke one after another, and destroyed the Nagano and Kuragano clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>輝虎は信玄の攻勢を食い止めようと上野和田城を攻めたが失敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he attacked Kozuke Wada-jo Castle so as to prevent the Shingen&apos;s offensive, Terutora failed it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terutora attempted to stave off the offensive attacks of Shingen at Kozuke at Wada-jo Castle, but failed.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terutora attempted to stave off the offensive attacks of Shingen at Kozuke at Wada-jo Castle, but failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>そのため謙信に味方・降伏していた関東の豪族らが次々と北条に降る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, powerful families in the Kanto region who had taken the side of and/or surrendered to Kenshin surrendered to the Hojo clan one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, powerful families in the Kanto region who were allied to Kenshin surrendered to the Hojo clan one after another.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, powerful families in the Kanto region who were allied to Kenshin surrendered to the Hojo clan one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>上野厩橋城の北条高広まで北条に寝返った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even Takahiro KITAJO of Umayabashi-jo Castle in Kozuke Province went over to the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even Takahiro KITAJO of Umayabashi-jo Castle in Kozuke Province switched to the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even Takahiro KITAJO of Umayabashi-jo Castle in Kozuke Province switched to the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>さらに輝虎は奥州進出を目指す常陸の佐竹氏とも対立するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Terutora came to conflict with the Satake clan in Hitachi Province who aimed at debouching into Oshu (Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, Terutora aimed to advance on the Satake clan in Hitachi Province at Oshu (Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Terutora came to conflict with the Satake clan in Hitachi Province who aimed at invading Oshu (Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正が文意から外れていましたので、翻訳者の訳に戻しました。（debouching into　を　invadingとしました）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="81">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）、新しく将軍となった足利義昭からも関東管領に任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1568, Tetutora was also appointed to Kanto Kanrei by a new shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1568, Tetutora was assigned to Kanto Kanrei postion by a new shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1568, Tetutora was assigned to Kanto Kanrei postion by a new shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="82">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）、越中の一向一揆と椎名康胤が武田信玄と通じたため、越中を制圧するために松倉城 (越中国)・守山城 (越中国)を攻撃したが、5月に信玄と通じた重臣の本庄繁長の謀反のため越後に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Terutora attacked Matsukura-jo Castle (Ecchu Province) and Moriyama-jo Castle (Ecchu Province) to take Ecchu Province in control in 1568 because an uprising of Ikko sect followers occurred in Ecchu Province and Yasutane SHIINA trafficked with Shingen TAKEDA, Tetutora returned to Echigo Province in June 1568 due to a rebellion caused by his senior vassal, Shigenaga HONJO, who trafficked with Shingen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1568, Terutora attacked Matsukura-jo Castle (Ecchu Province) and Moriyama-jo Castle (Ecchu Province) to suppress an uprising of the Ikko sect followers in Ecchu Province caused by Yasutane SHIINA who contracted with Shingen TAKEDA, but he returned to Echigo Province in June 1568 due to a rebellion caused by his senior vassal, Shigenaga HONJO, who had also contracted with Shingen.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1568, Terutora attacked Matsukura-jo Castle (Ecchu Province) and Moriyama-jo Castle (Ecchu Province) to suppress an uprising of the Ikko sect followers in Ecchu Province caused by Yasutane SHIINA who contracted with Shingen TAKEDA, but he returned to Echigo Province in June 1568 due to a rebellion caused by his senior vassal, Shigenaga HONJO, who had also contracted with Shingen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>11月に繁長の謀反を鎮圧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1568, Tetutora settled the Shigenaga&apos;s rebellion.</e>
<cmt>11月→November 1568[新暦に換算すると、11月1日は11月29日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1568, Terutora suppressed the Shigenaga rebellion.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1568, Terutora suppressed the Shigenaga rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>12月、武田と断交した今川氏真に救援を懇願される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1568, he was begged for help by Ujizane IMAGAWA who severed diplomatic relations with the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>12月→December 1568[新暦に換算すると、12月1日は12月29日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1568, Ujizane IMAGAWA who severed diplomatic relations with the Takeda clan appealed to Terutora for help.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1568, Ujizane IMAGAWA who severed diplomatic relations with the Takeda clan appealed to Terutora for help.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>永禄12年（1569年）には蘆名盛氏の仲介を受け、本庄繁長から嫡男・本庄顕長を人質として差し出させることで、繁長の帰参を許した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1569, through the assistance of Moriuji ASHINA, Terutora allowed Shigenaga HONJO to return to the service of his master in exchange for causing Shigenaga to submit own legitimate son, Akinaga HONJO, as a hostage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1569, with the assistance of Moriuji ASHINA, Terutora permitted Shigenaga HONJO to return to the service of his master in exchange, he was to offer his own legitimate son, Akinaga HONJO, as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1569, with the assistance of Moriuji ASHINA, Terutora permitted Shigenaga HONJO to return to the service of his master in exchange, he was to offer his own legitimate son, Akinaga HONJO, as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>また繁長と手を結んでいた出羽の大宝寺義増も輝虎に降伏し、出羽庄内地方を手にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimasu DAIHOJI in Dewa Province who had an alliance with Shigenaga also surrendered to Terutora, and as a result, Terutora obtained the Shonai region in Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>庄内地方→Shonai region[対訳では、Shonai Region と、&quot;region&quot;を大文字にて表記しておりますが、用語統一リストに従い、小文字に変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimasu DAIHOJI from Dewa Province, had an alliance with Shigenaga, surrendered to Terutora and as a result, Terutora claimed the Shonai region in Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimasu DAIHOJI from Dewa Province, had an alliance with Shigenaga, surrendered to Terutora and as a result, Terutora claimed the Shonai region in Dewa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="87">
<j>永禄12年（1569年）3月、武田信玄を牽制するため関東管領である輝虎にとっては宿敵である北条氏康と同盟する（越相同盟）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1569, in order to warn against Shingen TAKEDA, Terutora concluded an alliance with Ujiyasu HOJO who was an old enemy for Terutora assuming Kanto Kanrei (the Etsu-So Alliance (the Echigo and Sagami alliance)).</e>
<cmt>永禄12年（1569年）3月→March 1569[新暦に換算すると、3月1日は3月28日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1569, in order to check against Shingen TAKEDA, Terutora concluded an alliance with Ujiyasu HOJO an old enemy of Terutora who was a Kanto Kanrei (the Etsu-So Alliance (the Echigo and Sagami alliance)).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1569, in order to check against Shingen TAKEDA, Terutora concluded an alliance with Ujiyasu HOJO an old enemy of Terutora who was a Kanto Kanrei (the Etsu-So Alliance (the Echigo and Sagami alliance)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>この同盟に基づき、上野国の北条方の豪族は輝虎に降る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Powerful families in Kozuke Province who took the side of Hojo clan surrendered to Terutora under this alliance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this alliance, powerful families in Kozuke Province who had taken the side of the Hojo clan, surrendered to Terutora.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this alliance, powerful families in Kozuke Province who had taken the side of the Hojo clan, surrendered to Terutora.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>北条高広も帰参が許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahiro KITAJO was also allowed to return to the service of his own master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahiro KITAJO was forgiven and allowed to return to the service of his own master.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahiro KITAJO was forgiven and allowed to return to the service of his own master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>元亀元年（1570年）、氏康の7男（異説あり）である北条三郎を養子として迎えた輝虎は、三郎のことを大いに気に入って上杉景虎という自身の初名を与えるとともに、一族衆として厚遇したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1570, Terutora who adopted Saburo HOJO, the seventh son of Ujiyasu (there is another theory) really liked Saburo, and treated him very well as the whole family people along with giving Saburo his own original name, Kagetora UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1570, Terutora adopted Saburo HOJO, the seventh son of Ujiyasu (a different opinion exists), he really liked Saburo giving his own original name, Kagetora UESUGI, as well as treating him kindly as one family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1570, Terutora adopted Saburo HOJO, the seventh son of Ujiyasu (a different opinion exists), he really liked Saburo giving his own original name, Kagetora UESUGI, as well as treating him kindly as one family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>12月には法号「不識庵謙信」を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1571, he called himself &apos;Fushikian Kenshin&apos; as posthumous Buddhist name.</e>
<cmt>12月→January 1571[新暦に換算すると、12月1日は翌年(1571年)の1月6日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1571, he referred to himself &apos;Fushikian Kenshin&apos; a posthumous Buddhist name.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1571, he referred to himself &apos;Fushikian Kenshin&apos; a posthumous Buddhist name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>越中・関東出兵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dispatch of troops to Ecchu Province and Kanto region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dispatch of troops to Ecchu Province and Kanto region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dispatch of troops to Ecchu Province and Kanto region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="92">
<j>元亀2年（1571年）、北条氏康が死去し、後を継いだ北条氏政は上杉との同盟を破棄、武田信玄と再び和睦したため、その後両軍と利根川を挟み対陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1571, since Ujimasa HOJO who succeeded to a post of Ujiyasu HOJO after his death broke up the alliance with the Uesugi clan and made peace with Shingen TAKEDA again, Terutora was encamped facing with both armies each other at both sides of Tone-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1571, after the death of Ujiyasu HOJO, his successor Ujimasa HOJO broke up the alliance with the Uesugi clan and again reconciled with Shingen TAKEDA, later Terutora was encamped at Tone-gawa River sandwiched between both the armies.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1571, after the death of Ujiyasu HOJO, his successor Ujimasa HOJO broke up the alliance with the Uesugi clan and again reconciled with Shingen TAKEDA, later Terutora was encamped at Tone-gawa River sandwiched between both the armies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>8月、北国に矛先を転じ、越中国の一向一揆勢力らと戦い富山城を奪う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1571, Terutora who turn the target to the northern province fought with the power of uprising of Ikko sect followers, and took over Toyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>8月→August 1571[新暦に換算すると、8月1日は8月31日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1571, Terutora shifted his focus to the northern province, battled with the power uprising from the Ikko sect followers of Ecchu Province and usurped Toyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1571, Terutora shifted his focus to the northern province, battled with the power uprising from the Ikko sect followers of Ecchu Province and usurped Toyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>11月、大規模に動員した信玄と交戦状態に入った、織田信長の同盟の申し出を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1571, Terutora accepted an offer of alliance from Nobunaga ODA who went into combat with Shingen carrying out large-scale mobilization.</e>
<cmt>11月→November 1571[新暦に換算すると、11月1日は11月27日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1571, Terutora accepted an offer of alliance from Nobunaga ODA, mobilizing on a large scale they went into combat with Shingen.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1571, Terutora accepted an offer of alliance from Nobunaga ODA, mobilizing on a large scale they went into combat with Shingen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>その後越中に出陣したが、信玄に通じて反乱を起こした一向一揆に悩まされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he departed for the front in Ecchu Province thereafter, Terutora was annoyed with an uprising of Ikko sect followers who trafficked with Shingen and caused a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he departed for the front in Ecchu Province, Terutora was annoyed with an uprising of Ikko sect followers who contracted with Shingen to cause a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he departed for the front in Ecchu Province, Terutora was annoyed with an uprising of Ikko sect followers who contracted with Shingen to cause a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>年末まで一向一揆と戦った末に、これを制圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After battling with an uprising of Ikko sect followers until the end of the year, he finally subdued the uprising.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After battling with the Ikko sect followers until the end of the year, he finally subdued the uprising.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After battling with the Ikko sect followers until the end of the year, he finally subdued the uprising.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="97">
<j>元亀4年（1573年）、宿敵・武田信玄が病没して武田氏の脅威が薄らぎ越中の過半を制圧、江馬氏の服属で飛騨にも力を伸ばした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1573, since a threat of Takeda clan weakened because Shingen TAKEDA, the old enemy, died of illness, Terutora took major part of territories in Ecchu Province in control, and extended his influence to Hida Province by the Ema clan&apos;s yielding allegiance to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1573, a weak threat from the Takeda clan as Shingen TAKEDA, an old enemy, was submerged in sickness, Terutora seized major parts of territories in Ecchu Province, and extended his influence to the Hida Province as the Ema clan yielded allegiance to him.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1573, a weak threat from the Takeda clan as Shingen TAKEDA, an old enemy, was submerged in sickness, Terutora seized major parts of territories in Ecchu Province, and extended his influence to the Hida Province as the Ema clan yielded allegiance to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>同年に北条氏政が上野に侵攻、これに対するため天正2年（1574年）、関東に出陣して新田金山城主の由良氏を攻撃して戦果をあげた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Ujimasa HOJO invaded Kozuke Province, and in order to respond to such invasion, Kenshin departed for the fort in the Kanto region in 1574, and yielded military results by attacking the Yura clan, lord of Nitta Kaneyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Ujimasa HOJO invaded Kozuke Province, because of this Kenshin departed for the front in the Kanto region in 1574, and attacked the Yura clan, lord of Nitta Kaneyama-jo Castle to yield military results.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Ujimasa HOJO invaded Kozuke Province, because of this Kenshin departed for the front in the Kanto region in 1574, and attacked the Yura clan, lord of Nitta Kaneyama-jo Castle to yield military results.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="99">
<j>北条氏政が下総関宿城の簗田氏を攻撃するや、謙信は北条方の武蔵騎西城・忍城・鉢形城下など諸城を相次いで攻めて後方かく乱を狙ったが失敗、関宿城は降伏してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although, as soon as Ujimasa HOJO attacked the Yanada clan of Sekijuku-jo Castle in Shimousa Province, he aimed to throw the backward into confusion by successively attacking castles such as Musashi Kisai-jo Castle, Oshi-jo Castle and Hachigata-jo Castle which took the side of Hojo clan, Kenshin failed it and Sekijuku-jo Castle surrendered.</e>
<cmt>騎西城→Kisai-jo Castle[Wikipedia 『騎西城』より]忍城→Oshi-jo Castle[対訳では、Oshi Castle と表記されておりますが、他の城の表記に合わせ、変更しました]鉢形城→Hachigata-jo Castle[Wikpedia 『鉢形城』より]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as Ujimasa HOJO attacked the Yanada clan of Sekijuku-jo Castle in Shimousa Province, Kenshin aimed at creating confusion by successively attacking castles such as Musashi Kisai-jo Castle, Oshi-jo Castle and Hachigata-jo Castle of the Hojo clan, but he failed but Sekijuku-jo Castle surrendered.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as Ujimasa HOJO attacked the Yanada clan of Sekijuku-jo Castle in Shimousa Province, Kenshin aimed at creating confusion by successively attacking castles such as Musashi Kisai-jo Castle, Oshi-jo Castle and Hachigata-jo Castle of the Hojo clan, but he failed but Sekijuku-jo Castle surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>同年12月19日、剃髪して法印大和尚に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 19, 1575, Kenshin became a monk and was appointed to hoindaikasho (highest-ranking Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt>同年12月19日→January 19, 1575[こよみのページより]法印大和尚→hoindaikasho (highest-ranking Buddhist priest)[説明の英訳は、Wikipediaの『僧位』の項目、その他コトバンク等において、「僧位の最上位」と記載されているので、これを英訳しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 19, 1575, Kenshin became a monk and was appointed to hoindaikasho (highest-ranking Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 19, 1575, Kenshin became a monk and was appointed to hoindaikasho (highest-ranking Buddhist priest).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>天正3年（1575年）1月11日、養子の喜平次顕景の名を上杉景勝と改めさせ、弾正少弼の官途を譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 3, 1575, Kenshin caused his adopted child, Kiheiji Akikage, to change the name to Kagekatsu UESUGI, and transferred kanto (government service) of danjo-shohitsu.</e>
<cmt>天正3年（1575年）1月11日→March 3, 1576[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 3, 1575, the adopted child, Kiheiji AKIKAGE, of Kenshin changed his name to Kagekatsu UESUGI, and gave up becoming a kanto (government service) of danjo-shohitsu.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 3, 1575, the adopted child, Kiheiji AKIKAGE, of Kenshin changed his name to Kagekatsu UESUGI, and gave up becoming a kanto (government service) of danjo-shohitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>織田信長との戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle with Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle with Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle with Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="102">
<j>天正4年（1576年）2月、信長との戦いで苦境に立たされていた本願寺顕如と講和する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1576, Kenshin conciliated with Kennyo HONGANJI who was put in a difficult situation in a battle with Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>天正4年（1576年）2月→March 1576[新暦に換算すると、2月1日が3月11日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1576, Kenshin conciliated with Kennyo HONGANJI and was placed in a difficult situation, leading to a battle with Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1576, Kenshin conciliated with Kennyo HONGANJI and was placed in a difficult situation, leading to a battle with Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>このとき、武田勝頼とも和睦して信長との同盟を破棄し、新たに謙信を盟主とする信長包囲網を築き上げたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Kenshin who made peace with Katsuyori TAKEDA and broke up the alliance with Nobunaga built up an anti-Nobunaga network with setting Kenshin as a new leader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Kenshin reconciled with Katsuyori TAKEDA and broke up the alliance with Nobunaga and built up an anti-Nobunaga network with Kenshin as a new leader.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Kenshin reconciled with Katsuyori TAKEDA and broke up the alliance with Nobunaga and built up an anti-Nobunaga network with Kenshin as a new leader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>越中・能登（畠山領）への援軍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reinforcement in Ecchu Province and Noto Province (Hatakeyama&apos;s territory)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reinforcement in Ecchu Province and Noto Province (Hatakeyama&apos;s territory)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reinforcement in Ecchu Province and Noto Province (Hatakeyama&apos;s territory)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>天正4年（1576年）9月、名目上管領畠山氏が守護をつとめる越中に侵攻して一向一揆支配下の富山城、増山城を落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1576, Kenshin invaded Ecchu Province where the Shogunal Deputy Hatakeyama clan served as Shugo (provincial constable) nominally, and conquered Toyama-jo Castle and Masuyama-jo Castle under control of an uprising of Ikko sect followers.</e>
<cmt>天正4年（1576年）9月→October 1576[新暦に換算すると、9月1日が10月3日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1576, Kenshin invaded Ecchu Province where the Shogunal Deputy Hatakeyama clan served as Shugo (provincial constable) nominally, and conquered Toyama-jo Castle and Masuyama-jo Castle under control of an uprising of Ikko sect followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1576, Kenshin invaded Ecchu Province where the Shogunal Deputy Hatakeyama clan served as Shugo (provincial constable) nominally, and conquered Toyama-jo Castle and Masuyama-jo Castle under control of an uprising of Ikko sect followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>次いで椎名康胤（越中守護代）の蓮沼城を陥落させ康胤を討ち取り、騒乱の越中を平定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Kenshin took control of Hasunuma-jo Castle of Yasutane SHIINA (Ecchu shugodai), killed Yastane, and suppressed Ecchu Province in the turbulence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Kenshin took control of Hasunuma-jo Castle of Yasutane SHIINA (Ecchu shugodai), killed Yastane, and suppressed the turbulence in Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Kenshin took control of Hasunuma-jo Castle of Yasutane SHIINA (Ecchu shugodai), killed Yasutane, and suppressed the turbulence in Ecchu Province.</e>
<cmt>YastaneをYasutaneに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="106">
<j>同11月、能登に進み能登の七尾城を囲んだ（七尾城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1576, Kenshin invaded Noto Province, and besieged Nanao-jo Castle in Noto Province (the Battle of Nanao-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1576, Kenshin invaded Noto Province, and besieged Nanao-jo Castle in Noto Province (the Battle of Nanao-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1576, Kenshin invaded Noto Province, and besieged Nanao-jo Castle in Noto Province (the Battle of Nanao-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>しかし七尾城は堅城であり、攻めあぐんで越年する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kenshin struggled with an attack to Nanao-jo Castle due to its toughness, and kept over the winter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kenshin struggled desperately at Nanao-jo Castle a strong fortress, and they remained till the end of the year.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kenshin struggled desperately at Nanao-jo Castle a strong fortress, and they remained till the end of the year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>天正5年（1577年）、春日山に一時撤退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1577, Kenshin temporarily withdrew to Mt. Kasuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1577, Kenshin temporarily withdrew to Mt. Kasuga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1577, Kenshin temporarily withdrew to Mt. Kasuga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>その間に敵軍によって上杉軍が前年に奪っていた能登の諸城は落とされたが、閏7月、再び能登に侵攻し、七尾城を包囲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although castles in Noto Province conquered by the Uesugi army in the previous year were conquered by the enemy army during that time, Kenshin invaded Noto Province again and besieged Nanao-jo Castle in August 1577.</e>
<cmt>閏7月→August 1577[新暦に換算すると、閏7月1日が8月24日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castles in Noto Province were conquered by the Uesugi army in the previous year were reconquered by the enemy during that time, Kenshin invaded Noto Province again and besieged Nanao-jo Castle in August 1577.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castles in Noto Province were conquered by the Uesugi army in the previous year were reconquered by the enemy during that time, Kenshin invaded Noto Province again and besieged Nanao-jo Castle in August 1577.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>このとき、城内で疫病が流行、厭戦気分が蔓延した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, an epidemic went around within the castle, and a feeling of being weary of war spread.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, an epidemic spread within the castle, and war weariness was prevalent.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, an epidemic spread within the castle, and war weariness was prevalent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>9月15日に遊佐続光（能登守護代）らが謙信と通じて反乱を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 5, 1577, Tsugumitsu YUSA (Noto shugodai) and others trafficked with Kenshin and caused a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処9月15日→November 5, 1577[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 5, 1577, Tsugumitsu YUSA (Noto shugodai) and others trafficked with Kenshin and caused a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 5, 1577, Tsugumitsu YUSA (Noto shugodai) and others trafficked with Kenshin and caused a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>織田信長と通じていた長続連らは殺され、七尾城は落城し能登の傀儡国主である畠山春王丸も病により没したため、能登は上杉謙信の支配下に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Tsugutsura CHO and others who trafficked with Nobunaga ODA were killed, Nanao-jo Castle fell, and Haruomaru HATAKEYAMA, puppet lord of Noto Province, died of illness, Noto Province came under the control of Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Tsugutsura CHO and others, who trafficked with Nobunaga ODA, were killed, Nanao-jo Castle fell and Haruomaru HATAKEYAMA, a puppet lord of Noto Province, died of illness, Noto Province came under the control of Kenshin UESUGI..</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Tsugutsura CHO and others, who trafficked with Nobunaga ODA, were killed, Nanao-jo Castle fell and Haruomaru HATAKEYAMA, a puppet lord of Noto Province, died of illness, Noto Province came under the control of Kenshin UESUGI..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>上杉謙信には名門畠山家の復興が思慮にあり、有力国人を廃したうえで畠山義春を能登の国主として擁立する計画であったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kenshin UESUGI intended to revive the Hatakeyama family, family of pedigree, and planned to support Yoshiharu HATAKEYAMA as a lord of Noto Province after expelling powerful local lords.</e>
<cmt>有力国人→powerful local lords[上記にて、「国人」を&quot;local lord&quot;と表記しているので、&quot;(kokujin)&quot;の表記は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kenshin UESUGI intended to revive the Hatakeyama family, a family pedigree, and planned to support Yoshiharu HATAKEYAMA as lord of Noto Province after expelling powerful local lords.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kenshin UESUGI intended to revive the Hatakeyama family, a family pedigree, and planned to support Yoshiharu HATAKEYAMA as lord of Noto Province after expelling powerful local lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="114">
<j>また、この戦いの後、畠山義隆の息子を養子にすると書かれた謙信書状が出されており、この子は春王丸自身や実際には畠山義続の子であるとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, after this battle, Kenshin wrote a letter of intending to adopt a son of Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA, and it is said that this son referred to Haruomaru himself, or practically a son of Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, after this battle, Kenshin wrote a letter intending to adopt a son of Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA, and it is said that this son referred to hiself as Haruomaru, but was actually a son of Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, after this battle, Kenshin wrote a letter intending to adopt a son of Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA, and it is said that this son referred to hiself as Haruomaru, but was actually a son of Yoshitsugu HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>織田軍との交戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle with the Oda army</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle with the Oda army</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle with the Oda army</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="115">
<j>一方、長続連の援軍要請を受けていた織田氏は、柴田勝家らの先発隊3万、信長率いる本隊1万8000が加賀国に向かっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Oda clan which was requested by Tsugutura CHO for reinforcement was on the way to Kaga Province with the advance party of 30,000 soldiers led by Katsuie SHIBATA and so on, and the main force of 18,000 soldiers led by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the Oda clan received a request from Tsugutura CHO for reinforcement as Katsuie SHIBATA and so on, was on the way to Kaga Province with an advance party of 30,000 soldiers, and a main force of 18,000 soldiers led by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Oda clan received a request from Tsugutura CHO for reinforcement as Katsuie SHIBATA and so on, was on the way to Kaga Province with an advance party of 30,000 soldiers, and a main force of 18,000 soldiers led by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="116">
<j>謙信はこれを迎え撃つため、9月17日に末森城 (能登国)を落とし、9月18日には松波城を攻め落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to counterattack such armies, Kenshin conquered Suemori-jo Castle (Noto Province) on November 7, 1577, and attacked and conquered Matsunami-jo Castle on November 8, 1577.</e>
<cmt>9月17日→November 7, 1577[こよみのページより]9月18日→November 8, 1577[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to counterattack such armies, Kenshin conquered Suemori-jo Castle (Noto Province) on November 7, 1577, and attacked and conquered Matsunami-jo Castle on November 8, 1577.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to counterattack such armies, Kenshin conquered Suemori-jo Castle (Noto Province) on November 7, 1577, and attacked and conquered Matsunami-jo Castle on November 8, 1577.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>9月23日、柴田勝家率いる織田軍は、手取川を渡河したところでようやく七尾城の陥落を知った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 13, 1577, the Oda army led by Katsuie SHIBATA finally knew the fall of Nanao-jo Castle when crossing the Tetori-gara River.</e>
<cmt>9月23日→November 13, 1577[こよみのページより]手取川→Tetori-gawa River[用語集を検索し、他の川名の表記に合わせました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 13, 1577, the Oda army commanded by Katsuie SHIBATA finally came to know of the fall of Nanao-jo Castle while crossing the Tetori-gara River.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 13, 1577, the Oda army commanded by Katsuie SHIBATA finally came to know of the fall of Nanao-jo Castle while crossing the Tetori-gara River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>慌てた勝家は撤退命令を出したが、さらに松任城に進軍した上杉軍は手取川の渡河に手間取る織田軍を追撃して撃破したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that although Katsuie in a panic issued an order to withdraw, the Uesugi army which further advanced to Matsuto-jo Castle chased and obliterated the Oda army having trouble with crossing the Tetori-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>松任城→Matsugo-jo Castle[http://www15.ocn.ne.jp/~nanao/kaga/kagamap/matsuto_jyo.html より]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that although Katsuie in a panic issued an order to withdraw, the Uesugi army further advanced to Matsuto-jo Castle pursued and obliterated the Oda army while they were crossing the Tetori-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that although Katsuie in a panic issued an order to withdraw, the Uesugi army further advanced to Matsuto-jo Castle pursued and obliterated the Oda army while they were crossing the Tetori-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>なお、戦いの規模については諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are various theories about a scale of battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are various theories about the scale of the battle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are various theories about the scale of the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>最期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">End</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">End</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="120">
<j>天正5年（1577年）12月18日、謙信は春日山城に帰還し、12月23日には次なる遠征に向けての大動員令を発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin returned to Kasugayama-jo Castle on February 4, 1578, and issued large-scale mobilization orders for the next expedition on February 9, 1578.</e>
<cmt>天正5年（1577年）12月18日→February 4, 1578[こよみのページより]12月23日→February 9, 1578[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin returned to Kasugayama-jo Castle on February 4, 1578, and issued a large-scale mobilization order for the next expedition on February 9, 1578.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin returned to Kasugayama-jo Castle on February 4, 1578, and issued a large-scale mobilization order for the next expedition on February 9, 1578.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>天正6年（1578年）3月15日に遠征を開始する予定だったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin seemed to intend to start the expedition on May 1, 1578.</e>
<cmt>天正6年（1578年）3月15日→May 1, 1578[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin seemed to intend to start the expedition on May 1, 1578.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin seemed to intend to start the expedition on May 1, 1578.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>しかしその6日前である3月9日、遠征の準備中に春日山城で倒れ、3月13日、急死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on April 25, 1578, six days before that day, Kenshin fell in Kasugayama-jo Castle while making preparations for expedition, and died suddenly on April 29, 1578.</e>
<cmt>3月9日→April 25, 1578[こよみのページより]3月13日→April 29, 1578[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on April 25, 1578, six days before the start, Kenshin fell and died suddenly on April 29, 1578 in Kasugayama-jo Castle while preparing for the expedition.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on April 25, 1578, six days before the start, Kenshin fell and died suddenly on April 29, 1578 in Kasugayama-jo Castle while preparing for the expedition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>享年49。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 49.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 49.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 49.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>倒れてからの昏睡状態より、死因は脳溢血と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that the cause of his death was cerebral hemorrhage judging from a coma after falling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cause of his death was said to have been cerebral hemorrhage, judging from a coma after his fall.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cause of his death was said to have been cerebral hemorrhage, judging from a coma after his fall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>遺骸には鎧を着せ太刀を帯びさせて甕の中へ納め漆で密封した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His body was dressed in armor with a sword, put in an earthenware pot and sealed closely with lacquer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His body was dressed in armor with a sword, placed in an earthenware pot and sealed with lacquer.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His body was dressed in armor with a sword, placed in an earthenware pot and sealed with lacquer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>この甕は上杉家が米沢に移った後も米沢城本丸一角に安置され、明治維新の後、歴代藩主が眠る御廟へと移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This earthenware pot was enshrined at a corner of Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of Yonezawa-jo Castle even after the Uesugi family moved to Yonezawa, and after the Meiji Restoration, it was moved to a mausoleum where successive lords of the domain were laid to rest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This earthenware pot was enshrined in a corner at Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of Yonezawa-jo Castle even after the Uesugi family moved to Yonezawa, later after the Meiji Restoration, it was moved to a mausoleum where successive lords of the domain were laid to rest.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This earthenware pot was enshrined in a corner at Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of Yonezawa-jo Castle even after the Uesugi family moved to Yonezawa, later after the Meiji Restoration, it was moved to a mausoleum where successive lords of the domain were laid to rest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="127">
<j>未遂に終わった遠征では上洛して織田信長を打倒しようとしていたとも、関東に再度侵攻しようとしていたとも言われているが、詳細は不明（近年の研究では関東侵攻説が有力になりつつある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are two theories that in the attempted expedition, Kenshin intended to go up to Kyoto and defeat Nobunaga ODA, and that Kenshin intended to invade the Kanto region again, details are unknown (according to the research of recent years, a theory of invasion into the Kanto region is being widely-accepted).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two attempted expeditions, first was that Kenshin intended to go up to Kyoto and defeat Nobunaga ODA, and the next was he intended to invade the Kanto region once again, but the details are unknown (according to recent research, the invasion into the Kanto region is widely accepted).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two attempted expeditions, first was that Kenshin intended to go up to Kyoto and defeat Nobunaga ODA, and the next was he intended to invade the Kanto region once again, but the details are unknown (according to recent research, the invasion into the Kanto region is widely accepted).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>『その時歴史が動いた』（日本放送協会、2007年4月4日放送）では、「関東侵攻後、信長を打倒し京へ上洛」が有力説とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the TV program, &quot;Sonotoki Rekishiga Ugoita&quot; (Then, the history moved) (broadcasted on April 4, 2007 by Japan Broadcasting Corporation (NHK)), a theory that &apos;Kenshin defeated Nobunaga and went up to Kyoto after invading the Kanto region&apos; was determined to be widely-accepted.</e>
<cmt>『その時歴史が動いた』→&quot;Sonotoki Rekishiga Ugoita&quot; (Then, the history moved)[説明の英訳は、仮訳です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the TV program, &quot;Sonotoki Rekishiga Ugoita&quot; (The movement of History) (broadcasted on April 4, 2007 by Japan Broadcasting Corporation (NHK)), &apos;Kenshin defeated Nobunaga and went up to Kyoto after invading the Kanto region&apos; was widely-accepted.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the TV program, &quot;Sonotoki Rekishiga Ugoita&quot; (The movement of History) (broadcasted on April 4, 2007 by Japan Broadcasting Corporation (NHK)), &apos;Kenshin defeated Nobunaga and went up to Kyoto after invading the Kanto region&apos; was widely-accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>辞世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death poem</e>
<cmt>辞世→death poem[対訳では、&quot;death&quot;と表記されておりますが、本文を見ますと「句」が記載されており、また、辞世は、『死に臨んで残す言葉・詩歌』（http://kotobank.jp/word/辞世)なので、変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death poem</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death poem</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="129">
<j>「極楽も 地獄も先は 有明の 月の心に 懸かる雲なし」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Gokurakumo Jigokumo Sakiwa Ariakeno Tsuki no Kokoroni Kakarukumo nashi&apos; (Even if I am going to Buddhist paradise or hell, if my mind is as clear as pre-dawn moon, I will have no worry and anxiety)</e>
<cmt>この句は、「極楽と地獄の何処へ往こうとも夜明け前の月のような澄み渡った透明な心なら何の不安も迷いもない」との意味になるので（http://www.geocities.jp/satopyon0413/poem002.htm）、この意味を英訳しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Gokurakumo Jigokumo Sakiwa Ariakeno Tsuki no Kokoroni Kakarukumo nashi&apos; (Even if I am going to Buddhist paradise or hell, if my mind is as clear as pre-dawn moon, I will have no worry and anxiety)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Gokurakumo Jigokumo Sakiwa Ariakeno Tsuki no Kokoroni Kakarukumo nashi&apos; (Even if I am going to Buddhist paradise or hell, if my mind is as clear as pre-dawn moon, I will have no worry and anxiety)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="130">
<j>「四十九年 一睡の夢 一期の栄華 一盃の酒」（「嗚呼 柳緑 花紅」と続く史料もある）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Shijukyunen Issuinoyume Ichigonoeiga Ippainosake&apos; (A 49-year life is like a one-night dream, single-period prosperity and a cup of sake) (there is a historical material containing a subsequent phrase, &apos;Ah, Yanagimidori Hanakurenai&apos; (Oh, willow is green and a flower is red).)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;Shijukyunen Issuinoyume Ichigonoeiga Ippainosake&apos; (A 49-year life is like a one-night dream, single-period prosperity and a cup of sake) (there is a historical material containing a subsequent phrase, &apos;Ah, Yanagimidori Hanakurenai&apos; (Oh, willow is green and a flower is red).)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;Shijukyunen Issuinoyume Ichigonoeiga Ippainosake&apos; (A 49-year life is like a one-night dream, single-period prosperity and a cup of sake) (there is a historical material containing a subsequent phrase, &apos;Ah, Yanagimidori Hanakurenai&apos; (Oh, willow is green and a flower is red).)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="131">
<j>生まれつきのカリスマ性を持ち、兄から呼びもどされて元服すると長尾家家臣だけでなく、豪族の心もつかんだとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Kenshin was charismatic by nature, and grabbed the interest of not only vassals of Nagao family but also powerful families when he was called back by his older brother and reached the manhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Kenshin was charismatic by birth, and grabbed the interest of not only vassals of Nagao family but also powerful families when he was called back by his older brother on reaching manhood.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Kenshin was charismatic by birth, and grabbed the interest of not only vassals of Nagao family but also powerful families when he was called back by his older brother on reaching manhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="132">
<j>自らを毘沙門天の化身と称したり天罰と信じて戦を行う、短気であるなど、奇抜で苛烈な一面がある一方で、よく涙を流す、戦国大名らしからぬほど非常に繊細な面もあったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that he had an unconventional and severe aspect like identifying himself as an incarnation of Bishamonten, fighting under a belief that it was a punishment of Heaven, being impatient and so on, while he also had an aspect of being too delicate for a warring lord like shedding tears often.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was unconventional and strange in some aspects like identifying himself as an incarnation of Bishamonten, fighting for divine justice, being impatient and short tempered and so on, while in other aspects he was striking and harsh, he was unlike a warring lord as he was too delicate and often shedded tears.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was unconventional and strange in some aspects like identifying himself as an incarnation of Bishamonten, fighting for divine justice, being impatient and short tempered and so on, while in other aspects he was striking and harsh, he was unlike a warring lord as he was too delicate and often shedded tears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>また、養子の上杉景勝に頻繁に手紙を送ったり呼び寄せたり（景勝は正式に養子になる以前は父・政景の居城である坂戸城にいたことが多かった）する子煩悩な一面もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, he had another aspect of loving his children dearly like frequently writing letters to his adopted child, Kagekatsu UESUGI and calling him over (before being adopted officially, Kagekatsu often stayed at Sakato-jo Castle which was a residential castle of his father, Masakage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, he had another aspect of loving his children dearly like frequently writing letters to his adopted child, Kagekatsu UESUGI, inviting and doting on him (before being adopted officially, Kagekatsu often stayed at Sakato-jo Castle which was the residential castle of his father, Masakage).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, he had another aspect of loving his children dearly like frequently writing letters to his adopted child, Kagekatsu UESUGI, inviting and doting on him (before being adopted officially, Kagekatsu often stayed at Sakato-jo Castle which was the residential castle of his father, Masakage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="134">
<j>戦略家・戦術家としてだけではなく、和歌に通じ、達筆でもあり、近衛稙家から和歌の奥義を伝授されるなど、公家との交流も深い文化人でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was not only a strategist and tactician but also a man of culture who deeply exchanged with court nobles because he was acquainted with waka (Japanese poetry), had good handwriting and received instruction in esoteric points of waka from Taneie KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was not only a strategist and tactician but also a man of culture who interacted with court nobles because he was acquainted with waka (Japanese poetry), had good handwriting and received instruction in esoteric points of waka from Taneie KONOE.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was not only a strategist and tactician but also a man of culture who interacted with court nobles because he was acquainted with waka (Japanese poetry), had good handwriting and received instruction in esoteric points of waka from Taneie KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>特に源氏物語を始めとする恋愛物を好んで読んでおり、上洛した際に開催した歌会でも見事な雅歌（恋歌）を読み、参加者全員を驚かせたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, he preferably read love stories such as Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji) and so on, and it is said that everyone at Uta-kai (poem competition) held when Kenshin went up to Kyoto was surprised to hear his splendid Gaka (koiuta (lovers poetry)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He especially liked to read love stories such as Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji) and so on, and it is said that when Kenshin went up to Kyoto for Uta-kai (poem competition) everyone was surprised to hear his splendid Gaka (koiuta (lovers poetry)).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He especially liked to read love stories such as Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji) and so on, and it is said that when Kenshin went up to Kyoto for Uta-kai (poem competition) everyone was surprised to hear his splendid Gaka (koiuta (lovers poetry)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>琵琶を奏でる趣味もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had a hobby of playing the Biwa (Japanese lute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also had a hobby of playing the Biwa (Japanese lute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also had a hobby of playing the Biwa (Japanese lute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="137">
<j>七尾城の戦いのとき、謙信は有名な『十三夜』の詩を作ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that at the time of the Battle of Nanao-jo Castle, Kenshin composed a famous poem, &quot;the Thirteenth Night.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that at the time of the Battle of Nanao-jo Castle, Kenshin composed a famous poem, &quot;the Thirteenth Night.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that at the time of the Battle of Nanao-jo Castle, Kenshin composed a famous poem, &quot;the Thirteenth Night.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="138">
<j>軍神毘沙門天の熱心な信者で、自らの旗印にも「毘」の文字を使った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an earnest believer in the god of war, Bishamonten, and also used a letter of &apos;毘&apos; (Bi of Bishamonten) for an emblem on own flag.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a fervent believer in the god of war, Bishamonten, and also used a letter of &apos;毘&apos; (Bi of Bishamonten) for an emblem on his own flag.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a fervent believer in the god of war, Bishamonten, and also used a letter of &apos;毘&apos; (Bi of Bishamonten) for an emblem on his own flag.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="139">
<j>青年期までは曹洞宗の古刹、林泉寺 (上越市)で師の天室光育から禅を学び、上洛時には臨済宗大徳寺の宗九のもとに参禅し「宗心」という戒名を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until his adolescence, Kenshin learned Zen from his master Koiku TENSHITSU at Rinsen-ji Temple (Joetsu City) which was an ancient temple of Soto school of Buddhism, and when going up to Kyoto, he practiced Zen meditation under Soku of Daitoku-ji Temple of Rinzai sect and was granted a posthumous Buddhist name of &apos;Soshin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until his adolescence, Kenshin learned Zen from his master Koiku TENSHITSU at Rinsen-ji Temple (Joetsu City) which was an ancient temple of Soto school of Buddhism, and when he went to Kyoto, he practiced Zen meditation under Soku of Daitoku-ji Temple of Rinzai sect and was granted a posthumous Buddhist name of &apos;Soshin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until his adolescence, Kenshin learned Zen from his master Koiku TENSHITSU at Rinsen-ji Temple (Joetsu City) which was an ancient temple of Soto school of Buddhism, and when he went to Kyoto, he practiced Zen meditation under Soku of Daitoku-ji Temple of Rinzai sect and was granted a posthumous Buddhist name of &apos;Soshin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>晩年には真言宗に傾倒し、高野山金剛峯寺の清胤_(真言宗)から伝法潅頂を受け阿闍梨権大僧都の位階を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last years, Kenshin made a commitment to the Shingon sect, received Denpo-kanjo (esoteric Buddhist ritual of pouring water on the top of monk&apos;s head for transfer of Dahrma) from Shoin (Shingon sect) of Kongobu-ji Temple on Mt. Koya, and was granted a rank of Ajari (a master of esoteric Buddhism) Daisozu (the highest grade that can be held by one who has reached the second highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処位階→rank[対訳では、Ikai (Court rank) と表記されておりますが、この場合の位階は僧階を指すので、&quot;rank&quot;としました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last years, Kenshin made a commitment to the Shingon sect, received Denpo-kanjo (esoteric Buddhist ritual of pouring water on the top of monk&apos;s head for transfer of Dahrma) from Shoin (Shingon sect) of Kongobu-ji Temple on Mt. Koya, and was granted a rank of Ajari (a master of esoteric Buddhism) Daisozu (the highest grade that can be held by one who has reached the second highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last years, Kenshin made a commitment to the Shingon sect, received Denpo-kanjo (esoteric Buddhist ritual of pouring water on the top of monk&apos;s head for transfer of Dahrma) from Shoin (Shingon sect) of Kongobu-ji Temple on Mt. Koya, and was granted a rank of Ajari (a master of esoteric Buddhism) Daisozu (the highest grade that can be held by one who has reached the second highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="141">
<j>一般には「戦上手の内政下手」という印象があるが、実際には衣料の原料となる青苧を栽培し、日本海ルートで全国に広め、財源とするなど、領内の物産流通の精密な統制管理を行い莫大な利益を上げていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a general impression of Kenshin is that he was &apos;good at military administration, but not good at domestic administration,&apos; the fact was that Kenshin strictly regulated and managed the distribution of products within the territory, and made enormous profits by cultivating Aoso which was fiber materials for clothing, spreading it nationwide through the Japan Sea route and earned money from it as source of funds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A general impression of Kenshin was being &apos;good at military administration, but no good at domestic administration,&apos; in actual fact Kenshin strictly regulated and managed the distribution of products within the territory such as Aoso, a fiber material for clothing, spreading it nationwide through the Japan Sea route and made enormous profits which was used as source of funds.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A general impression of Kenshin was being &apos;good at military administration, but no good at domestic administration,&apos; in actual fact Kenshin strictly regulated and managed the distribution of products within the territory such as Aoso, a fiber material for clothing, spreading it nationwide through the Japan Sea route and made enormous profits which was used as source of funds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>謙信が死去した時、春日山城には2万7140両の蓄えがあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kasugayama-jo Castle had a reserve of 27,140 ryo (unit of gold currency) when Kenshin died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kasugayama-jo Castle had a reserve of 27,140 ryo (unit of gold currency) when Kenshin died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kasugayama-jo Castle had a reserve of 27,140 ryo (unit of gold currency) when Kenshin died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>上杉軍の行動を支える軍費の大半は通商によって得られており、頼山陽が美談として激賞した「敵に塩を送る」という逸話も、実際には軍費調達の必要上から甲斐・信濃の商人への塩販売を禁じなかっただけと見ることも出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most military expenditures supporting the activities of Uesugi army were obtained from commerce, and an anecdote that &apos;Kenshin had sent salt to an enemy&apos; which was much admired by Sanyo RAI as a heartwarming story can also be interpreted as meaning that Kenshin did not practically prohibit merchants in Kai Province and Shinano Province from selling salt due to the need to procure military expenditures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most military expenditures supporting the Uesugi army were obtained by commerce, a highly praised anecdote &apos;send salt to the enemy&apos; was admired by Sanyo RAI as a heartwarming story, in actual fact Kenshin did not prohibit the selling of salt by the merchants in Kai Province and Shinano Province as an important source of funds for military expenditure.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most military expenditures supporting the Uesugi army were obtained by commerce, a highly praised anecdote &apos;send salt to the enemy&apos; was admired by Sanyo RAI as a heartwarming story, in actual fact Kenshin did not prohibit the selling of salt by the merchants in Kai Province and Shinano Province as an important source of funds for military expenditure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>だが越後国人たちの離反には度々悩まされているように、謙信も信玄同様、国人衆の連合盟主という地位から脱することができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as being often annoyed with rebellions of powerful families in Echigo Province, Kenshin as well as Shingen could not escape from a social status as a leader of alliance among powerful local lords in a province.</e>
<cmt>連合→alliance[対訳では、&quot;combination&quot;と表記されておりますが、用語集を参照し、変更しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, often being troubled with rebellions by powerful families in Echigo Province, Kenshin as well as Shingen could not escape from the leader of the alliance among powerful local lords in the province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, often being troubled with rebellions by powerful families in Echigo Province, Kenshin as well as Shingen could not escape from the leader of the alliance among powerful local lords in the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="145">
<j>合戦では情報を得ることを重視し、軒猿（担猿）という忍者集団を擁していたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that he placed importance on receiving information in the battle, and supported a ninja group including ninja called Nokizaru (also called Tanzaru).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that he placed importance on receiving information in battle, and employed a ninja group called Nokizaru (also called Tanzaru).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that he placed importance on receiving information in battle, and employed a ninja group called Nokizaru (also called Tanzaru).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="146">
<j>吉川元春の使者・佐々木定経が謙信と対面したとき、「音に聞こえし大峰の五鬼、葛城高天の大天狗（謙信）にや」と謙信のことを大天狗扱いするなど、「六尺近い偉丈夫」が有力説とされてきたが、「小柄」と表記されている文献もいくつか存在し、謙信の身長については諸説があり定かではないのが実情であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it has been considered to be a widely-accepted theory that Kenshin was &apos;ijofu&apos; (a great man) approx. 1.818 meters tall&apos; because Sadatsune SASAKI, a messenger of Motoharu KIKKAWA, treated Kenshin as Otengu (big tengu (a mountain spirit, portrayed as winged and having a long nose)) with saying, &apos;As I heard, you are Otengu (Kenshin) of Katsuragi Takama of Goki (five oni demons) of Omine,&apos; Kenshin&apos;s height is actually uncertain because there are several literatures describing that Kenshin was a &apos;small&apos; person and there are various theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadatsune SASAKI, an enemy of Motoharu KIKKAWA on meeting Kenshin considered him to be an Otengu (big tengu (a mountain spirit, portrayed as winged and having a long nose)), and is said to have said &apos;I hear you are an Otengu of Katsuragi TAKAMA, Goki (five oni demons) of Omine,&apos; other leading theories are &apos; a great man of about 1.818 m height,&apos; but in fact his height was uncertain as several literature describes Kenshin as a &apos;small&apos; person.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadatsune SASAKI, an enemy of Motoharu KIKKAWA on meeting Kenshin considered him to be an Otengu (big tengu (a mountain spirit, portrayed as winged and having a long nose)), and is said to have said &apos;I hear you are an Otengu of Katsuragi TAKAMA, Goki (five oni demons) of Omine,&apos; other leading theories are &apos; a great man of about 1.818 m height,&apos; but in fact his height was uncertain as several literature describes Kenshin as a &apos;small&apos; person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>しかし、近年の研究で遺品の甲冑の大きさなどから五尺二寸ほど（約156cm）であったことがわかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as a result of research of recent years, it is found from a size of armor among articles left by the deceased that his height was about 156 centimeters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent research revealed, a armor among articles left by the deceased, indicating that his height was about 156 centimeters.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent research revealed, a armor among articles left by the deceased, indicating that his height was about 156 centimeters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>当時の男性の平均身長は159cm程度であったため、屈強な武将たちの中で考えると「小柄」という表現が正しいことがわかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the average height of men at that time was about 159 centimeters, it is known that an expression of being a &apos;small&apos; man among tough busho (Japanese military commander) is correct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the average height of men at the time was about 159 centimeters, an expression of being a &apos;small&apos; man among tough busho (Japanese military commander) was appropriate.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the average height of men at the time was about 159 centimeters, an expression of being a &apos;small&apos; man among tough busho (Japanese military commander) was appropriate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="149">
<j>死去する1か月前の2月、謙信は京都から画家を呼び寄せて自らの肖像画と後姿を描かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1578 one month before he died, Kenshin called over an artist from Kyoto and asked such artist to draw his portrait and a picture of his back shot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1578, a month before his death, Kenshin summoned an artist from Kyoto to make a self portrait and also a painting of his back.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1578, a month before his death, Kenshin summoned an artist from Kyoto to make a self portrait and also a painting of his back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>肖像画は現在でもよく知られている謙信像だが、後姿はなんと盃を描かせたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the portrait showed an image of Kenshin which is well known even at present, it was amazed that he asked the artist to draw a picture of sake cup as his back shot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the portrait showing an image of Kenshin is still well known, it was amazing that the artist was asked to draw a picture of a sake cup in place of his back.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the portrait showing an image of Kenshin is still well known, it was amazing that the artist was asked to draw a picture of a sake cup in place of his back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>このときのことを謙信は、「この盃すなわち我が後影なり」と語ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that about the situation of this time, Kenshin said, &apos;This sake cup showed an image of my back shot.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the picture of his back Kenshin is believed to have said, &apos;This sake cup shows an image of my shadow.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the picture of his back Kenshin is believed to have said, &apos;This sake cup shows an image of my shadow.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>謙信には現存する同時代の肖像画が存在しないが、高野山無量光院にはかつて晩年期を描いた画像が所蔵されており、1893年（明治31年）の火災で焼失したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there exists no portrait of Kenshin at that time, and a picture of Kenshin in his later years used to be possessed in Muryoko-in Temple on Mt. Koya, the picture was lost due to fire in 1893.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Presently, there exists no contemporary portrait of Kenshin, but a collection of pictures of Kenshin in his later years were once possessed by Muryoko-in Temple on Mt. Koya, in 1893, the paintings were lost due to fire.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Presently, there exists no contemporary portrait of Kenshin, but a collection of pictures of Kenshin in his later years were once possessed by Muryoko-in Temple on Mt. Koya, in 1893, the paintings were lost due to fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>江戸時代には信玄はじめ他の戦国諸大名と同様に軍記物による影響を受け、軍陣武者像や法体武将像、仏画風僧侶像など多様な謙信のイメージが確立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, as well as Shingen and other Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period), various images of Kenshin such as an image of military warrior, Hottai (religious appearance) busho or Buddhist monk in the style of Buddhist painting were established under the influence of gunkimono (war tales).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, Shingen as well as other Sengoku daimyos (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) together attempted to record, in the form of a gunkimono (war tales), various images of Kenshin such as a military warrior, Hottai (religious appearance) busho or a Buddhist monk, in the style of Buddhist painting.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Shingen as well as other Sengoku daimyos (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) together attempted to record, in the form of a gunkimono (war tales), various images of Kenshin such as a military warrior, Hottai (religious appearance) busho or a Buddhist monk, in the style of Buddhist painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="154">
<j>誓文の血判から判定された血液型はAB型である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was determined from a seal of blood to written oath that he had type AB blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was determined from a written oath which was sealed with blood, that his blood type was AB.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was determined from a written oath which was sealed with blood, that his blood type was AB.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>性格・行動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characters and behavior</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characters and behavioral characteristics</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characters and behavioral characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="155">
<j>常軌を逸した行動も取ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he also behaved eccentrically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that he behaved eccentrically.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that he behaved eccentrically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>永禄12年（1559年）には上洛中、堺で無礼を働いた旅宿の主を手討ちにし、それに抗議した町人たちを追い払い、さらに町に放火したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that during his stay in Kyoto in 1559, Kenshin put a lord of inn who was rude in Sakai to death with his sword, drove out citizens who protested against such act, and furthermore, set fire to a town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his stay in Kyoto in 1559, Kenshin put a lord of an inn in Sakai to death as he was rude, then drove out the citizens who protested against such an act, and furthermore, set fire to the town.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his stay in Kyoto in 1559, Kenshin put a lord of an inn in Sakai to death as he was rude, then drove out the citizens who protested against such an act, and furthermore, set fire to the town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>他にも厩橋城の城代・長尾謙忠とその郎党を「謀反の疑い有り」として討ったこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides the above, Kenshin had killed Kanetada NAGAO, Jodai (the keeper of castle) of Umayabashi-jo Castle, and his retainers by reason that &apos;he suspected them of rebellion.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Kenshin had killed Kanetada NAGAO, Jodai (the keeper of castle) of Umayabashi-jo Castle, and his retainers by reason that &apos;he suspected them of rebellion.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Kenshin had killed Kanetada NAGAO, Jodai (the keeper of castle) of Umayabashi-jo Castle, and his retainers by reason that &apos;he suspected them of rebellion.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>これらの逸話は彼の奇矯な性格の一面を伝えているが、全てに確証があるわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although these anecdotes tell one face of his bizarre character, all are not corroborated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These anecdotes report one side of his bizarre character but all are not corroborated.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These anecdotes report one side of his bizarre character but all are not corroborated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="159">
<j>永禄4年（1561年）、関東管領の就任式では忍城城主・成田長泰の非礼に激昂し、顔面を扇子で打ちつけたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that at the ceremony for assumption of Kanto Kanrei in 1561, Kenshin got very angry at irreverent behavior of Nagayashi NARITA, lord of Oshi-jo castle, and slapped him in the face with sensu (folding fan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that during the ceremony for assuming the position of Kanto Kanrei in 1561, Kenshin was upset with the indecent behavior of Nagayashi NARITA, lord of Oshi-jo castle, and slapped him in the face with a sensu (folding fan).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that during the ceremony for assuming the position of Kanto Kanrei in 1561, Kenshin was upset with the indecent behavior of Nagayashi NARITA, lord of Oshi-jo castle, and slapped him in the face with a sensu (folding fan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>諸将の面前で辱めを受けた成田長泰は直ちに兵を率いて帰城してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayasu NARITA who was embarrassed in front of warlords immediately led soldiers and returned to his castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayasu NARITA was humiliated in front of other warlords, he immediately led his soldiers and returned to his castle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayasu NARITA was humiliated in front of other warlords, he immediately led his soldiers and returned to his castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>原因は諸将が下馬拝跪する中、成田長泰のみが馬上から会釈をしたためであったが、成田氏は藤原氏の流れをくむ名家で、武家棟梁の源義家にも馬上から会釈を許された家柄であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this was because only Nagayasu NARITA bowed without dismounting from a horse while warlords bowed after dismounting from a horse, the Narita clan was an important family descended from the Fujiwara clan, and belonged to a family lineage which was allowed to bow even to MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, the head of the samurai (warrior) families, without dismounting from a horse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reasons were attributed to Nagayasu NARITA bowing without dismounting from a horse while warlords usually bowed after dismounting from a horse, the Narita clan descended from the Fujiwara clan, a family lineage which was given permission to bow without dismounting to the likes of, MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, the head of the samurai (warrior) families.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reasons were attributed to Nagayasu NARITA bowing without dismounting from a horse while warlords usually bowed after dismounting from a horse, the Narita clan descended from the Fujiwara clan, a family lineage which was given permission to bow without dismounting to the likes of, MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, the head of the samurai (warrior) families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>謙信はこの故事を知らなかったと思われるが、この事件によって関東諸将の謙信への反感が急速に高まり、以後の関東進出の大きな足かせとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kenshin did not seem to know this tradition, this incident rapidly increased an antipathy toward Kenshin among warlords in the Kanto region, and largely stood in the way of his debouching into the Kanto region thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin did not seem to be aware of this tradition, and this incident rapidly increased an antipathy toward him among the warlords in the Kanto region, which was later a major obstacle in his advancing to the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin did not seem to be aware of this tradition, and this incident rapidly increased an antipathy toward him among the warlords in the Kanto region, which was later a major obstacle in his advancing to the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>この事件は、謙信の激昂しやすく短慮な一面を伝える逸話として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident is known as an anecdote telling one of his aspects that Kenshin got very angry easily and was impulsive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident is known as an anecdote informing of Kenshin&apos;s short temper and indiscreet nature.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident is known as an anecdote informing of Kenshin&apos;s short temper and indiscreet nature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>ただし、成田氏の地位はこのように尊大な態度を取れるほど過大ではなく、義家を馬上で迎える先例も原史料では認められず、研究者間はこれを事実とは認めていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the social position of Narita clan was not as high as taking such arrogant behavior, and any precedent of having Yoshiie without dismounting from a horse is not found in the original historical materials, researchers do not recognize this as a fact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the social position of the Narita clan was not as high as to show such arrogant behavior, and any precedent of bowing to Yoshiie without dismounting is not found in any original historical materials, researchers do not recognize this as a fact.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the social position of the Narita clan was not as high as to show such arrogant behavior, and any precedent of bowing to Yoshiie without dismounting is not found in any original historical materials, researchers do not recognize this as a fact.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>自己の正当性への確信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confidence in own rightness</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confidence in own rightness</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confidence in own rightness</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="165">
<j>戦場において、銃弾が頭髪をかすめようとも、自分に当たるわけがないと信じて恐れもなく戦ったり、合戦前には自分の正当性を示す願文を神仏に奉納した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At a battlefield, Kenshin dared to fight under a belief that a bullet would never hit him even though it grazed his hair, and he dedicated ganmon (prayer) showing own rightness to Shinto and Buddhist deities before the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At a battlefield, Kenshin fought without fear as he believed that even if a bullet grazed his hair it could not hit him, he dedicated ganmon (prayer) for self rightness to Shinto and Buddhist deities before any battle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At a battlefield, Kenshin fought without fear as he believed that even if a bullet grazed his hair it could not hit him, he dedicated ganmon (prayer) for self rightness to Shinto and Buddhist deities before any battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>部下への配慮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consideration to subordinates</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consideration to subordinates</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consideration to subordinates</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="166">
<j>天正元年（1573年）8月に越中国と加賀国の国境にある朝日山城を攻めた際に、一向一揆による鉄砲の乱射を受けて謙信は一時撤退を命じたが、吉江景資の子・与次だけは弾が飛び交う中で奮戦して撤退しようとしなかったため、謙信は与次を陣内に拘禁した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he ordered to withdraw temporarily due to random shooting by an uprising of Ikko sect followers when attacking Asahiyama-jo Castle at the border between Ecchu Province and Kaga Province in September 1573, Kenshin held Yoji, the son of Kagesuke YOSHIE, in custody within the camp because only Yoji, fought bravely in a flurry of bullets and did not withdraw as ordered.</e>
<cmt>天正元年（1573年）8月→September 1573[新暦に換算すると、8月1日は9月7日となるので（こよみのページより）]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin ordered a temporarily withdrawal due to random shooting by an uprising of Ikko sect followers while attacking Asahiyama-jo Castle at the border between Ecchu Province and Kaga Province in September 1573, he demanded Yoji, the son of Kagesuke YOSHIE, to remain in custody within the camp as he fought bravely in a flurry of bullets and did not withdraw as ordered.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin ordered a temporarily withdrawal due to random shooting by an uprising of Ikko sect followers while attacking Asahiyama-jo Castle at the border between Ecchu Province and Kaga Province in September 1573, he demanded Yoji, the son of Kagesuke YOSHIE, to remain in custody within the camp as he fought bravely in a flurry of bullets and did not withdraw as ordered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>驚いた周辺は与次を許すように申し入れたが、謙信は「ここで与次を戦死させたら、越後の父母（吉江景資夫妻）に面目が立たなくなる」とこれを拒んで、事情を吉江家に伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although surprised surrounding people requested Kenshin to forgive him, Kenshin refused the request with saying, &apos;if Yoji was killed in this battle, I will be too shamed to face his parents (Mr. and Mrs. Kagesuke YOSHIE) in Echigo Province,&apos; and told the Yoshie family the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surprised people requested Kenshin to forgive him, but he refused saying, &apos;if Yoji was killed in this battle, I would be too ashamed to face his parents (Mr. and Mrs. Kagesuke YOSHIE) in Echigo Province,&apos; and explained the facts of the situation to the Yoshie family.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surprised people requested Kenshin to forgive him, but he refused saying, &apos;if Yoji was killed in this battle, I would be too ashamed to face his parents (Mr. and Mrs. Kagesuke YOSHIE) in Echigo Province,&apos; and explained the facts of the situation to the Yoshie family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>与次は間もなく許されて、急死した中条景資の婿養子となって中条景泰と改名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoji who was forgiven soon became an adopted son-in-law of Kagesuke NAKAJO who died suddenly, and changed his name to Kageyasu NAKAJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoji was soon forgiven, he became an adopted son-in-law of Kagesuke NAKAJO who died suddenly, and was renamed to Kageyasu NAKAJO.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoji was soon forgiven, he became an adopted son-in-law of Kagesuke NAKAJO who died suddenly, and was renamed to Kageyasu NAKAJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>出家騒動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disturbance over becoming a priest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disturbance over becoming a priest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disturbance over becoming a priest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="169">
<j>家臣団の内部抗争・国人層の離反・信玄との戦いが膠着状態に陥りつつある状況に嫌気がさした謙信は毘沙門天堂に篭ることが多くなり、次第に信仰の世界に入っていくようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin who was fed up with an internal struggle among vassals, estrangement of Kokujin formation and the situation that a battle with Shingen got deadlocked came to frequently go into the Bishamonten-do Hall and to enter the world of religious belief gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin was fed up with internal struggles among vassals, estrangements of Kokujin formation and frustrated with stale mate battles with Shingen, so he frequently confined himself at Bishamonten-do Hall to gradually enter the world of religious beliefs.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin was fed up with internal struggles among vassals, estrangements of Kokujin formation and frustrated with stale mate battles with Shingen, so he frequently confined himself at Bishamonten-do Hall to gradually enter the world of religious beliefs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>弘治2年（1556年）3月23日、家臣団に出家の意向を伝え、6月28日には春日山城を出奔、高野山を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 12, 1556, Kenshin told his vassals his intention of becoming a priest, and on August 13, 1556, he ran away from Kasugayama-jo Castle and headed for Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>弘治2年（1556年）3月23日→May 12, 1556[こよみのページより]6月28日→August 13, 1556[こよみのページより]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 12, 1556, Kenshin informed his vassals, his intention of becoming a priest, and on August 13, 1556, he ran away from Kasugayama-jo Castle and headed for Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 12, 1556, Kenshin informed his vassals, his intention of becoming a priest, and on August 13, 1556, he ran away from Kasugayama-jo Castle and headed for Mt. Koya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>しかし8月17日、大和国の葛城山山麓、葛上郡吐田郷村で家臣が追いつき必死に懇願した結果、謙信は出家を思いとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on September 30, 1556, as a result of desperate request by vassals who caught up with Kenshin at Handago village, Katsujo County at the foot of Mt. Katsuragi in Yamato Province, Kenshin was dissuaded from becoming a priest.</e>
<cmt>8月17日→September 30, 1556[こよみのページより]吐田郷→Handago[http://www.yomiuri.co.jp/e-japan/nara/kikaku/050/5.htm より]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on September 30, 1556, Kenshin was dissuaded from becoming a priest by the desperate requests of the vassals who caught up with him at Handago village, Katsujo County at the foot of Mt. Katsuragi in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on September 30, 1556, Kenshin was dissuaded from becoming a priest by the desperate requests of the vassals who caught up with him at Handago village, Katsujo County at the foot of Mt. Katsuragi in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>謙信の奇矯な性格をよく表している逸話とされているが、家臣団が謙信に「以後は謹んで臣従し二心を抱かず」との誓紙を差し出したことで騒動は治まっていることから、人心掌握を目的とした計画的な行動だったともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this is regarded as an anecdote exactly expressing a Kenshin&apos;s bizarre character, it has been said that this was planned behavior aiming to win the hearts and minds of the people because the disturbance was settled by vassals&apos; submitting a written oath of &apos;serving respectfully and having no treachery thereafter.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following anecdote expresses the bizarre character of Kenshin, it is said that the incident was deliberately planned, aiming to win the hearts and minds of the people who caused disturbances, the issue was finally settled by submitting a written oath to &apos;serve respectfully and entertain no treachery thereafter.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following anecdote expresses the bizarre character of Kenshin, it is said that the incident was deliberately planned, aiming to win the hearts and minds of the people who caused disturbances, the issue was finally settled by submitting a written oath to &apos;serve respectfully and entertain no treachery thereafter.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>宿敵・武田信玄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old enemy, Shingen TAKEDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingen TAKEDA, an old enemy.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingen TAKEDA, an old enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="173">
<j>信玄の死を伝え聞いた食事中の謙信は、「吾れ好敵手を失へり、世に復たこれほどの英雄男子あらんや（『日本外史』より）」と箸を落として号泣したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kenshin who heard of Shingen&apos;s death while eating dropped chopsticks and cried out with saying, &apos;I lost a closest rival, and such a hero as Shingen will never appear again in this world (according to &quot;Nihon Gaishi&quot; (historical book on Japan).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kenshin heard of Shingen&apos;s death while eating, he dropped his chopsticks and cried out saying, &apos;I lost the closest rival, and such a hero will never appear again in this world (according to &quot;Nihon Gaishi&quot; (historical book on Japan).&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kenshin heard of Shingen&apos;s death while eating, he dropped his chopsticks and cried out saying, &apos;I lost the closest rival, and such a hero will never appear again in this world (according to &quot;Nihon Gaishi&quot; (historical book on Japan).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>後世の創作の可能性が高いが、「信玄亡き今こそ武田攻めの好機」と攻撃を薦める家臣の意見を「勝頼風情にそのような事をしても大人げない」と退けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a possibility that the above story was made up in future generations is high, when his vassal submitted an opinion of recommending an attack with saying, &apos;The time when Shingen died is a good chance to attack the Takeda clan,&apos; Kenshin rejected such opinion with saying, &apos;It is stupid to do such a thing to a mean person like Katsuyori.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a high possibility that the following incident has been fabricated in later generations, when his vassal recommended an attack saying, &apos;With Shingen&apos;s death it is a good chance to attack the Takeda clan,&apos; Kenshin dismissed it by replying &apos;It is a childish thing to do, even for a person like Katsuyori.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a high possibility that the following incident has been fabricated in later generations, when his vassal recommended an attack saying, &apos;With Shingen&apos;s death it is a good chance to attack the Takeda clan,&apos; Kenshin dismissed it by replying &apos;It is a childish thing to do, even for a person like Katsuyori.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="175">
<j>信玄との生涯にわたる因縁からか、それが転じて二人の間には友情めいたものがあったのではないかと現在でも推測されることがあるが、実際のところ謙信は信玄をかなり嫌っていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is sometimes assumed even now that a lifelong fate with Shingen might change to a kind of friendship between Kenshin and Shingen, the fact is that Kenshin seemed to hate Shingen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today there is a speculation that a lifelong fate with Shingen may have changed to a kind of friendship between Kenshin and Shingen, but the fact is that Kenshin seemed to hate Shingen.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today there is a speculation that a lifelong fate with Shingen may have changed to a kind of friendship between Kenshin and Shingen, but the fact is that Kenshin seemed to hate Shingen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>信玄が父親を追放したり、謀略を駆使して敵を貶めたりするのは謙信に言わせるところの道徳観に反しており（もっとも、戦国という時代を考えれば、信玄の行いは別にあってもおかしくないものだが）、謙信は信玄の行いに激怒したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that for Kenshin, it ran contrary to a sense of morality that Shingen expelled his father and misled his enemies by fully using tricks (not but that Shingen&apos;s actions were not especially odd in consideration to the period of Sengoku (warlike period)), and Kenshin was furious at such Shingen&apos;s actions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Shingen expelled his father and misled his enemies by using tricks (not that Shingen&apos;s actions were especially strange considering it was the Sengoku period (warlike period)), but Kenshin was furious as it was contrary to his morals.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Shingen expelled his father and misled his enemies by using tricks (not that Shingen&apos;s actions were especially strange considering it was the Sengoku period (warlike period)), but Kenshin was furious as it was contrary to his morals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>信玄との利益を度外視した数々の闘争は、謙信が純粋に信玄を嫌っていたことが原因だという説もある（もっともこれらは道徳観に反する行いが理由とも解釈できるため、謙信がいわれもなく信玄個人を「毛嫌い」していたという確証はない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory that a number of conflicts with Shingen which took no account of profit was caused by a reason that Kenshin genuinely hated Shingen (since it is possible to understand that the reason was Shingen&apos;s actions running contrary to the sense of morality, there is no conclusive evidence that Kenshin &apos;disliked&apos; Shingen himself without any reason).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory suggests that Shingen ignored profits made from several conflicts, this was a cause for Kenshin genuinely hating Shingen, (also, Shingen&apos;s actions run contrary to Kenshin&apos;s sense of morality, but there is no conclusive evidence that Kenshin &apos;disliked&apos; Shingen as an individual).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory suggests that Shingen ignored profits made from several conflicts, this was a cause for Kenshin genuinely hating Shingen, (also, Shingen&apos;s actions run contrary to Kenshin&apos;s sense of morality, but there is no conclusive evidence that Kenshin &apos;disliked&apos; Shingen as an individual).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>しかし、嫌っていた武田信玄が今川氏真によって塩止めを受けたときは（武田氏の領国甲斐国と信濃国は内陸のため、塩が取れない。これを見越した氏真の行動であった）、氏真の行いを「卑怯な行為」と批判し、「私は戦いでそなたと決着をつけるつもりだ。だから、越後の塩を送ろう」といって、信玄に塩を送ったという（「敵に塩を送る」という言葉はここから派生したといわれている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that when Shingen TAKEDA whom Kenshin disliked received supply stoppage of salt (Kai Province and Shinano Province under the control of Takeda clan did not produce salt because they were inland provinces, and such stoppage was Ujimasa&apos;s activities based on such condition), Shingen criticized Ujimasa&apos;s activities as &apos;being unmanly,&apos; and Kenshin sent salt to Shingen with saying, &apos;I will send salt to Echigo Province because I intend to have it out with you through a battle (it is believed that a phrase &apos;sending salt to an enemy&apos; originated from this anecdote).</e>
<cmt>後列の二つの文と併せて一つの文となっているので、句読点に係らず、一つの文として英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujimasa IMAGAWA had stopped the supply of salt to Shingen TAKEDA who Kenshin disliked, (Ujimasa had anticipated this as Kai and Shinano Provinces under the control of Takeda clan did not produce salt being inland provinces), Shingen criticized this as &apos;a cowardly act,&apos; and Kenshin sent salt to Shingen saying, &apos;I send you salt from Echigo Province as I intend to settle with you through battle (it is believed that the phrase &apos;sending salt to an enemy&apos; originated from this anecdote).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujimasa IMAGAWA had stopped the supply of salt to Shingen TAKEDA who Kenshin disliked, (Ujimasa had anticipated this as Kai and Shinano Provinces under the control of Takeda clan did not produce salt being inland provinces), Shingen criticized this as &apos;a cowardly act,&apos; and Kenshin sent salt to Shingen saying, &apos;I send you salt from Echigo Province as I intend to settle with you through battle (it is believed that the phrase &apos;sending salt to an enemy&apos; originated from this anecdote).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>この時、感謝の印として信玄が謙信に送ったとされる福岡一文字の在銘太刀「弘口」一振（塩留めの太刀）は重要文化財に指定され、東京国立博物館に所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, one sword of &apos;Hirokuchi&apos; with an inscription of Fukuoka Ichimonji (a sword for supply stoppage of salt) which was regarded to be sent by Shingen to Kenshin as a token of gratitude was designated as the important cultural property, and is possessed in the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, as a token of gratitude Shingen sent a Fukuoka Ichimonji (a sword for supply stoppage of salt) a sword with &apos;Hirokuchi&apos; inscribed, this has been designated as an important cultural property, and is in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, as a token of gratitude Shingen sent a Fukuoka Ichimonji (a sword for supply stoppage of salt) a sword with &apos;Hirokuchi&apos; inscribed, this has been designated as an important cultural property, and is in the possession of the Tokyo National Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>私生活</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Private life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Private life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Private life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="180">
<j>謙信の部下は、謙信の食事を見ただけでもうすぐ戦に行くのかどうかが分かったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that when looking at Kenshin&apos;s meals, Kenshin&apos;s vassals could know whether he would go into battle soon or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Kenshin&apos;s vassals could know whether he would go into battle or not just by a look his meals.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Kenshin&apos;s vassals could know whether he would go into battle or not just by a look his meals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>これは、普段はあまり食べない謙信が、戦の前になるとかなりの量を食べたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because Kenshin who did not eat so much usually ate a significant amount of food before going into battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because Kenshin normally did not eat much, but ate a significant amount before going into battle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because Kenshin normally did not eat much, but ate a significant amount before going into battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="182">
<j>生涯不犯を貫いたため、その子供は全員（上杉景勝・上杉景虎・畠山義春・山浦景国）養子だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kenshin made a lifelong commitment to strictly observe the Buddhist commandment that all priest should have been celibate, all of his children (Kagekatsu UESUGI, Kagetora UESUGI, Yoshiharu HATAKEYAMA and Kagekuni YAMAURA) were adopted children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kenshin made a lifelong commitment to strictly observe the Buddhist commandment of celibacy, all of his children (Kagekatsu UESUGI, Kagetora UESUGI, Yoshiharu HATAKEYAMA and Kagekuni YAMAURA) were adopted.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kenshin made a lifelong commitment to strictly observe the Buddhist commandment of celibacy, all of his children (Kagekatsu UESUGI, Kagetora UESUGI, Yoshiharu HATAKEYAMA and Kagekuni YAMAURA) were adopted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="183">
<j>永禄2年（1559年）、上洛した謙信と交流した近衛前久は「この間は度々おいで候て、華奢なる若衆を多く集め候て、大酒までにて、たびたび夜をあかし申し候、少弼（謙信）は若いのが好みとの由承り候」と謙信を観察しており、この書状と謙信が生涯にわたって女犯を一切断ったことを結びつけて、謙信は専ら男色のみを愛好したと見る歴史家もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1559, when having a relationship with Kenshin who went up to Kyoto and observing him, Sakihisa KONOE wrote his impression in a letter that &apos;shohitsu (assistant director of danjodai., Imperial Prosecuting and Investigating Office under the ritsuryo system) (referring to Kenshin) seemed to prefer young people because he often came over the other day, gathered many frail wakashu (younger members of soson village system), often drank a lot of sake through the night,&apos; and by relating this letter to the fact that Kenshin had no relationship with women throughout a lifetime, some historians consider that Kenshin preferred only men.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1559, while in Kyoto an acquaintance, Sakihisa KONOE, expressed his impression in a letter, &apos;shohitsu (assistant director of danjodai., Imperial Prosecuting and Investigating Office under the ritsuryo system) (referring to Kenshin) seemed to prefer young people as he often gathered many frail wakashu (younger members of soson village system), and often drank a lot of sake through the night,&apos; some historians related this letter to the fact that Kenshin had no relationship with women throughout his lifetime, and concluded that he preferred men.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1559, while in Kyoto an acquaintance, Sakihisa KONOE, expressed his impression in a letter, &apos;shohitsu (assistant director of danjodai., Imperial Prosecuting and Investigating Office under the ritsuryo system) (referring to Kenshin) seemed to prefer young people as he often gathered many frail wakashu (younger members of soson village system), and often drank a lot of sake through the night,&apos; some historians related this letter to the fact that Kenshin had no relationship with women throughout his lifetime, and concluded that he preferred men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>但し、男色(衆道)を愛好することは戦国武将の間では、極めて一般的な風習であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was a quite general custom among busho (Japanese military commanders) in the Sengoku period to be Nanshoku (shudo) (gay).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Nanshoku (shudo) (gay) was a general custom among the busho (Japanese military commanders) in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Nanshoku (shudo) (gay) was a general custom among the busho (Japanese military commanders) in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="185">
<j>謙信には複数の恋物語が伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More than one love story was handed down for Kenshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many love stories were handed down for Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many love stories were handed down for Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>ひとつは、彼がまだ二十代の折、敵将の上野・平井城主千葉采女の娘である伊勢姫と恋に落ちたが、重臣（柿崎景家ら）の猛烈な反対によって引き裂かれ、娘が剃髪出家した後、ほどなくして自害してしまい、食事ものどを通らず病床に伏せてしまうほどに心を痛めたというもの（「松隣夜話」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One was that although he fell in love with Isehime, a daughter of Uneme CHIBA who was his enemy commander and was a lord of Hirai-jo Castle in Kozuke Province when he was still in his twenties, they were divided by a strong opposition from a senior vassal (Kageie KAKIZAKI and others), and soon after taking the tonsure and becoming a priest, the daughter killed herself, and Kenshin could not eat anything and distressed himself so much as taking to his bed (&apos;Shorin Yawa&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One was that Kenshin still in his twenties fell in love with Isehime, a daughter of Uneme CHIBA an enemy commander and lord of Hirai-jo Castle in Kozuke Province, they were torn apart by strong opposition from a senior vassal (Kageie KAKIZAKI and others), after taking tonsure and becoming a priest, the daughter killed herself, Kenshin was distressed to the extent of not eating and finally becoming bedridden. (&apos;Shorin Yawa&apos;).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One was that Kenshin still in his twenties fell in love with Isehime, a daughter of Uneme CHIBA an enemy commander and lord of Hirai-jo Castle in Kozuke Province, they were torn apart by strong opposition from a senior vassal (Kageie KAKIZAKI and others), after taking tonsure and becoming a priest, the daughter killed herself, Kenshin was distressed to the extent of not eating and finally becoming bedridden (&apos;Shorin Yawa&apos;).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>この他にも、謙信の侍女として仕えていた直江景綱の長女や、近衛前久の妹・絶姫との間にほぼ同様の逸話があり、このような悲痛な経験が謙信を独身主義へと導く一端になったと仄めかしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the above, there are almost similar anecdotes of falling love with the first daughter of Kagetsuna NAOE who served as a waiting woman of Kenshin, and with Taehime who was a younger sister of Sakihisa KONOE, and it is suggested that such heartbreaking experiences were part of contributing factor that led Kenshin to be a celibatist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the above, there are almost similar anecdotes of falling in love with the first daughter of Kagetsuna NAOE who served as a waiting woman of Kenshin, and with Taehime who was a younger sister of Sakihisa KONOE, and it is suggested that such heartbreaking experiences were a contributing factor which led Kenshin to become a celibate.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the above, there are almost similar anecdotes of falling in love with the first daughter of Kagetsuna NAOE who served as a waiting woman of Kenshin, and with Taehime who was a younger sister of Sakihisa KONOE, and it is suggested that such heartbreaking experiences were a contributing factor which led Kenshin to become a celibate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>こうした謙信の悲痛な恋物語は今日でも多くの小説やドラマなどで採り入れられているが、いずれも軍記などの不確かな史書のみで語られる伝説に過ぎず、実証はされていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although such Kenshin&apos;s heartbreaking love stories are introduced in many novels and dramas even now, any of them is just a legend stated in only uncertain history books such as war chronicle and so on, and is not demonstrated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin&apos;s heartbreaking love stories are introduced in many novels and dramas even today, most of them are legends written in only certain history books such as war chronicles and so on, and is not proved.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin&apos;s heartbreaking love stories are introduced in many novels and dramas even today, most of them are legends written in only certain history books such as war chronicles and so on, and is not proved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="189">
<j>謙信が女性と交渉した事実が確認できないことについて様々な説があるが、いずれも確かな根拠に基づいたものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are various theories about being impossible to confirm the fact that Kenshin had a relationship with women, any of them is not based on a reliable evidence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories on facts of Kenshin&apos;s relationship with women, which cannot be confirmed, they are not based on reliable evidence.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories on facts of Kenshin&apos;s relationship with women, which cannot be confirmed, they are not based on reliable evidence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>心理学的な観点から、信心深く立派な女性であった母青岩院と姉仙桃院（景勝の母）の影響があったと推測する見方（幼少期に高潔な人格の女性から深い愛情を注がれた男性は、成長すると他の女性にも同じ高潔さを無意識に求めるため、次第に周囲の女性に幻滅して興味を示さなくなる傾向にあり、謙信もその一人だったのではないかというもの）や、半陰陽説や上杉謙信女性説といった俗談の類から、毘沙門天あるいは飯縄権現信仰の妻帯禁制を堅く守っていたとする説などが存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From psychological viewpoints, there is a viewpoint of assuming that Kenshin was influenced by his mother named Seiganin and his older sister named Sentoin (Kagekatsu&apos;s mother) who were religious and splendid women (a theory that Kenshin was one of men who were deeply loved by a woman of noble character in childhood because such men seek for the same nobleness from other women unconsciously when growing up, and tend to become disillusioned with and show less interest in surrounding women gradually), and there are also other theories including a kind of vulgar belief that Kenshin UESUGI was intersexual or female, and a theory that he strictly observed a ban of marriage based on the belief of Bishamonten or Izuna-gongen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From psychological viewpoints, one assumes that Kenshin was influenced by his mother, Seiganin, and his older sister, Sentoin (Kagekatsu&apos;s mother), who were religious and splendid women (a theory that men who are deeply loved by noble women in childhood, unconsciously seek the same nobleness from other women when growing up, and they are gradually disillusioned with and show less interest in surrounding women), Kenshin may have been one such person, there are other theories including a kind of vulgar belief that Kenshin UESUGI was intersexual or female, also that he strictly observed a ban of marriage based on the belief of Bishamonten or Izuna-gongen.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From psychological viewpoints, one assumes that Kenshin was influenced by his mother, Seiganin, and his older sister, Sentoin (Kagekatsu&apos;s mother), who were religious and splendid women (a theory that men who are deeply loved by noble women in childhood, unconsciously seek the same nobleness from other women when growing up, and they are gradually disillusioned with and show less interest in surrounding women), Kenshin may have been one such person, there are other theories including a kind of vulgar belief that Kenshin UESUGI was intersexual or female, also that he strictly observed a ban of marriage based on the belief of Bishamonten or Izuna-gongen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="191">
<j>大の酒好きであったが、他人と酒を酌み交わすような飲み方を好まず、ひとり縁側に出て、梅干だけを肴に手酌で飲んでいたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that although he liked sake very much, Kenshin did not prefer to have a drink with others, stepped out onto a veranda (a narrow wooden passage along the end of a house facing the garden) and helped himself to sake while eating pickled ume (plum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kenshin liked sake very much, he did not prefer to drink with others, he would step out onto a veranda (a narrow wooden passage along the end of a house facing the garden) and help himself to sake while eating pickled ume (plum).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kenshin liked sake very much, he did not prefer to drink with others, he would step out onto a veranda (a narrow wooden passage along the end of a house facing the garden) and help himself to sake while eating pickled ume (plum).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="192">
<j>死因について、過度の飲酒とつまみの梅干による塩分の取りすぎによる高血圧が原因の脳血管障害と言われている（雪の中、厠で倒れたと史料にあることも、死因が脳溢血だと考えられる一因である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that the cause of his death was a cerebral vascular disturbance due to hypertension caused by excessive drinking and excessive intake of salt by pickled ume (plum) eaten with sake (a description in a historical material that he fell in a toilet in the snow contributes to the theory that the cause of his death was cerebral hemorrhage)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that the cause of his death was cerebral vascular disturbance due to hypertension caused by excessive drinking and intake of salt by pickled ume (plum) eaten with sake (a historical material describes that he fell in a toilet in the snow causing cerebral hemorrhage).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that the cause of his death was cerebral vascular disturbance due to hypertension caused by excessive drinking and intake of salt by pickled ume (plum) eaten with sake (a historical material describes that he fell in a toilet in the snow causing cerebral hemorrhage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>他に、厠で用を足していた時に信長の派遣で雪隠隠れをしていた刺客に槍で刺されて殺害されたという説、婦人病（詳細は上杉謙信女性説に記載）で亡くなったとという奇説や、酒の飲みすぎからくる胃癌、食道癌説、織田信長にヒ素で毒殺されたなどの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides the above, there are others including a theory that when he had a wash, Kenshin was killed with a spear by a murderer who was dispatched by Nobunaga and hid in secchin (lavatory), a strange theory that he died of women&apos;s disease (detailed information is given in the theory that Kenshin UESUGI was female), a theory that Kenshin died of gastric or esophageal cancer due to excessive drinking of sake, and a theory that he was killed with arsenic poison by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides the above, there are other theories one was that when Kenshin went to the lavatory he was killed with a spear by a murderer who was dispatched by Nobunaga, another strange theory that he died of women&apos;s disease (details are stated in Kenshin UESUGI was female), others are Kenshin died of gastric or esophageal cancer due to excessive drinking of sake, and that he was killed with arsenic poison by Nobunaga ODA are still other theories.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides the above, there are other theories one was that when Kenshin went to the lavatory he was killed with a spear by a murderer who was dispatched by Nobunaga, another strange theory that he died of women&apos;s disease (details are stated in Kenshin UESUGI was female), others are Kenshin died of gastric or esophageal cancer due to excessive drinking of sake, and that he was killed with arsenic poison by Nobunaga ODA are still other theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="194">
<j>40歳（1569年）の時、脳血管障害（と思われる）を発症、左下肢を動かしにくくなった、と言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he had the onset of cerebral vascular disturbance (believed to be) at the age of 40 (in 1569), and came to have a difficulty in moving his lower leg.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he had an onset of cerebral vascular disturbance (believed to be) at the age of 40, in 1569, and had difficulty in moving his left lower extremity.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he had an onset of cerebral vascular disturbance (believed to be) at the age of 40, in 1569, and had difficulty in moving his left lower extremity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>戦国大名として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="195">
<j>謙信は織田信長と対抗できる最後の一人だったため、当時からその死は相当な衝撃を与えたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kenshin was the last person who could beat Nobunaga ODA, his death seemed to give a considerable shock even at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kenshin was the last person who could oppose Nobunaga ODA, his death seemed to be a considerable shock at the time.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kenshin was the last person who could oppose Nobunaga ODA, his death seemed to be a considerable shock at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>謙信の葬儀は3月15日に執り行なわれたが、このときのことを『北越軍談』はこう記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kenshin&apos;s funeral ceremony was performed on May 1, 1578, and the situation at this time was described in &quot;Kitakoshi Gundan&quot; as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin&apos;s funeral ceremony was performed on May 1, 1578, the situation at the time is described in &quot;Kitakoshi Gundan&quot; as follows.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin&apos;s funeral ceremony was performed on May 1, 1578, the situation at the time is described in &quot;Kitakoshi Gundan&quot; as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="197">
<j>「家門・宿老・侍隊将・奉行・頭人・近習・外様、出棺の前後を打囲て行列の姿堂々たれ共、獅竜の部伍に事替り、衆皆哭慟の声を呑み、喪服の袂を絞りければ、街に蹲る男女老若共に泪止め兼ねたり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A procession of Kamon (family), Shukuro (chief vassal), Samurai taisho (in charge of guard and departure for the front in a war), Bugyo (magistrate), Tonin (the director), Kinju (attendant) and tozama (outside feudal lord) who walked before and after the coffin carried out was magnificent, brave troops followed, all people squeezed sleeves of morning dress to suppress a sound of crying out, and men and women of all ages crouching in a town could not suppress tears. It was as if a red star (referring to Zhuge Liang) fell and the Shoku (Shu) army tumbled during camping in Gojogen (Wuzhang Plains), and was just like not only officers and men in Kasugayama-jo Castle but also those coming to and gathering in the castle town suddenly lost a helm while sailing, and drifted with the waves in a giant sea.&apos;</e>
<cmt>後列の文と併せて一つの括弧にくくられているので、句読点に係らず、一つの文として英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A magnificent procession of all who walked before and after the coffin were, Kamon (family), Shukuro (chief vassal), Samurai taisho (in charge of guard and departure for the front in a war), Bugyo (magistrate), Tonin (the director), Kinju (attendant) and tozama (outside feudal lord), brave troops followed, people suppressed the sound of crying with their sleeves, and men and women of all ages could not suppress tears. It was as if a red star (referring to Zhuge Liang) fell and the Shoku (Shu) army tumbled while camping in Gojogen (Wuzhang Plains), not only officers and men in Kasugayama-jo Castle but also those gathered in the castle town, suddenly lost a helm while sailing, and drifted with the waves into the giant sea.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A magnificent procession of all who walked before and after the coffin were, Kamon (family), Shukuro (chief vassal), Samurai taisho (in charge of guard and departure for the front in a war), Bugyo (magistrate), Tonin (the director), Kinju (attendant) and tozama (outside feudal lord), brave troops followed, people suppressed the sound of crying with their sleeves, and men and women of all ages could not suppress tears.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>「彼五丈原の営中、赤星（諸葛亮）落て蜀軍傾覆するが如く、春日山の郭内は云にや及ぶ、城下に来り集る将士、宛然航路に楫を失ひ、巨海の波に漂ふに斉し」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was as if a red star (referring to Zhuge Liang) fell and the Shoku (Shu) army tumbled while camping in Gojogen (Wuzhang Plains), not only officers and men in Kasugayama-jo Castle but also those gathered in the castle town, suddenly lost a helm while sailing, and drifted with the waves into the giant sea.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="199">
<j>戦では無類の強さを発揮した謙信が天下を取れなかった理由は越中国の一向一揆に手間取ったこともあげられる（謙信は仏を信仰していたが、信仰していたのは真言宗）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A reasons why Kenshin who demonstrated his incomparable strength in the battle could not gain full control of the nation was that he had a lot of trouble settling an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Ecchu Province (although he believed in Buddhism, Kenshin professed the Shingon sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A reason why Kenshin, who demonstrated unrivaled strength in battle, could not gain full control of the nation was that he had to often settle uprisings of the Ikko sect followers in Ecchu Province (although he believed in Buddhism, Kenshin professed the Shingon sect).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A reason why Kenshin, who demonstrated unrivaled strength in battle, could not gain full control of the nation was that he had to often settle uprisings of the Ikko sect followers in Ecchu Province (although he believed in Buddhism, Kenshin professed the Shingon sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>同じく北陸の大名であった朝倉氏も加賀の一向宗に悩まされ地盤を越えた戦略を取ることが出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Asakura clan who was daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Hokuriku region as well as Kenshin was also annoyed with the Ikko sect in Kaga Province and could not take strategies beyond the foothold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simarly, the daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) of the Asakura clan in the Hokuriku region was annoyed with the Ikko sect in Kaga Province and his strategies did not work out beyond the foothold.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, the daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) of the Asakura clan in the Hokuriku region was annoyed with the Ikko sect in Kaga Province and his strategies did not work out beyond the foothold.</e>
<cmt>SimarlyをSimilarlyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public estimation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public estimation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public estimation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="201">
<j>軍事能力に卓越しており、「越後の龍」や「軍神」などと後世で評されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin had an outstanding ability in military affairs, and was reputed to be &apos;Echigo no Ryu&apos; (dragon in Echigo Province) or &apos;god of war&apos; in future generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin had an outstanding ability in military affairs, and was reputed to be &apos;Echigo no Ryu&apos; (dragon of Echigo Province) or &apos;god of war&apos; in future generations.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin had an outstanding ability in military affairs, and was reputed to be &apos;Echigo no Ryu&apos; (dragon of Echigo Province) or &apos;god of war&apos; in future generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>一般には謙信は天才型で、迅速な用兵と駆け引きの的確さから生涯殆どの戦で勝利をおさめたという見方が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General view is that Kenshin was a genius and won in almost all of his lifetime battles thanks to rapid tactics and accurate strategy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally Kenshin was considered a genius and won almost all of his lifetime battles due to rapid tactics and accurate strategy.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally Kenshin was considered a genius and won almost all of his lifetime battles due to rapid tactics and accurate strategy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>天正4年に甲斐の僧・教賀が長福寺の空陀に送った書状によれば、宿敵たる武田信玄も常々謙信をして「日本無双之名大将」と評していたそうである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a letter sent to Ada of Chofuku-ji Temple by Kyoga, a priest in Kai Province, in 1576, even Shingen TAKEDA of old enemy always reputed Kenshin as &apos;Unrivaled Taisho (general) in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a letter sent by Kyoga to a priest at Ada of Chofuku-ji Temple in Kai Province, in 1576, Shingen TAKEDA an old enemy always described Kenshin as an &apos;Unrivaled Taisho (general) in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a letter sent by Kyoga to a priest at Ada of Chofuku-ji Temple in Kai Province, in 1576, Shingen TAKEDA an old enemy always described Kenshin as an &apos;Unrivaled Taisho (general) in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>謙信と他大名との鉄砲、弓、馬などの軍事編成の比はさほど差異はなく、戦術的にも大きな違いはないが、上杉軍は敵と敵のぶつかりあい、直接戦闘では圧倒的な強さを誇っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although when comparing Kenshin and other daimyo (Japanese feudal lords), there was only a small difference in a military organization such as teppo (gun), bows, horses and so on, and was not a big difference in strategies, the Uesugi army was proud of overwhelming strength in direct battles between enemies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When comparing Kenshin and other daimyo (Japanese feudal lords), in a military organization such as teppo (gun), bows, horses and so on there was only a small difference, and not much difference in strategies, but the Uesugi army was proud of their own overwhelming strength in direct combats with enemies.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When comparing Kenshin and other daimyo (Japanese feudal lords), in a military organization such as teppo (gun), bows, horses and so on there was only a small difference, and not much difference in strategies, but the Uesugi army was proud of their own overwhelming strength in direct combats with enemies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="204">
<j>上杉軍の強さは、謙信の死後も、織田信長の支配地域において｢武田軍と上杉軍の強さは天下一である」と噂されるほどのものであった（大和国興福寺蓮成院記録・天正十年三月の項を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uesugi army was so strong that it was rumored in the area ruled by Nobunaga ODA even after Kenshin&apos;s death that &apos;both the Takeda army and the Uesugi army had unrivaled strength in the nation&apos; (refer to the article of March in the Tensho era (April 1582) in Yamato no kuni Kofuku-ji Renjo-in kiroku (the records of Kofuku-ji Temple and Renjo-in Temple).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after Kenshin&apos;s death, the Uesugi army was so strong that it was rumored in the area ruled by Nobunaga ODA that &apos;both the Takeda army and the Uesugi army had unrivaled strength in the nation&apos; (refer to the article of March in the Tensho era (April 1582) in Yamato no kuni Kofuku-ji Renjo-in kiroku (the records of Kofuku-ji Temple and Renjo-in Temple).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after Kenshin&apos;s death, the Uesugi army was so strong that it was rumored in the area ruled by Nobunaga ODA that &apos;both the Takeda army and the Uesugi army had unrivaled strength in the nation&apos; (refer to the article of March in the Tensho era (April 1582) in Yamato no kuni Kofuku-ji Renjo-in kiroku (the records of Kofuku-ji Temple and Renjo-in Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>つまり、日本全国の情報が集まる戦国時代の京都周辺の人々にとって、「武田軍と上杉軍が日本最強」ということはほとんど常識であり、謙信の死後もその評価が揺らぐことはなかったということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that, for people around Kyoto in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) where nationwide information gathered, it was almost common sense that &apos;the Takeda army and the Uesugi army were stronger than any other army in Japan,&apos; and that such public estimation was firm even after Kenshin died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the people around Kyoto where nationwide information gathered during the Sengoku period (period of warring states), it was understood that &apos;the Takeda army and the Uesugi army were stronger than any other army in Japan,&apos; and such public estimation was firm even after the death of Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the people around Kyoto where nationwide information gathered during the Sengoku period (period of warring states), it was understood that &apos;the Takeda army and the Uesugi army were stronger than any other army in Japan,&apos; and such public estimation was firm even after the death of Kenshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>その生涯で約70回もの合戦を行い、敗北は僅か2回と伝えられ、野戦に限れば北条氏康との生野山合戦の1回のみとされる（『謙信公御年譜』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is told that Kenshin battled as many as about 70 times throughout his lifetime, and was defeated only twice, and it is believed that only in terms of open battle, he was defeated only once in the Battle of Ikunoyama with Ujiyasu HOJO (&quot;Kenshinko Gonenpu&quot; (Chronological Record of Kenshin)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is told that Kenshin battled as many as about 70 times throughout his lifetime, and was defeated only twice, and it is also believed that in terms of open battle, he was defeated only once at the Battle of Ikunoyama with Ujiyasu HOJO (&quot;Kenshinko Gonenpu&quot; (Chronological Record of Kenshin)).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is told that Kenshin battled as many as about 70 times throughout his lifetime, and was defeated only twice, and it is also believed that in terms of open battle, he was defeated only once at the Battle of Ikunoyama with Ujiyasu HOJO (&quot;Kenshinko Gonenpu&quot; (Chronological Record of Kenshin)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="207">
<j>軍事面で評されることが多いが、内政面に関しても大きな失政はなく、綿密に計画された金山運営で大きな利益をあげることに成功しており、また日本海側の海上交易の要衝としての利益も大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he is often reputed in terms of military affairs, Kenshin did not conduct remarkable misgovernment in terms of domestic administration, succeeded in making big profits on the management of gold mine based on the in-depth strategy, and also made big profits as an important point of commerce through a Japan Sea route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin was often reputed for his management in military affairs, as regards to domestic administration there was no big mismanagement, he succeeded in making big profits from the gold mine based on detailed strategy, and also made huge profits from maritime trade through the Japan Sea route.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin was often reputed for his management in military affairs, as regards to domestic administration there was no big mismanagement, he succeeded in making big profits from the gold mine based on detailed strategy, and also made huge profits from maritime trade through the Japan Sea route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>これらのことから一概に「戦上手の内政下手」とは言えない（補足として、謙信の年貢の収納高は推定99万7000石、武田信玄は推定83万5000石で最盛期は100万石超。経済力では両者ほぼ互角である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Looking at the above, it cannot be completely said that he was &apos;good at military administration, but not good at domestic administration&apos; (supplementarily speaking, since it was estimated that Kenshin&apos;s stored amount of nengu (land tax) was 997,000 koku (of rice) (a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter) and Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s stored amount of nengu was 835,000 koku and exceeded one million koku at peak, their economic powers were almost even).</e>
<cmt>後列の文と併せて一つの文となるので、句読点に係らず、後列の文を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the above example one cannot say Kenshin was &apos;good at military administration, but not good at domestic administration&apos; (As a supplement, it was estimated that Kenshin&apos;s stored amount of nengu (land tax) was 997,000 koku (of rice) (a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter) and Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s was 835,000 koku which exceeded one million koku at the peak, their economic powers were almost even).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the above example one cannot say Kenshin was &apos;good at military administration, but not good at domestic administration&apos; (As a supplement, it was estimated that Kenshin&apos;s stored amount of nengu (land tax) was 997,000 koku (of rice) (a unit of volume: rice 1-koku is 180.39 liter, lumber 1-koku is 0.278 cubic meter) and Shingen TAKEDA&apos;s was 835,000 koku which exceeded one million koku at the peak, their economic powers were almost even).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>豊富な資金力を生かして民政面でも成果を上げており、太田資正は、｢謙信の代になって越後の民衆の生活水準が劇的に向上しており、民を慈しむ優秀な領主である｣と高い評価を下している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kenshin who put his enormous wealth to good use also got good results in the civil administration, Sukemasa OTA highly evaluated him as &apos;a good feudal lord caring for the people because people&apos;s standard of living in Echigo Province was enhanced dramatically after Kenshin became a feudal lord.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin put enormous wealth to good use and showed good results due to his civil administration, Sukemasa OTA highly evaluated him as &apos;a good feudal lord as people&apos;s standard of living in Echigo Province improved dramatically after Kenshin became a feudal lord.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin put enormous wealth to good use and showed good results due to his civil administration, Sukemasa OTA highly evaluated him as &apos;a good feudal lord as people&apos;s standard of living in Echigo Province improved dramatically after Kenshin became a feudal lord.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="210">
<j>野戦での電光石火で神がかり的な采配に比べ、攻城戦には失敗し撤退することもしばしばあった（小田原城、臼井城、唐沢山城等）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though he took lightning-fast and inspired command in the open battle, Kenshin often failed in the battle of attacking a castle and withdrew (Odawara-jo Castle, Usji-jo Castle, Karasawayama-jo Castle and so on).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inspite of being possessed with special powers to move at lightning speed and inspire command in open battle, Kenshin often failed in the siege of castles and withdrew (Odawara-jo Castle, Usji-jo Castle, Karasawayama-jo Castle and so on).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inspite of being possessed with special powers to move at lightning speed and inspire command in open battle, Kenshin often failed in the siege of castles and withdrew (Odawara-jo Castle, Usji-jo Castle, Karasawayama-jo Castle and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>小田原城といえば、巨大な総構えを持つ城塞都市というイメージが強いが、当時は総構えどころか、三の丸も存在しない程度の規模であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Odawara-jo Castle has a strong image of fortified city having a huge sogamae (outer citadel), its scale was as small as having neither sogamae nor Sannomaru at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, Odawara-jo Castle had a strong image of a fortified city with a huge sogamae (outer citadel), but its actual scale was small having neither sogamae nor Sannomaru.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, Odawara-jo Castle had a strong image of a fortified city with a huge sogamae (outer citadel), but its actual scale was small having neither sogamae nor Sannomaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>小田原包囲と同時に行っていた玉縄城などの支城攻略も失敗に終わっており、その後の北条の逆襲を招く結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin also failed in attacks on branch castles such as Tamanawa-jo Castle and so on which were conducted at the same time as besieging Odawara-jo Castle, and due to this failure, he was counterattack by the Hojo clan thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin failed in attacks on branch castles such as Tamanawa-jo Castle and so on, which were conducted at the same time as besieging Odawara-jo Castle, and due to this failure, he was counterattacked by the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin failed in attacks on branch castles such as Tamanawa-jo Castle and so on, which were conducted at the same time as besieging Odawara-jo Castle, and due to this failure, he was counterattacked by the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>武田・北条両大名家と繰り広げた長期に渡る大規模な持久戦で露呈した脆さは致命的であり、直接の対陣での敗北は殆ど無いにも関わらず、関東においては最終的に上野の一部以外は殆ど失ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to his deadly vulnerability exposed in the large-scale prolonged and protracted battle with both Daimyo families (feudal lord families) of Takeda and Hojo, Kenshin finally lost lands in the Kanto region except for part of Kozuke Province even though he was not almost defeated in the direct confrontation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin&apos;s vulnerability was exposed in the large-scale prolonged and protracted battles with both Daimyo families (feudal lord families) of Takeda and Hojo, although Kenshin was not defeated in direct confrontation, he finally lost lands in the Kanto region except for a part of Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin&apos;s vulnerability was exposed in the large-scale prolonged and protracted battles with both Daimyo families (feudal lord families) of Takeda and Hojo, although Kenshin was not defeated in direct confrontation, he finally lost lands in the Kanto region except for a part of Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="214">
<j>持久戦の弱さは、豪雪地帯から遠く補給線の貧弱な敵地に向けて長期的な軍事行動を取ることが不可能であり、それゆえに短期的な活動で多大な成果を得なくてはならなかったことが原因であると見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the vulnerability in the protracted battle resulted from an obligation of obtaining tremendous benefits from short-term activities because he could not take long-term military activities toward an enemy territory which was far from a snowy area and had a poor supply line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vulnerability in the protracted battles resulted because it was difficult to transport military artilleries from snow areas to far off enemy territories with poor line supplies, hence he was forced to participate in short-term activities to achieve greater results.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vulnerability in the protracted battles resulted because it was difficult to transport military artilleries from snow areas to far off enemy territories with poor line supplies, hence he was forced to participate in short-term activities to achieve greater results.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>また、直接の軍事行動で敗北は殆どなかったものの、占領地を直接支配しなかったがために謙信が帰国するたび関東衆の離反を許すこととなり、北条・武田に対しての長期戦略は上野の一部を得るにとどまってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was seldom defeated in the direct military activities, Kenshin had to admit estrangements of people in the Kanto region which were conducted whenever he returned to his province because he did not directly rule territories, and only obtained part of Kozuke Province in the long-term strategy for the Hojo clan and the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin was seldom defeated in direct military activities, as he did not directly rule in the occupied territories he forgave people who were estranged, and this happened whenever he returned to his province, in long-term strategies he only obtained part of Kozuke Province from the Hojo clan and the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin was seldom defeated in direct military activities, as he did not directly rule in the occupied territories he forgave people who were estranged, and this happened whenever he returned to his province, in long-term strategies he only obtained part of Kozuke Province from the Hojo clan and the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>結果として武田の北進を阻み、北条の躍進を停滞させるなど、国防に成功したものの、侵略の成果は乏しいものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though he eventually succeeded in the defense of his provision by interrupting Takeda&apos;s debouching into the north and holding up Hojo&apos;s breakthrough, results Kenshin obtained from the invasion were poor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though he eventually succeeded in defending his provision by interrupting Takeda proceeding into the north and holding up Hojo&apos;s breakthrough, the results Kenshin obtained from the invasion were poor.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though he eventually succeeded in defending his provision by interrupting Takeda proceeding into the north and holding up Hojo&apos;s breakthrough, the results Kenshin obtained from the invasion were poor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>特に臼井城の攻防では原胤貞2千の軍勢に上杉1万5千と7倍以上であったにもかかわらず、胤貞より指揮を受け継いだ軍師・白井入道浄三に大敗している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the offensive and defensive battle of Usui-jo Castle, the Uesugi army was severely defeated by Shirai Nyudo Josan who was a strategist taking over the command from Tanesada HARA even though its military force with 15,000 soldiers was at least seven times bigger than that of Tanesada with 2,000 soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the offensive and defensive battle of Usui-jo Castle, Shirai Nyudo JOSAN, a strategist who took over command from Tanesada HARA with a troop of 2,000 soldiers severely defeated the Uesugi army with a military force of 15,000 soldiers at least seven times bigger than that of Tanesada.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the offensive and defensive battle of Usui-jo Castle, Shirai Nyudo JOSAN, a strategist who took over command from Tanesada HARA with a troop of 2,000 soldiers severely defeated the Uesugi army with a military force of 15,000 soldiers at least seven times bigger than that of Tanesada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>ただしこの合戦は一次資料による裏づけが存在しないため、議論の余地を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this battle leaves room for discussion because primary materials had no evidence to support.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this battle leaves room for discussion because the primary materials had no evidence.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this battle leaves room for discussion because the primary materials had no evidence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="219">
<j>第四次川中島の合戦の直前、10万を超える東国の大連合軍を率いて一気に小田原城などに攻め込み北条氏を滅亡寸前まで追い詰めたが、隙をついて武田信玄が信濃にて軍事行動を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although right before the fourth Battle of Kawanakajima, Kenshin who led big allied forces of Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) with more than 100,000 soldiers attacked Odawara-jo Castle and so on at a burst, and drove the Hojo clan to the verge of the fall, Shingen TAKEDA took military actions in Shinano Province in an unguarded moment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before the fourth Battle of Kawanakajima, Kenshin led a big allied force of Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) with more than 100,000 soldiers attacked Odawara-jo Castle in one stroke, and cornered the Hojo clan to the brink of collapse, Shingen TAKEDA took military actions in Shinano Province in an unguarded moment.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before the fourth Battle of Kawanakajima, Kenshin led a big allied force of Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) with more than 100,000 soldiers attacked Odawara-jo Castle in one stroke, and cornered the Hojo clan to the brink of collapse, Shingen TAKEDA took military actions in Shinano Province in an unguarded moment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>だが、信玄は上杉氏諸将の不安をあおるために行動を起こしただけで本気で戦をする気はなかった（事実、上杉軍が動きを止めた後すぐに撤退している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Shingen just took actions to make warlords of Uesugi clan uneasy, and had no intention to fight seriously (in fact, Shingen withdrew immediately after the Uesugi army stopped the action).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Shingen just took actions to make the warlords of Uesugi clan uneasy, and had no intention to fight seriously (in fact, Shingen withdrew immediately after the Uesugi army stopped the action).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Shingen just took actions to make the warlords of Uesugi clan uneasy, and had no intention to fight seriously (in fact, Shingen withdrew immediately after the Uesugi army stopped the action).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>謙信は信玄の意図を見抜いていて作戦続行を主張したが、関東諸将の反対で撤退するしかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he insisted on continuing a strategy because he had an insight into Shingen&apos;s designs, Kenshin had to withdraw due to an objection from warlords in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he insisted on continuing the strategy because he had insight in Shingen&apos;s designs, Kenshin had to withdraw due to objections from the warlords in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he insisted on continuing the strategy because he had insight in Shingen&apos;s designs, Kenshin had to withdraw due to objections from the warlords in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>一説によれば、武田信玄はこのことをさして「もしあの時、時間を置かず一気に小田原城を攻めていたら防御の十分でなかった城は陥落し、さしもの北条氏康も滅ぼされていたであろう。そうすれば甲斐の国も危なかった」と述べたと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, it is told that Shingen TAKEDA thought of this situation and said, &apos;If Kenshin attacked Odawara-jo Castle at a burst without an interval, the castle with insufficient defense system would fall, and even Ujiyasu HOJO would be ruined, and if so, Kai Province would be in trouble.&apos;</e>
<cmt>後列の文と併せて一つの文となるので、句読点に係らず、下の文を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, Shingen TAKEDA refered to this situation and said, &apos;If at that moment Kenshin attacked Odawara-jo Castle in one stroke without an interval, the castle with insufficient defense system would fall, and Ujiyasu HOJO would be ruined, if this was the case, Kai Province would be in danger.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, Shingen TAKEDA refered to this situation and said, &apos;If at that moment Kenshin attacked Odawara-jo Castle in one stroke without an interval, the castle with insufficient defense system would fall, and Ujiyasu HOJO would be ruined, if this was the case, Kai Province would be in danger.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>また、足利氏を守るために三好氏・松永氏討伐を画策していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Kenshin schemed to subdue the Miyoshi clan and the Matsunaga clan in order to protect the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Kenshin schemed to subdue the Miyoshi clan and the Matsunaga clan in order to protect the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Kenshin schemed to subdue the Miyoshi clan and the Matsunaga clan in order to protect the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>上洛が出来さえすれば成功の可能性は高く（若狭・越中間は航路があり上杉氏には水軍もあったため加賀一向一揆は無視できた。また、幕臣である越前の朝倉氏・若狭の一色氏の協力は得られた可能性が高い）、謙信を警戒した三好・松永から大量の貢物を送られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the probability was high that the scheme was successful if Kenshin could go up to Kyoto (he could ignore an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga Province because there was a sea route between Wakasa Province and Ecchu Province and the Uesugi clan had Suigun (warriors battle in the sea, and moreover, he could probably obtain cooperation from the Asakura clan in Echizen Province and the Isshiki clan in Wakasa Province who were shogun&apos;s retainers), the Miyoshi clan and the Matsunaga who were cautious about Kenshin sent enormous amounts of tributes to him.</e>
<cmt>後列の文と併せて一つの文となるので、句読点に係らず、後列の文を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a high probability that the scheme would have been successful if Kenshin had gone up to Kyoto (he could have ignored an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga Province because there was a sea route between Wakasa Province and Ecchu Province and the Uesugi clan had Suigun (warriors battle in the sea), moreover, he could probably have obtained cooperation from the Asakura clan in Echizen Province and the Isshiki clan in Wakasa Province who were the shogun&apos;s retainers), the Miyoshi clan and the Matsunaga who were cautious about Kenshin sent enormous amounts of tributes to him.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a high probability that the scheme would have been successful if Kenshin had gone up to Kyoto (he could have ignored an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga Province because there was a sea route between Wakasa Province and Ecchu Province and the Uesugi clan had Suigun (warriors battle in the sea), moreover, he could probably have obtained cooperation from the Asakura clan in Echizen Province and the Isshiki clan in Wakasa Province who were the shogun&apos;s retainers), the Miyoshi clan and the Matsunaga who were cautious about Kenshin sent enormous amounts of tributes to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>しかし、このときも家臣の反対で実行に移せなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kenshin could not also put in practice at this time due to an objection from his vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kenshin could not excute his actions at the time due to objection from his vassals.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kenshin could not excute his actions at the time due to objection from his vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>いずれも謙信の電光石火・神出鬼没ぶりや戦術眼の高さがうかがえる逸話だが、家臣団の反対で中止せざるをえなくなっている所に謙信の限界があるとの意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although any of the above anecdotes shows Kenshin&apos;s lightning-fast and elusive characters and excellence in strategy, some people say that his limiting point was that he had to call off due to an objection from vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above anecdotes show Kenshin&apos;s lightning-fast, elusive characters and excellence in strategy, his limiting point was that he had to call off due to an objection from vassals.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above anecdotes show Kenshin&apos;s lightning-fast, elusive characters and excellence in strategy, his limiting point was that he had to call off due to an objection from vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="227">
<j>有名無実な関東管領職にこだわり続けた面から、形式に拘る形式主義者、実質よりも権威を重んじる権威主義者、室町幕府体制の復興を願う復古主義者と評する声がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the viewpoint of continuing to stick to titular Kanto Kanrei, some people say that Kenshin was a formalist sticking to forms, an authoritarian respecting authority rather than substance, and a reversionist wishing for revival of Muromachi bakufu system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処復古主義者→reversionist[Personal Dictionary for Windows - Eijiro81 より]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the viewpoint of continuing the job of a titular Kanto Kanrei, some people say that Kenshin was a formalist, particular about forms, an authoritarian respecting authority rather than substance, and a reversionary hoping for revival of the Muromachi bakufu system.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the viewpoint of continuing the job of a titular Kanto Kanrei, some people say that Kenshin was a formalist, particular about forms, an authoritarian respecting authority rather than substance, and a reversionary hoping for revival of the Muromachi bakufu system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>しかし、謙信の時代の関東や越後では畿内と違い関東管領職の権威はある程度通用したとの評もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, other people say that during the era of Kenshin, the authority of Kanto Kanrei was valid to some extent in the Kanto region and Echigo Province differently from in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during the era of Kenshin, the authority of Kanto Kanrei was valid to some extent in the Kanto region and Echigo Province and different in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during the era of Kenshin, the authority of Kanto Kanrei was valid to some extent in the Kanto region and Echigo Province and different in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>また、権威や管領職への敬意は、謙信の義理堅さをあらわしているとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, it can also be said that the respect for authority or for Kanryo shoku (a post of Chief Adviser) showed Kenshin&apos;s strong sense of duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, it can also be said that respect for authority or for Kanryo shoku (a post of Chief Adviser) showed Kenshin&apos;s strong sense of duty.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, it can also be said that respect for authority or for Kanryo shoku (a post of Chief Adviser) showed Kenshin&apos;s strong sense of duty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="230">
<j>一方で、大義名分を盾にし自己正当化をすることに拘り（合戦する際の理由で自身を正当化するのは秀吉や家康もしており当然ではあるが）、自身を毘沙門天の転生と信じるなど、天才特有の自己愛の強さの証左である、との評価も一部にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, there is also public estimation among some other people that it proves his strong narcissism peculiar to a genius to stick to justifying himself by applying a legitimate reason (it is natural to justify himself at the time of battle because Hideyoshi and Ieyasu also did the same thing) and to believe that he was a reincarnation of Bishamonten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On one hand, there is insistence that he had legitimate reason to protect his self justification (it is natural to justify himself at the time of battle because Hideyoshi and Ieyasu also did the same) on the other, he believed that he was a reincarnation of Bishamonten, there is evidence of his strength of specific narcissistic genius.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On one hand, there is insistence that he had legitimate reason to protect his self justification (it is natural to justify himself at the time of battle because Hideyoshi and Ieyasu also did the same) on the other, he believed that he was a reincarnation of Bishamonten, there is evidence of his strength of specific narcissistic genius.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>また、名門への羨望があったからこそ、山内上杉家を継いだとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, it can be said that Kenshin succeeded to the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family because of strong envy toward a family of pedigree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, it is said that Kenshin succeeded to the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family because he was envious of the family pedigree.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, it is said that Kenshin succeeded to the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family because he was envious of the family pedigree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>ただし、元来越後上杉家が守護を勤め、越後上杉被官家臣が数多くいた越後を統一するには、上杉家宗家である山内上杉家の家督は必要不可欠であったとする指摘もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is also pointed out that since the Echigo-Uesugi family originally assumed Shugo (provincial constable), the family headship of Yamanouchi-Uesugi family, Soke (head of family, originator) of Uesugi family, was essential to unify Echigo Province where many hikan (low-level bureaucrat) vassals of Echigo-Uesugi family existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was also pointed out that the Echigo-Uesugi family originally served as Shugo (provincial constable), the headship of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family, a Soke (head of family, originator) of the Uesugi family, was indispensable to unify Echigo Province where a large number of hikan (low-level bureaucrat) vassals of Echigo-Uesugi family existed.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was also pointed out that the Echigo-Uesugi family originally served as Shugo (provincial constable), the headship of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family, a Soke (head of family, originator) of the Uesugi family, was indispensable to unify Echigo Province where a large number of hikan (low-level bureaucrat) vassals of Echigo-Uesugi family existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="233">
<j>関東管領職という室町幕府の役職を全うし、多くの利益を期待できない関東出陣を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin fulfilled Kanto Kanrei, the post of Muromachi bakufu, and conducted the departure for the front in the Kanto region even though he could not anticipate large profits from such departure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin completed the Kanto Kanrei post of Muromachi bakufu, as he did not expect to benefit from large profits he departed for the front in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin completed the Kanto Kanrei post of Muromachi bakufu, as he did not expect to benefit from large profits he departed for the front in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>また、数々の戦いの多くが、村上義清、小笠原長時、上杉憲政らの旧領復権のための戦いであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin carried out many battles almost for the reinstatement of former territory of Yoshikiyo MURAKAMI, Nagatoki OGASAWARA, Norimasa UESUGI and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin carried out many battles to reinstate the former territories of Yoshikiyo MURAKAMI, Nagatoki OGASAWARA, Norimasa UESUGI and so on.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin carried out many battles to reinstate the former territories of Yoshikiyo MURAKAMI, Nagatoki OGASAWARA, Norimasa UESUGI and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="235">
<j>生前に前もって後継者を決定しなかったとされ、謙信の死後、御館の乱勃発の引き金となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kenshin did not decide his successor beforehand in his days of nature, and this matter triggered an occurrence of Otate War after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kenshin did not appoint his successor before his death, this matter triggered an occurrence of the Otate War.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kenshin did not appoint his successor before his death, this matter triggered an occurrence of the Otate War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>これは上杉家にとって大きな痛手となり、景勝の代での衰退と没落の道を辿る元凶となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This War damaged the Uesugi family very badly, and became the most significant source of heading down the path of decline and fall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This War was a serious blow to the Uesugi family and became the most significant source of heading down the path to decline and ruin replacing the picturesque scenery.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This War was a serious blow to the Uesugi family and became the most significant source of heading down the path to decline and ruin replacing the picturesque scenery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>謙信時代に獲得した北国（加賀・能登・越中）の大部分は、後に柴田勝家によって奪われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most territories in northern provinces (Kaga Province, Noto Province and Ecchu Province) obtained in the era of Kenshin were seized by Katsuie SHIBATA thereafter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most territories in northern provinces (Kaga Province, Noto Province and Ecchu Province) acquired in the era of Kenshin were later seized by Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most territories in northern provinces (Kaga Province, Noto Province and Ecchu Province) acquired in the era of Kenshin were later seized by Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="238">
<j>謙信の義理堅さ、約束事に対する姿勢は大変有名で、北条氏康は彼について「信玄と信長は表裏常なく、頼むに足りぬ人物だ。謙信だけは請け合ったら骨になっても義理を通す人物だ。それ故、肌着を分けて若い大将の守り袋にさせたい」と発言している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin&apos;s strong sense of duty and attitude toward convention were very famous, and Ujimasa HOJO said about him as follows: &apos;Shingen and Nobunaga was always honest and reliable. Only Kenshin fulfills duties when he receives an offer even after he dies. Therefore, I want to make a guardian pouch for young Taisho (general) with part of his underwear.&apos;</e>
<cmt>後列の二つの文と併せて一つの文となるので、句読点に係らず、下の文を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin&apos;s strong sense of duty and attitude towards convention were very famous, and Ujimasa HOJO said about him as follows: &apos;Shingen and Nobunaga are always honest and reliable. Kenshin fulfilled duties when he was requested even after his death. Hence, he wished to make talisman for the protection of young Taisho (general) with part of his underclothes&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin&apos;s strong sense of duty and attitude towards convention were very famous, and Ujimasa HOJO said about him as follows: &apos;Shingen and Nobunaga are always honest and reliable. Kenshin fulfilled duties when he was requested even after his death. Hence, he wished to make talisman for the protection of young Taisho (general) with part of his underclothes&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>ちなみに謙信の関東出陣回数は17回であり、どれもことごとく徒労に終わるものだったが、これも謙信の義理堅さを証明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, 17 departures for the front in the Kanto region by Kenshin which were all vain efforts also prove his strong sense of duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, 17 departures for the front in the Kanto region by Kenshin were all vain efforts, which proved his strong sense of duty.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, 17 departures for the front in the Kanto region by Kenshin were all vain efforts, which proved his strong sense of duty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="240">
<j>また、武田信玄は死に臨んで跡継ぎの武田勝頼に「謙信は義理がたい武将なので、人に頼られれば決して見捨てる事はない。自分の死後は謙信を頼れ」と遺言したと甲陽軍鑑にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, &quot;Koyo Gunkan&quot; (record of the military exploits of the Takeda family, compiled by one of the Takeda vassals and completed in 1616 by Kagenori OBATA) had a description that Shingen TAKEDA said to his successor, Katsuyori TAKEDA, in his last moment, &apos;As he is a busho having a strong sense of duty, Kenshin will never abandon people if he is counted on. Trust Kenshin after I die.&apos;</e>
<cmt>後列の文と併せて一つの文となるので、句読点に係らず、後列の文を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Koyo Gunkan&quot; (record of the military exploits of the Takeda family, compiled by one of the Takeda&apos;s vassal and completed in 1616 by Kagenori OBATA) quotes Shingen TAKEDA to his successor, Katsuyori TAKEDA, in his last moment, &apos;Kenshin is a busho having a strong sense of duty, he will never abandon the people if he is counted on. Trust him after I die.&apos;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Koyo Gunkan&quot; (record of the military exploits of the Takeda family, compiled by one of the Takeda&apos;s vassal and completed in 1616 by Kagenori OBATA) quotes Shingen TAKEDA to his successor, Katsuyori TAKEDA, in his last moment, &apos;Kenshin is a busho having a strong sense of duty, he will never abandon the people if he is counted on. Trust him after I die.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>当時は仇敵の武田側からすらも謙信は頼まれれば断れない性格だと評されていたことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This description shows that Kenshin was reputed even by the Takeda clan, his enemy at that time, to have a character of never refusing anything when asked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takeda clan, his bitter enemy at the time, acknowledged that Kenshin was reputed to have a character of never refusing anything when requested.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takeda clan, his bitter enemy at the time, acknowledged that Kenshin was reputed to have a character of never refusing anything when requested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="242">
<j>藤木久志は著書である『雑兵たちの戦場』（朝日新聞社・1995年刊）で「上杉謙信は越後の民衆にとっては他国に戦争と言うベンチャービジネスを企画実行した救い主であるが、襲われた関東など戦場の村々は略奪を受け地獄を見た」と、通常言われる義人・上杉謙信像とは別の上杉軍の姿こそが実態であったとし、このセンセーショナルな「出稼ぎ」説は多くの識者から支持を得て広く世間に浸透した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a book named &apos;Battle fields of zohyo&apos; (common soldiers) (published by The Asahi Shimbun Company in 1995) and written by Hisashi FUJIKI, he presented a theory that a true picture was an image of Uesugi army different from the image of Kenshin UESUGI who was usually reputed as a loyal person based on a phrase that &apos;although Kenshin was a savior for people in Echigo Province because he planned and implemented venture business called war in other provinces, villages in the Kanto region which became battlefields suffered looting and were in the hellish situation,&apos; and this sensational theory of &apos;battling away from home&apos; was supported by many experts and widely penetrated among the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a book named &apos;Battle fields of zohyo&apos; (common soldiers) (published by The Asahi Shimbun Company in 1995) written by Hisashi FUJIKI, he presented a theory that the image of the Uesugi army was different from the real Kenshin UESUGI who was usually reputed as a loyal person based on a phrase that &apos;Kenshin was a savior of the people in Echigo Province because he planned and implemented venture business called war in other provinces, stricken villages in the Kanto region, which were battlefields, suffered looting and he had seen hell,&apos; this sensational theory of &apos;working away from home&apos; was supported by many experts and widely spread among the public.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a book named &apos;Battle fields of zohyo&apos; (common soldiers) (published by The Asahi Shimbun Company in 1995) written by Hisashi FUJIKI, he presented a theory that the image of the Uesugi army was different from the real Kenshin UESUGI who was usually reputed as a loyal person based on a phrase that &apos;Kenshin was a savior of the people in Echigo Province because he planned and implemented venture business called war in other provinces, stricken villages in the Kanto region, which were battlefields, suffered looting and he had seen hell,&apos; this sensational theory of &apos;working away from home&apos; was supported by many experts and widely spread among the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>しかし、市村高男は『東国の戦国合戦』（吉川弘文館・2009年刊）で「合戦の主体となる正規の軍隊はどのようにして軍資金等を確保することができたのか」、「敵地には略奪するほどの諸物資が存在したのであろうか」、「社会状況の具体的な提示があるものの、戦闘に至る直接の契機についてはもとより、それらの社会状況と合戦を開始する権力側のいきさつがどのように関連していたのか」など、数々の疑問を呈しており、今後の議論が待たれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Takao ICHIMURA raised many questions in his book, &quot;Togoku no Sengoku Kassen&quot; (Battles in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) during the Sengoku period) (published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc. in 2009), like &apos;how the official army forming the main body in the battle could secure war funds and so on,&apos; &apos;whether the enemy territory had various kinds of goods to be looted,&apos; &apos;although the social condition was presented concretely, it is wonder how a situation of the authority side starting the battle as well as a direct opportunity leading to the battle was related to such social conditions,&apos; and so on, and future discussions are expected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Takao ICHIMURA raised many questions in his book, &quot;Togoku no Sengoku Kassen&quot; (Battles in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) during the Sengoku period) (published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc. in 2009), like &apos;how the official army forming the main constituent in battle secured war funds and so on,&apos; &apos;whether the enemy territory was plundered and various kinds of goods looted,&apos; &apos;although the social condition was presented concretely, it is wonder how a situation of the authority side starting the battle as well as a direct opportunity leading to the battle was related to such social conditions,&apos; and so on, and future discussions are expected.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Takao ICHIMURA raised many questions in his book, &quot;Togoku no Sengoku Kassen&quot; (Battles in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) during the Sengoku period) (published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc. in 2009), like &apos;how the official army forming the main constituent in battle secured war funds and so on,&apos; &apos;whether the enemy territory was plundered and various kinds of goods looted,&apos; &apos;although the social condition was presented concretely, it is wonder how a situation of the authority side starting the battle as well as a direct opportunity leading to the battle was related to such social conditions,&apos; and so on, and future discussions are expected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>墓所・霊廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graveyard and mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graveyard and mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graveyard and mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="244">
<j>謙信の遺骸は甲冑を着せて甕に納め、葬られたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Kenshin&apos;s body was dressed in Kacchu (armor), put in an earthenware pot, and buried.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin&apos;s body was dressed in a Kacchu (armor), placed in an earthenware pot and buried.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin&apos;s body was dressed in a Kacchu (armor), placed in an earthenware pot and buried.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="245">
<j>遺骸は当初春日山城下の林泉寺 (上越市)に埋葬されたが、長尾上杉家の転封に伴って、会津若松城、ついで米沢城内に改葬されたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was firstly buried at Rinsen-ji Temple (Joetsu City) in a castle town of Kasugayama-jo Castle, the body was reburied in Aizu Wakamatsu-jo Castle and then in Yonezawa-jo Castle along with changing the territory of Nagao-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kenshin was first buried at Rinsen-ji Temple (Joetsu City) in a castle town of Kasugayama-jo Castle, the body was reburied in Aizu Wakamatsu-jo Castle as the Nagao-Uesugi family moved territories and then in Yonezawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kenshin was first buried at Rinsen-ji Temple (Joetsu City) in a castle town of Kasugayama-jo Castle, the body was reburied in Aizu Wakamatsu-jo Castle as the Nagao-Uesugi family moved territories and then in Yonezawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="246">
<j>明治維新後は米沢藩の歴代藩主が眠る上杉家廟所（山形県米沢市）に再度、改葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the body was reburied again in the mausoleum of Uesugi family (Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture) where successive lords of Yonezawa Domain were laid to rest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the body was reburied in the mausoleum of the Uesugi family (Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture) where successive lords of Yonezawa Domain were laid to rest.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the body was reburied in the mausoleum of the Uesugi family (Yonezawa City, Yamagata Prefecture) where successive lords of Yonezawa Domain were laid to rest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>春日山林泉寺 (上越市)（新潟県上越市）と高野山と栃尾市美術館の前庭（新潟県栃尾市）にも墓が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave remains not only in Rinsen-ji Temple of Mt. Kasuga (Joetsu City) (Joetsu City, Niigata Prefecture) but also in Mt. Koya and a front yard of Tochio City Art Museum (Tochio City, Niigata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>栃尾市美術館→Tochio City Art Museum[仮訳です。栃尾市美術館を検索したところ、長岡市所在とありましたが、本文の記述に従い、栃尾市としました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave remains not only in Rinsen-ji Temple of Mt. Kasuga (Joetsu City) (Joetsu City, Niigata Prefecture) but also in Mt. Koya and in the front yard of Tochio City Art Museum (Tochio City, Niigata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave remains not only in Rinsen-ji Temple of Mt. Kasuga (Joetsu City) (Joetsu City, Niigata Prefecture) but also in Mt. Koya and in the front yard of Tochio City Art Museum (Tochio City, Niigata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="248">
<j>江戸時代の米沢藩では謙信は藩祖として崇敬を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin was revered as the original forefather of the domain by the Yonezawa Clan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin was revered as the original forefather of the domain by the Yonezawa Clan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin was revered as the original forefather of the domain by the Yonezawa Clan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>明治5年（1872年）に米沢城本丸跡に創建された上杉神社（別格官幣社）に上杉鷹山と共に祀られ、明治35年に別格官幣社に昇格し、神体は謙信一柱となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1872, Kenshin was enshrined with Yozan UESUGI in Uesugi-jinja Shrine (Bekkaku Kanpeisha (a special government shrine)) which was founded at remains of Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of Yonezawa-jo Castle, and after Uesugi -jinja Shrine was promoted to Bekkaku-Kanpeisha in 1902, only Kenshin came to be enshrined there as shintai (sacred object).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1872, Kenshin was enshrined with Yozan UESUGI in Uesugi-jinja Shrine (Bekkaku Kanpeisha (a special government shrine)) which was founded on the remains of Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of Yonezawa-jo Castle, and after Uesugi -jinja Shrine was promoted to Bekkaku-Kanpeisha in 1902, only Kenshin came was enshrined there as shintai (sacred object).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1872, Kenshin was enshrined with Yozan UESUGI in Uesugi-jinja Shrine (Bekkaku Kanpeisha (a special government shrine)) which was founded on the remains of Honmaru (the keep of a castle) of Yonezawa-jo Castle, and after Uesugi -jinja Shrine was promoted to Bekkaku-Kanpeisha in 1902, only Kenshin came was enshrined there as shintai (sacred object).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>明治41年（1908年）9月9日、従二位が贈られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 9, 1908, he was awarded the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 9, 1908, he was awarded the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 9, 1908, he was awarded the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>（なお上杉鷹山は、松岬神社にて上杉景勝、直江兼続らと共に祀られるようになった。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In addition, Yozan UESUGI came to be enshrined with Kagekatsu UESUGI, Kanetsugu NAOE and others in Matsugasaki-jinja Shrine.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In addition, Yozan UESUGI came to be enshrined with Kagekatsu UESUGI, Kanetsugu NAOE and others in Matsugasaki-jinja Shrine.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In addition, Yozan UESUGI came to be enshrined with Kagekatsu UESUGI, Kanetsugu NAOE and others in Matsugasaki-jinja Shrine.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 浄三入道(id:170774), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), Cprobot(id:97843), Tast(id:29478), Lupinoid(id:68), Kamakura(id:472), ブレイズマン(id:183852), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), ヘキサ(id:106141), MioUzaki(id:89034), Dsimic(id:178324), A-Taul(id:41790), 俊(id:14924), 秀の介(id:490), 海獺(id:153448), Shimoxx(id:9332), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Maakun(id:16735), FlaBot(id:30804), Kouko0515(id:100370), シェーラ(id:17988), Thomo(id:169717), SINOBU(id:28887), Rogn(id:240310), Azirosas(id:143367), 松茸(id:27535), Seibuabina(id:37532), 立つのかよ(id:111350), 秋田城之介(id:95273), Kagetudo(id:163875), MDR-SK(id:192066), Hamichan(id:4829), Rusk(id:9895), TakuyaMurata(id:156), R28Bot(id:177951), 海衛士(id:19229), Arutoki(id:132405), Junger(id:10282), 人造人間だみゃ～ん(id:119413), JOQR(id:150111), Suisui(id:69), Mameneko(id:785), ギリトバット(id:229476), ドルチェット(id:46458), Harupri(id:133581), Ash Crow(id:26765), マリアヤ(id:245178), Sgi1962(id:80778), HqB774PW0(id:311341), 錬金初級(id:214460), ズダンマグナム(id:182031), ジール(id:222755), ひろっきー(id:87284), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Kone(id:377), Arawodas(id:213174), Volfgang(id:98768), KASAGI(id:24405), Bankokuya(id:91191), ゲッターピジョン(id:84950), Kentin(id:6768), 石川入婿(id:106304), ミッドランドライダー(id:40104), 水野白楓(id:22811), Kalz(id:92749), Agira(id:109845), Yanahan(id:2437), APOINT(id:224219), サテツ(id:4106), Aboshi(id:9318), Kamitani(id:30757), Newport8865(id:71168), Geogie(id:143809), Ash(id:15625), Nalc(id:139567), Chikara1983(id:59556), こいつぅ(id:2105), Shuto1415(id:63738), SieBot(id:126695), Los688(id:12316), 松本ゆきお(仮)(id:117128), 三角箱(id:295696), Yasumi(id:44933), 出羽卒族(id:283926), Eskimbot(id:29676), Nikm(id:245385), MT.Stone(id:2812), 直正(id:13317), ぷらら(id:115742), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), グリング(id:224998), Ks aka 98(id:35909), Tamago915(id:11009), Sabkakusikaku(id:277058), Rokurokusanjin(id:285204), Kzhr(id:131), 谷英樹(id:173520), 常陸介(id:176100), M-sho-gun(id:88956), MystBot(id:224584), 浩(id:70121), Stanislaus(id:1806), Ilfc(id:68743), Euphrates(id:38277), Shinyafortune(id:42940), Cinnamon(id:11208), Williams(id:116236), 東犀川三四郎(id:285590), 219市115丁223番151号(id:15789), R463(id:150079), 小者(id:172526), 彩華1226(id:64711), Morguryk(id:98507), ぷらんたん(id:58446), 上(id:14148), KSKS(id:97637), Muro Bot(id:217619), Wrightbus(id:13796), Monboco(id:223218), Dojo(id:32472), MD242(id:11277), Snow rabbit(id:95634), Resto1578(id:168692), 蘭綾王(id:189560), 花蝶風月雪月花警部(id:163674), Reggaeman(id:6214), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), ジャンショーグン(id:57919), ふんかさい(id:62417), Ziel(id:143645), Wikied(id:194340), 味っ子(id:17086), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Sillago(id:187189), 背筋(id:238135), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Bandalgom(id:31841), Jinnsg(id:43599), 怪蘇(id:45514), Rei-bot(id:94097), 梅澤 威志(id:17353), Funhouse(id:169027), 越中掾(id:149423), ネッツのネット(id:224875), Piasu9(id:134995), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), やりたこ(id:113528), Etopirica(id:32491), 学問好き(id:309655), Hat2867(id:67840), Sat.K(id:3751), 廿粁(id:219234), KENPEI(id:11349), Majimegao(id:149982), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), ゐ(id:795), Fromm(id:71291), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Nonnonba(id:124424), Kenshinw(id:194278), Safkan(id:423), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Saaki(id:43602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>