<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>橘元任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Mototo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Mototo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Mototo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>橘元任（たちばな の もととう、生没年不詳）は、平安時代中期の官人・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Mototo (date of birth and death unknown) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) and a kajin (a waka poet) who lived in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Mototo (date of birth and death unknown) was a government official (one of low to medium rank) and a kajin (waka poet) who lived in the mid Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Abbreviation avoided, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Mototo (year of birth and death unknown) was a government official (one of low to medium rank) and a kajin (waka poet) who lived in the mid Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>date→year</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は橘永愷（能因）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was TACHIBANA no Nagayasu (Noin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was TACHIBANA no Nagayasu (Noin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was TACHIBANA no Nagayasu (Noin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>橘基家・橘忠元・橘良元の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the father of TACHIBANA no Motoie, TACHIBANA no Tadamoto and TACHIBANA no Yoshimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of TACHIBANA no Motoie, TACHIBANA no Tadamoto and TACHIBANA no Yoshimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of TACHIBANA no Motoie, TACHIBANA no Tadamoto and TACHIBANA no Yoshimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大学寮を経て、散位従五位下だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served for Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) and was in Sani Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade courtier without post).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served the Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) and was a Sani Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade courtier without post).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served the Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system) and was a Sani Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade courtier without post).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『勅撰作者部類』には内記とあり、永承元年（1046年）叙爵と記載される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Chokusen Sakusha Burui&quot; (a list of the anthologists who compiled the Imperial collections of waka poems), it was recorded that he worked for naiki (secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs) and was conferred a peerage in 1046.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Chokusen Sakusha Burui&quot; (the list of the anthologists who compiled the Imperial collections of waka poems), it was recorded that he worked for naiki (secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs) and had a peerage conferred on him in 1046.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Chokusen Sakusha Burui&quot; (the list of the anthologists who compiled the Imperial collections of waka poems), it was recorded that he worked for naiki (secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs) and had a peerage conferred on him in 1046.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『後拾遺和歌集』に2首（歌番号83・244）、『金葉和歌集』に2首（歌番号170・664）、『詞花和歌集』に1首（歌番号82）それぞれ入集。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His two waka (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) were selected for &quot;GoShui Wakashu&quot; (Later gleanings of Japanese poems)(No.83.244), other two waka were selected for &quot;Kinyo Wakashu&quot; (Kinyo Collection of Japanese poems), and other one waka was selected for &quot;Shika Wakashu&quot; (shika collection of Japanese poems)(No.82).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two of his waka (traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) were selected for &quot;GoShui Wakashu&quot; (Later Gleanings of Japanese Poems)(No.83.244), another two waka were selected for &quot;Kinyo Wakashu&quot; (Kinyo Collection of Japanese poems), and further one waka was selected for &quot;Shika Wakashu&quot; (Shika Collection of Japanese Poems)(No.82).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two of his waka (traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) were selected for &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; (Later Gleanings of Japanese Poems)(No.83.244), another two waka were selected for &quot;Kinyo Wakashu&quot; (Kinyo Collection of Japanese poems)(No.170.664), and further one waka was selected for &quot;Shika Wakashu&quot; (Shika Collection of Japanese Poems)(No.82).</e>
<cmt>GoShui→Goshui「（歌番号170・664）」訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>