<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原基経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mototsune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Mototsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mototsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 基経（ふじわらの もとつね、承和 (日本)3年（836年）－寛平3年1月13日 (旧暦)（891年2月24日））は、平安時代前期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mototsune (born in 836 (third year of the Jowa era) and died on January 13, 891 (lunar calendar) (Feburary 24, 891)) was a court noble in the early Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Mototsune (born in 836 (third year of the Jowa era) and died on January 13, 891 (lunar calendar) (Feburary 24, 891)) was a court noble in the early Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mototsune (born in 836 and died on February 28 in 891) was a court noble in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。スペルを訂正。ピリオドを追加February 24→February 28に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家藤原長良の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Third son of FUJIWARA no Nagara of the Fujiwara Hokke (Northern Branch of the Fujiwara clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Nagara of the Northern Branch of the Fujiwara clan (Fujiwara Hokke).</e>
<cmt>grammar, terms</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Nagara of the Northern Branch of the Fujiwara clan (Fujiwara Hokke).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は藤原総継の娘の藤原乙春。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Fusatsugu&apos;s daughter FUJIWARA no Otoharu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was FUJIWARA no Fusatsugu&apos;s daughter FUJIWARA no Otoharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was FUJIWARA no Fusatsugu&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Otoharu.</e>
<cmt>コンマを挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>養父は藤原良房。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His foster parent was FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His foster parent was FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His foster father was FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa.</e>
<cmt>｢養父」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>子に藤原時平、藤原忠平など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were FUJIWARA no Tokihira, FUJIWARA no Tadahira, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children include FUJIWARA no Tokihira, and FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children include FUJIWARA no Tokihira and FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>コンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幼名は手古。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Teko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Teko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Teko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>堀川大臣と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Horikawa no Otodo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Horikawa no Otodo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Horikawa no Otodo.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>摂政であった叔父・良房の養子となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His became the foster child of his uncle Yoshifusa, who was the regent (sesshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His became the foster child of his uncle Yoshifusa, who was the regent (sesshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His became the foster child of his uncle Yoshifusa, who was the Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>｢摂政」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>養父の死後、引き続き朝廷の実権を握る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of his foster father, he continued to wield the real power at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Yoshifusa, he succeeded him in wielding the real power at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Yoshifusa, he succeeded him in wielding the real power at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>陽成天皇を暴虐であるとして廃し、光孝天皇を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accused Emperor Yozei of being tyrannic, disposed him and crowned Emperor Koko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accused Emperor Yozei of being tyrannic, disposed him, and installed Emperor Koko in his place.</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accused Emperor Yozei of being tyrannic, disposed him, and installed Emperor Koko in his place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>次の宇多天皇のとき阿衡事件を起こして、権勢を世に知らしめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the next Emperor Uta, he caused the Ako Incident, and showed his power to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of the next emperor, Emperor Uda, he caused the Ako Incident, making a public display of his power.</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear due to lack of detail</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of the next emperor, Emperor Uda, he caused the Ako Incident, making a public display of his power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天皇から大政を委ねられ、日本史上初の関白に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor left the country&apos;s rule to him, and he became the first Kampaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor entrusted the governance of the country to him, and he became the first Kampaku (chief advisor to the Emperor) in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor entrusted the governance of the country to him, and he became the first Kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the Emperor) in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>｢関白」の表記を修正。小文字を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>用語リストにしたがって修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>時の権力者であった叔父の藤原良房に嫡子がいなかったことから、その養嗣子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his uncle FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa who was the power that be did not have his own son, he became Yoshifusa&apos;s adoptive heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because his uncle, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, who occupied a powerful position in the government,had no sons of his own son, Mototsune became Yoshifusa&apos;s adoptive heir.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because his uncle, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, who occupied a powerful position in the government, had no sons of his own, Mototsune became Yoshifusa&apos;s adoptive heir.</e>
<cmt>スペースを挿入。「嫡子がいなかった」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>仁寿元年（852年）東宮殿で元服した際に、文徳天皇が自ら加冠するほどの厚遇を受け、正六位上に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the first year of the Ninju era (852) when he underwent the cermony of attaining manhood at Togun-den, he treated very kindly, as the Emperor Montoku himself crowned him and he was also promoted to the court rank of Shorokui-jo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the first year of the Ninju era (852), when he underwent the cermony of attaining manhood at Togun-den, he was treated very kindly, as the Emperor Montoku himself had placed the court headgear on mototsune&apos;s head, and he was also promoted to the court rank of Shorokui-jo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 851, when he underwent the ceremony of attaining manhood at Togun-den, he was treated very kindly, as the Emperor Montoku himself had placed the court headgear on Mototsune&apos;s head, and he was also promoted to the court rank of Shorokuijo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。ハイフンを削除。名前の小文字を大文字に。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>斉衡年間（854年 - 857年）から天安 (日本)年間（857年 - 859年）に左兵衛尉、少納言、左近衛少将を経て蔵人頭に補せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Saiko era (854-857) and the Tenan era (857-859) he was Sahyoe no jo, Shonagon and Sakone no shosho and then became Kurodo no To.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Saiko era (854-857) and the Tenan era (857-859), he held the positions of Sahyoe no jo, Shonagon, and Sakone no shosho, eventually becoming Kurodo no To.</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During 854-857 and 857-859, he held the positions of Sahyoe no jo (third-ranked officer of Sahyoe-fu, the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards), Shonagon (Lesser counselor), and Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), eventually becoming Kurodo no To (Head Chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。スペースを削除。「左兵衛尉、少納言、左近衛少将、蔵人頭」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>貞観 (日本)年間（859年 - 877年）に左近衛中将に転じて、参議に任ぜられて公卿に列する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Jogan era he became Sakono-e-chujo, (&quot;General of the Left&quot;) was named councillor (sangi) and became a court noble (Kuge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Jogan era he became Sakono-e-chujo, (&quot;General of the Left&quot;), was named a councillor (sangi), and became a member of the nobility (Kuge).</e>
<cmt>grammar, terms</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 859-877, he became Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards), was named Sangi (councilor), and became a member of Kugyo (the top court officials).</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。クォーテーションマークを削除。「左近衛中将」「参議」「公卿」を修正。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>貞観8年（866年）、応天門の炎上の際し大納言伴善男が左大臣源信 (公卿)を誣告し、右大臣藤原良相が左近衛中将であった基経に逮捕を命じるも、基経はこれを怪しみ養父の良房に告げ、良房の尽力によって、源信は無実となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the eigth year of the Jogan era (866) at the time of the fire at the Otenmon Gate, the chief councillor of state TOMO no Yoshio falsely accused the Minister of the Left (official in Nara and Heian periods) MINAMOTO no Makoto (a court noble), and the Minister of the Right FUJIWARA no Yoshimi ordered Mototsune, who was General of the Left at the time, to arrest MINAMOTO no Makoto, but Mototsune was suspicious and notified his foster father Yoshifusa, whose efforts helped to prove MINAMOTO no Makoto&apos;s innocence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the eigth year of the Jogan era (866), at the time of the fire at the Otenmon Gate, TOMO no Yoshio, the chief councillor of state falsely accused MINAMOTO no Makoto, a member of the nobility who held the position of Minister of the Left (an official post that existed during the Nara and Heian periods), whereupon FUJIWARA no Yoshimi, who held the position of Minister of the Right ordered Mototsune, who was General of the Left at the time, to arrest MINAMOTO no Makoto; however, Mototsune was suspicious of the charges, and notified his foster father Yoshifusa, whose efforts helped to prove MINAMOTO no Makoto&apos;s innocence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 866, at the time of the fire at the Otenmon Gate, TOMO no Yoshio, Dainagon (chief councilor of state) falsely accused MINAMOTO no Makoto (Kugyo) who held the position of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left), whereupon FUJIWARA no Yoshimi, who held the position of Udaijin (Minister of the Right) ordered Mototsune, who was Sakone no chujo, to arrest MINAMOTO no Makoto; however, Mototsune was suspicious of the charges, and notified his foster father Yoshifusa, whose efforts helped to prove MINAMOTO no Makoto&apos;s innocence.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。「大納言」「公卿」｢左大臣」｢右大臣」を修正。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、密告があり、伴善男が真犯人とされ、流罪となり、連座した大伴氏、紀氏が大量に処罰され、これら上古からの名族へ大打撃を与えた（応天門の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards there was an anonymous tip and TOMO no Yoshio was called the true culprit and deported, while members of the Otomo and Ki clans, which had also been implicated in the crime, were punished in great numbers, which was big blow for these ancient great clans (Otenmon no hen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, there was an anonymous tip that led to the discover that TOMO no Yoshio was the true culprit, whereupon he was banished, while members of the Otomo and Ki clans, which had also been implicated in the crime, were punished in great numbers, which was big blow for these ancient great clans (see the account in the &quot;Otenmon no hen&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, there was an anonymous tip that led to the discover that TOMO no Yoshio was the true culprit, whereupon he was banished, while members of the Otomo and Ki clans, which had also been implicated in the crime, were punished in great numbers, which was big blow for these ancient great clans (Otenmon Incident).</e>
<cmt>「（応天門の変）」の意味を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>同年、従三位に叙し、中納言を拝す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year he became Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Chunagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year he was promoted to the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), and appointed to the post of Chunagon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he was promoted to the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and appointed to the post of Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動。「中納言」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>その後、左近衛中将を兼ね、更に左近衛大将へ進み、陸奥国出羽国按察使を兼ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also assumed the post of Sakone no chujo and later was promoted even higher to the postof Sakone no daisho (Great General of the Left) and at the same time was the Azechi (Inspector) for Mutsu and Dewa Provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently he also assumed the post of Sakone no chujo, and was promoted to the even higher post of Sakone no daisho (Great General of the Left), while at the same time holding the post of Azechi (Inspector) for Mutsu and Dewa Provinces.</e>
<cmt>gammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, he also assumed the post of Sakone no chujo and was promoted to the even higher post of Sakone no daisho (Great General of the Left), while at the same time holding the post of Azechi (Inspector) for Mutsu and Dewa Provinces.</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>貞観12年（870年）大納言に転じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the twelfth year of the Jogan era he became Dainagon (Chief councillor state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to the post of Dainagon (Chief councillor state) in the twelfth year of the Jogan era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to the post of Dainagon in 870.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。｢大納言」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>貞観14年（872年）右大臣を拝する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the fourteenth year of the Jogan era he was named Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was named Minister of the Right in the fourteenth year of the Jogan era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was named Udaijin in 872.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。｢右大臣」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>同年、摂政だった養父良房が死去、代わって朝廷において実権を握った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year his foster father Yoshihisa died and he assumed real power at the Imperal court instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, his foster father, Yoshihisa, died, and Mototsune succeeded him in wielding real power at the Imperal court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, his foster father, Yoshihisa, died and Mototsune succeeded him in wielding real power at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>コンマを削除。court を大文字に。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>基経の実妹の藤原高子は清和天皇の女御で、第一皇子陽成天皇を生んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsune&apos;s sister FUJIWARA no Takaiko was a court lady of Emperor Seiwa and gave birth to the Emperor&apos;s first child, the later Emperor Yozei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsune&apos;s sister, FUJIWARA no Takaiko, was a court lady of Emperor Seiwa, and gave birth to the Emperor&apos;s first child, who later became Emperor Yozei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsune&apos;s sister, FUJIWARA no Takaiko was a court lady of Emperor Seiwa and gave birth to the Emperor&apos;s first child, who later became Emperor Yozei.</e>
<cmt>コンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>翌年、従二位に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year he was named Junii, (Junior Second Rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year he was promoted to the court rank of Junii, (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, he was promoted to the court rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>コンマを移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>貞観18年（876年）清和天皇は貞明親王に譲位（陽成天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the eigthteenth year of the Jogan era (876), the Emperor Seiwa renounced his title to Imperial Prince Sadaakira (Emperor Yozei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the eigthteenth year of the Jogan era (876), the Emperor Seiwa abdicated, passing his title to Imperial Prince Sadaakira (Emperor Yozei).</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 876, the Emperor Seiwa abdicated, passing his title to Imperial Prince Sadaakira (Emperor Yozei).</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>まだ9歳と幼少であったため、良房の先例に従い基経は摂政に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Emperor was only 9 years old, Mototsune was named Sesshu (regent), following the precedent set by Yoshifusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Emperor was only 9 years old at the time, Mototsune was named Sesshu (regent), following the precedent set by Yoshifusa.</e>
<cmt>grammarr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Emperor was only 9 years old at the time, Mototsune was named Sessho (regent), following the precedent set by Yoshifusa.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>元慶2年（878年）、出羽国で蝦夷の俘囚が反乱を起こしたため、能吏で知られた藤原保則、小野春風らを起用し、翌年までにこれを鎮撫せしめた（元慶の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the second year of the Gangyo era (878), Yezo (northern part of Meiji-era Japan, esp. Hokkaido, but also Sakhalin and the Kuril Islands) Fushu prisoners caused a revolt in Dewa province, andthe likes of FUJIWARA no Yasunori, ONO no Harukaze, who were known as able officials were applied to the task, and the next year succeeded in putting down the revolt (known as &quot;Gangyo no ran&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the second year of the Gangyo era (878), Yezo (northern part of Meiji-era Japan, primarily consisting of Hokkaido, but also Sakhalin and the Kuril Islands) Fushu prisoners caused a revolt in Dewa province, andofficials such as FUJIWARA no Yasunori, ONO no Harukaze, who were known for their resourcefullness, were assigned the task of restoring the peace; by the following year they had succeeded in putting down the revolt (known as &quot;Gangyo no ran&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 878, Ezo (northern part of Japan) Fushu prisoners caused a revolt in Dewa Province, andofficials such as FUJIWARA no Yasunori, ONO no Harukaze, who were known for their resourcefulness, were assigned the task of restoring the peace; by the following year they had succeeded in putting down the revolt (Gangyo War).</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。｢蝦夷」の表記、説明を修正。地名の表記を大文字に統一。「（元慶の乱）」の表記を修正。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>元慶3年（879年）、菅原是善らと編纂した日本文徳天皇実録全10巻を完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the third year of the Gankyo era (879) he completed together with SUGAWARA no Koreyoshithe Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku (the fifth of the six classical Japanese history texts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the third year of the Gankyo era (879), along with with SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi and others, he completed work on the ten volume Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku (the fifth of the six classical Japanese history texts).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 879, along with SUGAWARA no Koreyoshi and others, he completed work on the ten volume Nihon Montoku Tenno Jitsuroku (the fifth national history, covering years 850-858 (reign of Montoku)).</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。「日本文徳天皇実録」の説明を修正。with を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>元慶4年（880年）太政大臣を拝す（同年、摂政を改めて関白となると『公卿補任』などにあるが、正史の『日本三代実録』にはなく、江戸時代に編纂された『大日本史』などでは、この時の関白宣下を採っていない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the fourth year of the Gankyo era (880) he was named Grand Minister, Chancellor of the Realm (Daijo daikan) (In the &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot; and other sources it is written that his title of Sesshu was renewed and he that he became Kampaku, but nothing thereof is mentioned in the official history &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts)&quot; and in the &quot;Dainihon-shi&quot; compiled in the Edo period there the imperial proclamation as Kampaku at that time is not recorded).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was named Grand Minister, Chancellor of the Realm (Daijo daikan) in the fourth year of the Gankyo era (880), (The accounts provided in the &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot; and other sources maintain that his title of Sesshu was renewed, and that he became Kampaku, however, those occurrences are not collaborated by the official history the &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts), and the &quot;Dainihon-shi&quot;, which was compiled in the Edo period, contains no record of an Imperial proclamation appointing him as Kampaku at that time).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was named Daijo daikan (Grand minister of state) in 880, (The accounts provided in the &quot;Kugyo bunin&quot; (directory of court nobles) and other sources maintain that his title of Sessho was renewed, and that he became Kanpaku, however, those occurrences are not collaborated by the official history the &quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts), and the &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great history of Japan), which was compiled in the Edo period, contains no record of an Imperial proclamation appointing him as Kanpaku at that time).</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。「太政大臣」の説明を修正。「関白」の表記を修正。クォーテーションマークを統一。『公卿補任』、『大日本史』の説明を追加。スペースを削除。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>翌年、従一位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year he became Juichii, (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, he was promoted to the court rank of Juichii, (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, he was promoted to the court rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>コンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>元慶6年（882年）、陽成天皇が元服するが、この頃から関係が険悪になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the sixth year of the Gankyo era (882) Emperor Yozei attained his adulthood, and from that time on their relationship worsened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the sixth year of the Gankyo era (882), Emperor Yozei reached adulthood, and from that time onward their relationship worsened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 882, Emperor Yozei reached adulthood and from that time onward their relationship worsened.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。コンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>基経は辞職を申し出るが、許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsune offered his resignation but was not accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsune offered his resignation, but it was not accepted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsune offered his resignation, but it was not accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これはこの時代の記録によく見られる儀礼的な辞退ではなく、政治的な意味があったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that this was not the kind of ceremonial resignation that can be seen often in the records of this period, but that it had a political meaning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that this was not the usual type of ceremonial resignation that is often recounted in the records for this period, but that it was a gesture having a political meaning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that this was not the usual type of ceremonial resignation that is often recounted in the records for this period, but that it was a gesture having a political meaning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その後、基経は出仕をボイコットする挙に出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Mototsune started to boycott attendance at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After submitting his resignation, Mototsune ceased to attend the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After submitting his resignation, Mototsune ceased to attend the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="36">
<j>元慶7年（883年）11月、宮中で乳母紀全子の子・源益が殺される事件が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the seventh year of the Gankyo era (883) an incident occurred where the child of the wet mother KI no Matako (KI no Zenshi), MINAMOTO no Masaru was killed at the court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the seventh year of the Gankyo era (883), an incident occurred in which the child of the wet nurse KI no Matako (KI no Zenshi), MINAMOTO no Masaru, was killed on the premises of the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Devember 883, an incident occurred in which the child of the wet nurse KI no Matako (KI no Zenshi), MINAMOTO no Masaru, was killed on the premises of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。court を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>それが本当に殺人事件なのか、あるいは過失致死といった類の事故なのかは明らかではなく、また犯人も不明とされたが、宮中では陽成天皇が殴り殺したのだと噂された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown, whether this was really murder or an accidental death and the murderer was said to be unknown, but at court there were rumors that the Emperor Yozei had beaten him to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unknown, whether this was actually a murder or an accidental death. and the murderer was also said to be unknown, but at court there were rumors that the Emperor Yozei had beaten him to death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unknown, whether this was actually a murder or an accidental death, and the murderer was also said to be unknown, but at Court there were rumors that the Emperor Yozei had beaten him to death.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを修正。court を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="38">
<j>この事件の直後、馬好きの陽成天皇が厩を禁中につくり、卑位の者に世話をさせ、飼っていた事実が明らかになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident the fact became known that the Emperor Yozei, who was very fond of horses, built a stable in his own palace (Kinchu), and let low-ranking folk tend for the horses he kept there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after the occurrence of that incident, the fact that the Emperor Yozei, who was very fond of horses, had built a stable in his own palace (Kinchu), and was having low-ranking folk tend to the horses he kept there came to light.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after the occurrence of that incident, the fact that the Emperor Yozei, who was very fond of horses, had built a stable in his own palace (Kinchu), and was having low-ranking folk tend to the horses he kept there came to light.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>基経は宮中に入り、天皇の取り巻きと馬を駆逐させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsune went to Court and had the Emperor&apos;s followers and the horses of the Emperor removed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsune went to Court, and had the Emperor&apos;s followers and the horses of the Emperor removed.</e>
<cmt>inconsitent capitalization of &quot;court&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsune went to Court, and had the Emperor&apos;s followers and the horses of the Emperor removed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>陽成天皇は後の記録には暴君として描かれており、それによると天皇は蛙を捕え、蛇を捕え、または犬と猿を闘わせて喜び、人を木に登らせて墜落死させたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor has been described as a tyrant in later records and it is said that he enjoyed catching frogs and snakes, and having dogs and monkeys fight with each other, and that he ordered people to climb trees and let them fall to their deaths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Yozei is described as a tyrant in later records, which recount that he was said to have enjoyed catching frogs and snakes, having dogs and monkeys fight with each other, and ordering people to climb trees so he could watch them fall to their deaths.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Yozei is described as a tyrant in later records, which recount that he was said to have enjoyed catching frogs and snakes, having dogs and monkeys fight with each other, and ordering people to climb trees so he could watch them fall to their deaths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="41">
<j>元慶8年（884年）、基経は天皇の廃立を考え、仁明天皇のときに廃太子された恒貞親王に打診したが、既に出家していた親王から拒否された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the eigth year of the Gankyo era (884), Mototsune was thinking about toppling the Emperor and asked Imperial Prince Tsunesada, who had been made Haitaishi (defunct Prince) at the time of Emperor Nimmyo, but the Imperial prince had already become a monk and refused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the eigth year of the Gankyo era (884), Mototsune was trying to find a way to remove the Emperor, so he approached Prince Tsunesada, who had been made Haitaishi (defunct Prince) at the time of Emperor Nimmyo presumably to sound him out as to whether he would be interested in acceding to the throne, but the Prince had already taken the tonsure to become a monk, and refused.</e>
<cmt>unclear, so I filled in the blanks</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 884, Mototsune was trying to find a way to remove the Emperor, so he approached Prince Tsunesada, who had been made Haitaishi (defunct Prince) at the time of Emperor Nimmyo presumably to sound him out as to whether he would be interested in acceding to the throne, but the Prince had already taken the tonsure to become a monk, and refused.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>そこで仁明天皇の第三皇子の光孝天皇が謙虚寛大な性格であったので、これを新帝と決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the third son of the Emperor Nimmyo, the Emperor Koko was of a modest and generous character Mototsune decided on him to become the new emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this juncture, Mototsune decided to have the third son of the Emperor Nimmyo, who was of a modest and generous character, installed on the throne as Emperor Koko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this juncture, Mototsune decided to have the third son of the Emperor Nimmyo, who was of a modest and generous character, installed on the throne as Emperor Koko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>時康親王の母は藤原総継の娘・藤原沢子で、基経の母・乙春とは姉妹であり、基経は時康親王の従兄弟にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mother of the Imperial Prince Tokiyasu was FUJIWARA no Futatsugu&apos;s daughter FUJIWARA no Takushi, and she was also a sister of Mototsune&apos;s mother Otoharu, making Mototsune a cousin of the Imperial Prince Tokiyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Tokiyasu&apos;s mother was FUJIWARA no Takushi, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Futatsugu, and she was also a sister of Mototsune&apos;s mother, Otoharu, making Mototsune a cousin of the Prince Tokiyasu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Tokiyasu&apos;s mother was FUJIWARA no Takushi, a daughter of FUJIWARA no Futatsugu, and she was also a sister of Mototsune&apos;s mother, Otoharu, making Mototsune a cousin of the Prince Tokiyasu.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィを統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>公卿を集めて天皇の廃位と時康親王の推戴を議したところ、左大臣源融（嵯峨天皇の第12皇子）は自分もその資格があるはずだと言いだした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he assembled the court nobles to discuss toppling the emperor and replace him with the Imperial Prince Tokiyasu, the Minister of the Left, MINAMOTO no Toru (the twelfth son of Emperor Saga) suddenly said that he himself should also have the qualification to become emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he assembled the court nobles to discuss deposing the emperor and replacing him with Prince Tokiyasu, the Minister of the Left, MINAMOTO no Toru (the twelfth son of Emperor Saga) asserted that he himself also had the pedigree, and was therefore qualified to become emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he assembled the court nobles to discuss deposing the emperor and replacing him with Prince Tokiyasu, the Minister of the Left, MINAMOTO no Toru (the twelfth son of Emperor Saga) asserted that he himself also had the pedigree, and was therefore qualified to become emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>基経は姓を賜った者が帝位についた例はないと退け、次いで参議藤原諸葛が基経に従わぬ者は斬ると恫喝に及び、廷議は決した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsune rejecte this claim by saying that there exists no precedent where somebody who has received a family name has become emperor, and then the councillor FUJIWARA no Morofuji threatened that anybody who did not follow Mototsune would be killed, and thus the imperial assembly made up its mind.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsune rejected this claim, maintaining that there was no precedent for a descendant of an empror who had been given a family name (e.g., Taira, Minamoto) to become emperor, and then FUJIWARA no Morofuji, a sangi councillor, threatened to have anyone who did not follow Mototsune&apos;s plan killed, and the deliberations were thereby brought to an end.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsune rejected this claim, maintaining that there was no precedent for a descendant of an emperor who had been given a family name (e.g., Taira, Minamoto) to become emperor, and then FUJIWARA no Morofuji, a sangi councilor, threatened to have anyone who did not follow Mototsune&apos;s plan killed, and the deliberations were thereby brought to an end.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>公卿会議の決定を持って、陽成天皇に退位を迫った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the decision of the assembly of the court nobles, he urged the Emperor Yozei to abdicate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having secured the decision of the assembly of the court nobles, Mototsune urged the Emperor Yozei to abdicate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having secured the decision of the assembly of the court nobles, Mototsune urged the Emperor Yozei to abdicate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>孤立した年少の天皇に、抗する術はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The isolated young emperor did not have the capacity to resist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The isolated young emperor did not have the capacity to resist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The isolated young emperor did not have the capacity to resist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="48">
<j>基経は時康親王を即位させた（光孝天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsune then enthroned the Imperial Prince Tokiyasu (Emperor Koko).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsune then had Prince Tokiyasu (Emperor Koko) enthroned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsune then had Prince Tokiyasu (Emperor Koko) enthroned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>光孝天皇は擁立に報いるために太政大臣である基経に大政を委任する詔まで発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To repay Mototsune for his enthronement the Emperor Koko issued an imperial decree to delegate all power to the Daijo daijin Mototsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To repay Mototsune for installing him on the throne, Emperor Koko issued an imperial decree delegating all power to the Daijo daijin Mototsune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To repay Mototsune for installing him on the throne, Emperor Koko issued an imperial decree delegating all power to the Daijo daijin Mototsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>天皇は既に55歳だったが、皇嗣の決定も基経に委ねるつもりで、あえて定めなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was already 55 years old, and he intentionally did not name an imperial heir in order to leave the decision to Mototsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was already 55 years old, and he intentionally did not name an heir, so as to leave the decision to Mototsune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was already 55 years old, and he intentionally did not name an heir, so as to leave the decision to Mototsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="51">
<j>仁和3年（887年）、光孝天皇が重篤に陥ると、基経は第7皇子の宇多天皇を皇嗣に推挙した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the third year of the Ninna era (887) Emperor Koko was on his deathbed, and Mototsune proposed to make the Emperor Uda, the seventh son of the Emperor, the imperial heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the third year of the Ninna era (887), Emperor Koko was on his deathbed, and Mototsune proposed to make the Emperor&apos;s seventh son, Prince Sadami (who subsequently became Emperor Uda) heir to the thone.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 887, Emperor Koko was on his deathbed, and Mototsune proposed to make the Emperor&apos;s seventh son, Prince Sadami (who subsequently became Emperor Uda) heir to the throne.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>定省は天皇の意中の皇子であり、天皇は基経の手を取って喜んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadami was the favourite prince of the emperor and the emperor was so happy that he took the hands of Mototsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadami was the Emperor&apos;s favourite son, and the emperor was so happy that he grasped Mototsune&apos;s hands in thanks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadami was the Emperor&apos;s favorite son, and the emperor was so happy that he grasped Mototsune&apos;s hands in thanks.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>臣籍降下した者が即位した先例がないため、臨終の天皇は定省を親王に復し、東宮となした日に崩じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there existed no precedence where somebody who had been stripped of his title had been enthroned, the Emperor on his deathbed reinstated Sadami as imperial prince and passed away on the day Sadami became a prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there had existed no precedent for someone who had been given a family name (a practice which had the effect of stripping a son of an emperor of his title as Prince, and removing him from the line of candidates eligible to inherit the throne) to become Emperor, Emperor Koko reinstated Sadami as Prince from his deathbed, and passed away on that same day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there had existed no precedent for someone who had been given a family name (a practice which had the effect of stripping a son of an emperor of his title as Prince, and removing him from the line of candidates eligible to inherit the throne) to become Emperor, Emperor Koko reinstated Sadami as Prince from his deathbed, and passed away on that same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>定省はただちに即位した（宇多天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadami was enthroned at once (Emperor Uda).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadami was enthroned at once as Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadami was enthroned at once as Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="55">
<j>宇多天皇は先帝の例に倣い大政を基経に委ねることとし、左大弁橘広相に起草させ「万機はすべて太政大臣に関白し、しかるのにち奏下すべし」との詔をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Uda followed the example of the preceding emperor and delegated all power to Mototsune, asking the Saidaiben (Controller of the Left) TACHIBANA no Hiromi to write a draft and issue the imperial rescript: &quot;All political matters should be advised upon by the Chancellor of the Realm, and make it so&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Uda followed the example of the preceding emperor and delegated all power to Mototsune, requesting that TACHIBANA no Hiromi, the Saidaiben (Controller of the Left), write a draft and issue an Imperial Rescript declaring, &quot;The decisions on all political matters shall be entrusted to the Chancellor of the Realm (Kanpaku), and so be it&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Uda followed the example of the preceding emperor and delegated all power to Mototsune, requesting that TACHIBANA no Hiromi, the Sadaiben (major controller of the left), write a draft and issue an Imperial Rescript declaring, &quot;The decisions on all political matters shall be entrusted (kanpakusuru) to the Daijo daijin (Grand minister of state), and so be it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「太政大臣」を修正。ピリオドを移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>関白の号がここで初めて登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title of Kanpaku (the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) appeared for the first time.</e>
<cmt>訳抜け</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>基経は儀礼的にいったん辞意を乞うが、天皇は重ねて広相に起草させ「宜しく阿衡の任を以て、卿の任となすべし」との詔をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first Mototsune expressed ceremonially his will to resign, but the emperor asked Hiromi again to draft an imperial rescript which said:&quot;he should take over the task of Ako and take one the task of a state minister&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsune initially put forth a polite expression of his desire to decline the appointment and resign; however, the emperor again asked Hiromi again to draft an Imperial Rescript declaring, &quot;Mototsune should be appointed as Ako, and assume the post of a state minister&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar, terms</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsune initially put forth a polite expression of his desire to decline the appointment and resign; however, the emperor again asked Hiromi again to draft an Imperial Rescript declaring, &quot;Mototsune should be appointed as Ako, and assume the post of a state minister.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>阿衡とは中国の故事によるものだが、これを文章博士藤原佐世が「阿衡には位貴しも、職掌なし」と基経に告げたため、基経はならばと政務を放棄してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ako is derived from Chinese classic texts and because FUJIWARA no Sukeyo had reported this to Mototsune as &quot;that he would receive the high position of Ako, but would have no official duties&quot;, and therefore Mototsune all at once abandoned all his political duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ako is a term derived from classical Chinese texts, and because FUJIWARA no Sukeyo had described the scenario to Mototsune as one in whicc, &quot;he would receive the high position of Ako, but it would be merely ceremonious, and would have no official duties&quot;; therefore, Mototsune was able to abandoned all his political duties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ako is a term derived from classical Chinese texts, and because FUJIWARA no Sukeyo, Monjo hakase (professor of literature), had described the scenario to Mototsune as one in which, &quot;he would receive the high position of Ako, but it would be merely ceremonious, and would have no official duties&quot;; therefore, Mototsune was able to abandoned all his political duties.</e>
<cmt>スペルを訂正。「文章博士」を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="59">
<j>問題が長期化して半年にもおよび政務が渋滞してしまい宇多天皇は困りはて、真意を伝えて慰撫するが、基経は納得しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the problem was protracted and lasted more than half a year, the Emperor Uda was so distressed that he conveyed his true feelings and tried to appease him, but Mototsune was not convinced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because this issue became protracted and had not been resolved after more than half a year, it became troublesome for Emperor Uda, who made an attempt to convey his true intentions on the matter to Mototsune in an effort to try to appease him, but Mototsune would not accept.</e>
<cmt>grammar, somewhat unclear</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because this issue became protracted and had not been resolved after more than half a year, it became troublesome for Emperor Uda, who made an attempt to convey his true intentions on the matter to Mototsune in an effort to try to appease him, but Mototsune would not accept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>阿衡の職掌について学者に検討させ、広相は言いがかりであることを抗弁するが、学者たちは基経の意を迎えるばかりだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He asked scholars to examine the official duties of Ako, and Hiromi protested that Mototsune was accusing him falsely, but the scholars were all siding with Mototsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsune had some scholars examine what the official duties of the Ako were, whereupon Hiromi protested that Mototsune was reproaching him without grounds; however, the scholars all sided with Mototsune.</e>
<cmt>grammar, unclear background info</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiromi had some scholars examine what the official duties of the Ako were, and protested that Mototsune was reproaching him without grounds; however, the scholars all sided with Mototsune.</e>
<cmt>主語を「広相」に修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>結局、広相を罷免し、天皇が自らの誤りを認める詔を発布することで決着がついた（阿衡事件）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually he dismissed Hiromi and the whole issue was solved when the emperor himself admitted his mistake in an imperial rescript he issued (Ako incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Mototsune had Hiromi dismissed, and the whole issue was resolved when the emperor himself issued an Imperial Rescript admitting his mistake (the Ako incident).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Mototsune had Hiromi dismissed, and the whole issue was resolved when the Emperor himself issued an Imperial Rescript admitting his mistake (the Ako incident).</e>
<cmt>emperor を大文字に。コンマを移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>これにより藤原氏の権力が天皇よりも強いことをあらためて世に知らしめることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this event the public was again reminded of the fact that the Fujiwara clan was more powerful than the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This event served as a clear reminder to the public that the Fujiwara clan was in actuality more powerful than the emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This event served as a clear reminder to the public that the Fujiwara clan was in actuality more powerful than the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>emperor を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>基経はなおも広相を流罪とすることを求めるが、菅原道真が書を送って諫言しておさめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsune was asking to deport Hiromi, but the problem was settled with SUGAWARA no Michizane writing a letter admonishing Hiromi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsune was demanding that Hiromi be banished; however, calm was restored when SUGAWARA no Michizane sent a letter to Hiromi, admonishing him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsune was still demanding that Hiromi be banished; however, calm was restored when SUGAWARA no Michizane sent a letter to Mototsune, admonishing him.</e>
<cmt>「なおも」を追加。Hiromi を Mototune に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>この事件は天皇にとって屈辱だったようで、基経の死後に菅原道真を重用するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident was very humiliating for the emperor and therefore he gave SUGAWARA no Michizane an important position after Mototsune&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident was very humiliating for Emperor Uda, who therefore promoted SUGAWARA no Michizane to an important position as a trusted and close advisor after Mototsune&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident was very humiliating for Emperor Uda, who therefore promoted SUGAWARA no Michizane to an important position as a trusted and close advisor after Mototsune&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="65">
<j>宇多天皇と基経との関係は一応修復され、政務をとりはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship between the Emperor Uda and Mototsune had been repaired for the time being and Mototsune took charge of political affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between the Emperor Uda and Mototsune had been restored for the time being, and Mototsune took charge of political affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between the Emperor Uda and Mototsune had been restored for the time being, and Mototsune took charge of political affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>仁和4年（888年）に娘の藤原温子が女御に上がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the fourth year of the Ninna era (888) his daughter FUJIWARA no Onshi became a court lady.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the fourth year of the Ninna era (888), Mototsune&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Onshi, became a court lady.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 888, Mototsune&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Onshi became a court lady.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。コンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="67">
<j>寛平3年（891年）、基経は病床につき死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the third year of the Kambyo era he fell ill and died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the third year of the Kambyo era, he fell ill and died.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 891, he fell ill and died.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>正一位が贈られ、昭宣と諡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded Shoiichi (Senior First Rank) and received the posthumous name Mototsune (with different Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously awarded the court rank of Shoiichi (Senior First Rank) and received the name Mototsune (with different Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously awarded the court rank of Shoiichi (Senior First Rank) and received the name Mototsune (with different Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="69">
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of government posts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of government posts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of office and rank</e>
<cmt>用語集にしたがって修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="70">
<j>仁寿2年（852年）1月、蔵人に補任（この頃に良房の養子になったとみられる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January of the second year of the Ninju era (852) he was named keeper of the imperial court&apos;s storehouses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January of the second year of the Ninju era (852), he was named keeper of the Imperial Court&apos;s storehouses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 852: He was appointed as Kurodo (Chamberlain) (and seemed to became the foster son of Yoshifusa around this time).</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正。「蔵人」を修正。「この頃に良房の養子になったとみられる」を追加In January 852, he→January 852: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="71">
<j>仁寿4年（854年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourth year of the Ninju era (854)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fourth year of the Ninju era (854)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 854</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="72">
<j>1月、左兵衛少尉に遷任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January he became Sahyoe shoi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January he became Sahyoe shoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February: He became Sahyoe no shojo (Third-ranked Assistant Officer of Sahyoe-fu, the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>「左兵衛少尉」を修正。コンマを挿入In February, he→February: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="73">
<j>10月11日、従五位下に叙し、侍従に任官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 11th he was made Ju Go-I (junior grade of the fifth court rank) and became chamberlain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 11th, he was awarded the court rank of Ju Go-I (junior grade of the fifth court rank), and became chamberlain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 8: He was awarded the court rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and became Jiju (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「従五位下、侍従」を修正。コンマを削除On November 8, he→November 8: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>（侍従は11月2日任官の説あり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(According to another theory he was named chamberlain on November 2nd)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(According to an alternative account, he was named chamberlain on November 2nd)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to an alternative account, he was named Jiju on November 29).</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「侍従」を修正。ピリオドを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="75">
<j>斉衡2年（855年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second year of the Saiko era (855)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second year of the Saiko era (855)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 855</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="76">
<j>1月15日、左兵衛佐を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since January 15th he also held the position of Sahyoe-sa (Undersecretary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 15th he was appointed to the post of Sahyoe-sa (Undersecretary), held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 10: He was appointed to the post of Sahyoe no suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards), held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>日付表示を修正。ピリオドを挿入。「左兵衛佐」を修正On February 10, he→February 10: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="77">
<j>4月20日、蔵人に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 20th he was also made keeper of the imperial court&apos;s storehouses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 20th, he was also made keeper of the Imperial Court&apos;s storehouses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 13: He was also made Kurodo.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。アポストロフィを統一On May 13, he→May 13: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="78">
<j>天安 (日本)元年（857年）3月、少納言を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March of the first year of the Tenan era (857) he also held the position of Shonagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March of the first year of the Tenan era (857), he was appointed to the post of Shonagon, held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 857: He was appointed to the post of Shonagon, held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正In April 857, he→April 857: Heに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="79">
<j>天安2年（858年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second year of the Tenan era (858)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second year of the Tenan era (858)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 858</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="80">
<j>1月15日、左兵衛佐を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 15th he also held the position of Sahyoe-sa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 15th he was appointed to the post of Sahyoe-sa, held concurrently with his other post.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 6, he was appointed to the post of Sahyoe no suke, held concurrently with his other post.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「左兵衛佐」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>・蔵人・少納言・侍従如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retained the positions of keeper of the imperial court&apos;s, Shonagon and chamberlain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">consistency</e>
<cmt>grammar, capitalization?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He remained in the positions of Kurodo, Shonagon and Jiju.</e>
<cmt>原文どおりに訳しました。チェッカーの方の修正の意味が不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="82">
<j>9月14日、左近衛少将に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 14th he changed to the post of Sakon-e no shosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 14th, he was transferred to the post of Sakon-e no shosho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 28, he was transferred to the post of Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「左近衛少将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>少納言如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retained the position of Shonagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained the position of Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained the position of Shonagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="84">
<j>10月、蔵人頭に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October he also became head of the keepers of the imperial court&apos;s storehouses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he also became head of the keepers of the Imperial Court&apos;s storehouses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Novemberber, he also became Kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt>「蔵人頭」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="85">
<j>11月25日、播磨介を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 25th he also held the position of Harima no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 25th, he was appointed to the post of governor of Harima province (Harima no suke), held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 6, 859, he was appointed to the post of Harima no suke (assistant governor of Harima Province), held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「播磨介」を修正。小文字を大文字に表記を統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="86">
<j>貞観_(日本)2年（860年）11月16日、正五位下に昇叙し、蔵人頭・左近衛少将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 16th of the second year of the Jogan era (860) he was promoted to Shogo-i-ge, (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)and retained the positions of head of the keepers of the imperial court&apos;s store houses and Sakon-e no shosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 16th of the second year of the Jogan era (860), he was promoted to the court rank of Shogo-i-ge, (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade),and retained the positions of head of the keepers of the Imperial Court&apos;s store houses and Sakon-e no shosho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 5, 861, he was promoted to the court rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained the positions of Kurodo no to and Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記を修正。スペースを削除。「正五位下、蔵人頭、左近衛少将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="87">
<j>貞観3年（861年）1月8日、従四位下に昇叙し、蔵人頭・左近衛少将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 8th of the third year of the Jogan era (861) he was promoted to Jushi i-ge, (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) and retained the positions of head of the keepers of the imperial court&apos;s store houses and Sakon-e no shosho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 8th of the third year of the Jogan era (861), he was promoted to the court rank of Jushi i-ge, (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and retained the positions of head of the keepers of the Imperial Court&apos;s store houses and Sakon-e no shosho.</e>
<cmt>grammar, capitalization of titles issues…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 25, 861, he was promoted to the court rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and retained the positions of Kurodo no to and Sakone no shosho.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記を修正。「従四位下、蔵人頭、左近衛少将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="88">
<j>貞観5年（863年）2月10日、左近衛中将に転任し、蔵人頭如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 10th of the fifth year of the Jogan era (863) he changed position to Sakon-e no chujo (Vice-Secretary of left Imperial Guard) and retained his position of head of the keepers of the imperial court&apos;s store houses</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 10th of the fifth year of the Jogan era (863), he was trasferred to the post of Sakon-e no chujo (Vice-Secretary of left Imperial Guard), and retained his position of head of the keepers of the Imperial Court&apos;s store houses</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 7, 863, he was transferred to the post of Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) and retained his position of Kurodo no to.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記を修正。「左近衛中将、蔵人頭」を修正。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="89">
<j>貞観6年（864年）1月16日、参議に補任し、左近衛中将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 16th of the sixth year of the Jogan era (864) he also became councillor (sangi) and retained the position of Sakon-e no chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 16th of the sixth year of the Jogan era (864), he was appointed as a councillor (sangi), and retained the position of Sakon-e no chujo.</e>
<cmt>grammar, capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 1, 864, he was appointed as Sangi, and retained the position of Sakone no chujo.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記を修正。「参議、左近衛中将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="90">
<j>貞観7年（865年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seventh year of the Jogan era (865).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seventh year of the Jogan era (865).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 865</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="91">
<j>1月27日、阿波権守を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 27th he also became the Awagon no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 27th, he was appointed to the post of governor of Awagon Province (Awagon no kami), held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 2, he was appointed to the post of Awa no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Awa Province), held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「阿波権守」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="92">
<j>3月28日、伊予守を兼任し、阿波権守を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 28th he also became Iyo no kami and resigned from the post of the Awagon no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 28th, he was appointed to the post of governor of Iyo province (Iyo no kami), and resigned from the post of the Awagon no kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar, titles…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 1, he was appointed to the post of governor of Iyo no Kami (Governor of Iyo Province), and resigned from the post of the Awa no Gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「伊予守、阿波権守」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="93">
<j>貞観8年（866年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eigth year of the Jogan era (866)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eigth year of the Jogan era (866)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 866</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="94">
<j>1月7日、従四位上に昇叙し、参議・左近衛中将・伊予守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 7th he was promoted to Jushi i-jo, (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and retained the positions of Sangi, Sakon-e no chujo and Iyo no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 7th, he was promoted to the court rank of Jushi i-jo, (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), and retained the positions of Sangi, Sakon-e no chujo, and Iyo no kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 31, he was promoted to the court rank of Jushiijo, (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), and retained the positions of Sangi, Sakone no chujo, and Iyo no kami.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「従四位上、左近衛中将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="95">
<j>3月23日、正四位下に昇叙し、参議・左近衛中将・伊予守如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 23rd he was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Lower Fourth Court Rank) and retained the positions of Sangi, Sakon-e no chujo and Iyo no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 23rd, he was promoted to the court rank of Shoshiinoge (Lower Fourth Court Rank), and retained the positions of Sangi, Sakon-e no chujo, and Iyo no kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 16, he was promoted to the court rank of Shoshiinoge (Lower Fourth Court Rank), and retained the positions of Sangi, Sakone no chujo, and Iyo no kami.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「左近衛中将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="96">
<j>12月8日、中納言に転任し、従三位に昇叙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 8th he changed position to Chunagon and was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 8th, he was transferred to the post of Chunagon, and was promoted to the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 21, 867, he was transferred to the post of Chunagon, and was promoted to the court rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="97">
<j>貞観9年（867年）1月14日、左近衛中将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 14th of the ninth year of the Jogan era (867) he also held the post of Sakon-e no chujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 14th of the ninth year of the Jogan era (867), he was appointed to the post of Sakon-e no chujo, held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 26, 867, he was appointed to the post of Sakone no chujo, held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記を修正。「左近衛中将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="98">
<j>貞観10年（868年）5月26日、左近衛中将を去り、左近衛大将を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 26th of the tenth year of the Jogan era (868) he left the position of Sakon-e no chujo and also held the post of Sakon-e no taisho (Western Commander).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 26th of the tenth year of the Jogan era (868), he left the position of Sakon-e no chujo, and was appointed to the post of Sakon-e no taisho (Western Commander), held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 24, 868, he left the position of Sakone no chujo, and was appointed to the post of Sakone no taisho (Western Commander), held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記を修正。「左近衛中将、左近衛大将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="99">
<j>貞観11年（869年）1月13日、陸奥出羽按察使を兼任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 13th of the eleventh year of the Jogan era (869) he also held the position of Mutsu-Dewa Azechi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 13th of the eleventh year of the Jogan era (869), he was appointed to the position of Mutsu-Dewa Azechi, held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 3, 869, he was appointed to the position of Mutsu-Dewa Azechi (local inspector of Mutsu and Dewa Provinces), held concurrently with his other posts.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記を修正。「陸奥出羽按察使」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="100">
<j>貞観12年（870年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twelfth year of the Jogan era (870)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twelfth year of the Jogan era (870)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 870</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="101">
<j>1月13日、大納言に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 13th he changed to position of Dainagon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 13th, he was transferred to to post of Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 21, he was transferred to the post of Dainagon.</e>
<cmt>日付表記をを修正。to を the に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="102">
<j>1月28日、左近衛大将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 28th he retained the position of Sakon-e no taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 28th, he retained the position of Sakon-e no taisho.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 8, he retained the position of Sakone no taisho.</e>
<cmt>日付表記をを修正。to を the に修正。「左近衛大将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="103">
<j>2月、陸奥出羽按察使如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February he retained the position of Mutsu-Dewa-Azechi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, he retained the position of Mutsu-Dewa-Azechi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, he retained the position of Mutsu-Dewa Azechi.</e>
<cmt>「陸奥出羽按察使」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="104">
<j>貞観14年（872年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourteenth year of the Jogan era (872)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fourteenth year of the Jogan era (872)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 872</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="105">
<j>8月25日、正三位に叙し、右大臣に転任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 25th he was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and changed to the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 25th he was promoted to the court rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), and transferred to the post of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 5, he was promoted to the court rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), and transferred to the post of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>日付表記をを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="106">
<j>8月29日、左近衛大将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 29th he retained the position of Sakon-e no taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 29th, he retained the position of Sakon-e no taisho.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 9, he retained the position of Sakone no taisho.</e>
<cmt>日付表記をを修正。「左近衛大将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="107">
<j>11月29日、摂政宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 29th he was declared regent (Sessho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 29th he was appointed as regent (Sessho).</e>
<cmt>grammar, capitalization?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 5, 873, he was appointed as Sessho (regent).</e>
<cmt>日付表記をを修正。「摂政」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>右大臣・左近衛大将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retained the position of Udaijin, Sakon-e no taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained the positions of Udaijin, and Sakon-e no taisho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained the positions of Udaijin, and Sakone no taisho.</e>
<cmt>「左近衛大将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="109">
<j>貞観15年（873年）1月7日、従二位に昇叙し、摂政・右大臣・左近衛大将如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 7th he was promoted to Junii, (Junior Second Rank), and retained the positions of Sessho, Udaijin and Sakon-e no taisho..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 7th, he was promoted to the court rank of Junii, (Junior Second Rank), and retained the positions of Sessho, Udaijin, and Sakon-e no taisho..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 12, 873, he was promoted to the court rank of Junii, (Junior Second Rank), and retained the positions of Sessho, Udaijin, and Sakone no taisho..</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記をを修正。「左近衛大将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="110">
<j>貞観19年（877年）2月、左近衛大将を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February of the nineteenth year of the Jogan era (877) he resigned from the position of Sakon-e no taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February of the nineteenth year of the Jogan era (877), he resigned from the position of Sakon-e no taisho.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, 877, he resigned from the position of Sakone no taisho.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記をを修正。「左近衛大将」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="111">
<j>元慶4年（880年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourth year of the Gankyo era (880)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fourth year of the Gankyo era (880)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 880</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="112">
<j>11月8日、関白に補任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 8th he also assumed the position of Kampaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 8th he also assumed the position of Kampaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 17, he also assumed the position of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「関白」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>右大臣如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retained the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained the position of Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="114">
<j>12月4日、太政大臣宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 4th he was declared Daijo daijin (Chief minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 4th he was appointed as Daijo daijin (Chief minister).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 11, he was appointed as Daijo daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>日付表記を修正。「関白」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>関白如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retained the position of Kampaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained the position of Kampaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained the position of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>「関白」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="116">
<j>元慶5年（881年）1月15日、従一位に昇叙し、関白・太政大臣如元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 15th of the fifth year of the Gankyo era (881) he was promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) and remained Kampaku and Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 15th of the fifth year of the Gankyo era (881), he was promoted to the court rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank), and retained the posts of Kampaku and Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 21, 881, he was promoted to the court rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank), and retained the posts of Kanpaku and Daijo daijin.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記をを修正。「関白」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="117">
<j>仁和3年（887年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Third year of the Ninna era (887)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Third year of the Ninna era (887)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 887</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="118">
<j>11月21日、関白宣下（正式な詔が降る）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 21st he was declared Kampaku (the day the official imperial rescript was issued).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 21st he was appointed as Kampaku (the day the official imperial rescript was issued).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 13, he was appointed as Kanpaku (the day the official imperial rescript was issued).</e>
<cmt>日付表記をを修正。「関白」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="119">
<j>11月26日、関白辞すも、阿衡に補任の旨。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 26th he resigned from the position of Kampaku, but was asked to become Ako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 26th, he resigned from the position of Kampaku, but was asked to accept a position as Ako.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 18, he resigned from the position of Kanpaku, but was asked to accept a position as Ako.</e>
<cmt>日付表記をを修正。「関白」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="120">
<j>仁和4年（888年）6月2日、阿衡を止め、関白に復す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 2nd of the fourth year of the Ninna era (888) he stopped being Ako and returned to the position of Kampaku..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 2nd of the fourth year of the Ninna era (888), he resigned as Ako, and returned to the position of Kampaku..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 18, 888, he resigned as Ako, and returned to the position of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記をを修正。「関白」を修正。ピリオドを削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="65">
<sen id="121">
<j>寛平2年（890年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second year of Kampyo (890)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second year of Kampyo (890)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 890</e>
<cmt>年号表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="66">
<sen id="122">
<j>2月19日、准三宮宣下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 19 he was declared Ju-Sangu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 19, he was promoted to the court rank of Ju-Sangu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, rank?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 17, he was promoted to the court rank of Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress).</e>
<cmt>「准三宮」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="67">
<sen id="123">
<j>12月14日、関白を辞す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 14 he resigned from the position of Kampaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 14, he resigned from the post of Kampaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 31, 891, he resigned from the post of Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>「関白」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="68">
<sen id="124">
<j>寛平3年（891年）1月13日、薨去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 13th of the third year of the Kampyo era (891) he passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 13th of the third year of the Kampyo era (891), he died.</e>
<cmt>grammar, consitency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 28, 891, he died.</e>
<cmt>年号、日付表記をを修正。4の日付と一致しません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>享年56。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 56 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 56 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 56.</e>
<cmt>「享年」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>贈正一位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was posthumously awarded Shoichii, (Senior First Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was posthumously awarded the court rank of Shoichii, (Senior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was posthumously awarded the court rank of Shoichii, (Senior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>謚号：昭宣公。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His posthumous name was Shosen-ko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His posthumous name was Shosen-ko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His posthumous name was Shosenko.</e>
<cmt>「昭宣公」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>越前国に封ず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was buried in Echizen province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was buried in Echizen province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was buried in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>province を大文字に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="69">
<sen id="129">
<j>後世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he died</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he died</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>基経を中祖とする藤原北家および藤原北家と近しい関係にある村上源氏が朝廷の主流を占めつづけたこともあり、近代以前には暴君・陽成天皇を廃した「功臣」として前漢の霍光に擬える説が儒学者を中心に唱えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fujiwara Hokke, which had Mototsune as his Nakaso (main ancestor) and the Murakami-Genji clan, which had a close relationship with the Fujiwara Hokke continued to occupy the mainstream of the Imperial court, and before modern times mainly Confucian scholars were putting forward the argument that Mototsune was similiar to Huo Guang of the Former Han Dynasty as he was a &quot;model vassal&quot; who had toppled the tyrannical Emperor Yozei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The northern branch of the Fujiwara clan (Fujiwara Hokke), of which Mototsune was an important progentor (Nakaso), and the Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan), which had a close relationship with the Fujiwara Hokke continued to hold sway over the Imperial court, and before modern times, those putting forward the argument that Mototsune was similiar to Huo Guang of the Former Han Dynasty, in that he was a &quot;model vassal&quot; who had toppled the tyrannical Emperor Yozei, were mainly scholars of Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>grammar, what is the point of this apparently favorable comparison?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The northern branch of the Fujiwara clan (Fujiwara Hokke), of which Mototsune was an important progenitor (Nakaso), and the Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan), which had a close relationship with the Fujiwara Hokke continued to hold sway over the Imperial Court, and before modern times, those putting forward the argument that Mototsune was similar to Huo Guang of the Former Han Dynasty, in that he was a &quot;model vassal&quot; who had toppled the tyrannical Emperor Yozei, were mainly scholars of Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>「村上源氏」を修正。court を大文字に。スペルを訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>北畠親房（村上源氏）は神皇正統記において廃位を称賛し、その「積善の余慶」によって基経の子孫が摂政関白を独占したと記述している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikafusa KITABATAKE (Genji MURAKAMI) praised the toppling of Emperor Yozei in the Jinno shotoki, writing that due to the &quot;fortunate heredity of his good deeds&quot; Mototsune&apos;s descendents could monopolize the position of Sessho kampaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikafusa KITABATAKE (a member of the Murakami-Genji clan) praised the toppling of Emperor Yozei in the Jinno shotoki, writing that due to the &quot;by virtue of his good deeds&quot; Mototsune&apos;s descendents were able to monopolize the positions of Sessho and Kampaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar, again, although the contraditions should be apparent to any educated person from the Occident, from the quote &quot;monopololize the positions&quot;..., this is also a biased historical citation, as they were allied politically, as mentioned above. Why are no critical accounts cited?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikafusa KITABATAKE (a member of the Murakami-Genji clan) praised the toppling of Emperor Yozei in the Jinno shotoki, writing that due to the &quot;by virtue of his good deeds&quot; Mototsune&apos;s descendents were able to monopolize the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除。「関白」を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Cprobot(id:97843), Eskimbot(id:29676), 水野白楓(id:22811), 三浦大輔(id:93377), Extrahitz(id:26245), Cozycoji(id:87757), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Snap55(id:89773), BAKU(id:55205), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), Masyu(id:31065), Yonoemon(id:55450), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 代言人(id:33675), UMBRO(id:100484), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Loveless(id:129239), Point136(id:211299), YOSHI438(id:174755), Yas(id:739), 伏儀(id:142093), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Atsasebo(id:95407), Zell(id:23939), 小太刀(id:18154), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>