<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平知康</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomoyasu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tomoyasu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomoyasu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 知康（たいら の ともやす 生没年不詳）は平安時代末期の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomoyasu was a noble who lived in the Late Heian Period (years of his birth and death, not known)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tomoyasu was a noble who lived in the Late Heian Period (years of his birth and death, not known)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tomoyasu was a noble who lived in the late Heian period (years of his birth and death, not known).</e>
<cmt>late、period小文字にしました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>壱岐守平知親の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the son of TAIRA no Tomochika who was Iki no Kami (governor of Iki Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of TAIRA no Tomochika who was Iki no Kami (governor of Iki Province).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of TAIRA no Tomochika who was Iki no kami (governor of Iki Province).</e>
<cmt>kami小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>検非違使左衛門尉、鼓の名手で鼓判官（つづみのほうがん）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and the saemon no jo (a secretary of the Left Division of Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guard) and he was good at tapping a tsuzumi (hand drum) and, therefore, called Tsuzumi no Hogan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and the saemon no jo (a secretary of the Left Division of Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guard) and he was good at tapping a tsuzumi (hand drum) and, therefore, called Tsuzumi no Hogan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a kebiishi (a police and judicial chief) and the saemon no jo (a secretary of the Left Division of Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guard) and he was good at tapping a tsuzumi (hand drum) and, therefore, called Tsuzumi no Hogan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>北面の武士で、後白河天皇の信任篤く近臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Hokumen no Bushi (Imperial Palace Guard) and he won the confidence of the Emperor Goshirakawa and became a trusted vassal of Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a Hokumen no Bushi (Imperial Palace Guard) and he won the confidence of the Emperor Goshirakawa and became a trusted vassal of Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a Hokumen no Bushi (Imperial Palace Guard) and he won the confidence of the Emperor Goshirakawa and became a trusted vassal of Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）7月に源義仲が伊勢平氏を追い入京すると、法皇の使いとして幾度か義仲を訪れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1183, when MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka entered into Kyoto chasing Ise Heishi (Taira clan from Ise), he visited Yosinaka several times as an errand of the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1183, when MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka entered into Kyoto chasing Ise Heishi (Taira clan from Ise), he visited Yosinaka several times as an errand of the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1183, when MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka entered into Kyoto chasing Ise Heishi (Taira clan from Ise), he visited Yosinaka several times as an errand of the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>7月補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『平家物語』では兵の乱暴狼藉を鎮めるよう求めたところ、義仲から「和殿が鼓判官といふは、万（よろず）の人に打たれたか、張られたか」と尋ねられて面食らい、法皇に義仲討伐を進言したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;), it is described that, when Tomoyashu required Yoshinaka to suppress riotous behaviors by soldiers, he was bewildered by Yoshinaka&apos;s question, &quot;Is the reason why you are called as Tsuzumi no Hogan that you have been hit or tapped by many person?&quot; and he suggested the Cloistered Emperor to subjugate Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (&quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot;), it is described that, when Tomoyashu required Yoshinaka to suppress riotous behaviors by soldiers, he was bewildered by Yoshinaka&apos;s question, &quot;Is the reason why you are called as Tsuzumi no Hogan that you have been hit or tapped by many person?&quot; and he suggested the Cloistered Emperor to subjugate Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of the Heike), it is described that, when Tomoyasu required Yoshinaka to suppress riotous behaviors by soldiers, he was bewildered by Yoshinaka&apos;s question, &apos;Is the reason why you are called as Tsuzumi no Hogan that you have been hit or tapped by many person?&apos; and he suggested the Cloistered Emperor to subjugate Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>説明括弧内の&quot;を削除しました。Tomoyasuスペル訂正しました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>知康は院御所の法住寺殿に兵を集めて、公然と義仲に対決姿勢を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoyasu raised an army at Hoju-ji Dono, which was the palace of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and showed confrontation stance against Yoshinaka openly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoyasu raised an army at Hoju-ji Dono, which was the palace of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and openly confronted Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoyasu raised an army at Hojuji-dono Palace, which was the palace of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, and openly confronted Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>法住寺殿→Hojuji-dono Palace</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>法皇方は義仲に洛外退去を要求し、応じねば追討の宣旨を下すと通告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor&apos;s side required Yoshinaka to go out of Kyoto and notified that they would issue a senji () if this senji was not honored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cloistered Emperor&apos;s side required Yoshinaka to go out of Kyoto and notified that they would issue a senji () if this senji was not honored.</e>
<cmt>Robert: Probably need to explain what a senji is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor&apos;s side required Yoshinaka to go out of Kyoto and notified that they would issue a senge (imperial proclamation) if this senge was not honored.</e>
<cmt>宣旨→senge (imperial proclamation)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>怒った義仲は寿永2年（1183年）11月19日、法住寺殿を攻撃、知康が防戦の指揮を取るが、さんざんに敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 19, 1183, Yoshinaka got angry and attacked the Hoju-ji Dono and Tomoyasu, who took command of a defensive battle, suffered a crushing defeat and Goshirakawa was caught by Yoshinaka and confined (Hoju-ji Gassen (Battle of Hoju-ji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 19, 1183, Yoshinaka became angry and attacked the Hoju-ji Dono and Tomoyasu, who took command of a defensive battle, and suffered a crushing defeat. Goshirakawa was caught by Yoshinaka and confined (Hoju-ji Gassen (Battle of Hoju-ji).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 10, 1184, Yoshinaka became angry and attacked Hojuji-dono Palace and Tomoyasu, who took command of a defensive battle, and suffered a crushing defeat.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。法住寺殿→Hojuji-dono Palace一原文一訳文の例外処理。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>後白河院は義仲に捕らえられ幽閉されてしまった（法住寺合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa was caught by Yoshinaka and confined (Battle of Hoju-ji).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理。Hoju-ji Gassen (削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>敗れた知康は解官される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Defeated Tomoyasu was dismissed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The defeated Tomoyasu was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The defeated Tomoyasu was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>元暦2年（1185年）、検非違使に復官、在京していた源義経に接近する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1185, he was reappointed to the kebiishi and he approached to Yoshitsune who was in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1185, he was reappointed to the kebiishi and approached Yoshitsune who was in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1185, he was reappointed to the kebiishi and approached Yoshitsune who was in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>平家滅亡後に、源頼朝と義経が不和になり、義経が都落ちすると、知康は再び解官されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the fall of Taira family, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and Yoshitsune fell out with each other and Yoshitsune exiled from the capital, Tomoyasu was dismissed again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the fall of Taira family, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and Yoshitsune fell out with each other and Yoshitsune was exiled from the capital, Tomoyasu was dismissed again.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the fall of Taira family, when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and Yoshitsune fell out with each other and Yoshitsune was exiled from the capital, Tomoyasu was dismissed again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>後に鎌倉へ下向して、2代征夷大将軍の源頼家に仕えて側近となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Tomoyasu went away from Kyoto to Kamakura and worked under MIMAMOTO no Yoriie, who was the second Seii Taishogun (shogun), and became his close aide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Tomoyasu went away from Kyoto to Kamakura and worked under MIMAMOTO no Yoriie, who was the second Seii Taishogun (shogun), and became his close aide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Tomoyasu went away from Kyoto to Kamakura and worked under MIMAMOTO no Yoriie, who was the second Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), and became his close aide.</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍→Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>建仁3年（1203年）、頼家が追放され伊豆国修善寺に幽閉されると、知康は帰洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1203, when Yoriie was exiled and confined in Shuzen-ji Temple in Izu Province, Tomoyasu came back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1203, when Yoriie was exiled and confined in Shuzen-ji Temple in Izu Province, Tomoyasu came back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1203, when Yoriie was exiled and confined in Shuzen-ji Temple in Izu Province, Tomoyasu came back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 味っ子(id:17086), 代言人(id:33675), Toki-ho(id:10691), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>