<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原安親</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasuchika</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yasuchika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasuchika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 安親（ふじわら の やすちか、延喜22年（922年） - 長徳2年3月5日 (旧暦)（996年3月26日））は、平安時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasuchika (922 - March 26, 996) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived in the middle era of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yasuchika (922 - March 26, 996) was a kugyo (top court official) who lived during the middle era of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yasuchika (922 - March 31, 996) was a kugyo (court noble) who lived during the middle era of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一グレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京職藤原中正の三男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Nakamasa at Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Nakamasa at Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third son of FUJIWARA no Nakamasa at Kyoshiki (the Capital Bureau).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>妹の藤原時姫は摂政藤原兼家の正室で一条天皇の外祖母。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tokihime, a sister younger than he, was the lawful wife of FUJIWARA no Kaneie, Sessho (regent), and was the mother of the mother of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tokihime, a sister younger than he, was the lawful wife of FUJIWARA no Kaneie, Sessho (regent), and was the mother of the mother of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tokihime, his younger sister, was the lawful wife of FUJIWARA no Kaneie, Sessho (regent), and was the mother of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>重複削除用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正三位・参議。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Sangi (a councilor) at the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Sangi (a councilor) at the rank of Shosanmi (Senior 3rd Rank).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Sangi (a councilor) at the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>朱雀上皇の蔵人から天暦7年（953年）に六位蔵人となり、天徳 (日本)元年（957年）に36歳で従五位下に叙爵されて父と同じ摂津守となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 953, he became Rokui no kurodo (kurodo with the sixth rank) in 953 from Kurodo (a chamberlain) for retired Emperor Suzaku, and awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) at the age of 36, assuming Settsu no kami (a governor of Settsu Province) the same post as his father&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 953, he became Rokui no kurodo (kurodo, 6th rank) in 953 from Kurodo (chamberlain) for retired Emperor Suzaku, and was awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior 5th Rank, Lower Grade) at the age of thirty-six, assuming Settsu no kami (a governor of Settsu Province) the same post as his father&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 953, he became Rokui no kurodo (kurodo, Sixth rank) from Kurodo (chamberlain) for retired Emperor Suzaku, and was awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) at the age of thirty-six in 957, assuming Settsu no kami (a governor of Settsu Province) the same post as his father&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>in 953重複削除用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>応和2年（962年）には従五位上大和国守となり、安和元年（968年）に正五位下に叙され、翌年に春宮権大進に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to kokushu (a governor) of Yamato Province at the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) in 962, was awarded the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 968, and then was appointed to togu-gonnodaishin (an official post of the imperial prince-related institute called &quot;togubo&quot;) in the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to kokushu (governor) of Yamato Province at the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior 5th Rank, Upper Grade) in 962, was awarded the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior 5th Rank, Lower Grade) in 968, and then was appointed to togu-gonnodaishin (an official post of the imperial prince-related institute called &quot;togubo&quot;) the next year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to kokushu (governor) of Yamato Province at the rank of Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) in 962, was awarded the rank of Shogoinoge (Senior fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 968, and then was appointed to togu-gonnodaishin (an official post of the imperial prince-related institute called &quot;togubo&quot;) the next year.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>円融天皇の即位による功労で従四位下になり、相模国守・大和国守を経て、永観2年（984年）に春宮亮となり、翌年に従四位上に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Enyu ascended the throne, he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade) for his contribution to the enthronement, became Togu no suke (an assistant master in the Crown Prince&apos;s quarters) in 984 after assuming kokushu of Sagami Province and kokushu of Yamato Province, and then was awarded the rank of Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Enyu ascended the throne, he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior 4th Rank, Lower Grade) for his contribution to the enthronement, became Togu no suke (an assistant master in the Crown Prince&apos;s quarters) in 984 after assuming kokushu of Sagami Province and kokushu of Yamato Province, and then was awarded the rank of Jushiijo (Junior 4th Rank, Upper Grade) in the next year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Enyu ascended the throne, he was awarded Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) for his contribution to the enthronement, became Togu no suke (an assistant master in the Crown Prince&apos;s quarters) in 984 after assuming kokushu of Sagami Province and kokushu of Yamato Province, and then was awarded the rank of Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in the next year.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>寛和の変とともに蔵人頭・修理権大夫になり、一条天皇即位の功労で正四位上に叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Kanwa incident occurred, he became Kurodo no to (the head chamberlain) and Shuri gon no daibu (a provisional master in the office of palace repairs), and was awarded the rank of Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade) for his contribution to the enthronement of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kanwa incident occurred, he became Kurodo no to (the head chamberlain) and Shuri gon no daibu (a provisional master in the office of palace repairs), and was awarded the rank of Shoshiinojo (Senior 4th Rank Upper Grade) for his contribution to the enthronement of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kanwa incident occurred, he became Kurodo no to (the head chamberlain) and Shuri gon no daibu (a provisional master in the office of palace repairs), and was awarded the rank of Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade) for his contribution to the enthronement of Emperor Ichijo.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>義兄・藤原兼家の引き立てで、新帝の外戚として兼家の子供たちに次ぐ昇進を遂げ、永延元年（987年）に参議に任命され公卿に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Receiving favors of FUJIWARA no Kaneie, his elder bother-in-law, he was promoted next to Kaneie&apos;s children as a maternal relative of the new emperor, being appointed to Sangi (a councilor) and becoming a kugyo in 987.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Receiving favors from FUJIWARA no Kaneie, his elder bother-in-law, he was promoted next to Kaneie&apos;s children as a maternal relative of the new emperor, being appointed to Sangi (a councilor) and becoming a kugyo in 987.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Receiving favors from FUJIWARA no Kaneie, his elder bother-in-law, he was promoted next to Kaneie&apos;s children as a maternal relative of the new emperor, being appointed to Sangi (a councilor) and becoming a kugyo in 987.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後も、永祚 (日本)元年（989年）に従三位、正暦2年（991年）に正三位に叙されたが、正三位参議兼修理権大夫在任中に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after that, he was awarded the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 989 and Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 991, but died while he assumed Sangi and Shuri gon no daibu at the rank of Shosanmi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after that, he was awarded the rank of Jusanmi (Junior 3rd Rank) in 989 and Shosanmi (Senior 3rd Rank) in 991, but died while he assumed Sangi and Shuri gon no daibu at the rank of Shosanmi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after that, he was awarded the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in 989 and Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) in 991, but died while he assumed Sangi and Shuri gon no daibu at the rank of Shosanmi.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Andee(id:20421), YOSHI438(id:174755), Snap55(id:89773), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>