<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>六角政頼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masayori ROKKAKU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masayori ROKKAKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masayori ROKKAKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>六角政頼（ろっかくまさより、生没年不詳）は、室町時代後期の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masayori ROKKAKU (it is unknown when he was born and when he was died) lived in the latter half of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masayori ROKKAKU (dates of birth and death unknown) lived in the latter half of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Revised for brevity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masayori ROKKAKU (dates of birth and death unknown) lived in the latter half of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>六角久頼の子であり、六角高頼の父と推定される人物（異説では高頼当人である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Hisayori ROKKAKU and is considered to have been the father of Takayori ROKKAKU (or Takayori himself according to a theory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Hisayori ROKKAKU and is considered to have been the father of Takayori ROKKAKU (one theory has it that he was Takayori himself).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Hisayori ROKKAKU and is considered to have been the father of Takayori ROKKAKU (one theory has it that he was Takayori himself).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>四郎？。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiro (a name)?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He may have used the name Shiro</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He may have used the name Shiro.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名は亀寿又は亀寿丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Kameju or Kamejumaru in his younger days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Kameju or Kamejumaru in his younger days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Kameju or Kamejumaru in his younger days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ただし、成人後の名前は確定されておらず、政勝、高貞ともされ、はっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his name in the adulthood is not fixed, and is said to have been Masakatsu or Takasada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his adult name is not fixed, and is said to have been Masakatsu or Takasada.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his adult name is not fixed, and is said to have been Masakatsu or Takasada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>近江国守護。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assumed shugo (provincial constable) of Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the shugo (governor) of Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the shugo (governor) of Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>父の久頼の没後、従兄弟の六角政尭（六角時綱の子）の後見を受けるものの、のちに幕府の思惑と政尭の策略により守護職を剥奪される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father, Hisayori, died, he was placed in the custody of Masataka ROKKAKU (a son of Tokitsuna ROKKAKU), his cousin, but later, his shugo post was deprived due to intentions of the bakufu and Masataka&apos;s ploys.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his father, Hisayori, died, he was placed in the custody of his cousin, Masataka ROKKAKU (a son of Tokitsuna ROKKAKU), but was later stripped of his shugo post due to the shogunate&apos;s plans and Masataka&apos;s ploys.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father, Hisayori, died, he was placed in the custody of his cousin, Masataka ROKKAKU (a son of Tokitsuna ROKKAKU), but was later stripped of his shugo post due to the shogunate&apos;s plans and Masataka&apos;s ploys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>のち政尭の失脚により守護に返り咲いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Masataka fell from the power and Masayori regained the shugo post.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, with Masataka&apos;s fall from power, Masayori regained his shugo post and</e>
<cmt>Revised to remake one sentence with F13</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, with Masataka&apos;s fall from power, Masayori regained his shugo post.</e>
<cmt>文末がピリオドで終わるよう、原文/訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、まもなく応仁の乱が勃発し、亀寿（政頼）は西軍に所属した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, soon the Onin War (the war in the Onin era) started, and Kameju (Masayori) belonged to the western group in the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">with the outbreak of the Onin War not long after, Kameju (Masayori) joined the Western Army.</e>
<cmt>Revised to remake one sentence with F12</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with the outbreak of the Onin War not long after, Kameju (Masayori) joined the Western Army.</e>
<cmt>冒頭にHowever追加原文の冒頭を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>戦乱により領内も混乱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Affected by the war, the state of the territories became chaotic as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the war, the situation in the domains grew chaotic and</e>
<cmt>Revised to remake one sentence with F15</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the war, the situation in the domains grew chaotic.</e>
<cmt>文末がピリオドで終わるよう、原文/訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>六角氏も、北近江の京極氏の力を背景に政尭、政信（六角持綱の子）が東軍につくなど分裂状態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The power of the Rokkaku clan was also divided, for example, with Masataka and Masanobu (a son of Mochitsuna ROKKAKU) belonging to the eastern group.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Rokkaku Clan became divided, with Masataka and Masanobu (a son of Mochitsuna ROKKAKU), supported by the Kyogoku Clan of northern Omi, joining the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt>Revised to remake one sentence with F14</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rokkaku clan became divided, with Masataka and Masanobu (a son of Mochitsuna ROKKAKU), supported by the Kyogoku clan of northern Omi, joining the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt>文頭の頭文字を大文字に変更、Clan→clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一族の六角六郎や伊庭氏、山内氏の協力もあり亀寿（政頼）は1471年に政尭を自刃させるなど抗争に勝ち抜き六角氏の家督を確保した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Getting cooperation of Rokuro ROKKAKU of his clan, of the Iba clan and of the Yamanouchi clan as well, he wan the battle, for example, making Masataka kill himself in 1471, and captured the head position of the Rokkaku clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the cooperation of Rokuro ROKKAKU of his clan, of the Iba Clan and of the Yamanouchi Clan as well, he won the battle, making Masataka kill himself in 1471, and secured the headship of the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the cooperation of Rokuro ROKKAKU of his clan, of the Iba clan and of the Yamanouchi clan as well, he won the battle, making Masataka kill himself in 1471, and secured the headship of the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clanに統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>応仁の乱終了後に六角氏が将軍足利義尚の討伐を受けた際には、子の高頼と共に伊賀に逃れるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he fled to Iga together with his son, Takayori, when the Rokkaku clan was chased by Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA after the Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he fled to Iga together with his son, Takayori, when the Rokkaku clan was chased by Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA after the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he fled to Iga together with his son, Takayori, when the Rokkaku clan was chased by Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA after the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>室町時代後期から戦国時代 (日本)初期の六角氏の系図ははっきりしない部分が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many parts, in the later years of the Muromachi period to the early Sengoku period (period of warring states), of the family tree of the Rokkaku clan are unclear.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many parts of the Rokkaku Clan family tree of the latter years of the Muromachi period to the early Sengoku (Warring States) period are unclear.</e>
<cmt>Word orderRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many parts of the Rokkaku clan family tree of the latter years of the Muromachi period to the early Sengoku (Warring States) period are unclear.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clanに統一文末がピリオドで終わるよう、原文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そのため、応仁の乱の際に活動した「六角亀寿」（六角亀寿丸）と記録のある人物が誰に比定されるかは諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there are many theories concerning who the person recorded as Kameju ROKKAKU (Kamejumaru ROKKAKU), having been active in the Onin War, was actually.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there are many theories concerning who the person recorded as Kameju ROKKAKU (Kamejumaru ROKKAKU), who was active during the Onin War, actually was.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarityWord order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there are many theories concerning who the person recorded as Kameju ROKKAKU (Kamejumaru ROKKAKU), who was active during the Onin War, actually was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>『応仁記』においては「六角四郎高頼」という名前がみえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Rokkaku Shiro Takayori is found in &quot;Oninki (The Record of the Onin War).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Rokkaku Shiro Takayori is found in &quot;Oninki (The Record of the Onin War)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Revised punctuation to remake one sentence with F22</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of &apos;Rokkaku Shiro Takayori&apos; is found in &quot;Oninki&quot; (The Record of the Onin War).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加/位置修正、余分なピリオド消去文末がピリオドで終わるよう、原文/訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>通説では高頼の生年は久頼の没後である（ただし、高頼の生年は久頼の生前とする説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also commonly said that Takayori was born after Hisayori died (there is also the theory in which Takayori was born before Hisayori died).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and it is commonly believed that Takayori was born after Hisayori died (though there is also a theory that he was born before Hisayori died).</e>
<cmt>Revised to remake one sentence with F21</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly believed that Takayori was born after Hisayori died (though there is also a theory that he was born before Hisayori died).</e>
<cmt>文頭のand削除、itの頭文字を大文字に変更文末がピリオドで終わるよう、原文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そのため、久頼の子で高頼の父に当たる人物のことであると推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is supposed that he might be a person who was a son of Hiwayori and the father of Takayori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is supposed that he might be a son of Hisayori and the father of Takayori.</e>
<cmt>Revised for claritySpelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is supposed that he might be a son of Hisayori and the father of Takayori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、義尚に討伐を受けた際に伊賀に逃れたのは高頼とその嫡男の六角氏綱ともされることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it is sometimes said that the persons who were chased by Yoshihisa and fled to Iga were Takayori and his heir, Ujitsuna ROKKAKU.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it is sometimes said that the persons who were chased by Yoshihisa and fled to Iga were Takayori and his heir, Ujitsuna ROKKAKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it is sometimes said that the persons who were chased by Yoshihisa and fled to Iga were Takayori and his heir, Ujitsuna ROKKAKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかしながら、氏頼は当時まだ出生しておらず不自然である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ujiyori had not been born at that time and the theory is unantural.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this is questionable since Ujiyori had not been born at that time and</e>
<cmt>Revised to remake one sentence with F26</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this is questionable since Ujiyori had not been born at that time.</e>
<cmt>文末がピリオドで終わるよう、原文/訳文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そのため、高頼と共に伊賀に逃れたのは高頼の父の政頼（政勝）とする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there is also the theory insisting that the person who fled to Iga together with Takayori was his father, Masayori (Masakatsu).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">therefore, there is also a theory that the person who fled to Iga together with Takayori was his father, Masayori (Masakatsu).</e>
<cmt>Revised to remake one sentence with F25</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there is also a theory that the person who fled to Iga together with Takayori was his father, Masayori (Masakatsu).</e>
<cmt>文頭の頭文字を大文字に変更原文の冒頭を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ktr(id:30468), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>