<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>井上井月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seigetsu INOUE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seigetsu INOUE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seigetsu INOUE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>井上 井月（いのうえ せいげつ、文政5年（1822年）？ - 明治20年2月16日 (旧暦)（1887年3月10日））は、日本の江戸時代末期から明治時代初期の俳人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seigetsu INOUE (born in 1822 [?] and died on February 16, 1887) was a haiku poet in the end of the Edo period and the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seigetsu INOUE (born in 1822 [?] and died on February 16, 1887) was a haiku poet during the end of the Edo period and the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seigetsu INOUE (c. 1822 - March 10, 1887) was a haiku poet during the end of the Edo period and the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>生年にはcircaを用い、没年は西暦に改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本名は一説に井上克三（いのうえかつぞう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some say his real name was Katsuzo INOUE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some say his real name was Katsuzo INOUE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some say his real name was Katsuzo INOUE.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>別号に柳の家井月。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name was Seigetsu YANAGINOYA</e>
<cmt>「柳の家」の読み方不明のため、YANAGINOYA　としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name was Seigetsu YANAGINOYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another name was Seigetsu YANAGINOYA.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>信州南信地方を中心に活動し、放浪と漂泊を主題とした俳句を詠み続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active mainly in the southern part of Shinshu region and continued to make hike whose subjects were wandering and roaming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active mainly in the southern part of the Shinshu region and continued to make haiku whose subjects were wandering and roaming.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active mainly in the southern part of the Shinshu region and continued to make haiku whose subjects were wandering and roaming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その作品は、後世の芥川龍之介や種田山頭火をはじめ、つげ義春などに影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His work had influence on other later poets and novelists such as Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA, Santoka TANEDA and Yoshiharu TSUGE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His work influenced other later poets and novelists such as Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA, Santoka TANEDA and Yoshiharu TSUGE.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His work influenced other later poets and novelists such as Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA, Santoka TANEDA and Yoshiharu TSUGE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>放浪俳人井月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A wandering haiku poet, Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wandering haiku poet, Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wandering haiku poet, Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>井月は文政5年（1822年）､越後の越後長岡藩生まれと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is estimated he was born in 1822 in the Echigo-Nagaoka Domain, Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is estimated he was born in 1822 in the Echigo-Nagaoka Domain, Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is estimated he was born in 1822 in the Echigo-Nagaoka Domain, Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>井月の少年期から30代半ばまでの行状は全く不明であるが、巷説によると天保10年（1839年）には一旦江戸に出ているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It remains unknown how he was doing from his boyhood to his mid-thirties, but rumor has it that he went to Edo in 1839.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It remains unknown what he was doing from his boyhood to his mid-thirties, but rumor has it that he went to Edo in 1839.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It remains unknown what he was doing from his boyhood to his mid-thirties, but rumor has it that he once went to Edo in 1839.</e>
<cmt>「一旦」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>嘉永5年（1852年）に長野にて版行された、吉村木鵞の母の追悼集に、井月の発句「乾く間もなく秋暮れぬ露の袖」が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His hike &apos;Kawakumamonaku akikurenu tsuyunosode&apos; (In fall, darkness comes quickly after sunset, so, the laundry does not dry completely)&apos; appeared in a memorial collection tribute to MOKUGA Yoshimura&apos;s mother published in 1852 in Nagano.</e>
<cmt>俳句、「乾く間もなく秋暮れぬ露の袖」→Kawakumamonaku akikurenu tsuyunosode&apos; (In fall, darkness comes quickly after sunset, so, the laundry does not dry completely) と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His haiku &apos;Kawakumamonaku akikurenu tsuyunosode&apos; (In fall, darkness comes quickly after sunset, so, the laundry does not dry completely)&apos; appeared in a memorial collection tribute to MOKUGA Yoshimura&apos;s mother published in 1852 in Nagano.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His haiku &apos;Kawakumamonaku akikurenu tsuyunosode&apos; (In fall, darkness comes quickly after sunset, so, the laundry does not dry completely)&apos; appeared in a memorial collection tribute to Mokuga YOSHIMURA&apos;s mother published in 1852 in Nagano.</e>
<cmt>MOKUGA Yoshimura↓Mokuga YOSHIMURA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、翌年、同じく長野で開板された吉村木鵞編纂の句集『きせ綿』に、「稲妻や網にこたへし魚の影」の句が採られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in 1853, his hike &apos;Inazumaya aminikotaeshi sakananokage&apos; (Lightening flashed on a net in which fish was caught) appeared in &quot;Kisewata&quot;, a hike collection which was compiled by Mokuga YOSHIMURA and published in Nagano.</e>
<cmt>俳句、「稲妻や網にこたへし魚の影」→Inazumaya aminikotaeshi sakananokage&apos; (Lightening flashed on a net in which fish was caught) と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in 1853, his haiku &apos;Inazumaya aminikotaeshi sakananokage&apos; (Lightening flashed on a net in which fish was caught) appeared in &quot;Kisewata,&quot; a haiku collection compiled by Mokuga YOSHIMURA and published in Nagano.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in 1853, his haiku &apos;Inazumaya aminikotaeshi sakananokage&apos; (Lightening flashed on a net in which fish was caught) appeared in &quot;Kisewata,&quot; a haiku collection compiled by Mokuga YOSHIMURA and published in Nagano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>従って、この頃には俳人として活動していたと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is presumed that he was active as a haiku poet around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is presumed that he was active as a haiku poet around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is presumed that he was active as a haiku poet around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>安政5年（1858年）ごろ、30代後半の壮年であった井月は南信地方を訪れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1858, he visited the southern part of Nagano Prefecture in his late thirtieth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 1858, he visited the southern part of Nagano Prefecture in his late thirties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 1858, he visited the southern part of Nagano Prefecture in his late thirties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>以来約30年の間、死去するまで上伊那を中心に放浪生活を送り続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, he had been wondering around Kamiina Province until he died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, he had been wondering around Kamiina Province until he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, he had been wandering around Kamiina region until he died.</e>
<cmt>wondering→wanderingKamiina Province→Kamiina region</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>元来、「多少好学の風があり、風流風雅を嗜む傾き」のある土地であったため、俳諧の師匠として井月は伊那谷の人士に歓迎された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that place, some local people had a love of learning and embraced elegant and sophisticated atmosphere, so, people in upper class in Inadani welcomed Seigetsu as a haikai instructor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that place, some local people had a love of learning and embraced an elegant and sophisticated atmosphere, so, people in the upper class in Inadani welcomed Seigetsu as a haiku instructor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that place where &apos;some local people had a love of learning and embraced an elegant and sophisticated atmosphere&apos;, people in the upper class in Inadani welcomed Seigetsu as a haiku instructor.</e>
<cmt>引用符を補完しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>こうして井月は伊那谷の趣味人たちに発句の手ほどきをしたり、連句の席を持ったり、詩文を揮毫すた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, he taught these people how to make haiku, held some meetings where people made a series of haiku together, and composed poems or passages.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, he taught these people how to write haiku, held some meetings where people made a series of haiku together, and composed poems or passages.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, he taught these people how to write haiku, held some meetings where people made a series of haiku together, and composed poems or passages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そして、その見返りとして、酒食や宿、いくばくかの金銭などの接待を受けつつ、南信州一帯を放浪した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In turn, he received sake (Japanese alcohol), accommodation and some money and with these treatments, he was wandering around the whole area of the southern part of Shinshu region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In turn, he received sake (Japanese alcohol), accommodation and some money, and with this treatment, he was able to wander around the whole area of the southern part of the Shinshu region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In turn, he received sake (Japanese alcohol), meals, accommodation and some money, and with this treatment, he was able to wander around the whole area of the southern part of the Shinshu region.</e>
<cmt>mealsを追加しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>井月は「典型的な酒仙の面影が髣髴とする」ほどの酒好きであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He loved drinking sake like &apos;a typical man who experiences transcendent ecstasy in drink&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He loved drinking sake like &apos;a typical man who experiences transcendent ecstasy in drink.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He loved drinking sake like &apos;a typical man who experiences transcendent ecstasy in drink.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのため、「人の顔さえ見れば酒を勧める」、悠長な土地柄であった伊那谷は、ほとんど金銭を持たず、蓄えも無かった井月にとって、いつでも酒の相伴にあずかることの出来る、魅力的な土地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Inadani was an attractive place for Seigetsu, who had little money and no savings and was entertained with sake for free, because local residents in Inadani were so easygoing and carefree that &apos;they offered sake to anybody&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Inadani was an attractive place for Seigetsu, who had little money and no savings and was entertained with sake for free, because local residents in Inadani were so easygoing and carefree that &apos;they offered sake to anybody.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Inadani was an attractive place for Seigetsu, who had little money and no savings and was entertained with sake for free, because local residents in Inadani were so easygoing and carefree that &apos;they offered sake to anybody.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>体中シラミだらけで、直ぐに泥酔しては寝小便をたれたという井月を、土地の女性や子供たちは「乞食井月」と呼んで忌避した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became lousy, easily drank himself into a stupor and wetted his bed, so, local women and children hated and kept him away, calling him &apos;a beggar Seigetsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became lousy, easily drank himself into a stupor and wet his bed, so, local women and children hated him and kept him away, calling him &apos;a beggar Seigetsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became lousy, easily drank himself into a stupor and wet his bed, so, local women and children hated him and kept him away, calling him &apos;a beggar Seigetsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、俳句を趣味とする富裕層の男性たちが井月を優遇し、中には弟子として師事するものもいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, wealthy men who liked to make haiku gave favorable treatment to him and some of them had Seigetsu as their teacher.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, wealthy men who liked to write haiku gave favorable treatment to him and some of them had Seigetsu as their teacher.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, wealthy men who liked to write haiku gave favorable treatment to him and some of them had Seigetsu as their teacher.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>文久3年（1863年）5月、高遠藩の当時の家老・岡村菊叟と面会し、句集『越後獅子』の序文を乞う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, 1863, he met the then chief retainer of the Takato Domain, kikuso OKAMURA and asked him to write a foreword to a collection of haiku, &quot;Echigo shishi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, 1863, he met the then chief retainer of the Takato Domain, kikuso OKAMURA and asked him to write a foreword to a collection of haiku, &quot;Echigo shishi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, 1863, he met the then chief retainer of the Takato Domain, Kikuso OKAMURA and asked him to write a foreword to a collection of haiku, &quot;Echigo shishi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>kikuso→Kikuso</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>『越後獅子』は井月が京都、江戸、大阪をはじめ、各国の俳人の発句を集めた句集であり、書名は菊叟の命名による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Echigo shishi&quot;was a collection of hokku that Seigetsu selected from various haiku made by haiku poets across from Japan such as Kyoto, Edo and Osaka, and compiled them and then, Kikuso gave it a title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Echigo shishi&quot;was a collection of hokku that Seigetsu selected from various haiku made by haiku poets across from Japan such as Kyoto, Edo and Osaka, and compiled them and then, Kikuso gave it a title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Echigo shishi&quot;was a collection of hokku that Seigetsu selected from various haiku made by haiku poets across from Japan such as Kyoto, Edo and Osaka, and compiled them and then, Kikuso gave it a title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、この序文は、井月が長岡出身と自称していたことを記した最初の記録となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This foreword was the first record which showed that Seigetsu said he was from Nagaoka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This foreword was the first record which showed that Seigetsu said he was from Nagaoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This foreword was the first record which showed that Seigetsu said he was from Nagaoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>元治元年（1864年）、善光寺宝勝院の梅塘をたずね、100日間ほど滞在し、『家つと集』を編集する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, he visited Baito of Hosho-in of Zenko-ji Temple, stayed there for 100 days and compiled &quot;Ietsuto shu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, he visited Baito of Hosho-in of Zenko-ji Temple, stayed there for 100 days and compiled &quot;Ietsuto shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, he visited Baito of Hosho-in of Zenko-ji Temple, stayed there for around 100 days and compiled &quot;Ietsuto shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「ほど」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>明治2年（1869年）、富県村（現伊那市）の日枝神社の奉納額を揮毫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1869, he wrote with a brush honogaku (votive tablet) of Hie-jinja Shrine in Tomigata-mura (present-day Ina City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1869, he wrote with a brush honogaku (votive tablet) of Hie-jinja Shrine in Tomigata-mura (present-day Ina City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1869, he wrote honogaku (votive tablet) with a brush for Hie-jinja Shrine in Tomigata-mura (present-day Ina City).</e>
<cmt>語順を変えました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>翌年には東春近村の五社神社、西春近村の地蔵堂の奉納額を揮毫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year, he wrote with brush honogaku of Gosha-jinja Shrine in Higashi haruchika-mura and Jizodo in Nishi haruchika-mura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, he wrote with brush honogaku of Gosha-jinja Shrine in Higashi haruchika-mura and Jizodo in Nishi haruchika-mura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, he wrote honogaku with brush for Gosha-jinja Shrine in Higashi haruchika-mura and for Jizodo in Nishi haruchika-mura.</e>
<cmt>語順を変えました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この後も、たびたび社寺の奉納額を手がけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After writing these two honogaku, he often wrote with brush other honogaku of temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After writing these two honogaku, he often wrote with a brush other honogaku of temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After writing these two honogaku, he often wrote other honogaku for temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>with a brushを削除しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>明治5年（1872年）9月、伊那村にて「柳廼舎送別書画展覧会」が開催され、出席者は113名を数えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, 1872, &apos;Ryunaisha soubetsu shoga tenrankai&apos; (Ryunaisha farewell calligraphy and paintings exhibition) was held in Ina-mura and 113 people came to see it.</e>
<cmt>「柳廼舎」の読み方不明のため、「Ryunaisha」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, 1872, &apos;Ryunaisha soubetsu shoga tenrankai&apos; (Ryunaisha farewell calligraphy and paintings exhibition) was held in Ina-mura and 113 people came to see it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, 1872, &apos;Yanaginoya soubetsu shoga tenrankai&apos; (Yanaginoya farewell calligraphy and paintings exhibition) was held in Ina-mura and 113 people came to see it.</e>
<cmt>「廼舎」の読みは「のや」ですので、6列に倣って訳出しましたhttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=%E3%81%97%E3%81%AE%E3%81%B6&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;index=10113308283100&amp;pagenum=11</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>明治7年（1874年）、美篶村（現伊那市）の橋爪玉斎と句画を合作している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1874, he collaborated with Gyokusai HASHIZUME coming from Misuzu-mura (present-day Ina City) on haiku and paintings.</e>
<cmt>「橋爪玉斎」は読み方不明のため「Gyokusai HASHIZUME」 としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1874, he collaborated with Gyokusai HASHIZUME coming from Misuzu-mura (present-day Ina City) on haiku and paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1874, he collaborated with Gyokusai HASHIZUME coming from Misuzu-mura (present-day Ina City) on haiku and paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>明治9年（1876年）9月、伊那町の唐木菊園のもとで、「菊詠集序」を執筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, 1876, he wrote &apos;Kiku eishujo&apos;, when he was taken care of by Kikuen KARAKI in Ina-cho.</e>
<cmt>「唐木菊園」、「菊詠集序」は読み方不明のため、それぞれ「Kikuen KARAKI」、「Kiku eishujo」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, 1876, he wrote &apos;Kiku eishujo&apos;, while he was taken care of by Kikuen KARAKI in Ina-cho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, 1876, he wrote &apos;Kiku eishujo&apos;, while he was taken care of by Kikuen KARAKI in Ina-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="30">
<j>明治12年（1879年）3月、上水内郡（現中条村）の久保田盛斎のもとで、「俳諧正風起證」を執筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, 1879, he wrote &apos;Haikai seifukito&apos;, when he was taken care of by Seisai KUBOTA in Kamiminochi-gun (present-day Nakajyo-mura).</e>
<cmt>「久保田盛斎」、「俳諧正風起證」はそれぞれ読み方不明のため、 「Seisai KUBOTA」、 「&apos;Haikai seifukito&apos;」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, 1879, he wrote &apos;Haikai seifukito,&apos; when he was being taken care of by Seisai KUBOTA in Kamiminochi-gun (present-day Nakajyo-mura).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, 1879, he wrote &apos;Haikai seifukito,&apos; when he was being taken care of by Seisai KUBOTA in Kamiminochi-gun (present-day Nakajyo-mura).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この頃、当地に庵を立てて定住しようと試みたことが久保田宛の書簡から読み取れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His letter sent to KUBOTA showed that he tried to build a thatched cottage and settle there around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His letter sent to KUBOTA showed that he tried to build a thatched cottage and settle there around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His letter sent to KUBOTA showed that he tried to build a thatched cottage and settle there around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>同書簡中には、新しい庵に移住するため、長岡で戸籍を取る必要を述べているが、これも井月の出自の論拠となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this letter, he also said that he needed to have a family register in Nagaoka in order to move to the new cottage, which shows another evidence for his birthplace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this letter, he also said that he needed to have a family register in Nagaoka in order to move to the new cottage, which shows other evidence for his birthplace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this letter, he also said that he needed to have a family register in Nagaoka in order to move to the new cottage, which shows other evidence for his birthplace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、手続き上に問題があり、定住は叶わず、南信州に帰還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were some problems about the necessary procedures, so, he gave up settling and went back to the southern part of Shinshu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were some problems about the necessary procedures, so, he gave up settling and went back to the southern part of the Shinshu region.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were some problems about the necessary procedures, so, he gave up settling and went back to the southern part of the Shinshu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="34">
<j>明治18年（1885年）秋ごろ、句集『余波の水茎（なごりのみづぐき）』を刊行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the autumn in 1885, he published a collection of haiku, &quot;Nagori no mizuguki&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the autumn in 1885, he published a collection of haiku, &quot;Nagori no mizuguki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the autumn in 1885, he published a collection of haiku, &quot;Nagori no mizuguki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>本書は、井月が集めた諸家の発句をまとめたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a collection of haiku compiled by Seigetsu who selected hokku made by various haiku poets.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a collection of haiku compiled by Seigetsu who selected hokku made by various haiku poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a collection of haiku compiled by Seigetsu who selected hokku made by various haiku poets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>そして、井月の弟子であった美篶村の塩原梅関（本名折治）が開板したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, his disciple, Baiseki SHIOBARA (his real name was Setsuji) coming from Misuzu-mura published this collection of haiku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　　「塩原梅関（本名折治）」は読み方不明のため、「Baiseki SHIOBARA (his real name was Setsuji)」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, his disciple, Baiseki SHIOBARA (his real name was Setsuji) coming from Misuzu-mura published this collection of haiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, his disciple, Baiseki SHIOBARA (his real name was Setsuji) coming from Misuzu-mura published this collection of haiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>本書の跋として井月は、後に代表句と評される「落栗の座を定むるや窪溜り」を、「柳の家」の署名とともに残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a postscript, he made haiku, &apos;Ochigurino zawosadamuruya kubodamari&apos; (I was like a rolling chestnut, because I didn&apos;t settle in a place, but now, I&apos;m trying to settle at Otakubo), which was considered as one of his most famous haiku with his signature, &apos;Yanagino ya&apos;.</e>
<cmt>俳句「落栗の座を定むるや窪溜り」を、http://www.valley.ne.jp/~zaza/seigetu.htmを参考に、「&apos;Ochigurino zawosadamuruya kubodamari&apos; (I was like a rolling chestnut, because I didn&apos;t settle in a place, but now, I&apos;m trying to settle at Otakubo)」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a postscript, he made haiku, &apos;Ochigurino zawosadamuruya kubodamari&apos; (I was like a rolling chestnut, because I didn&apos;t settle down in one place, but now, I&apos;m trying to settle in Otakubo), which was considered as one of his most famous haiku with his signature, &apos;Yanagino ya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a postscript, he made haiku, &apos;Ochigurino zawosadamuruya kubodamari&apos; (I was like a rolling chestnut, because I didn&apos;t settle down in one place, but now, I&apos;m trying to settle in Otakubo), which was considered as one of his most famous haiku with his signature, &apos;Yanagino ya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>同年、井月の健康を案じた塩原梅関の取り計らいにより塩原家に入籍し、塩原清助と名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he entered in Baikan SHIOBARA&apos;s family register through an arrangement of Baikan who was worried about Seigetsu&apos;s health and then, he called himself Seisuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he was entered into Baikan SHIOBARA&apos;s family register through an arrangement of Baikan who was worried about Seigetsu&apos;s health and then, he called himself Seisuke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he was entered into Baikan SHIOBARA&apos;s family register through an arrangement of Baikan who was worried about Seigetsu&apos;s health and then, he called himself Seisuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="39">
<j>明治19年（1886年）12月末ごろ、伊那村にて病のため道に行き倒れているのを発見される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the end of December, 1886, he was found falling on the street because of sickness in Ina-mura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the end of December, 1886, he was found falling on the street because of sickness in Ina-mura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the end of December, 1886, he was found falling on the street because of sickness in Ina-mura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>塩原家に運び込まれ看病を受けるが、翌年の明治20年（1887年）2月16日 (旧暦)に、66歳にて没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was carried to and attended by the Shiobara family, but the next year, on February 16, 1887, he died at the age of 66.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was carried to and attended by the Shiobara family, but the next year, on February 16, 1887, he died at the age of sixty-six.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was carried to and attended by the Shiobara family, but the next year, on February 16, 1887, he died at the age of sixty-six.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>大正9年（1920年）、塩原家にて三十三回忌が営まれ、句碑が建てられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1920, a memorial service for the thirty-second anniversary of his death was held by the Shiobara family and a stone tablet inscribed with a haiku was built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1920, a memorial service for the thirty-second anniversary of his death was held by the Shiobara family and a stone tablet inscribed with haiku was built.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1920, a memorial service for the thirty-third anniversary of his death was held by the Shiobara family and a stone tablet inscribed with haiku was built.</e>
<cmt>thirty-second→thirty-third</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Birth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Place of Origin</e>
<cmt>定訳に改めました</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>井月の出自については諸説あるが、ほとんど不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various views about his birth, but it has remained unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various views about his birth, but it remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various views about his place of origin, but it remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>定訳に改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>没年から逆算すると文政5年（1822年）生まれとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you count the year of his death backward, the year of his birth will be 1822.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If you count the year of his death backward, the year of his birth will be 1822.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If you count the year of his death backward, the year of his birth will be 1822.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>「本名が井上克三であり、越後長岡藩出身である」ことを、高遠藩家老の岡村菊叟に告げているが、長岡藩の文書が現存していないため確定されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He told the chief retainer of the Takato Domain, Kikuso OKAMURA that his real name was Katsuzo INOUE and he was born in the Echigo-Nagaoka Domain, but it has not been determined because it was not mentioned in any document of the Nagaoka Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He told the chief retainer of the Takato Domain, Kikuso OKAMURA that his real name was Katsuzo INOUE and he was born in the Echigo-Nagaoka Domain, but it has not been determined because it was not mentioned in any document of the Nagaoka Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He told the chief retainer of the Takato Domain, Kikuso OKAMURA that his real name was Katsuzo INOUE and he was born in the Echigo-Nagaoka Domain, but it has not been determined because it was not mentioned in any document of the Nagaoka Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>他には、世話になった酒屋への書簡一通に「井上克三」との署名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, there was his signature, &apos;Seigetsu INOUE&apos; in a letter sent to a sake shop in which he was under the care.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there was his signature, &apos;Seigetsu INOUE&apos; in a letter sent to a sake shop where he was under care.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there was his signature, &apos;Katsuzo INOUE&apos; in a letter sent to a sake shop where he was under care.</e>
<cmt>Seigetsu→Katsuzo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、塩原家に入籍後、義理の娘に婿養子を斡旋するための口上書に「末広侍人井上井月」との自署を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, after he entered in the Shiobara&apos;s family register, he left his signature, &apos;Suehiro Saburaibito Seigetsu INOUE&apos; in verbal note which was designated to help his daughter-in -law find a husband who was able to be adopted by her family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, after he entered in the Shiobara&apos;s family register, he left his signature, &apos;Suehiro Saburaibito Seigetsu INOUE&apos; in verbal note which was designated to help his daughter-in -law find a husband who was able to be adopted by her family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, after he entered in the Shiobara&apos;s family register, he left his signature, &apos;Suehiro Saburaibito Seigetsu INOUE&apos; in verbal note which was designated to help his daughter-in -law find a husband who was able to be adopted by her family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>また、井月の作品の一部に、越後方言に顕著な「イ音」と「エ音」の混同が見られるため、これを越後地方出身の証拠とする論もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, some argue there is evidence that he was born in Echigo region, because in some part of his work, &apos;i sound&apos; and &apos;e sound&apos; were mixed, which was distinctive characteristics in a dialect of Echigo region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, some argue there is evidence that he was born in the Echigo region, because in some part of his work, the &apos;i sound&apos; and &apos;e sound&apos; were mixed, which was distinctive characteristics in the Echigo region dialect.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, some argue there is evidence that he was born in the Echigo region, because in some part of his work, the &apos;i sound&apos; and &apos;e sound&apos; were mixed, which was distinctive characteristics in the Echigo region dialect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>人柄・句柄について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality and Characteristic of his haiku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality and Characteristics of his haiku</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality and Characteristics of Haiku</e>
<cmt>hisを削除しました</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>井月は独特な語彙をよく用いているが、口癖としてもっとも著名なのが「千両千両」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He often used some unique words and the most famous pet phrase of his was &apos;senryo, senryo&apos; (money, money).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He often used some unique words and the most famous pet phrase of his was &apos;senryo, senryo&apos; (money, money).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He often used some unique words and the most famous pet phrase of his was &apos;senryo, senryo&apos; (money, money).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>「謝辞、賞賛詞、賀詞、感嘆詞として使用するは勿論、今日は、左様ならの挨拶まで、唯この千両千両......を以て済ます」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He said, &apos;You can make do with the phrase, &quot;senryo, senryo&quot; in any occasions ranging from gratitude, admiration, congratulate, exclamation to greetings such as hello and good-by&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He said, &apos;You can make do with the phrase, &quot;senryo, senryo&quot; in any occasions ranging from gratitude, admiration, congratulate, exclamation to greetings such as hello and good-by&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said &apos;he could make do with the phrase, &quot;senryo, senryo&quot; in any occasions ranging from gratitude, admiration, congratulation, exclamation to greetings such as hello and good-by.&apos;</e>
<cmt>主語を改めましたcongratulate→congratulation</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>饗応の際に相好を崩して「千両千両」と繰り返したという逸話が、数多く言い伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a lot of anecdotes handed down for generations that when he flatted someone, he repeated, &apos;Senryo, senryo&apos; with his face beaming with smiles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are a lot of anecdotes that have been handed down for generations about when he flattered someone, he repeated, &apos;Senryo, senryo&apos; his face beaming with a smile.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a lot of anecdotes that have been handed down for generations that he repeated &apos;Senryo, senryo&apos; beaming his face with a smile when he was invited to a banquet.</e>
<cmt>一部改めました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>井月の酒好きは当時、伊那谷一帯に知れ渡っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, everybody in the whole area of Inadani knew that he really loved sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, everybody in the whole area of Inadani knew that he really loved sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, everybody in the whole area of Inadani knew that he really loved sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>当然、井月には酒にまつわる句が数多く残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a matter of course, there are a lot of haiku left relating to his great appetite for sake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a matter of course, there are a lot of haiku left relating to his great appetite for sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a matter of course, there are a lot of haiku left relating to his great appetite for sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>秋の新酒を詠んだ「親椀につぎ零（こぼ）したり今年酒」、雪の日に残した「別れ端のきげむ直しや玉子酒」など、季節それぞれの酒を句にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made haiku relating to various sake for every season such as &apos;Oyawan ni tsugikoboshitari kotoshino sake&apos; (I pour this year&apos;s sake into oyawan, which was a bowl designated to be filled with rice offered to the deceased, till it overflowed&apos; for new sake in fall and &apos;Wakarehashi no kigemunaoshiya tamagozake&apos; (Get into a better temper by drinking sake with an egg in it when we say good-by) which was made on a snowy day.</e>
<cmt>俳句、「親椀につぎ零（こぼ）したり今年酒」、「別れ端のきげむ直しや玉子酒」をそれぞれ、&apos;Oyawan ni tsugikoboshitari kotoshino sake&apos; (I pour this year&apos;s sake into oyawan, which was a bowl designated to be filled with rice offerd to the deceased, till it overflowed）、&apos;Wakarehashi no kigemunaoshiya tamagozake&apos; (Get into a better temper by drinking sake with an egg in it when we say good-by) と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote haiku relating to sake for every season such as &apos;Oyawan ni tsugikoboshitari kotoshino sake&apos; (I pour this year&apos;s sake into oyawan, which was a bowl designated to be filled with rice offered to the deceased, till it overflowed&apos; for new sake in fall and &apos;Wakarehashi no kigemunaoshiya tamagozake&apos; (Get into a better temper by drinking sake with an egg in it when we say goodbye) which was made on a snowy day.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote haiku relating to sake for every season such as &apos;Oyawan ni tsugikoboshitari kotoshino sake&apos; (I pour this year&apos;s sake into oyawan, which was a bowl designated to be filled with rice offered to the deceased, till it overflowed) for new sake in fall and &apos;Wakarehashi no kigemunaoshiya tamagozake&apos; (Get into a better temper by drinking sake with an egg in it when we say goodbye) which was made on a snowy day.</e>
<cmt>overflowed&apos;→overflowed)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また、新酒が出来たことを知らせる酒屋の杉玉を指す「さかばやし」を詠み込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also made haiku relating to &apos;sakaya-bashi&apos; meaning sake shop sugitama, which announced that new sake was made.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also wrote haiku relating to &apos;sakaya-bashi&apos; meaning sake shop sugitama, which announced that new sake had been made.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also wrote haiku relating to &apos;sakabayashi&apos; meaning sake shop sugitama (a large ornamental ball made with cedar leaves), which announced that new sake had been made.</e>
<cmt>sakaya-bashi→sakabayashisugitamaに（）を補足しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>「油断なく残暑見舞やさかばやし」「朝寒の馬を待たせたさかばやし」などの句は、幕末から明治初期の伊那谷の一点景を表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yudan naku zanshomimaiya sakabayashi&apos; (Take care in the lingering summer heat, sakabayashi) and &apos;asazamu no umawomataseta sakabayashi&apos; (I kept a horse waiting in the cold morning, sakabayashi) were haiku which showed some views of Inadani from the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate to the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　　俳句、「油断なく残暑見舞やさかばやし」「朝寒の馬を待たせたさかばやし」をそれぞれ、&apos;Yudan naku zanshomimaiya sakabayashi&apos; (Take care in the lingering summer heat, sakabayashi)、&apos;asazamu no umawomataseta sakabayashi&apos; (I kept a horse waiting in the cold morning, sakabayashi) と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yudan naku zanshomimaiya sakabayashi&apos; (Take care in the lingering summer heat, sakabayashi) and &apos;asazamu no umawomataseta sakabayashi&apos; (I kept a horse waiting in the cold morning, sakabayashi) were haiku that showed some views of Inadani from the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate to the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yudan naku zanshomimaiya sakabayashi&apos; (Take care in the lingering summer heat, sakabayashi) and &apos;asazamu no umawomataseta sakabayashi&apos; (I kept a horse waiting in the cold morning, sakabayashi) were haiku that showed some views of Inadani from the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate to the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>井月は接待の酒肴や趣を逐一記録しており、現存する日記などを合わせると、明治16年12月から明治18年4月までの約1年半の、伊那谷における井月の寄食寄宿生活の動向がうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He recorded details of food and drink with which he was entertained and all these records including his existing diary shows how he enjoyed rent-and -food-free life for one and a half years from December, 1883 to April, 1885.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He recorded details of food and drink with which he was entertained and all these records including his existing diary shows how he enjoyed rent-and a free=food life for one and a half years from December, 1883 to April, 1885.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He recorded details of food and drink with which he was entertained and all these records including his existing diary shows the look of his life as a boarder in Inadani for one and a half years from December, 1883 to April, 1885.</e>
<cmt>一部改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>その中で、おのおのの家造りの濁り酒を「手製」と呼んで鍾愛している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These records show that he loved nigori-zake made by each family which he called &apos;hand-made&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These records show that he loved nigori-zake made by each family which he called &apos;hand-made.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These records show that he loved nigori-zake made by each family which he called &apos;hand-made.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>一方で、家の主人がいなかったため家人に粗末に扱われたり、厄介払いをされた場合は、日記に「風情なし」「粗末」、さらには「酒なし」「風呂なし」といちいち書き留める性格であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in case he was treated badly because the host of a family was out or he was got rid of a nuisance, he wrote down details in his diary about his treatment such as &apos;tasteless&apos;, &apos;shabby&apos;, or &apos;no sake&apos;, &apos;no bath&apos;, which shows his finicky characteristic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in case he was treated badly because the host of a family was out or he was got rid of as a nuisance, he wrote down details in his diary about his treatment such as &apos;tasteless,&apos; &apos;shabby,&apos; or &apos;no sake,&apos; &apos;no bath,&apos; which shows his finicky character.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in case he was treated badly because the host of a family was out or he was got rid of as a nuisance, he wrote down details in his diary about his treatment such as &apos;tasteless,&apos; &apos;shabby,&apos; or &apos;no sake,&apos; &apos;no bath,&apos; which shows his finicky character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="59">
<j>また、伊那谷の人士は、俳句作品ばかりでなく、井月の墨書、筆跡も珍重していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local people in the upper class of Inadani valued not only his haiku but also his ink writings and calligraphy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local people in the upper class of Inadani valued not only his haiku but also his ink writings and calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local people in the upper class of Inadani valued not only his haiku but also his ink writings and calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>「芭蕉に似た趣のあるばかりか、本阿弥光悦などのある特殊な作をさへ偲ばせる高雅な書品」（下島勲の評）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His writings are elegant and they even remind people of unique and outstanding work made by Basho MATSUO and Koetsu HONAMI&apos; (comment made by Isao SHINOJIMA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His writings are elegant and they even remind people of unique and outstanding done by Basho MATSUO and Koetsu HONAMI&apos; (comment done by Isao SHINOJIMA).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His writings are elegant and they even remind people of unique and outstanding work done by Basho MATSUO and Koetsu HONAMI&apos; (comment done by Isao SHIMOJIMA).</e>
<cmt>workを補足しましたSHINOJIMA→SHIMOJIMA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>特に井月は松尾芭蕉の『幻住庵記』（約1300字）を暗記していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He especially memorized &quot;Genjuan no ki&quot; (about 1300 words) written by Basho MATSUO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He especially memorized &quot;Genjuan no ki&quot; (about 1300 words) written by Basho MATSUO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He especially memorized &quot;Genjuan no ki&quot; (about 1300 words) written by Basho MATSUO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>ある紺屋の店先で、酒を飲みながら唐紙4枚に何の手本も無く、1000字以上をしたためたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he wrote more than 1000 words of it in four pieces of paper made from hemp or mulberry without any copybook while drinking at a dyer&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he wrote more than 1000 words of it on four pieces of paper made from hemp or mulberry without any copybook while drinking at a dyer&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he wrote more than 1000 words of it on four pieces of paper made from hemp or mulberry without any copybook while drinking at a dyer&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>この『幻住庵記』の筆跡を見た芥川龍之介は「入神と称するをも妨げない」と評した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA, who saw Seiget&apos;s writings of &quot;Genjuan no ki&quot;, said, &apos;No one denies he has divine skill&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA, who saw Seiget&apos;s writings of &quot;Genjuan no ki,&quot; said, &apos;No one denies he has divine skill.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA, who saw Seigetsu&apos;s writings of &quot;Genjuan no ki,&quot; said, &apos;No one denies he has divine skill.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Seiget&apos;s→Seigetsu&apos;s</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>作品について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Work</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works</e>
<cmt>Hisを削除しました</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>井月は芭蕉忌に際して「我道の神とも拝め翁の日」という句を残すほどに、松尾芭蕉を尊敬していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He respected Basho MATSUO so deeply that he made a haiku tribute to him at the memorial ceremony of the anniversary of his death, &apos;Wagamichi no kamitomoogame okina no hi&apos; (Everybody should join their hands in prayer for Basho as a god on the anniversary of his death).</e>
<cmt>俳句、「我道の神とも拝め翁の日」を　&apos;Wagamichi no kamitomoogame okina no hi&apos; (Everybody should join their hands in prayer for Basho as a god on the anniversary of his death)　と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He respected Basho MATSUO so deeply that he made a haiku tribute to him at the memorial ceremony of the anniversary of his death, &apos;Wagamichi no kamitomoogame okina no hi&apos; (Everybody should join their hands in prayer for Basho as a god on the anniversary of his death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He respected Basho MATSUO so deeply that he made a haiku tribute to him at the memorial ceremony of the anniversary of his death, &apos;Wagamichi no kamitomoogame okina no hi&apos; (Everybody should join their hands in prayer for Basho as a god on the anniversary of his death).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>芭蕉句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basho&apos;s haiku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basho&apos;s haiku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basho&apos;s haiku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>象潟や雨に西施が合歓の花</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kisagataya ameni seishiga nebunohana (Here, Kisagata is an entrancing beautiful place and silk flowers getting wet in the rain are like the Chinese beautiful woman, Seishi).</e>
<cmt>俳句、「象潟や雨に西施が合歓の花」を　Kisagataya ameni seishiga nebunohana (Here, Kisagata is an entrancing beautiful place and silk flowers getting wet in the rain are like the Chinese beautiful woman, Seishi)　と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kisagataya ameni seishiga nebunohana (Here, Kisagata is an entrancing beautiful place and silk flowers getting wet in the rain are like the Chinese beautiful woman, Seishi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakikataya ameni seishiga nebunohana (Here, Sakikata is an entrancing beautiful place and silk flowers getting wet in the rain are like the Chinese beautiful woman, Seishi.)</e>
<cmt>Kisagataya→Sakikatayaピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>ほろほろと山吹散るか滝の音</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horohoroto yamabukichiruka taki no oto (You hear the roar of the waterfall crashing into rocks and see Japanese roses scattering without the wind).</e>
<cmt>俳句、「ほろほろと山吹散るか滝の音」を　Horohoroto yamabukichiruka taki no oto (You hear the roar of the waterfall crashing into rocks and see Japanese roses scattering without the wind)　と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horohoroto yamabukichiruka taki no oto (You hear the roar of the waterfall crashing into rocks and see Japanese roses scattering without the wind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horohoroto yamabukichiruka taki no oto (You hear the roar of the waterfall crashing into rocks and see Japanese roses scattering without the wind.)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>面白うてやがて悲しき鵜舟かな</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omoshiroute yagatekanashiki ubune kana (You can enjoy seeing cormorant catch fish, but soon you will feel sad as the flame on the boat is dying out).</e>
<cmt>俳句、「面白うてやがて悲しき鵜舟かな」を　Omoshiroute yagatekanashiki ubune kana (You can enjoy seeing cormorants chatch fish, but soon you will feel sad as the flame on the boat is dying out)　と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omoshiroute yagatekanashiki ubune kana (You can enjoy seeing cormorant catch fish, but soon you will feel sad as the flame on the boat is dying out).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omoshiroute yagatekanashiki ubune kana (You can enjoy seeing cormorant catch fish, but soon you will feel sad as the flame on the boat is dying out.)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="69">
<j>井月句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seigetsu&apos;s haiku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seigetsu&apos;s haiku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seigetsu&apos;s haiku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>象潟の雨なはらしそ合歓の花</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kisagatano amenaharashiso nemu no hana (In an entrancing beautiful place, Kisagata, silk flowers are waiting until the rain lets up).</e>
<cmt>俳句、「象潟の雨なはらしそ合歓の花」をKisagatano amenaharashiso nemu no hana (In as entrancing beautiful place, Kisagata, silk flowers are waiting until the rain lets up)　と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kisagatano amenaharashiso nemu no hana (In an entrancing beautiful place, Kisagata, silk flowers are waiting until the rain lets up).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakikatano amenaharashiso nemu no hana (In an entrancing beautiful place, Sakikata, silk flowers are waiting until the rain lets up.)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>山吹に名をよぶ程の滝もがな</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamabukini nawoyobuhodono takimogana</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が不明なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamabukini nawoyobuhodono takimogana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamabukini nawoyobuhodono takimogana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>すくむ鵜に燃くず折るゝかゞり哉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukumuuni mokuzuoruru kagarinari</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が不明なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukumuuni mokuzuoruru kagarinari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukumuuni mokuzuoruru kagarinari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="73">
<j>以上のように、芭蕉を慕った井月の句は多数存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the mentioned above, Seigetsu made a lot of haiku relating to Basho&apos;s, which suggested that he adored Basho passionately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the mentioned above, Seigetsu created a lot of haiku relating to Basho&apos;s, which suggested that he adored Basho passionately.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the mentioned above, Seigetsu created a lot of haiku relating to Basho&apos;s, which suggested that he adored Basho passionately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>この点から、月並俳句が横行した幕末・明治初期にかけて、蕉門の再評価を目指した井月の姿勢がうかがわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding these haiku Seigetsu made, it can be said that he tried to reevaluate Shomon (Basho&apos;s school) from the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate to the early Meiji period during which mediocre haiku were prevalent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding these haiku Seigetsu wrote, it can be said that he tried to reevaluate Shomon (Basho&apos;s school) from the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate to the early Meiji period during which mediocre haiku were prevalent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding these haiku Seigetsu wrote, it can be said that he tried to reevaluate Shomon (Basho&apos;s school) from the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate to the early Meiji period during which mediocre haiku were prevalent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>その一方で、「鵜」の句の例にあるように、物事の全体を捉える芭蕉の感覚に対して、細部のみに収まってしまう井月の句柄の小ささも指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as &apos;u&apos; haiku suggested, it is pointed out that while Basho made haiku based on his broad views of things, Seigetsu made haiku based on his narrow views of things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as &apos;u&apos; haiku suggested, it is pointed out that while Basho wrote haiku based upon his broad view of things, Seigetsu wrote haiku based on his narrow view of things.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as &apos;u&apos; haiku suggested, it is pointed out that while Basho wrote haiku based upon his broad view of things, Seigetsu wrote haiku based on his narrow view of things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="76">
<j>また、井月は「俳諧雅俗伝」という文章を明治8年に染筆しているが、これは甲州の俳人である早川漫々の残した文章の要諦を写したもので、井月が正風俳諧の影響を受けていることが伺える</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He inked writings, &apos;haikaigazoku-den&apos; with brush in 1875, but this was the copy of important phrases written by Manman HAYAKAWA, who was a poet in Koshu Province, which shows that Seigetsu was influenced by Shofu haikai (a concept of haiku completed by Basho MATSUO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He inked writings, &apos;haikaigazoku-den&apos; with brush in 1875, but this was the copy of important phrases written by Manman HAYAKAWA, who was a poet in Koshu Province, showing that Seigetsu was influenced by Shofu haikai (a concept of haiku completed by Basho MATSUO).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He inked writings, &apos;haikaigazoku-den&apos; with brush in 1875, but this was the copy of important phrases written by Manman HAYAKAWA, who was a poet in Koshu Province, showing that Seigetsu was influenced by Shofu haikai (a concept of haiku completed by Basho MATSUO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="77">
<j>また、井月は同じ幕末期の俳人である小林一茶ともよく比較される（一茶が65歳で没したとき、井月は5歳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he is usually compared with Issa KOBAYASHI, who was a haiku poet in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate (when Issa died at the age of 65, he was five).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he is usually compared with Issa KOBAYASHI, who was a haiku poet in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate (when Issa died at the age of sixty-five, he was five).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he is usually compared with Issa KOBAYASHI, who was a haiku poet in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate (when Issa died at the age of sixty-five, he was five).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>特に、一茶の冬の句「ともかくもあなた任せの年の暮」、新年句「目出度さもちう位也おらが春」、に対して、井月が「目出度さも人任せなり旅の春」を残している点が注目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, it is noteworthy that Issa made haiku relating to winter, &apos;Tomokakumo anatamakaseno toshinokure&apos; (After doing your best, in the end, you should put everything into hands of Buddha) and haiku relating to a new year, &apos;Medetasamo chukurainari oragaharu&apos; (A new year has come and people are very happy about it, but I do not feel like celebrating New Year&apos;s like them), and responding to these Issa&apos;s haiku, Seigetsu made &apos;Medetasamo hitomakasenari harunotabi&apos; (A new year has come and people are happy about it, but I do not care about it, I&apos;m just enjoying my traveling).</e>
<cmt>俳句、「ともかくもあなた任せの年の暮」、「目出度さもちう位也おらが春」、「目出度さも人任せなり旅の春」 をそれぞれ　「&apos;Tonokakumo anatamakaseno toshinokure&apos; (After doing your best, in the end, you should put everything into hands of Buddha)」、 「&apos;Medetasamo chukurainari oragaharu&apos; (A new year has come and people are very happy about it, but I do not feel like celebrating New Year&apos;s like them)」、「Medetasamo hitomakasenari harunotabi&apos; (A new year has come and people are happy about it, but I do not care about it, I&apos;m just enjyoying my traveling)」　と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, it is noteworthy that Issa wrote haiku relating to winter, &apos;Tomokakumo anatamakaseno toshinokure&apos; (After doing your best, in the end, you should put everything into the hands of Buddha) and haiku relating to a new year, &apos;Medetasamo chukurainari oragaharu&apos; (A new year has come and people are very happy about it, but I do not feel like celebrating New Year&apos;s like them), and responding to these Issa&apos;s haiku, Seigetsu made &apos;Medetasamo hitomakasenari harunotabi&apos; (A new year has come and people are happy about it, but I do not care about it, I&apos;m just enjoying my travels).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, it is noteworthy that Issa wrote haiku relating to winter, &apos;Tomokakumo anatamakaseno toshinokure&apos; (After doing your best, in the end, you should put everything into the hands of Buddha) and haiku relating to a new year, &apos;Medetasamo chukurainari oragaharu&apos; (A new year has come and people are very happy about it, but I do not feel like celebrating New Year&apos;s like them), and responding to these Issa&apos;s haiku, Seigetsu made &apos;Medetasamo hitomakasenari harunotabi&apos; (A new year has come and people are happy about it, but I do not care about it, I&apos;m just enjoying my travels).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>これらの俳句の比較から、一茶の浄土真宗的な思想と無常観に対して、井月の現世肯定性、楽天性が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given the comparison between Issa&apos;s and Seigetsu&apos;s haiku, it is pointed out that Issa was under influence of the thought of the Jodoshin Sect and viewed life as transitory, on the other hand, Seigetsu had optimistic and realistic way of thinking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the comparison between Issa&apos;s and Seigetsu&apos;s haiku, it is pointed out that Issa was under influence of the thought of the Jodoshin Sect and viewed life as transitory, on the other hand, Seigetsu had an optimistic and realistic way of thinking.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the comparison between Issa&apos;s and Seigetsu&apos;s haiku, it is pointed out that Issa was under influence of the thought of the Jodoshin Sect and viewed life as transitory, on the other hand, Seigetsu had an optimistic and realistic way of thinking.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="80">
<j>また、井月は発句ばかりでなく、連句を巻くことも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seigetsu made not only hottku (the first line of a waka poem) but also renku (a series of haiku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seigetsu wrote not only hottku (the first line of a waka poem), but also renku (a series of haiku).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seigetsu wrote not only hokku (the first line of a waka poem), but also renku (a series of haiku).</e>
<cmt>hottku→hokku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>『井月全集』には64篇の連句が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a series of 64 haiku in &quot;Seigetsu zenshu&quot; (the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a series of sixty-four haiku in &quot;Seigetsu zenshu&quot; (the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a series of sixty-four renku in &quot;Seigetsu zenshu&quot; (the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku).</e>
<cmt>haiku→renku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>後世への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence for the future generations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence for the future generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence for the future generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>井月は自身の句集は残さなかったが、伊那谷の各地に発句の書き付けを残していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He did not left his own collection of haiku, but he left hokku in various area of Inadani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He did not leave his own collection of haiku, but left hokku in various aresa of Inadani.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He did not leave his own collection of haiku, but left hokku in various areas of Inadani.</e>
<cmt>aresa→areas</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>伊那谷出身の医師であり、自らも年少時に井月を見知っていた下島勲（俳号：空谷）は、井月作品の収集を思い立ち、伊那谷に居住していた実弟の下島五老に調査を依頼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isao SHIMOJIMA (another name as a poet was Kukoku) who was a doctor from Inadani and knew Seigetsu in his boyhood came up to the idea that he collected Seigetsu&apos;s work and asked his real brother, Goro SHIMOJIMA who lived in Inadani to research it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isao SHIMOJIMA (another name as a poet was Kukoku) who was a doctor from Inadani and knew Seigetsu during his boyhood and came up with the idea that he collected Seigetsu&apos;s work and asked his real brother, Goro SHIMOJIMA who lived in Inadani to research it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isao SHIMOJIMA (another name as a poet was Kukoku), who was a doctor from Inadani and knew Seigetsu during his boyhood, came up with the idea of collecting Seigetsu&apos;s work and asked his real brother Goro SHIMOJIMA, who lived in Inadani, to research it.</e>
<cmt>調整しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>そして大正10年（1921年）、『井月の句集』を出版する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, in 1921, he published &quot;Seigetsu no ku-shu&quot; (the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, in 1921, he published &quot;Seigetsu no ku-shu&quot; (the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, in 1921, he published &quot;Seigetsu no ku-shu&quot; (the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>本書の巻頭には、高浜虚子から贈られた「丈高き男なりけん木枯らしに」の一句が添えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The collection of haiku opened with haiku that Kyoshi TAKAHAMA presented, &apos;Taketakaki otokonariken kogarashini&apos;.</e>
<cmt>俳句、「丈高き男なりけん木枯らしに」は意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection of haiku opened with haiku that Kyoshi TAKAHAMA presented, &apos;Taketakaki otokonariken kogarashini&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection of haiku opened with haiku that Kyoshi TAKAHAMA presented, &apos;Taketakaki otokonariken kogarashini&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>この句が松尾芭蕉『野ざらし紀行』の発句「狂句木枯の身は竹斎に似たる哉」を踏まえている点から、虚子が井月を芭蕉と比較していたことが分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This haiku was made based on a hokku of Basho MATSUO&apos;s &quot;Nozarashi kiko&quot;, &apos;Kyoku kogarashinomiwa Chikusai ni nitaruya&apos; (I&apos;m wandering around making haiku, so I am like crazy Chikusai, a hero of a story), which indicates that Kyoshi compared Seigetsu with Basho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This haiku was created based upon the hokku of Basho MATSUO&apos;s &quot;Nozarashi kiko,&quot; &apos;Kyoku kogarashinomiwa Chikusai ni nitaruya&apos; (I&apos;m wandering around making haiku, so I am like crazy Chikusai, a hero of a story), which indicates that Kyoshi compared Seigetsu with Basho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This haiku was created based upon the hokku of Basho MATSUO&apos;s &quot;Nozarashi kiko,&quot; &apos;Kyoku kogarashinomiwa Chikusai ni nitaruya&apos; (I&apos;m wandering around making haiku, so I am like crazy Chikusai, a hero of a story), which indicates that Kyoshi compared Seigetsu with Basho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="87">
<j>また、下島が芥川龍之介の主治医であった縁から、『井月の句集』の跋文は芥川が執筆している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, SHIMOJIMA was Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA&apos;s doctor, so, AKUTAGAWA wrote a postscript of &quot;the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, SHIMOJIMA was Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA&apos;s doctor, so, AKUTAGAWA wrote a postscript to &quot;the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, SHIMOJIMA was Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA&apos;s doctor, so, AKUTAGAWA wrote a postscript to &quot;the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>芥川は「井月は時代に曳きずられながらも古俳句の大道は忘れなかつた」と井月を賞賛している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">AKUTAGAWA praised Seigetsu for his policy that while he tried to catch up with the times, he never forgot the basics of haiku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">AKUTAGAWA praised Seigetsu for his policy that while he tried to catch up with the times, he never forgot the basics of haiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">AKUTAGAWA praised Seigetsu for his policy that while he tried to catch up with the times, he never forgot the basics of haiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>また、芥川は｢咲いたのは動いているや蓮の花｣を井月の最高傑作と称揚しているが、皮肉にもこの俳句は井月の俳友であった橋爪山洲の作品であることが、芥川の没後に判明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also praised him for his haiku, &apos;Saitanowa ugoiteiruya hasunohana&apos; as his best haiku, but ironically, after AKUTAGAWA died, it was turned out that this haiku was made by Sanshu HASHIZUME, who was a poet and a friend of Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt>俳句、｢咲いたのは動いているや蓮の花｣は意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also praised him for his haiku, &apos;Saitanowa ugoiteiruya hasunohana&apos; as his best haiku, but ironically, after AKUTAGAWA died, it turned out that this haiku was created by Sanshu HASHIZUME, who was a poet and a friend of Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also praised him for his haiku, &apos;Saitanowa ugoiteiruya hasunohana&apos; as his best haiku, but ironically, after AKUTAGAWA died, it turned out that this haiku was created by Sanshu HASHIZUME, who was a poet and a friend of Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="90">
<j>昭和5年（1930年）10月には、下島勲・高津才次郎編集による『井月全集』が出版される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, 1930, &quot;The collected complete haiku of Seigetsu&quot; compiled by Isao SHIMOJIMA and Saijiro TAKATSU was published.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, 1930, &quot;The collected complete haiku of Seigetsu&quot; compiled by Isao SHIMOJIMA and Saijiro TAKATSU was published.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, 1930, &quot;The collected complete haiku of Seigetsu&quot; compiled by Isao SHIMOJIMA and Saijiro TAKATSU was published.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>『井月の句集』に掲載された虚子らの「井月賛」俳句と、芥川の序文はこの全集にも再掲され、井月の評価を高める役割を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seigetsu san&apos; haiku made by Kyoshi and printed in &quot;the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku&quot; and the postscript written by AKUTAGAWA were reprinted in this collected complete haiku of Seigetsu, which played an important role of receiving good reviews of his</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seigetsu san&apos; haiku made by Kyoshi and printed in &quot;the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku&quot; and the postscript written by AKUTAGAWA were reprinted in this collected complete haiku of Seigetsu, which played an important role in receiving good reviews.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seigetsu san&apos; haiku made by Kyoshi and printed in &quot;the collection of Seigetsu&apos;s haiku&quot; and the postscript written by AKUTAGAWA were reprinted in this collected complete haiku of Seigetsu, which played an important role in receiving good reviews.</e>
<cmt>冒頭の引用符を追加しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>また、本全集には、井月が残した日記も収録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, this collected complete haiku of Seigetsu included his diary he left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, this is the collection of the complete haiku of Seigetsu included his diary he left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This complete collection also includes his diary he left.</e>
<cmt>改変しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="93">
<j>昭和13（1938年）、上伊那郡東部教育会が国語副読本として『井月さん』を出版する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1938, Kamiina-gun tobu Education Board published &quot;Seigetsu-san&quot; as a supplementary Japanese textbook.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1938, Kamiina-gun tobu Education Board published &quot;Seigetsu-san&quot; as a supplementary Japanese textbook.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1938, East Kamiina-gun Education Board published &quot;Seigetsu-san&quot; as a supplementary Japanese textbook.</e>
<cmt>tobu→east</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="94">
<j>昭和31年（1956年）、作家の石川淳が伊那市を訪ねて井月の取材を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1956, Jun ISHIKAWA, a composer, visited Ina City and collected information about Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1956, Jun ISHIKAWA, a composer, visited Ina City and collected information about Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1956, Jun ISHIKAWA, a composer, visited Ina City and collected information about Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>そして、当時「文藝春秋 (雑誌)」に連載していた『諸国畸人伝』の一篇として「信濃国無宿風来俳人井月」を執筆。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote &apos;Shinshu no kuni mushuku furai haijin Seigetsu&apos; (Seigetsu, a haiku poet wandering around Shinano Province without settling) as a piece of his serial story, &quot;Shokoku kijin den&quot; (stories of unique people in various provinces) which he was writing at that time in &apos;Bungei shunju&apos; (magazine).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote &apos;Shinshu no kuni mushuku furai haijin Seigetsu&apos; (Seigetsu, a haiku poet wandering around Shinano Province without settling) as a piece of his serial story, &quot;Shokoku kijin den&quot; (stories of unique people in various provinces) which he was writing at that time in &apos;Bungei shunju&apos; (magazine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote &apos;Shinshu no kuni mushuku furai haijin Seigetsu&apos; (Seigetsu, a haiku poet wandering around Shinano Province without settling) as a piece of his serial story, &quot;Shokoku kijin den&quot; (stories of unique people in various provinces) which he was writing at that time in &apos;Bungei shunju&apos; (magazine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="96">
<j>昭和49年（1974年）11月、『井月全集』の増補復刻版として『井上井月全集』が伊那毎日新聞から出版され、決定版とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, 1974, &quot;The collected complete haiku of Seigetsu INOUE&quot; was published by Mainichi newspaper company as an enlarged and reprinted edition of &quot;The collected complete haiku of Seigetsu&quot; and it has been considered as a definitive edition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, 1974, &quot;The complete collection of haiku created by Seigetsu INOUE&quot; was published by the Mainichi newspaper company as an enlarged and reprinted edition of &quot;The collected complete haiku of Seigetsu&quot; and it has been considered a definitive edition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, 1974, &quot;The complete collection of haiku created by Seigetsu INOUE&quot; was published by the Ina Mainichi newspaper company as an enlarged and reprinted edition of &quot;The collected complete haiku of Seigetsu&quot; and it has been considered a definitive edition.</e>
<cmt>Inaを補足しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="97">
<j>昭和62年（1987年）には、井月没後100年を迎えて「井月百年祭」が開催された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1987, to celebrate the 100the anniversary of his death, &apos;the festival of 100th anniversary of Saigetsu&apos; was held.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1987, to celebrate the 100th anniversary of his death, &apos;the festival of 100th anniversary of Saigetsu&apos; was held.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1987, making the centennial of his death, &apos;100th anniversary of Seigetsu&apos; was held.</e>
<cmt>一部改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>句碑が3基建立された他、関係図書の復刊や、記念俳句大会などが行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The festival was celebrated by several events such as erecting three stone tablets inscribed with a haiku, republishing related books and holding a commemorative haiku convention.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The festival was celebrated by several events such as erecting three stone tablets inscribed with a haiku, republishing related books and holding a commemorative haiku convention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The festival was celebrated by several events such as erecting three stone tablets inscribed with a haiku, republishing related books and holding a commemorative haiku convention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>種田山頭火への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence on Santoka TANEDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence on Santoka TANEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence on Santoka TANEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="99">
<j>井上井月に影響を受けた一人に、自由律俳句の種田山頭火が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of haiku poets who came under the influence of Seigetsu was Santoka TANEDA who made haiku without fixed pattern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of haiku poets who came under the influence of Seigetsu was Santoka TANEDA who made haiku without fixed pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of haiku poets who came under the influence of Seigetsu was Santoka TANEDA who made haiku without fixed pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="100">
<j>山頭火日記の「昭和5年8月2日」の項には、次のように記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Diary of Santoka in the article of &apos;August 2, 1930&apos; described as follows;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Diary of Santoka in the article of &apos;August 2, 1930&apos; described as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Diary of Santoka in the article of &apos;August 2, 1930&apos; described as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>「樹明兄が借して下さつた『井月全集』を読む、よい本だつた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;I read the book, &quot;The collected complete haiku of Seigetsu&quot; that Kiakiani lent me and I found it very interesting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処    「樹明兄」の読み方不明のため、「Kiakiani」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;I read the book, &quot;The complete collection of haiku created by Seigetsu&quot; that Kiakiani lent me and I found it very interesting.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I read the book, &quot;The complete collection of haiku created by Seigetsu&quot; that Kiaki-ani lent me and I found it very interesting.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の末尾にカギカッコを追加し、訳文も併せて修正しましたハイフンを追加しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>「今までに読んでゐなければならない本だった。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the book I should have read up to the present.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the book I should have read up to the present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the book I should have read up to the present.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の末尾にカギカッコを追加し、訳文も併せて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>「井月の墓は好きだ、書はほんとうにうまい。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I like his grave and his writings are really great&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I like his grave and his writings are really great&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I like his grave and his writings are really great.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の末尾にカギカッコを追加し、訳文も併せて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="104">
<j>とある通り、山頭火は井月の句を繰り返し読み、思慕の情を持つようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As this article suggested, he repeatedly read Seigetsu&apos;s haiku and he was growing a deep attachment for him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this article suggests, he repeatedly read Seigetsu&apos;s haiku and he was growing a deep attachment to it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this article suggests, he repeatedly read Seigetsu&apos;s haiku and he was growing a deep attachment to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>昭和9年（1934年）3月、52歳の山頭火は井月の墓参を決意し、山口市から伊那谷に向けて東上する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1934, Santoka at the age of 52 was determined to visit Saigetsu&apos;s grave, so, he headed for the northeast from Yamaguchi City to Inadani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1934, Santoka at the age of 52 was determined to visit Saigetsu&apos;s grave, so, he headed northeast from Yamaguchi City to Inadani.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1934, Santoka at the age of 52 was determined to visit Saigetsu&apos;s grave, so, he headed northeast from Yamaguchi City to Inadani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>しかし、清内路峠付近は雪が深く、4月に信州飯田市に入ったところで肺炎を発症した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the ground around Seinaiji toge (ridge) was covered with deep snow, and when he came to Ida City, Shinshu Province in April, he developed pneumonia.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the ground around Seinaiji toge (ridge) was covered with deep snow, and when he came to Ida City, Shinshu Province in April, he developed pneumonia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the ground around Seinaiji toge (ridge) was covered with deep snow, and when he came to Ida City, Shinshu Province in April, he developed pneumonia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="107">
<j>そのため、2週間緊急入院することとなり、墓参を諦める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was immediately hospitalized for two weeks, therefore, he had to give up visiting Seigetsu&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was immediately hospitalized for two weeks, therefore, he had to give up visiting Seigetsu&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was immediately hospitalized for two weeks, therefore, he had to give up visiting Seigetsu&apos;s grave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="108">
<j>その4年後、昭和14年（1939年）3月31日、再び山口を出立し、5月3日、列車で天竜峡駅に着く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four years later, on March 31, 1939, he left Yamaguchi again and on May 3, he arrived at Tenryukyo Station by train.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four years later, on March 31, 1939, he left Yamaguchi again and on May 3, he arrived at Tenryukyo Station by train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four years later, on March 31, 1939, he left Yamaguchi again and on May 3, he arrived at Tenryukyo Station by train.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>その後、伊那谷に向かい、俳人であり長野県伊那弥生ヶ丘高等学校教諭だった前田若水の家に立ち寄り、若水の案内を得てようやく井月の墓参を果たす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he headed for Inadani and visited Jakusui MAEDA who was a haiku poet and a teacher in Ina yayoigaoka high school, and then, he could finally visited Seigetsu&apos;s grave under Jakusui&apos;s guidance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he headed for Inadani and visited Jakusui MAEDA who was a haiku poet and a teacher in Ina yayoigaoka high school, and then, he could finally visited Seigetsu&apos;s grave under Jakusui&apos;s guidance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he headed for Inadani and visited Jakusui MAEDA who was a haiku poet and a teacher in Ina yayoigaoka high school, and then, he could finally visited Seigetsu&apos;s grave under Jakusui&apos;s guidance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>山頭火の「風来居日記」の5月3日の項には、墓参の様子が100行ほどに渡って記されており、その中に、井月の墓を前にしての即吟を4句残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article of May 3 of Santoka&apos;s &apos;Furaikyo Nikki&apos; (the Diary of Furaikyo), he wrote some 100 sentences about how he paid tribute to Seigetsu in front of his grave, including four haiku he improvised there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article of May 3 of Santoka&apos;s &apos;Furaikyo Nikki&apos; (the Diary of Furaikyo), he wrote some 100 sentences about how he paid tribute to Seigetsu in front of his grave, including four haiku he improvised there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article of May 3 of Santoka&apos;s &apos;Furaikyo Nikki&apos; (the Diary of Furaikyo), he wrote some 100 sentences about how he paid tribute to Seigetsu in front of his grave, including four haiku he improvised there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="111">
<j>井月の墓を前にして</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In front of the Seigetsu&apos;s grave</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In front of Seigetsu&apos;s grave</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In front of Seigetsu&apos;s grave</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="112">
<j>・お墓したしくお酒をそゝぐ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">・Ohaka shitashiku osakewo sosogu (Like a close friend, I pour sake on his grave).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">・Ohaka shitashiku osakewo sosogu (Like a close friend, I pour sake on his grave).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">・Ohaka shitashiku osakewo sosogu (Like a close friend, I pour sake on his grave.)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="113">
<j>・お墓撫でさすりつゝ、はるばるまゐりました</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">・Ohakanade sasuritsutsu harubarumairimashita (While I softly touched the grave, I talked to him, &apos; I came here all the way &apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">・Ohakanade sasuritsutsu harubarumairimashita (While I softly touched the grave, I talked to him, &apos; I came here all the way &apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">・Ohakanade sasuritsutsu harubarumairimashita (While I softly touched the grave, I talked to him, &apos; I came here all the way.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="114">
<j>・駒ヶ根をまへにいつもひとりでしたね</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">・Komaganewomaeni itsumo hitorideshitane (You were always alone seeing the Komagane mountain range lying in front of you).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">・Komaganewomaeni itsumo hitorideshitane (You were always alone seeing the Komagane mountain range lying in front of you).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">・Komaganewomaeni itsumo hitorideshitane (You were always alone seeing the Komagane mountain range lying in front of you.)</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="115">
<j>・供へるものとては、野の木瓜の二枝三枝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">・Sonaeru monototewa nonokiurino futaeda mineda (My offereings are a few branches of mube tree [stauntonia hexaphylla Decne]).</e>
<cmt>「野の木瓜」は、http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%83%A0%E3%83%99より「ムベ（郁子、野木瓜、学名：Stauntonia hexaphylla）」を参考にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">・Sonaeru monototewa nonokiurino futaeda mineda (My offereings are a few branches of mube tree [stauntonia hexaphylla Decne]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">・Sonaeru monototewa nonokiurino futaeda mineda (My offereings are a few branches of mube tree [stauntonia hexaphylla Decne.])</e>
<cmt>ピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="116">
<j>日記の中に次のように書きつけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his diary, he wrote, &apos;I do not think about Basho and Issa, rather, I am always thinking about Rotsu and Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his diary, he wrote, &apos;I do not think about Basho and Issa, rather, I am always thinking about Rotsu and Seigetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his diary, he wrote as the following.</e>
<cmt>原文をsplit sampleに従って修正し、併せて訳文も修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>「私は芭蕉や一茶のことはあまり考えない、いつも考えているのは路通や井月のことである。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I am thinking how much they liked sake and how they ended their life.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I am thinking how much they liked sake and how they ended their lives.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I do not think about Basho and Issa, rather, I am always thinking about Rotsu and Seigetsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文をsplit sampleに従って修正し、併せて訳文も修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>「彼等の酒好きや最後のことである。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I am thinking how much they liked sake and how they ended their lives.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文をsplit sampleに従って修正し、併せて訳文も修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>このように、山頭火は井月の作品と生き方に影響を受けたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, it is presumed that Santoka came under the influence of Seigetsu&apos;s lifestyle and work.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, it is presumed that Santoka came under the influence of Seigetsu&apos;s lifestyle and work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, it is presumed that Santoka came under the influence of Seigetsu&apos;s lifestyle and work.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>また、蕉門の乞食僧俳人であった八十村路通などと合わせて、そこに放浪俳人の系譜を見ることもできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Including Rotsu YASOMURA, who was a begging monk and poet belonging to Basho school, his lifestyle can be traced back to these wandering haiku poets.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Including Rotsu YASOMURA, who was a begging monk and poet belonging to the Basho school, his lifestyle can be traced back to these wandering haiku poets.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coupled with Rotsu YASOMURA, who was a begging monk and poet belonging to the Basho school, his lifestyle can be traced back to these wandering haiku poets.</e>
<cmt>Including→Coupled with</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>つげ義春への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence on Yoshiharu TSUGE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence on Yoshiharu TSUGE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence on Yoshiharu TSUGE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>漫画家のつげ義春は、漫画作品『無能の人』の最終話である第6話「蒸発」に、井月を詳しく描いている（初出は1986年12月、「COMIC ばく」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu TSUGE, a cartoonist, depicted Seigetsu in detail in the last sixth episode, &apos;Johatsu&apos; (mysterious disappearance) of his cartoon, &quot;Muno no hito&quot; or incompetence people (first published in December 1986, &apos;COMIC baku&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu TSUGE, a cartoonist, depicted Seigetsu in detail in the last sixth episode, &apos;Johatsu&apos; (mysterious disappearance) of his cartoon, &quot;Muno no hito&quot; or incompetence people (first published in December 1986, &apos;COMIC baku&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu TSUGE, a cartoonist, depicted Seigetsu in detail in the last sixth episode, &apos;Johatsu&apos; (mysterious disappearance) of his cartoon, &quot;Muno no hito&quot; or incompetence people (first published in December 1986, &apos;COMIC baku&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>河原で石を売る主人公が、病人のふりをしながらよたよた歩く無為徒食の古書店主人山井（病をもじったもの）からむりやり貸し付けられた『漂泊俳人 井月全集』を読む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leading character who sells stones in a riverside reads a book, &quot;The collected complete haiku of Seigetsu, a wandering haiku poet&quot;, which he was forcibly lent out by YAMAI, the owner of a secondhand bookstore, who pretends to be a sick person, walks unsteadily and idles away his time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The leading character who sells stones in a riverside reads a book, &quot;The complete collection of haiku of Seigetsu, a wandering haiku poet,&quot; which he was forcibly lent by YAMAI, the owner of a secondhand bookstore, who pretends to be a sick person, walks unsteadily and idles away his time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The leading character who sells stones in a riverside reads a book, &quot;The complete collection of haiku of Seigetsu, a wandering haiku poet,&quot; which he was forcibly lent by YAMAI (a pun on a word of Yamai which means disease), the owner of a secondhand bookstore, who pretends to be a sick person, walks unsteadily and idles away his time.</e>
<cmt>（病をもじったもの）を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>そして、井月の半生をその死まで思い描きつつ、井月に自らや山井の姿を重ね合わせ、感慨にふけるという筋書きになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While reading, he imagines half of Seigetsu&apos;s life till his death, sees his and YAMAI&apos;s reflections in it and was buried in thoughts, which is the outline of the story.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While reading, he imagines half of Seigetsu&apos;s life till his death, sees his and YAMAI&apos;s reflections in it and was buried in thoughts, which is the outline of the story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While reading, he imagines half of Seigetsu&apos;s life till his death, sees his and YAMAI&apos;s reflections in it and was buried in thoughts, which is the outline of the story.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>最後は「井月も山井も大馬鹿ものだよ......」という主人公のセリフで締めくくられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last scene, he said to himself, &apos;Both Seigetsu and YAMAI are enormously stupid….&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last scene, he says to himself, &apos;Both Seigetsu and YAMAI are enormously stupid….&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last scene, he says to himself, &apos;Both Seigetsu and YAMAI are enormously stupid….&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="125">
<j>『蒸発』には以下のような句が引用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some haiku as given below were quoted in &quot;Johatsu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the haiku given below were quoted in &quot;Johatsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the haiku given below were quoted in &quot;Johatsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="126">
<j>降るとまで 人には見せて 花曇り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furutomade hitonihamisete hanagumori</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furutomade hitonihamisete hanagumori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furutomade hitoniwamisete hanagumori</e>
<cmt>ha→wa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>石菖や いつの世よりの 石の肌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekisho ya itsunoyoyorino ishinohada</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekisho ya itsunoyoyorino ishinohada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekisho ya itsunoyoyorino ishinohada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>何処やらに 鶴の声きく かすみかな</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dokoyarani tsurunokoekiku kasumikana</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dokoyarani tsurunokoekiku kasumikana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dokoyarani tsurunokoekiku kasumikana</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Su-no-G(id:52744), Point136(id:211299), Juqipedia(id:188816), 松岡徳次郎(id:218163), DDR(id:27381), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Goki(id:7107), アイザール(id:133157), Hideki1976(id:106957), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>