<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>姉小路顕朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akitomo ANEGAKOJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitomo ANEGAKOJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akitomo ANEGAKOJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>姉小路 顕朝（あねがこうじ あきとも、建暦2年（1212年） - 文永3年9月20日 (旧暦)（1266年10月19日））は、鎌倉時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akitomo ANEGAKOJI (1212 - October 19, 1266) was a Kugyo (high court noble), who lived during the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitomo ANEGAKOJI (1212 - October 19, 1266) was a Court noble who lived during the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>公卿→a Court noble&quot;who&quot;の前のカンマは特に必要ないので、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akitomo ANEGAKOJI (1212 - October 19, 1266) was a Court noble who lived during the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は参議姉小路宗房、母は左京大夫藤原清長の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sangi (councilor) Munefusa ANEGAKOJI, and his mother was the daughter of Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) FUJIWARA no Kiyonaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Sangi (councilor) Munefusa ANEGAKOJI, and his mother was the daughter of Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) FUJIWARA no Kiyonaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Sangi (councilor) Munefusa ANEGAKOJI, and his mother was the daughter of Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) FUJIWARA no Kiyonaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>妻は二条定高の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was the daughter of Sadataka NIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was the daughter of Sadataka NIJO.</e>
<cmt>文尾にピリオドを付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was the daughter of Sadataka NIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に姉小路忠方がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakata ANEGAKOJI was his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his children was Tadakata ANEGAKOJI.</e>
<cmt>初訳でも間違えではないのですが、「姉小路顕朝」についての項目なので、「彼のこども」を主語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his children was Tadakata ANEGAKOJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>父は散位の状態で病死したために、若年時には苦労したが暦仁元年（1238年）に右少弁に昇って以後は九条道家・後嵯峨上皇の信任を受けて昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father died by disease in the sate of Sani (courtier without post), he had a hard time while he was young, however, after holding the position of Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1238, he was promoted smoothly, gaining the confidence of Michiie KUJO Retired Emperor Gosaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he had a hard time when he was young because his father died of disease while being Sani (courtier without post), he was promoted thanks to the confidence of Michiie KUJO and the Retired Emperor Gosago after being promoted to Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1238.</e>
<cmt>（苦労した）が、→Although（&quot;although&quot;で始まる文章に変更しました。）昇る→be promoted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he had a hard time when he was young because his father died of disease while being Sani (courtier without post), he was promoted thanks to the confidence of Michiie KUJO and the Retired Emperor Gosago after being promoted to Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1238.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>特に後嵯峨上皇の元では伝奏を務めて、同院の院政における中核的な地位にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, under Retired Emperor Gosaga, he worked as a denso (job title to relay message of court&apos;s people to Emperor) and he played a central role in the Retired Emperor Gosaga&apos;s government.</e>
<cmt>同院の院政→Retired Emperor Gosaga&apos;s governmentとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, Akitomo who served as denso (job title to relay message of court&apos;s people to Emperor) under the Retired Emperor Gosaga took the central role in the Retired Emperor Gosaga&apos;s government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and&quot;でつなげず、関係代名詞を使用した方が簡潔になると判断し、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, Akitomo who served as denso (job title to relay message of court&apos;s people to Emperor) under the Retired Emperor Gosaga took the central role in the Retired Emperor Gosaga&apos;s government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>特に六波羅探題でさえ関与する事を渋った比叡山延暦寺関係の交渉において進んで交渉役を引き受けて問題解決を図った事によって上皇の信任を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, in the negotiation related to Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei, the issue in which even Rokuhara Tandai (the office of shogunal deputy in Kyoto placed by the Kamakura shogunate) was reluctant to be involved, he willingly assumed the charge of negotiation and succeeded in resolving the problem, and this lead him to gain further confidence of the Retired Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He particularly gained the confidence of the Retired Emperor because he willingly took charge of negotiating a matter related to Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei in which even Rokuhara Tandai (the office of shogunal deputy in Kyoto placed by the Kamakura shogunate) was reluctant to be involved, and resolved the matter.</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現にするため、「信任を得た」理由を、後に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He particularly gained the confidence of the Retired Emperor because he willingly took charge of negotiating a matter related to Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei in which even Rokuhara Tandai (the office of shogunal deputy in Kyoto placed by the Kamakura shogunate) was reluctant to be involved, and resolved the matter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>宝治2年（1248年）に参議に列すると2年後には権中納言に昇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed Sangi (councilor) in 1248, and two years later, he was promoted to Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He ranked as Sangi (councilor) in 1248, and two years after that, he was promoted to Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>列する→rank as</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He ranked as Sangi (councilor) in 1248, and two years after that, he was promoted to Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後按察使に転じて弘長2年（1262年）には中納言、文永2年には権大納言に昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he became Azechi (inspector of the provincial government), and in 1262, he was appointed Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), and in 1265 (表記の変更) he was promoted to Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitomo who became Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) after that was promoted to Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) in 1262, and to Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) in 1265.</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現にするため、関係代名詞を使用しました。文永2年→1265（（表記の変更）の語句も不要なので、削除しました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akitomo who became Azechi (inspector of the provincial government) after that was promoted to Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) in 1262, and to Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) in 1265.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>顕朝の家系で権大納言に昇った者はおらず、異例の人事であるとともに後嵯峨上皇一番の側近としての地位を内外に認められた証でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there was no other member who was ascended as high as Gon Dainagon in Akitomo&apos;s family line, this was not only an extraordinary career success but also an evidence that it was publicly recognized that he was the closest adviser to Retired Emperor Gosaga.</e>
<cmt>異例人事→extraordinary career successとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above promotion was exceptional and proved that his status as the closest adviser to the Retired Emperor Gosato was recognized publicly because no other person in the Akimoto&apos;s line had been promoted to Gon Dinagon.</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現にするため、語順を変更し、「異例人事」を「上記の昇進」とし、主語としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above promotion was exceptional and proved that his status as the closest adviser to the Retired Emperor Gosato was recognized publicly because no other person in the Akimoto&apos;s line had been promoted to Gon Dinagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、直後に病に倒れて翌年には出家、そのまま病没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, soon after that he fell ill, and the next year he entered into priesthood but died without recovering his health.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he fell ill soon after that, and he entered into priesthood in the following year, and then died as-is.</e>
<cmt>soon after that he fell ill→he fell ill soon after that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he fell ill soon after that, and he entered into priesthood in the following year, and then died as-is.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 中右(id:50196), ５１６(id:45205), Nevylax(id:38464), Cprobot(id:97843), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>