<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平生昌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Narimasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Narimasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Narimasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 生昌（たいらの なりまさ、生没年不詳）は、日本の平安時代中期の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Narimasa (dates of birth and death: unknown) was a court noble in the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Narimasa (dates of birth and death: unknown) was a court noble in the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Narimasa (years of birth and death unknown) was a court noble in the mid-Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>dates of birth and death: unknownを(years of birth and death unknownに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平氏平氏高棟王流贈従三位美作国平珍材の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the second son of TAIRA no Takaki in Mimasaku Province of the Takamuneo line, Heishi (Taira clan), who was raised to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the second son of TAIRA no Takaki in Mimasaku Province of the Takamuneo line, Heishi (Taira clan), who was raised to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of TAIRA no Takaki in Mimasaku Province of the Takamuneo line, Heishi (Taira clan), who was raised to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は備中国青河郡郡司の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Gunji (district manager) in Aoga Country, Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Gunji (district manager) in Aoga Country, Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Gunji (district manager) of Aoga County, Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>inをofに変更しました。CountryをCountyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同母兄に平惟仲があり、子に平雅康、平以康がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His elder brother-uterine is TAIRA no Korenaka and his sons are TAIRA no Masayasu and TAIRA no Mochiyasu&quot;平以康&quot;.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ対応しました。平以康の読みが不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>大学寮出身の叩き上げで、但馬国・中宮職（藤原定子）大進・備中国・播磨国などを歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked his way up as an official from Daigakuryo (training institute of Personal Authority in Heian Period to foster officials) and served in Tajima Province, at Imperial Palace as household official to Chugu (FUJIWARA no Teishi/Sadako), as Daishin (judicial official at the administrative office in Kyoto), and in Bicchu Province and in Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>大学寮→Daigakuryo (training institute of Personal Authority in Heian Period to foster officials) とローマ字表記の後ろに（）内に説明を入れました。 大進→定訳不明Teishin (judicial official at the administrative office in Kyoto)　（）の説明を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked his way up as an official from Daigakuryo (training institute of Personal Authority in Heian Period to foster officials) and served in Tajima Province, at the Imperial Palace as household official to Chugu (FUJIWARA no Teishi/Sadako), as Daishin (judicial official at the administrative office in Kyoto), and in Bicchu Province, and in Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>word spacing, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked his way up as an official from Daigakuryo (training institute of Personal Authority in Heian Period to foster officials) and served in Tajima Province, at the Imperial Palace as household official to Chugu (FUJIWARA no Teishi/Sadako), as Daishin (judicial official at the administrative office in Kyoto), and in Bicchu Province, and in Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>長徳2年（996年）藤原伊周が失脚して大宰権帥に左遷された（長徳の変）際、密かに播磨国から入京したが、生昌はこれを藤原道長に密告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 996 when, FUJIWARA no Korechika was transferred to Dazai Gon no Sochi (deputy administrator of Dazaifu) after his downfall (Chotoku Incident), he secretly returned from Harima Province to enter Kyoto, however Narimasa informed FUJIWARA no Michinaga against Korechika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 996 when, FUJIWARA no Korechika was transferred to Dazai Gon no Sochi (deputy administrator of Dazaifu) after his downfall (Chotoku Incident), he secretly returned from Harima Province to enter Kyoto, however Narimasa informed FUJIWARA no Michinaga about Korechika.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 996 when, FUJIWARA no Korechika was transferred to Dazai Gon no Sochi (deputy administrator of Dazaifu) after his downfall (Chotoku Incident), he secretly returned from Harima Province to enter Kyoto, however Narimasa informed FUJIWARA no Michinaga about Korechika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>長保元年（999年）8月9日 (旧暦)、一条天皇中宮であった藤原定子が敦康親王を懐妊し内裏を退出する際、生昌の邸を行啓先とした</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 26, 999, when Chugu (the Empress) of Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Teishi/ Sadako withdrew the Imperial Palace, as she was pregnant with Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, she chose Narimasa&apos;s residence to give birth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 26, 999, when Chugu (the Empress) of Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Teishi/ Sadako withdrew from the Imperial Palace, as she was pregnant with Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, she chose Narimasa&apos;s residence to give birth</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 26, 999, when Chugu (the Empress) of Emperor Ichijo, FUJIWARA no Teishi/ Sadako withdrew from the Imperial Palace, as she was pregnant with Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, she chose Narimasa&apos;s residence to give birth.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>（生家である二条邸が長徳元年（995年）夏に焼失したため。生昌邸が選ばれたのは、兄である惟仲の縁と思われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(She chose his residence because the residence of the Nijos, where she was born, was burned down in summer of 995, and there was a connection with him through his brother Tadanaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(She chose his residence because the residence of the Nijos, where she was born, was burned down in summer of 995, and there was a connection with him through his brother Tadanaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(She chose his residence because the residence of the Nijo, where she was born, was burned down in summer of 995, and there was a connection with him through his brother Tadanaka).</e>
<cmt>NijosをNijoに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当時定子に仕えていた清少納言は、この時の様子を『枕草子』第五段『大進生昌が家に、宮の出でさせ給ふに、』に記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sei Shonagon, who was serving Teishi/Sadako at that time, wrote this event in &quot;Makurano Soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book) 5th Story titled &apos;When Empress went down to the residence of Daishin Narimasa...&apos;</e>
<cmt>『大進生昌が家に、宮の出でさせ給ふに、』→定訳不明：&apos;When Empress went down to the residence of Daishin Narimasa,...&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sei Shonagon, who was serving Teishi/Sadako at that time, wrote about this event in the &quot;Makurano Soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book) 5th Story titled &apos;When the Empress went down to the residence of Daishin Narimasa...&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sei Shonagon, who was serving Teishi/Sadako at that time, wrote about this event in the &quot;Makurano Soshi&quot; (The Pillow Book) 5th Story titled &quot;When the Empress went down to the residence of Daishin Narimasa...&quot;</e>
<cmt>を&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>定子は翌年、同じく生昌邸で媄子内親王を出産し崩御した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year Teishi/ Sadako died after giving birth to Imperial Princess Bishi at the same Narimasa&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year Teishi/ Sadako died after giving birth to Imperial Princess Bishi at the same Narimasa&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year Teishi/ Sadako died after giving birth to Imperial Princess Bishi at the same Narimasa&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>寛弘6年（1009年）、東宮居貞親王（のちの三条天皇）御所への昇殿を許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1009 he was permitted to the imperial court of Imperial Crown Prince Okisada/ Iyasada (later 三条天皇Emperor Sanjo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1009 he was permitted to enter the imperial court of Imperial Crown Prince Okisada/ Iyasada (later 三条天皇Emperor Sanjo)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1009 he was permitted to enter the Imperial Palace of Imperial Crown Prince Okisada/ Iyasada (later Emperor Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>imperial courtを Imperial Palaceに変更しました。三条天皇を省きました。ピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>没年は不詳だが、長和5年（1016年）12月にはすでに卒去していたらしい（『日本紀略』長和5年12月10日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His date of death is not known, however, it seems that he had already died in December 1016/ January 1017 (the article of December 10, 1016 in old lunisolar calendar (January 16, 1017) in&quot;Nihon Ryakki&quot; (Summarized chronicle of Japan).</e>
<cmt>長和5年（1016年）12月→December 1016/ January 1017としました。もし「長和5年12月」なら西暦January 1017 になります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His date of death is not known, however, it seems that he had already died as of December 1016/ January 1017 (the article of December 10, 1016 in old lunisolar calendar (January 16, 1017) in&quot;Nihon Ryakki&quot; (Summarized chronicle of Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His date of death is not known, however, it seems that he had already died as of January, 1017 (the article of December 10, 1016 in&quot;Nihon Ryakki&quot; (Summarized chronicle of Japan)).</e>
<cmt>没年をグレゴリオ暦に変更しました。Lunisolarをlunarに変更しました。 in old lunar calendar (January 16, 1017)を削除しました。)を閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Lonicera(id:20638), YOSHI438(id:174755), Goki(id:7107), Mark-zero(id:48822), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>