<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>古高俊太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuntaro FURUTAKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuntaro FURUTAKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuntaro FURUTAKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>古高 俊太郎（ふるたか しゅんたろう、文政12年（1829年） - 元治元年7月20日 (旧暦)（1864年8月21日）は、攘夷派の志士の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuntaro FURUTAKA (1829-August 21, 1864) was one of patriots of Joi-ha (supporters of expulsion of the foreigners.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuntaro FURUTAKA (1829 - August 21, 1864) was among the patriots of the Joi-ha (supporters of the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuntaro FURUTAKA (1829 - August 21, 1864) was among the patriots of the Joi-ha (supporters of the expulsion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Personal Character</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストによる</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近江国栗太郡古高村（現・守山市）の郷士の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a child from the Goshi hierarchy in Furutaka-cho, Kurita-gun, Omi-no-kuni (now, Moriyama City.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a child from the Goshi hierarchy in Furutaka-cho, Kurita-gun, Omi-no-kuni (the present-day Moriyama City).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a child from the Goshi hierarchy in Furutaka-mura Village, Kurita County, Omi Province (the present-day Moriyama City).</e>
<cmt>地名表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>変名・湯浅喜右衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Changed name: Kiemon YUASA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He changed his name to Kiemon YUASA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His assumed name was Kiemon YUASA.</e>
<cmt>変名は偽名の意味と思うので、修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>諱は正順（まさより）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Masanori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name, however, was Masanori.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Masayori.</e>
<cmt>Masanori→Masayori</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>尊皇攘夷を唱える梅田雲浜の門を叩いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He called on Unpin UMEDA advocating Sonno-joi (slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the exclusion of foreigners.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He called on Unpin UMEDA, advocating Sonno-joi (a slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the exclusion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He called on Unpin UMEDA, advocating Sonno-joi (a slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the exclusion of foreigners).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>文久元年、京都河原町通四条上ル東で諸藩御用達・枡屋を継ぎ古道具、馬具を扱いながら、早くから宮部鼎蔵らと交流し、長州間者の大元締として情報活動と武器調達にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1861, he took over the Masuya with domain&apos;s warrant at Kawaramachi-dori Shijo Agaru Higashi, Kyoto to handle used articles and harness/trappings, and was engaged in information activities and the procurement of weapons as Omotojime (chief superintendent) for Choshu&apos;s spy having contact with Teizo MIYABE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1861, he took over the Masuya with the domain&apos;s warrant at Kawaramachi-dori Shijo Agaru Higashi, Kyoto, in order to handle used articles and harnesses/trappings, but he was also engaged in information activities and the procurement of weapons as the omotojime (chief superintendent) for Choshu&apos;s spy, since he had contact with Teizo MIYABE.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1861, he took over the business of Masuya, a purveyor to various domains, at Shijo Agaru Higashi, Kawaramachi-dori Street, Kyoto, in order to handle used articles and harnesses/trappings, but he was also engaged in information activities and the procurement of weapons as the omotojime (chief superintendent) of the Choshu domain&apos;s spies, since he had contact with Teizo MIYABE.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に沿うように書き換えました。地名表記の修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>新選組</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinsen-gumi Masterless Warrior Party</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinsen-gumi Masterless Warrior Party</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>元治元年6月5日 (旧暦)、新選組に踏み込まれ捕縛される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 5, 1864, he was suddenly attacked by Shinsen-gumi masterless warriors&apos; party and captured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 5, 1864, he was suddenly attacked and captured by the Shinsen-gumi Masterless Warrior Party.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 8, 1864, he was suddenly attacked and captured by the Shinsen-gumi Masterless Warrior Party.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>武器弾薬を押収され、諸藩浪士との書簡や血判書が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Weapons and ammunition were confiscated and letters exchanged with masterless warriors of various domains and paper with a seal of blood were found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Weapons and ammunition were confiscated along with letters exchanged with masterless warriors of various domains; additionally, papers sealed with blood were found.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Weapons and ammunition were confiscated; additionally, letters exchanged with masterless warriors of various domains and papers sealed with blood were found.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に沿うように書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>今も現存する壬生屯所前川邸の蔵で、局長近藤勇、副長土方歳三から直々に厳しい取調べを受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had harsh interrogations directly from Isami KONDO, chief and Toshizo HIJIKATA, vice chief in a storehouse of Maekawa Residence, Mibu Tamurojo post, still existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was subjected to harsh interrogations directly from the chief, Isami KONDO, and the vice-chief Toshizo HIJIKATA in a storehouse of the Maekawa residence, Mibu Tamurojo post, which still exists today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was subjected to harsh interrogations directly from the chief, Isami KONDO, and the vice-chief Toshizo HIJIKATA in a storehouse of the Maekawa residence, Mibu Tamurojo post, which still exists today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>二階から逆さ吊りにされ、足の甲から五寸釘を打たれ、それが突き抜けた足の裏の釘に百目蝋燭を立てられ火をつけられる過酷な拷問だったため、ついに古高も自白。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since FURUTAKA was terribly tortured with his body hung upside down from the second floor, Gosun-kugi long nails hammered in his insteps and lighting Hyakume-rosoku Candles placed on the nails penetrating his sole, he at last confessed himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FURUTAKA was severely tortured with his body hung upside down from the second floor, gosun-kugi (long nails) hammered into his insteps and Hyakume-rosoku candles placed on the nails penetrating his sole, so that ultimately he confessed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FURUTAKA was severely tortured with his body hung upside down from the second floor, gosun-kugi (long nails) hammered into his insteps and Hyakume-rosoku candles placed on the nails penetrating his sole, so that ultimately he confessed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>その内容は、八月十八日の政変後、京を追われた長州人らが六月下旬の強風の日を選んで御所に火を放ち、佐幕派公家の久邇宮朝彦親王を幽閉し京都守護職の松平容保以下佐幕派大名を殺害し、天皇を長州へ連れ去ろうとするものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The content of his confession was that after the Coups of August eighteenth, Choshu-jin (Choshu citizen,) etc. forced out of Kyo would set fire on the Imperial Palace on an certain very windy day in late June, confine Imperial Prince Asahiko KUNINOMIYA, Sabaku-ha (group of Feudal Government supporters) court noble, kill Katamori MATSUDAIRA and other Sabaku-ha Daimyo (feudal lords who support Feudal Government) and take away the Emperor to Choshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The content of his confession was that after the coup of August 18, the Choshu-jin (Choshu citizen,) etc. forced out of Kyo would set fire to the Imperial Palace on an certain very windy day in late June, thus confining Crown Prince Asahiko KUNINOMIYA and the Sabaku-ha (a group of feudal government supporters) court nobles; and would then kill Katamori MATSUDAIRA and other Sabaku-ha Daimyo (feudal lords who supported the feudal government) and take the Emperor to Choshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The content of his confession was that after the coup of August 18, the Choshu-jin (Choshu citizen,) etc. forced out of Kyo would set fire to the Imperial Palace on an certain very windy day in late June, thus confining Crown Prince Asahiko KUNINOMIYA, a Sabaku-ha (a group of feudal government supporters) court noble; and would then kill Katamori MATSUDAIRA and other Sabaku-ha Daimyo (feudal lords who supported the feudal government) and take the Emperor to Choshu.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に沿うように書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>すでに計画実行の志士が多数上洛、潜伏しており近々市中で同志の集会があることも判明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was figured out that a number of patriots intending to execute the plan had gone to Kyoto and were hiding there and that such supporters would meet together in the town soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was figured out that a number of patriots intending to execute the plan had gone to Kyoto and were hiding there, and that such supporters would soon gather in the town.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was figured out that a number of patriots intending to execute the plan had gone to Kyoto and were hiding there, and that such supporters would soon gather in the town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これを阻止したのが池田屋事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What thwarted this was Ikedaya Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This plot was thwarted by the occurrence of the Ikedaya Incident.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This plot was thwarted by the occurrence of the Ikedaya Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>古高は六角獄舎に収容されたが、7月20日に禁門の変の際に生じたどんどん焼けは京都市中を焼き尽くし、獄舎近辺まで延焼。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When FURUTAKA was being locked up in the Rokkaku prison house, Dondon-yake occurred at the time of Kimmon no Hen (Conspiracy of Kimmon) on July 20 burnt down inside Kyoto City and spread the fire close to the prison house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When FURUTAKA was locked up in the Rokkaku prison house, the Dondon-yake--which occurred at the time of Kimmon no Hen (the Conspiracy of Kimmon) on July 20--burned through Kyoto City, and the fire spread close to the prison house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When FURUTAKA was locked up in the Rokkaku prison house, the Dondon-yaki fire--which occurred at the time of Kinmon no Hen (the Conspiracy of Kinmon) on August 21--burned through Kyoto City, and the fire spread close to the prison house.</e>
<cmt>the Dondon-yake→the Dondon-yaki fireKimmon→Kinmon</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>火災に乗じて逃亡することを恐れた役人により、他の囚人とともに斬首となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Officials who were frightened about the escape of the prisoners under the fire beheaded him together with other prisoners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Officials who were frightened about the escape of those incarcerated due to the fire beheaded Furutaka together with other prisoners.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Officials who were frightened about the escape of those incarcerated due to the fire beheaded Furutaka together with other prisoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>享年36。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 36.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 36.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 36.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Opponent(id:720), Tanuki Z(id:612), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Boa(id:20845), 上田隼人(id:23104), Reggaeman(id:6214), Wei Yuan(id:13342), Y.o-ji-nn(id:39866), Yanahan(id:2437), 土方　誠(id:3651), たとゥ(id:25557), Maakun(id:16735), Rosemary org(id:71930), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>