<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大江千古</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;OE no Chifuru&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;OE no Chifuru&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Chifuru</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大江千古（おおえ の ちふる、貞観 (日本)8年（866年） - 延長 (元号)2年5月29日 (旧暦)（924年7月8日））は、平安時代の貴族、公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born in 866 and gone on July 8, 924, &quot;OE no Chifuru&quot; was a Court noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born in 866 and died on July 8, 924, &quot;OE no Chifuru&quot; was a Court noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Chifuru (866 - July 8, 924) was a court noble in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>表記を訂正しました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。court 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大江音人の九男で、兄に大江千里 (歌人)がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the ninth son of &quot;OE no Otondo,&quot; and he had an older brother &quot;OE no Chisato&quot; who was a maker of Japanese poetry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the ninth son of &quot;OE no Otondo,&quot; and he had an older brother &quot;OE no Chisato&quot; who was a maker of Japanese poetry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 9th son of OE no Otondo, and he had an older brother OE no Chisato who was a waka poet.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。&quot; &quot;削除しました。waka poetに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>従四位・式部省。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chifuru got the investiture of &quot;Jusii&quot; (Junior Fourth Court Rank), and of the official of &quot;Shikibu-sho&quot; (Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chifuru received the investiture of &quot;Jusii&quot; (Junior Fourth Court Rank), and of the official of &quot;Shikibu-sho&quot; (Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chifuru received the investiture of Jusii (Junior Fourth Rank), and of the official of Shikibusho (Ministry of Ceremonial).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。Court 削除しました。ハイフン削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>漢学について詳しく、醍醐天皇の侍読を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was familiar with the study of the Chinese classics, so he served as &quot;Jidoku&quot; (the imperial tutor) of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was familiar with the study of the Chinese classics, so he served as &quot;Jidoku&quot; (the imperial tutor) of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was familiar with the study of the Chinese classics, so he served as Jidoku (the Imperial tutor) of Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。Imperial 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>『後撰和歌集』に千古の「冬の歌」と「恋の歌」の二つの歌があり、『新古今和歌集』には延喜6年（906年）の日本紀竟宴の時に詠まれた千古の歌がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chifuru&apos;s two poems - one was about winter and the other was about love - were selected into &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry), and when the completion of &quot;Nihongi&quot; (the six classical Japanese history texts) was celebrated in 906, he made another poem, which was selected into &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>※「竟宴」とは、平安時代に宮中で勅撰和歌集の編纂などが終わった際に催された祝宴のことです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chifuru&apos;s two poems - one was about winter and the other was about love - were selected into &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry), and when the completion of &quot;Nihongi&quot; (the six classical Japanese history texts) was celebrated in 906, he made another poem, which was selected into &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chifuru&apos;s two poems, one was about winter and the other was about love, were selected into &quot;Gosen Wakashu&quot; (Later Selected Collection of Japanese Poetry), and when the completion of Nihongi (the six classical Japanese history texts) was celebrated in 906, he made another poem, which was selected into &quot;Shin Kokin Wakashu&quot; (New Collection of Ancient and Modern Japanese Poetry).</e>
<cmt>― をコンマに訂正しました。原文に合せて&quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>官歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Court rank &amp; title</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Court rank &amp; title</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Record of offices and ranks held</e>
<cmt>統一表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>924年（延長2年）5月29日、卒去（没日を2月2日とする説もある）時に伊予権守従四位下。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he passed away on July 8 (on March 14, a theory says), 924, he got the investiture of &quot;Iyo no Gon no kami&quot; (the provisional governor of Iyo Province), and of &quot;Jushiinoge&quot; (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he passed away on July 8 (on March 14, a theory says), 924, he received the investiture of &quot;Iyo no Gon no kami&quot; (the provisional governor of Iyo Province), and of &quot;Jushiinoge&quot; (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he passed away on July 8 (on March 14, a theory says), 924, he received the investiture of Iyo no Gon no kami (the provisional governor of Iyo Province), and of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Snap55(id:89773), 松茸(id:27535), 可怜(id:206074), Rghsk06(id:33185), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>