<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>堀尾忠晴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu HORIO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaharu HORIO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaharu HORIO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>堀尾 忠晴（ほりお ただはる、慶長4年（1599年）- 寛永10年9月24日 (旧暦)（1633年10月26日））は、江戸時代の外様大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu HORIO (1599-October 26, 1633) was a tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord) who lived in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaharu HORIO (1599 - October 26, 1633) was a tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord) who lived in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaharu HORIO (1599 - October 26, 1633) was a tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord) who lived in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>堀尾忠氏の子で、堀尾吉晴の孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu was a son of Tadauji HORIO and a grandson of Yoshiharu HORIO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Tadauji HORIO and a grandson of Yoshiharu HORIO.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Tadauji HORIO and a grandson of Yoshiharu HORIO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>出雲国松江藩第3代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu HORIO was the third Lord of the Matsue Domain in Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third Lord of the Matsue Domain in Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third Lord of the Matsue Domain in Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正室は徳川秀忠の養女（奥平家昌の娘）ビン姫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s seishitsu (the lawful wife) was Bin hime (Lady Bin), who was an adopted daughter of Hidetada TOKUGAWA (and a biological daughter of Iemasa OKUDAIRA.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaharu&apos;s lawful wife was Bin hime (Lady Bin), who was an adopted daughter of Hidetada TOKUGAWA (a daughter of Iemasa OKUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s lawful wife was Bin hime (Lady Bin), who was an adopted daughter of Hidetada TOKUGAWA (a daughter of Iemasa OKUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>娘に石川廉勝室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s daughters included the lawful wife of Kadokatsu ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaharu&apos;s daughters included the lawful wife of Kadokatsu ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s daughters included the lawful wife of Kadokatsu ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>官位は従四位下、山城国守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu was given an official rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade,) being the Yamashiro no kuni no kami (the Governor of Yamashiro Province.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaharu was given an official rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), being the Yamashiro no kuni no kami (the Governor of Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド、カンマの位置を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaharu was given an official rank of Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), being the Yamashiro no kuni no kami (the Governor of Yamashiro Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幼名は三之介。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s childhood name was Sannosuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaharu&apos;s childhood name was Sannosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s childhood name was Sannosuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>慶長9年（1604年）、父の忠氏が早世したため、幼くして後を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1604, at a young age Tadaharu succeeded his father Tadauji, who had died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1604, young Tadaharu succeeded his father Tadauji, who had died young.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1604, young Tadaharu succeeded his father Tadauji, who had died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし政治を取り仕切れるような年齢ではなかったため、祖父の吉晴が忠晴に代わって執政を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu, however, was too little to be a political leader then, and so his grandfather Yoshiharu administered the affairs of the domain on behalf of Tadaharu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was too little to be a political leader then, however, so his grandfather Yoshiharu administered the affairs of the domain on behalf of Tadaharu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was too little to be a political leader then, however, so his grandfather Yoshiharu administered the affairs of the domain on behalf of Tadaharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このとき伯母（吉晴の長女、名前は不明）と一族で筆頭家老の堀尾河内守（吉晴の娘の子）親子による家督横領の陰謀が発覚し、河内守と掃部の父子は流罪のうえ切腹を申し付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time such a plot was revealed that was to embezzle the headship of the family from Tadaharu, which had been planned by Tadaharu&apos;s paternal aunt (who was Yoshiharu&apos;s oldest daughter and whose name was unknown) and her son Horio Kawachi no kami (Horio, the Governor of Kawachi Province), who was the hitto karo (the head of chief retainers), and the Kawachi no kami and his son Kamon were banished to be executed by committing seppuku (the ritual form of suicide done by cutting one&apos;s own belly open when taking responsibility for one&apos;s own actions or to punish oneself).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time Tadaharu&apos;s paternal aunt (Yoshiharu&apos;s oldest daughter whose name was unknown) and Horio, Kawachi no kami (the Governor of Kawachi Province, a son of Yoshiharu&apos;s daughter) who was a member of the family and the hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) attempted to embezzle the headship of the family from Tadaharu, but the plot was revealed then the Kawachi no kami and the kamori (Housekeeping, his father) were exiled and ordered seppuku (suicide by disembowelment).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time Tadaharu&apos;s paternal aunt (Yoshiharu&apos;s oldest daughter whose name was unknown) and Horio, Kawachi no kami (the Governor of Kawachi Province, a son of Yoshiharu&apos;s daughter) who was a member of the family and the hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) attempted to embezzle the headship of the family from Tadaharu, but the plot was revealed then the Kawachi no kami and the kamori (Housekeeping, his father) were exiled and ordered seppuku (suicide by disembowelment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後の仙石騒動にも似た事件であり、有力外様大名家の内紛とあって改易されてもおかしくなかったが、吉晴が健在であったためか難を逃れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This resembled the Sengoku sodo disturbance to follow later and, therefore, deserved the kaieki sanction because it was an infighting within the household of a powerful tozama daimyo, but they narrowly escaped the sanction probably because Yoshiharu was in good health.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This resembled the Sengoku sodo Disturbance later and, therefore, deserved the Kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties) because it was family infighting of a powerful tozama daimyo, but they narrowly escaped the sanction probably because Yoshiharu was still alive.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This resembled the Sengoku sodo Disturbance later and, therefore, deserved the Kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties) because it was family infighting of a powerful tozama daimyo, but they narrowly escaped the sanction probably because Yoshiharu was still alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>慶長16年（1611年）、祖父が死去すると親政を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon his grandfather&apos;s death in 1611, Tadaharu initiated his own direct rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon his grandfather&apos;s death in 1611, Tadaharu initiated his own direct rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon his grandfather&apos;s death in 1611, Tadaharu initiated his own direct rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>忠晴と名乗ったのはこれ以降のことである（それ以前の諱は不明）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name Tadaharu began to be used since then (his former &apos;imina&apos; which is the real name is unknown.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then he called himself Tadaharu (his former personal name is unknown).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then he called himself Tadaharu (his former personal name is unknown).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>藩主としてこれといった治績は伝わっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No particular achievements by Lord Tadaharu Horio are known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No particular achievements by Lord Tadaharu HORIO are known.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No particular achievements by Lord Tadaharu HORIO are known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>大坂の役では武功を立てたほか、軍令違反を咎めた徳川家の軍奉行を器量で圧倒して黙らせるというエピソードを残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been known that Tadaharu distinguished himself in the Ozaka no eki (the Siege of Osaka) and that he silenced a gun bugyo (military commissioner) of the Tokugawa family, who had accused him of an act in violation of the military command, by his overwhelmingly high competence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been known that Tadaharu distinguished himself in the Siege of Osaka and that he silenced a gun bugyo (military commissioner) of the Tokugawa family, who had accused him of an act in violation of the military command, by his overwhelmingly high competence.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been known that Tadaharu distinguished himself in the Siege of Osaka and that he silenced a gun bugyo (military commissioner) of the Tokugawa family, who had accused him of an act in violation of the military command, by his overwhelmingly high competence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「仏の茂助」「鬼茂助」と言われた祖父の2つの顔を共に受け継ぐ名君・名将、どちらかといえば武の人であったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu was both a wise ruler and a great commander, who inherited such a dual character from his grandfather who had been called &apos;Hotoke no Mosuke&apos; (Saintly Mosuke) and &apos;Oni Mosuke&apos; (Devilish Mosuke), thus being more of a warrior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaharu was both a wise ruler and a great commander, who inherited such a dual character from his grandfather who had been called &apos;Hotoke no Mosuke&apos; (Saintly Mosuke) and &apos;Oni Mosuke&apos; (Devilish Mosuke), thus being more of a warrior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaharu was both a wise ruler and a great commander, who inherited such a dual character from his grandfather who had been called &apos;Hotoke no Mosuke&apos; (Saintly Mosuke) and &apos;Oni Mosuke&apos; (Devilish Mosuke), thus being more of a warrior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その男らしさを幕府からも信頼されたか、元和 (日本)5年（1619年）、福島正則が幕命によって信濃国川中島（高井野藩）に減転封されたとき、広島城の城受け取りを務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s masculinity appears to have been relied upon by the shogunate, in that in 1619 when Masanori FUKUSHIMA was transferred from Hiroshima to a smaller domain of Kawanakajima (Takaino-han Domain) in Shinano Province due to the shogunal sanction of kaieki, Tadaharu attended the handover of Hiroshima-jo Castle to be the recipient.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaharu&apos;s masculinity might have been relied upon by the shogunate that in 1619 when Masanori FUKUSHIMA was transferred from Hiroshima to a smaller domain of Kawanakajima (Takaino Domain) in Shinano Province due to the shogunal order, Tadaharu attended the handover of Hiroshima-jo Castle to be the recipient.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s masculinity might have been relied upon by the shogunate that in 1619 when Masanori FUKUSHIMA was transferred from Hiroshima to a smaller domain of Kawanakajima (Takaino Domain) in Shinano Province due to the shogunal order, Tadaharu attended the handover of Hiroshima-jo Castle to be the recipient.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>寛永10年（1633年）、死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu HORIO died in 1633.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1633.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1633.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>死因は酒害と推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s death was allegedly caused by alcohol.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that Tadaharu&apos;s death was caused by alcohol.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that Tadaharu&apos;s death was caused by alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>正室・側妾いずれとの間にも嗣子が無く、従兄弟の堀尾宗十郎（父親はおそらく堀尾氏泰であろう）を末期養子に立てることを希望したが認められず、ここに堀尾宗家は断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As neither his lawful wife nor his concubine gave birth to a son, Tadaharu wished his cousin Sojuro HORIO (whose father may have been Ujiyasu HORIO) to be his &apos;matsugo yoshi&apos; (a son adopted on one&apos;s deathbed), which was not permitted, thereby allowing the head family of the Horio to be extinct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As neither his lawful wife nor his concubine gave birth to a son, Tadaharu wished his cousin Sojuro HORIO (whose father may have been Ujiyasu HORIO) to be his Matsugo-yoshi (a son adopted on one&apos;s deathbed), which was not permitted, thereby allowing the head of the Horio family to be extinct.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As neither his lawful wife nor his concubine gave birth to a son, Tadaharu wished his cousin Sojuro HORIO (whose father may have been Ujiyasu HORIO) to be his Matsugo-yoshi (a son adopted on one&apos;s deathbed), which was not permitted, thereby allowing the head of the Horio family to be extinct.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>一族のうち、吉晴の従兄弟の堀尾但馬や吉晴の弟堀尾氏光の子堀尾氏晴などが越前松平家に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Horio family line, Tajima HORIO, who was Yoshiharu&apos;s cousin, and Ujiharu HORIO, whose father Ujimitsu was a younger brother of Yoshiharu, served the Matsudaira family of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Horio family line, Tajima HORIO, who was Yoshiharu&apos;s cousin, and Ujiharu HORIO, whose father Ujimitsu HORIO was a younger brother of Yoshiharu, served the Matsudaira family of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Horio family line, Tajima HORIO, who was Yoshiharu&apos;s cousin, and Ujiharu HORIO, whose father Ujimitsu HORIO was a younger brother of Yoshiharu, served the Matsudaira family of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>細川氏にも堀尾茂助（四代目）が仕えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mosuke HORIO (the fourth) served the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mosuke HORIO (the fourth) served the Hosokawa clan as well.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mosuke HORIO (the fourth) served the Hosokawa clan as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>墓所：東京都文京区千駄木の円成寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s grave: Enjo-ji Temple in Sendagi, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>「円成寺」読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaharu&apos;s grave: Enjo-ji Temple (円成寺) in Sendagi, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>読み不明の漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaharu&apos;s grave: Enjo-ji Temple (円成寺) in Sendagi, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>養源寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yogen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yogen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yogen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>島根県松江市の円成寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enjo-ji Temple in Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enjo-ji Temple in Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enjo-ji Temple in Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>京都府京都市右京区の春光院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunkoin Temple in Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunkoin Temple in Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunkoin Temple in Ukyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>江戸初期の書物「寧固斎談叢」では前田利常との恋愛関係が取りざたされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Neikosai Danso&quot; (the collection of commentaries by Neikosai) which was written in the early Edo period refers to a romantic relationship between Tadaharu HORIO and Toshitsune MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Neikosai Danso&quot; http://www.ccsenet.org/journal/index.php/ass/article/viewFile/3830/3585</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neikosai Danso&apos; (the collection of commentaries by Neikosai) which was written in the early Edo period refers to a romantic relationship between Tadaharu HORIO and Toshitsune MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neikosai Danso&apos; (the collection of commentaries by Neikosai) which was written in the early Edo period refers to a romantic relationship between Tadaharu HORIO and Toshitsune MAEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yonoemon(id:55450), Nnh(id:474), YurikBot(id:18605), Blowback(id:173308), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Reggaeman(id:6214), 松茸(id:27535), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), Point136(id:211299), Seibuabina(id:37532), こぶまき(id:38278), Sorrysorry(id:102591), シェーラ(id:17988), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>