<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上杉氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uesugi Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uesugi Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uesugi Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>上杉氏（うえすぎし、うえすぎうじ）は、日本の氏族の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uesugi clan (Uesugi-shi, Uesugi-uji) is one of the clans in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Uesugi Clan (pronounced either Uesugi-shi or Uesugi-uji in Japanese) was a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;&quot;Uesugi-shi, Uesugi-uji&quot;→&quot;pronounced either Uesugi-shi or Uesugi-uji in Japanese&quot;&quot;is one of the clans in Japan&quot;→&quot;was a Japanese clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Uesugi clan (pronounced either Uesugi-shi or Uesugi-uji in Japanese) was a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元は公家であるが、鎌倉幕府の将軍に選ばれた親王の従者として関東に下向し、武士化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally a court noble, it was picked by the Shogun of Kamakura Shogunate as a servant to a prince and went to Kanto, then became warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally aristocrats, they became warriors after moving to Kanto as vassals of Prince Munetaka when he was chosen to be Shogun,</e>
<cmt>&quot;a court noble&quot;→&quot;aristocrats&quot;Sentence mistranslated - the Prince was chosen to be Shogun not the clan to be his vasslas</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally aristocrats, they became warriors after moving to Kanto as vassals of Imperial Prince Munetaka when he was chosen to be Shogun.</e>
<cmt>,→.Imperialを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>京都府綾部市上杉が名字の地。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uesugi, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture is the place from which the surname was taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They took their name from Uesugi in Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is the place from which the surname was taken&quot;→&quot;They took their name from&quot; and movedAdded &quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They took their name from Uesugi in Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉時代、室町時代から江戸時代にかけて栄えた武家の一族が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The warrior family that prospered from Kamakura and Muromachi Periods to Edo Period is well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are well-known for being a warrior family that prospered from the Kamakura and Muromachi Periods to the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Reworded sentenceAdded &quot;the&quot; before period names</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are well-known for being a warrior family that prospered from the Kamakura and Muromachi Periods to the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出自・概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin and Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin and Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin and Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原北家勧修寺流の流れを汲み、鎌倉時代の中頃まで京都の中級公家の家柄であった、重房の代に至って丹波国何鹿郡上杉庄（うえすぎのしょう、現在の京都府綾部市上杉町周辺）を領したことにより上杉を名字とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Belonging to the Kajuji line of Fujiwara North Household, it was a mid-class court noble family, but during the generation of Shigefusa it put in charge of Uesugi no Sho in Ikaruga District of Tanba Province (present-day vicinity of Uesugicho, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture), thereby acquiring the surname of Uesugi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Belonging to the Kajuji line of the Northern (Hokke) Fujiwara, they were a middle rank aristocratic family until the mid-Kamakura Period, when Shigefusa Kajuji was put in charge of Uesugi no Sho in Ikaruga District of Tanba Province (present-day vicinity of Uesugicho, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture), thereby acquiring the surname of Uesugi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;line&quot;→&quot;branch&quot;&quot;Fujiwara North Household&quot;→&quot;the Northern (Hokke) Fujiwara&quot;&quot;it was a mid-class court noble family&quot;→&quot;they were a middle rank aristocratic family&quot;Added &quot;until the mid-Kamakura Period&quot;&quot;but during the generation of Shigefusa it&quot;→&quot;when Shigefusa Kajuji was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Belonging to the Kajuji line of the Northern (Hokke) Fujiwara, they were a middle rank aristocratic family until the mid-Kamakura Period, when Shigefusa Kajuji was put in charge of Uesugi no Sho in Ikaruga District of Tanba Province (present-day vicinity of Uesugicho, Ayabe City, Kyoto Prefecture), thereby acquiring the surname of Uesugi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>足利尊氏は当地で産まれたとの伝承が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a lore that Takauji ASHIKAGA was born in this region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a tradition that Takauji ASHIKAGA was born in this region.</e>
<cmt>&quot;lore&quot;→&quot;tradition&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a tradition that Takauji ASHIKAGA was born in this region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元々は、天皇家に仕える公家であったが、鎌倉時代後期、親王の将軍就任に従って鎌倉へ下向してのちに武士となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, they were court nobles who served the Imperial Family, but they moved to Kamakura upon the prince&apos;s installation as Shogun during late Kamakura Period, after which they became warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, they were court nobles who served the Imperial Family, but they moved to Kamakura upon Prince Munetaka&apos;s installation as Shogun during the late Kamakura Period, after which they became warriors.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the prince&apos;s&quot;→&quot;Prince Munetaka&apos;s&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, they were court nobles who served the Imperial Family, but they moved to Kamakura upon Imperial Prince Munetaka&apos;s installation as Shogun during the late Kamakura Period, after which they became warriors.</e>
<cmt>Imperialを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>のち足利氏の姻戚として勢力を伸ばした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They later expanded their power as relatives of Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They later expanded their power as relatives of Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They later expanded their power as relatives of Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>室町時代は鎌倉府にあって鎌倉公方の執事、次いで関東管領の職を世襲し、相模国、武蔵国、上野国、越後国など一門で4ヶ国の守護職を占める有力守護大名としても栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Muromachi Period they passed on the stewardship of Kamakura kobo and subsequently Kanto kanrei position through hereditary succession, and they also prospered as a powerful shugo daimyo family that single-handedly occupied Shugoshiki in 4 provinces of Sagami. Musashi, Kozuke and Echigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi Period they passed on the stewardship of the Kamakura Kubo and subsequently the Kanto Kanrei position through hereditary succession, and they also prospered as a powerful shugo daimyo family that held the governorship of Sagami, Musashi, Kozuke and Echigo Provinces.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;kobo&quot;→&quot;Kubo&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;k&apos;&quot;single-handedly occupied Shugoshiki in 4 provinces&quot;→&quot;held the governorship&quot;Full stop→commaAdded &quot;Provinces&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi Period they passed on the stewardship of the Kamakura Kubo and subsequently the Kanto Kanrei position (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) through hereditary succession, and they also prospered as a powerful shugo daimyo family that held the governorship of Sagami, Musashi, Kozuke and Echigo Provinces.</e>
<cmt>関東管領、説明補足 (A shogunal deputy for the Kanto region)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、従来より鎌倉府に仕え関東に拠点のあった山内上杉家と、当初は室町幕府に仕えて京都に在住した扇谷上杉家が、関東の覇権をかけて内紛を起こし次第に勢力を衰退させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, their power gradually declined due to the internal strife over hegemony in Kanto between Yamanouchi Uesugi family that was already based in Kanto and had been serving Kamakura-fu, and the Ogigayatsu Uesugi family that originally lived in Kyoto and served Muromachi-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, their power gradually declined due to internal strife over hegemony in Kanto between the Yamanouchi Uesugi family that was already based in Kanto and had been serving Kamakura-fu, and the Ogigayatsu Uesugi family that originally lived in Kyoto and served Muromachi-fu.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, their power gradually declined due to internal strife over hegemony in Kanto between the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family that was already based in Kanto and had been serving Kamakura-fu, and the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi family that originally lived in Kyoto and served Muromachi-fu.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)には関東における覇権を、次第に新興勢力である後北条氏に押され、山内上杉家の当主上杉憲政は、越後守護代として勢力を台頭させていた長尾氏の長尾景虎（後の上杉謙信）に上杉の名跡を譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Period of Civil War, hegemony over Kanto was gradually taken over by the newly arising force of Go-Hojo clan, and the head of Yamanouchi Uesugi family, Norimasa UESUGI, passed on the name of Uesugi to Kagetora NAGAO (later Kenshin UESUGI) of Nagao clan who was gaining power as shugodai in Echigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Warring States Period, control of Kanto was gradually taken over by the newly arising force of the Go-Hojo Clan, and the head of the Yamanouchi Uesugi family, Norimasa UESUGI, passed on the Uesugi name to Kagetora NAGAO (later Kenshin UESUGI) of the Nagao Clan, who was gaining power as the Governor of Echigo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Period of Civil War&quot;→&quot;Warring States Period&quot;Added &quot;Provinces&quot;&quot;hegemony over&quot;→&quot;control of&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;capitalized &apos;c&apos;Moved &quot;Uesugi&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added comma&quot;shugodai in&quot;→&quot;the Governor of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Warring States Period, control of Kanto was gradually taken over by the newly arising force of the Gohojo clan, and the head of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family, Norimasa UESUGI, passed on the Uesugi name to Kagetora NAGAO (later Kenshin UESUGI) of the Nagao clan, who was gaining power as the Governor of Echigo.</e>
<cmt>Go-Hojo Clan→Gohojo clan-補足Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>景虎は山内上杉家督、関東管領就任により上杉政虎（輝虎）と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagetora took on the name of Masatora (Terutora) UESUGI upon succeeding as the head of Yamanouchi Uesugi family and assuming the position of Kanto Kanrei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagetora took the name of Masatora (Terutora) UESUGI upon succeeding as head of the Yamanouchi Uesugi family and assuming the position of Kanto Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;on&quot; and &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagetora took the name of Masatora (Terutora) UESUGI upon succeeding as head of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family and assuming the position of Kanto Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これにより再び上杉氏は勢いを取り戻し、その養子上杉景勝（長尾氏のうち長尾氏より）は豊臣政権の五大老を務め、会津藩120万石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through this, Uesugi clan gradually regained power, and his adopted son, Kagekatsu UESUGI (from Nagao clan within Nagao clan), served as a Go-tairo in the Toyotomi government and received Aizu domain with 1.2 million koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this, the Uesugi Clan gradually regained power and his adopted son, Kagekatsu UESUGI (of the Nagao Clan), served n th Council of Five Elders (Go-Tairo) in the Toyotomi government and received Aizu domain, worth 1.2 million koku.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;The section in brackets makes no sense in Japanese or English so reworded it&quot;as a Go-tairo&quot;→&quot;on th Council of Five Elders (Go-Tairo)&quot;&quot;with&quot;→&quot;, worth&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through this, the Uesugi clan gradually regained power and his adopted son, Kagekatsu UESUGI (of the Nagao clan), served n th Council of Five Elders (Go-Tairo) in the Toyotomi government and received Aizu domain, worth 1.2 million koku.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代は米沢藩30万石（実高51万石）を領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Edo Period he ruled Yonezawa domain with 300,000 koku (510,000 koku in actuality).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo Period he ruled Yonezawa domain, worth 300,000 koku (in reality 510,000 koku).</e>
<cmt>&quot;with&quot;→&quot;worth&quot;&quot;in actuality&quot;→&quot;in reality&quot; and moved</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo Period he ruled Yonezawa domain, worth 300,000 koku (in reality 510,000 koku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>のち無嗣の危機に瀕したこともあり15万石（実高33万石）に減知されたが、幕末まで大名としての地位を維持した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, they faced a crisis of having no heir, and they were demoted to 150,000 koku (330,000 in actuality), but they maintained their position as a daimyo until the end of Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, they faced a crisis of having no heir, and they were demoted to 150,000 koku (in reality 330,000), but they maintained their position as daimyo until the end of Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in actuality&quot;→&quot;in reality&quot; and movedDeleted &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, they faced a crisis of having no heir, and they were demoted to 150,000 koku (in reality 330,000), but they maintained their position as daimyo until the end of Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>明治時代は華族に列し、伯爵を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Meiji Period they were included as a new nobility, and they were given the title of earl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji Period they were included in the new nobility and given the title of earl.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;as a&quot;→&quot;in the&quot; Deleted comma and &quot;they were&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji Period they were included in the new nobility and given the title of earl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉時代・南北朝時代・室町時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura Period and the Period of Southern and Northern Courts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura Period and Period of the Southern and Northern Courts.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura Period and Period of the Southern and Northern Courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>初代上杉重房のとき、鎌倉幕府の征夷大将軍に迎えられた宗尊親王に従って鎌倉へ下向し、有力御家人の足利氏と姻戚関係を結んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the first-generation period of Shigefusa UESUGI, they descended to Kamakura with Prince Munetaka who was installed as Seii Taishogun of Kamakura Shogunate, and they became relatives of the powerful feudal lord, Ashikaga clan, through arranged marriages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the time of the first Uesugi, Shigefusa, they moved to Kamakura with Prince Munetaka, who was installed as Seii Taishogun of the Kamakura Shogunate, and they became relatives of the powerful vassal family, the Ashikaga Clan, through arranged marriages.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the first-generation period of&quot;→&quot;the time of the first Uesugi, Shigefusa,&quot;&quot;descended&quot;→&quot;moved&quot;&quot;feudal lord&quot;→&quot;vassal family&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the time of the first Uesugi, Shigefusa, they moved to Kamakura with Imperial Prince Munetaka, who was installed as Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Kamakura Shogunate, and they became relatives of the powerful vassal family, the Ashikaga clan, through arranged marriages.</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍、説明補足 (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)Clan→clanImperialを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)、重房の孫・上杉憲房は妹の上杉清子が足利尊氏・足利直義兄弟の母であったことから尊氏を助けて功績を立て、上野国の守護に任ぜられて関東地方で南朝方の新田氏と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Period of Southern and Northern Courts, Shigefusa&apos;s grandson, Norifusa UESUGI, was assigned as Shugo of Kozuke Province for rendering a distinguished service by helping Takauji because his younger sister, Kiyoko UESUGI was the mother of brothers Takauji ASHIKAGA and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, and he fought against Nitta clan of Southern Court in Kanto Area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Period of the Southern and Northern Courts, Shigefusa&apos;s grandson, Norifusa UESUGI, whose younger sister, Kiyoko UESUGI, was Takauji and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA&apos;s mother, was assigned as Shugo (governor) of Kozuke Province as a reward for helping Takauji, and he fought against the Southern Court supporters, the Nitta Clan, in the Kanto Area.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;, (governor)&quot;for rendering a distinguished service by&quot;→&quot;as a reward for&quot;&quot;because his younger sister, Kiyoko UESUGI was the mother of brothers Takauji ASHIKAGA and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA&quot;→&quot;whose younger sister, Kiyoko UESUGI, was Takauji and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA&apos;s mother,&quot; and movedMoved &quot;Southern Court&quot;Added &quot;supporters&quot;, comma, &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Period of the Southern and Northern Courts, Shigefusa&apos;s grandson, Norifusa UESUGI, whose younger sister, Kiyoko UESUGI, was Takauji and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA&apos;s mother, was assigned as Shugo (governor) of Kozuke Province as a reward for helping Takauji, and he fought against the Southern Court supporters, the Nitta clan, in the Kanto Area.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>また、重房の別の孫は題目宗の僧となって日静と名乗り、京本圀寺や越後国三条本成寺（新潟県三条市）を有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, another grandson of Shigefusa became a monk named Nichijo of Daimoku-shu School, who owned Hongoku-ji Temple in Kyoto as well as Honjo-ji Temple in Sanjo, Echigo Province (Sanjo City, Niigata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, another grandson of Shigefusa became a monk named Nichijo, who followed the Daimoku doctrine and owned Hongoku-ji Temple in Kyoto, as well as Honjo-ji Temple in Sanjo, Echigo Province (Sanjo City, Niigata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>&quot;of Daimoku-shu School, who&quot;→&quot;, who followed the Daimoku doctrine and&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, another grandson of Shigefusa became a monk named Nichijo, who followed the Daimoku doctrine and owned Hongoku-ji Temple in Kyoto, as well as Honjo-ji Temple in Sanjo, Echigo Province (Sanjo City, Niigata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>師の名僧日印の問答対決を「鎌倉殿中問答」にまとめ、宗門の興隆を導いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He edited his accomplished master, Nichiin&apos;s debate in &quot;Kamakura Denchu Mondo&quot; and was implemental in the prospering of this school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He edited &quot;Kamakura Denchu Mondo&quot;, a collection of his accomplished master, Nichiin&apos;s debates and was implemental in the prospering of this school.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;&quot;Kamakura Denchu Mondo&quot;&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He edited &apos;Kamakura Denchu Mondo,&apos; a collection of his accomplished master, Nichiin&apos;s debates and was implemental in the prospering of this school.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>その後、観応の擾乱では高氏と対立するなど波乱もあったが、憲房の子の上杉憲顕の時代には上野・越後国・伊豆国の守護を兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, during Kanno Disturbance, there were troubles such as confrontations against Ko clan, but during Norifusa&apos;s son, Noriaki UESUGI&apos;s time he served as Shugo of Kozuke, Echigo Provinces and Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, during the Kanno Disturbance, there were troubles such as confrontations with the Ko Clan, but during Norifusa&apos;s son, Noriaki UESUGI&apos;s time, the family became Shugo of Kozuke, Echigo and Izu Provinces.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;there were troubles such as confrontations against Ko clan&quot;&quot;against&quot;→&quot;with&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;he served as&quot;→&quot;, the family became&quot;Deleted &quot;Provinces&quot;Made final &quot;Province plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, during the Kanno Disturbance, there were troubles such as confrontations with the Ko clan, but during Norifusa&apos;s son, Noriaki UESUGI&apos;s time, the family became Shugo of Kozuke, Echigo and Izu Provinces.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>上杉憲顕が1363年に鎌倉公方足利基氏の執事（管領）に任ぜられて、初代の関東管領になって以来、鎌倉に居住した一族から犬懸（いぬかけ）、山内（やまのうち）、宅間（たくま）、扇谷（おうぎがやつ）の4家が出た（頭に居住地名を冠している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1363, Noriaki UESUGI was assigned as a steward (kanrei) of Kamakura Kubo Motouji ASHIKAGA, and since he became the first generation Kanto kanrei 4 families developed from one single family that lived in Kamakura: Inukake, Yamanouchi, Takuma and Ogigayatsu (the name of the residential are is used at the beginning of the surname).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1363, Noriaki UESUGI was assigned as a steward (Kanrei) of Kamakura Kubo Motouji ASHIKAGA, and after he became the first Kanto Kanrei, the family split into four branches: the Inukake, the Yamanouchi, the Takuma and the Ogigayatsu (the name of their place of residence is used at the beginning of the surname).</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;k&apos;&quot;since&quot;→&quot;after&quot;Deleted &quot;generationCapitalized &apos;k&apos;&quot;4 families developed from one single family that lived in Kamakura&quot;→&quot;the Kamakura family split into four branches&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; before names&quot;the residential are&quot;→&quot;their place of residence&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1363, Noriaki UESUGI was assigned as a steward (Kanrei) of Kamakura Kubo Motouji ASHIKAGA, and after he became the first Kanto Kanrei, the family split into four branches: the Inukake, the Yamanouchi, the Takuma and the Ogigayatsu (the name of their place of residence is used at the beginning of the surname).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>宅間上杉家は早くに衰え、犬懸上杉家は上杉禅秀の乱により主流派から脱落したので、15世紀半ばからは憲顕の子孫山内上杉家と、憲顕の従兄弟の子孫扇谷上杉家の2家が有力となるが、関東管領の職はもっぱら山内上杉家の当主が独占した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takuma Uesugi family declined early, and Inukake Uesugi family dropped out from the main lineage after the Uprising of Uesugi Zenshu, therefore, from mid-15th century the 2 families of Yamanouchi Uesugi, the descendants of Noriaki, and Ogigayatsu Uesugi, the descendants of Noriaki&apos;s cousin, became dominant, but the Kanto kanrei position was dominated by the head of Yamanouchi Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takuma Uesugi family declined early, and the Inukake Uesugi family dropped out from the main lineage after the Uprising of Uesugi Zenshu, therefore, from the mid-15th century the 2 families of the Yamanouchi Uesugi, descendants of Noriaki, and the Ogigayatsu Uesugi, descendants of Noriaki&apos;s cousin, became dominant, with the Kanto Kanrei position being dominated by the head of the Yamanouchi Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot; before family namesAlthough it is part of the name of an incident, I wonder if &quot;Uesugi Zenshu&quot; shouldn&apos;t be &quot;Zenshu UESUGI&quot; to conform with other namesDeleted &quot;the &quot;before &quot;descendants&quot;&quot;but&quot;→&quot;with&quot;&quot;was &quot;→&quot;being&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takum-Uesugi family declined early, and the Inukake-Uesugi family dropped out from the main lineage after the Uprising of Zenshu UESUGI, therefore, from the mid-15th century the 2 families of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi, descendants of Noriaki, and the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi, descendants of Noriaki&apos;s cousin, became dominant, with the Kanto Kanrei position being dominated by the head of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>Uesugi Zenshu→Zenshu UESUGI-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この頃の山内上杉家当主であった関東管領上杉憲実は、足利学校の再興者として歴史に名を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto kanrei Norizane UESUGI, who was the head of Yamanouchi Uesugi family at this time, left his name in history as the one who restored the Ashikaga School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto Kanrei Norizane UESUGI, who was the head of Yamanouchi Uesugi family at this time, made his mark on history as the one who restored the Ashikaga School.</e>
<cmt>&quot;left his name in&quot;→&quot;made his mark on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto Kanrei Norizane UESUGI, who was the head of Yamanouchi-Uesugi family at this time, made his mark on history as the one who restored the Ashikaga School.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その一方、上杉氏と足利公方家の対立が鮮明となり、1454年には鎌倉公方足利成氏が関東管領上杉憲忠（憲実の子）を殺害したことに発する内乱（享徳の乱）が発生し、関東は応仁の乱よりも十数年早く事実上の戦国時代_(日本)に突入することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, antagonism between Uesugi clan and Ashikaga kubo family became clear, and in 1454, an internal strife (Kyoto War) began as a result of Kamakura kubo Shigeuji ASHIKAGA killing Kanto kanrei Noritada UESUGI, and Kanto effectively entered the Period of Civil War (in Japan) over 10 years prior to Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, antagonism between the Uesugi clan and the Ashikaga Kubo family broke into the open and, in 1454, civil war (the Kyotoku Incident) began when Kamakura Kubo Shigeuji ASHIKAGA killed Kanto Kanrei Noritada UESUGI, and Kanto effectively entered the Warring States Period over 10 years prior to the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>&quot;became clear&quot;→&quot;broke into the open&quot;&quot;an internal strife&quot;→&quot;civil war&quot;&quot;Kyoto War&quot;→&quot;the Kyotoku Incident&quot;&quot;as a result of&quot;→&quot;when&quot;Capitalized &apos;k&apos;&quot;Period of Civil War&quot;→&quot;Warring States Period&quot;Deleted &quot;(in Japan)&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, antagonism between the Uesugi clan and the Ashikaga Kubo family broke into the open and, in 1454, civil war (the Kyotoku Incident) began when Kamakura Kubo Shigeuji ASHIKAGA killed Kanto Kanrei Noritada UESUGI, and Kanto effectively entered the Warring States Period over 10 years prior to the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>戦国時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of Civil War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warring States Period</e>
<cmt>&quot;Period of Civil War&quot;→&quot;Warring States Period&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warring States Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>享徳の乱の際、扇谷・山内両上杉家は連合して古河公方（鎌倉公方の後身）と敵対していたが、古河公方との和睦後は両家で争うようになり、内紛の末に衰退し、新興の後北条氏に圧迫されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Kyoto War, Ogigayatsu and Yamanouchi Uesugi families formed an alliance and warred against Koga kubo (the later form of Kamakura kubo), but after making peace with Koga kubo they began to fight among themselves, and their powers declined at the end of the internal strife, and after Kawagoe Night Battle, they were under pressure by newly risen Go-Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kyotoku Incident, the Ogigayatsu and Yamanouchi Uesugi families formed an alliance and fought against the Koga Kubo (the later form of the Kamakura Kubo) but after making peace, they began to fight among themselves, leading to a decline in their power, and they came under pressure from the emerging Go-Hojo Clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kyoto War&quot;→&quot;the Kyotoku Incident&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;warred&quot;→&quot;fought&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;k&apos;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;k&apos;Deleted comma and &quot;with Koga kubo&quot;&quot;and their powers declined at the end of the internal strife&quot;→&quot;leading to a decline in their power&quot;Deleted &quot;and after Kawagoe Night Battle&quot; - not in Japanese original&quot;they were under pressure by&quot;→&quot;and they came under pressure from the&quot;&quot;newly risen&quot;→&quot;emerging&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kyotoku Incident, the Ogigayatsu- and Yamanouchi-Uesugi families formed an alliance and fought against the Koga Kubo (the later form of the Kamakura Kubo) but after making peace, they began to fight among themselves, leading to a decline in their power, and they came under pressure from the emerging Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>Go-Hojo Clan→Gohojo clan-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>武蔵国に勢力をもっていた扇谷上杉家は、1545年の河越夜戦で後北条氏に敗れて滅亡し、上野国を本拠としていた山内上杉家の上杉憲政も、河越夜戦以降は後北条氏の攻撃を直に受けるようになって勢力を衰退させていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogigayatsu Uesugi family, which had power in Musashi Province, lost against Go-Hojo clan at Kawagoe Bight Battle in 1545 and was destroyed, and Norimasa UESUGI of Yamanouchi Uesugi family, who was based in Kozuke Province, began to receive direct attacks from Go-Hojo clan after Kawagoe Night Battle, and their power also began to deteriorate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogigayatsu Uesugi family, which held power in Musashi Province, was defeated and destroyed by the Go-Hojo Clan at the Kawagoe Night Battle in 1545, and Norimasa UESUGI of the Yamanouchi Uesugi family, who was based in Kozuke Province, began to receive direct attacks from the Go-Hojo Clan, causing their power to also deteriorate.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;had&quot;→&quot;held&quot;&quot;lost against&quot;→&quot;was defeated and destroyed by&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;&quot;Bight&quot;→&quot;Night&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;deleted &quot;after Kawagoe Night Battle&quot;&quot;and their power also began to&quot;→&quot;causing their power to also&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogigayatsu-Uesugi family, which held power in Musashi Province, was defeated and destroyed by the Gohojo clan at the Kawagoe Night Battle in 1545, and Norimasa UESUGI of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family, who was based in Kozuke Province, began to receive direct attacks from the Gohojo Clan, causing their power to also deteriorate.</e>
<cmt>Go-Hojo Clan→Gohojo clan-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>憲政はついに関東を放棄し、もとは家臣筋であり外戚でもあった越後長尾氏を頼った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norimasa finally gave up Kanto, and he relied on Echigo Nagao clan, which originally was of a vassal lineage and also a kin through marriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norimasa finally gave up Kanto, and he came to rely on the Echigo Nagao Clan, which originally was of vassal lineage and also related through marriage.</e>
<cmt>&quot;relied&quot;→&quot;came to rely&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;deleted &quot;a&quot;&quot;a kin&quot;→&quot;related&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norimasa finally gave up Kanto, and he came to rely on the Echigo Nagao clan, which originally was of vassal lineage and also related through marriage.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1561年、憲政は山内上杉家の名跡と関東管領の職を、越後長尾氏の長尾景虎（後の上杉謙信）に譲り、自身は春日山に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1561, Norimasa passed on the name of Yamanouchi Uesugi and the position as Kanto kanrei to Kagetora NAGAO (later Kenshin UESUGI) of Echigo Nagai clan, and Norimasa moved to Kasuga-yama Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1561, Norimasa passed on the name of Yamanouchi Uesugi and the position of Kanto Kanrei to Kagetora NAGAO (later Kenshin UESUGI) of the Echigo Nagai Clan, and Norimasa moved to Kasuga-yama Mountain.</e>
<cmt>&quot;as&quot;→&quot;of&quot;Capitalized &apos;k&apos;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1561, Norimasa passed on the name of Yamanouchi-Uesugi and the position of Kanto Kanrei to Kagetora NAGAO (later Kenshin UESUGI) of the Echigo Nagai clan, and Norimasa moved to Kasuga-yama Mountain.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>深谷上杉家の上杉憲盛は武蔵国にとどまって北条氏との戦闘を継続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norimori UESUGI of Fukaya Uesugi family remained in Musashi Province and continued to fight against Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norimori UESUGI of the Fukaya Uesugi family remained in Musashi Province and continued to fight against the Hojo Clan.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norimori UESUGI of the Fukaya-Uesugi family remained in Musashi Province and continued to fight against the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>以後、長尾氏が上杉氏の嫡流を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From then on, Nagao clan claimed themselves as the heir lineage of the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From then on, the Nagao Clan proclaimed themselves heirs to the Uesugi Clan.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;&quot;claimed&quot;→&quot;proclaimed&quot;&quot;as the heir lineage of&quot;→&quot;heirs to&quot;Capitalized &apos;c</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From then on, the Nagao clan proclaimed themselves heirs to the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>上杉謙信は、越後を拠点として領国を関東と北陸地方に拡大したが、その死後、二人の養子上杉景勝と上杉景虎の間で家督争い（御館の乱）が起こり、この混乱によって関東地方の領国を喪失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI based himself in Echigo and expanded his territory in Kanto and in the Hokuriku Region, but after his death, a fight to become the head of the family (Otate War) developed between the two adopted sons, Kagekatsu UESUGI and Kagetora UESUGI, and because of this turmoil they lost their territories in the Kanto Region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshin UESUGI based himself in Echigo and expanded his territory into Kanto and the Hokuriku Region, but after his death, a fight to become the head of the family (Otate War) developed between his two adopted sons, Kagekatsu UESUGI and Kagetora UESUGI, and because of this turmoil they lost their territories in the Kanto Region.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot;→&quot;into&quot;deleted &quot;in&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshin UESUGI based himself in Echigo and expanded his territory into Kanto and the Hokuriku Region, but after his death, a fight to become the head of the family (Otate War) developed between his two adopted sons, Kagekatsu UESUGI and Kagetora UESUGI, and because of this turmoil they lost their territories in the Kanto Region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>この争いは、長尾一族の出身（越後長尾氏）で謙信の姉の子にあたる景勝が勝利し、上杉氏の名跡を継承するが、謙信・景勝以降の上杉氏（長尾上杉氏）では、謙信を初代、景勝を二代と称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The son of Kenshin&apos;s older sister who was from Nagao family (Echigo Nagao clan), Kagekatsu, won this war, and he inherited the name of Uesugi clan, but the Uesugi clan (Nagao Uesugi clan) members after Kenshin and Kagekatsu call Kenshin as the first generation and Kagekatsu as the second generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagekatsu, the son of Kenshin&apos;s older sister, who was from the Nagao family (the Echigo Nagao Clan), won this war and inherited the name of the Uesugi Clan, but later members of the clan (the Nagao Uesugi Clan) call Kenshin the first generation and Kagekatsu the second generation.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;Kagekatsu,&quot; Added comma, &quot;the&quot; and &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Deleted comma and &quot;he&quot;&quot;the Uesugi clan (Nagao Uesugi clan) members after Kenshin and Kagekatsu&quot;→&quot;later members of the clan (the Nagao Uesugi Clan)&quot;Deleted both &quot;as&quot;s</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagekatsu, the son of Kenshin&apos;s older sister, who was from the Nagao family (the Echigo Nagao clan), won this war and inherited the name of the Uesugi clan, but later members of the clan (the Nagao Uesugi clan) call Kenshin the first generation and Kagekatsu the second generation.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>安土桃山時代・江戸時代・明治時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azuchi-Momoyama Period, Edo Period and Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azuchi-Momoyama, Edo and Meiji Periods.</e>
<cmt>Deleted 1st and 2nd &quot;Period&quot;Made final &quot;Period&quot; plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azuchi-Momoyama, Edo and Meiji Periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>上杉景勝は、織田信長の横死後豊臣秀吉に仕え、五大老の一人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI after the death of Nobunaga ODA and he became one of the Go-tairo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagekatsu UESUGI served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI after the death of Nobunaga ODA, becoming one of the Go-tairo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and he became&quot;→&quot;, becoming&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI after the death of Nobunaga ODA, becoming one of the Go-tairo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この間、1587年には反抗した新発田重家を攻略して越後を再統一し、1589年には秀吉の命により佐渡国を平定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, in 1587, they captured opposing Shigeie SHIBATA and reunified Echigo, and in 1589 they restored order in Sado Province on Hideyoshi&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, in 1587 he captured the rebel Shigeie SHIBATA and reunified Echigo and in 1589, restored order in Sado Province on Hideyoshi&apos;s orders.</e>
<cmt>&quot;opposing&quot;→&quot;the rebel&quot;Deleted comma and &quot;he&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, in 1587 he captured the rebel Shigeie SHIBATA and reunified Echigo and in 1589, restored order in Sado Province on Hideyoshi&apos;s orders.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>越後、佐渡、出羽国庄内地方の91万石を領有し、領内に多くの金山を抱えてその実収入は120万石と言われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They owned 910,000 koku in Echigo and Sado Provinces as well as Shonai region in Dewa Province, and with many gold mines within their territory the actual income was said to have been 1.2 million koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He possessed Echigo and Sado Provinces as well as Shonai region in Dewa Province, totaling 910,000 koku, and with many gold mines within their territory, his actual income was said to have been 1.2 million koku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;They&quot;→&quot;He&quot;Moved &quot;910,000 koku&quot;Deleted &quot;in&quot;Added &quot;totalling&quot;&quot;their&quot;→&quot;his&quot;Added comma&quot;the&quot;→&quot;his&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He possessed Echigo and Sado Provinces as well as Shonai region in Dewa Province, totaling 910,000 koku, and with many gold mines within their territory, his actual income was said to have been 1.2 million koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>1598年、景勝は隣国の会津藩に移封され、陸奥国の会津・白河藩・田村郡・安達郡・福島藩・伊達郡・庄内（田川郡と飽海郡）・置賜郡、東蒲原郡、佐渡などに総計120万石を領有するが、1600年の関ヶ原の戦いに際して徳川家康に敵対し、米沢藩30万石（実高51万石余）に減封された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1598, Kagekatsu was transferred to the neighboring Aizu domain, and his territory of Mutsu Province&apos;s Aizu, Shirakawa Domain, Tamura District, Adachi District, Fukushima Domain, Date District, Shonai (Tagawa District and Akumi District), Okitama District, Higashikanbara District and Sado, totaled to 1.2 million koku, but he fought against Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, and he was demoted to 300,000 koku (510,000 koku in actuality) in Yonezawa domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1598, Kagekatsu was transferred to the neighboring Aizu domain, and his territories of Mutsu Province&apos;s Aizu, Shirakawa Domain, Tamura District, Adachi District, Fukushima Domain, Date District, Shonai (Tagawa District and Akumi District), Okitama District, Higashikanbara District and Sado, totaled 1.2 million koku but in the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he fought against Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and was demoted to 300,000 koku (in reality 510,000 koku) in Yonezawa domain.</e>
<cmt>Made &quot;territory&quot; pluraldeleted &quot;to&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Moved &quot;in the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600&quot;Deleted &quot;he&quot;&quot;in actuality&quot;→&quot;in reality&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1598, Kagekatsu was transferred to the neighboring Aizu domain, and his territories of Mutsu Province&apos;s Aizu, Shirakawa Domain, Tamura District, Adachi District, Fukushima Domain, Date District, Shonai (Tagawa District and Akumi District), Okitama District, Higashikanbara District and Sado, totaled 1.2 million koku but in the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he fought against Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and was demoted to 300,000 koku (in reality 510,000 koku) in Yonezawa domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>1664年、景勝の孫上杉綱勝が急死して断絶の危機を迎えたが、綱勝の舅保科正之（徳川家光の実弟）の尽力により、妹婿吉良義央（上野介、扇谷上杉家の女系子孫）の子上杉綱憲が綱勝の養子に入りした結果、半知15万石（実高30万石余）で家名存続することを許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1664, Kagekatsu&apos;s grandson, Tsunakatsu UESUGI, died suddenly and there was a crisis of ending the family, but because of the effort by Tsunakatsu&apos;s father-in-law, Masayuki HOSOKAWA (younger biological brother of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA), Tsunanori UESUGI, the son of his daughter&apos;s husband, Yoshihira KIRA (Kozu no suke, descendant of the female side of Ogigayatsu Uesugi family) became an adopted son of Tsunakatsu, and as a result the family was permitted to continue its family name with a half stipend of 150,000 koku (30,000 koku in actuality).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1664, Kagekatsu&apos;s grandson, Tsunakatsu UESUGI, died suddenly and there was a danger of the family dying out, but due to efforts by Tsunakatsu&apos;s father-in-law, Masayuki HOSOKAWA, who was a younger brother of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, Tsunanori UESUGI, the son of his daughter&apos;s husband, Yoshihira KIRA (Kozu no suke, descendant of the female side of Ogigayatsu Uesugi family) became an adopted son of Tsunakatsu, and as a result the family was permitted to continue its family name with a half stipend of 150,000 koku (30,000 koku in actuality).</e>
<cmt>&quot;crisis of ending the family&quot;→&quot;danger of the family dying out&quot;&quot;because of the effort&quot;→&quot;due to efforts&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1664, Kagekatsu&apos;s grandson, Tsunakatsu UESUGI, died suddenly and there was a danger of the family dying out, but due to efforts by Tsunakatsu&apos;s father-in-law, Masayuki HOSOKAWA, who was a younger brother of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, Tsunanori UESUGI, the son of his daughter&apos;s husband, Yoshihira KIRA (Kozu no suke, descendant of the female side of Ogigayatsu Uesugi family) became an adopted son of Tsunakatsu, and as a result the family was permitted to continue its family name with a half stipend of 150,000 koku (30,000 koku in actuality).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>上杉斉憲の代に18万石に加増される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Narinori UESUGI&apos;s generation they were promoted to 180,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Narinori UESUGI&apos;s time they were promoted to 180,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;By&quot;→&quot;In&quot;&quot;generation&quot;→&quot;time&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Narinori UESUGI&apos;s time they were promoted to 180,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>上杉氏は相次ぐ減封により規模を縮小させたが、越後の春日山城から持ち込んだ上杉謙信の遺骸を米沢城の本丸内に安置し、謙信崇拝に基づいた誇り高い士風を守った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uesugi&apos;s continuous demotions shrank its size, but they enshrined within the main wing of Yonezawa Castle the remains of Kenshin UESUGI brought in from Mt. Kasugayama Castle in Enchigo, and they maintained the proud samurai tradition based on Kenshin Worship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The continuous demotions reduced the size of the Uesugi, but they enshrined Kenshin UESUGI&apos;s remains, brought in from Mt. Kasugayama Castle in Echigo, within the keep of Yonezawa Castle the remains of Kenshin UESUGI, and they maintained a proud samurai tradition based on Kenshin Worship.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;Deleted &quot;Uesugi&apos;s&quot;&quot;shrank its size&quot;→&quot;reduced the size of the Uesugi&quot;&quot;main wing&quot;→&quot;keep&quot;&quot;the remains of Kenshin UESUGI&quot;→&quot;Kenshin UESUGI&apos;s remains&quot; and movedMoved &quot;brought in from Mt. Kasugayama Castle in Enchigo&quot;Spelling of &quot;Echigo&quot;&quot;the&quot;→&quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The continuous demotions reduced the size of the Uesugi, but they enshrined Kenshin UESUGI&apos;s remains, brought in from Mt. Kasugayama Castle in Echigo, within the keep of Yonezawa Castle the remains of Kenshin UESUGI, and they maintained a proud samurai tradition based on Kenshin Worship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、減封のため財政難に悩まされたが、江戸時代後期には上杉鷹山（治憲）が藩の殖産興業を行って財政を立て直した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, financial troubles caused by demotions troubled them, but during latter Edo Period Yozan UESUGI (Harunori) rebuilt their economy through encouraging new industries in the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, financial troubles caused by the demotions troubled them, but during the latter Edo Period, Yozan (Harunori) UESUGI rebuilt their economy through encouraging new industries in the domain.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;, &quot;the&quot; and commaMoved &quot;(Harunori)&quot;&quot;through&quot;→&quot;by&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, financial troubles caused by the demotions troubled them, but during the latter Edo Period, Yozan (Harunori) UESUGI rebuilt their economy through encouraging new industries in the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="42">
<j>明治維新後、米沢藩上杉家は華族に列し、伯爵を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, Yonezawa Domain Uesugi Family was included as a new nobility and was given a rank of earl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the Yonezawa Domain Uesugi Family was included in the new nobility and given the rank of earl.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;, &quot;the&quot;&quot;as a&quot;→&quot;in the&quot;Deleted &quot;was&quot;&quot;a&quot;→&quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Yonezawa Domain Uesugi Family was included in the new nobility and given the rank of earl.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また、分家米沢藩支藩上杉家は、子爵を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Uesugi branch family of branch domain of Yonezawa Domain received the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the branch family of the Yonezawa Domain Uesugi received the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Uesugi branch family of branch domain of Yonezawa Domai&quot;→&quot;the branch family of the Yonezawa Domain Uesugi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the branch family of the Yonezawa Domain Uesugi received the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="44">
<j>宇宙工学で宇宙航空研究開発機構宇宙科学研究本部教授の上杉邦憲は米沢藩上杉家の16代目当主にあたる（謙信から数えて17代目）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Aerospace engineering, Kuninori UESUGI, who is a professor at the Institute of Space and Astronautical Science at Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency, is the 16th head of Uesugi family of Yonezawa Domain (17th, counting from Kenshin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuninori UESUGI, who is a professor at the Institute of Space and Astronautical Science at the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency, is the 16th head of the Uesugi family of Yonezawa Domain (17th, counting from Kenshin).</e>
<cmt>Deleeted &quot;In Aerospace engineering&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuninori UESUGI, who is a professor at the Institute of Space and Astronautical Science at the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency, is the sixteenth head of the Uesugi family of Yonezawa Domain (seventeenth, counting from Kenshin).</e>
<cmt>16th→sixteenth17th→seventeenth</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="45">
<j>長尾上杉氏以外の系統も、江戸時代まで血統が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lineages other than Nagao Uesugi clan also continued into Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lineages other than the Nagao Uesugi Clan also continued into the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;The&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lineages other than the Nagao-Uesugi clan also continued into the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>深谷家上杉憲俊は平福藩藩士になり、宅間上杉家や扇谷家上杉憲勝の子孫は旗本になったと云われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noritoshi UESUGI of Fukaya family became a hanshi of Hirafuku Domain, and it is said that the descendants of Takuma Uesugi family and Norikatsu UESUGI of Ogigayatsu Uesugi family became hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noritoshi UESUGI of the Fukaya family became a hanshi (samurai) of Hirafuku Domain, and it is said that the descendants of the Takuma Uesugi family and Norikatsu UESUGI of the Ogigayatsu Uesugi family became hatamoto, vassals to the shogun.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;, &quot;(samurai), &quot;the&quot;, &quot;the&quot; and explanation &quot;hatamoto&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noritoshi UESUGI of the Fukaya family became a hanshi (samurai) of Hirafuku Domain, and it is said that the descendants of the Takuma-Uesugi family and Norikatsu UESUGI of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi family became hatamoto, vassals to the shogun.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>上杉満定の男系子孫である加賀爪氏は江戸幕府譜代大名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants of the male side of Mitsusada UESUGI became a fudai daimyo of Edo Shogunate,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants of the male side of Mitsusada UESUGI became fudai daimyo during the Edo Shogunate,</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;a&quot;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;during the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants of the male side of Mitsusada UESUGI became fudai daimyo during the Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>,→.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>上条政繁（上杉入庵）の次男・上杉長員の子孫は、旗本（高家）上杉氏として存続し、領地は下総国印旛郡・千葉郡などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants of Nagakazu UESUGI, the second son of Masashige JOJO (Nyuan UESUGI), survived as hatamoto (koke) Uesugi clan, and their territory included Inba District and Chiba District of Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants of Nagakazu UESUGI, the second son of Masashige JOJO (Nyuan UESUGI), survived as the hatamoto (koke) Uesugi Clan, and their territory included Inba District and Chiba District in Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;&quot;of&quot;→&quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants of Nagakazu UESUGI, the second son of Masashige JOJO (Nyuan UESUGI), survived as the hatamoto (koke) Uesugi clan, and their territory included Inba District and Chiba District in Shimousa Province.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>長男・景広の子孫は能登畠山家として上杉家に仕え、三男・義真の子孫も旗本（のち高家）畠山氏、上杉綱憲の挙兵を止めたのがその末裔である畠山義寧（千坂や色部だというのは俗説）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants of the eldest son, Kagehiro, served the Uesugi family as Noto Hatakeyama family, and the descendants of the third son, Yoshizane, also became hatamoto (later koke) Hatakeyama clan, and the one who stopped Tsunanori UESUGI&apos;s dispatching of troops was Yoshiyasu HATAKEYAMA (opinions that suggest Chizaka and Irobe are myths), the descendant of Yoshizane.</e>
<cmt>「その末裔」は三男・義真の末裔として訳しましたが、原文からは誰の末裔かが正確に読み取れませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants of the eldest son, Kagehiro, served the Uesugi family as the Noto Hatakeyama family, and descendants of the third son, Yoshizane, also became the hatamoto (later koke) Hatakeyama clan, and the one who stopped Tsunanori UESUGI&apos;s dispatching of troops was Yoshizane&apos;s descendant, Yoshiyasu HATAKEYAMA (opinions that suggest the Chizaka and Irobe Clans are myths), the descendant of Yoshizane.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;the descendant of Yoshizane&quot;→&quot;Yoshizane&apos;s descendant&quot; amd moveAdded &quot;the&quot; and &quot;Clans&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants of the eldest son, Kagehiro, served the Uesugi family as the Noto Hatakeyama family, and descendants of the third son, Yoshizane, also became the hatamoto (later koke) Hatakeyama clan, and the one who stopped Tsunanori UESUGI&apos;s dispatching of troops was Yoshizane&apos;s descendant, Yoshiyasu HATAKEYAMA (opinions that suggest the Chizaka and Irobe clans are myths), the descendant of Yoshizane.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>また米沢藩士としても、上杉憲政の後裔や千坂氏、山本寺氏など上杉家の庶家が存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Norimasa UESUGI&apos;s descendants and the vassal families belonging to the Uesugi clan, such as Chizaka clan and Sanbonji clan, continued to exist as Yonezawa hanshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Norimasa UESUGI&apos;s descendants and the vassal families belonging to the Uesugi clan, such as the Chizaka clan and the Sanbonji clan, continued to exist as Yonezawa hanshi.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; twice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Norimasa UESUGI&apos;s descendants and the vassal families belonging to the Uesugi clan, such as the Chizaka clan and the Sanbonji clan, continued to exist as Yonezawa hanshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>主な一族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Families</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Families</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Families</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>上杉氏には数多くの分家があり、上杉頼重、上杉憲房の子息の代で分かれた以下の系統が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many branch families of Uesugi clan, and the following lineages that branched out during the generations of the sons of Yorishige UESUGI and Norifusa UESUGI are well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many branch families of the Uesugi Clan, and the following lineages that branched out during the generations of the sons of Yorishige UESUGI and Norifusa UESUGI are the most well-known.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added &quot;the most&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many branch families of the Uesugi clan, and the following lineages that branched out during the generations of the sons of Yorishige UESUGI and Norifusa UESUGI are the most well-known.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>室町時代は隆盛したが、戦国時代以降の混乱によりいずれも没落しており、その末裔は上記のように旗本や諸藩士になる者が多く、江戸時代に大名として存続したのは長尾氏から上杉謙信を養子に迎えた山内上杉宗家と加賀爪氏のみとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They prospered during Muromachi Period, but they all declined because of the turmoil after the Period of Civil War, and as noted above, many of their descendants became hatamoto or hanshi of various domains, and the only ones that remained in existence as daimyo during Edo Period were Kagatsume clan and the main family of Yamanouchi Uesugi clan who adopted Kenshin UESUGI from Nagao clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They prospered during the Muromachi Period, but they all declined in the turmoil after the Warring States Period and, as noted above, many of their descendants became hatamoto or hanshi of various domains, the only ones remaining as daimyo during the Edo Period being the Kagatsume clan and the main Yamanouchi Uesugi Clan, who adopted Kenshin UESUGI from the Nagao Clan.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;because of&quot;→&quot;in&quot;&quot;Period of Civil War&quot;→&quot;Warring States Period&quot;Moved commaDeleted &quot;and&quot;&quot;that remained&quot;→&quot;remaining&quot;Deleted &quot;in existence&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;were&quot;→&quot;being&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Deleted &quot;family of&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added commaAdded &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They prospered during the Muromachi Period, but they all declined in the turmoil after the Warring States Period and, as noted above, many of their descendants became hatamoto or hanshi of various domains, the only ones remaining as daimyo during the Edo Period being the Kagatsume clan and the main Yamanouchi-Uesugi clan, who adopted Kenshin UESUGI from the Nagao clan.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>宅間上杉家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takuma Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takuma Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takuma Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>詫間上杉家とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also known as Takuma Uesugi Family.</e>
<cmt>名前に使われている漢字が違うだけなので英訳は同じです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also known as the Takuma Uesugi Family.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also known as the Takuma-Uesugi Family.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>憲房の養子上杉重能の系統。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of lineage of Shigeyoshi UESUGI, an adopted son of Norifusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descended from Shigeyoshi UESUGI, an adopted son of Norifusa.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Of lineage of&quot;→&quot;Descended from&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descended from Shigeyoshi UESUGI, an adopted son of Norifusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>重能が高師直との政争に破れ死去し、山内上杉家から養子を迎え存続したが、嫡流は次第に山内家に吸収されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeyoshi lost the political battle against KO no Moronao and died, and even though they continued to exist through adoption from Yamanouchi UESUGI family, the heir lineage eventually became absorbed by the Yamanouchi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeyoshi lost the political battle against KO no Moronao and died, and even though they continued to exist through adoption from the Yamanouchi UESUGI family, the heir lineage eventually became absorbed by the Yamanouchi family.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;&quot;heir lineage&quot;→&quot;line&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeyoshi lost the political battle against KO no Moronao and died, and even though they continued to exist through adoption from the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family, the heir lineage eventually became absorbed by the Yamanouchi family.</e>
<cmt>Yamanouchi UESUGI→Yamanouchi-Uesugi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>庶流としては、憲房の一子、上杉重兼の一族がおり、足利持氏の側近を務めた上杉憲直を輩出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the vassal lineage there is the family of a son of Norifusa, Shigekane UESUGI, and they have produced Norinao UESUGI, who served as a vassal of Mochiuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the illegitimate line, there is the family of a son of Norifusa, Shigekane UESUGI, which produced Norinao UESUGI, who served as a vassal of Mochiuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the vassal lineage&quot;→&quot;illegitimate line&quot;&quot;and they have&quot;→&quot;which&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the illegitimate line, there is the family of a son of Norifusa, Shigekane UESUGI, which produced Norinao UESUGI, who served as a vassal of Mochiuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>戦国期には北条氏綱に降り、後北条氏滅亡後は宅間上杉家を名乗り、徳川家康の旗本となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Period of Civil War they served Ujitsuna HOJO, and after the decline of Go-Hojo clan they used the name Takuma Uesugi family and became Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Warring States Period, they served Ujitsuna HOJO and, after the decline of the Go-Hojo Clan, they used the name Takuma Uesugi family and became Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Period of Civil War&quot;→&quot;Warring States Period,&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Warring States Period, they served Ujitsuna HOJO and, after the decline of the Gohojo clan, they used the name Takuma-Uesugi family and became Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>Go-Hojo Clan→Gohojo clanClan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>犬懸上杉家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inukake Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inukake Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inukake Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>憲房の子上杉憲藤の系統。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of lineage of Norifusa&apos;s son, Norifuji UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descended from Norifusa&apos;s son, Norifuji UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Of lineage of&quot;→&quot;Descended from&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descended from Norifusa&apos;s son, Norifuji UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>四条上杉家とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also known as Shijo Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also known as the Shijo Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also known as the Shijo-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>憲藤は足利尊氏の子の足利義詮の執事となり犬懸に在住し犬懸家の祖となったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norifuji became the steward of Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, the son of Takauji ASHIKAGA, and lived in Inukake and became the patriarch of Inukake family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norifuji became the steward of Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, the son of Takauji ASHIKAGA, and lived in Inukake, becoming the patriarch of Inukake family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and became&quot;→&quot;, becoming&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norifuji became the steward of Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, the son of Takauji ASHIKAGA, and lived in Inukake, becoming the patriarch of Inukake family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>憲藤の孫の上杉禅秀の代に上杉禅秀の乱により衰退し、関東の政治の主流派からは遠ざかったが、氏憲の子の多くは幕府に仕え血統は存続し、一部は堀越公方の関東執事となるなど、禅秀以降も関東の政治に足跡を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They declined due to the Uprising of Zenshu Uesugi during the generation of Norifuji&apos;s grandson, Zenshu UESUGI, and they were distanced from the main group in the government of Kanto, but many of Ujinori&apos;s children served the Shogunate and the bloodline continued to exist, and some of them even became Kanto shitsuji of Horigoe kubo, and they left footprints in the politics in Kanto even after Zenshu&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They declined due to the Uprising of Zenshu Uesugi during the generation of Norifuji&apos;s grandson, Zenshu UESUGI, and they were distanced from the main group in the government of Kanto, but many of Ujinori&apos;s children served the Shogunate and the bloodline continued to exist, and some of them even became Kanto shitsuji (stewards) to the Horigoe Kubo, and tcontinuing to make their mark in the politics of Kanto even after Zenshu&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(stewards)&quot;of&quot;→&quot;to&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;k&apos;&quot; and they left footprints in&quot;→&quot;continuing to make their mark&quot;&quot;in&quot;→&quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They declined due to the Uprising of Zenshu Uesugi during the generation of Norifuji&apos;s grandson, Zenshu UESUGI, and they were distanced from the main group in the government of Kanto, but many of Ujinori&apos;s children served the Shogunate and the bloodline continued to exist, and some of them even became Kanto shitsuji (stewards) to the Horigoe Kubo, and continuing to make their mark in the politics of Kanto even after Zenshu&apos;s time.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかし、戦国時代を境にその動静は確認できなくなり、没落したと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the Period of Civil War, their situation became unconfirmed, and it is considered that they became ruined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the Warring States Period, their status was unclear, and it is considered that they became ruined.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Period of Civil War&quot;→&quot;Warring States Period&quot;&quot;situation became unconfirmed&quot;→&quot;status was unclear&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the Warring States Period, their status was unclear, and it is considered that they became ruined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>山内上杉家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamanouchi Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamanouchi Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamanouchi-Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>憲房の子上杉憲顕の系統。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of lineage of Norifusa&apos;s son, Noriaki UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descended from Norifusa&apos;s son, Noriaki UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Of lineage of&quot;→&quot;Descended from&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descended from Norifusa&apos;s son, Noriaki UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>鎌倉移住以前は椙谷上杉家ともいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called Sugitani Uesugi family before they moved to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were also called the Sugitani Uesugi family before they moved to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It was&quot;→&quot;They were&quot; Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were also called the Sugitani-Uesugi family before they moved to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>山内上杉家を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to Yamanouchi Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to Yamanouchi Uesugi Family.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;f&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to Yamanouchi-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>Family→family-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>憲政から家督を譲られた上杉謙信（長尾景虎&lt;三条長尾家&gt;）の系統を特に長尾上杉氏とも呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lineage of Kenshin UESUGI (Kagetora NAGAO (Sanjo Nagao family)), who succeeded Norimasa, in particular, is also called Nagao Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants of Kenshin UESUGI (Kagetora NAGAO of the Sanjo Nagao family), who succeeded Norimasa, in particular, are also called the Nagao Uesugi Clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The lineage&quot;→&quot;Descendants&quot; &quot;is&quot;→&quot;are&quot; &quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants of Kenshin UESUGI (Kagetora NAGAO of the Sanjo Nagao family), who succeeded Norimasa, in particular, are also called the Nagao-Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>山内上杉家の分家として庁鼻和上杉家（後の深谷上杉家）が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a branch family of Yamanouchi Uesugi family, there exists Kobanawa Uesugi family (later Fukaya Uesugi family). Furthermore, Yoshihito SATAKE, head of the main family of Satake clan during Muromachi Period, was from Yamanouchi Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kobanawa Uesugi family (later the Fukaya Uesugi family) is a branch family of the Yamanouchi Uesugi family. Furthermore, Yoshihito SATAKE, head of the main family of the Satake Clan during the Muromachi Period, was from the Yamanouchi Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; before family namesMoved &quot;The Kobanawa Uesugi family (later the Fukaya Uesugi family)&quot;&quot;as&quot;→&quot;is&quot;Deleted &quot;there exists&quot;&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kobanawa-Uesugi family (later the Fukaya-Uesugi family) is a branch family of the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan-補足一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また、室町期の佐竹氏本家当主佐竹義人は山内上杉家の出身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Yoshihito SATAKE, head of the main family of the Satake clan during the Muromachi Period, was from the Yamanouchi-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>扇谷上杉家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogigayatsu Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogigayatsu Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogigayatsu-Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="69">
<j>憲房の兄上杉重顕の子の上杉朝定の子孫が鎌倉の扇谷の地に在住したのが始まり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It began when the descendants of Tomosada UESUGI, a son of Norifusa&apos;s older brother, Shigeaki UESUGI, lived in Ogigayatsu in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It began when the descendants of Tomosada UESUGI, a son of Norifusa&apos;s older brother, Shigeaki UESUGI, lived in Ogigayatsu in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It began when the descendants of Tomosada UESUGI, a son of Norifusa&apos;s older brother, Shigeaki UESUGI, lived in Ogigayatsu in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>二橋上杉家、八条上杉家とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also known as Futahashi Uesugi family or Hachijo Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also known as the Futahashi Uesugi family or the Hachijo Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; before family names</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also known as the Futahashi-Uesugi family or the Hachijo-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>扇谷上杉家を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to Ogigayatsu Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to Ogigayatsu Uesugi Family.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;f&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to Ogigayatsu-Uesugi Family.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>越後守護上杉家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Echigo-shugo Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Echigo-shugo Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Echigo-shugo Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>また、犬懸上杉家から越後守護を世襲する越後上杉家が分かれ（養子により血統的には山内上杉家）、越後国内に山本寺上杉家、山浦氏、上条上杉家を分家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Echigo Uesugi family, which practiced hereditary succession of Echigo shugo, branched out into Inukake Uesugi family (because of adoption, it is Yamanouchi Uesugi family by bloodline), Sanbonji Uesugi family, Yamaura Uesugi family and Jojo Uesugi family within Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Echigo Uesugi family, who were hereditary Shugo of Echigo Province, split into the Inukake Uesugi family (through adoption, it is the Yamanouchi Uesugi family by bloodline), and within Echigo Province,the Sanbonji Uesugi family, the Yamaura Uesugi family and the Jojo Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;The&quot;&quot;which practiced hereditary succession of Echigo shugo&quot;→&quot;who were hereditary Shugo of Echigo Province&quot;&quot;branched out&quot;→&quot;split&quot;Added &quot;the&quot; before family names&quot;because of&quot;→&quot;through&quot;Moved &quot;within Echigo Province&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Echigo-Uesugi family, who were hereditary Shugo of Echigo Province, split into the Inukake-Uesugi family (through adoption, it is the Yamanouchi Uesugi family by bloodline), and within Echigo Province, the Sanbonji-Uesugi family, the Yamaura-Uesugi family and the Jojo-Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>守護代の長尾氏と対立するようになり、上杉房定の代には長尾氏を抑え優勢となり全盛期を築き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They became antagonistic to Shugodai Nagao clan, and by Fusatada UESUGI&apos;s generation they suppressed Nagao clan, became dominant and created its glory days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They became antagonistic to the Deputy Shugo Nagao Clan and during Fusatada UESUGI&apos;s time, they defeated the Nagao Clan, becoming the dominant power in what was their heyday.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; and &quot;Deputy&quot;&quot;Shugodai&quot;→&quot;Shugo&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;&quot;by Fusatada UESUGI&apos;s generation&quot;→&quot;during Fusatada UESUGI&apos;s time,&quot;&quot;suppressed&quot;→&quot;defeated&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;&quot;became dominant&quot;→&quot;becoming the dominant power&quot;&quot;and created its glory days&quot;→&quot;in what was their heyday&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They became antagonistic to the Deputy Shugo Nagao clan and during Fusatada UESUGI&apos;s time, they defeated the Nagao clan, becoming the dominant power in what was their heyday.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>房定の死後は、上杉定実を擁する長尾為景によって上杉房能が自害に追い込まれるなど下克上され、上杉定実は為景の死後、伊達氏の支援により復権を図るものの天文の乱により挫折し、後継のないまま死去、1550年に断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Fusatada&apos;s death, there was a mutiny such as Fusayoshi UESUGI&apos;s suicide schemed by Tamekage NAGAO who supported Sadazane UESUGI, and after Tamekage&apos;s death Sadazane UESUGI attempted to regain power with the support of Date clan, but he was defeated in Tenbun War and died without an heir, thereby eliminating the family line in 1550.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Fusatada&apos;s death, there was a mutiny when Tamekage NAGAO, who supported Sadazane UESUGI, staged Fusayoshi UESUGI&apos;s suicide, then after Tamekage&apos;s death, Sadazane UESUGI attempted to regain power with the support of the Date Clan, but he was defeated in the Tenbun War and died without an heir, thereby eliminating the family line in 1550.</e>
<cmt>&quot;such as&quot;→&quot;when&quot;Changed word order&quot;and&quot;→&quot;then&quot;Added commaAdded &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;Added &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Fusatada&apos;s death, there was a mutiny when Tamekage NAGAO, who supported Sadazane UESUGI, staged Fusayoshi UESUGI&apos;s suicide, then after Tamekage&apos;s death, Sadazane UESUGI attempted to regain power with the support of the Date clan, but he was defeated in the Tenbun War and died without an heir, thereby eliminating the family line in 1550.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>千秋上杉家（小山田上杉家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chiaki Uesugi Family (Oyamada Uesugi Family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chiaki Uesugi Family (Oyamada Uesugi Family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chiaki-Uesugi Family (Oyamada-Uesugi Family)</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>憲房の庶兄上杉頼成の系統。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of lineage of Norifusa&apos;s older vassal brother, Yorinari UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descended from Norifusa&apos;s older brother, Yorinari UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Of lineage of&quot;→&quot;Descended from&quot;Deleted &quot;vassal&quot; - I&apos;m not sure where &apos;vassal&apos; comes from, as far as I know, &quot;庶&quot; means illegitimate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descended from Norifusa&apos;s older brother, Yorinari UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>上杉家では庶流筋であるが、子孫としては上杉定頼がおり、彼は一時扇谷上杉家の家督代行を務め、足利持氏に重用され安房国の守護となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though of vassal family&apos;s lineage within Uesugi family, the descendants include Sadayori UESUGI, who served as an acting head of Ogigayatsu Uesugi family at one point, and because he was valued by Mochiuji ASHIKAGA he became a shugo of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though an illegitimate line within the Uesugi family, descendants included Sadayori UESUGI, who served as acting head of the Ogigayatsu Uesugi family at one point and, because he was valued by Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, became Shugo of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;of vassal family&apos;s lineage&quot;→&quot;an illegitimate line&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted &quot;the&quot;Made &quot;include&quot; pastDeleted &quot;an&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Moved commaAdded commaDletd &quot;he&quot; and &quot;a&quot;Capitalized &apos;s&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though an illegitimate line within the Uesugi family, descendants included Sadayori UESUGI, who served as acting head of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi family at one point and, because he was valued by Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, became Shugo of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>長尾氏の養子となった上杉藤景の系統でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also of lineage of Fujikage UESUGI who was adopted by Nagao clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also the family of Fujikage UESUGI, who was adopted by the Nagao Clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;of lineage&quot;→&quot;the family&quot;Added commaAdded &quot;the&quot;Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also the family of Fujikage UESUGI, who was adopted by the Nagao clan.</e>
<cmt>Clan→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>長尾上杉家（米沢藩主家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagao Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagao Uesugi Family (Lords of Yonezawa)</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(Lords of Yonezawa)&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagao-Uesugi Family (Lords of Yonezawa)</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>上田長尾家出身の長岡顕景（景勝）は上杉謙信の養子となり、名を上杉景勝と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akikage NAGAOKA (Kagekatsu) from Ueda Nagao family was adopted by Kenshin UESUGI, and he changed his name to Kagekatsu UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akikage (Kagekatsu) NAGAOKA from the Ueda Nagao family was adopted by Kenshin UESUGI and changed his name to Kagekatsu UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;(Kagekatsu)&quot;Added &quot;the&quot;Deleted comma and &quot;he&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akikage (Kagekatsu) NAGAOKA from the Ueda Nagao family was adopted by Kenshin UESUGI and changed his name to Kagekatsu UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>謙信死後、御館の乱を制し、上杉氏の惣領となり、豊臣秀吉に仕え、会津120万石（陸奥国会津藩）を領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kenshin&apos;s death, he took hold of Otate War and became the soryo of Uesugi clan, served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and gained 1.2 million koku in Aizu (Aizu domain, Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kenshin&apos;s death, was victorious in the Odate War, becoming the leader of the Uesugi clan, served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and gained territory worth 1.2 million koku in Aizu (Aizu domain, Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>&quot;he took hold of Otate War and became the soryo of Uesugi clan&quot;→&quot;was victorious in the Odate War, becoming the leader of the Uesugi clan&quot; Added &quot;territory worth&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kenshin&apos;s death, was victorious in the Odate War, becoming the leader of the Uesugi clan, served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and gained territory worth 1.2 million koku in Aizu (Aizu domain, Mutsu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>秀吉の死後、関ヶ原の戦いでは石田三成ら西軍に付いだが、戦後に家康から罪を許され、出羽国米沢藩30万石で幕末まで存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara after Hideyoshi&apos;s death he was with the west army of Mitsunari ISHIDA, but after the battle he was pardoned by Ieyasu, and he continued to exist with 300,000 koku in Yonezawa domain in Dewa Province until the end of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Sekigahara after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, they sided with Mitsunari Ishida&apos;s Western Army, but after the battle they were pardoned by Ieyasu and continued to exist in the 300,000 koku Yonezawa domain in Dewa Province until the end of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Added comma&quot;he was with the west army of Mitsunari ISHIDA&quot;→&quot;they sided with Mitsunari Ishida&apos;s Western Army&quot;&quot;he was&quot;→&quot;they were&quot;Deleted comma and &quot;he&quot;&quot;with&quot;→&quot;in the&quot;Deleted &quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, they sided with Mitsunari Ishida&apos;s Western Army, but after the battle they were pardoned by Ieyasu and continued to exist in the 300,000 koku Yonezawa domain in Dewa Province until the end of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>庶家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vassal Families</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vassal Families</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vassal Families</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>千坂氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chizaka clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chizaka Clan</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chizaka Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>山浦氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamaura clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamaura Clan</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamaura Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>深谷氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukaya clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukaya Clan</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukaya Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>山本寺氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanbonji clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanbonji Clan</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanbonji Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>上条氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jojo clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jojo Clan</e>
<cmt>Capitalized &apos;c&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jojo Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>米沢藩支藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Branch domain of Yonezawa domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Branch clan of Yonezawa domain</e>
<cmt>&quot;domain&quot;→&quot;clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Branch clan of Yonezawa domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>上杉家家訓十六ヶ条</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">16 precepts of the Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">16 precepts of the Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">16 precepts of the Uesugi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>上杉謙信が残したといわれる家訓。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Precepts said to have been left by Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Precepts said to have been left by Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Precepts said to have been left by Kenshin UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="88">
<j>一、心に物なき時は心広く体泰なり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no materialistic things in your heart your body will be largely at peace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there are no materialistic things in your heart, your body will be at peace.</e>
<cmt>&quot;is&quot;→&quot;are&quot;deleted &quot;largely&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there are no materialistic things in your heart, your body will be at peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>一、心に我儘なき時は愛敬失わず</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no selfishness in your heart you won&apos;t forget winsomeness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no selfishness in your heart, you won&apos;t forget winsomeness.</e>
<cmt>Added comma&quot;winsomeness&quot;→&quot;courtesy&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no selfishness in your heart, you won&apos;t forget winsomeness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>一、心に欲なき時は義理を行う</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no greed in your heart you will oblige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no greed in your heart, you will oblige.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no greed in your heart, you will oblige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>一、心に私なき時は疑うことなし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no ego self in your heart you will not doubt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no ego in your heart, you will not doubt.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;self&quot;Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no ego in your heart, you will not doubt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>一、心に驕りなき時は人を救う</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no arrogance in your heart you will save people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no arrogance in your heart, you will save people.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no arrogance in your heart, you will save people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>一、心に誤りなき時は人を畏れず</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no mistake in your heart you will not fear people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no mistake in your heart, you will not fear people.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no mistake in your heart, you will not fear people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>一、心に邪見なき時は人を育てる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no evil thought in your heart you will nurture people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no evil thought in your heart, you will nurture people.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no evil thought in your heart, you will nurture people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>一、心に貪りなき時は人に諂うことなし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no endless greed in your heart you will not grovel to people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no endless greed in your heart, you will not grovel to people.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no endless greed in your heart, you will not grovel to people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>一、心に怒りなき時は言葉和らかなり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no anger in your heart your words will be gentle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no anger in your heart, your words will be gentle.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no anger in your heart, your words will be gentle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>一、心に堪忍ある時は事を調う</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is endurance in your heart you will be able to balance things.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is endurance in your heart, you will be able to balance things.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is endurance in your heart, you will be able to balance things.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>一、心に曇りなき時は心静かなり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no cloud in your heart your heart will be calm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no cloud in your heart, your heart will be calm.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no cloud in your heart, your heart will be calm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>一、心に勇ある時は悔やむことなし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is courage in your heart you will not regret.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is courage in your heart, you will not regret.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is courage in your heart, you will not regret.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>一、心賎しからざる時は願好まず</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no avarice in your heart you will not want to make wishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no avarice in your heart you will not desire.</e>
<cmt>&quot;want to make wishes&quot;→&quot;desire&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no avarice in your heart you will not desire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>一、心に孝行ある時は忠節厚し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is devotion in your heart you will be very loyal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is devotion in your heart, you will be very loyal.</e>
<cmt>Added comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is devotion in your heart, you will be very loyal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>一、心に自慢なき時は人の善を知り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no arrogance you will know the goodness in people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no arrogance in your heart, you will know the goodness in people.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;in your heart&quot; and comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no arrogance in your heart, you will know the goodness in people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>一、心に迷いなき時は人を咎めず</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When there is no confusion in your heart you do not berate people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When there is no confusion in your heart, you will not find fault with others.</e>
<cmt>Added comma&quot;do not berate people&quot;→&quot;will not find fault with others&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When there is no confusion in your heart, you will not find fault with others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Bakkai(id:7233), Y.Sanada(id:36926), 陽一(id:92099), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 味っ子(id:17086), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Sgi1962(id:80778), 百人(id:16483), Sen-K(id:17895), Frei(id:12101), Loveless(id:129239), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Caminante(id:39410), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 常陸介(id:176100), Gimbrow(id:65660), 山田のの子(id:99832), 万華鏡(id:24615), やりたこ(id:113528), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松平定治(id:146386), Vantey(id:22521), レッドバロン(id:173220), Boca samba(id:137526), Pitan(id:171), 海衛士(id:19229), Nalc(id:139567), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Safkan(id:423), Junger(id:10282), Suisui(id:69), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>