<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>世阿弥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zeami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zeami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>世阿弥（ぜあみ、せあみ（改称前）世阿彌陀佛、正平 (日本)18年/貞治2年（1363年）? - 嘉吉3年8月8日 (旧暦)（1443年9月1日）?）は日本の室町時代初期の猿楽師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami (Zeami or Seami, (before the change of name) Ze-amidabutu, 1363? ~ September 1, 1443?) was a Sarugaku-shi in Muromachi era.,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zeami (Zeami or Seami, (before the change of name) Ze-amidabutsu, 1363(?) (September 1, 1443{?}) was a Sarugaku-shi in the Muromachi era.</e>
<cmt>Unless it is made clear what a 猿楽師 is at another previous point, English readers will not understand the term &apos;Sarugaku-shi&apos;. 猿楽師の説明を簡潔に加えてください。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zeami (Zeami or Seami, (before the change of name) Ze-amidabutsu, 1363(?) (September 10, 1443{?}) was a Sarugaku (form of theater becoming the basis for Noh) performer in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Sarugaku-shi→Sarugaku performerとし、Sarugakuの補足追加、Muromachi era→Muromachi periodに修正September 1→September 10に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>父の観阿弥（觀阿彌陀佛）とともに猿楽（申楽とも。現在の能）を大成し、多くの書を残す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In cooperation with his father, Kanami (Kan-amidabutsu), Zeami perfected Sarugaku (present Noh [http://www.the-noh.com/index.html]) and left many books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In cooperation with his father, Kanami (Kan-amidabutsu), Zeami perfected Sarugaku (present Noh [http://www.the-noh.com/index.html]) and left many books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In cooperation with his father, Kanami (Kan-amidabutsu), Zeami perfected Sarugaku (present Noh) and left many books.</e>
<cmt>[http://www.the-noh.com/index.html]を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>観阿弥、世阿弥の能は観世流として現代に受け継がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh of Zeami and Kanami has been inherited up until now as Kanze-ryu (Kanze school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Noh practiced by Zeami and Kanami has been passed down to modernity as the Kanze-ryu (Kanze school).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Noh practiced by Zeami and Kanami has been passed down to modernity as the Kanze-ryu (Kanze school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>幼名は鬼夜叉、そして二条良基から藤若の名を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His childhood name was Oni-yasha and Yoshimoto NIJO donated him a name, Fujiwaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Oni-yasha and Yoshimoto NIJO bestowed upon him the name Fujiwaka.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Oni-yasha and Yoshimoto NIJO bestowed upon him the name Fujiwaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>通称は三郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His popular name was Saburo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His popular name was Saburo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His popular name was Saburo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>実名は元清。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was Motokiyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was Motokiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was Motokiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>父の死後、観世大夫を継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his father&apos;s death, he inherited Kanze-dayu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his father&apos;s death, he inherited the position of Kanze-dayu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his father&apos;s death, he inherited the position of Kanze-dayu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>40代以降に時宗の法名（時宗の男の法名（戒名）は阿弥陀如来（阿彌陀佛）号であり、ちなみに世は観世に由来）である世阿弥陀仏が略されて世阿弥と称されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his 40th and thereafter, Zeamidabutsu, his Homyo (Buddhist name) in Jishu (In jishu, Homyo (Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist names) of men is Amida-nyorai (Amidabutsu) Go (byname). Ze (Se) came from Kanze.), was abbreviated as Zeami and he became to be called Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his 40s and after, Zeamidabutsu, his Homyo (Buddhist name) in Jishu (In jishu, Homyo (Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist names) of men is Amida-nyorai (Amidabutsu) Go (byname). Ze (Se) came from Kanze) was abbreviated as Zeami and he became to be called Zeami.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t really understand the use of the all the parenthesis. Parenthesis are used somewhat sparingly in English, compared to Japanese. Is there a way to avoid using this much? It is very confusing to the reader.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his 40s and after, Zeamidabutsu, his Buddhist name in Jishu sect of Buddhism (In jishu, posthumous Buddhist names of men is Amida-nyorai (Amidabutsu) Go (byname). Ze (Se) came from Kanze) was abbreviated as Zeami and he became to be called Zeami.</e>
<cmt>Jishuのみでは意味が不明確なため、Jishu sect of Buddhism (初出) とし、訳文が明確になるよう、Homyo (Buddhist name)→Buddhist name、Homyo (Kaimyo (posthumous Buddhist names)→posthumous Buddhist namesのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>世の字の発音が濁るのは、足利義満の指示によるもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why Ze is pronounced as a dull sound is by an instruction by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA who first propagated the pronunciation of Ze in its voiced-consonant form--as opposed to the unvoiced-consonant sound of Se.</e>
<cmt>The distinction between voiced and unvoiced consonant sounds are unfamiliar to English speakers, and require add explanation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA who first propagated the pronunciation of Ze in its voiced-consonant form - as opposed to the unvoiced-consonant sound of Se.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami&apos;s Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Life of Zeami</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>世阿弥が生まれたとき父である観阿弥は31歳で、大和猿楽の有力な役者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Zeami was born, his father, Kanami was 31 years old and a leading player of Yamato-Sarugaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Zeami was born, his father, Kanami was 31 years old and a leading player of the Yamato-Sarugaku.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Zeami was born, his father, Kanami was 31 years old and a leading player of the Yamato-Sarugaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>世阿弥の母については、近年発見された文書により「播磨国揖保庄の永富左衛門六郎の娘」という説もあるが不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to Zeami&apos;s mother, there is an opinion based on recently found documents that she was &quot;a daughter of Saemon Rokuro NAGATOMI in Ibosho, Harima-no-kuni,&quot; but it may or may not be true.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently uncovered documents regarding Zeami&apos;s mother have revealed that she could have been &quot;a daughter of Saemon Rokuro NAGATOMI in Ibosho, Harima-no-kuni;&quot; however, the veracity of this claim is still in question.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently uncovered documents regarding Zeami&apos;s mother have revealed that she could have been &apos;a daughter of Saemon Rokuro NAGATOMI in Ibosho, Harima Province;&apos; however, the veracity of this claim is still in question.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、Harima-no-kuni→Harima Provinceに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>観阿弥がひきいる一座は興福寺の庇護を受けていたが京都へ進出し、醍醐寺の7日間興行などで名をとどろかせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The company lead by Kanami was patronized by Kofuku-ji Temple, but they moved in Kyoto and attained fame with seven-day performance in Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The troupe lead by Kanami was patronized by Kofuku-ji Temple, but they moved to Kyoto and attained fame with a seven-day performance in Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>wording; note that &apos;troupe&apos; is a less ambiguous word than &apos;company&apos; when it comes to acting</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troupe lead by Kanami was patronized by Kofuku-ji Temple, but they moved to Kyoto and attained fame with a seven-day performance in Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>世阿弥は幼少のころから父の一座に出演していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami appeared on stage with his father&apos;s company already in his early childhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zeami began his appearance on stage with his father&apos;s troupe from his early childhood.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zeami began his appearance on stage with his father&apos;s troupe from his early childhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>1374年または1375年、観阿弥が今熊野で催した猿楽（申楽）能に12歳の世阿弥が出演したとき、室町将軍足利義満の目にとまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1374 or 1375, when Zeami, who was 12 years old, appeared on stage in Sarugaku Noh performance held by Kanami, he caught Muromachi Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA&apos;s attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1374 or 1375, when Zeami, who was 12 years old at the time, appeared on stage in the Sarugaku Noh performance held by Kanami, he caught the attention of the Muromachi Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1374 or 1375, when Zeami, who was 12 years old at the time, appeared on stage in the Sarugaku Noh performance held by Kanami, he caught the attention of the Muromachi Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>以後、義満は観阿弥・世阿弥親子を庇護するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, Yoshimitsu patronized the father and son, Kanami and Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that performance, Yoshimitsu patronized both father and son, Kanami and Zeami.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that performance, Yoshimitsu patronized both father and son, Kanami and Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1378年の祇園会では将軍義満の桟敷に世阿弥が近侍し、公家の批判をあびている（「後愚昧記」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the occasion of Gion-e in 1378, Zeami attended the box of Shogun Yoshimitsu and he was subjected to criticism by Kuge (&quot;Gogumai-ki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the occasion of Gion-e in 1378, Zeami attended the box of Shogun Yoshimitsu and he was criticized by Kuge (&quot;Gogumai-ki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the occasion of Gion-e in 1378, Zeami attended the box of Shogun Yoshimitsu and he was criticized by Kuge (&apos;Gogumaiki,&apos; the journal of Kintada SANJO).</e>
<cmt>Gogumaikiとし、クォーテーションをシングルに変更、補足を追加 （参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=nT9CI5YQF_4C&amp;pg=PA463&amp;dq=Gogumaiki&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=4#v=onepage&amp;q=Gogumaiki&amp;f=false)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1384年に観阿弥が没して世阿弥は観世太夫を継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1384, Kanami died and Zeami succeeded the name Kanze-dayu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon Kanami&apos;s 1384 death, Zeami continued the line of Kanze-dayu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon Kanami&apos;s 1384 death, Zeami continued the line of Kanze-dayu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>当時の貴族・武家社会には、幽玄を尊ぶ気風があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, in aristocratic society and Samurai&apos;s society, there was general atmosphere to respect Yugen (the subtle and profound).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, there was a general atmosphere of reverence in aristocratic and Samurai society for the concept of Yugen (the subtle and profound).</e>
<cmt>wording; my compliments to the translator for selecting &apos;subtle and profound&apos; for Yugen.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, there was a general atmosphere of reverence in aristocratic and Samurai society for the concept of Yugen (the subtle and profound).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>世阿弥は観客である彼らの好みに合わせ、言葉、所作、歌舞、物語に幽玄美を漂わせる能の形式「夢幻能」を大成させていったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We can surmised that, to satisfy their taste as spectators, Zeami completed the Noh format &quot;Mugen-noh&quot; in which words, postures, songs and dances, and stories show beauty of Yugen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that Zeami created the Noh format &quot;Mugen-noh,&quot; where words, postures, songs and dances, and stories show the beauty of Yugen, so as to satisfy the tastes of his spectators.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that Zeami created the Noh format &apos;Mugen-noh,&apos; where words, postures, songs and dances, and stories show the beauty of Yugen, so as to satisfy the tastes of his spectators.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>一般に猿楽者の教養は低いものだったが、世阿弥は将軍や貴族の保護を受け、教養を身に付けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally speaking, cultural level of Sarugaku players was low, but Zeami had acquired some culture under patronage of Shogun and nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally speaking, the level of cultural training of the Sarugaku players was low, but Zeami had acquired some cultural training under the patronage of the Shogun and his nobles.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally speaking, the level of cultural training of the Sarugaku players was low, but Zeami had acquired some cultural training under the patronage of the Shogun and his nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>特に摂政二条良基には連歌を習い、これは後々世阿弥の書く能や能芸論に影響を及ぼしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially from Sessho, Yoshimoto NIJO, he learned Renga and this later gave influence to Noh and the Theory of Noh that Zeami wrote.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He learned Renga from Sessho, Yoshimoto NIJO, and this subsequently influenced Noh and Zeami&apos;s Theory of Noh.</e>
<cmt>wording; Renga requires an explanation in parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He learned Renga (linked verse) from a regent, Yoshimoto NIJO, and this subsequently influenced Noh and Zeami&apos;s Theory of Noh.</e>
<cmt>Rengaの補足追加、Sessho→a regentとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>義満の死後、将軍が足利義持の代になっても、世阿弥はさらに猿楽を深化させていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after Yoshimitsu&apos;s death, in the era of Shogun, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, Zeami had deepened Sarugaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after Yoshimitsu&apos;s death, Zeami continued to deepen Sarugakuin during Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA&apos;s reign as Shogun.</e>
<cmt>wording; 直訳調の文章を英語らしく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after Yoshimitsu&apos;s death, Zeami continued to deepen Sarugakuin during Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA&apos;s reign as Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>『風姿花伝』（1400年ごろ成立か）『至花道』が著されたのもこのころである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time &quot;Fushikaden (The Flowering Spirit) (written in sometime around 1400) and &quot;Shikado&quot; was written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time both Fushikaden (The Flowering Spirit) (circa 1400) and Shikado were written.</e>
<cmt>verb tense (was to were); note: quotations not required when citing text titles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time both &quot;Fushikaden&quot; (The Flowering Spirit) (circa 1400) and &quot;Shikado&quot; were written.</e>
<cmt>仕様書に基づき作品名にクォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>義持は猿楽よりも田楽好みであったため、義満のころほどは恩恵を受けられなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Yoshimochi preferred Dengaku to Sarugaku, benefits Zeami received became smaller than benefits given by Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Yoshimochi preferred Dengaku to Sarugaku, Zeami enjoyed less patronage than he received from Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Yoshimochi preferred Dengaku (ritual music and dancing in shrines and temples) to Sarugaku, Zeami enjoyed less patronage than he received from Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>Dengakuの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>義持が没し足利義教の代になると弾圧が加えられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshimochi&apos;s death, in the era of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, oppression to Zeami began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshimochi&apos;s death, the new Shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, began to oppress Zeami.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshimochi&apos;s death, the new Shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, began to oppress Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>1422年、観世大夫の座を長男の観世元雅に譲り、自身は出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1422, Zeami assigned the position of Kanze-dayu to his eldest son, Motomasa KANZE and he himself became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1422, Zeami assigned the position of Kanze-dayu to his eldest son, Motomasa KANZE and he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1422, Zeami assigned the position of Kanze-dayu to his eldest son, Motomasa KANZE and he became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかし将軍足利義教は、元雅の従兄弟にあたる観世三郎元重（音阿弥）を重用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, however, treated Saburo-motoshige KANZE (Onami), who was a cousin of Motomasa, preferentially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA gave preferential treatment to Saburo-motoshige KANZE (Onami), a cousin of Motomasa.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA gave preferential treatment to Saburo-motoshige KANZE (Onami), a cousin of Motomasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>仙洞御所への出入り禁止（1429年）、醍醐清滝宮の楽頭職罷免（1430年）など、世阿弥・元雅親子は地位と興行地盤を着実に奪われていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami and Motomasa, the father and son, were gradually lost their positions and bases for performance as seen from being barred from access to Sento-gosho (1429) and dismissal as Gakuto Title of Daigo-seiryogu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zeami and Motomasa, father and son, gradually lost their status and performance venues. They were barred from entering Sento-gosho (1429) and had the Gakuto title of Daigo-seiryogu revoked.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zeami and Motomasa, father and son, gradually lost their status and performance venues; they were barred from entering Sento-gosho (1429) and had the Gakuto title of Daigo-seiryogu revoked (1430).</e>
<cmt>(1430年)を訳出、二文に分かれているため一文になるよう修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>1432年、長男の観世元雅は伊勢安濃津にて客死してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1432, Zeami&apos;s eldest son, Motomasa KANZE died in Ise-Anotsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1432, Zeami&apos;s eldest son, Motomasa KANZE died in Ise-Anotsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1432, Zeami&apos;s eldest son, Motomasa KANZE died in Anotsu, Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>Ise-Anotsu→Anotsu, Ise Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>世阿弥自身も1434年に佐渡国に流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1436, Zeami himself was deported to Sado-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1436, Zeami himself was deported to Sado-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1436, Zeami himself was deported to Sado Province.</e>
<cmt>Sado-no-kuni→Sado Provinceに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1436年（永享8年）には『金島書』を著すが、その後の消息はよく分かっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1436, he wrote &quot;Kintosho&quot;, but his whereabouts and so on thereafter are not known clearly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1436, he wrote Kintosho, but his whereabouts and other details of his life remain unclear.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1436, he wrote &quot;Kintosho&quot; (The Book of Golden Island), but his whereabouts and other details of his life remain unclear.</e>
<cmt>Kintosho→クォーテーション・補足追加 (参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=Rty-xnBHkSsC&amp;pg=PR50&amp;dq=zeami+kintosho&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=4#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>晩年には大和国の禅寺・補巌寺に帰依していており、彼と妻の名を記した納帳が発見されている（香西精『世阿弥新考』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later days, Zeami became a believer in Zen temple, Figan-ji Temple in Yamato-no-kuni, and a Nocho (tax ledger) having his name and his wife&apos;s name was discovered (Tsutomu KOSAI, &quot;Zeami Shinko&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later days, Zeami joined the Zen temple Figan-ji in Yamato-no-kuni. A Nocho (tax ledger) has been discovered with both his name and his wife&apos;s (Tsutomu KOSAI, Zeami Shinko).</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t understand what Zeami Shinko is in this context? Is this the source for that info?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later days, Zeami joined the Zen temple Fugan-ji in Yamato Province. A Nocho (tax ledger) has been discovered with both his name and his wife&apos;s (Tsutomu KOSAI, &quot;Zeami Shinko&quot;(New thoughts on Zeami)).</e>
<cmt>「補巌寺(ふがんじ）」の読みの誤りを訂正、Yamato-no-kuni→Yamato Provinceとし、Zeami Shinkoにクォーテーション・補足を追加　(参照: http://www.tc.umn.edu/~cmedst/gmap/uploaded/Shamanism%20in%20the%20Origins%20of%20the%20No%20Theatre.pdf)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>後に帰洛したとも伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that, later, he came back to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also said to have returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also said to have returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>「観世小次郎画像賛」によれば嘉吉三年（1443年）に没したことになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kojiro KANZE Gazo-san&quot;, he died in 1443.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Kojiro KANZE Gazo-san, he died in 1443.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &apos;Kanze Kojiro Gazo-san,&apos; he died in 1443.</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、Kojiro KANZE Gazo-san→&apos;Kanze Kojiro Gazo-san&apos;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>業績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>世阿弥の作品とされるものには『高砂』『井筒』『実盛』など50曲近くがあり、現在も能舞台で上演されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are close to 50 plays including &quot;Takasago&quot;, &quot;Izutsu&quot;, and &quot;Sanemori,&quot;which are attributed to Zeami and they are played on Noh stages even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are close to 50 plays attributable to Zeami still performed on stage today, including Takasago, Izutsu, and Sanemori.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are close to 50 plays attributable to Zeami still performed on stage today, including &quot;Takasago,&quot; &quot;Izutsu,&quot; and &quot;Sanemori.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせクォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、『風姿花伝』などの芸論も史料価値だけではなく、文学的価値も高いとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His treatises on artistic performances, such as &quot;Fushikaden&quot; have been rated highly not only for their value as historical materials but also for their value as literary creations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His treatises on artistic performances, such as Fushikaden, have been lauded for both their historical and literary aesthetic value.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His treatises on artistic performances, such as Fushikaden, have been lauded for both their historical and literary aesthetic value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="38">
<j>芸道論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">View on Performing Art</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Views on Performing Arts</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Views on Performing Arts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>著書『風姿花伝』（『風姿華傳』、『花伝書』）では、観客に感動を与える力を「花」として表現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his books, &quot;Fushikaden&quot; and &quot;Kadensho&quot;, power to make audience sense excitement is expressed as &quot;Hana (flower.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his books, Fushikaden and Kadensho, the power to emotionally move his audience is expressed as &apos;Hana&apos; (flower).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his book, &quot;Fushikaden&quot; (or &quot;Kadensho&quot;), the power to emotionally move his audience is expressed as &apos;Hana&apos; (flower).</e>
<cmt>『花伝書』→『風姿花伝』の別名であるため、books→book、およびFushikaden and Kadensho→&quot;Fushikaden&quot; (or &quot;Kadensho&quot;)としました。(参照: http://kotobank.jp/word/%E8%8A%B1%E4%BC%9D%E6%9B%B8)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>少年は美しい声と姿をもつが、それは「時分の花」に過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boys have melodious voice and beautiful figure, but they are mere &quot;Jibun no Hana(the Flower of the moment).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boys have a melodious voice and beautiful figure, but they are merely &apos;Jibun no Hana&apos; (the Flower of the moment).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boys have a melodious voice and beautiful figure, but they are merely &apos;Jibun no Hana&apos; (the Flower of the moment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>能の奥義である「まことの花」は心の工夫公案から生まれると説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lectured that esoteric of Noh, &quot;Makoto no hana (the true Flower)&quot; is created by devising and elaboration by heart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He taught that the mystery of Noh is &apos;Makoto no hana (the true Flower),&apos; created by devising and elaboration by heart.</e>
<cmt>wording; I don&apos;t understand the lettering in red. 再翻訳をお願いいたします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He taught that the mystery of Noh is &apos;Makoto no hana&apos; (the true Flower), created by kufu (dedication to spiritual improvement) and koan (Zen question for meditation) within yourself.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動、「心の工夫公案」の表記を修正 (参照: http://tangorin.com/words/)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="42">
<j>「秘すれば花なり。秘せずは花なるべからず」として『風姿花伝』の内容は長らく秘伝とされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents of &quot;Fushikaden&quot; had long been treated as secret telling as &quot;If it is hidden, it is the Flower; if it is not hidden, it is not the Flower.[&quot;The Flowering Spirit&quot;; publisher: Kodansha International (2006/07), ISBN-10: 4770024991, ISBN-13: 978-4770024992]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The contents of Fushikaden were long kept secret--&quot;If it is hidden, it is the Flower; if it is not hidden, it is not the Flower. [Source: The Flowering Spirit, Kodansha International (2006/07), ISBN-10: 4770024991, ISBN-13: 978-4770024992].</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The contents of &quot;Fushikaden&quot; were long kept secret - &apos;If it is hidden, it is the Flower; if it is not hidden, it is not the Flower.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Fushikadenにクォーテーション追加、ハイフン削除、スペースおよび[]内の補足を削除、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="43">
<j>代表作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative Works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Key Works</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Key Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="44">
<j>世阿弥は数多くの謡曲を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami left many Yokyoku after him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zeami left many Yokyoku after him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zeami left many Yokyoku after him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>謡曲とは、能における節と詞（ことば）、または能の脚本（謡本）そのものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokyoku means staves and words for Noh or playbook for Noh itself (utai libretto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokyoku means staves and words for Noh or playbook for Noh itself (utai libretto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yokyoku means staves and words for Noh or playbook for Noh itself (Utai-bon (chant book)).</e>
<cmt>「謡本」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="46">
<j>弓八幡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yumiyawata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yumiyawata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yumi Yawata (The Bow at the Hachiman Shrine)</e>
<cmt>Yumi Yawataとし、補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>高砂 (能)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasago (Noh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasago (Noh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasago</e>
<cmt>Nohはあえて必要ないと思われますので削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>老松</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oimatsu (Noh)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oimatsu (Noh)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oimatsu (The Old Pine Tree)</e>
<cmt>Nohを削除、補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="49">
<j>実盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanemori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanemori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>頼政（平家物語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimasa (Heike Monogatari (The tale of the Heike)[http://www.kufs.ac.jp/toshokan/miyabi/heike.htm])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimasa (Heike Monogatari (The tale of the Heike)[http://www.kufs.ac.jp/toshokan/miyabi/heike.htm])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimasa (Heike Monogatari (The tale of the Heike))</e>
<cmt>[http://www.kufs.ac.jp/toshokan/miyabi/heike.htm]を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>忠度（平家物語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadanori (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadanori (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadanori (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>清経（平家物語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>敦盛（平家物語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsumori (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsumori (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsumori (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>八島 (能)（平家物語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yashima (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yashima (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yashima (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="55">
<j>井筒 (能)（伊勢物語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izutsu (Noh)(Ise Monogatari (The tales of Ise)[Publisher: Charles E. Tuttle Publishing (2005/11) ISBN-10: 4805307404, ISBN-13: 978-4805307403]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izutsu (Noh)(Ise Monogatari (The tales of Ise)[Publisher: Charles E. Tuttle Publishing (2005/11) ISBN-10: 4805307404, ISBN-13: 978-4805307403]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izutsu (Ise Monogatari (The tales of Ise))</e>
<cmt>Nohを削除、スペース・カッコを追加、[]内の文を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>恋重荷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koi no Omoni (The Burden of Love)[http://nohgakuland.com/weblog/archives/2005/06/post_14.html]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koi no Omoni (The Burden of Love)[http://nohgakuland.com/weblog/archives/2005/06/post_14.html]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koi no Omoni (The Burden of Love)</e>
<cmt>[]内の文を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>錦木</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishikigi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishikigi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishikigi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>砧 (能)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinuta</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinuta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinuta</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>葵上（あおいのうえ：源氏物語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aoi-no-ue (Genji Monogatari (The tale of Genji))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aoi-no-ue (Genji Monogatari (The tale of Genji))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aoi no Ue (Genji Monogatari (The tale of Genji))</e>
<cmt>Aoi no Ueとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>融</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toru</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toru</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="61">
<j>当麻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taema</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taema</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taema</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>野守（万葉集の歌が典拠）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nomori (Source: Verse in Manyo-shu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nomori (Source: Verse in Manyo-shu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nomori (Source: Verse in Manyo-shu, or Collection of Ten Thousand Leaves)</e>
<cmt>Manyo-shuの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>鍾馗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>鵺（ぬえ：平家物語）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nue (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nue (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nue (Heike Monogatari)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>桜川</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakuragawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakuragawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakuragawa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>花筐（はながたみ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hana-gatami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hana-gatami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hana-gatami (The flower Basket)</e>
<cmt>補足追加 (参照: http://www.noh-theater.com/english/schedule_2008.html)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>葦刈（あしかり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashikari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashikari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashikari (The Reed Cutter)</e>
<cmt>補足追加 (参照: http://www.museumstuff.com/learn/topics/List_of_Noh_plays:_A-M)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>春栄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>西行桜(さいぎょうざくら）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saigyo-zakura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saigyo-zakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saigyo-zakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>著作</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami&apos;s Works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zeami&apos;s Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zeami&apos;s Works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>世阿弥は父の遺訓、また自ら会得した芸術論を、「道のため、家のため」（『風姿花伝』）多数書き遺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami put down his father&apos;s teachings and his own acquired views on performing art in writing in order to approach his art as a mich - as a whole way of life and as a ie - as a family heritage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zeami wrote down his father&apos;s teachings and his own acquired views on the performing arts in order to approach his art as a michi--as a way of life--and as an ie--as a family heritage.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zeami wrote down his father&apos;s teachings and his own acquired views on the performing arts in order to approach his art as a michi - as a way of life, and as an ie - as a family heritage (&quot;Fushikaden&quot;).</e>
<cmt>（『風姿花伝』）を訳出、ハイフン消去、スペース、カンマ追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>その伝書は秘伝とされ、世阿弥の血筋を承けた越智観世家、そして観世宗家、また女婿禅竹を通じて金春家などが多く所蔵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Densho was treated as secrets and many of them are owned by Ochi-Kanze Family, that inherited Zeami&apos;s blood, Kanze family head [http://www.bushi.eu/A%20Sketch%20of%20the%20Present%20Japanese%20Martial%20Arts%20(Copyrights%20by%20M.%20Sterke,%202006,%20Tilburg).pdf], and Konbaru Family through Zenchiku, Musume Muko (son-in-law).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Densho were treated as secrets and many of them are owned by the Ochi-Kanze Family, who are the blood descendants of Zeami, the Kanze family head. [Source: http://www.bushi.eu/A%20Sketch%20of%20the%20Present%20Japanese%20Martial%20Arts%20(Copyrights%20by%20M.%20Sterke,%202006,%20Tilburg).pdf], and Konbaru Family through Zenchiku, Musume Muko (son-in-law).</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t understand how the lettering in red fits in to the rest of the passage. Please clarify.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Densho were treated as secrets and many of them are owned by the Ochi-Kanze family, who are the blood descendants of Zeami, the Kanze head family, and the Konparu family through Zeami&apos;s son-in-low, Zenchiku.</e>
<cmt>the Ochi-Kanze family、the Konparu familyとし、[]内の文を削除、the Kanze family head→the Kanze head familyとし、Zenchiku, Musume Muko (son-in-law)→ Zeami&apos;s son-in-low, Zenchikuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>室町後期に越智観世家が絶え、観世宗家から入った養子が再興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Ochi-Kanze died out in the late Muromachi era and an adopted child from Kanze family head restored it, most of Densho, of which Ochi-Kanze owned the largest part reportedly, were transferred to Kanze family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ochi-Kanze family died out in the late Muromachi era and an adopted child from the Kanze family had restored the text. Most of Densho, of which Ochi-Kanze reportedly owned the largest part, was transferred to the Kanze family head.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ochi-Kanze family died out in the late Muromachi period and an adopted child from the Kanze head family had restored the text.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」Muromachi era→Muromachi periodに修正、およびthe Kanze family→the Kanze head familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>越智観世が最も多く有していたといわれる伝書はあらかた観世宗家に渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of Densho, of which Ochi-Kanze reportedly owned the largest part, was transferred to the Kanze head family.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」the Kanze family head→the Kanze head familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>またそれとは別に、越智観世から複数の伝書が能を愛好した徳川家康に献上され、家康を通じて細川幽斎や織田信忠がこれを手に入れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Independently from that, multiple Densho were gave up to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who loved Noh by Ochi-Kanze and Yusai HOSOKAWA and Nobutada ODA obtained them through Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aside from this, multiple Densho were given to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who had an affinity for Noh by Ochi-Kanze and Yusai HOSOKAWA. Nobutada ODA later obtained them through Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>wording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aside from this, multiple Densho were given to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who had an affinity for Noh by Ochi-Kanze; Yusai HOSOKAWA and Nobutada ODA later obtained them through Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>二文→一文、および原文の内容に沿わない部分を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>近世にも能楽関係者や一部大名家を除いて出回ることは殆どなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except relevant people of Noh-gaku and certain families of feudal lord, Densho hardly got into circulation even in recent days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the exception of the relevant people of Noh-gaku and certain families of feudal lords, the Densho enjoyed little circulation even into recent times.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the exception of the relevant people of Noh and certain families of feudal lords, the Densho enjoyed little circulation even into recent times.</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、Noh-gaku→Nohに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>数少ない例外として、14代大夫の観世清親とともに世阿弥伝書の収集に尽力した15代大夫の観世元章が、1772年に『習道書』に注釈を加えて出版し、座衆の一部に配布したこと、元章の後援者であった田安宗武が観世大夫が所蔵する本の一部を書写したこと、そして1818年に柳亭種彦が家康の蔵書であった『申楽談儀』を手に入れ、周囲の文人数名が写本を作ったことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an exception, together with the 14th Tayu, Kiyochika KANZE, the 15th Tayu, Motoakira KANZE, who endeavored to collect Zeami Densho, published &quot;Shudosho&quot; in 1772 adding annotation and distributed to a part of Za-shu and Munetake TAYASU, Motoaki&apos;s sponsor, transcribed a part of books owned by Kanze Tayu, and in 1818, Tanehiko RYUTEI obtained &quot;Sarugaku Dangi&quot;, which was included in Ieyasu&apos;s collection and several men of letters around his transcribed it, but no Zeami&apos;s works came out in public other than those cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an exception, together with the 14th Tayu, Kiyochika KANZE, the 15th Tayu, Motoakira KANZE, who endeavored to collect Zeami Densho, published Shudosho in 1772 adding annotation and distributed to a part of Za-shu and Munetake TAYASU, Motoaki&apos;s sponsor, transcribed a part of books owned by Kanze Tayu, and in 1818, Tanehiko RYUTEI obtained Sarugaku Dangi, which was included in Ieyasu&apos;s collection and several men of letters around his transcribed it, but no Zeami&apos;s works came out in public other than those cases.</e>
<cmt>This is a run-on sentence. I can&apos;t grasp the full meaning. It should be broken down into at least two discrete sentences. Please don&apos;t place quotation marks around text titles.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As only a few exceptions, together with the 14th Tayu, Kiyochika KANZE, the 15th Tayu, Motoakira KANZE, who endeavored to collect Zeami Densho, published &quot;Shudosho&quot; (Learning the Way) in 1772 adding annotation and distributed to a part of Za-shu; and Munetake TAYASU, Motoaki&apos;s sponsor, transcribed a part of books owned by Kanze Tayu; and in 1818, Tanehiko RYUTEI obtained &quot;Sarugaku Dangi&quot; (Talks about Sarugaku), which was included in Ieyasu&apos;s collection and several men of letters around his transcribed it.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」あげられている「例外」は一つではないため、a exception→only a few exceptionsとし、仕様書に基づき&quot;Shudosho&quot;&quot;Sarugaku Dangi&quot;にクォーテーションを入れ、補足追加、セミコロン追加、余分なスペース削除(参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=UHNxVqaacEAC&amp;pg=PA55&amp;dq=zeami+shudosho&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=4#v=onepage&amp;q=zeami%20shudosho&amp;f=false)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>しかしながら、これ以外に目立った形で世阿弥の著作が表に出ることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, no Zeami&apos;s works came out in public other than those cases.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」but→Howeverとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>20世紀に入り、吉田東伍が『世阿弥十六部集』を出版し、当時知られていた世阿弥の伝書を一挙刊行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 20th century commenced, Togo YOSHIDA published &quot;Zeami jyu-roku bushu&quot; to introduce all of Zeami&apos;s Densho known at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 20th century, Togo YOSHIDA published the Zeami Ju-Roku Bushu to introduce all of Zeami&apos;s Densho known at that time.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 20th century, Togo YOSHIDA published the &quot;Zeami Ju-Roku Bushu&quot; (The Sixteen Treatises of Zeami) to introduce all of Zeami&apos;s Densho known at that time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Zeami Ju-Roku Bushu&quot;にクォーテーション・補足追加 (参照: http://www.genji54.com/japanese%20classical%20lit/general_introduction.htm)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>以後研究が進み、現在では世阿弥の伝書として二十一種が認められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then study developed and, at present, 21 kinds are recognized as Zeami&apos;s Densho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research on Zeami has progressed and has since identified, at present, 21 kinds of Densho from Zeami.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research on Zeami has progressed and has since identified, at present, 21 kinds of Densho from Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kanejan(id:78613), JAnDbot(id:66507), Sat666(id:127263), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Eskimbot(id:29676), 陽一(id:92099), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Maxima m(id:28947), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Mintleaf(id:2216), Electric goat(id:2935), Mishika(id:276), Yuming(id:17854), Hitomitoi(id:123773), Opponent(id:720), Michey.M(id:906), 名無し(id:7386), Rei-bot(id:94097), BotMultichill(id:132395), Loveless(id:129239), Chobot(id:20846), Sumaru(id:20609), Toki-ho(id:10691), Izayohi(id:13095), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), MH(id:1586), Aphaia(id:3132), NekoJaNekoJa(id:23311), Peachkiller(id:99202), Shinkansen(id:13703), Zwobot(id:23873), Gleam(id:4760), Azu(id:1328), Hashar(id:3639), RoboDick(id:34097), VolkovBot(id:105371), Mulukhiyya(id:710), SuisuiBot(id:10165), YurikBot(id:18605), Miya(id:1881), Louperibot(id:128971), Suisui(id:69), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), SieBot(id:126695), 栗花落(id:96208), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>