<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原兼雅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanemasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kanemasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanemasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 兼雅（ふじわら の かねまさ、久安4年（1148年） - 正治2年7月18日 (旧暦)（1200年8月29日））は、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけての公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanemasa (1148-August 29, 1200) was a kugyo (top court officials) from the end of the Heian period to the early days of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kanemasa (1148-August 29, 1200) was a kugyo (top court official) from the end of the Heian period to the early days of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kanemasa (1148-September 5, 1200) was a kugyo (top court official) from the end of the Heian period to the early days of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は花山院家の太政大臣藤原忠雅。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Tadamasa who was one of the Kazanin family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Tadamasa who was a member of the Kazanin family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Tadamasa who was a member of the Kazanin family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は院近臣である中納言藤原家成の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of a vice-councilor of state, FUJIWARA no Ienari who was In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of a vice-councilor of state, FUJIWARA no Ienari who was In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), FUJIWARA no Ienari who was In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier).</e>
<cmt>a vice-councilor of state→Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>従一位、左大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was Juichii (Junior First Rank) and Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was Juichii (Junior First Rank) and Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was Juichii (Junior First Rank) and Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>花山院忠経、五辻家経の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the father of Tadatsune KAZANIN and Ietsune ITSUTSUJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of Tadatsune KAZANIN and Ietsune ITSUTSUJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of Tadatsune KAZANIN and Ietsune ITSUTSUJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>父忠雅の後を継ぎ中央官界に進出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Succeeding to his father Tadamasa, he went into central officialdom.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Succeeding to his father Tadamasa, he went into central officialdom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Succeeding to his father Tadamasa, he went into central officialdom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>平清盛の娘を妻として、平氏政権下において順調に昇進を重ねる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, marrying TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s daughter, he had been promoted smoothly under the Taira-clan government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, marrying TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s daughter, he had been promoted smoothly under the Taira-clan government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, marrying TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s daughter, he had been promoted smoothly under the Taira-clan government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このため寿永2年（1183年）には源義仲によって一旦官職を追われるが、後白河天皇の信任を背景に文治3年（1187年）に元の地位である大納言に復帰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, he was once driven a government post by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka; however, he returned to his former post, chief councilor of state, in 1187 with confidence of Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, he was once driven from a government post by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka; however, he returned to his former post, chief councilor of state, in 1187 with confidence in him shown by Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, he was once driven from a government post by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka; however, he returned to his former post, Dainagon (chief councilor of state), in 1187 with confidence in him shown by Emperor Go-Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>chief councilor of state→Dainagon (chief councilor of state)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>以後正治2年に左大臣に至るまで昇進を重ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he had been promoted up to the Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 1200.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he was promoted up to the Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 1200.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he was promoted up to the Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) in 1200.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>激動期の宮廷にあって最終的に地位を全うしたことで、後世における花山院家の発展の基礎を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By having carried out the post in the end during the tempestuous period of the court, he built the foundation of Kazanin family&apos;s future prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By having carried out the post to the end during the tempestuous period of the court, he built the foundation of the Kazanin family&apos;s future prosperity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By having carried out the post to the end during the tempestuous period of the court, he built the foundation of the Kazanin family&apos;s future prosperity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>和歌、今様に通じた才人としても知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also known as a man of talent, well versed in the waka (traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and imayo (popular style of song in Heian period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also known as a man of talent, well versed in the waka (traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and imayo (popular style of song during the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also known as a man of talent, well versed in the waka (traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and imayo (popular style of song during the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 まさふゆ(id:232040), Masyu(id:31065), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>