<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>稲葉良通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimichi INABA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimichi INABA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimichi INABA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>稲葉 良通/稲葉 一鉄（いなば よしみち/いなば いってつ）は、戦国時代 (日本)から安土桃山時代にかけての武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimichi INABA/Ittetsu INABA was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku to Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimichi INABA/Ittetsu INABA was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the Sengoku to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimichi INABA/Ittetsu INABA was a busho (Japanese military commander) from the Sengoku to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>土岐氏、斎藤道三から斎藤氏3代、織田信長、豊臣秀吉に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Toki clan, three generations of Saito clan from Dosan SAITO, Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served the Toki clan, and three generations of Saito clan from Dosan SAITO, Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served the Toki clan, and three generations of Saito clan from Dosan SAITO, Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>美濃国曽根城主で、安藤守就（道足）、氏家直元（卜全）と併せて西美濃三人衆と併称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the lord of Sone-jo Castle in Mino Province and called as the Three of West Mino with Morinari (Michitari) ANDO and Naomoto (Bokuzen) UJIIE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the lord of Sone-jo Castle in Mino Province and known as one of the Three of West Mino with Morinari (Michitari) ANDO and Naomoto (Bokuzen) UJIIE.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the lord of Sone-jo Castle in Mino Province and known as one of the Three of West Mino with Morinari (Michitari) ANDO and Naomoto (Bokuzen) UJIIE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>号は一鉄（いってつ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His go (pen name) was Ittetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (pen name) was Ittetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (pen name) was Ittetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これが一徹という言葉の語源であるという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some says that it is the origin of a word ittetsu (meaning obstinate, stubborn).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some says that this is the origin of the word ittetsu (meaning obstinate, stubborn).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some says that this is the origin of the word ittetsu (meaning obstinate, stubborn).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>父は稲葉通則で六男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the sixth son to Michinori INABA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the sixth son to Michinori INABA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the sixth son to Michinori INABA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>母は国枝正助の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Shosuke KUNIEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Shosuke KUNIEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Shosuke KUNIEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>正室は三条西実枝の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Saneki SANJONISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His lawful wife was a daughter of Saneki SANJONISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His lawful wife was a daughter of Saneki SANJONISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>子に稲葉貞通、稲葉重通ほか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadamichi INABA and Shigemichi INABA were his sons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadamichi INABA and Shigemichi INABA were his sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadamichi INABA and Shigemichi INABA were his sons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸幕府第3代将軍・徳川家光の乳母となる春日局（ふく）の養祖父にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an adoptive grand father of Kasuga no Tsubone (Fuku) who was a menoto (wet nurse) of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third Shogun of Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an adoptive grand father of Kasuga no Tsubone (Fuku) who was a menoto (wet nurse) of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third Shogun of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an adoptive grand father of Kasuga no Tsubone (Fuku) who was a menoto (wet nurse) of Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third Shogun of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自・家督相続</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Status by birth/Succession to family headship</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Status by birth/Succession to family headship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Status by birth/Succession to family headship</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>一鉄の祖父・稲葉通貞は伊予国の名族・河野氏の一族で、彼の時代に美濃に流れて土豪になったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grand father of Ittetsu, Michisada INABA was from a family of Kono clan, who was a noble family in Iyo Province, and is said that the clan became a local clan as the family moved to Mino Province in his time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grand father of Ittetsu, Michisada INABA, was from a family of the Kono clan, who was a noble family in Iyo Province, and it is said that the clan became a local clan as the family moved to Mino Province in his time.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grand father of Ittetsu, Michisada INABA, was from a family of the Kono clan, who was a noble family in Iyo Province, and it is said that the clan became a local clan as the family moved to Mino Province in his time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、美濃安藤氏と同族で伊賀氏の末裔とされることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also he is said to be a descendant of Iga clan, the same family as Mino Ando clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also he is said to be a descendant of the Iga clan, which is the same family as the Mino Ando clan.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also he is said to be a descendant of the Iga clan, which is the same family as the Mino Ando clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>永正12年（1515年）、美濃の国人である稲葉通則の六男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1515, Ittetsu was born as the sixth son of Michinori INABA, who was a local lord in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1515, Ittetsu was born as the sixth son of Michinori INABA, who was a local lord in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1515, Ittetsu was born as the sixth son of Michinori INABA, who was a local lord in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>幼少時に崇福寺 (岐阜市)で僧侶となっていたが、大永5年（1525年）に父と兄が牧田の戦いで浅井亮政と戦って戦死したため、還俗して家督を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had become a Buddhist monk in Sofuku-ji Temple (Gifu Prefecture) when he was young however he quitted the priesthood and took over the reigns of the family, as his father and elder brother died in a battle against Sukemasa AZAI in 1525.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had become a Buddhist monk at Sofuku-ji Temple (Gifu Prefecture) when he was young, however, he quit the priesthood and took over the reigns of the family, as his father and elder brother died in a battle against Sukemasa AZAI in 1525.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had become a Buddhist monk at Sofuku-ji Temple (Gifu City) when he was young, however, he quit the priesthood and took over the reigns of the family, as his father and elder brother died in a battle against Sukemasa AZAI in 1525.</e>
<cmt>岐阜市です。Prefecture → City</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>土岐・斎藤氏時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of Toki/Saito clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period of Toki/Saito clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period of Toki/Saito clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>はじめ土岐氏に仕え、それを継承した斎藤氏時代にも3代に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He first served Toki clan and also served Saito clan, that succeeded from Toki clan, for 3 generations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He first served the Toki clan and also served the Saito clan, that succeeded the Toki clan, for three generations.</e>
<cmt>reword. I believe the intention is that the Saito clan are descendants of the Toki clan, but I am unsure.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He first served the Toki clan and subsequently served the Saito clan, that succeeded the Toki clan, for three generations.</e>
<cmt>alsoだと並行したようにも解釈できるので subsequentlyに変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>三人衆として最も有力な家臣団だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the three most powerful groups of vassal.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was part of one of the three most powerful groups of vassals.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was part of one of the three most powerful groups of vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのため、信長の美濃攻略で斎藤龍興を見限って信長に寝返ったことは、斎藤氏の滅亡を決定的にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore his decision to desert Tatsuoki SAITO to Nobunaga when Nobunaga invaded Mino Province made conclusive of fall of Saito clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore his decision to desert Tatsuoki SAITO to Nobunaga when Nobunaga invaded Mino Province made conclusive the fall of the Saito clan.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore his decision to desert Tatsuoki SAITO to Nobunaga when Nobunaga invaded Mino Province made conclusive the fall of the Saito clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>織田信長時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga ODA period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>永禄10年（1567年）からは信長に仕え、元亀元年（1570年）の姉川の戦いでは徳川家康と共に戦功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Nobunaga from 1567 and he showed distinguished war service with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in the Battle of Anegawa in 1570.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Nobunaga from 1567 and he showed distinguished war service with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in the Battle of Anegawa in 1570.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Nobunaga from 1567 and he showed distinguished war service with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in the Battle of Anegawa in 1570.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その後も近江国、摂津国、伊勢国、越前国など各地に転戦して武功を発揮したことから、美濃清水城を新たに与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued to show military exploits fighting on successive fronts in Omi Province, Settsu Province, Ise Province and Echizen Province therefore he was rewarded Shimizu-jo Castle in Mino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to show talent in his military exploits fighting on successive fronts in Omi Province, Settsu Province, Ise Province and Echizen Province and was therefore rewarded Shimizu-jo Castle in Mino.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then he continued to show talent in his military exploits fighting on successive fronts in Omi Province, Settsu Province, Ise Province and Echizen Province and was therefore rewarded Shimizu-jo Castle in Mino.</e>
<cmt>Since thenを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>石山戦争をはじめ、天正元年（1573年）の朝倉氏攻め、天正2年（1574年）の伊勢国長島一向一揆攻め、天正3年（1575年）の長篠の戦い、美濃岩村城攻め、天正8年（1580年）の加賀国加賀一向一揆攻めに参加して武功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took part in the Ishiyama War, the attack on Asakura clan in 1573, attack on Nagashima Ikko Ikki Revolt (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Nagashima) in Ise Province in 1574, the Battle of Nagashino in 1575 and the attack on Kaga Ikko Ikki Revolt (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga) in Kaga Province in 1580, and he showed distinguished services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took part in the Ishiyama War, the attack on the Asakura clan in 1573, the attack on the Nagashima Ikko Ikki Revolt (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Nagashima) in Ise Province in 1574, the Battle of Nagashino in 1575 and the attack on Kaga Ikko Ikki Revolt (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga) in Kaga Province in 1580, and he showed distinguished service throughout.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took part in the Ishiyama War, the attack on the Asakura clan in 1573, the attack on the Nagashima Ikko Ikki Revolt (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Nagashima) in Ise Province in 1574, the Battle of Nagashino in 1575 and the attack on Kaga Ikko Ikki Revolt (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Kaga) in Kaga Province in 1580, and he showed distinguished service throughout.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>天正2年（1574年）に剃髪して一鉄と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a monk in 1574 and named himself as Ittetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a monk in 1574 and named himself Ittetsu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a monk in 1574 and named himself Ittetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>本能寺の変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honnoji Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honnoji Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honnoji Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>天正10年（1582年）に信長が本能寺の変で死去すると、美濃で独立した大名になろうと画策する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga died in Honnoji Incident in 1582, he planned to become an independent daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident in 1582, he planned to become an independent daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga died in the Honnoji Incident in 1582, he planned to become an independent daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>かつて信長に追放されていた安藤守就の一族が、復権を目指して現在は稲葉領となっている旧領の本田城や北方城を攻撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family of Morinari ANDO, who was once exiled by Nobunaga, attacked their former territories Kitakata-jo Castle and Honda-jo Castle, which were territories of Inaba then, aiming for the reinstatement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family of Morinari ANDO, who were once exiled by Nobunaga, attacked their former territories Kitakata-jo Castle and Honda-jo Castle, which were territories of Inaba then, aiming for their reinstatement.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family of Morinari ANDO, who were once exiled by Nobunaga, attacked their former territories Kitakata-jo Castle and Honda-jo Castle, which were territories of Inaba then, aiming for their reinstatement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そのため守就と戦い、一族もろともこれを討ち果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fought against Morinari and destroyed Morinari and the family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought against Morinari and destroyed Morinari and their family.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought against Morinari and destroyed Morinari and their family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>天正11年（1583年）1月、娘婿である揖斐城主・堀池半之丞と戦い、その領地を支配下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1583, he fought against the lord of Ibi-jo Castle, Hannojo HORIIKE who was a adopted son-in-law and he ruled the territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1583, he fought against the lord of Ibi-jo Castle, Hannojo HORIIKE who was an adopted son-in-law, and then he ruled the territory.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1583, he fought against the lord of Ibi-jo Castle, Hannojo HORIIKE who was an adopted son-in-law, and then he ruled the territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>豊臣秀吉時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>羽柴秀吉が台頭するようになると、これに従うようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi HASHIBA, as Hideyoshi became powerful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Hideyoshi HASHIBA, as Hideyoshi became powerful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi HASHIBA, as Hideyoshi became powerful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>天正11年（1583年）の賤ヶ岳の戦いでは、秀吉に与して柴田勝家に与した不破氏の西保城を攻めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583, he followed Hideyoshi to attack Nishiho-jo Castle of Fuwa clan who followed Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583, he followed Hideyoshi to attack Nishiho-jo Castle of the Fuwa clan who followed Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Shizugatake in 1583, he followed Hideyoshi to attack Nishiho-jo Castle of the Fuwa clan who followed Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>天正12年（1584年）の小牧・長久手の戦いにも参加し、武功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took part in Battle of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584 and showed distinguished service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took part in the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584 and showed distinguished service.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took part in the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584 and showed distinguished service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>天正13年（1585年）に秀吉が関白になると、従三位・法印に叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1585, Hideyoshi became Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and he was conferred to Junior Third Court Rank, Hoin (a priest of the highest rank in the highest managerial position).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1585, Hideyoshi became Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and he was given the Junior Third Court Rank, Hoin (a priest of the highest rank in the highest managerial position).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1585, Hideyoshi became Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and he was given the Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank), Hoin (a priest of the highest rank in the highest managerial position).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一しました。Junior Third Court Rank → Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>天正16年（1588年）11月19日、美濃清水城にて死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on November 19, 1588 at Shimizu-jo Castle in Mono.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on November 19, 1588 at Shimizu-jo Castle in Mono.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on January 5, 1589 at Shimizu-jo Castle in Mono.</e>
<cmt>旧暦日付 → 西暦日付</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>享年74。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at age of 74.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>後を子の貞通が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son Sadamichi succeeded reigns of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son Sadamichi succeeded the reigns of the family.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son Sadamichi succeeded the reigns of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personality/Anecdote</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personality/Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personality/Anecdote</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>姉川の戦いのとき、織田信長は徳川家康に「我が手の者なら連れて行きなされ」と気前よく言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Battle of Anegawa, Nobunaga ODA generously said to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA &apos;if he is on my side, take him with you&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Anegawa, Nobunaga ODA generously said to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA &apos;if he is on my side, take him with you&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Anegawa, Nobunaga ODA generously said to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA &apos;you can take anyone from my retainers.&apos;</e>
<cmt>自分の部下から自由に選抜してよいという意味だと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>そこで家康は「稲葉一鉄殿を」と迷いもなく信長に進言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu proposed &apos;then I would take Lord Ittetsu INABA&apos; without hesitation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu proposed &apos;then I would take Lord Ittetsu INABA&apos; without hesitation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu proposed &apos;then I would take Lord Ittetsu INABA&apos; without hesitation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>あるとき、一鉄のことを信長に讒言する者があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once, there was a person who gave a slanderous account on Ittetsu to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once, there was a person who gave a slanderous account on Ittetsu to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once, there was a person who gave a slanderous account on Ittetsu to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>これを信じた信長は一鉄を殺そうとして茶会に招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga believed this and invited Ittetsu to tea gethering to kill Ittetsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga believed this and invited Ittetsu to a tea gathering to kill Ittetsu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga believed this and invited Ittetsu to a tea gathering to kill Ittetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし、床にかけられた禅僧の虚堂智愚の墨蹟を読みながら自己の無実を述べたので、信長は一鉄の無罪を信じたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Ittetsu spoke his innocence while reading bokuseki by a Zen priest Kido Chigu therefore Nobunaga believed Ittetsu being not guilty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ittetsu spoke his innocence while reading bokuseki by a Zen priest Kido Chigu and therefore Nobunaga believed that Ittetsu was not guilty.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ittetsu spoke his innocence while reading bokuseki (wrinting) on the wall by a Zen priest Kido Chigu and therefore Nobunaga believed that Ittetsu was not guilty.</e>
<cmt>(wrinting) on the wall を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これは一鉄が武勇だけでなく、文才にも優れていたことを示すものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tells that Ittetsu excelled at literary, not only the military prowess.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shows that Ittetsu excelled in literary talent, and not only military prowess.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shows that Ittetsu excelled in literary talent, and not only military prowess.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>頑固な一面があり、そのことから号の「一鉄」にかけられて、頑固一徹の言葉が生まれたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An aspect to his character was stubborn therefore a word Ganko Ittetsu (writes: 頑固一徹 and means adamant) was said to born from his name &apos;Ittetsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An aspect to his character was being stubborn, therefore the word Ganko Ittetsu (written: 頑固一徹 and meaning adamant) was said to be born from his name &apos;Ittetsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An aspect to his character was being stubborn, therefore the word Ganko Ittetsu (written: 頑固一徹 and meaning adamant) was said to be born from his name &apos;Ittetsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>斎藤利三（春日局（ふく）の父）の旧主であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a former lord of Toshimitsu SAITO (father of Kasuga no Tsubone (Fuku)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a former lord of Toshimitsu SAITO (father of Kasuga no Tsubone (Fuku)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a former lord of Toshimitsu SAITO (father of Kasuga no Tsubone [Fuku]).</e>
<cmt>カッコを整理しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>利三が明智光秀に仕えた際は信長を通じて抗議したが、利三を高く評価していた光秀には容れられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He protested through Nobunaga about Toshimitsu serving Mitsuhide AKECHI, but Mitsuhide did not accept it, as Mitsuhide highly rated Toshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He protested through Nobunaga about Toshimitsu serving Mitsuhide AKECHI, but Mitsuhide did not accept it, as Mitsuhide highly regarded Toshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He protested through Nobunaga about Toshimitsu serving Mitsuhide AKECHI, but Mitsuhide did not accept it, as Mitsuhide highly regarded Toshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nobunobunaga(id:117457), ドルチェット(id:46458), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kotoito(id:21045), Kamakura(id:472), 蚯蚓(id:254651), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), ブレイズマン(id:183852), BAKU(id:55205), FOZ(id:44646), Carkuni(id:79281), Douggers(id:56812), A-Taul(id:41790), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 満月(id:82772), ASAMA501(id:91947), KASAGI(id:24405), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>