<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本多忠勝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakatsu HONDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakatsu HONDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakatsu HONDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本多 忠勝（ほんだ ただかつ）は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代前期にかけての武将・大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakatsu HONDA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) who lived from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakatsu HONDA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) who lived from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakatsu HONDA was a busho (Japanese military commander) and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) who lived from the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>徳川氏の家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A vassal of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a vassal of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;He was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a vassal of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>上総大多喜藩初代藩主、伊勢桑名藩初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first lord of the Otaki Domain, Kazusa Province, and the first lord of the Kuwana Domain, Ise Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first lord of the Otaki Domain in Kazusa Province and the first lord of the Kuwana Domain in Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;He was&quot;; changed comma after &quot;Domain&quot; to &quot;in&quot; for both cases;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first lord of the Otaki Domain in Kazusa Province and the first lord of the Kuwana Domain in Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>忠勝系本多家宗家初代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first head of the Honda family of Tadakatsu lineage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first head of the Honda family of Tadakatsu lineage.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;He was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first head of the Honda family of Tadakatsu lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>安祥松平家（徳川本家）の最古参の安祥譜代の本多氏で、本多忠高の長男として天文17年（1548年）、三河国蔵前（現在の愛知県岡崎市）で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a Honda clan member as the oldest Anjo fudai (a fudai daimyo who had been serving Ieyasu since he was in Anjo) for the Anjo-Matsudaira family (the head family of the Tokugawas), born the first son of Tadataka HONDA in Kuramae, Mikawa Province (present Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) in 1548</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakatsu was a Honda clan member as the oldest Anjo fudai (a fudai daimyo who had been serving Ieyasu since he was in Anjo) for the Anjo-Matsudaira family (the head family of the Tokugawas), born the first son of Tadataka HONDA in Kuramae, Mikawa Province (present Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) in 1548.</e>
<cmt>He &gt; Tadakatsu;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakatsu was a Honda clan member as the oldest Anjo fudai (a fudai daimyo who had been serving Ieyasu since he was in Anjo) for the Anjo-Matsudaira family (the head family of the Tokugawa), born the first son of Tadataka HONDA in Kuramae, Mikawa Province (present Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) in 1548.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawas→Tokugawa と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幼い頃から徳川家康に仕え、永禄3年（1560年）の桶狭間の戦いの前哨戦である大高城兵糧入れで初陣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served for Ieyasu TOKUGAWA from an early age, and fought for the first time at the Otaka-jo Hyoro-ire (bringing of army provisions into Otaka-jo Castle), as a preliminary skirmish of the Battle of Okehazama in 1560.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served for Ieyasu TOKUGAWA from a young age, and fought for the first time at the Otaka-jo Hyoro-ire (bringing of army provisions into Otaka-jo Castle), as a preliminary skirmish of the Battle of Okehazama in 1560.</e>
<cmt>an early &gt; a young;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served for Ieyasu TOKUGAWA from a young age, and fought for the first time at the Otaka-jo Hyoro-ire (bringing of army provisions into Otaka-jo Castle), as a preliminary skirmish of the Battle of Okehazama in 1560.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このとき、同時に元服した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He celebrated his attainment of manhood at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He celebrated his attainment of manhood at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He celebrated his attainment of manhood at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>永禄6年（1563年）の三河一向一揆では、多くの本多一族が敵となる中で、家康に忠義を尽くして武功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Mikawa Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Mikawa Province) in 1563, he achieved military exploits, devoted to Ieyasu, while having most of the Honda families as enemies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Mikawa Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Mikawa Province) in 1563, he achieved military exploits devoting himself to Ieyasu as an enemy to most of the Honda families.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Mikawa Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko sect followers in Mikawa Province) in 1563, he achieved military exploits devoting himself to Ieyasu as an enemy to most of the Honda families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>永禄9年（1566年）には19歳にして同年齢の榊原康政や本多正重、都築秀綱らとともに旗本先手役に抜擢されて、与力50騎を付属される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1566 at the age of 19, he was selected as Hatamoto sakiteyaku (a direct retainer of the shogun, who led the way) along with men of his age, Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA, Masashige HONDA and Hidetsuna TSUZUKI, and given 50 Yoriki (police sergeants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1566 at the age of nineteen, he was selected as a Hatamoto sakiteyaku (a direct retainer of the shogun, who led the way) along with other men of his age, such as Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA, Masashige HONDA and Hidetsuna TSUZUKI, and he was given fifty Yoriki (police sergeants).</e>
<cmt>19 &gt; nineteen; 50 &gt; fifty; along with men of his age, &gt; along with other men of his age such as;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1566 at the age of 19, he was selected as a Hatamoto sakiteyaku (a direct retainer of the shogun, who led the way) along with other men of his age, such as Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA, Masashige HONDA and Hidetsuna TSUZUKI, and he was given 50 Yoriki (police sergeants).</e>
<cmt>nineteen→19,fifty→50 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>以後、忠勝は常に家康の居城の城下に住み、旗本部隊の将として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Tadakatsu always lived near the castle of Ieyasu, and performed well as a commander of the hatamoto troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, Tadakatsu always lived near Ieyasu&apos;s castle and performed well as a commander of the hatamoto troop.</e>
<cmt>After that &gt; Afterwards; eliminated comma after &quot;Ieyasu&quot;; castle of Ieyasu &gt; Ieyasu&apos;s castle;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, Tadakatsu always lived near Ieyasu&apos;s living castle and performed well as a commander of the hatamoto troop.</e>
<cmt>castle→living castle と修正しました。（居城）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>元亀元年（1570年）の姉川の戦いにも参加し、元亀3年（1572年）の二俣城の戦いの前哨戦たる一言坂の戦いで殿軍を努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also joined the Battle of Anegawa in 1570, and he took charge of the Dengun (the rear troop) at the Battle of Hitokotozaka as a preliminary skirmish of the Battle of Futamata-jo Castle in 1572.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakatsu also participated in the Battle of Anegawa in 1570 and took charge of the Dengun (the rear troop) at the Battle of Hitokotozaka as a preliminary skirmish of the Battle of Futamata-jo Castle in 1572.</e>
<cmt>He &gt; Tadakatsu; joined &gt; participated; added &quot;in&quot; after &quot;participated&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakatsu also participated in the Battle of Anegawa in 1570 and took charge of the Dengun (the rear troop) at the Battle of Hitokotozaka as a preliminary skirmish of the Battle of Futamata-jo Castle in 1572.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>武田氏方の小杉左近から「家康に過ぎたるものは二つあり、唐のかしらに本多平八」との狂歌の落書をもって賞賛されたことが有名である（「唐のかしら」は家康が趣味で集めていたヤクの尾毛を飾りに使った兜を指す）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is famous that Sakon KOSUGI from the Takeda clan praised him by means of rakusho (anonymous letter) of kyoka (comic and satirical poem) saying &apos;Ieyasu has two wonderful things; Kara no kashira (the Chinese heads) and Heihachi HONDA&apos; (&apos;Kara no kashira&apos; refers to helmets with tail hair of Yak which Ieyasu gathered for enjoyment).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a famous story about Sakon KOSUGI from the Takeda clan praising Tadakatsu with a rakusho (anonymous letter) of kyoka (comic and satirical poem) where he said &apos;Ieyasu has two wonderful things: Kara no kashira (the Chinese heads) and Heihachi HONDA&apos; (&apos;Kara no kashira&apos; refers to helmets with tail hair of Yak which Ieyasu gathered for enjoyment).</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a famous story about Sakon KOSUGI from the Takeda clan praising Tadakatsu with a rakusho (anonymous letter) of kyoka (comic and satirical poem) where he said &apos;Ieyasu has two things too good for him: Kara no kashira (the Chinese heads) and Heihachi HONDA&apos; (&apos;Kara no kashira&apos; refers to helmets with tail hair of Yak which Ieyasu gathered for enjoyment.)</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を修正しました。two wonderful thins→two things too good for him と修正しました。（「過ぎたる有り余るほどに優れている」ということから）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>12月の三方ヶ原の戦いにも参戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also joined the Battle of the Mikatagahara in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakatsu fought in the Battle of Mikatagahara in December.</e>
<cmt>He &gt; Tadakatsu; joined &gt; fought in; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Mikatagahara&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakatsu fought in the Battle of Mikatagahara in December (old calender).</e>
<cmt>12月を変換すると年をまたいでしまうため、(old calender)と補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天正3年（1575年）の長篠の戦いにも参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He joined the Battle of the Nagashino in 1575 as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also participated in the Battle of Nagashino in 1575.</e>
<cmt>joined &gt; participated; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Nagashino&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also participated in the Battle of Nagashino in 1575.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>天正10年（1582年）、本能寺の変が起きたとき、家康は忠勝ら少数の随行とともに堺市に滞在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, when the Honnoji Incident occurred, Ieyasu stayed in Sakai city with a few followers including Tadakatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Honnoji Incident occurred in 1582, Ieyasu stayed in Sakai city with a few of his followers, including Tadakatsu.</e>
<cmt>moved year to the middle of the sentence; added &quot;of his&quot; after &quot;a few&quot;; added comma after &quot;followers&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Honnoji Incident occurred in 1582, Ieyasu was staying in Sakai City with a few of his followers, including Tadakatsu.</e>
<cmt>stayed→was staying,city→City と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>家康が京都に行って信長の後を追おうと取り乱したのを忠勝が諌めて、｢本能寺の変徳川家康｣を行わせたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu became upset and tried to go to Kyoto to follow Nobunaga, but Tadakatsu gave advice to do &apos;Iga goe&apos; (Going over Iga).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理「本能寺の変徳川家康」はリンク先の単語で、サイト原文では「伊賀越え」となっていますので、それを訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ieyasu got upset and tried to go to Kyoto to follow Nobunaga, it is said that Tadakatsu was the one who warned, &quot;Our enemies are in Honnoji, TOKUGAWA Ieyasu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>changed translation for ｢本能寺の変徳川家康｣; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ieyasu lost his calm and tried to go to Kyoto to follow Nobunaga, it is said that Tadakatsu was the one who warned, &quot;Our enemies are in Honnoji, TOKUGAWA Ieyasu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>got upset→lost his calm と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="17">
<j>鹿角脇立兜（現存しており重要文化財）がシンボルで、天正12年（1584年）の小牧・長久手の戦いでの活躍などにより、豊臣秀吉からも東国一の勇士と賞賛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His symbol was Kazuno wakidate kabuto (helmet with an ornament in the shape of deer horns) (It still exists as an Important Cultural Property), and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI praised him as the best warrior in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) for his performance at the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakatsu&apos;s symbol was a Kazuno wakidate kabuto (a helmet with an ornament in the shape of deer horns) (It still exists as an Important Cultural Property), and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI praised him as the best warrior in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) for his performance at the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584.</e>
<cmt>His &gt; Tadakatsu&apos;s; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;Kazuno&quot;; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;helmet&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakatsu&apos;s symbol was a Kazuno wakidate kabuto (a helmet with an ornament in the shape of deer horns) (It still exists as an Important Cultural Property), and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI praised him as the best warrior in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) for his performance at the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute in 1584.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>徳川氏が豊臣氏の傘下に入ると従五位下・中務省に叙位・任官された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Tokugawa clan was affiliated with the Toyotomi clan, he was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed to work at the Ministry of Central Affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Tokugawa clan was affiliated with the Toyotomi clan, he was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed to work at the Ministry of Central Affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Tokugawa clan was affiliated with the Toyotomi clan, he was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and appointed to work at the Ministry of Central Affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>天正18年（1590年）、家康が関東地方に移封されると上総国大多喜（千葉県夷隅郡大多喜町）に榊原康政と共に、家臣団中第2位の10万石（1位は井伊直政の11万石）を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1590, when Ieyasu was transferred to the Kanto region, he was given 100 thousand koku, the second biggest crop yields among the vassals (Naomasa II got the biggest) along with Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA from Otaki, Kazusa Province (Otaki Town, Isumi County, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ieyasu was transferred to the Kanto region in 1590, Tadakatsu was given one hundred thousand koku, the second biggest crop yield among the vassals (Naomasa II had the biggest), along with Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA from Otaki, Kazusa Province (Otaki Town, Isumi County, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>moved year to the middle of the sentence; he &gt; Tadakatsu; 100 &gt; one hundred; added comma after &quot;biggest)&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ieyasu was transferred to the Kanto region in 1590, Tadakatsu was given 100,000 koku, the second biggest crop yield among the vassals (Naomasa II had the biggest as 110,000 koku), along with Yasumasa SAKAKIBARA from Otaki, Kazusa Province (Otaki Town, Isumi County, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>one hundred thousand→100.000 と修正しました。「11万石」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>江戸から遠くなっているのは、「譜代の将は敵が攻めてくる国境に配置する」との、家康の配置方針による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The location far from Edo was based on Ieyasu&apos;s deployment policy to &apos;deploy fudai no sho (military commander in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) on the border where the enemies make an attack.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That they were sent so far from Edo was due to Ieyasu&apos;s deployment policy to &apos;deploy fudai no sho (military commanders that were hereditary vassals to the Tokugawa family) on the border where enemies would make their attack.&apos;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That they were sent so far from Edo was due to Ieyasu&apos;s deployment policy to &apos;deploy fudai no sho (military commanders that were hereditary vassals to the Tokugawa family) on the border where enemies would make their attack.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>康政は北の真田や上杉に対する備え、忠勝は安房国の里見氏に対する備えである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasumasa was supposed to be against Sanada and Uesugi in the North, Tadakatsu against the Satomi clan in Awa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasumasa was to defend against Sanada and Uesugi to the north and Tadakatsu was to defend against the Satomi clan in the Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>was supposed to be against &gt; was to defend against; eliminated comma after &quot;North&quot;; Tadakatsu against the Satomi &gt; Tadakatsu was to defend against the Satomi; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Awa&quot;; made &quot;north&quot; lowercase;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasumasa was to defend against Sanada and Uesugi to the north and Tadakatsu was to defend against the Satomi clan in the Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）の関ヶ原の戦いでは家康本軍に従軍し、諸大名に書状を送って東軍方につける工作にも活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he belonged to the main troop of Ieyasu, and also engaged in the operation to send letters to territorial lords to have them take sides with the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, Tadakatsu was part of Ieyasu&apos;s main troop and engaged in an operation to send letters to territorial lords to have them take sides with the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt>he &gt; Tadakatsu; belonged to the main troop &gt; was in the main troop; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, Tadakatsu was part of Ieyasu&apos;s main troop and engaged in an operation to send letters to territorial lords to have them take sides with the Eastern Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この功績により、慶長6年（1601年）、伊勢国桑名藩（現在の三重県桑名市）10万石（一説に15万石）に移されると、それまでの大多喜領は次男・本多忠朝に別家5万石で与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this achievement, he was transferred to Kuwana Domain, Ise Province (present Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture) with 100 thousand koku (another theory holds 150 thousand koku), the former territory in Otaki was given to his second son Tadatomo HONDA with 50 thousand koku as a branch family.</e>
<cmt>原文と言葉の順序がずれているのを修正の上、下のセルと結合</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to his achievements, he was transferred to Kuwana Domain, Ise Province (present Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture) with one hundred thousand koku (another theory holds that it was one hundred fifty thousand koku), and the former territory in Otaki was given to his second son Tadatomo HONDA with fifty thousand koku as a branch family.</e>
<cmt>this &gt; his; 100 &gt; one hundred; 150 &gt; one hundred fifty; 50 &gt; fifty; fixed grammar;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to his achievements, he was transferred to Kuwana Domain, Ise Province (present Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture) with 100,000 koku (another theory holds that it was 150,000 koku) in 1601, and the former territory in Otaki was given to his second son Tadatomo HONDA with 50,000 koku as a branch family.</e>
<cmt>「1601年」を補いました。one hundred thousand→100,000,one hundred fifty thousand→150,000,fifty thousand→50,000 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>晩年は、戦乱の収束により本多正純などの若く文治に優れた者（吏僚派）が家康・徳川秀忠の側近として台頭してきたため、忠勝のような武功派は次第に江戸幕府の中枢から遠ざけられ、不遇であったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since young people who were good at civil administration (civilian party) such as Masazumi HONDA gained power as close advisors of Ieyasu and Hidetada TOKUGAWA due to the end of the wars, military exploit party members such as Tadakatsu were distanced from the center of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), so it is said that he was unhappy in his later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the end of the wars and those from the younger generation who were good at civil administration (civilian party), such as Masazumi HONDA, gaining power as close advisors to Ieyasu and Hidetada TOKUGAWA, military exploit party members such as Tadakatsu were distanced from the center of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and it is said that he was unhappy in his later years.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the end of the wars and those from the younger generation who were good at civil administration (civilian party), such as Masazumi HONDA, gaining power as close advisors to Ieyasu and Hidetada TOKUGAWA, military exploit party members such as Tadakatsu were distanced from the center of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and it is said that he was unhappy in his later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>慶長14年（1609年）6月、嫡男・本多忠政に家督を譲って隠居する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, 1609, he retired after transferring the responsibility for the family to his legitimate son Tadamasa HONDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, 1609, Tadakatsu retired after transferring responsibility for his family to his legitimate son Tadamasa HONDA.</e>
<cmt>he &gt; Tadakatsu; eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;responsibility&quot;; the &gt; his;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, 1609, Tadakatsu retired after transferring the family headship to his legitimate son Tadamasa HONDA.</e>
<cmt>responsibility for his family→the family headship と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>慶長15年（1610年）10月18日に桑名で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in Kuwana on December 3, 1610.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in Kuwana on December 3, 1610.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in Kuwana on December 3, 1610.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>享年63。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 63.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was sixty three years old.</e>
<cmt>63 &gt; sixty three; fixed to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 63 years old.</e>
<cmt>sixty three→63 と修正しました。（用語統一、「その他：31項」に従い）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>忠勝の子孫は、その後転封を繰り返して、姫路藩などを経由し、三河国岡崎藩5万石に落ち着いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of Tadakatsu repeatedly changed their territory, and settled in Okazaki Domain, Mikawa Province with 50 thousand koku via Himeji and other domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants of Tadakatsu repeatedly changed their territory, settling in Okazaki Domain, Mikawa Province with fifty thousand koku via Himeji and other domains.</e>
<cmt>50 &gt; fifty; eliminated &quot;and&quot; before &quot;settled&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendants of Tadakatsu repeatedly changed their territory, settling in Okazaki Domain, Mikawa Province with 50,000 koku via Himeji and other domains.</e>
<cmt>fifty thousand→50,000 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし忠勝の死後、その息子である本多忠政・本多忠朝を除いて、本多氏は幕府から重用されることは、ほとんど無かったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Tadakatsu, however, it is said that the Honda clan was hardly given important posts by the bakufu except his sons Tadamasa HONDA and Tadatomo HONDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Tadakatsu, however, it is said that the Honda clan was rarely given important posts by the bakufu except for his sons Tadamasa HONDA and Tadatomo HONDA.</e>
<cmt>hardly &gt; rarely; added &quot;for&quot; before &quot;his sons&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Tadakatsu, however, it is said that the Honda clan was rarely given important posts by the bakufu except for his sons Tadamasa HONDA and Tadatomo HONDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>但しこれは、歴代の本多家藩主が夭折・不行跡を繰り返したためとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it is also believed that this is because the successive lords of the Honda family repeatedly died young or misconducted themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is also believed that this was due to successive lords of the Honda family repeatedly dying young or misconducting themselves.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is also believed that this was due to successive lords of the Honda family repeatedly dying young or misconducting themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>武勇の家系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family line of heroes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family line of heroes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family line of heroes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>忠勝の叔父は徳川家中では武勇もって有名な植村氏明であり、また同じく叔父に槍の名手の本多忠真を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of Tadakatsu&apos;s uncles was Ujiaki UEMURA who was famous for his heroic acts amoung the Tokugawa vassals, and another uncle was Tadazane HONDA who was a master of spears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of Tadakatsu&apos;s uncles was Ujiaki UEMURA, famous for his heroic acts among the Tokugawa vassals, and another of his uncles was Tadazane HONDA, a master of spears.</e>
<cmt>who was &gt;,; amoung &gt; among; another uncle &gt; another of his uncles;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of Tadakatsu&apos;s uncles was Ujiaki UEMURA, famous for his heroic acts among the Tokugawa vassals, and another of his uncles was Tadazane HONDA, a master of spears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>家臣・家老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vassals and Chief retainers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vassals and Chief retainers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vassals and Chief retainers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>織田信照（中根平右衛門忠実）、織田信長の庶弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuteru ODA (Heiemon Tadazane NAKANE) was a half brother of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuteru ODA (Heiemon Tadazane NAKANE) was a half brother of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuteru ODA (Heiemon Tadazane NAKANE) was a half brother of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>家康の関東移封後、1591年頃から上総国大多喜10万石城主・大名となった本多忠勝に、付け家老として配される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Ieyasu moved to the Kanto region, he was assigned to serve as Tsukegaro (chief retainer assigned directly by the shogun) for Tadakatsu HONDA, who became a daimyo and the lord of Otaki, Kazusa Province with 100 thousand koku, around 1591.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Ieyasu moved to the Kanto region, Nobuteru was assigned to serve as Tsukegaro (a chief retainer assigned directly by the shogun) for Tadakatsu HONDA, who became a daimyo and the lord of Otaki, Kazusa Province with one hundred thousand koku around 1591.</e>
<cmt>he &gt; Nobuteru; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;chief&quot;; 100 &gt; one hundred; eliminated comma after &quot;koku&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Ieyasu moved to the Kanto region, Nobuteru was assigned to serve as Tsukegaro (a chief retainer assigned directly by the shogun) for Tadakatsu HONDA, who became a daimyo and the lord of Otaki, Kazusa Province with 100.000 koku around 1591.</e>
<cmt>one hundred thousand→100.000 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>子孫らは本多家の家老として職責を全うしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendants fulfilled their duties as chief retainers for the Honda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants fulfilled their duties as chief retainers for the Honda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants fulfilled their duties as chief retainers for the Honda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>都築秀綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsuna TSUZUKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsuna TSUZUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsuna TSUZUKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>本多家の筆頭家老として代々続く筑紫氏の初代にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first head of the Tsukushi clan, as the Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) for the Honda family for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsuna was the first head of the Tsukushi clan as the Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) for the Honda family for generations.</e>
<cmt>He &gt; Hidetsuna; eliminated comma after &quot;clan&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsuna was the first head of the Tsukushi clan as the Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) for the Honda family for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>本来今川家の家臣であったが、1568年末から開始される徳川家康の遠州侵攻で臣従。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though he was originally a vassal of the Imagawa family, he gained the position due to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s invasion of Enshu from the end of 1568.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he was originally a vassal of the Imagawa family, he gained the position due to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s invasion of Enshu at the end of 1568.</e>
<cmt>from &gt; at;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was originally a vassal of the Imagawa family, he gained the position due to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s invasion of Enshu started at the end of 1568.</e>
<cmt>Tough→Although と修正しました。started を補いました。（開始される）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>翌1569年には本領安堵を約す書状が家康から与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given a letter to assure honryo-ando (acknowledgment for inherited estate) by Ieyasu in 1569, the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year he was given a letter to assure honryo-ando (acknowledgment for an inherited estate) by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;the following year&quot; to the beginning of the sentence; eliminated &quot;1569&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year of 1569, he was given a letter to assure honryo-ando (acknowledgment for an inherited estate) by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>原文に忠実に、「1569年」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>忠勝の与力に加えられると、各地で勇戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fought valiantly when he joined Tadakatsu&apos;s yoriki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought valiantly when he joined Tadakatsu&apos;s yoriki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought valiantly when he joined Tadakatsu&apos;s yoriki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="40">
<j>梶勝忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsutada KAJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsutada KAJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsutada KAJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>都築氏と共に家老として代々、本多家を支えてきた梶氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kaji clan supported the Honda family as a chief retainer for generations along with the Tsuzuki clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the Tsuzuki clan, the Kaji clan supported the Honda family as chief retainers for generations.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;a&quot; before &quot;chief&quot;; retainer &gt; retainers; moved &quot;along with the Tsuzuki clan&quot; to the beginning of the sentence;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the Tsuzuki clan, the Kaji clan supported the Honda family as chief retainers for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="42">
<j>その祖は松平家一族である能見松平家光親の次男・親友とされ、勝忠はその親友の曾孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its founder was supposed to be Chikatomo, the second son of Mitsuchika of the Nomi Matsudaira family as one of the Matsudaira families, and Katsutada was a great grandson of Chikatomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsutada was a great grandson of Chikatomo, the founder of the Kaji clan and second son of Mitsuchika of the Nomi Matsudaira family as one of the Matsudaira families.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsutada was a great grandson of Chikatomo, the second son of Mitsuchika of the Nomi Matsudaira family as one of the Matsudaira families.</e>
<cmt>founder of the Kaji clan を削除しました。（その記述は無いため）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="43">
<j>元々家康の使い番として仕えていたが、1566年、忠勝が旗本先手役に任命されると同時に与力として本多隊に組み込まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He originally served as tsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) for Ieyasu, and in 1566, he was integrated into the Honda troop as a yoriki at the same time Tadakatsu was appointed as Hatamoto sakiteyaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He originally served as tsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol on the battlefield) for Ieyasu, and in 1566 was integrated into the Honda troop as a yoriki at the same time Tadakatsu was appointed as Hatamoto sakiteyaku.</e>
<cmt>in the battlefield &gt; on the battlefield; eliminated &quot;, he was&quot; after &quot;1566&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He originally served as tsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol on the battlefield) for Ieyasu, and in 1566 was integrated into the Honda troop as a yoriki at the same time Tadakatsu was appointed as Hatamoto sakiteyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="44">
<j>以降、忠勝隊の中心として多くの合戦に従軍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he took part in lots of battles as a key figure of the Tadakatsu troop.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took part in many battles from that point on as a key figure of the Tadakatsu troop.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took part in many battles from that point on as a key figure of the Tadakatsu troop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="45">
<j>1600年の関ケ原合戦に於いては、敵兵の放った矢によって愛馬・三国黒を失いながらも徒立ちで奮戦する忠勝に自分の馬を差し出し、忠勝の窮地を救ったという逸話が今に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remains an anecdote that, at the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he offered his horse to Tadakatsu, having lost his favorite horse Mikuniguro by the arrow discharged from an enemy soldier and still fought hard on foot, which saved Tadakatsu from the predicament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There remains an anecdote about Katsutada at the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600 where he offered his horse to Tadakatsu, who had lost his favorite horse Mikuniguro to an arrow shot by an enemy soldier, then continued to fight hard on foot, saving Tadakatsu from a tight situation.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There remains an anecdote about Katsutada at the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600 where he offered his horse to Tadakatsu, who had lost his favorite horse Mikuniguro to an arrow shot by an enemy soldier, then continued to fight hard on foot, saving Tadakatsu from a tight situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="46">
<j>また、関ケ原合戦後の1601年、忠勝の桑名移封の際には先発隊として桑名城に入城している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in 1601 after the Battle of Sekigahara, he entered the Kuwana-jo Castle as an advance party when Tadakatsu changed the territory to Kuwana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battle of Sekigahara, Katsutada entered the Kuwana-jo Castle as an advance party in 1601 when Tadakatsu changed the territory to Kuwana.</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;1601&quot; to the middle of the sentence; he &gt; Katsutada; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, Katsutada entered the Kuwana-jo Castle as an advance party in 1601 when Tadakatsu changed the territory to Kuwana.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="47">
<j>河合政光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamitsu KAWAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamitsu KAWAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamitsu KAWAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="48">
<j>旗本先手役に抜擢された忠勝の与力50騎の1人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of the 50 yoriki of Tadakatsu, who was selected as Hatamoto sakiteyaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamitsu was one of Tadakatsu&apos;s fifty yoriki, selected as a Hatamoto sakiteyaku.</e>
<cmt>He &gt; Masamitsu; 50 &gt; fifty; fifty yoriki of Tadakatsu &gt; Tadakatsu&apos;s fifty yoriki; eliminated &quot;who was&quot;; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;Hatamoto&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamitsu was one of Tadakatsu&apos;s 50 yoriki, selected as a Hatamoto sakiteyaku.</e>
<cmt>fifty→50 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>忠勝が大名になるとそのまま家老として支えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tadakatsu became a daimyo, he remained to serve him as a chief retainer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tadakatsu became a daimyo, he stayed to serve him as a chief retainer.</e>
<cmt>remained &gt; stayed;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tadakatsu became a daimyo, he stayed to serve him as a chief retainer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>知行5000石（内、与力給2500石を含む）を公儀だけから拝領。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received 5000 koku as chigyo (enfeoffment) only from the kogi (shogunate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only from the kogi (shogunate) did he receive five thousand koku as a chigyo (fief).</e>
<cmt>5000 &gt; five thousand; enfeoffment &gt; fief; added &quot;a&quot; before &quot;chigyo&quot;; rearranged sentence to read more smoothly;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only from the kogi (shogunate) did he receive 5,000 koku (including the reward for yoriki, 2,500 koku) as a chigyo (fief).</e>
<cmt>five thousand→5,000 と修正しました。「（内、与力給2500石を含む）」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>実弟・政一が又五郎の通称と家督を継いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His own younger brother Masakazu succeeded his common name Matagoro and the family estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His own younger brother Masakazu succeeded his common name Matagoro and the family estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His own younger brother Masakazu succeeded his common name Matagoro and the family estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>人物・逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His personality and anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes about Tadakatsu and his personality</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal profile and anecdotes</e>
<cmt>”用語統一”を参照、修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>徳川四天王・徳川十六神将・徳川三傑に数えられ、家康の功臣として現在も顕彰されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was counted amoung Tokugawa shitenno (four great generals serving for Tokugawa), Tokugawa juroku shinsho (16 great protective deities for Tokugawa) and Tokugawa sanketsu (best three vassals of Tokugawea), and he is still honored as a meritorious vassal of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was counted among the Tokugawa shitenno (the four great generals serving Tokugawa), Tokugawa juroku shinsho (sixteen great protective deities for Tokugawa) and Tokugawa sanketsu (the top three vassals of Tokugawa), and he is still honored as a meritorious vassal of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>amoung &gt; among; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Tokugawa shitenno&quot;; 16 :&gt; sixteen; added &quot;the&quot; before &quot;four&quot;; eliminated &quot;for&quot; before &quot;Tokugawa&quot;; Tokugawea &gt; Tokugawa; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was counted among the Tokugawa shitenno (the 4 great generals serving Tokugawa), Tokugawa juroku shinsho (the 16 great protective deities for Tokugawa) and Tokugawa sanketsu (the top 3 vassals of Tokugawa), and he is still honored as a meritorious vassal of Ieyasu today.</e>
<cmt>four→4,sixteen→16,three→3 と修正しました。（用語統一、「その他：31項」に従い）と修正しました。the, today を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>生涯において参加した合戦は五十七回に及んだが、いずれの戦いにおいてもかすり傷一つ負わなかったと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he took part in 57 battles in his life, it is said that he survived without a scratch in each battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he took part in fifty seven battles throughout his life, it is said that he survived every battle without a scratch.</e>
<cmt>57 &gt; fifty seven; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he took part in 57 battles throughout his life, it is said that he survived every battle without a scratch.</e>
<cmt>fifty seven→57 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>動きやすい軽装を好んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He preferred an light-duty outfit easy to move.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He preferred light equipment that let him move easily.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He preferred light equipment that let him move easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>忠勝は、自分とは対照的に重武装であり、全身に傷だらけの井伊直政を批判している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakatsu criticized Naomasa II, who was heavily-armed and covered all over with wounds in contrast with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakatsu contrasted himself with Naomasa II, criticizing his heavy armor and how he was covered with wounds.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakatsu contrasted himself with Naomasa II, criticizing his heavy armor and how he was covered with wounds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>小牧・長久手の戦いでは、わずか500名の軍勢を率いて秀吉自ら率いる8万の大軍と対峙し、秀吉の家臣、加藤清正・福島正則らが忠勝を討ち取るべしと進言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute, he led only 500 soldiers to confront the large force of 80 thousand which Hideyoshi himself led, when Kiyomasa KATO and Masanori FUKUSHIMA, vassals of Hideyoshi, advised to kill Tadakatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute when Tadakatsu led a mere five hundred soldiers to confront a force of eighty thousand led by Hideyoshi, vassals Kiyomasa KATO and Masanori FUKUSHIMA advised killing Tadakatsu.</e>
<cmt>he &gt; Tadakatsu; 500 five hundred; only &gt; mere; 80 &gt; eighty; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute when Tadakatsu led a mere 500 soldiers to confront a force of 80,000 led by Hideyoshi, vassals Kiyomasa KATO and Masanori FUKUSHIMA advised killing Tadakatsu.</e>
<cmt>five hundred→500,eighty thousand→80,000 と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>しかし、忠勝の姉川での勇猛ぶりを聞き知っていた秀吉は目に涙を浮かべ、以下のように言って忠勝を討ち取ることを禁じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Hideyoshi, who heard and knew Tadakatsu&apos;s gallantry at the Ane-gawa River, had tears in his eyes, and forbade to kill Tadakatsu, saying as follows.</e>
<cmt>「」処理、文を分割</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi, however, who had heard about Tadakatsu&apos;s gallantry at the Ane-gawa River, had tears in his eyes when he forbade the killing of Tadakatsu.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;saying as follows&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi, however, who had heard about Tadakatsu&apos;s gallantry at the Ane-gawa River, had tears in his eyes when he forbade the killing of Tadakatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>「わざと寡兵で我が大軍に勇を示すのは、我が軍を暫時喰い止めて家康の軍を遠ざけるためであろう。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;He is showing his bravery to the large force of ours intentionally with the outnumbered troop, probably because he intends to distance the troop of Ieyasu by holding our troop for a while.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi said to his men, &apos;He is purposely showing his bravery by leading an outnumbered troop against our large force, probably with the intention of putting distance between us and Ieyasu&apos;s army by holding our troop for a while.&apos;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi said to his men, &apos;He is purposely showing his bravery by leading an outnumbered troop against our large force, probably with the intention of putting distance between us and Ieyasu&apos;s army by holding our troop for a while.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>「徳川家を滅ぼした際にはかれを生け捕って我が家人にすべきなり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;When we destroy the Tokugawa family, we should take him alive to make him my kenin (retainer).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&apos;When we destroy the Tokugawa family, we should take him alive to make him my kenin (retainer).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&apos;When we destroy the Tokugawa family, we should take him alive to make him my kenin (retainer).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>秀吉・家康が和睦した後に秀吉に召しだされたとき、「秀吉の恩と家康の恩、どちらが貴殿にとっては重いか」と質問されると、「君のご恩は海より深いといえども、家康は譜代相伝の主君であって月日の論には及びがたし」と答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was called by Hideyoshi after Hideyoshi and Ieyasu were reconciled and asked &apos;Which is bigger for you, the gratitude for Hideyoshi or that for Ieyasu?&apos;, he answered &apos;Although the gratitude for you is deeper than the sea, Ieyasu is the lord of hereditary succession and it is difficult to overcome the passage of time.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi and Ieyasu reconciled, Hideyoshi called upon Tadakatsu and asked, &apos;Which is more important to you, the gratitude for Hideyoshi or that for Ieyasu?&apos;, and Tadakatsu answered, &apos;Although the gratitude for you is deeper than the sea, Ieyasu is the lord of hereditary succession and it is difficult to overcome the passage of time.&apos;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi and Ieyasu reconciled, Hideyoshi called upon Tadakatsu and asked, &apos;Which is more important to you, the gratitude for Hideyoshi or that for Ieyasu?&apos; and Tadakatsu answered, &apos;Although the gratitude for you is deeper than the sea, Ieyasu is the lord of hereditary succession and it is difficult to overcome the passage of time.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>織田信長にその並はずれた武勇を「花実兼備の勇士」と讃えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His exceptional heroic acts were praised by Nobunaga ODA as &apos;a hero with both bravery and intelligence.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His exceptional heroic acts were praised by Nobunaga ODA as &apos;a hero with both bravery and intelligence.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His exceptional heroic acts were praised by Nobunaga ODA as &apos;a hero with both bravery and intelligence.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また、豊臣秀吉には「東に本多忠勝という天下無双の大将がいるように、西には立花宗茂という天下無双の大将がいる」と勇将として引き合いに出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI cited him as a brave general, saying &apos;There is a peerless general named Tadakatsu HONDA in the east, and there is another peerless general named Muneshige TACHIBANA in the west.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI cited him as a brave general, saying, &apos;There is a peerless general named Tadakatsu HONDA in the east, and another peerless general named Muneshige TACHIBANA in the west.&apos;</e>
<cmt>added comma after &quot;saying&quot;; eliminated &quot;there is&quot; before &quot;another&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI cited him as a brave general, saying, &apos;There is a peerless general named Tadakatsu HONDA in the east, and another peerless general named Muneshige TACHIBANA in the west.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>愛知県岡崎市の岡崎城内と三重県桑名市の桑名城跡の九華公園内に、忠勝の銅像がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are statues of Tadakatsu inside Okazaki-jo Castle in Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture, and in the Kyuka Park in the remains of Kuwana-jo Castle in Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are statues of Tadakatsu inside Okazaki-jo Castle in Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture, and in Kyuka Park in the remains of Kuwana-jo Castle in Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;Kyuka&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are statues of Tadakatsu inside Okazaki-jo Castle in Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture, and in Kyuka Park in the remains of Kuwana-jo Castle in Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="64">
<j>忠勝は勇猛なだけではなく知略も備えた名将で、関ヶ原の戦いでは井伊直政と共に誓紙を何枚も発行して西軍武将の切り崩しにも務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakatsu was a great commander not only brave but also good at strategies, and he tried to break up the busho of the Western Army by issuing numbers of written oath with Naomasa II at the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakatsu was a great commander, not only brave but also good at strategies, and he tried to break up the busho of the Western Army by issuing countless numbers of written oath with Naomasa II at the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;countless&quot; before &quot;numbers&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakatsu was a great commander, not only brave but also good at strategies, and he tried to break up the busho of the Western Army by issuing countless numbers of written oath with Naomasa II at the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>また、政治家としても力量を発揮し、特に人心掌握に努めて領民の敬愛を集めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also displayed his ability as a politician, and it is said that he especially tried to control the public feeling and he was adored by the people of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also displayed abilities as a politician, and it is said that he tried especially hard to seize the hearts of the public and was adored by the people of the domain.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also displayed abilities as a politician, and it is said that he tried especially hard to seize the hearts of the public and was adored by the people of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="66">
<j>関ヶ原において西軍が敗戦した際、それに与した真田昌幸・真田信繁親子の助命を娘婿の真田信之と共に嘆願した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Western Army lost at Sekigahara, he and Nobuyuki SANADA, his daughter&apos;s husband, begged to save the lives of Masayuki SANADA and his son Nobushige SANADA, who took sides with the Western Army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Western Army lost at Sekigahara, he and Nobuyuki SANADA, his daughter&apos;s husband, begged for the lives of Masayuki SANADA and his son Nobushige SANADA, who had taken sides with the Western Army.</e>
<cmt>begged to save the lives &gt; begged for the lives; who took sides &gt; who had taken sides;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Western Army lost at Sekigahara, he and Nobuyuki SANADA, his daughter&apos;s husband, begged for the lives of Masayuki SANADA and his son Nobushige SANADA, who had taken sides with the Western Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>が、両名に散々煮え湯を飲まされている家康は強硬に拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Ieyasu, who was terribly suffered by these two, rejected consistently.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文原則例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu had suffered terribly due to these two men, however, and firmly refused.</e>
<cmt>But &gt; however; rejected consistenly &gt; firmly refused; fixed grammar;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu had suffered terribly due to these two men, however, and firmly refused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>またそれ以上に昌幸により上田城に釘付けにされた挙句に関ヶ原遅参という失態を演じ、家康のを勘気被った秀忠は強硬に死罪を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Hidetada who was stranded in Ueda-jo Castle by Masayuki and ended up going late to Sekigahara and offended Ieyasu, strongly insisted on the death penalty.</e>
<cmt>対訳および用語集にある「死罪」の「capital crime」とは死罪に値する犯罪を意味する言葉で、通常はdeath penaltyなどを持ちいると思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetada strongly insisted on the death penalty as well since he ended up offending Ieyasu by arriving late to Sekigahara after being stranded in Ueda-jo Castle by Masayuki.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetada strongly insisted on the death penalty as well since he was blamed on ending up offending Ieyasu by arriving late to Sekigahara after being stranded in Ueda-jo Castle by Masayuki.</e>
<cmt>「勘気被った」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>これに対して忠勝は「お聞き入れくだされなければ、それがしが殿と一戦仕る」と啖呵を切り、家康を唖然とさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, Tadakatsu declared defiantly to &apos;give a fight against Ieyasu if he were not to accept it,&apos; which made Ieyasu stunned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakatsu responded by defiantly declaring, &apos;If you do not grant this request then I will fight you,&apos; stunning Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more understandably;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakatsu responded by defiantly declaring, &apos;If you do not grant this request then I will fight you,&apos; stunning Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>結局は忠勝らの嘆願に折れる形で真田親子は紀伊高野山山麓の九度山に蟄居という処分に止まり、信濃国上田藩領は信之に与えられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, as a result of yielding to Tadakatsu&apos;s appeal, the father and the son only got a penalty to be confined in Kudoyama at the foot of Mt. Koya in Kii Province, and the territory of the Ueda Domain in Shinano Province was given to Nobuyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yielding to Tadakatsu&apos;s appeal in the end, the father and son only received a punishment of being confined in Kudoyama at the foot of Mt. Koya in Kii Province, and the territory of the Ueda Domain in Shinano Province was given to Nobuyuki.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yielding to Tadakatsu&apos;s appeal in the end, the father and son only received a punishment of being confined in Kudoyama at the foot of Mt. Koya in Kii Province, and the territory of the Ueda Domain in Shinano Province was given to Nobuyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="71">
<j>晩年、彼は小刀で持ち物に名前を彫っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years, he was carving his name on a short sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years, Tadakatsu was carving his name on a short sword.</e>
<cmt>he &gt; Tadakatsu;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later years, Tadakatsu was carving his name on his possessions using a short sword.</e>
<cmt>on→using （小刀”で”） と修正しました。「持ち物に」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>その時、うっかり手を滑らせ、指に小さな切り傷を負ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time he accidentally slid his hand, and made a small cut on his finger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accidentally slid his hand on the blade, making a small cut on his finger.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;on the blade&quot; after &quot;hand&quot;; and made &gt; making;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accidentally slid his hand on the blade, making a small cut on his finger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>忠勝は「わしの命運もここまでか」と嘆き、実際にその数日後に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakatsu lamented that &apos;his life would end&apos; and he died a few days later in fact.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lamented, &apos;My life must be coming to its end,&apos; and did in fact die a few days later.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lamented, &apos;My life must be coming to its end,&apos; and did in fact die a few days later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>これが彼の生涯で唯一の負傷だったと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was said to be his one and only injury in his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was said to be his one and only injury in his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was said to be his one and only injury in his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="75">
<j>出陣するとき、忠勝は愛槍である蜻蛉切と鹿角脇立兜、そして肩から大数珠をさげるのが常であったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he usually had Tonbokiri, his favorite spear, Kazuno wakidate kabuto, and a big juzu (rosary) on his shoulder when he went into the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he went into battle, it is said that he usually had his favorite spear Tonbokiri, his Kazuno wakidate kabuto (a helmet with an ornament in the shape of deer horns), and a big juzu (rosary) on his shoulder.</e>
<cmt>added description in parenthesis for &quot;Kazuno wakidate kabuto&quot;; rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he went into battle, it is said that he usually had his favorite spear Tonbokiri, his Kazuno wakidate kabuto (a helmet with an ornament in the shape of deer horns), and a big juzu (rosary) on his shoulder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>大数珠を身につけたのは、自らが葬った敵を弔うためであったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his wearing a big juzu meant to mourn for the enemies he himself killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the big juzu was meant to mourn for the enemies he himself had killed.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the big juzu was meant to mourn for the enemies he himself had killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="77">
<j>蜻蛉切（とんぼきり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tonbokiri spear</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tonbokiri spear (literally &quot;dragonfly cutter&quot;)</e>
<cmt>added literal translation in parenthesis;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tonbokiri spear (literally &quot;dragonfly cutter&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>蜻蛉切は元々服部氏の所有であったが、本多忠勝が後にそれを譲り受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Tonbokiri was originally owned by the Hattori clan, Tadakatsu HONDA got it later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Tonbokiri was originally owned by the Hattori clan, it was later inherited by Tadakatsu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>譲り受けた got &gt; inherited; fixed grammar;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Tonbokiri was originally owned by the Hattori clan, it was later inherited by Tadakatsu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>蜻蛉切は、忠勝が多くの功績を挙げた槍の号（あだ名）であり、その活躍により、この槍は「天下三名槍」の一つに数えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tonbokiri was a nickname of the spear with which Tadakatsu made quite a lot of achievements, and its success made this spear one of &quot;the best three spears in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nicknamed Tonbokiri was the spear with which Tadakatsu made many achievements, and its success made this spear one of &quot;the best three spears in Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nicknamed Tonbokiri was the spear with which Tadakatsu made many achievements, and its success made this spear one of &apos;the best three spears in Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>穂先に止まったトンボ（とんぼ）が真っ二つになったという逸話から、この名が付いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name came from the anecdote that a dragonfly perched on its tip and it was split in two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name came from an anecdote that a dragonfly perched on its tip and was split in two.</e>
<cmt>the anecdote &gt; an anecdote; eliminated &quot;it&quot; after &quot;and&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name came from an anecdote that a dragonfly perched on its tip and was split in two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>茎には村正の一派と言われる『藤原正真作』の銘があり、刃長43.8cmの笹穂型の大身槍である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its nakago (body of the tang) had an inscription of &quot;made by FUJIWARA no Masazane&quot; allegedly a Muramasa group member, and it was a Great spear with the blade length of 43.8cm in the shape of a bamboo leaf.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a long spear that had a blade with a length of 43.8cm in the shape of a bamboo leaf and had an inscription on the shaft that read, &quot;Made by FUJIWARA no Masazane,&quot; allegedly a Muramasa group member.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;nakago (body of the tang)&quot; and changed it to &quot;shaft&quot;; Great spear &gt; long spear; rearranged sentence to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a long spear that had a blade with a length of 43.8 cm in the shape of a bamboo leaf and had an inscription on the shaft that read, &quot;Made by FUJIWARA no Masazane,&quot; allegedly a Muramasa group member.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>柄の長さは6mほどであったといわれる（通常の長槍は4.5m）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that its hilt was about 6m long (A regular long spear has 4.5m).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the hilt was about 6m long (a regular long spear is 4.5m).</e>
<cmt>its hilt &gt; the hilt; A &gt; a;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the hilt was about 6 m long (A regular long spear is 4.5 m.)</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。カッコ内を修正しました。一桁の数字のスペルアウトですが、4.5 という数字と、m との兼ね合いからここではそのままにしてあります。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>しかし、晩年にはやはり体力の衰えが出てきたと見え、「槍は自分の力に合うものが一番」と言って槍の柄を短く詰めてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he seemed to reduce the state of strength in his later years after all, he shortened the hilt of the spear, saying &apos;The spear which fits your strength is the best.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in his later years as his physical strength began to decline, he shortened the hilt of the spear, saying &apos;The best spear is the one that fits your strength.&apos;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in his later years as his physical strength began to decline, he shortened the hilt of the spear, saying &apos;The best spear is the one that fits your strength.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>岡崎城などでそのレプリカを見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You can see its replica at Okazaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A replica of the spear can be seen at Okazaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A replica of the spear can be seen at Okazaki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 いいすく(id:136753), ドルチェット(id:46458), Bakkai(id:7233), Suguri F(id:11127), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), Reggaeman(id:6214), HI(id:72996), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), Chocoyoshi(id:170796), Big-KANA(id:195421), 宮本すぐる(id:40080), Kareha(id:36360), ホンダ(id:307610), YAMAARASHI(id:18211), Easyman(id:86871), るがこむ(id:181), 嫦娥(id:81469), A-Taul(id:41790), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Loveless(id:129239), Sabkakusikaku(id:277058), Maakun(id:16735), 六尺兄貴(id:132914), YukkeBot2(id:251491), ウィキ豊(id:82961), M-sho-gun(id:88956), Asura2007(id:78364), たね(id:10372), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 松茸(id:27535), Sat.K(id:3751), Yaky(id:22711), LaaknorBot(id:220851), 小者(id:172526), 彩華1226(id:64711), Baf(id:31737), Kamitani(id:30757), Carkuni(id:79281), Alecs.bot(id:194707), VolkovBot(id:105371), R28Bot(id:177951), Labyfrag(id:9446), Tonbi ko(id:27171), Kishitak(id:9134), Safkan(id:423), 人造人間だみゃ～ん(id:119413), SieBot(id:126695), Jmho(id:10472), 宇和島太郎(id:105130), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>