<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原広嗣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原広嗣（ふじわら の ひろつぐ、生年不詳 - 天平12年11月1日 (旧暦)（740年11月28日））は、奈良時代の廷臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu (year of birth unknown, died on November 28 AD 740) was a retainer of Imperial Court in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu (year of birth unknown - November 28, 740) was a retainer of Imperial Court in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>,died onを - を使って表し、AD 740のADを省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu (year of birth unknown - November 28, 740) was a retainer of Imperial Court in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原式家藤原宇合の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eldest son of FUJIWARA no Umakai from Fujiwara Shikike (a sub branch of Fujiwara family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of FUJIWARA no Umakai from Fujiwara Shikike (a sub branch of Fujiwara family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of FUJIWARA no Umakai from Fujiwara Shikike (a sub branch of Fujiwara family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は石上麻呂（一説には蘇我石川麻呂）の女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was ISONOKAMI no Maro (another theory said SOGA no Ishikawamaro).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of ISONOKAMI no Maro (one theory states that it was SOGA no Ishikawamaro).</e>
<cmt>ISONOKAMI no Maroをa daughter of ISONOKAMI no Maroに、 another theory saidをone theory states it was訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of ISONOKAMI no Maro (one theory states that it was SOGA no Ishikawamaro).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>朝廷において圧倒的な権力を誇っていた藤原四兄弟が相次いで亡くなった天平9年（737年）、従五位下に叙す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In AD 737, when Fujiwara four brothers who took pride in overwhelming power in the court had died one after another, he was appointed Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 737, when Fujiwara four brothers who was holding tremendous authority in Imperial Court died one after another, he was appointed Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.</e>
<cmt>ADを省略しました。  グラマーに問題がありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 737, when Fujiwara four brothers who was holding tremendous authority in Imperial Court died one after another, he was appointed Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天平10年、大養徳（大和国）守兼式部少輔となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In AD 738, he became Guide of Yamato Province and Junior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 738, he became Guide of Yamato Province and Junior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial.</e>
<cmt>ADを省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 738, he became Guide of Yamato Province and Junior Assistant Minister of the Ministry of Ceremonial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>朝廷内では、反藤原氏勢力が台頭した背景のもと、同年、親族への誹謗を理由に大宰少弐に左遷される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the court, under the background of the uprising anti-Fujiwara power, he was relegated in the same year to Dazai no shoni (Junior Assistant Govenor-General of Dazai-fu offices) because of the slander to the relative.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Imperial Court, under the background of the uprising anti-Fujiwara power, he was relegated in the same year to Dazai no shoni (Junior Assistant Govenor-General of Dazai-fu offices) because of the slander against his relatives.</e>
<cmt>courtを Imperial Courtに、toを againstに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Imperial Court, under the background of the uprising anti-Fujiwara power, he was relegated in the same year to Dazai no shoni (Junior Assistant Govenor-General of Dazai-fu offices) because of the slander against his relatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>広嗣は左遷を不服とし、天地の災厄の元凶であるのは、反藤原勢力の要である吉備真備と僧の玄ボウであるとの上奏文を朝廷に送る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Objecting to the relegation, Hirotsugu sent to the Imperial Court a report to the throne, saying that the ringleaders of the disaster of the world were KIBI no Makibi and GENBO, who were the main people in the anti-Fujiwara power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Objecting to the relegation, Hirotsugu sent a report to the throne in the Imperial Court saying that the ringleaders who caused the disaster to the world were the two main people in the anti-Fujiwara group, KIBI no Makibi and Genbo.</e>
<cmt>グラマーに問題がありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Objecting to the relegation, Hirotsugu sent a report to the throne in the Imperial Court saying that the ringleaders who caused the disaster to the world were the two main people in the anti-Fujiwara group, KIBI no Makibi and Genbo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、時の権力者左大臣橘諸兄はこれを謀反と受け取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, TACHIBANA no Moroe, who was at that time the powerful Minister of the Left, received this as an evidence of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, TACHIBANA no Moroe, who was at that time the powerful Minister of the Left, received this as an evidence of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, TACHIBANA no Moroe, who was at that time the powerful Minister of the Left, received this as an evidence of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>真備と玄昉の起用を進めたのは諸兄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Moroe who employed KIBI no Makibi and GENBO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Moroe who employed KIBI no Makibi and GENBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Moroe who employed KIBI no Makibi and GENBO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>疫病により被害を受けた民心安定策を批判するなど、その内実は諸兄その人への批判であることは明白であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The criticism to the public sentiment stability plan for the common people who had received damage due to the epidemic was clearly the criticism to Moroe himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The criticism toward the public sentiment stability plan for the commoners who had received damage from the epidemic was clearly the criticism toward Moroe himself.</e>
<cmt>グラマーに問題がありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The criticism toward the public sentiment stability plan for the commoners who had received damage from the epidemic was clearly the criticism toward Moroe himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>聖武天皇はこれに対して広嗣の召喚の勅を出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Responding to this, Emperor Shomu sent out an ordinance of summons for Hirotsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Responding to this, Emperor Shomu sent out an ordinance of summons to Hirotsugu.</e>
<cmt>グラマーに問題がありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Responding to this, Emperor Shomu sent out an ordinance of summons to Hirotsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>広嗣は勅に従わず、天平12年、弟の藤原綱手とともに大宰府の手勢や隼人などを加えた1万余を率いて反乱を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirotsugu did not follow the ordinance, and in AD 740, he, with his younger brother FUJIWARA no Tsunate, gathered and led his own forces/soldiers and Hayato imperial guides totaling 10,000 or more, and raised a revolt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirotsugu did not follow the ordinance, and in 740, he, with his younger brother FUJIWARA no Tsunate, gathered and led his 10,000 or more troop members including the ones in Dazaifu and raised a revolt.</e>
<cmt>ADを省略しました。  グラマーに問題がありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirotsugu did not follow the ordinance, and in 740, he, with his younger brother FUJIWARA no Tsunate, gathered and led his 10,000 or more troop members including the ones in Dazaifu and raised a revolt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし大野東人を大将軍とする追討軍に敗走し、最後は肥前国松浦郡で捕らえられ、同国唐津にて処刑された（藤原広嗣の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was defeated by the subjugation army whose big general was ONO no Azumahito, once retreated but was finally captured in Matsuura-gun County of Hizen Province, he was executed in Karatsu of the same province (the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was defeated by a punitive force led by Commander-in-Chief ONO no Azumahito and finally captured in Matsuura-gun District, Hizen Province and executed in Karatsu of the same province (called the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu).</e>
<cmt>グラマーに問題がありました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was defeated by a punitive force led by Commander-in-Chief ONO no Azumahito and finally captured in Matsuura-gun District, Hizen Province and executed in Karatsu of the same province (called the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これによって多くの式家関係者が処分を受け、奈良時代末期には一時的には政治の実権を握るものの後世における式家の不振を招く要因の一つになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, a lot of people related to the Shiki Family received execution, and in the end of Nara period, though the power of politics was temporarily possessed, it became one of the factors causing the slump of the Shiki Family in future generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, a lot of people related to the Shiki Family received punishments, and though they seized the political power temporarily at the end of Nara Period, this rebellion became one of the factors which weakened the power of the Shiki Family in future generations.</e>
<cmt>グラマーに問題がありました。     適切な単語が使われていませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, a lot of people related to the Shiki Family received punishments, and though they seized the political power temporarily at the end of Nara Period, this rebellion became one of the factors which weakened the power of the Shiki Family in future generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、新薬師寺の西隣に鎮座する「鏡神社」は藤原広嗣の怨霊を鎮めるために創建されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Kagami-jinja Shrine&quot; (Mirror Shinto shrine) enshrined to the west of Shinyakushi-ji Temple was built in order to calm down FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu&apos;s revengeful ghost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Kagami-jinja Shrine&quot; located to the west of Shinyakushi-ji Temple was built in order to soothe FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu&apos;s vengeful spirit.</e>
<cmt>鏡神社は固有名詞のため、英語に訳す必要はないと思います。    適切な単語が使われていませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Kagami-jinja Shrine&quot; located to the west of Shinyakushi-ji Temple was built in order to soothe FUJIWARA no Hirotsugu&apos;s vengeful spirit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 玄史生(id:43670), Goki(id:7107), 代言人(id:33675), MIO(id:31681), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Bit(id:2197), 味っ子(id:17086), 伏儀(id:142093), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Zippin(id:9885), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>