<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大内輝弘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teruhiro OUCHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teruhiro OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teruhiro OUCHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大内 輝弘（おおうち てるひろ、永正17年（1520年）？ - 永禄12年11月25日 (旧暦)（1569年1月1日））は、戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teruhiro OUCHI (1520? - January 1, 1569) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teruhiro OUCHI (1520? - January 1, 1569) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Warring States Period).</e>
<cmt>Explanation of &quot;Sengoku Period&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teruhiro OUCHI (c. 1520 - January 1, 1569) was a busho (Japanese military commander) in the Sengoku Period (Warring States Period).</e>
<cmt>c.　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第14代当主・大内政弘の次男・大内高弘の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a son of Takahiro OUCHI, who was a second son of Masahiro OUCHI, the fourteenth head of Ouchi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a son of Takahiro OUCHI, who was the second son of Masahiro OUCHI, the fourteenth head of Ouchi family.</e>
<cmt>There is only one second son so use &quot;the&quot; instead of &quot;a&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a son of Takahiro OUCHI, who was the second son of Masahiro OUCHI, the fourteenth head of Ouchi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子に大内武弘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a son named Takehiro Ouchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a son named Takehiro Ouchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a son named Takehiro OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>太郎左衛門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tarozaemon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tarozaemon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tarozaemon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>大内氏の一族であるが、大内義隆と対立していたため、早くから大内氏と敵対関係でもあり血縁関係でもあった大友氏を頼り、その客将となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he belonged to the Ouchi clan, he confronted with Yoshitaka Ouchi from early on and became a Kyakusho (guest busho) of the Otomo clan, which was hostile to the Ouchi clan despite of a blood relation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he belonged to the Ouchi clan, he opposed Yoshitaka Ouchi from the outset, and became aa Kyakubusho (guest busho) with the Otomo clan which was hostile in spite of the blood relations between the two clans.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he belonged to the Ouchi clan, he opposed Yoshitaka OUCHI from the outset, and became a guest busho (Japanese military commander) with the Otomo clan which was hostile in spite of the blood relations between the two clans.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大内氏の第18代の当主とされるが、実権は既に無く、大内義長の死によって大内氏は断絶したと見るのが正しいと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he is assumed as the eighteenth head of Ouchi clan, he had no real power and it should be correct to understand that Ouchi clan became extinct with the death of Yoshinaga OUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although became the eighteenth head of Ouchi clan, he had no real power, and the the Ouchi clan can be viewed as having died out with the death of Yoshinaga OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although became the 18th head of Ouchi clan, he had no real power, and the Ouchi clan can be viewed as having died out with the death of Yoshinaga OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）、大友義鎮が毛利元就と豊前地域の覇権を巡って争った際、大友軍は毛利軍の攻勢の前に、一時は壊滅の危機に立たされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1568 when Yoshishige OTOMO fought a battle with Motonari MORI over the hegemony of Buzen region, Otomo&apos; army once fell into the crisis of collapse due to the offensive by Mori&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1568, when Yoshishige OTOMO fought a battle with Motonari MORI over the hegemony of Buzen region, Otomo&apos; army were in a state of collapse in the face of attacks by Mori&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1568, when Yoshishige OTOMO fought a battle with Motonari MORI over the hegemony of Buzen region, Otomo&apos;s army was in a state of collapse in the face of attacks by Mori&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>宗麟の参謀である吉岡長増の進言により、宗麟は寄食していた輝弘に兵を与え、同年8月から9月にかけて、若林鎮興らの大友水軍を付けて、密かに海上から周防国に上陸させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the advice made by Nagamasu YOSHIOKA, a staff of Sorin, Sorin entrusted, from August to September of the same year, his soldiers to Teruhiro who sponged on Otomo clan and ordered him to land secretly in Suo Province with the help of Otomo Suigun (navy) headed by Shigeoki WAKABAYASHI,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On advice from Nagamasu YOSHIOKA, a member of his staff, Sorin entrusted, from August to September of the same year, his soldiers to Teruhiro who was dependent on the Otomo clan and ordered him to land secretly in Suo Province with the help of the Otomo navy headed by Shigeoki WAKABAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>Natural Enlglish</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On advice from Nagamasu YOSHIOKA, a member of his staff, from September to December of the same year Sorin entrusted his soldiers to Teruhiro who was dependent on the Otomo clan and ordered him to land secretly in Suo Province with the help of the Otomo navy headed by Shigeoki WAKABAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>輝弘の率いる兵力は少なかったが、水上戦では市川経好を撃破した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the number of soldiers under Teruhiro&apos;s command was small, he defeated Tsuneyoshi ICHIKAWA in the sea battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the number of soldiers under Teruhiro&apos;s command was small, he defeated Tsuneyoshi ICHIKAWA in a sea battle.</e>
<cmt>Natural Enlglish</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the number of soldiers under Teruhiro&apos;s command was small, he defeated Tsuneyoshi ICHIKAWA in a sea battle.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>大内氏の一族であったが故に周防に侵入すると、大内氏の遺臣の多くがこれに呼応した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he invaded into Suo Province since he belonged to Ouchi clan, many of former vassals of Ouchi clan responded to him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Teruhiro invaded Suo Province many former vassals of the Ouchi clan were ready to help him because of his family name.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Teruhiro invaded Suo Province many former vassals of the Ouchi clan were ready to help him because of his family name.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このため、周防国の毛利軍はその大半を北九州の戦線に投入していたため、苦戦を強いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the face of such situation, Mori&apos;s army in Suo Province was forced to have a tough battle because most of its soldiers were dispatched to the battlefield of Kitakyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With most of Mori&apos;s army dispatched to the battlefields of Kitakyushu, the remaining soldiers were forced into a difficult battle.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With most of Mori&apos;s army dispatched to the battlefields of northern Kyushu, the remaining soldiers were forced into a difficult battle.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし高嶺城を守る市川経好夫人が、少ない城兵を指揮し、徹底して抗戦したため、輝弘は山口の大内氏別邸築山屋形に入るに止まり、山口を完全に占領することができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the wife of Tsuneyoshi ICHIKAWA, who was in charge of defending Konomine-jo Castle, made a do-or-die resistance with a small number of soldiers in the castle, Teruhiro barely managed to enter Tsukiyama yakata (Tsukiyama residence), a villa of Ouchi clan located in Yamaguchi, but failed to occupy Yamaguchi completely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the wife of Tsuneyoshi ICHIKAWA, charged with defending Konomine-jo Castle, offered fierce resistance with a small band of soldiers and Teruhiro was stopped at Tsukiyama yakata (a villa of the Ouchi clan in Yamaguchi), and could not fully occupy Yamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the wife of Tsuneyoshi ICHIKAWA, charged with defending Konomine-jo Castle, offered fierce resistance with a small band of soldiers and Teruhiro was stopped at Tsukiyama yakata (a villa of the Ouchi clan in Yamaguchi), and could not fully occupy Yamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>輝弘の攻撃を知った元就は北九州攻略を諦め、即座に軍を返して、吉川元春、小早川隆景率いる精鋭を周防に向かわせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Motonari came to know the invasion by Teruhiro, he promptly gave up to capture Kitakyushu and ordered his elite troops headed by Motoharu KIKKAWA and Takakage Kobayakawa to head for Suo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Motonari found out about the invasion by Teruhiro, he promptly gave up on attacking Kitakyushu and sent his elite troops headed by Motoharu KIKKAWA and Takakage Kobayakawa to Suo.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Motonari found out about the invasion by Teruhiro, he promptly gave up on attacking north Kyushu and sent his elite troops headed by Motoharu KIKKAWA and Takakage KOBAYAKAWA to Suo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>輝弘はその報を受けると山口での抵抗を諦め、海路での脱出経路を探るべく海沿いへ脱出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Teruhiro was informed of the above, he abandoned to resist in Yamaguchi and ran away along the sea coast in order to seek the way to escape by a sea route.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Informed of this, Teruhiro abandoned his efforts in Yamaguchi and made for the coast in an attempt to escape by sea.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Informed of this, Teruhiro abandoned his efforts in Yamaguchi and made for the coast in an attempt to escape by sea.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかしながら、追撃厳しく富海（とのみ：現在の防府市）の茶臼山にて自害して果てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he eventually committed suicide at Mt. Chausu-yama in Tonomi (Hofu City) after being chased fiercely.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But he was chased down and caught at Mt. Chausu-yama in Tonomi (currently Hofu City), and ended up committing suicide.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But he was chased down and caught at Mt. Chausu in Tonomi (currently Hofu City), and ended up committing suicide.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>輝弘の山口乱入によって、毛利軍は本州に撤退せざるを得なくなり、大友氏は筑前国など北九州の毛利方の諸城の奪回に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to Teruhiro&apos;s invasion into Yamaguchi, Mori&apos;s army was forced to withdraw to Honshu (the main island of Japan) and as a result, Otomo clan succeeded in recapturing Mori&apos;s castles located in Kitakyushu including Chikuzen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of Teruhiro&apos;s invasion of Yamaguchi, Mori&apos;s army was forced to withdraw to Honshu (the main island of Japan), which allowed the Otomo clan to recapture Mori&apos;s castles in Chikuzen Province and elsewhere in Kitakyushu.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of Teruhiro&apos;s invasion of Yamaguchi, Mori&apos;s army was forced to withdraw to Honshu (the main island of Japan), which allowed the Otomo clan to recapture Mori&apos;s castles in Chikuzen Province and elsewhere in northern Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>大内輝弘は大友宗麟の捨て駒として利用されたともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that Teruhiro Ouchi was utilized by Sorin OTOMO as a sacrifice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it could be said that Teruhiro Ouchi was sacrificed by Sorin OTOMO.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it could be said that Teruhiro OUCHI was sacrificed by Sorin OTOMO.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Point136(id:211299), Kuma83(id:31177), Carbuncle(id:346), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Cprobot(id:97843), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>