<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原伊房</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korefusa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Korefusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korefusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 伊房（ふじわら の これふさ、長元3年（1030年） - 永長元年9月16日 (旧暦)（1096年10月4日））は、平安時代中期から後期にかけての公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korefusa (1030 - October 4, 1096) was a court noble who lived from the middle to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Korefusa (1030 - October 4, 1096) was a court noble who lived from the middle to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Korefusa (1030 - October 10, 1096) was a court noble who lived from the middle to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>世尊寺流の能書家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a noshoka (master of calligraphy) of Sesonji School (of Calligraphy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a noshoka (master of calligraphy) of the Sesonji School (of Calligraphy).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a noshoka (master of calligraphy) of the Sesonji School (of Calligraphy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大納言藤原行成の孫で、参議藤原行経の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the grandson of FUJIWARA no Yukinari, who held the title Dainagon (Major Counselor), and the son of FUJIWARA no Yukitsune, who held the title Sangi (councillor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the grandson of FUJIWARA no Yukinari, who held the title Dainagon (Major Counselor), and was the son of FUJIWARA no Yukitsune, who held the title Sangi (councillor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the grandson of FUJIWARA no Yukinari, who held the title Dainagon (chief councilor of state), and was the son of FUJIWARA no Yukitsune, who held the title Sangi (councillor).</e>
<cmt>Dainagon→統一表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正二位・中納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held the office of Chunagon (middle counsellor) and rose to the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the office of Chunagon (middle counsellor) and rose to the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the office of Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) and rose to the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>Chunagon→統一表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>1031年（長元4年）従五位に叙せられ、以後少納言・蔵人・木工寮・弁官などを歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in 1031, and thereafter held the titles Shonagon (Lesser counselor), Kurodo (Chamberlain), Mokuryo (Bureau of Carpentry), and benkan (officials of the dajokan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in 1031, and thereafter held the titles Shonagon (Lesser counselor), Kurodo (Chamberlain), Mokuryo (Bureau of Carpentry), and benkan (officials of the dajokan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded the rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) in 1031, and thereafter held the titles Shonagon (lesser councilor of state), Kurodo (Chamberlain), Mokuryo (Bureau of Carpentry), and benkan (officials of the dajokan).</e>
<cmt>Shonagon→統一表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1069年（延久元年）6月に蔵人頭、12月に左中弁に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in June 1069 (old calender) and Sachuben (middle controller of the left) in December 1069 (old calender).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in June 1069 (old calender) and Sachuben (middle controller of the left) in December 1069 (old calender).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in June 1069 (old calender) and Sachuben (middle controller of the left) in January 1070.</e>
<cmt>新暦表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1072年（延久4年）に右大弁・参議となり、この時の官位は正四位であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1072, he was appointed as Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) and Sangi, and on this occasion, he held the rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1072, he was appointed as Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) and Sangi, and on this occasion, he held the rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1072, he was appointed as Udaiben (Major Controller of the Right) and Sangi, and on this occasion, he held the rank of Shoshii (Senior Fourth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1080年（承暦4年）権中納言に任じられ、1082年（永保2年）正二位に叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) in 1080 and was awarded the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1082.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) in 1080 and was awarded the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1082.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Gon Chunagon (provisional vice-councilor of state) in 1080 and was awarded the rank of Shonii in 1082.</e>
<cmt>Gon Chunagon→統一表記に修正、Shonii→既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1094年（寛治8年）5月25日、遼と私貿易を行ったことをとがめられ、従二位に降格の上、停職を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 16, 1094, he was blamed for having private trading with Liao and was suspended from office, dropping to the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 16, 1094, he was blamed for having private trade with Liao and was suspended from office, dropping to the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 16, 1094, he was blamed for having private trade with Liao and was suspended from office, dropping to the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、死去の直前に復位が許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was allowed for restoration just before he died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was allowed restoration just before he died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was allowed restoration just before he died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>白河天皇に仕えた賢臣として、大江匡房・藤原為房とともに「前の三房」と並び称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an able retainer served Emperor Shirakawa, he was equally admired as &quot;saki no sanbo&quot; (former three retainers) with OE no Masafusa and FUJIWARA no Tamefusa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an able retainer serving Emperor Shirakawa, he was equally admired as &quot;saki no sanbo&quot; (former three retainers) with OE no Masafusa and FUJIWARA no Tamefusa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an able retainer serving Emperor Shirakawa, he was equally admired as &apos;saki no sanbo&apos; (former three retainers) with OE no Masafusa and FUJIWARA no Tamefusa.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Point136(id:211299), 伏儀(id:142093), 蔭人(id:80171), Snap55(id:89773), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>