<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日野俊基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimoto HINO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimoto HINO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimoto HINO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日野俊基（ひの としもと、生年不詳 - 元弘2年/正慶元年6月3日 (旧暦)（1332年6月26日））は、鎌倉時代末期の公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimoto HINO (date of birth unknown, died June 3, 1332 (old lunar calendar) (June 26, 1332)) was a court noble in the end of Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimoto HINO (date of birth unknown, died June 3, 1332 (old lunar calendar) (June 26, 1332)) was a court noble at the end of Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimoto HINO (date of birth unknown, died July 4, 1332) was a court noble at the end of Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除June 26→July 4に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は日野種範。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Tanenori HINO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Tanenori HINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Tanenori HINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>文保2年（1318年）に即位した後醍醐天皇の親政に参加し、蔵人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He joined shinsei (monarchy) of Emperor Godaigo, who enthroned in 1318, and became a kurodo (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined the shinsei (monarchy) of Emperor Godaigo, who was enthroned in 1318, and became a kurodo (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He joined the direct imperial rule of Emperor Godaigo, who was enthroned in 1318, and became a kurodo (chamberlain).</e>
<cmt>親政の訳、変更（用語集）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後醍醐の朱子学（宋学）志向に影響を受け、鎌倉幕府討幕のための謀議に加わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was influenced by Emperor Godaigo&apos;s Neo-confucianism (Shugaku), and participated in the conspiracy to attack the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was influenced by Emperor Godaigo&apos;s Neo-confucianism (Shugaku), and participated in the conspiracy to attack the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was influenced by Emperor Godaigo&apos;s Neo-confucianism (Sung-period neo-Cunfucianism), and participated in the conspiracy to attack the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shougun).</e>
<cmt>幕府の説明補足(Shugaku)→(Sung-period neo-Cunfucianism)（用語集）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>諸国を巡り反幕府勢力を募るが六波羅探題に察知された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He traveled across Japan to recruit anti-shogunate forces; however, Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) scented his move.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He traveled across Japan to recruit anti-shogunate forces; however, Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agent in Rokuhara, Kyoto) scented his moves.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He traveled across Japan to recruit anti-shogunate forces; however, Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agent in Rokuhara, Kyoto) scented his moves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>正中 (日本)元年（1324年）の正中の変で日野資朝らと逮捕されるが処罰は逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1324, he was arrested with Suketomo HINO in the Shochu Rebellion; however, he escapted punishment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1324, he was arrested with Suketomo HINO in the Shochu Rebellion; however, he escaped punishment.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1324, he was arrested with Suketomo HINO in the Shochu Disturbance; however, he escaped punishment.</e>
<cmt>正中の変、用語集に従って変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>京都へ戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、元徳3年/元弘元年（1331年）に発覚した2度めの討幕計画である元弘の変で再び捕らえられ、鎌倉の葛原岡で処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was arrested again in the Genko Rebellion, which was the second anti-shogunate plot that was uncovered in 1331, and was sentenced to death in Kuzuharagaoka, Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was arrested again in the Genko Rebellion, which was the second anti-shogunate plot uncovered in 1331, and was sentenced to death in Kuzuharagaoka, Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was arrested again in the Genko Incident, which was the second anti-shogunate plot uncovered in 1331, and was sentenced to death in Kuzuharagaoka, Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>元弘の変、用語集に従って変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>辞世の句は「秋を待たで葛原岡に消える身の露のうらみや世に残るらん」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His death haiku (Japanese poem) was &apos;I will die before autumn in Kuzuharagaoka. My bitterness will remain forever&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His death haiku (Japanese poem) was &apos;I will die before autumn in Kuzuharagaoka. My bitterness will remain forever&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His death haiku (Japanese poem) was &apos;I will die before autumn in Kuzuharagaoka. My bitterness will remain forever&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治維新後、南朝（吉野朝廷）が正統とされると俊基は倒幕の功労者として評価されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Southern Dynasty (Yoshino Imperial Court) became legitimate; people started to recognize Toshimoto as a person who has rendered distinguished service in the anti-shogunate movement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the Southern Dynasty (Yoshino Imperial Court) became legitimate; people started to recognize Toshimoto as a person who had rendered distinguished service in the anti-shogunate movement.</e>
<cmt>verb tnse</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Southern Court (Yoshino Imperial Court) became legitimate; people started to recognize Toshimoto as a person who had rendered distinguished service in the anti-shogunate movement.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Courtthe の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1887年（明治20年）には俊基を主祭神とする葛原岡神社が神奈川県鎌倉市梶原に創建され、俊基自身にも従三位が追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzuharagaoka-jinja Shrine was founded in Kajiwara, Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture in 1887; shusaijin (main enshrined deity) of the shrine was Toshimoto; Toshimoto was also raised to Jusani (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuzuharagaoka-jinja Shrine was founded in Kajiwara, Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture in 1887; the shusaijin (main enshrined deity) of the shrine was Toshimoto; Toshimoto was also promotoed to Jusani (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>article, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuzuharagaoka-jinja Shrine was founded in Kajiwara, Kamakura City, Kanagawa Prefecture in 1887; the shusaijin (main enshrined deity) of the shrine was Toshimoto; Toshimoto was also promotoed to Jusanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Jusani→Jusanmi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graveyard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graveyard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graveyard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>葛原岡神社の南にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His graveyard was located the south of Kuzuharagaoka-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His graveyard is located to the south of Kuzuharagaoka-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His graveyard is located to the south of Kuzuharagaoka-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また1927年（昭和2年）4月8日に国指定史蹟に指定され、財団法人俊基卿遺蹟保存会が遺跡の保護・管理を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designated as a national historic place on April 8, 1927; the remains are preserved and managed by Toshimoto-kyo Iseki Hozon Foundation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designated a national historic site on April 8, 1927; the remains are preserved and managed by the Toshimoto-kyo Iseki Hozon Foundation.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designated a national historic site on April 8, 1927; the remains are preserved and managed by the Toshimoto-kyo Iseki Hozon Foundation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), でここ(id:9565), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Goki(id:7107), 代言人(id:33675), 松茸(id:27535), Kamakura(id:472), Kzhr(id:131), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>