<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>姉小路忠方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakata ANEGAKOJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakata ANEGAKOJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakata ANEGAKOJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>姉小路 忠方（あねがこうじ ただかた、仁治2年（1241年） - 弘安5年12月19日 (旧暦)（1283年1月19日））は、鎌倉時代中期の公卿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakata ANEGAKOJI (1241 - January 19, 1283) was a Kugyo (high court noble), who lived during the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakata ANEGAKOJI (1241 - January 19, 1283) was a Court noble who lived during the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>公卿→a Court noble&quot;who&quot;の前のカンマは特に必要ないので、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakata ANEGAKOJI (1241 - January 19, 1283) was a Court noble who lived during the mid Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は権大納言姉小路顕朝、母は二条定高の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) Akitomo ANEGAKOJI, and his mother was the daughter of Sadataka NIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) Akitomo ANEGAKOJI, and his mother was the daughter of Sadataka NIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state) Akitomo ANEGAKOJI, and his mother was the daughter of Sadataka NIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>父が後嵯峨天皇の腹心であった事から、18歳で右少弁となり父の死後である文永5年（1268年）には参議に昇って後嵯峨上皇の伝奏を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his father was a trustworthy retainer of Emperor Gosaga, he became Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) at the age of 18, and in 1268 after his father&apos;s death he was ascended to Sangi (councilor) and took charge of Retired Emperor Gosaga&apos;s denso (job title to relay massages of court&apos;s people to Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his father was a trustworthy retainer of the Emperor Gosaga, Tadakata became Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) at the age of 18, and in 1268 after his father&apos;s death, he was promoted to Sangi (councilor) and served the Retired Emperor Gosaga as denso (job title to relay massages of court&apos;s people to Emperor).</e>
<cmt>昇る→promoted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his father was a trustworthy retainer of the Emperor Gosaga, Tadakata became Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) at the age of 18, and in 1268 after his father&apos;s death, he was promoted to Sangi (councilor) and served the Retired Emperor Gosaga as denso (job title to relay massages of court&apos;s people to Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>だが、3年後の文永8年（1271年）既に前年に正三位権中納言に昇進していた忠方は、同じ正三位権中納言でも宮中の序列が低い中御門経任が従二位に任じられた事で先を越されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1271, three years later, Tsunetada NAKANOMIKADO, whose order of precedence in the Imperial Court was lower than his, got ahead of Tadakata and he was ascended to Junii (Junior Second Rank), while Tsunetada was ranked Shosanmi Gon Chunagon (Senior Third Rank provisional vice-chief councilor of the state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1271 three years after that, Tadakata who had been promoted to Shosanmi Gon Chunagon (Senior Third Rank provisional vice-chief councilor of the state) in the previous year fell behind Tsunetada NAKANOMIKADO who was also Shosanmi Gon Chunagon but ranked lower than him in the Imperial Court, due to an event that Tsunetada was conferred to the Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>「中御門経任が忠方の先を越す」は、「忠方が中御門経任に先を越される」という意味であり、「姉小路忠方」に関する項目なので、「忠方」を主語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1271 three years after that, Tadakata who had been promoted to Shosanmi Gon Chunagon (Senior Third Rank provisional vice-chief councilor of the state) in the previous year fell behind Tsunetada NAKANOMIKADO who was also Shosanmi Gon Chunagon but ranked lower than him in the Imperial Court, due to an event that Tsunetada was conferred to the Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>忠方は経任とは不仲であった上に、後嵯峨上皇が父・顕朝亡き後の一番の腹心に顕朝の遺児である自分ではなく経任が指名された考えた忠方は憤慨する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakata felt indignant, because in addition to the fact that he was not getting well with Tsunetada, after his father Akitomo&apos;s death, Tsunetada got the appointment instead of Tadakata who was the bereaved child of Akitomo, the most trustworthy retainer of Retired Emperor Gosaga.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakata felt indignant because he was not getting well with Tsunetada, and he felt that the Retired Emperor Gosaga designated not Tadakata who was Akitomo&apos;s bereaved child but Tsunetada as the most trustworthy retainer after his father, Akitomo, died.</e>
<cmt>より簡潔な表現に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakata felt indignant because he was not getting well with Tsunetada, and he felt that the Retired Emperor Gosaga designated not Tadakata who was Akitomo&apos;s bereaved child but Tsunetada as the most trustworthy retainer after his father, Akitomo, died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そして、知行国である甲斐国を返上して官職を辞してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he returned back his chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom), Kai Province, and resigned from the government post</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, he returned Kai Province which was his chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom), and resigned from the government post.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Then&quot;の後にカンマを、また文尾にピリオドを付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, he returned Kai Province which was his chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom), and resigned from the government post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これによって暗に後嵯峨上皇の翻意を促そうしたものであると考えられているが、逆にその逆鱗に触れて宮中を追われてしまう形となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that by this behavior, he tried to call for Retired Emperor Gosaga&apos;s second thought indirectly, however, in return, his attempt incurred the Retired Emperor&apos;s wrath and he was expelled from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is considered that he committed this act to implicitly urge the Retired Emperor Gosaga to reconsider, his attempt incurred the Retired Emperor&apos;s wrath by contraries and resulted in his expulsion from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>～の翻意を促す→urge someone to reconsider～してしまう形となる→result in ～（「～の結果に終わる」の意味なので、result inに変更しました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is considered that he committed this act to implicitly urge the Retired Emperor Gosaga to reconsider, his attempt incurred the Retired Emperor&apos;s wrath by contraries and resulted in his expulsion from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>忠方は失意のうちに姉小路家伝来の文書を焼き捨てて（公家社会では事実上の家名の断絶を意味する）出家し、42歳の若さで病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakata burned down the Anegakoji family&apos;s monjo (written materials) handed down from their ancestors (in the cout noble society the loss of the family monjo practically meant the extinction of the family name), and went into priesthood and died young by disease at the age of 42.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disappointed Tadakata burned down the Anegakoji family documents handed down from their ancestors (in the court noble society, a loss of the family documents meant de facto extinction of family name), and went into priesthood, and then, died of disease at an early age of 42.</e>
<cmt>姉小路家伝来の文書→the Anegakoji family documents handed down from their ancestors（「姉小路家文書」をthe Anegakoji family documentsとしました。）公家社会→court society（&quot;court&quot;のミススペルを訂正しました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disappointed Tadakata burned down the Anegakoji family documents handed down from their ancestors (in the court noble society, a loss of the family documents meant de facto extinction of family name), and went into priesthood, and then, died of disease at an early age of 42.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これによって勧修寺流姉小路家は断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With his death he Anegakoji family of the Kajuji line had ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this, the Anegakoji family of the Kajuji line ended.</e>
<cmt>これによって→as a result of this（一般的な表現に変更しました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this, the Anegakoji family of the Kajuji line ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 中右(id:50196), ５１６(id:45205), Cprobot(id:97843), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>