<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>浅井了意</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoi ASAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoi ASAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoi ASAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>浅井 了意（あさい りょうい、慶長17年（1612年）- 元禄4年1月1日 (旧暦)（1691年1月29日））は、江戸時代前期の浄土真宗の僧・仮名草子作家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoi ASAI (1612-January 29, 1691) was the monk of Jodoshinshu (Pure Land Buddhist) sect in the early Edo Period and was the writer of Kana zoshi (story book written in kana (or in kana mixed with Chinese characters) in the early Edo period (primarily for the enlightenment and entertainment of women and children)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoi ASAI (1612-January 29, 1691) was a monk of the Jodoshinshu (Pure Land Buddhist) sect in the early Edo Period and was the writer of Kana zoshi (story book written in kana (or in kana mixed with Chinese characters) in the early Edo period (primarily for the enlightenment and entertainment of women and children)).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoi ASAI (1612-January 29, 1691) was a monk of the Jodo shin shu (True Pure Land Sect Buddhism) in the early Edo Period and was the writer of Kana zoshi (storybooks written in kana (the Japanese syllabary))</e>
<cmt>「Jodoshinshu (Pure Land Buddhist) sect」→「Jodo shin shu (True Pure Land Sect Buddhism)」としました。【登録用語修正】仮名草子→Kana zoshi (story book written in kana (or in kana mixed with Chinese characters) in the early Edo period (primarily for the enlightenment and entertainment of women and children))→Kana zoshi (storybooks written in kana (the Japanese syllabary))[http://www.uv.es/EBRIT/macro/macro_5003_38_59.html]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は東本願寺の末寺本照寺の住職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was the chief priest at Honsho-ji Temple, which was a branched temple of Higashi Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was the chief priest at Honsho-ji Temple, which was a branch temple of Higashi Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was the chief priest at Honsho-ji Temple, which was a branch temple of Higashi Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本名は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name was unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>号は松雲・瓢水子・羊岐斎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His go (official title) was Shoun (Pine Cloud), Hyosuishi (瓢水子), and Yokisai (羊岐斎).</e>
<cmt>瓢水子→Hyosuishi　（瓢水子),　羊岐斎→Yokisai (羊岐斎)[発音は確かですが、英語での意味が不明です。][定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (official title) was Shoun (Pine Cloud), Hyosuishi (瓢水子), and Yokisai (羊岐斎).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (official title) was Shoun (Pine Cloud), Hyosuishi, and Yokisai.</e>
<cmt>人名なので読みが確実であれば漢字は不要かと思い、除きました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>京都の出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He originated from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He originated from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He originated from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>父が本照寺の住職を追われ浪人し、容膝に師事して儒学・仏道・神道の三教に通じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father became unemployeed from the chief priest of the Honsho-ji Temple and became a disciple of Yoshitsu and taught the Three Creeds of Confucianism, Buddhism, and Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>容膝→Yoshitsu[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father became unemployeed as the chief priest of the Honsho-ji Temple and became a disciple of Yoshitsu and taught the Three Creeds of Confucianism, Buddhism, and Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being a wandering priest without a temple to serve, as his father became unemployed as the chief priest of the Honsho-ji Temple, Ryoi studied under Yoshitsu (容膝) to be acquainted with the Three Creeds of Confucianism, Buddhism, and Shintoism.</e>
<cmt>「After being a wandering priest without a temple to serve, as」を追加、「and became a disciple of Yoshitsu and taught」→「Ryoi studied under Yoshitsu (容膝) to be acquainted with」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後京都二条本性寺（真宗大谷派）の昭儀坊に住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later worked as the Shogibo of Kyoto Nijo Honsho-ji Temple (Shinshu Ootani School).</e>
<cmt>昭儀坊→Shogibo[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later worked as the Shogibo of Kyoto Nijo Honsho-ji Temple (Shinshu Ootani School).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later lived in the Shogibo priests&apos; lodge of Kyoto Nijo Honsho-ji Temple (Shinshu sect Otani school).</e>
<cmt>「worked as」→「lived in」としました。【登録用語修正】昭儀坊→Shogibo→Shogibo priests&apos; lodge</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>仏教書・和歌・軍書・古典の注釈書などを著す一方、「堪忍記」「可笑記評判」「東海道名所記」「本朝女鑑」など多岐にわたる著作を行い、1666年（寛文6年）に刊行された「御伽婢子（おとぎぼうこ）」は怪奇物の祖として後世に大きな影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he wrote annotation of Buddhist teachings, Waka, Military and Classic, he contributed to various works such as &quot;Kannin ki&quot; (The Record of Patience), &quot;Kashoki Hyoban&quot; (The Record of Amusing Rumors), &quot;Tokaido meisho no ki&quot; (Famous places along Tokaido), and &quot;Honchojokan,&quot; and &quot;Otogiboko&quot; published in 1666 influenced later generations as the forerunner of the horror stories.</e>
<cmt>「本朝女鑑」→&quot;Honchojokan&quot;, 「御伽婢子]→Otogiboko[発音は確かですが、意味は不明です。][定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he wrote the annotation of Buddhist teachings, Waka, Military and Classic, he contributed to various works such as &quot;Kannin ki&quot; (The Record of Patience), &quot;Kashoki Hyoban&quot; (The Record of Amusing Rumors), &quot;Tokaido meisho no ki&quot; (Famous places along Tokaido), and &quot;Honchojokan,&quot; and &quot;Otogiboko&quot; published in 1666 which influenced later generations as the forerunner of horror stories.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He not only wrote annotations on Buddhism, Waka, Military strategy and Classics, but also various works such as &apos;Kannin ki&apos; (The Record of Patience), &apos;Kashoki Hyoban&apos; (The Record of Amusing Rumors), &apos;Tokaido meisho no ki&apos; (Famous places along Tokaido Road), and &apos;Honcho jokan&apos; (Mirror of Japanese Women), and &apos;Otogiboko&apos; (A Charm Doll) published in 1666 influenced later generations as the forerunner of horror stories.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>仮名草子だけでも30部余りの作品があり、その中でも「浮世物語」は浮世坊が諸国を巡遊する物語であるが、仮名草子から浮世草子へ移り変わる作品として注目されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had thirty-something works of just Kanazoshi, and &quot;Ukiyo Monogatari&quot; (Tale of Ukiyo) was the story about Ukiyobo travelling and playing around various places but focused as the transitional work from Kana zoshi (story book written in kana (or in kana mixed with Chinese characters) in the early Edo period (primarily for the enlightenment and entertainment of women and children)) to Ukiyo-zoshi (type of Japanese fiction).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had thirty-something works of just Kanazoshi, and &quot;Ukiyo Monogatari&quot; (Tale of Ukiyo) was the story about Ukiyobo travelling and playing around various places but focused as the transitional work from Kana zoshi (story book written in kana (or in kana mixed with Chinese characters) in the early Edo period (primarily for the enlightenment and entertainment of women and children)) to Ukiyo-zoshi (type of Japanese fiction).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote over 30 works only for Kana zoshi, and among others in this category, &apos;Ukiyo Monogatari&apos; (Tale of Ukiyo) -- the story about Ukiyobo travelling and playing around various places -- attracted attention as the transitional work from Kana zoshi to Ukiyo zoshi (genre of novels, literally meaning &quot;tales of the floating world&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1692年（元禄5年）に刊行された「狗張子」によれば、1691年（元禄4年）1月1日に昭儀坊で亡くなったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Inuhariko&quot; published in 1692, he died on January 1, 1691 at Shogibo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Inuhariko&quot; published in 1692, he died on January 1, 1691 at Shogibo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Inuhariko&quot; (literally meaning &quot;a paper dog&quot;) published in 1692, he died on January 1, 1691 at Shogibo.</e>
<cmt>【登録用語修正】狗張子→Inuhariko→Inuhariko (literally meaning &quot;a paper dog&quot;)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>著書は数多いが、『浅井了意全集』（岩田書院、全19巻：予定）の刊行が2007年8月より開始されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had many written works, but &quot;Ryoi ASAI zenshu&quot; (collected edition of Ryoi ASAI) (Iwatashoin, Complete Nineteen Volumes, Scheduled) began to be published from August 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had many written works, but &quot;Ryoi ASAI zenshu&quot; (collected edition of Ryoi ASAI) (Iwatashoin, Complete Nineteen Volumes, Scheduled) began to be published from August 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had many written works, but &quot;Ryoi ASAI zenshu&quot; (collected edition of Ryoi ASAI) (Iwatashoin, Complete Nineteen Volumes, Scheduled) began to be published from August 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Takhas(id:93792), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), BOTarate(id:185620), Kaustuv(id:64800), R28Bot(id:177951), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Nighthawks(id:36125), Point136(id:211299), 栄華(id:123663), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), 捕澤(id:23785), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>