<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近衛政家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaie KONOE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaie KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaie KONOE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>近衛 政家（このえ まさいえ、文安元年（1444年） - 永正2年6月19日 (旧暦)（1505年7月20日））は、室町時代中期から戦国時代 (日本)前期にかけての公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaie KONOE (1444-July 20, 1505) was the Kuge (court noble), who lived between the mid-Muromachi Period to the early Sengoku Period (Warring State Period) (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaie KONOE (1444-July 20, 1505) was a Kuge (court noble), who lived between the mid-Muromachi Period to the early Sengoku Period (Warring State Period) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaie KONOE (1444 - July 30, 1505) was a Kuge (court noble), who lived between the mid-Muromachi period to the early the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>関白、太政大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had the title of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and Daijodaijin (Grand Minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the title of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and Daijodaijin (Grand Minister).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the title of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>用語集から補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原北家摂家近衛家13代当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the Thirteenth head of the Konoe family of Sekkan (regent and senior regent) House, the Northern Fujiwara Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the Thirteenth head of the Konoe family of Sekkan (regent and senior regent) House, of the Northern Fujiwara Family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 13th head of the Konoe family of Sekke (regent family), the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>用語集から補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一字名は霞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His one character name was Kasumi (Haze).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His one character name was Kasumi (Haze).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His one character name was Kasumi (Haze).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>号は後法興院。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His go (Buddhist name) was Gohoko-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His go (Buddhist name) was Gohoko-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His go (Buddhist name) was Gohokoin.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>文安元年（1444年）関白・太政大臣を務めた近衛房嗣の次男として生まれる（生年については1445年、1446年説もあり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in 1444 (there were theories stated that he was born in 1445 or 1446) as the second son to Fusatsugu KONOE, who served as the Kanpaku and Daijodaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in 1444 (there were theories stated that he was born in 1445 or 1446) as the second son to Fusatsugu KONOE, who served as the Kanpaku and Daijodaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in 1444 (there were theories stated that he was born in 1445 or 1446) as the second son to Fusatsugu KONOE, who served as the Kanpaku and Daijo-daijin.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>兄は近衛教基（右大臣）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His older brother was Norimoto KONOE (Udaijin (Minister of the Right)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His older brother was Norimoto KONOE (Udaijin, Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His older brother was Norimoto KONOE (Udaijin (Minister of the Right)).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>弟に道興（僧正准三后）、増運（大僧正准三后）、政深（権僧正法印）、政弁（大僧正）らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were Doko (with the rank of Daishojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) and Jusango (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress)), Zoun (with the ranks of Daizosho and Jusango), Masaduka (a highest ranking priest, next to a sojo) and Masasuke (政弁) (with the rank of daisojo) as his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt>増運→Zoun,政深→Masaduka, 政弁→Masasuke (政弁)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were Doko (with the rank of Daishojo, a Buddhist priest of the highest order and Jusango, honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress), Zoun (with the ranks of Daizosho and Jusango), Masaduka (the highest ranking priest, next to a sojo) and Masasuke (政弁) (with the rank of daisojo) as his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were Doko (Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest), Jusango (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress)), Zoun (daisojo (a Buddhist priest of the highest order) and Jusango), Masazuka (政深) (Gonsojo (the lowest grade that can be held by one who has reached the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests), Hoin (the highest rank in the hierarchy of Buddhist priests)), and Masasuke (政弁) (Daisojo) as his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt>ウェブに合わせ原文訳文とも修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>寛正3年（1462年）兄の教基が死去したのに伴い、近衛家を嗣ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the death of his older brother Norimoto, he took over the Konoe family in 1462.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the death of his older brother Norimoto, he took over the Konoe family in 1462.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the death of his older brother Norimoto, he took over the Konoe family in 1462.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌年従三位に叙され、近衛府に任ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was given the Jo (court official rank) Rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in the following year and was assigned to serve Konoefu (Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was given the Jo (court official rank) Rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in the following year and was assigned to serve Konoefu (Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was given the Jo (court official rank) Rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) in the following year and was assigned to serve Konoefu (Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後も連年昇進を続け、応仁元年（1467年）には大納言となり、文明 (日本)4年（1472年）には正二位内大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued receiving promotions and became Dainagon (Major Counselor) in 1467 and the Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) with the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1472.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued receiving promotions and became Dainagon (Major Counselor) in 1467 and the Naidaijin (Minister of the Center) with the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1472.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued receiving promotions and became Dainagon (chief councilor of state) in 1467 and the Naidaijin (Minister of the Interior) with the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank) in 1472.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>応仁の乱が終熄した文明11年（1479年）に関白左大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the end of Onin no Ran (Onin War) in 1479, he became the Kanpaku and Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) (he retired two years afterwards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the end of Onin no Ran (Onin War) in 1479, he became the Kanpaku and Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) (he retired two years afterwards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the end of the Onin War in 1479, he became the Kanpaku and Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) (he retired two years afterwards).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同15年関白を辞した後、長享2年（1488年）太政大臣に任命される（翌々年辞去）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he retired from the Kanpaku position in 1483, he was assigned to be Daijodaijin in 1488 (He left the position two years later).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he retired from the Kanpaku position in 1483, he was assigned to be Daijodaijin in 1488 (He left the position two years later).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he retired from the Kanpaku position in 1483, he was assigned to be Daijo-daijin in 1488 (He left the position two years later).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>明応6年（1497年）には准三宮となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gained the rank of Jusangu (one of the highest rank of Kuge and stands on the equal ground as the imperial family member) in 1497.</e>
<cmt>准三宮→Ju-sangu (one of the highest rank of Kuge and stands on the equal ground as the imperial family member)[http://kotobank.jp/word/准三宮]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gained the rank of Jusangu (one of the highest ranks of Kuge and stands on the equal footing as an imperial family member) in 1497.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gained the rank of Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress) in 1497.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>永正2年（1505年）、死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed away in 1505.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away in 1505.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away in 1505.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>享年62。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of sixty-two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of sixty-two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Died at the age of 62.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>子に近衛尚通がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child was Hisamichi KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His child was Hisamichi KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His child was Hisamichi KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>文化人としての側面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Perspective as a man of culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Perspective as a man of culture</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Perspective as a Man of Culture</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>政家は和歌に優れており、その歌は『新撰菟玖波集』に入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaie was highly skilled in waka (Japanese poem), and his poems were compiled among &quot;Shinsen Tsukubashu&quot; (New Selection of Renga Poetry of Tsukuba).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaie was highly skilled in waka (Japanese poem), and his poems were compiled among &quot;Shinsen Tsukubashu&quot; (New Selection of Renga Poetry of Tsukuba).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaie was highly skilled in waka (Japanese poem), and his poems were compiled among &quot;Shinsen Tsukubashu&quot; (New Selection of Renga Poetry of Tsukuba).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお明応9年8月13日 (旧暦)（1500年9月6日）に近江国守護六角高頼の招待で琵琶湖へ出向していた政家が、近江八景の和歌8首を即興で詠んだことが、近江八景の由来として広く知られているが、近年では八景の始まりは政家によるものではない（政家はこの時期、近江へ下向していない）とする説も有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is widely known that Masaie was invited to Lake Biwa on September 6, 1500 by Takayori ROKKAKU, who was the governor of the Province of Omi, and read out eight waka concerning Omi Hakkei (Eight Sceneries of Omi) impromptu that it became the origin of Omi Hakkei, but it is believed that Hakkei (Eight Sceneries) was not started by Masaie (there was a powerful theory that Masaie did not travel down to Omi at this time).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is widely known that Masaie was invited to Lake Biwa on September 6, 1500 by Takayori ROKKAKU, who was the governor of the Province of Omi, and he read eight waka concerning Omi Hakkei (Eight Sceneries of Omi) impromptu that it became the origin of Omi Hakkei, but it is believed that Hakkei (Eight Sceneries) was not started by Masaie (there was a powerful theory that Masaie did not travel down to Omi at this time).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is widely known that Masaie was invited to Lake Biwa on September 16, 1500 by Takayori ROKKAKU, who was Omi no kuni shugodai (provincial governor of Omi Province), and he read eight waka concerning Omi Hakkei (Eight Sceneries of Omi) impromptu became the origin of Omi Hakkei, but it is believed that Hakkei (Eight Sceneries) was not started by Masaie (there was a powerful theory that Masaie did not travel down to Omi at this time).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>近衛家は藤原氏嫡流として、藤原道長の日記『御堂関白記』をはじめとして、先祖代々の日記や朝廷儀式の記録など、重要な文書を相伝してきたが、政家は応仁・文明の乱に際し、これら大量の古文書を戦火の災いから避けるため、京都の北郊の岩倉に運び出しておいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Konoe Family inherited the important documents, diaries such as the diary of FUJIWARA no Michinaga called &quot;Mido Kanpakuki&quot; (Michinaga FUJIWARA&apos;s diary), and records of the imperial court ceremonies, and Masaie transferred many of these ancient documents to Iwakura located at the northern edge of Kyoto to avoid damages from the battle fires arising from the Onin-Bunmei Wars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Konoe Family inherited important documents, diaries such as the diary of FUJIWARA no Michinaga called &quot;Mido Kanpakuki&quot; (Michinaga FUJIWARA&apos;s diary), and records of the imperial court ceremonies, and Masaie transferred many of these ancient documents to Iwakura located at the northern edge of Kyoto to avoid damage from the battle fires arising from the Onin-Bunmei Wars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Konoe Family inherited important documents, diaries such as the diary of FUJIWARA no Michinaga called &quot;Mido Kanpakuki,&quot; and records of the imperial court ceremonies, and Masaie transferred many of these ancient documents to Iwakura located at the northern edge of Kyoto to avoid damage from the battle fires arising from the Onin-Bunmei Wars.</e>
<cmt>補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>このため乱の最中、近衛家の邸宅は焼失したものの、古文書類は難を逃れ後世に伝えられることとなった（詳しくは「陽明文庫」を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, while the palace of Konoe family fell to ashes, the ancient documents escaped from being damaged to be passed down different generations (For details, please refer to &quot;Yomei Bunko&quot; (the Yomei-Bunko Library)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, while the palace of Konoe family fell into ashes, the ancient documents escaped from being damaged to be passed down to different generations (For details, please refer to &quot;Yomei Bunko&quot; - the Yomei Bunko Library).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, while the palace of Konoe family fell into ashes by the wars, the ancient documents escaped from being damaged to be passed down to different generations (For details, please refer to &apos;Yomei Bunko&apos; (the Yomei Bunko Library)).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>また、政家自身が残した日記『後法興院記』も、室町時代中期の朝廷を知る上での貴重な史料として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dairy left by Masaie called &quot;Gohokoinki Diary&quot; was also regarded as the important historical document to study the imperial court of the mid-Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dairy left by Masaie called &quot;Gohokoinki Diary&quot; was also regarded as the important historical document to study the imperial court of the mid-Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dairy left by Masaie called &quot;Gohokoinki Diary&quot; is also regarded as the important historical document to study the imperial court of the mid-Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>現在形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>官職位階履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career and job grades</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career and Job Grades</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>寛正4年（1463年） 従三位近衛府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1463: He gained the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and was assigned to Konoefu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1463: Gained the rank of Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and was assigned to Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1463: Gained the rank of Jusanmi and was assigned to Konoefu.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>寛正5年（1464年） 中納言兼衛門府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1464: He gained the rank of Chunagon (the middle councilor) and was assigned to Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1464: Gained the rank of Chunagon (the middle councilor) and was assigned to Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1464: Gained the rank of Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) and also assigned to Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>寛正6年（1465年） 正三位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1465: He gained the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1465: Gained the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1465: Gained the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>文正元年（1466年） 従二位左近衛中将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1466: He gained the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1466: Gained the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1466: Gained the rank of Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>応仁元年（1467年） 大納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1467: He gained the rank of Dainagon (Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1467: Gained the rank of Dainagon (Major Counselor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1467: Gained the rank of Dainagon (chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>文明 (日本)4年（1472年） 正二位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1472: He gained the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1472: Gained the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1472: Gained the rank of Shonii.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>文明7年（1475年） 内大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1475: He became the Naidaijin (Minister of the Center).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1475: Became the Naidaijin (Minister of the Center).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1475: Became the Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>文明9年（1477年） 左近衛大将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1477: Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1477: Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1477: Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>文明10年（1478年） 辞去</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1478: He left the position in 1478.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1478: Left the position in 1478.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1478: Left the position.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="32">
<j>文明11年（1479年） 関白・左大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1479: He became the Kanpaku and Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1479: Became the Kanpaku and Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1479: Became the Kanpaku and Sadaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="33">
<j>文明13年（1481年） 左大臣を辞す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1481: He retired from the Sadaijin position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1481: Retired from the Sadaijin position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1481: Retired from the Sadaijin position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="34">
<j>文明15年（1483年） 関白を辞す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1483: He retired from the Kanpaku position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1483: Retired from the Kanpaku position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1483: Retired from the Kanpaku position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="35">
<j>長享2年（1488年） 太政大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1488: He became the Daijodaijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1488: Became the Daijodaijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1488: Became the Daijo-daijin.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="36">
<j>延徳2年（1490年） 辞去</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1490: He retired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1490: Retired.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1490: Retired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="37">
<j>明応6年（1497年） 准三宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1497: He became the Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1497: Became Jusangu (honorary rank next to the three Empresses: Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager, and Empress).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1497: Became Jusangu.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 トホホ川(id:50502), 伏儀(id:142093), TakuyaMurata(id:156), Goki(id:7107), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>