<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>豊原時秋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyohara no Tokiaki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyohara no Tokiaki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TOYOHARA no Tokiaki</e>
<cmt>Toyohara をTOYOHARA に修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>豊原 時秋（とよはら の ときあき、康和2年（1100年） - 没年未詳）は平安時代後期の楽人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyohara no Tokiaki (1100-death date unknown) was the gakunin (player) of the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyohara no Tokiaki (1100-death date unknown) was a gakunin (player) of the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyohara no Tokiaki (1100 - year of death unknown) was a gakunin (player) of the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>1100-death date unknown を1100 - year of death unknown に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>豊原時元を父として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as Toyohara no Tokimoto as his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born with Toyohara no Tokimoto as his father.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born with TOYOHARA no Tokimoto as his father.</e>
<cmt>Toyohara をTOYOHARA に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>豊原氏は代表的な三方楽所楽家の一つであり、時秋の祖父豊原時光、父の時元とも笙の大家として名高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyohara Clan represented one of the Raku families of Sanpo gakuso (organization of transmission of gagaku, ancient court music) and grandfather Tokimitsu TOYOHARA and father Tokimoto of Tokiaki were famous as the great masters of Sho (Japanese flute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Toyohara Clan represented one of the Raku families of Sanpo gakuso (organization of transmission of gagaku, ancient court music), and Tokiaki&apos;s grandfather Tokimitsu TOYOHARA and father Tokimoto were famous as the great masters of Sho (Japanese flute).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Toyohara clan represented one of the Raku families of Sanpo gakuso (organization of transmission of gagaku, ancient court music), and Tokiaki&apos;s grandfather Tokimitsu TOYOHARA and father Tokimoto were famous as the great masters of Sho (traditional Japanese wind instrument resembling panpipes).</e>
<cmt>Clan をclan に修正しました。Japanese flute をtraditional Japanese wind instrument resembling panpipes に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>寛治元年（1087年）、新羅三郎こと源義光は、後三年の役を戦う兄源義家を救援すべくため東上するが、時秋はこの後を追い、相模国足柄山にて戦場への同行を申し出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO Yoshimitsu and Shinra-Saburo travelled east to support his older brother Minamoto no Yoshie in Gosannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War) in 1087, but Tokiaki chased after and asked to accompany him to the battle on Ashigara Mountain in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO Yoshimitsu and Shinra-Saburo travelled east to support his older brother Minamoto no Yoshie in Gosannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War) in 1087, but Tokiaki chased after and asked to accompany him to the battle on Ashigara Mountain in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu or &quot;Shinra-Saburo&quot; traveled east to support his older brother MINAMOTO no Yoshie in Gosannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War) in 1087, but Tokiaki chased after and asked to accompany him to the battle on Mt. Ashigara in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>MINAMOTO Yoshimitsu にno を追記しました。and Shinra-Saburo をor &quot;Shinra-Saburo&quot; に修正しました。travelled をtraveled に修正しました。Minamoto をMINAMOTO に修正しました。Ashigara Mountain をMt. Ashigara に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>義光は時秋の亡父時元の笙の弟子であり、時元より笙の秘伝の一曲『大食調入詞』を授けられていたが、幼くして父と死別した時秋はこの時までその曲を知らぬままでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu was the Sho disciple of the late father of Tokiaki, Tokimoto, and inherited the secret Sho song, &quot;Daijikichonyushi,&quot; but Tokiaki did not learn that song as his father parted early from death.</e>
<cmt>大食調入詞→Daijikichonyushiと判断しました。[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu was a Sho disciple of the late father of Tokiaki, Tokimoto, and inherited the secret Sho song, &quot;Daijikichonyushi,&quot; but Tokiaki did not learn that song, as his father parted early from death.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu was a Sho disciple of the late father of Tokiaki, Tokimoto, and inherited the secret Sho song, &quot;Daijikichonyushi,&quot; but Tokiaki did not learn that song till then, as his father parted early from death.</e>
<cmt>「この時まで」訳漏れのためtill then を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>義光は、自らの戦死によって秘曲を伝える者が絶えることを惜しみ、ここで時秋に同曲を授け後事を託す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu regretted the termination of the successor to pass on the secret music from his own death in a battle and gave the music to Toshiaki asked him to pass it on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu regretted the termination of a successor to pass on the secret music from his own death in a battle and gave the music to Toshiaki, asking him to pass it on.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu regretted the termination of a successor to pass on the secret music from his own death in a battle and gave the music to Toshiaki, asking him to pass it on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>時秋はやむなく義光の説得を受け入れ、都に引き返したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiaki unwillingly accepted the persuasion by Yoshimitsu and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiaki unwillingly accepted Yoshimitsu&apos;s persuasion and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiaki unwillingly accepted Yoshimitsu&apos;s persuasion and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>以上は『古今著聞集』等に見える逸話であり、伝統を受け継ぐ者の心意気を伝える美談として史上に名高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the anecdote seen in works like &quot;Kokon chomon ju&quot; (A collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) and was well known fine historical episode told to represent the spirit of those who passed on traditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the anecdote seen in works such as &quot;Kokon chomon ju&quot; (A collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) and is a well-known fine historical episode told to represent the spirit of those who passed down traditions.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the anecdote seen in works such as &quot;Kokon Chomonju&quot;(Notable Tales Old and New) and is a well-known fine historical episode told to represent the spirit of those who passed down traditions.</e>
<cmt>Kokon chomon ju (A collection of Tales Heard, Past and Present) を&quot;Kokon Chomonju&quot;（Notable Tales Old and New) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかしながら、時秋の生年などから、実際に義光が師事したのは時光、戦場に赴く際に別れたのは時元と一代ずつ前であり、またその場所も足柄山ではなく逢坂関であったとする説が現在では有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, theories that Yoshimitsu actually studied under Tokimitsu, and those who proceeded for the battle was Tokimoto, who was one generation prior to Tokiaki as determined by his birth year and occured at Osaka no Seki rather than Mount Ashigara seemed most probable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the theory that seems most probable is that Yoshimitsu actually studied under Tokimitsu, and Tokimoto was the one who proceeded for the battle, who was one generation prior to Tokiaki as determined by his birth year, and the battle occured at Osaka no Seki rather than Mount Ashigara.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the theory that seems most probable is that Yoshimitsu in fact studied under Tokimitsu, and Tokimoto was the one who proceeded for the battle, who was one generation prior to Tokiaki as determined by his birth year, and the battle occurred at Osaka no Seki (the Osaka Barrier) rather than Mt. Ashigara.</e>
<cmt>occured をoccurred に修正しました。Osaka no seki に(the Osaka Barrier) を追記しました。Mount Ashigara をMt. Ashigara に修正しました。Actually→in fact</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>時秋は楽所勾当となり、篳篥の道で名を上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaki became Gakusho Koto (an office worker for the chamber of music) and spread his name in the way of hichiriki (small double-reed wind instrument).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaki became Gakusho Koto (an office worker for the chamber of music) and spread his name in the way of hichiriki (small double-reed wind instrument).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokaki became Gakusho Koto (an office worker for the chamber of music) and spread his name in the way of hichiriki (small double-reed wind instrument).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>仁平4年（1152年）から保元2年（1157年）まで雅楽允を務めていたことが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as Gagakujo between 1152 to 1157.</e>
<cmt>雅楽允→Gagakujoと判断しました。[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as Gagakujo between 1152 to 1157.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as Gagakujo (Secretary of the Bureau of Music) between 1152 to 1157.</e>
<cmt>Gagakujo に(Secretary of the Bureau of Music) を追記しました。参考：http://www.albany.edu/eas/205/rank%20chart.htm</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その子の豊原利秋以降も、豊原氏は代々朝廷に仕える楽家として続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the time his child, TOYOHARA no Toshiaki, Toyohara clan became a gakunin that continued to serve the imperial court generation after generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the time of his child, TOYOHARA no Toshiaki, the Toyohara clan became gakunin that continued to serve the imperial court generation after generation.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the time of his child, TOYOHARA no Toshiaki, the Toyohara clan became gakunin that continued to serve the imperial court generation after generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tmtm(id:14181), Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>