<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>濃姫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nohime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nohime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nohime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>濃姫（のうひめ、天文 (元号)4年（1535年）？ - 慶長17年7月9日 (旧暦)（1612年8月5日）？）は、斎藤道三の娘で、織田信長の正室。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nohime (July 7, 1535-August 5, 1612), was the daughter of Dosan SAITO and lawful wife of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nohime (July 7, 1535-August 5, 1612), was the daughter of Dosan SAITO and lawful wife of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nohime (1535 - August 5, 1612), was the daughter of Dosan SAITO and lawful wife of Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>日付修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諱は江戸時代に成立した『美濃国諸旧記』などから帰蝶（きちょう）とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Mino no Kuni Shokyuki&quot; (the Chronicle of Mino Province) which was compiled during the Edo period, and other sources, Kicho was apparently her posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>『美濃国諸旧記』は「みののくに しょきゅうき」と読んでいます。 http://porta.ndl.go.jp/service/servlet/Result_Detail?meta_item_no=I000147356&amp;meta_repository_no=R000000008</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Mino no Kuni Shokyuki&quot; (the Chronicles of Mino Province) which was compiled during the Edo period, and other sources, Kicho was apparently her posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Mino no Kuni Shokyuki&quot; (the Chronicles of Mino Province) which was compiled during the Edo period, and other sources, Kicho was apparently her posthumous name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名称について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About her name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About her name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About her name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>「鷺山殿」と呼ばれていたと『美濃国諸旧記』に記されているが、彼女は岐阜城で生まれ育っていると推測されており、「稲葉山城」がこの当時「井口城」「金華山城」と呼ばれていたことからして「井口殿」「金華山殿」などと呼ばれていたとの推測も可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is noted in &quot;Mino no Kuni Shokyuki&quot; that she was known as &quot;Sagiyama-dono,&quot; but it is also possible to speculate that she was known as &quot;Iguchi-dono&quot; or &quot;Kinka-dono&quot; because it is understood that she was born and raised in Gifu-jo Castle, which was also called the &quot;Inabayama-jo Castle,&quot; had the nicknames including &quot;Iguchi-jo Castle&quot; and &quot;Kinkayama-jo Castle&quot; at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is noted in &quot;Mino no Kuni Shokyuki&quot; that she was known as &quot;Sagiyama-dono,&quot; but it is also possible to speculate that she was known as &quot;Iguchi-dono&quot; or &quot;Kinka-dono,&quot; because it is understood that she was born and raised in Gifu-jo Castle, which was also called &quot;Inabayama-jo Castle,&quot; and had nicknames including &quot;Iguchi-jo Castle&quot; and &quot;Kinkayama-jo Castle&quot; at the time.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is noted in &quot;Mino no Kuni Shokyuki&quot; that she was known as &apos;Sagiyama-dono,&apos; but it is also possible to speculate that she was known as &apos;Iguchi-dono&apos; or &apos;Kinka-dono,&apos; because it is understood that she was born and raised in Gifu-jo Castle, which was also called &apos;Inabayama-jo Castle,&apos; and had nicknames including &apos;Iguchi-jo Castle&apos; and &apos;Kinkayama-jo Castle&apos; at the time.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、輿入れ前の天文17年（1548年）に父・斎藤道三が鷺山城を隠居所として移り住んでおり、濃姫と同腹の弟と考えられている斎藤孫四郎と斎藤喜平次も稲葉山城に居住していなかった事が明らかであるため、濃姫も道三と共に鷺山城に移り住んだ可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it is also possible that she had moved into Sagiyama Castle in 1548 with her father Dosan SAITO who used the castle as his retreat for his old age because it is also clear that Nohime and Magoshiro SAITO and Kiheiji SAITO, who are considered to be her younger brothers, lived at Inabayama Castle at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it is also possible that she moved into Sagiyama Castle in 1548 with her father Dosan SAITO who used the castle as his retreat for his old age, because it is also clear that Nohime and Magoshiro SAITO and Kiheiji SAITO, who are considered to be her younger brothers, lived at Inabayama Castle at the time.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it is also possible that she moved into Sagiyama-jo Castle before her marriage in 1548 with her father Dosan SAITO who used the castle as his retreat for his old age, because it is also clear that Nohime and Magoshiro SAITO and Kiheiji SAITO, who are considered to be her younger brothers, lived at Inabayama-jo Castle at the time.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その場合「鷺山殿」と呼ばれるのは妥当である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If that was the case, it is only appropriate for her to be called &quot;Sagiyama-dono.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If that was the case, it is only appropriate for her to be called &quot;Sagiyama-dono.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If that was the case, it is only appropriate for her to be called &apos;Sagiyama-dono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、稲葉山城に引き続き居住していたとしても、両親の住む鷺山城から輿入れの出立をしたとも考えられ、それにちなんで「鷺山殿」と呼ばれたと考えれば辻褄が合う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, it makes sense for her to be called &quot;Sagiyama-dono&quot; because it is also possible that her marriage procession departed from Sagiyama Castle where her parents lived even after she continued to live at Inabayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another possible reason it would make sense for her to be called &quot;Sagiyama-dono&quot; is that her marriage procession may have departed from Sagiyama Castle where her parents lived even after she continued to live at Inabayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another possible reason it would make sense for her to be called &apos;Sagiyama-dono&apos; is that her marriage procession may have departed from Sagiyama-jo Castle where her parents lived even after she continued to live at Inabayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、単に父・道三の居城にちなんで呼ばれたという可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there is a possibility that she was simply called &quot;Sagiyama-dono&quot; after her father Dosan&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is a possibility that she was simply called &quot;Sagiyama-dono&quot; after her father Dosan&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is a possibility that she was simply called &apos;Sagiyama-dono&apos; after her father Dosan&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>「濃姫」という通称は「美濃国出身の高貴な女性」という意味であり、結婚後のものとされるが、後世作られたものという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her common &quot;Nohime&quot; means &quot;a woman of high class from Mino Province&quot; and it is believed that she went by the common name after she married, but there is a theory that the name was given in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her common &quot;Nohime&quot; means &quot;a woman of high class from Mino Province&quot; and it is believed that she went by the common name after she married, but there is a theory that the name was given in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her common &apos;Nohime&apos; means &apos;a woman of high class from Mino Province&apos; and it is believed that she went by the common name after she married, but there is a theory that the name was given in later years.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>父は斎藤道三で、母は明智光継の娘・小見の方。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was Dosan SAITO and her mother was Ominokata, the daughter of Mitsutsugu AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>「小見の方」は「こみのかた」 http://www.gifucvb.or.jp/nobunaga/index.php?ID=14 「光継」は「みつつぐ」と読んでいます</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was Dosan SAITO and her mother was Ominokata, the daughter of Mitsutsugu AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was Dosan SAITO and her mother was Ominokata, the daughter of Mitsutsugu AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>明智光秀とは従兄妹同士という説があるが、光秀自身の前半生が不明であるため確定は出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that she and Mitsuhide AKECHI were cousins to each other, but it cannot be determined because the first half of the life of Mitsuhide remains unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that she and Mitsuhide AKECHI were cousins to each other, but it cannot be determined because the first half of the life of Mitsuhide remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that she and Mitsuhide AKECHI were cousins to each other, but it cannot be determined because the first half of the life of Mitsuhide remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>一般には、知的で気性のしっかりした女性であり、従順な妻という意味とは別の意味で、信長にとって良き妻であったとのイメージがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, she is considered to be an intelligent and composed woman and served as a good wife for Nobunaga, but not necessarily an obedient one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, she is considered to be an intelligent and composed woman and to have served as a good wife for Nobunaga, but she was not necessarily an obedient one.</e>
<cmt>added key words</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, she is considered to be an intelligent and composed woman and to have served as a good wife for Nobunaga, but she was not necessarily an obedient one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これはおそらく山岡荘八の小説の影響であると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This image on her apparently became widespread because of a novel by Sohachi YAMAOKA.</e>
<cmt>「小説」は１冊だと推測しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This image of her apparently became widespread because of a novel by Sohachi YAMAOKA.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This image of her apparently became widespread because of a novel by Sohachi YAMAOKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、信長は夫婦別居した部下を叱ったり、羽柴秀吉夫妻の喧嘩に仲裁に出たりと、家庭における妻の内助の役割を高く評価していた言動が多いものの、実際の彼の妻である濃姫の史料は極めて乏しく、その実像には謎が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Nobunaga appreciated highly of his wife&apos;s supportive role at home as she reprimanded a vassal who lived apart from his wife and tried to mediate in an argument between Hideyoshi HASHIBA and his wife, but much of her real character remains obscure because there are hardly any records about Nohime as Nobunaga&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Nobunaga highly appreciated his wife&apos;s supportive role at home as she reprimanded a vassal who lived apart from his wife and tried to mediate in an argument between Hideyoshi HASHIBA and his wife, but much of her real character remains obscure because there are hardly any records about Nohime as Nobunaga&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Nobunaga highly appreciated his wife&apos;s supportive role at home as she reprimanded a vassal who lived apart from his wife and tried to mediate in an argument between Hideyoshi HASHIBA and his wife, but much of her real character remains obscure because there are hardly any records about Nohime as Nobunaga&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>天文18年2月24日 (旧暦)（1549年3月23日）に政略結婚で信長に嫁いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She married Nobunaga as a matter of political strategy on March 23, 1549.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She married Nobunaga as a matter of political strategy on March 23, 1549.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She married Nobunaga as a matter of political strategy on March 23, 1549.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>二人の間には子ができなかったというのが通説だが、信長の子供は生母不明の者が多く、本当に子がいなかったかどうかは確認できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly viewed that she bore him no children, but there is no way to confirm whether they really had none because many of the biological mothers of Nobunaga&apos;s children were unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly viewed that she bore him no children, but there is no way to confirm whether they really had none, because the biological mothers of many of Nobunaga&apos;s children were unknown.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly viewed that she bore him no children, but there is no way to confirm whether they really had none, because the biological mothers of many of Nobunaga&apos;s children were unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>二人の間に娘のいる家系図が残っていたり、御台出産記事のある文献もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a genealogy that shows that they had a daughter and literature that she gave birth.</e>
<cmt>「御台」とは濃姫だと推測していまs。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are a genealogy that shows that they had a daughter and literature that she gave birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a genealogy that shows that they had a daughter and literature that she gave birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>ただし、一次資料ではないため無視されているというのが現状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But currently, these data are disregarded because they are not of primary sources.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But currently, these data are disregarded because they are not of primary sources.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But currently, these data are disregarded because they are not of primary sources.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>前述のようにその人物像は不明で、織田家に嫁いだ後の消息は早世説・離婚説など諸説に分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her character remains obscure as described earlier, and there are various theories about her life after she married into the ODA clan, with one theory saying she died young and the other saying she divorced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her character remains obscure as described earlier, and there are various theories about her life after she married into the ODA clan, with one theory saying she died young and another saying she divorced.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her character remains obscure as described earlier, and there are various theories about her life after she married into the Oda clan, with one theory saying she died young and another saying she divorced.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>本能寺の変の際に薙刀を振るって夫・信長とともに敵兵と戦って戦死したという説もあるが、歴史小説などで用いられているこの本能寺での死亡説の信憑性は低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is even a theory that says she died during the Honno-ji Incident as she took up the naginata halberd and fought the enemy forces with her husband Nobunaga, but the credibility of the theory that says that she died at Honno-ji Temple, the situation which has been used in historical novels and other forms of entertainment, is low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is even a theory that says she died during the Honno-ji Incident as she took up the naginata halberd and fought the enemy forces with her husband Nobunaga, but the theory that says that she died at Honno-ji Temple, the situation which has been used in historical novels and other forms of entertainment, has low credibility.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is even a theory that says she died during the Honno-ji Incident as she took up the naginata halberd and fought the enemy forces with her husband Nobunaga, but the theory that says that she died at Honno-ji Temple, the situation which has been used in historical novels and other forms of entertainment, has low credibility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>一説に、濃姫（帰蝶）の生存を示すのではないかと考えられる史料として、信長が美濃を制圧した時期である永禄12年（1569年）の『言継卿記』に斎藤家親族の「信長本妻」の記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory says that &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki,&quot; which was compiled in 1569 when Nobunaga conquered Mino Province, could show Nohime (Kicho) was alive because there is an entry in the diary that says that she was &quot;the lawful wife of Nobunaga&quot; of the SAITO family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory says that &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki,&quot; which was compiled in 1569 when Nobunaga conquered Mino Province, could show that Nohime (Kicho) was alive, because there is an entry in the diary that says that she was &quot;the lawful wife of Nobunaga&quot; of the SAITO family.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory says that &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki,&quot; which was compiled in 1569 when Nobunaga conquered Mino Province, could show that Nohime (Kicho) was alive, because there is an entry in the diary that says that she was &apos;the lawful wife of Nobunaga&apos; of the Saito family.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>『近江國輿地志』にも、信長と御台所が共に成菩提寺に止宿したと言う記述もあり、おそらく永禄11年（1568年）頃の記述と思われ、前述の『言継卿記』の記事の前年である事から帰蝶の事と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, there is an entry in &quot;Omi no Kuni Kochi-shi&quot; that says that Nobunaga and his wife stayed at Jobodai-ji Temple, and this &quot;wife&quot; is believed to be Kicho because it is also believed that the entry was written in 1568, the year before the above-mentioned entry from &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「近江國輿地志」の読みが確認できませんでしたが、「おおみのくに・こうちし」と読んでいます。「成菩提寺」は「じょうぼだいじ」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there is an entry in &quot;Omi no Kuni Kochi-shi&quot; that says that Nobunaga and his wife stayed at Jobodai-ji Temple, and this &quot;wife&quot; is believed to be Kicho, because it is also believed that the entry was written in 1568, the year before the above-mentioned entry from &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there is an entry in &quot;Omi no Kuni Kochi-shi&quot; that says that Nobunaga and his wife stayed at Jobodai-ji Temple, and this &quot;wife&quot; is believed to be Kicho, because it is also believed that the entry was written in 1568, the year before the above-mentioned entry from &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>なお当該記事には、御台出産が書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the applicable article mentions that Nobunaga&apos;s wife gave birth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the applicable article mentions that Nobunaga&apos;s wife gave birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the applicable article mentions that Nobunaga&apos;s wife gave birth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また『勢州軍記』には、信長の御台所である斎藤道三の娘に若君が生まれなかったため側室が生んだ織田信忠（幼名、奇妙または奇妙丸）を養子とし嫡男とした、などの記述も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And an entry and other information from &quot;Seishu Gunki&quot; say that Nobunaga&apos;s wife, who was the daughter of Dosan SAITO, bore him no children and that Nobutada ODA, who was given birth by one of Nobunaga&apos;s concubine, was adopted so that Nobunaga could make him the legitimate son.</e>
<cmt>「勢州軍記」は「せいしゅうぐんき」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And an entry and other information from &quot;Seishu Gunki&quot; say that Nobunaga&apos;s wife, who was the daughter of Dosan SAITO, bore him no children and that Nobutada ODA, who was born from one of Nobunaga&apos;s concubines, was adopted so that Nobunaga could make him the legitimate son.</e>
<cmt>verb</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And an entry and other information from &quot;Seishu Gunki&quot; say that Nobunaga&apos;s wife, who was the daughter of Dosan SAITO, bore him no children and that Nobutada ODA (his childhood name was Kimyo or Kimyomaru), who was born from one of Nobunaga&apos;s concubines, was adopted so that Nobunaga could make him the legitimate son.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また『明智軍記』にも尾張平定後の饗膳の際に、信長内室（正室の濃姫）が美濃討伐の命令を望む家臣達に感謝し、家臣達にたくさんのあわびなどを振舞ったという記載がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in &quot;Akechi Gunki&quot; (biography of Mitsuhide AKECHI), there is an entry that says that Nobunaga&apos;s wife (Nohime, the lawful wife) treated his vassals with many avalons and other delicacies at a banquet held after the suppression of Owari Province to express gratitude for their support for the order of the suppression of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in &quot;Akechi Gunki&quot; (biography of Mitsuhide AKECHI), there is an entry that says that Nobunaga&apos;s wife (Nohime, the lawful wife) treated his vassals with many avalons and other delicacies at a banquet held after the suppression of Owari Province to express gratitude for their support for the order of the suppression of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in &quot;Akechi Gunki&quot; (biography of Mitsuhide AKECHI), there is an entry that says that Nobunaga&apos;s wife (Nohime, the lawful wife) treated his vassals with many avalons and other delicacies at a banquet held after the suppression of Owari Province to express gratitude for their support for the order of the suppression of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>『明智軍記』は元禄年間（最古の元版は1693年版）の幕府作成のものであるので、史実と異なる点や歪曲している点なども多くみられるが、少なくとも作成時の段階では一般的に濃姫は尾張平定後も信長の正室として存在しており、道三亡き後濃姫が離縁された、亡くなったというような事実はなかった、という認識だったのではないかと推測できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because &quot;Akechi Gunki&quot; was compiled by the Shogunate in sometime between 1688 and 1703 (with the oldest original edition published in 1693), there are many entries that are different from historical facts and fabricated, however, it can be assumed that it had been generally understood, at least at the time when the biography was compiled, that Nohime remained to be Nobunaga&apos;s lawful wife after the suppression of Owari Province and that there were no facts that she died or she was divorced after Dosan died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because &quot;Akechi Gunki&quot; was compiled by the Shogunate sometime between 1688 and 1703 (with the oldest original edition published in 1693), there are many entries that are different from historical facts and fabricated; however, it can be assumed that it had been generally understood, at least at the time when the biography was compiled, that Nohime remained Nobunaga&apos;s lawful wife after the suppression of Owari Province and that there were no facts that she died or she was divorced after Dosan died.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because &quot;Akechi Gunki&quot; was compiled by the Shogunate sometime between 1688 and 1703 (with the oldest original edition published in 1693), there are many entries that are different from historical facts and fabricated; however, it can be assumed that it had been generally understood, at least at the time when the biography was compiled, that Nohime remained Nobunaga&apos;s lawful wife after the suppression of Owari Province and that there were no facts that she died or she was divorced after Dosan died.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>『織田信雄分限帳』に「安土殿」という女性が、600貫文の知行を与えられているのが記載されており、女性としては信雄正室、徳姫に続き三番目に記載され、土田御前と推測される「大方殿様」よりも先に記載されている事、安土城の「安土」という土地を冠されている事から、織田家における地位の高さがうかがえ、織田信雄の亡き父・信長の正室にあたるのではないかとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there is an entry in &quot;ODA Nobukatsu Gungencho&quot; (registers of vassals of Nobukatsu ODA) that says that a woman called &quot;Azuchi-dono&quot; was given chigyo fief worth 600 kanmon, and that she was listed third in the order of female vassals following Nobukatsu&apos;s lawful wife and Tokuhime, and that she was listed prior to &quot;Okatadono-sama,&quot; who is believed to be Dota-gozen, and that her name included &quot;Azuchi&quot; from Azuchi-jo Castle, it can be assumed that she retained a prominent position in the ODA family and she could be the lawful wife of Nobunaga, the deceased father of Nobukatsu ODA.</e>
<cmt>「織田信雄分限帳」は書名のため、姓名の順番はそのままにしています。「大方殿様」は「おおかたどのさま」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there is an entry in &quot;ODA Nobukatsu Gungencho&quot; (registers of vassals of Nobukatsu ODA) that says that a woman called &quot;Azuchi-dono&quot; was given chigyo fief worth 600 kanmon, that she was listed third in the order of female vassals following Nobukatsu&apos;s lawful wife and Tokuhime, that she was listed prior to &quot;Okatadono-sama,&quot; who is believed to be Dota-gozen, and that her name included &quot;Azuchi&quot; from Azuchi-jo Castle, it can be assumed that she retained a prominent position in the ODA family and she could be the lawful wife of Nobunaga, the deceased father of Nobukatsu ODA.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there is an entry in &quot;ODA Nobukatsu Bungencho&quot; (registers of vassals of Nobukatsu ODA) that says that a woman called &apos;Azuchi-dono&apos; was given chigyo fief worth 600 kanmon, that she was listed third in the order of female vassals following Nobukatsu&apos;s lawful wife and Tokuhime, that she was listed prior to &apos;Okatadono-sama,&apos; who is believed to be Dota-gozen, and that her name included &apos;Azuchi&apos; from Azuchi-jo Castle, it can be assumed that she retained a prominent position in the Oda family and she could be the lawful wife of Nobunaga, the deceased father of Nobukatsu ODA.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。記号を修正しました。人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>「局」が「妻子の居住する空間」を示すことから、奥でもっとも権威のあった正室を「御局」と称したとも考えられ、『織田信雄分限帳』に記載されているもっとも知行の多い「御局」が濃姫という可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the word &quot;tsubone&quot; means a space where a wife and her children live, it can be assumed that the lawful life was called &quot;Mitsubone&quot; because she was the most authoritative person in the inner hall of a castle, and that the &quot;Mitsubone&quot; who was given more chigyo fief than anyone else among those listed in &quot;ODA Nobukatsu Bungencho&quot; was Nohime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the word &quot;tsubone&quot; means a space where a wife and her children live, it can be assumed that the lawful life was called &quot;Mitsubone&quot; reflecting her status as the most authoritative person in the inner hall of a castle, and that the &quot;Mitsubone&quot; who was given more chigyo fief than anyone else among those listed in &quot;ODA Nobukatsu Bungencho&quot; was Nohime.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the word &apos;tsubone&apos; means &apos;a space where a wife and her children live,&apos; it can be assumed that the lawful life was called &apos;Mitsubone&apos; reflecting her status as the most authoritative person in the inner hall of a castle, and that the &apos;Mitsubone&apos; who was given more chigyo fief than anyone else among those listed in &quot;ODA Nobukatsu Bungencho&quot; was Nohime.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>また、信雄から見て父信長の正室である濃姫は、「大方殿様」の立場にあたる為、「大方殿様」が濃姫ではないと裏付ける史料がない以上、「大方殿様」を「土田御前」と決めつけることも早計である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, it would be premature to conclude that the &quot;Okatadono-sama&quot; was actually &quot;Dota-gozen,&quot; due to the fact that Nohime herself was regarded as &quot;Okatadono-sama&quot; because she was the lawful wife of Nobukatsu&apos;s father Nobunaga, and that there are no historical materials that can prove Nohime was not &quot;Okatadono-sama.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it would be premature to conclude that the &quot;Okatadono-sama&quot; was actually &quot;Dota-gozen,&quot; due to the fact that Nohime herself was regarded as &quot;Okatadono-sama&quot; because she was the lawful wife of Nobukatsu&apos;s father Nobunaga, and that there are no historical materials that can prove Nohime was not &quot;Okatadono-sama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it would be premature to conclude that the &apos;Okatadono-sama&apos; was actually &apos;Dota-gozen,&apos; due to the fact that Nohime herself was regarded as &apos;Okatadono-sama&apos; because she was the lawful wife of Nobukatsu&apos;s father Nobunaga, and that there are no historical materials that can prove Nohime was not &apos;Okatadono-sama.&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>『氏郷記』『総見院殿追善記』などには本能寺の変直後、安土城から落ち延びた信長妻子の中に「御台所」「北の方」の記述が見られ、安土殿（または御局）と同一人物とも推測できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Ujisato-ki,&quot; &quot;Sokenin-dono Tsuizen-ki&quot; and other materials, there are entries that the &quot;Midaidokoro,&quot; or the Shogun&apos;s wife, and &quot;Kitanokata&quot; were included in those who fled the Azuchi-jo Castle following the Honnoji Incident with Nobunaga&apos;s wife and children, so it can be assumed that Nohime was the same person as Azuchi-dono (or Mitsubone).</e>
<cmt>「氏郷記」は「うじさとき」、「総見院殿追善記」は「そうけんいんどのついぜんき」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Ujisato-ki,&quot; &quot;Sokenin-dono Tsuizen-ki&quot; and other materials, there are entries that the &quot;Midaidokoro,&quot; or the Shogun&apos;s wife, and &quot;Kitanokata&quot; were included in those who fled the Azuchi-jo Castle following the Honnoji Incident with Nobunaga&apos;s wife and children, so it can be assumed that Nohime was the same person as Azuchi-dono (or Mitsubone).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Ujisato-ki,&quot; &quot;Sokenin-dono Tsuizen-ki&quot; and other materials, there are entries that the &apos;Midaidokoro,&apos; or the Shogun&apos;s wife, and &apos;Kitanokata&apos; were included in those who fled the Azuchi-jo Castle following the Honnoji Incident with Nobunaga&apos;s wife and children, so it can be assumed that Nohime was the same person as Azuchi-dono (or Mitsubone).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この「御台所」「北の方」が濃姫だったとすると、本能寺の変の翌日であることから考えて、変時に彼女が本能寺にいたとするのは時間的に無理がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If &quot;Midaidokoro&quot; and &quot;Kitanokata&quot; were Nohime, it would be physically impossible for her to be present at Honno-ji Temple at the time of Honnoji Incident given the fact that she fled the Azuchi-jo Castle the day after the incident.</e>
<cmt>「翌日」というのは、「安土城から落ち延びた」ことを指しているという理解で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If &quot;Midaidokoro&quot; and &quot;Kitanokata&quot; were Nohime, it would be physically impossible for her to be present at Honno-ji Temple at the time of the Honnoji Incident, given the fact that she fled Azuchi-jo Castle the day after the incident.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If &apos;Midaidokoro&apos; and &apos;Kitanokata&apos; were Nohime, it would be physically impossible for her to be present at Honno-ji Temple at the time of the Honnoji Incident, given the fact that she fled Azuchi-jo Castle the day after the incident.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="31">
<j>結婚後は歴史の表舞台に一切名を残さなかったせいか、病弱説や離婚説、奥を取り仕切るだけの器量がなかったなどという評価がなされる事があったが、実際は信長の閨房における醜聞が一切表に出ずきちんと取り仕切られていたことから、決して無能な女性ではなく一正室多側室多愛妾多伽係という当時の奥制度をきちんと管理出来る女性だったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because she did not earn her place in history after she married, she was often considered she was poor in health or divorced, or even incapable of managing concubines and other female attendants of the castle; in fact, it can be assumed that she was indeed an able woman who could manage the O-oku system at the time, in which a shogun had one lawful wife and many other concubines and lovers, because Nobunaga&apos;s scandals related to his bedrooms never came out and were well managed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because she did not earn her place in history after she married, it has often been considered she was poor in health or divorced, or even incapable of managing concubines and other female attendants of the castle; in fact, it can be assumed that she was indeed an able woman who could manage the O-oku system at the time, in which a shogun had one lawful wife and many other concubines and lovers, because Nobunaga&apos;s scandals related to his bedrooms never came out and were well managed.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because she did not earn her place in history after she married, it has often been considered she was poor in health or divorced, or even incapable of managing concubines and other female attendants of the castle; in fact, it can be assumed that she was indeed an able woman who could manage the O-oku system at the time, in which a shogun had one lawful wife and many other concubines and lovers, because Nobunaga&apos;s scandals related to his bedrooms never came out and were well managed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="32">
<j>また婿である信長を美濃国の後継者と定めた道三の国譲状がある以上は、濃姫を正室としておくことが信長にとっても必用不可欠であった事もあり、その道三と対立した、兄・斎藤義龍筋の斎藤氏との諍いにより離縁して実家に返したという可能性は考えられず、美濃攻略を推し進めて行った背景には道三息女であり、また土岐氏の傍流明智氏の血を引く濃姫の（義龍が道三実子であった場合、土岐氏と血縁関係はない事になる）、婿である信長こそ正統な美濃の後継者であるという大義名分があったためという推測も成り立つこと、美濃攻略後に美濃衆が尾張衆と同様に待遇されていることからも、濃姫が美濃攻略前に病気などで亡くなったという可能性もないと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can also be assumed that Nobunaga could never divorce Nohime due to a dispute with the SAITO clan led by Dosan&apos;s opposing older brother Yoshitatsu SAITO because it was essential for Nobunaga to keep Nohime as his lawful wife for he received the letter from Dosan in which Dosan appointed his son-in-law Nobunaga as successor of Mino Province, and in addition, it can be understood that Nohime did not die of sickness or some other reasons before the Capture of Mino Province because of the fact that Nohime encouraged the attack on Mino Province for she was the daughter of Dosan and was linked by blood to the AKECHI clan, a branch of the TOKI clan (however, she wouldn&apos;t be linked by blood to the TOKI clan if Yoshitatsu was actually the son of Dosan), which could give her husband Nobunaga a good reason to be the legitimate successor of Mino Province, and also that the high-ranking officials of Mino Province were treated the same way as those of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>難解な長文のため、「旗本」の説明をはぶき、「高官」として翻訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can also be assumed that Nobunaga could never divorce Nohime due to a dispute with the SAITO clan led by Dosan&apos;s opposing older brother Yoshitatsu SAITO, because it was essential for Nobunaga to keep Nohime as his lawful wife, for he received the letter from Dosan in which Dosan appointed his son-in-law Nobunaga as successor of Mino Province, and in addition, it can be understood that Nohime did not die of sickness or some other reasons before the Capture of Mino Province, in view of the fact that Nohime encouraged the attack on Mino Province for she was the daughter of Dosan and was linked by blood to the AKECHI clan, a branch of the TOKI clan (however, she wouldn&apos;t be linked by blood to the TOKI clan if Yoshitatsu was actually the son of Dosan), which could give her husband Nobunaga a good reason to be the legitimate successor of Mino Province, and also that the high-ranking officials of Mino Province were treated the same way as those of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can also be assumed that Nobunaga could never divorce Nohime due to a dispute with the Saito clan led by Dosan&apos;s opposing older brother Yoshitatsu SAITO, because it was essential for Nobunaga to keep Nohime as his lawful wife, for he received the letter from Dosan in which Dosan appointed his son-in-law Nobunaga as successor of Mino Province, and in addition, it can be understood that Nohime did not die of sickness or some other reasons before the Capture of Mino Province, in view of the fact that Nohime encouraged the attack on Mino Province for she was the daughter of Dosan and was linked by blood to the Akechi clan, a branch of the Toki clan (however, she wouldn&apos;t be linked by blood to the Toki clan if Yoshitatsu was actually the son of Dosan), which could give her husband Nobunaga a good reason to be the legitimate successor of Mino Province, and also that the high-ranking officials of Mino Province were treated the same way as those of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="33">
<j>信長嫡男の信忠は濃姫が養子にしているが、濃姫があえて信忠を養子に迎えた理由として道三の国譲状により信長の美濃支配の正当性はあるものの、斎藤氏、土岐氏の血を引く濃姫の子供が信長の嫡男であればより円滑な美濃支配と後継者の正統性を強調できるためではないかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nohime adopted Nobunaga&apos;s legitimate son Nobutada, and it is believed that Nohime went ahead to adopt Nobutada because if the child of Nohime, who was linked by blood to the SAITO and TOKI clans, was the legitimate son of Nobunaga, Mino Province could have been ruled more smoothly and the authenticity of the heir could be emphasized on top of the letter from Dosan which named Nobunaga as successor of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nohime adopted Nobunaga&apos;s legitimate son Nobutada, and it is believed that Nohime went ahead to adopt Nobutada because if the child of Nohime, who was linked by blood to the SAITO and TOKI clans, was the legitimate son of Nobunaga, Mino Province could have been ruled more smoothly and the authenticity of the heir could be emphasized on top of the letter from Dosan which named Nobunaga as successor of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nohime adopted Nobunaga&apos;s legitimate son Nobutada, and it is believed that Nohime went ahead to adopt Nobutada because if the child of Nohime, who was linked by blood to the Saito and Toki clans, was the legitimate son of Nobunaga, Mino Province could have been ruled more smoothly and the authenticity of the heir could be emphasized on top of the letter from Dosan which named Nobunaga as successor of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>事実信長は家督を信忠に譲り、美濃と尾張の支配を信忠に委ねている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Nobunaga transfered responsibility for the family to Nobutada, and left the rule of Mino and Owari to Nobutada.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="35">
<j>『妙心寺史』には、天正11年6月2日（1583年）に信長公夫人主催で一周忌を執り行った記事があり、秀吉主催とは別の一周忌法会であるため、興雲院（お鍋の方）とは別人と推測され、「安土殿（または御局）」である可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Myoshinji-shi,&quot; or the chronicle of Myoshin-ji Temple, there is an entry that says that the wife of Nobunaga organized the first year anniversary of Nobunaga&apos;s death on June 2, 1583, so it is highly possible that this was &quot;Azuchi-dono (or Mitsubone)&quot; because it was a Buddhist mass not hosted by Hideyoshi and that the &quot;wife&quot; here would not refer to Kyounin (Onabe no kata).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Myoshinji-shi,&quot; or the chronicle of Myoshin-ji Temple, there is an entry that says that the wife of Nobunaga organized the first year anniversary of Nobunaga&apos;s death on June 2, 1583, so it is highly possible that this was &quot;Azuchi-dono (or Mitsubone)&quot; because it was a Buddhist mass not hosted by Hideyoshi and that the &quot;wife&quot; here would not refer to Kyounin (Onabe no kata).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Myoshinji-shi,&quot; or the chronicle of Myoshin-ji Temple, there is an entry that says that the wife of Nobunaga organized the first year anniversary of Nobunaga&apos;s death on July 20, 1583, so it is highly possible that this was &apos;Azuchi-dono (or Mitsubone)&apos; because it was a Buddhist mass not hosted by Hideyoshi and that the &quot;wife&quot; here would not refer to Kyounin (Onabe no kata).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>「安土殿（または御局）」が彼女であった場合、慶長17年7月9日 (旧暦)（1612年7月26日）に78歳で逝去、「養華院殿要津妙玄大姉」という法名で大徳寺総見院に埋葬されている事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And if &quot;Azuchi-dono (or Mitsubone)&quot; were Nohime, it would mean that she died on July 26, 1612, at age of 78 and was buried at Soken-in Temple, which stands in the compound of Daitoku-ji Temple, under the Buddhist posthumous name of &quot;Yokainden Yoshinmyo Daishi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「養華院殿要津妙玄大姉」の読みが確認できなかったので、「ようかいんでんようしんみょうげんだいし」と仮にあてています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And if &quot;Azuchi-dono (or Mitsubone)&quot; were Nohime, it would mean that she died on July 26, 1612, at age of 78 and was buried at Soken-in Temple, which stands in the compound of Daitoku-ji Temple, under the Buddhist posthumous name of &quot;Yokainden Yoshinmyo Daishi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And if &apos;Azuchi-dono (or Mitsubone)&apos; were Nohime, it would mean that she died on July 26, 1612, at age of 78 and was buried at Soken-in Temple, which stands in the compound of Daitoku-ji Temple, under the Buddhist posthumous name of &apos;Yokainden Yoshinmyo Daishi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Nobunobunaga(id:117457), Izayohi(id:13095), Makuin-goo(id:94937), Albambot(id:195288), Carbuncle(id:346), Reggaeman(id:6214), Cprobot(id:97843), Wankowanko(id:183521), MIO(id:31681), Daranome(id:1429), Doskoi 8(id:1070), Kamakura(id:472), Kichyou(id:19769), 蚯蚓(id:254651), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), 鞆(id:61733), Samanosuke(id:60695), MioUzaki(id:89034), Nnn(id:26535), ゐ(id:795), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), R28Bot(id:177951), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Pion(id:18787), こぶまき(id:38278), 満月(id:82772), Louperibot(id:128971), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>