<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平好風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoshikaze</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Yoshikaze</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoshikaze</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 好風（たいら の よしかぜ、生没年不詳）は、平安時代中期の人物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoshikaze (date of birth and death unknown) was a man in the mid Heian period of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Yoshikaze (dates of birth and death unknown) was a man in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>複数化、of Japanを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoshikaze (year of birth and death unknown) was a man in the mid Heian period.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに従い、year of birth and death unknownとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>従四位下、近衛府。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikaze was appointed to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikaze was appointed Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>to削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikaze was appointed Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in Konoefu (the Headquarters of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>桓武天皇の子・仲野親王の子・刑部省加賀国茂世王の長子であり、貞観 (日本)16年（874年）に臣籍降下して平氏を名乗るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikaze was the oldest son of TAIRA no Shigeyo (Prince Shigeyo) in Gyobusho (Ministry of Justice) of Kaga province, who was a son of Imperial Prince Nakano, who was a son of Emperor Kammu, and Yoshikaze demoted from nobility to subject in 874 and called himself one of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikaze was the oldest son of Prince Shigeyo in Gyobusho (Ministry of Justice) of Kaga province, who was a son of Imperial Prince Nakano, who was a son of Emperor Kammu, and Yoshikaze demoted from the Imperial family to a subject in 874 and called himself one of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせTAIRA no Shigeyo を削除、用語統一とは異なりますが「臣籍降下」を変更、冠詞挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikaze was the oldest son of Prince Shigeyo in Gyobusho (Ministry of Justice) of Kaga province, who was a son of Imperial Prince Nakano, who was a son of Emperor Kammu, and Yoshikaze demoted from the Imperial family to a subject in 874 and called himself one of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 味っ子(id:17086), Snow rabbit(id:95634), Andee(id:20421), 松茸(id:27535), Flatbarker(id:119836), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>