<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>音阿弥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>音阿弥（おんあみ、またはおんなみ 応永5年（1398年）- 文正2年（1467年）1月2日）は室町時代の猿楽能役者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onami (Onnami) (1398-February 6, 1467) was the sarugakuno actor (actor for sarugaku (comical mimicry and speech performance in Heian period of theatre popular in Japan during the eleventh to fourteenth centuries) of Noh (traditional masked dance-drama)) of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onami (Onnami) (1398-February 6, 1467) was a sarugakuno actor (actor for sarugaku (comical mimicry and speech performance in the Heian period of theatre popular in Japan during the eleventh to fourteenth centuries) of Noh (traditional masked dance-drama)) of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onami (Onnami) (1398 - February 15, 1467) was a sarugakuno actor (actor for sarugaku (form of theatre popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries) of Noh (traditional masked dance-drama)) of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>1398-February 6, 1467 を1398 - February 15, 1467 に修正しました。comical mimicry and speech performance in the Heian period of theatre popular in Japan during the eleventh to fourteenth centuries をform of theatre popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries に修正しました。Period をperiod に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>観世三郎元重。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also called as Saburo-motoshige KANZE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also called Saburo-motoshige KANZE.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;as&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also called Saburo-motoshige KANZE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>観阿弥の孫、世阿弥の甥に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the grandson of Kanami and the nephew of Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the grandson of Kanami and the nephew of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the grandson of Kanami and the nephew of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>三世観世大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the third Dayu KANZE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the third Dayu KANZE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the third Kanze-dayu.</e>
<cmt>Dayu KANZE をKanze-dayu に修正しました。※人名ではないため、上記の表記が適当かと思われます。出典：http://books.google.com/books?id=ux89AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA101&amp;dq=Kanze+dayu&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;hl=ja&amp;cd=11#v=onepage&amp;q=Kanze%20dayu&amp;f=false</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>足利義教の絶大な支援の下、世阿弥父子を圧倒し、70年近い生涯を第一人者として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the very strong support from Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, he became more powerful than the Zeami father and child and became active as a head actor almost throughout all seventy years of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under very strong support from Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, he became more powerful than Zeami and his child and became active as a head actor throughout almost the entire seventy years of his life.</e>
<cmt>rewording&quot;Zeami father and child&quot; seems to refer to Zeami and his child, Motomasa</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under very strong support from Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, he became more powerful than Zeami and his child and became active as a head actor throughout almost the entire seventy years of his life.</e>
<cmt>check 欄に記載されていた&quot;Zeami father and child&quot; seems to refer to Zeami and his child, Motomasa をG列のコメント欄に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>世阿弥の女婿・金春禅竹らとともに一時代を担い、他の芸能を押しのけて猿楽能が芸界の主流となる道を作って、祖父観阿弥、伯父世阿弥が築いた観世流を発展されることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked along with Zenchiku KONPARU, who was the son-in-law of Zeami, and laid a path to ensure Sarugakuno as the main art by pushing aside other arts, and developed the Kanze school established by his grandfather Kanami and uncle Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked along with Zenchiku KONPARU, who was the son-in-law of Zeami, and laid a path to ensure Sarugakuno as the main art form by pushing aside other art forms, and developed the Kanze school established by his grandfather Kanami and uncle Zeami.</e>
<cmt>added &apos;form&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked along with Zenchiku KONPARU, who was the son-in-law of Zeami, and laid a path to ensure Sarugakuno as the main art form by pushing aside other art forms, and developed the Kanze school established by his grandfather Kanami and uncle Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>その芸は連歌師心敬に「今の世の最一の上手といへる音阿弥」と評されたのを初め、同時代の諸書に「当道の名人」「希代の上手、当道に無双」などと絶賛され、役者としては世阿弥以上の達人であったと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His performance was highly regarded as &apos;Onami who could be said as the best of the present day&apos; by renga poet (linked-verse poet) Shinkei of the same period as well as being referred as &apos;the skilled in his path&apos; or &apos;the skilled performer unlike others&apos; by many manuscripts of that time and could be interpreted as the expert who surpassed Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His performance was highly regarded; &apos;Onami who could be said to be the best of the present day&apos; wrong renga poet (linked-verse poet) Shinkei of the same period, and many manuscripts of that time called him &apos;skilled in his path&apos; or &apos;a skilled performer unlike others&apos;; Onami could be interpreted as the expert who surpassed Zeami.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His performance was highly regarded; &apos;Onami who could be said to be the best of the present day&apos; described by a renga poet (linked-verse poet) Shinkei of the same period, and many manuscripts of that time called him &apos;skilled in his path&apos; or &apos;a skilled performer unlike others&apos;; Onami could be interpreted as the expert who surpassed Zeami.</e>
<cmt>wrong をdescribed by a に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>世阿弥の養子に</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being Adopted by Zeami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adoption by Zeami</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adoption by Zeami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>実父は世阿弥の弟四郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His biological father was Shiro, who was the younger brother of Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His biological father was Shiro, who was the younger brother of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His biological father was Shiro, who was the younger brother of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この四郎については詳しい来歴は知れず、諱も清信とする後代の伝書、元仲とする近世の系図、久次とする説など一致を見ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not well known about the background of this Shiro, and there is a mismatch between imina (personal name) of Kiyonobu claimed by the manuscript passed down generations, Motonaka claimed by the recent genealogy, and the thoery that stated him as Kyuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Little is known about the background of this Shiro, and there is a mismatch between the imina (personal name) of Kiyonobu claimed by the manuscript passed down generations, Motonaka claimed by the recent genealogy, and the theory that stated him to be Kyuji.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Little is known about the background of this Shiro, and there is a mismatch between the imina (personal name) of Kiyonobu claimed by the manuscript passed down generations, Motonaka claimed by the recent genealogy, and the theory that stated him to be Kyuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>世阿弥・音阿弥という天才の間に埋もれた「殆ど見るべきものの無い存在」と見る向きもあったが、世阿弥から著書『風姿花伝』を相伝されたことが分かっており、最近では観世座の脇之仕手として兄を支えて大夫にも匹敵する活躍をしていた人物と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a view that he was the &apos;existence that cannot be seen often&apos; between geniuses Zeami and Onami, but it was known that he inherited &quot;Fushikaden&quot; (The Flowering Spirit) written by Zeami and is believed in recent days as an assistant who supported the older brother as waki no shite (beside-the-doer role) of Kanze-za (Kanze guild) similar to a standard of a dayu (master).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a view that he was the &apos;existence that cannot be seen often&apos; between geniuses Zeami and Onami, but it was known that he inherited &quot;Fushikaden&quot; (The Flowering Spirit) written by Zeami and in recent days it is believed that he served as an assistant who supported the older brother as waki no shite (beside-the-doer role) of Kanze-za (Kanze guild) similar to a standard of a dayu (master).</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a view that he was the &apos;existence that cannot be seen often&apos; between geniuses Zeami and Onami, but it was known that he inherited &quot;Fushikaden&quot; (The Flowering Spirit) written by Zeami and in recent days it is believed that he served as an assistant who supported the older brother as waki no shite (beside-the-doer role) of Kanze-za (Kanze guild) similar to a standard of a dayu (master).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>子の大成後はそのワキも務めたようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child also fulfilled his duties as the side-role after reaching maturity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After reaching maturity, his child also fulfilled his duties in the side-role.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After reaching maturity, his child also fulfilled his duties in the side-role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>音阿弥の少年時代については不明だが、「三郎」の通称は祖父の観阿弥、伯父の世阿弥も使用したものであり、これを継承していることから、幼くして伯父・世阿弥の養嗣子になっていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unclear about the teenage days of Onami but could be interpreted that he was adopted by his uncle Zeami at young age since he inherited the alias &apos;Saburo&apos; was used by his grandfather Kanami and uncle Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Little is clear about the teenage days of Onami, but it could be interpreted that he was adopted by his uncle Zeami at a young age, since the alias he inherited, &apos;Saburo,&apos; was also used by his grandfather Kanami and uncle Zeami.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Little is clear about the teenage days of Onami, but it could be interpreted that he was adopted by his uncle Zeami at a young age, since the alias he inherited, &apos;Saburo,&apos; was also used by his grandfather Kanami and uncle Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>間もなく世阿弥には実子の観世元雅が生まれるが、音阿弥の元服に際してこの「三郎」の名を与えたことからも分かるように、世阿弥は観世座の後継者として音阿弥を考えていた時期があると思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after, Zeami sired a real son, Motomasa KANZE, but he gave the name of &apos;Saburo&apos; to Onami when he underwent Genpuku (Coming of Age Ceremony) and it was the time when Zeami considered Onami as the successor to the Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after, Zeami sired a real son, Motomasa KANZE, but he gave the name &apos;Saburo&apos; to Onami upon his Genpuku (Coming of Age Ceremony) and at this time Zeami considered Onami to be the successor to the Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after, Zeami sired a real son, Motomasa KANZE, but he gave the name &apos;Saburo&apos; to Onami upon his Genpuku (Coming of Age Ceremony) and at this time Zeami considered Onami to be the successor to the Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>その期待に応えて成長した音阿弥は、20代前半の応永20年代からその活動記録があり、若くして観世座の次世代の担い手として活躍を始めていたことが分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onami, who grew up under such expectations, had records of his activities when he was in early twenties in around 1413 and started participating while young as the next generation successor of Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onami, who grew up under such expectations, had records of his activities when he was in his early twenties around 1413, and while young he starting participating as the next-generation successor of the Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onami, who grew up under such expectations, had records of his activities when he was in his early twenties around 1413, and while young he started participating as the next-generation successor of the Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt>starting participating をstarted participating に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>観世大夫へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To Dayu KANZE (Kanze Master)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To Dayu KANZE (Kanze Master)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To Kanze-dayu (Kanze Master)</e>
<cmt>Dayu KANZE をKanze-dayu に修正しました。※人名ではないため、上記の表記が適当かと思われます。出典：http://books.google.com/books?id=ux89AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA101&amp;dq=Kanze+dayu&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;hl=ja&amp;cd=11#v=onepage&amp;q=Kanze%20dayu&amp;f=false</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>しかしながら、応永29年(1422年)、観世大夫の地位を受け継いだのはいとこの元雅であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the one who inherited the position of Dayu KANZE in 1422 was his cousin, Motomasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the one who inherited the position of Dayu KANZE in 1422 was his cousin, Motomasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the one who inherited the position of Kanze-dayu in 1422 was his cousin, Motomasa.</e>
<cmt>Dayu KANZE をKanze-dayu に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかしこの頃世阿弥父子はその創作活動の充実と反比例するように、田楽の増阿弥などに圧され、将軍家の寵を失いつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the father and child Zeami started to stray away from creative activities and was suppressed by Zoami of dengaku (a style of dancing and music performed in association with rice planting) and bagan to lose favor from the shogunke (Shogun family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Zeami and Motomasa started to stray away from creative activities and were suppressed by Zoami of dengaku (a style of dancing and music performed in association with rice planting) and they began to lose favor from the shogunke (Shogun family).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Zeami and Motomasa started to stray away from creative activities and were suppressed by Zoami of dengaku (a style of dancing and music performed in association with rice planting) and they began to lose favor from the shogunke (Shogun family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>一方で音阿弥は青蓮院門跡義円の寵愛を受け、応永34年（1427年）には義円の後援の元で勧進猿楽を行い、成功を収めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Onami was favored by Shoren-in Monzeki Gien (head priest of Shoren-in temple) and successfully performed kanjin (temple solicitation) sarugaku (form of theatre popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries) with the support of Gien in 1427.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Onami was favored by Shoren-in Monzeki Gien (head priest of Shoren-in temple) and successfully performed kanjin (temple solicitation) sarugaku (a form of theatre popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries) with the support of Gien in 1427.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Onami was favored by Shoren-in Monzeki Gien (head priest of Shoren-in temple) and successfully performed kanjin (temple solicitation) sarugaku (a form of theatre popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th centuries) with the support of Gien in 1427.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>正長2年(1429年)、この義円が還俗して将軍・足利義教となったことで、観世座の運命は大きく変わることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Gien returned to the secular life to become the Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA in 1429 that the destiny of Kanze guild greatly changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Gien returned to secular life to become the Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA in 1429, at which point the destiny of the Kanze guild greatly changed.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Gien returned to secular life to become the Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA in 1429, at which point the destiny of the Kanze guild greatly changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>義教は音阿弥を熱烈に支援する一方で世阿弥父子を冷遇し、永享元年（1429年）には、世阿弥と元雅の仙洞御所での演能が中止となり、翌年には世阿弥の有していた醍醐寺清滝宮の楽頭職が剥奪され、音阿弥に与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Yoshinori strongly supported Onami, he turned a cold eye on Zeami father and child, and performances of Zeami and Motomasa at Sento Imperial Palace were cancelled in 1429 and Gakuto-shiki (right to play sarugaku) of Daigo-ji Temple, Kiyotaki-miya Shrine was taken away from Zeami to be given to Onami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Yoshinori strongly supported Onami, he turned a cold eye on Zeami and Motomasa; performances of Zeami and Motomasa at Sento Imperial Palace were cancelled in 1429 and Gakuto-shiki (the right to perform sarugaku) of Daigo-ji Temple, Kiyotaki-miya Shrine was taken away from Zeami to be given to Onami.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Yoshinori strongly supported Onami, he turned a cold eye on Zeami and Motomasa; performances of Zeami and Motomasa at Sento Imperial Palace were cancelled in 1429 and Gakuto-shiki (the right to perform sarugaku) of Daigo-ji Temple, Kiyotaki-miya Shrine was taken away from Zeami to be given to Onami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>またこの年の興福寺薪能では、前年の元雅に代わり、音阿弥が大夫として参勤している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Onami performed Takigi-noh (Noh theater performed at night by a fire) at Kofuku-ji Temple of that year as dayu (master) instead of Motomasa of previous year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Onami performed Takigi-noh (Noh theater performed at night by a fire) at Kofuku-ji Temple of that year as dayu (master) instead of Motomasa, who had served as dayu the previous year.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Onami performed Takigi-noh (Noh theater performed at night by a fire) at Kofuku-ji Temple of that year as dayu (master) instead of Motomasa, who had served as dayu the previous year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>なおこの際、興福寺は彼の都合に合わせてか日程の変更・延長まで行っており、その権勢のほどがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kofuku-ji Temple adjusted and extended the schedule according to his needs, and it showed how strong his political strength was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofuku-ji Temple adjusted and extended the schedule according to his needs, and which showed how strong his political power was.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofuku-ji Temple adjusted and extended the schedule according to his needs, and which showed how strong his political power was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>こうして「観世大夫両座」と言われるように、音阿弥の活動も独立性を強め、ついには観世座の主導権を握るに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, activities of Onami started to be called as &apos;Kanzedaiyuryoza&apos; (troupe with also Dayu KANZE as leading actor) (観世大夫両座), and he eventually took the leadership of Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt>観世大夫両座→&apos;Kanzedaiyuryoza&apos; (troupe with also Dayu KANZE as leading actor)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, activities of Onami started to be called &apos;Kanzedaiyuryoza&apos; (troupe with Dayu KANZE as leading actor) (観世大夫両座), and he eventually assumed leadership of the Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, activities of Onami started to be called &apos;Kanzedaiyuryoza&apos; (troupe with Dayu KANZE as leading actor) (観世大夫両座), and he eventually assumed leadership of the Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>そんな中で永享4年（1432年）元雅は伊勢で没し（暗殺説も）、同6年には世阿弥自身が佐渡に流罪となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Motomasa passed away at Ise in 1432 (there was a assassination theory as well), and Zeami himself was exiled to Sado in 1434.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Motomasa passed away at Ise in 1432 (there was an assassination theory as well), and Zeami himself was exiled to Sado in 1434.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Motomasa passed away at Ise in 1432 (there was an assassination theory as well), and Zeami himself was exiled to Sado in 1434.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>かくして観世座から世阿弥父子の勢力は一掃され、これを受けて永享5年、音阿弥は正式に観世大夫の地位に就き、名実ともに能楽界の第一人者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zeami parent and child were removed from Kanze guild, and Onami officially gained the position of Dayu KANZE in 1433 to become the pioneer in the world of nogaku (the art of Noh).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zeami and Motomasa were removed from the Kanze guild, and Onami officially gained the position of Dayu KANZE in 1433 to become a pioneer in the world of nogaku (the art of Noh).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zeami and Motomasa were removed from the Kanze guild, and Onami officially gained the position of Kanze-dayu in 1433 to become a pioneer in the world of nogaku (the art of Noh).</e>
<cmt>Dayu KANZE をKanze-dayu に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>御用役者として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Official Actor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Official Actor</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Official Actor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>永享5年4月、音阿弥の大夫就任披露の勧進猿楽が、京の糺河原で挙行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kanjin sarugaku performance of Onami announcing his assignment to dayu post was held at Tadasu-gawara (Tadasu Riverbank), Kyoto in April 1433.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kanjin sarugaku performance of Onami announcing his assignment to the post of dayu was held at Tadasu-gawara (Tadasu Riverbank), Kyoto in April 1433.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kanjin sarugaku performance of Onami announcing his assignment to the post of dayu was held at Tadasu-gawara (Tadasu Riverbank), Kyoto in April 1433.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これを祝って人々が義教の元に参上していることから、この催しが義教の手で行われたものであり、音阿弥が将軍家の御用役者として認められていたことが分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As people went to pay a visit to Yoshinori celebrating this event, it could be observed that this activity was hosted by Yoshinori and Onami was accepted as the official actor of Shogunke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As people went to pay a visit to Yoshinori celebrating this event, it could be observed that this activity was hosted by Yoshinori and Onami was accepted as the official actor of Shogunke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As people went to pay a visit to Yoshinori celebrating this event, it could be observed that this activity was hosted by Yoshinori and Onami was accepted as the official actor of Shogunke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>諸侯は義教の意を迎えるためもあって音阿弥を厚遇し、将軍をもてなす席には音阿弥の能が欠かせぬほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal lords warmly welcomed Onami to show the will of Yoshinori, and the reception by shogun went without the the noh of Onami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal lords warmly welcomed Onami to show the will of Yoshinori, and the reception by shogun went without the noh of Onami.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal lords warmly welcomed Onami to show the will of Yoshinori, and the reception by shogun went without the noh of Onami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>我が世の春を謳歌する音阿弥であったが、一方で同9年、突如義教の勘気を蒙っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Onami sang praises of his own glory, he suddenly lost favors from Yoshinori in 1437.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Onami sang praises of his own glory, he suddenly lost the favor of Yoshinori in 1437.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the heyday of his time, Onami suddenly lost the favor of Yoshinori in 1437.</e>
<cmt>我が世の春を謳歌するsang praises of his own glory をIn the heyday of his time, Onami に修正しました。参考：http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%88%91%E3%81%8C%E4%B8%96%E3%81%AE%E6%98%A5</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この事件は貞成親王の耳にまで届き、「不定之世毎事如此」と驚嘆させしめたが、赤松満祐のとりなしで十日ほどで許されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident reached even the ears of Imperial Prince Sadafusa, who started &apos;不定之世毎事如此&apos; with surprise, but Onami was forgiven within approximately ten days due to the help of Mitsusuke AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>不定之世毎事如此[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident reached even the ears of Imperial Prince Sadafusa, who started &apos;不定之世毎事如此&apos; with surprise, but Onami was forgiven within approximately ten days due to the help of Mitsusuke AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident reached even the ears of Imperial Prince Sadafusa, who started &apos;不定之世毎事如此&apos; with surprise, but Onami was forgiven within approximately ten days due to the help of Mitsusuke AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>嘉吉元年（1441年）、その赤松満祐が、自邸で義教を暗殺するという挙に出る（嘉吉の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this Mitsusuke AKAMATSU schemed to assassinate Yoshinori in his own palace in 1441 (Kakitsu War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this Mitsusuke AKAMATSU schemed to assassinate Yoshinori in his own palace in 1441 (Kakitsu War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this Mitsusuke AKAMATSU schemed to assassinate Yoshinori in his own palace in 1441 (Kakitsu War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>それはまさに、饗応のため呼ばれた音阿弥が能「鵜羽」を舞うさなかでの出来事であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in a midst of the noh performance, &apos;U no ha&apos; (Cormorant plumes) of Onami invited for the party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in a midst of the noh performance, &apos;U no ha&apos; (Cormorant plumes) of Onami invited for the party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in a midst of the noh performance, &apos;U no ha&apos; (Cormorant plumes) of Onami invited for the party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>当道に無双</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being Disconnected from His Own Path</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being Disconnected from His Own Path</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being Disconnected from His Own Path</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>最大の後援者を失った音阿弥は一時困窮し、私的な勧進能を行うなどしてその打破に努めたようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onami, who lost his greatest supporter, temporarily fell into poverty and performed Kanjin noh (performances held to raise subscriptions for the construction of shrines or temples) in order to get himself out from that difficult situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onami, who lost his greatest supporter, temporarily fell into poverty and performed Kanjin noh (performances held to raise subscriptions for the construction of shrines or temples) in order to get himself out from that difficult situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onami, who lost his greatest supporter, temporarily fell into poverty and performed Kanjin noh (performances held to raise subscriptions for the construction of shrines or temples) in order to get himself out from that difficult situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>文安元年（1444年）の勧進能では観客席の値段を下げるなどの努力をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kanjin noh of 1444, he made efforts such as lowering the price of audience seats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kanjin noh of 1444, he made efforts such as lowering the price of audience seats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kanjin noh of 1444, he made efforts such as lowering the price of audience seats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>一方で金春座とともに幕府に訴えて、他座が京で猿楽を舞うのを妨害したりもしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he made a claim to bakufu (government by feudal lord) along with Konparu-za to prevent other za (trade-guild) from performing sarugaku in Kyo (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he made a claim to the bakufu (government by feudal lord) along with Konparu-za to prevent other za (trade-guilds) from performing sarugaku in Kyo (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he made a claim to the bakufu (government by feudal lord) along with Konparu-za to prevent other za (trade-guilds) from performing sarugaku in Kyo (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし義教の子・足利義政が長じて後の享徳元年（1452年）頃からは、その厚遇を受けることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he began to receive a warm welcome from the child of Yoshinori, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA since 1452.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, from 1452 he began to receive a warm welcome from the child of Yoshinori, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from around 1452 he began to receive a warm welcome from the child of Yoshinori, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>「頃」訳漏れのためaround を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>応仁の乱の中でも能を見ていたほどの愛好家である義政は音阿弥を高く評価し、再び表舞台に引き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimasa, who loved and watched noh even during the Onin War, greatly valued Onami and pulled him up the front stage once again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimasa, who loved and watched noh even during the Onin War, greatly valued Onami and pulled him up to the front stage once again.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimasa, who loved and watched noh even during the Onin War, greatly valued Onami and pulled him up to the front stage once again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>60歳を迎える長禄2年(1458年)頃には子の観世正盛に大夫の座を譲って出家し、以後法名の「音阿弥」を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onami passed the position of master to his child, Masamori KANZE in 1458 when he became sixty years old, and underwent shukke (become a Buddhist priest) with the homyo (Buddhist name) of &apos;Onami.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onami passed the position of master to his child, Masamori KANZE, in 1458 when he became sixty years old, and underwent shukke (became a Buddhist priest) with the homyo (Buddhist name) of &apos;Onami.&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onami passed the position of master to his child, Masamori KANZE, in 1458 when he became sixty years old, and entered priesthood with the homyo (Buddhist name) of &apos;Onami.&apos;</e>
<cmt>underwent shukke (became a Buddhist priest) を entered priesthood に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この名は観阿弥・世阿弥の後継者としての自負を示すものであろう（一字目を並べると「観世音菩薩」となる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name probably represented his self-conceitedness as the successor of Kanami and Zeami (when first letter of each names are aligned together, it became &apos;Kanzeon Bosatsu&apos; (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name probably represented his self-conceitedness as the successor of Kanami and Zeami (when the first letters of the names are aligned together, they become &apos;Kanzeon Bosatsu&apos; (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy)).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name probably represented his self-conceitedness as the successor of Kanami and Zeami (when the first letters of the names are aligned together, they become &apos;Kanzeon Bosatsu&apos; (the Buddhist Goddess of Mercy)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>世阿弥同様に出家の後も第一線で活動を続け、寛正5年（1464年）には正盛が義政の後援で行った糺河原での勧進猿楽でも、「邯鄲」「恋重荷」「二人静」「養老 (能)」など29番のうち12番でシテを務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar to Zeami, he performed even after shukke, and kanjin sarugaku on Tadasu-gawara was performed by Masamori with the support of Yoshimasa as the Shite (main performer) in twelve out of twenty-nine plays such as &apos;Kantan&apos; (The Pillow of Kantan, Noh play), &apos;Koi no Omoni&apos; (The Burden of Love), &apos;Futari Shizuka&apos; (a couple of the young ladies named Shizuka), and &apos;Yoro&apos; (Longevity springs, Noh play) in1464.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar to Zeami, he performed even after shukke, and kanjin sarugaku on Tadasu-gawara was performed by Masamori with the support of Yoshimasa as the Shite (main performer) in twelve out of twenty-nine plays, including &apos;Kantan&apos; (The Pillow of Kantan, Noh play), &apos;Koi no Omoni&apos; (The Burden of Love), &apos;Futari Shizuka&apos; (a couple of the young ladies named Shizuka), and &apos;Yoro&apos; (Longevity springs, Noh play) in1464.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar to Zeami, he performed even after entering priesthood, and kanjin sarugaku on Tadasu-gawara was performed by Masamori with the support of Yoshimasa as the Shite (main performer) in twelve out of twenty-nine plays, including &apos;Kantan&apos; (The Pillow of Kantan, Noh play), &apos;Koi no Omoni&apos; (The Burden of Love), &apos;Futari Shizuka&apos; (a couple of the young ladies named Shizuka), and &apos;Yoro&apos; (Longevity springs, Noh play) in 1464.</e>
<cmt>shukke をentering priesthood に修正しました。in1464 をin 1464 に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>この催しには義政・日野富子夫妻は無論のこと、関白二条持通、また有力守護大名たちが臨席し、観世座の権威を見せ付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This performance was viewed by Yoshimasa and Tomiko HINO couple, Mochimichi NIJO, who had the title of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), and powerful Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable), and showed off the authority of Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This performance was viewed by the couple Yoshimasa and Tomiko HINO, Mochimichi NIJO, who held the title of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), and powerful Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord serving as provincial constable), showing off the authority of the Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This performance was viewed by the couple Yoshimasa and Tomiko HINO, Mochimichi NIJO, who held the title of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), and powerful Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord serving as provincial constable), showing off the authority of the Kanze guild.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>同年には後花園天皇の御前で能を舞い、「老いて益々健在である」と義政を感嘆させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He performed noh in front of Emperor Gohanazono, and made Yoshimasa struck with administration as he said, &apos;he becomes better as he ages.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He performed noh in front of Emperor Gohanazono, and made Yoshimasa struck with admiration, as he said, &apos;he becomes better as he ages.&apos;</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He performed noh in front of Emperor Gohanazono, and made Yoshimasa struck with admiration, as he said, &apos;he becomes better as he ages.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>とはいえ政情の不安もあり、暮らし向きはそれほど楽でなかったようで、文正元年（1466年）には相国寺の蔭涼軒を訪ね、押し売り同然に小歌・小舞を披露したことが記録に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Onami seemed to worry the political situation, and the living status was not easy for it was stated on the records that he visited Inryoken Household of Sokoku-ji Temple in 1466 and forcefully performed a short song accompanied with shamisen and komai (short dances in Noh farce).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Onami seemed to worry about the political situation, and his life style was not easy, for it was stated in the records that he visited the Inryoken Household of Sokoku-ji Temple in 1466 and forcefully performed a short song accompanied with shamisen and komai (short dances in Noh farce).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Onami seemed to worry about the political situation, and his life style was not easy, for it was stated in the records that he visited the Inryoken Household of Sokoku-ji Temple in 1466 and forcefully performed a short song accompanied with shamisen and komai (short dances in Noh farce).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="43">
<j>翌2年に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He passed away in the following year of 1467.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He passed away in the following year of 1467.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He passed away in the following year of 1467.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>一休宗純に帰依してその引導を受けたと『四座役者目録』などに語られるが、疑わしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was stated in &quot;Yoza yakusha mokuroku&quot; (Catalog of Actors of the Four Noh Troupes) that he became a believer of Sojun IKKYU and received the requiem from him but is doubtful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was stated in &quot;Yoza yakusha mokuroku&quot; (Catalog of Actors of the Four Noh Troupes) that he became a believer of Sojun IKKYU and received a requiem from him, but this is doubtful.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was stated in &quot;Yoza yakusha mokuroku&quot; (Catalog of Actors of the Four Noh Troupes) that he became a believer of Sojun IKKYU and received a requiem from him, but this is doubtful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>墓所は酬恩庵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is located at Shuon-an Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is located at Shuon-an Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is located at Shuon-an Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="46">
<j>子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Children</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Children</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="47">
<j>嫡子で四世大夫を継いだ又三郎正盛（松盛）を始め、又四郎、小四郎（四郎左衛門）、与四郎（宗観）、八郎、五世大夫を継いだ観世之重（祐賢）、観世小次郎信光などの子があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting from his legitimate child Masamori MATASABURO (Matsumori) that succeeded to the fourth dayu postion, his children were Matashiro, Koshiro (or pronounced Shoshiro) (Shirozaemon), Yoshiro (Sokan), Hachiro, Koreshige KANZE (Sukekata), who became the fifth dayu, and Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting from his legitimate child Masamori MATASABURO (Matsumori) who succeeded to the fourth dayu postion, his children were Matashiro, Koshiro (or pronounced Shoshiro) (Shirozaemon), Yoshiro (Sokan), Hachiro, Koreshige KANZE (Sukekata), who became the fifth dayu, and Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting from his legitimate child Masamori MATASABURO (Matsumori) who succeeded to the fourth dayu position, his children were Matashiro, Koshiro (or pronounced Shoshiro) (Shirozaemon), Yoshiro (Sokan), Hachiro, Koreshige KANZE (Sukekata), who became the fifth dayu, and KANZE Kojiro Nobumitsu.</e>
<cmt>postion をposition に修正しました。Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO をKANZE Kojiro Nobumitsu に修正しました。出典：http://books.google.com/books?id=n_WRKJ0a6b8C&amp;pg=PA287&amp;dq=Kanze%E3%80%80Kojiro+Nobumitsu&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3&amp;hl=ja&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=Kanze%E3%80%80Kojiro%20Nobumitsu&amp;f=false</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>うち五世之重については長らく正盛の子とされてきたが、『尋尊記』などの記述から音阿弥の第六子とする説が近年有力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered for a long time that the fifth generation Koreshige was the child of Masamori, but it is most likely that he was the sixth child of Onami as written in &quot;Jinsonki&quot; (Diary of Jinson).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered for a long time that the fifth generation Koreshige was the child of Masamori, but it is most likely that he was the sixth child of Onami, as written in &quot;Jinsonki&quot; (Diary of Jinson).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered for a long time that the fifth generation Koreshige was the child of Masamori, but it is most likely that he was the sixth child of Onami, as written in &quot;Jinsonki&quot; (Diary of Jinson).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>大夫を継いだ二人を除く兄弟たちは、それぞれ脇、囃子方、あるいは作能などに回って、後継者を皆で支えたものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except for two brothers who became the Dayu, the rest of brothers took the roles of attendants, hayashikata (people who play hayashi, or the musical accompaniment), or sakuno (noh writers) and supported the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for two brothers who became the Dayu, the rest of the brothers took the roles of attendants, hayashikata (people who play hayashi, or musical accompaniment), or sakuno (noh writers) and supported the successor.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for two brothers who became the Dayu, the rest of the brothers took the roles of attendants, hayashikata (people who play hayashi, or musical accompaniment), or sakuno (noh writers) and supported the successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>特に第七子の信光は、権守として座の中心的な地位を担った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobumitsu, who was the seventh child of Onami, took the central role of the guild as the Gon no kami (provisional governor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobumitsu, who was the seventh child of Onami, took the central role of the guild as the Gon no kami (provisional governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobumitsu, who was the seventh child of Onami, took the central role of the guild as the Gon no kami (provisional governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>後世への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence to Future Generations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence to Future Generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence to Future Generations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>彼の時代に観世座と幕府権力の結びつきは決定的なものとなり、以後観世流が他を圧して能楽界の中心を担う契機を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The connection between the Kanze guild and bakufu power became definite during his time, and took the opportunity to make the Kanze school to suppress other schools and took the central part of the world of nogaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The connection between the Kanze guild and bakufu power became definite during his time, and the Kanze school took the opportunity to suppress other schools and take the central part of the world of nogaku.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The connection between the Kanze guild and bakufu power became definite during his time, and the Kanze school took the opportunity to suppress other schools and take the central part of the world of nogaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>一方で、能作者としても傑出した存在であった観阿弥、世阿弥、元雅とは対照的に、彼の作になる能は残っておらず（伝音阿弥作とする曲もあるが、一般的には認められていない）、また伝書の類も存在しない（『能優須知』が『歌舞髄脳記』の著者とするが、近世の偽書である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, none of the noh composed by him remained unlike Kanami, Zeami, and Motomasa who excelled as the noh writers (there is a music supposedly composed by 伝音阿弥 but not publically confirmed), and no densho (books handed down from ancestors) are present (Noyusuchi (能優須知) claimed that he was the author of &quot;Kabuzuinoki&quot; (The Essence of Dance and Song) but was written by people of current days).</e>
<cmt>伝音阿弥, Noyusuchi　（能優須知）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, none of the noh composed by him remained, unlike Kanami, Zeami, and Motomasa who excelled as noh writers (there is a piece of music supposedly composed by 伝音阿弥 but not publically confirmed), and no densho (books handed down from ancestors) are present (Noyusuchi (能優須知) claimed that he was the author of &quot;Kabuzuinoki&quot; (The Essence of Dance and Song), but this was written by people of current days).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, none of the noh composed by him remained, unlike Kanami, Zeami, and Motomasa who excelled as noh writers (there is a piece of music supposedly composed by 伝音阿弥 but not publicly confirmed), and no densho (books handed down from ancestors) are present (Noyusuchi (能優須知) claimed that he was the author of &quot;Kabuzuinoki&quot; (The Essence of Dance and Song), but this was written by people of current days).</e>
<cmt>publically をpublicly に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>その代わり役者としての活動によって、観世座を大成させ、また現代に至るまで名優としての名を遺したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, he raised Kanze guild as the actor and left his name as the greatest actor even to the present day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, he rose within the Kanze guild as an actor and left his name as the greatest actor even to the present day.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, he rose within the Kanze guild as an actor and left his name as the greatest actor even to the present day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>子の観世小次郎信光、さらにその子の観世長俊は能作者としても活躍し、世阿弥系の幽玄な作風とは異なる、音阿弥の芸風を受け継いだと思われる花やかな曲を多く作っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO and the child after him, Nagatoshi KANZE, was active as the noh writer and created many colorful music unlike the mysterious atmosphere of the way of Zeami by inheriting the flamboyant style of Onami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His child Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO and the child after him, Nagatoshi KANZE, inheriting the flamboyant style of Onami, were active as noh writers and created many pieces of colorful music unlike the mysterious atmosphere of the way of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His child KANZE Kojiro Nobumitsu and the child after him, Nagatoshi KANZE, inheriting the flamboyant style of Onami, were active as noh writers and created many pieces of colorful music unlike the mysterious atmosphere of the way of Zeami.</e>
<cmt>Nobumitsu KANZAKOJIRO をKANZE Kojiro Nobumitsu に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="55">
<j>正盛以降も観世大夫職は以後音阿弥の子孫により受け継がれ、当代の二十六世観世清和に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dayu KANZE position after Masamori was succeeded by the descendants of Onami and lead to the current twenty-sixth Kiyokazu KANZE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Masamori, the dayu KANZE position was succeeded by the descendants of Onami, leading to the current twenty-sixth Kiyokazu KANZE.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Masamori, the Kanze-dayu position was succeeded by the descendants of Onami, leading to the current twenty-sixth Kiyokazu KANZE.</e>
<cmt>Dayu KANZE をKanze-dayu に修正しました。文末にピリオドを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Sat666(id:127263), Singing(id:134656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>