<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>稲葉正成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanari INABA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanari INABA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanari INABA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>稲葉 正成（いなば まさなり、1571年（元亀2年）- 1628年10月14日（寛永5年9月17日 (旧暦)））は、戦国時代 (日本)、江戸時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanari INABA (1571 - October 14, 1628) was Samurai in period of civil war and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanari INABA (1571 - October 14, 1628) was a samurai during the warring states period and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanari INABA (1571 - October 14, 1628) was a military commander during the Period of Warring States and the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>美濃国十七条藩主、越後国糸魚川藩主、下野国真岡藩初代藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lord of Jushichijo Domain of the Mino Province, Itoigawa Domain of Echigo Province, the first Mooka Domain of Shimotsuke Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lord of Jushichijo Domain of the Mino Province, Itoigawa Domain of Echigo Province, the first Mooka Domain of Shimotsuke Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the lord of Jushichijo Domain of the Mino Province and Itoigawa Domain of Echigo Province, and the first lord of Mooka Domain of Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正成系稲葉家宗家初代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fist family head of the Inaba family of the orthodox line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first family head of the Inaba family of the orthodox line.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first head of the head family of the Inaba family of the Masanari line.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>林政秀の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second son of Masahide HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second son of Masahide HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the second son of Masahide HAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>母は安藤某の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was 安藤某.</e>
<cmt>安藤某→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was 安藤某.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of a Mr. Ando.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>正室は稲葉重通の娘、継室は稲葉重通の養女・福（春日局、斎藤利三の娘）、継々室は山内康豊の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was Shigemichi INABA&apos;s daughter, second wife was Shigemitsu INABA&apos;s adopted daughter, Fuku (Kasuga no Tsubone, Toshimitsu SAITO&apos;s daughter), third wife was Yasutoyo YAMAUCHI&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was Shigemichi INABA&apos;s daughter, second wife was Shigemitsu INABA&apos;s adopted daughter, Fuku (Kasuga no Tsubone, Toshimitsu SAITO&apos;s daughter), third wife was Yasutoyo YAMAUCHI&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was Shigemichi INABA&apos;s daughter, his second wife was Shigemichi INABA&apos;s adopted daughter, Fuku (Kasuga no Tsubone, Toshimitsu SAITO&apos;s daughter), and his third wife was Yasutoyo YAMAUCHI&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子は稲葉重通の娘との間に稲葉正次（長男）、娘（堀田正吉正室）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had two children between daughter of Shigemichi INABA, Masatsugu INABA (eldest son) and a daughter. (Masayoshi HOTTA&apos;s wife)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had two children between daughter of Shigemichi INABA, Masatsugu INABA (eldest son) and a daughter. (Masayoshi HOTTA&apos;s wife)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had two children with a daughter of Shigemichi INABA, Masatsugu INABA (eldest son) and a daughter (Masayoshi HOTTA&apos;s wife).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>春日局との間に稲葉正勝（次男）、稲葉正定（三男）、稲葉正利（五男）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had second son, Masakatsu INABA, the third son, Masasada INABA and the fifth son, Masatoshi INABA between Kasugano tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a second son, Masakatsu INABA, a third son, Masasada INABA and a fifth son, Masatoshi INABA between Kasugano tsubone.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a second son Masakatsu INABA, a third son Masasada INABA and a fifth son Masatoshi INABA with Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>山内康豊の娘との間に稲葉正吉（十男）、娘（朽木稙綱 (土浦藩主)正室）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had the tenth son, Masayoshi INABA and a daughter, Tanetsuna KUTSUKI &apos;s(the feudal lord of Tsuchiura domain) wife) between Yasutoyo YAMAUCHI&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a tenth son, Masayoshi INABA and a daughter, Tanetsuna KUTSUKI &apos;s(the feudal lord of Tsuchiura domain) wife) between Yasutoyo YAMAUCHI&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a tenth son Masayoshi INABA and a daughter (a wife of the feudal lord of Tsuchiura Domain Tanetsuna KUTSUKI) with Yasutoyo YAMAUCHI&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>養子は稲葉政貞。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His adopted son was Masasada INABA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His adopted son was Masasada INABA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His adopted son was Masasada INABA.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>はじめ林姓であったが、後に、美濃国の稲葉重通の婿となり、姓を林から稲葉と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially his surname was HAYASHI, but later on he became Shigemichi INABA&apos;s (Mino Province) son in law, then he changed his surname from YAHAYASHI to INABA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially his surname was HAYASHI, but later on he became Shigemichi INABA&apos;s (Mino Province) son in law, after which he changed his surname from YAHAYASHI to INABA.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially his surname was HAYASHI, but later on, as he married an heress of Shigemichi INABA in Mino Province, he changed his surname from Hayashi to Inaba.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ところが、重通の娘に先立たれたために代わりに重通の姪である福を養女として正成に嫁がせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Shigemichi&apos;s daughter died, his niece, Fuku was adopted to let her marry with Masanari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Shigemichi&apos;s daughter died, his niece, Fuku was adopted to let her marry Masanari.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Shigemichi&apos;s daughter died, Shigemishi adopted his niece Fuku and married her to Masanari.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これが後の春日局である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was later on called Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, she was called Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Fuku became Kasuga no Tsubone.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>正成は義父とともに豊臣秀吉に仕えたが、秀吉の命を受けて小早川氏に入った小早川秀秋の家臣（家老・5万石）となり、秀秋を補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanari and his father in law both served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and Masanari became aide of Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA, who became Kobayakawa clan (chief retainer, fifty thousand koku) due to order from Hideyoshi, and Masanari supported Hideaki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanari and his father in law both served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and Masanari became an aide to Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA, who became Kobayakawa clan (chief retainer, fifty thousand koku) due to an order from Hideyoshi, and Masanari supported Hideaki.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Masanari and his father-in-law served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and due to an order from Hideyoshi, Masanari became an aide (chief retainer, fifty thousand koku) to Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA, who became Kobayakawa clan, and supported Hideaki.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>四国・小笠原征伐で活躍し、朝鮮出兵（慶長の役）では秀秋に従軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He played an active role in Shikoku, Ogasawara subjugation, he also fought to support Hideaki at Japan&apos;s Invation of Korea. (Keicho Campaign)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He played an active role in Shikoku, Ogasawara subjugation, and also fought to support Hideaki at Japan&apos;s Invation of Korea. (Keicho Campaign)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He played an active role in subjugation of Ogasawara clan in Shikoku and also fought to support Hideaki at Japan&apos;s Invasion of Korea (Keicho Campaign).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）の関ヶ原の戦いでは、平岡頼勝と共に徳川家康と内通し、秀秋を東軍に寝返らせることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanari and Yorikatsu HIRAOKA had secret communication with Ieyaku TOKUGAWA at battle of Sekigahara in 1600, Masanari was able for Hideaki to go over to the East squad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanari and Yorikatsu HIRAOKA had secret communications with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA at the battle of Sekigahara in 1600, and Masanari was able to convince Hideaki to defect to the Eastern army.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanari and Yorikatsu HIRAOKA had secret communications with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA during the battle of Sekigahara in 1600, and Masanari was able to convince Hideaki to come over to the Eastern army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、戦後秀秋と対立し美濃に蟄居する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he retired in Mino Province after he had conflict with Hideaki after the War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he retired in Mino Province after conflicting with Hideaki after the War.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he came into conflict with Hideaki after the War, and retired in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>慶長7年（1602年）、秀秋が死去して小早川氏が断絶すると浪人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1602, after Hideaki died and the Kobayakawa clan discontinued, Masanari became ronin.(masterless samurai)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1602, after Hideaki died and the Kobayakawa clan discontinued, Masanari became ronin.(masterless samurai)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1602, after Hideaki died and the Kobayakawa clan discontinued, Masanari became a masterless warrrior.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>慶長9年（1604年）7月、家康の嫡孫・竹千代（後の徳川家光）の乳母が京都所司代板倉勝重によって募集された折に妻の福が志願して採用されると、福と離縁した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1604, when the position of menoto (a woman providing breast-feed to a highborn baby) for Ieyasu&apos;s legitimate grandchild, Takechiyo (later called Iemitsu TOKUGAWA) was advertised by Kyoto shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy), Katsushige ITAKURA, his wife, Fuku applied and got the position, then Masanari divorced to Fuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1604, when the position of menoto (a wet nurse who breast-fed a highborn baby) for Ieyasu&apos;s legitimate grandchild, Takechiyo (later called Iemitsu TOKUGAWA) was advertised by Kyoto shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy), Katsushige ITAKURA, his wife, Fuku applied and got the position, after which Masanari divorced Fuku.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July and August 1604, when the position of a wet nurse for Ieyasu&apos;s legitimate grandchild, Takechiyo (later called Iemitsu TOKUGAWA) was invited by the Kyoto deputy Katsushige ITAKURA, his wife Fuku applied for the position and was employed, after which Masanari divorced Fuku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その経緯については諸説あるが、正成が愛人を作ったと知った福が激怒して家を去ったとする説、勝手に乳母に応募したことに激怒した正成が離縁した説、乳母に採用されたことを知って「女房の御蔭で出世した」と言われるのを恥じて離縁状を出した説、更にこれらの出来事は全て口実で正成を家康に仕官させるために正成と福が示し合わせて離縁したとする説などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some theories of the background of above, such as Masanari had an affair with other woman and Fuku was furious and left him, or Masanari divorced Fuku after knowing she applied for the position without having Masanari&apos;s permission, or he divorced since he thought it would lose his face if he was called &apos;he was promoted due to his wife&apos;s&apos; success&apos; after knowing Fuku got the position of menoto, or furthermore, above were all reason for Masanari to serve Ieyasu, and they divorced on purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some theories concerning the background of the above, such as Masanari having an affair with other woman and Fuku being furious over this fact and leaving him, or Masanari divorcing Fuku after knowing she applied for the position without having Masanari&apos;s permission, or Masanori divorcing her since he thought he would lose his face if it was said that &apos;he was promoted due to his wife&apos;s&apos; success&apos; after knowing Fuku got the position of menoto. All of the above were reason for Masanari to serve Ieyasu, and they divorced on purpose.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories concerning the reason behind their decision to divorce: Masanari having an affair with another woman and Fuku being furious over this fact and leaving him; Masanari divorcing Fuku after finding out she had applied for the position without Masanari&apos;s permission; Masanori divorcing her since he thought he would lose face if it was said that &apos;he had been promoted due to his wife&apos;s success&apos; having discovered that Fuku had got the position of wet nurse; and Masanari and Fuku pre-arranged their divorce by using the above-mentioned stories as possible grounds in order to enable Masanari to serve Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>後に家康に召し出され、以後は徳川氏の家臣として仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, Masanari was appointed by Ieyasu to serve him, he became Tokugawa clan&apos;s aides after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, Masanari was appointed by Ieyasu to serve him, and he became Tokugawa clan&apos;s aide following this.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, Masanari was appointed by Ieyasu to serve him, and he became Tokugawa clan&apos;s aide since then.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>慶長12年（1607年）には旧領の美濃国内に1万石の領地を与えられ大名に列した（十七条藩）後、家康の孫にあたる松平忠昌の家老となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he was given ten thousand koku land within the former Mino Province in 1607 and he became Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), (Jushichijo Domain), he then became chief retainer of Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA, who was Ieyasu&apos;s grandchild.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was given ten thousand koku land within the former Mino Province in 1607 he became Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), (Jushichijo Domain), and chief retainer of Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA, who was Ieyasu&apos;s grandchild.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was given the land of 10,000 koku within the former Mino Province in 1607, he became a feudal lord of Jushichijo domain, and then chief retainer of Tadamasa MATSUDAIRA, who was Ieyasu&apos;s grandchild.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>大坂夏の陣では忠昌を補佐して戦功を挙げて、元和 (日本)4年（1618年）越後糸魚川に2万石の所領を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), he made achievement in the war to support Tadamasa, and was given twenty thousand koku of shoryo (territory) in 越後糸魚川 in 1624.</e>
<cmt>越後糸魚川→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), he successfully supported Tadamasa, and was given twenty thousand koku of shoryo (territory) in Echigo Itoigawa in 1624.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Summer Siege of Osaka, he successfully supported Tadamasa, and was given the territory of 20,000 koku in Itoigawa, Echigo province in 1618.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>寛永元年（1624年）、忠昌の越前転封に従わず再び浪人し、子の正勝の領内で蟄居を命ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1624 he did not follow Tadamasa&apos;s order to move Masanari&apos;s territory to Echizen, and he again became ronin, he was placed in confinement at home in his son, Masakatsu&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1624 he did not follow Tadamasa&apos;s order to move Masanari&apos;s territory to Echizen, and he again became ronin, and was placed in confinement at home in his son, Masakatsu&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1624, when he did not follow Tadamasa&apos;s order to move Masanari&apos;s territory to Echizen, he became a masterless warrior again and was placed in confinement at home in the territory of his son Masakatsu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>寛永4年（1627年）、独立した大名として再び召し出され下野真岡2万石に封じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1627, he was again appointed to serve as an independent Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), and was given twenty thousand koku territory of 下野真岡.</e>
<cmt>下野真岡→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1627, he was again appointed to serve as an independent Daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), and was given twenty thousand koku territory of 下野真岡.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1627, he was called again to serve as an independent feudal lord, and was given the territory of 20,000 koku in Mooka, Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>山内一豊とともに妻の「内助の功」の典型例とされる場合が多いが、関ヶ原や大坂の陣で武将としての力量を発揮しており、決して妻の縁だけで出世したわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was granted that he became successful due to his wife&apos;s help, same like 山内一豊, however his success was not just credit to his wife, he showed his ability in both as Samurai in Summer Siege of Osaka and battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>山内一豊→読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was granted that he became successful due to his wife&apos;s help, same like 山内一豊, however his success was not just credited to his wife, but in his demonstrated ability both as a samurai during Summer Siege of Osaka and the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was granted that he became successful due to his wife&apos;s help, like Katsutoyo YAMAUCHI, however, his success was not just credited to his wife but in his demonstrated ability both as a military commander during the Summer Siege of Osaka and the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>子孫は、山城国淀藩藩主として明治維新まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendant continued until the Meiji Restoration as the lord of Yamashiro Province domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendant continued until the Meiji Restoration as the lord of Yamashiro Province domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanari&apos;s descendants had continued until the Meiji Restoration as the lord of Yodo Domain of Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), Rusk(id:9895), Hyuuga(id:14767), Nnh(id:474), YurikBot(id:18605), Aotake(id:34929), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), Nerimaman(id:61206), Point136(id:211299), Yanahan(id:2437), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>