<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>村国子老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MURAKUNI no Oi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MURAKUNI no Oi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MURAKUNI no Oi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>村国 子老（むらくに の おい､生没年不明）は、日本の奈良時代の人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MURAKUNI no Oi (dates unknown) was a figure who lived during Japan&apos;s Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MURAKUNI no Oi (year of birth and death unknown) was a figure who lived during Japan&apos;s Nara period.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MURAKUNI no Oi (year of birth and death unknown) was a figure who lived during Japan&apos;s Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>姓（カバネ）は連。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His hereditary title was &quot;tsure&quot; (&quot;Companion&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His kabane (hereditary title) was Muraji.</e>
<cmt>読みを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His kabane (hereditary title) was Muraji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>741年に讃岐国介を解任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 741 he was dismissed from his post as Assistant Governor of Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 741 he was dismissed from his post as Sanuki no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 741 he was dismissed from his post as Sanuki no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>763年に外従五位下に進み、能登守になったが藤原仲麻呂の乱に連座して処分された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 763 he was promoted to outer (that is, outside the capital) junior fifth rank, lower grade (among those living outside the capital) and named the governor of Noto Province, but was implicated in FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s Revolt and punitively dismissed from his post and rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 763 he was promoted to Ge-jugoinoge (Jugoinoge [Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade] given to persons outside Kyoto) and named the governor of Noto Province, but was implicated in FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s Revolt and punitively dismissed from his post and rank.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 763 he was promoted to Ge-jugoinoge (Jugoinoge [Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade] given to persons outside Kyoto) and named the governor of Noto Province, but was implicated in FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s Revolt and punitively dismissed from his post and rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>770年に元の位に復帰し、771年園池正、772年伊豆守、出雲介を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 770 he was restored to his original rank, and then in 771 he was named the Jo (Director) of Gardens and Ponds before he was successively named, in 772, the governor of Izu and the assistant governor of Izumo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 770 he was restored to his original rank, and then in 771 he was named Sonoike no kami (director of gardens and ponds) before he was successively named, in 772, Izu no kami (governor of Izu province) and Izumo no suke (the assistant governor of Izumo province).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 770 he was restored to his original rank, and then in 771 he was named Sonoike no kami (director of gardens and ponds) before he was successively named, in 772, Izu no kami (governor of Izu province) and Izumo no suke (the assistant governor of Izumo province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>事績</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His achievements</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His achievements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>村国氏は美濃国各務郡の豪族で、村国男依が672年の壬申の乱で功を立てたことにより、朝廷でも知られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Murakuni clan was the most powerful local family in the Kakami district of Mino Province, and thanks to MURAKUNI no Oyori winning distinction in the fighting during the Jinshin War (of 672), their fame appears to have grown enough to be known to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Murakuni clan was the most powerful local family in the Kakami district of Mino Province, and thanks to MURAKUNI no Oyori winning distinction in the fighting during the Jinshin War (of 672), their fame appears to have grown enough to be known to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Murakuni clan was the most powerful local family in the Kakami district of Mino Province, and thanks to MURAKUNI no Oyori winning distinction in the fighting during the Jinshin War (of 672), their fame appears to have grown enough to be known to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>子老はその係累と思われるが、系譜は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oi is thought to have been a descendant of Oyori&apos;s, but his actual genealogy remains unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oi is thought to have been a descendant of Oyori&apos;s, but his actual genealogy remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oi is thought to have been a descendant of Oyori&apos;s, but his actual genealogy remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>天平13年（741年）5月27日に、讃岐国の介、正六位上村国連子老が、越後国の掾錦部男笠とともに、解任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 27th day of the fifth month of 741, the Companion MURAKUNI no Oi, who at that time was assistant governor of Sanuki Province and was of the senior sixth rank, upper grade, was dismissed from his post, as was NICHIKIBE no Okasa, the Jo (&quot;Helper&quot;) of Echigo Provice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 18th day of the seventh month of 741, MURAKUNI no Oi, who at that time was Sanuki no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Sanuki Province) and was Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade), was dismissed from his post, as was NICHIKIBE no Okasa, the Jo (secretary of provincial offices) of Echigo Provice.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the 18th day of the seventh month of 741, MURAKUNI no Oi, who at that time was Sanuki no kuni no suke (Assistant Governor of Sanuki Province) and was Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade), was dismissed from his post, as was NICHIKIBE no Okasa, the Jo (secretary of provincial offices) of Echigo Provice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>理由は、官長に礼を失いたがいに和順しなかったからとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for their dismissal is thought to have been that they failed to show gratitude to the head of government, neither taking their turn at pacification.</e>
<cmt>Note that I was unable to find any information about this term &quot;wajun suru&quot;, so was forced to guess at the translation.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for their dismissal is thought to have been that they failed to show gratitude to the head of government, with neither of them able to obey orders in a reasonable manner.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for their dismissal is thought to have been that they failed to show gratitude to the head of government, with neither of them able to obey orders in a reasonable manner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>位は元のままであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their court rank, however, remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their court rank, however, remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their court rank, however, remained unchanged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>天平宝字7年（763年）1月9日、子老は正六位上から外従五位下に進み、主船正に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the ninth day of the first month of 763. Oi was promoted from senior sixth rank, upper grade to outer junior fifth rank, lower grade, and was appointed the Jo (Director) of the Ministry of Ships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the first day of the third month of 763, Oi was promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) to Ge-jugoinoge (Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) given to persons outside Kyoto), and was appointed Shusen no kami (Director of the Ministry of Ships).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the first day of the third month of 763, Oi was promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) to Ge-jugoinoge (Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) given to persons outside Kyoto), and was appointed Shusen no kami (Director of the Ministry of Ships).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>翌8年（764年）8月4日に、能登守になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on the fourth day of the eighth month of 764, he was named the governor of Noto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on the eighth day of the ninth month of 764, he was named Noto no kami (the governor of Noto Province).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on the eighth day of the ninth month of 764, he was named Noto no kami (the governor of Noto Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>藤原仲麻呂の乱はその翌月に起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s Revolt broke out the following month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s Revolt broke out the following month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s Revolt broke out the following month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このとき村国氏の中では村国島主が仲麻呂の与党と見られて殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As regards Murakuni clan members affected by the revolt, MURAKUNI no Shimanushi was thought to be of Nakamaro&apos;s ruling faction and was consequently killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As regards Murakuni clan members affected by the revolt, MURAKUNI no Shimanushi was thought to be of Nakamaro&apos;s ruling faction and was consequently killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As regards Murakuni clan members affected by the revolt, MURAKUNI no Shimanushi was thought to be of Nakamaro&apos;s ruling faction and was consequently killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>子老の処分は明記されないが、能登守を解任され、位を奪われるか下げられるかしたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No records survive of how Oi was dealt with, but it seems that he was dismissed from his post as governor of Noto and either stripped of his court rank or demoted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No records survive of how Oi was dealt with, but it seems that he was dismissed from his post as Noto no kami (the governor of Noto Province) and either stripped of his court rank or demoted.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No records survive of how Oi was dealt with, but it seems that he was dismissed from his post as Noto no kami (the governor of Noto Province) and either stripped of his court rank or demoted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>翌年に平群虫麻呂が能登守に任命されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, HEGURI no Mushimaro was appointed governor of Noto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, HEGURI no Mushimaro was appointed Noto no kami.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, HEGURI no Mushimaro was appointed Noto no kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>宝亀元年（770年）10月1日に、正六位上から外従五位下に進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the first day of the tenth month of 770, Oi was promoted from the senior sixth rank, upper grade to the outer junior fifth rank, lower grade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the twenty seventh day of the tenth month of 770, Oi was promoted from Shorokuinojo to Ge-jugoinoge.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the twenty seventh day of the tenth month of 770, Oi was promoted from Shorokuinojo to Ge-jugoinoge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>翌年に園池正、宝亀5年（774年）に伊豆国守、出雲国介を歴任したところで、子老の記録は途切れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year after he was named Jo (Director) of Gardens and Ponds, and in 774 he was first made governor of Izu Province and then assistant governor of Izumo Province; after this point no further mention is made of Oi in the historical record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year after he was named Sonoike no kami (director of gardens and ponds), and in 774 he was first made Izu-no-kuni-no-kami (the governor of Izu Province) and then Izumo no suke (the assistant governor of Izumo province); after this point no further mention is made of Oi in the historical record.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year after he was named Sonoike no kami (director of gardens and ponds), and in 774 he was first made Izu-no-kuni-no-kami (the governor of Izu Province) and then Izumo no suke (the assistant governor of Izumo province); after this point no further mention is made of Oi in the historical record.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mymelo(id:122034), Kinori(id:443), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>