<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>吉田翔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syoh Yoshida</e>
<cmt>本人の公式サイトでは翔のスペルがSyohとなっています。http://www.syohyoshida-archives.com/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syoh Yoshida</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Syoh Yoshida</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>吉田翔（よしだ しょう、Syoh Yoshida、1984年1月24日 -）は、愛知県生まれの日本画家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Syoh Yoshida (January 24, 1984 -) is a Japanese-style painter who was born in Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Syoh Yoshida (January 24, 1984 -) is a Japanese-style painter who was born in Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Syoh YOSHIDA (January 24, 1984 -) is a Japanese-style painter who was born in Aichi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>2004年に大阪成蹊大学芸術学部学内ギャラリー・スペースBで開催されたグループ展「B-port -余白の地 -」より本格的に作家活動を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fully started his creation as an artist from the group exhibition &quot;B-port -Yohaku no chi-&quot; held at the gallery spaceB in Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art &amp; Design in 2004.</e>
<cmt>「spaceB」のspaceとBの間にスペースは不要。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He began his career as a creative artist with the group exhibition &quot;B-port -Yohaku no chi&quot; held in gallery spaceB at Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art &amp; Design, in 2004.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He launched his career as a creative artist in 2004 with his participation in a multi-artist exhibition entitled &apos;B-port -Yohaku no chi&apos; (literally, &quot;the Land on the Margins of B-port&quot;), which was held in gallery space B at Osaka Seikei University by the Faculty of Art and Design.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。Webで調べるとspace Bが多いのでスペースを入れたままにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>2006年には、個展「Beautiful Thing -美しいこと-」（spaceB／京都）、個展「Dark Lake -黒い湖 -」（CASPER’S Gallery／東京）を開催。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2006, he held the solo exhibition &quot;Beautiful Thing -Utsukushii koto-&quot; (at spaceB/Kyoto), and the solo exhibition &quot;Dark Lake -Kuroi Mizuumi-&quot; (CASPER&apos;S Gallery/Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2006, he held the solo exhibition &quot;Beautiful Thing -Utsukushii koto-&quot; (at spaceB/Kyoto), and the solo exhibition &quot;Dark Lake -Kuroi Mizuumi-&quot; (CASPER&apos;S Gallery/Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2006, two exhibitions devoted solely to his work were held, the &quot;Beautiful Thing - Utsukushii koto&quot; exhibition (at Space B in Kyoto) and the &quot;Dark Lake - Kuroi Mizuumi&quot; exhibition (at CASPER&apos;s Gallery in Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「Dark Lake -黒い湖 -」は、その模様が香港のクリエイティブ・ライフスタイル情報誌「The Outlook Magazine」（第54期10月号／Moden Media社-参照）に大きく取り上げられるなど、海外でも注目されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The content of &quot;Dark Lake -Kuroi Mizuumi-&quot; was covered largely in Hong Kong&apos;s creative lifestyle magazine &quot;The Outlook Magazine&quot; (the October issue in the term 54/published by Moden Media-reference), attracting attention abroad.</e>
<cmt>「Moden Media社」は「Modern Media社」の誤記かと思われますが、原文通り訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The content of &quot;Dark Lake--Kuroi Mizuumi&quot; was extensively covered in the Hong Kong-based creative lifestyle magazine &quot;The Outlook Magazine&quot; (the October issue in the fifty-fourth volume, published by Modern Media (reference), and thereby attracted attention abroad.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Dark Lake--Kuroi Mizuumi&apos; exhibition was extensively covered by the Hong Kong-based creative lifestyle magazine &apos;The Outlook Magazine&apos; (reference: the October issue of volume fifty-four, published by Modern Media), earning Yoshida recognition overseas also.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同年は、株式会社川島織物セルコンの浴衣ブランド「METEYUNDE」のデザイナーを担当するなど活動の幅を広げており、吉田デザインの浴衣「Float Flower」は、女優・宮崎あおいが着用するなど注目を浴びた（ゆかた夏きもの 着こなしBOOK 2006年度版／インデックス社-参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same year, the range of his creation expanded to the design of yukata (Japanese summer kimono) for Kawashima Selkon Textiles Co., Ltd.&apos;s yukata brand &quot;METEYUNDE&quot;: his design attracted attention as the actress Aoi MIYAZAKI wore the yukata named &quot;Float Flower&quot; (&quot;Yukata natsu kimono kikonashi BOOK 2006&quot;/published by Index Communications Corporation-reference).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same year, his creative range expanded to the design of yukata (Japanese summer kimono) for Kawashima Selkon Textiles Co., Ltd.&apos;s yukata brand &quot;METEYUNDE&quot;: his design attracted attention as the actress Aoi MIYAZAKI wore the yukata called &quot;Float Flower&quot; (&quot;Yukata natsu kimono kikonashi BOOK 2006,&quot; published by Index Communications Corporation (reference)).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in 2006, Yoshida expanded his creative horizons to include the designing of yukata (Japanese summer kimono) for Kawashima Selkon Textiles Co., Ltd&apos;s &apos;METEYUNDE&apos; brand; his designs attracted considerable attention after actress Aoi MIYAZAKI appeared wearing the &quot;Float Flower&quot; yukata, which Yoshida had designed (reference: &apos;Yukata natsu kimono kikonashi BOOK 2006,&apos; published by Index Communications Corporation).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>2008年には、新宿高島屋にて個展「Night Trace - 夜の跡 -」、Harbour City（香港）にて個展「Distant Promise - 遠い約束 -」を開催。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2008, he held the solo exhibition &quot;Night Trace - Yoru no ato -&quot; in Takashimaya Department Store Shinjuku Branch and the solo exhibition &quot;Distant Promise - Tooi yakusoku -&quot; in Harbour City (Hong Kong).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2008, he held the solo exhibition &quot;Night Trace - Yoru no ato&quot; in the Shinjuku branch of Takashimaya Department Store and the solo exhibition &quot;Distant Promise - Tooi yakusoku&quot; in Harbour City (Hong Kong).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2008, Yoshida launched two more solo exhibitions, one entitled &quot;Night Trace - Yoru no ato,&quot; that was held at the Shinjuku branch of the Takashimaya Department Store, and one entitled &quot;Distant Promise - Toi yakusoku&quot; in Harbour City (Hong Kong).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>主な実績は、2007年「京都府美術工芸新鋭選抜展 -新しい波- 2007」（京都府文化博物館／京都）入選、2008年「第11回岡本太郎現代芸術大賞」入選などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His major achievements include that his work was selected for &quot;Selected Artists in Kyoto -2007 New Wave-&quot; in 2007 (The Museum of Kyoto/Kyoto) and &quot;The 11th Taro Okamoto Award for Contemporary Art&quot; in 2008.</e>
<cmt>http://www.pref.kyoto.jp/news/bungei/18-senbatu.JPGhttp://www.taromuseum.jp/english/taroaward/taroaward_english.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His major achievements include the fact that his work was selected for &quot;Selected Artists in Kyoto -2007 New Wave&quot; in 2007 (The Museum of Kyoto/Kyoto) and &quot;The 11th Taro Okamoto Award for Contemporary Art&quot; in 2008.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notable achievements include his selection in the &apos;Selected Artists in Kyoto -2007 New Wave&apos; in 2007 (at the Museum of Kyoto) and his being chosen to receive &apos;The Eleventh Taro Okamoto Award for Contemporary Art&apos; in 2008.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>2008年オフィシャルウェブサイト「」開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He opened his official website &quot;SYOH YOSHIDA - ARCHIVES&quot; in 2008.</e>
<cmt>「」内が欠落していましたが、ウェブサイトから引用し訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He opened his official website &quot;SYOH YOSHIDA - ARCHIVES&quot; in 2008.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He opened his official website &apos;SYOH YOSHIDA - ARCHIVES&apos; in 2008.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>現在は、京都を拠点に個展開催、グループ展参加など国内外で精力的に活動を続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now he is based in Kyoto and energetically working to participate in solo and group exhibitions in Japan and abroad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today he is based in Kyoto, where he energetically participates in solo and group exhibitions in Japan and abroad.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today he is based in Kyoto, where he energetically participates in solo and group exhibitions in Japan and abroad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>日本国内における作品の主要取扱い画廊は、株式会社イムラアートギャラリー。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imura art gallery handles his work dominantly in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imura Art Gallery primarily handles his work in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within Japan, the Imura Art Gallery manages most of his work.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>画風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Style of painting</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Style of painting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His artistic style</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>日常の何気ない風景を日本画の体表的な材料である墨と胡粉のみを用いて表現しており、その独自の視点と色彩感覚で描かれた光と影の世界は浮遊感があり映像的です。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He expresses daily casual scenes using only black ink and chalk, the typical material used for the Japanese painting, and creates the world of light and shadow with his unique perspectives and sense of color, bringing a feeling of floating and image.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His work expresses daily casual scenes using only black ink and chalk (the typical materials used for Japanese painting) and he creates a world of light and shadow with his unique perspectives and sense of tonality, by which he creates a sense of floating images.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using only black ink and chalk--the typical materials in Japanese-style painting--he expresses the essence of relaxed, everyday life, and conjures up a world of light and shadow through his unique perspectives and sense of tonality, with which he creates an airy, floating impression in his images.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。two most surface-related→typical（体表的は代表的の誤りであると判断しました）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日本画の伝統的な素材や技法を継承しつつ、新たな絵画表現を追求しています。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While taking over the traditional material and technique of the Japanese painting, he seeks a new way of expression in painting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though he assumes the traditional material and technique of Japanese painting, he seeks a new means of expression through his work.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he has accepted the legacy of Japanese-style painting by using its traditional materials and techiques, he seeks a fresh new mode of expression through his work.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。Though→Although</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>1984年 愛知県名古屋市生まれ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1984 Born in Nagoya City, Aichi Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1984: Born in Nagoya City, Aichi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1984: Born in Nagoya City, Aichi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>2003年 成安造形短期大学造形芸術科美術コース日本画クラス卒業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2003 Graduated from Seian Junior College of Art and Design, Faculty of Art and Design, Art Course, Japanese Painting Class</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2003: Graduated from Seian Junior College of Art and Design, Faculty of Art and Design, Art Course, Japanese Painting Class</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2003: Graduated from Seian Junior College of Art and Design, Faculty of Art and Design, Art Course, Japanese Painting Class</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>2006年 大阪成蹊大学芸術学部美術・工芸学科絵画表現領域日本画工房卒業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2006 Graduated from Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art &amp; Design, Arts and Crafts Course, Painting Expression, Japanese Painting Workshop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2006: Graduated from Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art &amp; Design, Arts and Crafts Course, Painting Expression, Japanese Painting Workshop</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2006: Graduated from Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art and Design, Arts and Crafts Course, Painting Expression, Japanese Painting Workshop</e>
<cmt>&amp;→ and　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>2008年 大阪成蹊大学芸術学部美術学科絵画表現領域日本画工房研究課程修了</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2008 Completed the Postgraduate Course of Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art &amp; Design, Art Course, Painting Expression, Japanese Painting Workshop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2008: Completed the Postgraduate Course of Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art &amp; Design, Art Course, Painting Expression, Japanese Painting Workshop</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2008: Completed the postgraduate art course &quot;Painting Expression&quot; (a Japanese-style painting workshop) offered at Osaka Seikei University by the Faculty of Art and Design.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>受賞歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awards</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>2006年 「大阪成蹊大学芸術学部綜合芸術センター学生企画公募 2006」最優秀企画賞、個展開催</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2006, he won the award for the Best Exhibition Plan in &quot;Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art &amp; Design, Composite Art Center, Student Exhibition Plan Competition 2006,&quot; and held the solo exhibition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2006, he won the award for the Best Exhibition Plan in &quot;Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art &amp; Design, Composite Art Center, Student Exhibition Plan Competition 2006,&quot; and held a solo exhibition.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2006, Yoshida won the award for the Best Exhibition Plan in the &apos;2006 Student Exhibition Plan Competition of the Composite Art Center of Osaka Seikei University, Faculty of Art and Design,&apos; and also held a solo art exhibition.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>2007年 「京都府美術工芸新鋭選抜展 -新しい波- 2007」入選、正式出品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2007, his work was selected for &quot;Selected Artists in Kyoto -2007 New Wave-&quot; and officially exhibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2007, his work was selected for &quot;Selected Artists in Kyoto -2007 New Wave-&quot; and officially exhibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2007, his work was selected for &apos;Selected Artists in Kyoto -2007 New Wave-&apos; and put on official display.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>2008年 「第11回岡本太郎現代芸術大賞」入選、正式出品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2008, his work was selected for &quot;The 11th Taro Okamoto Award for Contemporary Art&quot; and officially exhibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2008, his work was selected for &quot;The 11th Taro Okamoto Award for Contemporary Art&quot; and officially exhibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2008, his work was selected for &apos;The Eleventh Taro Okamoto Award for Contemporary Art&apos; and put on official display.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>コミッションワーク</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commissioned work</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commissioned work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commissioned work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>2006年 「KAWASHIMA YUKATA COLLECTION 2006」株式会社川島織物セルコン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2006 &quot;KAWASHIMA YUKATA COLLECTION 2006&quot; by Kawashima Selkon Textiles Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2006: &quot;KAWASHIMA YUKATA COLLECTION 2006&quot; by Kawashima Selkon Textiles Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2006: &apos;KAWASHIMA YUKATA COLLECTION 2006&apos; by Kawashima Selkon Textiles Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TMA(id:141692), Water Carrier(id:161898), Goki(id:7107), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>