<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>橘俊綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Toshitsuna</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Toshitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Toshitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>橘 俊綱（たちばな の としつな、長元元年（1028年） - 寛治8年7月14日 (旧暦)（1094年8月27日））は、平安時代後期の官人・歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Toshitsuna (1028 - August 27, 1094) was a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) and poet of the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Toshitsuna (1028 - August 27, 1094) was a government official and poet during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>of→during; changed &quot;period&quot; to lowercase for consistency with other articles; eliminated &quot;(esp. one of low to medium rank)&quot; as it was awkward, seemed unecessary and is not consistent with other articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Toshitsuna (1028 - September 2, 1094) was a government official and poet during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>August 27 をSeptember 2 に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>讃岐守橘俊遠の養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was an adopted son of Toshitsuna TACHIBANA, Sanuki no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was an adopted son of Toshitsuna TACHIBANA who was the Sanuki no kami (governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>If &quot;俊綱&quot; is Toshitsuna, I am concerned about the reading for &quot;俊遠&quot; but I cannot find information on it</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was an adopted son of Toshitsuna TACHIBANA who was the Sanuki no kami (governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>実父は関白藤原頼通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His biological father was Chancellor FUJIWARA no Yorimichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His biological father was Chancellor FUJIWARA no Yorimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His biological father was Chancellor FUJIWARA no Yorimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正四位上・修理大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was granted Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade) and Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was granted Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade) and Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was granted Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) and Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>Rank Upper の間にカンマを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>伏見修理大夫と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Fushimi Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs of Fushimi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Fushimi Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs of Fushimi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Fushimi Shuri no daibu (Master of the Office of Palace Repairs of Fushimi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原師実とは両親を同じくする兄弟であるた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He and FUJIWARA no Morosane were brothers whose parents were the same.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshitsuna and FUJIWARA no Morosane were brothers with the same parents.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Toshitsuna&quot; since this is a new paragraph; Though I think &quot;biological brothers&quot; would be more straightforward, it is not explicitly stated, so I only fixed the grammar to read as smoothly as possible</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshitsuna and FUJIWARA no Morosane were brothers with the same parents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、実父の正妻隆姫女王と異母兄藤原通房への配慮から養子に出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Toshitsuna was put up for adoption in considerations for his father&apos;s legal wife, Princess Takahime and his half brother, FUJIWARA no Michifus.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Toshitsuna was put up for adoption in consideration for his father&apos;s legal wife, Princess Takahime and his half brother, FUJIWARA no Michifusa.</e>
<cmt>Michifus→Michifusa; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Toshitsuna was put up for adoption in consideration for his father&apos;s legal wife, Princess Takahime and his half brother, FUJIWARA no Michifusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>丹波国、播磨国、讃岐国、近江国、但馬国などの国司を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He consecutively filled the post of kokushi (provincial governors) of Tamba Province, Harima Province, Sanuki Province, Omi Province, and Tajima Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He consecutively filled the post of Kokushi (provincial governor) for Tamba Province, Harima Province, Sanuki Province, Omi Province, and Tajima Province.</e>
<cmt>of→for; capitalized &quot;Kokushi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He consecutively filled the post of Kokushi (provincial governor) of Tamba Province, Harima Province, Sanuki Province, Omi Province, and Tajima Province.</e>
<cmt>Kokushi (provincial governor) for をof に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その高貴な血筋に反して官位は正四位上にとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was not granted higher than Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank Upper Grade) for his high blood line.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to his bloodline, Toshitsuna was unable to receive a rank higher than Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;he&quot; to &quot;Toshitsuna&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to his bloodline, Toshitsuna was unable to receive a rank higher than Shoshiinojo.</e>
<cmt>7セル目に既出のため、 (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、その門地と財力により彼の西洞院邸は承暦3年（1079年）藤原賢子（白河天皇中宮）の出産の際の里邸になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However his residence, Nishi no toin-tei Premises became the place where FUJIWARA no Kenshi (Chugu of Emperor Shirakawa) gave birth a child because of his family origin and financial strength.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His residence in the Nishi no Toin-Tei Premises, however, became the birthplace for the son of FUJIWARA no Kenshi (Chugu of Emperor Shirakawa) in 1079 due to his family origin and financial strength.</e>
<cmt>added year; changed location of &quot;however&quot;; capitalized &quot;Toin-Tei&quot;; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His residence in the Nishi no Toin-Tei Premises, however, became the birthplace for the son of FUJIWARA no Kenshi (Chugu (Empress) of Emperor Shirakawa) in 1079 due to his family origin and financial strength.</e>
<cmt>Chugu に (Empress) を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>造園に造詣が深く、日本最古の庭園書である『作庭記』の著者の有力候補とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having a deep knowledge of landscape gardening, he is named as the most potential author of &quot;Sakutei-ki, &quot;the oldest book concerning gardens in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having a deep knowledge of landscape gardening, Toshitsuna became the leading candidate to author the &quot;Sakutei-ki, &quot;the oldest book concerning gardens in Japan.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;he&quot; to &quot;Toshitsuna&quot; since this is a new paragraph; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having a deep knowledge of landscape gardening, Toshitsuna became the leading candidate to author the &quot;Sakutei-ki, &quot;the oldest book concerning gardens in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>伏見の別邸は俊綱自ら造園を行い、「風流勝他、水石幽奇也」（『中右記』）と賞賛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshitsuna himself designed the garden of his second residence in Fushimi. which was highly praised in &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada) as &quot;a graceful garden with simple and elegant water and stones.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「風流勝他、水石幽奇也」は風流があり、水石が幽玄であると訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshitsuna himself designed the garden of his second residence in Fushimi. which was highly praised in &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada) as &quot;a graceful garden with simple elegant water and stones.&quot;</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshitsuna himself designed the garden of his second residence in Fushimi. which was highly praised in &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada) as &quot;a graceful garden with simple elegant water and stones.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『今鏡』において、弟の藤原師実が伏見の別邸を突然訪ねるも俊綱が豪奢にもてなした話や、俊綱が白河天皇に対して、院が造営した鳥羽離宮より伏見の別邸の方が優れていると問答をしたとの話が語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imakagami (the Mirror of the Present) describes that Toshitsuna lavished hospitality to his brother, FUJIWARA no Morosanehe, in his visit to the residence in Fushimi and that Toshitsuna was asked and responded Emperor Shirakaw that his residence was gracious than Toba Rikyu (Toba Imperial Villa) built for the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Imakagami (The Mirror of the Present), it is described how Toshitsuna lavishly showed hospitality to his brother FUJIWARA no Morosanehe during a visit to his residence in Fushimi, and in response to Emperor Shirakawa, there was discussion regarding whether or not Toshitsune&apos;s residence was more gracious than the Toba Rikyu (Toba Imperial Villa) built for the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>fixed typos; re-translated the second half since I was unable to understand it clearly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Imakagami&quot; (The Mirror of the Present), it is described how Toshitsuna lavishly showed hospitality to his brother FUJIWARA no Morosane during a visit to his second residence in Fushimi, and in response to Emperor Shirakawa, there was discussion regarding whether or not Toshitsune&apos;s second residence was more gracious than the Toba Rikyu (Toba Imperial Villa) built for the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>Imakagami にダブルコーテーションを追記しました。Morosanehe を Morosane に修正しました。his residence, Toshitsune&apos;s residence に各々 second を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>歌人としても活躍し、天喜4年（1056年）皇后寛子春秋歌合にも参加、承暦2年（1078年）内裏歌合には指導的役割を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also a remarkable poet; he participated in Empress Hiroko&apos;s Spring and Autumn Uta-awase as a poet in 1056 and in Dairi Utaawase (the palace poetry contest) as a teacher in 1078.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshitsuna was also a remarkable poet, participating in Empress Hiroko&apos;s Spring and Autumn Uta-awase as a poet in 1056 and in Dairi Uta-awase (a palace poetry contest) as a teacher in 1078.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;He&quot; to &quot;Toshitsuna&quot; since this is a new paragraph; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshitsuna was also a remarkable poet, participating in Empress Kanshi&apos;s Spring and Autumn Uta-awase as a poet in 1056 and in Dairi Uta-awase (a palace poetry contest) as a teacher in 1078.</e>
<cmt>Empress Hiroko を Empress Kanshi に修正しました。※用語集ではHiroko となっていますが、Empress Hiroko では Google books で一件もヒットしません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また自邸でもしばしば歌合・歌会を催した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He often held poetry contests or poetry gatherings at his residence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, he often held poetry contests and poetry gatherings at his residence.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Additionally&quot; for &quot;また&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, he often held poetry contests and poetry readings at his residence.</e>
<cmt>poetry gatherings をpoetry readings に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>特に伏見の別邸は能因・源経信・藤原通俊ら同時代の歌人たちの交流の場にもなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular his second residence in Fushimi was a meeting place of contemporary poets including Noin, MINAMOTO no Tsunenobu, and FUJIWARA no Michitoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, Toshitsuna&apos;s second residence in Fushimi was a meeting place for contemporary poets, including Noin, MINAMOTO no Tsunenobu, and FUJIWARA no Michitoshi.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, Toshitsuna&apos;s second residence in Fushimi was a meeting place for contemporary poets, including Noin, MINAMOTO no Tsunenobu, and FUJIWARA no Michitoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>『後拾遺和歌集』以下勅撰和歌集に合計12首入集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A total of twelve poets were selected for Chokusen wakashu (anthology of Japanese poetry compiled by Imperial command) including &quot;GoShui wakashu&quot;, Later gleanings of Japanese poems.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A total of twelve of his poems were selected for Chokusen Wakashu (Anthology of Japanese Poetry Compiled by Imperial Command), including &quot;Go Shui Wakashu&quot; (Later Gleanings of Japanese Poems).</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Wakashu&quot; and words for the collection titles where appropriate; fixed parenthesis and punctuation; changed &quot;poets&quot; to &quot;poems&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A total of twelve of his poems were selected for Chokusen Wakashu (Anthology of Japanese Poetry Compiled by Imperial Command), including &quot;Goshui Wakashu&quot; (Later Gleanings of Japanese Poems).</e>
<cmt>Go Shui をGoshui に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>説話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Setsuwa (anecdotes)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;Setsuwa&quot; as it seemed unecessary and unrelated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>『宇治拾遺物語』には、俊綱は昔尾張国の「俊綱」（すんごう）と言う僧侶であった時、熱田神宮の大宮司に侮辱を受けたが、のちに関白の息子として生まれ変わり尾張守となって、今度は熱田神宮の大宮司にかつての雪辱をした、との説話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji), Toshitsuna was insulted by the chief priest of Ise-jingu Shrinewhen when he was a priest of Owari Province, but he was reborn to be a son of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and revenged the chief priest of Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji), Toshitsuna was insulted by the chief priest of Ise-jingu Shrine while Toshitsuna was a priest of Owari Province, but he was reborn as a son of the Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and had revenge against the chief priest of Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally; fixed typos and spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji), Toshitsuna was insulted by the Daiguji (supreme priest) of Ise-jingu Shrine while Toshitsuna was a priest of Owari Province called Sungo, but he was reborn as a son of the Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and had revenge against the Daiguji of Atsuta-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>大宮司chief priest をDaiguji (supreme priest) に修正しました。「俊綱」（すんごう）訳漏れのためcalled Sungo を追記しました。ｔhe chief priest of Ise-jingu Shrine をthe Daiguji of Atsuta-jingu Shrine に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>『十訓抄』等にも、俊綱に関する説話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jikkinsho&quot; (Miscellany of Ten Maxims) and other books also include his setsuwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jikkinsho&quot; (Miscellany of Ten Maxims) and other books also include anecdotes that include Toshitsuna..</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more naturally; changed &quot;setsuwa&quot; to &quot;anecdotes&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jikkinsho&quot; (Miscellany of Ten Maxims) and other books also include anecdotes regarding Toshitsuna.</e>
<cmt>that include Toshitsuna.. をregarding Toshitsuna. に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), YOSHI438(id:174755), Tribot(id:186681), Snap55(id:89773), Ks8823(id:130146), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>