<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鬼室福信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukushin KISHITSU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukushin KISHITSU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukushin KISHITSU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鬼室 福信（きしつ ふくしん、生没年不詳）は、百済の王族・将軍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukushin KISHITSU (Kishitsu Fukushin or Gwisil Boksin, year of birth and death unknown) was a member of the loyal family of Kudara (Baekje) and general.</e>
<cmt>必要な部分に韓国語読みをRevised Romanizationで記します。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukushin KISHITSU (Boksin GWISIL, year of birth and death unknown) was a member of the loyal family of Kudara (Baekje) and general.</e>
<cmt>人名表記を指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukushin KISHITSU (Boksin GWISIL, year of birth and death unknown) was a member of the loyal family of Kudara (Baekje) and general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>義慈王の父である第30代武王 (百済)（余璋）の従子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a cousin of the 30th King of Kudara Bu (Bu-o or Mu-wang, real name was Yo Sho or Yeo Jang) who was the father of the 31th King Giji (Giji-o or Uija-wang).</e>
<cmt>余璋Yo Sho or Yeo Jang…「よ」が苗字です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a cousin of the 30th King of Baekje Mu (Bu-o or Mu-wang, real name was Sho YO or Jang Yeo) who was the father of the 31th King Uija (Giji-o or Uija-wang).</e>
<cmt>「百済」:Baekje, 「武」:Mu, 「義慈」:Uijaに変更し、「余璋」の姓名表記を指示書に合わせて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a cousin of the 30th King of Baekje Mu (Bu-o or Mu-wang, real name was Sho YO or Jang Yeo) who was the father of the 31th King Uija (Giji-o or Uija-wang).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>官位は恩率（三品官）、のち佐平（一品官）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His rank was Onsochi (third rank), later raised to Sahei (first rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was ranked as the third highest officer in Baekje, later raised to the first rank.</e>
<cmt>OnsochiもSaheiも、日本語読みと思われますので、削除して変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was ranked as the third highest officer in Baekje, later raised to the first rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>没した2か月後白村江の戦いで倭国と百済の連合軍が大敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only two months after his death, the allied forces of Yamato (Wakoku, Japan) and Kudara (Baekje, Korea) was completely defeated in the battle of Hakusukinoe (the battle of Baekgan).</e>
<cmt>白村江の戦いthe battle of Hakusukinoe (the battle of Baekgan)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After two months of his death, the allied forces of Yamato (Wakoku, Japan) and Kudara (Baekje, Korea) was completely defeated in Battle of Hakusukinoe (Battle of Baekgang).</e>
<cmt>「2ヵ月後」の訳を変更、「戦い」の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After two months of his death, the allied forces of Yamato (Wakoku, Japan) and Kudara (Baekje, Korea) was completely defeated in Battle of Hakusukinoe (Battle of Baekgang).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>義慈王時代の660年、唐と新羅の連合軍によって百済が滅亡した後も、旧臣らを糾合して抵抗運動を続け、百済の故都である泗沘城（現・忠清南道扶余郡）の奪還を試みた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although in 660 (in the period of King Giji), Kudara fell by the allied forces of Morokoshi (Tang, China) and Shiragi (Silla, Korea), even after that, Fukushin cooperated with other surviving followers in resisting and tried to regain the former capital of Kudara, Shihi-jo (Sabi-sen, present Buyeo-gun, Chungcheongnam-do).</e>
<cmt>泗沘城Shihi-jo (Sabi-sen)忠清南道Chungcheongnam-do扶余郡Buyeo-gun</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the fall of Baekje against the allied forces of the Tang Dynasty of China and Silla (Korea) in 660, the period of King Uija, he gathered the old retainers of the Baekje army and resisted them for regaining the former capital of Baekje, Sabi Castle (present Buyeo County, Chungcheongnam Province).</e>
<cmt>指示書に従い地名表記を変更し、全体を簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the fall of Baekje against the allied forces of the Tang Dynasty of China and Silla (Korea) in 660, the period of King Uija, he gathered the old retainers of the Baekje army and resisted them for regaining the former capital of Baekje, Sabi Castle (present Buyeo County, Chungcheongnam Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この頃、義慈王の王子であった扶余豊璋は、倭国との同盟の人質として倭国に滞留していたが、鬼室福信ら遺臣は、百済復興の旗印として擁するため豊璋の帰国と、倭国の軍事支援を求める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, a son of King Giji, Prince Fuyo Hosho (Buyeo Pungjang) had been in Yamato (Japan) as a hostage for the alliance between Kudara (Baekje) and Yamato; Fukushin and other followers needed Fuyo Hosho to re-establish the dynasty, so asked Yamato to send him back as well as for a support arms.</e>
<cmt>扶余豊璋Fuyo Hosho (Buyeo Pungjang)…「ふよ」が苗字。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, a son of King Uija, Prince Hosho FUYO (Pungjang BUYEO) had been in Yamato (Japan) as a hostage for the alliance between Kudara (Baekje) and Yamato; Fukushin KISHITSU and other surviving retainers asked Yamato to send Hosho back as a symbol of the re-establishment of Baekje and to provide military supports.</e>
<cmt>人名表記を、原文と指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, a son of King Uija, Prince Hosho FUYO (Pungjang BUYEO) had been in Yamato (Japan) as a hostage for the alliance between Kudara (Baekje) and Yamato; Fukushin KISHITSU and other surviving retainers asked Yamato to send Hosho back as a symbol of the re-establishment of Baekje and to provide military supports.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>斉明天皇・天智天皇は快くこれを了承し、積極的に百済復興を支援することとし、翌年正月には斉明天皇自ら、筑紫へ遠征する運びとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress of Yamato (Japan) Saimei and her son Emperor Tenji (Emperor Tenchi) fully approved of supporting Kudara in re-establishing, and in the next year, Empress Saimei herself went to Tsukushi Province (present Kyushu region of Japan).</e>
<cmt>筑紫Tsukushi Province</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress of Saimei and Emperor Tenji (Emperor Tenchi) fully agreed to this and decided to support the re-establishment of Baekje positively, and in the next year Empress Saimei herself went to Tsukushi Province (present Kyushu region of Japan).</e>
<cmt>前半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress of Saimei and Emperor Tenji (Emperor Tenchi) fully agreed to this and decided to support the re-establishment of Baekje positively, and in the next year Empress Saimei herself went to Tsukushi Province (present Kyushu region of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>『百済本紀』・『旧唐書百済伝』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kudara Hongi&quot; (History of Baekje) &quot;Kutojo Kudaraden&quot; (Volume of Records of Baekje, &quot;the Older Book of History of Tang&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kudara Hongi&quot; (History of Baekje), &quot;Kutojo Kudaraden&quot; (Old Tang History of Baekje)</e>
<cmt>『旧唐書百済伝』:Old Tang History of Baekje</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kudara Hongi&quot; (History of Baekje), &quot;Kutojo Kudaraden&quot; (Old Tang History of Baekje)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>『百済本紀』、『旧唐書百済伝』では、豊璋は翌662年5月に入国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kudara Hongi&quot; and &quot;Kutojo Kudaraden&quot;, in May, 662, Fuyo Hosho was sent back to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Kudara Hongi&quot; and &quot;Kutojo Kudaraden&quot;, Hosho got into the country in May, 662.</e>
<cmt>後半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Kudara Hongi&quot; and &quot;Kutojo Kudaraden&quot;, Hosho got into the country in May, 662.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このとき福信は王を迎えに出て、国政をみな委ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukushin greeted him and entrusted him the whole power of the administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukushin greeted and entrusted him with all the national politics.</e>
<cmt>後半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukushin greeted and entrusted him with all the national politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>倭国はこの後も福信あてに軍需物資を送り、福信も捕虜の唐人続守言らを倭国に送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Yamato kept sending military supplies to Fukushin, and Fukushin sent the captive Chinese soldiers including Shoku Shugen (Xu Shouyan) to Yamato in return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Yamato kept sending military supplies to Fukushin, and Fukushin sent the captive Chinese soldiers including Shugen SHOKU (Shouyan XU) to Yamato in return.</e>
<cmt>人名表記を指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Yamato kept sending military supplies to Fukushin, and Fukushin sent the captive Chinese soldiers including Shugen SHOKU (Shouyan XU) to Yamato in return.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>7月、扶余豊（扶余豊璋）は福信が自分を殺そうとしていることを察知し、逆に、これを殺した（出典）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, Fuyo Hosho scent Fukushin&apos;s plot to murder him, and killed Fukushin (in the record, Fuyo Hosho扶余豊璋 was written as Fuyo Ho扶余豊).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, Hosho FUYO scented Fukushin&apos;s plot to murder him, and killed Fukushin (in the record, Hosho FUYO 扶余豊璋 was written as Ho FUYO 扶余豊).</e>
<cmt>人名表記を指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, Hosho FUYO scented Fukushin&apos;s plot to murder him, and killed Fukushin (in the record, Hosho FUYO 扶余豊璋 was written as Ho FUYO 扶余豊).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>『日本書紀』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicle of Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicle of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicle of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>『日本書紀』では、663年6月に、百済王豊璋は福信の謀反を疑って捕らえ、その掌を穿って革紐で縛った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, in June, 663, King of Kudara Fuyo Hosho suspected Fukushin of treason and captured him; Fukushin was drilled a hole in his hands and tied by a leash.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, in June, 663, King of Kudara Hosho captured Fukushin on suspicion of treason and drilled a hole in his hands to strap.</e>
<cmt>簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, in June, 663, King of Kudara Hosho captured Fukushin on suspicion of treason and drilled a hole in his hands to strap.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それから諸臣に対して福信を斬るべきかと問うた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosho asked vassals whether Fukushin should be killed or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then he asked his vassals whether Fukushin should got slashed to death or not.</e>
<cmt>「斬る」をslash ~ to deathにし、訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then he asked his vassals whether Fukushin should got slashed to death or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>達率（二品官）の徳執得は「これは悪逆人であるから放しおくわけにはいかない」と答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Dachisochi (second rank) Toku Shitsutoku said that he was too cruel to be allowed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shitsutoku TOKU in the second highest official rank said that he was too cruel to be allowed.</e>
<cmt>人名表記を指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shitsutoku TOKU in the second highest official rank said that he was too cruel to be allowed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>福信は執得に唾して罵ったが、王は福信を斬らせ、その首を塩漬けにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Fukushin protested, spitting at Shintoku and cursing, the King ordered followers to kill him and salted his head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Fukushin protested spitting on Shintoku and cursing, the King did him slashed and salted his head.</e>
<cmt>後半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Fukushin protested spitting on Shintoku and cursing, the King did him slashed and salted his head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>福信の近親者と思われる鬼室集斯は天智4年2月（665年）（即位元年起算よると天智10年正月）に天智天皇から小錦下の位階を与えられ、天智8年（669年）近江国蒲生郡に送られ、そこで没したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 665, Shushi KISHITSU (Kishitsu Shushi or Gwisil Jipsa), who is considered to have been a relative of Fukushin, was given Shokinge (fifth rank); in 669, he was sent to Gamo-no-kori County, Omi Province, and died there.</e>
<cmt>鬼室集斯Shushi KISHITSU (Kishitsu Shushi or Gwisil Jipsa)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shushi KISHITSU (Jipsa GWISIL), who is considered as a relative of Fukushin, was given Shokinge (fifth court rank) by Emperor Tenji in February, 665 (in February, 671 due to the regnal year), and in 669 he was sent to Gamo County, Omi Province and died there.</e>
<cmt>「即位元年起算よると天智10年正月」などの訳漏れを補足しました。「蒲生郡」: Gamo Coutny</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shushi KISHITSU (Jipsa GWISIL), who is considered as a relative of Fukushin, was given Shokinge (fifth court rank) by Emperor Tenji in February, 665 (in February, 671 due to the regnal year), and in 669 he was sent to Gamo County, Omi Province and died there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>墓所は鬼室神社（滋賀県日野町 (滋賀県)）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave is located at Kishitsu-jinja Shrine (Hinocho, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave is located at Kishitsu-jinja Shrine (Hino Town, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>住所表記を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave is located at Kishitsu-jinja Shrine (Hino Town, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 田英(id:85936), Izayohi(id:13095), Kinori(id:443), Loveless(id:129239), Lupinoid(id:68), Kusunose(id:5719), Chobot(id:20846), トホホ川(id:50502), 葉月(id:25674), Alexbot(id:157199), Yuki80(id:163805), Tatsujin28(id:9300), Uraios(id:72687), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>