<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平高清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Takakiyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Takakiyo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Takakiyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 高清（たいら の たかきよ／平 六代　たいら の ろくだい）、承安 (日本)3年（1173年） - 建久10年2月5日 (旧暦)（1199年3月3日））は、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代前期にかけての平家一門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Takakiyo (TAIRA no Rokudai) 1173-March 3, 1199) was a member of the Taira clan who lived from the end of Heian period to early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Takakiyo (TAIRA no Rokudai) 1173 - March 3, 1199) was a member of the Taira clan who lived from the end of Heian period to early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Takakiyo (TAIRA no Rokudai) 1173 - March 10, 1199) was a member of the Taira clan who lived from the end of Heian period to early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は平維盛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was TAIRA no Koremori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was TAIRA no Koremori.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was TAIRA no Koremori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平清盛の曾孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the great-grandchild of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the great-grandchild of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the great-grandchild of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は権大納言藤原成親の娘・新大納言局。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was Shindainagon no Tsubine, who was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Narichika, who had a title of Gon no Dainagon (Provisional Major Councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was Shindainagon no Tsubine, who was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Narichika, who had a title of Gon no Dainagon (Provisional Major Councilor).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was Shindainagon no Tsubine, who was the daughter of FUJIWARA no Narichika, who had a title of Gon no Dainagon (Provisional Major Councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>幼名は平正盛から数えて直系の六代目に当たることに因んで「六代（ろくだい）」と名づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was the direct sixth descendant of TAIRA no Masamori, he was given the childhood name of &quot;Rokudai&quot; (the sixth direct descendant).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he was the direct sixth descendant of TAIRA no Masamori, he was given the childhood name of &quot;Rokudai&quot; (the sixth direct descendant).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he was the direct sixth descendant of TAIRA no Masamori, he was given the childhood name of &quot;Rokudai&quot; (the sixth direct descendant).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>高清という実名は高野山の歴史を記した『高野春秋編年輯録』などに記載されているが、『平家物語』が幼名の六代を用い続けているために「平 六代」の名前で呼ばれるのが一般的である（本項目でも、特に断りが無い限りは「（平）六代」と表記する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real name, Takakiyo, is recorded in &quot;Koya Shunju hennen shuroku&quot; (Compilation of many spring and falls of Koya) but since &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Taira family) continued to use the childhood name, Rokudai, it was common to call him as &quot;Taira Rokudai&quot; (In this clause, he will be referred as &quot;(Taira) Rokudai&quot; unless there is some issues involved).</e>
<cmt>『高野春秋編年輯録』→&quot;Koya Shunju hennen shuroku&quot; (Compilation of the many spring and falls of Koya)と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real name, Takakiyo, is recorded in &quot;Koya Shunju hennen shuroku&quot; (Compilation of many spring and falls of Koya) but since &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Taira family) continued to use the childhood name, Rokudai, it was common to call him as &quot;Taira Rokudai&quot; (In this clause, he will be referred as &quot;(Taira) Rokudai&quot; unless there is some issues involved).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real name, Takakiyo, is recorded in &quot;Koya Shunju hennen shuroku&quot; (Compilation of many spring and falls of Koya) but since &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Taira family) continued to use the childhood name, Rokudai, it was common to call him as &apos;Taira Rokudai&apos; (In this clause, he will be referred as &apos;(Taira) Rokudai&apos; unless there is some issues involved).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）、源義仲の攻勢の前に平氏が都落ちを決意したとき、維盛は都に慣れ親しんでいる妻を共に西国に落ち延びさせることは忍び難いとして、妻子を都に残して一門と共に西走する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Taira clan decided to leave Kyoto while under attacks by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka in 1183, Koremori felt uneasy to make his wife who was used to Miyako (Kyoto) to die with him in western countries from Kinki district and left his wife and child in Miyako to travel west along with his followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Taira clan decided to leave Kyoto while under attacks by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka in 1183, Koremori felt uneasy to make his wife who was used to Miyako (Kyoto) to die with him in western countries from Kinki district and left his wife and child in Miyako to travel west along with his followers.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Taira clan decided to leave Kyoto while under attacks by MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka in 1183, Koremori felt uneasy to make his wife who was used to Miyako (Kyoto) to die with him in western countries from Kinki district and left his wife and child in Miyako to travel west along with his followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このとき維盛は妻に対して子供のことを頼むと共に、自らに何かあったら再婚してほしいと言い残した（『平家物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koremori pleaded to his wife to take care of his child and told her that if something happened to him, he wants her to remarry (&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koremori pleaded to his wife to take care of his child and told her that if something happened to him, he wants her to remarry (&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koremori pleaded to his wife to take care of his child and told her that if something happened to him, he wants her to remarry (&quot;Heike Monogatari&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>六代は母と共に京都普照寺奥大覚寺北に潜伏していたが、平氏滅亡後の文治元年（1185年）12月、北条時政の捜索によって捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokudai hid along with his mother in Oku Daikaku-ji Temple of Fusho-ji Temple, Kyoto, but was captured by the searching Tokimasa HOJO after the Taira clan fell in December 1185.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokudai hid along with his mother in Oku Daikaku-ji Temple of Fusho-ji Temple, Kyoto, but was captured after a search conducted by Tokimasa HOJO after the Taira clan fell in December 1185.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokudai hid along with his mother in Oku Daikaku-ji Temple of Fusho-ji Temple, Kyoto, but was captured after a search conducted by Tokimasa HOJO after the Taira clan fell in December 1185.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>清盛の曾孫に当たることから本来なら鎌倉に送られて斬首になるところであったが、文覚上人の助命嘆願があって処刑を免れ、その身柄は文覚に預けられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was the great-grandson of Kiyomori, it was natural to send him to Kamakura to face decapitation, but he was dismissed due to the pleading by Priest Mongaku shonin to spear his life and was excepted from the execution, and his cutody was passed over to Mongaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he was the great-grandson of Kiyomori, it was natural to send him to Kamakura to face decapitation, but he was dismissed due to a plead by Priest Mongaku shonin to spare his life and was exempted from execution, and his cutody was passed over to Mongaku.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he was the great-grandson of Kiyomori, it was natural to send him to Kamakura to face decapitation, but he was dismissed due to a plead by Priest Mongaku shonin to spare his life and was exempted from execution, and his custody was passed over to Mongaku.</e>
<cmt>custodyスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、前述の維盛の妻（六代の母）は夫の死後に頼朝の信頼が厚い公卿の吉田経房と再婚しており、この事も六代の助命と関係している事が考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Rokudai was spared for his life since the wife of Koremori (mother of Rokudai) remarried Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, who was the Kugyo deeply trusted by Yoritomo, after the death of her husband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Rokudai spared his life since the wife of Koremori (mother of Rokudai) remarried Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, who was the Kugyo and deeply trusted by Yoritomo, after the death of her husband.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Rokudai spared his life since the wife of Koremori (mother of Rokudai) remarried Tsunefusa YOSHIDA, who was the Kugyo and deeply trusted by Yoritomo, after the death of her husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>文治5年（1189年）に六代は剃髪して妙覚と号す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokudai performed Teihatsu (tonsure) in 1189 and received the Go (byname) of Myokaku (妙覚).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokudai performed Teihatsu (tonsure) in 1189 and received the Go (byname) of Myokaku (妙覚).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokudai performed Teihatsu (tonsure) in 1189 and received the Go (byname) of Myokaku.</e>
<cmt>漢字表記は不要と考え削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>建久5年（1194年）には大江広元を通じて源頼朝と謁見し、異心無く出家したことを伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made an audience with MINAMOTO no Yoritomo through OE no Hiromoto in 1194 and told him that he became a priest without a plan for treason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had an audience with MINAMOTO no Yoritomo through OE no Hiromoto in 1194 and told him that he became a priest without plans of treason.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had an audience with MINAMOTO no Yoritomo through OE no Hiromoto in 1194 and told him that he became a priest without plans of treason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかしこのとき、頼朝は六代の姿を見てその聡明さを見抜き、危険視したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that Yoritomo saw through Rokudai about his wiseness and regarded him dangerous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that Yoritomo saw through Rokudai and regarded him as dangerous.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that Yoritomo saw through Rokudai and regarded him as dangerous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>が、このときはあまり気に留めず、六代をある寺の別当職に任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoritomo did not take into account at that time and assigned Rokudai as the Betto shiki post (secretary in the office of temple) to one temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoritomo did not take this into account at that time and assigned Rokudai as the Betto shiki post (secretary in the office of temple) to one temple.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoritomo did not take this into account at that time and assigned Rokudai as the Betto shiki post (secretary in the office of temple) to one temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>その後、六代は僧としての修行に出て諸国を回った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He later travelled around provinces on his trip for ascetic training of monk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later travelled around provinces on his trip for ascetic monk training.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later travelled around provinces on his trip for ascetic monk training.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ところが頼朝の死後、自分の庇護者であった文覚が土御門通親襲撃計画を企てたとして隠岐国に流罪に処されると、六代も猪熊の宿所にて検非違使の安倍資兼によって捕らえられ、田越川にて処刑されてしまったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Mongaku, who was a patron of him, was charged for scheming to attack Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO and was exiled to Oki Province, Rokudai was also captured by Sukekane ABE of Kebiishi (an officer in the Office of Police and Judicial Chief) at the lodging of Inokuma and was executed in Tagoe-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Mongaku, who was a patron, was charged for scheming to attack Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO and was exiled to Oki Province, Rokudai was also captured by Sukekane ABE of Kebiishi (an officer in the Office of Police and Judicial Chief) at the lodging of Inokuma and was executed in Tagoe-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Mongaku, who was a patron, was charged for scheming to attack Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO and was exiled to Oki Province, Rokudai was also captured by Sukekane ABE of Kebiishi (an officer in the Office of Police and Judicial Chief) at the lodging of Inokuma and was executed in Tagoe-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>享年27。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of twenty-seven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of twenty-seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>没年は建久9年（1198年）、元久2年（1205年）という説あり、斬られた場所も『平家物語』諸本で異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were theories that claim that the year he died was 1198 and 1205, and the place of his death differ in various books of &quot;Heike Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were theories that claim that the year he died was 1198 and 1205, and the place of his death differ in various books of &quot;Heike Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were theories that claim that the year he died was 1198 and 1205, and the place of his death differ in various books of &quot;Heike Monogatari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>墓所：逗子市史跡指定地とされている田越川辺小名柳作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His grave: It is kona and Ryusaku in Tagoe-gawa River district designated as a historic district of Zushi City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His grave: It is kona and Ryusaku in Tagoe-gawa River district designated as a historic district of Zushi City.</e>
<cmt>Robert: This doesn’t quite makes sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His grave: It is at Kona Yanagisaku, Tagoegawa District designated as a historic district of Zushi City.</e>
<cmt>田越川辺小名柳作→Kona Yanagisaku, Tagoegawa District</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>六代の死により、清盛の嫡流は完全に断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the death of Rokudai, the direct descendants of Kiyomori was completely annihilated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The direct descendants of Kiyomori were completely annihilated by the death of Rokudai,</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The direct descendants of Kiyomori were completely annihilated by the death of Rokudai,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), ゐ(id:795), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Point136(id:211299), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Kamakura(id:472), Kouko0515(id:100370), シェーラ(id:17988), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>