<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土方歳三</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo HIJIKATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo HIJIKATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo HIJIKATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>Infobox 軍人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A soldier</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A soldier</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A soldier</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>土方 歳三（ひじかた としぞう）、天保6年5月5日 (旧暦)（1835年5月31日） - 明治2年5月11日 (旧暦)（1869年6月20日））は、新選組副長、蝦夷共和国陸軍奉行並箱館市中取締裁判局頭取。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo HIJIKATA (6th Year of Tenpo, May 5th (Lunar Calendar)(May 31, 1835) - 2nd Year of Meiji, May 11th (Lunar Calendar)(June 20, 1869)) is the vice commander of Shinsen-gumi, vice-minister of the Army for Ezo Republic, and also chief of the Court for Torishimari of Hakodate city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo HIJIKATA (6th year of Tenpo, May 5th (Lunar Calendar)(May 31, 1835) - 2nd year of Meiji, May 11th (Lunar Calendar)(June 20, 1869)) was the vice commander of Shinsen-gumi, vice-minister of the Army for Ezo Republic, and also chief of the Court for Torishimari of Hakodate city.</e>
<cmt>副長の表現としては、他に&quot;sub-commander&quot;、&quot;vice captain&quot;、&quot;secretary&quot;なども見られる箱館市中取締裁判局頭取はセル103を見ると、箱館市中取締と陸海軍裁判局頭取のことだと思われる。定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo HIJIKATA (6th year of Tenpo, May 5th (Lunar Calendar)(May 31, 1835) - 2nd year of Meiji, May 11th (Lunar Calendar)(June 20, 1869)) was the vice commander of Shinsen-gumi, vice-minister of the Army for Ezo Republic, and also chief of the Court for Torishimari of Hakodate city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>諱は義豊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imina is Yoshitoyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His imina (posthumous name) is Yoshitoyo.</e>
<cmt>His 使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His imina (posthumous name) is Yoshitoyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>雅号は豊玉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pseudonym is Hogyoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His pseudonym is Hogyoku.</e>
<cmt>His 使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His pseudonym is Hogyoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幕末期の幕臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A vassal of the Tokugawa Shogunate at the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a vassal of the Tokugawa Shogunate at the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Hie was 使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a vassal of the Tokugawa Shogunate at the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>新選組鬼の副長として皆に恐れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Was feared by all as the vice commander of Shinsen-gumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Was feared by all as the vice commander of Shinsen-gumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Was feared by all as the vice commander of Shinsen-gumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>家紋は左三つ巴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family crest is Hidari Mitsudomoe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family crest is Hidari Mitsudomoe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family crest is Hidari Mitsudomoe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>多摩・試衛館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tama/Shiei-kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tama/Shiei-kan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tama/Shiei-kan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>武蔵国多摩郡石田(いしだ)村（現在の東京都日野市石田）に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born in Ishida village, Tama district, Mussashi province (is now Ishida, Hino city, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Ishida village, Tama district, Mussashi province (is now Ishida, Hino city, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>Hie was 使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Ishida village, Tama district, Musashi province (is now Ishida, Hino city, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>タイプミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>(6人兄弟の末っ子とされてきたが、近年になって発見された資料により、実は10人兄弟の末っ子であったことが判明した。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He has been said to be the youngest among 6 brothers and sisters, but materials discovered in recent years revealed that he was actually the youngest among 10 brothers and sisters.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He has been said to be the youngest among 6 brothers and sisters, but materials discovered in recent years revealed that he was actually the youngest among 10 brothers and sisters.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He has been said to be the youngest among 6 brothers and sisters, but materials discovered in recent years revealed that he was actually the youngest among 10 brothers and sisters.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>土方家は、多摩地方に広がる豪農の家系で「お大尽」とよばれる大百姓であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The HIJIKATA family were major farmers who come from a family line of rich farmers living widely in Tama region, that are called &quot;Odaijin&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The HIJIKATA family was a wealthy farmer called &quot;Odaijin&quot; who had farmed on large stretches of land in the Tama region for generations.</e>
<cmt>書き換え</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The HIJIKATA family was a wealthy farmer called &quot;Odaijin&quot; who had farmed on large stretches of land in the Tama region for generations.</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>出生前に父を失っており、6歳の時に母も失い次兄の喜六夫妻に育てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lost his father before birth and also lost his mother at the age of 6, and was brought up by his second oldest brother, Kiroku and Kiroku&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lost his father before he was born and his mother at the age of 6, and he was brought up by his second oldest brother, Kiroku and Kiroku&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>minor change</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lost his father before he was born and his mother at the age of 6, and he was brought up by his second oldest brother, Kiroku and Kiroku&apos;s wife.</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>これまで11歳の時に江戸上野の「松坂屋いとう呉服店」（現在の松坂屋上野店）へ奉公に出、すぐに番頭と喧嘩をし、日野に戻ってきてしまった、と伝えられていたが、先ごろ発表された石田村の人別帳控により、数えの11歳時は石田村に在住しており、奉公には出ていないことが判明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to now, it has been said that he went to work at &quot;Matsuzakaya Ito Gofuku store&quot; (is now Matsuzakaya Ueno store) in Ueno, Edo at the age of 11, and soon quaralled with the head clerk and returned to Hino, but according to a copy of Ninbetsu-cho of Ishida village which has been made public recently, it has become clear that he has been living in Ishida village when he was 11 years old, and has not gone to work in the store.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until now, it has been said that he went to work at &quot;Matsuzakaya Ito Gofuku store&quot; (present-day Matsuzakaya Ueno store) in Ueno, Edo at the age of 11, but soon quaralled with the head clerk and returned to Hino; according to a newly published copy of Ninbetsu-cho of Ishida village it became clear that he was living in Ishida village when he was 11 years old, and therefore had not yet gone to work at the store.</e>
<cmt>部分的に書き直し；　店名表記、確認できず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until now, it has been said that he went to work at &quot;Matsuzakaya Ito Gofuku store&quot; (present-day Matsuzakaya Ueno store) in Ueno, Edo at the age of 11, but soon quarreled with the head clerk and returned to Hino; according to a newly published copy of Ninbetsu-cho of Ishida village it became clear that he was living in Ishida village when he was 11 years old, and therefore had not yet gone to work at the store.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>欠損もあるが、この人別帳から、歳三が奉公に出ていたのは数えで14歳～24歳の10年間と考えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although some parts are missing from this Ninbetsu-cho, it has come to be assumed that Toshizo went to work for a period of 10 years from the age of 14 to 24 (counted in the old Japanese way).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are some missing parts based on this Ninbetsu-cho it is assumed that Toshizo went to work for a period of 10 years from the age of 14 to 24 (counted in the old Japanese way).</e>
<cmt>文章前半書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are some missing parts based on this Ninbetsu-cho it is assumed that Toshizo went to work for a period of 10 years from the age of 14 to 24 (counted in the old Japanese way).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>17歳の時には松坂屋上野店の支店である江戸伝馬町の木綿問屋（上野店の鶴店に対し、亀店（かめだな）と称された）に奉公に出され、そこで女性問題を起こして（番頭に衆道関係を迫られたとも言われている）日野に戻った、という伝説もあるが、前述の人別帳の存在から、現在ではその信憑性が疑問視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a legend that he was sent to work in a cotton wholesale store (was called Kamedana, in comparison with Ueno store which was called Tsurudana) in Edo Tenma-cho, a branch of Matsuzakaya Ueno store, but had problems with a woman there (there is also a rumour that he was forced sexual relationship by the head clerk) and returned to Hino, but due to the existence of the Ninbetsu-cho described above, reliability of such such stories are now doubted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a legend that he was sent to work at a cotton wholesale store (called Kamedana, in comparison with the Ueno store which was called Tsurudana) in Edo Tenma-cho, a branch of Matsuzakaya Ueno store, but because he had problems with a woman there (there is also a rumour that he was forced into a sexual relationship by the head clerk) he returned to Hino; however, due to the existence of the Ninbetsu-cho described above, the reliability of such such stories are now in doubt.</e>
<cmt>部分的に書き直し；　鶴店、確認とれず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a legend that he was sent to work at a cotton wholesale store (called Kamedana, in comparison with the Ueno store which was called Tsurudana) in Edo Tenma-cho, a branch of Matsuzakaya Ueno store, but because he had problems with a woman there (there is also a rumor that he was forced into a sexual relationship by the head clerk) he returned to Hino; however, due to the existence of the Ninbetsu-cho described above, the reliability of such stories are now in doubt.</e>
<cmt>Spelling revised.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>その後は実家秘伝の「石田散薬」を行商しつつ各地の道場で他流試合を重ね修業を積んだと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, it is said that he travelled and sold &quot;Ishida Sanyaku medicine&quot;, for which the secrets in processing of the medicine has been passed on in his family, and at the same time trained himself by fighting many kenjutsu matches with other schools in Dojo&apos;s located in various areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, it is said that he travelled and sold &quot;Ishida Sanyaku medicine&quot; whose secret recipe has been passed on in his family; at the same time he also trained himself by fighting in many swordsmanship matches with other schools in dojos located around the country.</e>
<cmt>石田散薬、裏づけとれず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, it is said that he traveled and sold &quot;Ishida Sanyaku medicine&quot; whose secret recipe has been passed on in his family; at the same time he also trained himself by fighting in many swordsmanship matches with other schools in dojos located around the country.</e>
<cmt>Spelling revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>日野の佐藤道場に出稽古に来ていた天然理心流4代目の近藤勇（後の新選組局長）とはこの頃出会ったと推測され、安政6年（1859）3月29日、天然理心流に正式入門した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that he met around that time Isami KONDO(who later became commander of Shinsen-gumi), the 4th Head of Tennen Rishin-ryu, who was visiting Sato Dojo in Hino for training, and on March 29 1859, Toshizo formally became a disciple of Tennen Rishin-ryu.</e>
<cmt>Kondo→ KONDO</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is around this time that he is assumed to have met Isami KONDO (who later became the commander of Shinsen-gumi), the 4th Head of Tennen Rishin-ryu, who was on a training trip to Sato Dojo in Hino; on March 29 1859, Toshizo formally became a disciple of Tennen Rishin-ryu.</e>
<cmt>書き出し変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is around this time that he is assumed to have met Isami KONDO (who later became the commander of Shinsen-gumi), the 4th Head of Tennen Rishin-ryu, who was on a training trip to Sato Dojo in Hino; on March 29 1859, Toshizo formally became a disciple of Tennen Rishin-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>歳三の姉佐藤のぶは姉弟の従兄弟でもある日野市日野宿名主の佐藤彦五郎に嫁いでおり、歳三も彦五郎宅にはよく出入りしていたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo&apos;s older sister, Nobu SATO, was married to Hikogoro SATO, who was also their cousin and Nanushi of Hino-jyuku, Hino city, and it is said that Toshizo often visited the residence of Hikogoro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo&apos;s older sister, Nobu SATO, was married to Hikogoro SATO, who was also their cousin and Nanushi (an officer) of Hino-jyuku, Hino city; it is said that Toshizo often visited the residence of Hikogoro.</e>
<cmt>名主→ officer?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo&apos;s older sister, Nobu SATO, was married to Hikogoro SATO, who was also their cousin and Nanushi (headman of the city) of Hino-jyuku, Hino city; it is said that Toshizo often visited the residence of Hikogoro.</e>
<cmt>名主の説明を修正。派遣される官吏ではなく村の代表のこと。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>彦五郎は大火に乗じて命を狙われたことがあり、それを契機に井上源三郎の兄、井上松五郎の勧めで天然理心流に入門、自宅の一角に道場を開いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikogoro had once been nearly killed during a major fire, and after such incident, he became a disciple of Tennen Rishin-ryu, following the advice of Matsugoro INOUE, an older brother of Genzaburo INOUE, and Hikogoro started a Dojo in a corner of his house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikogoro once was nearly killed during a major fire; after this incident, and on the advice of Matsugoro INOUE, an older brother of Genzaburo INOUE, Hikogoro became a disciple of Tennen Rishin-ryu and started a Dojo in a corner of his house.</e>
<cmt>部分的に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikogoro once was nearly killed during a major fire; after this incident, and on the advice of Matsugoro INOUE, an older brother of Genzaburo INOUE, Hikogoro became a disciple of Tennen Rishin-ryu and started a Dojo in a corner of his house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そんな縁から彦五郎は近藤と義兄弟の契りを結んでおり、天然理心流を支援した人でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to such background, Hikogoro took a pledge of brotherhood with KONDO, and supported Tennen Rishin-ryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this background Hikogoro took a pledge of brotherhood with KONDO and supported Tennen Rishin-ryu.</e>
<cmt>部分的に書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this background Hikogoro took a pledge of brotherhood with KONDO and supported Tennen Rishin-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>歳三もこの道場で腕を磨いたと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Toshizo also trained himself in kenjutsu at this Dojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Toshizo also trained himself in swordsmanship at this Dojo.</e>
<cmt>kenjutsu をswordsmanship に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Toshizo also trained himself in swordsmanship at this Dojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="21">
<j>近藤道場（試衛館）の仲間とともに、歳三は文久3年2月、幕府の征夷大将軍徳川家茂警護のための浪士組に応募して京都へ出立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 3rd Year of Bunkyu, February, Toshizo, together with his friends of Kondo Dojo (Shiei-kan), applied for the Roshigumi to guard Iemochi TOKUGAWA, Seii Taishogun of the Shogunate, and departed for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Taisyogun → Taishogun</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February of the 3rd year of Bunkyu, Toshizo, together with his comrades of Kondo Dojo (Shiei-kan), applied for the Roshigumi to guard Iemochi TOKUGAWA, Seii Taishogun of the Shogunate, and departed for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>friends を comrades に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February of the 3rd year of Bunkyu, Toshizo, together with his comrades of Kondo Dojo (Shiei-kan), applied for the Roshigumi to guard Iemochi TOKUGAWA, Seii Taishogun of the Shogunate, and departed for Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>新選組副長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vice Commander of Shinsenh-gumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vice Commander of Shinsenh-gumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vice Commander of Shinsenh-gumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>文久3年(1863)8月18日の八月十八日の政変後、壬生浪士組の活躍が認められ新選組が発足。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the political change on August 18 1863, the active role of Miburoshi-gumi was acknowledged, and Shinsen-gumi was set up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the political change on August 18 1863, the active role of Miburoshi-gumi was acknowledged, and Shinsen-gumi was set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the political change on August 18 1863, the active role of Miburoshi-gumi was acknowledged, and Shinsen-gumi was set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その後新見錦切腹、芹沢鴨などを自らの手で暗殺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, Nishiki NIMI committed hara-kiri, and Toshizo directly assassinated Kamo SERIZAWA and some others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, Nishiki NIMI committed hara-kiri, and Toshizo directly assassinated Kamo SERIZAWA and some others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, Nishiki NIMI committed hara-kiri, and Toshizo directly assassinated Kamo SERIZAWA and some others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>権力をにぎった近藤勇が局長となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isami KONDO, who acquired power, became the commander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isami KONDO, who acquired power, became the commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isami KONDO, who acquired power, became the commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>歳三は副長の地位に就き、局長近藤勇の右腕として京都治安警護維持にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo assumed the position as vice commander, and was engaged in maintaining peace and order in Kyoto, as Isami KONDO&apos;s right hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo assumed the position as vice commander, and as Isami KONDO&apos;s right hand man he engaged himself in maintaining peace and order in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一部変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo assumed the position as vice commander, and as Isami KONDO&apos;s right hand man he engaged himself in maintaining peace and order in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>新選組は助勤、監察など職務ごとに系統的な組織作りがなされ、頂点は局長であるが、実際の指揮命令は副長の歳三から発せられるようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Systematic structure by each duty, such as Jyokin, Kansatsu, etc., of Shinsen-gumi was formed, and while the Head of the organization is the commander, actual directing orders were given by Toshizo, the vice commander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Systematic structure by each duty such as Jyokin, Kansatsu, etc., of Shinsen-gumi was formed, and while the Head of the organization was the commander, the actual directing orders were given by Toshizo, the vice commander.</e>
<cmt>現在形から過去形に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Systematic structure by each duty such as Jyokin, Kansatsu, etc., of Shinsen-gumi was formed, and while the Head of the organization was the commander, the actual directing orders were given by Toshizo, the vice commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>元治元年（1864）6月5日池田屋事件の際は、半隊を率いて長州藩土佐藩藩士が頻繁に出入りしていた丹虎（四国屋）方面を探索して廻ったが、こちらは誰もいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon Ikedaya Incident on June 5 1864, Toshizo lead half of the troop to search around Tantora (Shikokuya), visited frequently by members of the Choshyu clan and the Tosa clan, but nobody was there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon Ikedaya Incident on June 5 1864, Toshizo lead half of the troop to search around Tantora (Shikokuya), visited frequently by members of the Choshyu clan and the Tosa clan, but nobody was there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon Ikedaya Incident on June 5 1864, Toshizo lead half of the troop to search around Tantora (Shikokuya), visited frequently by members of the Choshyu clan and the Tosa clan, but nobody was there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>すぐさま池田屋の応援に駆けつけたが、直ちに抜刀し踏み込まずに池田屋の周りを固め、後から駆けつけた会津藩、桑名藩の兵を池田屋に入らせず、新選組ただ一隊の手柄を守った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He promptly rushed to Ikedaya to assist and immediately had his men draw their swords from the sheath, but instead of entering the building they guarded the area around Ikedaya, so as not to allow soldiers from the Aizu clan and the Kuwana clan who arrived later, to enter Ikedaya, and thereby protected Shinsen-gumi&apos;s achievement as the only troop that handled the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He promptly rushed to Ikedaya to assist and immediately had his men draw their swords from the sheaths, but instead of entering the building they guarded the area around Ikedaya in order to prevent the soldiers of the Aizu and the Kuwana clans (who would arrive later) from entering Ikedaya, thereby ensuring that only Shinsen-gumi would receive full credit for the achievement.</e>
<cmt>後半書き換え</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He promptly rushed to Ikedaya to assist and immediately had his men draw their swords from the sheaths, but instead of entering the building they guarded the area around Ikedaya in order to prevent the soldiers of the Aizu and the Kuwana clans (who would arrive later) from entering Ikedaya, thereby ensuring that only Shinsen-gumi would receive full credit for the achievement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>まだ立場の弱い新選組の事を考えての行動だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such action were taken in consideration of the fact that Shinsen-gumi&apos;s position was still weak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such actions were taken with Shinsen-gumi&apos;s position, still weak at the time, in consideration.</e>
<cmt>後半書き換え</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such actions were taken with Shinsen-gumi&apos;s position, still weak at the time, in consideration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>歳三らしい冷静な機転である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tactful and calm action typical of Toshizo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a tactful and calculating wit typical of Toshizo.</e>
<cmt>単語変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a tactful and calculating wit typical of Toshizo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>そのため池田屋事件の恩賞は破格のものであり、勇名も一気に天下に轟いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, rewards received for Ikedaya Incident were unprecedented, and their name became widely known throughout the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, rewards received for Ikedaya Incident were unprecedented, and their names became widely known throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>name を names に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, rewards received for Ikedaya Incident were unprecedented, and their names became widely known throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>さらに幕府から、近藤を与力上席、隊士を与力とする内示まであったが、歳三は近藤を諌め与力よりも狙いは大名と、次の機会を待つよう進言し、近藤もこれを聞き入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shogunate unofficially notified to assign KONDO as Yoriki Joseki and Shinsen-gumi members as Yoriki, but Toshizo persuaded and adviced KONDO, that he should try to become a Daimyo rather than a Yoriki, and to wait for the next opportunity, and KONDO followed such advice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shogunate unofficially notified to assign KONDO as Yoriki Joseki (Head of Additional Soldiers) and Shinsen-gumi members as Yoriki (Additional Soldiers), but Toshizo persuaded KONDO not to settle for a Yoriki, aim for a Daimyo instead and wait for the next opportunity; KONDO heeded his advice.</e>
<cmt>後半書き換え；上席の読み方確認できず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shogunate unofficially notified to assign KONDO as Yoriki Joseki (Head of Additional Soldiers) and Shinsen-gumi members as Yoriki (Additional Soldiers), but Toshizo persuaded KONDO not to settle for a Yoriki, aim for a Daimyo instead and wait for the next opportunity; KONDO heeded his advice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>新選組内部では、常に新選組の規律を隊士らに遵守させ、規律を破った隊士に対しては切腹を命じており、隊士から恐れられていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within Shinsen-gumi, he always made members follow the rules of Shinsen-gumi, and ordered a member who broke the rules to conduct hara-kiri, so it is said that the members feared him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within Shinsen-gumi, he always made members follow the rules of Shinsen-gumi and ordered a hara-kiri to the members who broke the rules; it is said that the members feared him.</e>
<cmt>一部変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within Shinsen-gumi, he always made members follow the rules of Shinsen-gumi and ordered a hara-kiri to the members who broke the rules; it is said that the members feared him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>そのため、新選組隊士の死亡原因第1位は切腹であったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that the top reason for death of a Shinsen-gumi was due to hara-kiri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is said that the top reason for death of a Shinsen-gumi was due to hara-kiri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that the top reason for death of a Shinsen-gumi was due to hara-kiri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また脱走者は切腹または斬殺後見せしめにすることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, members who escaped from Shinsen-gumi were made to conduct hara-kiri, or were killed with a sword and exhibited as warning to others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, members who escaped from Shinsen-gumi were made to conduct hara-kiri or were killed with a sword and [their bodies] exhibited as warning to others.</e>
<cmt>説明のため [ ] 使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, members who escaped from Shinsen-gumi were made to conduct hara-kiri or were killed with a sword and [their bodies] exhibited as warning to others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="36">
<j>その後、副長の山南敬助を総長に据え、副長は土方1人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, the other vice commander, Keisuke YAMANAMI assumed the position of Soucho, and HIJIKATA became the only vice commander.</e>
<cmt>山南はさんなんという読み方も。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the other vice commander, Keisuke YAMANAMI assumed the position of Soucho, and HIJIKATA became the only vice commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the other vice commander, Keisuke YAMANAMI assumed the position of Soucho, and HIJIKATA became the only vice commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>隊の居場所がなくなり山南が脱走して切腹となった事件では、山南と土方との対立があったとされるが、実際は仲が良かったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the incident where YAMANAMI lost his position within Shinsen-gumi and escaped, and was ordered to conduct hara-kiri, it is said that there was a dispute between YAMANAMI and HIJIKATA, but actually they seemed to have been good friends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the incident where YAMANAMI was ordered to conduct a hara-kiri after he lost his position within Shinsen-gumi and escaped [and captured], it is said that there was a dispute between YAMANAMI and HIJIKATA, but actually they seemed to have been good friends.</e>
<cmt>説明のため [ ] 使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the incident where YAMANAMI was ordered to conduct a hara-kiri after he lost his position within Shinsen-gumi and escaped [and captured], it is said that there was a dispute between YAMANAMI and HIJIKATA, but actually they seemed to have been good friends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その後も隊の規律を守るために河合耆三郎、谷三十郎、武田観柳斎らを切腹あるいは斬殺させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, he also had Kisaburo KAWAI, Sanjyuro TANI, Kanryusai TAKEDA and some others conduct hara-kiri, or killed them by a sword, in order to maintain the order of Shinsen-gumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, he also had Kisaburo KAWAI, Sanjyuro TANI, Kanryusai TAKEDA and others conduct hara-kiri, or had them killed by a sword so as to maintain the order within Shinsen-gumi.</e>
<cmt>単語変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, he also had Kisaburo KAWAI, Sanjyuro TANI, Kanryusai TAKEDA and others conduct hara-kiri, or had them killed by a sword so as to maintain the order within Shinsen-gumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>伊東甲子太郎の御陵衛士にスパイの斎藤一を送るなどして伊東の近藤暗殺計画を未然に防ぎ、伊東、藤堂平助を暗殺し御陵衛士達を壊滅させた（油小路事件）（御陵衛士、及び伊東に関しては異説有り）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sent Hajime SAITO to Goryoeji formed by Kashitaro ITO, and took some other measures to successfully prevent ITO&apos;s plan to assassinate KONDO, and assassinated ITO and Heisuke TODO and completely destroyed Goryoeji (there are different stories regarding Goryoeji and ITO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sent Hajime SAITO to Goryoeji formed by Kashitaro ITO and took measures to successfully prevent ITO&apos;s plan to assassinate KONDO; he assassinated ITO and Heisuke TODO and completely destroyed Goryoeji (however, there are different stories regarding Goryoeji and ITO).</e>
<cmt>；使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sent Hajime SAITO to Goryoeji formed by Kashitaro ITO and took measures to successfully prevent ITO&apos;s plan to assassinate KONDO; he assassinated ITO and Heisuke TODO and completely destroyed Goryoeji (however, there are different stories regarding Goryoeji and ITO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>戊辰戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boshin War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boshin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boshin War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>慶応3年（1867）6月に幕臣に取り立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to a vassal of the Tokugawa Shogunate in June, 1867.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to a vassal of the Tokugawa Shogunate in June, 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to a vassal of the Tokugawa Shogunate in June, 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし同年10月14日に徳川慶喜が征夷大将軍を辞し大政奉還、12月9日に王政復古 (日本)の大号令が発せられるに至り、幕府は事実上崩壊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on October 14th of the same year, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA resigned from the position of Seii Taishogun, and upon Restoration of the Imperial Rule (Japan) on December 9th, the Shogunate essentially collapsed.</e>
<cmt>Taisyogun →Taishogun</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on October 14th of the same year, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA resigned from the position of Seii Taishogun, and upon Restoration of the Imperial Rule (Japan) on December 9th, the Shogunate essentially collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on October 14th of the same year, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA resigned from the position of Seii Taishogun, and upon Restoration of the Imperial Rule (Japan) on December 9th, the Shogunate essentially collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>慶応4年1月3日鳥羽・伏見の戦いに始まる戊辰戦争が勃発し、歳三は墨染事件で負傷した局長近藤勇の代わりに新選組を率いて戦うが、新政府軍の銃撃戦の前に敗北する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 4th Year of Keio January 13th, Boshin War started with the Battle of Toba Fushimi, and Toshizo lead Shinsen-gumi and fought as a deputy of commander, Isami KONDO, who was wounded in Sumizome Incident, but was defeated against the army of the new government in gun fighting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January, 13th, 4th year of Keio, Boshin War started with the Battle of Toba Fushimi; in place of Isami KONDO, who was wounded in Sumizome Incident, Toshizo lead Shinsen-gumi and fought as a deputy of commander but was defeated against the army of the new government in gun fighting.</e>
<cmt>原文に近いように in place of 追加；墨染の読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January, 13th, 4th year of Keio, Boshin War started with the Battle of Toba Fushimi; in place of Isami KONDO, who was wounded in Sumizome Incident, Toshizo lead Shinsen-gumi and fought as a deputy of commander but was defeated against the army of the new government in gun fighting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>歳三は鳥羽・伏見の戦いで敗北する以前の慶応元年頃から、これからは刀で戦ができない時代であると悟り、洋式の軍備を進め始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around the 1st Year of Keio, prior to being defeated in Battle of Toba Fushimi, Toshizo realized that from now on war cannot be fought with swords, and started to prepare westernized armaments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around the 1st year of Keio, prior to being defeated in Battle of Toba Fushimi, Toshizo realized that from now on war could not be fought with swords and he started to prepare western-style armaments.</e>
<cmt>cannnot から could not に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around the 1st year of Keio, prior to being defeated in Battle of Toba Fushimi, Toshizo realized that from now on war could not be fought with swords and he started to prepare western-style armaments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>鳥羽・伏見の戦いで敗れた幕府軍が大阪から江戸へ撤退した後、近藤は大久保大和、歳三は内藤隼人と一時名乗って甲斐国に向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Shogunate army, who lost Battle of Toba Fushimi, retreated from Osaka to Edo, KONDO temporarily named himself Yamato OKUBO and Toshizo named himself Hayato NAITO, and they set off to Kai province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Shogunate army lost Battle of Toba Fushimi and retreated from Osaka to Edo, KONDO temporarily named himself Yamato OKUBO and Toshizo named himself Hayato NAITO, and they set off to Kai province.</e>
<cmt>who 削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Shogunate army lost Battle of Toba Fushimi and retreated from Osaka to Edo, KONDO temporarily named himself Yamato OKUBO and Toshizo named himself Hayato NAITO, and they set off to Kai province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし3月6日甲州勝沼の戦いに敗退。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on March 6th they were defeated in Battle of Kosyu Katsunuma.</e>
<cmt>甲州勝沼の戦いの表記、裏づけとれず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on March 6th they were defeated in Battle of Kosyu Katsunuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on March 6th they were defeated in Battle of Kosyu Katsunuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>歳三は急ぎ援軍要請に向かったが、成功しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo rushed to request for reinforcements, but was not successful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo rushed to request for reinforcements but was not successful.</e>
<cmt>, 削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo rushed to request for reinforcements but was not successful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>その後、流山で再起を謀っていたが、4月3日不意の新政府軍包囲により局長近藤勇が新政府軍へ出頭。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, they were trying to recover power in Nagareyama, but on April 3rd, was suddenly surrounded by the army of the new government, and commander, KONDO, presented himself to the army of the new government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, they were trying to recover power in Nagareyama but on April 3rd, they were suddenly surrounded by the army of the new government; the commander, KONDO, surrendered himself to the army of the new government.</e>
<cmt>部分的に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, they were trying to recover power in Nagareyama but on April 3rd, they were suddenly surrounded by the army of the new government; the commander, KONDO, surrendered himself to the army of the new government.</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この時歳三が近藤の切腹を止めて出頭を勧めたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, it is said that Toshizo stopped KONDO from committing hara-kiri, and persuaded KONDO to present himself to the army of the new government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, it is said that Toshizo stopped KONDO from committing hara-kiri, and persuaded KONDO to present himself to the army of the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, it is said that Toshizo stopped KONDO from committing hara-kiri, and persuaded KONDO to present himself to the army of the new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>歳三は江戸へ向かい勝海舟らに直談判し近藤の助命を嘆願したが実現せず、慶応4年（1868）4月25日、近藤は板橋近辺（現JR板橋駅前に墓所有り）にて処刑（斬首）される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo went to Edo, and directly negotiated with Kaishu KATSU and others and pleaded to be spared KONDO&apos;s life, but was not successful, and KONDO was executed (beheaded) on April 25 1868, at a place close to Itabashi (currently, his tomb is located in front of JR Itabashi Station).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo went to Edo and directly negotiated with Kaishu KATSU and others and pleaded them to spare KONDO&apos;s life, but he was not successful; KONDO was executed (beheaded) on April 25 1868, at a place close to Itabashi (currently, his tomb is located in front of JR Itabashi Station).</e>
<cmt>them 追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo went to Edo and directly negotiated with Kaishu KATSU and others and pleaded them to spare KONDO&apos;s life, but he was not successful; KONDO was executed (beheaded) on April 25 1868, at a place close to Itabashi (currently, his tomb is located in front of JR Itabashi Station).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>近藤出頭後、助命嘆願のかたわら新選組を斎藤一（山口二郎）に託して会津へ向かわせ、島田魁ら数名の隊士のみを連れて大鳥圭介らが率いる旧幕府脱走軍と合流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After KONDO presented himself to the army of the new government, Toshizo, besides pleading for KONDO&apos;s life, entrusted Shinsen-gumi in the care of Hajime SAITO (Jiro YAMAGUCHI) and made them go to Aizu, and Toshizo himself only took a few members including Kai SHIMADA and joined the army led by Keisuke OTORI and others, which was formed by men who escaped from the army of the former Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After KONDO surrendered himself to the army of the new government, Toshizo, besides pleading for KONDO&apos;s life, entrusted Shinsen-gumi in the care of Hajime SAITO (Jiro YAMAGUCHI) and made them go to Aizu; Toshizo took only a few members including Kai SHIMADA and joined the army led by Keisuke OTORI and others, which was formed by men who escaped from the army of the former Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>presentedを surrendered に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After KONDO surrendered himself to the army of the new government, Toshizo, besides pleading for KONDO&apos;s life, entrusted Shinsen-gumi in the care of Hajime SAITO (Jiro YAMAGUCHI) and made them go to Aizu; Toshizo took only a few members including Kai SHIMADA and joined the army led by Keisuke OTORI and others, which was formed by men who escaped from the army of the former Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>4月11日に江戸城無血開城が成立すると江戸を脱走し、歳三は秋月登之助率いる先鋒軍の参謀を勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 11th, when evacuation of Edo Castle without bloodshed succeded, Toshizo escaped from edo, and acted as a staff officer of the vanguard army lead by Noborinosuke AKIZUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 11th, when evacuation of Edo Castle without bloodshed succeded, Toshizo escaped from Edo and acted as a staff officer of the vanguard army led by Noborinosuke AKIZUKI.</e>
<cmt>lead を led に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 11th, when evacuation of Edo Castle without bloodshed succeded, Toshizo escaped from Edo and acted as a staff officer of the vanguard army led by Noborinosuke AKIZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>下館藩・下妻藩を経て宇都宮城の戦いに勝利、宇都宮城を陥落させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They passed through the Shibodate clan, the Shimotsuma clan, and won Battle of Utsunomiya Castle, and conquered Utsunomiya Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They passed through the Shimodate clan and the Shimotsuma clan, and won the Battle of Utsunomiya Castle and conquered Utsunomiya Castle.</e>
<cmt>部分的に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They passed through the Shimodate clan and the Shimotsuma clan, and won the Battle of Utsunomiya Castle and conquered Utsunomiya Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし壬生の戦いに敗走、新政府軍と再度宇都宮で戦った際に足を負傷し、本軍に先立って会津へ護送されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they lost Battle of Mibu and fled, and fought again with the army of the new government in Utsunomiya, when Toshizo injured his leg, and he was escorted to Aizu before the main army went to Aizu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they lost Battle of Mibu and fled; they fought again with the army of the new government in Utsunomiya during which Toshizo injured his leg; he was escorted to Aizu before the main army arrived in Aizu.</e>
<cmt>部分的に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they lost Battle of Mibu and fled; they fought again with the army of the new government in Utsunomiya during which Toshizo injured his leg; he was escorted to Aizu before the main army arrived in Aizu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>会津では約3ヶ月間の療養生活を送り、この間に近藤勇の墓を天寧寺に建てたと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Aizu, he spent 3 months in recuperation, and it is said that during this time he built Isami KONDO&apos;s tomb in Tennei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Aizu, he spent 3 months in recuperation, and it is said that during this time he built Isami KONDO&apos;s tomb in Tennei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Aizu, he spent 3 months in recuperation, and it is said that during this time he built Isami KONDO&apos;s tomb in Tennei-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="55">
<j>全快して戦線に復帰した後は会津の防戦に尽力するが、8月母成峠の戦いの敗戦に伴い会津戦争が激化。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he fully recovered and returned to the battle line, he endeavored to protect Aizu, but Battle of Aizu intensified as the result of losing Battle of Bonari-toge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he fully recovered and returned to the battle line he endeavored to protect Aizu, but Battle of Aizu intensified after they lost the Battle of Bonari-toge in August.</e>
<cmt>後半変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he fully recovered and returned to the battle line he endeavored to protect Aizu, but Battle of Aizu intensified after they lost the Battle of Bonari-toge in August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>歳三は援軍を求めて庄内藩に向かうが、既に恭順体制の庄内においては入城さえ叶わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo visited the Shonai clan to request for reinforcements, but Shonai, which was already allegiance to the new government, did not allow him to even enter the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo visited the Shonai clan to request for reinforcements, but Shonai had already pledged allegiance to the new government and did not allow him to even enter the castle.</e>
<cmt>pledged allegiance に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo visited the Shonai clan to request for reinforcements, but Shonai had already pledged allegiance to the new government and did not allow him to even enter the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>歳三は会津から仙台へ向かうことを決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo decided to depart for Sendai from Aizu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo decided to depart for Sendai from Aizu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo decided to depart for Sendai from Aizu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>同じように戦列を離れた大鳥圭介に対して山口二郎（斎藤一）らは会津藩に忠誠を尽くすべきだと訴えたというが、箱館で記録された後の古文書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Jiro YAMAGUCHI (Hajime SAITO) and some others appealed to Keisuke OTORI who left the battle line in a way similar to Toshizo, that he should be loyal as possible to the Aizu clan, but this story is told by an old document which was recorded at a later date in Hakodate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Jiro YAMAGUCHI (Hajime SAITO) and others appealed to Keisuke OTORI, who left the battle line in a way similar to Toshizo, that he should be as loyal as possible to the Aizu clan; however, this story comes from an old document which was recorded at a later date in Hakodate.</e>
<cmt>as loyal as possible に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Jiro YAMAGUCHI (Hajime SAITO) and others appealed to Keisuke OTORI, who left the battle line in a way similar to Toshizo, that he should be as loyal as possible to the Aizu clan; however, this story comes from an old document which was recorded at a later date in Hakodate.</e>
<cmt>Double bite revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>土方は、会津藩領では新選組に復帰してはいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIJIKATA had not returned to Shinsen-gumi when they were in the domains of the Aizu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIJIKATA had not returned to Shinsen-gumi when they were in the domains of the Aizu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIJIKATA had not returned to Shinsen-gumi when they were in the domains of the Aizu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>そして、城下に残る山口たちと仙台へ天寧寺から離脱した隊士たちと新選組は分裂する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsen-gumi broke up into the group of YAMAGUCHI and others fho remained in the castle town, and the group of members who left at Tennei-ji temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsen-gumi broke up into the group of YAMAGUCHI and others who remained in the castle town and the group of members who left at Tennei-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>タイピングミス訂正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsen-gumi broke up into the group of YAMAGUCHI and others who remained in the castle town and the group of members who left at Tennei-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="61">
<j>仙台に至り榎本武揚率いる旧幕府海軍と合流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo arrived in Sendai, and joined the navy of the former Shogunate, lead by Takeaki ENOMOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo arrived in Sendai and joined the navy of the former Shogunate led by Takeaki ENOMOTO.</e>
<cmt>lead から led に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo arrived in Sendai and joined the navy of the former Shogunate led by Takeaki ENOMOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>榎本とともに奥羽越列藩同盟の軍議に参加し、同盟軍総督に推薦されたが、まもなく奥羽越列藩同盟が崩壊、同盟藩が次々と新政府軍に屈服した後は、戦う地がある限りどこまでも戦うことを決意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with ENOMOTO, Toshizo participated in military meetings of Ouetsu Reppan Domei (Northern Alliance), and was recommended to become General of Domei Army, but Ouetsu Reppan Domei soon collapsed, and after the clans which formed Domei Army surrended one after another to the army of the new government, Toshizo decided to fight wherever he can, so long as there is a place where he can fight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with ENOMOTO Toshizo participated in military meetings of Ouetsu Reppan Domei (Northern Alliance) and was recommended to become General of Domei Army; however, Ouetsu Reppan Domei soon collapsed, and after the clans forming the Domei Army surrended one after another to the army of the new government, Toshizo decided to fight until the end, so long as there is a place where he can fight.</e>
<cmt>同盟軍総督の裏づけとれず；「どこまでも戦う」は「最後まで戦う」という意味だと思うので until the end にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with ENOMOTO Toshizo participated in military meetings of Ouetsu Reppan Domei (Northern Alliance) and was recommended to become General of Domei Army; however, Ouetsu Reppan Domei soon collapsed, and after the clans forming the Domei Army surrended one after another to the army of the new government, Toshizo decided to fight until the end, so long as there is a place where he can fight.</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>新選組生き残り隊士に桑名藩士らを加えて大江丸に乗船し、榎本武揚らとともに10月12日仙台折浜（現宮城県石巻市折浜）を出航、蝦夷に渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsen-gumi members who remained alive, together with men from the Kuwana clan, boarded Oemaru, and with Takeaki ENOMOTO and others left Orinohama, Sendai (currently, Orinohama, Ishinomaki city, Miyagi prefecture) on October 12th, and went to Ezo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinsen-gumi members who remained alive boarded Oemaru along with the men from the Kuwana clan, and they left Orinohama, Sendai (currently, Orinohama, Ishinomaki city, Miyagi prefecture) with Takeaki ENOMOTO and others on October 12th and went to Ezo.</e>
<cmt>大江丸の読み方、裏づけとれず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinsen-gumi members who remained alive boarded Oemaru along with the men from the Kuwana clan, and they left Orinohama, Sendai (currently, Orinohama, Ishinomaki city, Miyagi prefecture) with Takeaki ENOMOTO and others on October 12th and went to Ezo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>函館戦争(戦死)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakodate War (Died in the War)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakodate War (Died in the War)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakodate War (Died in the War)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>土方歳三像</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The image of Toshizo HIJIKATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The image of Toshizo HIJIKATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The image of Toshizo HIJIKATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>10月20日、蝦夷地鷲の木に上陸後、歳三は間道軍総督となり五稜郭へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After landing on Washinoki of Ezo on October 20th, Toshizo became General of Kando Army and headed for Goryokaku.</e>
<cmt>間道軍総督の裏づけとれず。間道はわきみちのこと</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After landing on Washinoki of Ezo on October 20th, Toshizo became General of Kando Army and headed for Goryokaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After landing on Washinoki of Ezo on October 20th, Toshizo became General of Kando Army and headed for Goryokaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>新選組は大鳥圭介総督の下本道を進んだが、歳三には島田魁ら数名の新選組隊士が常に従っていたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsen-gumi travelled by the main road under the leadership of General Keisuke OTORI, but a few members of Shinsen-gumi including Kai SHIMADA, are said to have followed Toshizo.</e>
<cmt>本道は本街道のこと</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsen-gumi travelled by the main road under the leadership of General Keisuke OTORI, but a few members of Shinsen-gumi including Kai SHIMADA, are said to have followed Toshizo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsen-gumi traveled by the main road under the leadership of General Keisuke OTORI, but a few members of Shinsen-gumi including Kai SHIMADA, are said to have followed Toshizo.</e>
<cmt>Spelling revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>箱館・五稜郭を占領後、歳三は額兵隊などを率いて松前へ進軍し松前城（福山城）を陥落させ、残兵を江差まで追撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After occupying Goryokaku, Toshizo advanced his army, leading Gakuheitai army, etc., and conquered Matsumae Castle (Fukuyama Castle), and chased the retreating army of the enemy to Esashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After occupying Goryokaku in Hakodate Toshizo advanced his army including Gakuheitai army and others.; he conquered Matsumae Castle (Fukuyama Castle) and chased the retreating army of the enemy to Esashi.</e>
<cmt>函館が抜けてたので追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After occupying Goryokaku in Hakodate Toshizo advanced his army including Gakuheitai army and others.; he conquered Matsumae Castle (Fukuyama Castle) and chased the retreating army of the enemy to Esashi.</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>この時、榎本武揚は土方軍を海から援護するため、開陽丸で江差沖へ向かったが、暴風雨に遭い座礁。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, Takeaki ENOMOTO went to the offing of Esashi in order to support HIJIKATA&apos;s family from the sea, but his ship was stranded because of a storm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, Takeaki ENOMOTO went to the offing of Esashi in order to support HIJIKATA&apos;s family from the sea, but his ship was stranded because of a storm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Takeaki ENOMOTO went to the offing of Esashi in order to support HIJIKATA&apos;s family from the sea, but his ship was stranded because of a storm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>江差に上陸して開陽丸の沈没していく姿を見守っていた榎本と歳三は、そばにあった松を叩いて嘆き合ったと言われ、今でもその「嘆きの松」が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ENOMOTO, who landed in Esashi to watch Kaiyomaru sink, and Toshizo are said to have punched a pine tree which stood nearby and lamented together, and the &quot;Nageki no Matsu&quot; (pine tree of lament) remains today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ENOMOTO, who landed in Esashi, and Toshizo watched Kaiyomaru sink, and they are said to have punched a pine tree which stood nearby and lamented together; the &quot;Nageki no Matsu&quot; (pine tree of lament) still remains today.</e>
<cmt>榎本と歳三の両人が開陽丸の沈没をみていたと原文から読めるのでそのように変更；嘆きの松、表記確認できず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ENOMOTO, who landed in Esashi, and Toshizo watched Kaiyomaru sink, and they are said to have punched a pine tree which stood nearby and lamented together; the &quot;Nageki no Matsu&quot; (pine tree of lament) still remains today.</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>江差を無事占領した歳三は、一度松前城へ戻り、12月15日榎本が各国領事を招待して催した蝦夷地平定祝賀会に合わせて五稜郭へ凱旋した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo, who managed to occupy Esashi, temporarily returned to Matsumae Castle, and returned to Goryokaku on December 15th, for the Celebration of Conquest of Ezo held by ENOMOTO, to which ENOMOTO invited the consuls of various countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo, who managed to occupy Esashi, temporarily returned to Matsumae Castle; he returned to Goryokaku on December 15th for the Celebration of Conquest of Ezo held by ENOMOTO, to which ENOMOTO invited the consuls of various countries.</e>
<cmt>松前城の後にセミコロン使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo, who managed to occupy Esashi, temporarily returned to Matsumae Castle; he returned to Goryokaku on December 15th for the Celebration of Conquest of Ezo held by ENOMOTO, to which ENOMOTO invited the consuls of various countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>その後、幹部を決定する選挙が行われ、榎本を総裁とする蝦夷共和国（五稜郭が本陣）が成立、歳三は幹部として陸軍奉行並となり、箱館市中取締や陸海軍裁判局頭取も兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, an election to determine leaders was held, and Ezo Republic (headquarters in Goryokaku) was established, and Toshizo, as one of the leaders, became vice-minister of the Army, and concurrently served as Torishimari of Hakodate city, and chief of the Court of the Army and the Navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, an election to determine leaders was held, and Ezo Republic (headquarters in Goryokaku) was established; Toshizo, as one of the leaders, became vice-minister of the Army and concurrently served as Torishimari of Hakodate city and chief of the Court of the Army and the Navy.</e>
<cmt>歳三の前にセミコロン使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, an election to determine leaders was held, and Ezo Republic (headquarters in Goryokaku) was established; Toshizo, as one of the leaders, became vice-minister of the Army and concurrently served as Torishimari of Hakodate city and chief of the Court of the Army and the Navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>箱館の地でも歳三は冷静だったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Toshizo remained calm in Hakodate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Toshizo remained calm in Hakodate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Toshizo remained calm in Hakodate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>箱館政府が樹立され、榎本らが祝杯を交わしているときも歳三は一人沈黙を保ち、「今は騒ぎ浮かれる時ではない」と言っていたと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a story that, when Hakodate government was established, and ENOMOTO and others were drinking in celebration, Toshizo alone remained silent, and said that &quot;this is not the time for jubilation&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When ENOMOTO and others were drinking to celebrate the establishment of the Hakodate government Toshizo alone remained silent and said &quot;this is not the time for jubilation&quot;.</e>
<cmt>書き出し部分変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When ENOMOTO and others were drinking to celebrate the establishment of the Hakodate government Toshizo alone remained silent and said &quot;this is not the time for jubilation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Period revised.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>1月から2月にかけては箱館・五稜郭の整備にあたり、3月には新政府軍襲来の情報が入ったため、歳三は新政府軍の東艦奪取を目的とした宮古湾海戦に参加、作戦は失敗し多数の死傷者が出るも、歳三は生還する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was engaged in consolidating Hakodate/Goryokaku from January to February, and when the news of an attack by the army of the new government reached his ears in March, Toshizo participated in Naval Battle of Miyakowan which targeted to seize Azuma-kan of the army of the new government, but this operation failed, and many were wounded or died, but Toshizo managed to safely return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was engaged in consolidating Hakodate/Goryokaku from January to February, and when the news of an attack by the army of the new government reached his ears in March Toshizo participated in Naval Battle of Miyakowan which targeted to seize Azuma-kan of the army of the new government; however, this operation failed, and many died or were wounded, but Toshizo managed to return safely.</e>
<cmt>最後の部分でセミコロン使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was engaged in consolidating Hakodate/Goryokaku from January to February, and when the news of an attack by the army of the new government reached his ears in March Toshizo participated in Naval Battle of Miyakowan which targeted to seize Azuma-kan of the army of the new government; however, this operation failed, and many died or were wounded, but Toshizo managed to return safely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="75">
<j>明治2年（1869）4月9日、新政府軍が蝦夷地乙部に上陸を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 9 1869, the army of the new government started to land in Otobe, Ezo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 9, 1869, the army of the new government started to land in Otobe, Ezo.</e>
<cmt>On April 9の後に , 使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 9, 1869, the army of the new government started to land in Otobe, Ezo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>歳三は、二股口の戦いで新政府軍の進撃に対し徹底防戦する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo made every effort to defend against the attacks of the army of the new government in Battle of Futamataguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo made every effort to defend against the attacks of the army of the new government in Battle of Futamataguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo made every effort to defend against the attacks of the army of the new government in Battle of Futamataguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その戦闘中に新政府軍は鈴の音を鳴らし、包囲したと思わせる行動をとり、自軍が包囲されたと思った土方軍は動揺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the battle, the army of the new government used tactics where they rang bells, and misleaded the enemy in thinking that they were surrounded, and HIJIKATA army who thought that they were surrounded, was upset.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the battle, the army of the new government rang bells to trick the enemy into thinking that they were surrounded; HIJIKATA&apos;s army thought that they were surrounded and was upset.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the battle, the army of the new government rang bells to trick the enemy into thinking that they were surrounded; HIJIKATA&apos;s army thought that they were surrounded and was upset.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>これに対し歳三は「本当に包囲しようとするなら、音を隠し気づかれないようにする。」と冷静に状況を判断し、部下を落ち着かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo calmly judged the circumstances, and calmed his men down by telling them that &quot;if our enemy really wished to surround us, they will hide all noise so that we will not notice them&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo calmly judged the circumstances and calmed his men down by telling them that &quot;if our enemy really wished to surround us they would hide all noises so that we will not notice them&quot;.</e>
<cmt>will を would に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo calmly judged the circumstances and calmed his men down by telling them that &quot;if our enemy really wished to surround us they would hide all noises so that we will not notice them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Period revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>また、戦いの合間に歳三は部下達に自ら酒を振舞って廻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in between the fighting, Toshizo himself went around and offered his men a drink.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in between the fighting, Toshizo himself went around and offered his men a drink of sake.</e>
<cmt>sake 追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in between the fighting, Toshizo himself went around and offered his men a drink of sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>そして「酔って軍律を乱してもらっては困るので皆一杯だけだ」と言ったので、部下は笑って了承したと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He told them that &quot;only one drink for each of you, as I do not want you to get drunk and break the rules of the army&quot;to which comment his men laughed and agreed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He told them &quot;only one drink for each of you, as I do not want you to get drunk and break the rules of the army&quot;; his men laughed and agreed.</e>
<cmt>セミコロン使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He told them &quot;only one drink for each of you, as I do not want you to get drunk and break the rules of the army&quot;; his men laughed and agreed.</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>土方軍が死守していた二股口は連戦連勝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futamataguchi, which HIJIKATA army defended desparately, continued to win a series of battles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Futamataguchi, which HIJIKATA army defended desparately, continued to win a series of battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Futamataguchi, which HIJIKATA army defended desparately, continued to win a series of battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>しかし、もう一方の松前口が破られて退路が絶たれる危険が起こったため、やむなく二股口を退却、五稜郭へ帰還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the other entrance, Matsumaeguchi, fell under the attacks of the enemy, and as there was a risk that it will become impossible for them to retreat, they had no choice but to return to Goryokaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the other entrance at Matsumaeguchi fell under the attacks of the enemy, and as there was a risk of losing a route for a retreat they had no choice but to return to Goryokaku.</e>
<cmt>reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the other entrance at Matsumaeguchi fell under the attacks of the enemy, and as there was a risk of losing a route for a retreat they had no choice but to return to Goryokaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>歳三の命によって台場方面に進軍していた大野率いる兵士らは一時勢力を盛り返していたが、突然乱れて大野の必死の指揮にも関わらず総崩れとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The soldiers lead by OHNO, who were advancing to the direction of Daiba under the order of Toshizo, were temporarily regaining their power, but were suddenly out of order, and despite OHNO&apos;s desperate instructions, suffered a total defeat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The soldiers lead by OHNO, who were advancing in the direction of Daiba under the order of Toshizo, were temporarily regaining their power, but they suddenly lost control and suffered a total defeat despite OHNO&apos;s desperate instructions.</e>
<cmt>out of order を lost control に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The soldiers lead by OHNO, who were advancing in the direction of Daiba under the order of Toshizo, were temporarily regaining their power, but they suddenly lost control and suffered a total defeat despite OHNO&apos;s desperate instructions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>大野がやむを得ず引き返したところ、同じく陸軍奉行添役の安富才助から歳三の戦死を知らされたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OHNO had no choice but to return, and he was informed by Saisuke YASUTOMI, who was also an Assistant General of the Army, that Toshizo had died in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OHNO had no choice but to return, and he was informed by Saisuke YASUTOMI, who was also an Assistant General of the Army, that Toshizo had died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>陸軍奉行添役の裏づけとれず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OHNO had no choice but to return, and he was informed by Saisuke YASUTOMI, who was also an Assistant General of the Army, that Toshizo had died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>歳三の遺体は小芝長之助らに引き取られて、他の戦死者と共に五稜郭に埋葬されたとも、別の場所に安置されていたとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo&apos;s body was claimed by Chonosuke KOSHIBA and others, and is said to have been buried in Goryokaku with the bodies of others who died in the war, or to have been laid at another place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo&apos;s body was claimed by Chonosuke KOSHIBA and others, and is said to have been buried either in Goryokaku with the bodies of others who died in the war or in another place.</e>
<cmt>buried in から buried either in に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo&apos;s body was claimed by Chonosuke KOSHIBA and others, and is said to have been buried either in Goryokaku with the bodies of others who died in the war or in another place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>その場所は特定されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place has not been specified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other place [of burial] has not been specified.</e>
<cmt>明確化のために [of burial] を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other place [of burial] has not been specified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>享年35。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 35.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 35.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 35.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="88">
<j>辞世の句は「よしや身は蝦夷が島辺に朽ちぬとも魂は東（あずま）の君やまもらむ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His farewell poem was &quot;Even if my body decays around the islands of Ezo, my soul will protect my lord who lives in the East &quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His farewell poem was &quot;Even if my body decays around the islands of Ezo, my soul will protect my lord who lives in the East &quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His farewell poem was &quot;Even if my body decays around the islands of Ezo, my soul will protect my lord who lives in the East &quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="89">
<j>また「たとひ身は蝦夷の島根に朽ちるとも魂は東の君やまもらん」とも伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The poem is also known as &quot;Should my body decay in the islands of Ezo, my soul will protect by lord who lives in the East&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The poem is also known as &quot;Should my body decay in the islands of Ezo, my soul will protect my lord who lives in the East&quot;.</e>
<cmt>タイピングミス訂正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The poem is also known as &quot;Should my body decay in the islands of Ezo, my soul will protect my lord who lives in the East.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Space deleted. Period revised.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="90">
<j>墓所は、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His tomb is in,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The locations of his tombs are:</e>
<cmt>墓所が多数あるので複数形に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The locations of his tombs are:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>東京都日野市石田 石田寺（せきでんじ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekidenji temple of Ishida, Hino city, Tokyo,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekidenji temple of Ishida, Hino city, Tokyo,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekidenji temple of Ishida, Hino city, Tokyo,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>北海道函館市船見町 称名寺（慰霊碑）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomyo-ji temple of Funami-cho, Hakodate-city, Hokkaido (memorial).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shomyo-ji temple of Funami-cho, Hakodate-city, Hokkaido (memorial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomyo-ji temple of Funami-cho, Hakodate-city, Hokkaido (memorial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>福島県会津若松市東山町 天寧寺（慰霊木碑）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tennei-ji temple of Higashiyamamachi, Aizu-Wakamatsu city, Fukushima prefecture (wooden memorial).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tennei-ji temple of Higashiyamamachi, Aizu-Wakamatsu city, Fukushima prefecture (wooden memorial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tennei-ji temple of Higashiyamamachi, Aizu-Wakamatsu city, Fukushima prefecture (wooden memorial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>東京都北区 (東京都)滝野川 寿徳寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jyutokuji temple of Takinogawa, Kita-ku, Tokyo</e>
<cmt>滝野川は地名。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jyutokuji temple of Takinogawa, Kita-ku, Tokyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jyutokuji temple of Takinogawa, Kita-ku, Tokyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>東京都荒川区南千住 円通寺 (東京都荒川区)　ほか</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entsuji temple of Minami Senju, Arakawa-ku, Tokyo, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entsuji temple of Minami Senju, Arakawa-ku, Tokyo, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entsuji temple of Minami Senju, Arakawa-ku, Tokyo, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>小姓市村鉄之助</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo&apos;s Kosyo, Tetsunosuke ICHIMURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo&apos;s Kosyo (servant; personal assisitant), Tetsunosuke ICHIMURA</e>
<cmt>小姓の説明を（）内に追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo&apos;s Kosyo (servant; personal assisitant), Tetsunosuke ICHIMURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>歳三は死の直前に小姓を務めていた市村鉄之助に遺髪と写真を渡し、「日野の家族の元に届けてくれ」と命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just before his death, Toshizo handed locks of his hair to be kept as a memonto and his photograph to Tetsunosuke ICHIMURA, who served him as Kosyo, and ordered Tetsunosuke to &quot;deliver them to my family&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just before his death, Toshizo handed locks of his hair to be kept as a memonto and his photograph to Tetsunosuke ICHIMURA, who served him as Kosyo, and ordered Tetsunosuke to &quot;deliver them to my family in Hino&quot;.</e>
<cmt>日野が抜けてたので追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just before his death, Toshizo handed locks of his hair to be kept as a memonto and his photograph to Tetsunosuke CHIMURA, who served him as Kosyo, and ordered Tetsunosuke to &quot;deliver them to my family in Hino.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Space deleted. Period revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>それに対し市村は「私はこの地で討ち死にする覚悟でやってきました。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ICHIMURA refused this request, saying &quot;I came here to die in battle,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ICHIMURA refused this request, saying &quot;I came here to die in battle,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ICHIMURA refused this request, saying &quot;I came here to die in battle,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>誰か別の者に命じて下さい」と拒否する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">please give your order to someone else&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">please give your order to someone else&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">please give your order to someone else&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>それを聞いた歳三は「断るとあらば、今この場で討ち果たす」と鋭い眼光を向けて言い放つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On hearing this, Toshizo said with a glare &quot;if you refuse, I will kill you here now&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On hearing this, Toshizo said with a glare &quot;if you refuse, I will kill you here now&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On hearing this, Toshizo said with a glare &quot;if you refuse, I will kill you here now&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>その歳三の気迫に圧されて市村は首を縦に振った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ICHIMURA was overwhelmed by such strong spirit of Toshizo and agreed to his order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ICHIMURA was overwhelmed by such strong spirit of Toshizo and agreed to carry out his order.</e>
<cmt>命を実行するという意味だと思うのでそのように変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ICHIMURA was overwhelmed by such strong spirit of Toshizo and agreed to carry out his order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>日野に旅立つとき市村は窓に人影が写っていることに気づく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he departed for Hino, ICHIMURA realized that someone was standing by a window.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he departed for Hino, ICHIMURA realized that someone was standing by a window.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he departed for Hino, ICHIMURA realized that someone was standing by a window.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>「誰かは解りませんでしたが、おそらく土方さんだったのだと思います」と語り残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ICHIMURA left the words that &quot;I could not tell who it was, but probably it was Mr. HIJIKATA&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ICHIMURA left the words that &quot;I could not tell who it was, but probably it was Mr. HIJIKATA&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ICHIMURA left the words that &quot;I could not tell who it was, but probably it was Mr. HIJIKATA&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>その後市村は日野宿の佐藤彦五郎の元に無事届けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, ICHIMURA managed to safely deliver Toshizo&apos;s articles to Hikogoro SATO at Hino-jyuku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, ICHIMURA managed to safely deliver Toshizo&apos;s articles to Hikogoro SATO at Hino-jyuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, ICHIMURA managed to safely deliver Toshizo&apos;s articles to Hikogoro SATO at Hino-jyuku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="104">
<j>愛刀は太刀　和泉守兼定（いずみのかみかねさだ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His favorite swords were the sword, Izumi no Kami Kenesada</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His favorite swords were the sword, Izumi no Kami Kenesada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His favorite swords were the sword, Izumi no Kami Kenesada</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>小太刀　堀川国広（ほりかわくにひろ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and the small sword, Horikawa Kunihiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and the small sword, Horikawa Kunihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">and the small sword, Horikawa Kunihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="106">
<j>幼少時には風呂から上がると、よく裸のまま家の柱で相撲の稽古をしていたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that when he was a child, he often remained naked after taking a bath, and practiced Sumo with a pillar in his house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that when he was a child, he often remained naked after taking a bath, and practiced Sumo with a pillar in his house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when he was a child, he often remained naked after taking a bath, and practiced Sumo with a pillar in his house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>その柱は現在でも残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pillar still exists today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pillar still exists today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pillar still exists today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="108">
<j>→土方家の伝承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">=&gt; A story that has been handed down in the HIJIKATA family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">=&gt; A story that has been handed down in the HIJIKATA family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">=&gt; A story that has been handed down in the HIJIKATA family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>土方愛著『子孫が語る土方歳三』参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taken from &quot;Taizo HIJIKATA told by his descendants&quot; written by Meguji HIJIKATA.</e>
<cmt>意味どおりに訳した。書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taken from &quot;Taizo HIJIKATA told by his descendants&quot; written by Meguji HIJIKATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taken from &quot;Taizo HIJIKATA told by his descendants&quot; written by Meguji HIJIKATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>柱は土方歳三資料館に現存。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pillar is kept at Hijikata Toshizo Museum.</e>
<cmt>資料館の表記は同館のホームページ参照http://www.hijikata-toshizo.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pillar is kept at Hijikata Toshizo Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pillar is kept at Hijikata Toshizo Museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="111">
<j>甥（佐藤彦五郎の3男・為吉）が庭先で転んで額を切った時にはすぐさま駆け付けて「男の子の向かい傷だ。めでたいめでたい」と笑ってあやしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When his nephew (Hikogoro SATO&apos;s 3rd son, Tamekichi) fell down in the garden and cut his forehead, it is said that Taizo immediately rushed towards Tamekichi and laughed and caressed the boy, saying &quot;the boy is wounded when he was confronting the world, so joyful, so joyful&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When his nephew (Hikogoro SATO&apos;s 3rd son, Tamekichi) fell down in the garden and cut his forehead, it is said that Taizo immediately rushed towards Tamekichi, laughed and caressed the boy saying, &quot;the boy is wounded when he was confronting the world, so joyful, so joyful&quot;.</e>
<cmt>laughed の前の and 削除； 為吉、読み方裏づけとれず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his nephew (Hikogoro SATO&apos;s 3rd son, Tamekichi) fell down in the garden and cut his forehead, it is said that Taizo immediately rushed towards Tamekichi, laughed and caressed the boy saying, &quot;the boy is wounded when he was confronting the world, so joyful, so joyful.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Space deleted. Period revised.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="112">
<j>→佐藤家の伝承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">=&gt; A story that has been handed down in the SATO family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">=&gt; A story that has been handed down in the SATO family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">=&gt; A story that has been handed down in the SATO family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>佐藤昱著『聞きがき新選組』参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taken from &quot;Kikigaki Shinsengumi&quot; written by Akira SATO.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taken from &quot;Kikigaki Shinsengumi&quot; written by Akira SATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taken from &quot;Kikigaki Shinsengumi&quot; written by Akira SATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="114">
<j>天然理心流道場では歳三は中極意目録までの記録しか現存していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only records of Chugokui Mokuroku awarded to Toshizo remain in Tennen-Rishin-ryu dojo today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only records of Chugokui Mokuroku awarded to Toshizo remain in Tennen-Rishin-ryu dojo today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only records of Chugokui Mokuroku awarded to Toshizo remain in Tennen-Rishin-ryu dojo today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>行商中に学んだ様々な流派のクセが取れなかったようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that he could not get rid of the ways of various schools which he learnt while he was traveling as a peddler.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that he could not get rid of the ways of various schools which he learnt while he was traveling as a peddler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that he could not get rid of the ways of various schools which he learnt while he was traveling as a peddler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>しかし、実戦では滅法強かったと言われている（斬り合いの時、足下の砂を相手にぶつけてひるんだ隙に斬り伏せたり首を絞めて絞殺したりなど、縦横無尽に戦闘をしていたという）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, it is said that he was awfully strong in actual fighting (it is said that he actively fought, by such ways as throwing the sand on the ground at his opponent, and cutting the opponent down or strangling him, while the opponent flinched from Toshizo&apos;s attack).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, it is said that he was awfully strong in actual fighting (it is said that he fought with no restraints, for example, by throwing the sand on the ground at his opponent and slashing or strangling him while heflinched from Toshizo&apos;s initial attack).</e>
<cmt>（）内の文章書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, it is said that he was awfully strong in actual fighting (it is said that he fought with no restraints, for example, by throwing the sand on the ground at his opponent and slashing or strangling him while heflinched from Toshizo&apos;s initial attack).</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="117">
<j>後の洋装の写真などから、歳三は合理主義者で便利なものは便利と受け取る柔軟さをもっており、舶来の懐中時計なども持っていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As can be seen by his photo of a later year dressed in western clothing, it is said that Toshizo was a rationalist, and had the flexibility to accept useful things, and owned a western pocket watch, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As can be seen from his photo of a later year dressed in western clothing, it is said that Toshizo was a rationalist and had the flexibility to accept useful things; for example, he owned a western pocket watch, etc.</e>
<cmt>前置詞変更；セミコロン使用</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As can be seen from his photo of a later year dressed in western clothing, it is said that Toshizo was a rationalist and had the flexibility to accept useful things; for example, he owned a western pocket watch, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="118">
<j>隊内の気の置けない仲間には、「自分は、織田信長の生まれ変わりだろう。」と言ったことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He once said to colleagues of Shinsen-gumi who were close to him, &quot;probably I am reborn from Nobunaga ODA&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He once said to colleagues of Shinsen-gumi who were close to him, &quot;probably I am reborn from Nobunaga ODA&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He once said to colleagues of Shinsen-gumi who were close to him, &quot;probably I am reborn from Nobunaga ODA&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="119">
<j>陣中法度、局中法度などの厳しい隊規を考案したとされ、裏切り者やはみ出し者に容赦の無い刃を浴びせた歳三は、鬼の副長と呼ばれ普段は冷酷な人物とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he created strict rules for Shinsen-gumi, such as Jinchu Hatto and Kyokuchu Hatto, and mercilessly killed betrayers or those who did not follow the rules, and was referred to as the pitiless vice commander, and is said to have been generally a heartless person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he created strict rules for Shinsen-gumi, such as Jinchu Hatto and Kyokuchu Hatto, and mercilessly killed betrayers or those who did not follow the rules; he was referred to as the pitiless vice commander, and in general, he was considered to be a heartless person.</e>
<cmt>最後の部分の単語変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he created strict rules for Shinsen-gumi, such as Jinchu Hatto and Kyokuchu Hatto, and mercilessly killed betrayers or those who did not follow the rules; he was referred to as the pitiless vice commander, and in general, he was considered to be a heartless person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>しかし、箱館戦争にまで従った新選組隊士中島登によれば、箱館戦争当時には「温和で、母のように慕われていた」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to Nobori NAKAJIMA who followed Toshizo up to Hakodate War, at the time of Hakodate War &quot;he was mild and was loved by his men as if he was their mother&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to Nobori NAKAJIMA who followed Toshizo up to Hakodate War, at the time of Hakodate War &quot;he was mild and was admired by his men as if he was their mother&quot;.</e>
<cmt>love でもいいと思いますが</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to Nobori NAKAJIMA who followed Toshizo up to Hakodate War, at the time of Hakodate War &quot;he was mild and was admired by his men as if he was their mother.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Period revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>この頃には若い隊士を度々飲食に連れ歩いたり、相談事に乗ったりするようになったともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that around this time, he started to often take young members of Shinsen-gumi out to meals and drinks, and was confided their problems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that around this time, he started to often take young members of Shinsen-gumi out to meals and drink, and he listened to and advise them on their problems.</e>
<cmt>相談に乗るを　he listened to and advise them on their problems　にしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that around this time, he started to often take young members of Shinsen-gumi out to meals and drink, and he listened to and advise them on their problems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>ただしそれも、年齢を経た結果というよりも、自分の死に場所を見つけたという悟りに近い気持ちと、明日にも闘いで命を落とすかも知れない隊士の士気を上げるための、計算の上であったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is a view that this was not because he has become older, but because he almost sensed that he has found a place to die, and also because he tried to motivate his men, who may die fighting even on the following day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is a view that this was not because he has become older, but this was a calculated action based on his realization that he has found a place to die, as well as for motivationg his men who could die tomorrow in a battle.</e>
<cmt>後半書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is a view that this was not because he has become older, but this was a calculated action based on his realization that he has found a place to die, as well as for motivating his men who could die tomorrow in a battle.</e>
<cmt>Spelling revised.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="123">
<j>もともと色白で引き締まった顔立ちをしており（当時としては）長身であった為、京都にて新選組副長として活動していたときなどは、日野の仲間に向けて多数の女性からの恋文をまとめて送って自慢するほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was handsome with a fair complexion and firm features and was a tall man(at his time), so when he was acting as the vice commander of Shinsen-gumi in Kyoto, he sent a bundle of love letters he had received from many women, to his colleagues in Hino, to boast how popular he was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he was a tall (for that time), handsome man with a fair complexion and firm features he was very popular among ladies; when he was acting as the vice commander of Shinsen-gumi in Kyoto he sent to his colleagues in Hino a bundle of love letters he had received from many women so as to boast his popularity.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he was a tall (for that time), handsome man with a fair complexion and firm features he was very popular among ladies; when he was acting as the vice commander of Shinsen-gumi in Kyoto he sent to his colleagues in Hino a bundle of love letters he had received from many women so as to boast his popularity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="124">
<j>上洛間もない頃、小島鹿之助へ（一説に近藤道場の弟子たちにとも言われる）宛て大きな荷物が届く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after he went to Kyoto, a large package from him was delivered to the attention of Shikanosuke KOJIMA (one story says that the package was addressed to the disciples of KONDO Dojo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after he went to Kyoto, a large package from him arrived in attention to Shikanosuke KOJIMA (one story says that the package was addressed to the disciples of KONDO Dojo).</e>
<cmt>単語変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after he went to Kyoto, a large package from him arrived in attention to Shikanosuke KOJIMA (one story says that the package was addressed to the disciples of KONDO Dojo).</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>京土産でも送って来たかと開けてみると、彼を慕う芸者・舞妓からの恋文がびっしり詰められており、以下の和歌が手紙に添えられていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikanosuke opened the package thinking that Toshizo may have sent presents from Kyoto, but what was inside were many love letters from geisha&apos;s and apprentice geisha&apos;s who loved Toshizo. The following tanka poem is said to have been attached to a letter by Toshizo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikanosuke opened the package thinking that Toshizo might have sent presents from Kyoto, but the package was filled with love letters from geishas and apprentice geishas who were in love with Toshizo. The following tanka poem is said to have accompanied the letter [from Toshizo]:</e>
<cmt>部分的に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikanosuke opened the package thinking that Toshizo might have sent presents from Kyoto, but the package was filled with love letters from geishas and apprentice geishas who were in love with Toshizo. The following tanka poem is said to have accompanied the letter [from Toshizo]:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="126">
<j>報国の心ころわするゝ婦人哉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ladies make me forget to do my best for my country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ladies make me forget to do my best for my country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ladies make me forget to do my best for my country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>→小島鹿之助の伝承。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">=&gt; a story told by Shikanosuke KOJIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">=&gt; a story told by Shikanosuke KOJIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">=&gt; a story told by Shikanosuke KOJIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>小島政孝著『新選組余話』参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taken from &quot;Shinsen-gumi Yowa&quot; written by Masataka KOJIMA.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taken from &quot;Shinsen-gumi Yowa&quot; written by Masataka KOJIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taken from &quot;Shinsen-gumi Yowa&quot; written by Masataka KOJIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="129">
<j>宇都宮の戦いで足を負傷していた歳三は、慶応4年（1868）閏4月頃から7月頃（異説あり）まで、会津若松城下の宿で病床に伏していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo, who has wounded his leg in Battle of Utsunomiya, was in sickbed at an inn in the castle town of Aizu Wakamatsu from around April to July of Year 1868 (there are different views regarding the period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo, who had his leg wounded in Battle of Utsunomiya, was in sickbed at an inn in the castle town of Aizu Wakamatsu from around April to July of 1868 (there are different views regarding the period).</e>
<cmt>宇都宮の戦いは、セル78にある宇都宮城の戦いのことであると思われる</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo, who had his leg wounded in Battle of Utsunomiya, was in sickbed at an inn in the castle town of Aizu Wakamatsu from around April to July of 1868 (there are different views regarding the period).</e>
<cmt>Space deleted.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>ある日、同じ宿にいた幕臣で文官の望月光蔵が訪ねて来たが、歳三は寝ころんだまま「俺達と共に戦え」と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, Mitsuzo MOCHIZUKI, who was a vassal of the Shogunate and a public servant, and stayed at the same inn as Toshizo, visited him, but Toshizo remained in his bed and said &quot;fight with us&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, Mitsuzo MOCHIZUKI, a vassal of the Shogunate and a public servant who was staying at the same inn as Toshizo, visited him, but Toshizo remained in his bed and said to him, &quot;fight with us&quot;.</e>
<cmt>部分的に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, Mitsuzo MOCHIZUKI, a vassal of the Shogunate and a public servant who was staying at the same inn as Toshizo, visited him, but Toshizo remained in his bed and said to him, &quot;fight with us.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Period revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>その傲慢な態度にムッときた望月は「自分は文官だから戦う事はできない」と拒否。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MOCHIZUKI who was angry at such arrogant attitude, refused by saying &quot;I am a public servant so I cannot fight&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MOCHIZUKI who got annoyed by this arrogant attitude refused by saying, &quot;I am a public servant so I cannot fight&quot;.</e>
<cmt>angry から got annoyed に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MOCHIZUKI who got annoyed by this arrogant attitude refused by saying, &quot;I am a public servant so I cannot fight.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Period revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>すると歳三は「じゃあお前は何をしにこんな遠くまで来たんだ。臆病者め」と言い放った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Toshizo spoke unreservedly &quot;if so, what did you come so far away for, you coward!&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Toshizo spoke unreservedly &quot;then what did you come so far away for, you coward!&quot;</e>
<cmt>if so を then に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Toshizo spoke unreservedly &quot;then what did you come so far away for, you coward!&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>望月も黙っておれず「幸いにもあなた達は宇都宮城を奪ったが、それをすぐに奪われたではないか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MOCHIZUKI retorted that &quot;you were fortunate enough to seize Utsunomiya Castle, but wasn&apos;t the castle soon retaken?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MOCHIZUKI retorted that &quot;you were fortunate enough to seize Utsunomiya Castle, but wasn&apos;t the castle soon retaken?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MOCHIZUKI retorted that &quot;you were fortunate enough to seize Utsunomiya Castle, but wasn&apos;t the castle soon retaken?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>再び奪うことはもう難しいだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is probably difficult to seize the castle again now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is probably difficult to seize the castle again now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is probably difficult to seize the castle again now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>実に惜しいことだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Very regrettable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How regrettable.</e>
<cmt>very を how に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How regrettable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>あなたもまた臆病者と言わざるを得ない」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I have no choice but to call you a coward, also&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I have no choice but to call you a coward, also&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I have no choice but to call you a coward, also&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>望月にそう言われた歳三は「うるさい、俺の病床に障る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshizo who was told such words by Mochizuki, shouted &quot;Shut up, you are making my illness worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshizo, upon hearing Mochizuki, shouted &quot;Shut up, you are making my illness worse.</e>
<cmt>表現変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshizo, upon hearing Mochizuki, shouted &quot;Shut up, you are making my illness worse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>もう聞きたくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I do not want to hear any more from you,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I do not want to hear any more from you,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I do not want to hear any more from you,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>出て行け」と叫んだため、望月は部屋を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">leave&quot; so MOCHIZUKI left his room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">leave&quot; so MOCHIZUKI left his room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">leave&quot; so MOCHIZUKI left his room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>この時歳三は怒りのあまり望月に枕を投げつけたそうである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, Toshizo was so angry that he threw his pillow at MOCHIZUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, Toshizo was so angry that he threw his pillow at MOCHIZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, Toshizo was so angry that he threw his pillow at MOCHIZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="141">
<j>→望月光蔵著「夢乃うわ言」および望月子孫著『告白の告発』参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">=&gt;Taken from &quot;Yumeno Uwagoto&quot; written by Mitsuzo MOCHIZUKI and &quot;Kokuhaku no Kokuhatsu&quot; written by Shison MOCHIZUKI.</e>
<cmt>望月子孫の裏づけとれず。この方については、Wikipediaにしか記述なし書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">=&gt;Taken from &quot;Yumeno Uwagoto&quot; written by Mitsuzo MOCHIZUKI and &quot;Kokuhaku no Kokuhatsu&quot; written by Shison MOCHIZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">=&gt;Taken from &quot;Yumeno Uwagoto&quot; written by Mitsuzo MOCHIZUKI and &quot;Kokuhaku no Kokuhatsu&quot; written by Shison MOCHIZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="142">
<j>江戸で定宿としていたのが幕府御用達釜屋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Toshizo was in Edo, he normally stayed in Kamaya, an inn patronized by the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Toshizo was in Edo, he normally stayed in Kamaya, an inn patronized by the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Toshizo was in Edo, he normally stayed in Kamaya, an inn patronized by the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>品川宿の中でも大変賑わっていた茶屋で「慶応三年卯十月廿一日登（上）新撰組土方歳三御家族　門人共上下三十一人（休）釜屋半右衛門　九貫三百文」と言う記録が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was one of the busy Chaya restaurant among Shinagawa-syuku, and the following record remains today &quot;on 3rd year of Keio, October 21st, family and disciples ofr the Shinsen-gumi member, Toshizo HIJIKATA, totaling 31 people rested, Hanuemon KAMAYA, fee was 9 kan and 300 mon&quot;.</e>
<cmt>幕府御用達の宿＝茶屋となっているが、これは変。 「卯」は訳に反映させていない。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was one of the busy Chaya restaurants among Shinagawa-syuku, and the following record remains today: &quot;On October 21st, the third year of Keio, family and disciples of the Shinsen-gumi member, Toshizo HIJIKATA, totaling 31 people rested, Hanuemon KAMAYA, fee was 9 kan and 300 mon&quot;.</e>
<cmt>釜屋半右衛門の表記、裏づけとれず</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was one of the busy Chaya restaurants among Shinagawa-syuku, and the following record remains today: &quot;On October 21st, the third year of Keio, family and disciples of the Shinsen-gumi member, Toshizo HIJIKATA, totaling 31 people rested, Hanuemon KAMAYA, fee was 9 kan and 300 mon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Space deleted. Period revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>現在、釜屋の跡地（品川区青物横丁駅）には新撰組の記念碑が建てられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, a memorial of Shinsen-gumi is built at the site of Kamaya (now there is Aomono-yokocho Station of Shinagawa-ku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A memorial of Shinsen-gumi now stands at the site of Kamaya (currently, Aomono-yokocho Station, Shinagawa-ku).</e>
<cmt>部分的に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A memorial of Shinsen-gumi now stands at the site of Kamaya (currently, Aomono-yokocho Station, Shinagawa-ku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="145">
<j>趣味</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hobbies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hobbies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hobbies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>和歌や俳諧などを嗜むなど意外と風流人の面もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was surprisingly a person of taste, and enjoyed making tanka poems and haiku, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surprisingly, he was a person of taste, and he enjoyed making tanka poems and haiku, etc.</e>
<cmt>書き出し順序変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surprisingly, he was a person of taste, and he enjoyed making tanka poems and haiku, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>「豊玉発句集」などを自分で書して残すほど書き溜めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He has written many poems, and left the poetry book, &quot;Hogyoku Hokku-shu&quot;, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He has written many poems and left poetry books such as &quot;Hogyoku Hokku-shu&quot;, etc.</e>
<cmt>複数か単数か不明；書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He has written many poems and left poetry books such as &quot;Hogyoku Hokku-shu,&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>deleted excessing space</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="148">
<j>公用に 出て行く道や 春の月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I can see the spring moon on my way to a public duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I can see the spring moon on my way to a public duty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I can see the spring moon on my way to a public duty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="149">
<j>三日月の 水の底照る 春の雨</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The crescent moon is shining at the bottom of a puddle formed by the spring rain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The crescent moon is shining at the bottom of a puddle formed by the spring rain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The crescent moon is shining at the bottom of a puddle formed by the spring rain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="150">
<j>さしむかふ 心は清き 水かゞみ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">My heart is pure, as I face my reflection on the water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">My heart is pure, as I face my reflection on the water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">My heart is pure, as I face my reflection on the water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="151">
<j>水音に 添てきゝけり 川千鳥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I listen to the sounds made by a plover, together with the sounds of water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I listen to the sounds made by a plover, together with the sounds of water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I listen to the sounds made by a plover, together with the sounds of water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="152">
<j>山門を 見こして見ゆる 春の月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I see the spring moon over the temple gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I see the spring moon over the temple gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I see the spring moon over the temple gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="153">
<j>梅の花 一輪咲いても 梅は梅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If an apricot flower blooms, even if only one, it is still an apricot flower.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If an apricot flower blooms, even if only one, it is still an apricot flower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If an apricot flower blooms, even if only one, it is still an apricot flower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="154">
<j>春の草 五色までは 覚えけり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seven plants of spring, I manage to memorize up to five.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seven plants of spring, I manage to memorize up to five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seven plants of spring, I manage to memorize up to five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="155">
<j>うくひすや はたきの音も つひやめる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I cannot help resting my hand as I dust the shelves, when I hear a warbler sing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I cannot help resting my hand as I dust the shelves, when I hear a warbler sing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I cannot help resting my hand as I dust the shelves, when I hear a warbler sing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="156">
<j>あはら屋に 寝て居てさむし 春の月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is cold sleeping in a shabby house, the spring moon shines above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is cold sleeping in a shabby house, the spring moon shines above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is cold sleeping in a shabby house, the spring moon shines above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="157">
<j>しれば迷い しなければ迷はぬ 恋の道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The road of love, If you know it you are lost, if you know it not, you will not get lost.</e>
<cmt>後述の句と同じ。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The road of love, If you know it you are lost, if you know it not, you will not get lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The road of love, If you know it you are lost, if you know it not, you will not get lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="158">
<j>水の北 山の南や 春の月</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">North of the waters, and south of the mountains, is the spring moon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">North of the waters, and south of the mountains, is the spring moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">North of the waters, and south of the mountains, is the spring moon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="159">
<j>行く年の 月日の流れ 蚊帳の外</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The days and months of the year which pass by, I cannot do anything about it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The days and months of the year which pass by, I cannot do anything about it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The days and months of the year which pass by, I cannot do anything about it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="160">
<j>故郷に向かって　進む　五月雲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clouds of May fly towards my hometown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clouds of May fly towards my hometown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clouds of May fly towards my hometown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="161">
<j>知れば迷ひ　知らねば迷わぬ　恋の道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The road of love, If you know it you are lost, if you know it not, you will not get lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The road of love, If you know it you are lost, if you know it not, you will not get lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The road of love, If you know it you are lost, if you know it not, you will not get lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="162">
<j>ふりながら　きゆる雪あり　上巳こそ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is indeed the month of March, some snow vanish as they fall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is indeed the month of March, some snow vanish as they fall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is indeed the month of March, some snow vanish as they fall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="163">
<j>横に行　足跡はなし　朝の雪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the morning snow, there are no horizontal footsteps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the morning snow, there are no horizontal footsteps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the morning snow, there are no horizontal footsteps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>演じた俳優、声優</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actors and voice artists who played Toshizo HIJIKATA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actors and voice artists who played Toshizo HIJIKATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actors and voice artists who played Toshizo HIJIKATA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="164">
<j>『新選組血風録』や『燃えよ剣』での好演から栗塚旭が不世出の土方歳三役俳優として伝説的な存在と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the excellent performance given in &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; and &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot;, Asahi KURIZUKA is known as a legendery figure and a great actor playing the part of Toshizo HIJIKATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the excellent performance given in &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; and &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot;, Asahi KURIZUKA is known as a legendery figure and a great actor playing the part of Toshizo HIJIKATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the excellent performance given in &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; and &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot;, Asahi KURIZUKA is known as a legendary figure and a great actor playing the part of Toshizo HIJIKATA.</e>
<cmt>Spelling revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>ドラマ『新選組血風録』の製作開始時に隊士服を着た栗塚旭を見た司馬遼太郎が絶賛したというエピソードが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The episode that when Ryotaro SHIBA saw Asahi KURIZUKA wearing the uniform of Shinsen-gumi, SHIBA praised KURIZUKA, is known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is well known that when Ryotaro SHIBA saw Asahi KURIZUKA wearing the uniform of Shinsen-gumi, SHIBA highly praised KURIZUKA.</e>
<cmt>書き出し変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is well known that when Ryotaro SHIBA saw Asahi KURIZUKA wearing the uniform of Shinsen-gumi, SHIBA highly praised KURIZUKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>映画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Movies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="166">
<j>河津清三郎 『新撰組 第一部京洛風雲の巻、第二部池田屋騒動、第三部魔剣乱舞』（監督：萩原遼）1952年、東映</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Seizaburo KAWAZU &quot;Shinsen-gumi Part 1 the Book of Kyou Rakufu-kan, Part 2 Ikedaya Incident, Part 3 Maken-Ranbu&quot; (Director: Ryo HAGIWARA), Year 1952 by Toei.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明。以下のセルで映画やドラマ、ゲームなどのタイトルが不明なものについては、英語で書かれたホームページではそのままローマ字書きされていることが多い。&quot;acted by&quot; という表現はあまり聞かないが、映画用の正式な convention があるのでは？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Seizaburo KAWAZU &quot;Shinsen-gumi Part 1 the Book of Kyou Rakufu-kan, Part 2 Ikedaya Incident, Part 3 Maken-Ranbu&quot; (Director: Ryo HAGIWARA), Year 1952 by Toei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Seizaburo KAWAZU &quot;Shinsen-gumi Part 1 the Book of Kyou Rakufu-kan, Part 2 Ikedaya Incident, Part 3 Maken-Ranbu&quot; (Director: Ryo HAGIWARA), Year 1952 by Toei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>原健策 『新選組鬼隊長』（監督：河野寿一）1954年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Kensaku HARA &quot;Shinsen-gumi Oni Taicho&quot; (Director: Toshikazu KONO) Year 1954.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Kensaku HARA &quot;Shinsen-gumi Oni Taicho&quot; (Director: Toshikazu KONO) Year 1954.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Kensaku HARA &quot;Shinsen-gumi Oni Taicho&quot; (Director: Toshikazu KONO) Year 1954.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>山形勲 『新選組』（監督：佐々木康）1958年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Isao YAMAGATA &quot;Shinsen-gumi&quot; (Director: Yasushi SASAKI) Year 1958.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Isao YAMAGATA &quot;Shinsen-gumi&quot; (Director: Yasushi SASAKI) Year 1958.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Isao YAMAGATA &quot;Shinsen-gumi&quot; (Director: Yasushi SASAKI) Year 1958.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>黒川弥太郎 『壮烈新選組』（監督：佐々木康）1960年、東映</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Yataro KUROKAWA &quot;Souretsu Shinsen-gumi&quot;(Director: Yasushi SASAKI) Year 1960 by Toei.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Yataro KUROKAWA &quot;Souretsu Shinsen-gumi&quot;(Director: Yasushi SASAKI) Year 1960 by Toei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Yataro KUROKAWA &quot;Souretsu Shinsen-gumi&quot;(Director: Yasushi SASAKI) Year 1960 by Toei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>龍崎一郎 『風雲新撰組』（監督：毛利正樹）1961年、新東宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Ichiro RYUZAKI &quot;Fu-un Shinsen-gumi&quot; (Director: Masaki MORI) Year 1961 by Shintoho.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Ichiro RYUZAKI &quot;Fu-un Shinsen-gumi&quot; (Director: Masaki MORI) Year 1961 by Shintoho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Ichiro RYUZAKI &quot;Fu-un Shinsen-gumi&quot; (Director: Masaki MORI) Year 1961 by Shintoho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>加藤武 『新選組血風録 近藤勇』（監督：小沢茂弘）1963年、東映</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Takeshi KATO &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku Isami KONDO&quot; (Director: Shigehiro OZAWA)</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Takeshi KATO &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku Isami KONDO&quot; (Director: Shigehiro OZAWA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Takeshi KATO &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku Isami KONDO&quot; (Director: Shigehiro OZAWA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>天知茂 『新撰組始末記』（監督：三隅研次）1963年、大映</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Shigeru AMACHI &quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot; (Director: Kenji MISUMI), Year 1963 by Daiei.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Shigeru AMACHI &quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot; (Director: Kenji MISUMI), Year 1963 by Daiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Shigeru AMACHI &quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot; (Director: Kenji MISUMI), Year 1963 by Daiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>西村晃 『幕末残酷物語』（監督：加藤泰）1964年、東映</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Ko NISHIMURA &quot;Cruel Story of the Shogunate&apos;s Downfall&quot; (Director: Tai KATO), Year 1964 by Toei.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル、以下のホームページ参照http://www.timeout.com/film/people/315980/tai-kato.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Ko NISHIMURA &quot;Cruel Story of the Shogunate&apos;s Downfall&quot; (Director: Tai KATO), Year 1964 by Toei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Ko NISHIMURA &quot;Cruel Story of the Shogunate&apos;s Downfall&quot; (Director: Tai KATO), Year 1964 by Toei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>栗塚旭 『土方歳三 燃えよ剣』（監督：市村泰一）1966年、松竹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Toshizo HIJIKATA Moyeyo Ken&quot; (Director: Hirokazu ICHIMURA), Year 1966 by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Toshizo HIJIKATA Moyeyo Ken&quot; (Director: Hirokazu ICHIMURA), Year 1966 by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Toshizo HIJIKATA Moyeyo Ken&quot; (Director: Hirokazu ICHIMURA), Year 1966 by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>小林桂樹 『新選組』（監督：沢島忠）1969年、東宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Keiju KOBAYASHI &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; (Director: Tadashi SAWASHIMA), Year 1969 by Toho.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル、以下のホームページ参照http://www.variety.com/profiles/Film/main/112954/Shinsengumi.html?dataSet=1</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Keiju KOBAYASHI &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; (Director: Tadashi SAWASHIMA), Year 1969 by Toho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Keiju KOBAYASHI &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; (Director: Tadashi SAWASHIMA), Year 1969 by Toho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>高橋幸治 『沖田総司 (映画)』（監督：出目昌伸）1974年、東宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Koji TAKAHASHI &quot;Okita Soji (Movie)&quot; (Director: Masanobu DEME), Year 1974, by Toho.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル、以下のホームページ参照http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/ff20071012a1.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Koji TAKAHASHI &quot;Okita Soji (Movie)&quot; (Director: Masanobu DEME), Year 1974, by Toho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Koji TAKAHASHI &quot;Okita Soji (Movie)&quot; (Director: Masanobu DEME), Year 1974, by Toho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>西川のりお 『必殺! ブラウン館の怪物たち』（監督：広瀬襄）（1985年、必殺シリーズ）、松竹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Norio NISHIKAWA &quot;Hissatsu! Buraun-kan no Kaibutsu-tachi&quot; (Director: Jyo HIROSE) (Year 1985, Hissatsu Series), by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明。必殺シリーズそのものの表記は確認がとれなかったが、「必殺」については以下の松竹のホームページ参照。http://shochikuonline.jp/cinfo/s/000000123a/c/0007b1</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Norio NISHIKAWA &quot;Hissatsu! Buraun-kan no Kaibutsu-tachi&quot; (Director: Jyo HIROSE) (Year 1985, Hissatsu Series), by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Norio NISHIKAWA &quot;Hissatsu! Buraun-kan no Kaibutsu-tachi&quot; (Director: Jyo HIROSE) (Year 1985, Hissatsu Series), by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>杉本哲太 『幕末純情伝』（監督：薬師寺光幸）1991年、松竹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Tetta SUGIMOTO &quot;Bakumatsu Junjyo-den&quot; (Director: Mitsuyuki YAKUSHIJI)Year 1991, by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Tetta SUGIMOTO &quot;Bakumatsu Junjyo-den&quot; (Director: Mitsuyuki YAKUSHIJI)Year 1991, by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Tetta SUGIMOTO &quot;Bakumatsu Junjyo-den&quot; (Director: Mitsuyuki YAKUSHIJI)Year 1991, by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>ビートたけし 『御法度 (映画)』（監督：大島渚）1999年、松竹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Beat Takeshi &quot;Taboo (Movie)&quot; (Director: Nagisa OSHIMA, Year 1999, by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>ビートたけしの名前については、そのままの順番で表記。映画タイトル、以下のホームページ参照。御法度をローマ字書きしたGohattoという言葉が添えられていることもあるhttp://www.newyorkerfilms.com/nyf/t_elements/taboo/taboo_pk.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Beat Takeshi &quot;Taboo (Movie)&quot; (Director: Nagisa OSHIMA, Year 1999, by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Beat Takeshi &quot;Taboo (Movie)&quot; (Director: Nagisa OSHIMA, Year 1999, by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>中井貴一 『新撰組』（監督：市川崑）2000年、メディアボックス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Kiichi NAKAI &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; (Director: Kon ICHIKAWA), Year 2000, by Media Box.</e>
<cmt>映画タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Kiichi NAKAI &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; (Director: Kon ICHIKAWA), Year 2000, by Media Box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Kiichi NAKAI &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; (Director: Kon ICHIKAWA), Year 2000, by Media Box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>野村祐人 『壬生義士伝』（監督：大滝洋二郎）2003年、松竹</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Eugene NOMURA &quot;When the Last Sword is Drawn&quot; (Director: Yojiro OTAKI), Year 2003, by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>野村祐人の表記、公式ホームページを参照。http://www.eugenenomura.com/profile.html映画タイトルについては、このタイトルを使用している資料が多かったため、その表記を採用。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Eugene NOMURA &quot;When the Last Sword is Drawn&quot; (Director: Yojiro OTAKI), Year 2003, by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Eugene NOMURA &quot;When the Last Sword is Drawn&quot; (Director: Yojiro OTAKI), Year 2003, by Shochiku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>ドラマ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TV Dramas</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TV Dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TV Dramas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="182">
<j>栗塚旭 『新選組血風録』1965年、テレビ朝日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; Year 1965, by TV Asahi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; Year 1965, by TV Asahi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; Year 1965, by TV Asahi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>金内吉男 『竜馬がゆく (NHK大河ドラマ)』1968年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Yoshio KANEUCHI &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku (NHK Taiga Drama)&quot; Year 1968.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明。映画のタイトルと同じく、そのままローマ字書きされているものが多い</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Yoshio KANEUCHI &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku (NHK Taiga Drama)&quot; Year 1968.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Yoshio KANEUCHI &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku (NHK Taiga Drama)&quot; Year 1968.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>栗塚旭 『燃えよ剣』1970年、テレビ朝日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; Year 1970, by TV Asahi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; Year 1970, by TV Asahi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; Year 1970, by TV Asahi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>栗塚旭 『新撰組』1973年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; Year 1973.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; Year 1973.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Asahi KURIZUKA &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; Year 1973.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>藤竜也 『勝海舟 (NHK大河ドラマ)』1974年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Tatsuya FUJI &quot;Katsu Kaishu (NHK Taiga Drama) Year 1974.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Tatsuya FUJI &quot;Katsu Kaishu (NHK Taiga Drama) Year 1974.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Tatsuya FUJI &quot;Katsu Kaishu (NHK Taiga Drama) Year 1974.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>古谷一行 『新選組始末記』1977年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Ikko FURUYA &quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Ikko FURUYA &quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Ikko FURUYA &quot;Shinsen-gumi Shimatsuki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>伊達正三郎 『竜馬がゆく1982年版』テレビ東京</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Shozaburo DATE &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku Year 1982 version&quot; by TV Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Shozaburo DATE &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku Year 1982 version&quot; by TV Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Shozaburo DATE &quot;Ryoma ga Yuku Year 1982 version&quot; by TV Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>夏八木勲 『壬生の恋歌』1983年、日本放送協会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Isao NATSUYAGI &quot;Mibu no Koi Uta&quot; Year 1983, by NHK.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明日本放送協会はNHKのこと。http://www.nhk.or.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Isao NATSUYAGI &quot;Mibu no Koi Uta&quot; Year 1983, by NHK.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Isao NATSUYAGI &quot;Mibu no Koi Uta&quot; Year 1983, by NHK.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>近藤正臣 『白虎隊 (日本テレビ系テレビドラマ)』1986年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Masaomi KONDO &quot;Byakko-tai (Nippon Television Network TV Drama)&quot; Year 1986.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Masaomi KONDO &quot;Byakko-tai (Nippon Television Network TV Drama)&quot; Year 1986.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Masaomi KONDO &quot;Byakko-tai (Nippon Television Network TV Drama)&quot; Year 1986.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>竹脇無我 『新撰組』1987年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Muga TAKEWAKI &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; Year 1987.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Muga TAKEWAKI &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; Year 1987.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Muga TAKEWAKI &quot;Shinsengumi&quot; Year 1987.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>渡哲也 『五稜郭 (テレビドラマ)』 年末時代劇スペシャル 1988年、日本テレビ放送網</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Tetsuya WATARI &quot;Goryokaku (TV Drama)&quot; Year-end Jidaigeki Special, by Nippon Television Network.</e>
<cmt>五稜郭というタイトルにはFort Ezoという言葉が添えられているものが多いが、しっかりとした裏づけはとれていないセル281にもあるが、日本テレビの英語の社名がNippon Television Network Corporationであるhttp://www.ntv.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Tetsuya WATARI &quot;Goryokaku (TV Drama)&quot; Year-end Jidaigeki Special, by Nippon Television Network.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Tetsuya WATARI &quot;Goryokaku (TV Drama)&quot; Year-end Jidaigeki Special, by Nippon Television Network.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>役所広司 『燃えよ剣』1990年、テレビ東京</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Koji YAKUSHO &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; Year 1990, by TV Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Koji YAKUSHO &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; Year 1990, by TV Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Koji YAKUSHO &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; Year 1990, by TV Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>地井武男 『新撰組 池田屋の血闘』1992年、東京放送</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Takeo CHII &quot;Shinsen-gumi Ikedaya no Ketto&quot; Year 1992, Tokyo Broadcasting System.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Takeo CHII &quot;Shinsen-gumi Ikedaya no Ketto&quot; Year 1992, Tokyo Broadcasting System.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Takeo CHII &quot;Shinsen-gumi Ikedaya no Ketto&quot; Year 1992, Tokyo Broadcasting System.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>橋爪淳 『徳川慶喜 (NHK大河ドラマ)』1998年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Jyun HASHIZUME &quot;Tokugawa Yoshinobu (NHK Taiga Drama)&quot;Year 1998.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Jyun HASHIZUME &quot;Tokugawa Yoshinobu (NHK Taiga Drama)&quot;Year 1998.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Jyun HASHIZUME &quot;Tokugawa Yoshinobu (NHK Taiga Drama)&quot;Year 1998.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>村上弘明 『新選組血風録』1998年、テレビ朝日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Hiroaki MURAKAMI &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; Year 1998, by TV Asahi.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Hiroaki MURAKAMI &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; Year 1998, by TV Asahi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Hiroaki MURAKAMI &quot;Shinsengumi Keppuroku&quot; Year 1998, by TV Asahi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>伊原剛志 『壬生義士伝』2002年、テレビ東京</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Tsuyoshi IHARA &quot;When the Last Sword is Drawn&quot; Year 2002, by TV Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Tsuyoshi IHARA &quot;When the Last Sword is Drawn&quot; Year 2002, by TV Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Tsuyoshi IHARA &quot;When the Last Sword is Drawn&quot; Year 2002, by TV Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>山本耕史 『新選組!』2004年、NHK大河ドラマ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Koji YAMAMOTO &quot;Shinsengumi !&quot; Year 2004, NHK Taiga Drama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Koji YAMAMOTO &quot;Shinsengumi !&quot; Year 2004, NHK Taiga Drama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Koji YAMAMOTO &quot;Shinsengumi !&quot; Year 2004, NHK Taiga Drama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>山本耕史 『新選組!! 土方歳三 最期の一日』2006年、NHK（『新選組!』の続編）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Koji YAMAMOTO &quot;Shinsengumi !! Hijikata Toshizo Saigono Ichi-nichi&quot; Year 2006, by NHK (sequel to &quot;Shinsengumi !&quot;).</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Koji YAMAMOTO &quot;Shinsengumi !! Hijikata Toshizo Saigono Ichi-nichi&quot; Year 2006, by NHK (sequel to &quot;Shinsengumi !&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Koji YAMAMOTO &quot;Shinsengumi !! Hijikata Toshizo Saigono Ichi-nichi&quot; Year 2006, by NHK (sequel to &quot;Shinsengumi !&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>伊藤英明 『輪違屋糸里』2007年、TBS</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Hideaki ITO &quot;Wachigaiya Itosato&quot; Year 2007, by TBS.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトル表記不明。輪違屋糸里は｢わちがいやいとさと｣と読む。http://www.tbs.co.jp/itosato/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Hideaki ITO &quot;Wachigaiya Itosato&quot; Year 2007, by TBS.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Hideaki ITO &quot;Wachigaiya Itosato&quot; Year 2007, by TBS.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>演劇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theater</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theater</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theater</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="201">
<j>麻実れい 『星影の人』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Rei ASAMI &quot;Hoshikage no Hito&quot;.</e>
<cmt>劇タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Rei ASAMI &quot;Hoshikage no Hito&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Rei ASAMI &quot;Hoshikage no Hito&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>麻路さき 『誠の群像/魅惑II-ネオ・エゴイスト!』1997年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Saki ASAJI &quot;Makotono Gunzo/Miwaku II-Neo Egoist !&quot; Year 1997.</e>
<cmt>劇タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Saki ASAJI &quot;Makotono Gunzo/Miwaku II-Neo Egoist !&quot; Year 1997.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Saki ASAJI &quot;Makotono Gunzo/Miwaku II-Neo Egoist !&quot; Year 1997.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>小松和弘 『チオチモリンS』（2003年、演劇ユニット pan-dan笹公演）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Kazuhiro KOMATSU &quot;Chio Chimorin S&quot; (Year 2003, by theater unit pan-dan Sasa).</e>
<cmt>小松和弘、pan-dan笹、タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Kazuhiro KOMATSU &quot;Chio Chimorin S&quot; (Year 2003, by theater unit pan-dan Sasa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Kazuhiro KOMATSU &quot;Chio Chimorin S&quot; (Year 2003, by theater unit pan-dan Sasa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>㈱北海道テレコムセンター　テレコムホール</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokkaido Telecom Cente, Telecom Hall</e>
<cmt>㈱北海道テレコムセンターは平成17年4月に札幌総合情報センター(株）と合併。http://www.sweb.co.jp/enkaku.htmlテレコムホールもメディアMIXホールに改称されるhttp://engekilife.com/theater/2410</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokkaido Telecom Cente, Telecom Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokkaido Telecom Cente, Telecom Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>上川隆也『燃えよ剣』2004年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Tatsuya KAMIKAWA &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; Year 2004.</e>
<cmt>劇タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Tatsuya KAMIKAWA &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; Year 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Tatsuya KAMIKAWA &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot; Year 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>大泉洋 『LOOSER～失い続けてしまうアルバム～』（2004年、TEAM-NACS第10回公演）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Yo OIZUMI &quot;LOOSER - Ushinai Tsuzukete Shimau Album-&quot; (Year 2004, 10th performance of TEAM-NACS).</e>
<cmt>劇タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Yo OIZUMI &quot;LOOSER - Ushinai Tsuzukete Shimau Album-&quot; (Year 2004, 10th performance of TEAM-NACS).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Yo OIZUMI &quot;LOOSER - Ushinai Tsuzukete Shimau Album-&quot; (Year 2004, 10th performance of TEAM-NACS).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>札幌公演‐サッポロファクトリーホール 東京公演‐池袋サンシャイン劇場　アンコール公演‐日本青年館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sapporo Performance - Sapporo Factory Hall - Tokyo Performance - Ikebukuro Sunshine Theatre Encore Performane - Nippon-seinenkan.</e>
<cmt>池袋サンシャイン劇場は、同劇場のホームページを見ると正式には「池袋」は名称についていない。http://www.sunshine-theatre.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sapporo Performance - Sapporo Factory Hall - Tokyo Performance - Ikebukuro Sunshine Theatre Encore Performane - Nippon-seinenkan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sapporo Performance - Sapporo Factory Hall - Tokyo Performance - Ikebukuro Sunshine Theatre Encore Performance - Nippon-seinenkan.</e>
<cmt>Spelling revised.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>哀川翔 『KANSAI SUPER SHOW アボルダージュ』2004年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Sho AIKAWA &quot;KANSAI SUPER SHOW Aboru-daaju&quot; Year 2004.</e>
<cmt>劇タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Sho AIKAWA &quot;KANSAI SUPER SHOW Aboru-daaju&quot; Year 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Sho AIKAWA &quot;KANSAI SUPER SHOW Aboru-daaju&quot; Year 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>江田由紀浩、小山めぐみ 『桜襲さくらがさね』（2007年、劇団SKグループ第24回公演）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Yukihiro EDA and Megumi KOYAMA &quot;Sakura Gasane&quot; (Year 2007, 24th performance of Theater SK Group).</e>
<cmt>劇団SKグループの以下のホームページを見ると、SKGという略称が書かれているため、SK Groupという表記であると考えたhttp://www1.plala.or.jp/skg/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Yukihiro EDA and Megumi KOYAMA &quot;Sakura Gasane&quot; (Year 2007, 24th performance of Theater SK Group).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Yukihiro EDA and Megumi KOYAMA &quot;Sakura Gasane&quot; (Year 2007, 24th performance of Theater SK Group).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>東京公演‐シアターグリーン BIG TREE THEATER　札幌公演‐シアターZOO</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Performance - Theater Green BIG TREE THEATER Sapporo Performance - Theater Zoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Performance - Theater Green BIG TREE THEATER Sapporo Performance - Theater Zoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Performance - Theater Green BIG TREE THEATER Sapporo Performance - Theater Zoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>彩吹真央／音月桂 『星影の人』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Mao AYABUKI/Kei OTOZUKI &quot;Hoshikage no Hito&quot;.</e>
<cmt>劇タイトル表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Mao AYABUKI/Kei OTOZUKI &quot;Hoshikage no Hito&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Mao AYABUKI/Kei OTOZUKI &quot;Hoshikage no Hito&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>大浦薫『さくらのごとく～新選組桜真説～』（2005年2月、FA企画【舞台部門】さくらさくらカンパニー）京都演劇フェスティバル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Kaoru OURA &quot;SAKURA no gotoku, Like a cherry tree&quot; (February 2005, FA Kikaku [Theatre Division] Sakura Sakura Company) Kyoto Drama Festival.</e>
<cmt>劇タイトル、劇団の名前はセル307のNew York International Fringe Festivalの資料を参照(P.46）http://www.fringenyc.org/ELENA-UPLOADS/2006programguidesmall.pdf京都演劇フェスティバルの正式英語名称は確認できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Kaoru OURA &quot;SAKURA no gotoku, Like a cherry tree&quot; (February 2005, FA Kikaku [Theatre Division] Sakura Sakura Company) Kyoto Drama Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Kaoru OURA &quot;SAKURA no gotoku, Like a cherry tree&quot; (February 2005, FA Kikaku [Theatre Division] Sakura Sakura Company) Kyoto Drama Festival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>大浦薫『さくらのごとく～新選組桜真説～』（2006年8月、FA企画【舞台部門】さくらさくらカンパニー）The 2006 New York International　Fringe Festival　（NY国際芸術祭）参加作品　審査員特別賞受賞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Kaoru OURA &quot;SAKURA no gotoku, Like a cherry tree&quot; (August 2006, FA Kikaku [Theatre Division] Sakura Sakura Company) Participated in the 2006 New York International Fringe Festival, and received Judges&apos; Special Award.</e>
<cmt>審査員特別賞については同芸術祭のホームページ、過去の受賞者紹介には掲載されていないhttp://www.fringenyc.org/history/cguide1.asp#06</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Kaoru OURA &quot;SAKURA no gotoku, Like a cherry tree&quot; (August 2006, FA Kikaku [Theatre Division] Sakura Sakura Company) Participated in the 2006 New York International Fringe Festival, and received Judges&apos; Special Award.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Kaoru OURA &quot;SAKURA no gotoku, Like a cherry tree&quot; (August 2006, FA Kikaku [Theatre Division] Sakura Sakura Company) Participated in the 2006 New York International Fringe Festival, and received Judges&apos; Special Award.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>大浦薫 『北天幻桜～土方雪想夢～』（2008年、FA企画【舞台部門】さくらさくらカンパニー歴史モノローグシリーズ第3弾）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Kaoru OURA &quot;Hokuten Genou - HIJIKATA Sekisomu-&quot;(Year 2008, FA Kikaku [Theatre Division]Sakura Sakura Company History Monologue Series No. 3).</e>
<cmt>劇タイトル、表記不明歴史モノローグシリーズの表記、裏づけはとれていない</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Kaoru OURA &quot;Hokuten Genou - HIJIKATA Sekisomu-&quot;(Year 2008, FA Kikaku [Theatre Division]Sakura Sakura Company History Monologue Series No. 3).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Kaoru OURA &quot;Hokuten Genou - HIJIKATA Sekisomu-&quot;(Year 2008, FA Kikaku [Theatre Division]Sakura Sakura Company History Monologue Series No. 3).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>アニメ・ゲーム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Animation/TV Games</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Animation/TV Games</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Animation/TV Games</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="215">
<j>中田譲治 『PEACE MAKER鐵』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Jyoji Nakata &quot;Peacemaker Kurogane&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Jyoji Nakata &quot;Peacemaker Kurogane&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Jyoji Nakata &quot;Peacemaker Kurogane&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>檜山修之 『幕末機関説 いろはにほへと』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Nobuyuki HIYAMA &quot;Bakumatsu Kikansetsu Irohanihoheto&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Nobuyuki HIYAMA &quot;Bakumatsu Kikansetsu Irohanihoheto&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Nobuyuki HIYAMA &quot;Bakumatsu Kikansetsu Irohanihoheto&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>楠大典 『陸奥圓明流外伝 修羅の刻』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Taiten KUSUNOKI &quot;Mutsu Enmei Ryugaiden Shura no Toki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>ドラマタイトルは不明。ローマ字書きされていることが多い</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Taiten KUSUNOKI &quot;Mutsu Enmei Ryugaiden Shura no Toki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Taiten KUSUNOKI &quot;Mutsu Enmei Ryugaiden Shura no Toki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>小山力也 『るろうに剣心 -明治剣客浪漫譚-』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Rikiya KOYAMA &quot;Rurouni Kenshin: Meiji Kenyaku Romantan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Rikiya KOYAMA &quot;Rurouni Kenshin: Meiji Kenyaku Romantan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Rikiya KOYAMA &quot;Rurouni Kenshin: Meiji Kenyaku Romantan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>置鮎龍太郎 『幕末恋華 新選組』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Ryotaro OKIAYU &quot;Bakumatsu Renka Shinsengumi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Ryotaro OKIAYU &quot;Bakumatsu Renka Shinsengumi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Ryotaro OKIAYU &quot;Bakumatsu Renka Shinsengumi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>子安武人 『新撰組群狼伝』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Takehito KOYASU &quot;Shinsengumi Gunrouden&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Takehito KOYASU &quot;Shinsengumi Gunrouden&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Takehito KOYASU &quot;Shinsengumi Gunrouden&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>ラジオ・ドラマCD</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Radio/Drama CD&apos;s</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Radio/Drama CD&apos;s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Radio/Drama CD&apos;s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="221">
<j>上川隆也 『風光る (渡辺多恵子)』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Tatsuya KAMIKAWA &quot;Kaze Hikaru (Taeko Watanabe)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「風光る」は漫画のタイトル、渡辺多恵子は作者。http://flowers.shogakukan.co.jp/interview/interview_11.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Tatsuya KAMIKAWA &quot;Kaze Hikaru (Taeko Watanabe)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Tatsuya KAMIKAWA &quot;Kaze Hikaru (Taeko Watanabe)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>平川大輔 『ひなたの狼 新選組綺談』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acted by Daisuke HIRAKAWA &quot;Hinata no Ookami: Shinsengumi Kidan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acted by Daisuke HIRAKAWA &quot;Hinata no Ookami: Shinsengumi Kidan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acted by Daisuke HIRAKAWA &quot;Hinata no Ookami: Shinsengumi Kidan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>土方歳三を主人公とした作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ｗorks with Toshizo HIJIKATA as the main character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ｗorks featuring Toshizo HIJIKATA as the main character.</e>
<cmt>reworded</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Workes featuring Toshizo HIJIKATA as the main character.</e>
<cmt>Double bite revised.</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="223">
<j>土方歳三が登場する作品は、新選組新選組を題材にした作品、Category新選組を題材とした作品も参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding works in which Toshizo HIJIKATA appears, refer also to works based on Shinsen-gumi and Category Shinsen-gumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding works in which Toshizo HIJIKATA appears, refer also to works based on Shinsen-gumi and Category Shinsen-gumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding works in which Toshizo HIJIKATA appears, refer also to works based on Shinsen-gumi and Category Shinsen-gumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>小説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Novels</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Novels</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="224">
<j>司馬遼太郎 『燃えよ剣』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Ryotaro SHIBA &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot;.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Ryotaro SHIBA &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Ryotaro SHIBA &quot;Moeyo Ken&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>大内美予子『土方歳三』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Miyoko OUCHI &quot;Hijikata Toshizo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Miyoko OUCHI &quot;Hijikata Toshizo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Miyoko OUCHI &quot;Hijikata Toshizo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>広瀬仁紀 『土方歳三 散華』1982年 ISBN 4872701364</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Niki HIROSE &quot;Hijikata Toshizo Sange&quot; Year 1982, ISBN 4872701364</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Niki HIROSE &quot;Hijikata Toshizo Sange&quot; Year 1982, ISBN 4872701364</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Niki HIROSE &quot;Hijikata Toshizo Sange&quot; Year 1982, ISBN 4872701364</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>萩尾農『散華・土方歳三』1989年 ISBN 4829110686</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Minori HAGIO &quot;Sange ・Hijikata Toshizo&quot; Year 1989, ISBN 4829110686</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Minori HAGIO &quot;Sange ・Hijikata Toshizo&quot; Year 1989, ISBN 4829110686</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Minori HAGIO &quot;Sange ・Hijikata Toshizo&quot; Year 1989, ISBN 4829110686</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>後に改訂され『土方歳三 散華』としても出版されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">was later revised, and also published as &quot;Hijikata Toshizo Sange&quot;.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">was later revised, and also published as &quot;Hijikata Toshizo Sange&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">was later revised, and also published as &quot;Hijikata Toshizo Sange&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>ISBN 4404016174</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ISBN 4404016174</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ISBN 4404016174</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ISBN 4404016174</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="230">
<j>北原亞以子 『歳三からの伝言』ISBN 4062748304</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Aiko KITAHARA &quot;Toshizo karano Dengon&quot; ISBN 4062748304.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Aiko KITAHARA &quot;Toshizo karano Dengon&quot; ISBN 4062748304.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Aiko KITAHARA &quot;Toshizo karano Dengon&quot; ISBN 4062748304.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>北原亞以子 『暗闇から 土方歳三異聞』1995年 ISBN 440853241X</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Aiko KITAHARA &quot;Kurayami kara Hijikata Toshizo Ibun&quot; ISBN 440853241X.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Aiko KITAHARA &quot;Kurayami kara Hijikata Toshizo Ibun&quot; ISBN 440853241X.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Aiko KITAHARA &quot;Kurayami kara Hijikata Toshizo Ibun&quot; ISBN 440853241X.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>中場利一『バラガキ-土方歳三青春譜』 2000年 ISBN 4062738678 （ISBNは文庫版）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Riichi NAKABA &quot;Baragaki - Hijikata Toshizo Seishun-fu&quot; Year 2000, ISBN 4062738678 (the ISBN is for pocket book version).</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Riichi NAKABA &quot;Baragaki - Hijikata Toshizo Seishun-fu&quot; Year 2000, ISBN 4062738678 (the ISBN is for pocket book version).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Riichi NAKABA &quot;Baragaki - Hijikata Toshizo Seishun-fu&quot; Year 2000, ISBN 4062738678 (the ISBN is for pocket book version).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>秋山香乃 『歳三往きてまた』2002年 ISBN 4835537459</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Kano AKIYAMA &quot;Toshizo Yukite Mata&quot; Year 2002, ISBN 4835537459.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Kano AKIYAMA &quot;Toshizo Yukite Mata&quot; Year 2002, ISBN 4835537459.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Kano AKIYAMA &quot;Toshizo Yukite Mata&quot; Year 2002, ISBN 4835537459.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>北方謙三『黒龍の柩』2002年 上 ISBN 4620106607、下 ISBN 4620106615</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Kenzo KITAKATA &quot;Kokuryu no Hitsugi&quot; Year 2002, Book 1 ISBN 4620106607, Book 2 ISBN 4620106615.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明。書名の読み方は「こくりゅうのひつぎ」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Kenzo KITAKATA &quot;Kokuryu no Hitsugi&quot; Year 2002, Book 1 ISBN 4620106607, Book 2 ISBN 4620106615.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Kenzo KITAKATA &quot;Kokuryu no Hitsugi&quot; Year 2002, Book 1 ISBN 4620106607, Book 2 ISBN 4620106615.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>池波正太郎 『色』（短編集「炎の武士」収録）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Shotaro IKENAMI &quot;Iro&quot; (included in his book of short stories, &quot;Honoo no Bushi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Shotaro IKENAMI &quot;Iro&quot; (included in his book of short stories, &quot;Honoo no Bushi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Shotaro IKENAMI &quot;Iro&quot; (included in his book of short stories, &quot;Honoo no Bushi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>吉岡平 『火星の土方歳三』（朝日ソノラマ） - 函館で死亡した後、エドガー・ライス・バローズの『火星シリーズ』の火星に転生した土方歳三の活躍を描くSF作品。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Hitoshi YOSHIOKA &quot;Toshizo HIJIKATA on Mars&quot; (Asahi Sonorama) - A SF novel which tells the adventures of Toshizo HIJIKATA, after he died in Hakodate and is reborn on Mars in &quot;Mars Series&quot; of Edgar Rice Burroughs.</e>
<cmt>朝日ソノラマは昨年6月に営業を停止。朝日新聞社が引き継ぐ。http://publications.asahi.com/sonorama/http://www.itmedia.co.jp/news/articles/0706/21/news101.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Hitoshi YOSHIOKA &quot;Toshizo HIJIKATA on Mars&quot; (Asahi Sonorama) - A SF novel which tells the adventures of Toshizo HIJIKATA, after he died in Hakodate and is reborn on Mars in &quot;Mars Series&quot; of Edgar Rice Burroughs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Hitoshi YOSHIOKA &quot;Toshizo HIJIKATA on Mars&quot; (Asahi Sonorama) - A SF novel which tells the adventures of Toshizo HIJIKATA, after he died in Hakodate and is reborn on Mars in &quot;Mars Series&quot; of Edgar Rice Burroughs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>2004年　ISBN 4257770341</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Year 2004 ISBN 4257770341</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Year 2004 ISBN 4257770341</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Year 2004 ISBN 4257770341</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>漫画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="238">
<j>斎藤岬 『ひなたの狼』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Misaki SAITO &quot;Hinatano Ookami&quot;.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Misaki SAITO &quot;Hinatano Ookami&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Misaki SAITO &quot;Hinatano Ookami&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>望月三起也 『俺の新選組』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Mikiya MOCHIZUKI &quot;Ore no Shinsengumi&quot;</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Mikiya MOCHIZUKI &quot;Ore no Shinsengumi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Mikiya MOCHIZUKI &quot;Ore no Shinsengumi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>盛田賢司 『月明星稀 - さよなら新選組』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Kenji MORITA &quot;Getsumei Seiki - Sayonara Shinsengumi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Kenji MORITA &quot;Getsumei Seiki - Sayonara Shinsengumi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Kenji MORITA &quot;Getsumei Seiki - Sayonara Shinsengumi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>秋月こお 『青春新撰組BARAGAKI!』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Ko AKIZUKI &quot;Seishun Shinsengumi BARAGAKI !&quot;.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Ko AKIZUKI &quot;Seishun Shinsengumi BARAGAKI !&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Ko AKIZUKI &quot;Seishun Shinsengumi BARAGAKI !&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>神田たけ志 『北の獅子 真説・土方歳三伝』 - 箱館戦争に焦点を絞って描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Takeshi KANDA &quot;Kitano Shishi Shinsetsu Hijikata Taizo den&quot;- is focused on Hakodate War.</e>
<cmt>書名表記不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Takeshi KANDA &quot;Kitano Shishi Shinsetsu Hijikata Taizo den&quot;- is focused on Hakodate War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Takeshi KANDA &quot;Kitano Shishi Shinsetsu Hijikata Taizo den&quot;- is focused on Hakodate War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="243">
<j>菅野文 『北走新選組』 - 収録されている短編のうち『殉白』は土方歳三を主役とし、蝦夷共和国の陸軍奉行をつとめた大鳥圭介とのからみを描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Aya KANNO &quot;Hokusou Shinsengumi&quot;- of the short comics included in this book, &quot;Junbaku&quot; has Toshizo HIJIKATA as the main character, and describes his relationship with Keisuke OTORI, who served as the General of the Army.</e>
<cmt>北走新選組の読み方は「ほくそうしんせんぐみ」http://www.s-book.net/plsql/net_isbn?isbn=4592188101殉白は「じゅんぱく」と読む</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Aya KANNO &quot;Hokusou Shinsengumi&quot;- of the short comics included in this book, &quot;Junbaku&quot; has Toshizo HIJIKATA as the main character, and describes his relationship with Keisuke OTORI, who served as the General of the Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Aya KANNO &quot;Hokusou Shinsengumi&quot;- of the short comics included in this book, &quot;Junbaku&quot; has Toshizo HIJIKATA as the main character, and describes his relationship with Keisuke OTORI, who served as the General of the Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Jono(id:2208), 講師(id:71860), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), WHITE STORM(id:195041), Cprobot(id:97843), Tast(id:29478), Lupinoid(id:68), Swind(id:30993), MioUzaki(id:89034), Northface(id:70750), Shin-改(id:9914), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Morio(id:35464), 真琴(id:12629), Yas(id:739), とんちゃん2(id:39111), Maakun(id:16735), Sleepygreen(id:8068), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Peehyoro Acala(id:170), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), Baldr(id:123441), TI(id:29132), いたる(id:58536), Tiyoringo(id:70026), ＫｏＺ(id:48584), よもすがら(id:212112), 松平忠輝(id:115291), Zwobot(id:23873), R28Bot(id:177951), 海衛士(id:19229), おきた(id:18906), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), 神奈川大学2年経済学部経済学科(id:1107), Suisui(id:69), King-wise(id:19033), ToePeu.bot(id:157833), みょうじ(id:124419), Resto1578(id:168692), 松岡龍獅(id:143549), Yard(id:59322), Tolor(id:113670), PaPaPaPa(id:87231), 富岡志郎(id:73297), 北天幻桜(id:191879), Paseri0924(id:151116), Rai koku(id:1661), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 味っ子(id:17086), 土方　誠(id:3651), Sutou(id:32), たとゥ(id:25557), Sgi1962(id:80778), E diaz 49(id:72115), 認定者(id:99098), Johncapistrano(id:969), 竜馬(id:14477), パの字(id:34188), CasinoKat(id:43789), 海亀(id:48936), 平 誠(id:2586), Purplerain(id:31985), Chobot(id:20846), Loveless(id:129239), こぶまき(id:38278), Bankokuya(id:91191), ゲッターピジョン(id:84950), Seven(id:2130), とんちゃん(id:28988), Kirari(id:206294), 与左衛門(id:159462), 為次郎(id:40514), 水野白楓(id:22811), Unun(id:176023), Tekken(id:546), Yanahan(id:2437), 政岡幸輔(id:89690), Ro-(id:36890), Marine-Blue(id:20162), Dakara(id:1745), Tanuki Z(id:612), 油谷サトシ(id:27516), Nonnonba(id:124424), 上田隼人(id:23104), Miya(id:1881), VTS(id:68763), MS472(id:58603), K-kazumasa(id:9265), Poike(id:1271), Louperibot(id:128971), A-tak(id:31856), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>