<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>古田重然</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigenari FURUTA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigenari FURUTA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigenari FURUTA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>古田 重然（ふるた しげなり／しげてる）は、戦国時代 (日本)の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigenari FURUTA was a Japanese warrior who lived during the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigenari FURUTA was a Japanese warrior who lived during the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigenari FURUTA was a Japanese warrior who lived during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>他の記事と用語を合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一般的には茶道・古田 織部（ふるた おりべ）として有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a tea ceremony master, he is widely known as Oribe FURUTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a tea ceremony master, he is widely known as Oribe FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a tea ceremony master, he is widely known as Oribe FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通称は左介。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His common name was Sasuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His common name was Sasuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His common name was Sasuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初名は景安。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His initial name was Keian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His initial name was Keian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first given name was Keian.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「織部」の名は、壮年期に従五位下織部正（織部助）の官位を叙任したことに由来している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He named himself Oribe as a tea ceremony master after the fact that he was awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Oribe no Kami (Director of Weaving Office), in the prime of his life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He named himself Oribe as a tea ceremony master after the fact that he was awarded the rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), Oribe no Kami (Director of Weaving Office), in the prime of his life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His name &apos;Oribe&apos; as a tea ceremony master originated from the fact that he was awarded the rank of Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Director of Weaving Office, in the prime of his life.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>千利休が大成させた茶道を継承しつつ、大胆かつ自由な気風を好み、茶器製作・建築・造園などにわたって「織部好み」と呼ばれる一大流行を安土桃山時代にもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While following in the footsteps of SEN no Rikyu, who brought the art of tea ceremony to perfection, he also developed a lively and creative style of art and created an art trend known as the &quot;Oribe style&quot; in pottery, architecture and gardening during the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While following in the footsteps of SEN no Rikyu, who brought the art of tea ceremony to perfection, he also developed a lively and creative style of art and created an art trend known as the Oribe style in pottery, architecture and gardening during the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While following the footsteps of SEN no Rikyu, who brought the art of tea ceremony to perfection, he also developed a lively and creative style of art and created an art trend known as the Oribe style in pottery, architecture and gardening during the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief personal history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>語頭を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>天文13年（1544年）、美濃国本巣郡の山口城主（古田重安？）の弟で、茶人の古田重定（茶坊主の勘阿弥、還俗し主膳重正と改名）の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigenari (or Oribe) FURUTA was born in 1544 as a son of Shigesada FURUTA, a tea ceremony master (known by his Buddhist name, Kannami; he later renamed himself Shigemasa SHUZEN as he returned to secular life), who was also a younger brother of the Lord of the Yamaguchi Castle (his name is believed to have been Shigeyasu FURUTA.)</e>
<cmt>「主膳重正」の読み方が確認できません。「古田重安」の読み方が確認できません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigenari (or Oribe) FURUTA was born in 1544 as a son of Shigesada FURUTA, a tea ceremony master (known by his Buddhist name, Kannami; he later renamed himself Shigemasa SHUZEN as he returned to secular life), who was also a younger brother of the Lord of the Yamaguchi Castle (his name is believed to have been Shigeyasu FURUTA).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigenari (or Oribe) FURUTA was born in 1544 as a son of Shigesada FURUTA, a tea ceremony master (known by his Buddhist name Kannami of tea-server, he later renamed himself Shigemasa SHUZEN as he returned to secular life), who was also a younger brother of the Lord of the Yamaguchi-jo Castle in Motosu-gun County, Mino Province (whose name is believed to have been Shigeyasu FURUTA).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>織部も父の薫陶を受け、武将としての経歴を歩みつつ、茶人としての強い嗜好性を持って成長する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pursuing a career as a warrior, Oribe also acquired a sophisticated taste for tea ceremony under the influence of his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pursuing a career as a warrior, Oribe also acquired a sophisticated taste for the tea ceremony under the influence of his father.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pursuing a career as a warrior, Oribe also acquired a sophisticated taste for the tea ceremony under his father.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後に伯父の養子となったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is believed to have been adopted by his uncle as his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to have been adopted by his uncle as his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to have been adopted by his uncle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>永禄9年（1567年）、織田信長の美濃進駐とともにその家臣として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigenari became Nobunaga ODA&apos;s retainer when Nobunaga attacked Mino Province in 1567.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigenari became Nobunaga ODA&apos;s retainer when Nobunaga attacked Mino Province in 1567.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigenari became Nobunaga ODA&apos;s retainer when Nobunaga attacked Mino Province in 1567.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>翌年の信長の上洛に従軍し、摂津国攻略に参加したことが記録に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a record, he joined Nobunaga&apos;s army when Nobunaga visited the emperor in Kyoto in the following year and fought in Nobunaga&apos;s battle in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a record, he joined Nobunaga&apos;s army when Nobunaga visited the emperor in Kyoto in the following year and fought in Nobunaga&apos;s battle in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a source, he joined Nobunaga&apos;s army when Nobunaga visited Kyoto in the following year and fought in Nobunaga&apos;s battle in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>永禄11年（1569年）に摂津茨木城主中川清秀の妹せんと結婚。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1569, Shigenari married Sen, a younger sister of Kiyohide NAKAGAWA, the Lord of the Ibaraki Castle in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1569, Shigenari married Sen, a younger sister of Kiyohide NAKAGAWA, the Lord of Ibaraki Castle in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1569, Shigenari married Sen, a younger sister of Kiyohide NAKAGAWA (the Lord of Ibaraki-jo Castle in Settsu Province).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>清秀は当時の織部より身分の高い人物であり、信長が織部にある程度目をかけていたことがうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyohide was higher in rank than Oribe at the time and Oribe&apos;s marriage suggests that he was in favor of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyohide was higher in rank than Oribe at the time and Oribe&apos;s marriage suggests that he was in the favor of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyohide was higher in rank than Oribe at the time, which suggests that Oribe was in the favor of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>天正4年（1576年）には山城国乙訓郡上久世荘（現在の京都市南区）の代官となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1576, Oribe became an administrator of Kamikuze no sho (now, Minami Ward of Kyoto City), Okkun-gun, Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1576, Oribe became an administrator of Kamikuze no sho (now, Minami Ward of Kyoto City), Okkun-gun, Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1576, Oribe became an administrator of Kamikuze no sho (now, Minami-ku Ward of Kyoto City), Otokuni-gun District, Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>乙訓郡を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その後も羽柴秀吉（のちの豊臣秀吉）の播磨国攻めや明智光秀の丹波国攻めに従軍するなど、禄高は3百貫と少ないながらも、武将として活動している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He subsequently joined the army of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) during the attack on Harima Province and the army of Mitsuhide AKECHI during the attach on Tanba Province, making a successful career as a war leader despite his small salary of 300 koku.</e>
<cmt>3百貫[300 koku]：銭一貫＝米一石（これには諸説があってはっきりと分りませんが）として換算して訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He subsequently joined the army of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) during the attack on Harima Province, and the army of Mitsuhide AKECHI during the attach on Tanba Province, making a successful career as a war leader despite his small salary of 300 koku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He subsequently joined the army of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) during the attack on Harima Province and the army of Mitsuhide AKECHI during the attack on Tanba Province, making a successful career as a war leader despite his small stipend of 300 koku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>信長死後は豊臣秀吉に仕え、天正13年（1585年）秀吉が関白になると、織部正（従五位下）の位階と山城国西岡に所領3万5000石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga&apos;s death, Shigenari served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and in 1585, when Hideyoshi was appointed as Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor), Shigenari was awarded the rank of Oribe no Kami (Jugoinoge; Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and a territory worth 35,000 koku in Nishioka, Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga&apos;s death, Shigenari served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and in 1585, when Hideyoshi was appointed as Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor), Shigenari was awarded the rank of Oribe no Kami (Jugoinoge; Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and a territory worth 35,000 koku in Nishioka, Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga&apos;s death, Shigenari served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and in 1585, when Hideyoshi was appointed as the Chief Adviser to the Emperor, Shigenari was awarded an official title Oribe-no-Kami, appointed to Jugoinoge; Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade and given a territory worth 35,000 koku in Nishioka, Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後、九州征伐、小田原征伐に参加し、文禄の役では朝鮮に渡海して従軍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He subsequently joined Hideyoshi&apos;s army in the battles in Kyushu and Odawara and fought overseas during the war to conquer Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He subsequently joined Hideyoshi&apos;s army in the battles in Kyushu and Odawara and fought overseas during the war to conquer Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He subsequently joined Hideyoshi&apos;s army in the battles in Kyushu and Odawara, and fought overseas to conquer Korea in the Bunroku War.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>天正10年（1582年）から千利休の書簡に織部の名前が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oribe&apos;s name began appearing in letters written by SEN no Rikyu starting in 1582.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oribe&apos;s name began appearing in letters written by SEN no Rikyu starting in 1582.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oribe&apos;s name began appearing in letters written by SEN no Rikyu starting in 1582.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この間に利休と知り合い、弟子入りしたものと考えられ、のちに利休七哲のひとりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is believed to have become acquainted with Rikyu around this time and joined his tea ceremony group as one of his disciples, among whom he later came to be known as one of Rikyu&apos;s seven closest disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to have become acquainted with Rikyu around this time and joined his tea ceremony group as one of his disciples; among whom he later came to be known as one of Rikyu&apos;s seven closest disciples.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to have become acquainted with Rikyu around this time and joined his tea ceremony group as one of his disciples; among whom he later came to be known as one of Rikyu Shichitetsu (Rikyu&apos;s seven closest disciples).</e>
<cmt>利休七哲のローマ字読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>天正19年（1591年）に秀吉によって利休の追放（切腹の前段階）が決まると、利休と親交のあった諸将が秀吉をはばかって現れない中、織部とやはり利休七哲のひとりである細川忠興のみが堂々と利休の見送りを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Rikyu was discharged from his duties (before committing seppuku) by Hideyoshi in 1591, Oribe and Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, who was also among Rikyu&apos;s seven closest disciples, had a farewell meeting with Rikyu out in the open, while Hideyoshi&apos;s retainers who were acquainted with Rikyu avoided meeting him in fear of incurring Hideyoshi&apos;s wrath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Rikyu was discharged from his duties (before committing seppuku) by Hideyoshi in 1591, Oribe and Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, who were also among Rikyu&apos;s seven closest disciples, had a farewell meeting with Rikyu out in the open. In contrast, Hideyoshi&apos;s retainers who were acquainted with Rikyu avoided meeting him in fear of incurring Hideyoshi&apos;s wrath.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Rikyu was discharged from his duties (preliminary step of committing seppuku) by Hideyoshi in 1591, Oribe and Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, who were also among Rikyu Shichitetsu, had a farewell meeting with Rikyu boldly and fearlessly, while Hideyoshi&apos;s retainers who were acquainted with Rikyu avoided meeting him in fear of incurring Hideyoshi&apos;s wrath.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>利休死後は、その地位を継承するかのように豊臣家の筆頭茶人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oribe succeeded Rikyu after his death as the tea ceremony master of the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oribe succeeded Rikyu after his death as the tea ceremony master of the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Rikyu died, Oribe succeeded to Rikyu&apos;s position as the tea ceremony master of the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）には嫡子重広に家督を譲り、隠居したといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is reported to have yielded his position as head of the family to Shigehiro, his heir, and retired from office in 1598.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is reported to have yielded his position as head of the family to Shigehiro, his heir, and retired from office in 1598.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is reported to have yielded his position as the head of the family to Shigehiro, his heir, and retired from office in 1598.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）9月の関ヶ原の戦いでは東軍に与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara in October 1600, Oribe fought for Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>慶長5年（1600年）9月[October 1600]：旧暦の９月はグレゴリオ暦の10月になりますので、Octoberとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Sekigahara in October 1600, Oribe fought for Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara in October 1600, Oribe fought for Ieyasu TOKUGAWA of the Eastern squad.</e>
<cmt>東軍を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし師・利休と同じように反骨精神も旺盛で、徳川幕府の意向を無視することも少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he had a rebellious spirit just like his teacher, Rikyu, and often disobeyed the orders of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he had a rebellious spirit just like his teacher, Rikyu, and often disobeyed the orders of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he had a rebellious spirit just like his teacher, Rikyu, and often disobeyed the orders of the Tokugawa shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>またこの頃の織部は茶の湯を通じて朝廷、貴族、寺社、経済界と様々なつながりを持ち、全国の大名にすら多大な影響力を与える存在にもなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this time, Oribe had established extensive connections with the imperial court, court nobles, temples and shrines, as well as business groups through tea ceremonies, wielding powerful influence even on feudal lords around the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time, Oribe had established extensive connections with the imperial court, court nobles, temples and shrines, as well as business groups through tea ceremonies, wielding powerful influence even on feudal lords around the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time, Oribe had established extensive connections with the imperial court, court nobles, temples and shrines, as well as business groups through tea ceremonies, wielding great influence even on feudal lords around the country.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>このため家康陣営から次第にその影響力・存在を危険視されるようになったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people believe that he gradually came to be seen by Tokugawa government groups as having influence that might undermine their power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people believe that he gradually came to be seen by Tokugawa government groups as having influence that might undermine their power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people believe that he gradually became to be seen by Tokugawa government groups as having influence that might undermine their power.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>1615年（慶長20年）の大坂の役のおり、織部の茶頭である木村宗喜が、豊臣氏に内通して京に放火（混乱に乗じて家康暗殺を意図した説がある）を企んだとされる疑いで京都所司代の板倉勝重に捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Battle of Osaka in 1615, Muneyoshi KIMURA, who served Oribe as his tea ceremony master, was arrested by Katsushige ITAKURA, Chief Director of the Kyoto Police, on the charge of having organized a conspiracy in collaboration with the Toyotomi clan to set fire to Kyoto (some people believe that he intended to assassinate Ieyasu by taking advantage of the disturbance caused by the fire).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Battle of Osaka in 1615, Muneyoshi KIMURA, who served Oribe as his tea ceremony master, was arrested by Katsushige ITAKURA, Chief Director of the Kyoto Police, on the charge of having organized a conspiracy in collaboration with the Toyotomi clan to set fire to Kyoto (some people believe that he intended to assassinate Ieyasu by taking advantage of the disturbance caused by the fire).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Battle of Osaka in 1615, Muneyoshi KIMURA, who served Oribe as his tea ceremony master, was arrested by Katsushige ITAKURA of the Kyoto deputy on charge of having organized a conspiracy in collaboration with the Toyotomi clan to set fire to Kyoto (Some people believe that he intended to assassinate Ieyasu by taking advantage of the disturbance caused by the fire).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>木村の主君である織部も、豊臣氏と内通しており、戦後に豊臣秀頼の遺児豊臣国松を匿ったなどの嫌疑をかけられ、大坂落城後の6月11日に切腹を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oribe, who was Muneyoshi KIMURA&apos;s lord, was also suspected of communicating secretly with the Toyotomi clan and was ordered to commit seppuku on July 6, after the Osaka Castle was burnt down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oribe, who was Muneyoshi KIMURA&apos;s lord, was also suspected of communicating secretly with the Toyotomi clan and was ordered to commit seppuku on July 6, after Osaka Castle was burnt down.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oribe, the lord of Kimura, was also suspected of communicating secretly with the Toyotomi clan and was ordered to commit seppuku on July 6, after Osaka-jo Castle was burnt down, on charge of harboring Kunimatsu TOYOTOMI who was an orphan of Hideyori TOYOTOMI after the war.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>織部はこれに対し、一言も釈明せずに自害している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oribe obeyed the order and committed seppuku without making any excuse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oribe obeyed the order and committed seppuku without making any excuse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oribe obeyed the order and committed seppuku without making any explanation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>享年72。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>同時に織部の嫡子・重広も切腹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eldest son, Shigehiro, was ordered to commit seppuku along with Oribe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His eldest son, Shigehiro, was ordered to commit seppuku along with Oribe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His legitimate son, Shigehiro, was ordered to commit seppuku along with Oribe.</e>
<cmt>訳語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>木村宗喜も処刑されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneyoshi KIMURA was also executed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muneyoshi KIMURA was also executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muneyoshi KIMURA was also executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>次男・重尚（前田利常家臣）と三男・重広（池田光政家臣）も二日後の6月13日切腹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oribe&apos;s second son, Shigenao (Toshitsune MAEDA&apos;s retainer), and his third son, Shigehiro (Mitsumasa IKEDA&apos;s retainer) committed seppuku two days later, on July 8.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oribe&apos;s second son, Shigenao (Toshitsune MAEDA&apos;s retainer), and his third son, Shigehiro (Mitsumasa IKEDA&apos;s retainer) committed seppuku two days later, on July 8.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oribe&apos;s second son, Shigenao (Toshitsune MAEDA&apos;s retainer), and his third son, Shigehiro (Mitsumasa IKEDA&apos;s retainer) committed seppuku two days later, on July 8.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>豊臣秀頼の家臣だった四男・重行は追っ手を逃れ、6月24日興聖寺の父・兄の墓前で割腹。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His fourth son, Shigeyuki, who served Hideyori TOYOTOMI as his retainer, escaped his enemies and committed seppuku on July 19 in front of the graves of his father and brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His fourth son, Shigeyuki, who served Hideyori TOYOTOMI as his retainer, escaped his enemies and committed seppuku on July 19 in front of the graves of his father and brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His fourth son, Shigeyuki, who served Hideyori TOYOTOMI as his retainer, escaped his enemies and committed seppuku on July 19 in front of the graves of his father and brothers in Kosho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>興聖寺を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>五男・重久は大阪夏の陣で戦死しており、重然直系の子孫は断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His fifth son, Shigehisa, died in the Battle of Osaka in 1615, causing the Oribe family to perish altogether.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His fifth son, Shigehisa, died in the Battle of Osaka in 1615, causing the Oribe family to perish completely.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His fifth son, Shigehisa, died in the Summer Siege of Osaka, causing the direct line of Oribe family to perish completely.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>織部の茶の湯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oribe&apos;s tea ceremony art</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oribe&apos;s tea ceremony art</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oribe&apos;s tea ceremony art</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>織部は、利休の「人と違うことをせよ」という教えを忠実に実行し、利休の静謐さと対照的な動的で破調の美を確立させ、それを一つの流派に育て上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Faithful to Rikyu&apos;s teaching that one should develop one&apos;s original style, Oribe established a style of dynamic beauty contrastive to the serene beauty of Rikyu and created a tea ceremony school based on his style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Faithful to Rikyu&apos;s teaching that one should develop one&apos;s original style, Oribe established a style of dynamic beauty contrastive to the serene beauty of Rikyu and created a tea ceremony school based on his style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Faithful to Rikyu&apos;s teaching that one should develop one&apos;s original style, Oribe established a style of dynamic &apos;aesthetic of discord&apos; contrastive to the serene beauty of the style of Rikyu, and created a tea ceremony school based on his style.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>職人や陶工らを多数抱え、彼らに創作活動をさせ、織部焼、織部流の創始者とされている（ただし、織部焼への関わりを示す資料は殆ど残っていない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is believed to have hired a large number of craftsmen and pottery workers to have them create works of art that are known as Oribe-style earthenware (Oribe yaki) and artworks (however, there are few remaining documents that show his relationship with Oribe yaki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to have hired a large number of craftsmen and pottery workers to have them create works of art that are known as Oribe-style earthenware (Oribe yaki) and artworks (however, there are few remaining documents that show his relationship with Oribe yaki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to have hired a large number of craftsmen and pottery workers to have them create works of art, having been the founder of the Oribe-style earthenware and the Oribe school (however, there are few remaining documents that show his relationship with Oribe yaki).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>代表的な茶室に、義弟藪内剣仲に譲った「燕庵」（重要文化財）が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tea ceremony room known as Kennan (important cultural property), which he bequeathed to his brother-in-law, Kenchu YABUUCHI, is one of the tea ceremony rooms that represent his style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tea ceremony room known as Kennan (important cultural property), which he bequeathed to his brother-in-law, Kenchu YABUUCHI, is one of the tea ceremony rooms that represents his style.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tea ceremony room known as &quot;Ennan&quot;, an important cultural property, which he handed over to his brother-in-law Kenchu YABUCHI, is one of the tea ceremony rooms that represents his style.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>織部作の茶杓は、日本刀を想像させるほど櫂先鋭く、いかにも戦国時代を生きた武人茶人らしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tea spoons created by Oribe, sharply pointed just like Japanese swords, remind us of the brave warrior tea ceremony master who lived during the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tea spoons created by Oribe, sharply pointed just like Japanese swords, remind us of the brave warrior tea ceremony master who lived during the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bamboo tea spoon created by Oribe, sharply pointed just like Japanese swords, remind us of the brave warrior tea ceremony master who lived during the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>書は左へ斜めにずれるのが特徴で、桑田忠親は本阿弥光悦に影響を与えたのではないかと推測している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His calligraphy strokes have the characteristic of slanting to the left, which the historian Tadachika KUWATA believes to have affected the calligraphy of Koetsu HONAMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His calligraphy strokes have the characteristic of slanting to the left, which the historian Tadachika KUWATA believes to have affected the calligraphy of Koetsu HONAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His calligraphy strokes was characteristic of slanting to the left, which Tadachika KUWATA believes to have affected the calligraphy of Koetsu HONAMI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>茶書として「織部百ヶ条」を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote a tea ceremony book, &quot;Oribe Hyakkajo&quot; (One Hundred Rules of Tea Ceremony).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote a tea ceremony book, &apos;Oribe Hyakkajo&apos; (One Hundred Rules of Tea Ceremony).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote the tea ceremony book, &apos;Oribe Hyakkajo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="43">
<j>茶道の弟子とされる人物には小堀政一（遠州）、上田重安（宗箇）、徳川秀忠、金森可重らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are believed to have been Oribe&apos;s disciples include Masakazu (or Enshu) KOBORI, Shigeyasu UEDA (or Soko), Hidetada TOKUGAWA and Arishige KANAMORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who are believed to have been Oribe&apos;s disciples include Masakazu (or Enshu) KOBORI, Shigeyasu UEDA (or Soko), Hidetada TOKUGAWA and Arishige KANAMORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who are believed to have been Oribe&apos;s disciples are Masakazu (or Enshu) KOBORI, Shigeyasu UEDA (or Soko), Hidetada TOKUGAWA and Arishige KANAMORI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>岐阜県岐阜市の未来会館には「織部賞展示コーナー」が常設してある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Mirai Hall in Gifu City, Gifu Prefecture, there is a permanent space for the display of Oribe Award-winning art products.</e>
<cmt>未来会館[Mirai Hall]: http://www.miraikaikan.jp/ を参照しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Mirai Hall in Gifu City, Gifu Prefecture, there is a permanent space for the display of Oribe Award-winning art products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Mirai Hall in Gifu City, Gifu Prefecture, there is a permanent space for the display of Oribe Award-winning art products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Ayukata(id:65714), Foldingfan(id:234775), てら1971(id:131768), Hskwk(id:9797), Yoko8001(id:197944), Aotake(id:34929), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), Swindbot(id:151304), Hide-sp(id:145562), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), Kamitani(id:30757), Aboshi(id:9318), Interregnum(id:25269), Yukichi99(id:29402), R28Bot(id:177951), 怪蘇(id:45514), Point136(id:211299), Nekosuki600(id:21263), こぶまき(id:38278), Shimoxx(id:9332), Klesha(id:203751), Kouko0515(id:100370), Jmho(id:10472), 立志堂(id:132177), SA2B(id:149015), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>