<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>片桐且元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumoto KATAGIRI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumoto KATAGIRI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto KATAGIRI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>片桐 且元（かたぎり かつもと）は、安土桃山時代・江戸時代の大名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumoto KATAGIRI is the daimyo who reigned during the Azuchi-Momoyama and Edo periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumoto KATAGIRI was a daimyo (lord) who lived during the Azuchi-Momoyama and Edo periods.</e>
<cmt>the&apos;→&apos;a&apos;&apos;reigned&apos;→&apos;lived&apos;added definition of daimyo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto KATAGIRI was a daimyo (lord) who lived during the Azuchi-Momoyama and Edo periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>賤ヶ岳の七本槍の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is one of the Shichihonyari of Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of the Shichihonyari (Seven Spears) of Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt>is&apos;→&apos;was&apos;added translation of Shichihonyari</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of the Shichihonyari (Seven Spears) of Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>豊臣秀吉より豊臣姓をゆるされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He gained a permission to use TOYOTOMI surname by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He gained Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s permission to use the TOYOTOMI surname.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order.Deleted &apos;a&apos;, &apos;by&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He gained Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s permission to use the TOYOTOMI surname.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>父は近江国の戦国大名・浅井氏家臣の片桐直貞、母は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father is Naosada KATAGIRI, the retainer of the sengoku daimyo (daimyo during the Sengoku period) ASAI Family, but his mother is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Naosada KATAGIRI, a retainer of the ASAI family, who were daimyo during the Sengoku period, but his mother is unknown.</e>
<cmt>is&apos;→&apos;was&apos;&apos;the&apos;→&apos;a&apos;Deleted Sengoku daimyoChanged word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Naosada KATAGIRI, a retainer of the AZAI Clan, who were daimyo during the Sengoku period, but his mother is unknown.</e>
<cmt>ASAI→AZAI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>弟に小泉藩主となった片桐貞隆がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brother is Sadataka KATAGIRI who became the head of Koizumi Han.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother was Sadataka KATAGIRI who became the head of Koizumi Han (fief).</e>
<cmt>is&apos;→&apos;was&apos;Added definition of Han</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother was Sadataka KATAGIRI who became the head of Koizumi Domain (fief).</e>
<cmt>Han→Domain</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>統一ルール</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>近江国浅井郡須賀谷（滋賀県長浜市須賀谷）の浅井氏配下の小領主・片桐直貞の子として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the son of a small feudal lord, Sadataka KATAGIRI, who served under the ASAI Family in Sugatani, Azai-gun (district), Omi no Kuni (Sugatani, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Sugatani, Azai-gun, Omi no Kuni (present day Sugatani, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture), the son of a minor feudal lord, Naosada KATAGIRI, who served the ASAI Family.</e>
<cmt>Changed word order.&apos;small&apos;→&apos;minor&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Sugatani, Azai-gun, Omi no Kuni (present day Sugatani, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture), the son of a minor feudal lord, Naosada KATAGIRI, who served the AZAI Clan.</e>
<cmt>ASAI→AZAI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>須賀谷は浅井氏の本拠地・小谷城と山続きであり、同城の支城の一つとして機能するとともに、須賀谷温泉が湧出するために湯治場としても利用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugatani was connected by mountains to the ASAI Family&apos;s main headquarter of Odani Castle and functioned as its supporting castle and a hot spring since it was where Sugatani hot spring water flowed out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugatani was connected by mountains to the ASAI family stronghold of Odani Castle and served both as a supporting castle and a resort, due to the Sugatani hot springs.</e>
<cmt>Family&apos;s main headquarter&apos;→&apos;family stronghold&apos;&apos;functioned as its&apos;→&apos;served both as a&apos;&apos;hot spring&apos;→&apos;resort&apos;&apos;since it was where Sugatani &apos;hot spring water flowed out&apos;→&apos;due to the Sugatani hot springs&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugatani was connected by mountains to the AZAI Clan stronghold of Odani Castle and served both as a supporting castle and a resort, due to the Sugatani hot springs.</e>
<cmt>ASAI→AZAI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>元亀元年（1570年）から天正元年（1573年）9月1日 (旧暦)にかけての織田信長による浅井長政への攻撃に際しては小谷城の落城まで一貫して浅井方として戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fought on the side of Nagamasa ASAI until the fall of Odani Castle by Nobunaga Oda&apos;s attacks from 1570 to September 1, 1573.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought on the side of Nagamasa ASAI until the fall of Odani Castle following Nobunaga ODA&apos;s seige from 1570 to September 1, 1573.</e>
<cmt>by Nobunaga Oda&apos;s attacks&apos;→&apos;following Nobunaga ODA&apos;s seige&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought on the side of Nagamasa AZAI until the fall of Odani Castle following Nobunaga ODA&apos;s seige from 1570 to September 1, 1573.</e>
<cmt>ASAI→AZAI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>落城前日（8月29日 (旧暦)）の日付の浅井長政から片桐直貞に宛てられた感状が現在も残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The letter of appreciation from Nagamasa ASAI to Naosada KATAGIRI on August 29, the day before the castle fell, is present even to the current day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The letter of appreciation from Nagamasa ASAI to Naosada KATAGIRI, written on August 29, the day before the castle fell, is still in existance.</e>
<cmt>Added comma and &apos;written&apos;&apos;present even to the current day&apos;→&apos;still in existance&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The letter of appreciation from Nagamasa AZAI to Naosada KATAGIRI, written on August 29, the day before the castle fell, is still in existance.</e>
<cmt>ASAI→AZAI</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>且元が家督を継いだ時期は定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is uncertain when Katsumoto inherited the family estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is uncertain when Katsumoto inherited the family estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is uncertain when Katsumoto inherited the family estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>天正7年（1579年）ごろ、同じ近江生まれの石田三成らと共に長浜城 (近江国)時代の羽柴秀吉（豊臣秀吉）の家臣として仕えたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he served as a vassal under Hideyoshi HASHIBA (TOYOTOMI Hideyoshi) during the Nagahama Castle (Omi no Kuni) period along side Mitsunari ISHIDA born in same Omi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he served as a vassal of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) during the Nagahama Castle (Omi no Kuni) period alongside Mitsunari ISHIDA, who was born in same province of Omi.</e>
<cmt>under&apos;→&apos;of&apos;Added &apos;later&apos;Made &apos;along side&apos; one word&apos;born in same Omi&apos;→&apos;who was born in same province of Omi&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he served as a vassal of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (later Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), around 1579, during the Nagahama Castle (Omi no Kuni) period alongside Mitsunari ISHIDA, who was born in same province of Omi.</e>
<cmt>「1579年ごろ」が欠落</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>天正11年（1583年）5月、信長死後に対立した織田家の柴田勝家との賤ヶ岳の戦い（近江国伊香郡）で福島正則や加藤清正らと共に活躍し、「賤ヶ岳七本槍」の一人に数えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He played an active role with Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Kiyomasa KATO to be counted as one of the &apos;Shichihonyari of Shizugatake&apos; during the Battle of Shizugatake (Ika-gun (district), Omi no Kuni) against the opposing Katsuie SHIBATA in May 1583 after Nobunaga&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1583, after Nobunaga&apos;s death, he fought alongside Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Kiyomasa KATO during the Battle of Shizugatake (Ika-gun, Omi no Kuni) against the Katsuie SHIBATA, becoming one of the &apos;Seven Spears of Shizugatake&apos;</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1583, after Nobunaga&apos;s death, he fought alongside Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Kiyomasa KATO during the Battle of Shizugatake (Ika-gun, Omi no Kuni) against the Katsuie SHIBATA, becoming one of the &apos;Shichihonyari (Seven Spears) of Shizugatake&apos;</e>
<cmt>七本やりの訳語を統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このとき、秀吉から戦功を賞されて3千石を与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded by Hideyoshi with 3000 koku at this time for his successful achievements during the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded by Hideyoshi with 3000 koku for his achievements during the battle.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &apos;at this time&apos;, &apos;successful&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded by Hideyoshi with 3000 koku for his achievements during the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後は前線で活躍する武将ではなく、奉行人としての後方支援などの活動が中心となり、道奉行としての街道整備や、九州征伐では軍船の調達、小田原合戦では小田原城の接収に立会い、奥州仕置では浅利事件の調査を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, he was active not on front lines as a military general but served mainly as a supporting bugyo, and he worked as the road maintaining road bugyo, supplied military ship during Kyushu Conquest, attended requisition of Odawara Castle during the Battle of Odawara, and investigated the Asari Incident as Oshushioki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, he served not as a general on the front lines but mainly as a supporting bugyo (commissioner), concerned with highway maintenance as the Highway Bugyo, the supply military of ships during the Kyushu Campaign and he attended the requisition of Odawara Castle during the Battle of Odawara, as well as investigating the Asari Incident as an Oshushioki, or judge.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, he served not as a general on the front lines but mainly as a supporting bugyo (commissioner), concerned with highway maintenance as the Highway Bugyo, the supply military of ships during the Kyushu Campaign and he attended the requisition of Odawara Castle during the Battle of Odawara, as well as investigating the Asari Incident as an Oshushioki, or judge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、各地の検地や境界争論の調停、鎌倉の鶴岡八幡宮の修復造営などに携わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also measured farms and their harvest quota, acted as a mediator for borderline conflicts, and participated in the reconstruction project of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also surveyed farms and their harvest quota, acted as a mediator for border conflicts, and participated in the reconstruction project of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>measured&apos;→&apos;surveyed&apos;&apos;borderline&apos;→&apos;border&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also surveyed farms and their harvest quota, acted as a mediator for border conflicts, and participated in the reconstruction project of Tsurugaoka Hachiman-gu Shrine in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>秀吉の朝鮮出兵（文禄の役）では、釜山（現在の釜山市）に駐在し、晋州城攻撃などに参加。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He stationed himself in Busan (current Busan City) during Hideyoshi&apos;s dispatch of troops to Korea (Bunroku no Eki) and participated in the attack of Jinju Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was stationed in Busan (present day Busan City) during Hideyoshi&apos;s dispatch of troops to Korea (Bunroku no Eki) and participated in the attack of Jinju Castle.</e>
<cmt>stationed himself&apos;→&apos;was stationed&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was stationed in Busan (present day Busan City) during Hideyoshi&apos;s dispatch of troops to Korea (Bunroku no Eki) and participated in the attack of Jinju Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>文禄2年（1593年）に帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned to Japan in 1593.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Japan in 1593.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Japan in 1593.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）には摂津国茨木城主、慶長3年（1598年）には大坂城番となり、城詰めとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became the lord of Ibraki Castle in Settsu no Kuni (Settsu Province) in 1595 and became the shirodume (samurai that served a castle) when assigned with the Osaka Castle guard duty in 1598.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the lord of Ibraki Castle in Settsu no Kuni (Settsu Province) in 1595 and became the shirodume (samurai that served a castle) when assigned with the Osaka Castle guard duty in 1598.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the lord of Ibraki Castle in Settsu no Kuni (Settsu Province) in 1595 and became the shirodume (samurai that served a castle) when assigned with the Osaka Castle guard duty in 1598.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>且元が与えられた所領は播磨国に一万石ほどに過ぎなかったが、秀吉の晩年には豊臣秀頼の傅役の一人に任され、羽柴姓も与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The land given to Katsumoto was no more than 10,000 koku Harima no Kuni (Harima Province) but was assigned as the guardian tutor of Hideyori TOYOTOMI late in his life and was given the surname of Hashiba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land given to Katsumoto, Harima no Kuni, was worth no more than 10,000 koku but, in Hideyoshi&apos;s later years, he was assigned as the guardian tutor of Hideyori TOYOTOMI and given the surname Hashiba.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land given to Katsumoto, Harima no Kuni, was worth no more than 10,000 koku but, in Hideyoshi&apos;s later years, he was assigned as the guardian tutor of Hideyori TOYOTOMI and given the surname Hashiba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>秀吉死後は秀頼を補佐し、慶長5年（1600年）9月の関ヶ原の戦い後、五大老筆頭の徳川家康から大和国竜田藩に2万8千石の所領を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He supported Hideyori after Hideyoshi&apos;s death and was given 28,000 koku Tatsuta Han in Yamato no Kuni after the Battle of Sekigahara in September 1600 by Godairo Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He supported Hideyori after Hideyoshi&apos;s death and after, the Battle of Sekigahara in September 1600, was given the 28,000 koku Tatsuta Han in Yamato no Kuni by the Godairo (Council of Five Elders) leader, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He supported Hideyori after Hideyoshi&apos;s death and after the Battle of Sekigahara in September 1600, was given the 28,000 koku Tatsuta Domain in Yamato no Kuni by the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) leader, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>カンマ取りました。Han→DomainGodairo→Gotairo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その後も秀頼を補佐し、豊臣氏と徳川氏の対立を避けることに尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued to serve Hideyori and tried his best to avoid confrontations between TOYOTOMI and TOKUGAWA Families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to serve Hideyori and tried his best to diffuse confrontations between the TOYOTOMI and TOKUGAWA families.</e>
<cmt>avoid → diffuse</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to serve Hideyori and tried his best to diffuse confrontations between the TOYOTOMI and TOKUGAWA families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>慶長19年（1614年）、大坂の役方広寺鐘銘事件が起こって対立が激化すると、且元は戦争を避けるために必死で家康との和平交渉に奔走したが、家康と交渉している間に大野治長や秀頼生母の淀殿から家康との内通を疑われるようになり、大坂城を逐電した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the relationship worsened due to the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple Bell in the Siege of Osaka, he made an effort to have peace talks with Ieyasu to prevent war, but this negotiation made him to be suspected of leaking information to Ieyasu from Harunaga ONO and Hideyori&apos;s mother, Yodo dono, that he had to secretly escape from Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the relationship worsened following the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple Bell during the Siege of Osaka, he made an effort to hold peace talks with Ieyasu aimed at preventing war, but this led Harunaga ONO and Hideyori&apos;s mother, Yodo-dono, to suspect him of leaking information to Ieyasu, forcing him to secretly escape from Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the relationship worsened following the Incident of Hoko-ji Temple Bell during the Siege of Osaka, he made an effort to hold peace talks with Ieyasu aimed at preventing war, but this led Harunaga ONO and Hideyori&apos;s mother, Yodo-dono, to suspect him of leaking information to Ieyasu, forcing him to secretly escape from Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これが徳川方の冬の陣の宣戦理由となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This became the reason for Ieyasu to declare war in the Fuyu no jin (the Winter War of Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This became a pretext for Ieyasu to declare war in the Fuyu no jin (the Winter War of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>the reason → a pretext</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This became a pretext for Ieyasu to declare war in the Fuyu no jin (the Winter War of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そして大坂の役が始まると家康に味方して戦後、4万石に加増された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the Siege of Osaka began, he sided with Ieyasu and was given 40,000 koku as a reward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the Siege of Osaka began, he sided with Ieyasu and was given 40,000 koku as a reward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the Siege of Osaka began, he sided with Ieyasu and was given 40,000 koku as a reward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>だが大坂の役後から二十日ほどして、突如の死を遂げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he suddenly died 20 days after the Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he suddenly died 20 days after the Siege of Osaka ended.</e>
<cmt>Add &apos;ended&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he suddenly died 20 days after the Siege of Osaka ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これには病死説もあれば、秀頼を救うことができなかった（且元は、大坂の陣で家康に味方する代償として、秀頼の助命を嘆願していたらしい）ことからの責任を感じて、自殺したとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some stated that he died of a disease, but it is also said that he committed suicide from feeling responsible for his inability to save Hideyori (is said that he pleaded to save the life of Hideyori in return for siding with Ieyasu during the Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some stated that he died of a disease, but it is also said that he committed suicide to take responsibilty for his inability to save Hideyori (it seems he pleaded for Hideyori&apos;s life in return for siding with Ieyasu during the Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some stated that he died of a disease, but it is also said that he committed suicide to take responsibilty for his inability to save Hideyori (it seems he pleaded for Hideyori&apos;s life in return for siding with Ieyasu during the Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>死後、子の孝利が遺跡を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death, his son Takatoshi inherited the estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his death, his son Takatoshi inherited the estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death, his son Takatoshi inherited the estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Character</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Character</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personal Profile</e>
<cmt>統一ルール</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>江戸時代に成立した『絵本太閤記』では、賤ヶ岳七本槍としての武勇伝が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His bravery was told in &quot;Ehon Taikoki&quot; written in Edo Period as the Shichihonyari of Shizugatake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His exploits as on of the Shichihonyari of Shizugatake were told about in &quot;Ehon Taikoki,&quot; written in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His exploits as one of the Shichihonyari of Shizugatake were told about in &quot;Ehon Taikoki,&quot; written in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>on→one</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>明治には、劇作家の坪内逍遥が史劇『桐一葉』において忠臣としての且元を描き、歴史学においても忠・不忠の視点で論じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Kiri Hitoha,&quot; written by the script writer Shoyo TSUBOUCHI, he described Katsumoto as a loyal subject, and historical studies debated about him from the loyal and disloyal perspectives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late 19th century, author Shoyo TSUBOUCHI described Katsumoto as a loyal subject in &quot;Kiri Hitoha (A Paulownia Leaf),&quot; and historical studies debated his loyalty or disloyalty.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Meiji period, author Shoyo TSUBOUCHI described Katsumoto as a loyal subject in &quot;Kiri Hitoha (A Paulownia Leaf),&quot; and historical studies debated his loyalty or disloyalty.</e>
<cmt>「明治」が「late 19th century」になっている。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>戦後に実証的研究が行われるようになると、昭和51年（1976年）に高木昭作は且元が豊臣家の家老でありつつも徳川方の国奉行であることに着目し、関ヶ原の合戦前後の政治状況を考察する際にも注目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the demonstration experiment began to be performed after the World War II, Shosaku TAKAGI pointed out in 1976 that Katsumoto was both the servant of TOYOTOMI Family as well as being the kuni (country) bugyo of TOKUGAWA, and he is closely observed to study the political situation before and after the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the growth of empirical research after World War II, Shosaku TAKAGI pointed out in 1976 that Katsumoto was both the chief retainer of the TOYOTOMI and one of TOKUGAWA&apos;s national bugyo, and that is important to study the political situation around the time of the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>Rewrote sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the growth of empirical research after World War II, Shosaku TAKAGI pointed out in 1976 that Katsumoto was both the chief retainer of the TOYOTOMI and one of TOKUGAWA&apos;s national bugyo, and that is important to study the political situation around the time of the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Lonicera(id:20638), Julius Caesar(id:181760), Nnh(id:474), 0null0(id:582), GoGoDoll(id:131511), 松茸(id:27535), ポテンシャル0(id:160803), Gedz(id:14192), Kotoito(id:21045), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 小者(id:172526), 未完(id:84727), Aboshi(id:9318), でここ(id:9565), Yonoemon(id:55450), 玄史生(id:43670), ひろくん(id:79638), Oreg(id:106900), けんち(id:5147), ５１６(id:45205), Jmho(id:10472), Mastarna(id:79102), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>