<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大野治長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harunaga ONO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harunaga ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harunaga ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大野 治長（おおの はるなが）は、安土桃山時代から江戸時代前期にかけての豊臣氏の家臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harunaga ONO was a vassal of the Toyotomi clan from the Azuchi-Momoyama period through to the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harunaga ONO was a vassal of the Toyotomi clan from the Azuchi-Momoyama period through to the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harunaga ONO was a vassal of the Toyotomi clan from the Azuchi-Momoyama period through to the early part of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>父は大野佐渡守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sadonokami ONO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Sadonokami ONO.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Ono Sado no kami (the governor of Sado Province).</e>
<cmt>佐渡守　の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>兄弟に大野治房・大野治胤、子は大野治徳ほか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His siblings were: Harufusa ONO/ Harutane ONO and child Harunori ONO and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His siblings were Harufusa ONO and Harutane ONO, and his children included Harunori ONO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His siblings were Harufusa ONO and Harutane ONO, and his children included Harunori ONO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は従五位修理亮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He held the rank at court of &quot;Jugoishurinosuke&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held the rank at court of &quot;Jugoishurinosuke&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held the rank at court of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) Shuri no suke (assistant officer of the Office of Palace Repairs).</e>
<cmt>官位の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>知行15000石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had a fiefdom of 15,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a fiefdom of 15,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a fiefdom of 15,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lifetime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lifetime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>永禄12年（1569年）、京都に生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto in 1569.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born in Kyoto, in 1569.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born in Kyoto, in 1569.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>豊臣秀吉の側室・淀殿の乳母である大蔵卿局の子に当たる関係から、秀吉に約3000石の馬廻衆として取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being a child of Okurakyo-no-tsubone, the wet-nurse to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s concubine Yodo-dono (Lady Yono), he was able to extract a stipend from Hideyoshi of 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a child of Okurakyo-no-tsubone, who had served as wet-nurse to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s concubine Yodo-dono (Lady Yono), he had the privilidge of collecting a stipend of 3,000 koku from Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a child of Okurakyo-no-tsubone, who had served as wet-nurse to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s concubine Yodo-dono (Lady Yodo), he served as Umamawarishu (bodyguard) with a stipend of 3,000 koku given from Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>馬廻衆　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>秀吉の死後は、豊臣秀頼の側近として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following Hideyoshi&apos;s death, he served as an advisor close to Hideyori TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following Hideyoshi&apos;s death, he served as an advisor close to Hideyori TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following Hideyoshi&apos;s death, he served as an advisor close to Hideyori TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos; としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし慶長4年（1599年）、徳川家康と本多正信の主従が策した家康暗殺疑惑事件の首謀者の一人として家康にその罪を問われ、下野国（栃木県）に流罪とされてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1599 following questioning by Ieyasu, he was banished to Shimotsuke Province (Tochigi Prefecture) as ringleader of a dubious incident to assassinate Ieyasu planned by master Ieyasu and servant Masanobu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>Original text does not make sense.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1599 following questioning by Ieyasu, he was banished to Shimotsuke Province (Tochigi Prefecture), under suscpicion of being a ringleader of a failed plot to assassinate Ieyasu that had been hacthed by Tokugawa Ieyasu and his servant Masanobu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>content based error in the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1599 following questioning by Ieyasu, he was banished to Shimotsuke Province (Tochigi Prefecture), under suspicion of being a ringleader of a failed plot to assassinate Ieyasu that had been hatched by servants of Tokugawa Ieyasu and Masanobu HONDA.</e>
<cmt>家康と本田正信の主従　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>だが翌慶長5年（1600年）、関ヶ原の戦いでは東軍に参戦し武功を上げ、家康から罪を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the following year, 1600, he joined forces with the Eastern army at the Battle of Sekigahara, distinguished himself in battle and his crime was pardoned by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the following year, 1600, he joined forces with the Eastern army at the Battle of Sekigahara and distinguished himself in battle, thereby earning a pardon for his crime from Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the following year, 1600, he joined forces with the Eastern army at the Battle of Sekigahara and distinguished himself in battle, thereby earning a pardon for his crime from Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>戦後、家康の命で「豊臣氏への敵意なし」という家康の書簡をもって豊臣家への使者を務めた後、江戸に戻らずそのまま大坂に残った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the battle at Ieyasu`s command he bore a note to Toyotomi&apos;s Clan that stated &quot;I bear no animosity towards the Toyotomi Clan&quot; whereupon he subsequently did not return to Edo and remained in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the battle, under orders from Ieyasu he bore a note from Ieyasu to the Toyotomi Clan, in which Ieyasu declared, &quot;I bear no animosity towards the Toyotomi Clan&quot; after which he remained in Osaka and did not return to Edo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the battle, under orders from Ieyasu he bore a note from Ieyasu to the Toyotomi clan, in which Ieyasu declared, &apos;I bear no animosity towards the Toyotomi clan&apos; after which he remained in Osaka and did not return to Edo.</e>
<cmt>”　→　&apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>慶長19年（1614年）、豊臣氏の家老であった片桐且元が追放されると、豊臣家を主導する立場となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1614 with the banishment of Toyotomi&apos;s chief retainer Katsumoto KATAGIRI, ONO filled the position of leading the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1614, upon the banishment of Toyotomi&apos;s chief elder retainer Katsumoto KATAGIRI, ONO came to be in a position to lead the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>somewhat unclear as to what exactly the Japanese phrase,「豊臣家を主導する立場となる」means.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1614, upon the banishment of Toyotomi&apos;s chief elder retainer Katsumoto KATAGIRI, ONO came to be in a position to lead the Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos; としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後豊臣家内部では主戦派が主流となり、各地から浪人を召抱えて大坂冬の陣に至るが、治長は消極的和平を主張し、真田信繁など主戦派と反目する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, the pro-war faction within the Toyotomi family gained ascendancy and enlisted the services of ronin (freelance) samurai from various parts of the country who engaged in the siege of Osaka campaign however, Harunaga half-heartedly sued for peace earning him the animosity of Nobushige SANADA&apos;s pro-war faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, the pro-war faction within the Toyotomi family gained ascendancy and enlisted the services of ronin (samurai who were not in the service of a daimyo, etc.) from various parts of the country to take part in the siege of Osaka winter campaign however; Harunaga passively sued for peace, earning him the animosity of Nobushige SANADA&apos;s pro-war faction.</e>
<cmt>grammar, and translation of &quot;大坂冬の陣&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, the pro-war faction within the Toyotomi family gained ascendancy and enlisted the services of ronin (samurai who were not in the service of a daimyo, etc.) from various parts of the country to take part in the Siege of Osaka winter campaign however; Harunaga passively sued for peace, earning him the animosity of Nobushige SANADA&apos;s pro-war faction.</e>
<cmt>’→&apos; としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>慶長20年（1615年）、大坂の役大坂夏の陣では征夷大将軍徳川秀忠の娘で秀頼の正室であった千姫を使者とし、己の切腹を条件に秀頼母子の助命を願うが、秀頼とともに大坂城の山里曲輪で自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1615 during the siege of Osaka summer campaign, Princess Sen (daughter of Hidetada TOKUGAWA the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and legal wife of Hideyori) acted as messenger for ONO on the condition he commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) to plead for clemency for Hideyori and mother but, ONO and Hideyori committed suicide in a mountain hamlet around about Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1615 during the summer campaign of the siege of Osaka, Princess Sen (who was a daughter of Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) as well as the legal wife of Hideyori) agreed to act as messenger for ONO, on the condition that he commit ritual suicide (&apos;seppuku&apos;, suicide by disembowelment), to plead for clemency for Hideyori and his mother, but ONO and Hideyori committed suicide in a mountain hamlet in the vicinity of Osaka Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1615 during the summer campaign of the Siege of Osaka, Harunaga sent Princess Sen (who was a daughter of Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) as well as the legal wife of Hideyori) as a messenger for ONO, to plead for clemency for Hideyori and his mother, on the condition that he commit ritual suicide (&apos;seppuku&apos;, suicide by disembowelment), but subsequently he and Hideyori committed suicide in a mountain hamlet in the vicinity of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>享年47。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Died at 47 years of age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 47.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 47.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>茶の湯を古田重然に学んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Studied the tea ceremony from Shigeteru FURUTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had studied the tea ceremony with Shigeteru FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had studied the tea ceremony with Shigenari FURUTA.</e>
<cmt>Shigenari としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>江戸時代を通じて、治長は淀殿と密通していたと噂されていた記録が残り、秀頼は秀吉の実子ではなく治長と淀殿の子であるとする説があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Throughout the Edo period, records remain and rumors abounded of Harunaga having an adulterous affair with Yodo-dono (Lady Yono) and theories exist that Hideyori was not the true child of Hideyoshi but the child of Harunaga and Yodo-dono (Lady Yono).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Records show that rumors abounded throughout the Edo period regarding Harunaga having an adulterous affair with Yodo-dono (Lady Yono), and some accounts maintain that Hideyori was not a biological child of Hideyoshi, but of Harunaga and Yodo-dono (Lady Yono).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Records show that rumors abounded throughout the Edo period regarding Harunaga having an adulterous affair with Yodo-dono, and some accounts maintain that Hideyori was not a biological child of Hideyoshi, but of Harunaga and Yodo-dono.</e>
<cmt>Yodo と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>前述の通り、淀殿の乳兄弟に当たるために両者の仲が極めて親密であったことと、豊臣家を滅ぼした「亡国の徒」として、彼を（儒教の観念から）悪人たらしめる為に姦通という罪をでっち上げるという意味合いから噂されたものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned previously, as foster brother and sister it is possible their relationship was extremely close but, with the demise of the Toyotomi family and with the accompanying &quot;futility of ruin&quot;, it could be thought of (from a Confucian sense of resignation) that rumors of the sin of adultery were created with a view to casting him as an evil person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, because he was a foster brother to Yodo-dono, it is likely that their relationship was extremely close; however, with the decline of the fortune of the Toyotomi family and the accompanying &quot;futility of ruin&quot;, it can also be thought that the rumors of the sin of adultery were created with a view to casting him as an evil person (from a Confucian sense of resignation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, because he was a foster brother to Yodo-dono, it is likely that their relationship was extremely close; however, with the decline of the fortune of the Toyotomi family and the accompanying &apos;futility of ruin,&apos; it can also be thought that the rumors of the sin of adultery were created with a view to casting him as an evil person (from a Confucian sense of resignation).</e>
<cmt>”　→　&apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lonicera(id:20638), Izayohi(id:13095), 0null0(id:582), Cprobot(id:97843), Gori(id:13656), 水野白楓(id:22811), Gedz(id:14192), Dream100(id:41924), でここ(id:9565), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), 赤井彗星(id:18381), らりた(id:1327), YurikBot(id:18605), 透明超人(id:134573), Loveless(id:129239), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Suisui(id:69), Kouko0515(id:100370), Jmho(id:10472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>