<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>源義兼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikane</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshikane</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikane</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>源 義兼（みなもと の よしかね、生没年不詳）は、平安時代末期の河内源氏の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikane (dates unknown) was a late-Heian period military commander of the Kawachi-genji branch of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshikane (dates unknown) was a late-Heian period military commander of the Kawachi-genji branch of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshikane (year of birth and death unknown) was a late-Heian period military commander of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>「生没年不詳」を修正しました。Kawachi-genji branch of the Minamoto clan→Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源義家（八幡太郎）の曾孫で、河内国石川源氏棟梁の源義基の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A descendant of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie (who was also known as Hachiman Taro), Yoshikane was the eldest son of MINAMOTO no Yoshimoto, the head of the Kawachi Ishikawa branch of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A descendant of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie (who was also known as Hachiman Taro), Yoshikane was the eldest son of MINAMOTO no Yoshimoto, the head of the Kawachi Ishikawa branch of the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A great-grandchild of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie (who was also known as Hachiman Taro), Yoshikane was the oldest son of MINAMOTO no Yoshimoto, the head of the Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan) in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>descendant→great-grandchild,eldest→oldest,Kawachi Ishikawa branch of the Minamoto clan→Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan) in Kawachi Province と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>石川判官代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the hogandai (administrative official) of Ishikawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the hogandai (administrative official) of Ishikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the hogandai (administrative official) of Ishikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>石川義兼とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known as Yoshikane ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as Yoshikane ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as Yoshikane ISHIKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikane&apos;s Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikane&apos;s Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>Yoshikane&apos;s を削除しました。（用語統一）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>治承四年（1180年）冬、平清盛の攻撃により義基ら石川源氏の主力が鳥羽（京都市伏見区）で壊滅した際、義兼は本拠地の石川城（大阪府南河内郡河南町）にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the winter of 1180, when Yoshimoto and the greater part of the Ishikawa Minamoto strength were destroyed by TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s assault at Toba (today&apos;s Fushimi-ku Ward in Kyoto), Yoshikane was at their clan stronghold of Ishikawa-jo Castle (present-day Kanan-cho, Minamikawachi-gun, Osaka Pref.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the winter of 1180, when Yoshimoto and the greater part of the Ishikawa Minamoto strength were destroyed by TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s assault at Toba (today&apos;s Fushimi-ku Ward in Kyoto), Yoshikane was at their clan stronghold of Ishikawa-jo Castle (present-day Kanan-cho, Minamikawachi-gun, Osaka Pref.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the winter of 1180, when Yoshimoto and the greater part of the Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan) strength were destroyed by TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s assault at Toba (today&apos;s Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City), Yoshikane was at their clan stronghold of Ishikawa-jo Castle (present-day Kanan-cho, Minamikawachi-gun, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Ishikawa Minamoto→Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan),Fushimi-ku Ward in Kyoto→Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City,Pref.→Prefecture と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>清盛は源義家以来の河内の石川源氏に止めを刺すべく、源季貞、平盛澄らを派遣して石川城を攻撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori, believing it was best to annihilate the entire Ishikawa branch of the Kawachi-genji, all those who were descended from MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, sent MINAMOTO no Suesada, TAIRA no Morizumi and others to attack Ishikawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori, believing it was best to annihilate the entire Ishikawa branch of the Kawachi-genji, all those who were descended from MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, sent MINAMOTO no Suesada, TAIRA no Morizumi and others to attack Ishikawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori, believing it was best to annihilate the entire Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan) in Kawachi, all those who were descended from MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, sent MINAMOTO no Suesada, TAIRA no Morizumi and others to attack Ishikawa-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Ishikawa branch of the Kawachi-genji→Ishikawa-Genji (MInamoto clan) in Kawachi と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>義兼は河内石川源氏の棟梁として、叔父の紺戸義広・二条義資らを率いて決死の防戦に努め、平家方を散々にてこずらせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikane, as the new head of the Kawachi Ishikawa Genji (Minamoto), led his uncles Yoshihira KONTO and Yoshisuke NIJO and threw himself wholeheartedly into a do-or-die defensive action, causing the attacking Taira army tremendous trouble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikane, as the new head of the Kawachi Ishikawa Genji (Minamoto), led his uncles Yoshihira KONTO and Yoshisuke NIJO and threw himself wholeheartedly into a do-or-die defensive action, causing the attacking Taira army tremendous trouble.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikane, as the new head of the Kawachi Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan), led his uncles Yoshihira KONDO and Yoshisuke NIJO and threw himself wholeheartedly into a do-or-die defensive action, causing the attacking Taira army tremendous trouble.</e>
<cmt>Ishikawa Genji (Minamoto)→Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan),KONTO→KONDO （「紺戸義広＝こんどよしひろ」と確認しました）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、やがて力尽きて落城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite his efforts, the defenders&apos; strength eventually was exhausted and the castle was captured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite his efforts, the defenders&apos; strength eventually was exhausted and the castle was captured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite his efforts, the defenders&apos; strength eventually was exhausted and the castle fell.</e>
<cmt>was captured→fell と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>義兼は覚悟を決めて自刃しようとしたところを、敵方の将兵に幾重にも折り重なれて生け捕りにされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikane had resolved to die, but just as he was preparing to stab himself, enemy soldiers dove on top of him one after another, and he was captured alive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikane had resolved to die, but just as he was preparing to stab himself, enemy soldiers dove on top of him one after another, and he was captured alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikane had resolved to die, but just as he was preparing to stab himself, enemy soldiers dove on top of him one after another, and he was captured alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、しばらく捕虜としての生活を余儀なくされるが、木曽義仲の入洛と平家の都落ちという混乱に乗じて脱出に成功。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he was compelled for a time to live as a prisoner of war, but in the confusion of Yoshinaka KISO&apos;s invasion of the capital and the Taira&apos;s consequent retreat, he seized the moment and successfully escaped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he was compelled for a time to live as a prisoner of war, but in the confusion of Yoshinaka KISO&apos;s invasion of the capital and the Taira&apos;s consequent retreat, he seized the moment and successfully escaped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he was compelled for a time to live as a prisoner of war, but in the confusion of Yoshinaka KISO&apos;s invasion of the capital and the Taira&apos;s consequent flight from the capital, he seized the moment and successfully escaped.</e>
<cmt>retreat→flight from the capital と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>河内に戻り石川源氏を再武装し、源頼朝の傘下に入り、河内源氏後裔の頼朝から「河内随一の源氏」と評される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He returned to Kawachi and set about rearming the Kawachi Ishikawa Genji, coming under the protection of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who--himself a descendant of the Kawachi Genji--later said of Yoshikane that &quot;He is the greatest of the Kawachi Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He returned to Kawachi and set about rearming the Kawachi Ishikawa Genji, coming under the protection of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who--himself a descendant of the Kawachi Genji--later said of Yoshikane that &quot;He is the greatest of the Kawachi Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He returned to Kawachi and set about rearming the Kawachi Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan), coming under the protection of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who--himself a descendant of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)--later said of Yoshikane that &quot;He is the greatest Genji (Minamoto clan) in Kawachi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Ishikawa Genji→Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan),Kawachi Genji→Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) と修正しました。クォーツ内を文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>義兼の子孫は、鎌倉幕府の御家人となり、南北朝時代 (日本)には石川源氏として存在し、その子孫は石川氏として存続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikane&apos;s descendants became gokenin (shogunal vassals) in the Kamakura bakufu (shogunate), surviving as the Ishikawa Genji into Japan&apos;s Period of Northern and Southern Courts, and thereafter continued his line under the name of the Ishikawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikane&apos;s descendants became gokenin (shogunal vassals) in the Kamakura bakufu (shogunate), surviving as the Ishikawa Genji into Japan&apos;s Period of Northern and Southern Courts, and thereafter continued his line under the name of the Ishikawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikane&apos;s descendants became gokenin (shogunal vassals) in the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), surviving as the Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan) into the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), and thereafter continued his line under the name of the Ishikawa clan.</e>
<cmt>「鎌倉幕府」に続くカッコ部分を修正しました。「南北朝時代（日本）」を修正しました。（用語統一）Ishikawa Genji→Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan) と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), Rusk(id:9895), GURAX(id:107578), Birdman(id:1040), Macss(id:87864), Knua(id:66861), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>