<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原刷雄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshio</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yoshio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原 刷雄（ふじわら の よしお、生没年不詳）は、奈良時代の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshio (year of birth and death unknown) was born to a noble family in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yoshio (year of birth and death unknown) was a noble in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>was a noble と省略。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshio (year of birth and death unknown) was a noble in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>太政大臣藤原仲麻呂（恵美押勝）の6男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the 6th son of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, the Grand Minister (EMI no Oshikatsu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the 6th son of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, the Grand Minister (EMI no Oshikatsu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the 6th son of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, the Grand Minister (EMI no Oshikatsu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は伴犬養女とされているが、不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that his mother was TOMO no Inukai no Musume but the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his mother was TOMO no Inukai no Musume but the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his mother was TOMO no Inukai no Musume but the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に藤原千世がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Chiyo was her daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Chiyo was his daughter.</e>
<cmt>his ではなく　her</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Chiyo was his daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>天平勝宝4年（752年）遣唐使の留学生として藤原清河に随行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accompanied FUJIWARA no Kiyokawa in 752 as an overseas student of the Kentoshi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He accompanied FUJIWARA no Kiyokawa in 752 as an exchange student and a Kentoshi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China),.</e>
<cmt>もっとわかりやすく訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He accompanied FUJIWARA no Kiyokawa in 752 as an exchange student and a Kentoshi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China),.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同6年4月頃帰国したと推察され、帰国後、無位から従五位下となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is inferred that he came back in April, 756, and was promoted from having no rank to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is guessed that he came back in April, 756, and was promoted from having no rank to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>guessed は　”ほのめかす”　という意味が強いので、assume と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is guessed that he came back in April, 756, and was promoted from having no rank to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天平宝字2年（758年）には父とともに「藤原恵美」朝臣の姓を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 758, he was given the name FUJIWARA no Emi Ason along with his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 758, he and his father were given the name FUJIWARA no Emi Ason.</e>
<cmt>この方が自然です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 758, he and his father were given the name FUJIWARA no Emi Ason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ところが、天平宝字8年（764年）に藤原仲麻呂の乱が起きて一族が悉く処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Fujiwara no Nakamaro&apos;s War occurred in 764, his family members were killed one after another.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Fujiwara no Nakamaro&apos;s War occurred in 764, his family members were executed one after another.</e>
<cmt>killed より　executed の方が正確です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Fujiwara no Nakamaro&apos;s War occurred in 764, his family members were executed one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>刷雄本人は若い時から禅行を修めていた（当時の社会で重んじられていた遣唐使留学生だった経歴が考慮されたものとも）として死を免れ、隠岐国に配流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that because he was an overseas student with the Kentoshi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China), which was highly respected in the society at that time, this was taken in to consideration, and he was exiled to Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that because he was an exchange student with the Kentoshi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China), which was highly respected in the society at that time, he was able to avoid execution, and was instead exiled to Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>overseas student を　exchange student に変訳。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that because he was an exchange student with the Kentoshi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China), which was highly respected in the society at that time, he was able to avoid execution, and was instead exiled to Oki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宝亀3年（772年）に赦免されて従五位下藤原朝臣に戻されて官界に復帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he was pardoned and released in 772, with the support of Fujiwara no Ason, Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), he returned to the government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he was pardoned and released in 772, he regained his position as Fujiwara no Ason, Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), and returned to politics.</e>
<cmt>文章の意味が変わっていたので変訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he was pardoned and released in 772, he regained his position as Fujiwara no Ason, Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), and returned to politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>6年後には従五位上に昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six years later he was promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Six years later he was promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six years later he was promoted to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>但馬国国司、刑部省、治部省、上総国守、大学寮、大舎人寮を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having held positions such as Governor of Tajima Province and Head of Kazusa Province, he also held positions in the Ministry of Justice, the Ministry of Civil Administration, the Bureau of Education and the Bureau of Imperial Attendants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having held positions such as Governor of Tajima Province and Head of Kazusa Province, he also held positions in the Ministry of Justice, the Ministry of Civil Administration, the Bureau of Education and the Bureau of Imperial Attendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having held positions such as Governor of Tajima Province and Head of Kazusa Province, he also held positions in the Ministry of Justice, the Ministry of Civil Administration, the Bureau of Education and the Bureau of Imperial Attendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>延暦10年（791年）に陰陽寮に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was assigned as the head of Divination in 791.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was assigned as the head of Divination in 791.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was assigned as the head of Divination in 791.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>淡海三船撰の『唐大和上東征伝』に、天平宝字7年（763年）5月に没した鑑真を悼む五言漢詩が収録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Todaiwajo Toseiden&quot; (Eastern Expedition of the Great T&apos;ang Monk) written by OMI no Mifune includes a Gogon Chinese-style poem that mourns Jianzhen who died in May, 763.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Todaiwajo Toseiden&quot; (Eastern Expedition of the Great T&apos;ang Monk) written by OMI no Mifune, includes a Gogon Chinese-style poem mourning Jianzhen, who died in May, 763.</e>
<cmt>comma を足しました。あとmourningのほうがこの場合自然かと。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Todaiwajo Toseiden&quot; (Eastern Expedition of the Great T&apos;ang Monk) written by OMI no Mifune, includes a Gogon Chinese-style poem mourning Jianzhen, who died in May, 763.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、『尊卑分脈』において、刷雄の兄弟とされている藤原薩雄は、刷雄と同一人物とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a view, in &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a Japanese genealogical text), that FUJIWARA no Yoshio (薩雄) who is said to be a brother of Yoshio (刷雄), are in fact the same person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a Japanese genealogical text), there is a hypothesis that FUJIWARA no Yoshio (薩雄), who is said to be a brother to Yoshio (刷雄), are in fact the same person.</e>
<cmt>この方が文章がまとまります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (a Japanese genealogical text), there is a hypothesis that FUJIWARA no Yoshio (薩雄), who is said to be a brother to Yoshio (刷雄), are in fact the same person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>薗田香融は『続日本紀』にある天平宝字2年の無位から従五位下とする記述は当時の遣唐留学生の叙位としては異例なだけではなく、当時健在であった4人の兄の位階の昇進の例（いずれも正六位上から従五位下に昇進している）を越してしまう事を指摘してこの記事には誤りが含まれているとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koyu SONODA claims that &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan II) has false information for the following reasons : In the year 758, it would have been extremely unusual, that FUJIWARA no Yoshio as an overseas student in Kentoshi-shi would receive Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) from No Rank; This means that he was in the same rank as his four older brothers, who were still alive and well at this point, who were promoted one rank from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koyu SONODA claims that &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan II) has false information for the following reason: In the year 758, it would have been extremely unusual for FUJIWARA no Yoshio as an exchange student Kentoshi to be promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) from no rank, for this would mean that he was promoted ahead of his four older brothers (The older brothers were promoted one rank from Shorokuinojo [Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade] to Jugoinoge).</e>
<cmt>文章の意味がかわっていたので変訳。『続日本紀』によるとよしおは兄より上に昇進したことになる。ほんやくしゃは、兄と同じ階級に昇進したと訳しています。あと英語に訳すとき当時健在という表現はあまりしないので、省きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koyu SONODA claims that &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan II) has false information for the following reason: In the year 758, it would have been extremely unusual for FUJIWARA no Yoshio as an exchange student Kentoshi to be promoted to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) from no rank, for this would mean that he was promoted ahead of his four older brothers (The older brothers were promoted one rank from Shorokuinojo [Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade] to Jugoinoge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>よって、『続日本紀』翌年天平宝字3年6月庚戊に正六位上から従五位下に叙された薩雄を刷雄と同一人物とする説を述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, he has a view that the Yoshio (薩雄) who, according to &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan II), was honored in July 759 with Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) and promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade), was in fact Yoshio(刷雄).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　また、同音異名の人物に関する記述につき、漢字名を織り込んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, there is a theory that Yoshio(薩雄), who, according to &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan II), was honored in July 759 with Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), and promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade), is the one and the same person as Yoshio(刷雄).</e>
<cmt>この方が文章がまとまります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, there is a theory that Yoshio(薩雄), who, according to &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicles of Japan II), was honored in July 759 with Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), and promoted from Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade), is the one and the same person as Yoshio(刷雄).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天平宝字2年の父・仲麻呂は「恵美押勝」に改名している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshio&apos;s father, Nakamaro, changed his name to &apos;EMI no Oshikasu&apos; in 758.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshio&apos;s father, Nakamaro, changed his name to &apos;EMI no Oshikasu&apos; in 758.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshio&apos;s father, Nakamaro, changed his name to &apos;EMI no Oshikasu&apos; in 758.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>吉川敏子は、前後して若い頃に仏道修行をしていた刷雄に「菩薩」に通じる&quot;薩&quot;の字が与えらた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Toshiko YOSHIKAWA, at the same time, it is likely that Yoshio was given the Chinese character 薩 for his name, which relates to 菩薩 (Bodhisattva), as he had Buddhist trainings when he was young and that during the EMI no Oshikatsu&apos;s War, he was deprived of his new name and made to use his former name. This would suppose that the two Yoshios mentioned are in fact the same person.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処　また、漢字名の解説文が含まれるため、漢字を文中に織り込んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Toshiko YOSHIKAWA, it was likely that during his early Buddhist training, Yoshio was given the Chinese character 薩 for his name, which relates to 菩薩 (Bodhisattva).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすく変訳しました。一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Toshiko YOSHIKAWA, it was likely that during his early Buddhist training, Yoshio was given the Chinese character 薩 for his name, which relates to 菩薩 (Bodhisattva).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、恵美押勝の乱の際に剥奪されて旧名の刷雄に戻されたとすれば、両者が同一人物としての説明が可能であると唱えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if it was true that he was deprived of his new name during the Rebellion of Emi no Oshikatsu and forced to use his former name, the theory that the two are the same person would be possible.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if it was true that he was deprived of his new name during the Rebellion of Emi no Oshikatsu and forced to use his former name, the theory that the two are the same person would be possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), YOSHI438(id:174755), 水野白楓(id:22811), ごまふあざ(id:36855), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>