<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>島清興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyooki SHIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyooki SHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyooki SHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>島 清興（しま きよおき）は、安土桃山時代の武将で石田三成の家臣（軍師）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyooki SHIMA was a busho and vassal (strategist) of Mitsunari ISHIDA in the Azuchi-momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyooki SHIMA was a busho (military commander) and vassal (strategist) of Mitsunari ISHIDA who lived during the Azuchi-momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;(military commander)&quot;in &gt; who lived during</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyooki SHIMA was a busho (military commander) and vassal (strategist) of Mitsunari ISHIDA who lived during the Azuchi-momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>通称である「島 左近（しま さこん）」の名で一般に広く知られ、「治部少（三成）に過ぎたるものが二つあり 島の左近と佐和山の城」と謳われるほどの人物であった（本項目でも、特に断りが無い限りは「（島）左近」と表記する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was widely known under the common name of &apos;Sakon SHIMA&apos;, and he was a great samurai who was admired so that it was said that &apos;Jibusho (Mitsunari) had two unworthy things: Sakon SHIMA and Sawayama castle&apos; (unless otherwise noted, he was called &apos;Sakon (SHIMA)&apos; in this section).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was widely known by the common name of &apos;Sakon SHIMA&apos;, and he was respected so much that it was said that &apos;Jibusho (Mitsunari) had two valuable things: Sakon SHIMA and Sawayama castle&apos; (his name is noted as &apos;Sakon (SHIMA)&apos; in this section unless otherwise specified).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was widely known by the common name of &apos;Sakon SHIMA&apos;, and he was respected so much that it was said that &apos;Jibusho (Mitsunari) had two valuable things: Sakon SHIMA and Sawayama-jo castle&apos; (his name is noted as &apos;Sakon (SHIMA)&apos; in this section unless otherwise specified).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧内へ移動→ピリオドを括弧内の外へ出しました（括弧内が全く独立した文ではなく、文の最初が小文字になっているため）。Sawayama castle→Sawayama-jo castle</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>実名は俗に勝猛（かつたけ）ともいうが、文書から確かなのは清興（きよおき）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is commonly said that his real name was Katsutake, but Kiyooki was correct according to archives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is commonly said that his real name was Katsutake, but Kiyooki is correct according to archives.</e>
<cmt>was &gt; is</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is commonly said that his real name was Katsutake, but Kiyooki is correct according to archives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>娘（珠）は柳生利巌の継室で、剣豪として名高い柳生厳包は外孫にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His daughter was the second wife of Toshiyoshi YAGYU, and Yoshikane YAGYU who was famous as a kengo (a great swordsman) was his grandchild from a daughter married into another family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His daughter was the second wife of Toshiyoshi YAGYU, and Yoshikane YAGYU who was famous as a kengo (a great swordsman) was his grandchild.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;from a daughter married into another family&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His daughter was the second wife of Toshiyoshi YAGYU, and Yoshikane YAGYU who was famous as a kengo (a great swordsman) was his grandchild.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>対馬国出身説もあるが現在では大和国出身であることが明らかとなっている（近年では「島左近」は筒井氏家臣である島氏代々の名乗りで清興以前にも「島左近」を名乗る者がいたという説もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that states that he was born in Tsushima Province, but it is currently clear that he was born in Yamato Province (recently there is also another theory that states that &apos;Sakon SHIMA&apos; was a name of the Shima clan who served the Tsutsui clan and there was a person named &apos;Sakon SHIMA&apos; before Kiyooki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory stating that he was born in Tsushima Province, but it is now clear that he was born in Yamato Province (recently there has also been another theory that &apos;Sakon SHIMA&apos; was a name of the Shima clan who served the Tsutsui clan and that there was a another person named &apos;Sakon SHIMA&apos; before Kiyooki).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory stating that he was born in Tsushima Province, but it is now clear that he was born in Yamato Province (recently there has also been another theory that &apos;Sakon SHIMA&apos; was a name of the Shima clan who served the Tsutsui clan and that there was another person named &apos;Sakon SHIMA&apos; before Kiyooki).</e>
<cmt>a another→anotherピリオドを括弧内へ移動→ピリオドを括弧内の外へ出しました。（括弧内文の最初が小文字になっているため）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>畠山氏・筒井氏・豊臣氏時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ages of Hatakeyama, Tsutsui, and Toyotomi clans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hatakeyama, Tsutsui, and Toyotomi Clan Periods</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hatakeyama, Tsutsui, and Toyotomi Clan Periods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>大和国の国人の家系に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born in a family line of local lords in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyooki SHIMA was born in a family of local lords of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyooki SHIMA was born in a family of local lords of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>島氏は今の奈良県生駒郡平群町周辺の在地領主であったと考えられており、島清興は、当初は隣国河内国の守護で、大和国にも勢力を扶植していた畠山氏に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shima clan was considered to be a resident landholder around present Heguri-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture, and Kiyooki SHIMA was initially a shugo (military governor) of the adjacent province, Kawachi Province, and served the Hatakeyama family who wielded their influence on Yamato Province as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shima clan was considered to be a resident landholder around present-day Heguri-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture, and Kiyooki SHIMA was initially a shugo (military governor) of the adjacent province of Kawachi, and served the Hatakeyama clan who wielded their influence in Yamato Province as well.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shima clan was considered to be a resident landholder around present-day Heguri-cho, Ikoma County, Nara Prefecture, and Kiyooki SHIMA was initially a shugo (military governor) of the adjacent province of Kawachi, and served the Hatakeyama clan who wielded their influence in Yamato Province as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>畠山高政が三好長慶と戦った教興寺の戦いに参加したが、畠山高政は敗北し、島清興も敗走している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took part in the Battle of Kyoko-ji Temple in which Takamasa HATAKEYAMA fought against Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, but Takamasa HATAKEYAMA defeated and Kiyooki SHIMA fled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took part in the Battle of Kyoko-ji Temple in which Takamasa HATAKEYAMA fought Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, but Takamasa HATAKEYAMA was defeated and Kiyooki SHIMA fled.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took part in the Battle of Kyoko-ji Temple in which Takamasa HATAKEYAMA fought Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, but Takamasa HATAKEYAMA was defeated and Kiyooki SHIMA fled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その際、筒井順政の指揮下で戦ったことが縁で畠山氏の没落後、筒井氏に従属する領主の一人となり、次第に頭角を現し、順政の後をわずか二歳で継いだ筒井順慶を侍大将として盛り立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he fought under command of Junsei TSUTSUI in the battle, he became one of local lords belonging to the Tsutsui clan after the fall of the Hatakeyama clan, came to the front gradually, and as a samurai taisho (a warrior who gives the order of battle and maneuvers the troops), he supported Junkei TSUTSUI who succeeded Junsei at the age of no older than 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he fought under command of Junsei TSUTSUI during this time, he became one of the local lords belonging to the Tsutsui clan after the fall of the Hatakeyama clan, gradually distinguished himself, and as a samurai taisho (a warrior who gives battle orders and maneuvers troops), he supported Junkei TSUTSUI who succeeded Junsei at the age of no older than 2.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he fought under command of Junsei TSUTSUI during this time, he became one of the local lords belonging to the Tsutsui clan after the fall of the Hatakeyama clan, gradually distinguished himself, and as a samurai taisho (a warrior who gives battle orders and maneuvers troops), he supported Junkei TSUTSUI who succeeded Junsei at the age of no older than two.</e>
<cmt>2→two</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>大和国の覇権を争って松永久秀との厳しい戦い（筒井城の戦い、東大寺大仏殿の戦い）を続け、一時は筒井家の居城さえ失うほどの苦境に立たされても順慶を支え続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued difficult fighting against Hisahide MATSUNAGA (Battle of Tsutsui Castle, Battle of Daibutsu-den Hall (the Great Buddha hall) of Todai-ji Temple) to win the hegemony of Yamato Province and continued to support Junkei even when the castle of the Tsutsui clan was lost temporarily and had a tough time.</e>
<cmt>筒井城の戦いはBattle of Tsutsui Castle、東大寺大仏殿の戦いはBattle of Daibutsu-den Hall (the Great Buddha hall) of Todai-ji Templeと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to fight an intense battle against Hisahide MATSUNAGA (Battle of Tsutsui Castle, Battle of Daibutsu-den Hall (the Great Buddha hall) of Todai-ji Temple) for control of Yamato Province and continued to support Junkei even during a crisis in which the castle of the Tsutsui clan was temporarily lost.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to fight an intense battle against Hisahide MATSUNAGA (Battle of Tsutsui-jo Castle, Battle of Daibutsu-den Hall [the Great Buddha hall] of Todai-ji Temple) for control of Yamato Province and continued to support Junkei even during a crisis in which the castle of the Tsutsui clan was temporarily lost.</e>
<cmt>Tsutsui→Tsutsui-jo括弧内の括弧を[]に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その活躍から松倉重信（右近）と並んで筒井家の両翼「右近左近」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He and Shigenobu MATSUKURA (Ukon) were called two wings (Ukon and Sakon) of the Tsutsui clan due to his good showing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He and Shigenobu MATSUKURA (Ukon) were called the two wings (Ukon and Sakon) of the Tsutsui clan due to their conspicuous service.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He and Shigenobu MATSUKURA (Ukon) were called the two wings (Ukon and Sakon) of the Tsutsui clan due to their conspicuous service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>松永久秀を倒し本能寺の変といった存亡の危機も乗り越えて筒井家による大和国の統一を成し遂げたが、その後まもなく苦楽をともにした主君である順慶が病に倒れてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He defeated Hisahide MATSUNAGA, got over a life-or-death crisis at &quot;the Honnoji Incident&quot;, and helped the Tsutsui clan to unify Yamato Province, but soon after that, his load, Junkei, with whom he shared joys and sorrows, succumbed to disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He defeated Hisahide MATSUNAGA, got over a life-or-death crisis at &quot;the Honnoji Incident&quot;, and helped the Tsutsui clan to unify Yamato Province, but soon after that, his load, Junkei, with whom he shared joys and sorrows, succumbed to disease.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He defeated Hisahide MATSUNAGA, got over a life-or-death crisis at &quot;the Honnoji Incident&quot;, and helped the Tsutsui clan to unify Yamato Province, but soon after that, his load, Junkei, with whom he shared joys and sorrows, succumbed to disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>後を継いだ順慶の甥筒井定次とは意見が合わず、筒井家を辞することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He disagreed with the nephew of Junkei, Sadatsugu TSUTSUI, who succeeded Junkei, and left the Tsutsui clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had a disagreement with the nephew of Junkei, Sadatsugu TSUTSUI, who succeeded Junkei, and left the Tsutsui clan.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had a disagreement with the nephew of Junkei, Sadatsugu TSUTSUI, who succeeded Junkei, and left the Tsutsui clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後は豊臣秀長・豊臣秀保らに仕えたが、大和豊臣家の断絶とともに浪人となって近江国に隠棲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then served Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, Hideyasu TOYOTOMI and so on, but after the extinction of the Yamato Toyotomi family, he became a ronin (masterless samurai) and led secluded life in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He went on to serve Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, Hideyasu TOYOTOMI and others, but after the fall of the Yamato Toyotomi family, he became a ronin (masterless samurai) and led a secluded life in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He went on to serve Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, Hideyasu TOYOTOMI and others, but after the fall of the Yamato Toyotomi family, he became a ronin (masterless samurai) and led a secluded life in Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>石田氏時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age of Ishida clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishida Clan Period</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishida Clan Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>その頃、近江の領主となった石田三成から、左近に仕官の要請があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA who became the local lord of Omi asked Sakon to serve him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari ISHIDA who became the local lord of Omi asked Sakon to serve him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA who became the local lord of Omi asked Sakon to serve him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>それまでも多くの要請を断ってきた左近はやはり断るが、三成の必死の説得により仕官を受け入れ、2万石の俸禄で召し抱えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakon who had declined many requests until then also declined the request, but he finally accepted the offer after earnest persuasion of Mitsunari and was employed with a horoku (salary) of 200,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakon, who had declined many requests until then, also declined that of Ishida but he finally accepted after his earnest persuasion of and was employed with a horoku (stipend) of 200,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakon, who had declined many requests until then, also declined that of Ishida but he finally accepted after his earnest persuasion and was employed with a horoku (stipend) of 200,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>persuasion of→persuasion</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは、当時の三成の禄高4万石のうちの半分を与えられるという破格の待遇であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was an unprecedented promotion because a half of the horoku of 400,000 koku of Mitsunari in those days was given to Sakon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was treatment unprecedented at the time because a half of Ishida&apos;s horoku of 400,000 koku was given to Sakon.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was treatment unprecedented at the time because a half of Mitsunari&apos;s horoku of 400,000 koku was given to Sakon.</e>
<cmt>Ishida&apos;s→Mitsunari&apos;s</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>もっとも、島左近が石田三成に仕えたのは、三成が佐和山19万石の城主になってからという説も有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a reliable theory that states that Sakon SHIMA served Mitsunari ISHIDA after he had become a castellan of Sawayama, a 190,000 koku fief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a reliable theory which states that Sakon SHIMA served Mitsunari ISHIDA after he had become lord of Sawayama, a 190,000 koku fief.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a reliable theory which states that Sakon SHIMA served Mitsunari ISHIDA after he had become lord of Sawayama, a 190,000 koku fief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>それでも破格の待遇であったことには違いがない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was still an unprecedented promotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even so, it was still an unprecedented promotion.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even so, it was still an unprecedented promotion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>『多聞院日記』には、天正20年（1592年）4月に左近の妻が「今江州サホノ城（＝佐和山城）ニアリ」と書かれており、その頃には三成に仕えていたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since &quot;Tamonin nikki diary&quot; says that the wife of Sakon was &apos;now in Goushu Sasehono-jo Castle (Sawayama Castle) in April, 1592&apos;, it was considered that he served Mitsunari at that time.</e>
<cmt>江州サホノ城はGoushu Sasehono-jo Castleと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it is stated in &quot;Tamonin nikki&quot; that the wife of Sakon was &apos;now in Goushu Sasehono-jo Castle (Sawayama Castle)&apos; in April, 1592, it is thought that he served Mitsunari at that time.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it is stated in &quot;Tamonin nikki&quot; (Diary compiled at Tamonin Temple) that the wife of Sakon was &apos;now in Goshu Saho no shiro (Sawayama-jo Castle)&apos; in May, 1592, it is thought that he served Mitsunari at that time.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦「多聞院日記」の説明補足Goushu→GoshuSawayama→Sawayama-jo「サホノ城」「Sasehono-jo」→Saho no shiro(佐保時綱が築いた城）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>朝鮮の役では三成に従軍し、朝鮮へ渡海して軍務の補佐をしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took part in a campaign in the War in Korea with Mitsunari, crossed the sea to Korea and supported military duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During war in Korea, Sakon SHIMA joined Mitsunari and traveled to Korea where he assisted with military affairs.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During war in Korea, Sakon SHIMA joined Mitsunari and traveled to Korea where he assisted with military affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>慶長3年（1598年）、豊臣秀吉が没して、徳川家康が権力を振りかざすようになると、それを危険に感じた左近は三成に家康暗殺計画を持ちかけるが、大義名分にこだわる三成はそれを受け入れなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI died in 1598 and Ieyasu Tokugawa began to exert his power, Sakon considered it dangerous, and proposed a plan to assassinate Ieyasu to Mitsunari, but Mitsunari considered it unjustifiable and did not accept it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI died in 1598 and Ieyasu Tokugawa began to exert his power, Sakon considered it dangerous, and proposed a plan to assassinate Ieyasu to Mitsunari, but Mitsunari considered it unjustifiable and did not accept it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI died in 1598 and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA began to exert his power, Sakon considered it dangerous, and proposed a plan to assassinate Ieyasu to Mitsunari, but Mitsunari considered it unjustifiable and did not accept it.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa→TOKUGAWA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>有名なのは近江国水口岡山城の長束正家に、会津征伐で東下する家康をもてなさせ、城内に忍び込んだ左近達が斬るという作戦である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a famous plan that Masaie NAGATSUKA in the Minakuchi-okayama Castle in Omi Province welcomed Ieyasu who traveled east to conquest Aizu and Sakon and others sneaked into the castle and killed Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a famous plot in which it was planned that Masaie NAGATSUKA of Minakuchi-okayama Castle in Omi Province would welcome Ieyasu who had traveled east to conquest Aizu before Sakon and others sneaked into the castle and killed him.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a famous plot in which it was planned that Masaie NAGATSUKA of Minakuchi-okayama-jo Castle in Omi Province would welcome Ieyasu who had traveled east to conquest Aizu before Sakon and others sneaked into the castle and killed him.</e>
<cmt>城名に -jo 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>正家は渋々左近の策に同意し、家康と約束を取り付ける事に成功したが、前夜に家康の元へ間諜からの報告が入り、この約束をすっぽかしたため、左近の計画は失敗に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masaie agreed with the Sakon&apos;s plan reluctantly, succeeded in making a promise with Ieyasu, but he received a report from kancho (spies) at the presious night and broke the promise, causing the Sakon&apos;s plan to fail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masaie reluctantly agreed to Sakon&apos;s plan, and succeeded in making a promise with Ieyasu but he received a report from kancho (spy) during the previous night and broke the promise, causing the Sakon&apos;s plan to fail.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masaie reluctantly agreed to Sakon&apos;s plan, and succeeded in making a promise with Ieyasu but he received a report from kancho (spy) during the previous night and broke the promise, causing the Sakon&apos;s plan to fail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）の関ヶ原の戦いの前日には、会津の上杉景勝、また北からの万一の伊達政宗の裏切りに備えて江戸からなかなか動けないはずの家康の美濃国赤坂到着の報に動揺する西軍の兵たちを鼓舞するために、兵五百を率いて東軍側の中村一栄・有馬豊氏両隊に小競り合いを挑み（杭瀬川の戦い）、明石全登（宇喜多秀家家臣）隊と共に完勝した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the day before the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, Sakon fought against the &apos;eastern&apos; army of Kazuhide NAKAMURA and Toyouji ARIMA with 500 soldiers (Battle of Kuise-gawa River) and won a complete victory with the squad of Takenori AKASHI (vassal of the Hideie UKITA family) to encourage soldiers of the &apos;western&apos; army who were frightened by a report of arrival of Ieyasu at Akasaka, Mino Province, who was believed not to be able to move from Edo in fear of betrayal of Kagekatsu UESUGI of Aizu and Masamune DATE in the north region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To encourage the soldiers of the &apos;western&apos; army, who were frightened by a report that Ieyasu arrived at Akasaka, Mino Province, though he was considered not to be able to move from Edo in fear of betrayal of Kagekatsu UESUGI of Aizu and Masamune DATE in the north region, Sakon led a squad of 500 soldiers to fight against the &apos;eastern&apos; army of Kazuhide NAKAMURA and Toyouji ARIMA (Battle of Kuise-gawa River) in the evening before the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, and his squad and the squad of Takenori AKASHI (vassal of the Hideie UKITA family) won a complete victory.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To encourage the soldiers of the &apos;western&apos; army, who were frightened by a report that Ieyasu arrived at Akasaka, Mino Province, though he was considered not to be able to move from Edo in fear of betrayal of Kagekatsu UESUGI of Aizu and Masamune DATE in the north region, Sakon led a squad of 500 soldiers to fight against the &apos;eastern&apos; army of Kazuhide NAKAMURA and Toyouji ARIMA (Battle of Kuise-gawa River) in the evening before the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, and his squad and the squad of Takenori AKASHI (vassal of Hideie UKITA) won a complete victory.</e>
<cmt>the Hideie UKITA family→Hideie UKITA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、その夜に島津義弘・小西行長らと共に提案した夜襲は、またもや三成に受け入れられずに終わった（夜襲はそもそも進言されていないという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the night attack proposed by Sakon, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU and Yukinaga KONISHI at that night was not approved by Mitsunari (there is also a theory that states that no night attack was proposed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the night attack proposed by Sakon, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU and Yukinaga KONISHI at that night was not approved by Mitsunari (there is also a theory that states that no night attack was proposed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the night attack proposed by Sakon, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU and Yukinaga KONISHI at that night was not approved by Mitsunari (there is also a theory that states that no night attack was proposed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>夜襲策の出典は「日本戦史（旧日本軍参謀本部編）」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plan of the night attack was written in the &apos;History of Japanese Warfare (Old Japanese Military staff headquarters)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>旧日本軍参謀本部編はOld Japanese Military Staff Headquartersと訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plan of the night attack was written in the &apos;History of Japanese Warfare (Old Japanese Military staff headquarters)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plan of the night attack was written in the &apos;History of Japanese Warfare (Old Japanese Military staff headquarters)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>関ヶ原の戦い本戦においては、最初は西軍有利に進み、左近も自ら陣頭に立ち奮戦するが黒田長政の鉄砲隊に横合いから銃撃され負傷、一時撤退する（この時、死亡したとも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the final battle of the Battle of Sekigahara, the &apos;western&apos; army gained an advantage at first and Sakon took the lead and fought bravely, but he was wounded by shooting sideways by a firearms troop of Nagamasa KURODA and withdrew temporarily (it is also said that he died at this time).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the final battle of the Battle of Sekigahara, the &apos;western&apos; army was the first to gain an advantage and Sakon took the lead and fought bravely, but he was shot from the flank by Nagamasa KURODA&apos;s firearm unit and made a temporary retreat (it is also said that he died at this time).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency and to correctly reflect the source text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the final battle of the Battle of Sekigahara, the &apos;western&apos; army was the first to gain an advantage and Sakon took the lead and fought bravely, but he was shot from the flank by Nagamasa KURODA&apos;s firearm unit and made a temporary retreat (it is also said that he died at this time).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧内へ移動→ピリオドを括弧内の外へ出しました。（括弧内文の最初が小文字になっているため）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>正午過ぎ、小早川秀秋の寝返りを皮切りに西軍は総崩れとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After noon, the &apos;western&apos; army collapsed completely due to betrayal of Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After noon, the &apos;western&apos; army collapsed completely due to betrayal by Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>of &gt; by</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After noon, the &apos;western&apos; army collapsed completely due to betrayal by Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>左近は討ち死にを覚悟して再び出陣、正面の田中吉政・黒田長政らの軍に突撃し、奮戦した末に敵の銃撃により討ち死にしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakon took departure for the front again while preparing for death in battle, attacked the army of Yoshimasa TANAKA, Nagamasa KURODA and so on at the front, and fought bravely, but was shot dead by the enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakon prepared to die in battle and once again departed for the front where he attacked the armies of Yoshimasa TANAKA, Nagamasa KURODA and others in assault in which it is said that he fought bravely but was shot dead by the enemy.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakon prepared to die in battle and once again departed for the front where he attacked the armies of Yoshimasa TANAKA, Nagamasa KURODA and others in assault in which it is said that he fought bravely but was shot dead by the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>江戸初期、筑前福岡城において関が原に出陣し島を目撃した武将達が島の服装について若侍相手に語り合ったが、物指、陣羽織、具足に至るまでそれぞれの記憶が違い、これは島のあまりの恐ろしさの故に記憶が定かではなかったためとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, busho (Japanese military commanders) who fought in Sekigahara and witnessed Shima told young samurai about the clothes of Shima, but their memories of his ruler, Jinbaori (sleeveless campaign jacket worn over armor) and armor were different from each other, and it is said that it was because their memories were hazy due to the horrible appearance of Shima.</e>
<cmt>物指は、rulerとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, busho (Japanese military commanders) who fought in Sekigahara and witnessed Shima told young samurai about the clothes of Shima, but their memories of his measurements, jinbaori (sleeveless campaign jacket worn over armor) and armor differed, and it is said that this was because their memories were hazy due to the horrible appearance of Shima.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, busho (Japanese military commanders) who fought in Sekigahara and witnessed Shima told young samurai about the clothes of Shima, but their memories of his measurements, jinbaori (sleeveless campaign jacket worn over armor) and armor differed, and it is said that this was because their memories were hazy due to the horrible appearance of Shima.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>異説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Different opinion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Different Theories</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Different Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="32">
<j>この説は、関ヶ原の合戦で戦死した西軍大将として大谷吉継と共に首が見つかっておらず（大谷吉継の場合は側近の湯浅五助が切腹の介錯を行い、首級を埋めた場所を語らず死亡したため発見されなかった）、さらには合戦後に京都で左近を目撃したと称する者が相次いだためとされているが、真相は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory is based on a fact that the heads of Sakon and Yoshitsugu Otani, taisho of the &apos;western&apos; army who died in the Battle of Sekigahara, were not found (in case of Yoshitsugu Otani, his close adviser, Gosuke YUASA, assisted him in committing hara-kiri by beheading him and died without telling where the head was buried, and therefore it was not found), and there were many people who said that they saw Sakon in Kyoto after the battle, but the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory is based on the fact that the heads of Sakon and Yoshitsugu Otani, taisho of the &apos;western&apos; army who died in the Battle of Sekigahara, were never found (in the case of Yoshitsugu Otani, his close adviser, Gosuke YUASA, assisted him in committing hara-kiri by beheading him and later died without telling anyone where the head was buried, and it was therefore never found), and there were many people who said that they saw Sakon in Kyoto after the battle, but the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory is based on the fact that the heads of Sakon and Yoshitsugu OTANI, taisho of the &apos;western&apos; army who died in the Battle of Sekigahara, were never found (in the case of Yoshitsugu OTANI, his close adviser, Gosuke YUASA, assisted him in committing Seppuku [suicide by disembowelment] by beheading him and later died without telling anyone where the head was buried, and it was therefore never found), and there were many people who said that they saw Sakon in Kyoto after the battle, but the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>文章が繋がらないためウェブで確認したところ、この前に来るべき文が抜けていますが、原文どおりに訳しております。Otani→OTANI切腹の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、京都市の立本寺には島清興の墓があり、また位牌や過去帳も塔頭に残されていることから、関ヶ原の戦い後、逃れてこの寺の僧として、32年後に死去したとされている点がその根拠となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is based on a fact that there is a tomb of Kiyooki SHIMA in Ryuhon-ji Temple of Kyoto City and his Buddhist mortuary tablet and family register of deaths remain in a sub-temple, especially one founded to commemorate the death of a high priest, and it is said that Shima escaped after the Battle of Sekigahara and died as a priest of this temple 32 years after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is based on a fact that there is a tomb of Kiyooki SHIMA in Ryuhon-ji Temple in Kyoto City and his Buddhist mortuary tablet and family register of deaths remain in a sub-temple, in particular one founded to commemorate the death of a high priest, and it is said that Shima escaped after the Battle of Sekigahara and died as a priest of this temple 32 years later.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is based on a fact that there is a tomb of Kiyooki SHIMA in Ryuhon-ji Temple in Kyoto City and his Buddhist mortuary tablet and family register of deaths remain in a sub-temple, in particular one founded to commemorate the death of a high priest, and it is said that Shima escaped after the Battle of Sekigahara and died as a priest of this temple 32 years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hatabon(id:146971), Kanejan(id:78613), 石井田健四朗(id:97044), Hannah(id:15935), Cprobot(id:97843), HI(id:72996), ＤＦ．Ｋｉｎｇ(id:48817), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Snap55(id:89773), Dusk00(id:48236), How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Hate the Bomb(id:297350), Bentley(id:27731), Goki(id:7107), 代言人(id:33675), Loveless(id:129239), こぶまき(id:38278), Kouko0515(id:100370), KASAGI(id:24405), M-sho-gun(id:88956), ゆず湯(id:190382), Bergmann(id:85282), Raff(id:14006), 水野白楓(id:22811), Nippon Dog(id:107912), くしなだ(id:16095), Yanahan(id:2437), 葉月(id:25674), Aboshi(id:9318), Kagetudo(id:163875), 前田左衛門佐(id:194701), YurikBot(id:18605), Nonnonba(id:124424), Fievarsty(id:201483), Snowchild-152(id:265254), 暇編集(id:222403), Jmho(id:10472), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>