<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>有吉熊次郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumajiro ARIYOSHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumajiro ARIYOSHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumajiro ARIYOSHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>有吉 熊次郎（ありよし くまじろう、天保13年（1842年） - 元治元年7月19日 (旧暦)（1864年8月20日））は、日本の武士･長州藩、尊皇攘夷派の志士。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumajiro ARIYOSHI (1842-August 20, 1864) was a Japanese samurai, a patriot who belonged to Sonno-Joi-ha (supporters of the principle of advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) from the Cyoshu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumajiro ARIYOSHI (1842-August 20, 1864) was a Japanese samurai, a patriot who belonged to Sonno-Joi-ha (supporters of the principle of advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) from the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>Cyoshu→Choshuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumajiro ARIYOSHI (1842-August 20, 1864) was a Japanese samurai, a patriot who belonged to Sonno-Joi-ha (supporters of the principle of advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) from the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>熊次郎は通称で、諱は良明（もしくは良朋）、字は子徳、本姓は藤原を称し、墓碑の刻字には藤原良明とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was commonly called Kumajiro; his real name was 良明 or 良朋; his by-name was Shitoku; his main name was FUJIWARA; and the epitaph on his gravestone was 藤原良明.</e>
<cmt>「良明」の読み方がはっきりわからなかったので、漢字のみ入れました。「字」の定訳がわからなかったので、「by-name」を使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was commonly called Kumajiro; his real name was Yoshiaki (良明) or Yoshitomo (良朋); his by-name was Shitoku; his main name was FUJIWARA; and the epitaph on his gravestone was Yoshiaki FUJIWARA (藤原良明).</e>
<cmt>良明→Yoshiaki (良明)、良朋→Yoshitomo (良朋)、藤原良明→Yoshiaki FUJIWARA (藤原良明)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was commonly called Kumajiro; his real name was Yoshiaki (良明) or Yoshitomo (良朋); his by-name was Shitoku; his main name was FUJIWARA; and the epitaph on his gravestone was Yoshiaki FUJIWARA (藤原良明).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>贈正五位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded the title of Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was awarded the posthumous rank of Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>title→posthumous rankとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was awarded the posthumous rank of Shogoi (Senior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>作家有吉佐和子の曾祖父にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a great-grandfather of a novelist, Sawako ARIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a great-grandfather of a novelist, Sawako ARIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a great-grandfather of a novelist, Sawako ARIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>天保13年（1842年）、長州藩士有吉忠助の次男（近習有吉傳十郎の弟）として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1843, he was born as the second son of a feudal retainer of the Choshu clan, Tadasuke ARIYOSHI (a younger brother of a kinju [attendant], 傳十郎 ARIYOSHI).</e>
<cmt>「傳十郎」の読み方がはっきりわからなかったので（「でんじゅうろう」かとも思いましたが）、漢字のみ入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1842, he was born as the second son of a feudal retainer of the Choshu clan, Tadasuke ARIYOSHI (a younger brother of a kinju [attendant], Denjuro [傳十郎] ARIYOSHI).</e>
<cmt>1843→1842に修正、傳十郎→Denjuro [傳十郎]としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1842, he was born as the second son of a feudal retainer of the Choshu clan, Tadasuke ARIYOSHI (a younger brother of a kinju [attendant], Denjuro [傳十郎] ARIYOSHI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藩校の明倫館に学んだのち、安政4年（1857年）、16歳の時に土屋蕭海の紹介により吉田松陰の松下村塾に入塾する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After studying at hanko (a domain school) called Meirinkan, in 1857, at the age of 16, he entered to Matsushitamura Juku School by Shoin YOSHIDA introduced by Shokai TSUCHIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After studying at hanko (a domain school) called Meirinkan, in 1857, at the age of 16, he entered Shoka Sonjuku School by Shoin YOSHIDA introduced by Shokai TSUCHIYA.</e>
<cmt>entered to→entered、Matsushitamura Juku→Shoka Sonjukuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After studying at hanko (a domain school) called Meirinkan, in 1857, at the age of 16, he entered Shoka Sonjuku School by Shoin YOSHIDA introduced by Shokai TSUCHIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>松陰は、「才」の岡部富太郎（子揖）、「実直」の有吉（子徳）、「沈毅」の寺島忠三郎（子大）と評して、この3名を一つのグループとして力にしようと考えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoin valued Tomitaro OKABE (子揖 Shiyu) of &apos;intelligence&apos;, ARIYOSHI (子徳 Shitoku) of &apos;honesty&apos;, and Chuzaburo TERAJIMA (子大 Shidai) of &apos;composure&apos;, and was contemplating making these three a group which would help him.</e>
<cmt>「子揖、子徳、子大」の読みをすべて通常の音読みで入れました。「力にしようと」の文意が解釈しづらかったので、「松陰の力となるようなグループにしようと」というように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoin valued Tomitaro OKABE (子揖 Shiyu) of &apos;intelligence,&apos; Ariyoshi (子徳 Shitoku) of &apos;honesty,&apos; and Chuzaburo TERAJIMA (子大 Shidai) of &apos;composure,&apos; and was contemplating making these three a group which would help him.</e>
<cmt>ARIYOSHI→Ariyoshiとし、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、カンマの位置を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoin valued Tomitaro OKABE (子揖 Shiyu) of &apos;intelligence,&apos; Ariyoshi (子徳 Shitoku) of &apos;honesty,&apos; and Chuzaburo TERAJIMA (子大 Shidai) of &apos;composure,&apos; and was contemplating making these three a group which would help him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>安政5年（1858年）、松陰の老中間部詮勝暗殺計画に血盟をしたことから、外叔の白根多助により家に幽閉される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1858, accused of his sealing a written pledge of the assassination scheme of Roju (senior councils of the Tokugawa shogunate) Akikatsu MANABE planned by Shoin with his blood, he was put under house arrest by his uncle in his mother&apos;s line, Tasuke SHIRANE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1858, accused of his sealing a written pledge of the assassination scheme of Roju (senior councils of the Tokugawa shogunate) Akikatsu MANABE planned by Shoin with his blood, he was put under house arrest by his uncle in his mother&apos;s line, Tasuke SHIRANE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1858, accused of his sealing a written pledge of the assassination scheme of Roju (senior councils of the Tokugawa shogunate) Akikatsu MANABE planned by Shoin with his blood, he was put under house arrest by his uncle in his mother&apos;s line, Tasuke SHIRANE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>松陰が野山獄に再投獄された際は、その罪状を問うために周布政之助ら重役宅に押しかけた塾生8名の中の一人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was one of eight Matsushitamura Juku School students who rushed to the houses of executives such as Masanosuke SUFU in order to inquire the reason for Shoin&apos;s criminal charge when Shoin was put in Noyama Prison again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was one of eight Shoka Sonjuku School students who rushed to the houses of executives such as Masanosuke SUFU in order to inquire the reason for Shoin&apos;s criminal charge when Shoin was put in Noyama Prison again.</e>
<cmt>Matsushitamura Juku→Shoka Sonjukuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was one of eight Shoka Sonjuku School students who rushed to the houses of executives such as Masanosuke SUFU in order to inquire the reason for Shoin&apos;s criminal charge when Shoin was put in Noyama Prison again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>文久元年（1861年）、高杉晋作に随い御番手として江戸へ遊学、桜田の藩邸内にある有備館に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1861, he went to Edo as an obante (a guard to defend Edo Bay) accompanying Shinsaku TAKASUGI for study purposes, and stayed in Yubikan on the premise of the Choshu hantei (the residence maintained by a daimyo) in Sakurada.</e>
<cmt>「御番手」を「江戸湾を警備する警備員」としました。(参考http://www.webkohbo.com/info3/takasugi/shanghai.html)「藩邸」のみだと意味がわかりづらいかと思ったので、「長州藩邸」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1861, he went to Edo as an obante (a guard to defend Edo Bay) accompanying Shinsaku TAKASUGI for study purposes, and stayed in Yubikan on the premises of the Choshu hantei (the residence maintained by a daimyo) in Sakurada.</e>
<cmt>premise→premisesに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1861, he went to Edo as an obante (a guard to defend Edo Bay) accompanying Shinsaku TAKASUGI for study purposes, and stayed in Yubikan on the premises of the Choshu hantei (the residence maintained by a daimyo) in Sakurada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>文久2年（1862年）、高杉ら同志と武州金澤（金沢八景）で外国公使を刺殺しようとしたが、計画が事前に藩主世子の毛利定広に伝わったため実行に到らず、謹慎を命ぜられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1862, he attempted to assassinate a foreign minister in Kanazawa, Musashi Province with his fellow members including TAKASUGI, but the scheme was known to the heir of the lord of the domain, Sadahiro MORI, in advance and was not put into practice, and then the members were ordered confinement to the hantei.</e>
<cmt>「謹慎」が、この場合「藩邸内に謹慎」だと思いますので、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1862, he attempted to assassinate a foreign minister in Kanazawa, Musashi Province with his fellow members including Takasugi, but the scheme was known to the heir of the lord of the domain, Sadahiro MORI, in advance and was not put into practice, and then the members were ordered confinement to the hantei.</e>
<cmt>TAKASUGI→Takasugiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1862, he attempted to assassinate a foreign minister in Kanazawa, Musashi Province with his fellow members including Takasugi, but the scheme was known to the heir of the lord of the domain, Sadahiro MORI, in advance and was not put into practice, and then the members were ordered confinement to the hantei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>謹慎中の同志は御楯組結成の血盟書を作る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fellow members under confinement made a written pledge to form a group named Mitategumi and sealed it with their blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fellow members under confinement made a written pledge to form a group named Mitategumi and sealed it with their blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fellow members under confinement made a written pledge to form a group named Mitategumi and sealed it with their blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この時に血判署名した同志は有吉を含む、高杉、久坂玄瑞、大和弥八郎、長嶺内蔵太、志道聞多（井上馨）、松島剛蔵、寺島、赤禰幹之丞（赤根武人）、山尾庸三、品川弥二郎の11名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The members who sealed the pledge on this occasion were these eleven: TAKASUGI, Genzui KUSAKA, Yahachiro YAMATO, Kurata NAGAMINE, Monta SHIZI (Kaoru INOUE), Gozo MATSUSHIMA, TERAJIMA, Mikinojo AKANE (Taketo AKANE), Yozo YAMAO, Yajiro SHINAGAWA, and ARIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>「寺島」の読み方が、ウェブ上で「てらしま」としているものがありましたが、</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The members who sealed the pledge on this occasion were these eleven: Takasugi, Genzui KUSAKA, Yahachiro YAMATO, Kurata NAGAMINE, Monta SHIJI (Kaoru INOUE), Gozo MATSUSHIMA, Terajima, Mikinojo AKANE (Taketo AKANE), Yozo YAMAO, Yajiro SHINAGAWA, and Ariyoshi.</e>
<cmt>TAKASUGI→Takasugi、TERAJIMA→Terajima、ARIYOSHI→Ariyoshiとし、SHIZI→SHIJIに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The members who sealed the pledge on this occasion were these eleven: Takasugi, Genzui KUSAKA, Yahachiro YAMATO, Kurata NAGAMINE, Monta SHIJI (Kaoru INOUE), Gozo MATSUSHIMA, Terajima, Mikinojo AKANE (Taketo AKANE), Yozo YAMAO, Yajiro SHINAGAWA, and Ariyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>同年、品川御殿山の英国公使館焼き討ち事件に参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he took part in the fire attack of the legation of Britain located in Shinagawa Gotenyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he took part in the fire attack of the legation of Britain located in Shinagawa Gotenyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he took part in the fire attack of the legation of Britain located in Shinagawa Gotenyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>文久3年（1863年）、藩命により航海術を学び、その後京都学習院への出仕を命じられ、京洛での尊攘運動に邁進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1863, he studied seamanship by orders of his clan, and then was ordered to serve in Kyoto Gakushuin School, where in capital Kyoto he pushed forward with the Sonjo (Sonno-Joi) movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1863, he studied seamanship by orders of his clan, and then was ordered to serve in Kyoto Gakushuin School, where in capital Kyoto he pushed forward with the Sonjo (Sonno-Joi) movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1863, he studied seamanship by orders of his clan, and then was ordered to serve in Kyoto Gakushuin School, where in capital Kyoto he pushed forward with the Sonjo (Sonno-Joi) movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同年、八月十八日の政変により帰国後、久坂、堀真五郎らと山口にて八幡隊を結成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, after returning to Choshu due to the Political Change on August 18, he formed a group named Hachimantai with KUSAKA, Shingoro HORI and other members in Yamaguchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, after returning to Choshu due to the Coup of August 18 (September 30 in new calendar), he formed a group named Hachimantai with Kusaka, Shingoro HORI and other members in Yamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>KUSAKA→Kusakaとし、「政変」の統一事項に基づき、the Coup of August 18に修正、カッコ内に新暦表記を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, after returning to Choshu due to the Coup of August 18 (September 30 in new calendar), he formed a group named Hachimantai with Kusaka, Shingoro HORI and other members in Yamaguchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>元治元年（1864年）の池田屋事件では、吉田稔麿ら同志と会合中に新選組に襲撃されるが、乱闘から長州藩邸に逃げ込み、事件の生き証人としてその悲報を国許に伝える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ikedaya Incident in 1864, he was attacked by Shinsengumi during the meeting with other fellow members including Toshimaro YOSHIDA, but escaped from the scuffle to the Choshu hantei, and then went to inform the people in Choshu Domain of this sad news as a witness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ikedaya Incident in 1864, he was attacked by Shinsengumi during the meeting with other fellow members including Toshimaro YOSHIDA, but escaped from the scuffle to the Choshu hantei, and then went to inform the people in the Choshu Domain of this sad news as a witness.</e>
<cmt>the Choshu Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ikedaya Incident in 1864, he was attacked by Shinsengumi during the meeting with other fellow members including Toshimaro YOSHIDA, but escaped from the scuffle to the Choshu hantei, and then went to inform the people in the Choshu Domain of this sad news as a witness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その際、事件により厳重警戒中の京都を飛脚に変装して出立している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, he disguised himself as a hikyaku (an express messenger in the old days) to leave Kyoto under a strict watch due to the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, he disguised himself as a hikyaku (an express messenger in the old days) to leave Kyoto under a strict watch due to the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, he disguised himself as a hikyaku (an express messenger in the old days) to leave Kyoto under a strict watch due to the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>同年、急進派の藩士らと上京、禁門の変（蛤御門の変）において重傷を負い、久坂、寺島らとともに鷹司邸内で自刃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, he went to Kyoto with other feudal retainers of the radical party, and in the Kinmon Incident (the rebellion at the Hamaguri-gomon Gate), he got severely injured and killed himself in the Takatsukasa House and so did KUSAKA and TERAJIMA.</e>
<cmt>「蛤御門の変」を「the rebellion at the Hamaguri-gomon Gate」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, he went to Kyoto with other feudal retainers of the radical party, and in the Kinmon Incident (the rebellion at the Hamaguri-gomon Gate), he got severely injured and killed himself in the Takatsukasa House and so did Kusaka and Terajima.</e>
<cmt>KUSAKA→Kusaka、TERAJIMA→Terajimaとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, he went to Kyoto with other feudal retainers of the radical party, and in the Kinmon Incident (the rebellion at the Hamaguri-gomon Gate), he got severely injured and killed himself in the Takatsukasa House and so did Kusaka and Terajima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>享年23。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The age of death was 23.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died at the age of 23.</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 23.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>墓所は京都市の京都霊山護国神社、山口市の朝日山招魂社（八幡隊招魂場）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His graveyards are located in Kyoto Ryozen Gokoku-jinja Shrine, in Kyoto City, and Mt. Asahi Shokon-sha Shrine in Yamaguchi City (Hachimantai Shokonjo [a shrine made for enshrining Hachimantai members who died for the nation]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His graveyards are located in Kyoto Ryozen Gokoku-jinja Shrine, in Kyoto City, and Mt. Asahi Shokon-sha Shrine in Yamaguchi City (Hachimantai Shokonjo [a shrine made for enshrining Hachimantai members who died for the nation]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His graveyards are located in Kyoto Ryozen Gokoku-jinja Shrine, in Kyoto City, and Mt. Asahi Shokon-sha Shrine in Yamaguchi City (Hachimantai Shokonjo [a shrine made for enshrining Hachimantai members who died for the nation]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Cprobot(id:97843), Zzzz(id:16596), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>