<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一色義春</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>一色 義春（いっしき よしはる、文正元年（1466年） - 文明 (日本)16年9月4日 (旧暦)（1484年9月23日））は室町時代の守護大名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu ISSHIKI (1466 - September 23, 1484) was a Shugo Daimyo (protector feudal lords) who lived in Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu ISSHIKI (1466 - September 23, 1484) was a Shugo Daimyo (protector feudal lords) who lived during the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu ISSHIKI (1466 - October 2, 1484) was a Shugo Daimyo (protector feudal lords) who lived during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>ユリウス→グレゴリオ暦に修正、Muromachi periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一色義直の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the heir of Yoshinao ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the heir of Yoshinao ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the heir of Yoshinao ISSHIKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>五郎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was called Goro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was called Goro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was called Goro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>左京大夫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His position was Sagyo no Daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His position was Sagyo no Daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His position was Sakyo no Daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices).</e>
<cmt>Sagyo no Daibu→Sakyo no Daibuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>妻は山名教豊の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Noritoyo YAMANA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was a daughter of Noritoyo YAMANA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was a daughter of Noritoyo YAMANA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>文明 (日本)5年（1473年）、応仁の乱の東西両軍の総帥山名宗全と細川勝元が相次いで没し、足利義尚の将軍職就任が実現すると、和睦の気運が高まり、翌文明6年（1474年）4月に山名政豊と細川政元との間で和議が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1473, the leaders of Eastern and Western Camps in the Onin battle, Sozen YAMANA and Katsujmoto HOSOKAWA died in succession and Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA assumed the post of Shogun, wish to peace became stronger and next year, in April 1474, peace was concluded between Masatoyo YAMANA and Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1473, the leaders of Eastern and Western Camps in the Onin battle, Sozen YAMANA and Katsujmoto HOSOKAWA died in succession and Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA assumed the post of Shogun, wishing for peace to become stronger and the next year, in April 1474, peace was concluded between Masatoyo YAMANA and Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1473, the leaders of Eastern and Western Camps in the Onin War, Sozen YAMANA and Katsujmoto HOSOKAWA died in succession and Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA assumed the post of Shogun, wishing for peace to become stronger and the next year, in April 1474, peace was concluded between Masatoyo YAMANA and Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、Onin battle→Onin Warに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一色氏ではこれまで西軍に属して戦ってきた一色義直が東軍に帰順、隠居して家督を嫡男義春に譲ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Isshiki clan, Yoshinao ISSHIKI who had fought on the Western Camp side returned to allegiance to the Eastern Camp and it was decided that Yoshinao should retire and surrender the headship of the family to his heir Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Isshiki clan, Yoshinao ISSHIKI who had fought on the Western Camp side returned his allegiance to the Eastern Camp and it was decided that Yoshinao would retire and surrender the headship of the family to his heir Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Isshiki clan, Yoshinao ISSHIKI who had fought on the Western Camp side returned his allegiance to the Eastern Camp and it was decided that Yoshinao would retire and surrender the headship of the family to his heir Yoshiharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>同年閏5月、義春は応仁の乱以来、武田氏・細川氏に奪われていた丹後国守護を取り戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In intercalary fifth month in the same year, Yoshiharu retrieved the position of Shugo (provincial constable) for Tango Province that had been taken by the Takeda clan and Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the intercalary fifth month of the same year, Yoshiharu retrieved the position of Shugo (provincial constable) for Tango Province that had been taken by the Takeda and Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the intercalary sixth month of the same year, Yoshiharu retrieved the position of Shugo (provincial constable) for Tango Province that had been taken by the Takeda and Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>丹後では武田氏・細川氏配下の武将が所領返還を行おうとせず、合戦となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tango, busho (Japanese military commander) under the Takeda clan and Hosokawa clan did not return the fief and a battle occurred.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tango, busho (Japanese military commander) under the Takeda clan and Hosokawa clan did not return the fief and a battle occurred.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tango, busho (Japanese military commander) under the Takeda clan and Hosokawa clan did not return the fief and a battle occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>若狭国守護武田国信は4月に交わされた和議に参加していたため、援軍を送ることができず、同年9月、丹後に在った武田軍の主将逸見真正が自害し、一色氏の丹後での旧領回復は順調に進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Kuninobu TAKEDA, who was the Shugo for Wakasa Province, could not send any reinforcement because he was a party to a peace treaty made in April and, therefore, 逸見真正=&gt;? HENMI[定訳不明] who was the leader of the Takeda Camp in Tango committed a suicide in September, and recovery of the fief of the Isshiki clan in Tango developed smoothly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Kuninobu TAKEDA, who was the Shugo for Wakasa Province, could not send any reinforcements because he was party to a peace treaty made in April and, therefore, 逸見真正=&gt;? HENMI[定訳不明] who was the leader of the Takeda Camp in Tango committed suicide in September, and they smoothly recovered the fief of the Isshiki clan in Tango.</e>
<cmt>Grammar Robert: still unsure of translation of word in question</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Kuninobu TAKEDA, who was the Shugo for Wakasa Province, could not send any reinforcements because he was party to a peace treaty made in April and, therefore, ? HENMI (逸見真正) who was the leader of the Takeda Camp in Tango committed suicide in September, and they smoothly recovered the fief of the Isshiki clan in Tango.</e>
<cmt>&quot;逸見真正→? HENMI[定訳不明]&quot;→? HENMI (逸見真正)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>文明9年（1477年）5月、室町幕府は北畠政郷に与えていた伊勢国北半国守護職を義春に与えたため、伊勢において北畠軍と一色軍の間で合戦が起こり、北畠軍が勝利している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1477, as the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) gave the position of Shugoshoku for the half of Ise Province, which had been given to Masasato KITABATAKE, a battle occurred in Ise between the Kitabatake Camp and Isshiki Camp and the Kitabatake Camp won the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1477, as the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) gave the position of Shugoshoku for half of Ise Province, which had been given to Masasato KITABATAKE, a battle occurred in Ise between the Kitabatake Camp and Isshiki Camp in which the Kitabatake Camp won the battle.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1477, as the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) gave the position of Shugoshoku for half of Ise Province, which had been given to Masasato KITABATAKE, a battle occurred in Ise between the Kitabatake Camp and Isshiki Camp in which the Kitabatake Camp won the battle.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>文明10年（1478年）、父義直の幕府出仕が認められ、その後見を得て幕政に参与したが、文明16年（1484年）9月4日病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1473, his father, Yoshinao, was allowed to enter the service of the bakufu and, thanks to his support, Yoshiharu was involved in the administration by the bakufu but he died on September 4, 1484.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1473, his father, Yoshinao, was allowed to enter the service of the bakufu and, thanks to his support, Yoshiharu was involved in the administration by the bakufu but died on September 4, 1484.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1478, his father, Yoshinao, was allowed to enter the service of the bakufu and, thanks to his support, Yoshiharu was involved in the administration by the bakufu but died on October 2, 1484.</e>
<cmt>In 1473→In 1478に修正、およびファイル冒頭の日付表記より、September 4, 1484 (旧暦)→October 2, 1484に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>享年19。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was nineteen years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was nineteen years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was nineteen years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>義春を信頼していた将軍義尚は、その死を悼み猿楽の興行を中止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihisa, who was Shogun and trusted Yoshiharu, mourned his death and stopped performance of Sarugaku (present Noh).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihisa, who was Shogun and trusted Yoshiharu, mourned his death and stopped performance of Sarugaku (present Noh).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihisa, who was Shogun and trusted Yoshiharu, mourned his death and stopped performance of Sarugaku (present Noh).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>丹後守護には義直が再任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Shugo for Tango, Yoshinao was reappointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Shugo for Tango, Yoshinao was reappointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Shugo for Tango, Yoshinao was reappointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), Nalc(id:139567), GAVVA(id:47103), Cprobot(id:97843), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>