<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>広大院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodaiin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodaiin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodaiin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>広大院（こうだいいん、安永 (元号)2年6月18日 (旧暦)（1773年8月6日） - 天保15年11月10日 (旧暦)（1844年12月19日））は江戸時代後期の女性で、11代将軍・徳川家斉正室（御台所）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodaiin (August 6, 1773 - December 19, 1844) was a lady in the late Edo period and a lawful wife of the 11th shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodaiin (August 6, 1773 - December 19, 1844) was a lady in the late Edo period and a lawful wife of the 11th shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;lawful&quot;の前の空白を半角分削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodaiin (August 6, 1773 - December 19, 1844) was a lady in the late Edo period and a lawful wife of the 11th shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>実父は薩摩藩8代藩主・島津重豪、実母は側室・市田氏（慈光院 (島津重豪側室)）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father was the 8th lord of Satsuma domain Shigehide SHIMAZU and the mother was a noble&apos;s concubine Ichidashi (Jikoin (a concubine to Shigehide SHIMAZU)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father was the 8th lord of Satsuma domain Shigehide SHIMAZU and the mother was his concubine from Ichida family (Jikoin).</e>
<cmt>すでに夫の名前が直前に書かれているので、「側室」の訳中の&quot;noble&apos;s&quot; を his に変更しました。  「市田氏」をそのまま Ichidashi とするとわかりにくいのではないかと思い、念のため from Ichida family としておきました。  原文の最後のカッコ書きの(島津重豪側室)の部分は、前の部分と同じことなので、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father was the 8th lord of Satsuma domain Shigehide SHIMAZU and the mother was his concubine from Ichida family (Jikoin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>市田氏は薩摩藩大坂蔵屋敷の足軽という下級武士階級の出身であるとされるが異説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichidashi was said to be from the family of low rank-ranking samurai ashigaru (common foot soldier) to Osaka kurayashiki (warehouse-residence) of Satsuma domain while there existed other rumors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Ichida family was from lower-ranking samurai ashigaru (common foot soldier) of Osaka kurayashiki (warehouse-residence) of Satsuma domain while other theories exist.</e>
<cmt>前文同様、Ichidashi を Ichida family に訂正しました。 それに伴い、関連する他の部分も大幅に訂正しました。 「異説もある」部分の時制を整え、rumor ではなくtheory に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Ichida family was from lower-ranking samurai ashigaru (common foot soldier) of Osaka kurayashiki (warehouse-residence) of Satsuma domain while other theories exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>養父は近衛経熙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her foster father was Tsunehiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her foster father was Tsunehiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her foster father was Tsunehiro KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>実名は寧姫、篤姫、茂姫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her real names were Yasushihime, Atsuhime and Shigehime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her real names were Yasushihime, Atsuhime and Shigehime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real names were Yasushihime, Atsuhime and Shigehime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後に天璋院が「篤姫」を名乗ったのは広大院にあやかったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshoin&apos;s nanori (announcement of her name) of Atsuhime at later date was shared from Kodaiin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Tenshoin announced her name as Atsuhime following the example of Kodaiin.</e>
<cmt>Toshoin&apos;s nanori というのはわかりにくいので（そもそもToshoin というのは間違いです）、文章自体を大幅に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Tenshoin announced her name as Atsuhime following the example of Kodaiin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>弟に奥平昌高（実の生母は鈴木氏の娘）、姉に敬姫（奥平昌男婚約者）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She had younger brother Masataka OKUDAIRA (biological mother was a daughter of Suzuki clan) and elder sister Keihime (fiancée to Masao OKUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She had a younger brother Masataka OKUDAIRA (biological mother was a daughter of Suzuki clan) and an elder sister Keihime (fiancée to Masao OKUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt>younger の前と elder の前に冠詞をつけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She had a younger brother Masataka OKUDAIRA (biological mother was a daughter of Suzuki clan) and an elder sister Keihime (fiancée to Masao OKUDAIRA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>婚約・御台所へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was engaged and became Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her engagement and a path to Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman)</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので、それらしく訳しなおしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her engagement and a path to Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>茂姫は安永 (元号)2年（1773年）6月18日 (旧暦)に鹿児島城で誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigehime was born June 18 (old calendar), 1773 in Kagoshima-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigehime was born on June 18 (old lunar calendar), 1773 in Kagoshima-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>born の後に on を加え、旧暦の訳を old lunar calendar に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigehime was born on June 18 (old lunar calendar), 1773 in Kagoshima-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>最初の名は「篤姫」「於篤」といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was first called &quot;Astuhime&quot; and &quot;Oatsushi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was first called &quot;Atsuhime&quot; and &quot;Oatsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「於篤」の読みを訂正しました。ピリオドの位置を訂正しました。　　スペルミス： Astuhime → Atsuhime に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was first called &quot;Atsuhime&quot; and &quot;Oatsu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>茂姫は誕生後、そのまま国許の薩摩にて養育されていたが、徳川治済の息子・豊千代（後の徳川家斉）と3歳のときに婚約し、薩摩から江戸に呼び寄せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after her birth, she was sent and reared in her hometown Satsuma but she was called to Edo from Satsuma when she was engaged with Toyochiyo (later day Ienari TOKUGAWA), the son of Harusada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After her birth, she was raised in her hometown Satsuma but she was called to Edo from Satsuma when she was engaged with Toyochiyo (later day Ienari TOKUGAWA), the son of Harusada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>最初のsoon は文脈から不必要と考え、削除しました。生まれた鹿児島城は薩摩内にあると思われるので、sent の部分を削除しました。reared → raised に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After her birth, she was raised in her hometown Satsuma but she was called to Edo from Satsuma when she was engaged with Toyochiyo (later day Ienari TOKUGAWA), the son of Harusada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その婚約の際に名を篤姫から茂姫に改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of this engagement, she changed her name from Atsuhime to Shigehime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of this engagement, she changed her name from Atsuhime to Shigehime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of this engagement, she changed her name from Atsuhime to Shigehime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>茂姫は婚約に伴い芝三田の薩摩藩上屋敷から江戸城内の一橋邸に移り住み、「御縁女様」と称されて婚約者の豊千代と共に養育されていたが、10代将軍徳川家治の嫡男徳川家基の急逝で豊千代が次期将軍と定められた際、この婚約が問題となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the engagement, she was called &quot;Goenjosama&quot; and moved from Satsuma clan kamiyashiki in Shiba Mita to Hitotsubashi mansion inside the Edo-jo Castle and reared with Toyochiyo however the 10th shogun Ieharu TOKIGAWA&apos;s legitimate son Iemoto&apos;s unexpected death led to Toyochiyo to be the next shogun, it stirred some problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the engagement, she was called &quot;Goenjosama&quot; and moved from Satsuma clan kamiyashiki in Shiba Mita to Hitotsubashi mansion inside the Edo-jo Castle and was raised with Toyochiyo, however, when the 10th shogun Ieharu TOKIGAWA&apos;s legitimate son Iemoto died unexpectedly and Toyochiyo was decided to be the next shogun, this engagement became a problem.</e>
<cmt>reared → was raised に訂正しました。  However の前後にコンマをつけました。  led to → led 不必要と考え、to を削除しました。　　「この婚約が」以下の部分がわかりにくかったので、however 以降を when の節で始めることで訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the engagement, she was called &quot;Goenjosama&quot; and moved from Satsuma clan kamiyashiki in Shiba Mita to Hitotsubashi mansion inside the Edo-jo Castle and was raised with Toyochiyo, however, when the 10th shogun Ieharu TOKIGAWA&apos;s legitimate son Iemoto died unexpectedly and Toyochiyo was decided to be the next shogun, this engagement became a problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>将軍家の正室は五摂家か宮家の姫というのが慣例で、大名の娘、しかも外様大名の姫というのは全く前例がなかったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a tradition that shogun&apos;s lawful wife must be a daughter from Gosekke (five families of Fujiwara clan) or from Miyake (families allowed to have the status of Imperial family) and it was unprecedented for a daughter of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) let along tozama daimyo (non-Tokugawa daimyo) to become shogun&apos;s lawful wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was because of the tradition that shogun&apos;s lawful wife must be a daughter from Gosekke (five families of Fujiwara clan) or from Miyake (families allowed to have the status of Imperial family) and it was unprecedented for a daughter of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) especially tozama daimyo (non-Tokugawa daimyo) to become shogun&apos;s lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>前文と続いているため、it was a tradition → it was because of the tradition に訂正しました。   Let along の部分がよくわからないので、especially に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was because of the tradition that shogun&apos;s lawful wife must be a daughter from Gosekke (five families of Fujiwara clan) or from Miyake (families allowed to have the status of Imperial family) and it was unprecedented for a daughter of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) especially tozama daimyo (non-Tokugawa daimyo) to become shogun&apos;s lawful wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このとき、この婚約は重豪の義理の祖母に当たる浄岸院の遺言であると重豪は主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her father Shigehide insisted that the marriage arrangement was the will of his mother in law Joganin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her father Shigehide insisted that this engagement was the will of his grandmother in law Joganin.</e>
<cmt>marriage arrangement → engagement に訂正しました。   「祖母」なので mother → grandmother に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her father Shigehide insisted that this engagement was the will of his grandmother in law Joganin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>浄岸院は徳川綱吉・徳川吉宗養女であったため幕府側もこの主張を無視できず、このためこの婚儀は予定通り執り行われることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the fact that Joganin was an adopted child of Tunayoshi TOKUGAWA and Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, Bakufu (Japanese feudal government) was unable overrule his claim and allowed the marriage to take place as planned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the fact that Joganin was an adopted child of Tunayoshi TOKUGAWA and Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, Bakufu (Japanese feudal government) was unable to overrule his claim and allowed the marriage to take place as planned.</e>
<cmt>unable の後にto を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the fact that Joganin was an adopted child of Tunayoshi TOKUGAWA and Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, Bakufu (Japanese feudal government) was unable to overrule his claim and allowed the marriage to take place as planned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>茂姫と家斉の婚儀は婚約から13年後の寛政元年（1789年2月4日）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The marriage of Shigehime and Ienari took place on February 4, 1781, 13 years after the engagement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The marriage of Shigehime and Ienari took place on February 4, 1789, 13 years after the engagement.</e>
<cmt>数字間違い：1781 → 1789 に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The marriage of Shigehime and Ienari took place on February 4, 1789, 13 years after the engagement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>茂姫は天明元年（1781年）10月頃に、豊千代とその生母・お富の方と共に一橋邸から江戸城西の丸に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigehime together with Toyochiyo and his biological mother Otominokata moved to Nishinomaru quarter in the Edo-jo Castle from Hitotsubashi quarter around October 1781.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigehime together with Toyochiyo and his biological mother Otominokata moved to Nishinomaru quarter in the Edo-jo Castle from Hitotsubashi quarter around October 1781.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigehime together with Toyochiyo and his biological mother Otominokata moved to Nishinomaru quarter in the Edo-jo Castle from Hitotsubashi quarter around October 1781.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また将軍家の正室は公家や宮家の娘を迎える事が慣例であるため、茂姫は家斉が将軍に就任する直前の天明7年（1787年）11月15日 (旧暦)に島津家と縁続きであった近衛家及び近衛経熙の養女となるために茂姫から寧姫と名を改め、経熙の娘として家斉に嫁ぐ際、名を再び改めて「近衛寔子（このえただこ）」として結婚することとなったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a tradition and customary for a lawful wife of shogun to be selected from daughters of Kuge (a court noble) and Miyake (families allowed to have the status of Imperial family), so Shigehime changed her name to Yasuhime in order to be an adopted child of Tsunehiro KONOE just prior to Ienaga became shogun on November 15, 1787 and married to Ienaga with yet again changed name as Tadako KONOE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a tradition and customary for a lawful wife of shogun to be selected from daughters of Kuge (a court noble) and Miyake (families allowed to have the status of Imperial family), so Shigehime changed her name to Yasuhime in order to be an adopted child of Tsunehiro KONOE who was related to Shimazu family just prior to Ienari became shogun on November 15, 1787 and married Ienari with yet again changed her name to Tadako KONOE.</e>
<cmt>「家斉」の訳がIenaga となっているので訂正しました。 文法ミス： married to → married に訂正しました。 「島津家と縁続きであった」の部分が訳漏れでしたので、追加しました。　　changed name as → changed her name to に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a tradition and customary for a lawful wife of shogun to be selected from daughters of Kuge (a court noble) and Miyake (families allowed to have the status of Imperial family), so Shigehime changed her name to Yasuhime in order to be an adopted child of Tsunehiro KONOE who was related to Shimazu family just prior to Ienari became shogun on November 15, 1787 and married Ienari with yet again changed her name to Tadako KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、父・重豪の正室・保姫は夫・家斉の父・治済の妹であり、茂姫と家斉は義理のいとこ同士という関係であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also her father Shigehide&apos;s lawful wife Yasuhime was Ienari&apos;s father Harusada&apos;s younger sister and Shigehime and Ienari were cousins in law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also her father Shigehide&apos;s lawful wife Yasuhime was Ienari&apos;s father Harusada&apos;s younger sister and Shigehime and Ienari were cousins in law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also her father Shigehide&apos;s lawful wife Yasuhime was Ienari&apos;s father Harusada&apos;s younger sister and Shigehime and Ienari were cousins in law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>権勢と薩摩藩政への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her reins of power and influence to Satsuma domain governance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her reins of power and influence to Satsuma domain governance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her reins of power and influence to Satsuma domain governance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>この結婚により、島津重豪は前代未聞の「将軍の舅である外様大名」となり、後に「高輪下馬将軍」といわれる権勢の基となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this marriage, Shigehide SHIMAZU became an unprecedented father in law of Shogun that led to form a reins of power later to be called &quot;Takanawa geba shogun&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this marriage, Shigehide SHIMAZU became an unprecedented father in law of Shogun that led to form a reins of power later to be called &quot;Takanawa geba shogun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this marriage, Shigehide SHIMAZU became an unprecedented father in law of Shogun that led to form a reins of power later to be called &quot;Takanawa geba shogun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>一方、実母である市田氏はその権勢により弟の市田盛常を薩摩藩一所持格（本来島津一族でないとなれない地位）に取り立て、同じ重豪側室で島津斉宣の母である公家の娘・堤氏（春光院 (島津重豪側室)）を江戸から鹿児島県に追いだし、自らは重豪の正室同様に振る舞ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her biological mother Ichida on the other hand placed her brother Moritsune ICHIDA to the position of Satsumahan issho mocchi (position only reserved for Shimazu clan) and acted as if she was a lawful wife of Shigehide after sending Shigehide&apos;s another concubine Tsutsumi who was Narinobu SHIMAZU&apos;s mother and a daughter of Kuge (Shunkoin (a concubine of Shigehide SHIMAZU)) to Kagoshima from Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, her biological mother Ichida placed her younger brother Moritsune ICHIDA to the position of Satsumahan issho mochi (position only reserved for Shimazu clan) with her power and acted as if she was a lawful wife of Shigehide after sending Shigehide&apos;s another concubine Tsutsumi who was Narinobu SHIMAZU&apos;s mother and a daughter of Kuge (Shunkoin (a concubine of Shigehide SHIMAZU)) to Kagoshima from Edo.</e>
<cmt>「その権勢により」の部分が訳漏れでしたので、on the other hand を文頭に置き、with her power を後に加えました。　　「弟」なのでbrother の前にyounger を入れました。 スペルミス： mocchi → mochi に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, her biological mother Ichida placed her younger brother Moritsune ICHIDA to the position of Satsumahan issho mochi (position only reserved for Shimazu clan) with her power and acted as if she was a lawful wife of Shigehide after sending Shigehide&apos;s another concubine Tsutsumi who was Narinobu SHIMAZU&apos;s mother and a daughter of Kuge (Shunkoin (a concubine of Shigehide SHIMAZU)) to Kagoshima from Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このような市田一族による薩摩藩政の私物化は後の近思録崩れの原因の一つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reckless management and misappropriation of Satsuma domain finance by Ichida clan led to one of the causes for the occurrence of Kinshikuzure Incident later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reckless management and misappropriation of Satsuma domain governance by Ichida clan led to one of the causes for the occurrence of Kinshiroku-kuzure Incident later.</e>
<cmt>management と and の間の空白を半角分削除しました。「薩摩藩政」の訳がSatsuma domain finance とされていますが、finance の分野に及んだかは原文からは定かではないので、これ以前の訳に合わせてgovernance としました。   Kinshikuzure → Kinshiroku-kuzure に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reckless management and misappropriation of Satsuma domain governance by Ichida clan led to one of the causes for the occurrence of Kinshiroku-kuzure Incident later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>寛政8年（1796年）には家斉の五男・徳川敦之助を産む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She bore a son Atsunosuke TOKUGAWA as the fifth son to Ienari in 1796.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gave birth to a son Atsunosuke TOKUGAWA as the fifth son of Ienari in 1796.</e>
<cmt>bore が不自然なような気がしたので、gave birth to に変更しました。  Son to → son of に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gave birth to a son Atsunosuke TOKUGAWA as the fifth son of Ienari in 1796.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>御台所が男子を出生するのは2代将軍・徳川秀忠正室崇源院以来であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A birth of son by Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun) was since the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s seishitsu (lawful wife).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the first time that Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun) gave birth to a baby boy since the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife did.</e>
<cmt>訳が少々不自然な感じがしたので、大幅に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the first time that Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun) gave birth to a baby boy since the second shogun Hidetada TOKUGAWA&apos;s lawful wife did.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>但し、その3年前に側室が産んだ徳川家慶が将軍家世子と定められていたため、敦之助は御三卿の一つ・清水徳川家の養子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However a son bore by a concubine three years earlier was selected to the heir of shogun, Atsunosuke was adopted by one of gosankyo (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family), Shimizu Tokugawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However a son born to a concubine three years earlier was selected to the heir of shogun, Atsunosuke was adopted by one of gosankyo (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family), Shimizu-Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a son bore by&quot; の部分が不自然なので、&quot;a son born to&quot;に訂正しました。 　「清水徳川家」の訳を定訳に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However a son born to a concubine three years earlier was selected to the heir of shogun, Atsunosuke was adopted by one of gosankyo (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family), Shimizu-Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この慶事により茂姫、及び島津重豪の威勢はますます盛んになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This auspicious event further bolstered Shigehime and Shigehide SHIMAZU&apos;s influence and power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This auspicious event further bolstered Shigehime and Shigehide SHIMAZU&apos;s influence and power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This auspicious event further bolstered Shigehime and Shigehide SHIMAZU&apos;s influence and power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>が、敦之助はわずか3年後の寛政11年（1799年）に亡くなってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Atsunosuke died only in three years in1799.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Atsunosuke died only three years later in1799.</e>
<cmt>However の後にコンマを入れました。  in three years → three years later に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Atsunosuke died only three years later in1799.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、寛政10年（1798年）にも懐妊するが流産してしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was pregnant in 1789 but had a miscarriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was pregnant in 1798 but had a miscarriage.</e>
<cmt>数字間違い： 1789 → 1798 に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was pregnant in 1798 but had a miscarriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>このころには、驕慢な振る舞いの多い茂姫を家斉は厭うようになり、茂姫は大勢いる側室たちに寵愛を奪われ、その後2度と家斉の子供を産むことはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From around this time Shigenari began to dislike Shigehime who became arrogant and fell out of his favor to many other concubines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From around this time Shigenari began to dislike Shigehime who became arrogant and fell out of his favor to many other concubines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From around this time Shigenari began to dislike Shigehime who became arrogant and fell out of his favor to many other concubines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>異母弟で9代藩主の島津斉宣が隠居後、財政難を理由に幾度も幕府に要請した薩摩帰国が却下されたのは、広大院の意図によるものとされるが、その理由は享和元年の母・お登勢の方（市田氏）死後に斉宣が市田一族を薩摩藩政から排除したことに対して広大院が激怒したことにあるといわれ、御台所の権威を背景に、薩摩藩政にも大きな影響力を及ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repeated denials of the petition by the 9th Satsuma domain lord Narinobu SHIMAZU to return to Satsuma after his retirement for financial reason were believed to be the works of Kodaiin because of her enrage stemming from the event that Narinobu excluded Ichida clan from Satsuma government and as such she wielded a considerable clout under the authority of Midaidocoro to Satsuma government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Repeated denials of the petition by the 9th Satsuma domain lord Narinobu SHIMAZU to return to Satsuma after his retirement for financial reason were believed to be the works of Kodaiin because of her anger stemming from the event that Narinobu excluded Ichida clan from Satsuma government and as such she wielded a considerable clout under the authority of Midaidokoro to Satsuma government.</e>
<cmt>enrage には名詞の意味はないので、anger に置き換えました。  clout と under の間の空白を半角分削除しました。 スペルミス： Midaidocoro → Midaidokoro に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Repeated denials of the petition by the 9th Satsuma domain lord Narinobu SHIMAZU to return to Satsuma after his retirement for financial reason were believed to be the works of Kodaiin because of her anger stemming from the event that Narinobu excluded Ichida clan from Satsuma government and as such she wielded a considerable clout under the authority of Midaidokoro to Satsuma government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>天保3年（1833年）には、市田義宜（甥で薩摩藩家老）を通じて藩主・島津斉興（広大院から見れば義宜と同じく甥にあたる）に、嫡子・島津斉彬の養子として夫・家斉の嫡男である家慶の子・徳川慶昌を入れるよう持ちかけたが、義宜と斉興は広大院に丁寧に断りをいれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1833, through Yoshinobu ICHIDA (her nephew and Satsuma karo (a chief retainer)), she suggested to the lord of the domain Narioki SHIMAZU (also her nephew same as Yoshinobu) to adopt her husband Ienari&apos;s legitimate child Ieyoshi&apos;s son Iemasa TOKUGAWA however Narioki and Yoshinobu declined politely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1833, through Yoshinobu ICHIDA (her nephew and Satsuma karo (a chief retainer)), she suggested to the lord of the domain Narioki SHIMAZU (also her nephew same as Yoshinobu) to adopt her husband Ienari&apos;s legitimate child Ieyoshi&apos;s son Yoshimasa TOKUGAWA however Narioki and Yoshinobu declined politely.</e>
<cmt>「慶昌」の読みが Iemasa となっていましたので、Yoshimasa に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1833, through Yoshinobu ICHIDA (her nephew and Satsuma karo (a chief retainer)), she suggested to the lord of the domain Narioki SHIMAZU (also her nephew same as Yoshinobu) to adopt her husband Ienari&apos;s legitimate child Ieyoshi&apos;s son Yoshimasa TOKUGAWA however Narioki and Yoshinobu declined politely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her later years</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her later years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>天保8年（1837年）、夫・家斉が隠退して大御所となって西の丸に移ると茂姫も西の丸に移り、「大御台様」と称せられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1837, after her husband Ienari retired as Ogosho (leading figure) and moved their quarters to Nishinomaru, she moved along with him and be called &quot;Omidaisama&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1837, after her husband Ienari retired as Ogosho (leading figure) and moved their quarters to Nishinomaru, she moved along with him and was called &quot;Omidaisama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>最初のand の前の空白を半角分削除しました。 文法ミス： be called → was called に訂正しました。 　ピリオドの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1837, after her husband Ienari retired as Ogosho (leading figure) and moved their quarters to Nishinomaru, she moved along with him and was called &quot;Omidaisama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>天保12年（1841年）、夫・家斉の死去に伴い落飾して「広大院」を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1841, due to her husband Ienari&apos;s death, she became nun and bore the name &quot;Kodaiin&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1841, due to her husband Ienari&apos;s death, she took the tonsure and announced her name as &quot;Kodaiin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「落飾して」にあたる部分の訳を、定訳にあるとおり、became nun → took the tonsure に訂正しました。 bore the name → announced her name as に変更しました。  ピリオドの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1841, due to her husband Ienari&apos;s death, she took the tonsure and announced her name as &quot;Kodaiin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>翌年従一位の官位を授かり、以後「一位様」と呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following year, she received official court rank Juichii (Junior First Rank) and hence called &quot;Ichii-sama&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following year, she received official court rank Juichii (Junior First Rank) and hence was called &quot;Ichii-sama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>called → was called に訂正しました。　　ピリオドの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following year, she received official court rank Juichii (Junior First Rank) and hence was called &quot;Ichii-sama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>広大院は夫の死去後、西の丸大奥から本丸大奥に移り、一の御殿・新座敷（将軍生母の居室）を「松の御殿」と改称して住むようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of her husband, she moved from Nishinomaru O-oku to Honmaru O-oku and lived in Ichino Goten shin zashiki (Shogun&apos;s mother&apos;s room) after renaming it &quot;Matsuno Goten&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of her husband, she moved from Nishinomaru O-oku to Honmaru O-oku and lived in Ichino Goten shin zashiki (Shogun&apos;s mother&apos;s room) after renaming it &quot;Matsuno Goten.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of her husband, she moved from Nishinomaru O-oku to Honmaru O-oku and lived in Ichino Goten shin zashiki (Shogun&apos;s mother&apos;s room) after renaming it &quot;Matsuno Goten.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>晩年には、家斉側室の一人・専行院が家斉の娘・溶姫（母はお美代の方）を生母とする前田慶寧を次期将軍に擁立しようと企む陰謀を阻止するが、これが最後の御台所らしい行動であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last years, she foiled the plot by one of Ienari&apos;s concubines Senkoin to have Yoshiyasu MAEDA whose mother was daughter of Ienari Youhime (biological mother was Omiyonokata) as next shogun and it was the last of like Midaidokoro&apos;s action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last years, she foiled the plot by one of Ienari&apos;s concubines Senkoin to have Yoshiyasu MAEDA whose mother was Yohime (her biological mother was Omiyonokata), a daughter of Ienari, become the next shogun, which was her last action that Midaidokoro should take.</e>
<cmt>&quot;daughter of Ienari Youhime&quot;の部分がわかりにくいので、語順を変えました。また、Youhime → Yohime に訂正しました。　&quot;to have Yoshiyasu&quot; に続く部分がas で始まっているのはおかしいので、become に訂正しました。  and it was → which was に置き換えました。  &quot;the last of like Midaidokoro&apos;s action&quot; は少々不自然な気がするので、&quot;her last action that Midairdokoro should take&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last years, she foiled the plot by one of Ienari&apos;s concubines Senkoin to have Yoshiyasu MAEDA whose mother was Yohime (her biological mother was Omiyonokata), a daughter of Ienari, become the next shogun, which was her last action that Midaidokoro should take.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>広大院はお美代の方をよく思っておらず、この企みを防止した後に、家斉死去における落飾を許さず、お美代の方を大奥から追放、以後、お美代の方は娘たちの婚家（加賀藩前田氏、広島藩浅野氏）を転々とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodaiin disliked Omiyonokata and after foiled her plot, she did not allow her to become a nun and ousted her from O-oku, Omiyonokata afterwards visited her daughter&apos;s husband&apos;s families (the Maeda clan of Kaga Domain, the Asano clan of Hiroshima Domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kodaiin disliked Omiyonokata, after foiling her plot, Kodaiin did not allow her to become a nun and ousted her from O-oku, which made Omiyonokata afterwards live with her daughter&apos;s husband&apos;s families one after another (the Maeda clan of Kaga Domain, the Asano clan of Hiroshima Domain).</e>
<cmt>文法ミス：　after foiled → after foiling に訂正しました。誰を指すshe なのかはっきりさせるため、一部名前に置き換えました。  文全体が冗長でわかりにくいので、接続詞を使って整理しました。  「転々とした」のニュアンスが出ていないので、one after another を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kodaiin disliked Omiyonokata, after foiling her plot, Kodaiin did not allow her to become a nun and ousted her from O-oku, which made Omiyonokata afterwards live with her daughter&apos;s husband&apos;s families one after another (the Maeda clan of Kaga Domain, the Asano clan of Hiroshima Domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="38">
<j>天保12年（1842年）に12代将軍・徳川家慶付き上臈・姉小路が食する天ぷら調理が原因で火事を起こし、本丸を全焼させてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1824, Honmaru was burned down by fire while cooking tempura to be served to Anekoji who was the 12th Shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA&apos;s joro (high ranking monk).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1824, Honmaru was burned down by fire while cooking tempura to be served to Anekoji who was the 12th Shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA&apos;s joro (high ranking woman).</e>
<cmt>上臈の注釈が間違っていると思われますので、訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1824, Honmaru was burned down by fire while cooking tempura to be served to Anekoji who was the 12th Shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA&apos;s joro (high ranking woman).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この火事で広大院は御末の奥女中におぶわれて吹上御殿に避難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodaiin was evacuated to Fukiage Goten carried by one of oku-jochu&apos;s back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodaiin was evacuated to Fukiage Goten carried by one of oku-jochu&apos;s back.</e>
<cmt>carried by →　carried on に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodaiin was evacuated to Fukiage Goten carried by one of oku-jochu&apos;s back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>この火事は奥女中が数百人死亡するという大惨事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The catastrophic fire killed few hundred oku-jochu (a maid working in the domestic quarters of shogun or daimyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The catastrophic fire killed a few hundreds of oku-jochu (a maid working in the domestic quarters of shogun or daimyo).</e>
<cmt>few hundred → a few hundreds of に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The catastrophic fire killed a few hundreds of oku-jochu (a maid working in the domestic quarters of shogun or daimyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="41">
<j>1844年に大奥にて死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She deceased in O-oku in 1844.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She deceased in O-oku in 1844.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She deceased in Ooku in 1844.</e>
<cmt>Ookuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>法名「広大院殿超誉妙貞仁大姉」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her posthumous Buddhist name was &quot;Kodaiin tonocho homaretai sadahito Daishi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her posthumous Buddhist name was &quot;Kodaiin tonocho homaretai sadahito Daishi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her posthumous Buddhist name was &quot;Kodaiin tonocho homaretai sadahito Daishi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>墓所は増上寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her burial place was at Zojo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her burial place was at Zojo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her burial place was at Zojo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>夫の家斉とは別の寺に葬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was buried in a different temple from Ienari&apos;s one.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ：完全に訳抜けでしたので、代わりに訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was buried in a different temple from Ienari&apos;s one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>墓所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Burial place</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Burial place</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Burial place</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="45">
<j>戦後、増上寺・徳川家墓所が西武鉄道に売却された際に広大院の墓も発掘されたが、身長は143.8cmであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, when the burial grounds for Tokugawa family at Zojo-ji was sold to Seibu Railway Co., Ltd., Kodaiin&apos;s grave was also dag up and her height was determined to be 143.8 cm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, when the burial ground for Tokugawa family at Zojo-ji was sold to Seibu Railway Co., Ltd., Kodaiin&apos;s grave was also dug up and her height was determined to be 143.8 cm.</e>
<cmt>when の前の空白を半角分削除しました。  grounds → ground 単数に戻しました。  スペルミス： dag → dug に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, when the burial ground for Tokugawa family at Zojo-ji was sold to Seibu Railway Co., Ltd., Kodaiin&apos;s grave was also dug up and her height was determined to be 143.8 cm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>同時期に発掘された他の将軍正室・側室の遺骨と比較してもかなり小さかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her physic was small in cooperation to other remains of Shogun&apos;s lawful wife and concubine that were dug up at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her body was pretty small in comparison to other remains of Shogun&apos;s lawful wives and concubines that were dug up at the same time.</e>
<cmt>physic → 単にbody としました。   「かなり」に相当する部分が抜けているので、small の前に pretty を入れました。 単語間違い： cooperation → comparison に訂正しました。wife and concubine を複数にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her body was pretty small in comparison to other remains of Shogun&apos;s lawful wives and concubines that were dug up at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ちなみに広大院は生前は美女で知られていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, she was know to be a beautiful woman during her lifetime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, she was known to be a beautiful woman during her lifetime.</e>
<cmt>文法ミス： know → known に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, she was known to be a beautiful woman during her lifetime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>広大院の墓の残存状況は悪く、着物の刺繍であったとおぼしき繊維製品が泥水の中にぷかぷか浮いていたという状況で、遺骨以外の遺品はほとんど見つからなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The condition of Kodaiin&apos;s graveyard was deteriorated in such some embroidery believed to be on kimono were floating in mud water and a very little articles were found other than the corpse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The condition of Kodaiin&apos;s graveyard was deteriorated in such some embroidery believed to be on kimono was floating in mud water and a very little articles were found other than the corpse.</e>
<cmt>were floating → was floating に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The condition of Kodaiin&apos;s graveyard was deteriorated in such some embroidery believed to be on kimono was floating in mud water and a very little articles were found other than the corpse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>（参考文献　『増上寺徳川将軍墓とその遺品・遺体』）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reference literature &quot;Zojo-ji Temple Tokugawa Shogun&apos;s graveyard and its corpse and articles left by the deceased&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reference literature &quot;Zojo-ji Temple Tokugawa Shogun&apos;s graveyard and its corpse and articles left by the deceased&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reference literature &quot;Zojo-ji Temple Tokugawa Shogun&apos;s graveyard and its corpse and articles left by the deceased&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>また彼女の墓所には壮麗な八角塔が建てられていたのだが、この発掘のどさくさに紛れ、この墓塔は行方不明になったままである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there was a magnificent hakkaku (star anise) at the burial ground however during the excavation confusion, it disappeared and remained missing since.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there was a magnificent hakkaku (star anise) at the burial ground however during the excavation confusion, it disappeared and remains missing since then.</e>
<cmt>行方不明の状態は現在も続いているので、現在形になおしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there was a magnificent hakkaku (star anise) at the burial ground however during the excavation confusion, it disappeared and remains missing since then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>改葬後は他の将軍正室は夫と並んで合葬されたのに対し、広大院は桂昌院、月光院等の側室と共に合葬墓に入れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the reburial, other Shogun&apos;s wives and concubines were buried along side their husband, Kodaiin was buried in group burial along with Katsurashoin, Gekkoin and other concubines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the reburial, while other Shogun&apos;s lawful wives were buried along side their husbands, Kodaiin was buried in group burial along with Katsurashoin, Gekkoin and other concubines.</e>
<cmt>誤訳： 合葬された中に側室は含まれていないので、最初のconcubines を削除しました。「のに対し」の部分が訳されていないので、while を文の始めに加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the reburial, while other Shogun&apos;s lawful wives were buried along side their husbands, Kodaiin was buried in group burial along with Katsurashoin, Gekkoin and other concubines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Juqipedia(id:188816), やりたこ(id:113528), VolkovBot(id:105371), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), Knua(id:66861), Chobot(id:20846), こぶまき(id:38278), Alexbot(id:157199), 飲んでも飲まれるな(id:120588), Y-take(id:132371), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>