<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>二条師基</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromoto NIJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromoto NIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moromoto NIJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二条 師基（にじょう もろもと、正安3年（1301年） - 正平 (日本)20年 / 貞治4年1月26日 (旧暦)（1365年2月17日））は、鎌倉時代末期から南北朝時代 (日本)にかけての公卿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromoto NIJO (1301 – February 17, 1365) was a noble between the late Kamakura Period and the period of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromoto NIJO (1301 – February 17, 1365) was a noble between the late Kamakura Period and the period of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moromoto NIJO (1301 – February 17, 1365) was a court noble between the late Kamakura Period and the period of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt>noble→court noble</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>南北分裂後は南朝 (日本)方に属し、正平6年（1351年）以降、後村上天皇の下で関白をつとめるなど、南朝政権の重鎮のひとりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Imperial Court broken up into the Northern and Southern courts, Moromoto belonged to the Southern Court and served as Kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the emperor) under Emperor Gomurakami subsequent to 1351, being one of the heavyweights of the Southern Court government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Imperial Court broke into the Northern and Southern courts, Moromoto belonged to the Southern Court and served as Kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the emperor) under Emperor Gomurakami subsequent to 1351, being one of the heavyweights of the Southern Court government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Imperial Court broke into the Northern and Southern courts, Moromoto belonged to the Southern Court and served as Kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the emperor) under Emperor Gomurakami subsequent to 1351, being one of the heavyweights of the Southern Court government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>父は、関白二条兼基。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromoto&apos;s father was Kanpaku Kanemoto NIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromoto&apos;s father was Kanpaku Kanemoto NIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moromoto&apos;s father was Kanpaku Kanemoto NIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>母は花山源氏、蔵人頭・源兼任の娘である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was from the Kazan Genji (Minamoto Clan) being the daughter of Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) MINAMOTO no Kaneto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was from the Kazan Genji (Minamoto Clan) being the daughter of Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) MINAMOTO no Kaneto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was from the Kazan Genji (Minamoto Clan) being the daughter of Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) MINAMOTO no Kaneto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父について、『公卿補任』正和元年（1312年）の条は、兼基の子である二条道平とする一方で、兼基が死去した建武 (日本)元年（1334年）の条では、道平と師基が8月22日に「父」の喪に服した旨が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to Moromoto&apos;s father, there is the chapter for 1312 in Kugyobunin (Directory of Court Nobles) that mentions Michihira NIJO, the son of Kanemoto but, in the chapter covering 1334, it is written that Michihira and Moromoto went into mourning for &apos;their father&apos; on August 22.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to Moromoto&apos;s father, there is the chapter for 1312 in Kugyobunin (Directory of Court Nobles) that mentions Michihira NIJO, the son of Kanemoto but, in the chapter covering 1334, it is written that Michihira and Moromoto went into mourning for &apos;their father&apos; on August 22.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to Moromoto&apos;s father, there is the chapter for 1312 in &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (Directory of Court Nobles) that mentions Michihira NIJO, the son of Kanemoto but, in the chapter covering 1334, it is written that Michihira and Moromoto went into mourning for &apos;their father&apos; on August 22.</e>
<cmt>引用符を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、道平と師基の年齢差を考えても親子より兄弟とした方が自然である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, considering the age difference between Michihira and Moromoto, it seems natural to assume that they were brothers and not father and son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, considering the age difference between Michihira and Moromoto, it seems natural to assume that they were brothers and not father and son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, considering the age difference between Michihira and Moromoto, it seems natural to assume that they were brothers and not father and son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以下では、兼基を父、道平を兄として解説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following descriptions are based on the assumption with Kanemoto being the father and Michihira being the older brother of Moromoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following descriptions are based on the assumption of Kanemoto being the father and Michihira being the older brother of Moromoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following descriptions are based on the assumption of Kanemoto being the father and Michihira being the older brother of Moromoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉幕府の滅亡と建武中興期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fall of the Kamakura Shogunate and the Kenmu Restoration period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fall of the Kamakura Shogunate and the Kenmu Restoration period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fall of the Kamakura Shogunate and the Kenmu Restoration period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>1311年（応長元年）6月15日、11歳で元服、従五位上に叙され、禁色・昇殿を許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 15, 1311, Moromoto celebrated genpuku (the coming-of-age ceremony) at age 11 and conferred Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) whereby he became authorized to use kinjiki (seven colors traditionally reserved for the imperial family and nobility) and to attend the court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 15, 1311, Moromoto celebrated genpuku (the coming-of-age ceremony) at age 11 and was conferred Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) whereby he became authorized to use kinjiki (seven colors traditionally reserved for the imperial family and nobility) and to attend the court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 15, 1311, Moromoto celebrated genpuku (the coming-of-age ceremony) at age 11 and conferred Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) whereby he became authorized to use kinjiki (literally, &quot;forbidden colours,&quot; seven colours tradionally reserved for the imperial family and nobility) and to attend the court.</e>
<cmt>Lower Grade→Upper Grade</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1318年（文保2年）に後醍醐天皇が即位した時点で、正二位行大納言となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1318, Moromoto was正二位行大納言 as at Emperor Godaigo&apos;s accession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>正二位行大納言 - 読み・意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1318, Moromoto was正二位行大納言 as at Emperor Godaigo&apos;s accession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1318, Moromoto had been promoted to Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state), as at Emperor Godaigo&apos;s accession to the throne.</e>
<cmt>正二位行大納言は正ニ位権大納言だと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>後醍醐天皇は鎌倉幕府の打倒を目指し、1331年（元弘元年）、元弘の乱が勃発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1331, with Emperor Godaigo aspiring to bring down the Kamakura Shogunate, Genko War broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1331, with Emperor Godaigo aspiring to bring down the Kamakura Shogunate, the Genko War broke out.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1331, with Emperor Godaigo aspiring to bring down the Kamakura Shogunate, the Genko War broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1333年（元弘3年 / 正慶2年）5月7日に六波羅探題が陥落した後、師基は九州における幕府の重要拠点である鎮西探題を攻略するため大宰権帥に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 7, 1333, after the fall of Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), Moromoto was assigned as Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) to capture Chinzei tandai (office of the military governor of Kyushu) which was the critical stronghold of the shogunate in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 7, 1333, after the fall of Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), Moromoto was assigned as Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) to capture Chinzei tandai (office of the military governor of Kyushu) which was the critical stronghold of the shogunate in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 7, 1333, after the fall of Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), Moromoto was assigned as Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) to capture Chinzei tandai (office of the military governor of Kyushu) which was the critical stronghold of the shogunate in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>師基は軍を率いて九州へ向かうが、鎮西探題は既に少弐貞経、大友貞宗ら九州の御家人によって5月25日に陥落しており、大宰府において尊良親王を中心として戦後処置が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leading an army, Moromoto headed Kyushu but Chizai Tandai had been seized by various gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura, Muromachi and Edo periods) including Sadatsune SHONI and Sadamune OTOMO and, with Imperial Prince Takayoshi taking the lead, those gokenin were dealing with the post war matters in Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leading an army, Moromoto headed Kyushu but Chizai Tandai had been seized by various gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura, Muromachi and Edo periods) including Sadatsune SHONI and Sadamune OTOMO and, with Imperial Prince Takayoshi taking the lead, those gokenin were dealing with the post war matters in Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leading an army, Moromoto headed Kyushu but Chizai Tandai had been seized by various gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura, Muromachi and Edo periods) including Sadatsune SHONI and Sadamune OTOMO and, with Imperial Prince Takayoshi taking the lead, those gokenin were dealing with the post war matters in Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>師基は大宰府で親王を補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromoto assisted the Imperial Prince in Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromoto assisted the Imperial Prince in Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moromoto assisted the Imperial Prince in Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>大宰権帥となっ師基は、長門国守護を兼任したという説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that Moromoto became Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices and had a concurrent assignment as Nagato no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Nagato Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that Moromoto became Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices and had a concurrent assignment as Nagato no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Nagato Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that Moromoto became Dazai gon no sochi and had a concurrent assignment as Nagato no kuni Shugo (provincial constable of Nagato Province).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>重要史料である「長門国守護職次第」には、鎌倉時代最後の守護である北条時直（元弘3年（1333年）5月26日降伏）の後、建武の新政期に後醍醐天皇によって守護に任じられ建武 (日本)元年（1334年）5月10日に入部した厚東武実の前に、「輔大納言」という人物が守護であったことを記載する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the important historical book &apos;Nagato no kuni Shugoshoku Shidai&apos; (the Ritual Protocol of Provincial Constable of Nagato Province), it is written that, after the last provincial constable of Nagato Province of the Kamakura Period Tokinao HOJO (who surrendered on May 26, 1333), the person known as &apos;Suke no Dainagon&apos; was the provincial constable prior to Takezane KOTO who came on board on May 10, 1334 being appointed by Emperor Godaigo during times of the new Kenmu administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the important historical book &apos;Nagato no kuni Shugoshoku Shidai&apos; (the Ritual Protocol of Provincial Constable of Nagato Province), it is written that, after the last provincial constable of Nagato Province of the Kamakura Period Tokinao HOJO (who surrendered on May 26, 1333), the person known as &apos;Suke no Dainagon&apos; was the provincial constable prior to Takezane KOTO who came on board on May 10, 1334 being appointed by Emperor Godaigo during times of the new Kenmu administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the important historical book &apos;Nagato no kuni Shugoshoku Shidai&apos; (the Ritual Protocol of Provincial Constable of Nagato Province), it is written that, after the last provincial constable of Nagato Province of the Kamakura Period Tokinao HOJO (who surrendered on May 26, 1333), the person known as &apos;Suke no Dainagon&apos; was the provincial constable prior to Takezane KOTO who came on board on May 10, 1334 being appointed by Emperor Godaigo during times of the new Kenmu administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この人物について、当時、権大納言であり筑前国の大宰府にいた二条師基が相当する可能性はあるが、万里小路宣房または地元豪族である豊田氏の一族とする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is possible that the said person corresponded to Moromoto NIJO who was located in Dazaifu in Chikuzen Province in those days but there also are opinions that it was either Nobufusa MADENOKOJI or a member of the Toyota clan, the local Gozoku (local ruling family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible that the said person corresponded to Moromoto NIJO who was located in Dazaifu in Chikuzen Province in those days but there also are some opinions that it was either Nobufusa MADENOKOJI or a member of the Toyota clan, the local Gozoku (local ruling family).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible that the said person corresponded to Moromoto NIJO who was located in Dazaifu in Chikuzen Province in those days but there also are some opinions that it was either Nobufusa MADENOKOJI or a member of the Toyota clan, the local Gozoku (local ruling family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>足利尊氏の反乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rebellion of Takauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rebellion of Takauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rebellion of Takauji ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>1335年（建武2年）、足利尊氏が反旗を翻し京へ攻め上ってくると、建武の新政に不満をもつ諸国の武士もこれに呼応し蜂起する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1335, as Takauji ASHIKAGA, rising in revolt, charged into Kyoto, samurai in various regions dissatisfied with the Kenmu Restoration rose in response to Takauji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1335, as Takauji ASHIKAGA, rising in revolt, charged into Kyoto, samurai in various regions dissatisfied with the Kenmu Restoration rose in response to Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1335, as Takauji ASHIKAGA, rising in revolt, charged into Kyoto, samurai in various regions dissatisfied with the Kenmu Restoration rose in response to Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>京では防御態勢が整えられ、師基は西北の山陰道方面の守りを任せられて、証月坊慶政開基の法華山寺（京都市西京区御陵峰ヶ堂）に布陣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With defensive measures being placed in Kyoto, Moromoto was assigned to cover the vicinity of Sanin-do Road in the northwest of Kyoto taking up a position at Hokke-san Temple (Misasagi Minegado, Nishigyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City) founded by Shogetsubo Keisei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With defensive measures being placed in Kyoto, Moromoto was assigned to cover the vicinity of the Sanin-do Road in northwest Kyoto taking up a position at Hokke-san Temple (Misasagi Minegado, Nishigyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City) founded by Shogetsubo Keisei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With defensive measures being placed in Kyoto, Moromoto was assigned to cover the vicinity of the Sanin-do Road in northwest Kyoto taking up a position at Hokke-san Temple (Misasagi Minegado, Nishigyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City) founded by Shogetsubo Keisei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、1336年（建武3年）1月8日、但馬国・丹後国の兵を率いた久下氏らに撃破され、大枝山が占拠された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 8, 1336, however, Moromoto&apos;s army was obliterated by the enemy side including the Kuge clan leading soldiers of Tajima and Tango provinces whereby Mt. Oe was seized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 8, 1336, however, Moromoto&apos;s army was obliterated by the enemy including the Kuge clan leading soldiers of Tajima and Tango provinces whereby Mt. Oe was seized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 8, 1336, however, Moromoto&apos;s army was obliterated by the enemy including the Kuge clan leading soldiers of Tajima and Tango provinces whereby Mt. Oe was seized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この軍勢は、新田一族の江田行義の軍によってその日のうちに追い払われたが、結局、その年の5月に京都は足利軍に奪われ、天皇とその軍勢は比叡山に籠った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this enemy force was driven away by the army of Yukiyoshi EDA of the Nitta clan before the day was over, ultimately, Kyoto was seized by the Ashikaga army in May of that year and the Emperor and his army retreated by Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this enemy force was driven back by the army of Yukiyoshi EDA of the Nitta clan before the day was over, ultimately, Kyoto was seized by the Ashikaga army in May of that year and the Emperor and his army retreated to Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this enemy force was driven back by the army of Yukiyoshi EDA of the Nitta clan before the day was over, ultimately, Kyoto was seized by the Ashikaga army in May of that year and the Emperor and his army retreated to Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>6月に入ると比叡山は東西から繰り返し攻められるが、新田義貞等の奮闘により防衛に成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early June, Mt. Hiei was repeatedly attacked by the enemy forces on the east and west sides of the mountain but it was successfully defended thanks to strenuous efforts of the allies including Yoshisada Nitta.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In early June, Mt. Hiei was repeatedly attacked byenemy forces on the east and west sides of the mountain but it was successfully defended thanks to strenuous efforts of the allies including Yoshisada Nitta.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In early June, Mt. Hiei was repeatedly attacked by enemy forces on the east and west sides of the mountain but it was successfully defended thanks to strenuous efforts of the allies including Yoshisada Nitta.</e>
<cmt>スペースを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>足利軍の士気が低下したのを見て、官軍は6月30日に反攻に転じ、京都市中に侵攻するが撃退される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seeing that the Ashikaga army&apos;s morale was shaken, the Imperial army shifted to counteroffensive on June 30 invading the streets of Kyoto but was driven off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seeing that the Ashikaga army&apos;s morale was shaken, the Imperial army shifted to the counter offensive on June 30 invading the streets of Kyoto, but was driven off.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seeing that the Ashikaga army&apos;s morale was shaken, the Imperial army shifted to the counter offensive on June 30 invading the streets of Kyoto, but was driven off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>『太平記』によると、この失敗により意気消沈していたところ、7月5日、二条師基が加賀国・越前国の軍勢を率いて官軍に合流したことで再度奮起し、第2回・第3回の京都市中への攻撃を実行、師基も兵を率いて参戦する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Taiheiki (The Record of the Great Peace), on July 5, leading the armies of Kaga and Echizen provinces, Moromoto NIJO joined the Imperial Army, that had been dejected by the above-described defeat, and the Imperial Army once again roused themselves to make the second and third attacks in the streets of Kyoto and Moromoto, commanding an army, also participated in war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Taiheiki (The Record of the Great Peace), on July 5, leading the armies of Kaga and Echizen provinces, Moromoto NIJO joined the Imperial Army, that had been dejected by the above-described defeat, and the Imperial Army once again roused themselves to make the second and third attacks in the streets of Kyoto and Moromoto, commanding an army, also participated in war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace), on July 5, leading the armies of Kaga and Echizen provinces, Moromoto NIJO joined the Imperial Army, that had been dejected by the above-described defeat, and the Imperial Army once again roused themselves to make the second and third attacks in the streets of Kyoto and Moromoto, commanding an army, also participated in war.</e>
<cmt>引用符を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、いずれも撃退され、膠着状態になったところで後醍醐天皇と足利尊氏との和睦へと物語は展開する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial army and Moromoto&apos;s army were beaten back by the enemy side each time whereby thesituation became deadlocked and the storyline then would lead to the passage in which Emperor Godaigo and Takauji ASHIKAGA made peace with one another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial army and Moromoto&apos;s army were beaten back by the enemy side each time whereby thesituation became deadlocked and the storyline then would lead to the passage in which Emperor Godaigo and Takauji ASHIKAGA made peace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial army and Moromoto&apos;s army were beaten back by the enemy side each time whereby thesituation became deadlocked and the storyline then would lead to the passage in which Emperor Godaigo and Takauji ASHIKAGA made peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、この3回に渡る京都侵攻作戦は、『梅松論』『常楽記』が6月30日の出来事として記すもので、『太平記』ではストーリー構成上、この日の戦いを3分割して描いていると推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These 3 operations to invade Kyoto, however, are recorded to have taken place on June 30 according to Baishoron (Historical tale compiled in 1349) and Jorakuki and, hence, it is supposed that, in Taiheiki, these battles on that day were broken up into 3 segments to better organize the storyline.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These 3 operations to invade Kyoto, however, are recorded to have taken place on June 30 according to the Baishoron (Historical tale compiled in 1349) and Jorakuki and, hence, it is supposed that, in Taiheiki, these battles on that day were broken up into 3 segments to better organize the storyline.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These 3 operations to invade Kyoto, however, are recorded to have taken place on June 30 according to the &quot;Baishoron&quot; (Historical tale compiled in 1349) and &quot;Jorakuki&quot; and, hence, it is supposed that, in &quot;Taiheiki&quot;, these battles on that day were broken up into 3 segments to better organize the storyline.</e>
<cmt>引用符を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>和睦成立後、比叡山にいた官軍の大部分は、後醍醐天皇と共に京都へ帰る者と、皇太子恒良親王を奉じて新田義貞と共に越前へ下る者とに分かれたが、師基はどちらにも加わらず、中院定平らと共に河内国へ落ちのびた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the peace accord was reached, the majority of the Imperial army camped at Mt. Hiei was divided into 2 groups with one returning to Kyoto with Emperor Godaigo and the other going down to Echizen Province with Yoshisada NITTA, following the Crown Prince Tsuneyoshi but Moromoto, not joining the either group, fled to Kawachi Province with some of his allies including Sadahira NAKANOIN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the peace accord was reached, the majority of the Imperial army camped at Mt. Hiei was divided into 2 groups with one returning to Kyoto with Emperor Godaigo and the other going down to Echizen Province with Yoshisada NITTA, following the Crown Prince Tsuneyoshi but Moromoto, not joining the either group, fled to Kawachi Province with some of his allies including Sadahira NAKANOIN.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the peace accord was reached, the majority of the Imperial army camped at Mt. Hiei was divided into 2 groups with one returning to Kyoto with Emperor Godaigo and the other going down to Echizen Province with Yoshisada NITTA, following the Crown Prince Tsuneyoshi but Moromoto, not joining the either group, fled to Kawachi Province with some of his allies including Sadahira NAKANOIN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>後醍醐天皇は京都で幽閉されるが、12月21日に脱出に成功し、吉野において朝廷（南朝）を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo was incarcerated in Kyoto but, escaping successfully on December 21 he established a court (the Southern Court) in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Godaigo was incarcerated in Kyoto but, escaping successfully on December 21 he established a court (the Southern Court) in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo was incarcerated in Kyoto but, escaping successfully on December 21 he established a court (the Southern Court) in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>こうして南北朝時代が始まり、師基は、翌1337年（建武4年）1月に吉野朝廷に参内する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Period of the Northern and Southern Courts thus began and, in January of the following year 1337, Moromoto went to the Yoshino Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Period of the Northern and Southern Courts thus began and, in January of the following year 1337, Moromoto went to the Yoshino Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Period of the Northern and Southern Courts thus began and, in January of the following year 1337, Moromoto went to the Yoshino Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>二条家は、兄の道平が北朝 (日本)に、弟の師基が南朝に従い、分裂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The House of Nijo was divided, with the older brother Michihira following the Northern Court while the younger brother Moromoto going with the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The House of Nijo was divided, with the older brother Michihira following the Northern Court while the younger brother Moromoto going with the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The House of Nijo was divided, with the older brother Michihira following the Northern Court while the younger brother Moromoto going with the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>師基は、1339年（延元4年 / 暦応2年）に後村上天皇が即位した時点で内大臣、その後、左大臣に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1339, Moromoto was appointed as Naidaijin (the Minister of the Interior) as at Emperor Gomurakami&apos;s accession to the throne and was later assigned as Sadaijin (the Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1339, Moromoto was appointed as Naidaijin (the Minister of the Interior) as at Emperor Gomurakami&apos;s accession to the throne and was later assigned as Sadaijin (the Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1339, Moromoto was appointed as Naidaijin (the Minister of the Interior) as at Emperor Gomurakami&apos;s accession to the throne and was later assigned as Sadaijin (the Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>観応の擾乱と正平の一統</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanno Disturbance and Shohei no itto (a temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanno Disturbance and Shohei no itto (a temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanno Disturbance and Shohei no itto (a temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>1350年（正平 (日本)5年 / 観応元年）、北朝側（幕府）の内部抗争である観応の擾乱が勃発する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1350, the Kanno Disturbance, an internal fighting within the Northern Court (the shogunate), broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1350, the Kanno Disturbance, an internal battle within the Northern Court (the shogunate), broke out.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1350, the Kanno Disturbance, an internal battle within the Northern Court (the shogunate), broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>劣勢に陥った足利直義は南朝軍の力を借りて挽回を図ろうと12月に南朝に降伏を申し入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, the underdog Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA, planning to make a comeback with help of the Southern Court army, offered his submission to the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, the underdog Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA, planning to make a comeback with help of the Southern Court army, offered his submission to the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, the underdog Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA, planning to make a comeback with help of the Southern Court army, offered his submission to the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この対応をめぐって重臣らで議論がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senior vassals discussed options for responding to Naoyoshi&apos;s offer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senior vassals discussed options for responding to Naoyoshi&apos;s offer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senior vassals discussed options for responding to Naoyoshi&apos;s offer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>洞院実世は偽りの投降と見抜き、降伏の受け入れに反対、むしろこの機会に直義を討伐して北朝側の戦力を削減させるべきと主張する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Predicting it was a false surrender, Saneyo TOIN opposed to accepting Naoyoshi&apos;s offer of submission arguing that they should take that opportunity to put down Naoyoshi to reduce the Northern Court&apos;s war potential, instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Predicting it was a false surrender, Saneyo TOIN opposed accepting Naoyoshi&apos;s offer of submission arguing that they should take that opportunity to put down Naoyoshi to reduce the Northern Court&apos;s war potential, instead.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Predicting it was a false surrender, Saneyo TOIN opposed accepting Naoyoshi&apos;s offer of submission arguing that they should take that opportunity to put down Naoyoshi to reduce the Northern Court&apos;s war potential, instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これに対し、二条師基と北畠親房は受け入れに賛成し、直義派との合同により南北朝間の形勢逆転を図ることを主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromoto NIJO and Chikafusa KITABATAKE, on the other hand, were in favor of accepting the offer urging that they try to turn the tide of the battle between the Northern and Southern Courts by joining the force with the Naoyoshi faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromoto NIJO and Chikafusa KITABATAKE, on the other hand, were in favor of accepting the offer urging that they try to turn the tide of the battle between the Northern and Southern Courts by joining forces with the Naoyoshi faction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moromoto NIJO and Chikafusa KITABATAKE, on the other hand, were in favor of accepting the offer urging that they try to turn the tide of the battle between the Northern and Southern Courts by joining forces with the Naoyoshi faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>その結果、後村上天皇は、直義の降伏を受け入れ、12月13日、勅免の宣旨が下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gomurakami, consequently, accepted Naoyoshi&apos;s surrender and, on December 13, an imperial letter of pardon by an edict was issued.</e>
<cmt>ちょく‐めん【勅免】 勅命による赦免http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%8B%85%E5%85%8D</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gomurakami, consequently, accepted Naoyoshi&apos;s surrender and, on December 13, an imperial letter of pardon by an edict was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gomurakami, consequently, accepted Naoyoshi&apos;s surrender and, on December 13, an imperial letter of pardon by an edict was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この決定を受けて、南朝側諸将は足利直義軍に合流し、翌年1月、足利尊氏・高師直軍と交戦し、これを撃ち破る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon hearing this decision, the various military commanders on the Southern Court side joined the army of Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA and, in January of the following year, battled with and defeated the armies of Takauji ASHIKAGA and Moronao KO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon hearing this decision, the various military commanders on the Southern Court side joined the army of Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA and, in January of the following year, battled with and defeated the armies of Takauji ASHIKAGA and Moronao KO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon hearing this decision, the various military commanders on the Southern Court side joined the army of Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA and, in January of the following year, battled with and defeated the armies of Takauji ASHIKAGA and Moronao KO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、直義は京を制圧するや直ちに南朝から離反する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As soon as Kyoto was conquered, however, Naoyoshi defected from the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as Kyoto was conquered, however, Naoyoshi defected from the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as Kyoto was conquered, however, Naoyoshi defected from the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>尊氏と直義は和睦をするが、両者間の火種は燻り続け、尊氏方、直義方、そして南朝の三つ巴状態に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji and Naoyoshi reconciled but a flashpoint between them remained and the situation returned to the previous three-way struggle among the Takauji group, the Naoyoshi group and the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji and Naoyoshi reconciled, but a flashpoint between them remained and the situation returned to the previous three-way struggle among the Takauji group, the Naoyoshi group, and the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji and Naoyoshi reconciled, but a flashpoint between them remained and the situation returned to the previous three-way struggle among the Takauji group, the Naoyoshi group, and the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>次に南朝に降伏を申し入れてきたのは足利尊氏であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Takauji ASHIKAGA who offered the Southern Court his submission next.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Takauji ASHIKAGA who offered the Southern Court his submission next.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Takauji ASHIKAGA who offered the Southern Court his submission next.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>南朝側首脳陣は、直義の裏切りを教訓にして今回は慎重にならざるを得なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Learning a lesson from Naoyoshi&apos;s betrayal, the Southern Court leaders were obliged to be cautious this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Learning a lesson from Naoyoshi&apos;s betrayal, the Southern Court leaders were obliged to be cautious this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Learning a lesson from Naoyoshi&apos;s betrayal, the Southern Court leaders were obliged to be cautious this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>しかし、一時的な偽降を逆手にとって、尊氏が直義を討伐するため京を離れている間に、京都を奪還し北朝を吸収し解消してしまう計画を立てたうえで、10月24日付で尊氏に対し勅免および直義追討の綸旨を下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Turning Naoyoshi&apos;s temporary false surrender around to their advantage, the Southern Court had planned to recapture Kyoto to absorb and eliminate the Northern Court while Takauji was away from Kyoto to subjugate Naoyoshi, an Imperial Order dated October 24 to search and kill Naoyoshi was given to Takauji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Turning Naoyoshi&apos;s temporary false surrender around to their advantage, the Southern Court had planned to recapture Kyoto to absorb and eliminate the Northern Court while Takauji was away from Kyoto to subjugate Naoyoshi, an Imperial Order dated October 24 to search and kill Naoyoshi was given to Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Turning Naoyoshi&apos;s temporary false surrender around to their advantage, the Southern Court had planned to recapture Kyoto to absorb and eliminate the Northern Court while Takauji was away from Kyoto to subjugate Naoyoshi, an Imperial Order dated October 24 to search and kill Naoyoshi was given to Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>尊氏が京を発った後、北朝の崇光天皇を廃位し、関白二条良基の職務を停止し、親南朝派の洞院公賢を左大臣に任じ京における公事を委ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Takauji left Kyoto, Emperor Suko of the Northern Court was dethroned and the post of Chief Advisor to the Emperor Yoshimoto NIJO was brought to an end whereby the pro-Southern Court Kinkata TOIN was assigned as the Minister of the Left making him in charge of kuji (public duties) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Takauji left Kyoto, Emperor Suko of the Northern Court was dethroned and the post of Chief Advisor to the Emperor Yoshimoto NIJO was brought to an end whereby the pro-Southern Court Kinkata TOIN was assigned as the Minister of the Left making him in charge of kuji (public duties) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Takauji left Kyoto, Emperor Suko of the Northern Court was dethroned and the post of Kanpaku Yoshimoto NIJO was brought to an end whereby the pro-Southern Court Kinkata TOIN was assigned as the Minister of the Left making him in charge of kuji (public duties) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Chief Advisor to the Emperor→Kanpaku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>そして、12月28日に二条師基は関白に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, on December 28, Moromoto NIJO was appointed as Chief Advisor to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, on December 28, Moromoto NIJO was appointed as Chief Advisor to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, on December 28, Moromoto NIJO was appointed as Kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>Chief Advisor to the Emperor→Kanpaku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>翌1352年（正平7年 / 観応3年）閏2月、関東と畿内において足利軍と交戦を開始、19日に後村上天皇が男山（石清水八幡宮）まで行幸し、そこに留まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February of the following year, 1352 which was a leap year, the Southern Court forces began fighting the Ashikaga army in the Kanto and Kinai regions and, on the 19th, Emperor Gomurakami went to Mt. Otoko (Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine) where he remained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February of the following year, 1352 which was a leap year, the Southern Court forces began fighting the Ashikaga army in the Kanto and Kinai regions and, on the 19th, Emperor Gomurakami went to Mt. Otoko (Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine) where he remained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February of the following year, 1352 which was a leap year, the Southern Court forces began fighting the Ashikaga army in the Kanto and Kinai regions and, on the 19th, Emperor Gomurakami went to Mt. Otoko (Iwashimizu Hachiman-gu Shrine) where he remained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>足利方の反攻が厳しくなり、5月11日に男山が陥落、後村上天皇は河内国へ撤退するが、追撃も激しく撤退戦において官軍は多くの犠牲を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Ashikaga force&apos;s counteroffensive intensified, Mt. Otoko fell on May 11 and wile Emperor Gomurakami retreated to Kawachi Province, the Imperial army was pursued fiercely suffering numerous casualties during the retreating battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Ashikaga force&apos;s counteroffensive intensified, Mt. Otoko fell on May 11 and while Emperor Gomurakami retreated to Kawachi Province, the Imperial army was pursued fiercely suffering numerous casualties during the retreating battle.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Ashikaga force&apos;s counteroffensive intensified, Mt. Otoko fell on May 11 and while Emperor Gomurakami retreated to Kawachi Province, the Imperial army was pursued fiercely suffering numerous casualties during the retreating battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>その中には、二条師基の次男、教忠も含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noritada, the second son of Moromoto NIJO, was among them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noritada, the second son of Moromoto NIJO, was among them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noritada, the second son of Moromoto NIJO, was among them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>大塔若宮の反乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Rebellion of Oto no wakamiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rebellion of Oto no wakamiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rebellion of Oto no wakamiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>二条師基は、1359年（正平14年 / 延文4年）6月17日に出家し、法名を光明台院と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 17, 1359, Moromoto NIJO became a priest with the Buddhist name of Komyodaiin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 17, 1359, Moromoto NIJO became a priest with the Buddhist name of Komyodaiin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 17, 1359, Moromoto NIJO became a priest with the Buddhist name of Komyodaiin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>したがって、遅くともこのときまでには、関白職を長男、教基に譲っていたはずであるが、その時期は未詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, it seems that Moromoto should have passed the post of Kanpaku on to his eldest son Norimoto by then at the latest but that timing remains unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, it seems that Moromoto should have passed the post of Kanpaku on to his eldest son Norimoto by then at the latest but that timing remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, it seems that Moromoto should have passed the post of Kanpaku on to his eldest son Norimoto by then at the latest but that timing remains unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし、出家はしたが、隠居をしたわけではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromoto entered the priesthood but it did not mean he went into retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromoto entered the priesthood but it did not mean he went into retirement.</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moromoto entered the priesthood but it did not mean he went into retirement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>1360年（正平15年 / 延文5年）4月25日、大塔宮護良親王の子で南朝側であった興良親王（大塔若宮）が、赤松氏範らと共に、突然、南朝の本拠である賀名生行宮を襲撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 25, 1360, Imperial Prince Okiyoshi (also known as Oto no wakamiya), together with his supporters including Ujinori AKAMATSU, made a surprise attack on Anoangu, the headquarters of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 25, 1360, Imperial Prince Okiyoshi (also known as Oto no wakamiya), together with his supporters including Ujinori AKAMATSU, made a surprise attack on Anoangu, the headquarters of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 25, 1360, Imperial Prince Okiyoshi (also known as Oto no wakamiya), together with his supporters including Ujinori AKAMATSU, made a surprise attack on Anoangu, the headquarters of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>翌日、二条師基は大将軍に任ぜられ、反撃を開始、3日後に鎮圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following day, Moromoto NIJO was appointed as Dai Shogun (the Great General) and launched a counterattack repressing the rebellion after 3 days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following day, Moromoto NIJO was appointed as Dai Shogun (the Great General) and launched a counterattack repressing the rebellion after 3 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following day, Moromoto NIJO was appointed as Dai Shogun (the Great General) and launched a counterattack repressing the rebellion after 3 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>興良親王は逃してしまったが、反乱軍のほとんどの兵は討ち取り、または、捕らえることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Imperial Prince Okiyoshi managed to escape, Moromoto&apos;s army successfully killed or captured most of the soldiers of the rebel army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Imperial Prince Okiyoshi managed to escape, Moromoto&apos;s army successfully killed or captured most of the soldiers of the rebel army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Imperial Prince Okiyoshi managed to escape, Moromoto&apos;s army successfully killed or captured most of the soldiers of the rebel army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>最後の参陣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromoto&apos;s last participation in war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromoto&apos;s last participation in war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moromoto&apos;s last participation in war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>1361年（正平16年 / 康安元年）12月、細川清氏・楠木正儀らと共に、京都の奪還作戦に参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1361, along with various allies including Kiyouji HOSOKAWA and Masanori KUSUNOKI, Moromoto participated in the operation to regain Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December 1361, along with various allies including Kiyouji HOSOKAWA and Masanori KUSUNOKI, Moromoto participated in the operation to regain Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December 1361, along with various allies including Kiyouji HOSOKAWA and Masanori KUSUNOKI, Moromoto participated in the operation to regain Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>ただし、『神護寺交衆任日次第』に「同（1361年12月）八日、宮方軍勢二条関白、帥大納言師基御息入京」とあることから、参戦していたのは師基自身ではなく長男の教基とも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is, however, considered that it was Moromoto&apos;s eldest son Norimoto and not Moromoto who participated in war based on the entry in Jingoji Kyoshuninjitsu stating &apos;On December 8, 1361, the Imperial army including the son of Nijo Kanpaku 帥大納言師基entered Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>帥大納言師基　－　読み・意味不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is, however, considered that it was Moromoto&apos;s eldest son Norimoto and not Moromoto who participated in war based on the entry in Jingoji Kyoshuninjitsu stating &apos;On December 8, 1361, the Imperial army including the son of Nijo Kanpaku 帥大納言師基entered Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is, however, considered that it was Moromoto&apos;s eldest son Norimoto and not Moromoto who participated in war based on the entry in &quot;Jingoji Kyoshuninjitsu&quot; stating &apos;On December 8, 1361, the Imperial army including the son of Nijo Kanpaku Sochi Dainagon Moromoto entered Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>引用符を追加帥大納言をSochi Dainagonとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>死去</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>『大乗院日記目録』によると、1365年（正平20年 / 貞治4年）1月26日没、享年66であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Daijoin Nikkimokuroku, Moromoto died on January 26, 1365 at the age of 66.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Daijoin Nikkimokuroku, Moromoto died on January 26, 1365 at the age of 66.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Daijoin Nikkimokuroku&quot;(Catalog of the diary of Daijoin), Moromoto died on January 26, 1365 at the age of 66.</e>
<cmt>引用符を追加、文献の説明を追加。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>妻子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>妻は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moromoto&apos;s wife was unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moromoto&apos;s wife was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moromoto&apos;s wife was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>子は、二条教基と教忠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children included Norimoto and Noritada NIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included Norimoto and Noritada NIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included Norimoto and Noritada NIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>長慶天皇・後亀山天皇の生母、嘉喜門院の実父ないし養父との説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that Moromoto was either the biological or adoptive father of Kakimon-in who was the birth mother of Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that Moromoto was either the biological or adoptive father of Kakimon-in who was the birth mother of Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama.</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that Moromoto was either the biological or adoptive father of Kakimon-in who was the birth mother of Emperor Chokei and Emperor Gokameyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>官位履歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career of job grade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career and job grade</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career and job grade</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>官位と位階の履歴は以下の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of his court ranks and orders is as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of his court ranks and orders is as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of his court ranks and orders is as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>年齢は数え年、月日は旧暦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ages are given based on the traditional Japanese system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ages are given based on the traditional Japanese system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ages are given based on the traditional Japanese system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Oxhop(id:2551), 伏儀(id:142093), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>