<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原公則</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinnori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kinnori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinnori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原公則（ふじわら　の　きんのり、生没年不詳）は、平安時代後期の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinnori (dates of birth and death unknown) was a court noble in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kinnori (dates of birth and death unknown) was a court noble during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinnori (year of birth and death unknown) was a court noble during the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>概ね11世紀の半ばから後期にかけて活動。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was active from about the mid to the late eleventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was active from about the middle to the late eleventh century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was active from about the middle to the late 11th century.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原北家魚名流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Uona of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was related to FUJIWARA no Uona of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the Uona lineage of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたので、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>民部少輔藤原伊伝の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A son of Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs) FUJIWARA no Koretsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the son of Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs) FUJIWARA no Koretsugu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the son of Minbu shoyu (Junior Assistant Minister of Popular Affairs) FUJIWARA no Koretsugu.</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたので、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>文徳源氏源章経の養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An adopted son of Montoku-Genji (Minamoto clan) MINAMOTO no Akitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An adopted son of the Montoku-Genji (Minamoto clan) MINAMOTO no Akitsune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An adopted son of the Montoku-Genji (Minamoto clan) MINAMOTO no Akitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>従四位下（または従四位上）・備後守。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank), or Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), Bingo no kuni kokushi (the provincial governor of Bingo Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He held Jushii (Junior Fourth Rank), or Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), Bingo no kuni kokushi (the provincial governor of Bingo Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He held Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), (or Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)), Bingo no kami (Governor of Bingo Province).</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたので、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>摂関家藤原師通の家司を務める一方、信濃国・河内国・尾張国・伊勢国の国守等地方官を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While serving as Keishi (household superintendent) of Sekkan-ke (family which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Moromichi, he successively held the positions of local officials such as Shinano no kuni no kami (Governor of Shinano Province), Kawachi no kuni no kami (Governor of Kawachi Province), Owari no kuni no kami (Governor of Owari Province), and Ise no kuni no kami (Governor of Ise Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While serving as Keishi (household superintendent) of Sekkan-ke (family which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Moromichi, he successively held the positions of local officials such as Shinano no kuni no kami (Governor of Shinano Province), Kawachi no kuni no kami (Governor of Kawachi Province), Owari no kuni no kami (Governor of Owari Province), and Ise no kuni no kami (Governor of Ise Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While serving as Keishi (household superintendent) of Sekkan-ke (family which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Moromichi, he successively held the positions of local officers such as Governors of Shinano Province, Kawachi Province, Owari Province and Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>長久元年（1040年）、乱立する荘園に憂い、それを阻止すべく荘園の停止を朝廷に訴えるなどの活動を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1040, being concerned with scattered shoen (manor), he took action to inhibit that by requesting the imperial court to terminate shoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1040, being concerned with scattered shoen (manor), he took action to inhibit them by requesting the imperial court to terminate shoen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1040, being concerned with scattered shoen (manor), he took action to inhibit them by requesting the Imperial Court to terminate shoen.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>それを契機として、同年「長久の荘園整理令」を皮切りに数度に亘り荘園整理令が発令された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This triggered official announcement of several decrees restricting the expansion of private estates, starting with the &quot;Chokyu Decree Restricting the Expansion of Private Estates.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This triggered an official announcement of several decrees starting with the &quot;Chokyu Decree Restricting the Expansion of Private Estates.&quot;</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This triggered an official announcement of several decrees starting with the &apos;Chokyu Decree Restricting the Expansion of Private Estates&apos; to organize shoen.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Snap55(id:89773), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>