<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>勧修寺経理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneosa KAJUJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneosa KASHUJI</e>
<cmt>原文の読みに合わせKASHUJIとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneosa KASHUJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>勧修寺 経理（かしゅうじ つねおさ、文政8年10月12日 (旧暦)（1825年11月21日）公式の記録類では、生日を文政11年10月12日（1828年11月18日）とされているが、勧修寺家の雑掌などを務め、尚侍勧修寺徳子より経理の教育係に任じられた地下人官人袖岡文景の日記『山城国京都袖岡玄蕃助家記』（国文学研究資料館所蔵）天保10年4月8日条に「……山科殿より御入輿 万千姫御腹文政八年十月十二日御出生、当年真実十五歳、（中略）漸至当春 稲丸殿御家督治定、御年齢真実十五歳候所、相省十二歳ヲ以今般初位従五位下御申上ニ相成候……」と記しており、年齢を3歳ずらして届け出たことを記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneosa KAJUJI (born on October 12 in the eighth year of the Bunsei era in old calendar, (November 21, 1825): although public records say that he was born on October 12 in the 11th year of the Bunsei era (November 18, 1828), his real birthday was three years earlier, according to &quot;The family record by Genbanosuke YUOKA in the Province of Yamashiro, Kyoto (in the possession of National Institute of Japanese Literature),&quot; the diary of Bunkei YUOKA, who was a &apos;Jigenin&apos; (a court official who wasn&apos;t Tenjobito) and government official and served as &apos;zassho (a person in charge of miscellaneous tasks)&apos; for the Kajuji family and was asked to educate Tuneosa by Tokuko KAJUJI: the diary, written on April 8 in the tenth year of the Tempo era, says, &apos;the fact is that Tsuneosa is fifteen years old this year; Senhime, who came to the family as a bride, gave a birth to him on October tenth in the tenth year of the Bunsei Era (1825); however it is recorded that he is only twelve years old and was given his first rank, Junior Fifth-low Court Rank....&apos;</e>
<cmt>袖岡文景の読み方が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneosa KASHUJI (Although he was born on November 21, 1825, his birthday was officially recorded as November 18, 1828): in &quot;Yamashiro no Kuni Kyoto SODEOKA Genbanosuke Kaki&quot; (The Family Chronicle of Genbanosuke SODEOKA in Kyoto, Yamashiro Province), (housed in the National Institute of Japanese Literature), written by Fumikage SODEOKA, a Jige official (the government officials of lower- ranked courtiers who were not allowed to enter the court) and a Zassho (or Karei: butler) served for the Kashuji family, who was asked to be a private tutor of Tsuneosa by Nariko KASHUJI, it is read &apos;.....Mansenhime who came to the family as a bride gave a birth to Tsuneosa on October twelfth in the eighth year of the Bunsei era, so Tsuneosa&apos;s true age was fifteen years old this year; however it was recorded that he was only twelve years old when he was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) as his first court rank....&apos; in the section of April 8, the tenth year of the Tempo era, which means his age was reported three years younger than actual for the official recording.</e>
<cmt>万千姫はMansenhimeとしましたが、読み方が確認できる資料は見つかりませんでした。家記中に記載の年月日は西暦には直していません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneosa KASHUJI (Although he was born on November 21, 1825, his birthday was officially recorded as November 18, 1828): in &quot;Yamashiro no Kuni Kyoto SODEOKA Genbanosuke Kaki&quot; (The Family Chronicle of Genbanosuke SODEOKA in Kyoto, Yamashiro Province), (housed in the National Institute of Japanese Literature), written by Fumikage SODEOKA, a Jige official (the government officials of lower- ranked courtiers who were not allowed to enter the court) and a Zassho (or Karei: butler) served for the Kashuji family, who was asked to be a private tutor of Tsuneosa by Nariko KASHUJI, it is read &apos;.....Mansenhime who came to the family as a bride gave a birth to Tsuneosa on October twelfth in the eighth year of the Bunsei era, so Tsuneosa&apos;s true age was fifteen years old this year; however it was recorded that he was only twelve years old when he was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) as his first court rank....&apos; in the section of April 8, the tenth year of the Tempo era, which means his age was reported three years younger than actual for the official recording.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>なお、同日条には、経理の同母兄・穂波経治（阿古丸）の年齢（公式には文政7年7月13日生）も「穂波殿御相続之時御年齢一ヶ年相退」と記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also wrote in the same diary that Tsuneosa&apos;s elder brother, to who Senhim gave a birth, Tsuneharu HONAMI (Akomaru) (who was officialy recorded to have been born on July 13 Bunsei 7) was actually one year older than he was publicly recorded &quot;at the time of &apos;Honami dono&apos;&apos;s succession.&quot;</e>
<cmt>経治の読み方がわかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same section, the age of Tsuneharu HONAMI (Akomaru), the older brother of Tsuneosa, born on August 7, 1824 according to the official record, was mentioned one year younger when he succeeded to the Honami family.</e>
<cmt>文政7年7月13日は西暦1824年8月7日です。「」内は特に分けずに訳しました。「年齢一ヶ年相退」は「年齢を一年減らしている」と解釈しました　older -&gt; younger</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same section, the age of Tsuneharu HONAMI (Akomaru), the older brother of Tsuneosa, born on August 7, 1824 according to the official record, was mentioned one year younger when he succeeded to the Honami family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本項では、同記事の出生日を採用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This passage is written based on that diary.</e>
<cmt>Paragraphが複数ある、というので、passageを使っています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this paragraph, the birthday in the family chronicle is adopted.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this paragraph, the birthday in the family chronicle is adopted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>詳細は西村慎太郎「近世後期堂上公家勧修寺家の雑掌について―蔵人方地下官人袖岡文景『家記』を事例に」（初出『史料館研究紀要』第34号（2003年3月）・所収「堂上公家雑掌の地下官人」（加筆・改題）『近世朝廷社会と地下官人』（吉川弘文館、2008年） ISBN 978-4-642-02330-6 P274-275）を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the details in &apos;On Zassho of the Kajuji family, the Toshokuge of late recent times ---&quot;the Family Record&quot; written by Fumikage Yuoka, &apos;Kurogata Jigekajin&apos; as an example&quot;&apos; by Shintaro NISHIMURA (the first appearance in &quot;Proceedings of Historical Museum&quot; No. 34 (March, 2003)) included in &apos;Zassho Jigekajin of Toshokuge&apos; and &quot;the Medieval Imperial Court and Jigekanjin (addition and alteration to the original),&quot; (Yoshikawa KobunkanInc., 2008) ISBN 978-4-642-02330-6 P274-275).</e>
<cmt>袖岡文景の読み方が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For detail information, refer to &apos;On Zassho (or Karei: butler) of the Kashuji family, the Toshokuge (high court nobility who is allowed to enter the Imperial Palace) of late modern ages ---&quot;Kaki&quot; (The Family Chronicle) written by Fumikage SODEOKA, Kurodogata Jigekanjin (lower-ranked courtiers who were not allowed to enter the court official of Chamberlain&apos;s Office)&apos; as an example&quot; by Shintaro NISHIMURA (the first appearance was in &quot;Proceedings of Historical Museum&quot; No. 34 [March, 2003]) included in &apos;Zassho Jigekanjin of Toshokuge&apos; (addition and alteration to the original) and &quot;the Medieval Imperial Court and Jigekanjin&quot; (Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc., 2008) ISBN 978-4-642-02330-6 P274-275).</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For detail information, refer to &apos;On Zassho (or Karei: butler) of the Kashuji family, the Toshokuge (high court nobility who is allowed to enter the Imperial Palace) of late modern ages ---&quot;Kaki&quot; (The Family Chronicle) written by Fumikage SODEOKA, Kurodogata Jigekanjin (lower-ranked courtiers who were not allowed to enter the court official of Chamberlain&apos;s Office)&apos; as an example&quot; by Shintaro NISHIMURA (the first appearance was in &quot;Proceedings of Historical Museum&quot; No. 34 [March, 2003]) included in &apos;Zassho Jigekanjin of Toshokuge&apos; (addition and alteration to the original) and &quot;the Medieval Imperial Court and Jigekanjin&quot; (Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc., 2008) ISBN 978-4-642-02330-6 P274-275).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>－明治4年6月19日 (旧暦)（1871年8月5日）は、幕末の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A court noble in the end of the Edo Period (born on August 5, 1871).</e>
<cmt>原文の主語が不明です。また、以前からの問題ですが、最初に-があると処理に問題が生じるので、-は省いています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneosa passed away on August 5, 1871, and was a Kuge (court noble) in the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>明治4年6月19日は経理が亡くなった日付です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneosa passed away on August 5, 1871, and was a Kuge (court noble) in the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>勧修寺経則の3男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneosa KAJUJI was the third son of Tsunenori KAJUJI.</e>
<cmt>修理が主語と判断しました。また、経則の読み方は確認できませんでした。（Tsunenoriとしています。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneosa was the third son of Tsunetoki KASHUJI.</e>
<cmt>KAJUJI -&gt; KASHUJI経則：つねときhttp://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%8B%A7%E4%BF%AE%E5%AF%BA%E7%B5%8C%E5%89%87</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneosa was the third son of Tsunetoki KASHUJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>勧修寺顕彰（経則養子）の養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted to Akiteru KAJUJI (who was adopted to Teunenori).</e>
<cmt>修理が顕彰の養子で、顕彰が経則の養子と判断しました。経則の読み方は確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by Akiteru KASHUJI (adopted son of Tsunetoki).</e>
<cmt>KAJUJI -&gt; KASHUJI</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by Akiteru KASHUJI (adopted son of Tsunetoki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幼名は稲丸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His child name was Inamaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His childhood name was Inamaru.</e>
<cmt>child name -&gt; childhood name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His childhood name was Inamaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>実兄に穂波経治、子に勧修寺顕允（伯爵）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real brother was Tsuneharu HONAMI and his son was Akimitsu KAJUJI (a count).</e>
<cmt>経治 (Tsuneharuとしています）、顕允(Akimitsuとしています）の読み方が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His biological brother was Tsuneharu HONAMI and his son was Akiyoshi KASHUJI (a count).</e>
<cmt>real -&gt; biologicalKAJUJI -&gt; KASHUJI顕允：あきよし下記サイトしか読みが掲載されていませんでした。ひとまず「あきよし」としています。http://www.purunus.com/index.php/%E5%8B%A7%E4%BF%AE%E5%AF%BA%E9%A1%95%E5%85%81</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His biological brother was Tsuneharu HONAMI and his son was Akiyoshi KASHUJI (a count).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>実父・経則が従兄弟である顕彰に家督を譲った後に誕生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born after his biological father, Tsunenori, gave the family estate to his cousin, Akiteru.</e>
<cmt>経則の読み方は確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born after his biological father, Tsunetoki, gave the reigns of the Kashuji family to his cousin, Akiteru.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born after his biological father, Tsunetoki, gave the reigns of the Kashuji family to his cousin, Akiteru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、顕彰の後継者を巡って経則と顕彰、勧修寺家の家臣の間に対立が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That resulted in a confrontation about the successor between Tsunenori and Akiteru and also among the vassals of the Kajuji family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The succession to the family caused a confrontation over the heir to Akiteru between Tsunetaka and Akiteru involving the vassals of the Kashuji family.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The succession to the family caused a confrontation over the heir to Akiteru between Tsunetaka and Akiteru involving the vassals of the Kashuji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その結果、兄・経治と穂波経度（顕彰の子）はともに穂波家への養子として出されて（経治が穂波家を継ぎ、経度を養子とする）経理が後継者となり、天保10年4月8日（1839年5月20日）に従五位下が授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The confrontation was settled in the following way; Tsuneosa&apos;s elder brother, Tsuneharu, and Tsunetada HONAMI (Akiteru&apos;s son) were adopted to the Honami family (Tsuneharu succceeded to the Honami family and adopted Tsunetada), and Tsuneosa succeeded to the Kajuji family and &apos;Jugoinoge((Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was given to him on May 20, 1839 (April 8, the tenth year of the Tempo era).</e>
<cmt>経度の読み方が確認できませんでした（Tsunetadaとしています）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The confrontation was settled in the following way; Tsuneosa&apos;s older brother, Tsuneharu, and Tsunenori HONAMI (a son of Akiteru) were adopted by the Honami family (Tsuneharu succeeded to the Honami family and adopted Tsunenori), and Tsuneosa succeeded to the Kashuji family and was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on May 20, 1839.</e>
<cmt>穂波経度：ほなみ　つねのりhttp://www1.parkcity.ne.jp/sito/k80.html</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The confrontation was settled in the following way; Tsuneosa&apos;s older brother, Tsuneharu, and Tsunenori HONAMI (a son of Akiteru) were adopted by the Honami family (Tsuneharu succeeded to the Honami family and adopted Tsunenori), and Tsuneosa succeeded to the Kashuji family and was conferred Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) on May 20, 1839.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>廷臣八十八卿列参事件に養父・顕彰及び穂波経度とともに参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneosa participated in Teishin hachiju-hachi kyo ressan jiken (Demo of eighty-eight retainers of Imperial Court) together with his adopted father, Akinori and Tsunetada HONAMI.</e>
<cmt>経度の読み方が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneosa participated in Teishin hachiju-hachi kyo ressan jiken (Demo of eighty-eight retainers of Imperial Court) together with his foster father, Akiteru and Tsunenori HONAMI.</e>
<cmt>adopted father -&gt; foster fatherAkinori -&gt; AkiteruTsunetada -&gt; Tsunenori</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneosa participated in Teishin hachiju-hachi kyo ressan jiken (Demo of eighty-eight retainers of Imperial Court) together with his foster father, Akiteru and Tsunenori HONAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>文久3年（1863年）に右少弁、元治元年（1864年）に蔵人に任じられるが、勧修寺家が毛利氏の執奏家であったために禁門の変に座して官職を奪われて蟄居を命じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">AlthoughTsuneosa was appointed to Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) on the third year of the Bunkyu era (1863) and Kurodo (Chamberlain) in the first year of the Ganji era (1864), he was deprived of those government posts and ordered to confined to his house, related to Kinmon Incident (Conspiracy of Kimmon), since the Kajuji family had been the &apos;Shisso&apos; family of the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Tsuneosa was appointed to Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1863 and Kurodo (Chamberlain) in 1864, he was dismissed from the government posts and placed under house arrest over the charge of the involvement of Kinmon Incident (Conspiracy of Kinmon) as the Kashuji family had been the Shisso family (the family which served as the intermediary between the Court and the Shogunate government) of the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>英文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Tsuneosa was appointed to Ushoben (Minor Controller of the Right) in 1863 and Kurodo (Chamberlain) in 1864, he was dismissed from the government posts and placed under house arrest over the charge of the involvement of Kinmon Incident (Conspiracy of Kinmon) as the Kashuji family had been the Shisso family (the family which served as the intermediary between the Court and the Shogunate government) of the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>明治元年（1868年）1月に赦免され、閏4月に従四位下右中弁に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, the first year of the Meiji era (1868), Tsuneosa was forgiven and appointed to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right) in April.</e>
<cmt>閏4月の定訳が見つかりませんでした。Aprilとだけ書いています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1868, he was forgiven and appointed to Jushiinoge Uchuben (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, Middle Controller of the Right) in May.</e>
<cmt>明治元年閏4月は西暦1868年5月です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1868, he was forgiven and appointed to Jushiinoge Uchuben (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, Middle Controller of the Right) in May.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>