<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>下毛野石代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>下毛野 石代（しもつけぬ の いわしろ、生没年不詳）は、飛鳥時代から奈良時代にかけての貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro (year of birth and death unknown) was a noble who lived from Asuka period to Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro (year of birth and death unknown) was a noble who lived from Asuka period to Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro (year of birth and death unknown) was a noble who lived from Asuka period to Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>下野国を本拠地とする下毛野氏の出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was from the Shimotsukenu clan based in Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was from the Shimotsukenu clan based in Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was from the Shimotsukenu clan based in Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本姓は下毛野朝臣だが、続日本紀によると707年（慶雲4年）3月22日 (旧暦)、一族の下毛野古麻呂が石代の姓を「下毛野朝臣」から「下毛野川内朝臣」に変更することを朝廷に上申し、許可が下りていることから、この時点で下毛野川内朝臣に改姓したものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His main name was SHIMOTSUKENU no Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles), however, according to Shoku Nihongi (a history book), on May 2, 707, SHIMOTSUKENU no Komaro, a member of his family, asked the Imperial Court if SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro could change Iwashiro&apos;s family name into &apos;SHIMOTSUKENU no Kawachi Ason&apos; from &apos;SHIMOTSUKENU no Ason&apos; and received permission for it, therefore it is believed that Iwashiro changed his family name into SHIMOTSUKENU no Kawachi Ason at this point.</e>
<cmt>「下毛野川内朝臣」の「川内」の正確な読み不明でした。ここでは「かわち」という読みにしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His main name was SHIMOTSUKENU no Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles), however, according to Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan Continued), on May 2, 707 or March 22 on the old calendar, SHIMOTSUKENU no Komaro, a member of his family, asked the Imperial Court if SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro could change Iwashiro&apos;s family name into &apos;SHIMOTSUKENU no Kawachi Ason&apos; from &apos;SHIMOTSUKENU no Ason&apos; and received permission for it, therefore it is believed that Iwashiro changed his family name into SHIMOTSUKENU no Kawachi Ason at this point.</e>
<cmt>・続日本紀は、用語集の用語検索を参考に修正しました。・念のため旧暦も併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His main name was SHIMOTSUKENU no Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles), however, according to Shoku Nihongi (Chronicle of Japan Continued), on May 2, 707, SHIMOTSUKENU no Komaro, a member of his family, asked the Imperial Court if SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro could change Iwashiro&apos;s family name into &apos;SHIMOTSUKENU no Kawachi Ason&apos; from &apos;SHIMOTSUKENU no Ason&apos; and received permission for it, therefore it is believed that Iwashiro changed his family name into SHIMOTSUKENU no Kawachi Ason at this point.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>701年（大宝 (日本)元年）7月21日 (旧暦) - 文武天皇の命を受け、官人を代表し亡くなった多治比嶋を誄する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 2, 701, Iwashiro offered tributes to the exploits of departed TAJIHI no Shima on behalf of government official (lower or middle ranked) by order of the Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 2, 701or July 21 on the old calendar, Iwashiro offered tributes to the exploits of departed TAJIHI no Shima on behalf of government official (lower or middle ranked) by order of the Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt>・念のため旧暦も併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 2, 701, Iwashiro offered tributes to the exploits of departed TAJIHI no Shima on behalf of government official (lower or middle ranked) by order of the Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この時、石代の官位は従七位下であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwashiro&apos;s rank was Jushichii (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade) at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwashiro&apos;s rank was Jushichii (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade) at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwashiro&apos;s rank was Jushichii (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade) at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>715年（霊亀元年）1月10日 (旧暦) - 従六位下を下賜される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was granted Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) on February 22, 715.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was granted Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) on February 22, 715 or January 10 on the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>・念のため旧暦も併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was granted Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade) on February 22, 715.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>720年（養老4年）9月29日 (旧暦) - 陸奥国で起きた陸奥按察使上毛野廣人殺害事件に対し、この時左京亮従五位下であった石代は元正天皇より征夷副将軍に任ぜられ、これを征伐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 7, 720, when the murder of KAMITSUKENO Hiroto, Inspector of Mutsu (Mutsu no Azechi) occurred in Mutsu Province, Iwashiro who had been sakyo no suke (a governor who supervised central administration, security and administration of justice) was appointed to Seii fukushogun (sub commander of the expeditionary force against the barbarians) by the Empress Gensho and conquered it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 7, 720 or September 29 on the old calendar, when the murder of KAMITSUKENO Hiroto, Inspector of Mutsu (Mutsu no Azechi) occurred in Mutsu Province, Iwashiro who had been sakyo no suke (a governor who supervised central administration, security and administration of justice) and ranked as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was appointed to Seii fukushogun (sub commander of the expeditionary force against the barbarians) by the Empress Gensho and conquered it.</e>
<cmt>・従五位下がなかったので追加しました。・念のため旧暦も併記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 7, 720, when the murder of KAMITSUKENO Hiroto, Inspector of Mutsu (Mutsu no Azechi) occurred in Mutsu Province, Iwashiro who had been sakyo no suke (a governor who supervised central administration, security and administration of justice) and ranked as Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was appointed to Seii fukushogun (sub commander of the expeditionary force against the barbarians) by the Empress Gensho and conquered it.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 FCTR2(id:213046), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>