<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>馬加康胤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutane MAKUWARI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutane MAKUWARI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutane MAKUWARI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>馬加 康胤（まくわり やすたね、応永5年（1398年）? - 康正2年11月1日 (旧暦)（1456年11月28日））は、室町時代の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutane MAKUWARI (c.1398 - November 28, 1456) was a warlord in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutane MAKUWARI (c.1398 - November 28, 1456) was a warlord during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutane MAKUWARI (c.1398 - November 28, 1456) was a warlord during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は平氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real surname was &quot;Heishi&quot; (the Taira clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real surname was &quot;Heishi&quot; (the Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real surname was &quot;Heishi&quot; (the Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>千葉介・千葉満胤の子で、千葉 康胤（ちば やすたね）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a son of Tsunetane Chibanosuke, Chiba no suke (assistant governor of Chiba Province), he was also called Yasutane CHIBA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a son of Tsunetane Chibanosuke, Chiba no suke (assistant governor of Chiba Province), he was also called Yasutane CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a son of Mitsutane CHIBA, Chiba no suke (assistant governor of Chiba Province), he was also called Yasutane CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>「Tsunetane Chibanosuke」→「Mitsutane CHIBA」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>享徳の乱に乗じて、千葉氏宗家を攻め滅ばしてその19代当主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of Kyotoku War (a war between the Muromachi bakuru and its Kanto kanrei (deputy of shogun, who governed the Kanto region), Yasutane attacked and destroyed the head of the Chiba family, and became the nineteenth head of the clan himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of the Kyotoku War (a war between the Muromachi bakufu and its Kanto kanrei (deputy of shogun, who governed the Kanto region), Yasutane attacked and destroyed the head of the Chiba family, and became the nineteenth head of the clan himself.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of the Kyotoku War (series of battles between the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and the Kanto kanrei (shogun&apos;s deputy for the Kanto area), he attacked and destroyed the head family of the Chiba clan, and became the 19th head of the clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>下総国千葉郡馬加村（現在の千葉県千葉市花見川区幕張）に居を構えたことから「馬加」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because he built his residence in Makuwari-mura village, Chiba District, Shimousa Province (the present day&apos;s Makuhari, Hanamigawa-ku Ward, Chiba City, Chiba Prefecture), he called himself &quot;Makuwari&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because he built his residence in Makuwari-mura village, Chiba District, Shimousa Province (the present day Makuhari, Hanamigawa-ku Ward, Chiba City, Chiba Prefecture), he called himself &quot;Makuwari.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because he took up his residence in Makuwari-mura village, Chiba-gun, Shimosa Province (present-day Makuhari, Hanamigawa-ku Ward, Chiba City, Chiba Prefecture), he called himself &apos;Makuwari.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>享徳の乱において、鎌倉公方足利成氏と関東管領上杉氏が対立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyotoku War, Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, who had served as Kamakura kubo (governor-general of the Kanto region), feuded with the Uesugi clan, who had served as Kanto kanrei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kyotoku War, Shigeuji ASHIKAGA, who had served as the Kamakura kubo (governor-general of the Kanto region), feuded with the Uesugi clan, who had served as Kanto kanrei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kyotoku War, the Kamakura kubo (governor-general of the Kanto region) Shigeuji ASHIKAGA feuded with Kanto kanrei, the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その結果、成氏は、上杉氏を支持する京都の室町幕府の追討を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Shigeuji was attacked by the Muromachi bakufu in Kyoto, who supported the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Shigeuji was attacked by the Muromachi bakufu in Kyoto, who supported the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Shigeuji was hunted down by the Muromachi bakufu in Kyoto, which supported the Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>成氏は鎌倉を追われて下総国古河城（現在の茨城県古河市）に入り、「古河公方」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeuji, who left Kamakura, moved into Koga-jo Castle in Shimousa Province (today&apos;s Koga City, Ibaraki Prefecture), and called himself &quot;Koga kubo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeuji, who left Kamakura, moved into Koga-jo Castle in Shimousa Province (today&apos;s Koga City, Ibaraki Prefecture), and called himself &quot;Koga kubo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeuji fled Kamakura for Koga-jo Castle in Shimosa Province (present-day Koga City, Ibaraki Prefecture) where he called himself &apos;Koga kubo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>そのため、下総国の守護であった千葉氏の元には、幕府と成氏の双方から支援の依頼が寄せられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, requests for support came to the Chiba clan, who had governed the Province, from the both shogunate and Shigeuji sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, requests for support came to the Chiba clan, who had governed the Province, from both the shogunate and Shigeuji sides.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, both bakufu and Shigeuji called on military reinforcements from the Chiba clan, the shugo (military governor) of Shimosa Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>千葉氏宗家当主である千葉胤直は幕府の依頼を受けて成氏討伐に乗り出すが、叔父である康胤は成氏支援を主張して対立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanenao CHIBA, who was the head of the Chiba clan, set out to attack Shigeuji at the request of the bakufu, but his uncle, Yasutane, opposed to it, insisting that they should support Shigeuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanenao CHIBA, who was the head of the Chiba clan, set out to attack Shigeuji at the request of the bakufu, but his uncle, Yasutane, opposed it, insisting that they should support Shigeuji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanenao CHIBA, the head of the Chiba clan, set out to defeat Shigeuji to comply with the bakufu&apos;s request, but Tanenao&apos;s uncle Yasutane opposed it, insisting that they should send military reinforcements to Shigeuji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これに筆頭重臣の地位を巡る原氏と円城寺氏の対立が絡んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This confrontation was further exacerbated by the hostility between the Hara and Enjoji clans, who had been vying for the position of the chief retainer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This confrontation was further exacerbated by the hostility between the Hara and Enjoji clans, who had been vying for the position of the chief retainer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This confrontation was exacerbated by a power struggle between the Hara clan and the Enjoji clan over the position of the chief retainer.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>家中は二分される事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the whole clan was divided into two.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the whole clan was divided into two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the retainers of the Chiba clan split into two camps.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>そこで1455年（享徳4年）、康胤は原胤房とともに、千葉胤直・胤宣父子を猪鼻（亥鼻城）（現在の千葉県千葉市中央区 (千葉市)亥鼻）に攻め、千田庄（現在の千葉県香取郡多古町付近）へ追いやった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1455, Yasutane, together with Tanefusa HARA, attacked Tanenao CHIBA and his son, Tanenobu CHIBA, who were at Inohana (Inohana-jo Castle) (the present day&apos;s Inohana, Chuo-ku Ward, Chiba City, Chiba Prefecture), and drove them out to Sendasho (today&apos;s Tako-machi, Katori-gun, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1455, Yasutane, together with Tanefusa HARA, attacked Tanenao CHIBA and his son, Tanenobu CHIBA, who were at Inohana (Inohana-jo Castle) (the present day&apos;s Inohana, Chuo-ku Ward, Chiba City, Chiba Prefecture), and drove them out to Sendasho (today&apos;s Tako-machi, Katori-gun, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1455, Yasutane, together with Tanefusa HARA, attacked Tanenao CHIBA and Tanenao&apos;s son Tanenobu CHIBA at Inohana (Inohana-jo Castle) (present-day Inohana, Chuo-ku Ward, Chiba City, Chiba Prefecture), and drove them into Chida no sho Manor (present-day the area in and around Tako-machi Town, Katori-gun County, Chiba Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直し、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後、千田庄の多古城・島城にたてこもる胤直父子や円城寺尚任を攻め滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasutane eventually destroyed Tanenao, his son, Tanenobu, and Hisato ENJOJI, who had barricaded themselves at Tako-jo Castle and Shima-jo Castle in Sendasho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutane eventually destroyed Tanenao, his son, Tanenobu, and Hisato ENJOJI, who had barricaded themselves at Tako-jo Castle and Shima-jo Castle in Sendasho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutane eventually destroyed Tanenao, Tanenao&apos;s son Tanenobu, and Hisato ENJOJI, who had entrenched themselves in Tako-jo Castle and Shima-jo Castle in Chida no sho Manor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>仏に仕える身にありながら千葉氏第19代当主千葉 康胤（ちば やすたね）を名乗る（しかし前当主を生涯立てていた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he was a priest, he became the nineteenth head of the Chiba clan (but, he never failed to pay respect to the ex-lord for the rest of his life).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was a priest, he became the nineteenth head of the Chiba clan (but, he never failed to pay respect to the ex-lord for the rest of his life).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he had become a priest, that is to say he had renounced the world, he still titled himself the 19th head of the Chiba clan Yasutane CHIBA (but he never failed to pay respect to the former head of the clan for the rest of his life).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>これに対して、室町幕府の征夷大将軍足利義政は、この乱を治めるため歌人で千葉氏の一族でもある美濃国郡上郡篠脇城主東常縁を派遣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To quell the war, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;the great general who subdues barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu, dispatched Tsuneyori TO, who was the lord of Shinowaki-jo Castle in Gujo-gun, Mino Province, a poet, and a relative of the Chiba clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To quell the war, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;the great general who subdues barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu, dispatched Tsuneyori TO, who was the lord of Shinowaki-jo Castle in Gujo-gun, Mino Province, a poet, and a relative of the Chiba clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To cope with the situation, Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA dispatched Tsuneyori TO, the lord of Shinowaki-jo Castle in Gujo-gun, Mino Province, who was a poet and also a member of the Chiba clan, to quell the disturbances.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>康胤の最期については、上総国八幡（現在の千葉県市原市八幡町）の村田川で常縁に討たれたという伝承があるが、不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a legend, Yasutane was attacked and killed by Tsuneyori in the Murata-gawa River in Hachiman, Kamifusa Province (the present day&apos;s Yawata-cho, Ichihara City, Chiba Prefecture) although this remains unproven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to legend, Yasutane was attacked and killed by Tsuneyori in the Murata-gawa River in Hachiman, Kamifusa Province (the present day&apos;s Yawata-cho, Ichihara City, Chiba Prefecture) although this remains unproven.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to legend, Yasutane was killed by Tsuneyori in the Murata-gawa River in Yawata in Kazusa Province (present-day Yawata-cho Town, Ichihara City, Chiba Prefecture), although this remained unproven.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。文字化けを直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), 梟(id:117930), Okapia2(id:98589), Bonten2007(id:156965), 海衛士(id:19229), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Juyukichi(id:16958), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>