<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>片岡直輝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoteru KATAOKA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoteru KATAOKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoteru KATAOKA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>片岡 直輝（かたおか なおてる、安政3年7月3日 (旧暦)（1856年8月3日） - 昭和2年（1927年）4月13日）は、明治・大正・昭和初期の実業家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoteru KATAOKA (August 3, 1856 - April 13, 1927) was a businessman in the Meiji, Taisho and early Showa periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoteru KATAOKA (August 3, 1856 - April 13, 1927) was a businessman in the Meiji, Taisho and early Showa periods.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoteru KATAOKA (August 3, 1856 - April 13, 1927) was a businessman in the Meiji, Taisho and early Showa periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>貴族院議員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A member of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A member of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A member of the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>土佐国出身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His birthplace was in Tosa province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His birthplace was in Tosa province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His birthplace was in Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>片岡直温の兄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elder brother to Naoharu Kataoka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elder brother to Naoharu Kataoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elder brother to Naoharu KATAOKA.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>戦前の関西経済を牽引した人物の一人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the personalities who contributed the economic development and growth of Kansai region before the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the personalities who contributed to the economic development and growth of Kansai region before the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the personalities who contributed to the economic development and growth of Kansai region before the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出生から日銀退職まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From his birth to the time of his separation from Nichigin. (The National Bank of Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From his birth to the time of his separation from Nichigin. (The National Bank of Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From his birth to the time of his separation from Bank of Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>7月3日、父・孫五郎直英と母・信子の長男として土佐国高岡郡下半山村（現高知県津野町）で誕生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born to the first son to Naohide MAGOGORO and Nobuko in Tosa Province, Takaoka gun, Shitahansanson (present Kochi Prefecture, Tsuno Machi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born to the first son to Naohide MAGOGORO and Nobuko in Tosa Province, Takaoka gun, Shitahansanson (present Kochi Prefecture, Tsuno Machi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Born to the first son to Naohide MAGOGORO and Nobuko in Shitahansan village, Takaoka County, Tosa Province (present Tsuno Machi, Kochi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>住所表記修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>生家は近隣に家のない寂しい一軒家であったが、直輝や弟・直温が幼少時代を過ごした時期は幕末であり、その立地条件から勤王の志士に秘密の集会所として、また潜伏場所としてたびたび利用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He lived his childhood along with his younger brother Naoharu in the house he was born which was located in isolated location during the end of Edo Period, and because of its isolation, the place was often used by the loyalists to Emperor for their clandestine meetings and hiding place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He lived his childhood along with his younger brother Naoharu in the house where he was born located in an isolated location during the end of the Edo Period, and because of its isolation, the place was often used by loyalists to the Emperor for their clandestine meetings and as a hiding place.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He lived his childhood along with his younger brother Naoharu in the house where he was born located in an isolated location during the end of the Edo period, and because of its isolation, the place was often used by loyalists to the Emperor for their clandestine meetings and as a hiding place.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その当時、直輝や直温はまだ少年であり、あまり深く関わることはなかったが、父・直英は勤王に傾倒していたため、私財を投じて支援した結果、家計は火の車であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Naoteru and Naoharu were too young to be involved at the time, their father Naohide was deeply devoted to support the loyalists for Emperor and they were struggling to make ends meet as a result of spending his own funds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Naoteru and Naoharu were too young to be involved at the time, their father Naohide was deeply devoted to support the loyalists for Emperor and they were struggling to make ends meet as a result of spending his own funds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Naoteru and Naoharu were too young to be involved at the time, their father Naohide was deeply devoted to support the loyalists for Emperor and they were struggling to make ends meet as a result of spending his own funds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>さらに追い打ちをかけるように、その父が病没してしまい多大な借金だけが残され、母・信子は借金を返すため昼夜を問わず働き続け、また直温は東林寺に預けられて兄弟は別れることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Worse still, their father died from illness and left them a large debt that compelled their mother Nobuko to work day and night in order to repay the debt, and consequently the brothers were separated as Naoharu was sent to Torinji-temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Worse still, their father died from illness and left them a large debt that compelled their mother Nobuko to work day and night in order to repay the debt, and consequently the brothers were separated as Naoharu was sent to Torinji-temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Worse still, their father died from illness and left them a large debt that compelled their mother Nobuko to work day and night in order to repay the debt, and consequently the brothers were separated as Naoharu was sent to Torin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>直輝は勉学に励み、14歳の時に十数人の弟子を取り、わずかの報酬ながら家計を助けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoteru studied assiduously and he had a little over ten students under his aegis when he was fourteen in which he was able to help the household with his meager earnings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoteru studied assiduously and he had a little over ten students under his aegis when he was fourteen in which he was able to help the household with his meager earnings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoteru studied assiduously and he had a little over ten students under his aegis when he was fourteen in which he was able to help the household with his meager earnings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、信子が直温を寺より引き取ることとなり、直温に信子と家のことを頼み5月、16歳の時に上京する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Nobuko brought back Naoharu from the temple and he left for Tokyo in May when he was sixteen after making the necessary arrangement for the household and Naoharu to Nobuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Nobuko brought Naoharu back from the temple and he left for Tokyo in May when he was sixteen after making the necessary arrangement for the household and Naoharu to Nobuko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Nobuko brought Naoharu back from the temple and he left for Tokyo in May when he was sixteen after making the necessary arrangement for the household and Naoharu to Nobuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>上京後は親族に寄食し、まず電信学校に入学したが志に合わず、その後に海軍主計学校へ入学することとなる（両校とも就学中は学費が必要なかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After arriving in Tokyo, he stayed with his relatives house and enrolled in a telegraph school but after learning it was not to his liking, he enrolled in the Naval Accounting School (neither school required tuition).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After arriving in Tokyo, he stayed at his relatives house and enrolled in telegraph school but after learning it was not to his liking, he enrolled in the Naval Accounting School (neither school required tuition).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After arriving in Tokyo, he stayed at his relatives house and enrolled in telegraph school but after learning it was not to his liking, he enrolled in the Naval Accounting School (neither school required tuition).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>随行員や軍艦の員外乗船などを経験し、、海軍主計学校卒業とともに海軍主計副として海軍入りする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He enlisted in the Navy as an assistant Naval Pay Officer upon graduation after having the experiences of being an accompanying attendant, non-crew member warship boarding and like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He enlisted in the Navy as an assistant Naval Pay Officer upon graduation after having the experiences of being an accompanying attendant, non-crew member warship boarding and like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He enlisted in the Navy as an assistant Naval Pay Officer upon graduation after having the experiences of being an accompanying attendant, non-crew member warship boarding and like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>主計課長心得、中主計を経て、西郷従道海軍大臣が欧米各国へ派遣されるにあたり、その随行員として抜擢されたことに合わせ海軍大主計となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to the position of the director of the Navy budget bureau after the ranks of shukeikacho kokoroe (assistant to pay officer section chief) and chushukei (assistant director) of the Navy budget bureau in time with his selection as a member of the Navy Minister Michitugu SAIGO&apos;s suite that was sent to Europe and North America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to the position of the director of the Navy budget bureau after the ranks of shukeikacho kokoroe (assistant to pay officer section chief) and chushukei (assistant director) of the Navy budget bureau in time with his selection as a member of the Navy Minister Michitugu SAIGO&apos;s suite that was sent to Europe and North America.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to the position of the director of the Navy budget bureau after the ranks of shukeikacho kokoroe (assistant to pay officer section chief) and chushukei (assistant director) of the Navy budget bureau in time with his selection as a member of the Navy Minister Michitsugu SAIGO&apos;s suite that was sent to Europe and North America.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>帰国後は、海相外遊中の残務の取り扱いなどを代行、フランスへの派遣、また「厳島 (巡洋艦)」主計長の兼任など尽力したが、9月、その任を解かれ武官時代に終わりを告げることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon return, he rendered his services in handling the work left over from the Minister of the Navy&apos;s official travel abroad, went to France, also assumed the position of chief accounting officer of a cruiser Itsukushima however his military career ended when he was discharged from the duties in September.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon his return, he rendered his services in handling the work left over from the Minister of the Navy&apos;s official travel abroad, went to France, also assumed the position of chief accounting officer of the cruiser Itsukushima however his military career ended when he was discharged from his duties in September.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon his return, he rendered his services in handling the work left over from the Minister of the Navy&apos;s official travel abroad, went to France, also assumed the position of chief accounting officer of the cruiser Itsukushima however his military career ended when he was discharged from his duties in September.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>海軍を去った後の7月、直輝と同郷であった河野敏鎌内務大臣の推挙を受け秘書官に任命されて文官時代が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After leaving the Navy, the following July he was appointed to the position of secretary to the Homeland Minister Tagama KONO upon recommendation from which his civil officer career began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After leaving the Navy, the following July he was appointed to the position of secretary to the Homeland Minister Tagama KONO upon recommendations from which his civil officer career began.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After leaving the Navy, the following July he was appointed to the position of secretary to the Homeland Minister Togama KONO upon recommendations from which his civil officer career began.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>同年9月、河野内相が文部大臣になると再び文相秘書官となるが、3月、文相が井上毅へ親任されるに際して依願免官となると、内務省 (日本)に復帰し大阪書記官に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following September, KONO was appointed to Minister of Education by the Emperor, and as a result, KATAOKA was appointed to Secretary of Osaka after returning to the Ministry of the Interior (Japan) since he was discharged as Secretary to the Minister of Education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following September, KONO was appointed to Minister of Education by the Emperor, and as a result, KATAOKA was appointed to Secretary of Osaka after returning to the Ministry of the Interior (Japan) since he was discharged as Secretary to the Minister of Education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following September, Kono was appointed to Minister of Education by the Emperor, and as a result, Kataoka was appointed to Secretary of Osaka after returning to the Ministry of the Interior (Japan) since he was discharged as Secretary to the Minister of Education.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。赤字部分が訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>上水道敷設、大阪港建設、下水道整備などを指揮し才腕を振るったが、4月、内務省を去り文官時代を終える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He directed a number of successful projects including waterworks, Osaka Harbor, and sewer systems however his civil servant career ended when he left the Ministry of the Interior in April.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He directed a number of successful projects including waterworks, Osaka Harbor, and sewer systems however his civil servant career ended when he left the Ministry of the Interior in April.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He directed a number of successful projects including waterworks, Osaka Harbor, and sewer systems however his civil servant career ended when he left the Ministry of the Interior in April.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>そして同年6月、日本銀行に入行する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He took a position with Japan National Bank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He took a position with the Japan National Bank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He took a position with the Bank of Japan in June the same year.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れしました。用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>まずは見習いとして銀行の実務を経験し、同年10月に大阪支店長心得に、そして2月、大阪支店長に抜擢をされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a period of bank apprenticeship, he was appointed to the position of an assistant Osaka branch manager in October the same year and then the position of the Osaka branch manager in February the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a period of bank apprenticeships, he was appointed to the position of an assistant Osaka branch manager in October the same year and then the position of the Osaka branch manager in February the following year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a period of bank apprenticeships, he was appointed to the position of an assistant Osaka branch manager in October the same year and then the position of the Osaka branch manager in February the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>当時の日銀大阪支店長といえば関西財界を支配する力があり、3月に日本銀行支配役を免ぜられるまでの日銀時代に、後の実業家としての地盤が築かれることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that time, the position of the Osaka branch manager of Japan National Bank wielded a power to control the Kansai region financial world and his tenure at Nichigin Era contributed in building his aspirations of becoming a businessman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During that time, the position of the Osaka branch manager of Japan National Bank gave him the power to control the Kansai region financial world and his tenure at Nichigin Era contributed in building his aspirations of becoming a businessman.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During that time, the position of the Osaka branch manager of Bank of Japan gave him the power to control the Kansai region financial world and his tenure at the Bank of Japan era contributed in building his aspirations of becoming a businessman.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>実業家として</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Businessman</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Businessman</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Businessman</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>ガス事業関連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gas business</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gas business</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gas business</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>日銀を去った後の1899年（明治32年）、大阪瓦斯の社長に推挙され、同社社長となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After he left Nichigin (Japan National Bank), he took position as company president upon recommendation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he left Nichigin (Japan National Bank), he took a position as company president upon recommendation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he left Bank of Japan, he took a position as company president of Osaka Gas Company upon recommendation.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>大阪瓦斯の設立は1896年（明治29年）だが、その後に襲った経済不況によって経ち行かなくなり名義だけの存在となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Gas Company was founded in 1899. H4owever due to the following deflation it dissolved and existed in name only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Gas Company was founded in 1899. H4owever due to the following deflation it dissolved and existed in name only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Gas Company was founded in 1899, however due to the following deflation it dissolved and existed in name only.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>それを浅野総一郎が株式の過半数を取得・買収した後、関西経済に通じている直輝を同社社長として迎えた、という経緯がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Soichiro ASANO who bought out the company after acquiring majority shares of the stocks and put Naoteru in the president position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Soichiro ASANO who bought out the company after acquiring the majority shares of the stocks and put Naoteru in the president position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Soichiro ASANO who bought out the company after acquiring the majority shares of the stocks and put Naoteru, who knew a lot about economic situation in Kansa region, in the president position.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、この当時は外資を積極的に受け入れて経済を活性化させようという動きがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, there were movements to revitalize the economy by actively inviting foreign investments. Naoteru was suited for coordinating American investors and engineers with his foreign language skill which he acquired while in the Navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, there were movements to revitalize the economy by actively inviting foreign investments. Naoteru was suited for coordinating American investors and engineers with his foreign language skills that he acquired while in the Navy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, there were movements to revitalize the economy by actively inviting foreign investments.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>米国人投資家や技術者と話の折り合いをつける調整役として、海軍時代の経験で外国語に堪能だった直輝は適任であったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoteru was suited for coordinating American investors and engineers with his foreign language skills that he acquired while in the Navy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>第一次世界大戦時の物価高騰に伴うガス料金引き上げが大阪市の反対に遭い遂行できず、その後業績が悪化したことを理由に7月、同社社長を解任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was dismissed in July after the operating results plummeted due to the company&apos;s price hike plan for the gas rates in order to cope with the inflation after the First World War was denied by Osaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was dismissed in July after operating results plummeted due to the company&apos;s price hike plan for the gas rates in order to cope with inflation after the First World War was denied by Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was dismissed in July after operating results plummeted due to the company&apos;s price hike plan for the gas rates in order to cope with inflation after the First World War was denied by Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>日露戦争時の策源地（兵站のための後方基地）であった広島市において支店を開設した際、広島の人々と交友を深めた関係で、大林芳五郎の要請により広島ガスの設立に協力、設立後の同社社長を務め、同社の基礎を築き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He contributed to the founding of Hiroshima Gas Company and was later appointed as president upon request of Yoshigoro OBAYASHI whom he had befriended and other locals during his time in Hiroshima where he opened a branch office, the location of which there was a rear logistic base during the Russo -Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He contributed to the founding of Hiroshima Gas Company and was later appointed as president upon request of Yoshigoro OBAYASHI whom he had befriended and other locals during his time in Hiroshima where he opened a branch office, the location of which there was a rear logistic base during the Russo -Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He contributed to the founding of Hiroshima Gas Company and was later appointed as president upon request of Yoshigoro OBAYASHI whom he had befriended and other locals during his time in Hiroshima where he opened a branch office, the location of which there was a rear logistic base during the Russo -Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>それと同時に広島電気軌道の取締役にもなったが、2月に両社を退任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also at the same time, he became a managing director of Hiroshima Electric Rail Company but resigned from both companies in February.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also at the same time, he became a managing director of Hiroshima Electric Rail Company, but resigned from both companies in February.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also at the same time, he became a managing director of Hiroshima Electric Rail Company, but resigned from both companies in February.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="30">
<j>頃、全国主要都市においてガス会社が相次いで設立される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, numerous gas companies were established in the major cities around the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, numerous gas companies were established in the major cities around the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, numerous gas companies were established in the major cities around the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>大阪市では前述の大阪瓦斯があったが、隣接する堺市にはガス会社がなく、大阪瓦斯が堺市のガス事業を行なうことが検討された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka City, there was Osaka Gas Company already as mentioned earlier however none existed in the neighboring Sakai City, and it was under examination for Osaka Gas Company to provide the service to Sakai City as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Osaka City, there was Osaka Gas Company already as mentioned earlier however none existed in the neighboring Sakai City, and it was under examination for Osaka Gas Company to provide the service to Sakai City as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Osaka City, there was Osaka Gas Company already as mentioned earlier however none existed in the neighboring Sakai City, and it was under examination for Osaka Gas Company to provide the service to Sakai City as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、それを行なうには株主総会を経て定款を変更することや、大阪市の同意を必要とすることなど、早期の立ち上げが困難だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To do so however required the change of the company article through the shareholder meeting and the consent from Osaka City amongst others that made an early project commencement impossible. Sakai Gas Company was newly founded and he assumed the president position as well until he was dismissed from Osaka Gas Company as the president.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To do so however required the change of the company articles through a shareholder meeting and the consent from Osaka City amongst others that made an early project commencement impossible. Sakai Gas Company was newly founded and he assumed the president position as well until he was dismissed from Osaka Gas Company as the president.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To do so however required the change of the company articles through a shareholder meeting and the consent from Osaka City amongst others that made an early project commencement impossible.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ことから堺瓦斯を新たに設立し、大阪瓦斯社長を解任されるまで堺瓦斯社長も兼任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai Gas Company was newly founded and he assumed the president position as well until he was dismissed from Osaka Gas Company as the president.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>ガス製造を行なう際、副産物としてコールタールが得られるが、それを有効利用するために蒸留してクレオソート油を製造し、木材防腐用として販売することが検討され、東洋木材防腐が設立される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gas manufacturing produced a by-product coal tar and as a result Toyo Lumber Preservation Company was founded to make and distribute creosote oil by distillation for lumber preservation use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gas manufacturing produced a by-product coal tar and as a result Toyo Lumber Preservation Company was founded to make and distribute creosote oil by distillation for lumber preservation use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gas manufacturing produced a by-product coal tar and as a result Toyo Lumber Preservation Company was founded to make and distribute creosote oil by distillation for lumber preservation use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>実業界を去るまで同社取締役を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assumed the position of president until his retirement form the business world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He assumed the position of president until his retirement form the business world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He assumed the position of president until his retirement form the business world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>電気鉄道関連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Electric railway business</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Electric railway business</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Electric railway business</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>明治30年代、大阪市と紀州方面を結ぶ鉄道会社は南海鉄道と高野鉄道があったが設備が十分でなく、また南海本線は所要時間2時間以上であったため、絶対的な輸送力が不足していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the 30&apos;s of the Meiji period, the existing Nankai Railway and Koya Railway systems were inadequate in connecting Osaka City and Kishu (present Wakayama prefecture) as the commute took over two hours by Nankay Main Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the 30&apos;s of the Meiji period, the existing Nankai Railway and Koya Railway systems were inadequate in connecting Osaka City and Kishu (present Wakayama prefecture) as the commute took over two hours by Nankay Main Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the 30&apos;s of the Meiji period, the existing Nankai Railway and Koya Railway systems were inadequate in connecting Osaka City and Kishu (present Wakayama prefecture) as the commute took over two hours by Nankai Main Line.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>そこで大阪市と堺市を結ぶ阪堺電気軌道が12月に設立され、同社社長を務めることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, KATAOKA assumed the role of president of the newly founded Hankai Tramway Co., Ltd. which served to connect the cities between Osaka and Sakai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, KATAOKA assumed the role of president of the newly founded Hankai Tramway Co., Ltd. which served to connect the cities between Osaka and Sakai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Kataoka assumed the role of president of the newly founded Hankai Tramway Co., Ltd. which served to connect the cities between Osaka and Sakai.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>阪堺電気軌道は南海鉄道と路線が競合していたため、両社間において競争が起こったが、不毛な競争を終息させるため両社間で合併協議がなされ、、南海鉄道が阪堺電気軌道を吸収合併することと決まり、面目上、阪堺電気軌道側から南海鉄道社長が選出されることになったため、引き続き南海鉄道の社長となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankai Tramway Co., Ltd. and Nankai Railway&apos;s lines overlapped creating useless competition and to avert such competition, both companies were merged by Hankai Tramway Co., Ltd. being merged to Nankai Railway and he remained as the president under the condition of the merger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankai Tramway Co., Ltd. and Nankai Railway&apos;s lines overlapped creating useless competition and to avert such competition, both companies were merged by Hankai Tramway Co., Ltd. merging with Nankai Railway and he remained as the president under the conditions of the merger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankai Tramway Co., Ltd. and Nankai Railway&apos;s lines overlapped creating useless competition and to avert such competition, both companies were merged by Nankai Railway merging with Hankai Tramway Co., Ltd. and he remained as the president under the conditions of the merger.</e>
<cmt>合併の関係を修正しました。スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>だが、直輝は有能だった南海電鉄側の大塚惟明に実務を任せることにしたため、その報告を聞き協議するだけの立場にとどめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Naoteru delegated the day-to-day business operations to Tadaaki OTSUKA from Nankai Railway and limited his involvement to listening and discussing over the report with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Naoteru delegated the day-to-day business operations to Tadaaki OTSUKA from Nankai Railway and limited his involvement to listening and discussing over the report with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Naoteru delegated the day-to-day business operations to Tadaaki OTSUKA from Nankai Railway and limited his involvement to listening and discussing over the report with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>9月、貴族院議員に勅撰されていたことや実業界から身を引くことを決意していたため、辞表を提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, he was elected to become a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) by Imperial order and also decided to retire from the business world. He associated with the company in the capacity of an advisor after resigning from the company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, he was elected to become a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) by Imperial order and also decided to retire from the business world. He associated with the company in the capacity of an advisor after resigning from the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, he was elected to become a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) by Imperial order and also decided to retire from the business world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>その後は相談役として同社と関わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He associated with the company in the capacity of an advisor after resigning from the company.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>次期社長は大塚惟明に決まったが、健康上の理由により早期の後継者を選出する必要が出たため、その選出に関わることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaaki OTSUKA was elected to be a successor president however due to his health reason, it was necessary to select an early successor and he was involved in that process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaaki OTSUKA was elected to be a successor president however due to his health reason, it was necessary to select an early successor and he was involved in that process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaaki OTSUKA was elected to be a successor president however due to his health reason, it was necessary to select an early successor and he was involved in that process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>1907年（明治40年）4月、阪神電気鉄道の株主総会が開かれたが、それに先立ち社長であった外山修造が引退し、総会時は社長は空席のままだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1907, Shuzo TOYAMA retired as president just prior to the shareholder&apos;s meeting of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. which left the president&apos;s position vacant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1907, Shuzo TOYAMA retired as president just prior to the shareholder&apos;s meeting of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. which left the president&apos;s position vacant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1907, Shuzo TOYAMA retired as president just prior to the shareholder&apos;s meeting of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. which left the president&apos;s position vacant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>そのため直輝を社長に、という打診があったが、この際はガス事業の事情により辞退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoteru was approached to become the president however, he declined because of his involvement in the gas business at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoteru was approached to become the president however, he declined because of his involvement in the gas business at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoteru was approached to become the president however, he declined because of his involvement in the gas business at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>12月、北大阪電気軌道が設立され同社取締役となるが、わずか数ヶ月で阪神電鉄に吸収合併されることとなり、阪神電鉄の取締役となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, he became a managing director of Kita Osaka Electric Tramway when it was founded and within a few months, he became a managing director of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. when it was merged with the company.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, he became the managing director of Kita Osaka Electric Tramway when it was founded and within a few months, he became the managing director of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. when it merged with the company.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, he became the managing director of Kita Osaka Electric Tramway when it was founded and within a few months, he became the managing director of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. when it merged with the company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>1917年（大正6年）、今西林三郎が専務取締役の解任を申し出たことに際し、同年大阪瓦斯社長を解任されていたこと、関西の私鉄を一つにまとめ上げるという理想があったことなどがあり、この際は快く引き受け空席だった社長を務めることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1917, he gladly accepted to fill the vacancy as president in light of Rynsabro IMANISHI&apos;s proposal to dismissal a senior managing director and having his own desire of consolidating private railway companies in Kansai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1917, he gladly accepted to fill the vacancy as president in light of Rynsabro IMANISHI&apos;s proposal to dismis a senior managing director and realize his own desire of consolidating private railway companies in Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1917, he gladly accepted to fill the vacancy as president in light of Rinsaburo IMANISHI&apos;s proposal to dismiss a senior managing director and realize his own desire of consolidating private railway companies in Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>南海鉄道や大阪電気軌道とも関係が深く、理想が実現する可能性は低くなかったが、結局その理想の実現には至らず、南海電鉄社長辞任と同じ理由により1922年（大正11年）社長を辞任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were high hopes of utilizing his deep-rooted connections with Nankai Railway and Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd., however this never came to be since he resigned as president in 1922 by the same reason when he resigned as president of Nankai Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were high hopes of utilizing his deep-rooted connections with Nankai Railway and Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd., however this never came to pass since he resigned as president in 1922 for the same reason he resigned as president of Nankai Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were high hopes of utilizing his deep-rooted connections with Nankai Railway and Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd., however this never came to pass since he resigned as president in 1922 for the same reason he resigned as president of Nankai Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="48">
<j>生駒トンネル建設に際し、多大な負債が発生した発注元の大阪電気軌道、また建設を担当した大林組を支援し再建する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He supported and revived the construction project owner Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. and its contractor Obayashi Gumi that incurred massive debt from the Ikoma tunnel project.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He supported and revived the construction project owner Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. and its contractor Obayashi Gumi that incurred massive debt from the Ikoma tunnel project.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He supported and revived the construction project owner Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. and its contractor Obayashi Gumi that incurred massive debt from the Ikoma tunnel project.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>それについては次節の北浜銀行関連に譲る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More about this to be covered in the following Kitahama Bank incidents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More about this to be covered in the following Kitahama Bank incidents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More about this to be covered in the following Kitahama Bank incidents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>北浜銀行関連</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitahama Bank incidents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitahama Bank incidents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitahama Bank incidents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>、大阪日々新聞に北浜銀行の経営放漫記事が掲載される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An article about reckless management practices at Kitahama Bank was published in Osaka Nichinichi Shinbun (Newspaper).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An article about reckless management practices at Kitahama Bank was published in Osaka Nichinichi Shinbun (Newspaper).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An article about reckless management practices at Kitahama Bank was published in Osaka Nichinichi Shinbun (Newspaper).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>記事の内容はかなり誇張されたものであったが、全ての記事を荒唐無稽として排斥できない面もあったため、同年3月に取り付け騒ぎが起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite the story being exacerbated, there existed a sliver of truth which took its toll on the bank in March of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite the story being exacerbated, there existed a sliver of truth which took its toll on the bank in March of the same year.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite the story being exacerbated, there existed a sliver of truth which took its toll on the bank in March of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>最初の頃は、現在における銀行間取引市場より潤沢な資金が借りられたため大きな混乱は生じなかったが、日を追う毎に手形交換所を通じて巨額の引き出しをされるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the problem was kept under control due to ample funds from the bank&apos;s trading exchange market, huge withdrawals were made through the note clearing house as the days went by.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the problem was kept under control due to ample funds from the bank&apos;s trading exchange market, huge withdrawals were made through the note clearing house as days went by.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the problem was kept under control due to ample funds from the bank&apos;s trading exchange market, huge withdrawals were made through the note clearing house as days went by.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>その動きを察知した直輝は渡辺千代三郎とともに、東京にあって未だ事情を知らない北浜銀行頭取岩下清周に無断で対策を講じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By detecting such development, Naoteru together with Chiyosabro WATANABE took counter measures of their own without consulting with the president of Kitahama Bank Kiyochika IWASHITA who was then in Tokyo unbeknownst to the developing event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By detecting such development, Naoteru together with Chiyosabro WATANABE took counter measures of their own without consulting with the president of the Kitahama Bank Kiyochika IWASHITA who was then in Tokyo unbeknownst to a developing event.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By detecting such development, Naoteru together with Chiyosaburo WATANABE took counter measures of their own without consulting with the president of the Kitahama Bank Kiyochika IWASHITA who was then in Tokyo unbeknownst to a developing event.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>まず取り付け騒ぎの原因となっている新聞記事の差し止めを求め大阪府知事や新聞社主宰と交渉し、その間に岩下へ電報を打電、急遽大阪に戻った岩下は自ら新聞社主宰を訪れ、記事停止の了解を得ることはできたが時既に遅く、その翌日には一時引き出しができない事態を生じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, after negotiating an agreement with the Governor of Osaka and the chief editor of the newspaper company to stop publishing the article, he sent a telegraph to IWASHITA and upon arriving in Osaka he visited the chief editor of the newspaper company to put a stop to the article which ended up being too late as the bank had insufficient funds to satisfy customer withdrawal requests the next day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, after negotiating an agreement with the Governor of Osaka and the chief editor of the newspaper company to stop publishing the article, he sent a telegraph to IWASHITA and upon arriving in Osaka he visited the chief editor of the newspaper company to put a stop to the article which ended up being too late as the bank had insufficient funds to satisfy customer withdrawal requests the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, after negotiating an agreement with the Governor of Osaka and the chief editor of the newspaper company to stop publishing the article, he sent a telegraph to Iwashita and upon arriving in Osaka he visited the chief editor of the newspaper company to put a stop to the article which ended up being too late as the bank had insufficient funds to satisfy customer withdrawal requests the next day.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>北浜銀行に関係のある人々が急遽集められ対策を講じることとなったが、最初に支援を要請した藤田財閥の藤田男爵は先代の遺言により銀行と深い関わりを持つことを断られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amongst the chaos of those associated with Kitahama Bank, the first request for financial aid to Fujita Zaibatsu was rejected by Baron FUJITA because of his father&apos;s will stated not to get too deeply involved with the bank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amongst the chaos of those associated with Kitahama Bank, the first request for financial aid to Fujita Zaibatsu was rejected by Baron FUJITA because of his father&apos;s will stating his desire for them not to get too deeply involved with the bank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amongst the chaos of those associated with Kitahama Bank, the first request for financial aid to Fujita Zaibatsu was rejected by Baron FUJITA because of his father&apos;s will stating his desire for them not to get too deeply involved with the bank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>次の策として日本銀行支店へ北浜銀行の救済方法を相談すると、日銀本店に連絡し対策を講じてもらうこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, he consulted with the Nichigin branch office and received cooperation to arrange a means of rescuing Kitahama Bank through the Nichigin Honten (head office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, he consulted with the Nichigin branch office and received cooperation to arrange a means of rescuing Kitahama Bank through the Nichigin Honten (head office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, he consulted with the Bank of Japan branch office and received cooperation to arrange a means of rescuing Kitahama Bank through the Bank of Japan head office.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また24日、大阪手形交換所は大蔵大臣、日銀総裁に至急救援が必要との旨の陳情書を提出、大阪府知事からも救済を要請してもらう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, on 24th, Osaka Tegata Kokansho (note exchange) filed a petition requesting need of emergency aid to the Finance Minister and the head of the Nichigin while the Governor of Osaka Prefecture filed a petition for a rescue aid as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, on the 24th, Osaka Tegata Kokansho (note exchange) filed a petition requesting need of emergency aid to the Finance Minister and the head of the Nichigin while the Governor of Osaka Prefecture filed a petition for rescue aid as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, on the 24th, Osaka Tegata Kokansho (note exchange) filed a petition requesting need of emergency aid to the Finance Minister and the head of the Bank of Japan while the Governor of Osaka Prefecture filed a petition for rescue aid as well.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>同日中、日銀本店において北浜銀行を特別融通により救済することが決議されたが、この融通は300万円が限度とされ、わずか3日後には再び引き出しができなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the request for the special loan to rescue Kitahama Bank was approved on that same day at Nichigin Honten, the loan for only 3 million yen depleted in three days and withdrawals were unable to be met once again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the request for the special loan to rescue Kitahama Bank was approved on that same day at Nichigin Honten, the loan for only three million yen was depleted within three days and withdrawals were unable to be met once again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the request for the special loan to rescue Kitahama Bank was approved on that same day at the Bank of Japan head office, the loan for only three million yen was depleted within three days and withdrawals were unable to be met once again.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>再度善後策を講じることになり渡辺が日銀支店に相談すると、日銀総裁と大蔵大臣が協議して北浜銀行重役が責任を負うならば必要資金を融通する用意があることを聞き出し、最も了解が得られにくいと思われた藤田男爵の了解を取り付けるべく、藤田男爵から最も信頼の厚かった谷口房藏に説得を要請、夜を徹して説得に当たった結果、藤田男爵家からの承諾を得ることができ、29日から引き出しが可能となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon further consultation between the Finance Minister and the head of Nichigin and under the condition that Kitahama Bank executives would assume responsibility for the loan, necessary funds were granted and withdrawals were once again possible from the 29th after Fusazo TANIGUCHI, who was most entrusted and was successful in persuading Baron Fujita who was the thought to be the least likely to cooperate with their plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon further consultation between the Finance Minister and the head of Nichigin and under the condition that Kitahama Bank executives would assume responsibility for the loan, necessary funds were granted and withdrawals were once again possible from the 29th after Fusazo TANIGUCHI, who was most entrusted and was successful in persuading Baron Fujita who was the thought to be the least likely to cooperate with their plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon further consultation between the Finance Minister and the head of Bank of Japan and under the condition that Kitahama Bank executives would assume responsibility for the loan, necessary funds were granted and withdrawals were once again possible from the 29th after Fusazo TANIGUCHI, who was most entrusted and was successful in persuading Baron Fujita who was the thought to be the least likely to cooperate with their plan.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>岩下はこの責任を取り頭取を辞することになり、次の頭取を決めることになったが、岩下を北浜銀行から完全排除すべきという考えの重役が新頭取に杉村正太郎を立て重役会を刷新し、新体制で経営をスタートさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bank was reorganized with the appointment of Shotaro IWASHITA as the new head of the bank who had the opinion of the executives in insisting the complete exclusion of IWASHITA and his clan from Kitahama Bank upon his resignation for taking his responsibility for the event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bank was reorganized with the appointment of Shotaro IWASHITA as the new head of the bank who had the opinion of the executives in insisting the complete exclusion of IWASHITA and his clan from Kitahama Bank upon his resignation for taking his responsibility for the event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bank was reorganized with the appointment of Shotaro SUGIMURA as the new head of the bank who had the opinion of the executives in insisting the complete exclusion of Iwashita and his clan from Kitahama Bank upon his resignation for taking his responsibility for the event.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>だが、それからすぐ同行名古屋支店において100万円の横領事件が発覚し、同年8月、臨時総会にて北浜銀行の事業継続は困難との理由を以て臨時休業を発表し解任を申し出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after, a one million yen embezzlement scandal erupted at the Nagoya branch of the bank and he proposed his dismissal from the president position due to its difficulty to remain as a going concern during the emergency shareholder meeting held in August of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after, a one million yen embezzlement scandal erupted at the Nagoya branch of the bank and he proposed his dismissal from the president position due to its difficulty to remain as a going concern during the emergency shareholder meeting held in August of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after, a one million yen embezzlement scandal erupted at the Nagoya branch of the bank and he proposed his dismissal from the president position due to its difficulty to remain as a going concern during the emergency shareholder meeting held in August of the same year.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>このままでは銀行が破産してしまうため直輝は次の頭取を探すことになるが、なかなか良い人材は見つからなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoteru searched for his successor to avert the bankruptcy however couldn&apos;t find any good candidate for the position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoteru searched for his successor to avert the bankruptcy, however, couldn&apos;t find any good candidate for the position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoteru searched for his successor to avert the bankruptcy, however, couldn&apos;t find any good candidate for the position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>同年11月、株式で成功していた高倉藤平が頭取になり北浜銀行は三度の出発となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of the same year, Kitahama Bank made its third start with Tohei TAKAKURA who made a success in the stock market as the head of the bank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, Kitahama Bank made its third start with Tohei TAKAKURA who made a success in the stock market as the head of the bank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the same year, Kitahama Bank made its third start with Tohei TAKAKURA who made a success in the stock market as the head of the bank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>直輝がこの北浜銀行の危機に深く関わったのは、破綻が関西経済に容易ならざる悪影響を与えることもあったが、大阪電気軌道の経営破綻と、その先にある友人の大林芳五郎が社長を勤めた大林組の破綻があったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for Naoteru&apos;s deep involvement in the crisis was not only out of his concern that such failure would affect the economy of the Kansai region but also a subsequent failure of Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. and Obayashi Gumi whose president was his friend Yoshigoro OBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for Naoteru&apos;s deep involvement in the crisis was not only out of his concern that such failure would affect the economy of the Kansai region but also a subsequent failure of Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. and Obayashi Gumi whose president was his friend Yoshigoro OBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for Naoteru&apos;s deep involvement in the crisis was not only out of his concern that such failure would affect the economy of the Kansai region but also a subsequent failure of Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. and Obayashi Gumi whose president was his friend Yoshigoro OBAYASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>北浜銀行に取り付け騒ぎが起こった一番の原因は、生駒トンネル建設工事で無謀とも思われる多額の資金を大阪電気軌道に貸し出したためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The underlying reason for the toll taken at Kitahama Bank was a reckless massive loan made to Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. in connection with the Ikoma tunnel construction project.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The underlying reason for the toll taken at Kitahama Bank was the reckless massive loan made to Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. in connection with the Ikoma tunnel construction project.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The underlying reason for the toll taken at Kitahama Bank was the reckless massive loan made to Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. in connection with the Ikoma tunnel construction project.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>実際、大阪電気軌道は生駒トンネルの建設費用により経営が圧迫され危機的状況に陥っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. was struggling to stay afloat because of the cost of Ikoma tunnel construction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. was struggling to stay afloat because of the cost of Ikoma tunnel construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. was struggling to stay afloat because of the cost of Ikoma tunnel construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>また、建設を請け負った大林組は約束手形が無価値同然となり、ほとんど支払いを受けられなかったため、こちらも危機的状況に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also its project contractor Obayashi Gumi was facing a short of insolvency without getting paid after the promissory notes became worthless.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also its project contractor Obayashi Gumi was facing insolvency without getting paid after the promissory notes became worthless.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also its project contractor Obayashi Gumi was facing insolvency without getting paid after the promissory notes became worthless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>大林組、北浜銀行を救済するためには大阪電気軌道を改革することが最も重要であったため、直輝はその改革に乗り出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoteru moved to reorganize Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. as the most important priority in order to rescue Obayashi Gumi and Kitahama Bank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoteru moved to reorganize Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. as the most important priority in order to rescue Obayashi Gumi and the Kitahama Bank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoteru moved to reorganize Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. as the most important priority in order to rescue Obayashi Gumi and the Kitahama Bank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>まず、北浜銀行と大林組を除く巨額の債権をもつ三井物産と協議し、改革案を案出する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, he submitted a proposed reorganizational plan to Mitsui Bussan, one of the major creditors excluding Kitahama Bank and Obayashi Gumi, after their consultation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, he submitted a proposed reorganizational plan to Mitsui Bussan, one of the major creditors excluding Kitahama Bank and Obayashi Gumi, after their consultation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, he submitted a proposed reorganizational plan to Mitsui Bussan, one of the major creditors excluding Kitahama Bank and Obayashi Gumi, after their consultation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>さらに他の債権者を含む関係者から、社長などの推薦指名を委嘱された直輝は、大阪電気軌道の幹部に大槻龍治を中心として新たな新体制を成立させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoteru reorganized the new management team with Ryuji OTSUKI as its principal after he was requested by the creditors and the people of concern for the recommendation of new president and among other matters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoteru reorganized the new management team with Ryuji OTSUKI as its principal after he was requested by the creditors and the people of concern for the recommendation of new president and among other matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoteru reorganized the new management team with Ryuji OTSUKI as its principal after he was requested by the creditors and the people of concern for the recommendation of new president and among other matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>その後、乗客数の増加や経費削減により大阪電気軌道の経営は改善することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The business at Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. improved afterwards with the increased ridership and the cost cutting measures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The business at Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. improved afterwards with the increased ridership and cost cutting measures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The business at Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. improved afterwards with the increased ridership and cost cutting measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>その一方で大林組の再建にも力を尽くす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Obayashi Gumi did their best for reconstruction.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>大阪電気軌道発注工事での約束手形が無価値同然となっていたため、破綻による損失を少しでも軽減するべく、債権を持つ多数の銀行は差し入れている担保品にかかわらず回収に動いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the creditor banks moved to foreclose on the loans regardless of the collaterals held in order to minimize their losses in the event of insolvency when the promissory notes issued in connection with the construction project by Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. were found to be worthless.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the creditor banks moved to foreclose on the loans regardless of the collaterals held in order to minimize their losses in the event of insolvency when the promissory notes issued in connection with the construction project by Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. were found to be worthless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the creditor banks moved to foreclose on the loans regardless of the collaterals held in order to minimize their losses in the event of insolvency when the promissory notes issued in connection with the construction project by Osaka Electric Tramway Co., Ltd. were found to be worthless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>直輝はなんとか救済できないものかと渡辺とともに多数の銀行を奔走し、担保品による借入額を満額まで調達できるように交渉したが謝絶された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with WATANABE, Naoteru negotiated with many creditor banks to extend the loan to the full amount of the collateral value but was unsuccessful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with WATANABE, Naoteru negotiated with many creditor banks to extend the loan to the full amount of the collateral value, but was unsuccessful.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with Watanabe, Naoteru negotiated with many creditor banks to extend the loan to the full amount of the collateral value, but was unsuccessful.</e>
<cmt>人名修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>1915年（大正4年）、二十数万円の資金が調達できなければ強制処分すると、いくつかの銀行に通告される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1915, he was notified by few of the creditor banks that the loan would be foreclosed if around two hundred thousand yen could not be raised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1915, he was notified by few of the creditor banks that the loan would be foreclosed if around two hundred thousand yen could not be raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1915, he was notified by few of the creditor banks that the loan would be foreclosed if around two hundred thousand yen could not be raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>渡辺は東京の岸淸一博士を訪ね、数万円を借り、また三井銀行から担保総額の約七掛けにあたる有価証券の提供と、直輝、渡辺、岸の3名による連帯債務とすることを条件に約20万円の資金を融通され、危急の事態は回避された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Watanabe went to see Dr. Seiichi KISHI in Tokyo and borrowed some tens of thousands of yen from him also they received a loan from Mitsui Bank with the condition of surrendering negotiable instruments with the value equal to 70% of the loan amount along with jointly cosigning the loan by the three Naoteru, WATANABE and KISHI to avert the crisis situation in the end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Watanabe went to see Dr. Seiichi KISHI in Tokyo and borrowed some tens of thousands of yen from him also they received a loan from Mitsui Bank on the condition of surrendering negotiable instruments with the value equal to seventy percent of the loan amount along with jointly cosigning the loan by the three Naoteru, WATANABE and KISHI to avert the crisis situation in the end.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Watanabe went to see Dr. Seiichi KISHI in Tokyo and borrowed some tens of thousands of yen from him also they received a loan of around two hundred thousand yen from Mitsui Bank on the condition of surrendering negotiable instruments with the value equal to seventy percent of the loan amount along with jointly cosigning the loan by the three Naoteru, Watanabe and Kishi to avert the crisis situation in the end.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その後も家政整理に関わり、株式会社化された後も相談役として後援した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He continued to be involved with in-house organizational matters and supported the company as an advisor even after it became a joint stock corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He continued to be involved with in-house organizational matters and supported the company as an advisor even after it became a joint stock corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He continued to be involved with in-house organizational matters and supported the company as an advisor even after it became a joint stock corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="78">
<j>、北浜銀行で行員による株券偽造事件が発覚、損害額は八十数万円に上る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A stock certificate forgery by an employee at Kitahama Bank was brought to light with damage amounting to eight hundred thousand yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A stock certificate forgery by an employee at Kitahama Bank was brought to light with damage amounting to eight hundred thousand yen.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A stock certificate forgery by an employee at Kitahama Bank was brought to light with damage amounting to eight hundred thousand yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>そしてその金銭的損害よりも信用的損害が大きいため、再度の取り付け騒ぎが起こってもおかしくない状況となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Damage to the bank&apos;s credibility was far greater than the monetary losses as this brought on the possibility of another crisis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Damage to the bank&apos;s credibility was far greater than the monetary losses as this brought on the possibility of another crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Damage to the bank&apos;s credibility was far greater than the monetary losses as this brought on the possibility of another crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>直輝は渡辺千代三郎に銀行間の調整を要請し、渡辺の努力により損害賠償額の5分の1にて示談が成立、円満解決となり危機は回避された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoteru requested Chiyosaburo WATANABE to coordinate between banks and with his diligent efforts, the crisis was averted and settled at one fifth the amount of the full liability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoteru requested Chiyosaburo WATANABE to coordinate between banks and with his diligent efforts, the crisis was averted and settled at one fifth the amount of the full liability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoteru requested Chiyosaburo WATANABE to coordinate between banks and with his diligent efforts, the crisis was averted and settled at one fifth the amount of the full liability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>北浜銀行はその後、に三十四銀行と合併し、その歴史を閉じることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitahama Bank later merged with Sanjushi Bank and thus ended its mark in history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitahama Bank later merged with Sanjushi Bank and thus ended its mark in history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitahama Bank later merged with Sanjushi Bank and thus ended its mark in history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>晩年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later years</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>実業界から身を引く少し前の、貴族院議員に勅選されたが、国政に翼賛するより他は煩累を避け、孫とともに悠々自適の生活を送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as a member of the House of Peers by order of the Emperor just before retiring from the business world and, other than supportive participation in national politics, he spent his days in quiet retirement with his grandchildren by staying away from annoying matters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as a member of the House of Peers by order of the Emperor just before retiring from the business world and, other than supportive participation in national politics, he spent his days in quiet retirement with his grandchildren by staying away from annoying matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as a member of the House of Peers by order of the Emperor just before retiring from the business world and, other than supportive participation in national politics, he spent his days in quiet retirement with his grandchildren by staying away from annoying matters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="83">
<j>1926年（大正15年）12月、腹痛を覚える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 1926, he felt a stomachache.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1926, he felt a stomachache.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1926, he felt a stomachache.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>膵臓炎と診断され治療を受けて一旦快方に向かうが、翌年の3月、十二指腸潰瘍を併発し、同年4月13日午前0時53分永眠する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was diagnosed as a pancreatic cancer and the condition improved at one time after treatment but in March the following year, it developed into a duodenal ulcer and he left in peace at 12:53 AM in April the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was diagnosed as having pancreatic cancer and the condition improved at one time after treatment, but in March the following year, it developed into a duodenal ulcer and he left in peace at 12:53 AM in April the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was diagnosed as having pancreatitis and the condition improved at one time after treatment, but in March the following year, it developed into a duodenal ulcer and he left in peace at 12:53 AM in April the same year.</e>
<cmt>病名を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>享年72。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His age at death was 72.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His age at death was 72.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 72.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mobnoboka(id:35218), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Aqualand(id:115455), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), 松茸(id:27535), Complex01(id:10454), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>