<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大野群右衛門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunemon ONO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunemon ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunemon ONO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大野群右衛門（おおの ぐんえもん）は、赤穂藩浅野氏の家老大野知房の嫡男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunemon ONO was the eldest legitimate son of Tomousa ONO, Karo (chief retainer) of the Asano family of Ako Domain.</e>
<cmt>大野知房の読み方は確認できていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunemon ONO was the eldest legitimate son of Tomofusa ONO, a chief retainer of the Asano clan of Ako Domain.</e>
<cmt>大野知房→Tomofusa ONOa chief retainer of the Asano clanに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunemon ONO was the eldest legitimate son of Tomofusa ONO, a chief retainer of the Asano clan of Ako Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>赤穂藩では部屋住みの身ながら大野家の家禄と別に米20石を支給されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Ako Domain, the Ono family was given 20 koku of rice in addition to &apos;Karoku (hereditary stipend)&apos; to the family although Gunemon was still &apos;heyazumi (an adult-age eldest son who has yet to come into his inheritance)&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Ako Domain, the Ono family was given 20 koku of rice in addition to Karoku (hereditary stipend) to the family although Gunemon was still heyazumi (an adult-age eldest son who has yet to come into his inheritance).</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&apos; &apos;削除しました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Ako Domain, the Ono family was given 20 koku of rice in addition to Karoku (hereditary stipend) to the family although Gunemon was still heyazumi (an adult-age eldest son who has yet to come into his inheritance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父とともに不忠臣として悪名高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunemon as well as his father was notorious for being unloyal to their lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunemon as well as his father was notorious for being unloyal to their lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunemon as well as his father was notorious for being unloyal to their lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>赤穂藩改易後に父大野九郎兵衛が藩内で孤立すると、元禄14年（1701年）4月12日に父とともに赤穂から逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the change of rank of Ako Domain, Kurobei (Tomofusa) Ono became isolated and Gunemon, together with his father fled from Ako on April 12, 1701.</e>
<cmt>父親の名が突然大野九郎兵衛になっているので、九郎兵衛(知房）としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the change of rank of Ako Domain, Kurobe (Tomofusa) ONO became isolated and Gunemon, together with his father fled from Ako on May 19, 1701.</e>
<cmt>Kirobeに訂正しました。ONOに訂正しました。グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the change of rank of Ako Domain, Kurobe (Tomofusa) ONO became isolated and Gunemon, together with his father fled from Ako on May 19, 1701.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幼い娘を置き去りにしての逃亡であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that they left Gunemon&apos;s young daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that they left Gunemon&apos;s young daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that they left Gunemon&apos;s young daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後の消息は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunemon was never to be heard of again from that time on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunemon was never to be heard of again from that time on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunemon was never to be heard of again from that time on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただ伊藤東涯によると父大野九郎兵衛は、「伴閑精」と称して、京都の仁和寺の辺りに住んでいたというので、嫡男の群右衛門もその辺で暮らしたのであろうか。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Togai ITO said that Gunemon&apos;s father, Kurobei ONO lived near the Ninna-ji Temple in Kyoto, calling himself &apos;Seikan BAN,&apos; Gunemon seemed to live around there.</e>
<cmt>「伴閑精」の読み方が確認できていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Togai ITO said that Gunemon&apos;s father, Kurobe ONO lived near the Ninna-ji Temple in Kyoto, calling himself &apos;Seikan BAN&apos; (伴閑精), Gunemon seemed to live around there.</e>
<cmt>Kirobeに訂正しました。伴閑精→定訳不明。漢字補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Togai ITO said that Gunemon&apos;s father, Kurobe ONO lived near the Ninna-ji Temple in Kyoto, calling himself &apos;Seikan BAN&apos; (伴閑精), Gunemon seemed to live around there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>歌舞伎「仮名手本忠臣蔵」においてはお軽の父を殺害する悪役斧定九郎（おの さだくろう）として登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunemon is changed into a villain, Sadakuro ONO (this ONO means an ax), who killed Okaru&apos;s father in &apos;Kanadehon Chushingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers)&apos; of Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors).</e>
<cmt>「斧」と「大野」の表記の差が的確に表現できていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kabuki &apos;Kanadehon Chushingura&apos; (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers, a historical play dealing with the retainers of Ako Domain), Sadakuro ONO (斧) modeled after Gunemon ONO (大野) appears as a villain, who killed Okaru&apos;s father.</e>
<cmt>NC_CheckI&apos;m not sure if it is necessary to explain the difference of Chinese characters between &apos;斧&apos; (ax) and &apos;大野.&apos; These has the same sound. A kind of wordplay in Kabuki script. 「仮名手本忠臣蔵」の説明補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kabuki &apos;Kanadehon Chushingura&apos; (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers, a historical play dealing with the retainers of Ako Domain), Sadakuro ONO (斧) modeled after Gunemon ONO (大野) appears as a villain, who killed Okaru&apos;s father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>現代の忠臣蔵のドラマでもこれと史実の大野の氏が混ざって「大野定九郎」として登場してくることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern &apos;Chusingura&apos; dramas, a new character, &apos;Sadakuro ONO,&apos; is created as the mixture of Sadakuro ONO (ax) and the real family name of ONO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern &apos;Chusingura&apos; dramas, a new character, &apos;Sadakuro ONO (大野)&apos; is created as the intermingling of Sadakuro and the family name of a historical figure, Gunemon ONO.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。表現を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern &apos;Chusingura&apos; dramas, a new character, &apos;Sadakuro ONO (大野)&apos; is created as the intermingling of Sadakuro and the family name of a historical figure, Gunemon ONO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>群右衛門については資料が少なく、史実の元禄赤穂事件上ではあまり目立たない人物であるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since there are few documents on Gunemon, it can be said that he was in shade in the real Genroku Ako Incident.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since there are few documents on Gunemon, it can be said that he was in shade in the real Genroku Ako Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since there are few documents on Gunemon, it can be said that he was in shade in the real Genroku Ako Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>が、仮名手本忠臣蔵の中で見せたその凶悪な姿から忠臣蔵を扱った時代劇の中では吉良義央に次ぐ悪役として（時には吉良より凶悪に）大活躍することが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since he is described as a villain in &apos;Kanadehon Chushingura,&apos; historical plays dealing with &apos;Chushingura,&apos; Sadakuro ONO often plays outstandingly as the second villai after Yoshinaka KIRA (sometimes even more wickedly than Yoshinaka KIRA).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since he was described as a villain in &apos;Kanadehon Chushingura,&apos; Sadakuro ONO often plays outstandingly as the second villain after Yoshinaka KIRA (sometimes even more wickedly than Yoshinaka KIRA).</e>
<cmt>wasに訂正しました。「仮名手本忠臣蔵」の説明は前出の為削除しました。villainスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since he was described as a villain in &apos;Kanadehon Chushingura,&apos; Sadakuro ONO often plays outstandingly as the second villain after Yoshinaka KIRA (sometimes even more wickedly than Yoshinaka KIRA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>