<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>松平宗武</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetake MATSUDAIRA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetake MATSUDAIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetake MATSUDAIRA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>松平 宗武（まつだいら むねたけ）は、丹後国宮津藩の第7代（最後の）藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetake MATSUDAIRA was the seventh (the last) lord of the Miyazu domain, Tango Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetake MATSUDAIRA was the seventh (the last) lord of the Miyazu Domain, Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>domainの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetake MATSUDAIRA was the seventh (the last) lord of the Miyazu Domain, Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本庄松平家10代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the tenth generation of the Honjo Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the tenth generation of the Honjo Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the tenth generation of the Honjo Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>弘化3年（1846年）6月9日、第6代藩主・松平宗秀の五男として生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was born as the fifth son of Munehide MATSUDAIRA, the sixth lord of domain on July 31, 1846.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was born as the fifth son of Munehide MATSUDAIRA, the sixth lord of the Domain on July 31, 1846.</e>
<cmt>the sixth lord of domain→the sixth lord of the Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was born as the fifth son of Munehide MATSUDAIRA, the sixth lord of the Domain on July 31, 1846.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>慶応2年（1866年）、第2次長州征伐で父・宗秀は幕府軍長州征討補佐を務めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1866, his father Munehide served as the assistant for subjugation of Choshu by the bakufu on the Second conquest of Choshu in 1866.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1866, his father Munehide served as the assistant for subjugation of Choshu by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) on the Second conquest of Choshu in 1866.</e>
<cmt>bakufuの補足追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1866, his father Munehide served as the assistant for subjugation of Choshu by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) on the Second conquest of Choshu in 1866.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、幕府軍の戦況不利を見て独断で長州藩の家老を釈放するなどしたことから、幕命により10月29日に強制隠居処分に処せられたため、家督を継いで第7代藩主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since his father released a chief retainer of the Choshu domain on his own authority by looking at bad war situation, his father was forced to retire by the bakufu on December 5, so he succeeded the position of the seventh lord of domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since his father released a chief retainer of the Choshu Domain on his own authority by looking at bad war situation, his father was forced to retire by the bakufu on December 5, so he succeeded to the position of the seventh lord of the Domain.</e>
<cmt>domainの頭文字を大文字に変更、余分なスペース消去、succeeded the position of the seventh lord of domain→succeeded to the position of the seventh lord of the Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since his father released a chief retainer of the Choshu Domain on his own authority by looking at bad war situation, his father was forced to retire by the bakufu on December 5, so he succeeded to the position of the seventh lord of the Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>慶応4年（1868年）の戊辰戦争では、山城国八幡の警護を勤めるなど、はじめは新政府に恭順していたが、このときに新政府軍に発砲して敵対したため、朝敵とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Boshin Civil War in 1868, he had deference to the new government first as he served as the guard of Hachiman, Yamashiro Province, but he was against the army of new government and fired them, so he was considered as Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Boshin Civil War in 1868, he had deference to the new government at first as he served as the guard of Hachiman, Yamashiro Province, but he was against the army of new government and fired at them, so he was considered as the Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>first→at first、fired them→fired at them、Emperor&apos;s enemy→the Emperor&apos;s enemyとしました。NC_Check</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Boshin Civil War in 1868, he was loyal to the new government at first as he served as a guard for Hachiman, Yamashiro Province, but he opposed the army of the new government and fired at them, so he was considered an enemy of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>had→showed</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして西園寺公望率いる山陰鎮撫使に降伏して許されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was forgiven when he surrendered the repression delegate lead by Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was forgiven when he surrendered the repression delegate to the Sanin region lead by Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>the repression delegate→the repression delegate to the Sanin regionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was forgiven when he surrendered the repression delegate to the Sanin region lead by Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>明治2年（1869年）6月19日、版籍奉還により宮津藩知事に任じられ、明治4年（1871年）7月15日の廃藩置県で藩知事を免職された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to the governor of the Miyazu domain by Hanseki-hokan (return of lands and people to the emperor) on July 27, 1869 and dismissed the position by Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) on August 30, 1871.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to the governor of the Miyazu Domain by Hanseki-hokan (return of lands and people to the emperor) on July 27, 1869 and dismissed the position by Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) on August 30, 1871.</e>
<cmt>domainの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to the governor of the Miyazu Domain by Hanseki-hokan (return of lands and people to the emperor) on July 27, 1869 and dismissed the position by Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) on August 30, 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>明治6年（1873年）からは開拓使として北海道の農業開拓に従事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked on development of agriculture in Hokkaido Prefecture as the Development Commissioner.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1873, he worked on development of agriculture in Hokkaido Prefecture as the Development Commissioner.</e>
<cmt>「明治6年（1873年）からは」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1873, he worked on development of agriculture in Hokkaido Prefecture as the Development Commissioner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、父が死去すると宮津に戻り、以後は宮司として働く一方で、俳句の世界をたしなんだといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he returned to Miyazu once his father died, and while he worked as Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) afterward, he was fond of Haiku world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he returned to Miyazu once his father died, and while he worked as Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) afterward, he was fond of Haiku world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he returned to Miyazu once his father died, and while he worked as Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) afterward, he was fond of Haiku world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治26年（1893年）4月28日に死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died on April 28, 1893.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died on April 28, 1893.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died on April 28, 1893.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>享年48。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was 48 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was 48 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was 48 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), ドルチェット(id:46458), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>