<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平忠盛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadamori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tadamori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadamori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 忠盛（たいら の ただもり）は、平安時代末期の武将。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadamori was a samurai at the end of Heian era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tadamori was a samurai at the end of Heian era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadamori was a samurai at the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Heian era→Heian periodに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伊勢平氏庶流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collateral line of Ise-Heishi clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collateral line of Ise-Heishi clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collateral line of Ise-Heishi (Taira clan).</e>
<cmt>Ise-Heishi clan→Ise-Heishi (Taira clan）とし、文末のピリオドを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平清盛の父。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Father of TAIRA no Kiyomori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the father of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the father of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>平氏で初めて昇殿を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first Taira clan to be accepted to visit the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first among the Taira to be accepted to visit the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first among the Taira clan to be accepted to visit the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>Taira→Taira clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>父は平正盛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was TAIRA no Masamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was TAIRA no Masamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was TAIRA no Masamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>烏帽子親は河内源氏の棟梁の源義忠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eboshi-oya (guardian) was MINAMOTO no Yoshitada who was a leader of Kawachi-Genji clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His eboshi-oya (guardian) was MINAMOTO no Yoshitada who was a leader of Kawachi-Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His eboshi-oya (guardian) was MINAMOTO no Yoshitada who was a leader of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>Kawachi-Genji clan→Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>生涯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biography</e>
<cmt>統一リストの表記に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>父正盛は白河天皇に仕え、河内源氏の棟梁、源義忠に息女を娶わせるなどして勢力を伸ばした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamori&apos;s father, Masamori served for the Emperor Shirakawa and also married off his daughter to MINAMOTO no Yoshitada who was a leader of Kawachi-Genji clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori&apos;s father, Masamori served for the Emperor Shirakawa and also married off his daughter to MINAMOTO no Yoshitada--a leader of Kawachi-Genji clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori&apos;s father, Masamori served for the Emperor Shirakawa and also married off his daughter to MINAMOTO no Yoshitada - a leader of Kawachi-Genji.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除、スペースを追加、Kawachi-Genji clan→Kawachi-Genjiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>河内源氏が義忠の死後、衰退するなか源氏の与党を従えつつ忠盛も白河上皇、鳥羽天皇に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshitada died, while Kawachi-Genji clan declined in strength, Tadamori brought Kawachi-Genji clan retainers with him and served for the retired Emperor Shirakawa and the Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshitada died, while the Kawachi-Genji clan declined in strength, Tadamori brought the Kawachi-Genji clan retainers with him and served for the retired Emperor Shirakawa and the Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshitada died, while the Kawachi-Genji declined in strength, Tadamori brought the Kawachi-Genji retainers with him and served for the Retired Emperor Shirakawa and the Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>Kawachi-Genji clan→Kawachi-Genji、the Retired Emperor Shirakawaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>天永2年（1111年）検非違使となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed as kebiishi (Kyoto police) in 1111.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed as kebiishi (Kyoto police) in 1111.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed as Kebiishi (police and judicial chief) in 1111.</e>
<cmt>「検非違使」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>天永4年（1113年）日枝神社の盗賊夏焼大夫を討ち取り、従五位下に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he killed the robber Natsuyagi dayu who had burglarized the Hie jinja Shrine, he was rewarded Ju go-i no ge for his achivement in 1113.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he killed the robber Natsuyagi dayu, who had burglarized the Hie jinja Shrine, he was rewarded Ju go-i no ge for his achivement in 1113.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he killed the robber Natsuyagi dayu, who had burglarized the Hie-jinja Shrine, he was rewarded Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) for his achivement in 1113.</e>
<cmt>Hie jinja Shrine→Hie-jinja Shrine、Ju go-i no ge→Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>永久 (元号)元年（1113年）永久の強訴に父正盛とともに出動して興福寺の大衆の入京を阻止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the event of Eikyu-no-goso (violent plea in Eikyu period) in 1113, Tadamori worked with his father Masamori to stop the troops of Kofuku-ji Temple coming into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event of Eikyu-no-goso (violent plea in Eikyu period) in 1113, Tadamori worked with his father Masamori to stop the troops of Kofuku-ji Temple coming into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event of Eikyu no goso (violent plea in the Eikyu era) in 1113, Tadamori worked with his father Masamori to stop the troops of Kofuku-ji Temple coming into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Eikyu-no-gosoのハイフンをとり、in Eikyu period→in the Eikyu eraに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、伯耆国守となり右馬権頭も兼任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, he became kokushu of Hoki Province and also appointed for uma gon no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, he became kokushu (provincial governor) of Hoki Province and was also appointed to the position of uma gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>The explanation of the term &quot;kokushu&quot; was added.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, he became the Governor of Hoki Province and was also appointed to the position of Uma no gon no kami (Provisional Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに基づき、「伯耆国守」→the Governor of Hoki Provinceに修正、および「右馬権頭」の表記を修正、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>永久 (元号)5年（1117年）鳥羽天皇に入内した藤原璋子の政所別当になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1117, he became a betto of mandokoro for FUJIWARA no Shoshi who was married to the Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1117, he became a mandokoro betto (Secretary of government office) for FUJIWARA no Shoshi who was married to the Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>The explanation of the term &quot;mandokoro betto&quot; was added.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1117, he became a mandokoro betto (Secretary of government office) for FUJIWARA no Shoshi who was married to the Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>元永2年（1119年）賀茂臨時祭に際して新舞人として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served as shin-maibito in Kamo no rinjisai in 1119.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as shin-maibito (traditional Japanese Court dancer) in Kamo no rinjisai (imperial festival held in November) in 1119.</e>
<cmt>The explanations of the terms &quot;shin-maibito&quot; and &quot;Kamo no rinjisai&quot; were added.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as shin-maibito (traditional Japanese Court dancer) in Kamo no rinjisai (imperial festival held in November) in 1119.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>保安 (元号)元年（1120年）越前国受領となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a zuryo (local governer) of Echizen Province in 1120.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a zuryo (local governer) of Echizen Province in 1120.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a zuryo (local governer) of Echizen Province in 1120.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>在任中、越前国敦賀郡で殺人事件が起こり犯人の日吉神社神人を逮捕、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During his service, a murder happened in Tsuruga District, Echizen Province and a jinin of Hiyoshi-jinja Shrine was arrested.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his service, a murder occured in Tsuruga District, Echizen Province and a jinin of Hiyoshi-jinja Shrine was arrested.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his service, a murder occured in Tsuruga District, Echizen Province and a jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) of Hiyoshi-jinja Shrine was arrested.</e>
<cmt>神人→&quot;jinin&quot;のみでは意味が不明確なため補足をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>検非違使に引き渡す途中で、延暦寺の悪僧が犯人の身柄を奪取したため朝廷は悪僧を捕らえ、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a lapsed monk of the Enryaku-ji Temple took over him on the way to take the murder to Kebiishi, the imperial court caught the monk.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a lapsed monk of the Enryaku-ji Temple kidnapped him on the way to take the murderer to the Kebiishi (Kyoto police), the imperial court caught the monk.</e>
<cmt>wordingThe explanation of the term &quot;Kebiishi&quot; was added.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a lapsed monk of the Enryaku-ji Temple kidnapped him on the way to take the murderer to the Kebiishi, the imperial court caught the monk.</e>
<cmt>「検非違使」→前出のためKebiishiのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>延暦寺の強訴が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Enryaku-ji Temple made a plea for the monk violently.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Enryaku-ji Temple violently demonstrated for the monk.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Enryaku-ji Temple violently demonstrated for the monk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>白河法皇は延暦寺の要求に屈せず、忠盛をかばった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa protected Tadamori without bowing to pressure from the Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>白河法皇として訳していますが、この年では白河上皇ではないでしょうか？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa protected Tadamori without bowing to pressure from Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa protected Tadamori without bowing to pressure from Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>保安2年（1121年）院の昇殿を許される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamori was permitted to visit the cloistered emperor&apos;s palace in 1121.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori was permitted to visit the cloistered emperor&apos;s palace in 1121.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori was permitted to visit the cloistered emperor&apos;s palace in 1121.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この頃、修理権大夫・藤原宗兼の娘、宗子（池禅尼）を正室とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About this time, he took Muneko (later Ike no zenni) to his official wife, who was a daughter of shuri gondayu FUJIWARA no Munekage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About this time, he took Muneko (later Ike no zenni) to be his official wife; she was a daughter of shuri gondayu, FUJIWARA no Munekage.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About this time, he took Muneko (later Ike no zenni) to be his official wife; she was a daughter of the Shuri gon no daibu (Provisional Master in the Office of Palace Repairs), FUJIWARA no Munekage.</e>
<cmt>「修理権大夫」の表記を修正、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>昇殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Visiting the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Visiting the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Visiting the Imperial Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>大治2年（1127年）従四位下に叙され、備前国守となり左馬権頭も兼ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamori was rewarded Ju shi-i no ge in 1127 and also became the kokushu of Bizen Province and was appointed for Sama no gon no kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori was rewarded Ju shi-i no ge in 1127 and also became the kokushu of Bizen Province and was appointed for the position of Sama no gon no kami.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori was rewarded Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1127 and also became the Govenor of Bizen Province and was appointed for the position of Sama no gon no kami (Provisional Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>「従四位下」、「備前国守」の表記を統一リストに基づき修正、および「左馬権頭」の補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>さらに、牛や馬の管理を行う院の御厩司となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, he served in &quot;Miumaya no tsukasa,&quot; where managed cows and horses in the palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, he served in Miumaya no tsukasa, where he managed cows and horses in the palace.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he served in Miumaya no tsukasa, where he managed cows and horses in the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>大治4年（1129年）山陽道・南海道の海賊を追討する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He hunted and killed pilates in Sanyo-do and Nankai-do in 1129.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He hunted and killed pirates in Sanyo-do and Nankai-do in 1129.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He hunted and killed pirates in Sanyo-do and Nankai-do in 1129.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これは、正式な宣旨ではなく院宣と検非違使別当宣（別当は待賢門院の兄・三条実行）によるものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was not by an official imperial edict but by the retired emperor&apos;s edict and the kebiishi betto&apos;s edict. (At that time, brother of Taikenmonin, Saneyuki SANJO was the betto.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was not by official imperial edict, but by the retired emperor&apos;s edict and the kebiishi betto&apos;s edict. (At that time, the brother of Taikenmonin, Saneyuki SANJO was the betto).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was not by official Imperial edict, but by the Retired Emperor&apos;s edict and the Kebiishi betto (Superintendent) &apos;s edict. (At that time, the brother of Taikenmonin, Saneyuki SANJO was the betto).</e>
<cmt>Imperial edict, the Retired Emperor&apos;s edict, the Kebiishi betto (Superintendent) &apos;s edictとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>白河法皇が崩じて、鳥羽上皇が院政をとると御給として忠盛は正四位下に叙される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired Emperor Toba took over the cloistered rule after the Cloistered Emperor Shiraka died, and awarded Sho shi-i no ge to Tadamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired Emperor Toba took over the cloistered rule after the Cloistered Emperor Shiraka died, and awarded Sho shi-i no ge rank to Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Retired Emperor Toba took over the cloistered rule after the Cloistered Emperor Shirakawa died, and awarded Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) rank to Tadamori.</e>
<cmt>The Retired Emperor Tobaとし、Shiraka→Shirakawa、Sho shi-i no ge→Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>天承2年（1132年）上皇勅願の観音堂である得長寿院造営の落慶供養に際して、千体観音を寄進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1132, Tadamori donated the Sentai Kannon (thousand deity) to the Tokuchoju-in Temple for the completion ceremony by the the retired imperial plea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1132, Tadamori donated the Sentai Kannon (thousand deity) to the Tokuchoju-in Temple for the completion ceremony by the retired imperial plea.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1132, for the completion ceremony of the Tokuchoju-in Temple, a Kannon-do Hall built at the Retired Emperor&apos;s behest, Tadamori donated the Sentai Kannon (thousand deity) to the temple.</e>
<cmt>原文の内容に沿わない部分があるため一部訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その功績により内昇殿を許可された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was permitted Naishoden (to visit the special room in the imperial palace) for his donation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was permitted Naishoden (to visit the special room in the imperial palace) for his donation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was permitted Naishoden (to visit the special room in the imperial palace) for his donation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>『平家物語』では武士である忠盛が殿上人となったことを憎んだ公卿たちによる闇討ちが企てられるが、忠盛は銀箔の木刀によって公卿たちを脅す機転によって防ぎ、鳥羽上皇から賞される（殿上闇討）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;The Tale of the Heike,&quot; nobles hated Tadamori because he became Tenjobito and they plotted a surprise attack, however, Tadamori used his wit to save himself with threatening nobles with silver-plated wooden sword. [Surprise attack in the Palace (Tenjo no yamiuchi)]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to The Tale of the Heike, nobles hated Tadamori because he became Tenjobito. They plotted a surprise attack; however, Tadamori used his wit to save himself by threatening nobles with a silver-plated wooden sword [Surprise attack in the Palace (Tenjo no yamiuchi)].</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;The Tale of the Heike,&quot; nobles hated Tadamori because he became Tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace). They plotted a surprise attack; however, Tadamori used his wit to save himself by threatening nobles with a silver-plated wooden sword (Tenjo no yamiuchi, or Surprise attack in the Palace)</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせ、クォーテーションを入れ、「殿上人」の補足を追加、(殿上闇討)の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>内昇殿は武士では摂関期の源頼光の例があるものの、この当時では破格の待遇だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a case of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu that was permitted Naishoden, however, Tadamori was treated very well at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was the case of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu that was granted Naishoden; however, Tadamori was treated very well at that time.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was the case of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu that was granted Naishoden; however, Tadamori was treated very well at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>藤原宗忠は「この人の昇殿猶未曾有の事なり」（『中右記』）と評した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Munetada wrote &quot;there was no case that such a person was permitted to visit the special imperial room.&quot; (&quot;Chuuki&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Munetada wrote &quot;it is unprecedented that such a person was permitted to visit the special imperial room (Chuuki).</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Munetada wrote &apos;it is unprecedented that such a person was permitted to visit the special imperial room&apos; (&quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary written by FUJIWARA no Munetada)).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、『中右記』の読み、表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>鳥羽法皇の寵愛が美福門院に移り藤原家成が院近臣筆頭の地位を確立すると、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Cloistered Emperor Toba made a favorite of Bifukumonin, her cousin FUJIWARA no Ienari was well-established as the head of trusted vassals (in no kinshin).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Cloistered Emperor Toba made a favorite of Bifukumonin--her cousin FUJIWARA no Ienari was well-established as the head of trusted vassals (in no kinshin).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Cloistered Emperor Toba made a favorite of Bifukumonin - her cousin FUJIWARA no Ienari was well-established as the head of In no kinshin (the retired emperor&apos;s trusted vassals).</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除、スペースを追加、「院近臣」の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>忠盛は妻の宗子が家成の従兄弟であったことから親密な関係を築いていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamori developed a close relationship with Ienari because his wife Muneko was Ienari&apos;s cousin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori developed a close relationship with Ienari because his wife Muneko was Ienari&apos;s cousin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori developed a close relationship with Ienari because his wife Muneko was Ienari&apos;s cousin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>保延元年（1135年）中務省に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to work in the Ministry of Central Affairs (Nakatsukasa-sho) in 1135.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to work in the Ministry of Central Affairs (Nakatsukasa-sho) in 1135.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to work in the Nakatsukasa-sho (Ministry of Central Affairs) in 1135.</e>
<cmt>the Nakatsukasa-sho (Ministry of Central Affairs)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>西海の海賊を追討について忠盛か源為義が適当か公卿が議し、忠盛が追討使に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kugyos discussed who should be qualified between Tadamori and MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi for hunting and killing the pirates in the western sea, and appointed Tadamori to do it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kugyos discussed who should be qualified between Tadamori and MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi for hunting and killing the pirates in the western sea. He subsequently appointed Tadamori to the task.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kugyos (the top court officials) discussed who should be qualified between Tadamori and MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi for hunting and killing the pirates in the western sea. He subsequently appointed Tadamori to the task.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Kugyos&quot;に補足を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>忠盛は海賊を追捕して降伏した者を家人にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamori caught pirates and accepted some of the pirates who surrendered as retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori caught pirates and accepted some of the pirates who surrendered as retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori caught pirates and accepted some of the pirates who surrendered as retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>同年、美作国守に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this year, he was appointed as a kokushu of Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this year, he was appointed as a kokushu of Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this year, he was appointed as the Govenor of Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>a kokushu of Mimasaka Province→the Govenor of Mimasaka Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>保延5年（1140年）興福寺衆徒の強訴に出動して入京を阻止する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the event of violent plea of the Kofuku-ji Temple armed priests, Tadamori stopped their coming into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori prevented the violent demonstrations of the armed priests of Kofuku-ji Temple from coming into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori prevented the violent demonstrations of the armed priests of Kofuku-ji Temple from coming into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この頃、忠盛は院御厩司から長官である別当になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About this time, he was promoted to the betto (head) of Miumaya no tsukasa in cloistered government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About this time, he was promoted to the betto (head) of Miumaya no tsukasa in the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About this time, he was promoted to the betto (head) of Miumaya no tsukasa in the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>忠盛は右馬権頭・左馬権頭を歴任し、宮中の馬を管理する馬寮の職務に携わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamori held positions such as Uma no gon no kami and Sama no gon no kami successively and was involved in the bureau of horses (meryo) which managed horses in the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori held positions such as Uma no gon no kami and Sama no gon no kami; and, was involved in the bureau of horses (meryo), which managed horses in the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori held positions such as Uma no gon no kami and Sama no gon no kami; and, was involved in the Meryo (Bureau of Horses), which managed horses in the imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>「ローマ字(英訳)」の順にし&quot;the Meryo (Bureau of Horses)&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>職務内容の共通性から馬寮と院御厩の職員を兼ねることは自然なことであり、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not unusual that Tadamori held both the bureau of horses (meryo) and the Miumaya no tsukasa positions considering the commonality of works.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not unusual that Tadamori held positions in both the bureau of horses (meryo) and the Miumaya no tsukasa considering the similarities of the duties.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not unusual that Tadamori held positions in both the Meryo and the Miumaya no tsukasa considering the similarities of the duties.</e>
<cmt>前出のためMeryoのみの表記としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>戦闘における騎馬の重要性からも院御厩別当への就任は軍事貴族である忠盛にとって大きいものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was was very important for Tadamori, who was a military noble, to accede to the betto of Miumaya no tsukasa because troop-horses were important for battles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was was very important for Tadamori, who was a military noble, to accede to the betto of Miumaya no tsukasa because of the importance of calvalry to battles.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was was very important for Tadamori, who was a military noble, to accede to the betto of Miumaya no tsukasa because of the importance of calvalry to battles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>天養元年（1144年）正四位上に叙され、尾張国守となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was rewarded Sho shi-i no jo in 1144 and also became kokushu of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was rewarded Sho shi-i no jo in 1144 and also became kokushu of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was rewarded Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade) in 1144 and also became the Governor of Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>Shoshiinojo (Senior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)、およびthe Governor of Owari Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>忠盛は鳥羽院庁の四位別当としても活動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamori served as Shi-i Betto in the Toba cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori served as Shi-i Betto in the Toba cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori served as Shi-i Betto (chief administrator of fourth rank) in the Toba cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Shi-i Betto&quot;に補足を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>同僚の藤原忠隆は貴族でありながら乗馬の達人で意気投合するところがあったのか、忠隆の子・隆教は忠盛の娘を妻に迎えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his co-worker FUJIWARA no Tadataka was very good horse rider even though he was noble, Tadamori seemed to get along fine with him, and Tadataka&apos;s son, Takanori married Tadamori&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his co-worker FUJIWARA no Tadataka was a fine equestrian despite being a noble, Tadamori seemed to get along with him. Tadataka&apos;s son, Takanori married Tadamori&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his co-worker FUJIWARA no Tadataka was a fine equestrian despite being a noble, Tadamori seemed to get along with him, and Tadataka&apos;s son, Takanori married Tadamori&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>二文に分かれているため、一文になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>なお、忠隆の妻・栄子は崇徳上皇の乳母であり、忠盛の妻・宗子は崇徳の長子・重仁親王の乳母だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadataka&apos;s wife, Eiko was nanny of the retired Emperor Sutoku and Tadamori&apos;s wife, Muneko was nanny of the first son of the retired Emperor Sutoku, Imperial Prince Shigehito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadataka&apos;s wife, Eiko was the nanny to the retired Emperor Sutoku, and Tadamori&apos;s wife, Muneko, was the nanny to the first son of the retired Emperor Sutoku, Imperial Prince Shigehito.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadataka&apos;s wife, Eiko was the nanny to the Retired Emperor Sutoku, and Tadamori&apos;s wife, Muneko, was the nanny to the first son of the Retired Emperor Sutoku, Imperial Prince Shigehito.</e>
<cmt>the Retired Emperor Sutokuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>久安2年（1146年）播磨国守に任じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed kokushu of Harima Province in 1146.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed kokushu of Harima Province in 1146.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed the Governor of Harima Province in 1146.</e>
<cmt>kokushu of Harima Province→the Governor of Harima Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>翌年6月15日、清盛の郎党が祇園神社神人と小競り合いを起こし、延暦寺が忠盛・清盛の流罪を要求して強訴を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s retainers and jinnins of Gion-jinja Shrine had a skirmish on June 15, 1147 and the Enryaku-ji Temple pleaded violently to deport Tadamori and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori&apos;s retainers and jinnins of Gion-jinja Shrine had a skirmish on June 15, 1147 and the Enryaku-ji Temple protested violently for the deportation of Tadamori and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s retainers and jinnins of Gion-jinja Shrine had a skirmish on June 15, 1147 and the Enryaku-ji Temple protested violently for the deportation of Tadamori and Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>鳥羽法皇は忠盛の有する軍事的・経済的実力の重要性から藤原頼長の反対を押し切って擁護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor Toba supported Tadamori because of his strong military and financial power over FUJIWARA no Yorinaga&apos;s opposition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cloistered Emperor Toba supported Tadamori because of his strong military and financial power over FUJIWARA no Yorinaga&apos;s opposition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Emperor Toba supported Tadamori because of his strong military and financial power over FUJIWARA no Yorinaga&apos;s opposition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>仁平元年（1151年）刑部卿となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamori became gyobukyo (minister of justice) in 1151.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori became gyobukyo (minister of justice) in 1151.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori became Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice) in 1151.</e>
<cmt>刑部卿→頭文字を大文字にし、Gyobukyo (Minister of Justice)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>仁平3年（1153年）出家して没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a priest and died in 1153.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a priest and died in 1153.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a priest and died in 1153.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>左大臣・藤原頼長は「数国の吏を経、富巨万を累ね、奴僕国に満ち、武威人にすぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Minister of the Left, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga said, &quot;He had served as kokushu for several provinces, made a lot of money, had many retainers in his provinces and he had great military power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Minister of the Left, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga stated, &quot;He had served as kokushu for several provinces, made a lot of money, had many retainers in his provinces and he had great military power.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Minister of the Left, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga stated, &apos;He had served as the governor for several provinces, made a lot of money, had many retainers in his provinces and he had great military power.</e>
<cmt>原文にあわせ、シングルクォーテーションに変更、kokushu for several provinces→the governor for several provincesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>人となり恭倹、いまだかつて奢侈の行いあらず、時人これを惜しむ」と評した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was modest person and didn&apos;t roll in luxury. He is solely missed among us.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was a modest person and did not accept luxury. He is solely missed among us.&quot;</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was a modest person and did not accept luxury. He is solely missed among us.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文にあわせ、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="56">
<j>忠盛は諸国の受領を歴任したことに加えて、日宋貿易にも従事して莫大な富を蓄え、平氏政権の礎を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He created immense wealth from kokushu of several provinces and from trading between Japan and the Song Dynasty, that established the base of the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He created immense wealth from kokushu of several provinces and from trading between Japan and the Song Dynasty; and, this established the base of the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He created immense wealth from serving as the governor of several provinces and from trading between Japan and the Song Dynasty; and, this established the base of the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt>from kokushu of several provinces→from serving as the governor of several provincesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="57">
<j>歌人としても知られ、家集『平忠盛集』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also known as poet and his works include the anthology of poem &quot;Taira no Tadamori shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also known as a poet and his works include the poem anthology Taira no Tadamori Shu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also known as a poet and his works include the poem anthology &quot;Taira no Tadamori Shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Cprobot(id:97843), 古聞(id:110289), 春野秋葉(id:36725), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), 葉月(id:25674), 沢田(id:40580), 小者(id:172526), Kamitani(id:30757), 彩華1226(id:64711), Enosi(id:19649), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ゐ(id:795), 代言人(id:33675), Peregrine falcon(id:53947), Yas(id:739), Junger(id:10282), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>