<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>勝川春章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunsho KATSUKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunsho KATSUKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunsho KATSUKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>勝川 春章（かつかわ しゅんしょう、享保11年（1726年） - 寛政4年12月8日 (旧暦)（1793年1月19日））は、江戸時代の浮世絵師。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunsho KATSUKAWA (1726 - January 19, 1783) was an ukiyoe artist who lived in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunsho KATSUKAWA (1726 - January 19, 1793) was an ukiyoe artist in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>・「1793年」が「1783」となっていたので修正しました。・who livedが余分と思われるので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunsho KATSUKAWA (1726 - January 19, 1793) was an ukiyoe artist in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は不詳、俗称は要助（あるいは祐助とも）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His real last name was never known, and his nick name was Yosuke (or Yusuke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His real last name is unknown, but his nickname was Yosuke (or Yusuke).</e>
<cmt>・「不詳」は現在において不明ということだと思いますので、現在形にしました。・接続詞を変更しました。・nicknameを１語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His real last name is unknown, but his nickname was Yosuke (or Yusuke).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>宮川春水に学ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He studied under Shunsui Miyagawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He studied under Shunsui Miyagawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He studied under Shunsui Miyagawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>画姓は初め宮川、または勝宮川、後に勝川と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his artist name, he selected the family name of Miyagawa, or Katsumiyagawa sometimes, and later called himself Katsukawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an artist, he used the surname of Miyagawa or Katsumiyagawa at first, and later Katsukawa.</e>
<cmt>・簡潔化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an artist, he used the surname of Miyagawa or Katsumiyagawa at first, and later Katsukawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>弟子には葛飾北斎がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of his disciples was Hokusai KATSUSHIKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his pupils was Hokusai KATSUSHIKA.</e>
<cmt>・disciplesをpupilsに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his pupils was Hokusai KATSUSHIKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>春章は、容貌を役者によって差別化しない鳥居派の役者絵とは異なる、写実的で、ブロマイド的な役者似顔絵を完成させ、大衆に支持された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike kabuki actor paintings of the Torii School, Shunsho did not discriminate about how actors were drawn, established realistic portrait-like art, and was widely accepted by the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunsho established realistic art of kabuki actor portraits different from those by artists of the Torii school, who applied the same drawing style to every actor&apos;s portrait, and Shunsho&apos;s prints were widely accepted by the public.</e>
<cmt>・元の訳は、春章が「差別化しない」となってしまっているようですので、原文通り鳥居派が「差別化しない」となるよう変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunsho established realistic art of kabuki actor portraits different from those by artists of the Torii school, who applied the same drawing style to every actor&apos;s portrait, and Shunsho&apos;s prints were widely accepted by the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのはじめとなったのは、一筆斎文調との合作として明和7年（1770年）に発表した『絵本舞台扇』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His established style was first seen in &quot;Ehonbutaiogi&quot; that he published jointly with Buncho IPPITSUSAI in 1770.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His established style was first seen in &quot;Ehonbutaiogi&quot; (Books of Actor Portraits), which he published jointly with Buncho IPPITSUSAI in 1770.</e>
<cmt>・『絵本舞台扇』の説明を加えました。・関係代名詞をthatから非制限用法のwhichに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His established style was first seen in &quot;Ehonbutaiogi&quot; (Books of Actor Portraits), which he published jointly with Buncho IPPITSUSAI in 1770.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、文調と比較して、明快な色彩と、素直で誇張のない表現で、人気を博した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to Buncho&apos;s art, Shunsho&apos;s art was more vivid and honest with no exaggerations, and his work became popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunsho&apos;s works became popular, as they were vivid and honest with no exaggerations, compared to Buncho&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>・因果関係を明示する訳文にした方が自然と考え、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunsho&apos;s works became popular, as they were vivid and honest with no exaggerations, compared to Buncho&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>特に「東扇（あずまおおぎ）」の連作は、人気役者の似顔絵を扇に仕立てて身近に愛用するために、扇の形に線が入っており、大首絵（おおくびえ）の先駆的作品とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his &apos;Azuma Ogi&apos; series, a fan-shaped frame was drawn on each sheet of paper and the portrait of a popular actor was drawn in that frame so that it could be used as a fan, and this work style was believed to be the pioneer of an ukiyoe style called Okubie (or large-head pictures).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his &apos;Azuma Ogi&apos; series depicting portraits of popular actors, a fan-shaped frame was drawn on each sheet of paper so that people could use it to make a fan (ogi) and enjoy seeing it in their daily life, and this series&apos; half-lengths are believed to have been the pioneering works later developed into Okubie (&quot;large-head&quot; pictures).</e>
<cmt>・「身近に愛用する」の部分を訳に入れました。・原文の「～とされる」が「～とされていた」となっていたのを修正しました。・pioneerが誤用と思われるので変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his &apos;Azuma Ogi&apos; series depicting portraits of popular actors, a fan-shaped frame was drawn on each sheet of paper so that people could use it to make a fan (ogi) and enjoy seeing it in their daily life, and this series&apos; half-lengths are believed to have been the pioneering works later developed into Okubie (&quot;large-head&quot; pictures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>勝川派は、役者似顔絵を得意として、多数の弟子を抱え隆盛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The specialty of the Katsukawa School was actor portraits, and the school flourished with many disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The specialty of the Katsukawa school was actor portraits, and the school flourished with many apprentices.</e>
<cmt>・Schoolのsを小文字にしました。・disciplesを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The specialty of the Katsukawa school was actor portraits, and the school flourished with many apprentices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>天明後期には勝川派を代表する座を弟子の春好と春英に譲り、春章は肉筆画に専念していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Tenmei era, he let his disciples Shunko and Shunei represent the school, and he started to focus on brush painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Tenmei era, he handed over the leadership position of the school to his apprentices, Shunko and Shunei, and he started to focus on brush paintings.</e>
<cmt>・letが口語的なので変更しました。・disciplesを変更しました。・paintingを複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Tenmei era, he handed over the leadership position of the school to his apprentices, Shunko and Shunei, and he started to focus on brush paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>特に細密な美人画は当時から称賛されていたようで、「春章一幅価千金」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His bijinga (portrait of beautiful women) seem to have been highly recognized at that time and were described as &apos;Shunsho Ippuku Atai Senkin.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His detailed bijinga (portraits of beautiful women) seem to have been highly recognized at that time, and were described as &apos;Shunsho Ippuku Atai Senkin&apos; (One painting by Shunsho is worth a thousand gold coins).</e>
<cmt>・「細密な」を加えました。・portraitを複数形にしました。・「春章一幅価千金」の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His detailed bijinga (portraits of beautiful women) seem to have been highly recognized at that time, and were described as &apos;Shunsho Ippuku Atai Senkin&apos; (One painting by Shunsho is worth a thousand gold coins).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>肉筆画の代表作としては、肉筆美人画「雪月花図」（三幅対、重要文化財指定、MOA美術館蔵）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the most famous brush paintings is a bijinga &apos;Setsugekkazu&apos; (3-panel work, designated important cultural property, and owned by the MOA, Museum of Art).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of his most famous brush paintings is a bijinga &apos;Setsugekkazu&apos; (Paintings of Snow, the Moon, and flowers) (3-panel work, designated important cultural property, and owned by the MOA Museum of Art).</e>
<cmt>・theをhisに変更しました。・「雪月花図」の意味を訳出しました。・美術館の名称を公式サイトに従って、the MOA Museum of Art（コンマなし）としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of his most famous brush paintings is a bijinga &apos;Setsugekkazu&apos; (Paintings of Snow, the Moon, and flowers) (3-panel work, designated important cultural property, and owned by the MOA Museum of Art).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 VolkovBot(id:105371), MIsogi(id:20599), DragonBot(id:161936), Cprobot(id:97843), Yas(id:739), Hermes(id:21387), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), SieBot(id:126695), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>