<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>九条尚忠</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisatada KUJO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisatada KUJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisatada KUJO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>九条 尚忠（くじょう ひさただ、寛政10年7月25日 (旧暦)（1798年9月5日） － 明治4年8月21日 (旧暦)（1871年10月5日））は、江戸時代後期から明治の公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisatada KUJO (male, September 5, 1798 to October 5, 1871) is a court noble who lived from late Edo period to Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisatada KUJO (male, September 5, 1798 to October 5, 1871) is a court noble who lived from late Edo period to Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisatada KUJO (September 5, 1798 - October 5, 1871) is a court noble who lived from late Edo period to Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>male,削除しました。to ハイフンに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>官位は従一位・関白。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KUJO&apos;s official title was Juichii (junior first rank) and Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KUJO&apos;s official title was Juichii (junior first rank) and Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisatada&apos;s official title was Juichii (Junior First Rank) and Kanpaku (chief advisor to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Kujoを主語にすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatada&apos;sと訂正しました。(Junior First Rank)大文字にしました。ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>左大臣・二条治孝の子で、母は樋口基康の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KUJO was a son of Harutaka NIJO, the minister of the left, and KUJO&apos;s mother was a daughter of Motoyasu HIGUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KUJO was a son of Harutaka NIJO, the minister of the left, and KUJO&apos;s mother was a daughter of Motoyasu HIGUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisatada was a son of Harutaka NIJO, the minister of the left, and his mother was a daughter of Motoyasu HIGUCHI.</e>
<cmt>Kujoを主語にすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatadaと訂正しました。KUJO&apos;sはhisとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>九条道孝は長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michitaka KUJO was the first son of KUJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michitaka KUJO was the first son of KUJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michitaka KUJO was the first son of Hisatada.</e>
<cmt>Kujoとすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatadaと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>孝明天皇の妃・英照皇太后は娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Empress Dowager Eisho, the wife of Emperor Komyo, was a daughter of KUJO&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Empress Dowager Eisho, the wife of Emperor Komyo, was a daughter of KUJO&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Empress Dowager Eisho, the wife of Emperor Komyo, was a daughter of Hisatada.</e>
<cmt>Kujoとすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatadaと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大正天皇の妃・貞明皇后は孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Empress Teimei, the wife of Emperor Taisho, was a grandchild of KUJO&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress Teimei, the wife of Emperor Taisho, was a grandchild of KUJO&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Teimei, the wife of Emperor Taisho, was a grandchild of Hisatada.</e>
<cmt>Kujoとすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatadaと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>権大納言・九条輔嗣に養育された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KUJO was raised by Suketsugu KUJO, the chief councillor of state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KUJO was raised by Suketsugu KUJO, the chief councillor of state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisatada was raised by Suketsugu KUJO, Gon Dainagon (the chief councillor of state).</e>
<cmt>Kujoとすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatadaと訂正しました。Gon Dainagon、括弧補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>長期間関白職を務めた鷹司政通から職を受け継ぐこととなったが、女癖の悪さもあり、各方面より警戒された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it was determined that KUJO succeeded to the position of kanpaku from Masamichi TAKATSUKASA who had fulfilled the duty of kanpaku for a long time, people in many sections were cautious about KUJO because of the reasons including that KUJO could not keep his hands off women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it was determined that KUJO succeeded to the position of kanpaku from Masamichi TAKATSUKASA who had fulfilled the duty of kanpaku for a long time, people in many sections were cautious about KUJO because he could not keep his hands off women.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it was determined that Hisatada succeeded to the position of kanpaku from Masamichi TAKATSUKASA who had fulfilled the duty of kanpaku for a long time, people in many sections were cautious about Hisatada because he could not keep his hands off women.</e>
<cmt>Kujoとすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatadaと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1858年、アメリカはじめ諸外国との通商に際して、幕府が日米修好通商条約の勅許調印を求めてきた時、幕府との協調路線を推進して条約許可を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1858 when the Bakufu requested the Emperor to sign to permit the Harris Treaty with the US for starting trade with foreign countries including the US, KUJO promoted to take a cooperative line with the Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and demanded the permission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1858 when the Bakufu requested the Emperor to sign the Harris Treaty with the US to initiate trade with foreign countries including the US, KUJO promoted cooperation with the Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and demanded permission to carry out the treaty.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1858 when the Bakufu requested the Emperor to sign the Harris Treaty with the US to initiate trade with foreign countries including the US, Hisatada promoted cooperation with the Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and demanded permission to carry out the treaty.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。Kujoとすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatadaと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし同年、幕府との協調路線に反発する88人の公卿たちの猛烈な抗議活動により条約勅許はならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the same year, the permission by the Emperor could not be established due to the fierce protest actions by 88 higher-ranked officials of the Imperial Court who were against the cooperative line with the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the same year, the permission by the Emperor could not be established due to fierce protest by 88 higher-ranking officials of the Imperial Court who were against the cooperative line with the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the same year, the permission by the Emperor could not be established due to fierce protest by 88 higher-ranking officials of the Imperial Court who were against the cooperative line with the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（いわゆる「廷臣八十八卿列参事件」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(So-called &quot;Case of 88 Imperial Court Officials&apos; Marching&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(So-called &quot;Case of 88 Imperial Court Officials&apos; Marching&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(So-called &quot;Case of 88 Imperial Court Officials&apos; Marching&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、復職を許されたが、その後も幕府との協調路線を推進し、公武合体運動の一環である和宮降嫁を積極的に推し進めたため、一部の過激な尊皇攘夷派から糾弾されて、謹慎を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though KUJO was permitted to return to his position later on, he still continued to promote the cooperative line with the Bakufu and actively drove the marriage of Kazu no Miya, the Imperial princess, with Shogun as a part of the movement to establish a coalition government by the Imperial Court and the Bakufu and, therefore, KUJO was denounced by the extremists of the faction which advocated to revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians, and KUJO was ordered to stay at home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though KUJO was permitted to return to his position later on, he still continued to promote the cooperative line with the Bakufu and actively drove the marriage of Kazu no Miya, the Imperial princess, with Shogun as a part of the movement to establish a coalition government by the Imperial Court and the Bakufu and, therefore, KUJO was denounced by the extremists of the faction which advocated revering the Emperor and expelling the barbarians, and KUJO was ordered to stay at home.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Hisatada KUJO was permitted to return to his position later on, he still continued to promote the cooperative line with the Bakufu and actively drove the marriage of Imperial Princess Kazunomiya with Shogun as a part of the movement to establish a coalition government by the Imperial Court and the Bakufu and, therefore, Hisatada was denounced by the extremists of the faction which advocated revering the Emperor and expelling the barbarians, and Hisatada was ordered to stay at home.</e>
<cmt>Kujoとすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatadaと訂正しました。Kazu no MiyaをImperial Princess Kazunomiyaに訂正しました。, the Imperial princess,削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>74歳で死去。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KUJO died at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KUJO died at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died at the age of 74.</e>
<cmt>KUJOをHeに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>墓所は京都市東山区の東福寺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KUJO&apos;s grave is located in Tofuku-ji temple in Higashiyama Ward in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KUJO&apos;s grave is located in Tofuku-ji temple in Higashiyama Ward in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisatada&apos;s grave is located in Tofuku-ji temple in Higashiyama Ward in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Kujoとすると混乱する可能性があるので、Hisatadaと訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TakuyaMurata(id:156), ノトス(id:42992), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), たとゥ(id:25557), トホホ川(id:50502), 伏儀(id:142093), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), ウラヌス(id:25954), Frozen-mikan(id:6130), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>