<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京極マリア</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maria KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maria KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maria KYOGOKU</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京極 マリア（きょうごく まりあ、天文 (元号)11年（1542年）頃 - 元和 (日本)4年7月1日 (旧暦)（1618年8月20日））は戦国時代 (日本)の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maria KYOGOKU (around 1542-August 20, 1618) was a woman who lived during the Sengoku Period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maria KYOGOKU (around 1542-August 20, 1618) was a woman who lived during the Sengoku Period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maria KYOGOKU (around 1542 - August 20, 1618) was a woman who lived during the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>戦国時代の補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>実名は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her real name was unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her real name was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real name was unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>当時は夫婦別姓なので本来は京極姓で呼ぶのは適切ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the couple had different surnames at that time, it was not suitable to call a person with a Kyogoku (family name).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since couples had different surnames at that time, it was not suitable to call a person with a Kyogoku (family name).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since couples had different surnames at that time, it was not suitable to call her with a family name of Kyogoku.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天文 (元号)11年（1542年）頃、近江国の支配権を京極氏より奪った浅井氏の当主浅井久政の次女、浅井長政の姉として小谷城で生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was born around 1542 at Kotani Castle as the second daughter to Hisamasa AZAI, the family head of the Azai clan who snatched away the power from the Kyogoku clan to rule the Omi no kuni (Omi Province), and was the older sister to Nagamasa AZAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was born around 1542 at Kotani Castle as the second daughter to Hisamasa AZAI, the family head of the Azai clan who snatched away power from the Kyogoku clan to rule the Omi no kuni (Omi Province), and was the older sister to Nagamasa AZAI.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was born around 1542 at Kotani-jo Castle as the second daughter to Hisamasa AZAI, the family head of the Azai clan who snatched away power from the Kyogoku clan to rule the Omi Province, and as the older sister to Nagamasa AZAI.</e>
<cmt>Kotani-jo としました。Omi Province　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>京極高吉に嫁ぎ、子は永禄6年（1563年）に小谷城で京極高次、元亀3年（1572年）に京極高知、時期は定かでないが京極竜子、他に二人の娘（氏家行広室、朽木宣綱室）を設ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She married Takayoshi KYOGOKU and had children, Takatsugu KYOGOKU in 1563 at Kotani Castle, Takatomo KYOGOKU in 1572, Tatsuko KYOGOKU (date uncertain), and two other daughters (the wives of Yukihiro UJIE and Nobutsuna KUTSUKI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She married Takayoshi KYOGOKU and had children, Takatsugu KYOGOKU in 1563 at Kotani Castle, Takatomo KYOGOKU in 1572, Tatsuko KYOGOKU (date uncertain), and two other daughters (the wives of Yukihiro UJIE and Nobutsuna KUTSUKI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She married Takayoshi KYOGOKU and had children, Takatsugu KYOGOKU in 1563 at Kotani-jo Castle, Takatomo KYOGOKU in 1572, Tatsuko KYOGOKU (date uncertain), and two other daughters (the wives of Yukihiro UJIIE and Nobutsuna KUTSUKI).</e>
<cmt>Kotani-jo, UJIIE としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天正元年（1573年）より前に、夫は嫡男の高次を織田信長に人質として送り上平寺に隠居しており、そこで共に暮らしたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her husband sent his progeny, Takatsugu, to Nobunaga ODA as a hostage before 1573 and retired at the Johei-ji Temple, and it is believed that she resided there as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her husband sent his progeny, Takatsugu, to Nobunaga ODA as a hostage before 1573 and retired at Johei-ji Temple, and it is believed that she resided there as well.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her husband sent his progeny, Takatsugu, to Nobunaga ODA as a hostage before 1573 and retired at Johei-ji Temple, and it is believed that she resided there as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>天正9年（1581年）、夫と共に安土城城下でグネッキ・ソルディ・オルガンティノ神父より洗礼を受け、洗礼名としてドンナ・マリアを授かるが、その数日後に夫は死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was christened with her husband at the castle town of Azuchi Castle by Priest Gnecchi-Soldo Organtino in 1581 and received the Christian name of Donna Maria, but her husband died within a few days later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was christened with her husband at the castle town of Azuchi Castle by Priest Gnecchi-Soldo Organtino in 1581 and received the Christian name of Donna Maria, but her husband died a few days later.</e>
<cmt>omitted &quot;within&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was christened with her husband at the castle town of Azuchi-jo Castle by Priest Gnecchi-Soldo Organtino in 1581 and received the Christian name of Donna Maria, but her husband died a few days later.</e>
<cmt>Azuchi-jo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>天正15年（1587年）にバテレン追放令が豊臣秀吉により発せられた後も信仰を貫き、秀吉の側室となった竜子を除く四人の子が洗礼を受けたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She continue to pursue Christianity even after Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI declared a deportation edict of Christians, and four of her children are believed to be christened except for Tatsuko, who became the concubine of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She continued to pursue Christianity even after Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI declared a deportation edict of Christians, and four of her children are believed to be christened; all her children other than Tatsuko, who became the concubine of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She continued to pursue Christianity even after Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI declared a deportation edict of Christians in 1587, and four of her children are believed to be christened; all her children other than Tatsuko, who became the concubine of Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>1587年　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>京都、大坂での布教活動を経て、関ヶ原の戦いの後には次男の高知が領した丹後国泉源寺村（京都府舞鶴市）に移り住み、高知の庇護の下此御堂という建物を中心に布教活動を行い、更なる信仰を深めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She performed missionary works in Kyoto and Osaka, moved to Sengenji village, Tango no kuni (Tango Province) (Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture) ruled by her second son Takatomo after the Battle of Sekigahara, performed missionary works centered around the building called Komido patronized by Takatomo, and further pursued her religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She performed missionary works in Kyoto and Osaka, moved to Sengenji village, Tango no kuni (Tango Province) (Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture) ruled by her second son Takatomo after the Battle of Sekigahara, performed missionary works centered around the building called Komido patronized by Takatomo, and further pursued her religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She performed missionary works in Kyoto and Osaka, moved to Sengenji Village, Tango Province (Maizuru City, Kyoto Prefecture) ruled by her second son Takatomo after the Battle of Sekigahara, performed missionary works centered around the building called Komido patronized by Takatomo, and further pursued her religion.</e>
<cmt>Tango Province としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>泉源寺村は丹後の最東端に位置し丹後若狭の国境に近いことから選んだとされ、長男が領する若狭の小浜にも度々足を運んだともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sengenjimura was chosen since it was located at the most eastern part of Tango and closest to the border of Tango-Wakasa, and she occasionally visited Kohama in Wakasa ruled by her eldest son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengenjimura was chosen since it was located at the most eastern part of Tango and closest to the border of Tango-Wakasa, and she occasionally visited Kohama in Wakasa ruled by her eldest son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengenji Village was chosen since it was located at the most eastern part of Tango and closest to the border of Tango-Wakasa, and she occasionally visited Obama in Wakasa ruled by her eldest son.</e>
<cmt>若狭の小浜→Obama と解釈し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>地元の民には「泉源寺様」と呼び慕われ、元和 (日本)4年（1618年）7月1日に亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was praised by the local people as &quot;Sengenji sama&quot; (Lady Sengenji) and passed away on July 1, 1618.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was praised by the local people as &quot;Sengenji sama&quot; (Lady Sengenji) and passed away on July 1, 1618.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was praised by the local people as &apos;Sengenji sama&apos; (Lady Sengenji) and passed away on August 20, 1618.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>法名は養福院殿法山寿慶大禅定尼と伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her Homyo (Buddhist name) has been told as Yofukuin dono Hozan Jukei Daizenjoni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her Homyo (Buddhist name) has been said to be Yofukuin dono Hozan Jukei Daizenjoni.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her Homyo (Buddhist name) has been said to be Yofukuin dono Hozan Jukei Daizenjoni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 前田左衛門佐(id:194701), M-sho-gun(id:88956), 代言人(id:33675), 俊(id:14924), パトロールカー(id:173570), Cprobot(id:97843), Sakurako h(id:80733), こぶまき(id:38278), NDR(id:5500), Kagetudo(id:163875), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>