<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>少弐頼尚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinao SHONI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinao SHONI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinao SHONI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>少弐 頼尚（しょうに よりなお（よりひさ）、1293年（永仁元年） - 1371年（建徳2年/応安4年））は、南北朝時代 (日本)、室町時代の九州の武将である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinao (also Yorihisa) SHONI (born 1293, died 1371) was a Kyushu military commander who lived during Japan&apos;s period of Northern and Southern Courts and into the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinao (also Yorihisa) SHONI (born 1293, died 1371) was a Kyushu military commander who lived during Japan&apos;s period of Northern and Southern Courts and into the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinao (also Yorihisa) SHONI (1293 - 1371) was a Kyushu military commander who lived during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and into the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正しました。「南北朝時代」（日本）を修正しました。（用語統一）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>少弐氏当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the head of the Shoni clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the head of the Shoni clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the head of the Shoni clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>父は少弐貞経。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father was Sadatsune SHONI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father was Sadatsune SHONI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father was Sadatsune SHONI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に少弐直資、少弐冬資、少弐頼澄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His sons included Naosuke SHONI, Fuyusuke SHONI, and Yorizumi SHONI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His sons included Naosuke SHONI, Fuyusuke SHONI, and Yorizumi SHONI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His sons included Naosuke SHONI, Fuyusuke SHONI, and Yorizumi SHONI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>法名は、梅渓本通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinao&apos;s homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was Baikei Hontsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinao&apos;s homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was Baikei Hontsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinao&apos;s homyo (posthumous Buddhist name) was Baikei Hontsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1333年（元弘3年）に鎌倉幕府討幕運動である元弘の乱が起こると賛同し、父の貞経に従って九州における北条氏勢力であった博多の鎮西探題北条英時を滅ぼす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Genko War, a war whose object was to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (which was controlled by the Hojo clan), broke out in 1333, Yorinao joined his father Sadatsune--both of whom were in support of the war--in a campaign to destroy Hidetoki HOJO, the chinzei tandai (military governor) of Hakata and the leader of the Hojo clan&apos;s strongest forces in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Genko War, a war whose object was to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (which was controlled by the Hojo clan), broke out in 1333, Yorinao joined his father Sadatsune--both of whom were in support of the war--in a campaign to destroy Hidetoki HOJO, the chinzei tandai (military governor) of Hakata and the leader of the Hojo clan&apos;s strongest forces in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Genko War, a war whose object was to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), broke out in 1333, Yorinao joined his father Sadatsune--both of whom were in support of the war--in a campaign to destroy Hidetoki HOJO, the chinzei tandai (military governor) of Hakata and the force of the Hojo clan in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>「鎌倉幕府」に続くカッコ部分を修正しました。the leader of the Hojo clan&apos;s strongest forces in Kyushu→the force of the Hojo clan in Kyushu と修正しました。（”最大勢力を率いていた”とはないので）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>鎌倉幕府滅亡後に後醍醐天皇の建武の新政が始まり、親政から離反した足利尊氏が九州へ落ち延びてくると頼尚は尊氏を迎えるために赤間関へ赴き、その最中に宮方に属した菊池武敏、阿蘇惟直に大宰府（福岡県福岡市）を攻められ父の貞経が戦死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Kamakura bakufu was destroyed, Emperor Godaigo&apos;s Kemmu Restoration began, but when Takauji ASHIKAGA, who had become disillusioned with Godaigo&apos;s direct imperial rule, tried to take refuge in Kyushu, Yorinao marched out to Akamaseki barrier to meet him; while en route, however, Dazaifu (the modern-day city of Fukuoka in Fukuoka Pref.) was attacked by Taketoshi KIKUCHI and Korenao ASO, both supporters of the Emperor, and his father Sadatsune was killed in the ensuing battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Kamakura bakufu was destroyed, Emperor Godaigo&apos;s Kemmu Restoration began, but when Takauji ASHIKAGA, who had become disillusioned with Godaigo&apos;s direct imperial rule, tried to take refuge in Kyushu, Yorinao marched out to Akamaseki barrier to meet him; while en route, however, Dazaifu (the modern-day city of Fukuoka in Fukuoka Pref.) was attacked by Taketoshi KIKUCHI and Korenao ASO, both supporters of the Emperor, and his father Sadatsune was killed in the ensuing battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kamakura bakufu was destroyed, the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s Kemmu Restoration began, but when Takauji ASHIKAGA, who had become disillusioned with Godaigo&apos;s direct imperial rule, tried to take refuge in Kyushu, Yorinao marched out to Akamaseki barrier to meet him; while en route, however, Dazaifu (the modern-day Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prefecture) was attacked by Taketoshi KIKUCHI and Korenao ASO, both supporters of the Emperor, and his father Sadatsune was killed in the ensuing battle.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。city of Fukuoka in Fukuoka Pref,→Fukuoka City, Fukuoka Prefecture と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1336年（建武 (日本)3年）に頼尚は足利勢とともに筑前国多々良浜の戦い（福岡市東区 (福岡市)）で菊池氏らを撃破し、再び京都を目指す尊氏に従い畿内まで従軍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336, Yorinao was part of the Ashikaga force that crushed the army of the Kikuchi clan in the battle of Tatarahama in Chikuzen Province (modern-day Higashi-ku Ward of the city of Fukuoka), and accompanied Takauji--who had once again set his sights on recapturing the capital of Kyoto--on his campaign into the Kinai (the region around Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336, Yorinao was part of the Ashikaga force that crushed the army of the Kikuchi clan in the battle of Tatarahama in Chikuzen Province (modern-day Higashi-ku Ward of the city of Fukuoka), and accompanied Takauji--who had once again set his sights on recapturing the capital of Kyoto--on his campaign into the Kinai (the region around Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336, Yorinao was part of the Ashikaga force that crushed the army of the Kikuchi clan in the battle of Tatarahama in Chikuzen Province (modern-day Higashi Ward, Fukuoka City), and accompanied Takauji--who had once again set his sights on recapturing the capital of Kyoto--on his campaign into the Kinai (the region around Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Higashi-ku Ward of the city of Fukuoka→Higashi Ward, Fukuoka City と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>頼尚は恩賞として筑前国、豊前国、肥後国、対馬国などの守護職を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinao was rewarded for his service by being made the governor of several provinces, including Chikuzen, Buzen, Higo, and Tsushima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinao was rewarded for his service by being made the governor of several provinces, including Chikuzen, Buzen, Higo, and Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinao was rewarded for his service by being appointed the governor of several provinces, including Chikuzen, Buzen, Higo, and Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>made→appointed と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>足利家で尊氏と弟の足利直義が対立した観応の擾乱が発生し、1349年（貞和5年/正平 (日本)4年）に直義の養子の足利直冬が九州へ逃れると頼尚は娘を娶せて直冬を擁立し、九州における足利勢力である九州探題の一色範氏と争うが、直冬が没落したために領地の大半は没収される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After internecine strife within the Ashikaga family blossomed into outright opposition between Takauji and his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA in what became known as the Kanno Disturbance, Tadayoshi&apos;s adopted son Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA sought refuge in Kyushu, and Yorinao chose to back Tadafuyu, giving him his own daughter in marriage and falling into armed conflict with Noriuji ISSHIKI, the Kyushu tandai (military commissioner) and bastion of Ashikaga strength in Kyushu, but Tadafuyu was destroyed, and consequently the greater part of Yorinao&apos;s territory was confiscated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After internecine strife within the Ashikaga family blossomed into outright opposition between Takauji and his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA in what became known as the Kanno Disturbance, Tadayoshi&apos;s adopted son Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA sought refuge in Kyushu, and Yorinao chose to back Tadafuyu, giving him his own daughter in marriage and falling into armed conflict with Noriuji ISSHIKI, the Kyushu tandai (military commissioner) and bastion of Ashikaga strength in Kyushu, but Tadafuyu was destroyed, and consequently the greater part of Yorinao&apos;s territory was confiscated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After internecine strife within the Ashikaga family blossomed into outright opposition between Takauji and his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA in what became known as the Kanno Disturbance, Tadayoshi&apos;s adopted son Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA sought refuge in Kyushu in 1349, and Yorinao chose to back Tadafuyu, giving him his own daughter in marriage and falling into armed conflict with Noriuji ISSHIKI, the Kyushu tandai (military commissioner) and the force of Ashikaga in Kyushu, but Tadafuyu was destroyed, and consequently the greater part of Yorinao&apos;s territory was confiscated.</e>
<cmt>「1349年」を補いました。bastion of Ashikaga strength→the force of Ashikaga と修正しました。（意味合いが強すぎるため）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さらに吉野朝廷は後醍醐天皇の皇子である懐良親王を征西将軍として九州へ派遣し、懐良は南九州へ入り菊池氏に迎えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, when Imperial Prince Kaneyoshi (also pronounced &quot;Kanenaga&quot;), Emperor Godaigo&apos;s own son, was named seisei shogun (general who pacifies the west) and sent by the Yoshino Court (that is, the Southern Court) on a military expedition to Kyushu, he entered Kyushu in the south and went to join forces with the Kikuchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, when Imperial Prince Kaneyoshi (also pronounced &quot;Kanenaga&quot;), Emperor Godaigo&apos;s own son, was named seisei shogun (general who pacifies the west) and sent by the Yoshino Court (that is, the Southern Court) on a military expedition to Kyushu, he entered Kyushu in the south and went to join forces with the Kikuchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, when the Imperial Prince Kaneyoshi (also pronounced &quot;Kanenaga&quot;), the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s own son, was sent by the Yoshino Court (that is, the Southern Court) as seisei shogun (general who pacifies the west) on a military expedition to Kyushu, he entered the southern Kyushu and went to join forces with the Kikuchi clan.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1359年（延文4年/正平14年）には少弐氏は菊池武光ら征西将軍勢力と筑後川の戦いで敗れ、1361年には頼尚は大宰府有智山城を追われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1359, the Shoni clan was defeated by Takemitsu KIKUCHI and the rest of the seisei shogun&apos;s army in the Battle of Chikugo-gawa River, and in 1361 Yorinao was driven back to Uchiyama-jo Castle in Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1359, the Shoni clan was defeated by Takemitsu KIKUCHI and the rest of the seisei shogun&apos;s army in the Battle of Chikugo-gawa River, and in 1361 Yorinao was driven back to Uchiyama-jo Castle in Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1359, the Shoni clan was defeated by Takemitsu KIKUCHI and the rest of the seisei shogun&apos;s army in the Battle of Chikugo-gawa River, and in 1361 Yorinao was driven back from Uchiyama-jo Castle in Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>driven back to→driven back from と修正しました。（を（から）追われる）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1371年に没、享年77。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died in 1371 at the age of 77.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He died in 1371 at the age of 77.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He died in 1371 at the age of 77.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Kozo(id:15492), Yonoemon(id:55450), 代言人(id:33675), Cprobot(id:97843), Lupinoid(id:68), Kanoe(id:17203), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Bmeg(id:118515), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>