<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平経正</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tsunemasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tsunemasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tsunemasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平 経正（たいら の つねまさ、生年未詳 - 寿永3年2月7日 (旧暦)（1184年3月20日））は、平安時代末期の武将、歌人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tsunemasa (birth year unknown to March 20, 1184).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tsunemasa (birth year unknown to March 20, 1184).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tsunemasa (birth year unknown to March 27, 1184) was a busho (Japanese military commander) and a kajin (waka poet) in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。訳抜け「平安時代末期の武将、歌人。」補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平経盛の長男で、弟に平経俊、平敦盛がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the eldest son of TAIRA no Tsunemori; TAIRA no Tsunetoshi and TAIRA no Atsumori were his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the eldest son of TAIRA no Tsunemori; TAIRA no Tsunetoshi and TAIRA no Atsumori were his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the eldest son of TAIRA no Tsunemori; TAIRA no Tsunetoshi and TAIRA no Atsumori were his younger brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平清盛の甥にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a nephew of Taira no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a nephew of Taira no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a nephew of TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>TAIRA大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官位は正四位下に昇叙し、但馬国守、皇太后宮亮、左馬権頭を歴任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and served as a director of Tajima Province, Taikotaigogu no suke (assistant master of the grand empress dowager&apos;s household), Sama no gon no kami (Provisional Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and served as a director of Tajima Province, Taikotaigogu no suke (assistant master of the grand empress dowager&apos;s household), Sama no gon no kami (Provisional Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade), and served as Tajima no kuni no kami (governor of Tajima Province), Kotaigogu no suke (assistant master of the empress dowager&apos;s household), Sama no gon no kami (Provisional Captain of Samaryo, Left Division of Bureau of Horses).</e>
<cmt>但馬国守→Tajima no kuni no kami (governor of Tajima Province)皇太后宮亮→Kotaigogu no suke (assistant master of the empress dowager&apos;s household)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>一門の中の俊才として知られ、歌人、また琵琶の名手として名を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was known as the brilliant person of his family, and also gave himself a good reputation as an expert of kajin (waka poet) and a biwa (Japanese lute) player.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was known as the brilliant person of his family, and also earned reputation as an expert of kajin (waka poet) and a biwa (Japanese lute) player.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was known as the brilliant person of his family, and also earned reputation as an expert of kajin (waka poet) and a biwa (Japanese lute) player.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原俊成や仁和寺五世門跡覚性法親王といった文化人と親交が深かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had close relations with intellectual people such as FUJIWARA no Toshinar and Ninna-ji Temple the fifth generation monzeki (temple rank) Monk Prince Kakusho.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。データベースでは Cloisered Imperial Prince Kakushoでしたが、→Monk Prince Kakusho としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had close relations with intellectual people such as FUJIWARA no Toshinar and Ninna-ji Temple the fifth generation monzeki (temple rank) Monk Prince Kakusho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had close relations with intellectual people such as FUJIWARA no Toshinari and Ninna-ji Temple the fifth generation monzeki (temple rank) Cloisered Imperial Prince Kakusho.</e>
<cmt>Toshinari訂正しました。Cloisered Imperial Prince Kakushoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>とりわけ覚性からは、経正が幼少時を仁和寺で過ごしたこともあり、楽才を認められ琵琶の銘器『青山』を下賜されるなど寵愛を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Tsunemasa spent his time at Ninna-ji Temple when he was young, he was in favor of Kakusho; he was recognized in his music talents and granted &quot;Aoyama&quot;, an excellent biwa, by Kakusho.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Tsunemasa spent his time at Ninna-ji Temple when he was young, he was in favor of Kakusho; he was recognized for his music talents and granted &quot;Aoyama&quot;, an excellent biwa, by Kakusho.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Tsunemasa spent his time at Ninna-ji Temple when he was young, he was in favor of Kakusho; he was recognized for his music talents and granted &quot;Aoyama,&quot; an excellent biwa, by Kakusho.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>寿永2年の平家都落ちの際に仁和寺に駆けつけ、拝領の『青山』を返上し和歌を残した逸話は、『平家物語』中「経正都落」、『源平盛衰記』中「経正仁和寺宮ヘ参リシ事」条などで著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Taira clan exiled from the capital in 1183, he rushed to Niwa-ji temple and returned &quot;Aoyama&quot; which he was granted and offered waka; such episode was famous in `Tsunemasa no Miyakoochi&apos; (Tsunemasa&apos;s Flight from the Capital) of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike) and `経正仁和寺宮ヘ参リシ事&apos; article of &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans), etc.</e>
<cmt>経正仁和寺宮ヘ参リシ事→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Taira clan was exiled from the capital in 1183, he rushed to Niwa-ji temple and returned &quot;Aoyama&quot; which he was granted and offered waka; such episode was famous in `Tsunemasa no Miyakoochi&apos; (Tsunemasa&apos;s Flight from the Capital) of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike) and `経正仁和寺宮ヘ参リシ事&apos; article of &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans), etc.</e>
<cmt>Robert: &quot;which he was granted and offered waka&quot; doesn&apos;t make any sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Taira clan was exiled from the capital in 1183, he rushed to Ninna-ji Temple and returned &quot;Aoyama&quot; which he was granted and offered waka; such episode was famous in &apos;Tsunemasa no Miyakoochi&apos; (Tsunemasa&apos;s Flight from the Capital) of &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (The tale of the Heike) and &apos;An episode of Tsunemasa&apos;s visit to Ninna-ji Temple&apos; article of &quot;Genpei Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans), etc.</e>
<cmt>Niwa-jiをNinna-jiに訂正しました。Temple大文字にしました。全角の’を半角に訂正しました。`経正仁和寺宮ヘ参リシ事&apos; を、&apos;An episode of Tsunemasa&apos;s visit to Ninna-ji Temple&apos;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>寿永3年、一ノ谷の戦いにおいて、河越重房の手勢に討ち取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1184, he was avenged by Shigefusa KAWAGOE&apos;s own forces in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1184, he was avenged by Shigefusa KAWAGOE&apos;s own forces in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1184, he was avenged by Shigefusa KAWAGOE&apos;s own forces in the Battle of Ichinotani.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>公式に確認されている子女はないが、後世彼の子孫を称するものに生嶋氏がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children were not officially recognized, but the Ikushima clan referred themselves as his descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children were not officially recognized, but the Ikushima clan referred to themselves as his descendants.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children were not officially recognized, but the Ikushima clan referred to themselves as his descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また能の演目である『経政』は、経正を題材とした修羅物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;経政&quot; a program of Noh, was Shura-mono (Plays featuring the ghosts of warriors) which features Tsunemasa as a theme.</e>
<cmt>経政→読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;経政&quot; a program of Noh, was Shura-mono (Plays featuring the ghosts of warriors) which features Tsunemasa as a theme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tsunemasa&quot; (経政) a program of Noh, was Shura-mono (Plays featuring the ghosts of warriors) which features Tsunemasa as a theme.</e>
<cmt>&quot;経政&quot;→&quot;Tsunemasa&quot; (経政)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 霧木諒二(id:9795), Azusayumi7(id:21082), ゐ(id:795), Goki(id:7107), Hannah(id:15935), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>