<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤原成隆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Naritaka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Naritaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Naritaka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤原成隆（ふじわら の なりたか、生没年未詳）は平安時代末期の廷臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Naritaka (date of birth and death unknown) was a retainer of Imperial Court in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Naritaka (date of birth and death unknown) was a retainer of the Imperial Court at the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Naritaka (year of birth and death unknown) was a retainer of the Imperial Court at the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>左京大夫藤原家隆 （関白藤原師通の三男）の長男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the first son of Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) FUJIWARA no Ietaka, who was the third son of the chief adviser to the Emperor FUJIWARA no Moromichi.</e>
<cmt>「(左京大夫)」は重複しているので訳出していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the first son of Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) FUJIWARA no Ietaka, who was the third son of the chief adviser to the Emperor FUJIWARA no Moromichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the first son of Sakyo no daibu (Master of the Eastern Capital Offices) FUJIWARA no Ietaka, who was the third son of Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Moromichi.</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたので、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>母は土佐守藤原盛実の娘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Tosa no kuni no kami (the governor of Tosa Province) FUJIWARA no Morizane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother was the daughter of Tosa no kuni no kami (the governor of Tosa Province) FUJIWARA no Morizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother was the daughter of Tosa no kami (Governor of Tosa Province) FUJIWARA no Morizane.</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたので、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>子に隆親、孝定らがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His children included Takachika and Takasada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His children included Takachika and Takasada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His children included Takachika and Takasada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>官位は従四位上、少納言、皇后宮権亮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His official court rank was Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), shonagon (Lesser counselor), and Kogogushoku (officer for serving the Empress in household ministry).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His official court rank was Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), shonagon (Lesser counselor), and Kogogushoku (officer serving the Empress in the household ministry).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His official court rank was Jushiinojo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade), Shonagon (lesser councilor of state), and Kogo no miya gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Empress&apos;s Household).</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたので、原文・訳文共に修正しました。統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>仁平3年（1153年）に従四位上に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was appointed to Jushiijo in 1153.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was appointed to Jushiijo in 1153.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was appointed to Jushiinojo in 1153.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>左大臣藤原頼長とは父方・母方の双方で従兄弟同士の間柄であり、その関係から頼長の家司、近習として活動。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaijin (minister of the left) FUJIWARA no Yorinaga was his cousin both on his paternal and maternal sides, so he acted as Keishi (household superintendent) and kinju (attendant) of Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaijin (minister of the left) FUJIWARA no Yorinaga was his cousin both on his paternal and maternal sides, so he acted as Keishi (household superintendent) and kinju (attendant) of Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) FUJIWARA no Yorinaga was his cousin both on his paternal and maternal sides, so he acted as Keishi (household superintendent) and kinju (attendant) of Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱に当たっては、頼長とともに崇徳上皇方に参加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Hogen War in 1156, he joined the retired Emperor Sutoku side with Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Hogen War in 1156, he joined the retired Emperor Sutoku side with Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Hogen War in 1156, he joined the Retired Emperor Sutoku side with Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>敗戦後、上皇の命を受け、頼長を護衛し騎馬に同乗して敗走するが、頼長は源重貞の放った矢に当たり重傷を負う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After they were defeated, he received an order from the retired emperor to guard Yorinaga, and they rode on the same horse to flight, but Yorinaga was pierced by the arrow shot by MINAMOTO no Shigesada and was badly injured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After they were defeated, he received an order from the retired emperor to guard Yorinaga, and they rode on the same horse to flight, but Yorinaga was pierced by the arrow shot by MINAMOTO no Shigesada and was badly injured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After they were defeated, he received an order from the retired emperor to guard Yorinaga, and they rode on the same horse to flight, but Yorinaga was pierced by the arrow shot by MINAMOTO no Shigesada and was badly injured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>介護の甲斐なく頼長が死亡すると、成隆は数日間仁和寺に潜伏した末、出家した上で官軍に投降。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yorinaga died in spite of care, Naritaka hid out in the Ninna-ji Temple for several days, became a priest and surrender to the Imperial army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yorinaga died in spite of care, Naritaka hid out at Ninna-ji Temple for several days, became a priest and surrender to the Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yorinaga died in spite of care, Naritaka hid out at Ninna-ji Temple for several days, became a priest and surrender to the Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>審議の末に阿波国への流罪に処せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was exiled to Awa Province after consideration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was exiled to Awa Province after some consideration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was exiled to Awa Province after some consideration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『尊卑分脈』の記述によれば、その後帰京し没したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the description of Sonpi Bunmyaku (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that records the lineages of the aristocracy), he later returned to Kyoto and deceased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the description of Sonpi Bunmyaku (a text compiled in the fourteenth century that recorded the lineages of the aristocracy), he later returned to Kyoto and died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the description of &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku&quot; (Bloodlines of Noble and Base), he later returned to Kyoto and died.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション、用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Andee(id:20421), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>