<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>西園寺家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saionji Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saionji Family</e>
<cmt>It should take the article &quot;The.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saionji Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>西園寺（さいおんじ）家は、藤原氏の流れを汲む公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saionji Family is a court noble that is descended from Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saionji Family is court nobility descended from the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saionji Family were court nobility descended from the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>is→wereA family cannot be a noble given that the word &quot;noble&quot; is used to refer to a single person (as a noun), so the last change should not have been made.Also, the tense should be changed to the past tense and the verb should take the third person plural here, I think.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原氏藤原北家閑院流で、家格は清華家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saionji Family is of Fujiwara clan Fujiwara-hokke Kaninryu, and the Kakaku is Seiga Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saionji Family is of the Fujiwara clan Fujiwara-hokke Kaninryu, and the Kakaku is the Seiga Family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saionji Family was of the Fujiwara clan Fujiwara-hokke Kaninryu, and the Kakaku (family rank of court nobility) was the Seiga Family.</e>
<cmt>is→was(family rank of court nobility)補足A brief explanation or hint as to what Kakaku means is necessary, I think. Also, the tense is incorrect.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>洞院家、今出川家（菊亭家）は西園寺家の分かれである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toin Family and Imadegawa/Kikutei Family are branch families of Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Toin Family and Imadegawa/Kikutei Family are branch families of the Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Toin Family and Imadegawa/Kikutei Family were branch families of the Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt>are→were</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、西園寺の名字を名乗った有力な支流として伊予国の武家西園寺氏がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there is a samurai family, Saionji clan in Iyo-no-kuni as a major offshoot who used the surname of Saionji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there is a samurai family--the Saionji clan in Iyo-no-kuni--as a major offshoot that used the Saionji surname.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a samurai family--the Saionji clan in Iyo-no-kuni--as a major offshoot that used the Saionji surname.</e>
<cmt>Moreover, 削除is→wasJust because the Japanese says &quot;また&quot; doesn&apos;t mean you have to use a word like &quot;moreover&quot; if it is not suited to the flow of information, which it isn&apos;t here in my opinion.Again, the tense is incorrect.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家紋は左三つ巴を使用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest is Hidari-mitsudomoe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest is Hidari-mitsudomoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest is Hidari-mitsudomoe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>西園寺家は藤原公実の三男藤原通季を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The originator of Saionji Family is FUJIWARA no Michisue, the third son of FUJIWARA no Kimizane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The originator of the Saionji Family is Fujiwara no Michisue, the third son of Fujiwara no Kimizane.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The progenitor of the Saionji Family was FUJIWARA no Michisue, the third son of FUJIWARA no Kimizane.</e>
<cmt>名字大文字originator→progenitoris→wasEven to a native speaker of English who cannot read the Japanese to check the intended meaning, it should be clear that the use of the word &quot;originator&quot; is suspect here. The sentence seems to be saying that FUJIWARA no Michisue is the originator of the Saionji family, but given that we are not talking about the creator of something like a TV show, surely a more natural term would be &quot;progenitor&quot;.Again, the tense is incorrect.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>通季の曾孫西園寺公経のとき、源頼朝の姪を妻としていたことから承久の乱に際して鎌倉幕府の縁者として警戒されて朝廷に幽閉され、かえって乱後に幕府の信任を受けて関東申次として朝廷の実権を握り、太政大臣にまでのぼって家格を高めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the generation of Kintsune SAIONJI who was a great grandchild of Michisue, Kintsune was confined at the time of Jokyu-no ran War by the Imperial court since he was watched out for as a relative of Kamakura Shogunate for the reason that he married niece of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, but after the War Kintsune gained the confidence of the Shogunate, ruled the Imperial court as Kanto Moshitsugi, and climbed up to the grand minister of state to raise Kakau of Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the generation of Kintsune SAIONJI, who was a great grandchild of Michisue, Kintsune was confined at the time of the Jokyu-no-ran War by the Imperial Court since he was watched over as a relative of the Kamakura shogunate for the reason that he had married the niece of Minamoto no Yoritomo; however, after the War Kintsune he gained the confidence of the shogunate, ruled the Imperial Court as Kanto Moshitsugi, and rose to a position as grand minister of state while raising Kakau, of the Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kintsune SAIONJI, who was a great grandson of Michisue, was confined by the imperial court during the Jokyu-no-ran War because, having married the niece of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, he was being watched over as a relative of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun); after the war, however, Kintsune gained the confidence of the shogunate, wielded the real power in the imperial court through holding the office of Kanto Moshitsugi, and rose to the position of Daijo daijin (grand minister of state), raising the social standing of the Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt>Referring to what someone did during their own generation is strange in English so I have deleted that part. Also, please ask the translator not to use unexplained Japanese terms like &quot;kakau&quot; (which is spelt incorrectly anyway) in their translation. When I first read the translation I thought &quot;Kakau&quot; was the name of a child that Kintsune was raising.&quot;shogunate&quot; -&gt; &quot;bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>西園寺の家名は、公経が京都（山城国葛野郡北山荘）の別邸に建立した寺の名前に由来している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family name of Saionji comes from the name of the temple Kintsune built at Bettei in Kyoto (Kitayama-so, Kadono-gun, Yamashiro-no-kuni).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family name of Saionji comes from the name of the temple Kintsune built at Bettei, in Kyoto (Kitayama-so, Kadono-gun, Yamashiro-no-kuni).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family name of Saionji comes from the name of the temple Kintsune built at Bettei, in Kyoto (Kitayama-so, Kadono-gun, Yamashiro-no-kuni).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この堂は、別名、北山殿ともいわれ、現在の金閣寺は足利義満が西園寺家よりこの土地を譲られて建てたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This hall is also called as Kitayama-dono Palace, and the current Kinkaku-ji Temple was built by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA after he was given this land by Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This hall is also called Kitayama-dono Palace, and the current Kinkaku-ji Temple was built by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA after he was given this land by the Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This hall is also called Kitayama-dono Palace, and the current Kinkaku-ji Temple was built by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA after he was given this land by the Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>公経以来鎌倉幕府の後援を受け、鎌倉時代を通じて摂家をしのぐ勢力をもった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the generation of Kintsune, Saionji Family gained support from Kamakura Shogunate and came to power that surpassed Sekke throughout the Kamakura era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the generation of Kintsune, the Saionji Family gained support from the Kamakura shogunate and came to power that surpassed the sekke throughout the Kamakura era.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the generation of Kintsune, the Saionji Family gained support from the Kamakura shogunate and came to power that surpassed the sekke throughout the Kamakura era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>西園寺実兼は大覚寺統に接近し、亀山法皇や後醍醐天皇に娘を入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanekane SAIONJI approached Daikaku-ji to Genealogy and made his daughters marry Kameyama ho-ou Ex-emperor or Godaigo Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanekane SAIONJI approached Daikaku-ji through genealogy and made his daughters marry Kameyama ho-ou, the ex-emperor, or Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanekane SAIONJI approached Daikaku-ji through genealogy and made his daughters marry Kameyama ho-ou, the ex-emperor, or the Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、その息子西園寺公衡以後は、大覚寺統が幕府から距離を置くようになると今度は持明院統を支援して大覚寺統との対立を深めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But since the generation of Sanekane&apos;s son Kinhira SAIONJI, Saionji Family this time supported Jimyoin-to Genealogy when Daikaku-ji to Genealogy started to keep a distance from the Shogunate, thereby deepening the conflict with Daikaku-ji to Genealogy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the generation of Sanekane&apos;s son Kinhira SAIONJI, the Saionji Family supported the Jimyoin-to genealogy when the Daikaku-ji to genealogy began keeping a distance from the shogunate, thereby deepening the conflict with the Daikaku-ji to genealogy.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the generation of Sanekane&apos;s son Kinhira SAIONJI, the Saionji Family this time supported the Jimyoin-to genealogy when the Daikakuji-to genealogy started to keep a distance from the bakufu, thereby deepening the conflict with the Daikakuji-to genealogy.</e>
<cmt>Daikakuji-to に修正&quot;shogunate&quot; -&gt; &quot;bakufu&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、西園寺公宗のときに鎌倉幕府が滅亡して関東申次の役を解任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, at the generation of Kinmune SAIONJI, Saionji Family was dismissed from the post of Kanto Moshitsugi after the fall of Kamakura Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, at the generation of Kinmune SAIONJI, the Saionji Family was dismissed from the post of Kanto Moshitsugi after the fall of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, at the generation of Kinmune SAIONJI, the Saionji Family was dismissed from the post of Kanto Moshitsugi after the fall of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>公宗は北条氏の残党である北条泰家(時興)を匿い、建武の新政を開始した後醍醐天皇を暗殺し、持明院統の後伏見上皇を擁立する謀叛を計画し、弟の西園寺公重の密告で計画が露見した事により公宗は逮捕、処刑される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinmune harbored Yasuie HOJO who was a remnant of Hojo clan, assassinated Godaigo Emperor who started Kenmu-no-shinsei, plotted a rebellion to back Gofushimi Ex-emperor of Jimyoin-to Genealogy, and was arrested and executed since the plot was exposed by betrayal of Kinmune&apos;s younger brother Kinshige SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinmune harbored Yasuie HOJO, who was a remnant of the Hojo clan, assassinated Emperor Godaigo, who had started Kenmu-no-shinsei; plotted a rebellion to back the ex-emperor Gofushimi of Jimyoin-to genealogy; and was arrested and executed, the plot having been exposed by the betrayal of Kinmune&apos;s younger brother, Kinshige SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinmune harbored Yasuie HOJO, who was a remnant of the Hojo clan, the assassinated Emperor Godaigo, who had started Kenmu-no-shinsei; plotted a rebellion to back the ex-emperor Gofushimi of Jimyoin-to genealogy; and was arrested and executed, the plot having been exposed by the betrayal of Kinmune&apos;s younger brother, Kinshige SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>南北朝時代には公宗の子西園寺実俊が北朝 (日本)に仕えて右大臣にのぼり、家名を再興する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Nanbokucho era, Kinmune&apos;s son Sanetoshi SAIONJI served Hokucho (Japan) to climbed up to minister of he right, whereby the family name was restored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Nanbokucho era, Kinmune&apos;s son Sanetoshi SAIONJI served Hokucho (Japan) and rose to the post of minister of the right, whereby the family name was restored.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, Kinmune&apos;s son Sanetoshi SAIONJI served Hokucho (Japan) and rose to the post of minister of the right, whereby the family name was restored.</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の訳を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>室町時代・江戸時代には琵琶を家業とする家としても知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi and Edo eras, Saionji Family was also known as Biwa Japanese lute player as family business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi and Edo periods the Saionji Family was also known for having biwa (Japanese lute) players as a family business.</e>
<cmt>Plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi and Edo periods the Saionji Family was also known for having biwa (Japanese lute) players as a family business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>江戸初期には西園寺実晴が細川忠興の嫡男（後に廃嫡）細川忠隆こと長岡休無の長女徳姫を御台所に迎えて左大臣までのぼるが、長岡休無は西園寺家に種々の資金助成をし600石の遺産贈与もしている(綿考輯録)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Early Edo era, Saneharu SAIONJI welcomed Tokuhime, who was the eldest daughter of Kyumu NAGAOKA or Tadataka HOSOKAWA who was the heir (later lost the right to inheritance) of Tadaoki hosokawa, as Midaidokoro to climb up to minister of the left, and Kyumu NAGAOKA offered various financial support to Saionji Family including a donated property of 600 koku (Menko-shuroku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the early Edo period, Saneharu SAIONJI welcomed Tokuhime, who was the eldest daughter of Kyumu NAGAOKA, or Tadataka HOSOKAWA, who was the heir (but later lost the right to inheritance) of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, as Midaidokoro to rise to the post of minister of the left; and Kyumu NAGAOKA offered various kinds of financial support to the Saionji Family, including a donated property of 600 koku (Menko-shuroku).</e>
<cmt>Cap</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early days of the Edo period, Saneharu SAIONJI welcomed Tokuhime, who was the eldest daughter of Kyumu NAGAOKA (also known as Tadataka HOSOKAWA), as the Midaidokoro (wife of a shogun or a highest-ranking nobleman) of the heir (later disinherited) of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, and invited her to accept the post of Sadaijin (minister of the left); moreover, Kyumu NAGAOKA offered various forms of financial support to the Saionji family, including donating a property that yielded 600 koku of rice (Menko-shuroku).</e>
<cmt>Please check if I have understood this correctly. Also, please have the translator check what &quot;綿考輯録&quot; means and either translate it or provide a hint for the reader. A native speaker of English reading this is unlikely to know what &quot;Menko-shuroku&quot; is supposed to mean.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>幕末に同じ閑院流の徳大寺家から西園寺公望が養子に入り、明治維新を経て政治家として活躍、内閣総理大臣などを歴任し、元老として大正・昭和の政界に重きをなした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo era, Kinmochi SAIONJI was adopted from Tokudaiji Family of the same Kaninryu, worked as a politician after Meiji Restration, served as prime minister, and had a great influence as Genro on the polotical scene in Taisho and Showa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, Kinmochi SAIONJI was adopted from the Tokudaiji Family of the same kaninryu, worked as a politician after the Meiji Restoration, served as prime minister, and had great influence as a genro on the political scene during the Taisho and Showa eras.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, Kinmochi SAIONJI was adopted from the Tokudaiji Family of the same kaninryu, worked as a politician after the Meiji Restoration, served as prime minister, and had great influence as a genro on the political scene during the Taisho and Showa eras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ちなみに公望は、西園寺家の家業である筈の琵琶の演奏が苦手であったが、首相在任中に明治天皇から悪戯半分に「久しぶりに西園寺家の琵琶が聞きたい」と言われ、宮内省の雅楽寮の職員と琵琶の共演をさせられて四苦八苦したというエピソードが伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an anecdote that Kinmochi was not good at playing Biwa Japanese lute, which should have been the family bisuness of Saionji Family, and during Kinmochi&apos;s holding office as prime minister Meiji Emperor said out of mischief to Kinmochi, &quot;For the first time in a long while, I would like to listen to Biwa Japanese lute,&quot; and therefore he was forced to play Biwa Japanese lute in dire distress together with the officials of Utaryo in the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an anecdote that Kinmochi was not good at playing the biwa Japanese lute, which should have been the family business of the Saionji Family, and during Kinmochi&apos;s time in office as prime minister, Emperor Meiji said out of mischief to Kinmochi, &quot;For the first time in a long while, I would like to listen to biwa Japanese lute,&quot; and therefore he was forced to play the biwa Japanese lute in dire distress together with the officials of Utaryo in the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an anecdote that Kinmochi was not good at playing the biwa Japanese lute, which should have been the family business of the Saionji Family, and during Kinmochi&apos;s time in office as prime minister, the Emperor Meiji said out of mischief to Kinmochi, &quot;For the first time in a long while, I would like to listen to biwa Japanese lute,&quot; and therefore he was forced to play the biwa Japanese lute in dire distress together with the officials of Utaryo in the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), ドルチェット(id:46458), Y.Sanada(id:36926), 与左衛門(id:159462), MIsogi(id:20599), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Hosokawajun(id:72875), Himazin(id:22034), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Masyu(id:31065), Mymelo(id:122034), 海衛士(id:19229), Point136(id:211299), 寂華(id:83725), Safkan(id:423), NDR(id:5500), 伊(id:146699), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>