<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>松永氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsunaga clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsunaga clan</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsunaga clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>松永氏（まつながし）は大和国の戦国大名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsunaga clan is a warlord in Yamato-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsunaga clan was a warlord group in Yamato-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsunaga clan was a warlord group in Yamato-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>松永氏は祖先の武内宿禰から16世の孫真済が若狭国国司となり、同国遠敷郡松永荘より紀松永と称したことに始まるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsunaga clain is believed to originate from Shinzei, the sixteenth generation from the ancestor TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, who became Kokushi official of Wakasa-no-kuni and called himself Matsunaga KI naming after Matsunaga no sho, Domain of Onyu in Wakasa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the Matsunaga clan originated from Shinzei, the sixteenth generation from the ancestor TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, who had become a Kokushi official of Wakasa-no-kuni and therefore called himself Matsunaga KI, after Matsunaga no sho, the domain of Onyu, in Wakasa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the Matsunaga clan originated from Shinzei, the sixteenth generation from the ancestor TAKENOUCHI no Sukune, who had become a Kokushi official of Wakasa-no-kuni and therefore called himself Matsunaga KI, after Matsunaga no sho, the domain of Onyu, in Wakasa-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これによると紀氏の流れということになるが、戦国大名の松永氏は藤原氏または源氏を自称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that Matsunaga clan is descended from Ki clan, but the warlord Matsunaga clan called themselves as being descended from Fujiwara clan or Genji (Gen clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that the Matsunaga clan is descended from the Ki clan, but the warlords of the Matsunaga clan referred to themselves as being descended from the Fujiwara clan or the Genji (Gen clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that the Matsunaga clan is descended from the Ki clan, but the warlords of the Matsunaga clan referred to themselves as being descended from the Fujiwara clan or the Genji (Gen clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>乱世における一代の奸雄・松永久秀を祖とする大名家であるが、この久秀は出自すら詳しくわかっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsunaga clan is a family of feudal lord whose originator is Hisahide MATSUNAGA, a Kanyu (crafty hero) in a period of troublous times, but even the place of origin of Hisahide is not known in detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsunaga clan was a family of feudal lords whose originator was Hisahide MATSUNAGA, a Kanyu (crafty hero) from a period of troublesome times, but even the specifics of Hisahide&apos;s place of origin are not known.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsunaga clan was a family of feudal lords whose originator was Hisahide MATSUNAGA, a Kanyu (crafty hero) from a period of troublesome times, but even the specifics of Hisahide&apos;s place of origin are not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ただ、近年の研究から山城国の石清水八幡宮近辺が有力説として上がり、そのために同じ山城出身の美濃国を乗っ取った斎藤道三と旧知の間柄にあったという説まで存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, recent study revealed Iwashimizu Hachimangu in Yamashiro-no-kuni as the widely-accepted theory, and from this theory there is even a theory that Dosan SAITO who was also from Yamashiro and took over Mino-no-kuni was old friend of Hisahide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, recent study has brought forth Iwashimizu Hachimangu in Yamashiro-no-kuni as the widely accepted theory, and from this theory there comes another theory that Dosan SAITO, who was also from Yamashiro and had assumed control of Mino-no-kuni, was an old friend of Hisahide.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, recent study has brought forth Iwashimizu Hachimangu in Yamashiro-no-kuni as the widely accepted theory, and from this theory there comes another theory that Dosan SAITO, who was also from Yamashiro and had assumed control of Mino-no-kuni, was an old friend of Hisahide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>久秀は最初、細川氏に仕えていた三好長慶の右筆となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, Hisahide became Yuhitsu (amanuensis) of Chokei/Nagayoshi MIYOSHI who served Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, Hisahide became Yuhitsu (amanuensis) of Chokei (Nagayoshi MIYOSHI), who served the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, Hisahide became Yuhitsu (amanuensis) of Chokei (Nagayoshi MIYOSHI), who served the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そしてめきめきと実力を現し、京都奉行から三好氏の宰相にまでなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Hisahide emerged rapidly as Kyoto magistrate and thereafter even prime minister of Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisahide then emerged rapidly as a Kyoto magistrate and thereafter as prime minister of the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisahide then emerged rapidly as a Kyoto magistrate and thereafter as prime minister of the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>軍事面や築城に優れ、1560年には陪臣の身でありながら主家同様に室町幕府の御相伴衆にまで列せられているのを見てもわかるように、松永氏は久秀の優秀な能力において成長を遂げていったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisahide excelled at military strategy and fortification, and as is apparent from the fact that in 1560 although he as still vavasor, he, as well as his master&apos;s house, was appointed as Shobanshu (officials who accompany Shogun) of Muromachi Shogunate, Matsunaga clan came a long way thanks to Hisahide&apos;s excellent ability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisahide excelled at military strategy and fortification, and, as is apparent from the fact that in 1560, although he was still a vavasor, he (including his master&apos;s house) was appointed as a shobanshu (an official who accompanies the shogun) of the Muromachi shogunate; thus the Matsunaga clan had come a long way, thanks to Hisahide&apos;s excellent abilities.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisahide excelled at military strategy and fortification, and, as is apparent from the fact that in 1560, although he was still a vavasor, he (including his master&apos;s house) was appointed as a shobanshu (an official who accompanies the shogun) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun); thus the Matsunaga clan had come a long way, thanks to Hisahide&apos;s excellent abilities.</e>
<cmt>&quot;shogunate&quot; -&gt; &quot;bakufu&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし1561年の長慶の弟・十河一存の急死や1563年の長慶の子・三好義興の死は、久秀の毒殺説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is the widely-accepted theory that sudden death of Chokei&apos;s younger brother Kazumasa SOGO in 1561 and death of Chokei&apos;s son Yoshioki MIYOSHI in 1563 are attributed to poisoning by Hisahide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is a widely accepted theory that the sudden death of Chokei&apos;s younger brother Kazumasa SOGO in 1561 and the death of Chokei&apos;s son Yoshioki MIYOSHI in 1563 were the results of poisoning by Hisahide.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is a widely accepted theory that the sudden death of Chokei&apos;s younger brother Kazumasa SOGO in 1561 and the death of Chokei&apos;s son Yoshioki MIYOSHI in 1563 were the results of poisoning by Hisahide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>少なくとも、1564年の長慶の弟・安宅冬康の死は久秀が長慶に讒言して殺させたものであり、久秀はどうも三好氏の乗っ取りを企んでいたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At least, death of Chokei&apos;s younger brother Fuyuyasu ATAGI in 1564 is attributed to murder which was caused by Hisahide&apos;s slander to Chokei, and it seems that Hisahide was trying to take over Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At least, the death of Chokei&apos;s younger brother Fuyuyasu ATAGI in 1564 is attributed to murder, which was caused by Hisahide&apos;s slander of Chokei, and it seems that Hisahide was trying to take over the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the very least the death of Chokei&apos;s younger brother Fuyuyasu ATAGI in 1564 is attributed as murder, as the end result of Hisahide&apos;s slander against Chokei; moreover, it appears that Hisahide was trying to take over the Miyoshi clan.</e>
<cmt>Nevertheless&apos; は「少なくとも」の訳として間違い。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同年、長慶も病死して三好氏が弱体化すると久秀は畿内における覇権を握ろうと1565年、時の将軍・足利義輝を殺害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year Chokei also died of an illness which led to weakening of Miyoshi clan, and in 1565 Hisahide murdered Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, Shogun of the period, trying to gain the hegemony in Kinai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the same year Chokei also died of an illness, which led to the weakening of the Miyoshi clan, and in 1565 Hisahide murdered Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, the Shogun of the period, in an attempt to gain the hegemony in Kinai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the same year Chokei also died of an illness, which led to the weakening of the Miyoshi clan, and in 1565 Hisahide murdered Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, the Shogun of the period, in an attempt to gain the hegemony in Kinai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そして三好三人衆と対立しながらも一時は畿内における覇権を掌握し、松永氏の最盛期を築き上げたが、1568年、織田信長が義輝の弟・足利義昭を奉じて上洛してくると、信長の優れた器量と圧倒的軍事力を知って、名器・九十九髪茄子を信長に献上して降伏し、信長の家臣となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While being opposed to Nagayasu MIYOSHI, Tomomichi IWANARI and Masayasu MIYOSHI, Hisahide for a while gained the hegemony in Kinai, which lead to full bloom of Matsunaga clan, but in 1568 when Nobunaga ODA came to Kyoto supporting Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, Yoshiteru&apos;s younger brother, since Hisahide noticed Nobunaga&apos;s excellent caliber and overwhelming military power, Hisahide presented a fine art work, Tsukumonasu (chinese tea caddy), to Nobunaga to yield, and became Nobunaga&apos;s vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While being opposed to Nagayasu MIYOSHI, Tomomichi IWANARI and Masayasu MIYOSHI, Hisahide for a while gained the hegemony in Kinai, which lead to the full blossoming of the Matsunaga clan; however, in 1568, when Nobunaga ODA came to Kyoto in support of Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, Yoshiteru&apos;s younger brother, since Hisahide noticed Nobunaga&apos;s excellent caliber and overwhelming military power, Hisahide presented a fine art work--a tsukumonasu (Chinese tea caddy)--to Nobunaga as a sign that he would yield, and thus he became Nobunaga&apos;s vassal.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While being opposed to Nagayasu MIYOSHI, Tomomichi IWANARI and Masayasu MIYOSHI, Hisahide for a while gained the hegemony in Kinai, which lead to the full blossoming of the Matsunaga clan; however, in 1568, when Nobunaga ODA came to Kyoto in support of Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, Yoshiteru&apos;s younger brother, since Hisahide noticed Nobunaga&apos;s excellent caliber and overwhelming military power, Hisahide presented a fine art work--a tsukumonasu (Chinese tea caddy)--to Nobunaga as a sign that he would yield, and thus he became Nobunaga&apos;s vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし久秀は、信長が義昭と対立して信長包囲網が敷かれて窮地に陥ると、これに背いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Nobunaga became opposed to Yoshiaki and faced a predicament because a military cordon around Nobunaga was organized, Hisahide betrayed Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Nobunaga became opposed to Yoshiaki and faced a predicament because a military cordon around Nobunaga had been organized, Hisahide betrayed Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Nobunaga became opposed to Yoshiaki and faced a predicament because a military cordon around Nobunaga had been organized, Hisahide betrayed Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかしこのときは武田信玄の死や室町幕府の滅亡など悪条件が重なって、1573年末に織田信長に降伏している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But at this time the combined bad conditions such as death of Shingen TAKEDA and downfall of Muromachi Shogunate made Hisahide surrender to Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But at this time the combined bad conditions such as the death of Shingen TAKEDA and the downfall of Muromachi Shogunate made Hisahide surrender to Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at this time various negative factors, such as the death of Shingen TAKEDA and the downfall of Muromachi bakufu, compelled Hisahide surrender to Nobunaga ODA at the end of 1573.</e>
<cmt>「悪条件」の訳として&apos;negative conditions&apos; は不適当。 &apos;negative factors&apos; としました。&quot;Shogunate&quot; -&gt; &quot;bakufu&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>そして1577年、上杉謙信の能登国・加賀国侵攻に呼応して、再び謀反を起こし信貴山城に立て籠もる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in 1577, in response to Kenshin UESUGI&apos;s invasion to Noto-no-kuni and Kaga-no-kuni, Hisahide raise a rebellion again and was shut up in Shigisan Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1577, in response to Kenshin UESUGI&apos;s invasion of Noto-no-kuni and Kaga-no-kuni, Hisahide raised a rebellion again and was shut up within Shigisan Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1577, in response to Kenshin UESUGI&apos;s invasion of Noto-no-kuni and Kaga-no-kuni, Hisahide raised a rebellion again and was shut up within Shigisan Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、織田軍は手取川の戦いで上杉謙信に敗北していたものの十分な余力を残していたため、久秀は各個撃破の戦略を採った織田軍にあえなく追い詰められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Oda army had sufficient power to spare although the army was defeated by Kenshin UESUGI at the Battle at Tetori River, Hisahide was soon driven into a corner by Oda army that took the defeat-on-by-one strategy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the Oda army had power to spare--despite the defeat by Kenshin UESUGI in the Battle of the Tetori River--Hisahide was soon driven into a corner by the Oda army, which used the strategy of defeat one by one.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the Oda army had power to spare--despite the defeat by Kenshin UESUGI in the Battle of the Tetori River--Hisahide was soon driven into a corner by the Oda army, which used the strategy of defeat one by one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>久秀は信長がかねてから所望していた古天明平蜘蛛を抱いて爆死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisahide died in an explosion with embracing Kotenmyo Hiragumo, a teakettle, that Nobunaga had been wishing for.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisahide died in an explosion by embracing Kotenmyo Hiragumo, a tea kettle, in an answer to Nobunaga&apos;s wish.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisahide died in an explosion by embracing Kotenmyo Hiragumo, a tea kettle, that Nobunaga had wanted to possess.</e>
<cmt>「所望していた」の意味が出るように訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このとき、久秀の嫡男・松永久通も自害して、戦国大名としての松永氏は完全に滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Hisahide&apos;s heir, Hisamichi MATSUNAGA also killed himself, which resulted in complete downfall of Matsunaga clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Hisahide&apos;s heir, Hisamichi MATSUNAGA also killed himself, which resulted in the complete downfall of the Matsunaga clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Hisahide&apos;s heir, Hisamichi MATSUNAGA also killed himself, which resulted in the complete downfall of the Matsunaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>だが、出家して放浪中であった久秀の息子松永永種が生き残り、その息子である松永貞徳は俳人として名を残したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that Hisahide&apos;s son, Nagatane MATSUNAGA, who became a priest and led a wandering life, survived and that his son Teitoku MATSUNAGA left his name to posterity as a Haiku poet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that Hisahide&apos;s son, Nagatane MATSUNAGA, who ultimately became a priest and led a wandering life, survived, and that his son Teitoku MATSUNAGA left his name to posterity as a Haiku poet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that Hisahide&apos;s son, Nagatane MATSUNAGA, who ultimately became a priest and led a wandering life, survived, and that his son Teitoku MATSUNAGA left his name to posterity as a Haiku poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、尾張藩に松永国華という儒学者もいたが、この人物も子孫とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was also a confucianist whose name is Kokka MATSUNAGA in domain of Owari, and he was also concidered the descendant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was also a Confucianist whose name was Kokka MATSUNAGA in the domain of Owari, and he too was considered a descendant.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was also a Confucianist whose name was Kokka MATSUNAGA in the domain of Owari, and he too was considered a descendant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 らりた(id:1327), Nnh(id:474), 紗羅 憐霞(id:170382), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 植木園(id:98882), Kusunose(id:5719), NipponDaemon(id:10068), Riekanu(id:65656), せくそろじすと(id:9002), Assann(id:19332), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>