<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中院家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakanoin family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nakanoin family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nakanoin family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中院家（なかのいんけ）は、大臣家の家格を有する公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakanoin family was a kuge (court noble) with kakaku (family status) of daijinke (the third highest status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nakanoin family were kuge (court nobles) with kakaku (family status) of daijinke (the third highest status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nakanoin family were kuge (court nobles) with kakaku (family status) of daijinke (the third highest status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>村上源氏で久我家の分家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was from Seiwa-Genji and a branch of the Kuga family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They came from Seiwa-Genji and a branch of the Kuga family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They came from Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan) and a branch of the Kuga family.</e>
<cmt>「村上源氏」誤訳のため訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は500石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was 500 koku (approx. 90.2 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karoku (hereditary stipend) during the Edo Period was 500 koku (approx. 90.2 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) during the Edo Period was 500 koku (approx. 90.2 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家紋は六つ竜胆車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its kamon (family crest) is Mutsurindoguruma (six gentians in a circle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its kamon (family crest) is Mutsurindoguruma (six gentians in a circle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its kamon (family crest) is Mutsurindoguruma (six gentians in a circle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>伯爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Marquis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marquis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marquis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>村上天皇の皇子具平親王の子孫で内大臣を務めた源通親（土御門通親）の五男、中院通方を祖として創設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was founded by Michikata NAKANOIN, who was the fifth son of MINAMOTO no Michichika (NAKANOIN Michichika) who was a descendant of Imperial Prince Tomohira of the Emperor Murakami and worked as Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>「内大臣」は、その定義自体が不明確であり、定訳も不明であるため、英訳を付けていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was founded by Michikata NAKANOIN, who was the fifth son of MINAMOTO no Michichika (NAKANOIN Michichika) who was a descendant of Imperial Prince Tomohira of the Emperor Murakami and worked as Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was founded by Michikata NAKANOIN, who was the fifth son of MINAMOTO no Michichika (Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO) who was a descendant of Imperial Prince Tomohira of the Emperor Murakami and worked as Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>「土御門通親」誤訳のため訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>大臣家の一つとして鎌倉時代初期にその家格を固めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family made its kakaku (family status) as one of daijinke firmly established at the beginning of the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family made its kakaku (family status) as one of daijinke firmly established at the beginning of the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family made its kakaku as one of daijinke firmly established at the beginning of the Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>中院通勝は江戸時代前期にかけての公家で二条派の歌人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michikatsu NAKANOIN was a kuge around the beginning of the Edo Period and kajin (waka poet) of the Nijo school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michikatsu NAKANOIN was a kuge around the beginning of the Edo Period and a kajin (waka poet) of the Nijo school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michikatsu NAKANOIN was a kuge around the beginning of the Edo Period and a kajin (waka poet) of the Nijo school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>細川幽斎（幽斎）に学んで和歌・和学を極め、歌書等を表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He mastered waka and wagaku (study in Japanese classical literatures) learning from Yusai Hosokawa and wrote waka anthologies and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He mastered waka and wagaku (study in Japanese classical literature) learning from Yusai Hosokawa and wrote waka anthologies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He mastered waka and wagaku (study in Japanese classical literature) learning from Yusai HOSOKAWA and wrote waka anthologies.</e>
<cmt>Hosokawa→HOSOKAWA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1579年（天正7年）中納言正三位に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1579, he was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Grade) Chunagon (middle counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1579, he was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Grade) Chunagon (middle counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1579, he was promoted to Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>Grade→Rank中納言の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸時代中期には霊元天皇歌壇で活躍することとなる中院通躬がでた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle of the Edo Period, Michimi NAKANOIN who played an active role in the poetry circles of the Emperor Reigen, appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the middle of the Edo Period, Michimi NAKANOIN who played an active role in the poetry circles of the Emperor Reigen, appeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the middle of the Edo Period, Michimi NAKANOIN who played an active role in the poetry circles of the Emperor Reigen, appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>中院通富は江戸時代末期、国事に奔走し、明治維新後、参与となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last days of the Edo Period, Michitomi NAKANOIN devoted himself to the interest of state and, after Meiji Restoration, appointed to sanyo (councilor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last days of the Edo Period, Michitomi NAKANOIN devoted himself to the interest of the state and, after the Meiji Restoration, was appointed to sanyo (councilor).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last days of the Edo Period, Michitomi NAKANOIN devoted himself to the interest of the state and, after the Meiji Restoration, was appointed to sanyo (councilor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>明治17年伯爵位を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1884, the peerage of count was conferred on him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1884, the peerage of count was conferred on him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1884, the peerage of count was conferred on him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>現在、中院家の邸宅跡には護王神社が鎮座している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, the Goo-jinja Shrine is located in the site where mansion of the Nakanoin family existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, Goo-jinja Shrine is located on the site where the mansion of the Nakanoin family existed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, Goo-jinja Shrine is located on the site where the mansion of the Nakanoin family existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中院文庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakanoin bunko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakanoin bunko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakanoin bunko (library)</e>
<cmt>(library) 追記</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>中院通規により京都大学に中院家代々の貴重な文書類が寄贈され、中院文庫と名付けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Precious documents handed down by successive generations of the Nakanoin family were donated to Kyoto University by Michinori NAKANOIN and named Nakanoin bunko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Precious documents handed down by successive generations of the Nakanoin family were donated to Kyoto University by Michinori NAKANOIN and named Nakanoin bunko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Precious documents handed down by successive generations of the Nakanoin family were donated to Kyoto University by Michinori NAKANOIN and named Nakanoin bunko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>二条派歌道の宗匠の家柄の一つでもあったので、歌道に関する文書類が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the family one of family lineages of a master of Nijo school waka poetry, a large number of documents related to kado were included..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being a family of one of the family lineages of a master of Nijo school waka poetry, a large number of documents related to kado were included..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being a family of one of the family lineages of a master of Nijo school waka poetry, a large number of documents related to kado (the art of versification) were included..</e>
<cmt>歌道の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), DCyokohama(id:26779), 代言人(id:33675), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 松茸(id:27535), Hosokawajun(id:72875), トホホ川(id:50502), Rimota(id:65657), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>