<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>花山院家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kasannoin family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kazanin family</e>
<cmt>From line 21 onwards 花山院 is translated as Kazanin.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kazanin Family</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>花山院家（かさんのいんけ）は、藤原氏藤原北家師実流の嫡流（花山院流）の家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kasannoin family was a direct descendant of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan-Morozane group (Kasannoin group).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kasannoin family was directly descended from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan-Morozane branch (Kazanin branch).</e>
<cmt>&quot;a direct descendant&quot; suggests a single person rather than a family. Also, I think &quot;branch&quot; is better than group here, and that &quot;Kazanin&quot; should be used instead of &quot;Kassanoin&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kasannoin family was directly descended from the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan-Morozane branch (Kazanin branch).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>家格は清華家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was ranked as &quot;Seiga ke,&quot; one of the family status of the Court Nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was ranked as &quot;Seiga ke,&quot; a type of family status in the court nobility.</e>
<cmt>A neater collective term for &quot;court nobles&quot; is &quot;court nobility&quot;. I don&apos;t think capital letters are required.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was ranked as Seiga family, a type of family status in the court nobility.</e>
<cmt>ke→family 他の記事と合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代後期の藤原師実の次男花山院家忠に始まり、家名は家忠が父師実から譲り受けた邸宅花山院（東一条院）にちなむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family established in the late Heian period by Ietada KAZANIN, the second son of FUJIWARA no Morozane, and was named after the Kazanin palace (Higashi ichijo in) which Ietada inherited from his father, Morozane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established in the late Heian period by Ietada KAZANIN, the second son of FUJIWARA no Morozane, the family was named after the Kazanin palace (Higashi ichijo in) which Ietada inherited from his father, Morozane.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established in the late Heian period by Ietada KAZANIN, the second son of FUJIWARA no Morozane, the family was named after the Kazanin palace (Higashi ichijo in) which Ietada inherited from his father, Morozane.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家忠の孫花山院忠雅が太政大臣、その子で後白河上皇の近臣である花山院兼雅が左大臣に進み、清華家としての家格が確立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family status as &quot;Seiga ke&quot; was secured after Tadamasa KAZANIN, Ietada&apos;s grandson, became the Grand Minister of State, and his son, Kanemasa KAZANIN who was a tursted vassal of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, was promoted to the Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family status of &quot;Seiga ke&quot; was secured after Tadamasa KAZANIN, Ietada&apos;s grandson, became the Grand Minister of State, and his son, Kanemasa KAZANIN who was a tursted vassal of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, was promoted to the Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;as&quot; to &quot;of&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family status of Seiga family was secured after Tadamasa KAZANIN, Ietada&apos;s grandson, became the Grand Minister of State, and his son, Kanemasa KAZANIN who was a trusted vassal of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, was promoted to the Minister of the Left.</e>
<cmt>ke→family他の記事と合わせました。スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)、嫡流は北朝に仕えたが、支流の花山院師信とその子花山院師賢は後醍醐天皇の側近で、その子孫は吉野朝廷に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), the direct descendants of the family served the Northern Dynasty, but other descendants of a branch family such as Moronobu KAZANIN and his son, Morokata KAZANIN, who were close aides of Emperor Godaigo, served the Yoshino Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), the direct descendants of the family served the Northern Dynasty, but Moronobu KAZANIN and his son, Morokata KAZANIN, who belonged to a branch family, were close aides of Emperor Godaigo, and their descendents served the Yoshino Court.</e>
<cmt>Changed to follow source text more closely.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), the direct descendants of the family served the Northern Court, but Moronobu KAZANIN and his son, Morokata KAZANIN, who belonged to a branch family, were close aides of Emperor Godaigo, and their descendents served the Yoshino Court.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この系統の末裔の女性が南北朝統一後に後小松天皇の宮中に入り、天皇の寵愛を受けて誕生したのが一休宗純であると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A female descendant of this lineage, who served at Court, won the Emperor&apos;s favor and gave birth to a child, later known as Sojun IKKYU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One direct female descendant, who served at Court, won the Emperor&apos;s favor and gave birth to a child, later known as Sojun IKKYU.</e>
<cmt>In the initial translation it is not clear which lineage is meant by &quot;this lineage&quot;. I have rewritten the sentence assuming that the lady is a direct descendent.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One direct female descendant, who served at Court of Emperor Gokomatsu, won the Emperor&apos;s favor and gave birth to a child, later known as Sojun IKKYU.</e>
<cmt>of Emperor Gokomatsu を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は、概ね715石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was about 715 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was about 715 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was about 715 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>家道は書道・笙であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Calligraphy and &quot;Sho&quot; (a reed pipe) were the family&apos;s vocations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family vocations were calligraphy and &quot;Sho&quot; (a type of reed pipe).</e>
<cmt>I think it is better to make vocations the subject here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family vocations were calligraphy and Sho (a type of reed pipe).</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>明治維新以後、忠遠のとき侯爵に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the family was ranked as a marquis at the time of Tadato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Meiji Restoration onwards, starting with Tadato, the head of the family held the rank of marquis.</e>
<cmt>A以降 has the sense of &quot;from A onwards&quot; rather than &quot;after A&quot;. Also, I think that the rank of marquis is held by a single person rather than a family. It may therefore be better to say &quot;the head of the family held…&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Meiji Restoration onwards, starting with Tadato, the head of the family held the rank of marquis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kaba(id:17904), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 伏儀(id:142093), 伊(id:146699), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>