<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>新家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinke (the new family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinke (new family)</e>
<cmt>&quot;The&quot; is unnecessary here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinke (new family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>新家（しんけ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinke (the new family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinke (new family)</e>
<cmt>&quot;The&quot; is unnecessary here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinke (new family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>公家の格式の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the statuses of court noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinke is a type of status in the court nobility.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinke is a type of status in the court nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本項にて解説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Described in the main paragraph.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Described in the main section.</e>
<cmt>The main part may be more than one paragraph. Hence, &quot;section&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Described in the main section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>1884年の華族令によって、華族になる資格を得て成立した家の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a family that became eligible to be a nobility by Kazoku Rei (Law of Nobility) in 1884.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This family became eligible to join the nobility by the Kazoku Rei (Law of Nobility) enacted in 1884.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This family became eligible to join the nobility by the Kazoku Rei (Law of Nobility) enacted in 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>旧大名・旧公家を除いた家々の事であり、特に明治維新で活躍した元勲の家とその後の国家への功労によって華族に加えられた家を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The families excluding the former daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) and the former court noble, and especially the families of genkun (the statesmen who contributed in the Meiji Restoration) which played actively for the Meiji Restoration and those which were named as nobility due to their service for the nation afterward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinke refers to families which were not daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) or former court nobles but were allowed to join the nobility as a reward for their contribution at the Meiji restoration (families of the so-called genkun) or for services to the nation thereafter.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinke refers to families which were not daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) or former court nobles but were allowed to join the nobility as a reward for their contribution at the Meiji Restoration (families of the so-called genkun) or for services to the nation thereafter.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>新家（しんけ）とは公家の家格の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinke is one of the family statuses of court noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinke is a type of family status in the court nobility.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinke is a type of family status in the court nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>文禄・慶長年間以後に成立した家々（ほぼ江戸時代のそれと重なる）を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means the families established after the Bunroku and Keicho periods (they are almost the same with those in the Edo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinke refers to families established after the Bunroku and Keicho periods (i.e. a period roughly corresponding to the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>I am not sure about this. Please check. The orignal translation is unclear and needs to be revised. Also, it is not clear what &quot;it&quot; refers to. I have interpreted &quot;it&quot; to mean &quot;Shinke&quot; but this gives 2 different definitions of shinke (that of line 9 and that of line 12).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinke refers to families established after the Bunroku and Keicho periods (i.e. a period roughly corresponding to the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これに対してそれ以前からの家を旧家と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, the families which had existed since the previous period were called kyuka (family of ancient extraction).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The families which existed before this period are called kyuka (families of ancient extraction).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The families which existed before this period are called kyuka (families of ancient extraction).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>137家あるとされる堂上家の中で68家（ただし、後述の広幡家・醍醐家を新家に含めるかどうかについては議論の余地がある）が新家に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among 137 Dojo families, 68 of them (whether the after-mentioned Hirohata family and the Daigo family are included in Shinke or not is still controversial) corresponds to Shinke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among 137 Dojo families, 68 of them are Shinke (though whether Hirohata family and the Daigo family mentioned below are Shinke or not is still controversial).</e>
<cmt>Natural English. Also 「ただし」 is not translated in trans 1.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among 137 Dojo families, 68 of them are Shinke (though whether Hirohata family and the Daigo family mentioned below are Shinke or not is still controversial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>新家のほとんどが豊臣政権末期からの100年間、ほぼ後に17世紀と呼ばれる時期に設立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the Shinke families were established in 100 years from the last days of the Toyotomi government, which is later called the 17th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the Shinke families were established within 100 years of the end of the Toyotomi government, a period roughly corresponding to the 17th century.</e>
<cmt>Natural English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the Shinke families were established within 100 years of the end of the Toyotomi government, a period roughly corresponding to the 17th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸幕府は戦国時代_(日本)の戦乱で衰退した朝廷に対しては、禁中並公家諸法度などで統制する一方、朝廷自体の衰亡は征夷大将軍があくまでも朝廷に任命されている以上、望ましい状況ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) controlled the Imperial Court which weakened in the domestic wars by the Kinchu narabini kuge shohatto, a set of regulations that applied to the emperor and the Kyoto nobles; however, the decline of the Imperial Court itself was not a desirable state as seii taishogun (great general who subdues the barbarians) was appointed by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) controlled the Imperial Court, which had been weakened in the domestic wars, by means of the Kinchu narabini kuge shohatto, a set of regulations that applied to the emperor and the Kyoto nobles, a weak Imperial Court was not in the interests of the bakufu because it was the Imperial court which appointed the seii taishogun (great general who subdues the barbarians).</e>
<cmt>I have made this English more natural, but the link (if any) between the shogun of &quot;headed by a shogun&quot; and the &quot;seii taishogun&quot; is unclear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) controlled the Imperial Court, which had been weakened in the domestic wars, by means of the Kinchu narabini kuge shohatto, a set of regulations that applied to the emperor and the Kyoto nobles, a weak Imperial Court was not in the interests of the bakufu because it was the Imperial court which appointed the seii taishogun (great general who subdues the barbarians).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、朝廷統制の必要上、朝廷権力を摂関家に独占させるような体制作りをしたために、そこから排除された公家達から「反幕府感情」が生み出される危惧もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As required for controlling the Imperial Court, the bakufu created the system which allowed the line of regents and advisers to dominate the power of the Imperial Court, and there were a risk such system could produce &quot;the anti-bakufu sentiment&quot; by the court nobles who were excluded from the system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To control the Imperial Courth, the bakufu created a system which allowed a series of regents and advisers to dominate the Imperial court, but there was a risk that this would produce &quot;anti-bakufu sentiment&quot; among the court nobles who were excluded from the system.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To control the Imperial Court, the bakufu created a system which allowed a series of regents and advisers to dominate the Imperial court, but there was a risk that this would produce &apos;anti-bakufu sentiment&apos; among the court nobles who were excluded from the system.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正原文の｢｣に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そこで本来ならば口減らしのために出家させるのが通例だった公家の嫡男以外の男子に家禄を授けて新しい家を興させ、こうした公家の不満をそらす一方で公家の減少を防いで朝廷運用に必要な最低限の人員を確保しようとする意図があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this context, the bakufu granted the hereditary stipend to males other than the heir of the court nobles who usually became priests for reducing the mouths to feed and permitted them to establish new families to reduce complaints of these court nobles; on the other hand, the bakufu also had the intention to avoid the decline of the number of court nobles and secure the minimum number of people required for the operation of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this context, the bakufu granted hereditary stipends not just to the heirs but to other sons of the nobility (who would otherwise have become priests to reduce the burdent on their families) and permitted these other sons to establish new families, thereby placating the nobility while at the same time avoiding a decline in the number of court nobles and retaining the minimum number of people required for the operation of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this context, the bakufu granted hereditary stipends not just to the heirs but to other sons of the nobility (who would otherwise have become priests to reduce the burden on their families) and permitted these other sons to establish new families, thereby placating the nobility while at the same time avoiding a decline in the number of court nobles and retaining the minimum number of people required for the operation of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>南北朝～室町時代に断絶した家も多く、その家名の復活も図られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of families terminated from the period of the Northern and Southern Courts to the Muromachi period, and the names of these families became the target of restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many families had been discontinued in the period including the Northern and Southern Courts period and the Muromachi period, and the family names of these became targets for restoration.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many families had been discontinued in the period including the Northern and Southern Courts period and the Muromachi period, and the family names of these became targets for restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>新家のほとんどが羽林家・名家 (公家)・半家 (公家)に属しており、公卿に昇進しても非参議に終わるケースが殆どであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the Shinke families belonged to the Urin family, the Mei-ke family (court noble), and the Han-ke family (court noble): in many cases they didn&apos;t become councilors even if they were promoted to the court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the Shinke families had the status of Urin or Meike (type of court nobility) and Han-ke (type of court nobility), but, despite their promotion to the nobility, did not generally become councilors.</e>
<cmt>Natural Enlgish</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the Shinke families had the status of Urin or Meike (type of court nobility) and Han-ke (type of court nobility), but, despite their promotion to the nobility, did not generally become councilors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ただし、八条宮家から臣籍降下した広幡家（正親町源氏）と一条家（摂関家）から分家した醍醐家は、摂関家に次ぐ清華家に加えられて後には左大臣にまで昇進した者もおり、他の新家との待遇の差は歴然としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, among the Hirohata family (Ogimachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)) which became a subject of the state from the Hachijomiya family, a member of the Imperial family, and the Daigo family which became a branch of the Ichijo family (the line of regents and advisers), some were added to the Seiga family which was second to the line of regents and advisers and eventually were promoted to sadaijin (minister of the left): the gap in the status between these two families and other Shinke families were unbridgeable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were two families whose status was manifestly different from the other Shinke families, these being the Hirohata family (Ogamachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)) which was a part of the Hachijomiya family that had lost its membership of the Imperial family and the Daigo family (a branch family of the Ichijo family of regents): these families had the status of seiga just below the rank of regent and included members who advanced as far as sadaijin (minister of hte left).</e>
<cmt>Trans 1 is very difficult to understand. I have attempted a new translation but this needs checking.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were two families whose status was manifestly different from the other Shinke families, these being the Hirohata family (Ogimachi-Genji (Minamoto clan)) which was a part of the Hachijomiya family that had lost its membership of the Imperial family and the Daigo family (a branch family of the Ichijo family of regents): these families had the status of seiga just below the rank of regent and included members who advanced as far as sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このため、この両家を新家として一括りにしてもいいのかについては疑問視する説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this context, some opinions doubt if these two families could be in the same group or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence, it is sometimes questioned whether these two families can be grouped with the other shinke families.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence, it is sometimes questioned whether these two families can be grouped with the other shinke families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>一方、地下人の場合も新たに官位を授けられた者やその家のことを新家と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, jigenin (a lower rank of ancient Japanese nobility) who newly gained the official rank and their family were called Shinke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the other end of the scale, the families of jigenin (a lower rank in the nobility) who newly attained the rank of official were also called Shinke.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think &quot;一方&quot; can really be translated as &quot;On the other hand&quot; here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the other end of the scale, the families of jigenin (a lower rank in the nobility) who newly attained the rank of official were also called Shinke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>一般に実務官僚たる地下は堂上よりも出入りが頻繁で、特に医療に関する専門知識や特殊技能が求められた典薬寮では、在野の医師が新たに官位を与えられて新家として地下家になる例が他の官職より多かったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, the jige which was a practical government official had more frequent comings and goings than the Dojo did; there were more examples especially in Tenyakuryo (the Bureau of Medicine) than the other government posts as doctors of out of power newly obtained the official ranks and became the jige families as Shinke because they were required to have medical expert knowledge and special skills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, with more frequent comings and goings than the Dojo, it seems that it was often ex-doctors from the Tenyakuryo (the Bureau of Medicine where medical expertise and special skills were required) who joined jige families as Shinke.</e>
<cmt>Trans 1 really doesn&apos;t make sense. I am not sure about my (simplified) translation either. It needs checking.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, with more frequent comings and goings than the Dojo, it seems that it was often ex-doctors from the Tenyakuryo (the Bureau of Medicine where medical expertise and special skills were required) who joined jige families as Shinke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 DCyokohama(id:26779), わたあめひみつ(id:81640), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>