<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>清原氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyohara clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyohara clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyohara clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>清原氏（きよはらし）は、平安時代の氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyohara clan is a family, lineage, in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kiyohara clan was a family (lineage) of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kiyohara clan was a family (lineage) of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>舎人親王にはじまる皇別氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families branched out from the Imperial family, starting with Prince Toneri.</e>
<cmt>皇別氏族→family branched out from the Imperial family[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Families branched out from the Imperial Family, starting with Prince Toneri.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Families branched out from the Imperial Family, starting with Imperial Prince Toneri.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Princeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代は中堅貴族であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyohara clan was a middle-ranking nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kiyohara clan was a middle-ranking nobility.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kiyohara clan was a nobility of middle rank during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>平安時代　追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>清原深養父、清少納言などが有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KIYOHARA no Fukayabu and Sei Shonagon are famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KIYOHARA no Fukayabu and Sei Shonagon are famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KIYOHARA no Fukayabu and Sei Shonagon are famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>またこの氏族の末裔との見方もある氏族に、出羽清原氏がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family that is sometimes considered as the descendant of this Kiyohara clan is Dewakiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Dewakiyohara clan is the family that is sometimes considered to be the descendant of this Kiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Dewakiyohara clan is the family that is sometimes considered to be the descendant of this Kiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;Overview&quot; -&gt; &quot;Summary&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天武天皇の皇子舎人親王の血筋を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Claims to be related by blood to Prince Toneri, prince of Emperor Temmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were claims of a blood relationship to Prince Toneri, the prince of Emperor Temmu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were claims of a blood relationship to Imperial Prince Toneri, the prince of the Emperor Temmu.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Princeとしました。&quot;the&quot;を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>四世王であった小倉王の子清原夏野が、小倉王の弟石浦王の子清原長谷ともども臣籍降下して清原真人の姓を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natsuno KIYOHARA, child of Ogura O (King) who was the fourth generation king, together with KIYOHARA no Hase, child of Ishiura O (King) who was a younger brother of Ogura O (King), descended to the status of subject, and was given the surname of KIYOHARA no Mahito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natsuno KIYOHARA, the child of Ogura O (King), who was the fourth-generation king, together with KIYOHARA no Hase, the child of Ishiura O (King), who was a younger brother of Ogura O (King), descended to the status of subject and was given the surname of KIYOHARA no Mahito.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natsuno KIYOHARA, the child of Ogura O (King), who was the fourth-generation king, together with KIYOHARA no Hase, the child of Ishiura O (King), who was a younger brother of Ogura O (King), descended to the status of subject and was given the surname of KIYOHARA no Mahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>以来、中堅貴族として活躍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, infuluential as a middle-ranking nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, it was influential as a middle-ranked nobility.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, it was influential as a middle-ranked nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>清原深養父は歌人としても名を残す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KIYOHARA no Fukayabu left the name also as a poet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KIYOHARA no Fukayabu also left his name as a poet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KIYOHARA no Fukayabu also left his name as a poet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>清原元輔の娘、清少納言は『枕草子』を著したことでも有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sei Shonagon, daughter of KIYOHARA no Motosuke, is also famous as a writer of &quot;Makurano Soshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sei Shonagon, the daughter of KIYOHARA no Motosuke, is also famous as a writer of &quot;Makurano Soshi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sei Shonagon, the daughter of KIYOHARA no Motosuke, is also famous as the author of &quot;Makurano Soshi (the Pillow Book).&quot;</e>
<cmt>(the Pillow Book)追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>後世、清原姓を称する氏族は下野国・紀伊国・豊後国などに分布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In posterity, the families having the surname of Kiyohara are distributed in the Province of Shimotsuke, the Province of Kii, and the Province of Bungo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In posterity, the families having the surname of Kiyohara were distributed over the provinces of Shimotsuke, Kii and Bungo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In posterity, the families having the surname of Kiyohara were distributed over the provinces of Shimotsuke, Kii and Bungo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>この他、神別の海氏の中からも清原姓を賜った者がおり（舎人親王の子孫であるように記す系図が多いが、これは明らかな仮冒である）、その子孫は公家の舟橋家をはじめ、庶家を多数輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than these families, among Umi-uji branched out of a family of god, there were some who were given the surname of Kiyohara (although many genealogies say that they are the descendant of Prince Toneri, these genealogies are clearly distortion), and from the descendants many houses of illegitimated child including the House of Funabashi that is a court noble were produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than these families, among the Umi-uji (branched from a family of gods), there were some who were given the surname of Kiyohara (although many genealogies say they are descended from Prince Toneri, these genealogies are clearly distortions), and from the descendants many houses of illegitimate children, including the House of Funabashi, which is a court noble, were produced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than these families, among the Umi-uji (branched from a family of gods), there were some who were given the surname of Kiyohara (although many genealogies say they are descended from Imperial Prince Toneri, these genealogies are clearly distortions), and from the descendants many houses of illegitimate children, including the Funabashi Family, which is a court nobility, were produced.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Prince Toneri　としました。&quot;House of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～Family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>清原家は漢文の注釈などを家業にする文章の家で、現在京都大学に所蔵されている清家文庫はかつてこの清原家が所持していたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The House of Kiyohara is the family of writing, the business of which is to write notes to Chinese, and the Seike library that is now housed in Kyoto University was once owned by the House of Kiyohara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The House of Kiyohara was a family of scribes, the business of which was to write notes to Chinese, and the Seike Library, which is now housed at Kyoto University, was once owned by the House of Kiyohara.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kiyohara Family was a family of scribes, the business of which was to write notes to Chinese, and the Seike Library, which is now housed at Kyoto University, was once owned by the Kiyohara Family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;House of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～Family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>室町時代の清原宣賢は、吉田神社詞官神道家吉田兼倶の3男だったが、明経博士だった清原家に養子として入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobukata KIYOHARA in the Muromachi period was the third son of Kanetomo YOSHIDA, and was adopted by the House of Kiyohara that was Myogyo-hakase, professor of Confusian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobukata KIYOHARA, of the Muromachi period, was the third son of Kanetomo YOSHIDA and was adopted by the House of Kiyohara, which was Myogyo-hakase, professor of Confucian studies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobukata KIYOHARA, of the Muromachi period, was the third son of Kanetomo YOSHIDA who was a shintoist of Yoshida-jinja Shrine, and was adopted by the House of Kiyohara, which was Myogyo-hakase, professor of Confucian studies.</e>
<cmt>a shintoist of the Yoshida-jinja Shrineとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>宣賢は宮中に仕えて講義を行い、明経道を整理して多くの国学、儒学の論文著作をおこなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobukata served Imperial court and gave lectures, and systematized Myogyo-do, the study of Confusian classics and made many monograph of the study of Japanese classical literature and Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>国学→the study of Japanese classical literature[『新和英中辞典』研究社]、　儒学→Confucianism [『新和英中辞典』研究社]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobukata served the Imperial Court, gave lectures and systematized Myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics) in addition to producing many monographs of the study of Japanese classical literature and Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobukata served the Imperial Court, gave lectures and systematized Myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics) in addition to producing many monographs of the study of Japanese classical literature and Confucianism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>享禄2年（1529年）に宮仕えから身を引き、剃髪して環翠軒宗武と号し、学者としての活動に専念した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1529 he retired from serving Imperial court, took the tonsure, called himself Munetake KANSUIKEN, and concentrated in activities as a scholar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1529 he retired from service to the Imperial Court, took the tonsure, called himself Munetake KANSUIKEN and concentrated on activities as a scholar.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1529 he retired from service to the Imperial Court, took the tonsure, called himself Munetake KANSUIKEN and concentrated on activities as a scholar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>国学者・儒学者で歴史上屈指の碩学とされ、多くの著作がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is a Japanese classical scholar and Confusian scholar, and is considered as one of the historically greatest scholars, and there are many books written by him.</e>
<cmt>国学者→a Japanese classical scholar[『新和英中辞典』研究社]、　儒学者→a Confusian scholar [『新和英中辞典』研究社]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a scholar of Japanese classics and Confucian studies; he is considered as one of history&apos;s greatest scholars, and he wrote many books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a scholar of Japanese classics and Confucian studies; he is considered as one of history&apos;s greatest scholars, and he wrote many books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>彼の著作物は現在も多く残されており、日本国学研究の基礎資料となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of his books are exsisting now, and they serve as a basis for the study of Japanese classics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of his books still exist, and they serve as a basis for the study of Japanese classics.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of his books still exist, and they serve as a basis for the study of Japanese classics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、清原家は4代後の秀賢から舟橋家を称したため、清原宣賢を「船橋大外記宣賢」と記した史料もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some historical data show Nobukata KIYOHARA as &quot;Funabashi Dai-Geki Nobukata,&quot; since the House of Kiyohara started calling themselves the House of Funabashi from Hidekata who is the fourth generation thereafter.</e>
<cmt>「船橋大外記野宣賢」→&quot;Funabashi Dai-Geki Nobukata&quot; [「大外記」とは書官のこと]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the historical data shows Nobukata KIYOHARA as &quot;Funabashi Dai-Geki Nobukata,&quot; since the House of Kiyohara started calling itself the House of Funabashi from Hidekata, who was the fourth generation thereafter.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the historical data calls Nobukata KIYOHARA as &apos;Funabashi Dai-Geki Nobukata,&apos; since the House of Kiyohara started calling itself the House of Funabashi from Hidekata, who was the fourth generation thereafter.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→ &apos; &apos; showsを calls　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Sat666(id:127263), Nnh(id:474), 三郎兵衛(id:14304), Kawai(id:5634), Law soma(id:45202), Tetsu9(id:14553), Iwaro(id:60082), 葉月(id:25674), Peachkiller(id:99202), Greenland4(id:114494), Kamitani(id:30757), Kurz(id:1601), Kinori(id:443), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 寂華(id:83725), NDR(id:5500), Nipisiquit(id:62077), Chac(id:21208), ウラヌス(id:25954), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>