<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山科家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamashina family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamashina family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamashina Family</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山科家（やましなけ）は、羽林家の家格を有する公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamashina family was a court noble with a family status of the Urin family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamashina family was court nobility with a family status of &quot;Urin&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamashina family was court nobility with a family status of Urin.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家四条流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijo-ryu (the Shijo line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shijo-ryu (the Shijo line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shijo-ryu (the Shijo line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家名は家領があった京都山科に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family name came from Yamashina, Kyoto where the territory of the family existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family name came from Yamashina, Kyoto where they held territory.</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family name came from Yamashina, Kyoto where they held territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家業は装束・衣紋で江戸時代には高倉家（藪家）とともに装束色目を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family business was costumes and clothing, and it was in charge of costumes and colors with the Takakura family (the Yabu family) in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family business was costumes and clothing, and, in the Edo period, it was in charge of costumes and colors together with the Takakura family (the Yabu family).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family business was costumes and clothing, and, in the Edo period, it was in charge of costumes and colors together with the Takakura family (the Yabu family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は300石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 300 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 300 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 300 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>四条家成の六男藤原実教の猶子となった中納言藤原教成を祖として平安時代末期に創設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancestor was FUJIWARA no Norinari, the Deputy Chief of the Councilor of State, who became yushi (Japanese old system of adoption) of FUJIWARA no Sanenori, the sixth son of Ienari SHIJO, and the family was created at the end-Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was established at the end of the Heian period by FUJIWARA no Norinari, the Deputy Chief of the Councilor of State, who was adopted (under yushi, an old Japanese system of adoption) byFUJIWARA no Sanenori, the sixth son of Ienari SHIJO</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was established at the end of the Heian period by FUJIWARA no Norinari, the Deputy Chief of the Councilor of State, who was adopted (under yushi, an old Japanese system of adoption) by FUJIWARA no Sanenori, the sixth son of Ienari SHIJO.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>南北朝時代_(日本)の山科教言以後、代々内蔵頭を輩出して朝廷財政を運営した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Noritoki YAMASHINA in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, the family produced kuranokami, the head of kuraryo (a kind of finance ministry in the Ritsuryo system), for generations and managed the finance of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the time of Noritoki YAMASHINA in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, the family produced kuranokami, heads of kuraryo (a kind of finance ministry in the Ritsuryo system), for generations and managed the finances of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the time of Noritoki YAMASHINA in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, the family produced kuranokami, heads of kuraryo (a kind of finance ministry in the Ritsuryo system), for generations and managed the finances of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の山科言継（ときつぐ）は日記『言継卿記』を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokitsugu YAMASHINA in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) wrote &quot;Tokitsugu-kyoki (Tokitsugu journal).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitsugu YAMASHINA wrote &quot;Tokitsugu-kyoki&quot; (Tokitsugu journal) in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitsugu YAMASHINA wrote &quot;Tokitsugu-kyoki&quot; (Tokitsugu journal) in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『言継卿記』は、戦国時代の京都を中心とする畿内の情勢を知る上で必要不可欠な一級史料として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tokitsugu-kyoki (Tokitsugu journal)&quot; is known as the primary historical data essential to understand the state of the territories in the vicinity of the capital and under the direct imperial rule in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tokitsugu-kyoki (Tokitsugu journal)&quot; is well known as a primary source indispensible to understanding the situation of territories in the vicinity of the capital and under direct imperial rule in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tokitsugu-kyoki&quot; (Tokitsugu journal) is well known as a primary source indispensable to understanding the situation of territories in the vicinity of the capital and under direct imperial rule in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>言継の息子言経は、勅勘をこうむり摂津国に下ったため、一族の猪熊教利が一時期、山科を名乗り朝廷に仕える、しかし、徳川家康の意向により、言経が朝廷に複帰したため、教利は、猪熊教利と名を変えざるをえなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Tokitsune, the son of Tokitsugu, went down to the Province of Settsu because of chokkan (charge from an emperor), Noritoshi INOKUMA of the family identified himself as YAMASHINA and served the Imperial Court; however, Noritoshi had to change the name to Noritoshi INOKUMA because Tokitsugu returned to the Imperial Court due to the intention of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokitsune, the son of Tokitsugu, went to Settsu Province under chokkan (direct orders from the emperor), and so Noritoshi INOKUMA who was of of the same family took on the name of YAMASHINA and served the Imperial Court, but when Tokitsugu was brought back to the Imperial Court by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Noritoshi had to change his name back to Noritoshi INOKUMA.</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokitsune, the son of Tokitsugu, went to Settsu Province under chokkan (direct orders from the emperor), and so Noritoshi INOKUMA who was of the same family took on the name of YAMASHINA and served the Imperial Court, but when Tokitsugu was brought back to the Imperial Court by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Noritoshi had to change his name back to Noritoshi INOKUMA.</e>
<cmt>of削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治維新後、山科言縄（ときなお）の時に伯爵位を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earlship was granted to the family in the period of Tokinao YAMASHINA after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An earldom was granted to the family in the time of Tokinao YAMASHINA, after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>I think &quot;earldom&quot; may be the corect term.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An earldom was granted to the family in the time of Tokinao YAMASHINA, after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 玄史生(id:43670), Riekanu(id:65656), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>