<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>細川氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosokawa clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosokawa clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>細川氏（ほそかわし）は、本姓は源氏、鎌倉時代から江戸時代にかけて栄えた武家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa clan was a samurai family that prospered between Kamakura period to Edo period, the real family name was Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosokawa clan was a samurai family that prospered between the Kamakura period to the Edo period, the original family name was Genji.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。real→original と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosokawa clan was a samurai family that prospered between the Kamakura period to the Edo period, the original family name was Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>家系は清和源氏の一流河内源氏の流れを汲む足利氏の支流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family line was a branch family of Ashikaga clan that descended from Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), one of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family line was a branch family of the Ashikaga clan that descended from the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), one of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family line was a branch family of the Ashikaga clan that descended from the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan), one of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>細川という名字は鎌倉時代13世紀に三河国額田郡細川郷（現在の愛知県岡崎市細川町周辺）に土着したことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surname Hosokawa originated from the fact that the family settled in Hosokawa-go, Nukata district, Mikawa-no-kuni (presently around Hosokawa-cho, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) in Kamakura period, in 13th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surname Hosokawa originated from the fact that the family settled in Hosokawa-go, Nukata County, Mikawa Province (presently around Hosokawa-cho, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) in the 13th century of Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>district→County,Mikawa-no-kuni→Mikawa Province,「鎌倉時代13世紀」の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surname Hosokawa originated from the fact that the family settled in Hosokawa-go, Nukata County, Mikawa Province (presently around Hosokawa-cho, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) in the 13th century of Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)の動乱では、足利将軍家の一門として、北朝 (日本)・室町幕府方として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At a disturbance in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Hosokawa clan was actively involved as a family of the Ashikaga Shogunal family and took side of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the disturbance in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), the Hosokawa clan actively involved as a family of the Ashikaga Shogunal family, and took the side of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) of the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>a→the,in→of と修正しました。was を削除し、the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the disturbance in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), the Hosokawa clan actively involved as a family of the Ashikaga Shogunal family, and took the side of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) of the Northern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そして、畿内・四国を中心に一門で八か国の守護を占める有力守護大名となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They became dominant Shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) and the family held Shugo (a provincial military governor) of 8 provinces in Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) and Shikoku region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They became a powerful Shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) and the family held Shugo (a provincial military governor) of eight provinces in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) and the Shikoku region.</e>
<cmt>a, the を補いました。dominant→powerful,8→eight と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They became a powerful Shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) and the family held Shugo (a provincial military governor) of eight provinces in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) and the Shikoku region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>細川頼之は管領として3代征夷大将軍足利義満をよく補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA assisted the 3rd shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA well as a kanrei (Shogunal Deputy).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA assisted the third shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA well as a kanrei (Shogunal Deputy).</e>
<cmt>3rd→third と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA assisted the third shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA well as a kanrei (Shogunal Deputy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>以後嫡流（京兆家）は代々管領に任ぜられ、斯波氏・畠山氏とともに三管領の一つに数えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that his direct descendant (Keicho family) was successively appointed to kanrei and was counted as one of Sankanrei (three families in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy), along with Shiba clan and Hatakeyama clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, his direct descendant (Keicho family) was appointed to kanrei for generations, and was counted as one of Sankanrei (three families in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy), along with the Shiba clan and the Hatakeyama clan.</e>
<cmt>カンマ、the を補いました。successively→for generations と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, his direct descendant (Keicho family) was appointed to kanrei for generations, and was counted as one of Sankanrei (three families in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy), along with the Shiba clan and the Hatakeyama clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>応仁の乱で細川勝元は東軍の総帥となり、その子細川政元は明応の政変で10代将軍足利義稙を退けて幕府の実権を掌握した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumoto HOSOKAWA became a commander-in-chief for the &apos;eastern&apos; army in the Onin War, and his son Masamoto HOSOKAWA took over the real power of bakufu ousting the 10th Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA in Meio Coup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumoto HOSOKAWA became the commander-in-chief for the eastern army in the Onin War, and his son Masamoto HOSOKAWA took over the real power of the bakufu, ousting the 10th Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA in the Meio Coup.</e>
<cmt>a→the と修正しました。the, カンマを補いました。クォーツを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto HOSOKAWA became the commander-in-chief for the eastern army in the Onin War, and his son Masamoto HOSOKAWA took over the real power of the bakufu, ousting the 10th Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA in the Meio Coup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし政元は生涯独身を貫き実子がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Masamoto remained single all his life and did not have single biological child.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Masamoto remained single all his life and did not have a single biological child.</e>
<cmt>a を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Masamoto remained single all his life and did not have a single biological child.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのうえ、養子を3人も迎えており、その後継争いの中で殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, he received 3 children for adoption but later he was killed in a contest for succession.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処原文が分かりにくいのですが、「養子を迎えたことによる家督争いで、自信も家臣にころされた」ようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, he had three adopted children, and later he was killed in a contest of succession.</e>
<cmt>received 3 children for adoption→had three adopted children,but→and,for→of と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he had three adopted children, and later he was killed in a contest of succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>細川氏は2派に分かれそれぞれに被官や畿内近国の諸勢力が結びついて争う（両細川の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa clan was divided to 2 families that both were associated with hikan (low-level bureaucrat) and powers in the Kinai-Kingoku area and fought against each other (Ryohosokawa War).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hosokawa clan was split into two that each of them associated with hikan (low-level bureaucrat) or the powers in the Kinai-Kingoku area, and fought against each other (Ryohosokawa War).</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。divided to 2→split into two,families that both were associated→that each of them associated,and →or,スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hosokawa clan was split into two that each of them associated with hikan (low-level bureaucrat) or the powers in the Kinai-Kingoku area, and fought against each other (Ryohosokawa War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>政元の養子の一人細川澄元の出身の阿波守護家の守護代三好氏が畿内に進出し、その勢力は主家を凌ぐようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyoshi clan, the Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Shugo (military governor) family of Awa and where one of Masamoto&apos;s adopted child Sumimoto HOSOKAWA was from, advanced into Kinai region and their power outdid that of master&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Miyoshi clan, the Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) of Shugo (military governor) family of Awa and which one of Masamoto&apos;s adopted children Sumimoto HOSOKAWA was from, advanced into Kinai region and their power came to overwhelm that of the head family.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。「守護代」を修正しました。where→which,child→children,「主家を凌ぐようになる」の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan, the Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) of Shugo (military governor) family of Awa and which one of Masamoto&apos;s adopted children Sumimoto HOSOKAWA was from, advanced into Kinai region and their power came to overwhelm that of the head family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>織田信長が15代将軍足利義昭を擁立して、畿内から三好氏の勢力を一掃すると、細川昭元は信長に属しその妹婿となったが、昔日の権勢を回復することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nobunaga ODA backed up 15th shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and drove Miyoshi clan out from the Kinai region, Akimoto HOSOKAWA served Nobunaga and became the husband of Nobunaga&apos;s younger sister, but never retrieved reins of power in old days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nobunaga ODA backed up the 15th shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and drove the Miyoshi clan out from the Kinai region, Akimoto HOSOKAWA served Nobunaga and became the husband of Nobunaga&apos;s younger sister, but never retrieved the reins of power in his old days.</e>
<cmt>the, his を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nobunaga ODA backed up the 15th shogun, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and drove the Miyoshi clan out from the Kinai region, Akimoto HOSOKAWA served Nobunaga and became the husband of Nobunaga&apos;s younger sister, but never retrieved the reins of power in his old days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>一方、傍流の和泉上（半国）守護家の細川幽斎（幽斎）は足利義昭の側近としてその将軍職就任に奔走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Yusai HOSOKAWA (Yusai) from Shugo family of upper Izumi (hangoku (half a province)), a branch, served Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA as a close associate for Yoshiaki&apos;s appointment to shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Yusai HOSOKAWA (Yusai) from a branch line of the Shugo family of upper Izumi (hangoku [half a province]), served Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA as a close associate for Yoshiaki&apos;s appointment to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>オーダーを修正しました。カッコ内を修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Yusai HOSOKAWA (Yusai) from a branch line of the Shugo family of upper Izumi (hangoku [half a province]), served Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA as a close associate for Yoshiaki&apos;s appointment to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、後には長男で奥州家に養子に出した細川忠興（三斎）とともに織田信長の配下として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, later he was actively involved as a vassal of Nobunaga ODA with his eldest son Tadaoki HOSOKAWA (Sansai), who was put up for adoption to the Oshu family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, later he was actively involved as a vassal of Nobunaga ODA with his first son Tadaoki HOSOKAWA (Sansai), who was put up for adoption to the Oshu family.</e>
<cmt>eldest→first と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, later he was actively involved as a vassal of Nobunaga ODA with his first son Tadaoki HOSOKAWA (Sansai), who was put up for adoption to the Oshu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>本能寺の変では縁戚の明智光秀に味方せず、後に天下人となる豊臣秀吉に服した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Honnoji Incident, he did not take a side with Mitsuhide AKECHI, his own relative, and served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who later became tenkabito (person becoming the ruler of the country).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Honnoji Incident, he did not support Mitsuhide AKECHI, his own relative, and served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who later became tenkabito (person becoming the ruler of the country).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。take a side with→support と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Honnoji Incident, he did not support Mitsuhide AKECHI, his own relative, and served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who later became tenkabito (person becoming the ruler of the country).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、忠興は関ヶ原の戦いの功により豊前国小倉藩39万9千石を領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Tadaoki possessed 399,000 Koku (approximately 71975.61cubic meters) in the Kokura domain, Buzen Province for his distinguished service in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Tadaoki came to possess 399,000 koku of the Kokura Domain in Buzen Province by his distinguished service in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>possessed→came to possess,Koku→koku,in→of,domain→Domain,for→by と修正しました。カッコ内を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Tadaoki came to possess 399,000 koku of the Kokura Domain in Buzen Province by his distinguished service in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>その子細川忠利の代に肥後国熊本藩54万石の領主となり、明治維新に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa clan became a feudal lord of 540,000 Koku (approximately 97410.60 cubic meters) in Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province at the generation of Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA, son of Tadaoki, and reached to Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>領主になったのは、「その子細川忠利」ですが、そう訳した場合、「その子細川忠利の代」が抜けるので、代わりに、「細川氏は」と主語をつけました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hosokawa clan became a feudal lord of 540,000 Koku of the Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province in the generation of Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA, the son of Tadaoki, then reached the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。in→of,at→in,and→then と修正しました。to, (approximately 97410.60 cubic meters)を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hosokawa clan became a feudal lord of 540,000 Koku of the Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province in the generation of Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA, the son of Tadaoki, then reached the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>明治時代には侯爵となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heads of the family became a marquis in Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>伯爵となった当主は数人いたので、「一族の当主は」と主語をたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The heads of the family became marquis in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。a を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The heads of the family became marquis in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>子孫の細川護煕は熊本県知事・内閣総理大臣を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morihiro HOSOKAWA, a descendant of Hosokawa clan, became a governor of Kumamoto Prefecture and a prime minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morihiro HOSOKAWA, a descendant of the Hosokawa clan, became a governor of Kumamoto Prefecture and a prime minister.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morihiro HOSOKAWA, a descendant of the Hosokawa clan, became a governor of Kumamoto Prefecture and a prime minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>細川氏は、多くの大名の中でも、鎌倉、室町から江戸、現代まで名門として続いた希有の家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among many daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), Hosokawa clan is a rare family of pedigree that continued since Kamakura, Muromachi, and Edo period to present days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among many daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), the Hosokawa clan is a rare family of pedigree that continued since the Kamakura period, the Muromachi period, and Edo period to present days.</e>
<cmt>the, period を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among many daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), the Hosokawa clan is a rare family of pedigree that continued since the Kamakura period, the Muromachi period, and Edo period to present days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>細川氏と中世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa clan and medieval period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosokawa clan and the medieval period</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosokawa clan and the medieval period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>細川氏の開祖は、足利氏の祖・足利義康の庶長子である源義清 (矢田判官代)とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originator of Hosokawa clan is said to be MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo (Yada no Hangandai) who was the eldest illegitimate child (who were born out of wedlock) of Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA, the founder of Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>用語集では庶長子：the eldest child born out of wedlockとありますが、文中に入れる場合に文がだれてしまうので、意味としては、「庶子＝非嫡出子」なのでthe eldest illegitimate child (who were born out of wedlock)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The originator of the Hosokawa clan is said to be MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo (Yada no Hangandai) who was the first illegitimate child (who were born out of wedlock) of Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA, the founder of the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。eldest→first,スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The originator of the Hosokawa clan is said to be MINAMOTO no Yoshikiyo (Yada no Hangandai) who was the first illegitimate child (who were born out of wedlock) of Yoshiyasu ASHIKAGA, the founder of the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>平安時代末期、義清は源義仲に属し、都から追い落とした平家軍との戦である備中国水島の戦いで戦死している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of Heian period, Yoshikiyo was affiliated with MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka and Yoshikiyo died in the Battle of Mizushima, the battle against deposed Taira clan, in Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of Heian period, Yoshikiyo was affiliated with MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and Yoshikiyo died in the Battle of Mizushima, in Bicchu Province, the battle against the Taira clan fled from the capital.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。 文後半部分を文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of Heian period, Yoshikiyo was affiliated with MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and Yoshikiyo died in the Battle of Mizushima, in Bicchu Province, the battle against the Taira clan fled from the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>鎌倉時代に、足利本家の足利義氏 (足利家3代目当主)が三河守護となると、義清の孫細川義季は兄の戸賀崎義宗・仁木実国らとともに三河国へ進出し、細川郷を領して細川二郎と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (the 3rd head of ASHIKAGA family) of Ashikaga head family, became Mikawa Shugo in Kamakura period, Yoshikiyo&apos;s grand son Yoshisue HOSOKAWA advanced into Mikawa Province with his elder brothers Yoshimune TOGASAKI and Sanekuni NIKI, and ruled over Hosokawa-go taking the name of Jiro HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (the third head of the ASHIKAGA family) of the Ashikaga head family became Mikawa Shugo in the Kamakura period, Yoshikiyo&apos;s grandson Yoshisue HOSOKAWA advanced into Mikawa Province with his older brothers Yoshimune TOGASAKI and Sanekuni NIKI, and ruled over Hosokawa-go, and called himself Jiro HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>3rd→third,grand son→grandson,elder→older,taking the name of→and called himself と修正しました。the,　カンマを補いました。カンマを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (the third head of the ASHIKAGA family) of the Ashikaga head family became Mikawa Shugo in the Kamakura period, Yoshikiyo&apos;s grandson Yoshisue HOSOKAWA advanced into Mikawa Province with his older brothers Yoshimune TOGASAKI and Sanekuni NIKI, and ruled over Hosokawa-go, and called himself Jiro HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし同じ足利一門でも、斯波氏や畠山氏の家格が高く本家からの独立性が強かったのとは異なり、この時代の細川氏はさほど有力な御家人ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though the clan was of Ashikaga clan, Hosokawa clan in this period was not a powerful gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods), unlike Shiba clan and Hatakeyama clan whose kakaku (family status) were high and were highly independent from the head family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the clan was of the Ashikaga clan, the Hosokawa clan in this period was not a powerful gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and the Muromachi through the Edo periods), unlike the Shiba clan and the Hatakeyama clan whose kakaku (family status) were high and were highly independent from the head family.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。Even though→Although と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the clan was of the Ashikaga clan, the Hosokawa clan in this period was not a powerful gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and the Muromachi through the Edo periods), unlike the Shiba clan and the Hatakeyama clan whose kakaku (family status) were high and were highly independent from the head family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その活動の記録はほとんど残されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Records of the activities in that period are hardly remained.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「その」前文の（スプリットしたため）「この時代の」にかかっているため、念のためin the period と補足しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The records of the activities in that period are hardly remained.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The records of the activities in that period are hardly remained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>鎌倉時代末期から南北朝時代にかけて、細川和氏・細川頼春兄弟やその従兄弟の細川顕氏・細川定禅らが足利尊氏に従う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brothers of Kazuuji HOSOKAWA and Yoriharu HOSOKAWA and their male cousin, Akiuji HOSOKAWA and Jozen HOSOKAWA served Takauji ASHIKAGA through the end Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brothers of Kazuuji HOSOKAWA and Yoriharu HOSOKAWA and their male cousins, Akiuji HOSOKAWA and Jozen HOSOKAWA served Takauji ASHIKAGA through the end of Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>cousin→cousins と修正しました。of を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brothers of Kazuuji HOSOKAWA and Yoriharu HOSOKAWA and their male cousins, Akiuji HOSOKAWA and Jozen HOSOKAWA served Takauji ASHIKAGA through the end of Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>元弘3年/正慶2年（1333年）に、尊氏が倒幕の兵を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1333, Takauji took up arms to overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1333, Takauji raised the army to overthrow the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>took up arms→raised the army,Shogunate→shogunate と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1333, Takauji raised the army to overthrow the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そこで和氏は上杉重能とともに後醍醐天皇に帰順を願う使者の役割を果たし、京都の六波羅探題攻撃にも加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazuuji, with Shigeyoshi UESUGI, filled a role of an envoy requesting for Emperor Godaigo to return to allegiance and also he joined to attack on Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazuuji, with Shigeyoshi UESUGI, played the role of envoys requesting for the Emperor Godaigo to return to the allegiance, and also he joined to attack on Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>filled→played,an envoy→envoys と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazuuji, with Shigeyoshi UESUGI, played the role of envoys requesting for the Emperor Godaigo to return to the allegiance, and also he joined to attack on Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>さらに新田義貞に奉じられて鎌倉を陥落させた尊氏の嫡子・千寿王（後の2代将軍足利義詮）を補佐するために下向し、義貞に対抗して鎌倉を足利氏に掌握させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover Kazuuji left the capital to assist legitimate child of Takauji, Senjuo (later Second Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), who had taken Kamakura with the order of Yoshisada NITTA, and he made Ashikaga clan to take control of Kamakura, opposing Yoshisada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover Kazuuji left the capital to assist the legitimate child of Takauji, Senjuo (later the second Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), who had taken Kamakura with the order of Yoshisada NITTA, and he assisted the Ashikaga clan to take control of Kamakura, opposing Yoshisada.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。made→assisted,カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover Kazuuji left the capital to assist the legitimate child of Takauji, Senjuo (later the second Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), who had taken Kamakura with the order of Yoshisada NITTA, and he assisted the Ashikaga clan to take control of Kamakura, opposing Yoshisada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>和氏と顕氏は、尊氏の命により四国に渡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazuuji and Akiuji traveled to Shikoku with an order of Takauji.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazuuji and Akiuji traveled to Shikoku with an order of Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazuuji and Akiuji traveled to Shikoku with an order of Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>阿波国、讃岐国を中心に南朝 (日本)方との争いを勝ち抜き、在地豪族の被官化を押し進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There they achieved a final victory in battle against the Southern Court (Japan) around Awa Province and Sanuki Province and moved ahead with hikanka (to become a vassal of a Samurai family) of local powerful clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They won through the battles against the Southern Court (Japan) around Awa Province and Sanuki Province, and promoted hikanka (to become a vassal of a Samurai family) of local powerful clans.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They won through the battles against the Southern Court (Japan) around Awa Province and Sanuki Province, and promoted hikanka (to become a vassal of a Samurai family) of local powerful clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>この時代に、細川氏は有力な守護大名へと成長する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa clan became a powerful Shugo daimyo in this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hosokawa clan became a powerful Shugo daimyo in this period.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hosokawa clan became a powerful Shugo daimyo in this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="35">
<j>和氏の嫡子である細川清氏は、当初将軍義詮の執事職（後の管領）として幕政の実権を握った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, Kiyouji HOSOKAWA, a legitimate child of Kazuuji, held real power of shogunate government as a steward (later kanrei (shogunal deputy)) of Shogun, Yoshiakira.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, Kiyouji HOSOKAWA, a legitimate child of Kazuuji, held the real power of the shogunate government as a steward (later kanrei [shogunal deputy]) of the Shogun, Yoshiakira.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, Kiyouji HOSOKAWA, a legitimate child of Kazuuji, held the real power of the shogunate government as a steward (later kanrei [shogunal deputy]) of the Shogun, Yoshiakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>しかし、佐々木道誉の讒言により失脚し（康安の政変）、南朝方に属して滅んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he was overthrown by a slander of Doyo SASAKI (the Koan Coup), and was eliminated after sided with the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he was overthrown by a slander of Doyo SASAKI (the Koan Coup), and was eliminated after sided with the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he was overthrown by a slander of Doyo SASAKI (the Koan Coup), and was eliminated after sided with the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また顕氏の子・細川繁氏も急死し、頼春の嫡子である細川頼之が細川氏で随一の実力者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeuji HOSOKAWA, son of Akiuji, also died suddenly, therefore Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, a legitimate child of Yoriharu, became the most influential person in Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeuji HOSOKAWA, the son of Akiuji, also died suddenly, therefore Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, a legitimate child of Yoriharu, became the most influential person in the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeuji HOSOKAWA, the son of Akiuji, also died suddenly, therefore Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, a legitimate child of Yoriharu, became the most influential person in the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>代々幕府の管領に任ぜられることになる京兆家は、頼之の弟でその養子となった細川頼元の後裔を指し、その他の有力な庶家も、多くは頼之の時代に派生している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho family that was successively appointed to bakufu kanrei refers to descendant of Yorimoto HOSOKAWA, Yoriharu&apos;s younger brother who later became Yoriharu&apos;s adopted child, and many of other powerful branch families were also derived in the period of Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keicho family that was successively appointed to bakufu kanrei refers to the descendant of Yorimoto HOSOKAWA, Yoriharu&apos;s younger brother who later became Yoriharu&apos;s adopted child, and the many of other powerful branch families were also derived in the period of Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keicho family that was successively appointed to bakufu kanrei refers to the descendant of Yorimoto HOSOKAWA, Yoriharu&apos;s younger brother who later became Yoriharu&apos;s adopted child, and the many of other powerful branch families were also derived in the period of Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="39">
<j>室町時代の細川氏は、京兆家を中心とした同族連合体とも言うべき集団を形成することで、一族間の内訌の危険を減らした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Muromachi period, Hosokawa clan reduced risk of internal discord between families by forming a group so-called clan alliance, centering on Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Muromachi period, the Hosokawa clan reduced the risk of the internal discord within the family by forming a group so-called a clan alliance, centering on the Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>the, a を補いました。between families→within the family と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, the Hosokawa clan reduced the risk of the internal discord within the family by forming a group so-called a clan alliance, centering on the Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>これにより有力守護の勢力を削ごうとする将軍の干渉を排し、管領・有力守護の地位を保ち続けたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this they rejected influence of Shogun trying to reduce power of dominant Shugo, and kept status of kanrei and dominant Shugo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this way they rejected the influence of the shogun trying to reduce the power of the dominant Shugo, and kept the status of kanrei and a dominant Shugo.</e>
<cmt>way, the, a を補いました。Shogun→shogun と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this way they rejected the influence of the shogun trying to reduce the power of the dominant Shugo, and kept the status of kanrei and a dominant Shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>京兆家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keicho family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keicho family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>細川氏の嫡流で、摂津国・丹波国などの守護大名を世襲したと同時に、代々「室町幕府」の管領職に任命を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was the legitimate line of HOSOKAWA clan and the family was successively appointed to post of kanrei in &apos;Muromachi Bakufu&apos;, as well as taking over as Shugo daimyo in Settsu and Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was the legitimate line of the Hosokawa clan, and the family was successively appointed to the post of kanrei in &apos;Muromachi bakufu,&apos; as well as being hereditary Shugo daimyo in Settsu Province, Tanba Province and so on.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。HOSOKAWA→Hosokawa,Bakufu→bakufu,taking over as→being hereditary,カンマの位置を修正しました。Province, and so on を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was the legitimate line of the Hosokawa clan, and the family was successively appointed to the post of kanrei in &apos;Muromachi bakufu,&apos; as well as being hereditary Shugo daimyo in Settsu Province, Tanba Province and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>京兆（けいちょう）とは右京大夫の唐名で、当主が代々任ぜられたことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho was a Tang name of Ukyo no daibu and originated from the fact that family head filled the post for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keicho was a Tang name for Ukyo no daibu, and originated from that the family head was appointed to the post for generations.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。the fact を削除しました。of→for,filled→was appointed to と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keicho was a Tang name for Ukyo no daibu, and originated from that the family head was appointed to the post for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>細川頼之は中国管領、四国管領を歴任し、讃岐国・阿波国・土佐国など四国の分国化を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA successively filled the post of &quot;Chugoku Kanrei&quot; (shogunal deputy for the Chugoku region) and Shikoku Kanrei (shogunal deputy for the Shikoku region), and advanced provincial allotment of Shikoku, including Sanuki, Awa and Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA successively took the post of Chugoku Kanrei (shogunal deputy for the Chugoku region) and Shikoku Kanrei (shogunal deputy for the Shikoku region), and promoted the provincial allotment of Shikoku, including these provinces of Sanuki, Awa and Tosa.</e>
<cmt>filled→took, the を補いました。advanced→promoted,Sanuki, Awa and Tosa Province→these provinces of Sanuki, Awa and Tosa と修正しました。クォーツを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA successively took the post of Chugoku Kanrei (shogunal deputy for the Chugoku region) and Shikoku Kanrei (shogunal deputy for the Shikoku region), and promoted the provincial allotment of Shikoku, including these provinces of Sanuki, Awa and Tosa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>中央では管領となり、幼少の将軍足利義満を補佐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At central government, he assisted young Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>「中央」＝「中央政治」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the central government, he assisted young Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the central government, he assisted young Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>頼之は義満の信任は厚かったものの、天授 (日本)5年/康暦元年（1379年）の康暦の政変で一旦没落する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoriyuki gained the confidence of Yoshimitsu, he was temporarily demoted in Koryaku Coup happened in 1379.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoriyuki gained the confidence of Yoshimitsu, he was temporarily fallen in Koryaku Coup happened in 1379.</e>
<cmt>demoted→fallen と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yoriyuki gained the confidence of Yoshimitsu, he was temporarily fallen in Koryaku Coup happened in 1379.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>しかし、四国に渡り阿波を中心とする分国支配を堅持することにより敵対勢力を退け、やがて中央政界に復帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he repulsed enemy forces by traveling to Shikoku and steadfastly maintaining provincial control centering on Awa, and in time returned to national political arena.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he repulsed the enemy forces by traveling to Shikoku and steadfastly maintaining the provincial control centering on Awa, and soon returned to the national political arena.</e>
<cmt>カンマ、the を補いました。 in time→soon と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he repulsed the enemy forces by traveling to Shikoku and steadfastly maintaining the provincial control centering on Awa, and soon returned to the national political arena.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>自身は僧籍を理由に、弟の細川頼元を管領に推した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He recommended his younger brother Yorimoto HOSOKAWA for kanrei post as he reasoned that he was in priesthood.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He recommended his younger brother Yorimoto HOSOKAWA for the kanrei post as he reasoned that he was in priesthood.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He recommended his younger brother Yorimoto HOSOKAWA for the kanrei post as he reasoned that he was in priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>細川氏は畠山氏・斯波氏両氏とともに三管領、また幕府宿老として重きをなした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa clan was influential as chief vassal of bakufu and Sankanrei along with both Hatakeyama and Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hosokawa clan was influential as a chief vassal of bakufu and Sankanrei along with the Hatakeyama and the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>the,a を補いました。both を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hosokawa clan was influential as a chief vassal of bakufu and Sankanrei along with the Hatakeyama and the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>細川勝元は3度にわたり計23年間も管領職を歴任し、山名宗全（持豊）と手を結び畠山氏を弱体化させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsumoto HOSOKAWA successively filled the post of kanrei for 3 times, total of 23 years, and weakened Hatakeyama clan linking up with Sozen (Mochitoyo) YAMANA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsumoto HOSOKAWA successively took the post of kanrei for 3 times, total of 23 years, and weakened the Hatakeyama clan linking up with Sozen (Mochitoyo) YAMANA.</e>
<cmt>filled→took と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsumoto HOSOKAWA successively took the post of kanrei for 3 times, total of 23 years, and weakened the Hatakeyama clan linking up with Sozen (Mochitoyo) YAMANA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし将軍家や守護家の家督相続問題などで宗全と対立し、東軍の総帥として足利義視を推戴した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he was opposed to Sozen on issues in succession to Shogun and Shugo family headship and he had put forward Yoshimi ASHIKAGA as a commander of the &apos;eastern&apos; army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he opposed Sozen on the issues in succession of the Shogun and Shugo family headship and he sipported Yoshimi ASHIKAGA as a commander of the eastern army.</e>
<cmt>thewas opposed→opposed,to→of,had put forward→supported と修正しました。クォーツを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he opposed Sozen on the issues in succession of the Shogun and Shugo family headship and he sipported Yoshimi ASHIKAGA as a commander of the eastern army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>宗全率いる西軍との間で11年に及ぶ応仁の乱を引き起こし、その途中に病没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He brought about Onin war, which lasted for 11years, against the &apos;western&apos; army led by Sozen, in the course he died from illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He caused the Onin war, which lasted for 11years, against the western army led by Sozen, then in the course, he died from illness.</e>
<cmt>brought about→caused the,then, カンマを補いました。クォーツを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He caused the Onin war, which lasted for 11years, against the western army led by Sozen, then in the course, he died from illness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の畿内は、将軍と京兆家を中心とした争乱が続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kinai region, conflicts between Shogun and Keicho family continued in the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kinai region, the conflicts between Shogun and the Keicho family continued in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。「戦国時代」の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kinai region, the conflicts between Shogun and the Keicho family continued in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>勝元の子・細川政元は明応の政変で将軍足利義稙（義稙）を廃立、政敵の畠山政長を抹殺し幕政の実権を掌握した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Son of Katsumoto, Masamoto HOSOKAWA achieved enthronement and dethronement of Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA (Yoshitane) in Meio Coup, and murdered political enemy Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, gaining real power of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The son of Katsumoto, Masamoto HOSOKAWA achieved the enthronement and dethronement of the Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA (Yoshitane) in Meio Coup, and killed the political enemy Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, and gaining the real power of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>the, and を補いました。murdered→killed と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The son of Katsumoto, Masamoto HOSOKAWA achieved the enthronement and dethronement of the Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA (Yoshitane) in Meio Coup, and killed the political enemy Masanaga HATAKEYAMA, and gaining the real power of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>畠山・斯波両氏は没落し、京兆家は管領職を独占するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Hatakeyama clan and Shiba clan was ruined and Keicho family gained exclusive possession of kanrei post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both the Hatakeyama clan and the Shiba clan were ruined and the Keicho family gained exclusive possession of kanrei post.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。was→were と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the Hatakeyama clan and the Shiba clan were ruined and the Keicho family gained exclusive possession of kanrei post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>しかし政元は妻帯せず、細川澄之・細川澄元・細川高国の3人を養子に迎えたため、家督争いが生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However Masamoto did not get married and adopted 3 sons, Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA and Takakuni HOSOKAWA, which caused a succession dispute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Masamoto did not marry anyone and adopted three sons, Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA and Takakuni HOSOKAWA, which caused a succession dispute.</e>
<cmt>get married→marry anyone,3→three と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Masamoto did not marry anyone and adopted three sons, Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, Sumimoto HOSOKAWA and Takakuni HOSOKAWA, which caused a succession dispute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>永正4年（1507年）、政元は澄之を推す配下に暗殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1507, Masamoto was murdered by a vassal supporting Sumiyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1507, Masamoto was assassinated by a vassal supporting Sumiyuki.</e>
<cmt>murdered→assassinated と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1507, Masamoto was assassinated by a vassal supporting Sumiyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="57">
<j>その後、澄元が澄之を討った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Sumimoto killed Sumiyuki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Sumimoto killed Sumiyuki.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Sumimoto killed Sumiyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>さらに翌年、前将軍足利義尹（義稙）を擁する周防国守護大内義興と結んだ高国が、将軍足利義澄と澄元を京都から追い落として管領となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet in the next year, Takakuni linked up with Yoshioki OUCHI, the Shugo of Suo Province that support former Shogun Yoshitada ASHIKAGA (Yoshitane), and became kanrei after deposing Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA and Sumimoto from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet in the next year, Takakuni linked up with Yoshioki OUCHI, the Shugo of Suo Province that supported the former Shogun Yoshitada ASHIKAGA (Yoshitane), and became kanrei after expelling the Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA and Sumimoto from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>support→supported,deposing→expelling と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet in the next year, Takakuni linked up with Yoshioki OUCHI, the Shugo of Suo Province that supported the former Shogun Yoshitada ASHIKAGA (Yoshitane), and became kanrei after expelling the Shogun Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA and Sumimoto from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>大永7年（1527年）に、今度は澄元の子細川晴元が高国を追い落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1527, this time son of Sumimoto, Harumoto HOSOKAWA deposed Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1527, this time the son of Sumimoto, Harumoto HOSOKAWA defeated Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。deposed→defeated と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1527, this time the son of Sumimoto, Harumoto HOSOKAWA defeated Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>さらに享禄4年（1531年）に高国を滅ぼし（大物崩れ）、台頭する家宰の三好元長も討ち、将軍足利義晴を擁立して幕政を握る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover Sumimoto exterminated Takakuni in 1527 (Daimotsu kuzure (the Battle of Daimotsu)), also killed Kasai (main retainer), Motonaga MIYOSHI who gained power and he seized shogunate government by supporting Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover Sumimoto exterminated Takakuni in 1527 (Daimotsu kuzure [the Battle of Daimotsu]), also killed Motonaga MIYOSHI of Kasai (main retainer), who was gaining power, and he seized the shogunate government by supporting Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正、オーダーを修正、gainedr→was gaining と修正しました。the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover Sumimoto exterminated Takakuni in 1527 (Daimotsu kuzure [the Battle of Daimotsu]), also killed Motonaga MIYOSHI of Kasai (main retainer), who was gaining power, and he seized the shogunate government by supporting Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>しかし天文 (元号)18年（1549年）、晴元は三好元長の嫡男三好長慶に近江国へと追われ、その政権は崩壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in 1549, the legitimate child of Motonaga MIYOSHI, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, expelled Harumoto to Omi Province and the government was collapsed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in 1549, the legitimate child of Motonaga MIYOSHI, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI expelled Harumoto to Omi Province, and the government was collapsed.</e>
<cmt>カンマを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in 1549, the legitimate child of Motonaga MIYOSHI, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI expelled Harumoto to Omi Province, and the government was collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>晴元はその後も将軍足利義輝を擁して長慶との争いを続けるが、永禄4年（1561年）に和睦し、その2年後に没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that Harumoto continued battle against Nagayoshi supporting Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA but he made peace in 1561 and he died 2 years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that Harumoto continued to battle against Nagayoshi by supporting Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, but he made peace in 1561 and died two years later.</e>
<cmt>to, by, カンマを補いました。 2→two と修正しました。he を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that Harumoto continued to battle against Nagayoshi by supporting Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, but he made peace in 1561 and died two years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="63">
<j>晴元の嫡子細川信良は、足利義昭に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legitimate child of Harumoto, Nobuyoshi HOSOKAWA served Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legitimate child of Harumoto, Nobuyoshi HOSOKAWA served Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legitimate child of Harumoto, Nobuyoshi HOSOKAWA served Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>後に織田信長に近臣として仕え、昭元から信良と名を改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he served Nobunaga ODA as a trusted vassal and changed his name from Akimoto to Nobuyoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he served Nobunaga ODA as a trusted vassal and changed his name from Akimoto to Nobuyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he served Nobunaga ODA as a trusted vassal and changed his name from Akimoto to Nobuyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>しかし、最早政治的に何ら影響を及ぼす存在ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he was no longer a politically influential person in anyway.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he was no longer a politically influential person in anyway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he was no longer a politically influential person in anyway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>昭元の嫡子細川元勝（頼範）は、豊臣秀頼の近臣として大坂城に在り、大坂の役では豊臣方となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legitimate child of Akimoto, Motokatsu HOSOKAWA (Yorinori) stayed at Osaka-jo Castle as a trusted vassal of Hideyori TOYOTOMI, and he sided with Toyotomi in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legitimate child of Akimoto, Motokatsu HOSOKAWA (Yorinori) stayed at Osaka-jo Castle as a trusted vassal of Hideyori TOYOTOMI, and he sided with Toyotomi in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legitimate child of Akimoto, Motokatsu HOSOKAWA (Yorinori) stayed at Osaka-jo Castle as a trusted vassal of Hideyori TOYOTOMI, and he sided with Toyotomi in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>敗戦後は讃岐国に隠棲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a defeat, he lived in seclusion in Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the defeat, he lived in seclusion in Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt>a→the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the defeat, he lived in seclusion in Sanuki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>のちに妹の嫁ぎ先秋田実季を頼り常陸国宍戸藩に赴き、そこで客分として迎え入れられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later he went to Shishido Domain of Hitachi Province relying on Sanesue AKITA, his younger sister&apos;s husband, and was received as a guest.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later he went to Shishido Domain of Hitachi Province relying on Sanesue AKITA, his younger sister&apos;s husband, and was welcomed as a guest.</e>
<cmt>received→welcomed と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later he went to Shishido Domain of Hitachi Province relying on Sanesue AKITA, his younger sister&apos;s husband, and was welcomed as a guest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>元勝の嫡子 細川義元の時に秋田氏の家臣に列し、子孫は家老として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the time of Yoshimoto HOSOKAWA, the legitimate child of Motokatsu, he was ranked in vassal of the Akita clan, and the descendant served as Karo (chief retainer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the time of Yoshimoto HOSOKAWA, the legitimate child of Motokatsu, he became a vassal of the Akita clan, and the descendants served as Karo (chief retainer).</e>
<cmt>was ranked in vassal→became a vassal,descendants→descendants と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the time of Yoshimoto HOSOKAWA, the legitimate child of Motokatsu, he became a vassal of the Akita clan, and the descendants served as Karo (chief retainer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>義元以降は、細川宣元（義元の子）、細川忠元（宣元の子）、細川孚元（忠元の養子、三春藩家老・小野寺泰忠の子）、細川昌元（孚元の養子、藩主秋田延季の七男）と家督が継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshimoto, reigns of the family were succeeded as follows, Nobumoto HOSOKAWA (son of Yoshimoto), Tadamoto HOSOKAWA (son of Nobumoto), Fumoto HOSOKAWA (adopted son of Tadamoto, son of Yasutada ONODERA who was a Karo of Miharu clan) and Masamoto HOSOKAWA (adopted son of Fumoto, seventh son of Nobusue AKITA who was the lord of domain).</e>
<cmt>「忠元の養子」と「孚元の養子」の後に「。」があり分割されていましたが、文の内容としてはここで分割する必要がありませんでしたので、「。」を「、」に変え、3文扱いだったものを1文につなげました。「細川孚元」の読みは推察です。（「孚」はフまたはマコトと読み、父親からの名前を取っているので「～モト」となるのではないかと考えます。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshimoto, the reigns of the family were succeeded as follows, Nobumoto HOSOKAWA (the son of Yoshimoto), Tadamoto HOSOKAWA (the son of Nobumoto), Fumoto HOSOKAWA (the adopted son of Tadamoto, the son of Yasutada ONODERA who was a Karo of the Miharu clan) and Masamoto HOSOKAWA (the adopted son of Fumoto, the seventh son of Nobusue AKITA who was the lord of the domain).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshimoto, the reigns of the family were succeeded as follows, Nobumoto HOSOKAWA (the son of Yoshimoto), Tadamoto HOSOKAWA (the son of Nobumoto), Fumoto HOSOKAWA (the adopted son of Tadamoto, the son of Yasutada ONODERA who was a Karo of the Miharu clan) and Masamoto HOSOKAWA (the adopted son of Fumoto, the seventh son of Nobusue AKITA who was the lord of the domain).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>典厩家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenkyu family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenkyu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenkyu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>細川氏（京兆家）の分家の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a branch family of Hosokawa clan (Keicho family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a branch family of the Hosokawa clan (Keicho family).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a branch family of the Hosokawa clan (Keicho family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>細川持賢を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founder of the family was Mochitaka HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the family was Mochitaka HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the family was Mochitaka HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>基本的には分国を所領としておらず、初期には京兆家の内衆（重臣衆）を束ねる役割を果たしていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the family did not hold provinces under control as a shoryo (territory) and initially they were taking a role of managing Keicho family&apos;s Uchishu (chief vassals).</e>
<cmt>ここでの「基本的には」をそのまま訳すと意味が分かりにくくなるので、次文から、「当初は」といったようなニュアンスで訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the family did not hold provinces under control as a shoryo (territory) and initially they were taking a role of managing the Keicho family&apos;s Uchishu (chief vassals).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the family did not hold provinces under control as a shoryo (territory) and initially they were taking a role of managing the Keicho family&apos;s Uchishu (chief vassals).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>後に摂津国西成郡（中嶋郡）の分郡守護を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later they filled post of Bungunshugo (a provincial constable of a specially given province in gun unit) of Nishinari-gun (Nakajima county), Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later they took the post of Bungunshugo (a provincial constable of a specially given gun [county] unit of a province) of Nishinari County (Nakajima County), Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>filled→took,-gun→County,county→County,カッコ内を修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later they took the post of Bungunshugo (a provincial constable of a specially given gun [county] unit of a province) of Nishinari County (Nakajima County), Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>細川政国、細川政賢と続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Headship of the family was succeeded to Masakuni HOSOKAWA and to Masataka HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>「家督は」と解釈します。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The headship of the family was succeeded to Masakuni HOSOKAWA and to Masataka HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The headship of the family was succeeded to Masakuni HOSOKAWA and to Masataka HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>当主が右馬頭もしくは右馬助を官途としたことから、その唐名にちなんで典厩家と呼ばれるようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto (government service) of family head was Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses) or Umanosuke (deputy minister of the institution for the horse care) therefore the family started to be called Tenkyu family from a Tang name of the Kanto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto (government service) of the family head was Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses) or Umanosuke (deputy minister of the institution for the horse care), therefore, the family started to be called Tenkyu family from a Tang name of the Kanto.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto (government service) of the family head was Uma no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses) or Umanosuke (deputy minister of the institution for the horse care), therefore, the family started to be called Tenkyu family from a Tang name of the Kanto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>持賢は、京兆家当主の座を13歳で継いだ勝元を補佐する立場にあり、持賢の猶子で2代当主となった政国も、9歳で京兆家を継いだ政元の幼少時の後見役であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochitaka was at the role of supporting Katsumoto, who succeeded the headship of Keicho family at age of 13, and Masakuni, an adopted child of Mochitaka and the second family head of Tenkyu family, was also a conservator of Masamoto, who succeeded Keicho family at 9 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochitaka was at the role of supporting Katsumoto, who succeeded the headship of the Keicho family at the age of 13, and Masakuni, an adopted child of Mochitaka and the second family head of the Tenkyu family, was also a conservator of Masamoto, who succeeded the Keicho family at 9 years old.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochitaka was at the role of supporting Katsumoto, who succeeded the headship of the Keicho family at the age of 13, and Masakuni, an adopted child of Mochitaka and the second family head of the Tenkyu family, was also a conservator of Masamoto, who succeeded the Keicho family at 9 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>政賢は永正の錯乱に際しては、細川澄元に与して細川高国と対立したが、船岡山の戦いで戦死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masataka opposed Takakuni HOSOKAWA by following Sumimoto HOSOKAWA in Eisho Disturbance but he died in the Battle of Funaokayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masataka opposed Takakuni HOSOKAWA by following Sumimoto HOSOKAWA in the Eisho Disturbance, but he died in the Battle of Funaokayama.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masataka opposed Takakuni HOSOKAWA by following Sumimoto HOSOKAWA in the Eisho Disturbance, but he died in the Battle of Funaokayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>その後は高国の与党で政賢の縁戚であった細川尹賢が継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that the headship was succeeded to Tadakata HOSOKAWA who was a relative of Masataka and the ruling party of Takakuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the headship was succeeded by Tadakata HOSOKAWA, who was a relative of Masataka and an ally of Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。to→by,the ruling party→an ally と修正しました。（ここでの”与党”とは”同調する仲間”と理解しました）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the headship was succeeded by Tadakata HOSOKAWA, who was a relative of Masataka and an ally of Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>尹賢は高国の大物崩れの戦いでの顛末を知り、細川晴元側に寝返ろうとしたものの許されず殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakata found out the course of battle at Takakuni&apos;s Daimotsu kuzure (the Battle of Daimotsu) and tried to switch sides to Harumoto HOSOKAWA, but was not forgiven and murdered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakata found out the detail of Takakuni in Daimotsu kuzure (the Battle of Daimotsu), and tried to switch side to Harumoto HOSOKAWA, but was not forgiven and killed.</e>
<cmt>course→detail,the を補いました。sides→side,murdered→killed と修正しました。前半を文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakata found out the detail of Takakuni in Daimotsu kuzure (the Battle of Daimotsu), and tried to switch side to Harumoto HOSOKAWA, but was not forgiven and killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>細川氏綱は、高国の後継者として晴元と対立を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA continues to oppose Harumoto, as a successor of Takakuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA continues to oppose Harumoto, as the successor of Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>a→the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA continues to oppose Harumoto, as the successor of Takakuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>氏綱は、晴元から離反した三好長慶に担がれて晴元を倒し、室町幕府最後の管領となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujitsuna defeated Harumoto as Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, who defected from Harumoto, prevailed upon him and he became the last Kanrei of Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujitsuna defeated Harumoto, as deceived by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, who defected from Harumoto, and he became the last Kanrei of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujitsuna defeated Harumoto, as deceived by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, who defected from Harumoto, and he became the last Kanrei of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>しかし傀儡にすぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he was no more than a puppet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he was no more than a puppet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he was no more than a puppet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>その死後は氏綱の弟の細川藤賢が典厩家の当主となり、将軍足利義昭に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death, Ujitsuna&apos;s younger brother Fujikata HOSOKAWA took over as head of Tenkyu family and served Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After he died, Ujitsuna&apos;s younger brother Fujikata HOSOKAWA became the head of Tenkyu family, and served the Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>his death→he died,took over as→became the と修正しました。the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After he died, Ujitsuna&apos;s younger brother Fujikata HOSOKAWA became the head of Tenkyu family, and served the Shogun Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>義昭が織田信長と反目し挙兵した際には、義昭とともに抗戦したが降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He fought with Yoshiaki when Yoshiaki took up arms against Nobunaga ODA, but was defeated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fought with Yoshiaki when Yoshiaki took up arms against Nobunaga ODA, but surrendered.</e>
<cmt>was defeated→surrendered と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fought with Yoshiaki when Yoshiaki took up arms against Nobunaga ODA, but surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>その後は信長に臣従し近江坂本城の守備を任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that he served Nobunaga and appointed to defense of Sakamoto-jo Castle in Omi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that he served Nobunaga and appointed to the defense of Sakamoto-jo Castle in Omi.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that he served Nobunaga and appointed to the defense of Sakamoto-jo Castle in Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>野州家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yashu family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yashu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yashu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>細川氏（京兆家）の分家の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a branch family of Hosokawa clan (Keicho family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a branch family of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a branch family of the Hosokawa clan (the Keicho family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>細川満元の弟である細川満国を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founder of the family was Mitsukuni HOSOKAWA, who was a younger brother of Mitsumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founder of the family was Mitsukuni HOSOKAWA, who was a younger brother of Mitsumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founder of the family was Mitsukuni HOSOKAWA, who was a younger brother of Mitsumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>細川持春、細川教春、細川政春、細川晴国と続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Headship of the family was succeeded as follows, Mochiharu HOSOKAWA, Noriharu HOSOKAWA, Masaharu HOSOKAWA and Harukuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>「家督が」と解釈します。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The headship of the family was succeeded as follows, Mochiharu HOSOKAWA, Noriharu HOSOKAWA, Masaharu HOSOKAWA and Harukuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The headship of the family was succeeded as follows, Mochiharu HOSOKAWA, Noriharu HOSOKAWA, Masaharu HOSOKAWA and Harukuni HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>持春、教春が2代にわたって下野守を名乗ったことから野州家の名が定着したようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name, Yashu family was established as Mochiharu and Noriharu wore the title of Shimotsuke no kami (the governer of Shimotsuke Province) over 2 generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name, Yashu family seems to be established as Mochiharu and Noriharu wore the title of Shimotsuke no kami (the governer of Shimotsuke Province) over two generations.</e>
<cmt>was→seems to be,2→two と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name, Yashu family seems to be established as Mochiharu and Noriharu wore the title of Shimotsuke no kami (the governer of Shimotsuke Province) over two generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>備中国浅口郡と伊予国宇摩郡の分郡守護を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family filled a post of Bungunshugo of Asakuchi-gun, Bicchu Province and Uma-gun, Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family served as Bungunshugo of Asakuchi County, Bicchu Province and Uma County, Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>filled a post of→served as, Asakuchi-gun→Asakuchi County,Uma-gun→Uma County と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family served as Bungunshugo of Asakuchi County, Bicchu Province and Uma County, Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>野州家から京兆家には、教春の子の勝之が勝元のもとへ、政春の子の高国は政元のもとへと、2代にわたって猶子が続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adoption of children into Keicho family from Yashu family happened 2 generation in a row, son of Noriharu, Katsuyuki, was adopted into Katsumoto and son of Masaharu, Takakuni, was adopted into Masamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The adoption of children into the Keicho family from the Yashu family continued for two generations, the son of Noriharu, Katsuyuki was adopted into Katsumoto and the son of Masaharu, Takakuni was adopted into Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。happened→continued for,2 generation in a row→two generations,カンマを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The adoption of children into the Keicho family from the Yashu family continued for two generations, the son of Noriharu, Katsuyuki was adopted into Katsumoto and the son of Masaharu, Takakuni was adopted into Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="93">
<j>また持春の子・細川政国が典厩家の持賢の養子に入り、その政国が典厩家の第2代当主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also son of Mochiharu, Masakuni HOSOKAWA, was adopted to Mochitaka HOSOKAWA of Tenkyu family, and Masakuni succeeded as the second family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the son of Mochiharu, Masakuni HOSOKAWA was adopted to Mochitaka HOSOKAWA of the Tenkyu family, and Masakuni succeeded as the second family head.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。カンマを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the son of Mochiharu, Masakuni HOSOKAWA was adopted to Mochitaka HOSOKAWA of the Tenkyu family, and Masakuni succeeded as the second family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>このように、京兆家との一体性が強い典厩家との間にも緊密な関係を保っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yashu family also maintained such close relationship with Tenkyu family, which had solid relationship with Keicho family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yashu family also maintained such close relationship with the Tenkyu family, which had a solid relationship with the Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>the, a を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yashu family also maintained such close relationship with the Tenkyu family, which had a solid relationship with the Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="95">
<j>野州家は将軍近習としての性格を有した一方で、京兆家、典厩家とも密接な関係を保ち、結果として細川氏一門の幕政関与に貢献したと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yashu family possessed nature of Shogun attendant but on the other hand, they maintained close relationship with Keicho family and Tenkyu family, as a result, it is believed, they had contributed to involvement of Hosokawa clan in bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yashu family possessed its nature as a shogun attendant, but on the other hand, they maintained the close relationship with the Keicho family and the Tenkyu family, as a result, it is assumed, they had contributed to the involvement of the Hosokawa clan in bakufu.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。nature of Shogun→its nature as a shogun,believed→assumed と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yashu family possessed its nature as a shogun attendant, but on the other hand, they maintained the close relationship with the Keicho family and the Tenkyu family, as a result, it is assumed, they had contributed to the involvement of the Hosokawa clan in bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="96">
<j>政春の子・高国は、管領細川政元の養子として京兆家に入り、その家督争いに躍り出ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni, a son of Masaharu, was adopted into Keicho family as a son of Kanrei, Masamoto HOSOKAWA and he came suddenly into prominence in succession dispute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni, the son of Masaharu, was adopted into the Keicho family as a son of Kanrei, then he came to be in the dispute of the family headship.</e>
<cmt>a→the と修正しました。the を補いました。後半部分を文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni, the son of Masaharu, was adopted into the Keicho family as a son of Kanrei, then he came to be in the dispute of the family headship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>また通政は、戦国時代にその所領の維持を図ったのだが、出雲国の尼子晴久の圧迫を受け伊予国へ逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Michimasa intended to maintain their shoryo in the Sengoku period but fled to Iyo Province, as he was threatened by Haruhisa AMAGO of Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Michimasa intended to maintain their shoryo in the Sengoku Period, but fled to Iyo Province, as he was oppressed by Haruhisa AMAGO of Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt>period→Period,threatened→oppressed と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Michimasa intended to maintain their shoryo in the Sengoku Period, but fled to Iyo Province, as he was oppressed by Haruhisa AMAGO of Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>通政の甥・細川通薫（通重）が備中支配の回復を試みるが、中国地方に勢力を伸ばした毛利氏の客将となり、子孫は長州藩に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A nephew of Michimasa, Michitada (Michishige) HOSOKAWA tried to regain Bicchu control but he became a guest shogun of Mori clan that extended the power in Chugoku Region, and his descendants served Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A nephew of Michimasa, Michitada (Michishige) HOSOKAWA tried to regain the control of Bicchu, but he became a guest commander of the Mori clan that extended the power in the Chugoku region, and his descendants served the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>Bicchu control→control of Bicchu,shogun→commander,Region→region と修正しました。 the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A nephew of Michimasa, Michitada (Michishige) HOSOKAWA tried to regain the control of Bicchu, but he became a guest commander of the Mori clan that extended the power in the Chugoku region, and his descendants served the Choshu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>阿波細川家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awa Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Awa Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Awa Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="99">
<j>阿波細川氏は14世紀中頃、細川頼之の弟・細川詮春に始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Awa Hosokawa family started with Akiharu HOSOKAWA, a younger brother of Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, in the middle of 14th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Awa Hosokawa family started with Akiharu HOSOKAWA, a younger brother of Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, around the middle of 14th century.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。in→around と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Awa Hosokawa family started with Akiharu HOSOKAWA, a younger brother of Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, around the middle of 14th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>阿波守護を代襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family succeeded to Awa Shugo by representation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family succeeded the Shugo of Awa by representation.</e>
<cmt>to Awa Shugo→the Shugo of Awa と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family succeeded the Shugo of Awa by representation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>他の細川庶流家とは異なり、室町幕府の相伴衆を努める家柄であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike other Hosokawa branch families, Awa Hosokawa family filled a role of Shobanshu (officials who accompany the Shogun) of Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the other Hosokawa branch families, the Awa Hosokawa family served as Shobanshu (officials who accompany the Shogun) of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。filled a role of→served as と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the other Hosokawa branch families, the Awa Hosokawa family served as Shobanshu (officials who accompany the Shogun) of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>京兆家を上屋形と呼ぶのに対し、阿波細川家は下屋形あるいは阿波屋形と尊称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho family was called Kamiyakata whereas Awa Hosokawa family was given an honorific title, Shimoyakata or Awayakata (a title of the Hosokawa clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereas the Keicho family was called Kamiyakata, the Awa Hosokawa family was given an honorific title, Shimoyakata or Awayakata.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。オーダーを修正しました。カッコ部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereas the Keicho family was called Kamiyakata, the Awa Hosokawa family was given an honorific title, Shimoyakata or Awayakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>細川成之のころから讃岐守護も兼任するようになり、阿波讃岐細川家とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the time of Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA, the family also served concurrently as Sanuki Shugo and they are also called Awa Sanuki Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the time of Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA, the family also served as Sanuki Shugo concurrently, and they are also called the Awa Sanuki Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。オーダーを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the time of Shigeyuki HOSOKAWA, the family also served as Sanuki Shugo concurrently, and they are also called the Awa Sanuki Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>また代々の当主は、讃岐守を称したことから讃州家ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also they are called Sanshu family as successive generations of the family heads professed to be Sanuki no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also they are called the Sanshu family as successive generations of the family heads professed to be Sanuki no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also they are called the Sanshu family as successive generations of the family heads professed to be Sanuki no kami (the governor of Sanuki Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="105">
<j>当主は幕府の宿老会議にも度々列席するなど、京兆家に次ぐ細川家として高い家格を有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family head often attended chief vassal meetings in bakufu and their kakaku (family status) was second to that for Keicho family, among Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family head often attended the chief vassal meetings of the bakufu, and their kakaku (family status) was second to that of the Keicho family, among the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>in→of,for→of と修正しました。the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family head often attended the chief vassal meetings of the bakufu, and their kakaku (family status) was second to that of the Keicho family, among the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>数え方によって変わるが10代で終わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it varies depends on how to count, family line ended with 10th family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it varies depends on how to count, the family line ended at the 10th generation.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。with 10th family head→at the 10th generation と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it varies depends on how to count, the family line ended at the 10th generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="107">
<j>詮春から数えて4代目の細川持常は、6代将軍足利義教の信任が厚く、永享12年（1440年）に戦死したとされる一色義貫に代わり三河国守護職も兼任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochitsune HOSOKAWA, the fourth family head counting from Akiharu, gained trust from the sixth shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA and he served as an additional post of Mikawa Province Shugo, replacing Yoshitsura ISSHIKI who was said to have died in a battle in 1440.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochitsune HOSOKAWA, the fourth family head counting from Akiharu, gained trust from the sixth shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, and he served as an additional post of the Shugo of Mikawa Province, replacing Yoshitsura ISSHIKI who was said to have died in a battle in 1440.</e>
<cmt>カンマ を補いました。Mikawa Province Shugo→the Shugo of Mikawa Province と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochitsune HOSOKAWA, the fourth family head counting from Akiharu, gained trust from the sixth shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, and he served as an additional post of the Shugo of Mikawa Province, replacing Yoshitsura ISSHIKI who was said to have died in a battle in 1440.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>しかし一色義貫の死が義教の陰謀によるものであったため、持常とそれを継いだ成之が三河国に守護権を確立する際には、一色残党の激しい抵抗に遭い、多大な犠牲を払った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However because the death of Yoshitsura ISSHIKI was a plot of Yoshinori, the remnants (of a defeated party) of Isshiki fiercely resisted when Mochitsune and his successor Shigeyuki establish authorization of Shugo in Mikawa Province and they had made great sacrifice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the death of Yoshitsura ISSHIKI was a plot of Yoshinori, the remnants (of a defeated party) of Isshiki fiercely resisted when Mochitsune and his successor Shigeyuki were establishing the authorization of Shugo in Mikawa Province, and they made a great sacrifice.</e>
<cmt>カンマ, a, the を補いました。establish→were establishing と修正しました。 had を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the death of Yoshitsura ISSHIKI was a plot of Yoshinori, the remnants (of a defeated party) of Isshiki fiercely resisted when Mochitsune and his successor Shigeyuki were establishing the authorization of Shugo in Mikawa Province, and they made a great sacrifice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="109">
<j>義教の信任厚い持常は、嘉吉の乱で義教が暗殺された後、赤松満祐征伐のため播磨国に出兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshinori was murdered in Kakitsu War, Mochitsune, who was confidential of Yoshinori, dispatched troops to Harima Provicne for subjugation of Mitsusuke AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshinori was assassinated in the Kakitsu War, Mochitsune, who was a confidential of Yoshinori, dispatched troops to Harima Provicne for the subjugation of Mitsusuke AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>murdered→assassinated, と修正しました。the, a を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshinori was assassinated in the Kakitsu War, Mochitsune, who was a confidential of Yoshinori, dispatched troops to Harima Provicne for the subjugation of Mitsusuke AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>しかし、山名宗全（宗全）に一歩遅れる形となり、播磨守護職は山名氏のものとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he fell a step behind of Sozen YAMANA and Yamana clan took post of Harima Shugo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he fell a step behind of Sozen YAMANA, and the Yamana clan took the post of Harima Shugo.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he fell a step behind of Sozen YAMANA, and the Yamana clan took the post of Harima Shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>播磨を巡る山名氏と阿波細川家の潜在的対立は、持常の後を継いだ成之の、赤松家の再興運動への助力という形になって現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Potential rivalry between Yamana clan and Awa Hosokawa clan over Harima was revealed as Shigeyuki, who took over the family head after Mochitsune, supporting in a restoration movement of the Akamatsu family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The potential rivalry between the Yamana clan and the Awa Hosokawa clan over Harima, was revealed as Shigeyuki, who succeeded the family head after Mochitsune, supporting in the restoration movement of the Akamatsu family.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。took over→succeeded,a→the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The potential rivalry between the Yamana clan and the Awa Hosokawa clan over Harima, was revealed as Shigeyuki, who succeeded the family head after Mochitsune, supporting in the restoration movement of the Akamatsu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>これらのことは、当初は友好的な関係にあった山名氏と細川京兆家との関係悪化を招き、応仁の乱の遠因ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These worsened relationship between Yamana clan and Hosokawa Keicho family that was originally in friendly term, and also became an underlying cause of Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These worsened the relationship between the Yamana clan and the Hosokawa Keicho family that was originally in friendly term, and it also became an underlying cause of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>the, it を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These worsened the relationship between the Yamana clan and the Hosokawa Keicho family that was originally in friendly term, and it also became an underlying cause of the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>成之は、応仁の乱では東軍として京兆家を盛り立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeyuki backed up Keicho family in Onin War as the &apos;eastern&apos; army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeyuki backed up the Keicho family in the Onin War as the eastern army.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。クォーツを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeyuki backed up the Keicho family in the Onin War as the eastern army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>しかし、細川勝元の没後、政元の時代においては、権力集中を図る京兆家としばしば対立し、摂津守護代の薬師寺元一の反乱に関与するなどした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in the time of Masamoto after death of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, the family often opposed to Keicho family, which planned concentration of power, and the family were involved in rebellion of Motokazu YAKUSHIJI who was a deputy Shugo of the Province of Settsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the time of Masamoto after Katsumoto HOSOKAWA died, the family often opposed to the Keicho family, which was seeking the concentration of its power, and the family was involved in the rebellion of Motokazu YAKUSHIJI, who was a deputy Shugo of the Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>death of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA→ Katsumoto HOSOKAWA died,planned→was seeking,were→was,Province of Settsu→Settsu Province と修正しました。カンマ、the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the time of Masamoto after Katsumoto HOSOKAWA died, the family often opposed to the Keicho family, which was seeking the concentration of its power, and the family was involved in the rebellion of Motokazu YAKUSHIJI, who was a deputy Shugo of the Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>成之は孫である澄元を、政元の養子に送りこむことに成功するものの、それは畿内の争乱をさらに激化させることになり、政元暗殺とその後の「永正の錯乱」へと事態は進展するのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Shigeyuki succeeded to give Sumimoto, his grand son, to Masamoto as an adopted child, it intensified conflict in Kinai region and a situation was led to assasination of Masamoto and later &apos;Eisho Disturbance&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shigeyuki succeeded to give Sumimoto, his grand son to Masamoto as an adopted child, it intensified the conflict in the Kinai region and the situation led the assassination of Masamoto and the &apos;Eisho Disturbance&apos; afterwards.</e>
<cmt>カンマを修正しました。the を補いました。a→the,was led to→led,assasination→assassination,最後の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shigeyuki succeeded to give Sumimoto, his grand son to Masamoto as an adopted child, it intensified the conflict in the Kinai region and the situation led the assassination of Masamoto and the &apos;Eisho Disturbance&apos; afterwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="116">
<j>なお、成之の次子の細川之勝（後の細川義春）は備中国守護の細川勝久の養子となっていたが、成之の嫡男の細川政之が早世したため、義春と改名し阿波守護家を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeyuki&apos;s second child, Yukikatsu HOSOKAWA (later Yoshiharu HOSOKAWA) had been an adopted child of Katsuhisa HOSOKAWA, Shugo of Bicchu Province, but he took over as the Shugo family of Awa after changing name to Yoshiharu, as Shigeyuki&apos;s legitimate child, Masayuki HOSOKAWA, died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeyuki&apos;s second child, Yukikatsu HOSOKAWA (later Yoshiharu HOSOKAWA) had been an adopted child of Katsuhisa HOSOKAWA, the Shugo of Bicchu Province, but he succeeded the Shugo family of Awa after changing the name to Yoshiharu, as Shigeyuki&apos;s legitimate child, Masayuki HOSOKAWA, died young.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。took over as→succeeded と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeyuki&apos;s second child, Yukikatsu HOSOKAWA (later Yoshiharu HOSOKAWA) had been an adopted child of Katsuhisa HOSOKAWA, the Shugo of Bicchu Province, but he succeeded the Shugo family of Awa after changing the name to Yoshiharu, as Shigeyuki&apos;s legitimate child, Masayuki HOSOKAWA, died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>後に義春の子の細川之持が短期間であるが備中守護にも任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later Yukimochi HOSOKAWA, Yoshiharu&apos;s son, was appointed to Bicchu Shugo for a short period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later Yukimochi HOSOKAWA, Yoshiharu&apos;s son, was appointed to Bicchu Shugo for a short period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later Yukimochi HOSOKAWA, Yoshiharu&apos;s son, was appointed to Bicchu Shugo for a short period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="118">
<j>成之自身は長命であったが、子である政之（1488年没）と義春（1494年没）に先立たれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Shigeyuki lived long life, he had his sons, Masayuki (died in 1488) and Yoshiharu (died in 1494), died ahead of him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Shigeyuki lived a long time, his sons, Masayuki (died in 1488) and Yoshiharu (died in 1494), died before him.</e>
<cmt>life→a long time,he had his sons→his sons,ahead of→before と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Shigeyuki lived a long time, his sons, Masayuki (died in 1488) and Yoshiharu (died in 1494), died before him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>さらに1511年の成之の死の翌年には孫の之持が夭折するなど、寿命に恵まれない当主がつづく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the family head with unfortunate life span continued, such as in a year after Shigeyuki&apos;s death, in 1511, his grand son Yukimochi also died young.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the family head with unfortunate life span continued, as his grand son Yukimochi also died young a year after Shigeyuki&apos;s death, in 1511.</e>
<cmt>such as→as,オーダーを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the family head with unfortunate life span continued, as his grand son Yukimochi also died young a year after Shigeyuki&apos;s death, in 1511.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>若年の当主が続く成之以降の阿波細川家においては、家宰の三好氏が台頭することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chief vassal, Miyoshi clan gained power in Awa Hosokawa clan after the time of Shigeyuki, as young family heads were followed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chief vassal of the Miyoshi clan gained power in the Awa Hosokawa clan, which the youth family heads continued after the time of Shigeyuki.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。スムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chief vassal of the Miyoshi clan gained power in the Awa Hosokawa clan, which the youth family heads continued after the time of Shigeyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>澄元を擁した三好之長は、畿内において細川高国と抗争を続けたが敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukinaga MIYOSHI backed up Sumimoto and continued the conflict against Takakuni HOSOKAWA in Kinai region, but was defeated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukinaga MIYOSHI backed up Sumimoto and continued to fight against Takakuni HOSOKAWA in the Kinai region, but was defeated.</e>
<cmt>the conflict→to fight と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukinaga MIYOSHI backed up Sumimoto and continued to fight against Takakuni HOSOKAWA in the Kinai region, but was defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>澄元もまた京兆家の主導権を取り戻せぬまま夭折する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumimoto also died young before taking back initiative of Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimoto also died young before taking back initiative of the Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimoto also died young before taking back initiative of the Keicho family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="123">
<j>一方、之持の子の細川持隆は三好元長の補佐の元で成長すると、澄元の子の晴元や元長と協調し足利義維を擁立し、堺公方とするなど幕府と対立を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, son of Yukimochi, Mochitaka HOSOKAWA grew up in assistance of Motonaga MIYOSHI, and he continued confrontation against bakufu, such as cooperating with Harumoto, son of Sumimoto, and Motonaga to enthrone Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA as Sakai Kubo (head of (Sakai-based) municipal government).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the son of Yukimochi, Mochitaka HOSOKAWA grew up in the care of Motonaga MIYOSHI, and he continued the confrontation against the bakufu, such as cooperating with Harumoto, the son of Sumimoto, and Motonaga to support Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA as Sakai Kubo (head of [Sakai-based) municipal governmen]).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。assistance→the care,enthrone→support,カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the son of Yukimochi, Mochitaka HOSOKAWA grew up in the care of Motonaga MIYOSHI, and he continued the confrontation against the bakufu, such as cooperating with Harumoto, the son of Sumimoto, and Motonaga to support Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA as Sakai Kubo (head of [Sakai-based) municipal governmen]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>堺幕府の解体後は、義維を阿波に迎え、平島公方としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After disorganization of Sakai bakufu, he invited Yoshitsuna to Awa as Hirashima Kubo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the disorganization of the Sakai bakufu, he invited Yoshitsuna to Awa as Hirashima Kubo.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the disorganization of the Sakai bakufu, he invited Yoshitsuna to Awa as Hirashima Kubo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>江口の戦いで晴元が没落し、三好長慶が将軍足利義輝をも追放して畿内の実権を握ると、義維の将軍擁立を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He claimed enthronement of Yoshitsuna to Shogun, when Harumoto was collapsed in Battle of Eguchi and Nagayoshi MIYOSHI gained real power of Kinai region by expelling Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He claimed the enthronement of Yoshitsuna to shogun, when Harumoto was collapsed in the Battle of Eguchi and Nagayoshi MIYOSHI gained real power of the Kinai region by expelling Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。Shogun→shogun と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He claimed the enthronement of Yoshitsuna to shogun, when Harumoto was collapsed in the Battle of Eguchi and Nagayoshi MIYOSHI gained real power of the Kinai region by expelling Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>しかし、義輝との全面対立を望まない長慶の弟の三好義賢と対立し、天文22年（1553年）、義賢により暗殺されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he was in opposition to Nagayoshi&apos;s younger brother Yoshikata MIYOSHI, who did not wish for full confrontation against Yoshiteru, and he was murdered in 1553 by Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he opposed Nagayoshi&apos;s younger brother Yoshikata MIYOSHI, who did not wish for the full-scale confrontation against Yoshiteru, and he was assassinated in 1553 by Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt>was in opposition to→opposed,full→the full-scale,murdered→assassinated と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he opposed Nagayoshi&apos;s younger brother Yoshikata MIYOSHI, who did not wish for the full-scale confrontation against Yoshiteru, and he was assassinated in 1553 by Yoshikata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="127">
<j>持隆の子・細川真之は、義賢とその子の三好長治の元での傀儡でしかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochitaka&apos;s son, Saneyuki HOSOKAWA was no more than a puppet to Yoshitaka and his son Nagaharu MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochitaka&apos;s son, Saneyuki HOSOKAWA was no more than a puppet of Yoshitaka and his son Nagaharu MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>to→of と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochitaka&apos;s son, Saneyuki HOSOKAWA was no more than a puppet of Yoshitaka and his son Nagaharu MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>長治が悪政により阿波を混乱させると、真之は新たに台頭しつつあった土佐の長宗我部元親と手を結び復権を図り、長治を滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nagaharu disturbed Awa by his misrule, Saneyoshi planned for restoration of rights by linking up with Motochika CHOSOKABE, who started gain power in Tosa and eliminated Nagaharu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nagaharu disturbed Awa by his misrule, Saneyoshi planned to regain his position by linking up with Motochika CHOSOKABE, who started gain power in Tosa, and eliminated Nagaharu.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。for the restoration of rights→to regain his position</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nagaharu disturbed Awa by his misrule, Saneyoshi planned to regain his position by linking up with Motochika CHOSOKABE, who started gain power in Tosa, and eliminated Nagaharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>しかし、天正10年（1582年）に長治の弟の十河存保に攻められて自刃し滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he was attacked by Masayasu SOGO, the younger brother of Nagaharu, and fell with jijin (commit suicide with one&apos;s sword).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was attacked by Masayasu SOGO, the younger brother of Nagaharu, and died by jijin (commit suicide with one&apos;s sword) in 1582.</e>
<cmt>カンマ、in 1582 を補いました。fell with→died by と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was attacked by Masayasu SOGO, the younger brother of Nagaharu, and died by jijin (commit suicide with one&apos;s sword) in 1582.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>和泉守護家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo (military governor) family of Izumi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo (military governor) family of Izumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo (military governor) family of Izumi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>和泉国では細川庶流二家による、国内を分割しない共同管理方式の守護二人制が採用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Izumi Province, 2 branch families of Hosokawa adapted double Shugo system, which was a joint control method that does not divide a Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Izumi Province, the two branch families of Hosokawa adapted double Shugo system, which was a joint control method that does not divide a Province.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。2→two,does→did と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Izumi Province, the two branch families of Hosokawa adapted double Shugo system, which was a joint control method that does not divide a Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>両守護家の祖は、細川頼長（頼之の甥）と細川基之（頼之の猶子）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founders of both Shugo families were Yorinaga HOSOKAWA (a nephew of Yoriyuki) and Motoyuki HOSOKAWA (an adopted child of Yoriyuki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founders of both Shugo families were Yorinaga HOSOKAWA (a nephew of Yoriyuki) and Motoyuki HOSOKAWA (an adopted child of Yoriyuki).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founders of both Shugo families were Yorinaga HOSOKAWA (a nephew of Yoriyuki) and Motoyuki HOSOKAWA (an adopted child of Yoriyuki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>前者を上守護家、後者を下守護家と呼んだらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former was called Shugo family of upper Izumi Province while the other was called Shugo family of lower Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt>upperとlowerのみになると、上下が何を指しているのか（力関係、地域的なものetc）が不明になってしまうので、ドキュメント中から、和泉～と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that, the former was called the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province while the other was called the Shugo family of lower Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt>It is assumed that を補いました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that, the former was called the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province while the other was called the Shugo family of lower Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="133">
<j>守護二人制の採用理由として、和泉国は大国であるがゆえに権力の分散を目的としたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that adaptation of double Shugo system was aimed at divergence of power, as Izumi Province was a taigoku (major province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that adaptation of double Shugo system was aimed at the divergence of power, as Izumi Province was a taigoku (major province).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that adaptation of double Shugo system was aimed at the divergence of power, as Izumi Province was a taigoku (major province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>ただし頼長と基之はそれ以前から備後、土佐の守護も併任されており、別に何らかの理由が存在した可能性が推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However some other possibilities are suspected as Yorinaga and Motoyuki acted concurrently as Shugo of Bingo and Tosa before taking the post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However some other possibilities are suspected as Yorinaga and Motoyuki appointed concurrently to the Shugo of Bingo and Tosa before taking the post.</e>
<cmt>acted as→appointed to と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However some other possibilities are suspected as Yorinaga and Motoyuki appointed concurrently to the Shugo of Bingo and Tosa before taking the post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="135">
<j>和泉上（半国）守護家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo family of upper (half province) Izumi Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo family of upper (half province) Izumi Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo family of upper (half province) Izumi Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>細川頼之の弟・頼有の子孫が14世紀中頃から和泉守護を代々務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants of Yoriari, a younger brother of Yoriyuki, successively filled a post of Izumi Shugo since mid 14th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants of Yoriari, a younger brother of Yoriyuki, successively filled the post of Izumi Shugo from the mid 14th century.</e>
<cmt>a→the と修正しました。since→from the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants of Yoriari, a younger brother of Yoriyuki, successively filled the post of Izumi Shugo from the mid 14th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>頼長のあと、持有、教春、常有（教春の弟）、元有（常有の孫）と守護職を世襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochiari, Noriharu, Tsuneari (a younger brother of Noriharu) and Motoari (a grand son of Tsuneari) filled posts of Shugo by heredity, after Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochiari, Noriharu, Tsuneari (a younger brother of Noriharu) and Motoari (a grand son of Tsuneari) served as Shugo by heredity, after Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>filled posts of→served as と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochiari, Noriharu, Tsuneari (a younger brother of Noriharu) and Motoari (a grand son of Tsuneari) served as Shugo by heredity, after Yorinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>細川元有は和泉下守護家とともに紀伊国守護畠山尚順と同盟を組み、管領細川政元と敵対していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoari HOSOKAWA and Shugo family of lower Izumi Province formed an alliance with Shugo of Kii Province Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA, together they were contending against Kanrei, Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoari HOSOKAWA and the Shugo family of lower Izumi Province formed an alliance with Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA of the Shugo of Kii Province, and they were hostile to the Kanrei, Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。オーダーを変更し修正しました。後半部分を文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoari HOSOKAWA and the Shugo family of lower Izumi Province formed an alliance with Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA of the Shugo of Kii Province, and they were hostile to the Kanrei, Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>しかし、両守護家は政元に大敗し恭順し、そのため畠山尚順に攻め込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However both Shugo families were soundly defeated and yielded to Masamoto therefore they were invaded by Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However both Shugo families were soundly defeated and obeyed Masamoto, therefore they were invaded by Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>yielded to→obeyed と修正しました。カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However both Shugo families were soundly defeated and obeyed Masamoto, therefore they were invaded by Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>元有が1500年に戦死して以後は衰退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family declined after Motoari died in a battle in 1500.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family declined after Motoari died in a battle in 1500.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family declined after Motoari died in a battle in 1500.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>子・細川元常の代には守護とは名ばかりで、弟の三淵晴員とともに将軍足利義晴の近臣となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo was in name only in generation of Mototsune HOSOKAWA, a son of Motoari, and he and his brother Harukazu MITSUBUCHI became trusted vassal of Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo was in name only in the generation of Mototsune HOSOKAWA, the son of Motoari, and he and his brother Harukazu MITSUBUCHI became trusted vassals of the Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。a→the,vassal→vassals と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo was in name only in the generation of Mototsune HOSOKAWA, the son of Motoari, and he and his brother Harukazu MITSUBUCHI became trusted vassals of the Shogun, Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>元常には子供がおらず、弟・晴員の次男・細川幽斎を養嗣子として家督を譲った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsune did not have a child therefore he adopted Yusai HOSOKAWA, the second son of his younger brother Harukazu and handed over the headship of a family to Yusai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsune did not have a child therefore he adopted Yusai HOSOKAWA, the second son of his younger brother Harukazu, and handed over the family headship to Yusai.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。headship of a family→family headship と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsune did not have a child therefore he adopted Yusai HOSOKAWA, the second son of his younger brother Harukazu, and handed over the family headship to Yusai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="143">
<j>藤孝の後、和泉上守護家の流れは次男・細川興元が継ぎ常陸谷田部藩の祖となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Fujitaka, the second son Okimoto HOSOKAWA took over the line of Shugo family of upper Izumi Province and became founder of Hitachi Yatabe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Fujitaka, the second son Okimoto HOSOKAWA succeeded the line of the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province, and became the founder of the Hitachi Yatabe clan.</e>
<cmt>took over→succeeded と修正しました。カンマ、the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Fujitaka, the second son Okimoto HOSOKAWA succeeded the line of the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province, and became the founder of the Hitachi Yatabe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>興元の興の字は兄・細川忠興からのもので、元の字は藤孝の養父・元常に因むといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that letter &apos;興&apos; in Okimoto (興元) was taken from his elder brother Tadaoki (忠興) HOSOKAWA and letter &apos;元&apos; was taken from Mototsune (元常), a foster father of Fujitaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the letter &apos;興&apos; in Okimoto (興元) was after his older brother Tadaoki (忠興) HOSOKAWA, and the letter &apos;元&apos; was after Mototsune (元常), the foster father of Fujitaka.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。taken from→after,elder→older,a→the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the letter &apos;興&apos; in Okimoto (興元) was after his older brother Tadaoki (忠興) HOSOKAWA, and the letter &apos;元&apos; was after Mototsune (元常), the foster father of Fujitaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>明治期に子爵に列せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was ranked as viscount in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was ranked as viscount in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was ranked as viscount in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>なお藤孝の長子である忠興は、幼少期に将軍家の命で奥州家細川輝経の養子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eldest son of Fujitaka, Tadaoki became adopted child of Terutsune HOSOKAWA of Oshu family when he was young, with an order of Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the first son of Fujitaka, Tadaoki became adopted child of Terutsune HOSOKAWA of the Oshu family when he was young, with an order of the Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>Moreover, the を補いました。eldest→first と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the first son of Fujitaka, Tadaoki became adopted child of Terutsune HOSOKAWA of the Oshu family when he was young, with an order of the Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>そのため、子孫の肥後細川家は系譜上奥州家の流れといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore his descendant, Higo Hosokawa family was genealogically a line of Oshu family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore his descendant, the Higo Hosokawa family was genealogically a line of the Oshu family.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore his descendant, the Higo Hosokawa family was genealogically a line of the Oshu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="148">
<j>和泉下（半国）守護家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo family of lower (half province) Izumi Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo family of lower (half province) Izumi Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo family of lower (half province) Izumi Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>基之のあと、持久（基之の孫）、勝信（基経の誤記か）、細川政久が守護職を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochihisa (a grand son of Motoyuki), Katsunobu (could be a recording error of Mototsune) and Masahisa HOSOKAWA successively took over the post of Shugo, after Motoyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochihisa (a grand son of Motoyuki), Katsunobu (could be a recording error of Mototsune) and Masahisa HOSOKAWA successively served as Shugo, after Motoyuki.</e>
<cmt>took over the post of→served as と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochihisa (a grand son of Motoyuki), Katsunobu (could be a recording error of Mototsune) and Masahisa HOSOKAWA successively served as Shugo, after Motoyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>政久は和泉上守護家と同盟し、その上で畠山尚順と結び細川政元に対抗したがその後は恭順した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masahisa opposed to Masamoto HOSOKAWA by forming alliance with Shugo family of upper Izumi Province and also linked up with Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA, but later submitted to Masamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masahisa opposed to Masamoto HOSOKAWA by forming an alliance with the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province and also linked up with Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA, but later obeyed Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>an, the を補いました。submitted to →obeyed と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masahisa opposed to Masamoto HOSOKAWA by forming an alliance with the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province and also linked up with Hisanobu HATAKEYAMA, but later obeyed Masamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>しかし尚順に攻め込まれ戦死をとげた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However he died in a battle when Hisanobu invaded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he died in a battle when Hisanobu invaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he died in a battle when Hisanobu invaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>政元は畠山尚順を河内で破り、和泉に攻め入り支配を回復したが、そののち和泉下守護家がその地位を保つことはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto defeated Hisanobu HAYAKEYAMA in Kawachi and invaded Izumi to recover a control but Shugo family of lower Izumi Province could not maintain the status after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamoto defeated Hisanobu HAYAKEYAMA in Kawachi and invaded Izumi to recover the control, but the Shugo family of lower Izumi Province could not maintain the status after that.</e>
<cmt>a→the と修正しました。the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamoto defeated Hisanobu HAYAKEYAMA in Kawachi and invaded Izumi to recover the control, but the Shugo family of lower Izumi Province could not maintain the status after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>備中守護家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo family of Bicchu Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo family of Bicchu Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo family of Bicchu Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="153">
<j>頼之の末弟・細川満之を祖とし、細川頼重、細川氏久、細川勝久と代々守護職を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founder of the family was Mitsuyuki HOSOKAWA, the youngest brother of Yoriyuki, and a post of Shugo was successively taken over to Yorishige HOSOKAWA, Ujihisa HOSOKAWA and to Katsuhisa HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the family was Mitsuyuki HOSOKAWA, the youngest brother of Yoriyuki, and a post of Shugo was successively taken over to Yorishige HOSOKAWA, Ujihisa HOSOKAWA and to Katsuhisa HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the family was Mitsuyuki HOSOKAWA, the youngest brother of Yoriyuki, and a post of Shugo was successively taken over to Yorishige HOSOKAWA, Ujihisa HOSOKAWA and to Katsuhisa HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>他に伊予国新居郡などの領有の記録もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there is a record showing possession of Nii County, Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there is a record showing the possession of Nii County, Iyo Province and so on.</e>
<cmt>the, and so on を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there is a record showing the possession of Nii County, Iyo Province and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="155">
<j>備中国はもともと京兆家や阿波守護家など、他の有力守護家の影響が強く及んでおり、庄氏を初めとする国人統制も困難を極めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bicchu Province was originally strongly affected by other dominant Shugo family, such as Keicho family and Awa Shugo family, and control of kokujin, including the Sho clan, was in utmost difficulty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bicchu Province was originally strongly affected by the other dominant Shugo families, such as the Keicho family and the Awa Shugo family, and the control of kokujin, including the Sho clan, was in utmost difficulty.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。family→families と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bicchu Province was originally strongly affected by the other dominant Shugo families, such as the Keicho family and the Awa Shugo family, and the control of kokujin, including the Sho clan, was in utmost difficulty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>頼重などは1431年に謎の狂死を遂げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorishige mysteriously died in a fit of madness in 1431.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorishige mysteriously died in a fit of madness in 1431.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorishige mysteriously died in a fit of madness in 1431.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>勝久の代に、庄元資（伊豆守）との争乱が勃発し（備中大合戦）、これは備中守護家が勝利した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the generation of Katsuhisa, a war against Motosuke SHO (Izu no kami (Governor of Izu Province)) broke out (the great battle in Bicchu), and Shugo family of Bicchu won in the battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the generation of Katsuhisa, a war against Motosuke SHO (Izu no kami [Governor of Izu Province]) broke out (the great battle in Bicchu), and the Shugo family of Bicchu won in the battle.</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the generation of Katsuhisa, a war against Motosuke SHO (Izu no kami [Governor of Izu Province]) broke out (the great battle in Bicchu), and the Shugo family of Bicchu won in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>しかし、国内の混乱はますます加速する一方で、以後次第に勢力を弱めていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However disturbance within Province was increasingly accelerated and the family gradually weakened its power after that.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the disturbance within its province was increasingly accelerated, and the family gradually weakened its power after that.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。Province→its province,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the disturbance within its province was increasingly accelerated, and the family gradually weakened its power after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>阿波守護家から迎えた勝久の養子である之勝（細川義春）は、実兄・政之の死に伴い後に阿波守護家に戻ったため、勝久の系統がその後守護に就任することはなく、事実上守護家は断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukikatsu (Yoshiharu HOSOKAWA), Katsuhisa&apos;s adopted child from Shugo family of Awa, returned to Shugo family of Awa, as his real elder brother Masayuki died, therefore line of Katsuhisa did not take a position of Shugo after that and the Shugo family was practically ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukikatsu (Yoshiharu HOSOKAWA), Katsuhisa&apos;s adopted child from the Shugo family of Awa, returned to the Shugo family of Awa, as his real older brother Masayuki died, therefore, the line of Katsuhisa did not take a position of Shugo after that, and the Shugo family was practically ended.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。elder→older と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukikatsu (Yoshiharu HOSOKAWA), Katsuhisa&apos;s adopted child from the Shugo family of Awa, returned to the Shugo family of Awa, as his real older brother Masayuki died, therefore, the line of Katsuhisa did not take a position of Shugo after that, and the Shugo family was practically ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="160">
<j>以降は阿波守護家の細川之持（義春の子）が一時的に備中守護を継いだ後、数年の空白を経て、管領となった細川高国の実父である野州家の細川政春が備中守護となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Yukimochi HOSOKAWA (a son of Yoshiharu) of Shugo family of Awa temporarily took over Bicchu Shugo and Masaharu HOSOKAWA of Yashu family, who was a biological father of Kanrei Takakuni HOSOKAWA, became Bicchu Shugo after few years of blank.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Yukimochi HOSOKAWA (the son of Yoshiharu) of the Shugo family of Awa temporarily succeeded the Bicchu Shugo, and Masaharu HOSOKAWA of Yashu family, who was a biological father of the Kanrei Takakuni HOSOKAWA, became the Bicchu Shugo after few years of blank.</e>
<cmt>a→the,took over→succeeded と修正しました。the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Yukimochi HOSOKAWA (the son of Yoshiharu) of the Shugo family of Awa temporarily succeeded the Bicchu Shugo, and Masaharu HOSOKAWA of Yashu family, who was a biological father of the Kanrei Takakuni HOSOKAWA, became the Bicchu Shugo after few years of blank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>しかし、1518年以降、備中守護の任命は長く為されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However appointment of Bicchu Shugo did not last long after 1518.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the appointment of Bicchu Shugo was not made for long time on and after 1518.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。did not last long→was not made for long time on と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the appointment of Bicchu Shugo was not made for long time on and after 1518.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>備中は戦国に突入したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bicchu entered in warlike period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bicchu entered in warlike period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bicchu entered in warlike period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>淡路守護家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo family of Awaji Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo family of Awaji Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo family of Awaji Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="163">
<j>細川氏の庶流の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a branch family of Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a branch family of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a branch family of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>和氏・頼春の弟の細川師氏を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founder of the family was Morouji HOSOKAWA who was a younger brother of Kazuuji and Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the family was Morouji HOSOKAWA who was a younger brother of Kazuuji and Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the family was Morouji HOSOKAWA who was a younger brother of Kazuuji and Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>師氏の子・細川氏春は、和氏の子・清氏が南朝に降伏すると、それに従って幕府方と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujiharu HOSOKAWA, a son of Morouji, fought against the Shogunate side, as Kiyouji, a son of Kazuuji, submitted to Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujiharu HOSOKAWA, the son of Morouji, fought against the shogunate side, as Kiyouji, the son of Kazuuji, surrendered to the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>a→the,Shogunate→shogunate,submitted→surrendered と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujiharu HOSOKAWA, the son of Morouji, fought against the shogunate side, as Kiyouji, the son of Kazuuji, surrendered to the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>子孫は代々淡路国守護。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendant successively filled the post of Shugo of Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendant successively filled the post of Shugo of Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendant successively filled the post of Shugo of Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>将軍直属軍である奉公衆の一番番頭も務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family also served as first head of hokoshu (a military post in Muromachi Shogunate) that was an army immediately under the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>「一番番頭」の意味については推察です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family also served as the first head of hokoshu (a military post in Muromachi Shogunate) that was an army immediately under the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family also served as the first head of hokoshu (a military post in Muromachi Shogunate) that was an army immediately under the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>戦国時代初期に細川尚春が三好之長に滅ぼされ断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was ended in the beginning of Sengoku period, as Hisaharu HOSOKAWA was eliminated by Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was ended in the beginning of the Sengoku Period, as Hisaharu HOSOKAWA was eliminated by Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。period→Period と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was ended in the beginning of the Sengoku Period, as Hisaharu HOSOKAWA was eliminated by Yukinaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>奥州家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oshu family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oshu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oshu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="169">
<j>細川氏の庶流の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a branch family of Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a branch family of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a branch family of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>大外様ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Otozama (the great tozama, or outside Lords).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Otozama (the great tozama, or outside lords).</e>
<cmt>Lords→lords と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Otozama (the great tozama, or outside lords).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>和氏・頼春の従兄弟の細川顕氏の子孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was a descendant of Akiuji HOSOKAWA, who was a male cousin of Kazuuji and Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was a descendant of Akiuji HOSOKAWA, who was a male cousin of Kazuuji and Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was a descendant of Akiuji HOSOKAWA, who was a male cousin of Kazuuji and Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>顕氏の兄弟はそれぞれが武勇に優れ活躍したが、彼等は顕氏に先立ちこの世を去る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiuji&apos;s brothers were excellent in military prowess and did splendid service, but they died before Akiuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiuji&apos;s brothers were excellent in military prowess and did splendid service, but they died before Akiuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiuji&apos;s brothers were excellent in military prowess and did splendid service, but they died before Akiuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>残った顕氏は讃岐、土佐などの領国化に励み実力をつけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained Akiuji devoted himself to territorialize Sanuki and Tosa, and built up power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surviving Akiuji devoted himself to territorialize Sanuki and Tosa, and built up the power.</e>
<cmt>Remained→surviving と修正し。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surviving Akiuji devoted himself to territorialize Sanuki and Tosa, and built up the power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>嫡流の和氏の死後、その弟の頼春と並んで細川氏の実力者となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Kazuuji, the main line, he became a powerful person ranked with Kazuuji&apos;s younger brother, Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Kazuuji of the main line, he became an influential person together with Kazuuji&apos;s younger brother, Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>of を補い修正しました。a powerful→an influential,ranked→together と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Kazuuji of the main line, he became an influential person together with Kazuuji&apos;s younger brother, Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>顕氏は観応の擾乱で活躍するも、やがて頼春と前後して死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiuji made remarkable service in Kanno Disturbance but died around the same time as Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiuji played an active role in the Kanno Disturbance, but died around the same time as Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>made remarkable service→played an active role と修正しました。the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiuji played an active role in the Kanno Disturbance, but died around the same time as Yoriharu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>顕氏の実子の細川繁氏は顕氏の領国を受け継ぎ、有力者として武功を積むも急死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeuji HOSOKAWA, a real son of Akiuji, took over Akiuji&apos;s territory and gained military exploits, but died suddenly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeuji HOSOKAWA, a real son of Akiuji, succeeded Akiuji&apos;s territory and gained the military exploits, but died suddenly.</e>
<cmt>took over→succeeded と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeuji HOSOKAWA, a real son of Akiuji, succeeded Akiuji&apos;s territory and gained the military exploits, but died suddenly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>その後は、和氏の子・細川業氏が後を継いで存続したが、讃岐など領国は頼春の子・頼之に押さえられ、以後は京兆家に従属的な立場となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the family was continued as Nariuji HOSOKAWA, a son of Kazuuji, took over the headship of the family, but territories including Sanuki was taken by Yoriyuki, a son of Yoriharu, and family became subordinate to Keicho family since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the family was continued as Nariuji HOSOKAWA, a son of Kazuuji, succeeded the headship of the family, but the territories including Sanuki was taken by Yoriyuki, the son of Yoriharu, and the family became subordinate to the Keicho family after that.</e>
<cmt>Later→After that,took over→succeeded,a→the,since then→after that と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the family was continued as Nariuji HOSOKAWA, a son of Kazuuji, succeeded the headship of the family, but the territories including Sanuki was taken by Yoriyuki, the son of Yoriharu, and the family became subordinate to the Keicho family after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>しかし、業氏は3代将軍足利義満、業氏の子孫の細川晴経は13代将軍足利義輝の加冠の際の理髪役を務めるなど、有力な幕臣であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the family was a powerful retainer of Shogun, such as Nariuji performed a haircut at kakan (put a crown on a young man&apos;s head on a genpuku ceremony) of the third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and Harutsune HOSOKAWA, a descendant of Nariuji, also performed a haircut at kakan of thirteenth Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the family was a powerful retainer of the shogun, such as Nariuji performed a haircut at the kakan (put a crown on a young man&apos;s head on a genpuku ceremony) of the 3rd Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and Harutsune HOSOKAWA, a descendant of Nariuji, also performed a haircut at the kakan of the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>カンマ, the を補いました。Shogun→the shogun,third→3rd,thirteenth→13th と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the family was a powerful retainer of the shogun, such as Nariuji performed a haircut at the kakan (put a crown on a young man&apos;s head on a genpuku ceremony) of the 3rd Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and Harutsune HOSOKAWA, a descendant of Nariuji, also performed a haircut at the kakan of the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="179">
<j>和泉上守護家の藤孝の子・忠興が戦国時代末期の当主細川輝経の養子となり奥州家を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaoki, a son of Fujitaka of Shugo family of upper Izumi Province, became an adopted child to Terutsune HOSOKAWA, the family head in the end of Sengoku period, and inherited Oshu family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaoki, the son of Fujitaka of the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province, became an adopted child to Terutsune HOSOKAWA, the family head in the end of Sengoku Period, and inherited the Oshu family.</e>
<cmt>a→the,period→Period と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaoki, the son of Fujitaka of the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province, became an adopted child to Terutsune HOSOKAWA, the family head in the end of Sengoku Period, and inherited the Oshu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>細川氏と近世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa clan and modern times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosokawa clan and the modern times</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosokawa clan and the modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>肥後細川家（豊前小倉藩、肥後熊本藩主家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higo Hosokawa family (the Kokura domain, Buzen Province, master&apos;s house of the Kumamoto domain in Higo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higo Hosokawa family (the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province, the master&apos;s house of the Kumamoto Domain in Higo)</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higo Hosokawa family (the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province, the master&apos;s house of the Kumamoto Domain in Higo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="180">
<j>和泉上守護家の出身の細川幽斎（幽斎）は、はじめ室町幕府15代将軍足利義昭を支えたが、のち織田信長に属して姓を長岡と改め、丹後国12万石を領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, Yusai HOSOKAWA (Yusai) from Shugo family of upper Izumi Province supported 15th Shogun of Muromachi bakufu, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA but later he served Nobunaga ODA, changing surname to Nagaoka, and the family possessed 120,000 koku (33360 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, Yusai HOSOKAWA (Yusai) from the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province supported the 15th shogun of the Muromachi bakufu, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, but later he served Nobunaga ODA, changing the surname to Nagaoka, and the family possessed 120,000 koku of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。Shogun→shogun と修正しました。カッコ部分を削除し、「丹後国」を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, Yusai HOSOKAWA (Yusai) from the Shugo family of upper Izumi Province supported the 15th shogun of the Muromachi bakufu, Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, but later he served Nobunaga ODA, changing the surname to Nagaoka, and the family possessed 120,000 koku of Tango Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="181">
<j>長男の細川忠興（三斎）は、紀伊国雑賀攻めで初陣し、信長の部将として活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His eldest son, Tadaoki (Sansai) HOSOKAWA took uijin (first battle) in Saiga of Ki Province attack and did splendid service as busho (commanding officer) of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His first son, Tadaoki (Sansai) HOSOKAWA took uijin (first battle) in the attack of Saiga of Ki Province, and did splendid service as busho (commanding officer) of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>eldest→first,Saiga of Ki Province attack→the attack of Saiga of Ki Province と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His first son, Tadaoki (Sansai) HOSOKAWA took uijin (first battle) in the attack of Saiga of Ki Province, and did splendid service as busho (commanding officer) of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="182">
<j>本能寺の変では、妻・細川ガラシャの父・明智光秀に与せず、豊臣秀吉に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yusai did not follow Mitsuhide AKECHI who was father of his wife, Gracia HOSOKAWA and served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yusai did not follow Mitsuhide AKECHI who was the father of his wife, Garasha HOSOKAWA, and served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。Gracia→Garasha と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yusai did not follow Mitsuhide AKECHI who was the father of his wife, Garasha HOSOKAWA, and served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="183">
<j>幽斎は古今伝授の継承者、忠興は千利休の高弟として、文化面でも重きをなした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yusai and Tadaoki were also influential in cultural field, as Yusai was a successor of Kokin denju (the secret transmissions of the &quot;Kokinshu,&quot; Anthology of Old and New Japanese Poems) and Tadaoki was a high-caliber disciple of SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yusai and Tadaoki were also influential in the cultural field, as Yusai was a successor of Kokin denju (the secret transmissions of the &quot;Kokinshu,&quot; Anthology of Old and New Japanese Poems) and Tadaoki was a high-caliber disciple of SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yusai and Tadaoki were also influential in the cultural field, as Yusai was a successor of Kokin denju (the secret transmissions of the &quot;Kokinshu,&quot; Anthology of Old and New Japanese Poems) and Tadaoki was a high-caliber disciple of SEN no Rikyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="184">
<j>秀吉の死後、徳川家康（東軍）と石田三成（西軍）らの争いが始まると、東軍につき、ガラシャは西軍の人質になることを拒んで自害、幽斎は田辺城_(丹後国)で2ヶ月に及ぶ籠城戦を戦い、忠興は関ヶ原の戦いで活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a battle between Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (the &apos;eastern&apos; army) and Mitsunari ISHIDA (the &apos;western&apos; army) started after the death of Hideyoshi, the family sided with the &apos;eastern&apos; army, there, Gracia committed suicide refusing to be a hostage of the &apos;eastern&apos; army, Yusai fought in a tact of holding the castle at Tanabe-jo Castle (Tango Province) for 2 month and Tadaoki did distinguished service in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the battle between Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (the eastern army) and Mitsunari ISHIDA (the western army) started after the death of Hideyoshi, the family sided with the eastern army, there, Garasha committed suicide refusing to be a hostage of the eastern army, Yusai fought in a siege of Tanabe-jo Castle (Tango Province) for two month and Tadaoki did distinguished service in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを削除しました。Gracia→Garasha,a→the,2→two と修正しました。「篭城戦を戦い」の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the battle between Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (the eastern army) and Mitsunari ISHIDA (the western army) started after the death of Hideyoshi, the family sided with the eastern army, there, Garasha committed suicide refusing to be a hostage of the eastern army, Yusai fought in a siege of Tanabe-jo Castle (Tango Province) for two month and Tadaoki did distinguished service in the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>戦後は細川姓に復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the battle, they changed surname back to Hosokawa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the battle, they changed the surname back to Hosokawa.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the battle, they changed the surname back to Hosokawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>功により豊前国小倉藩39万9千石を経て、忠興の子・3代細川忠利の時代に肥後国熊本藩54万石を領し、幕末まで237年統治。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of distinguished services, the family possessed 399,000 koku (71975.61 cubic meters) in the Kokura domain, Buzen Province and later at generation of Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA, the third and son of Tadaoki, they possessed 540,000 koku (97410.6 cubic meters) in Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province and ruled for 237 years, until the end of Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the distinguished services, the family possessed 399,000 koku in the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province, and later at the generation of Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA, the third and son of Tadaoki, they possessed 540,000 koku in Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province and ruled for 237 years, until the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。カッコ部分を削除しました。domain→Domain,Period→period と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the distinguished services, the family possessed 399,000 koku in the Kokura Domain, Buzen Province, and later at the generation of Tadatoshi HOSOKAWA, the third and son of Tadaoki, they possessed 540,000 koku in Kumamoto Domain, Higo Province and ruled for 237 years, until the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>明治に至り侯爵となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family became a marquis in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family became a marquis in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family became a marquis in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="188">
<j>肥後細川家には藩主一門重臣として長岡内膳家と長岡刑部家があり、支藩としては新田（高瀬）支藩と宇土支藩があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Higo Hosokawa family, there were Nagaoka-naizen family and Nagaoka-Gyobu family as senior vassal of the lord family, and branch clan of Shinden (Takase) and branch clan of Uto as branch domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Higo Hosokawa family, there were the Nagaoka-naizen family and the Nagaoka-Gyobu family as senior vassals of the lord family, and the branch clan of Shinden (Takase) and the branch clan of Uto as branch domains.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。vassal→vassals,domain→domains と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Higo Hosokawa family, there were the Nagaoka-naizen family and the Nagaoka-Gyobu family as senior vassals of the lord family, and the branch clan of Shinden (Takase) and the branch clan of Uto as branch domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>また、上卿三家といわれる世襲家老、松井氏（長岡佐渡、代々八代城3万石の城代）・米田氏（長岡監物）・有吉氏の三家があり、いずれも藤孝時代からの重臣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there were three hereditary karo (the house elder) called the three families of shokei (the top court officials), the Matsui clan (Jodai (the keeper of castle) of Yatsushiro-jo Castle 30,000 koku (5411.7 cubic meters) in Nagaoka, Sado, for generations), the Komeda clan (Nagaoka Kambutsu duty) and the Ariyoshi clan, and all were senior vassals since the time of Fujitaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there were three hereditary karo (chief retainer) called the three families of shokei (the top court officials), the Matsui clan (Jodai [the keeper of castle] of Yatsushiro-jo Castle 30,000 koku in Nagaoka, Sado, for generations), the Komeda clan (Nagaoka Kambutsu duty) and the Ariyoshi clan, and all were senior vassals from the time of Fujitaka.</e>
<cmt>the house elder→chief retainer,since→from,カッコ内を修正し、(5411.7 cubic meters) を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there were three hereditary karo (chief retainer) called the three families of shokei (the top court officials), the Matsui clan (Jodai [the keeper of castle] of Yatsushiro-jo Castle 30,000 koku in Nagaoka, Sado, for generations), the Komeda clan (Nagaoka Kambutsu duty) and the Ariyoshi clan, and all were senior vassals from the time of Fujitaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>なお、常陸谷田部藩は支藩ではなく、独立の藩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitachi Yatabe clan was not a branch clan, but an independent clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hitachi Yatabe Domain was not a branch domain, but an independent domain.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。clan→Domain, domain と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hitachi Yatabe Domain was not a branch domain, but an independent domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="191">
<j>8代細川重賢は、藩校時習館の創設や殖産興業など宝暦の改革と呼ばれる藩政改革を行い「肥後の鳳凰」と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 8th family head, Shigekata HOSOKAWA carried out reformation of domain duties called Horeki Reform, which included the foundation of han school Jishukan and encouragement of new industries, and he was called &apos;a phoenix of Higo&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth family head, Shigekata HOSOKAWA carried out the reformation of domain duties called the Horeki Reform, which included the foundation of han school Jishukan and the encouragement of new industries, and he was called &apos;a phoenix of Higo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。8th→eighth,ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth family head, Shigekata HOSOKAWA carried out the reformation of domain duties called the Horeki Reform, which included the foundation of han school Jishukan and the encouragement of new industries, and he was called &apos;a phoenix of Higo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>出羽国米沢藩の上杉鷹山や紀伊国紀州藩の徳川治貞（紀州の麒麟）とともに江戸時代中期の三名君とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is counted as three wise rulers in the middle of the Edo period along with Yozan UESUGI of Yonezawa Domain, Dewa Province and Harusada TOKUGAWA (Kirin (a mythical Chinese animal) of Kii) in the Kishu Domain, Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is counted as the three wise rulers in the middle of the Edo period along with Yozan UESUGI of Yonezawa Domain, Dewa Province and Harusada TOKUGAWA (Kirin [a mythical Chinese animal] of Kii) of the Kishu Domain, Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。in→of,カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is counted as the three wise rulers in the middle of the Edo period along with Yozan UESUGI of Yonezawa Domain, Dewa Province and Harusada TOKUGAWA (Kirin [a mythical Chinese animal] of Kii) of the Kishu Domain, Kii Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>熊本藩では江戸時代を通じて百姓一揆等が殆ど見られず農民は豊かであったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that peasants were wealthy in Kumamoto domain and peasant&apos;s revolt did not happen throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that those peasants were wealthy in the Kumamoto Domain, and almost no peasants&apos; revolt happened throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>those, the, カンマを補いました。domain→Domain,後半部分を文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that those peasants were wealthy in the Kumamoto Domain, and almost no peasants&apos; revolt happened throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>しかし、藩財政は厳しく、江戸・大坂の大商人からの借金に対しては何度も踏み倒して貧乏細川と嫌われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However finance of the clan was a hard one and they were disliked and called &apos;indigent Hosokawa&apos;, as they repeatedly failed to pay debts to Great Merchants in Edo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the finance of the clan was a hard one and they were disliked and called &apos;indigent Hosokawa,&apos; as they repeatedly failed to pay debts to those great merchants in Edo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>the, those, カンマを補いました。カンマの位置を修正、Great Merchants→great merchants と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the finance of the clan was a hard one and they were disliked and called &apos;indigent Hosokawa,&apos; as they repeatedly failed to pay debts to those great merchants in Edo and Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="195">
<j>国宝保存会会長を務めた16代細川護立は「美術の殿様」といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 16th family head, Moritatsu HOSOKAWA became the chair person of National Treasure Reserve Committee and he was called &apos;a lord of art&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 16th family head, Moritatsu HOSOKAWA became the chair person of the National Treasure Reserve Committee and he was called &apos;the lord of art.&apos;</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。a→the,ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 16th family head, Moritatsu HOSOKAWA became the chair person of the National Treasure Reserve Committee and he was called &apos;the lord of art.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>細川家伝来の多数の美術品や自らの収集品などを収蔵した財団法人永青文庫を開設している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He established Eisei Bunko Foundation that stored many art works passed down in Hosokawa family and his own collections.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He established Eisei Bunko Foundation that stored many art works passed down in the Hosokawa family and his own collections.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He established Eisei Bunko Foundation that stored many art works passed down in the Hosokawa family and his own collections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>近衛文麿の首相秘書官であった17代細川護貞は戦時中政治的活動も行い『細川日記』を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 17th family head, Morisada HOSOKAWA took a post of secretary of the prime minister, Fumimaro KONOE, he also worked in political action during wartime and left &quot;Hosokawa diary&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 17th family head, Morisada HOSOKAWA took a post of secretary of the prime minister, Fumimaro KONOE, he also worked in political action during wartime and left the &quot;Hosokawa diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 17th family head, Morisada HOSOKAWA took a post of secretary of the prime minister, Fumimaro KONOE, he also worked in political action during wartime and left the &quot;Hosokawa diary.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>護貞は美術、華道、茶道の愛好家としても知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morisada is known as fanciers of arts, flower arrangement and Sado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morisada is known as a fancier of arts, flower arrangement and Sado.</e>
<cmt>fanciers→a fancier と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morisada is known as a fancier of arts, flower arrangement and Sado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="199">
<j>護貞の子・18代細川護熙は熊本県知事を務めた後日本新党を結成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Son of Morisada, the 18th family head Morihiro HOSOKAWA, formed Japan New Party after taking a post of the governor of Kumamoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The son of Morisada, the 18th family head Morihiro HOSOKAWA, formed Japan New Party after serving as the governor of Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。taking a post of→serving as と修正しました。ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The son of Morisada, the 18th family head Morihiro HOSOKAWA, formed Japan New Party after serving as the governor of Kumamoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>1993年（平成5年）に内閣総理大臣となり非自民党連立政権を成立させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became prime minister in 1993 and formed non-LDP coalition administration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a prime minister in 1993 and formed the non-LDP coalition administration.</e>
<cmt>a, the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a prime minister in 1993 and formed the non-LDP coalition administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>その弟で近衛家を相続した近衛忠てるは日本赤十字社社長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His younger brother, Tadateru KONOE who inherited Konoe Family was a President of Japanese Red Cross Society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His younger brother, Tadateru KONOE who inherited the Konoe Family, was the president of Japanese Red Cross Society.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。a→the,President→president と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His younger brother, Tadateru KONOE who inherited the Konoe Family, was the president of Japanese Red Cross Society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>細川（長岡）内膳家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa (Nagaoka) naizen family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosokawa (Nagaoka) naizen family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosokawa (Nagaoka) naizen family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="202">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの後、忠興は徳川家との関係を重視し、警戒を解くために嫡男・細川忠隆とその妻・千世（前田利家の娘）の離縁を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the battle of Sekigahara, Tadaoki attached a great deal of importance to relationship with Tokugawa family, therefore he ordered a divorce of his legitimate son Tadataka HOSOKAWA and Tadataka&apos;s wife Chiyo (a daughter of Toshiie MAEDA) to end Tokugawa family&apos;s vigilance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the battle of Sekigahara, Tadaoki considered the importance of the relationship with the Tokugawa family, therefore he ordered a divorce of his legitimate son Tadataka HOSOKAWA and Tadataka&apos;s wife Chiyo (a daughter of Toshiie MAEDA) to end the Tokugawa family&apos;s vigilance.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。attached a great deal of→considered,to→of と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the battle of Sekigahara, Tadaoki considered the importance of the relationship with the Tokugawa family, therefore he ordered a divorce of his legitimate son Tadataka HOSOKAWA and Tadataka&apos;s wife Chiyo (a daughter of Toshiie MAEDA) to end the Tokugawa family&apos;s vigilance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>これに反発した忠隆を廃嫡・勘当、家康に人質として差し出していた三男・内記（忠利）を跡継ぎとし、徳川家への臣従の意思を表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaoki showed a will of vassalage to Tokugawa family by disinherit Tadataka who opposed to the order, and made his third son Naiki (Tadatoshi), who had been presented at Ieyasu as a hostage, a successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaoki showed a will of vassalage to the Tokugawa family by disinherit Tadataka who opposed the order, and made his third son Naiki (Tadatoshi), who had been presented at Ieyasu as a hostage, the successor.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。to を削除しました。a→the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaoki showed a will of vassalage to the Tokugawa family by disinherit Tadataka who opposed the order, and made his third son Naiki (Tadatoshi), who had been presented at Ieyasu as a hostage, the successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="204">
<j>廃嫡された忠隆は、京都で謹慎蟄居して長岡休無と号して祖父・細川幽斎の許に身を寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disinherited Tadataka stayed at his grand father Yusai HOSOKAWA and was at Kinshin Chikkyo (being placed in confinement at home) in Kyoto, naming himself Kyumu NAGAOKA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disinherited Tadataka stayed at his grand father Yusai HOSOKAWA, and was at Kinshin Chikkyo (being placed in confinement at home) in Kyoto, naming himself Kyumu NAGAOKA.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disinherited Tadataka stayed at his grand father Yusai HOSOKAWA, and was at Kinshin Chikkyo (being placed in confinement at home) in Kyoto, naming himself Kyumu NAGAOKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>幽斎死去後には細川家から扶持米3千石が給されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Yusai, 3000 koku (541.17 cubic meters) of Fuchimai (salary rice) was supplied from Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yusai died, 3,000 koku of Fuchimai (salary rice) was supplied from the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>the death of Yusai→Yusai died,3000→3,000 と修正しました。カッコ部分を削除し、the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yusai died, 3,000 koku of Fuchimai (salary rice) was supplied from the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>公家社会と細川家を結ぶ能や茶の湯の数寄者として、京都で余生を過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He spent the rest of his life in Kyoto as a Sukisha (zen philosopher) in Chanoyu (the tea ceremony) and Noh that connected court noble society and Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He spent the rest of his life in Kyoto as a Sukisha (zen philosopher) in Chanoyu (the tea ceremony) and Noh, that connected the court noble society and the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>カンマ、the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He spent the rest of his life in Kyoto as a Sukisha (zen philosopher) in Chanoyu (the tea ceremony) and Noh, that connected the court noble society and the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>後妻・喜久との間に生まれた長岡忠恒・長岡忠春は、休無の死後に細川光尚から肥後熊本に招かれて熊本藩の一門家臣長岡内膳家となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune NAGAOKA and Tadaharu NAGAOKA, who were born between Kyumu and his second wife Kiku, were invited to Kumamoto, Higo by Mitsunao HOSOKAWA after the death of Kyumu and became Nagaoka-naizen family, a vassal of Kumamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune NAGAOKA and Tadaharu NAGAOKA, who were born between Kyumu and his second wife Kiku, were invited to Kumamoto, Higo by Mitsunao HOSOKAWA after the death of Kyumu and became the Nagaoka-naizen family, a vassal of the Kumamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune NAGAOKA and Tadaharu NAGAOKA, who were born between Kyumu and his second wife Kiku, were invited to Kumamoto, Higo by Mitsunao HOSOKAWA after the death of Kyumu and became the Nagaoka-naizen family, a vassal of the Kumamoto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>細川綱利時代に忠春の子・忠重（忠季）が計6千石を継ぎ、子孫は代々一門首座に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the time of Tsunatoshi HOSOKAWA, Tadashige (Tadasue), a son of Tadaharu, took over total of 6000 koku (1082.34 cubic meters) and his descendant successively ranked as head of families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the time of Tsunatoshi HOSOKAWA, Tadashige (Tadasue), the son of Tadaharu, succeeded the total of 6000 koku, and his descendant successively ranked as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>a→the, took over→succeeded,families→family と修正しました。カッコ部分を削除し、the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the time of Tsunatoshi HOSOKAWA, Tadashige (Tadasue), the son of Tadaharu, succeeded the total of 6000 koku, and his descendant successively ranked as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>家紋は五七桐および細川九曜紋のほかに、ガラシャ出自を偲び明智氏の土岐桔梗紋を裏紋とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest was Goshichi no kiri and nine-planet crest of the Hosokawa family, and Toki&apos;s family crest of a stylized Chinese bellflower of Akechi clan was used for the Ura-mon to remember Gracia, the family background.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest was Goshichi no kiri and the nine-planet crest of the Hosokawa family, and Toki&apos;s family crest of a stylized Chinese bellflower of the Akechi clan was used for the Ura-mon to remember Garasha, the family background.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。Gracia→Garasha と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest was Goshichi no kiri and the nine-planet crest of the Hosokawa family, and Toki&apos;s family crest of a stylized Chinese bellflower of the Akechi clan was used for the Ura-mon to remember Garasha, the family background.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>明治時代に細川姓へ復し、男爵を授爵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family changed surname back to Hosokawa in Meiji period and granted a title of baronage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family changed the surname back to Hosokawa in the Meiji period and was granted a title of baronage.</e>
<cmt>the, was を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family changed the surname back to Hosokawa in the Meiji period and was granted a title of baronage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>江戸時代の藩主の御茶屋で、明治時代に細川内膳家が住んだ熊本郊外の砂取邸跡は水前寺江津湖公園の一部（熊本県立図書館庭園）として整備されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sunatori-tei site, which was originally a ochaya (rest house) of the lord in Edo period and where Hosokawa-naizen family lived in Meiji period, in the suburbs of Kumamoto is maintained as a part of Suizenji-Ezuko Park (Kumamoto prefectural library garden).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sunatori-tei site, which was originally an ochaya (rest house) of the lord in the Edo period and where the Hosokawa-naizen family lived in the Meiji period, in the suburbs of Kumamoto is maintained as a part of the Suizenji-Ezuko Park (Kumamoto Prefectural library garden).</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。a→an,prefectural→Prefectural と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sunatori-tei site, which was originally an ochaya (rest house) of the lord in the Edo period and where the Hosokawa-naizen family lived in the Meiji period, in the suburbs of Kumamoto is maintained as a part of the Suizenji-Ezuko Park (Kumamoto Prefectural library garden).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>政治評論家細川隆元とその甥細川隆一郎は内膳家の牧崎分家の出である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryugen HOSOKAWA, a political critic, and his nephew Ryuichiro HOSOKAWA were from a branch family of Makizaki of Naizen family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryugen HOSOKAWA, a political critic, and his nephew Ryuichiro HOSOKAWA were from a branch family of Makizaki of the Naizen family.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryugen HOSOKAWA, a political critic, and his nephew Ryuichiro HOSOKAWA were from a branch family of Makizaki of the Naizen family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>細川（長岡）刑部家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hosokawa (Nagaoka) Gyobu&apos;s family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hosokawa (Nagaoka) Gyobu&apos;s family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hosokawa (Nagaoka) Gyobu&apos;s family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="213">
<j>忠興の五男・細川興孝が2万5千石を与えられて興す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was founded when Okitaka HOSOKAWA, Tadaoki&apos;s fifth son, was given 25,000 koku (4509.75 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was founded when Okitaka HOSOKAWA, Tadaoki&apos;s fifth son, was given 25,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was founded when Okitaka HOSOKAWA, Tadaoki&apos;s fifth son, was given 25,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>代々「長岡刑部」か「長岡図書」を名乗り、家禄1万石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family took name of &apos;Nagaoka-Gyobu family&apos; or &apos;Nagaoka book&apos; for generations and Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 10,000 koku (1803.9 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family took the name of &apos;Nagaoka-Gyobu family&apos; or &apos;Nagaoka book&apos; for generations and the Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>the を補い、カッコ部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family took the name of &apos;Nagaoka-Gyobu family&apos; or &apos;Nagaoka book&apos; for generations and the Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>明治時代に細川姓へ復し、男爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family changed surname back to Hosokawa in Meiji period and granted a title of baronage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family changed the surname back to Hosokawa in the Meiji period and was granted a title of baronage.</e>
<cmt>the, was を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family changed the surname back to Hosokawa in the Meiji period and was granted a title of baronage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>刑部家が熊本郊外の子飼に設けた下屋敷（旧細川刑部邸）は県の重要文化財に指定され、現在は熊本城三の丸に移築・公開されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyobu family&apos;s suburban residence built in Kokai, the suburb of Kumamoto, was designated as the prefectural important cultural property, and presently it has been reconstruct and open to the public at Sannomaru (outer part of the castle) of Kumamoto-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gyobu family&apos;s suburban residence built in Kokai, the suburb of Kumamoto, was designated as the prefectural important cultural property, and presently it has been reconstructed and open to the public at Sannomaru (outer part of the castle) of Kumamoto-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。reconstruct→reconstructed と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gyobu family&apos;s suburban residence built in Kokai, the suburb of Kumamoto, was designated as the prefectural important cultural property, and presently it has been reconstructed and open to the public at Sannomaru (outer part of the castle) of Kumamoto-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>高瀬細川家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takase Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takase Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takase Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="217">
<j>肥後熊本藩の支藩・熊本藩肥後新田藩、のち高瀬藩3万5千石の藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was the lord of Kumamoto domain Higo Shinden domain, a branch domain of Higo Kumamoto domain, and later became the lord of Takase domain with 35,000 koku (6313.65 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>「熊本藩肥後新田藩」の訳については推察です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was the lord of the Higo Shinden Domain of the Kumamoto Domain, a branch domain of the Higo Kumamoto Domain, and later became the lord of the Takase Domain with 35,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。the を補いました。domain→Domain と修正しました。カッコ部分を削除しました。なお、「熊本藩肥後新田藩」の定訳は不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family ruled a branch domain of the Higo Kumamoto Domain known as the Higo Shinden Domain (an area of land that had been newly made into a rice field with a yield of more than 10,000 koku) of the Kumamoto Domain, and later ruled the Takase Domain, which yielded 35,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>細川光尚の子・細川利重から10代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family continued for 10 generations since Toshishige HOSOKAWA, a child of Mitsunao HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was the 10th generation after Toshishige HOSOKAWA, a child of Mitsunao HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>continued for 10 generations→was the 10th generation,since→after と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was the 10th generation after Toshishige HOSOKAWA, a child of Mitsunao HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>江戸鉄砲洲に住み、幕末に肥後高瀬（熊本県玉名市）に移ったため高瀬藩とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family lived in Cannon Sandbar in Edo and moved to Higo, Takase (Tamana City, Kumamoto Prefecture) therefore they are also called as Takase clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family lived in the Cannon Sandbar in Edo and moved to Higo, Takase (Tamana City, Kumamoto Prefecture) in the end of Edo period, therefore they are also called as the Takase clan.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。「幕末に」を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family lived in the Cannon Sandbar in Edo and moved to Higo, Takase (Tamana City, Kumamoto Prefecture) in the end of Edo period, therefore they are also called as the Takase clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>本家6代の細川宣紀は利重の子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 6th family head of head family, Nobunori HOSOKAWA was a son of Toshishige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixth family head of the head family, Nobunori HOSOKAWA was a son of Toshishige.</e>
<cmt>6th→sixth,the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixth family head of the head family, Nobunori HOSOKAWA was a son of Toshishige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>宇土細川家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uto Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uto Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uto Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="221">
<j>肥後熊本藩の支藩・熊本藩宇土藩（熊本県宇土市）3万石の藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was the lord of Kumamoto domain Uto Domain (Kumamoto prefecture Uto city), a branch domain of Higo Kumamoto domain, with 30,000 koku (5411.7 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was the lord of the Uto Domain of the Kumamoto Domain (Uto City, Kumamoto Prefecture), a branch domain of the Higo Kumamoto Domain, with 30,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。Kumamoto Domain Uto Domain→Uto Domain of the Kumamoto Domain,domain→Domain,カッコ内を修正しました。カッコ部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was the lord of the Uto Domain of the Kumamoto Domain (Uto City, Kumamoto Prefecture), a branch domain of the Higo Kumamoto Domain, with 30,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>忠興の四男・細川立孝の子の細川行孝から11代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family continued for 11 generations since Yukitaka HOSOKAWA, a son of Tatsutaka HOSOKAWA who was the fourth son of Tadaoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was the 11th generation after Yukitaka HOSOKAWA, a son of Tatsutaka HOSOKAWA who was the fourth son of Tadaoki.</e>
<cmt>前半部分を文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was the 11th generation after Yukitaka HOSOKAWA, a son of Tatsutaka HOSOKAWA who was the fourth son of Tadaoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>5代細川興文は本藩の細川重賢と協力して藩校温知館の創設や水道による農地灌漑・殖産興業に努めるなど藩政改革を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 5th family head, Okinori HOSOKAWA cooperated with Shigekata HOSOKAWA of Honpan (the original domain) for reformation of domain duties such as the foundation of han school Onchikan, and the farmland Irrigation and encouragement of new industries through a channel.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifth family head, Okinori HOSOKAWA cooperated with Shigekata HOSOKAWA of Honpan (the original domain) for the reformation of domain duties such as the foundation of the han school, Onchikan, and the farmland irrigation and the encouragement of new industries of local productions.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。5th→fifth,Irrigation→irrigation,through a channel→ of local productions と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifth family head, Okinori HOSOKAWA cooperated with Shigekata HOSOKAWA of Honpan (the original domain) for the reformation of domain duties such as the foundation of the han school, Onchikan, and the farmland irrigation and the encouragement of new industries of local productions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>外様支藩主ながら幕府老中任用も議せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though he was the lord of a branch domain of tozama (outsider), his appointment to bakufu roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders) was discussed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The appointment of him to be a bakufu roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders) was discussed, as he was the lord of a branch domain of tozama (outsider).</e>
<cmt>オーダーを変更し、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The appointment of him to be a bakufu roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders) was discussed, as he was the lord of a branch domain of tozama (outsider).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>本家10代の細川斉茲、12代の細川斉護は宇土細川家の出身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 10th family head, Narishige HOSOKAWA and the 12th family head, Narimori HOSOKAWA of head family were both from Uto Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 10th family head, Narishige HOSOKAWA and the 12th family head, Narimori HOSOKAWA of head family were both from the Uto Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 10th family head, Narishige HOSOKAWA and the 12th family head, Narimori HOSOKAWA of head family were both from the Uto Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>常陸谷田部細川家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitachi Yatabe Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitachi Yatabe Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitachi Yatabe Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="226">
<j>常陸国谷田部藩（茨城県つくば市）1万6200石の藩主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was the lord of Hitachi Yatabe domain (Tsukuba City, Ibaraki Prefecture) with 16,000 koku (2922.318 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was the lord of the Yatabe Domain in Hitachi Province (Tsukuba City, Ibaraki Prefecture) with 16,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。「常陸国谷田部藩」を修正しました。カッコ部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was the lord of the Yatabe Domain in Hitachi Province (Tsukuba City, Ibaraki Prefecture) with 16,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>細川藤孝の次子・細川興元より9代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family continued for 9 generations since Okimoto HOSOKAWA, the second child of Fujitaka HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was the ninth generation after Okimoto HOSOKAWA, the second child of Fujitaka HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was the ninth generation after Okimoto HOSOKAWA, the second child of Fujitaka HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>藩祖の興元は細川忠興の弟にあたるが、谷田部藩は熊本藩の支藩ではなく、れっきとした独立の藩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founder of the clan, Okimoto was a younger brother of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, but Yatabe clan was not a branch clan of Kumamoto clan, but it was an independent clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the clan, Okimoto was a younger brother of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, but the Yatabe clan was not a branch clan of the Kumamoto clan, it was an independent clan.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。but を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the clan, Okimoto was a younger brother of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, but the Yatabe clan was not a branch clan of the Kumamoto clan, it was an independent clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Y.Sanada(id:36926), Ittyon(id:1348), Okapia2(id:98589), Nnh(id:474), Pazuzu(id:103079), Reggaeman(id:6214), 888asa88(id:161608), 8888aa8888(id:244382), Charenji(id:7908), Annogoo(id:127074), 陽一(id:92099), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Doskoi 8(id:1070), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Andee(id:20421), Sutou(id:32), Túrelio(id:220515), ブレイズマン(id:183852), GAVVA(id:47103), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), Blowback(id:173308), MizunoH(id:112470), カラジチ(id:109621), こぶまき(id:38278), 寂華(id:83725), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), 伊(id:146699), Yosemite(id:5808), Kouko0515(id:100370), 目白梅(id:141468), Albambot(id:195288), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), Hosokawajun(id:72875), Sat.K(id:3751), Peachkiller(id:99202), Riekanu(id:65656), 小者(id:172526), Kamitani(id:30757), 前田左衛門佐(id:194701), くろくろ(id:60664), Rusk(id:9895), SilvonenBot(id:190970), Yukichin(id:725), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), Wabisabix(id:16770), こいつぅ(id:2105), 故城一片之月(id:109503), トホホ川(id:50502), けんち(id:5147), 編集仁王(id:208160), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>