<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>木寺宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidera no Miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidera no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kideranomiya Family</e>
<cmt>Kideranomiyaとし、Familyを加えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>木寺宮（きでらのみや）は、鎌倉時代から室町時代中期にかけて存続した宮家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidera no Miya is one of Imperial Houses that existed from the Kamakura period through the middle Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidera no Miya was one of Imperial Houses that existed from the Kamakura period through to the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kideranomiya family was one of Imperial Houses that existed from the Kamakura period through to the middle of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>木寺宮の表記を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>常盤井宮家に次いで、世襲親王家の体裁を備えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidera no Miya followed Tokiwai no Miya to establish the system of hereditary house of prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidera no Miya followed Tokiwai no Miya to establish the system of the hereditary household of the prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kideranomiya family followed the Tokiwainomiya family to establish the system of the hereditary household of the prince.</e>
<cmt>The Kideranomiya family, the Tokiwainomiya familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>始祖は後二条天皇の皇子である皇太子邦良親王、初代はその嫡男の康仁親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original forefather is Emperor Go-Nijo&apos;s prince, Prince Kuninaga, and the first generation is his son and heir Prince Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original forefather is Emperor Go-Nijo&apos;s prince, Prince Kuninaga, and the first generation is his son and heir Prince Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original forefather is the Emperor Gonijo&apos;s prince, Imperial Prince Kuninaga, and the first generation is his son and heir Imperial Prince Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt>Go-Nijo→Gonijoとしました。親王→Imperial Princeとしました。&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>宮家号の由来は、邦良親王以下の代々の殿宅が洛西の葛野郡木寺（仁和寺付近）にあったことによるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the title of the imperial house comes from the fact that the house over generations after Prince Kuninaga was located in Kuzono County Kidera Temple (near Ninna-ji Temple) in Rakusei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the title of the imperial household comes from the fact that the house, over generations after Prince Kuninaga, was located in Kuzono County Kidera Temple (near Ninna-ji Temple) in Rakusei.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the title of the imperial household comes from the fact that the house, over generations after Prince Kuninaga, was located in Kuzono County Kidera Temple (near Ninna-ji Temple) in Rakusei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>経済的に衰微した後は、遠江国に移ったともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kidera no Miya declined economically, it is also said that they moved into the Province of Totomi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kidera no Miya declined economically, it is also said that they moved into the Province of Totomi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kideranomiya family declined economically, it is also said that they moved into Totomi Province.</e>
<cmt>the Kideranomiya family, Totomi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;Brief overview&quot; -&gt; &quot;Summary&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後宇多天皇は、孫の邦良親王を大覚寺統の正嫡と定めて御領を譲与し、後醍醐天皇の御領も将来は邦良親王に譲与すること、尊治親王が即位しても一代に限り、その子孫は親王として邦良親王の一流に臣事することを処置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Uda decided that his grandson Prince Kuninaga be the heir of Daikakuji-To Line and transferred the fiefs to him, and ordered that the fiefs of Emperor Go-Daigo should also be transferred to Prince Kuninaga in the future and that even if Prince Takaharu took the throne it would be limited for one generation, and his descendant should be subordinated by the line of Prince Kuninaga, as prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Uda decided that his grandson Prince Kuninaga should be the heir of Daikakuji-To Line and transferred the fiefs to him, and ordered that the fiefs of Emperor Go-Daigo should also be transferred to Prince Kuninaga in the future and that even if Prince Takaharu took the throne it would be limited to one generation, and his descendant should be subordinated by the line of Prince Kuninaga, as prince.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gouda decided that his grandson Imperial Prince Kuninaga should be the heir of Daikakuji-To Line and transferred the fiefs to him, and ordered that the fiefs of Emperor Godaigo should also be transferred to Imperial Prince Kuninaga in the future and that even if Imperial Prince Takaharu took the throne it would be limited to one generation, and his descendant should be subordinated by the line of Prince Kuninaga, as Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>親王→Imperial Princeとしました。天皇名の表記をGo-Uda→Gouda, Go-Daigo→Godaigoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1318年、尊治親王に皇位が移ると（後醍醐天皇）、邦良親王は皇太子に立てられたが、鎌倉幕府との交渉が膠着し、即位することなく薨去した（1326年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1318 when the throne was transferred to Prince Takaharu (Emperor Go-Daigo), Prince Kuninaga was raised as crown prince, but he died without taking the position because the negotiation with the Kamakura Shogunate was stuck.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1318 when the throne was transferred to Prince Takaharu (Emperor Go-Daigo), Prince Kuninaga was raised as crown prince, but he died without taking the position because the negotiation with the Kamakura Shogunate was stalemated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1318 when the throne was transferred to Imperial Prince Takaharu (Emperor Godaigo), Imperial Prince Kuninaga was raised as crown prince, but he died without taking the position because the negotiation with the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was stalemated.</e>
<cmt>親王→Imperial Princeとしました。Go-Daigo→Godaigoに修正しました。鎌倉幕府の表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>次いで邦良親王の子・康仁親王が光厳天皇（持明院統）の皇太子に立てられるが、1333年に鎌倉幕府が滅亡し、後醍醐天皇が隠岐島から京都に還幸すると、光厳天皇の即位は取り消されて、それに伴い康仁親王も皇太子を廃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Prince Kuninaga&apos;s son Prince Yasuhito was raised as crown prince of Emperor Kogen (Jimyoin-To Line), but in 1333 the Kamakura Shogunate was ruined, and when Emperor Go-Daigo returned to Kyoto from Okinoshima island, accession to the throne of Emperor Kogen was cancelled, which also entailed cancellation of Prince Yasuhito becoming the crown prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Prince Kuninaga&apos;s son, Prince Yasuhito, was raised as crown prince of Emperor Kogen (Jimyoin-To Line), but in 1333 the Kamakura Shogunate was ruined, and when Emperor Go-Daigo returned to Kyoto from Okinoshima island, accession to the throne of Emperor Kogen was cancelled, which also entailed cancellation of Prince Yasuhito becoming the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Imperial Prince Kuninaga&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Yasuhito, was raised as crown prince of Emperor Kogon (Jimyoin-To Line), but in 1333 the Kamakura bakufu was ruined, and when Emperor Godaigo returned to Kyoto from Okinoshima island, accession to the throne of Emperor Kogon was cancelled, which also entailed cancellation of Imperial Prince Yasuhito becoming the crown prince.</e>
<cmt>親王→Imperial Prince, Go-Daigo→Godaigo, 鎌倉幕府→Kamakura bakufu (前出のためローマ字表記のみ) としました。光厳天皇の読みの誤りを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>更に、後醍醐天皇は傍流にもかかわらず、自己の子孫による皇統独占に執着し、康仁親王の皇位への道をことごとく閉ざした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in spite of the fact that Emperor Go-Daigo was of the branch line, he sticked to try to occupy the Imperial line by his descendants, and shut the every door of the path to the throne by Prince Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in spite of the fact that Emperor Go-Daigo was of the branch line, he tried to occupy the Imperial line using his descendants, and shut the every door of the path to the throne by Prince Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in spite of the fact that Emperor Godaigo was of the branch line, he tried to occupy the Imperial line using his descendants, and shut the every door of the path to the throne by Imperial Prince Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt>親王→Imperial Prince, Go-Daigo→Godaigoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>大覚寺統の血筋であるはずの木寺宮が持明院統（北朝 (日本)）寄りの立場を取るようになったのは、このためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the reason why Kidera no Miya that should be the blood line of Daikakuji-To Line became to take the position of the Jimyoin-To (Northern Court (Japan)) side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the reason why Kidera no Miya, that should be the blood line of the Daikakuji-To Line came to take the position of the Jimyoin-To (Northern Court - Japan) side.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the reason why the Kideranomiya family, that should be the blood line of the Daikakuji-To Line came to take the position of the Jimyoin-To (Northern Court - Japan) side.</e>
<cmt>the Kideranomiya familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>『康富記』によると、康仁親王の後の木寺宮は、邦恒王 ─ 世平王 ─ 木寺宮邦康親王と3代を経て、室町時代中期まで存続した（邦恒王・世平王は早世したため、親王宣下を受けた記録がない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kofuki,&quot; the Kidera no Miya after Prince Yasuhito continued through three generations, Prince Kunitsune, 世平王, and Prince Kidera no Miya Kuniyasu, and existed till the middle Muromachi period (since Prince Kunitsune and 世平王 died young, there is no record showing that they declared as prince).</e>
<cmt>世平王→定訳不明、該当する読みを見つけることができませんでした</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Kofuki,&quot; the Kidera no Miya after Prince Yasuhito continued through three generations, Prince Kunitsune, 世平王, and Prince Kidera no Miya Kuniyasu, and existed untill the middle the Muromachi period (since Prince Kunitsune and 世平王 died young, there is no record showing that they were declared as prince).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Yasutomi-Ki&quot; (Diaries of Yasutomi NAKAHARA), the Kidera no Miya after Imperial Prince Yasuhito continued through three generations, Prince Kunitsune, 世平王, and Imperial Prince Kidera no Miya Kuniyasu, and existed untill the middle the Muromachi period (since Prince Kunitsune and 世平王 died young, there is no record showing that they were declared as Imperial Prince).</e>
<cmt>『康富記』の読みの誤りを訂正、および補足をいれました。親王→Imperial Princeとしました。余分なスペースを消去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>邦康親王の子には師煕親王（静覚入道親王）などがいるが、一等史料による限り、その後の子孫は確認されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Kuniyasu had sons including Prince 師煕 (Prince Jokaku-nyudo), but as long as excellent historical documents are referred, there is no descendant thereafter confirmed.</e>
<cmt>師煕親王→定訳不明、該当する読みを見つけることができませんでした、　静覚入道→Seikakuji-nyudo→Jokaku-nyudo[ウィキペディアでしか確認できませんでした]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Kuniyasu had sons including Prince 師煕 (Prince Jokaku-nyudo), but as long as excellent historical documents have been referred to, there has been no descendant, thereafter, confirmed.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Kuniyasu had sons including Imperial Prince 師煕 (priestly Imperial Prince Jokaku), but as long as excellent historical documents have been referred to, there has been no descendant, thereafter, confirmed.</e>
<cmt>親王→Imperial Princeとしました。入道親王を統一リストの表現に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>1　2　3　4</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 2 3 4</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 2 3 4</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 2 3 4</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>後二条天皇─邦良親王─康仁親王─邦恒王─世平王─木寺宮邦康親王─師煕親王</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Nijo, Prince Kuninaga, Prince Yasuhito, Prince Kunitsune, 世平王, prince Kidera no Miya Kuniyasu, 師煕親王</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Nijo, Prince Kuninaga, Prince Yasuhito, Prince Kunitsune, 世平王, prince Kidera no Miya Kuniyasu, 師煕親王</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gonijo, Imperial Prince Kuninaga, Imperial Prince Yasuhito, Prince Kunitsune, 世平王, Imperial Prince Kideranomiya Kuniyasu, 師煕親王</e>
<cmt>木寺宮邦康親王→Imperial Prince Kideranomiya Kuniyasuとしました。Emperor Go-Nijoのハイフンをとりました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>遠江国下向と子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Going away from metropolis to the Province of Totomi and descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Going away from metropolis to the Province of Totomi and descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Going away from metropolis to Totomi Province and descendants</e>
<cmt>Totomi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>先の康仁親王については、南朝 (日本)方荘園の遠江国入野（静岡県浜松市）に下向してを興し、そこに落ち着いたという伝承があって、親王の屋敷跡・墓所・真影とされるものが同寺内に伝存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the above-mentioned Prince Yasuhito, there is a tradition that he move from the metropolis to Irino, the Province of Totomi (Hamamatsu City, Shizuoka Prefecture), which was a private estate of the Southern Court (Japan), and settled there, and in a temple there there are the site of prince&apos;s residence, grave, true portrait.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the above-mentioned Prince Yasuhito, there is a tradition that he move from the metropolis to Irino, the Province of Totomi (Hamamatsu City, Shizuoka Prefecture), which was a private estate of the Southern Court (Japan), and settled there, and in a temple there there is the site of the prince&apos;s residence, his grave, and a true portrait.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the above-mentioned Imperial Prince Yasuhito, there is a tradition that he move from the metropolis to Irino, Totomi Province (Hamamatsu City, Shizuoka Prefecture), which was a private estate of the Southern Court (Japan), and settled there, and in a temple there there is the site of the prince&apos;s residence, his grave, and a true portrait.</e>
<cmt>Totomi Provinceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>親王が京都付近で没したことは『園太暦』に見えているので、伝承そのものには疑問があるが、少なくとも子孫の木寺宮が入野に下向した事実はあったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it is known from &quot;Entairyaku&quot; that the prince died near Kyoto, there remain some doubts about the tradition itself, but at least there seemed to exist the fact that the descendant of Kidera no Miya moved into Irino.</e>
<cmt>園太暦→Entaireki→Entairyaku[デジタル大辞泉]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it is known from &quot;Entairyaku&quot; that the prince died near Kyoto, there remain some doubts about the tradition itself, but at least there seemed to exist the fact that the descendant of Kidera no Miya moved into Irino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it is known from &quot;Entairyaku&quot; (Diary of Kinkata TOIN) that the prince died near Kyoto, there remain some doubts about the tradition itself, but at least there seemed to exist the fact that the descendant of the Kideranomiya family moved into Irino.</e>
<cmt>『園太暦』の補足を入れました。the Kideranomiya familyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その時期は、中央の記録から消えた邦康親王以降ということになろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering when, it can be said that it occurred after Prince Kuniyasu, which should not exist in the record of the central government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering when, it can be said that it occurred after Prince Kuniyasu, which should not exist in the record of the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering when, it can be said that it occurred after Imperial Prince Kuniyasu, which should not exist in the record of the central government.</e>
<cmt>親王→Imperial Princeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ただし、これらを具体的に裏付けるような史料はまだ見つかっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is no historical documents that specifically supports the fact yet to be found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, historical documents that specifically support that fact, have yet to be found.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, historical documents that specifically support that fact, have yet to be found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>『龍雲寺文書』によれば、永禄～天正の頃、当寺に「大宮様」が住んでいたが、武田氏方の軍役を務めていたため、徳川家康に攻められ、寺を焼いて信州に逃走している（1580年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Ryoun-ji Temple documents,&quot; during the period of Eiroku to Tensho, there lived &quot;Omiyasama&quot; in the temple, but because he was envolved in the position of military service of the Takeda clan side, he was attacked by Ieyasu Tokugawa, and the temple was burnt, which made him escape to Shinshu (1580).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Ryoun-ji Temple documents,&quot; during the period of Eiroku to Tensho, &quot;Omiyasama&quot; lived in the temple, but because he was envolved in the position of military service of the Takeda clan side, he was attacked by Ieyasu Tokugawa, and the temple was burnt down, which forced him to escape to Shinshu (1580).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Ryoun-ji Temple documents,&quot; during the period of Eiroku to Tensho, &apos;Omiyasama&apos; lived in the temple, but because he was envolved in the position of military service of the Takeda clan side, he was attacked by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and the temple was burnt down, which forced him to escape to Shinshu (1580).</e>
<cmt>一部シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。Tokugawa→TOKUGAWAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>「大宮様」とは赤津中務少輔のことで、木寺宮（康仁親王）8世との寺伝がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a temple tradition that the &quot;Omiyasama&quot; was the eighth generation Akatsu-nakatsukasa sho and Kidera no Miya (Prince Yasuhito).</e>
<cmt>少輔→shoni→sho[デジタル大辞泉、ご確認ください]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a temple tradition that the &quot;Omiyasama&quot; was the eighth generation Akatsu-nakatsukasa sho and Kidera no Miya (Prince Yasuhito).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a temple tradition that the &apos;Omiyasama&apos; was Akatsu-nakatsukasa sho, the eighth generation of the Kideranomiya family (Imperial Prince Yasuhito).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。親王→Imperial Prince、木寺宮→the Kideranomiya familyとし、文章を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>実際に皇族の子孫などであった可能性は高いが、その詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is high possibility that that person was the descendant of the imperial family, but the details are not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is high possibility that that person was the descendant of the imperial family, but the details are not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is high possibility that that person was the descendant of the imperial family, but the details are not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>なお、『寛政譜』に大沢基宿の母や知久頼氏の妻の出自と伝える「木寺宮」はこの一族かと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, it is considered that &quot;Kidera no Miya&quot; that was transmitted to be the origins of mother of Motoie OSAWA and a wife of Yoriuji CHIKU in &quot;Kanseifu&quot; is this family.</e>
<cmt>大沢基宿→Motosuku OSAWA→Motoie OSAWA[wikipediaでしか探すことができませんでした。ご確認ください]、　知久頼氏→読み方わかりませんでした</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, it is considered that &quot;Kidera no Miya,&quot; that was transmitted to be the origins of the mother of Motoie OSAWA and the wife of Yoriuji CHIKU in &quot;Kanseifu,&quot; is this family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, it is considered that &apos;Kideranomiya&apos;, that was transmitted to be the origins of the mother of Motoie OSAWA and the wife of Yoriuji CHIKU in &quot;Kanseifu&quot;(genealogies of vassals in Edo Bakufu), is this family.</e>
<cmt>Kideranomiya&apos;とし、カンマの位置を変更しました。『寛政譜』の補足を入れ、カンマの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>地方に下った宮家の例としては他に五辻宮が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for an example of the Imperial Houses that moved into the local region, there is Gotsuji no Miya other than that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for an example of the Imperial Houses that moved into the local region, there is Gotsuji no Miya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for an example of the Imperial Houses that moved into the local region, there is Gotsuji no Miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), 可怜(id:206074), 水野白楓(id:22811), Dojo(id:32472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>