<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>園家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sono family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sono family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sono Family</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>園家（そのけ）は、日本の氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sono family was a Japanese shizoku (clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sono family was a shizoku clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sono family was a shizoku clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>公家・華族の家柄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family status was kuge (court noble) and peerage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family status was kuge (court noble) and peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family status was kuge (court noble) and peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>公家としての家格は羽林家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family status as a kuge was urinke (the fourth highest family status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family status as a kuge was urinke (the fourth highest family status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family status as a kuge was urinke (the fourth highest family status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>華族としての家格は伯爵家だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family status as a peerage was count.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family status as a peerage was count.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family status as a peerage was count.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原北家持明院家の庶家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Branch family of the Jimyoin family of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were a branch of the Jimyoin family of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were a branch of the Jimyoin family of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>家業は雅楽、神楽（琵琶）、華道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family businesses were gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), ancient Shinto music and dancing (biwa (Japanese lute)) and flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family businesses were gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), ancient Shinto music and dancing (biwa - Japanese lute) and flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family businesses were gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music), ancient Shinto music and dancing (biwa - Japanese lute) and flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>生花は青山流（青山御流、園家御家流、青山御家御流とも）宗家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to flower arrangement, it was the head of Seizan school (also, Seizan goryu, Sonoke oieryu and Seizan oiegoryu).</e>
<cmt>「流派名」の正しい読みは不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were the head of Seizan school of flower arrangement (also, Seizan goryu, Sonoke oieryu, and Seizan oiegoryu).</e>
<cmt>gramamr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were the head of Seizan school of flower arrangement (also, Seizan goryu, Sonoke oieryu, and Seizan oiegoryu).</e>
<cmt>全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>家紋は、杏葉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its family crest is kyoyo (trapping).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest was kyoyo (trapping).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its kamon (family crest) is kyoyo (trapping).</e>
<cmt>The family crest was→Its kamon (family crest) is</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>藤原北家藤原道長の二男、右大臣藤原頼宗の子孫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga of the Northern House of Fujiwara clan, descendant of FUJIWARA no Yorimune, udaijin (minister of the right)</e>
<cmt>意味不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga of the Northern House of Fujiwara clan was a descendant of FUJIWARA no Yorimune, udaijin (minister of the right)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga of the Northern House of Fujiwara clan was a descendant of FUJIWARA no Yorimune, Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足udaijin (minister of the right)→Udaijin (Minister of the Right)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉時代持明院基家の三男参議園基氏によって創設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was founded in the Kamakura Period by Motouji SONO, sangi (councilor), who was the third son of Motoie JIMYOIN.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sono family was founded in the Kamakura Period by Motouji SONO, sangi (councilor), the third son of Motoie JIMYOIN.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sono family was founded in the Kamakura period by Motouji SONO, sangi (councilor), the third son of Motoie JIMYOIN.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>基氏は後堀河天皇に仕え、後堀河天皇崩御後、仏に供花したことを機縁とし、挿花を能くし生花青山流の基礎を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motouji served the Emperor Gohorikawa and after the death of the Emperor Gohorikawa, starting from offering flowers to Buddha, he learned and became good at flower arrangement and established the foundation of Seizan school flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>「青山流」の正しい読みは不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motouji served Emperor Gohorikawa and after the death of the Emperor, starting from offering flowers to Buddha, he learned and became good at flower arrangement and established the foundation of the Seizan school of flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motouji served Emperor Gohorikawa and after the death of the Emperor, starting from offering flowers to Buddha, he learned and became good at flower arrangement and established the foundation of the Seizan school of flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>室町時代の園基秀の時に、後花園天皇より「青山」の号を賜る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Motohide SONO was the family head in the Muromachi Period, the Emperor Gohanazono donated him the name &quot;Seizan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「青山」の正しい読みは不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Motohide SONO was the family head during the Muromachi Period, Emperor Gohanazono granted him the name &quot;Seizan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Motohide SONO was the family head during the Muromachi period, Emperor Gohanazono granted him the name &apos;Seizan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語統一&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は186石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was 186 koku (approx. 65.1cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karoku (hereditary stipend) during the Edo Period was 186 koku (approx. 65.1cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) during the Edo period was 186 koku (approx. 65.1 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代前期の当主園基任・園基音親子はいずれも娘（壬生院・新広義門院）を後水尾天皇の後宮に入れており、それぞれ後光明天皇と霊元天皇両天皇を出産した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family heads in the beginning of the Edo Period, Mototo SONO and his son Motonari SONO sent their daughters (Mibuin and Shinkogimonin) to the Emperor Gomizunoo&apos;s kokyu (empress&apos;s residence) and the daughters gave birth to the Emperor Gokomyo and the Emperor Reigen respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family heads during the beginning of the Edo Period, Mototo SONO and his son Motonari SONO sent their daughters (Mibuin and Shinkogimonin) to the Emperor Gomizunoo&apos;s kokyu (empress&apos;s residence) and the daughters gave birth to Emperor Gokomyo and Emperor Reigen respectively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family heads during the beginning of the Edo period, Mototo SONO and his son Motonari SONO sent their daughters (Mibuin and Shinkogimonin) to the Emperor Gomizunoo&apos;s kokyu (empress&apos;s residence) and the daughters gave birth to Emperor Gokomyo and Emperor Reigen respectively.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>天皇の外祖父の地位を得て園家は宮中に隠然たる力を持つにいたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obtaining the position of maternal grandfather of the emperor, the Sono family acquired latent power in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Holding the position of maternal grandfather of the emperor, the Sono family acquired latent power in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Holding the position of maternal grandfather of the emperor, the Sono family acquired latent power in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>基任と基音の二人には左大臣が追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) was conferred posthumously on both Mototo and Motonari</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) was conferred posthumously to both Mototo and Motonari</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) was conferred posthumously to both Mototo and Motonari.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>さらに基音の子である園基福（霊元天皇の叔父にあたる）は羽林家としては異例の准大臣に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Jun-daijin (Vice Minister) was conferred on Motoyoshi SONO (an uncle of the Emperor Reigen) that was quite exceptional for urinke.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Jun-daijin (Vice Minister) was conferred to Motoyoshi SONO (an uncle of Emperor Reigen) that was quite exceptional for urinke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Jun-daijin (Vice Minister) was conferred to Motoyoshi SONO (an uncle of Emperor Reigen) that was quite exceptional for urinke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>またそれ以降の当主についても早世したもの以外は全員が大納言となる（それまでの園家は中納言が極官だった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of family heads other than those passed away young were appointed to Dainagon (Before that, kyokkan for the Sono family was Chunagon).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All family heads other than those that passed away young were appointed to Dainagon (Before that, kyokkan for the Sono family was Chunagon).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All family heads other than those that passed away young were appointed to Dainagon (Before that, kyokkan for the Sono family was Chunagon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>江戸時代後期の当主園基衡（園基持）は華道に精進し、「活花手引」を著した事で知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohira SONO (Motomochi SONO)who was the family head in the latter part of the Edo Period devoted himself to kado (flower arrangement) and he is known for his book &quot;Ikebana Tebiki (literally,guide on flower arrangement).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohira SONO (Motomochi SONO)the family head during the latter part of the Edo Period devoted himself to kado (flower arrangement) and he is known for his book &quot;Ikebana Tebiki (literally, guide on flower arrangement).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohira SONO (Motomochi SONO)the family head during the latter part of the Edo period devoted himself to kado (flower arrangement) and he is known for his book &quot;Ikebana Tebiki&quot; (literally, guide on flower arrangement).</e>
<cmt>用語統一&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>幕末、明治維新期の園基祥は、安政勤王八十八廷臣の一人として国事に奔走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motosachi SONO, in the peirod of the end of the Edo Period and Meiji Restoration, devoted himself to the interest of the nation as one of Ansei kinno eighty-eight teishin (Eighty-eight court nobles who protested the U.S.-Japan Treaty of Amity and Commerce in the Ansei era),</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motosachi SONO, near the end of the Edo Period and the Meiji Restoration, devoted himself to the interest of the nation as one of the Ansei kinno eighty-eight teishin (Eighty-eight court nobles who protested the U.S.-Japan Treaty of Amity and Commerce during the Ansei era),</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motosachi SONO, near the end of the Edo period and the Meiji Restoration, devoted himself to the interest of the nation as one of the Ansei kinno eighty-eight teishin (Eighty-eight court nobles who protested the U.S.-Japan Treaty of Amity and Commerce during the Ansei era).</e>
<cmt>全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>維新後明治17年（1885年）7月8日に伯爵位を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration on July 8, 1885, the peerage of count was conferred on him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, on July 8, 1885, the peerage of count was conferred upon him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, on July 8, 1885, the peerage of count was conferred upon him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>明治天皇に典侍として仕えた園祥子は基祥の二女で、天皇との間に猷仁親王、輝仁親王、静子内親王、恒久王妃昌子内親王（竹田宮恒久王妃）、房子内親王（北白川宮成久王妃）、允子内親王（朝香宮鳩彦王妃）、聡子内親王（東久邇宮稔彦王妃）、多喜子内親王の皇子女を儲けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sachiko SONO who served the Emperor Meiji as a tenji (a court lady of the first rank) was the second daughter of Motosachi and gave birth with the Emperor to Imperial Prince Michihito, Imperial Prince Teruhito, Imperial Princess ShizukoImperial Princess Shizuko, Imperial Princess Masako who married Prince Takedanomiya Tsunehisa, Imperial Princess Fusako who married Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Naruhisa, Imperial Princess Nobuko who married Prince Asakanomiya Yasuhiko, Imperial Princess Toshiko who married Prince Higashikuninomiya Naruhiko and Imperial Princess Takiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sachiko SONO who served Emperor Meiji as a tenji (a court lady of the first rank) was the second daughter of Motosachi and she gave birth to Imperial Prince Michihito, Imperial Prince Teruhito, Imperial Princess ShizukoImperial Princess Shizuko, Imperial Princess Masako who married Prince Takedanomiya Tsunehisa, Imperial Princess Fusako who married Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Naruhisa, Imperial Princess Nobuko who married Prince Asakanomiya Yasuhiko, Imperial Princess Toshiko who married Prince Higashikuninomiya Naruhiko, and Imperial Princess Takiko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sachiko SONO who served Emperor Meiji as a tenji (a court lady of the first rank) was the second daughter of Motosachi and she gave birth to Imperial Prince Michihito, Imperial Prince Teruhito, Imperial Princess Shizuko, Imperial Princess Masako who married Prince Takedanomiya Tsunehisa, Imperial Princess Fusako who married Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Naruhisa, Imperial Princess Nobuko who married Prince Asakanomiya Yasuhiko, Imperial Princess Toshiko who married Prince Higashikuninomiya Naruhiko, and Imperial Princess Takiko.</e>
<cmt>重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>園基信は華道家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motonobu SONO was an expert on flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motonobu SONO was an expert on flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motonobu SONO was an expert on flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>青山流第28代家元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the twenty-eighth head of the Seizan school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the twenty-eighth head of the Seizan school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the twenty-eighth head of the Seizan school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>著書に「青山御流・活花手引種」、「青山いけばな」などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Seizan Goryu/Ikebana Tebikigushu (Guide on flower arrangement of Seizan Goryu School),&quot; &quot;Seizan Ikebana&quot; as and so on.</e>
<cmt>書名の正しい読みは不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wrote &quot;Seizan Goryu/Ikebana Tebikigushu (Guide on flower arrangement of Seizan Goryu School),&quot; &quot;Seizan Ikebana.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wrote &quot;Seizan Goryu/Ikebana Tebikigushu&quot; (Guide on flower arrangement of Seizan Goryu School), &quot;Seizan Ikebana.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>系譜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genealogy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Gimbrow(id:65660), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>