<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>正親町三条家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ogimachisanjo Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogimachisanjo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogimachisanjo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>正親町三条家（おおぎまちさんじょうけ・正親町三條家）は、藤原氏藤原北家閑院流の三条家の分家で、大臣家の家格を有する公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ogimachisanjo family was a branch family of the Sanjo family which was the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan of the Kan-in Line, being a family of court noble with their social standing being the house of minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogimachisanjo family was a branch family of the Sanjo family which was the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan of the Kan-in Line, being a family of court nobles with their social standing being the house of the minister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogimachisanjo family was a branch family of the Sanjo family which was the Kan-in Line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, being a family of court nobles with their social standing being the house of minister.</e>
<cmt>the house of the minister→the house of minister the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan of the Kan-in Line→the Kan-in Line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また家祖の公氏は、嵯峨とも西郊とも称したので、この家の、別称を嵯峨という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the founder of the family Kinuji OGIMACHISANJO also referred himself as to SAGA and SAIKO, this family was also known as SAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the founder of the family, Kinuji OGIMACHISANJO also referred himself as SAGA and SAIKO, this family was also known as SAGA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the founder of the family, Kinuji OGIMACHISANJO also referred himself as SAGA and SAIKO, this family was also known as SAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この家の分家である三条西家もまた大臣家の家格を有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjonishi family, their branch family, also had a social standing of the house of minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjonishi family, their branch family, also had the social standing of the house of the minister.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjonishi family, their branch family, also had the social standing of the house of minister.</e>
<cmt>the house of the minister→the house of minister</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>三条実房の次男三条公氏を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder was Kinuji SANJO, the second son of Sanefusa SANJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder was Kinuji SANJO, the second son of Sanefusa SANJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder was Kinuji SANJO, the second son of Sanefusa SANJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>4代目正親町三条実躬までは大納言が極位極官であったが、5代目正親町三条公秀の娘で北朝光厳天皇の典侍であった藤原秀子（陽禄門院）が、崇光天皇、後光厳天皇を産み、天皇の外戚になったため、大臣家となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to the time of the fourth family head Sanemi OGIMACHISANJO, as Dainagon (chief councilor of state) was the highest court rank or government post available, the OGIMACHISANJO family, having become the maternal relative of the Emperor, with FUJIWARA no Hideko (Yorokumon-in), who was the daughter of the fifth family head Kinhide OGIMACHISANJO and Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) to Emperor Kogen of the Northern Court producing Emperor Suko and Emperor Gokogon, was made the house of minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up to the time of the fourth family head Sanemi OGIMACHISANJO, as Dainagon (chief councilor of state) was the highest court rank or government post available, the OGIMACHISANJO family, having become the maternal relative of the Emperor, with FUJIWARA no Hideko (Yorokumon-in), who was the daughter of the fifth family head Kinhide OGIMACHISANJO and Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) to Emperor Kogen of the Northern Court producing Emperor Suko and Emperor Gokogon, was made the house of the minister.</e>
<cmt>gramamr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up to the time of the fourth family head Sanemi OGIMACHISANJO, as Dainagon (chief councilor of state) was the highest court rank or government post available, the OGIMACHISANJO family, having become the maternal relative of the Emperor, with FUJIWARA no Hideko (Yorokumon-in), who was the daughter of the fifth family head Kinhide OGIMACHISANJO and Naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank) to Emperor Kogen of the Northern Court producing Emperor Suko and Emperor Gokogon, was made the house of minister.</e>
<cmt>the house of the minister→the house of minister</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸時代の禄高は350石余。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rokudaka (stipend) for the OGIMACHISANJO family was approximately 350 koku in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rokudaka (stipend) for the OGIMACHISANJO family was approximately 350 koku during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rokudaka (stipend) for the OGIMACHISANJO family was approximately 350 koku during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>明治維新後は、侯爵（はじめ伯爵）を授爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the family was granted the title of Marquis (following the initial title of Count).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the family was granted the title of Marquis (following the initial title of Count).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the family was granted the title of Marquis (following the initial title of Count).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>正親町三条実愛は、三条家の三条実美との区別のために、それまで別称であった嵯峨（さが）に改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To distinguish from Sanetomi SANJO of the Sanjo family, Sanenaru Ogimachi-SANJO changed his surname to SAGA which had previously been used as the alias.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To distinguish them from Sanetomi SANJO of the Sanjo family, Sanenaru Ogimachi-SANJO changed his surname to SAGA which had previously been used as an alias.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To distinguish them from Sanetomi SANJO of the Sanjo family, Sanenaru Ogimachi-SANJO changed his surname to SAGA which had previously been used as an alias.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>29代嵯峨実勝の長女　嵯峨浩は中国清朝の皇帝愛新覚羅溥儀の皇弟愛新覚羅溥傑と日本国のために国際結婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiro SAGA, the oldest daughter of the 29th head of the Saga family Saneto SAGA, married Fuketsu AISHINKAKURA who was the brother of Emperor Fugi AISHINKAKURA of the Qing Dynasty for the good of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiro SAGA, the oldest daughter of the twenty-nineth head of the Saga family Saneto SAGA, married Fuketsu AISHINKAKURA who was the brother of Emperor Fugi AISHINKAKURA of the Qing Dynasty for the good of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiro SAGA, the oldest daughter of the twenty-nineth head of the Saga family Saneto SAGA, married Fuketsu AISHINKAKURA who was the brother of Emperor Fugi AISHINKAKURA of the Qing Dynasty for the good of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、「おおぎまちさんじょう」は日本の名字では最も長い物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OGIMACHISANJO was the longest surname in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OGIMACHISANJO was the longest surname in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OGIMACHISANJO was the longest surname in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Gimbrow(id:65660), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Kaba(id:17904), 水野白楓(id:22811), 松茸(id:27535), ぎぼうし(id:139427), Point136(id:211299), Jay Phillippe(id:229305), 総州之毛豆(id:26880), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>