<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>安倍氏 (奥州)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Abe clan (Oshu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Abe clan (Oshu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Abe clan (Oshu)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>安倍氏（あべ し）は平安時代の陸奥国（後の陸中国）の豪族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Abe clan was a Gozoku (local ruling family) in Mutsu Province (later Rikuchu Province, and Oshu is another name of Mutsu Province) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Abe clan was a Gozoku (local ruling family) in Mutsu Province (later Rikuchu Province, and Oshu is another name of Mutsu Province) who lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一の「レビュー結果」（2009/7/31）に従い、lived in theの部分を who lived duringに修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Abe clan was a Gozoku (local ruling family) in Mutsu Province (later Rikuchu Province, and Oshu is another name of Mutsu Province) who lived during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roots</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roots</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>そのルーツは明らかでなく、『平泉雑記』が伝える安倍氏自身の家伝によれば、神武天皇に殺された畿内の王長脛彦の兄安日彦をその始祖とし、安日彦の津軽亡命をもって安倍氏の発祥としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roots of the Abe clan have not been clarified yet, but according to the family tradition of the Abe clan itself passed down by the &quot;Hiraizumi Zakki&quot; (Miscellaneous notes on Hiraizumi), they thought that the earliest ancestor of the Abe clan was Abihiko, the older brother of Nagasunehiko, the king of the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) who had been killed by Emperor Jinmu, and that the origin of the Abe clan was Abihiko&apos;s exile to Tsugaru.</e>
<cmt>Excel原稿の「平泉雑記」をWeb原稿に合わせて「『平泉雑記』」に訂正しました（『』で囲んで資料扱いにしました）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roots of the Abe clan have not been clarified, but according to the family tradition that the Abe clan passed down in the &quot;Hiraizumi Zakki&quot; (Miscellaneous notes on Hiraizumi), their earliest ancestor was Abihiko, the older brother of Nagasunehiko, the king of the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) who had been killed by Emperor Jinmu, and the Abe clan originated when Abihiko fled to Tsugaru.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、部分的に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The roots of the Abe clan have not been clarified, but according to the family tradition that the Abe clan passed down in the &quot;Hiraizumi Zakki&quot; (Miscellaneous notes on Hiraizumi), their earliest ancestor was Abihiko, the older brother of Nagasunehiko, the king of the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) who had been killed by Emperor Jinmu, and the Abe clan originated when Abihiko fled to Tsugaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>安藤系図、藤崎系図にも同様の記述が見られ、真偽は別にして安倍氏の後裔はそのような自己意識を持っていたことは確かである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The similar description can be found in the Ando genealogy and the Fujisaki genealogy, so, true or not, it is certain that the descendants of the Abe clan had such consciousness of themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar descriptions can be found in the Ando and the Fujisaki genealogy; therefore, apart from ascertaining facts, it is for certain that the descendants of the Abe clan identified themselves in such a way.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar descriptions can be found in the Ando and the Fujisaki genealogy; therefore, apart from ascertaining facts, it is for certain that the descendants of the Abe clan identified themselves in such a way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>後世の研究では、秋田の蝦夷の帰順を得た阿倍比羅夫（藤崎系図）に起源をもとめたり、蝦夷をアイヌの祖先と同一視する立場からabeをapeと読み替えて完全な土着の先住民とみる説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The studies of later years have also presented an opinion that the origin of the Abe clan could be sought through ABE no Hirafu (the Fujisaki genealogy) who forced the Ezo (natives in the northern districts of Japan) in Akita into submission, or another opinion that the Abe clan could be seen as the perfectly native aborigines by changing the reading of the name from &quot;abe&quot; to &quot;ape&quot; from the standpoint of identifying the Ezo with the ancestors of the Ainu tribe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Studies in the later years have also presented with opinions that the origin of the Abe clan could be sought through ABE no Hirafu (the Fujisaki genealogy) who forced the Ezo (natives in the northern districts of Japan) in Akita into submission; or by changing the reading of the name from &quot;abe&quot; to &quot;ape&quot; from the standpoint of identifying the Ezo with the ancestors of the Ainu tribe, the Abe clan could be seen as completely indigenous.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、部分的に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Studies in the later years have also presented with opinions that the origin of the Abe clan could be sought through ABE no Hirafu (the Fujisaki genealogy) who forced the Ezo (natives in the northern districts of Japan) in Akita into submission; or by changing the reading of the name from &quot;abe&quot; to &quot;ape&quot; from the standpoint of identifying the Ezo with the ancestors of the Ainu tribe, the Abe clan could be seen as completely indigenous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>あるいは奥州に下った中央官人の安倍氏のいずれかが任地で子孫を残したとも、朝廷に従った蝦夷（俘囚）とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Alternatively, it is also said that anyone of the Abe clan who was a central government official and came down to Oshu left his descendants at his place of appointment, or that the Ezo (Fushu [barbarians]) who had submitted themselves to the Imperial Court were the ancestors of the Abe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In turn, it is also said that any one of the Abe clan who was a central government official, came down to Oshu and left his offspring at the place of his post, or that the Ezo (Fushu [barbarians]) who had submitted themselves to the Imperial Court were the ancestors of the Abe clan.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、部分的に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In turn, it is also said that any one of the Abe clan who was a central government official, came down to Oshu and left his offspring at the place of his post, or that the Ezo (Fushu [barbarians]) who had submitted themselves to the Imperial Court were the ancestors of the Abe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>「俘囚長」を巡る議論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discussion about &quot;Chief of Fushu&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discussion on &quot;Chief of Fushu&quot;</e>
<cmt>aboutよりonが、より原文の意味に近いと考え修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discussion on &quot;Chief of Fushu&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>安倍氏は俘囚長(俘囚の中から大和朝廷の権力によって選出された有力者）であったとの説が広く流布しているが、文献上では安倍氏を俘囚長とする記述は存在しておらず、康平7年の太政官符に「故俘囚首安倍頼時」との記載があるのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the opinion has been circulated widely that the Abe clan was the Chief of Fushu (chief of barbarians, that is, the influential persons who had been selected from Fushu by the authority of the Yamato Imperial Court), there is not a description that says the Abe clan was the Chief of Fushu in the documents, except for an only description that says &quot;the late Chief of Fushu ABE no Yoritoki&quot; in Dajokanpu (official documents issued by Dajokan, Grand Council of State) in 1064.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the opinion that the Abe clan was the Chief of Fushu (chief of barbarians, that is, the influential persons who had been selected from Fushu by the authority of the Yamato Imperial Court) is widely disseminating, there are no descriptions in documents stating the Abe clan to be the Chief of Fushu, with the exception of a description, &quot;the late Chief of Fushu ABE no Yoritoki,&quot; in Dajokanpu (official documents issued by Dajokan, Grand Council of State) in 1064.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、部分的に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the opinion that the Abe clan was the Chief of Fushu (chief of barbarians, that is, the influential persons who had been selected from Fushu by the authority of the Yamato Imperial Court) is widely disseminating, there are no descriptions in documents stating the Abe clan to be the Chief of Fushu, with the exception of a description, &quot;the late Chief of Fushu ABE no Yoritoki,&quot; in Dajokanpu (official documents issued by Dajokan, Grand Council of State) in 1064.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>軍事貴族としての安倍氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Abe Clan as Military Aristocracy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Abe Clan as Military Aristocracy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Abe Clan as Military Aristocracy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>従来、安倍氏を東北地方の在地の土豪と捉え、前九年の役を中央による辺境支配への反乱と見る解釈が主流であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been the main current until now to recognize the Abe clan as a local Dogo (powerful family) in the Tohoku region, and to interpret Zen Kunen no Eki (the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War) as a rebellion against the domination over the remote regions by the central government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has hitherto been the mainstream to recognize the Abe clan as a local Dogo (powerful family) in the Tohoku region, and to interpret Zen Kunen no Eki (the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War) as a rebellion against the domination over the remote regions by the central government.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、部分的に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has hitherto been the mainstream to recognize the Abe clan as a local Dogo (powerful family) in the Tohoku region, and to interpret Zen Kunen no Eki (the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War) as a rebellion against the domination over the remote regions by the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし近年の軍事貴族研究の進展とともに、安倍氏を王朝国家特有の「兵(つわもの)」と見る考え方が登場している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in accordance with the progress in the studies about the military aristocracy in recent years, there appeared a view to regard the Abe clan as &quot;Tsuwamono&quot; (soldiers) characteristic of the Imperial Court State.</e>
<cmt>Web原稿によると、この文の元のテキストの「律令制には」以下と1行下の文のテキストは「「兵(つわもの)」」に関する脚注の内容であり、本文は「「兵(つわもの)」から3行下の「と見る考え方が登場している。」に続いています。そこで、「「兵(つわもの)」」の直後に「と見る考え方が登場している。」を移動し、「律令制には」以下と1行下の文を、主語を補って独立した2つの文にしました。なお、元の「と見る考え方が登場している。」の行にはparというtagが付けられていますが、実際にはその後の「関幸彦は、」以下の文も同じ段落としてこの文に続いています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in accordance with the progress of the studies in recent years on the military aristocracy, a view to regard the Abe clan as &quot;Tsuwamono&quot; (soldiers) characteristic of the Imperial Court State have emerged.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、部分的に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in accordance with the progress of the studies in recent years on the military aristocracy, a view to regard the Abe clan as &quot;Tsuwamono&quot; (soldiers) characteristic of the Imperial Court State have emerged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「兵(つわもの)」は、律令制には規定されていない軍事力で、地方で頻発する騒擾事件の鎮圧の為に用いられた一種の傭兵団。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsuwamono&quot; were military force not provided in the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), and they were a kind of mercenary troops that were utilized to suppress civil disorder incidents which occurred very frequently in the provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsuwamono&quot; were military force not specified in the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), and they were a kind of mercenary troops that were utilized to suppress civil disorder incidents which frequently occurred in the provinces.</e>
<cmt>頻発はfrequentlyで十分なため、veryを消去致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tsuwamono&quot; were military force not specified in the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), and they were a kind of mercenary troops that were utilized to suppress civil disorder incidents which frequently occurred in the provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>中世の武士とは異なり、土地の所有と支配にはさほどこだわらない集団であったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are thought to have been groups of soldiers who did not stick to the possession and ruling of land so persistently as the samurai (warriors) in the Medieval (Kamakura and Muromachi) period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the samurai (warriors) of the Medieval (Kamakura and Muromachi) period, they are thought to have been groups of soldiers who were not particularly concerned about possessing and ruling of land.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、部分的に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the samurai (warriors) of the Medieval (Kamakura and Muromachi) period, they are thought to have been groups of soldiers who were not particularly concerned about possessing and ruling of land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>関幸彦は、平氏や源氏、秀郷流藤原氏のような中央の貴族の末流の軍事貴族とは別にして、在地の土豪が中央の権力に従って軍事貴族したものも存在したであろうと指摘し、安倍氏もこの中に含まれるのではないかと論じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukihiko SEKI has indicated that, apart from the military aristocracy who were descendants of the central nobles such as the Taira clan, the Minamoto clan, and the Fujiwara clan of the Hidesato line, there were also those who had changed from the local Dogo into the military aristocracy under the authority of the central government, and has argued that the Abe clan was also one of them.</e>
<cmt>原文の「軍事貴族した」を「軍事貴族化した」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukihiko SEKI has indicated that, apart from the military aristocracy who were descendants of the central nobles such as the Taira clan, the Minamoto clan, and the Fujiwara clan of the Hidesato line, there may also have been those who had changed into the military aristocracy from the local Dogo under the authority of the central government, and argued that the Abe clan may also have been one of this kind.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、部分的に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukihiko SEKI has indicated that, apart from the military aristocracy who were descendants of the central nobles such as the Taira clan, the Minamoto clan, and the Fujiwara clan of the Hidesato line, there may also have been those who had changed into the military aristocracy from the local Dogo under the authority of the central government, and argued that the Abe clan may also have been one of this kind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その傍証として関は、『陸奥話記』において安倍頼時が「大夫(五位の官位を持つ者の通称）」と呼ばれていることを指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a piece of circumstantial evidence for it, Seki indicated that ABE no Yoritoki is called &quot;Daibu&quot; (a common name of those who had been granted Goi [Fifth Rank] as an official rank) in &quot;Mutsu Waki&quot; (A Record of Mutsu, or A Chronicle of the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As its corroborating evidence, Seki indicated that ABE no Yoritoki is called &quot;Daibu&quot; (a common name of those who had been granted Goi [Fifth Rank] as an official rank) in &quot;Mutsu Waki&quot; (A Record of Mutsu, or A Chronicle of the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、部分的に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As its corroborating evidence, Seki indicated that ABE no Yoritoki is called &quot;Daibu&quot; (a common name of those who had been granted Goi [Fifth Rank] as an official rank) in &quot;Mutsu Waki&quot; (A Record of Mutsu, or A Chronicle of the Earlier Nine Years&apos; War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>前九年の役と安倍氏の滅亡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zen Kunen no Eki and the Fall the Abe Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zen Kunen no Eki and the Fall the Abe Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zen Kunen no Eki and the Fall the Abe Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>安倍氏は婚姻などによって勢力を拡大し、忠良の子、安倍頼時の代に最も勢力を広げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Abe clan extended their power by means of marriages and others, and in the time of ABE no Yoritoki, a child of Tadayoshi, their power reached its maximum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Abe clan extended their power through marriages and so on, and they were most influential in the time of ABE no Yoritoki who was a child of Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Abe clan extended their power through marriages and so on, and they were most influential in the time of ABE no Yoritoki who was a child of Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>安倍氏は北上川流域の奥六郡（現在の岩手県内陸部）を拠点として糠部（現在の青森県東部）から亘理・伊具（現在の宮城県南部）にいたる広大な地域に影響力を発揮していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Abe clan established its foothold in Okuroku-gun (inland six districts, at present the inland area of Iwate Prefecture) surrounding the Kitakami-gawa River, and showed a great influence on the extensive regions from Nukanobu (at present the eastern part of Aomori Prefecture) to Watari and Igu (at present the southern part of Miyagi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Abe clan established its foothold in Okuroku-gun (inland six districts, at present the inland area of Iwate Prefecture) surrounding the Kitakami-gawa River, and exhibited great influence on the vast regions from Nukanobu (at present the eastern part of Aomori Prefecture) to Watari and Igu (at present the southern part of Miyagi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>showed a great influenceの部分を修正するなでお、より自然な表現となるように致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Abe clan established its foothold in Okuroku-gun (inland six districts, at present the inland area of Iwate Prefecture) surrounding the Kitakami-gawa River, and exhibited great influence on the vast regions from Nukanobu (at present the eastern part of Aomori Prefecture) to Watari and Igu (at present the southern part of Miyagi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし後に安倍貞任が朝廷と対立し、源頼義率いる討伐軍との間で前九年の役と呼ばれる戦いを繰り広げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But later, ABE no Sadato conflicted with the Imperial Court, and the Abe clan fought a series of battles called &quot;Zen Kunen no Eki&quot; against the suppression forces headed by MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on however, ABE no Sadato came into conflict with the Imperial Court, and the Abe clan fought a series of battles called &quot;Zen Kunen no Eki&quot; against the suppression forces headed by MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on however, ABE no Sadato came into conflict with the Imperial Court, and the Abe clan fought a series of battles called &quot;Zen Kunen no Eki&quot; against the suppression forces headed by MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>安倍氏は頼義に対し終始優勢のうちに戦いを続けたが秋田仙北の俘囚主清原氏が度重なる頼義の要請に応えて参戦すると、これを支えきれず貞任は敗北。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Abe clan continued to predominate over Yoriyoshi throughout all battles, but after the Kiyohara clan, the master of Fushu in Senboku of Akita, accepted Yoriyoshi&apos;s repeated demands and entered into the war, Sadato came to be unable to fight on against them and was defeated.</e>
<cmt>Excel原稿の「俘囚主出羽清原氏」をWeb原稿に合わせて「俘囚主清原氏」に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Abe clan continued to predominate over Yoriyoshi throughout all battles, but after the Kiyohara clan, the master of Fushu in Senboku of Akita, participated in the war after accepting Yoriyoshi&apos;s repeated requests, Sadato was unable to continue fighting, and was defeated.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Abe clan continued to predominate over Yoriyoshi throughout all battles, but after the Kiyohara clan, the master of Fushu in Senboku of Akita, participated in the war after accepting Yoriyoshi&apos;s repeated requests, Sadato was unable to continue fighting, and was defeated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>安倍氏の勢力は失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The power of the Abe clan was lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Abe clan lost its power.</e>
<cmt>語順を変え、より自然な表現となるように致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Abe clan lost its power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>頼時の三男・安倍宗任、五男・安倍正任はそれぞれ、伊予国（のちに筑前国の宗像）、肥後国に配流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ABE no Muneto, the third son of Yoritoki, and ABE no Masato, the fifth son of Yoritoki, were exiled to Iyo Province (later to Munakata, Chikuzen Province) and Higo Province, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ABE no Muneto who was the third son of Yoritoki, and ABE no Masato who was the fifth son of Yoritoki, were exiled to Iyo Province (later to Munakata, Chikuzen Province) and Higo Province, respectively.</e>
<cmt>カンマの数を減らし、なるべく文章がとぎれない形に修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ABE no Muneto who was the third son of Yoritoki, and ABE no Masato who was the fifth son of Yoritoki, were exiled to Iyo Province (later to Munakata, Chikuzen Province) and Higo Province, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、亘理（宮城県亘理町）の豪族藤原経清の妻となっていた頼時の娘は清原武貞の妻となり、息子（後の藤原清衡）も武貞に引き取られ、養子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Yoritoki&apos;s daughter, who had been the wife of FUJIWARA no Tsunekiyo, a local ruling family in Watari (Watari-cho, Miyagi Prefecture), became the wife of KIYOHARA no Takesada, and her son (later FUJIWARA no Kiyohira) was also taken in by Takesada and adopted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Yoritoki&apos;s daughter who had been the wife of FUJIWARA no Tsunekiyo, a local ruling family in Watari (Watari-cho, Miyagi Prefecture), became the wife of KIYOHARA no Takesada, and her son (later FUJIWARA no Kiyohira) was also taken in and was adopted by Takesada.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Yoritoki&apos;s daughter who had been the wife of FUJIWARA no Tsunekiyo, a local ruling family in Watari (Watari-cho, Miyagi Prefecture), became the wife of KIYOHARA no Takesada, and her son (later FUJIWARA no Kiyohira) was also taken in and was adopted by Takesada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>清原氏は安倍氏の地位を受け継いだが、後三年の役で滅亡し、藤原清衡がその地位を継承して奥州藤原氏による黄金時代を築き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kiyohara clan succeeded to the position of the Abe clan, but they were destroyed by Go Sannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War), so FUJIWARA no Kiyohira succeeded the position and built up the golden age by the Oshu Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kiyohara clan succeeded to the position of the Abe clan, but Go Sannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War) led to their downfall, and FUJIWARA no Kiyohira succeeded the Kiyohara clan, establishing the golden age of the Oshu Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kiyohara clan succeeded to the position of the Abe clan, but Go Sannen no Eki (the Later Three Years&apos; War) led to their downfall, and FUJIWARA no Kiyohira succeeded the Kiyohara clan, establishing the golden age of the Oshu Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>末裔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>前九年の役で一旦滅亡したが、その子孫を称する人々が現れ繁栄して現在に至っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Abe clan were ruined once by Zen Kunen no Eki, but those who represented themselves as descendants of the Abe clan have appeared and prospered to result in the present situation.</e>
<cmt>Excel原稿の「人々がれ」をWeb原稿に合わせて「人々が現れ」に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Abe clan fell at one time due to Zen Kunen no Eki, but those who claimed themselves as the descendants of the Abe clan have appeared, prospered, and lived to this day.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Abe clan fell at one time due to Zen Kunen no Eki, but those who claimed themselves as the descendants of the Abe clan have appeared, prospered, and lived to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>安倍貞任の子孫を名乗る津軽安東氏・安藤氏、その後裔で戦国大名として活躍した秋田氏、安倍宗任の子孫を名乗る九州松浦党とその後裔である平成時代の総理大臣安倍晋三が特に有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The particularly famous persons among them are the Tsugaru Ando (安東 or 安藤) clan who called themselves descendants of ABE no Sadato, the Akita clan who were descendants of the Tsugaru Ando clan and were active as a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period), the Kyushu Matsuura Party who called themselves descendants of ABE no Muneto, and Shinzo ABE who is a descendant of the Kyushu Matsuura Party and was Prime Minister in the Heisei era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly famous among them are the Tsugaru Ando (安東 or 安藤) clan who claimed themselves as the descendants of ABE no Sadato, the Akita clan who were descendants of the Tsugaru Ando clan that were active as a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period), the Kyushu Matsuura Party who claimed themselves as the descendants of ABE no Muneto, and Shinzo ABE who is a descendant of the Kyushu Matsuura Party and was a Prime Minister in the Heisei era.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly famous among them are the Tsugaru Ando (安東 or 安藤) clan who claimed themselves as the descendants of ABE no Sadato, the Akita clan who were descendants of the Tsugaru Ando clan that were active as a Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period), the Kyushu Matsuura Party who claimed themselves as the descendants of ABE no Muneto, and Shinzo ABE who is a descendant of the Kyushu Matsuura Party and was a Prime Minister in the Heisei era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>また昭和初期に総理大臣・海軍大臣として活躍した米内光政も安倍貞任の末裔であると自負していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Mitsumasa YONAI who was active as Prime Minister and Navy Minister in the early Showa era took pride in being a descendant of ABE no Sadato</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Mitsumasa YONAI who was active as a Prime Minister and a Navy Minister in the early Showa era took pride in being the descendant of ABE no Sadato.</e>
<cmt>より自然な表現となるよう、修正致しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Mitsumasa YONAI who was active as a Prime Minister and a Navy Minister in the early Showa era took pride in being the descendant of ABE no Sadato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), やりたこ(id:113528), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), Reggaeman(id:6214), Law soma(id:45202), Tetsu9(id:14553), 陽一(id:92099), Yanahan(id:2437), Peachkiller(id:99202), でここ(id:9565), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Kinori(id:443), Kropsoq(id:10072), Point136(id:211299), Hno3(id:56786), 越中掾(id:149423), Rabbit(id:12621), FlaBot(id:30804), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>