<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>室町家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi Family</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>室町家（むろまちけ）は、羽林家の家格を有する公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi family was a court noble with a family status of the Urin family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi family was court nobility with a family status of the Urin.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;noble&quot; to &quot;nobility&quot;. Avoided repetition of &quot;family&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi family was court nobility with a family status of the Urin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家閑院家流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaninke-ryu (the Kanin line) of the northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaninke-ryu (the Kanin line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaninke-ryu (the Kanin line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>西園寺家の一門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sept of the Saionji clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sept of the Saionji clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sept of the Saionji clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家紋は唐花。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest was kara-hana (a kind of Chinese arabesque pattern).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest was kara-hana (a kind of Chinese arabesque pattern).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest was kara-hana (a kind of Chinese arabesque pattern).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家業は和琴、筝。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family business was thirteen-stringed koto and so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family business was thirteen-stringed koto and so (Japanese harp).</e>
<cmt>OK, but explation of &quot;so&quot; may be required.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family business was thirteen-stringed koto and so (Japanese harp).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は200石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 200 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 200 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 200 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>伯爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earls</e>
<cmt>Removed &quot;.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>分家に西四辻家・竹中家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The branch included the Nishiyotsutsuji family and the Takenaka family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The branch included the Nishiyotsutsuji family and the Takenaka family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The branch included the Nishiyotsutsuji family and the Takenaka family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>鎌倉時代西園寺公経の四男、四辻実藤によって創立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was created by Sanefuji YOTSUTSUJI, the fourth son of Kintsune SAIONJI, in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family originated with Sanefuji YOTSUTSUJI, the fourth son of Kintsune SAIONJI, in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;was created by&quot; to &quot;originated with&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family originated with Sanefuji YOTSUTSUJI, the fourth son of Kintsune SAIONJI, in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>四辻と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The go (family name) was Yotsutsuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The go (family name) was Yotsutsuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The go (family name) was Yotsutsuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>本家、洞院家、清水谷家とともに、西園寺四流の一つで名門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the four Saionji families together with the head family, the Toin family, and the Shimizudani family, and was the family of pedigree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One the four Saionji families was family of pedigree together with the head family, the Toin family, and the Shimizudani family.</e>
<cmt>Changed order for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A distinguished family, the Muromachi family was one of the four Saionji families, the others being the head family, the Toin family, and the Shimizudani family.</e>
<cmt>The sentence didn&apos;t make sense and was grammatically incorrect. Also, I think &quot;distinguished family&quot; works better as a translation of &quot;名門&quot; than &quot;family of pedigree&quot; does.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>江戸時代初頭、四辻公遠の娘・与津子は後水尾天皇の典侍となり、天皇の寵愛を受けて皇子（夭折）と皇女（後の文智女王）を儲けたが、これが徳川和子の入内直前の出来事であったため、江戸幕府の怒りを買い、一時宮中から追放される羽目にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yotsuko, the daughter of Kinto YOTSUTSUJI, became a maid of honor of Emperor Gomizunoo in the beginning of the Edo period, and had a prince (premature death) and a princess (later Bunchijoo) in Emperor&apos;s favor; however, she invoked the wrath of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as it was just before the marriage with Kazuko TOKUGAWA, and she was expelled from the court for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yotsuko, the daughter of Kinto YOTSUTSUJI, became a maid of honor of Emperor Gomizunoo in the beginning of the Edo period and, while in the Emperor&apos;s favor, gave birth to a prince (who died young) and a princess (later Bunchijoo), but the births took place shortly before the marriage of Emperor Gomizunoo to Kazuko TOKUGAWA and thus invoked the wrath of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), with the result that she was temporarily expelled from the court.</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yotsuko, the daughter of Kinto YOTSUTSUJI, became a maid of honor of the Emperor Gomizunoo in the beginning of the Edo period and, while in the Emperor&apos;s favor, gave birth to a prince (who died young) and a princess (later Bunchijoo), but the births took place shortly before the marriage of the Emperor Gomizunoo to Kazuko TOKUGAWA and thus invoked the wrath of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), with the result that she was temporarily expelled from the court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>幕末、明治維新期の四辻公賀は、国事に奔走し維新後は、越後府知事、三等陸軍少将、宮内権大丞、雅楽助を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinyoshi YOTSUTSUJI worked hard for affairs of state at the end of Edo period to the Meiji Restoration, and he served as the Governor of Echigo Prefecture, the third army major, Kunaigondaijo, and gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) no suke after the Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinyoshi YOTSUTSUJI worked hard in the government from the end of Edo period to the Meiji Restoration, and then served as the Governor of Echigo Prefecture, a major in the army, and Kunaigondaijo, and gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) no suke after the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinyoshi YOTSUTSUJI worked hard in the government from the end of Edo period to the Meiji Restoration, and then served as the Governor of Echigo Prefecture, a major in the army, and Kunaigondaijo, and gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) no suke after the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>室町公康によって家名を四辻から室町に改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinyasu MUROMACHI. changed the family name from Yotsutsuji to Muromachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinyasu MUROMACHI. changed the family name from Yotsutsuji to Muromachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinyasu MUROMACHI. changed the family name from Yotsutsuji to Muromachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>明治17年室町公康に対して、伯爵位を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earlship was given to Kinyasu MUROMACHI in 1884.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earlship was given to Kinyasu MUROMACHI in 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earlship was given to Kinyasu MUROMACHI in 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>室町公大（きんもと）は、貴族院議員を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinmoto MUROMACHI served as the member of the House of Lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinmoto MUROMACHI served as a member of the House of Lords.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;the&quot; to &quot;a&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinmoto MUROMACHI served as a member of the House of Lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>室町公藤（きんふじ）は昭和34年掌典長に就任し、宮中祭祀に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinfuji MUROMACHI assumed the post of shotencho, the chief of shotenshoku (the section of the Imperial Household Agency handling the court ritual), in 1959 and was committed to the religious service in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinfuji MUROMACHI assumed the post of shotencho, the chief of shotenshoku (the section of the Imperial Household Agency handling court rituals), in 1959 and dedicated himself to religious service in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;was comitted&quot; to &quot;dedicated himself&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinfuji MUROMACHI assumed the post of shotencho, the chief of shotenshoku (the section of the Imperial Household Agency handling court rituals), in 1959 and dedicated himself to religious service in the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Riekanu(id:65656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>