<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>水戸徳川家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mito Tokugawa family</e>
<cmt>月日iの表示に付きましては、旧暦から西暦に返還して訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mito Tokugawa family</e>
<cmt>タイトルなのでtheを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mito Tokugawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>水戸徳川家（みととくがわけ）は、常陸国水戸市にあった徳川氏の一支系で、徳川御三家のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mito Tokugawa family was located in Mito City of the Hitachi Province, being one of the subsidiary lines of the Tokugawa clan and one of the Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mito Tokugawa family was one of branches of the Tokugawa family rooted in Mito City in Hitachi Province, and one of Tokugawa Gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にし、文法の誤りを直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mito Tokugawa family was one of branches of the Tokugawa family rooted in Mito City in Hitachi Province, and one of Tokugawa Gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>単に水戸家ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mito Tokugawa family was simply referred to as the Mito family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also simply referred to as the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also simply referred to as the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1606年（慶長11）9月23日、徳川家康の十一男である徳川頼房が常陸国下妻10万石を与えられ家を興す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 24th, 1606, after the Tokugawa Bakufu had given Yorifusa TOKUGAWA, the eleventh son of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, a territory with one hundred thousand koku (approximately 18 million liters of crop yield) at Shimotsuma in Hitachi Province, Yorifusa founded his own family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 24, 1606, Yorifusa TOKUGAWA, the 11th son of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, was given a fief of one hundred thousand koku (which yielded approx. 18 million liters of rice) in Shimotsuma in Hitachi Province, and started his own family.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。また日付表記を改めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 24, 1606, Yorifusa TOKUGAWA, the 11th son of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, was given a fief of one hundred thousand koku (which yielded approx. 18 million liters of rice) in Shimotsuma in Hitachi Province, and started his own family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1636年（寛永13年）7月、徳川姓を賜姓される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August of 1636, the Emperor gave the surname of Tokugawa to Yorifusa&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1636, he was allowed the use of the family name &quot;Tokugawa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「賜姓」をしたのは天皇ではないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1636, he was allowed the use of the family name &quot;Tokugawa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>タイトルなのでtheを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>徳川家康の十一男徳川頼房を家祖とし、江戸時代を通じて水戸藩を治めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorifusa TOKUGAWA, the eleventh son of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, was the founder of the Mito Tokugawa family, and the Mito Tokugawa family governed over the Mito Domain during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mito Tokugawa family was founded by Yorifusa TOKUGAWA, the 11th son of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and governed Mito Domain throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正し、表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mito Tokugawa family was founded by Yorifusa TOKUGAWA, the 11th son of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and governed Mito Domain throughout the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>格式は徳川御三家のひとつとして大廊下に詰め、屋形を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For background evidence to the social status of the Mito Tokugawa family, the Mito Tokugawa family worked at the Ooroka (the station for a daimyo [Japanese feudal lord], and the gosanke [three privileged branches of Tokugawa family] were located in the upper room while other daimyos were in the lower room.) in the clan&apos;s gosanke position and was permitted to have a yakata (an honorific title) title.</e>
<cmt>“原文では、「屋形を許された」とありますがWebで確認後、「屋形号を許された」と修正致してから訳してあります。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E6%B0%B4%E6%88%B8%E5%BE%B3%E5%B7%9D%E5%AE%B6”</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was granted a social status to work at the Oroka (the best office for daimyos [Japanese feudal loads] in Edo Castle) as one of Tokugawa Gosanke and received the title of Yakata (an honorific title).</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was granted a social status to work at the Oroka (the best office for daimyos [Japanese feudal loads] in Edo Castle) as one of Tokugawa Gosanke and received the title of Yakata (an honorific title).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>領国の石高は実収が25万石程度であったが、御三家の格式を気にして高直しをした結果、公称は38万石であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kokudaka (a system for determining land value for tribute purposes in the Edo period) of the Mito Tokugawa family&apos;s territory was in real values totally nearly twenty-five thousand Koku (approximately 45 million liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The real kokudaka (a crop yield) of the family&apos;s fief was about 25 thousand koku (approx. 45 million liters of rice), but the family padded it caring the reputation as one of Tokugawa Gosanke, so formally it was announced as 38 thousand koku (approx. 68.4 million liters of rice).</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔に改めました。原文通り本文と次の２文をまとめ、一文としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The real kokudaka (a crop yield) of the family&apos;s fief was about 25 thousand koku (approx. 45 million liters of rice), but the family padded it caring the reputation as one of Tokugawa Gosanke, so formally it was announced as 38 thousand koku (approx. 68.4 million liters of rice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これは水戸藩の財政を厳しくする一因でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This inflated evaluation of the Kokudaka caused severe financial strain upon the affairs of the Mito Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This window-dressing was one of the causes of financial stringency of the Mito Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was one of the causes of financial stringency of the Mito Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>window-dressingを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、将軍家宗家が「征夷大将軍」と現すために三葉を表にした表葵御紋であるのに対して、水戸家の葵御紋は三葉が裏になった裏葵御紋が正紋であるために、正式には御三家ではない説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, in order to present the family title, &quot;Seii Taishogun&quot; (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians and great unifying leader), the Soke (the head family) of the Shogun family, decorated the family crest of the Tokugawa clan with the face side of trefoil for the wild ginger trefoil, and this referred to the Omote Aoi-no-Gomon (face side of the wild ginger trefoil family crest of the Tokugawa clan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest of the head family of the Tokugawa clan (the linage of the Shogun) was Omote Aoi-no-Gomon (the family crest of a face-side-up trefoil of wild ginger), in which the front of a trefoil was depicted to represent the shogun&apos;s title &quot;Seiitaishogun&quot; (the commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians), while that of the Mito family was Ura Aoi-no-Gomon (the family crest of a back-side-up trefoil of wild ginger); therefore, there exists an opinion which holds that officially the Mito family was not recognized as Tokugawa Gosanke.</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現に改めました。なるべく原文に近くするため、本文と、次の２文を一文にまとめました（原文では本文と以下３文が一文となっています）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest of the head family of the Tokugawa clan (the linage of the Shogun) was Omote Aoi-no-Gomon (the family crest using front sides of three leaves of Hollyhock), in which front sides of Hollyhock leaves were depicted to represent the shogun&apos;s title &apos;Seii Taishogun&apos; (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), while that of the Mito family was Ura Aoi-no-Gomon (the family crest using undersides of three leaves of Hollyhook); therefore, there exists an opinion which holds that officially the Mito family was not recognized as Tokugawa Gosanke.</e>
<cmt>“Seiitaishogun” (the commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians)→ &apos;Seii Taishogun&apos; (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)(統一リストに合わせました）a face-side-up trefoil of wild ginger→using front sides of three ｌeaves of Hollyhocka back-side-up trefoil of wild gingery→using undersides of three leaves of Hollyhook</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>さらに、紀州徳川家の祖である徳川頼宣は同母兄であるので、ある時期まで紀州家の分家であると考られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, up to a certain time period, historian and experts had proposed that the Mito Tokugawa family was a branch family of the Kishu family; this was because Yorinobu TOKUGAWA, who was the founder of the Kishu Tokugawa Family, was an elder brother of the same mother of Yorifusa TOKUGAWA, who was the founder of the Mito Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, since Yorinobu TOKUGAWA, the founder of the Kishu Tokugawa Family, and Yorifusa were brothers by the same mother (Yorinobu was the older), the Mito family had been considered to be a branch of the Kishu family for a while after its foundation.</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現に改めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, since Yorinobu TOKUGAWA, the founder of the Kishu Tokugawa Family, and Yorifusa were brothers by the same mother (Yorinobu was the older), the Mito family had been considered to be a branch of the Kishu family for a while after its foundation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>尾張家・紀州家から見ると、極官の官位が低く（他のニ家は大納言だが、水戸家は権中納言）、石高が低いことなどから一段格下の家柄というのが世間一般の認識ではある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When we compare the Mito Tokugawa family with the Owari family and Kishu family, the kyokkan (the most high rank which one could be appointed) of the Mito Tokugawa family&apos;s official Imperial court rank was lower than other two families (two other family ranks included the Dainagon [chief councilor of state], but the Mito family&apos;s rank included the Gon Chunagon [a provisional vice-councilor of state].)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mito family&apos;s kyokkan (the highest rank one could be appointed in his lineage) in the Imperial Court rank system is lower than those of the Owari family and Kishu family (those of these two families were Dainagon [the Chief Councilor of State], while that of the Mito family was Gon Chunagon [the provisional Middle Councilor of State]), and the kokudaka of the Mito family was lower than those of these two families; therefore, it is generally considered that its social status was lower by one rank than those of the other two families.</e>
<cmt>文法の誤りを直し、表現を簡潔にしました。また、原文により近くするため、本文と次の文をまとめて一文としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mito family&apos;s kyokkan (the highest rank one could be appointed in his lineage) in the Imperial Court rank system is lower than those of the Owari family and Kishu family (those of these two families were Dainagon [the Chief Councilor of State], while that of the Mito family was Gon Chunagon [the provisional Vice-Councilor of State]), and the kokudaka of the Mito family was lower than those of these two families; therefore, it is generally considered that its social status was lower by one rank than those of the other two families.</e>
<cmt>Middle Councilor of State→Vice-Councilor of State(統一用語リストに従いました）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、水戸家自体が関八州にあり、また治める常陸国は延喜式における大国かつ親王任国である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Mito family resided in kanhasshu (eight Edo-period provinces of Kanto [Sagami, Musashi, Awa, Kazusa, Shimousa, Hitachi, Kouzuke, and Shimotsuke]) and governed the Hitachi Province that Engi-Shiki (set of ancient Japanese governmental regulations) system recognized as the Taikoku (major provinces); and Hitachi Province was also a Shinno Ninkoku (provinces which Imperial princes assigned for the Kokushi [the governmental official]).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Mito family was based within kanhasshu (eight provinces which composed the Kanto region in the Edo period) and governed Hitachi Province, which had been recognized as a taikoku (the best ranked provinces) and Shinno-Ningoku (provinces whose official governors were the Imperial princes) in Engishiki (a set of ancient Japanese governmental regulations).</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Mito family was based within kanhasshu (eight provinces which composed the Kanto region in the Edo period) and governed Hitachi Province, which had been recognized as a taikoku (the best ranked provinces) and Shinno-Ningoku (provinces whose official governors were the Imperial princes) in Engishiki (a set of ancient Japanese governmental regulations).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そして、下記の支系の中に高松藩12万石という徳川御連枝の中では破格の禄高を誇る家系がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following section, the Takamatsu Domain appeared in the subsidiary line of the Mito family and the Takamatsu family had proudly possessed the rokudaka (stipend) with one hundred and twenty thousand koku (approximately 21.6 million liters of crop yield); the family&apos;s rokudaka was exceptional among those Gorenshi (an honorific naming for a brother of a prestigious nobleman) of the Tokugawa clan family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the rokudaka (a stipend) allowed to Takamatsu Domain, a branch domain of Mito, was 120 thousand koku (approx. 21.6 million liters of rice), which was exceptionally high among those granted to the other off-shoots of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the rokudaka (a stipend) allowed to Takamatsu Domain, a branch domain of Mito, was 120 thousand koku (approx. 21.6 million liters of rice), which was exceptionally high among those granted to the other off-shoots of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>さらに、支系には他にも3つの藩が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the Mito family had three other subsidiary lines of families that were to become three domains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there were as many as three domains which were governed by the branches of the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため語を変え、表現も簡潔に改めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there were as many as three domains which were governed by the branches of the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これらの事情を考慮すると、上位とされる2家と実際には同等であるとの説も存在する</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In consideration of the facts detailed in previously explained, some historian and experts expressed the theory that the Mito family was the co-equal to the other two families which had seemed to be of a higher rank than that of the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there exists another opinion which says that the Mito family was equally prestigious to the other two families which were generally thought to be higher in social status.</e>
<cmt>過剰な訳出部を修正し、表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there exists another opinion which says that the Mito family was equally prestigious to the other two families which were generally thought to be higher in social status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>水戸家当主は征夷大将軍の補佐役であるとされ、参勤交代せず江戸定府の例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family head of the Mito family was the lieutenant for the Seii Taishogun, so the family was excused from the sankinkotai (daimyo&apos;s alternating Edo residence) practice and assigned to be an Edo Jofu (a Daimyo feudal lord&apos;s retainer who remained permanently in Edo with their lord, his family and their own family clan, during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of the Mito family was regarded as the assistant to Seiitaishogun, so the family was excused from sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and remained in Edo all the time.</e>
<cmt>簡潔な表現に改めました。「江戸定府」は行為を示す語で、人を指しているものだとは思えないので、訳は改めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of the Mito family was regarded as the assistant to Seiitaishogun, so the family was excused from sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and remained in Edo all the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>御三家であっても水戸家からは将軍は出さない原則であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A principle existed during this period that the Mito family would not produce a Shogun even though they were one of the gosanke families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A principle existed that a Shogun should not be chosen from the Mito family even though it was one of Tokugawa Gosanke.</e>
<cmt>語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A principle existed that a Shogun should not be chosen from the Mito family even though it was one of Tokugawa Gosanke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>なお、一橋徳川家の養子に入っていた九代藩主徳川斉昭の子徳川慶喜が十五代将軍となることによって江戸幕府最後の将軍を出すこととなったが、あくまで一橋家から将軍を出したのであって水戸家から将軍を出したわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, a son of Nariaki TOKUGAWA who was the ninth lord of the Mito domain, became an adopted child of the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family, eventually becoming the 15th Shogun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, the fifteenth Shogun Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was a son of Nariaki TOKUGAWA, the ninth lord of Mito Domain, so the last Shogun of the Edu shogunate was in truth from the Mito family; however, he had been adopted to the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family, and therefore formally he was from the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family, that is to say, this was not exactly the case that a Shogun was selected from the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>分かりづらい表現や文法の誤りがあるので書き直しました。文の流れをよくするため、原文通り本文と次の文をまとめ一文にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, the fifteenth Shogun Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was a son of Nariaki TOKUGAWA, the ninth lord of Mito Domain, so the last Shogun of the Edu shogunate was in truth from the Mito family; however, he had been adopted to the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family, and therefore formally he was from the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family, that is to say, this was not exactly the case that a Shogun was selected from the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>水戸家は代々「大日本史」をはじめ水戸学を学び、代々勤皇の家として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mito family had learned Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) for generations, starting with the &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (literally, Great History of Japan); the Mito family had been renowned for its pro-Imperial position for generations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mito family had learned Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in Mito Domain) starting with&quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (literally, Great History of Japan) and been known as a pro-Imperial family for generations.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔に改めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mito family had learned Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in Mito Domain) starting with&quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (literally, Great History of Japan) and been known as a pro-Imperial family for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「もし徳川宗家と朝廷との間に戦が起きたならば躊躇うことなく帝を奉ぜよ」といった家伝あった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that there was a Mito family tradition, &quot;If war would start between the Soke (the head family) family of the Tokugawa family clan and the Imperial Court, we have to follow the Emperor.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the precepts of the Mito family stated &quot;the Mito family shall follow the Emperor without hesitation if a war ever starts between the soke (the head family) of the Tokugawa clan and the Imperial Court.&quot;</e>
<cmt>文法の誤りを直し、訳漏れ部を補い、分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the precepts of the Mito family stated &quot;the Mito family shall follow the Emperor without hesitation if a war ever starts between the soke (the head family) of the Tokugawa clan and the Imperial Court.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そのため幕臣たちからは親藩でありながら外様大名と同様に警戒されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Mito family was a Shinpan (Tokugawa&apos;s relatives), shogunate retainers were watchful of the Mito family in the manner of a tozamadaimyo (non-Tokugawa daimyo) because of the Mito family&apos;s political attitudes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, although the Mito family was a branch of the Tokugawa family, shogunate retainers were watchful of it in the same manner as they were of tozamadaimyo (non-Tokugawa daimyo).</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にし、文法の誤りを直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, although the Mito family was a branch of the Tokugawa family, shogunate retainers were watchful of it in the same manner as they were of tozamadaimyo (non-Tokugawa daimyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>水戸家の支系（御連枝）は、讃岐国高松藩の高松松平家、陸奥国守山藩の守山松平家、常陸国常陸府中藩の府中松平家、常陸国宍戸藩の宍戸松平家の4家を数える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The subsidiary line of the Mito family (Gorenshi [an honorific naming for a brother of a prestigious nobleman]) were comprised from the four following families: the Takamatsu Matsudaira family of the Takamatsu Domain in Sanuki Province, the Moriyama Matsudaira Family of the Moriyama Domain in Mutsu Province, the Fuchu Matsudaira Family of the Hitachifuchu Domain in Hitachi Province, and the Shishido Matsudaira Family of the Shishido Domain in Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The subsidiary lines (called &quot;Gorenshi&quot;) of the Mito family were the Takamatsu Matsudaira family of Takamatsu Domain in Sanuki Province, the Moriyama Matsudaira family of Moriyama Domain in Mutsu Province, the Fuchu Matsudaira family of Hitachifuchu Domain in Hitachi Province, and the Shishido Matsudaira family of Shishido Domain in Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The subsidiary lines (called &quot;Gorenshi&quot;) of the Mito family were the Takamatsu Matsudaira family of Takamatsu Domain in Sanuki Province, the Moriyama Matsudaira family of Moriyama Domain in Mutsu Province, the Fuchu Matsudaira family of Hitachifuchu Domain in Hitachi Province, and the Shishido Matsudaira family of Shishido Domain in Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>水戸徳川家の歴代当主は比較的短命・無子の者が少なく、江戸時代の後半には他家に養子に出した例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relatively speaking, the descendant family heads of the Mito Tokugawa family came from those family members who lived the longest, and it was a rare case to have had no child in the family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relatively speaking, the successive family heads of the Mito Tokugawa family lived a long life and were blessed with children, so many sons from the family were adopted into other families during the late half of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。原文通り本文と次の文を一文にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relatively speaking, the successive family heads of the Mito Tokugawa family lived a long life and were blessed with children, so many sons from the family were adopted into other families during the late half of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>尾張藩の徳川慶勝、会津藩の松平容保は水戸家から高須藩に養子に入った松平義和の系統である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA of the Owari Domain and Katamori MATSUDAIRA of the the Aizu Domain, were from the lineage of Katamori MATSUDAIRA, who was previously adopted into the Takasu Domain from the Mito family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA of Owari Domain and Katamori MATSUDAIRA of Aizu Domain were descendants of Yoshinari MATSUDAIRA, who had been adopted into the lord family of Takasu Domain from the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA of Owari Domain and Katamori MATSUDAIRA of Aizu Domain were descendants of Yoshinari MATSUDAIRA, who had been adopted into the lord family of Takasu Domain from the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>明治維新後は華族に列し、侯爵を授けられ、さらに公爵にのぼった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Mito family lined up with the kazoku (noble) family and received the title of marquis; then they were elevated to the rank of duke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the Mito family ranked among kazoku (the nobility) with the title of Marquis, and later the title was raised to Duke.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the Mito family ranked among kazoku (the nobility) with the title of Marquis, and later the title was raised to Duke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>十三代当主徳川圀順は、財団法人水府明徳会を設立して伝来の大名道具や古文書を寄贈し、散逸を防ぐ措置を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuniyuki TOKUGAWA, the thirteenth family head, established the Suifu-Meitokukai Foundation and donated items previously handed down from their ancestors to the Foundation; items such as tools of the daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and ancient documents.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuniyuki TOKUGAWA, the 13th family head, established the Suifu-Meitokukai Foundation and donated to it the items which had been handed down to the family, such as daimyo&apos;s (Japanese feudal lord&apos;s) belongings and ancient documents, in order to prevent them from being scattered and lost.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしましました。また、原文通り本文と次の文をまとめて一文としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuniyuki TOKUGAWA, the 13th family head, established the Suifu-Meitokukai Foundation and donated to it the items which had been handed down to the family, such as daimyo&apos;s (Japanese feudal lord&apos;s) belongings and ancient documents, in order to prevent them from being scattered and lost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>同財団は1977年水戸市の徳川光圀の茶室跡に彰考館徳川博物館を開き、その保存・展示につとめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1977, this foundation opened The Tokugawa Museum of the Shoko-Kan Museum at the a tea room of Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA, which still remained in Mito City, this foundation made an effort to preserve and display the legacy of the Mito family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1977, this foundation opened the Shoko-Kan Tokugawa Museum at the site of Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA&apos;s tea room in Mito City for the purpose to preserve and exhibit the legacy of the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1977, this foundation opened the Shoko-Kan Tokugawa Museum at the site of Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA&apos;s tea room in Mito City for the purpose to preserve and exhibit the legacy of the Mito family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>歴代当主と後嗣たち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The successive family heads and their successors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Successive family heads and their offspring</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので最初のtheは除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive family heads and their offspring</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>水戸家は儒教を尊ぶ気風が強く、歴代藩主には漢風の諡号が贈られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mito family greatly respected Confucianism; this was significant to their family character; so successive lords of the Mito Domain were given the Chinese fashion title posthumously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mito family highly respected Confucianism in character; thus successive lords of the Mito family were given posthumous Buddhist titles in Chinese fashion.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mito family highly respected Confucianism in character; thus successive lords of the Mito family were given posthumous Buddhist titles in Chinese fashion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>初代（藩主）　徳川頼房 - 威公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first (the lord of a Domain): Yorifusa TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Iko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first (the lord of the domain): Yorifusa TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 威公)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first (the lord of the domain): Yorifusa TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 威公)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>松平頼重（高松藩初代藩主）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorishige MATSUDAIRA (the first lord of the Takamatsu Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorishige MATSUDAIRA (the first lord of Takamatsu Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorishige MATSUDAIRA (the first lord of Takamatsu Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="32">
<j>綱方（当初は、彼が光圀の養子になったのだが、夭折したため、代わって綱條が光圀の養子となった。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunakata (first, he became the adopted child of Mitsukuni but died prematurely, so Tsunaeda became the adopted child of Mitsukuni instead.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunakata (At first he was adopted to Mitsukuni but died prematurely, so Tsunaeda was adopted to him instead.)</e>
<cmt>簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunakata (At first he was adopted to Mitsukuni but died prematurely, so Tsunaeda was adopted to him instead.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="33">
<j>綱條（水戸藩三代藩主徳川綱條）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunaeda (the third lord of the Mito Domain, Tsunaeda TOKUGAWA)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunaeda (the third lord of Mito Domain, Tsunaeda TOKUGAWA)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunaeda (the third lord of Mito Domain, Tsunaeda TOKUGAWA)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="34">
<j>頼侯（高松藩三代藩主松平頼豊の父、すなわち水戸藩四代藩主徳川宗堯の祖父）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritoshi (a father of Yorimoto MATSUDAIRA, the third lord of the Takamatsu Domain; in other words, a grandfather of Munetaka TOKUGAWA, the fourth lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritoshi (the father of Yoritoyo MATSUDAIRA, the third lord of Takamatsu Domain; that is, the grandfather of Munetaka TOKUGAWA, the fourth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>名前の読みを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritoshi (the father of Yoritoyo MATSUDAIRA, the third lord of Takamatsu Domain; that is, the grandfather of Munetaka TOKUGAWA, the fourth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="35">
<j>光圀（二代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsukuni (the second lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsukuni (the second lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsukuni (the second lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="36">
<j>松平頼元（常陸額田藩主→守山藩）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimoto MATSUDAIRA (a lord of the Nukada Domain of the Hitachi Province, later he became a lord of the Moriyama Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimoto MATSUDAIRA (the lord of Nukada Domain in Hitachi Province [which was later relocated to become Moriyama Domain])</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。「常陸額田藩」が後に場所を改め「守山藩」となるのであって、頼元が守山藩主になるわけではないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimoto MATSUDAIRA (the lord of Nukada Domain in Hitachi Province [which was later relocated to become Moriyama Domain])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="37">
<j>松平頼隆（常陸府中藩初代藩主）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritaka MATSUDAIRA (the first lord of the Hitachifuchu Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritaka MATSUDAIRA (the first lord of Hitachifuchu Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritaka MATSUDAIRA (the first lord of Hitachifuchu Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="38">
<j>松平頼雄（宍戸藩初代藩主）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorikatsu MATSUDAIRA (the first lord of the Shishido Domain of Hitachi Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorikatsu MATSUDAIRA (the first lord of Shishido Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorikatsu MATSUDAIRA (the first lord of Shishido Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="39">
<j>二代（藩主）　徳川光圀 – 義公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second (the lord of the Domain): Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Giko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second (the lord of the domain): Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 義公)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second (the lord of the domain): Mitsukuni TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 義公)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="40">
<j>松平頼常（高松藩二代藩主）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritsune MATSUDAIRA (the second lord of the Takamatsu Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritsune MATSUDAIRA (the second lord of Takamatsu Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritsune MATSUDAIRA (the second lord of Takamatsu Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="41">
<j>三代（藩主）　徳川綱條 - 粛公　（支藩高松藩から養子、光圀の兄の子にあたる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third (the lord of the domain): Tsunaeda TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Sukuko. (An adopted child from the Takamatsu Domain, a branch domain; and he was a child of Mitsukuni&apos;s elder brother.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third (the lord of the domain): Tsunaeda TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 粛公) (adopted from the lord family of Takamatsu Domain, a branch domain of Mito; a son of Mitsukuni&apos;s elder brother.)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third (the lord of the domain): Tsunaeda TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 粛公) (adopted from the lord family of Takamatsu Domain, a branch domain of Mito; a son of Mitsukuni&apos;s elder brother.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="42">
<j>吉孚（夭折）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshizane (premature death)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizane (died prematurely)</e>
<cmt>語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizane (died prematurely)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="43">
<j>四代（藩主） 徳川宗堯 - 成公　（支藩高松藩から養子、夫人は吉孚の子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The forth (the lord of the domain): Munetaka TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Seiko. (An adopted child from the Takamatsu Domain, a branch domain; and his wife was a daughter of Yoshizane.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The forth (the lord of the domain): Munetaka TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 成公) (adopted from Takamatsu Domain, a branch domain of Mito; his wife was a daughter of Yoshizane)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The forth (the lord of the domain): Munetaka TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 成公) (adopted from Takamatsu Domain, a branch domain of Mito; his wife was a daughter of Yoshizane)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="44">
<j>宗翰（五代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munemoto (the fifth lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munemoto (the fifth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munemoto (the fifth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="45">
<j>五代（藩主）　徳川宗翰 - 良公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fifth (the lord of the domain): Munemoto TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Ryoko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifth (the lord of the domain): Munemoto TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 良公)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifth (the lord of the domain): Munemoto TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 良公)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="46">
<j>治保（六代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumori (the sixth lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumori (the sixth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumori (the sixth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="47">
<j>六代（藩主）　徳川治保 - 文公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixth (the lord of the domain): Harumori TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Bunko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixth (the lord of the domain): Harumori TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 文公)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixth (the lord of the domain): Harumori TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 文公)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>治紀（七代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harutoshi (the seventh lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harutoshi (the seventh lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harutoshi (the seventh lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>松平義和（尾張藩支藩美濃国高須藩九代藩主）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinari MATSUDAIRA (the ninth lord of the Takasu Domain of Mino Province, a branch domain of the Owari Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinari MATSUDAIRA (the ninth lord of Takasu Domain, a branch domain of Owari, in Mino Province)</e>
<cmt>簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinari MATSUDAIRA (the ninth lord of Takasu Domain, a branch domain of Owari, in Mino Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>七代（藩主）　徳川治紀 - 武公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seventh (the lord of the domain): Harutoshi TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Buko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seventh (the lord of the domain): Harutoshi TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 武公)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seventh (the lord of the domain): Harutoshi TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 武公)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>斉脩（八代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narinobu (the eighth lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narinobu (the eighth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narinobu (the eighth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>斉昭（九代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nariaki (the ninth lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nariaki (the ninth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nariaki (the ninth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="52">
<j>八代（藩主）　徳川斉脩 - 哀公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eighth (the lord of the domain): Narinobu TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Aiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth (the lord of the domain): Narinobu TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 哀公)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth (the lord of the domain): Narinobu TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 哀公)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>（実子なし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(He had no child of his own)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(He had no child)</e>
<cmt>簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He had no child)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>九代（藩主）　徳川斉昭 - 烈公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ninth (the lord of the domain): Nariaki TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Retsuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ninth (the lord of the domain): Nariaki TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 烈公)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ninth (the lord of the domain): Nariaki TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 烈公)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>慶篤（十代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiatsu (the tenth lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiatsu (the tenth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiatsu (the tenth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>徳川慶喜（一橋徳川家へ養子、十五代将軍となる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA (He became the adopted child of the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family; and he would become the fifteenth Shogun.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA (adopted into the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family; the fifteenth Shogun)</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA (adopted into the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family; the fifteenth Shogun)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>昭武（清水徳川家へ養子、のち水戸藩十一代藩主）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akitake (He became the adopted child of the Shimizu Tokugawa family, and later he became the eleventh lord of the Mito Domain.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitake (adopted into the Shimizu Tokugawa family; later, the eleventh lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akitake (adopted into the Shimizu Tokugawa family; later, the eleventh lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="57">
<j>十代（藩主）　徳川慶篤 - 順公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tenth (the lord of the domain): Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Junko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tenth (the lord of the domain): Yoshiatsu TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 順公)</e>
<cmt>名前の読みを直しました。諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tenth (the lord of the domain): Yoshiatsu TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 順公)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="58">
<j>篤敬（十二代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsuyoshi (the twelfth lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsuyoshi (the twelfth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>表現の統一のため、theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsuyoshi (the twelfth lord of Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="59">
<j>十一代（藩主）　徳川昭武 - 節公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eleventh (the lord of the domain): Akitake TOKUGAWA and his posthumous title was Setsuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eleventh (the lord of the domain): Akitake TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 節公)</e>
<cmt>諡号はあえて音読みする必要性はないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eleventh (the lord of the domain): Akitake TOKUGAWA (his posthumous title: 節公)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="60">
<j>徳川武定（水戸徳川家分家（「松戸徳川家」、子爵、海軍造船中将。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takesada TOKUGAWA (the fonder of the &quot;Matsudo Tokugawa family,&quot; a branch family of the Mito Tokugawa family; and he became the Viscount and also became a lieutenant general in the shipbuilding division of the Imperial Japanese Navy.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takesada TOKUGAWA (the founder of the &quot;Matsudo Tokugawa family,&quot; a branch family of the Mito Tokugawa family; a viscount; a vice-admiral in the shipbuilding division of the Imperial Japanese Navy)</e>
<cmt>海軍中将は「vice-admiral」とします（lieutenant generalは陸軍中将）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takesada TOKUGAWA (the founder of the &quot;Matsudo Tokugawa family,&quot; a branch family of the Mito Tokugawa family; a viscount; a vice-admiral in the shipbuilding division of the Imperial Japanese Navy)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>水戸徳川侯爵家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Marquis family of the Mito Tokugawa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mito Tokugawa Marquis family</e>
<cmt>簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mito Tokugawa Marquis family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>十二代（侯爵）　徳川篤敬　（式部次官）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The twelfth (marquis): Atsuyoshi TOKUGAWA (he became a shikibu Jikan [vice-minister of the ministry of court ceremonies during the Meiji Era])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twelfth (a marquis): Atsuyoshi TOKUGAWA (Shikibu Jikan [the vice-minister of the ministry of court ceremonies during the Meiji Era])</e>
<cmt>冠詞を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The twelfth (a marquis): Atsuyoshi TOKUGAWA (Shikibu Jikan [the vice-minister of the ministry of court ceremonies during the Meiji Era])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>圀順（十三代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuniyuki (the thirteenth lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuniyuki (the thirteenth family head)</e>
<cmt>明治に入ってからの人なので、水戸藩主ではないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuniyuki (the thirteenth family head)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="63">
<j>徳川宗敬（一橋徳川家に養子、貴族院副議長、参議院議員。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneyoshi TOKUGAWA (He became an adopted child of Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family; later he became the Deputy Chairman of the House of Peers and later became a member of the House of Councilors.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muneyoshi TOKUGAWA (adopted into the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family; the deputy chairman of the House of Peers; a member of the House of Councilors)</e>
<cmt>簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muneyoshi TOKUGAWA (adopted into the Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family; the deputy chairman of the House of Peers; a member of the House of Councilors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="64">
<j>十三代（侯爵、のち公爵） 徳川圀順　（日本赤十字社社長、貴族院議長）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The thirteenth (marquis and later duke): Kuniyuki TOKUGAWA (He became the President of the Japanese Red Cross Society; later he became president of Kizokuin [the House of Peers].)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The thirteenth (a marquis, and later a duke): Kuniyuki TOKUGAWA (the President of the Japanese Red Cross Society; the president of the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt>簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The thirteenth (a marquis, and later a duke): Kuniyuki TOKUGAWA (the President of the Japanese Red Cross Society; the president of the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="65">
<j>圀斉（十四代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuninari (the fourteenth lord of the Mito Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuninari (the fourteenth family head)</e>
<cmt>明治以降の人なので、水戸藩主ではないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuninari (the fourteenth family head)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>戦後の水戸徳川宗家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of the Mito Tokugawa family after the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mito Tokugawa family heads after the war</e>
<cmt>簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mito Tokugawa family heads after the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>十四代当主　徳川圀斉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourteenth family head: Kuninari TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourteenth family head: Kuninari TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourteenth family head: Kuninari TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="67">
<j>斉正（十五代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narimasa (The fifteenth family head)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narimasa (the fifteenth family head)</e>
<cmt>小文字に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narimasa (the fifteenth family head)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>十五代当主　徳川斉正</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fifteenth family head: Narimasa TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifteenth family head: Narimasa TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifteenth family head: Narimasa TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="69">
<j>斉礼（十六代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narinori (The sixteenth family head)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narinori (the sixteenth family head)</e>
<cmt>小文字に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narinori (the sixteenth family head)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="70">
<j>十六代当主　徳川斉礼 (水戸)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixteenth family head: Narinori TOKUGAWA (Mito City)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixteenth family head: Narinori TOKUGAWA (Mito City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixteenth family head: Narinori TOKUGAWA (Mito City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 みょうじ(id:124419), やりたこ(id:113528), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Nnh(id:474), SKYWALKER(id:24517), Aotake(id:34929), Reggaeman(id:6214), 松茸(id:27535), Charenji(id:7908), Lupinoid(id:68), YuBon(id:39634), Yogy(id:36183), Maeda(id:2461), るがこむ(id:181), Arpeggio(id:9385), YurikBot(id:18605), A-Taul(id:41790), 海衛士(id:19229), Point136(id:211299), トホホ川(id:50502), 越中掾(id:149423), Safkan(id:423), Suisui(id:69), 孝宏(id:56494), Iiyaman(id:193472), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>