<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>世襲親王家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seshu-Shinno-ke (the hereditary Imperial prince&apos;s family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seshu-Shinno-ke (the hereditary Imperial prince&apos;s family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seshu-Shinno-ke (the hereditary Imperial prince&apos;s family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>世襲親王家（せしゅうしんのうけ）とは、また「定親王家」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seshu-Shinno-ke is also known as &quot;the Tei-Shinno-ke&quot; (the legitimate Imperial prince&apos;s family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seshu-Shinno-ke is also known as &quot;the Tei-Shinno-ke&quot; (the legitimate Imperial prince&apos;s family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seshu-Shinno-ke is also known as &quot;the Tei-Shinno-ke&quot; (the legitimate Imperial prince&apos;s family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸時代において、当今の天皇との血統の遠近に拘らず、代々親王宣下を受けることで親王の身位を保持し続けた四つの宮家をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the Seshu-Shinno-ke was the name for the four princely houses that retained the title of Imperial Prince for generations by order of the Emperor regardless of their genealogical distance from the reigning Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the Seshu-Shinno-ke was the name for the four princely houses that retained the title of Imperial Prince for generations by order of the Emperor regardless of their genealogical distance from the reigning Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the Seshu-Shinno-ke was the name for the four princely houses that retained the title of Imperial Prince for generations by order of the Emperor regardless of their genealogical distance from the reigning Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>中世以来、四辻宮や岩倉宮などいくつもの宮家が存在したが、これらの宮家は親王の身位とともに継承されるとは限らないので世襲宮家ではあるものの、世襲親王家ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the medieval ages, there had been several princely houses, such as the Yotsutsujinomiya and the Iwakuranomiya, which were not the Seshu-Shinno-ke, but the Seshu-Miya-ke (hereditary princely houses) because they did not always succeed to the title of Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the middle ages, there were several princely houses, including the Yotsutsujinomiya and the Iwakuranomiya, which were not the Seshu-Shinno-ke, but Seshu-Miya-ke (hereditary princely houses) because they did not always succeed to the title of Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>Removed &quot;the&quot; for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the middle ages, there were several princely houses, including the Yotsutsujinomiya and the Iwakuranomiya, which were not the Seshu-Shinno-ke, but Seshu-Miya-ke (hereditary princely houses) because they did not always succeed to the title of Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これらの世襲宮家は、建前上は正統な皇位継承権をもつ家系であることを主張できる存在ではあったが、必ずしも皇統断絶の危機に備えて存続していたのではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These Seshu-Miya-ke claimed in theory that they legitimately had the right of succession to the Imperial Throne, but they were not necessarily for the event that the Imperial line should die out.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These Seshu-Miya-ke had a legitimate right to succession to the Imperial Throne, but they were not just there to ensure succesion in the event that the Imperial line should die out.</e>
<cmt>My interpretation is that one of their functions was to supply the succesion in the event of an imperial crisis but that they had other functions too.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These Seshu-Miya-ke had a legitimate right of succession to the Imperial Throne, and were not there only to ensure succession in the event that the Imperial line should die out.</e>
<cmt>意味不明瞭。 “just there” → “there only”I think &quot;and&quot; is a more appropriate conjunction for this sentence (the use of &quot;but&quot; here doesn&apos;t seem to make logical sense to me).</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>伏見宮家から後花園天皇が践祚した時に、自動的に伏見宮家の血筋が皇室に横滑りし、弟の伏見宮貞常親王も皇弟となって伏見宮家というくくりを無くす選択肢もありえた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Gohanazono from the Fushiminomiya family acceded to the throne, the bloodline of the Fushiminomiya family automatically slipped into the main line, and the family could have had a choice to eliminate the demarcation between the Fushiminomiya family and the reigning Imperial Family in such a way that Imperial Prince Sadatsune FUSHIMINOMIYA became a successor to Emperor Gohanazono as his brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Gohanazono from the Fushiminomiya family acceded to the throne, the bloodline of the Fushiminomiya family became the main line, and the family could have chosen to eliminate the demarcation between the Fushiminomiya family and the reigning Imperial Family so that Emperor Gohanazono would be succeeded by Imperial Prince Sadatsune FUSHIMINOMIYA, Emperor Gohanazono&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Emperor Gohanazono from the Fushiminomiya family acceded to the throne, the bloodline of the Fushiminomiya family became the main line, and the family could have chosen to eliminate the demarcation between the Fushiminomiya family and the reigning Imperial Family so that the Emperor Gohanazono would be succeeded by Imperial Prince Sadatsune FUSHIMINOMIYA, the Emperor Gohanazono&apos;s brother.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし実際には貞常親王が伏見宮家の当主を継承し、伏見宮家の財産を皇室に統合することはせず、後花園天皇は貞常親王に「永世伏見御所と称すべし」との勅許を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Imperial Prince Sadatsune, who actually inherited the head of the family without combining its property with the Imperial Family&apos;s, was given a sanction by Emperor Gohanazono that &quot;the Fushiminomiya family should permanently call itself Imperial palace of Fushimi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Imperial Prince Sadatsune became the head of the Fushinomiya family without combining its property with that the Imperial Family&apos;s, with Emperor Gohanazono granting the family the right &quot;to call itself the Imperial palace of Fushimi on a permanent basis.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Imperial Prince Sadatsune became the head of the Fushiminomiya family without combining its property with that of the Imperial Family, with the Emperor Gohanazono granting the family the right &quot;to call itself the Imperial palace of Fushimi on a permanent basis.&quot;</e>
<cmt>所有格必要。“that the”→.”that of the” “family”の所有格不要。 “Family&apos;s”-&gt;”Family”&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これが皇位継承資格者を確保するという目的をもった世襲親王家の始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a beginning of the Seshu-Shinno-ke that had a pool of potential successors to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the beginning of the Seshu-Shinno-ke which could offer a pool of potential successors to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;is&quot; to &quot;was&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the beginning of the Seshu-Shinno-ke which could offer a pool of potential successors to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>世襲親王家はしばしば当今の天皇の直系に男子が不在の際に皇位継承資格者を輩出し、万世一系とされる皇統の維持に寄与してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seshu-Shinno-ke often contributed to maintaining an unbroken Imperial lineage by providing a successor to the Imperial Throne when a male heir was not present in the direct line of the reigning Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seshu-Shinno-ke often contributed to maintaining an unbroken Imperial lineage by providing a successor to the Imperial Throne when a male heir was not present in the direct line of the reigning Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seshu-Shinno-ke often contributed to maintaining an unbroken Imperial lineage by providing a successor to the Imperial Throne when a male heir was not present in the direct line of the reigning Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし明治維新後には旧皇室典範によって永世皇族制が採用され、親王宣下および世襲親王家の制度は廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after the Meiji Restoration, the former Imperial Family Law stipulated a system of permanent Imperial Family membership, and abolished the Imperial order of conferring the title of Imperial Prince and the system of the Seshu-Shinno-ke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after the Meiji Restoration, an Imperial Family Law was passed stipulating a system of permanent Imperial Family membership, and abolishing the Imperial order that had conferred the title of Imperial Prince and the system of the Seshu-Shinno-ke.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after the Meiji Restoration, an Imperial Family Law was passed stipulating a system of permanent Imperial Family membership, and abolishing the Imperial order that had conferred the title of Imperial Prince and the system of the Seshu-Shinno-ke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これは、一旦世襲親王家として定めると、世代を経て皇統との血縁関係が離れていっても容易にこれを解消することができず、弾力ある運用が難しくなるためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If not, it would be difficult for the flexible application of the law; once the Seshu-Shinno-ke was stipulated, it could not be easily abolished even though its blood relation became distant from the reigning Imperial line through generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was necessary for the resilience of the Meiji system - if the rights of the Seshu-Shinno-ke were accepted under the law, they could not have been easily rescinded, even as the blood line diverged from the reigning imperial line over the generations.</e>
<cmt>It is not really clear what is meant here. I have tried to interpret the first translation but this requires checking.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was necessary for the resilience of the Meiji system - if the rights of the Seshu-Shinno-ke were accepted under the law, they could not have been easily rescinded, even as the blood line diverged from the reigning imperial line over the generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>世襲親王家（四親王家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seshu-Shinno-ke (Four Imperial prince&apos;s families)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seshu-Shinno-ke (Four Imperial prince&apos;s families)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seshu-Shinno-ke (Four Imperial prince&apos;s families)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>伏見宮家：始祖は北朝 (日本)3代崇光天皇の皇子、伏見宮栄仁親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fushiminomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Yoshihito FUSHIMINOMIYA, the third Northern Court Emperor Suko&apos;s son</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fushiminomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Yoshihito FUSHIMINOMIYA, the son of Emperor Suko of the third Northern Court</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability. The possesive &quot;&apos;s&quot; is awkward after a long string of nouns.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fushiminomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Yoshihito FUSHIMINOMIYA, the son of the Emperor Suko of the third Northern Court</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>昭和22年（1947年）、同系の10宮家とともに臣籍降下する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1947, the family was reduced to commoner status along with 10 other collateral princely houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1947, the family was reduced to commoner status along with 10 other princely houses of the same line.</e>
<cmt>I think &quot;collateral&quot; is misused here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1947, the family was reduced to commoner status along with 10 other princely houses of the same line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>桂宮家：始祖は第106代正親町天皇の皇孫、八条宮智仁親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Katsuranomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Toshihito HACHIJONOMIYA, the 106th Emperor Ogimachi&apos;s grandson</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Katsuranomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Toshihito HACHIJONOMIYA, the grandson of the 106th Emperor Ogimachi</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability. The possesive &quot;&apos;s&quot; is awkward after a long string of nouns.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Katsuranomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Toshihito HACHIJONOMIYA, the grandson of the hundred-sixth Emperor Ogimachi</e>
<cmt>106th→hundred-sixth</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>明治14年（1881年）に第12代当主の桂宮淑子内親王の薨去により断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1881, the family died out with the death of Imperial Princess Sumiko, the 12th head of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1881, the family died out with the death of Imperial Princess Sumiko, the 12th head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1881, the family died out with the death of Imperial Princess Sumiko, the twelfth head of the family.</e>
<cmt>12th→twelfth</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>なお、世襲親王家および近現代の宮家において、内親王もしくは女王_(皇族)が当主とされたのはこの淑子内親王の一例だけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Imperial Princess Sumiko was an only example that Imperial Princess or a female member of the Imperial Family became the head of the Seshu-Shinno-ke or the modern and post-modern princely houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not that Imperial Princess Sumiko is the only example of an Imperial Princess (or female member of the Imperial Family) becoming the head of the Seshu-Shinno-ke or a modern princely house.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that Imperial Princess Sumiko is the only example of an Imperial Princess (or female member of the Imperial Family) becoming the head of the Seshu-Shinno-ke or a modern princely house.</e>
<cmt>Not→Note</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>有栖川宮家：始祖は第107代後陽成天皇の皇子、高松宮好仁親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Arisugawanomiiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Yoshihito TAKAMATSUNOMIYA, the 107th Emperor Goyozei&apos;s son</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Arisugawanomiiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Yoshihito TAKAMATSUNOMIYA, the son of the 107th Emperor Goyozei</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability. The possesive &quot;&apos;s&quot; is awkward after a long string of nouns.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Arisugawanomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Yoshihito TAKAMATSUNOMIYA, the son of the hundred-seventh Emperor Goyozei.</e>
<cmt>107th→hundred-seventhピリオド補足 Arisugawanomiiya→ Arisugawanomiya</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>大正2年（1913年）に断絶したが、大正天皇の第3皇子の高松宮宣仁親王が有栖川宮家の祭祀を継承する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1913, the family died out, but Imperial Prince Nobuhito TAKAMATSUNOMIYA, the third son of Emeperor Taisho, carried on religious services of the Arisugawanomiya family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1913, the family died out, but Imperial Prince Nobuhito TAKAMATSUNOMIYA, the third son of Emeperor Taisho, carried on religious services of the Arisugawanomiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1913, the family died out, but Imperial Prince Nobuhito TAKAMATSUNOMIYA, the third son of the Emperor Taisho, carried on the religious services of the Arisugawanomiya family.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス。 “ Emeperor”-&gt; ”Emperor”. “the”定冠詞必要。 “on religious”-&gt;”on the religious”&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>閑院宮家：始祖は第113代東山天皇の皇子、閑院宮直仁親王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kaninnomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Naohito KANINNOMIYA, the 113th Emperor Higashiyama&apos;s son</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kaninnomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Naohito KANINNOMIYA, the son of the 113th Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability. The possesive &quot;&apos;s&quot; is awkward after a long string of nouns.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kaninnomiya family, founded by Imperial Prince Naohito KANINNOMIYA, the son of the hundred and thirteenth Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>英語として不自然。 -&gt; hundred and thirteenth.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>幕末に当主を欠いたが、明治維新後に伏見宮家から王子を迎えて当主とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, there was no head in the family, so that it accepted a prince of the Fushiminomiya family as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, there was noone to become head of the family, and so a prince of the Fushiminomiya family was accepted as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, there was no one to become head of the family, and so a prince of the Fushiminomiya family was accepted as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>noone→no one</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>昭和22年に皇籍離脱し、昭和63年（1988年）に断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1947, the family lost its membership as the Imperial Family, and died out in 1988.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1947, the family lost its right to membership of the Imperial Family, and died out in 1988.</e>
<cmt>Usage.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1947, the family lost its right to membership of the Imperial Family, and died out in 1988.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>世襲親王家出身の天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperors from the Seshu-Shinnno-ke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperors from the Seshu-Shinnno-ke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperors from the Seshu-Shinno-ke</e>
<cmt>Shinnno→Shinno</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>第102代後花園天皇：伏見宮貞成親王の第1皇子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 102th Emperor Gohanazono: the first son of Imperial Prince Sadafusa FUSHIMINOMIYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 102th Emperor Gohanazono: the first son of Imperial Prince Sadafusa FUSHIMINOMIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hundred and second Emperor Gohanazono: the first son of Imperial Prince Sadafusa FUSHIMINOMIYA</e>
<cmt>英語として不自然。 -&gt; “hundred and second”.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>第111代後西天皇　有栖川宮家当主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 111th Emperor Gosai: the head of the Arisugawanomiya family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 111th Emperor Gosai: the head of the Arisugawanomiya family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hundred and eleventh Emperor Gosai: the head of the Arisugawanomiya family</e>
<cmt>英語として不自然。 -&gt; “hundred and eleventh”.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="26">
<j>第119代光格天皇：閑院宮典仁親王の第6王子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 119th Emperor Kokaku: the sixth son of Imperial Prince Sukehito KANINNOMIYA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 119th Emperor Kokaku: the sixth son of Imperial Prince Sukehito KANINNOMIYA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hundred nineteenth Emperor Kokaku: the sixth son of Imperial Prince Sukehito KANINNOMIYA</e>
<cmt>英語として不自然。 -&gt; “hundred and nineteenth”.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Murasagi(id:79122), Fryed-peach(id:63402), R-h(id:46562), ゐ(id:795), Oyoyoyo(id:196287), MIsogi(id:20599), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), Brownsugar(id:20678), 黒砂糖(id:38164), 伏儀(id:142093), Shakujii kid(id:7158), 井上経介(id:32753), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>