<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>岡崎家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okazaki family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Okazaki family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Okazaki Family</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>岡崎家（おかざきけ）は、藤原北家高藤（勧修寺流）流中御門家庶家の堂上家、家格は、名家 (公家)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Okazaki family was Toshoke and a collateral branch of the Nakanomikado family of the Takato line (Kajuji line) of the Northern House of the FUJIWARA clan, with the court noble family rank of Meike.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Okazaki family were Toshoke and a collateral branch of the Nakanomikado family of the Takato line (Kajuji line) of the Northern House of the FUJIWARA clan, with the court noble family rank of Meike.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Okazaki family were Toshoke and a collateral branch of the Nakanomikado family of the Takato line (Kajuji line) of the Northern House of the FUJIWARA clan, with the court noble family rank of Meike.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>大納言・中御門尚長の次男である、中御門宣持が、「岡崎」を称したのにはじまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Okazaki family started when Nobumochi, the second son of Major Counselor, Naonaga NAKAMIKADO, called himself &apos;Okazaki&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Okazaki family started when Nobumochi, the second son of Major Counselor, Naonaga NAKAMIKADO, called himself &apos;Okazaki&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Okazaki family started when Nobumochi, the second son of Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Naonaga NAKAMIKADO, called himself &apos;Okazaki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語統一ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>初代・内匠頭（非参議・従三位）・岡崎宣持以降、江戸時代の石高は、蔵米30石であったが、明治に至り華族に列し子爵に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the first generation Nobumochi OKAZAKI who was the official architect for the Imperial Building Bureau (Hisangi, Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank)), the hereditary stipend during the Edo period was 30 koku; but since the Meiji period, the family ranked as Kazoku (nobiliity) and was conferred upon the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the first generation, Nobumochi OKAZAKI was the official architect for the Imperial Building Bureau (Hisangi, Jusanmi - Junior Third Rank), his hereditary stipend during the Edo period was thirty koku, but since the Meiji period, the family ranked as Kazoku (nobiliity) and was conferred the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the first generation, Nobumochi OKAZAKI was the official architect for the Imperial Building Bureau (Hisangi, Jusanmi - Junior Third Rank), his hereditary stipend during the Edo period was thirty koku, but since the Meiji period, the family ranked as Kazoku (nobility) and was conferred the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>家紋は竹に雀、菩提所は宝憧寺、居所は梨木町西側南角とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest was &apos;Bamboo and Sparrow&apos;; the family temple was Hoshoji Temple; and the family residence was located in Nishigawa Minamisumi, Nashikicho.</e>
<cmt>「梨木町西側南角」の読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest was &apos;Bamboo and Sparrow,&apos; the family temple was the Hoshoji Temple; and the family residence was located in Nishigawa Minamisumi, Nashikicho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest was &apos;Bamboo and Sparrow,&apos; the family temple was the Hosho-ji Temple; and the family residence was located in Nishigawa Minamisumi, Nashikicho.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>