<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蒲生氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gamo Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gamo Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gamo Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蒲生氏（がもうし）は日本の氏族の一つ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gamo clan is a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gamo clan is a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gamo clan is a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>近江蒲生氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omi Gamo clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omi Gamo clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omi Gamo clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原秀郷を祖と称する藤原氏の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omi Gamo clan is one of the Fujiwara families whose forefather is said to be FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omi Gamo clan was one of the Fujiwara clan and they had been saying that they originated from FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omi Gamo clan was one of the Fujiwara clan and they had been saying that they originated from FUJIWARA no Hidesato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近江国蒲生郡を中心に勢力を築き、藤原惟俊の代から蒲生氏を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan first established its power base in the Gamo County of Omi Province and identified themselves as the Gamo clan beginning with FUJIWARA no Koretoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan first established its power base in Gamo County of Omi Province and FUJIWARA no Koretoshi began to call himself the Gamo clan.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan first established its power base in Gamo County of Omi Province and FUJIWARA no Koretoshi began to call himself the Gamo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>室町時代には近江国の守護大名となった六角氏に客将として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Muromachi period when the Rokkaku clan became shugo daimyo (shugo were Japanese provincial military governors that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) of Omi Province, the Gamo clan served as the Kyakusho (extra shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Muromachi period, the Gamo clan served Shugo Daimyo (provincial military governors) of Omi Province the Rokkaku clan as a guest samurai.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, the Gamo clan served Shugo Daimyo (provincial military governors) of Omi Province the Rokkaku clan as a guest samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の初期の蒲生貞秀は、守護の六角高頼をよく補佐し、六角氏の戦国大名化に貢献したが、嫡男の秀行が早世したため、その死後に嫡孫の蒲生秀紀と子の蒲生高郷との間に争いがおきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the beginning of the Sengoku period (Japan), Sadahide (貞秀) GAMO strongly supported the Shugo (guard) Takayori ROKKAKU, which also helped the Rokkaku clan gain status as Sengoku-daimyo (warring lord); however because Sadahide&apos;s heir, Hideyuki, died young a conflict arose between Sadahide&apos;s grandchild and legitimate heir, Hidenori GAMO, and Sadahide&apos;s son, Takasato GAMO, to take control of the family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処; Sadahide は2人いるので（貞秀と定秀）、それぞれ漢字の名前を括弧で追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Sengoku period (Period of Warring States in Japan), Sadahide (貞秀) GAMO strongly supported Shugo (provincial military governors) Takayori ROKKAKU to make the Rokkaku clan one of powerful Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period); however, Sadahide&apos;s heir Hideyuki died young and before naming the new heir, Sadahide died, therefore, a conflict arose between Hideyuki&apos;s oldest son Hidenori GAMO and Sadahide&apos;s son Takasato GAMO.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Sengoku period (Period of Warring States in Japan), Sadahide (貞秀) GAMO strongly supported Shugo (provincial military governors) Takayori ROKKAKU to make the Rokkaku clan one of powerful Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period); however, Sadahide&apos;s heir Hideyuki died young and before naming the new heir, Sadahide died, therefore, a conflict arose between Hideyuki&apos;s oldest son Hidenori GAMO and Sadahide&apos;s son Takasato GAMO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>高郷が勝利し以後は高郷系が当主として続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, Takasato won in the conflict and ever since then, Takasato&apos;s family served as the head of the family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, Takasato won and ever since then, the head of the clan was selected from Takasato&apos;s line.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, Takasato won and ever since then, the head of the clan was selected from Takasato&apos;s line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>高郷の子の蒲生定秀は六角氏の宿老として活躍するが、蒲生賢秀の代に六角氏が織田氏に滅ぼされると、蒲生氏は織田氏に属し、賢秀の子である蒲生氏郷が織田信長の娘婿に迎えられるなど重用されたため、織田政権とそれを継承した豊臣政権において蒲生氏は大大名として大きく躍進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasato&apos;s son, Sadahide (定秀) GAMO, served as a syukuro (a chief vassal of a samurai family); however, during the time of Katahide GAMO when the Rokkaku clan was destroyed by the Oda clan, the Gamo clan belonged to the Oda clan and were given important statuses, such as having Katahide&apos;s son, Ujisato GAMO, as the adopted son-in-law of Nobunaga ODA; this led the Gamo clan successlly serve as daidaimyo (a feudal lord with a greater stipend) during the Oda and Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasato&apos;s son, Sadahide (定秀) GAMO served the Rokkaku clan as Syukuro (a chief vassal of a samurai family); however, during the period of Katahide GAMO, the Rokkaku clan was destroyed by the Oda clan; after that, the Gamo clan served the Oda clan and was given important status by the achievements and some occasion including the marriage between Katahide&apos;s son Ujisato GAMO and a daughter of Nobunaga ODA; therefore, the Gamo clan at last successfully became Daidaimyo (a feudal lord with a greater stipend) and played important roles during the period of the Oda government and the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。「娘婿」はこの場合養子にしたということではありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasato&apos;s son, Sadahide (定秀) GAMO served the Rokkaku clan as Syukuro (a chief vassal of a samurai family); however, during the period of Katahide GAMO, the Rokkaku clan was destroyed by the Oda clan; after that, the Gamo clan served the Oda clan and was given important status by the achievements and some occasion including the marriage between Katahide&apos;s son Ujisato GAMO and a daughter of Nobunaga ODA; therefore, the Gamo clan at last successfully became Daidaimyo (a feudal lord with a greater stipend) and played important roles during the period of the Oda government and the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、名将として知られた氏郷が若くして没したため蒲生氏は衰退し、徳川幕府の大名として存続することには成功したものの、その後も当主の夭折が続いたため後継がなく蒲生氏は断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after then reknowned great commander Ujisato died at a young age, the power of the Gamo clan declined even though the clan managed to survive as daimyo of the Tokugawa Shogunate. It was due to the successive deaths of their family heads, the clan lost their successors and the family line ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Ujisato, who had been well-known as a great commander, died young, the power of the Gamo clan declined, and even though the clan managed to survive as daimyo of the Tokugawa Shogunate, the family heads died young one after another, and finally the Gamo clan ended for the absence of the heir.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Ujisato, who had been well-known as a great commander, died young, the power of the Gamo clan declined, and even though the clan managed to survive as daimyo of the Tokugawa Shogunate, the family heads died young one after another, and finally the Gamo clan ended due to the absence of the heir.</e>
<cmt>for the absence of the heir→due to the absence of the heir</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>薩摩蒲生氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Satsuma GAMO clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Satsuma GAMO clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Satsuma GAMO clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>藤原教清を祖とする藤原氏の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Satsuma GAMO clan is one of the Fujiwara families whose forefather was FUJIWARA no Norikiyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Satsuma GAMO clan was one of the Fujiwara clan and they had been saying that they originated from FUJIWARA no Norikiyo.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Satsuma GAMO clan was one of the Fujiwara clan and they had been saying that they originated from FUJIWARA no Norikiyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>平安時代に教清の子の蒲生舜清が大隅国の荘園である蒲生院を拠点としたのが始まり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The GAMO clan began from the time when Shunsei GAMO, a son of FUJIWARA no Norikiyo, established his base in the Gamo-in manor, a shoen (manor in medieval Japan) in Osumi Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Shunsei GAMO, a son of FUJIWARA no Norikiyo, began to call himself the Gamo clan when he established his base in the Gamo-in Manor in Osumi Province.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Shunsei GAMO, a son of FUJIWARA no Norikiyo, began to call himself the Gamo clan when he established his base in the Gamo-in Manor in Osumi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>蒲生城を築き薩摩国、大隅国を中心に勢力を誇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan built the Gamo-jo Castle and exerted power especially in Osumi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan built the Gamo-jo Castle and exerted power especially in Osumi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan built the Gamo-jo Castle and exerted power especially in Osumi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、鎌倉時代から室町時代にかけて守護として君臨した島津氏の下風に立たされることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kamakura period and Muromachi period, the Gamo clan served under the reigns of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during the Kamakura period and Muromachi period, the Gamo clan had to bear under the reigns of the Shimazu clan which had been Shugo.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during the Kamakura period and Muromachi period, the Gamo clan had to bear under the reigns of the Shimazu clan which had been Shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)、蒲生茂清が登場し、肝付氏らと結んで内紛で衰退した島津氏と対抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the power of the Shimazu clan grew weak from internal conflicts during the Sengoku period, Shigekiyo GAMO banded with the Kimotsuki clan and fought with the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the power of the Shimazu clan grew weak from internal conflicts during the Sengoku period, Shigekiyo GAMO banded with the Kimotsuki clan and fought with the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the power of the Shimazu clan grew weak from internal conflicts during the Sengoku period, Shigekiyo GAMO banded with the Kimotsuki clan and fought with the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、島津氏の内紛を収めた島津貴久の反撃を受け衰退し、茂清の子の蒲生範清の代に降伏し、以後は島津氏の家臣となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Gamo clan lost its power and surrendered to the Shimazu clan during the time of Norikiyo GAMO&apos;s counterattack of Takahisa SHIMAZU.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Takahisa SHIMAZU who had succeed in ending the conflict launched a counterattack, the Gamo clan gradually declined, and at last Shigekiyo&apos;s son Norikiyo GAMO surrendered; after that, the Gamo clan served the Shimazu clan as vassal.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Takahisa SHIMAZU who had succeeded in ending the internal conflict launched a counterattack, the Gamo clan gradually declined, and at last Shigekiyo&apos;s son Norikiyo GAMO surrendered; after that, the Gamo clan served the Shimazu clan as vassal.</e>
<cmt>succeed →suceededconflict →internal conflict</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Loveless(id:129239), Iwaro(id:60082), 章奴(id:50198), Modeha(id:1276), BAKU(id:55205), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>