<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>富小路家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tominokoji family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tominokoji family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tominokoji family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>富小路家（とみのこうじけ）は藤原氏系の堂上家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tominokoji family was a toshoke (the hereditary lineage of court nobles allowed to enter the tenjonoma in the palace) in the line of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tominokoji family was a toshoke (within the hereditary lineage of court nobles allowed to enter the tenjonoma in the palace) down line of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tominokoji family was a toshoke (within the hereditary lineage of court nobles allowed to enter the tenjonoma in the palace) down line of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元来は九条家の諸大夫だった富小路俊通が二条家の庶家を自称する形で従三位に昇ったことから始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This family was originated from the fact that Toshimichi TOMINOKOJI who was originally a shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo) of the Kujo family was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) by insisting that his family was a branch family of the Nijo family.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味が不明ですが、訳文のように解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This family originated from the fact that Toshimichi TOMINOKOJI who was originally a shodaibu (aristocrat lower than Kugyo) of the Kujo family, and was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) by insisting that his family was a branch family of the Nijo family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This family originated from the fact that Toshimichi TOMINOKOJI who was originally a shodaibu (aristocrat lower than Kugyo) of the Kujo family, and was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) by insisting that his family was a branch family of the Nijo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>富小路俊通の子富小路資直が従三位となり昇殿を許可されて以後、堂上家の一員となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This family became a toshoke when Sukenao TOMINOKOJI, who was a son of Toshimichi TOMINOKOJI, was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and allowed to enter the tenjonoma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This family became a toshoke when Sukenao TOMINOKOJI, the son of Toshimichi TOMINOKOJI, was promoted to Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and allowed to enter the tenjonoma.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This family became a toshoke when Sukenao TOMINOKOJI, the son of Toshimichi TOMINOKOJI, was promoted to Jusanmi and allowed to enter the tenjonoma.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>家格は半家 (公家)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family status was hanke (lowest rank for toshoke)(noble).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family status was hanke (lowest rank for toshoke) (noble).</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family status was hanke (a kind of family status of the Court nobles) (kuge [court noble]).</e>
<cmt>半家、公家の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従二位・非参議を極官とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyokkan (the highest rank to which one can be appointed) was Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Hisangi (advisor at large).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyokkan (the highest rank one can be appointed to) was Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Hisangi (advisor at large).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyokkan (the highest rank one can be appointed to) was Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Hisangi (advisor at large).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は200石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was 200 koku (approx. 36.1cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karoku (hereditary stipend) during the Edo Period was 200 koku (approx. 36.1cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) during the Edo Period was 200 koku (approx. 36.1cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明治時代以降は子爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Meiji Period, viscount</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Meiji Period, they held the title viscount.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Meiji Period, they held the title viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tamago915(id:11009), Gimbrow(id:65660), Kaba(id:17904), ウラヌス(id:25954), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>