<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>佐伯氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Saeki Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saeki Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saeki Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>佐伯氏（さえきし）は古代日本の有力氏族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Saeki clan was a powerful clan in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saeki clan was a powerful clan in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saeki clan was a powerful clan in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中央伴造として佐伯部を率い、宮門警備や武力勢力として朝廷に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Saeki clan led Seki-be as the principal Tomo no miyatsuko (the chief of various departments at the Imperial Court) and served as security of the Imperial Palace&apos;s gates and as their military aid</e>
<cmt>佐伯部は、beを動詞と読み間違えないよう、-beとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saeki clan led Saeki-be (people served Yamato Dynasty and resided at Saeki) as the principal Tomo no miyatsuko (the chief of various departments at the Imperial Court) and served the Imperial Court as guard of the Imperial Palace&apos;s gates and as military aid.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saeki clan led Saeki-be (people served Yamato Dynasty and resided at Saeki) as the principal Tomo no miyatsuko (the chief of various departments at the Imperial Court) and served the Imperial Court as guard of the Imperial Palace&apos;s gates and as military aid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>因みに警備を担当した宮門は、氏族名から「佐伯門」と名付けられたが、平安宮では唐風文化の影響から、「さへき」に音通する「藻壁門」と改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The security of the Imperial Palace&apos;s gates was named &apos;佐伯門, Saeki gate&apos; but the security served at the Heian-kyu palace was named &apos;藻壁門, Soheki gate,&apos; due to Chinese pronunciation influence from Tang culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Palace&apos;s gates at which the Saeki clan had served was named &quot;Saeki-mon&quot; (Saeki Gate) after their surname, however, because Tang culture was the latest trend, Saeki-mon (佐伯門 pronounced as &quot;safeki-mon&quot; in those days and &quot;safeki&quot; was Japanese word) of Heian-kyu Palace which was built much later was changed to Soheki-mon (藻壁門 pronounced as &quot;saufeki-mon&quot; in those days and &quot;saufeki&quot; was the then Chinese pronunciation) which sound was very similar to Saeki-mon.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Palace&apos;s gates at which the Saeki clan had served was named &quot;Saeki-mon&quot; (Saeki Gate) after their surname, however, because Tang culture was the latest trend, Saeki-mon (佐伯門 pronounced as &quot;safeki-mon&quot; in those days and &quot;safeki&quot; was Japanese word) of Heian-kyu Palace which was built much later was changed to Soheki-mon (藻壁門 pronounced as &quot;saufeki-mon&quot; in those days and &quot;saufeki&quot; was the then Chinese pronunciation) which sound was very similar to Saeki-mon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>カバネは初め「連」であったが、天武天皇13年（685年）に同族の大伴氏等とともに「宿祢」を賜姓された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan&apos;s kabane (hereditary title) was initially &quot;Muraji,&quot; however, in 685 another title &quot;Sukune&quot; was bestowed together with other clans of the same family, such as the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan&apos;s kabane (hereditary title) was initially &quot;Muraji,&quot; however, in 685 another title &quot;Sukune&quot; was bestowed together with other clans of the same family, such as the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan&apos;s kabane (hereditary title) was initially &quot;Muraji,&quot; however, in 685 another title &quot;Sukune&quot; was bestowed together with other clans of the same family, such as the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>奈良時代以降、たびたびの政争に巻き込まれ（「関連項目」を参照）、そのたびに一族から処罰される者を出した事なども影響し、徐々に衰えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Nara period, conflicts arose from those frequently vying for political positions and some members of the Gamo clan became involved and were punished, which gradually weakened the power of the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Nara period, the clan was often involved in political conflicts (refer to the related articles), and every time member of the clan had to be punished, therefore, the clan gradually declined.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Nara period, the clan was often involved in political conflicts (refer to the related articles), and every time some members of the clan had to be punished, therefore, the clan gradually declined.</e>
<cmt>member →some members</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>天孫降臨の時にニニギを先導した天忍日命（あめのおしひのみこと）を祖とし、神別氏族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Saeki clan was considered as descendents of a family of gods; the forefather Amenooshihi-no-mikoto guided the way for Ninigi, the Prince of fertile rice-ears, during the time of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the Sun Goddess).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been believed that the Saeki clan was descendents of a god, Ame no Oshihi no Mikoto who had guided the way for Ninigi no Mikoto (the Prince of fertile rice-ears) when a god Ninigi no Mikoto had come down to the earth (the occasion has been called &quot;Tenson Korin&quot;).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been believed that the Saeki clan was descendents of a god, Ame no Oshihi no Mikoto who had guided the way for Ninigi no Mikoto (the Prince of fertile rice-ears) when a god Ninigi no Mikoto had come down to the earth (the occasion has been called &quot;Tenson Korin&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大伴室屋の時に大伴氏から別れた氏族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They separated from the Otomo clan during the time of OTOMO no Muroya.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They separated from the Otomo clan in the period of OTOMO no Muroya.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They separated from the Otomo clan in the era of OTOMO no Muroya.</e>
<cmt>period →era</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>読みと字義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reading and meaning of Saeki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reading and meaning of Saeki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reading and meaning of Saeki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>王権に仕え、宮廷警備等の任につくようになった後、外敵からの攻撃を「遮（さへ）ぎる者」という意味で「さへき」と呼ばれるようになったとの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory believed today is that from the time the clan sub-ordinated themselves to sovereignty and served as security guards of the Imperial Court, they came to be called by the family name &apos;Saheki,&apos; which meant &apos;people who sahekiru (prevent)&apos; in this case, from an enemy attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some historians had been saying that since the clan served as the guards of the Imperial Court to prevent (&quot;safeki-ru&quot; in ancient Japanese) the enemies from intruding, people began to call them &quot;safeki&quot; in ancient Japanese.</e>
<cmt>この説は現在は間違いだとされており、safeki-ruと書くのも間違っていますが、説明のしようがないのでそのまま一見納得できるようなかたちに書きます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some historians had been saying that since the clan served as the guards of the Imperial Court to prevent (&quot;safeki-ru&quot; in ancient Japanese) the enemies from intruding, people began to call them &quot;safeki&quot; in ancient Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>後世「さへき」が「さえき」と訛り、更に「さいき」に訛った地域もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years, the reading has changed from &apos;saheki&apos; to &apos;saeki&apos; and in some regions, to &apos;saiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years, the reading has changed from &apos;safeki&apos; to &apos;saeki&apos; and in some regions, to &apos;saiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>この時代はは行はFで発音されていたのでsafekiとなります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years, the reading has changed from &apos;safeki&apos; to &apos;saeki&apos; and in some regions, to &apos;saiki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、「佐伯」は「伯（尊い者）」を「佐（たすけ）る」という意味の当て字であろうとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory that claims that the kanji characters of Saeki, &apos;佐伯,&apos; are used to mean the people who &apos;佐る, tasukeru&apos; (support) the &apos;伯, haku&apos; (head).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some historian say that Saeki (佐伯) was a compound of 佐 (meant to support) and 伯 (meant a noble person) for describing the clan&apos;s duty which was to support a noble person.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some historian say that Saeki (佐伯) was a compound of 佐 (meant to support) and 伯 (meant a noble person) for describing the clan&apos;s duty which was to support a noble person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>同族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Figures from the same family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Figures from the same family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Figures from the same family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>佐伯造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saeki no Miyatsuko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saeki no Miyatsuko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saeki no Miyatsuko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>佐伯造（-みやつこ）は、『新撰姓氏録』右京神別上に見え、旧姓は「佐伯部」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAEKI no Miyatsuko is recorded in the Ukyo Shinbetsu (clans branched out of a family of god in the Western Capital Offices) of the Shinsen Shojiroku (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility) and his former surname is SAEKIBE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAEKI no Miyatsuko was recorded in the volume of Jo, Shinbetsu, Ukyo of &quot;Shinsen Shoji-roku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility), according to it, his former surname was &quot;Saekibe.&quot;</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAEKI no Miyatsuko was recorded in the volume of Jo, Shinbetsu, Ukyo of &quot;Shinsen Shoji-roku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility), according to it, his former surname was &quot;Saekibe.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>『日本書紀』によれば、市辺押磐皇子（いちのへのおしはのみこ）の舎人、佐伯部仲子（さへきべのなかちこ）の後裔で、仁賢天皇5年2月5日条に、諸国の佐伯部を集めて管掌にさせたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihon shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), he is a descendant of SAEKIBE no Nakachiko, who was the toneri (palace servant) of Prince Ichinobe no Oshihano; the article of February 5, 492 of the same book states that he gathered all the Saeki-be from each county and ….</e>
<cmt>「管掌させた」の部分に目的語が必要に思えましたが、見当たらなかったので、原文の意味が分からず、そこの部分が訳せませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Nihon shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), he was a descendant of SAEKIBE no Nakachiko, who was Toneri (palace servant) of Ichinobe no Oshiwa no Miko (Prince Ichinobe no Oshiwa); and according to the article of February 5, 492 of the same book, the Imperial Court summoned Saeki-be of various provinces to appoint them to Kajo (managers controlling lower officials and operating the court&apos;s various facilities).</e>
<cmt>翻訳者の指摘のように「管掌(かじょう)」のあとに「に」が抜けていますので、オリジナルに補います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Nihon shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), he was a descendant of SAEKIBE no Nakachiko, who was Toneri (palace servant) of Ichinobe no Oshiwa no Miko (Prince Ichinobe no Oshiwa); and according to the article of February 5, 492 of the same book, the Imperial Court summoned Saeki-be of various provinces to appoint them to Kajo (managers controlling lower officials and operating the court&apos;s various facilities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>佐伯首</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAEKI no Obito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAEKI no Obito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAEKI no Obito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>佐伯首（-おびと）は、『新撰姓氏録』河内国神別に見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAEKI no obito is recorded in the Kawachi County Shinbetsu (clans branched out of a family of god in the Kawachi County) of the Shinsen Shojiroku (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAEKI no Obito was recorded in the volume of Shinbetsu, Kawachi Province of &quot;Shinsen Shoji-roku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAEKI no Obito was recorded in the volume of Shinbetsu, Kawachi Province of &quot;Shinsen Shoji-roku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Japan Maik(id:254359), ひろくん(id:79638), 水野白楓(id:22811), 陽一(id:92099), 今泉総一郎(id:221465), Yanahan(id:2437), お掃除大好き(id:99320), 越中掾(id:149423), 胡亂堂(id:263343), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>