<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>柳生氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yagyu Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yagyu Clan</e>
<cmt>他の同様の記事と同じにします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yagyu Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>柳生氏（やぎゅうし）は日本の氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yagyu clan is a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yagyu clan was a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>時制。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yagyu clan was a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>新井白石が作成した系譜の『藩翰譜』（または後世の『寛政重修諸家譜』）によると、柳生氏の姓は菅原氏とされ、菅原道真が祖先とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hankanpu&quot; (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) compiled by Hakuseki ARAI (or &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (A record of family trees of samurai warriors of the Tokugawa Shogunate) published in later years), the original family name of the Yagyu clan is Sugawara, and Michizane SUGAWARA is said to have been the ancestor of the Yagyu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Hankanpu&quot; (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) compiled by Hakuseki ARAI and &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (A record of family trees of samurai warriors of the Tokugawa Shogunate) which was published in later years, the original family name of the Yagyu clan was Sugawara, and it is said that they were descendants of SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Hankanpu&quot; (Genealogy of the Protectors of the Shogunate) compiled by Hakuseki ARAI and &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (A record of family trees of samurai warriors of the Tokugawa Shogunate) which was published in later years, the original family name of the Yagyu clan was Sugawara, and it is said that they were descendants of SUGAWARA no Michizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし確証性が乏しく、柳生氏の系譜の比較考証が考慮する必要性がある（あるいは服部氏同様に秦氏の系統ともいわれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But there is no sufficient evidence to prove it, and the genealogy of the Yagyu clan has to be analyzed in detail (or another theory says they would be from the line of the Hata clan like the Hattori clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is no sufficient evidence to prove it, and the remaining genealogies of the Yagyu clan still have to be studied in detail; some historian says that they originated from the Hata clan like the Hattori clan.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is no sufficient evidence to prove it, and the remaining genealogies of the Yagyu clan still have to be studied in detail; some historian says that they originated from the Hata clan like the Hattori clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>実際の柳生氏の事項が明らかになるのは、南北朝時代 (日本)の柳生永珍（別名：宗珍、大膳亮柳生永家の子とされる）の頃からで、柳生家の家譜である『玉栄拾遺』によると、元弘3年（1331年）に、南朝 (日本)として、六波羅探題の北条仲時・北条時益の軍勢と戦った永珍は戦功によって、後醍醐天皇から賜った大和国小楊生（大楊生とも）庄の領主となり、柳生氏と名乗った事から始まるとされる（ただし、『玉栄拾遺』の記述自体も伝承の域を出ないという）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first record that mentions the Yagyu clan is about Nagayoshi YAGYU (aka Muneyoshi who was believed to be a child of Daizen no suke (the title of a person who was in charge of meals in the court) Nagaie YAGYU) in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), and according to the genealogy of the Yagyu clan &quot;Gyokuei Shui,&quot; Nagayoshi, who fought the forces of Nagatoki HOJO and Tokimasu HOJO of Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) as part of the Southern Court forces, became the ruling samurai of Koyagyusho (or Oyagyusho), a community in Yamato Province awarded by Emperor Godaigo for his military exploit and started using the name Yagyu (but the descriptions in Gyokuei Shui themselves are said to be none other than legendary stories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first record that mentions the Yagyu clan is about Nagayoshi YAGYU (Muneyoshi YAGYU) who was believed to be a child of Daizen no suke (person who was in charge of meals in the Imperial Court) Nagaie YAGYU in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan); and according to a genealogy of the Yagyu clan &quot;Gyokuei Shui,&quot; Nagayoshi supported the Southern Court and fought against the forces of Nagatoki HOJO and Tokimasu HOJO who had their base at Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), and for the achievement in the battles, Emperor Godaigo gave him the possession and status of the lord of Koyagyusho district (or Oyagyusho district) in Yamato Province, ever since then, he called himself the Yagyu clan; however, it is said that the articles in &quot;Gyokuei Shui&quot; are nothing but folklore.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first record that mentions the Yagyu clan is about Nagayoshi YAGYU (Muneyoshi YAGYU) who was believed to be a child of Daizen no suke (person who was in charge of meals in the Imperial Court) Nagaie YAGYU in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan); and according to a genealogy of the Yagyu clan &quot;Gyokuei Shui,&quot; Nagayoshi supported the Southern Court and fought against the forces of Nagatoki HOJO and Tokimasu HOJO who had their base at Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), and for the achievement in the battles, Emperor Godaigo gave him the possession and status of the lord of Koyagyusho district (or Oyagyusho district) in Yamato Province, ever since then, he called himself the Yagyu clan; however, it is said that the articles in &quot;Gyokuei Shui&quot; are nothing but folklore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>柳生家の発祥地は大和国添上郡柳生郷（現奈良市柳生地区）で、大和国北部にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The birth place of the Yagyu clan is Yagyu-go village, Sonokami-no-kori County, Yamato Province (today&apos;s Yagyu area, Nara city), which is located in the northern part of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The birth place of the Yagyu clan was Yagyu-go village, Sonokami-no-kori County, Yamato Province (today&apos;s Yagyu area, Nara City), which was located in the northern part of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>時制。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The birth place of the Yagyu clan was Yagyu-go village, Sonokami-no-kori County, Yamato Province (today&apos;s Yagyu area, Nara City), which was located in the northern part of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また「楊生」・「夜岐布」・「夜支布」・「養父」とも記され、いずれも「やぎう」と発音するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place name is also written using such Chinese characters as &quot;楊生,&quot; &quot;夜岐布,&quot; &quot;夜支布, &quot; and &quot;養父,&quot; which are all read &quot;ya-gyu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yagyu &quot;柳生&quot; was also written as &quot;楊生,&quot; &quot;夜岐布,&quot; &quot;夜支布, &quot; and &quot;養父,&quot; and they are considered to have been pronounced &quot;yagiu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>発音の変遷を意識してオリジナル著者は書いています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yagyu &quot;柳生&quot; was also written as &quot;楊生,&quot; &quot;夜岐布,&quot; &quot;夜支布, &quot; and &quot;養父,&quot; and they are considered to have been pronounced &quot;yagiu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)に、上泉信綱から新陰流を相伝された柳生宗厳（石舟斎）は、永珍（宗珍）から8代目の子孫に当たる人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetoshi YAGYU (Sekishusai), who inherited Shinkage-ryu, a school of swordfighting, from Nobutsuna KAMIIZUMI in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) is a descendant of the 8th generation from Nagayoshi (Muneyoshi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetoshi YAGYU (Sekishusai), who inherited Shinkage-ryu School of swordsmanship from Nobutsuna KAMIIZUMI in the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States), was a descendant of the 8th generation from Nagayoshi (Muneyoshi).</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetoshi YAGYU (Sekishusai), who inherited Shinkage-ryu School of swordsmanship from Nobutsuna KAMIIZUMI in the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States), was a descendant of the 8th generation from Nagayoshi (Muneyoshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>大名への出世街道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career Path to Daimyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career Path to Daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career Path to Daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>宗厳は戦国時代に、松永久秀に仕えたが、その久秀が織田信長と争って滅亡し、さらに豊臣秀吉の太閤検地によって隠田の罪で2000石の所領を没収されるなど、次第に落ちぶれていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetoshi served Hisahide MATSUNAGA in the Sengoku period, but his clan gradually dwindled as his master Hisahide was destroyed after fighting Nobunaga ODA, and Taiko Kenchi (Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey) revealed some hidden non-declared land in his domain and resulted in sequestration of a territory worth 2,000 goku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetoshi served Hisahide MATSUNAGA in the Sengoku period, however his clan gradually dwindled as his master Hisahide was destroyed by Nobunaga ODA, and he forfeited 2,000 goku (360.78 cubic meters of rice) of his territory for hiding rice fields at Taiko Kenchi (Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetoshi served Hisahide MATSUNAGA in the Sengoku period, however his clan gradually dwindled as his master Hisahide was destroyed by Nobunaga ODA, and he forfeited 2,000 koku (360.78 cubic meters of rice) of his territory on charge of hiding rice fields when Taiko Kenchi (Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey) was held.</e>
<cmt>2,000 goku→2,000 kokufor hiding→on charge of hidingat→when …was held</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、黒田長政の仲介により当時秀吉に次ぐ実力者であった徳川家康と出会った宗厳は、家康の前で「無刀取り」を披露したことにより、兵法指南役に迎えたいと申し出を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Munetoshi met Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the most powerful samurai after Hideyoshi in those days, through the arrangement of Nagamasa KURODA and performed &quot;Muto-dori&quot; (seizing opponent&apos;s sword being unarmed) in front of Ieyasu, and this performance made Ieyasu decide to hire Munetoshi as the instructor of swordplay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, by the arrangement of Nagamasa KURODA, Munetoshi met Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who was the most powerful samurai next to Hideyoshi at that time, and in front of Ieyasu, he performed &quot;Muto-dori&quot; (seizing opponent&apos;s sword without his own sword), and at a result, he was offered the position of the instructor of Heiho (art of warfare).</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, by the arrangement of Nagamasa KURODA, Munetoshi met Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who was the most powerful samurai next to Hideyoshi at that time, and in front of Ieyasu, he performed &quot;Muto-dori&quot; (seizing opponent&apos;s sword without his own sword), and as a result, he was offered the position of the instructor of Heiho (art of warfare).</e>
<cmt>at a result, →as a result,</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宗厳は当時、すでに66歳という老齢だったため、これを辞退し代わりに、五男の柳生宗矩を指南役として推挙したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he was already aged, 66 years old, he did not accept the offer but recommended his fifth son Munenori YAGYU as the instructor instead of him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Munetoshi was already 66 years old, he declined it and recommended his fifth son Munenori YAGYU as the instructor.</e>
<cmt>簡略化。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Munetoshi was already 66 years old, he declined it and recommended his fifth son Munenori YAGYU as the instructor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これは文禄3年（1594年）5月3日 (旧暦)のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was on May 3, 1594 (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was on May 3, 1594 (in old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was on May 3, 1594 (in old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのことが、『玉栄拾遺』にも詳細に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This episode is also recorded in detail in &quot;Gyokuei Shui.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details of this episode was recorded in &quot;Gyokuei Shui,&quot; the following is the part of that.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details of this episode was recorded in &quot;Gyokuei Shui,&quot; the following is the part of that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>「文禄甲午の年、聚楽紫竹村にて宗厳公の剣術始て神君（徳川家康）上覧。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;In the Kogo year of the Bunroku era (in 1594), at Juraku Shitiku-mura, Jinkun (Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) saw Munetoshi-ko (Munetoshi)&apos;s swordsmanship for the first time.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;In the Kogo year of the Bunroku era (in 1594), at Juraku Shitiku-mura, Jinkun (Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) saw Munetoshi-ko (Munetoshi)&apos;s swordsmanship for the first time.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「木刀を持玉ひ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jinkun took up a wooden sword.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jinkun took up a wooden sword.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「宗厳是を執るべしと上意あり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;And he ordered Munetoshi to take this wooden sword.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;And he ordered Munetoshi to take this wooden sword.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「即ち公無刀にて執り給ふ。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Then Ko (Munetoshi) took it in bare hands.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Then Ko (Munetoshi) took it in bare hands.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>「其時神君後ろへ倒れ玉はんとし、上手なり向後師たるべしとの上意の上、景則の刀を賜ひて誓詞を辱くす。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;At that moment, Jinkun (Ieyasu) was almost falling flat on his back; after returned to his seat and sat up straight against Ko (Munetoshi), he requested Ko to become his teacher and gave Ko the sword made by Kagenori to exchange promises.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;At that moment, Jinkun (Ieyasu) was almost falling flat on his back; after returned to his seat and sat up straight against Ko (Munetoshi), he requested Ko to become his teacher and gave Ko the sword made by Kagenori to exchange promises.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「時に5月3日也。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was on May 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;It was on May 3&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;It was on May 3&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>「且俸禄200石を賜ふ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was awarded 200 goku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jinkun (Ieyasu) gave Ko (Munetoshi) rice stipend 200 koku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Jinkun (Ieyasu) gave Ko (Munetoshi) rice stipend 200 koku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>なにはともあれ、信長・秀吉時代に落ちぶれた柳生氏は、家康時代に再び世に出ることとなったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yagyu clan, who declined in the days of Nobunaga and Hideyoshi, resurrected in the world in the age of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Yagyu clan that declined once in the period of Nobunaga and Hideyoshi resurrected in the world in the period of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Yagyu clan that declined once in the period of Nobunaga and Hideyoshi resurrected in the world in the period of Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>宗矩の台頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rise of Munenori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rise of Munenori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rise of Munenori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>宗矩は宗厳の五男である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munenori is the fifth son of Munetoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munenori was the fifth son of Munetoshi.</e>
<cmt>時制。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munenori was the fifth son of Munetoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>徳川氏に仕えることとなったのは、長男の柳生厳勝は久秀配下として筒井順慶と戦ったとき、鉄砲により戦傷を負い、次男の柳生久斎と三男の柳生徳斎は僧侶となり、四男の柳生宗章は中村一氏に仕官していたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munenori was available for serving the Tokugawa clan because the eldest son Yoshikatsu YAGYU was hurt by a gun in a battle against Junkei TSUTSUI as a vassal of Hisahide, the second son Kyusai YAGYU and the third son Tokusai YAGYU became Buddhist priests, and the fourth son Muneaki YAGYU served Kazuuji NAKAMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetoshi&apos;s first son Yoshikatsu YAGYU had served Hisahide and in the battle against Junkei TSUTSUI, he had been shot and badly injured; the second son Kyusai YAGYU and the third son Tokusai YAGYU had become priests; and the fourth son Muneaki YAGYU had served Kazuuji NAKAMURA; so when Ieyasu requested Munetoshi to become an instructor, only Munenori happened to be available for serving the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetoshi&apos;s first son Yoshikatsu YAGYU had served Hisahide and in the battle against Junkei TSUTSUI, he had been shot and badly injured; the second son Kyusai YAGYU and the third son Tokusai YAGYU had become priests; and the fourth son Muneaki YAGYU had served Kazuuji NAKAMURA; so when Ieyasu requested Munetoshi to become an instructor, only Munenori happened to be available for serving the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>家康に仕えた宗矩は、大いに活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munenori made great performance under Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munenori made great performance under Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munenori made great performance under Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1600年の関ヶ原の戦いでは家康の命を受けて大和の豪族の調略に従事し、西軍の後方攪乱作戦も務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he worked out a scheme to disturb local ruling clans of Yamato and conducted alarmist tactics in the rear area of the Western Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, by the order of Ieyasu, he played important role using especially his brain to suppress local governors of Yamato Province and to disturb the logistic support of the Western Army.</e>
<cmt>誤訳。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, by the order of Ieyasu, he played an important role using especially his brain to suppress local governors of Yamato Province and to disturb the logistic support of the Western Army.</e>
<cmt>played important role→played an important role</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>翌年、その功績により旧領2000石に加えて新たに1000石を加増され、徳川秀忠の兵法指南役となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, he was granted his former feud of 2,000 goku and an additional territory of 1,000 goku for his achievements in the Battle, and became the instructor of swordplay for Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, for the achievements in the battle, he was given additional stipend of 1,000 goku while maintaining the former stipend of 2,000 goku, and he was appointed to the instructor of Heiho for Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, for the achievements in the battle, he was given additional stipend of 1,000 goku while maintaining the former stipend of 2,000 goku, and he was appointed to the instructor of Heiho for Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>宗矩は秀忠からの信任が厚かったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munenori is said to have enjoyed the deep confidence of Hidetada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that Hidetada had every confidence in Munenori.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that Hidetada had every confidence in Munenori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1614年の大坂冬の陣では徳川軍の大和国の道案内役を務め、翌年の大坂夏の陣では秀忠の身辺警護を務め、敵兵7名を斬り殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Osaka Fuyu no Jin (Winter Siege of Osaka) in 1614, he lead the Tokugawa forces the way in Yamato Province, and in the Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka) in the following year he managed personal protection of Hidetada and killed seven enemy soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Winter Siege of Osaka of 1614, Munenori served as a guide to lead the large-scale Tokugawa Army in Yamato Province; in Summer Siege of Osaka of the next year, he served as a personal bodyguard for Hidetada and in fact he killed seven soldiers to protect his master.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Winter Siege of Osaka of 1614, Munenori served as a guide to lead the large-scale Tokugawa Army in Yamato Province; in Summer Siege of Osaka of the next year, he served as a personal bodyguard for Hidetada and in fact he killed seven soldiers to protect his master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>1621年からは徳川家光の兵法指南役となり、1629年には従五位下但馬国守を叙任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1621, he became the instructor of swordplay for Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, and was appointed as Tajima no kuni no kami (Governor of Tajima Province) with a court rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) in 1629.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1621, he became the instructor of Heiho for Iemitsu TOKUGAWA; and in 1629, he was appointed to Tajima-no-kuni no kami (Governor of Tajima Province) and given a court rank, Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1621, he became the instructor of Heiho for Iemitsu TOKUGAWA; and in 1629, he was appointed to Tajima-no-kuni no kami (Governor of Tajima Province) and given a court rank, Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1632年には井上政重らと共に総目付（後の大目付）に任じられ、3000石を加増された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1632, Munenori was appointed as Sometsuke (chief inspector of the Edo shogunate) (which was later renamed Ometsuke) together with Masashige INOUE and was granted additional 3,000 goku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1632, Munenori was appointed as Sometsuke (chief inspector of shogunate which was later renamed &quot;Ometsuke&quot;) together with Masashige INOUE and was given additional stipend 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1632, Munenori was appointed as Sometsuke (chief inspector of shogunate which was later renamed &quot;Ometsuke&quot;) together with Masashige INOUE and was given additional stipend 3,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1636年には4000石を加増され、合計1万石の大名となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1636, he obtained 4,000 goku additionally, which made him a daimyo with a total goku of 10,000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1636, he obtained 4,000 goku additionally, which made him a daimyo with a total goku of 10,000 (1803.9 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすく立方メートル表記を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1636, he obtained 4,000 goku additionally, which made him a daimyo with a total goku of 10,000 (1803.9 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1639年にも2000石、翌年にも500石を加増され、合計して1万2500石を領する大名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1639 and 1640, he was further awarded 2,000 goku and 500 goku, respectively, to become a daimyo with his feud of 12,500 goku in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1640, he was further awarded 2,000 goku and 500 goku, respectively, to become a daimyo with his feud of 12,500 goku (2254.875 cubic meters) in total.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすく立方メートル表記を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1640, he was further awarded 2,000 goku and 500 goku, respectively, to become a daimyo with his feud of 12,500 goku (2254.875 cubic meters) in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>宗矩と同時期に徳川氏に仕えていた小野派一刀流の開祖・小野忠明（御子神典膳）の所領はわずか600石ほどに過ぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaaki ONO (Mikogamitenzen), Munenori&apos;s contemporary vassal of the Tokugawa clan and the founder of Onohaittoryu school, was only allowed to have a territory worth about 600 goku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaaki ONO (Mikogamitenzen) was served the Tokugawa clan in the same period as Munenori, he was an instructor of swordsmanship as well and founded Ono-ha Itto-ryu School, however, he was given rice stipend only 600 koku (108.234 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。grammar and flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaaki ONO (Mikogamitenzen) who served the Tokugawa clan in the same period as Munenori, was an instructor of swordsmanship as well and founded Ono-ha Itto-ryu School, however, he was given rice stipend only 600 koku (108.234 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>was served →who served he was→was</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>一方の宗矩は家康・秀忠・家光の徳川三代に仕えて大名にまで栄進したのだから、相当の信任を受けていたことがうかがえるであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering the fact that Munenori served three Tokugawa shoguns, Ieyasu, Hidetada and Iemitsu, and was promoted to the daimyo class, it follows that he had the great confidence of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the fact that Munenori served three Tokugawa shoguns, Ieyasu, Hidetada and Iemitsu, and was promoted to the daimyo class, it follows that he had the great confidence of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the fact that Munenori served three Tokugawa shoguns, Ieyasu, Hidetada and Iemitsu, and was promoted to the daimyo class, it follows that he had the great confidence of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), Y.Sanada(id:36926), 松茸(id:27535), 味っ子(id:17086), Seibuabina(id:37532), Kamakura(id:472), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), 大日本帝國海軍博物學大尉(id:98848), 赤井彗星(id:18381), 下川直哉(id:248185), コネ(id:15481), KSKS(id:97637), Loveless(id:129239), Fievarsty(id:201483), Louperibot(id:128971), 石田光成(id:232658), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>