<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三室戸家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mimurodo family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mimurodo family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mimurodo Family</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三室戸家（みむろどけ、「みむろと」の読みは誤記）は、名家 (公家)の家格を有する公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mimurodo family (pronunciation &apos;Mimuroto&apos; is a recording error) had a court noble family rank of Meike.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mimurodo family (pronunciation &apos;Mimuroto&apos; is a recording error) held the court noble family rank of Meike.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mimurodo family (pronunciation &apos;Mimuroto&apos; is a recording error) held the court noble family rank of Meike.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家藤原真夏流日野家流柳原家庶流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A collateral branch of the Yanagiwaka family line of the Hino family line of the FUJIWARA no Manatsu line of the Northern House of the FUJIWARA clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were a collateral branch of the Yanagiwaka family line of the Hino family line of the FUJIWARA no Manatsu line of the Northern House of the FUJIWARA clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were a collateral branch of the Yanagiwara family line of the Hino family line of the FUJIWARA no Manatsu line of the Northern House of the FUJIWARA clan.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家業は文学・華道（竹真流）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family inherited the hereditary art of flower arrangement Chikushin School and literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family inherited the hereditary art of flower arrangement, the Chikushin School and literature.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family inherited the hereditary art of flower arrangement, the Chikushin School and literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は130石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hereditary stipend during the Edo period was 130 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their hereditary stipend during the Edo period was 130 koku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their hereditary stipend during the Edo period was 130 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家紋は鶴の丸（但し先端の羽根は本家同様3本）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its family crest was &apos;Wing-Spreading Crane&apos;, the wingtip feathers of which are three like the crest of the main family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its family crest was a &apos;Wing-Spreading Crane,&apos; the wingtip feathers of which are three like the crest of the main family.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its family crest was a &apos;Wing-Spreading Crane,&apos; the wingtip feathers of which are three like the crest of the main family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>明治維新後、子爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the family held the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the family held the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the family held the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>柳原資行の3男三室戸誠光（ともみつ）を祖として江戸時代前期に創設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mimurodo family was founded in the early Edo period by Tomomitsu, the third son of Sukeyuki YANAGIWARA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mimurodo family was founded during the early Edo period by Tomomitsu, the third son of Sukeyuki YANAGIWARA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mimurodo family was founded during the early Edo period by Tomomitsu, the third son of Sukeyuki YANAGIWARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>当初は北小路と称したが、寛文5年（1665年）7月、願いにより三室戸と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, they called themselves &apos;Kitakoji&apos;, but in September 1665, their petition was sanctioned and they were renamed &apos;Mimurodo&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, they called themselves &apos;Kitakoji,&apos; but in September 1665, their petition was sanctioned and they were renamed &apos;Mimurodo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, they called themselves &apos;Kitakoji,&apos; but in August 1665, their petition was sanctioned and they were renamed &apos;Mimurodo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>誠光の兄の柳原資廉は霊元天皇の従兄弟にあたり、武家伝奏をつとめて幕府との交渉に活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukekado YANAGIWARA, an elder brother of Tomomitsu and a cousin of Emperor Reigen, served as the court official intermediary between the court and the bakufu called Buke Denso and played an active role in negotiation--Incidentally, he had come from Kyoto to Edo castle and present during the Ako Incident, which was a bloodshed incident caused by Naganori ASANO, the lord of Ako in Harima Province, who was served as an attendant at a reception for the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukekado YANAGIWARA, an elder brother of Tomomitsu and a cousin of the Emperor Reigen, served as an official intermediary between the court and the bakufu called Buke Denso and played an active role in negotiations--Incidentally, he had come from Kyoto to Edo castle and was present during the Ako Incident, which was an act of bloodshed caused by Naganori ASANO, the lord of Ako in Harima Province, who served as an attendant at a reception for the shogun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukekado YANAGIWARA, an elder brother of Tomomitsu and a cousin of the Emperor Reigen, served as an official intermediary between the court and the bakufu called Buke Denso and played an active role in negotiations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>特に赤穂藩主浅野長矩が饗応役を務めた際に起こった刃傷事件（元禄赤穂事件）の時に江戸城に下向していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, he had come from Kyoto to Edo-jo Castle and was present during the Ako Incident, which was an act of bloodshed caused by Naganori ASANO, the lord of Ako in Harima Province, who served as an attendant at a reception for the shogun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>歴代は多く三位、非参議であったが、三室戸光村は参議に、三室戸能光は大納言に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of the MIMURODO family was promoted to Sanmi, Hisangi for many generations, except for Mitsumura MIMURODO who was promoted to Sangi and Yasumitsu MIMURODO who was promoted to Major Counselor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of the MIMURODO family was promoted to Sanmi, Hisangi for many generations, except for Mitsumura MIMURODO who was promoted to Sangi and Yasumitsu MIMURODO who was promoted to Major Counselor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of the Mimurodo family was promoted to Sanmi, Hisangi for many generations, except for Mitsumura MIMURODO who was promoted to Sangi and Yasumitsu MIMURODO who was promoted to Major Counselor.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>江戸期までは華道竹真流家元を称していたが、敬光により三重県桑名市にある寺に家元を譲っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family proclaimed the headmaster of Chikushin school of flower arrangement until the Edo period, but Yukimitsu MIMURODO transferred the headmaster title to a temple in Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family proclaimed the headmaster of the Chikushin school of flower arrangement until the Edo period, but Yukimitsu MIMURODO transferred the headmaster title to a temple in Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family proclaimed the headmaster of the Chikushin school of flower arrangement until the Edo period, but Yukimitsu MIMURODO transferred the headmaster title to a temple in Kuwana City, Mie Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>三室戸和光は大正期に伊勢神宮大宮司となり、三室戸雄光の実子三室戸治光も平安神宮宮司となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Taisho period, Masamitsu MIMURODO became the High Priest of Ise Grand Shrine; similarly, Harumitsu MIMURODO, a biological son of Takemitsu MIMURODO, became the head priest of Heian Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Taisho period, Masamitsu MIMURODO became the High Priest of the Ise Grand Shrine; similarly, Harumitsu MIMURODO, the biological son of Takemitsu MIMURODO, became the head priest of the Heian Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Taisho period, Masamitsu MIMURODO became the High Priest of the Ise Grand Shrine; similarly, Harumitsu MIMURODO, the biological son of Takemitsu MIMURODO, became the head priest of the Heian Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>三室戸敬光は昭和初期に貴族院 (日本)議員（会派は研究会）に互選され、特に1935年（昭和10年）に起こったいわゆる天皇機関説問題に際して、男爵菊池武夫 (陸軍軍人)議員とともに美濃部達吉を追求し辞職に追い込み、さらには国体明徴声明を岡田内閣に出させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Showa period, Yukimitsu MIMURODO was elected a member of the House of Peers (belonged to the group &apos;Kenkyukai&apos;) through mutual election; and in the dispute over &quot;Emperor as an organ of government Theory&quot; started in 1935, Yukimitsu, together with another member of the House, Baron Takeo KIKUCHI (the Japanese Imperial Army soldier), questioned Tatsukichi MINOBE, the advocate of the theory, and forced him to resign from the House of Peers, and besides, made Okada Cabinet to issue the Kokutai Meicho proclamation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the early Showa period, Yukimitsu MIMURODO was elected a member of the House of Peers (belonging to the group &apos;Kenkyukai&apos;) through mutual election; and in a dispute over the &quot;Emperor as an organ of government Theory&quot; started in 1935, Yukimitsu, together with another member of the House, Baron Takeo KIKUCHI (a Japanese Imperial Army soldier), questioned Tatsukichi MINOBE, the advocate of the theory, and forced him to resign from the House of Peers, and also, made the Okada Cabinet to issue the Kokutai Meicho proclamation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the early Showa period, Yukimitsu MIMURODO was elected a member of the House of Peers (belonging to the group &apos;Kenkyukai&apos;) through mutual election; and in a dispute over the &quot;Emperor as an organ of government Theory&quot; started in 1935, Yukimitsu, together with another member of the House, Baron Takeo KIKUCHI (a Japanese Imperial Army soldier), questioned Tatsukichi MINOBE, the advocate of the theory, and forced him to resign from the House of Peers, and also, made the Okada Cabinet to issue the Kokutai Meicho proclamation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>また1934年（昭和9年）には、斎藤内閣の商工大臣であった中島久万吉が雑誌「現代」2月号に転載された足利尊氏と足利時代（室町時代）を再評価すべきという感想を述べたことに対して、菊池議員と共に中島大臣を攻撃し辞職させたことでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was well-known that, in 1934, Kumakichi NAKAJIMA, the Minister of Commerce and Industry in the Sato Cabinet, stated in his article reprinted in February issue of monthly magazine &quot;Gendai&quot; (Modern times) that Takauji ASHIKAGA and the Ashikaga era (i.e., the Muromachi period) should be transvalued; and Yukimitsu, together with Takeo KIKUCHI, censured Kumakichi NAKAJIMA and forced him to resign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was well-known that, in 1934, Kumakichi NAKAJIMA, the Minister of Commerce and Industry in the Sato Cabinet, stated in his article reprinted in the February issue of the monthly magazine &quot;Gendai&quot; (Modern times) that Takauji ASHIKAGA and the Ashikaga era (i.e., the Muromachi period) should be transvalued; and Yukimitsu, together with Takeo KIKUCHI, censured Kumakichi NAKAJIMA and forced him to resign.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was well-known that, in 1934, Kumakichi NAKAJIMA, the Minister of Commerce and Industry in the Sato Cabinet, stated in his article reprinted in the February issue of the monthly magazine &quot;Gendai&quot; (Modern times) that Takauji ASHIKAGA and the Ashikaga era (i.e., the Muromachi period) should be transvalued; and Yukimitsu, together with Takeo KIKUCHI, censured Kumakichi NAKAJIMA and forced him to resign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、敬光は昭和初期に東京高等音楽学院長（現・国立音楽大学）を務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Showa period, Yukimitsu filled the post of the headmaster of the Tokyo-Koto-Ongakugakuin (present the Kunitachi College of Music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Showa period, Yukimitsu filled the post of the headmaster of the Tokyo-Koto-Ongakugakuin (present day Kunitachi College of Music).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Showa period, Yukimitsu filled the post of the headmaster of the Tokyo-Koto-Ongakugakuin (present day Kunitachi College of Music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>戦後、公職追放とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After World War II, Yukimitsu purged from public service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War II, Yukimitsu was purged from public service.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War II, Yukimitsu was purged from public service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>敬光の長男三室戸為光は、1938年（昭和13年）に東京高等音楽学院の大塚分教場を東邦音楽学校として（のちの東邦音楽大学・東邦音楽短期大学）を独立・創設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1938, Tamemitsu MIMURODO, the first son of Yukimitsu, made the Otsuka branch school of the Tokyo-Koto-Ongakugakuin independent to found Toho-Ongakugakko (later, Toho College of Music, and Toho Junior College of Music).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1938, Tamemitsu MIMURODO, the first son of Yukimitsu, made the Otsuka branch school of the Tokyo-Koto-Ongakugakuin independent to found Toho-Ongakugakko (later, the Toho College of Music, and Toho Junior College of Music).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1938, Tamemitsu MIMURODO, the first son of Yukimitsu, made the Otsuka branch school of the Tokyo-Koto-Ongakugakuin independent to found Toho-Ongakugakko (later, the Toho College of Music, and Toho Junior College of Music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 お掃除大好き(id:99320), BAKU(id:55205), 松茸(id:27535), M3HR(id:45797), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>