<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>唐橋家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house of Karahashi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house of Karahashi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Karahashi family</e>
<cmt>house of→family</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>唐橋家（からはしけ）は菅原在良（位階・式部省・贈従三位）（1041年 - 1121年）を祖とする堂上家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house of Karahashi, one of the houses of Dojo, was established by SUGAWARA no Ariyoshi (Court Rank, Department of Civil Office and Education, Conferred Junior Third Court Rank, 1041-1121).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house of Karahashi, one of the houses of Dojo, was established by SUGAWARA no Ariyoshi (Court Rank, Department of Civil Office and Education, Conferred Junior Third Rank, 1041-1121).</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;Junior Third Court Rank&quot; to &quot;Junior Third Rank&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Karahashi family, one of the houses of Dojo, was established by SUGAWARA no Ariyoshi (Court Rank, Department of Civil Office and Education, Conferred Junior Third Rank, 1041 - 1121).</e>
<cmt>house of→familyハイフンの前後にスペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>高辻是綱（位階・大学寮）（1030年 - 1107年）は在良の兄に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koretsuna TAKATSUJI (Court Rank, the Bureau of Educaion, 1030-1107) was Ariyoshi&apos;s elder brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koretsuna TAKATSUJI (Court Rank, the Bureau of Educaion, 1030-1107) was Ariyoshi&apos;s elder brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koretsuna TAKATSUJI (Court Rank, the Bureau of Education, 1030 - 1107) was Ariyoshi&apos;s elder brother.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンの前後にスペーススペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>正式には鎌倉時代末期から南北朝時代 (日本)の唐橋有雅（位階・大膳職）（1275年 - 1356年）から唐橋の家名を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family name of Karahashi was officially given during the time of Arimasa KARAHASHI (Court Rank, the Office of the Palace Table, 1275-1356) from the late Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family name of Karahashi was officially given during the time of Arimasa KARAHASHI (Court Rank, the Office of the Palace Table, 127j5-1356), some time between the late Kamakura period and the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>The name was not given over a period of time, so I changed &quot;from..to&quot; to &quot;some time between&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family name of Karahashi was officially given during the time of Arimasa KARAHASHI (Court Rank, the Office of the Palace Table, 1275 - 1356), some time between the late Kamakura period and the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>127j5-1356→1275 - 1356</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>室町時代には九条家の家司となるが、明応5年（1496年）に九条家の経営に関するトラブルから唐橋在数（位階・大学寮中務省）（1448年 - 1496年）が九条政基・九条尚経に殺害される事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the family served the house of Kujo as the household manager, but in 1496, the trouble over the house of Kujo&apos;s business occurred, which led to such a situation that Arikazu KARAHASHI (Court Rank, the Bureau of Educaion, Department of the Imperial Palace, 1448-1496) was killed by Masamoto KUJO and Hisatsune KUJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, the family served the house of Kujo as household managers, but in 1496, trouble occurred in connection the house of Kujo&apos;s business, and this led to the killing of Arikazu KARAHASHI (Court Rank, the Bureau of Education, Department of the Imperial Palace, 1448-1496) by Masamoto KUJO and hs son, Hisatsune KUJO.</e>
<cmt>Retained structure of first translation but improved readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the family served the Kujo family as household managers, but in 1496, trouble occurred in connection with the Kujo family&apos;s business, and this led to the killing of Arikazu KARAHASHI (Court Rank, the Bureau of Education, Department of the Imperial Palace, 1448 - 1496) by Masamoto KUJO and his son, Hisatsune KUJO.</e>
<cmt>house of→familyスペース削除ハイフンの前後にスペースhs→hisin connection→in connection with</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、菅原氏一族からの猛烈な抗議により、九条政基・九条尚経父子は後土御門天皇の勅勘を蒙ることになり、唐橋家の危機は免れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Sugawara family made a protest so strongly that Masamoto KUJO and his son, Hisatsune KUJO, incurred Emperor Gotsuchimikado&apos;s censure; thus, the house of Karahashi could get over the crisis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Sugawara family protested so strongly that Masamoto KUJO and Hisatsune KUJO were censured by Emperor Gotsuchimikado, and the house of Karahashi was able to overcome the crisis.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;his son&quot; to previous sentence, and changed for greater readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Sugawara clan protested so strongly that Masamoto KUJO and Hisatsune KUJO were censured by the Emperor Gotsuchimikado, and the Karahashi family was able to overcome the crisis.</e>
<cmt>house of→familyfamily→clan&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>家格は半家 (公家)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was ranked as &quot;Hanke,&quot; a type of family status of the Court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was ranked as &quot;Hanke,&quot; a type of family status in the Court nobility.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;of the Court nobles&quot; to &quot;in the court nobility&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was ranked as &quot;Hanke,&quot; a type of family status in the Court nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>唐橋在豊（1391年 - 1464年）以降、唐橋家は中務省・大学寮・大学寮等を経て、権大納言を極官とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house of Karahashi served as the official of Department of the Imperial Palace, Professor of Literature, and Director of the Bureau of Educaion after the time of Aritoyo KARAHASHI (1391-1464), and the top rank the family could attain was the Junior Chief Councillor of State.</e>
<cmt>「唐橋家は中務省・大学寮・大学寮等を経て」とありますが、意味がおかしいと思いWikipedia本文をあたったところ、「大内記・文章博士・大学頭を経て」となっていましたので、そのように訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the time of Aritoyo KARAHASHI (1391-1464) onwards, the house of Karahashi provided an official of Department of the Imperial Palace, a Professor of Literature, and a Director of the Bureau of Education, with the top rank attained being Junior Chief Councillor of State.</e>
<cmt>&quot;以降&quot; includes the time of Aritoyo. I aslo made changes for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the time of Aritoyo KARAHASHI (1391 - 1464) onwards, the Karahashi family provided an official of Department of the Imperial Palace, a Professor of Literature, and a Director of the Bureau of Education, with the top rank attained being Junior Chief Councillor of State.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンの前後にスペースhouse of→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代後期の唐橋在家は有職故実の研究に熱心で、元服について記した『冠儀浅寡抄』、笏についての『畢用録』、老人の装束故実をまとめた『宿徳装束抄』、狩衣について記した『布衣群色便蒙抄』など多くの著書がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Edo period, Ariie KARAHASHI was devoted to the study of court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette, and wrote many books: &quot;Kangi-senka-sho&quot; about the ceremony of attaining manhood, &quot;Hitsuyo-roku&quot; about a scepter, &quot;Syutoku-shozoku-sho&quot; about costumes for the aged, and &quot;Hoi-gunnshoku-benmo-sho&quot; about informal clothes worn by Court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Edo period, Ariie KARAHASHI devoted himself to the study of court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette, and wrote many books, including &quot;Kangi-senka-sho&quot; about the ceremony of attaining manhood, &quot;Hitsuyo-roku&quot; about scepters, &quot;Syutoku-shozoku-sho&quot; about the clothes of the old, and &quot;Hoi-gunnshoku-benmo-sho&quot; about informal clothes worn by Court nobles.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Edo period, Ariie KARAHASHI devoted himself to the study of court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette, and wrote many books, including &quot;Kangi-senka-sho&quot; about the ceremony of attaining manhood, &quot;Hitsuyo-roku&quot; about scepters, &quot;Shutoku-shozoku-sho&quot; about the clothes of the old, and &quot;Hoi-gunshoku-benmo-sho&quot; about informal clothes worn by Court nobles.</e>
<cmt>Syutoku→Shutokugunnshoku→gunshoku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>家業は紀伝道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house business: &quot;Kidendo,&quot; the study of the histories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house business, &quot;Kidendo,&quot; the study of the histories.</e>
<cmt>Changed colon to comma.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The house business, &quot;Kidendo,&quot; the study of the histories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は182石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 182 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 182 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 182 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>明治時代以降は子爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji period, the family was given the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji period, the family was given the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji period, the family was given the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Iwaro(id:60082), Haeha(id:9372), Kaba(id:17904), NDR(id:5500), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Law soma(id:45202), ウラヌス(id:25954), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>