<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>住友家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt>As a subhead</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>住友家（すみともけ）は住友財閥の創業者一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitomo Family is a founding family of Sumitomo Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sumitomo Family is a founding family of Sumitomo Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sumitomo Family is the founding family of Sumitomo Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt>The founder of the Sumitomo Zaibatsu is the Sumitomo family. I changed &quot;a&quot; to &quot;the.&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>住友家の起源－始祖・家祖・業祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of Sumitomo Family - earliest ancestor, Founder of a family, and Founder of business</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the Sumitomo Family: Earliest ancestor, founder of a family, and founder of business</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the Sumitomo Family: Earliest ancestor, progenitor, and business founder</e>
<cmt>As this is a subheading there is no need for an article and</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>住友家の始祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Earliest ancestor of Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Earliest ancestor of the Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Earliest ancestor of the Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>住友の姓は、戦国の末、もともと先祖に順美平内友定という人物がおり、桓武天皇の曾孫・高望王の二十二代目にその子・小太郎（忠重）が父の姓と名をとって「住友」の姓を称して室町将軍に仕えて、備中守に任じられたのに始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surname of Sumitomo originates from Kotaro (Tadashige), the 22nd generation descendant of Takamochi-oh who is a great grandson of Kanmu Emperor, who took the surname of &quot;Sumitomo&quot; after the surname and given name of his father, Masami Hirauchi Tomosada who lived in the end of Sengoku period, and Kotaro served Muromachi Shogun and was appointed to be Bichumori Guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surname of Sumitomo originates from Kotaro (Tadashige), the twenty-second-generation descendant of Takamochi-oh, a great grandson of Emperor Kanmu, who took the surname &quot;Sumitomo&quot; after the surname and given name of his father, Masami Hirauchi Tomosada, who lived at the end of the Sengoku period; and Kotaro served Shogun Muromachi and was appointed as the Bichumori guard.</e>
<cmt>This is generally a little hard to read but the main problem for the reader would be that the explanation of how the surname &quot;Sumitomo&quot; was created doesn&apos;t seem to make much sense. How do you get &quot;Sumitomo&quot; from &quot;Masami&quot; and &quot;Tomosada&quot;? It may be clear in Japanese, but an explanation that makes logical sense also needs to be provided in the English translation. 原文の「順美平内友定」という名前の姓と名をとるとなぜ「住友」になるのか、「順美」＝「住」と想像しウェブ等で調べましたが、確証がとれませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surname of Sumitomo originates from Kotaro (Tadashige), the twenty-second-generation descendant of Takamochi-oh, a great grandson of Emperor Kanmu, who took the surname &quot;Sumitomo&quot; after the surname and given name of his father, Masami Hirauchi Tomosada, who lived at the end of the Sengoku period; and Kotaro served Shogun Muromachi and was appointed as the Bichumori guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>平家の末裔である戦国武士だった住友家の先祖は、国取り物語の戦国時代 (日本)を有為転変の歴史を生きる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancestors of Sumitomo Family, who were Sengoku Samurai and descendants of Heike, lived in a history of shifts and changes in the Sengoku Period (Japan) when warriors fighted against each other to expand their lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ancestors of the Sumitomo Family, who were Sengoku samurai and descendants of Heike, lived during a history of shifts and changes in the Sengoku period of Japan, when warriors fought each other in order to expand their lands.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ancestors of the Sumitomo Family, who were Sengoku samurai and descendants of Heike, lived during the tumultuous period of Japanese history known as the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States), when warriors fought each other in order to expand their lands.</e>
<cmt>a history of shifts and changes in the Sengoku period→the tumultuous period of Japanese history known as Sengoku periodEven without looking at the Japanese, it seems safe to assume that &quot;a history of shifts and changes in the Sengoku period&quot; could probably be more naturally expressed as &quot;the tumultuous period of Japanese history known as the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States)&quot;.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>室町将軍に仕えた「始祖」・住友忠重の子・頼定は、足利義晴に仕え、頼定の子・定信は刑部承と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;earliest ancestor&quot; Tadashige SUMITOMO who served Muromachi Shogun had a son Yorisada who served Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, and Yorisada&apos;s son Sadanobu called himself as Osakabe-sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;earliest ancestor,&quot; Tadashige SUMITOMO, who served Shogun Muromachi, had a son called Yorisada who served Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, and Yorisada&apos;s son Sadanobu called himself Osakabe-sho.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;earliest ancestor,&quot; Tadashige SUMITOMO, who served Shogun Muromachi, had a son called Yorisada who served Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA, and Yorisada&apos;s son Sadanobu called himself Osakabe-sho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして、定信の子・定重は、今川義忠（今川義元の祖父）に仕えるが、定重の子・信定の代になり、今川氏が滅んでしまったので、摂津の中川清秀に仕え、入江土佐守と称し、中川十六騎の一人として知られたが、尾崎の陣で戦死してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Sadanobu&apos;s son Sadashige served Yoshitada IMAGAWA (grandfather of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA), and in the generation of Nobusada, a son of Sadashige, since Imagawa clan was extinguished, Sadashige served Kiyohide NAKAGAWA in Settsu and called himself as Irie Tosanokami Guard and was known as one of Nakagawa sixteen horse, but died in Ozaki-no-jin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Sadanobu&apos;s son Sadashige served Yoshitada IMAGAWA (the grandfather of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA); and in the generation of Nobusada a son of Sadashige, because the Imagawa clan was extinguished, Sadashige served Kiyohide NAKAGAWA in Settsu and called himself the Irie Tosanokami guard; he was known as one of the &quot;sixteen horses of Nakagawa&quot; but died in Ozaki-no-jin.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Sadanobu&apos;s son Sadashige served Yoshitada IMAGAWA (the grandfather of Yoshimoto IMAGAWA). After the Imagawa clan was destroyed during Nobusada&apos;s lifetime, Sadashige&apos;s son served Kiyohide NAKAGAWA in Settsu, calling himself the guardian of Irie Tosanokami. He was known as one of the &quot;sixteen horses of Nakagawa&quot;, but died during the Battle of Ozaki.</e>
<cmt>&quot;extinguished&quot; and &quot;in the generation of&quot; sound odd here so I have rewritten these parts of the sentence. Also, a native speaker of English is unlikely to know what &quot;XXX-no-jin&quot; means so this should be rendered in English as &quot;the Battle of XXX&quot;.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また入江土佐守（信定）の子・政俊は越前国の柴田氏に仕え、若狭守と称し越前丸岡城にあったが、柴田勝家と共に北庄城で滅んでしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Irie Tosanokami Guard (Nobusada)&apos;s son Masatoshi served Shibata clan in Echizen-no-kuni, called himself as Wakasamori Guard, and was in Echizen-Maruoka-jo Castle, but died in Hokujo-jo Castle together with Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Irie Tosanokami guard (Nobusada)&apos;s son Masatoshi served the Shibata clan in Echizen-no-kuni, called himself the Wakasamori guard; he was stationed in Echizen-Maruoka-jo Castle but died in Hokujo-jo Castle together with Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Irie Tosanokami guard (Nobusada)&apos;s son Masatoshi served the Shibata clan in Echizen-no-kuni, called himself the Wakasamori guard; he was stationed in Echizen-Maruoka-jo Castle but died in Hokujo-jo Castle together with Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>政俊の子・長行は、徳川家康の子で結城家へ養子入りした結城秀康に用いられるが、住友家の武家の歴史はここまでである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatoshi&apos;s son Nagamichi was employed by Hideyasu YUKI who was a son of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and was adopted as son-in-law by Yuki Family, which is the end of the history of Sumitomo Family as a Samurai family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatoshi&apos;s son Nagamichi was employed by Hideyasu YUKI, who was a son of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and was adopted as a son-in-law by the Yuki Family, thus ending the history of the Sumitomo as a Samurai family.</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatoshi&apos;s son Nagamichi was employed by Hideyasu YUKI, who was a son of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and was adopted as a son-in-law by the Yuki Family, thus ending the history of the Sumitomo as a Samurai family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>戦国の習いとはいえ、武家社会の興亡の激しさと無情を感じたのか長行は、自分の子供たちに武家の世界から足を洗わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamichi, who might have felt severity and heartlessness of ups and downs of the society of Samulai family although that was the way of Sengoku, ordered his children to leave the world of Samurai family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamichi, who might have felt the severity and heartlessness of the ups and downs of the society of samurai families (although that was the way of Sengoku), ordered his children to leave the world of samurai families.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamichi, who might have felt the severity and heartlessness of the ups and downs of the society of samurai families (although that was the way of Sengoku), ordered his children to leave the world of samurai families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>初代政友・「富士屋」の創業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first generation, Masatomo, foundation of &quot;Fujiya&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first generation, Masatomo, foundation of &quot;Fujiya&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first generation, Masatomo, foundation of &quot;Fujiya&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>長行の二男で兄の興兵衛に代わって家督を継いだ住友政友は、天正年間に生まれ、涅槃宗 (日本)の開祖、空源乃意上人にしたがって仏門に入り「文殊院空禅」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamichi&apos;s second son, Masatomo SUMITOMO, who inherited the family estate instead of his elder brother Kobe, was born in the Tenpo era, studied under Giyuishonin-Kugen, founder of Nehan-shu sect, and became a Buddhist to call himself as &quot;Monjuin Kuzen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamichi&apos;s second son, Masatomo SUMITOMO, who had inherited the family estate instead of his elder brother Kobe, was born during the Tenpo era, studied under Giyuishonin-Kugen (the founder of the Nehan-shu sect) and became a Buddhist who called himself &quot;Monjuin Kuzen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamichi&apos;s second son, Masatomo SUMITOMO, who had inherited the family estate instead of his elder brother Kobe, was born during the Tensho era, studied under Giyuishonin-Kugen (the founder of the Nehan-shu sect) and became a Buddhist who called himself &quot;Monjuin Kuzen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>天正のスペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>宏学達識で涅槃宗の後継者と見られていたが、寛永年間に涅槃宗が天台宗に吸収されたのを機に還俗し、洛中に、書籍と医薬品を商う「富士屋」を開き、号を嘉休と称し修道三昧の生活を始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being omniscient and considered as the successor of Nehan-shu sect, Masatomo came back to secular life after Nehan-shu sect was absorbed into Tendai-shu sect in the Kanei era, and opened &quot;Fujiya&quot; dealing with books and pharmaceuticals in Rakuchu, named the go Kakyu, and started the hardworking life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatomo, who was considered the omniscient successor of the Nehan-shu sect, returned to secular life after the Nehan-shu sect was absorbed into the Tendai-shu sect during the Kanei era and opened &quot;Fujiya,&quot; a business dealing with books and pharmaceuticals in Rakuchu (called the go-Kakyu), and started a hardworking life.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatomo, who was considered the omniscient successor of the Nehan-shu sect, returned to secular life after the Nehan-shu sect was absorbed into the Tendai-shu sect during the Kanei era and opened &quot;Fujiya,&quot; a business dealing with books and pharmaceuticals in Rakuchu (called himself Kakyu), and started a hardworking life.</e>
<cmt>the go-削除（号を訳してもわかりにくいので、嘉休と名乗ったと訳しました。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これが「町人・住友家」の興りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the beginning of &quot;Sumitomo Family as merchant.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This marked the beginning of the Sumitomo Family as merchants.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This marked the beginning of the Sumitomo Family as merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>政友は商売上の心得を『文殊院旨意書』にまとめたが、これは現在に至るまで住友グループ各社の社是の原型となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatomo wrote about directions pertaining to business in &quot;Monjuin&apos;s directions,&quot; which is the prototype of company codes of each company of the Sumitomo group to date.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatomo wrote instructions pertaining to business in &quot;Monjuin&apos;s Directions,&quot; which remains the prototype for company codes in each company of the Sumitomo Group to the present day.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatomo wrote instructions pertaining to business in &quot;Monjuin&apos;s Directions,&quot; which remains the prototype for company codes in each company of the Sumitomo Group to the present day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>住友家の家祖と業祖・「泉屋」の創業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founder of a family and Founder of business of Sumitomo Family, foundation of Senoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of a family and founder of the Sumitomo family business, the foundation of Senoku</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of a family and founder of the Sumitomo family business, the foundation of Senoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>住友家には、住友家の「家祖」と、住友家の事業の「業祖」の2人がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Smitomo Family, there are two people, &quot;Founder of a family&quot; of Sumitomo Family and &quot;Founder of business&quot; of Sumitomo Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sumitomo Family there are two distinctions: the &quot;founder of a family&quot; in the Sumitomo Family, and the &quot;founder of a business&quot; of the Sumitomo Family.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Sumitomo Family there are two distinctions: the &quot;founder of a family&quot; in the Sumitomo Family, and the &quot;founder of a business&quot; of the Sumitomo Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>嘉休こと住友政友（家祖）には一男一女があり、男の子政以には「富士屋」の跡を継がせ、女の子には、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatomo SUMITOMO (Founder of a family) called Kakyu had one son and one daughter: the son Seii inherited &quot;Fujiya&quot;; the daughter…. Riemon SOGA, who was Kakyu&apos;s elder sister&apos;s husband and dealing with copper, and believed in Nehan-shu sect and was a Buddist parishoner of Ku-zen (Masatomo), gave Masatomo material and mental support when Masatomo came back to the secular life to open &quot;Fujiya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「女の子には」の後の部分の前との関係がわかりませんでしたので、ここで区切って訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatomo SUMITOMO (the founder of a family), who was called Kakyu, had one son and one daughter: the son Seii inherited &quot;Fujiya&quot;; the daughter…. Riemon Soga, who was the husband of Kakyu&apos;s elder sister and a dealer in copper who believed in the Nehan-shu sect and was a Buddhist parishioner of Ku-zen (Masatomo), gave Masatomo material and mental support when Masatomo returned to the secular life and opened &quot;Fujiya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatomo SUMITOMO (the founder of a family), who was called Kakyu, had one son and one daughter: the son Seii inherited &quot;Fujiya&quot;; the daughter.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処ウェブサイト上でも原文の「女の子には、」の後に続くべき文が切れているようです。従って、「一原文一訳文の例外対処」として、文を分けましたが、前半は訳文でも途中で終っているかたちになっています。ご了承ください。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>嘉休の姉婿にあたる銅師で、涅槃宗の信徒であり、空禅（政友）の檀家であった蘇我理右衛門は、空禅が還俗して「富士屋」を開く際、物心両面で政友を助けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Riemon Soga, who was the husband of Kakyu&apos;s elder sister and a dealer in copper who believed in the Nehan-shu sect and was a Buddhist parishioner of Ku-zen (Masatomo), gave Masatomo material and mental support when Masatomo returned to the secular life and opened &quot;Fujiya.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そして蘇我理右衛門（業祖）の長子理兵衛友以（住友友以）を養子に迎えたことが、住友家と銅との出会いであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Riemon SOGA (Gounder of business)&apos;s eldest son Riemon Tomomochi (Tomomochi SUMITOMO) was adopted by Sumitomo Family, which turned out to be a encounter of Sumitomo Family with copper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eldest son of Riemon SOGA (the founder of a business), Riemon Tomomochi (Tomomochi SUMITOMO) was adopted by the Sumitomo Family, which turned out to be an encounter of the Sumitomo Family with copper.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eldest son of Riemon SOGA (the founder of a business), Riemon Tomomochi (Tomomochi SUMITOMO) was adopted by the Sumitomo Family, which turned out to be an encounter of the Sumitomo Family with copper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>忠重から数えて九世にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is the ninth generation of Tadashige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is the ninth generation of Tadashige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is the ninth generation of Tadashige.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>以後、大阪に居住し、代々銅商を営み「泉屋」の家号を用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Sumitomo Family lived in Osaka and ran a business as copper merchant for generations using a yago &quot;Senoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the Sumitomo Family lived in Osaka and ran a business as copper merchants for generations using the name &quot;Senoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the Sumitomo Family lived in Osaka and ran a business as copper merchants for generations using the name &quot;Senoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>南蛮吹き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nanban-fuki, copper refining method</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nanban-fuki, a method of refining copper</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nanban-fuki, a method of refining copper</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>住友家と精銅とは、切っても切り離せないものがあるが、その端緒となったのは、理右衛門が、天正19年、泉州堺浦に来た明人の白水から「南蛮吹き」と称される粗銅から銀を分離する精錬法を学んだことに始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitomo Family and copper refining have close connection, which began in the year 19 of Tensho when Riemon learned the refining method to separate silver from crude copper, which was called &quot;Nanban-fuki, copper refininhg method&quot; by Hakusui of Minjin (from Min) who came to Senshu-Sakaiura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sumitomo Family is closely connected with copper refining, which began in the year 19 of Tensho when Riemon learned the refining method used to separate silver from crude copper, which was called the &quot;Nanban-fuki copper refining method&quot; by Hakusui of Minjin (from Min), who had come to Senshu-Sakaiura.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sumitomo Family is closely connected with copper refining, which began in the year 19 of Tensho when Riemon learned the refining method used to separate silver from crude copper, which was called the &quot;Nanban-fuki copper refining method&quot; by Hakusui of Minjin (from Min), who had come to Senshu-Sakaiura.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>当時の日本では、粗銅の中に、金・銀などが含まれていることが知られておらず、また金や銀を分離するその精錬技術も未知のものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, it was not known in Japan that gold, silver, and the like were included in crude copper, and the refining technique to separate gold and silver was also not known yet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time it wasn&apos;t known in Japan that gold, silver and the like were contained in crude copper, nor was the refining technique for separating gold and silver known.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time it wasn&apos;t known in Japan that gold, silver and the like were contained in crude copper, nor was the refining technique for separating gold and silver known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>理右衛門は、明人の白水からその精錬方法を学ぶと、その技術を秘伝としてたが、この「南蛮吹き」のおかげで、住友家は粗銅から銀を取り出して、膨大な利益を上げるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Riemon learned from Hakusui of Minjin (from Min) the refining method and kept it secret, and thanks to the &quot;Nanban-fuki, copper refining method,&quot; Sumitomo Family raised enormous profit by taking silver from crude copper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Riemon learned from Hakusui of Minjin the refining method and kept it secret, and thanks to the Nanban-fuki copper refining method the Sumitomo Family gained enormous profit by extracting silver from crude copper.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Riemon learned from Hakusui of Minjin the refining method and kept it secret, and thanks to the Nanban-fuki copper refining method the Sumitomo Family gained enormous profit by extracting silver from crude copper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>別子銅山</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besshidozan Copper mine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Besshidozan copper mine</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Besshidozan copper mine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>住友理兵衛友以の孫にあたる住友友芳の代には、元禄4年に伊予の別子銅山の開堀に着手。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the generation of Tomoyoshi SUMITOMO, grandchild of Riemon Tomomochi SUMITOMO, excavation of Besshidozan Copper mine in Iyo was started in the year of 4 of Genroku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excavation at the Besshidozan copper mine in Iyo started in the year 4 of Genroku, in the generation of Tomoyoshi SUMITOMO, a grandchild of Riemon Tomomochi SUMITOMO.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Excavation at the Besshidozan copper mine in Iyo was started in the 4th year of Genroku, which was during the lifetime of Tomoyoshi SUMITOMO, a grandchild of Riemon Tomomochi SUMITOMO.</e>
<cmt>Again, I don&apos;t think &quot;in the generation&quot; is very natural so I have changed it to &quot;during the lifetime of&quot;. I&apos;ve also altered the ordering of information in the sentence to make it read more naturally.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>これが世界最大級の産銅量を誇る鉱山に成長し、重要な輸出品として日本を支えることとなると共に約280年にもわたって住友の重要な事業の柱となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This developed to be a mine that boasted the world-largesnt copper production, which had supported Japan as an important export item and had been the Sumitomo&apos;s major business for about 280 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This developed into a mine that boasted the world&apos;s greatest copper production, supporting Japan as an important export item and serving as the major Sumitomo business for approximately 280 years.</e>
<cmt>Usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This developed into a mine that boasted the world&apos;s greatest copper production, supporting Japan as an important export item and serving as the major Sumitomo business for approximately 280 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>今日の住友家の基礎、住友財閥の出発点は、この住友友芳が開発した別子銅山によって築き上げられたものであると言ってよく、事実、住友家の歴史の中では、この四世吉左衛門友芳をもって、「住友家中興の祖」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The foundation of Sumitomo Family today, or the starting point of Sumitomo Zaibatsu, can be said to have been built by the Besshidozan Copper mine Tomoyoshi SUMITOMO developed, and actually, in the history of Sumitomo Family, the fourth generation Kichizaemon Tomoyoshi is considered to be the &quot;restorer of Sumitomo Family.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The foundation of today&apos;s Sumitomo Family, or the starting point of Sumitomo Zaibatsu, can be said to have been built by the Besshidozan copper mine that Tomoyoshi SUMITOMO developed; and actually, in the history of the Sumitomo Family, the fourth-generation kichizaemon Tomoyoshi is considered to be the &quot;restorer of the Sumitomo Family.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foundation of today&apos;s Sumitomo Family, or the starting point of Sumitomo Zaibatsu, can be said to have been built by the Besshidozan copper mine that Tomoyoshi SUMITOMO developed; and in fact, in the history of the Sumitomo Family, the fourth-generation kichizaemon Tomoyoshi is considered to be the &quot;restorer of the Sumitomo Family.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="31">
<j>明治時代に入ってからは文化事業にも関わり、十五代目吉左衛門住友友純（ともいと）は大阪府立中之島図書館の建物を寄贈。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji era, Sumitomo family was engaged in cultural enterprise, and the fifteen generation Kichizaemon Tomoito SUMITOMO donated the building of Osaka Prefectural Nakanoshima Library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji era the Sumitomo family was engaged in cultural enterprises, and the fifteenth-generation kichizaemon Tomoito SUMITOMO donated the building that would become the Osaka Prefectural Nakanoshima Library.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji era the Sumitomo family was engaged in cultural enterprises, and the fifteenth-generation kichizaemon Tomoito SUMITOMO donated the building that would become the Osaka Prefectural Nakanoshima Library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その子十六代目吉左衛門住友友成はアララギ派の歌人でもあり、斉藤茂吉、川田順（住友本社の重役でもあった）とも交流があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoito&apos;s son, the sixteenth generation Kichizaemon Tomonari SUMITOMO was also a Araragi-ha poet and on close terms with Mokichi SAITO and Jun KAWADA (he was also an executive in Sumitomo main office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoito&apos;s son, the sixteenth-generation kichizaemon Tomonari SUMITOMO, was also a Araragi-ha poet and was on close terms with Mokichi SAITO and Jun KAWADA (who was also an executive at the Sumitomo main office).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoito&apos;s son, the sixteenth-generation kichizaemon Tomonari SUMITOMO, was also a Araragi-ha poet and was on close terms with Mokichi SAITO and Jun KAWADA (who was also an executive at the Sumitomo main office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、住友家当主が「吉左衛門」を名乗るようになったのは、三代当主住友友信（友以の子）からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, family head of Sumitomo Family started to call himself as &quot;Kichizaemon&quot; since the third generation of family head, Tomonobu SUMITOMO (son of Tomomochi.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the head of the Sumitomo Family began calling himself &quot;kichizaemon&quot; since he was the third generation of the family head, Tomonobu SUMITOMO (son of Tomomochi).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, it was from the third-generation head of the Sumitomo family, Tomonobu SUMITOMO (son of Tomomochi), that the heads of the Sumitomo family began calling themselves &quot;Kichizaemon.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Actually the tense here is OK as the sentence is structured in such a way that &quot;since&quot; is not being used in the sense of from a particular time in the past, but in the sense of &quot;because&quot;. This suggests that the English is a mistranslation, however, so I have corrected it. Please check this.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="34">
<j>住友財閥における住友家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitomo Family in Sumitomo Zaibatsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sumitomo Family in Sumitomo Zaibatsu</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sumitomo Family in Sumitomo Zaibatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="35">
<j>住友財閥における住友家、特に住友友純以降のそれは「君臨すれども統治せず」の立場をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitomo Family in Sumitomo Zaibatsu, specifically since Tomoito SUMITOMO, took the position, &quot;(he) reigns, but does&apos;t govern.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sumitomo Family in Sumitomo Zaibatsu, specifically since Tomoito SUMITOMO, took the position, &quot;(He) reigns but does not govern.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sumitomo Family in Sumitomo Zaibatsu, specifically since Tomoito SUMITOMO, took the position, &quot;(He) reigns but does not govern.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>財閥本社社長たる歴代吉左衛門の仕事は、究極的には財閥の事実上の最高権力者である住友本社（住友合資会社）総理事の信認に尽きるといってよく、個々の事業に口を差し挟む事はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the duty of successive Kichizaemon as president of Zaibatsu main company are reposal of trust in the head of directors of Sumitomo main company (Sumitomo Limited Partnership Corporation), and the successive Kichizaemon did not give any specific orders to the indivisual business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the duties of the successive kichizaemon as president of the zaibatsu (main company) are the repository of trust in the head of the directors of the main Sumitomo company (Sumitomo Limited Partnership Corporation); therefore, the successive kichizaemon did not give any specific orders to the individual businesses.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the duties of the successive Kichizaemon as president of the zaibatsu (main company) are the repository of trust in the head of the directors of the main Sumitomo company (Sumitomo Limited Partnership Corporation); therefore, the successive Kichizaemon did not give any specific orders to the individual businesses.</e>
<cmt>kichizaemon→Kichizaemon吉左衛門は確かにここではある個人の名前ではなくタイトルのような扱いですが、その場合にも語頭は大文字であると思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、16代目吉左衛門友成の兄弟である寛一・元夫は住友本社の株主ではあったが、本社はもちろん傘下事業の役員にも名を連ねることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, although Kanichi and Moto who were brothers of the sixteenth generation Kichizaemon Tomonari were stokholders of Sumitomo main company, they were never named as executive not only of the main company but also of the subsidiary companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, although Kanichi and Moto, who were brothers of the sixteenth-generation kichizaemon Tomonari, were stockholders of the Sumitomo main company, they were never named as executives of the main company or any of its subsidiary companies.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, although Kanichi and Moto, who were brothers of the sixteenth-generation Kichizaemon Tomonari, were stockholders of the Sumitomo main company, they were never named as executives of the main company or any of its subsidiary companies.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この点では三井家や岩崎家と対照的と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this respect, Sumitomo Family can be said to be in contrast to Mitsui Family and Iwasaki Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this respect the Sumitomo Family can be said to be in contrast with the Mitsui and Iwasaki families.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this respect the Sumitomo Family can be said to be in contrast with the Mitsui and Iwasaki families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="39">
<j>この傾向は実は江戸時代から存在していたが（当主が幼少、病弱その他の理由などで、経営に関わらなかったケースが多く、実権はいわゆる「大番頭」が握っていた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tendency has actually existed since the Edo era (there were many cases where family heads were not engaged in management because they were in infancy or in poor health, or for other reasons, in which cases so called &quot;Ohbanto&quot; controlled the business).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tendency has actually existed since the Edo period (there were many cases where family heads were not engaged in management because they were in infancy or in poor health, or for other reasons, and consequently the so-called &quot;ohbanto&quot; would control the business).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tendency has in fact existed since the Edo period (there were many cases where family heads were not engaged in management because they were in infancy or in poor health, or for other reasons, and consequently the so-called &quot;ohbanto&quot; would control the business).</e>
<cmt>&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>一方で会社法が整備され、他方で旧公家宮武家出身で実業家としての経験がない友純が当主となった明治に入ってからは、一層顕著になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Meiji era when Companies Act was established on one hand, and Tomoito SUMITOMO, who had no experience as a businessman since he was from old court noble Miyatake Family, became the family head on the other hand, this tendency became more prominent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Meiji era, when the Companies Act was established on one hand while, on the other hand, Tomoito SUMITOMO (who had no experience as a businessman since he was from the Miyatake Family of old court nobility) became the family head, this tendency became more prominent.</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Meiji era, when the Companies Act was established on one hand while, on the other hand, Tomoito SUMITOMO (who had no experience as a businessman since he was from the Miyatake Family of old court nobility) became the family head, this tendency became more prominent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="41">
<j>但し、三井財閥のように、財閥家族と財閥本社役員及び傘下企業の間に一種の緊張関係があった訳ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this does not mean that there were a kinde of tension between Zaibatu family and executives of the Zaibatu main campany or the subsidiary companies as Mitsui Zaibatsu had.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this does not mean there was any kind of tension between the Zaibatsu Family and executives of the Zaibatu main company or the subsidiary companies, as the Mitsui Zaibatsu had.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this does not mean there was any kind of tension between the Zaibatsu Family and executives of the Zaibatsu main company or the subsidiary companies, as the Mitsui Zaibatsu had.</e>
<cmt>Zaibatu→Zaibatsu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>吉左衛門を「家長様」と呼んでいた事に象徴されるように、上は総理事から下は一般社員までに至る吉左衛門に対する敬愛の念はすこぶる高く、歴代吉左衛門もまた、一方では文化事業を通じて住友の名を高め、他方では家長・財閥本社社長として企業モラルの引き締めの任に当たっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As symbolized from the fact that Kichizaemon was called &quot;Kacho-sama,&quot; respect for Kichizaemon from the high-ranking position of head of the directors down to rank and file was extremely high, and successive Kichizaemon raised the name of Sumitomo through the cultrual enterprise on one hand and tried to raise the corporate moral as the family head and president of Zaibatsu main company on the other hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As symbolized by the fact that Kichizaemon was called &quot;Kacho-sama,&quot; extremely high respect was accorded to the Kichizaemon, from the high-ranking position of head of the directors down to the rank and file, and the successive Kichizaemon elevated the Sumitomo name through the cultural enterprise on one hand while on the other hand trying to raise the corporate morale as the family head and president of the Zaibatsu main company.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As symbolized by the fact that Kichizaemon was called &quot;Kacho-sama,&quot; extremely high respect was accorded to the Kichizaemon, from the high-ranking position of head of the directors down to the rank and file, and the successive Kichizaemon elevated the Sumitomo name through the cultural enterprise on one hand while on the other hand trying to raise the corporate morale as the family head and president of the Zaibatsu main company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="43">
<j>財閥家族の指定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Designation of Zaibatsu family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designation of the Zaibatsu family</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designation of the Zaibatsu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>財閥家族の企業支配力を分散し、人的関係の切断がはかられたのが、財閥家族の指定であり、そして昭和22年11月に成立した「財閥同族支配力排除法」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To disperse the power to controlling business by Zaibatsu family and to break up the human relationship, Zaibatu family was designated and &quot;zaibatsu douzoku shihairyoku haijo hou &apos;48 [Law for the Termination of Zaibatsu Family Control] was established in November, 1947.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1947, in an effort to disperse the power to control business by the Zaibatsu family and to break up the human relationships, the Zaibatsu family was designated and &quot;zaibatsu douzoku shihairyoku haijo hou &apos;48 [Law for the Termination of Zaibatsu Family Control] was established.</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1947, in an effort to disperse the power to control business by the Zaibatsu family and to break up the human relationships, the Zaibatsu family was designated and &quot;zaibatsu douzoku shihairyoku haijo hou &apos;48 [Law for the Termination of Zaibatsu Family Control] was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>持株会社整理委員会は、占領軍当局の指令を受けて、財閥家族の範囲を確定する基準を下記のように選択した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Holding Company Liquidation Commission, in accordance with the order by the Occupation forces, selected the standards to determine the scope of Zaibatsu family as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Holding Company Liquidation Commission, in accordance with the order by the forces of the Allied Occupation, selected the standards by which to determine the scope of the Zaibatsu family as follows:</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Holding Company Liquidation Commission, in accordance with the order by the forces of the Allied Occupation, selected the standards by which to determine the scope of the Zaibatsu family as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="46">
<j>財閥家族姓を名乗る尊卑族三親等およびその家族（姻族を含まず）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancestry within the third degree using the surname of Zaibatsu family and their family (marriage not included)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancestry within the third degree using the surnames of the Zaibatsu family and their families (excluding by marriage)</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancestry within the third degree using the surnames of the Zaibatsu family and their families (excluding by marriage)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>所有有価証券、現金、預貯金額計100万円以上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One million yen or more in total of securities, cash, and deposits and savings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One million yen or more as the total of securities, cash, deposits and savings.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One million yen or more as the total of securities, cash, deposits and savings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>所有家屋500坪、宅地2,000坪、農地山林50町歩以上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1,650 sq. m. or more of houses, 6,600 sq. m. or more of housing land, and 4,959 a. or more of agricultural land and forest land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The established minimums were 1,650 square meters in houses, 6,600 square meters in housing land, and 4,959 acres of agricultural and/or forest land.</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The established minimums were 500 tsubo (approx. 1,600 square meters) in houses, 2,000 tsubo (approx. 6,500 square meters) in housing land, and 50 cho (approx. 120 acres) of agricultural and/or forest land.</e>
<cmt>The checker&apos;s point is a valid one. Also, I think that 50 cho is actually equal to about 120 acres, not 4,959 as the original translation says.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>当該会社発行株数に対し、持株比率10％以上の株式所有者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stockholder having a stake of 10% or more of stocks issued by the company in question.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A stockholder would have a stake of 10% or more of stocks issued by the company in question.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A stockholder who would have a stake of 10% or more of stocks issued by the company in question.</e>
<cmt>who挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>企業支配または経営発言力</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Power to control the business or influence on management</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power to control the business or influence management</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The power to control the business or influence management</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="51">
<j>以上の基準によって、昭和22年2月、住友家ではつぎのものが財閥家族に指定された</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the aobve-mentioned standards, the following people among Sumitomo Family were designated as Zaibatsu family in February, 1947.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the above-mentioned standards, in February 1947 the following people among the Sumitomo Family were designated as the Zaibatsu family:</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the above-mentioned standards, in February 1947 the following people among the Sumitomo Family were designated as the Zaibatsu family:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="52">
<j>第16代住友友成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixtenn generation, Tomonari SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixteenth generation, Tomonari SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixteenth-generation, Tomonari SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>sixteenth-generation としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>住友寛一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanichi SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanichi SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanichi SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>住友義輝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiteru SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiteru SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiteru SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>住友元夫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moto SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moto SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moto SUMITOMO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="56">
<j>住友家の親族・姻戚関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relatives and Marriges of Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relatives and Marriages of the Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt>&quot;Sumitomo Family&quot; should take the article &quot;The.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relatives and Marriages of the Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>ここでは、明治に入ってからの住友家とその親族・姻戚関係について述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hereinafter, Sumitomo Family since the Meiji era and their relatevies and marriages will be described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hereinafter the Sumitomo Family since the Meiji era, as well as their relatives and marriages, will be described.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hereinafter the Sumitomo Family since the Meiji era, as well as their relatives and marriages, will be described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="58">
<j>明治に入って、住友事業は12代目吉左衛門友親と、その子13代目吉左衛門友忠の下で営まれていたが、1890年に友親、友忠が相次いで亡くなり、男系相続者が途絶してしまう非運に見舞われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After entering upon the Meiji era, Sumitomo enterprise was administered by the twelfth generation Kichizaemon Tomochika and his son, the thirteenth generation Kichizaemon Tomotada, but misfortune hit Sumitomo Family that male heir extinguished because in 1890 Tomochika died and then Tomotada died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After entering the Meiji era, the Sumitomo enterprise activity was administered by the twelfth-generation kichizaemon Tomochika and his son, the thirteenth-generation kichizaemon Tomotada, but misfortune hit the Sumitomo Family with the passing of their male heirs in 1890, when Tomochika died, followed by Tomotada.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of the Meiji era, the Sumitomo enterprise was run by Kichizaemon Tomochika (the twelfth-generation Kichizaemon) and his son Kichizaemon Tomotada (the thirteenth-generation Kichizaemon). Misfortune struck the Sumitomo family, however, with the passing of their male heirs when Tomochika and then Tomotada died in 1890.</e>
<cmt>The instruction from the client seems a little unclear to me so please check whether I have corrected this according to the client&apos;s wishes. Also, the translator needs to be careful as writing &quot;twelfth-generation Kichizaemon Tomochika&quot; means there have been twelve generations of the same person, which is clearly not possible. The translator should be translating the meaning, not the words. I would also expect the NC to pick up on this kind of mistake (assuming a native speaker edited this, which doesn&apos;t look likely).</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>この時、住友家総理人広瀬宰平と大阪本店支配人伊庭貞剛は、友親の妻・登久に14代目吉左衛門を襲名させる一方、友忠の妹・満寿の婿養子として清華家の徳大寺隆麿を迎え、住友家の命脈をつないだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, sorinin of Sumitomo Family, Saihei HIROSE, and manager of Osaka main office, Teigo IBA, decided that Tomochika&apos;s wife, Toku would succeed to the name of the fourteenth generation Kichizaemon on one hand and that Takamaro TOKUDAIJI from Seiga Family would be adopted as son-in-law to marry Tomotada&apos;s younger sister Masu, whereby the blood line of Sumitomo Family was successfully maintained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time the sorinin of the Sumitomo Family, Saihei HIROSE, and the manager of the Osaka main office, Teigo IBA, decided that Tomochika&apos;s wife Toku would succeed to the name of the fourteenth-generation kichizaemon on one hand and that Takamaro TOKUDAIJI, from the Seiga Family, would be adopted as son-in-law to marry Tomotada&apos;s younger sister Masu, whereby the bloodline of the Sumitomo Family could be successfully maintained.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time the sorinin of the Sumitomo Family, Saihei HIROSE, and the manager of the Osaka main office, Teigo IBA, decided that Tomochika&apos;s wife Toku would succeed to the name of the fourteenth-generation Kichizaemon on one hand and that Takamaro TOKUDAIJI, from the Seiga Family, would be adopted as son-in-law to marry Tomotada&apos;s younger sister Masu, whereby the bloodline of the Sumitomo Family could be successfully maintained.</e>
<cmt>kichizaemon→Kichizaemon</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>これが15代目吉左衛門住友友純で、徳大寺実則、西園寺公望の実弟である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takamaro TOKUDAIJI became the fifteenth generation Kichizaemon Tomoito SUMITOMO, who is a brother of Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI and Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takamaro TOKUDAIJI became the fifteenth-generation kichizaemon Tomoito SUMITOMO, as a brother of Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI and Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takamaro TOKUDAIJI became the fifteenth-generation Kichizaemon Tomoito SUMITOMO, as a brother of Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI and Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>kichizaemon→Kichizaemon</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>実はこの清華家の徳大寺家は江戸時代に東山天皇の皇胤が養子に入っており、15代目吉左衛門友純をもって住友男爵家は、男系でたどれば近世の天皇の皇胤系に入れ替わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, in the Edo era, the Emperor blood line of Higashiyama Emperor was adopted by Tokudaiji Family of Seiga Family, and therefore, Sumitomo baron family since the fifteenth generation Kichizaemon Tomoito was exchanged to the Emperor blood line of the early-modern history when traced backed according to the male line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, during the Edo period the imperial bloodline of Emperor Higashiyama was adopted by the Tokudaiji Family of the Seiga Family, and therefore the Sumitomo Family was entitled to the status of baron because the fifteenth-generation kichizaemon Tomoito was exchanged to the imperial bloodline of the early-modern history when traced back according to the male line.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, during the Edo period the imperial bloodline of the Emperor Higashiyama was adopted by the Tokudaiji Family of the Seiga Family, and therefore the Sumitomo Family was entitled to the status of baron because the fifteenth-generation kichizaemon Tomoito was exchanged to the imperial bloodline of the early-modern history when traced back according to the male line.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="62">
<j>（男系系図：東山天皇━閑院宮直仁親王━鷹司輔平━鷹司政煕━鷹司政通━徳大寺公純━住友友純）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Family line according to male line: Higashiyama Emperor - Kanin-no-miya Imperial Prince Naohito - Sukehira TAKATSUKASA - Masahiro TAKATSUKASA - Masamichi TAKATSUKASA - Kinito TOKUDAIJI - Tomoito SUMITOMO)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Family line according to male line: Higashiyama Emperor - Kanin-no-miya Imperial Prince Naohito - Sukehira TAKATSUKASA - Masahiro TAKATSUKASA - Masamichi TAKATSUKASA - Kinito TOKUDAIJI - Tomoito SUMITOMO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Family line according to male line: Higashiyama Emperor - Kanin-no-miya Imperial Prince Naohito - Sukehira TAKATSUKASA - Masahiro TAKATSUKASA - Masamichi TAKATSUKASA - Kinito TOKUDAIJI - Tomoito SUMITOMO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="63">
<j>住友友純は、友親の長女・満寿夫人との間に4男1女（3男は早世）をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoito SUMITOMO and his wife Masu who is the Tomochika&apos;s eldest daughter had four sons (the third son died young) and one daugther, and since the eldest son Kanichi lost his right for inheritance, the second son Atsushi inherited Sumitomo family as the sixteenth generation Kichizaemon Tomonari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoito SUMITOMO and his wife Masu, who was Tomochika&apos;s eldest daughter, had four sons (the third son died young) and one daughter, and since the eldest son Kanichi lost his right to inheritance, the second son Atsushi inherited the Sumitomo Family as the sixteenth-generation Kichizaemon, Tomonari.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoito SUMITOMO and his wife Masu, who was Tomochika&apos;s eldest daughter, had four sons (the third son died while still a child) and one daughter.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>しかしながら、長男の寛一は廃嫡となり、次男の厚が16代目吉左衛門友成として住友家を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the eldest son, Kanichi, was disinherited, the second son, Atsushi, became head of the Sumitomo family, adopting the name Kichizaemon Tomonari to become the sixteenth-generation Kichizaemon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="65">
<j>住友吉左衛門友成は元東宮職御用掛の公爵西園寺八郎（西園寺公望の女婿・旧長門国山口藩（長州藩）藩主・公爵毛利元徳の8男）の次女・春子と結婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kichizaemon Tomonari SUMITOMO married Haruko, who is a second daughter of duke Hachiro SAIONJI, former Togu-shoku Goyo-gakari (Kinmochi SAIONJI&apos;s daugther&apos;s husband, the eighth son of duke Motonori MORI, feudal lord of old Nagato-no-kuni, Domain of Yamaguchi (Domain of Choshu)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kichizaemon Tomonari SUMITOMO married Haruko, a second daughter of the duke Hachiro SAIONJI, the former Togu-shoku Goyo-gakari (Kinmochi SAIONJI&apos;s daughter&apos;s husband, the eighth son of the duke Motonori MORI, a feudal lord of old Nagato-no-kuni, of the Domain of Yamaguchi (Domain of Choshu)).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kichizaemon Tomonari SUMITOMO married Haruko, a second daughter of the duke Hachiro SAIONJI, the former Togu-shoku Goyo-gakari (Kinmochi SAIONJI&apos;s daughter&apos;s husband, the eighth son of the duke Motonori MORI, a feudal lord of old Nagato-no-kuni, of the Domain of Yamaguchi (Domain of Choshu)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>友成・春子夫妻は男子に恵まれなかったものの2女をもうけ、長女・邦子は、旧侯爵・元伊勢神宮大宮司などを歴任した、佐々木行忠の長男行美（東京大学理学部教授）に嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Husband and wife, Tomonari and Haruko did not have sons but had two daughters, and the first daugther Kuniko married Ikumi (science faculty professor at Tokyo University), who is the first son of Yukisada SASAKI who was former marquess and served in the position of fomer Isejingu Daiguji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomonari and Haruko, as husband and wife, had no sons but had two daughters; the first daughter, Kuniko, married Ikumi (a science faculty professor at Tokyo University), who was the first son of Yukisada SASAKI, a former marquess who had served in the position of the former Isejingu Daiguji.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomonari and Haruko, as husband and wife, had no sons but had two daughters; the first daughter, Kuniko, married Ikumi (a science faculty professor at Tokyo University), who was the first son of Yukisada SASAKI, a former marquess who had served in the position of the former Isejingu Daiguji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>旧侯爵・佐々木行忠は、昭和17年に皇典講究所長、國學院大學長にあげられ、さらに国史編修院総裁を経て、昭和21年に東京大神宮宮司、同26年には伊勢神宮大宮司に就任した国史の大家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former marquess Yukisada SASAKI was an authority of Kokushi (national history), who was appointed as head of Koten Kokyujo and president of Kokugakuin University in 1942, and then served as President of Kokushi-henshu-in, Guji ofTokyo Daijingu in 1946, and Daiguji of Ise Jingu in 1951.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former marquess Yukisada SASAKI, an authority on Kokushi (national history), was appointed as head of Koten Kokyujo and president of Kokugakuin University in 1942, and then served as the president of Kokushi-henshu-in, Guji of Tokyo Daijingu in 1946 and Daiguji of Ise Jingu in 1951.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former marquess Yukisada SASAKI, an authority on Kokushi (national history), was appointed as head of Koten Kokyujo and president of Kokugakuin University in 1942, and then served as the president of Kokushi-henshu-in, Guji of Tokyo Daijingu in 1946 and Daiguji of Ise Jingu in 1951.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>なお行忠の祖父高行は枢密顧問官で明宮（大正天皇）の御教養主任だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukisada&apos;s grandfather Takayuki SASAKI was privy councilor and a head of education for Harunomiya (Taisho Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukisada&apos;s grandfather Takayuki SASAKI was privy councilor and a head of education for Harunomiya (Taisho Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukisada&apos;s grandfather Takayuki SASAKI was privy councilor and a head of education for Harunomiya (Taisho Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>一方友成・春子夫妻の次女・博子は、昭和電工元社長・安西正夫の次男・直之（三井不動産）に嫁いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Tomonari and Haruko&apos;s second daughter Hiroko married Naoyuki (Mitsui Fudosan Co., Ltd.), the second son of Masao ANZAI who was former president of Showa Denko K.K.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Tomonari and Haruko&apos;s second daughter Hiroko married Naoyuki (Mitsui Fudosan Co., Ltd.), the second son of Masao ANZAI, who had formerly been the president of Showa Denko K.K.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Tomonari and Haruko&apos;s second daughter Hiroko married Naoyuki (Mitsui Fudosan Co., Ltd.), the second son of Masao ANZAI, who was formerly the president of Showa Denko K.K.</e>
<cmt>名字大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>直之の兄、すなわち正夫の長男・安西孝之（元昭和エンジニアリング社長）は元日清製粉（現日清製粉グループ本社）社長・正田英三郎の次女・恵美子と結婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoyuki&apos;s elder broher, that is, Masao&apos;s first son Takayuki ANZAI (president of former Showa Engineering Co., Ltd.), married Emiko, who was the second daughter of Hidezaburo SHODA who was president of former Nisshin Seifun Group Inc. (current Head Office, Nisshin Seifun Group Inc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naoyuki&apos;s elder brother, in other words Masao&apos;s first son Takayuki ANZAI (the president of the former Showa Engineering Co., Ltd.), married Emiko, who was the second daughter of Hidezaburo SHODA, who was the president of the former Nisshin Seifun Group Inc. (the head office of which is now Nisshin Seifun Group Inc.).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naoyuki&apos;s elder brother, in other words Masao&apos;s first son Takayuki ANZAI (the president of the former Showa Engineering Co., Ltd.), married Emiko, who was the second daughter of Hidezaburo SHODA, who was the president of the former Nisshin Seifun Group Inc. (the head office of which is now Nisshin Seifun Group Inc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>恵美子の姉、すなわち正田の長女が美智子 (皇室)であるので住友家は安西家・正田家を通じて皇室と姻戚関係でつながっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Emiko&apos;s elder sister, that is SHODA&apos;s first daughter, is Michiko (Imperial family), Sumitomo Family is related by marriage with Imperial family through Anzai Family and Shoda Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Emiko&apos;s elder sister (Shoda&apos;s first daughter) is Michiko (of the Imperial Family), the Sumitomo Family is related by marriage to the Imperial Family through the Anzai and Shoda families.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Emiko&apos;s elder sister, or SHODA&apos;s first daughter, is Michiko (of the Imperial Family), the Sumitomo Family is related by marriage to the Imperial Family through the Anzai and Shoda families.</e>
<cmt>名字大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>また安西直之の妹公子を娶ったのが、住友銀行相談役堀田庄三の長男健介（住友銀行）であるから、岡橋林の跡を継いだ住友家評議員会の前委員長であった堀田庄三は、住友家の相談役、総理事格から、さらに踏み込んで、住友家と閨閥でつながった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, since the person who married Naoyuki ANZAI&apos;s younger sister Kimiko was Kensuke HOTTA (Sumitomo Bank), the first son of Shozo HOTTA who was Sodanyaku of Sumitomo Bank, Shozo HOTTA who was the former Iincho of Sumitomo family council after Shigeru OKAHASHI became related by Keibatsu, Keibatsu Blood Connection, with Sumitomo Family from the Sodanyaku of Sumitomo Bank, the Soriji rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, because the person who married Naoyuki ANZAI&apos;s younger sister Kimiko was Kensuke HOTTA (Sumitomo Bank), the first son of Shozo HOTTA, who was Sodanyaku of Sumitomo Bank, Shozo HOTTA, who was the former Iincho of the Sumitomo family council after Shigeru OKAHASHI became related by Keibatsu, there was a Keibatsu blood connection to the Sumitomo Family through the Sodanyaku of Sumitomo Bank, at the soriji rank.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, because the person who married Naoyuki ANZAI&apos;s younger sister Kimiko was Kensuke HOTTA (Sumitomo Bank), the first son of Shozo HOTTA, who was Sodanyaku of Sumitomo Bank, Shozo HOTTA, who was the former Iincho of the Sumitomo family council after Shigeru OKAHASHI became related by Keibatsu, there was a Keibatsu blood connection to the Sumitomo Family through the Sodanyaku of Sumitomo Bank, at the soriji rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>なお西園寺八郎の三男・西園寺不二男は鮎川義介の長女を娶り、自らも日産コンツェルン傘下の日産興業社長に就いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiro SAIONJI&apos;s third son Fujio SAIONJI married the eldest daugter of Yoshisuke AYUKAWA, and became president of Nissan Kogyo K.K., a subsidiary company of Nissan Konzern Company Group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiro Saionji&apos;s third son, Fujio SAIONJI, married the eldest daughter of Yoshisuke AYUKAWA and became the president of Nissan Kogyo K.K., a subsidiary company of the Nissan Konzern Company Group.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiro Saionji&apos;s third son, Fujio SAIONJI, married the eldest daughter of Yoshisuke AYUKAWA and became the president of Nissan Kogyo K.K., a subsidiary company of the Nissan Konzern Company Group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>元参議院議員で日中友好に努めた西園寺公一は八郎の長男であり、春子や不二男の長兄にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinkazu SAIONJI who was a former member of the House of Councilors and worked to improve ties between China and Japan is the eldest son of Hachiro SAIONJI and the eldest brother of Haruko and Fujio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinkazu SAIONJI, who was a former member of the House of Councilors and worked to improve ties between China and Japan, is the eldest son of Hachiro SAIONJI and the eldest brother of Haruko and Fujio.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinkazu SAIONJI, who was a former member of the House of Councilors and worked to improve ties between China and Japan, is the eldest son of Hachiro SAIONJI and the eldest brother of Haruko and Fujio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="75">
<j>住友友成の姉の孝は、旧壬生藩三万石の藩主鳥居忠文子爵三男忠輝（元住友本社取締役）を婿養子に迎えており住友忠輝と改名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomonari SUMITOMO&apos;s elder sister Takashi married Tadateru, the third son of viscount Tadabumi TORI who was the feudal lord of Domain of former Mibu thirty-thousand koku, and Tadateru changed his name to Tadateru SUMITOMO by being adopted as son-in-law by Sumitomo Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomonari SUMITOMO&apos;s elder sister Takashi married Tadateru, the third son of Viscount Tadabumi TORI, who was the feudal lord of the domain of the former Mibu (30,000 koku); consequently, Tadateru changed his name to Tadateru SUMITOMO through his adoption as a son-in-law by the Sumitomo Family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomonari SUMITOMO&apos;s elder sister Takashi married Tadateru, the third son of Viscount Tadabumi TORI, who was the feudal lord of the domain of the former Mibu (30,000 koku); consequently, Tadateru changed his name to Tadateru SUMITOMO through his adoption as a son-in-law by the Sumitomo Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>弟の住友元夫は、やはり旧小浜藩十万四千石の藩主酒井忠克（さかいただたえ）伯爵の七女寿枝子を娶っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomonari SUMITOMO&apos;s younger brother Moto SUMITOMO married Sueko, the seventh daughter of earl Tadaie SAKAI who was the feudal lord of Domain of former Obama fourteen-thousand koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomonari SUMITOMO&apos;s younger brother, Moto SUMITOMO, married Sueko, the seventh daughter of Earl Tadaie SAKAI, who was the feudal lord of the domain of the former Obama (14,000 koku).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomonari SUMITOMO&apos;s younger brother, Moto SUMITOMO, married Sueko, the seventh daughter of Earl Tadaie SAKAI, who was the feudal lord of the domain of the former Obama (14,000 koku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>寿枝子の姉香枝子は、旧高松藩主の末裔旧伯爵の松平頼明（まつだいらよりひろ、本郷学園理事）に嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sueko&apos;s elder sister, Kaeko, married former earl Yorihiro MATSUDAIRA (Riji of Hongo Gakuen) who was the descendant of the feudal lord of Domain of former Takamatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sueko&apos;s elder sister, Kaeko, married the former earl Yorihiro MATSUDAIRA (Riji of Hongo Gakuen), who was the descendant of the feudal lord of the domain of the former Takamatsu.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sueko&apos;s elder sister, Kaeko, married the former earl Yorihiro MATSUDAIRA (Riji of Hongo Gakuen), who was the descendant of the feudal lord of the domain of the former Takamatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>寿枝子の姉・小枝子は三菱財閥の創業者・岩崎弥太郎の孫に嫁ぎ、その娘・由利子（寿枝子の姪にあたる）は古生物学関連人物一覧で博士 (理学)の鎮西清高（京都大学名誉教授）に嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sueko&apos;s elder sister, Saeko, married grandchild of Yataro IWASAKI, the founder of Mitsubishi Zaibatsu, and her daughter Yuriko (niece of Sueko) married Kiyotaka CHINZEI (professor emeritus at Kyoto University) who was listed as doctor (sceience) in paleontology-related figure list.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sueko&apos;s elder sister, Saeko, married a grandchild of Yataro IWASAKI, the founder of Mitsubishi Zaibatsu, and her daughter Yuriko (niece of Sueko) married Kiyotaka CHINZEI (professor emeritus at Kyoto University), who was included on a list of important figures as a doctor (science) of paleontology.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sueko&apos;s elder sister, Saeko, married a grandchild of Yataro IWASAKI, the founder of Mitsubishi Zaibatsu, and her daughter Yuriko (niece of Sueko) married Kiyotaka CHINZEI (professor emeritus at Kyoto University), who was included on a list of important figures as a doctor (science) of paleontology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>また、鎮西と同じく古生物学者で理学博士の岩崎泰頴（弥太郎の曾孫で熊本大学名誉教授）は由利子の兄であり、寿枝子の甥にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasuhide IWASAKI (great-grandchild of Yataro and professor emeritus at Kumamoto University), who is also a paleontologist as Chinzei and sceience doctor, is Yuriko&apos;s elder brother and a nephew of Sueko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuhide IWASAKI (the great-grandchild of Yataro and a professor emeritus at Kumamoto University), who is also a paleontologist as Chinzei and a doctor of science, is Yuriko&apos;s elder brother and a nephew of Sueko.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuriko&apos;s elder brother and a nephew of Sueko, Yasuhide IWASAKI (the great-grandchild of Yataro and a professor emeritus at Kumamoto University) was, like CHINZEI, a paleontologist and a doctor of science.</e>
<cmt>as の使い方を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="80">
<j>友成の兄の住友寛一は、明治29年5月23日生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomonari&apos;s elder brother, Kanichi SUMITOMO, was born on May 23, 1896.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomonari&apos;s elder brother, Kanichi SUMITOMO, was born on May 23, 1896.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomonari&apos;s elder brother, Kanichi SUMITOMO, was born on May 23, 1896.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>前述のとおり若くして絵画に傾倒したため廃嫡され、以後画家・美術品収集家として過ごし、岸田劉生とも交流を持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, since he devoted himself to painting when he was young, he lost his right for inheritance, and thereafter he lived as a painter and art collector and was on close terms with Ryusei KISHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, since he devoted himself to painting when he was young, he lost his right to inheritance, and thereafter he lived as a painter and art collector and was on close terms with Ryusei KISHIDA.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, since he devoted himself to painting when he was young, he lost his right to inheritance, and thereafter he lived as a painter and art collector and was on close terms with Ryusei KISHIDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>泉屋博古館所蔵の中国書画のほとんどは寛一のコレクションである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Almost all the Chinese calligraphy and paintings in the possession of Senoku-hakuko-kan are Kanichi&apos;s collections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nearly all the Chinese calligraphy and paintings in the possession of Senoku-hakuko-kan are from Kanichi&apos;s collection.</e>
<cmt>Usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nearly all the Chinese calligraphy and paintings in the possession of Senoku-hakuko-kan are from Kanichi&apos;s collection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>また鎌倉市の景観重要建築物「村上邸」の茶室は、鎌倉にあった寛一邸から移築したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tea room of &quot;Murakami-tei,&quot; which is designated as Kamakura City&apos;s Landscapes important building, was transferred from Kanichi&apos;s house located in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tearoom of &quot;Murakami-tei,&quot; which is designated as an important building of the Kamakura City landscape, was transferred from Kanichi&apos;s house in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tearoom of &quot;Murakami-tei,&quot; which is designated as an important building of the Kamakura City landscape, was transferred from Kanichi&apos;s house in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>皆川宗光の娘との間に4男2女をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanichi and his wife who was a daughter of Munemitsu MINAGAWA had four sons and two daugters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanichi and his wife, a daughter of Munemitsu MINAGAWA, had four sons and two daughters.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanichi and his wife, a daughter of Munemitsu MINAGAWA, had four sons and two daughters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>長男の住友務は、元住友ビジネスコンサルティングと住友オーストラリア開発の会長を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their eldest son, Tsutomu SUMITOMO, served as president of former Sumitomo Business Consulting and Sumitomo Australia Development.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their eldest son, Tsutomu SUMITOMO, served as president of the former Sumitomo Business Consulting and Sumitomo Australia Development.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their eldest son, Tsutomu SUMITOMO, served as president of the former Sumitomo Business Consulting and Sumitomo Australia Development.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>住友務の長男進（日本電気）の妻揺子は東曹産業社長岩瀬徳郎の二女。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsutomu SUMITOMO&apos;s eldest son Susumu (NEC Corporation)&apos;s wifeYoko is the second daughter of Tokuro IWASE who is president of Toso Sangyo Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoko, the wife of Tsutomu SUMITOMO&apos;s eldest son Susumu (NEC Corporation), is the second daughter of Tokuro IWASE, who is president of Toso Sangyo Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoko, the wife of Tsutomu SUMITOMO&apos;s eldest son Susumu (NEC Corporation), is the second daughter of Tokuro IWASE, who is president of Toso Sangyo Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>岩瀬徳郎の父徳三郎は、元東洋曹達工業社長である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokuro IWASE&apos;s father, Tokusaburo, was president of former Toyo Soda Manufacturing Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokuro IWASE&apos;s father, Tokusaburo, was president of the former Toyo Soda Manufacturing Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokuro IWASE&apos;s father, Tokusaburo, was president of the former Toyo Soda Manufacturing Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>岩瀬徳郎の長女は、キッコーマン醤油一族である11代茂木七左衛門の養子賢三郎に嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eldest daughter of Tokuro IWASE married Kenzaburo who was adopted by the eleventh generation Shichi-zaemon MOGI, a member of Kikkoman Corporation family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eldest daughter of Tokuro IWASE married Kenzaburo, who was adopted by the eleventh-generation Shichi-zaemon MOGI, a member of the Kikkoman (Corporation) family.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eldest daughter of Tokuro IWASE married Kenzaburo, who was adopted by the eleventh-generation Shichi-zaemon MOGI, a member of the Kikkoman (Corporation) family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>また、住友務の妹文子は、元ミツワ石鹸社長の三輪善雄に嫁いでいるが、善雄の妹の佐登子は、元キッコーマン醤油10代社長茂木佐平治に嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Tsutomu SUMITOMO&apos;s younger sister Fumiko married Yoshio MIWA, president of former Mitsuwa Soap Corporation, and Yoshio&apos;s younger sister Satoko married Saheiji MOGI, the tenth president of former Kikkoman Corporation, whereby family of Kanichi SUMITOMO who is a brother of family head Kichizaemon has double Keibatu Blood Connection with Mogi Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Tsutomu SUMITOMO&apos;s younger sister Fumiko married Yoshio MIWA, the president of the former Mitsuwa Soap Corporation, and Yoshio&apos;s younger sister Satoko married Saheiji MOGI, the tenth president of the former Kikkoman Corporation, whereby the family of Kanichi SUMITOMO (a brother of the family head Kichizaemon) has a double Keibatsu blood connection with the Mogi Family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Tsutomu SUMITOMO&apos;s younger sister Fumiko married Yoshio MIWA, president of the former Mitsuwa Soap Corporation, and Yoshio&apos;s younger sister Satoko married Saheiji MOGI, the tenth president of the former Kikkoman Corporation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処The word &quot;president&quot; is not being used in conjunction with a name (e.g. President Obama) so capitalization is not required. Also, an article is not required before &quot;president&quot; here.Please ask the translator not to use unexplained Japanese terms like &quot;keibatsu&quot; in their translation. Also, this is not a case of a blood relation, this is simply a relationship by marriage.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>そのため、当主吉左衛門の兄住友寛一一族は、茂木一族と二重結合の閨閥関係にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the family of Kanichi SUMITOMO, who was a brother of the Kichizaemon, was related to the Mogi Family by marriage twice over.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>住友務の弟勝は、元関東電工会長の浅野八郎の娘桃枝を娶っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsutomu SUMITOMO&apos;s younger brother Masaru married Momoe who is a daughter of Hachiro ASANO, president of former Kanto Denko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsutomu SUMITOMO&apos;s younger brother Masaru married Momoe, a daughter of Hachiro ASANO, the president of the former Kanto Denko.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsutomu SUMITOMO&apos;s younger brother Masaru married Momoe, a daughter of Hachiro ASANO, the president of the former Kanto Denko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>浅野八郎は浅野財閥二代目総帥浅野総一郎の三男である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hachiro ASANO is the third son of Souichiro ASANO who was the second generation sosui of Asano Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hachiro ASANO is the third son of Souichiro ASANO, who was the second-generation sosui of Asano Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiro ASANO is the third son of Souichiro ASANO, who was the second-generation sosui of Asano Zaibatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>二代目総一郎の妻千代子は、自由民権運動の政治家・板垣退助の娘である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second generation Souichiro&apos;s wife Chiyoko is a daughter of Taisuke ITAGAKI, a politician who did Jiyu Minken Undo, Democratic Rgiths Campaign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second-generation Souichiro&apos;s wife, Chiyoko, is a daughter of Taisuke ITAGAKI, a politician who led Jiyu Minken Undo, the Democratic Rights Campaign.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second-generation Souichiro&apos;s wife, Chiyoko, is a daughter of Taisuke ITAGAKI, a politician who led Jiyu Minken Undo, the Democratic Rights Campaign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="94">
<j>当主の弟の住友元夫は、明治45年1月1日生まれ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family head&apos;s younger brother Moto was born on January 1, 1912.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family head&apos;s younger brother Moto was born on January 1, 1912.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family head&apos;s younger brother Moto was born on January 1, 1912.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>昭和11年に京大の物理学科を卒業、同21年に住友金属工業に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He graduated from Kyoto University, department of physics in 1936, and started working at Smitomo Metal Industries, Ltd. In1946.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He graduated from the Kyoto University Department of Physics in 1936, and started working at Sumitomo Metal Industries, Ltd., in 1946.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He graduated from the Kyoto University Department of Physics in 1936, and started working for Sumitomo Metal Industries, Ltd., in 1946.</e>
<cmt>started working at →started working for</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>製鋼所技術部研究課長、技術部長、同所長友成代理兼研究部長、中央技術研究所副所長を経て、昭和37年11月取締役中央技術研究所長となり、常務を経て、昭和45年11月専務に就任、同47年11月に相談役、住友精密工業会長となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became reserch chief of technical department of Seikosho, technical manager of Seikousho, deputy head of Seikousho for Tomonari and rearch manager at the same time, and vice head of Chuo Gijutsu Kenkyusho, Chuo Technical, and then became Torishimariyaku head of Chuo Gijutsu Kenkyusho, Chuo Technical in November, 1962, became Jomu, and then took a position of Senmu in Novembver, 1970, Sodanyaku and chairman of Sumitomo Precision Products Co., Ltd. in November, 1972.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became the research chief of the Technical Department of Seikosho, the technical manager of Seikousho, the deputy head of Seikousho for Tomonari and a research manager at the same time; subsequently, he was the vice head of Chuo Gijutsu Kenkyusho, Chuo Technical, and then became the Torishimariyaku head of Chuo Gijutsu Kenkyusho, Chuo Technical, in November 1962, became Jomu, and then took the position of Senmu in November 1970, Sodanyaku and chairman of Sumitomo Precision Products Co., Ltd. in November 1972.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became the research chief of the Technical Department of Seikosho, the technical manager of Seikousho, the deputy head of Seikousho for Tomonari and a research manager at the same time; subsequently, he was the vice head of Chuo Gijutsu Kenkyusho, Chuo Technical, and then became the Torishimariyaku head of Chuo Gijutsu Kenkyusho, Chuo Technical Laboratory, in November 1962, became Jomu, and then took the position of Senmu in November 1970, Sodanyaku and chairman of Sumitomo Precision Products Co., Ltd. in November 1972.</e>
<cmt>Laboratory追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>住友元夫の長男住友芳夫（住友金属工業）も、阪大大学院基礎工学研究科博士課程卒業の工学博士であるが、伯父の当主住友吉左衛門に嫡男がいないため、当主吉左衛門の養嗣子となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moto SUMITOMO&apos;s eldest son, Yoshio SUMITOMO, is also a doctor of engineering, graduating from Osaka University graduate school, doctor course of basic engineering, but since his uncle, family head Kichizaemon SUMITOMO had no legitimate son to be an heir, Yoshio was adopted by the family head Kichizaemon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moto SUMITOMO&apos;s eldest son, Yoshio SUMITOMO, is also a doctor of engineering, having graduated from the Osaka University graduate school&apos;s doctoral course in basic engineering; however, since his uncle, family head Kichizaemon SUMITOMO, had no legitimate son to be an heir, Yoshio was adopted by the family head Kichizaemon.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moto SUMITOMO&apos;s eldest son, Yoshio SUMITOMO, is also a doctor of engineering, having graduated from the Osaka University graduate school&apos;s doctoral course in basic engineering; however, since his uncle, family head Kichizaemon SUMITOMO, had no legitimate son to be an heir, Yoshio was adopted by the family head Kichizaemon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="98">
<j>このように、住友家は先代と二代続いて、旧華族と密接な閨閥関係を結んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, Sumitomo Family had close Keibatsu, Keibatsu Blood Connection with former noble over the two generations starting in the former generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, the Sumitomo Family had a close Keibatsu blood connection with former nobility over the two generations, starting with the previous generation.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, the Sumitomo Family had a close Keibatsu blood connection with former nobility over the two generations, starting with the previous generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>旧華族とのつながりといえば、当主吉左衛門の兄・寛一の子孫のほか、四男融が迎えた妻光子も旧公爵鷹司信輔の娘である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Speaking of connection with the former noble, in addition to the descendant of Kanichi, the elder brother of the family head Kichizaemon, Mitsuko who was a wife of the fourth child Toru was a daughter of former duke Hiromichi TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Speaking of the connection with the former noble, in addition to the descendant of Kanichi, the elder brother of the family head Kichizaemon, Mitsuko, who was the wife of the fourth child Toru, was a daughter of the former duke Hiromichi TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Speaking of the connection with the former noble, in addition to the descendant of Kanichi, the elder brother of the family head Kichizaemon, Mitsuko, who was the wife of the fourth child Toru, was a daughter of the former duke Hiromichi TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>鷹司家は、公卿の中でも最高の家柄である摂家であり、徳大寺家や西園寺家とは、代々深いつながりを持っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatsukasa Family is the highest ranking Sekke among dukes, and has close connection with Tokudaiji Family ad Saionji Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takatsukasa Family is the highest-ranking sekke among dukes, and has close ties with the Tokudaiji and Saionji families.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takatsukasa family is the highest-ranking regent family of all the court noble families, and has a close connection with the Tokudaiji and Saionji families.</e>
<cmt>Please ask the translator not to use unexplained Japanese terms like &quot;sekke&quot; in their translation. &quot;duke&quot; seems out of place as a translation of a Japanese title and the Kenkyusha online dictionary has it as &quot;court noble&quot; so I have changed this.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>例えば、先々代の住友友純や西園寺公望公爵、そして元侍従長の徳大寺実則公爵などの父親である徳大寺公純は、もともと鷹司家から徳大寺家へ養子入りした人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For instance, Kinto TOKUDAIJI, father of the family head two generations ago Tomoito SUMITOMO, duke Kinmochi SAIONJI, and duke Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI who was the former Grand Chamberlain, was adopted from Takatsukasa Family by Tokudaiji Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Kinto TOKUDAIJI, the father of the family head (two generations ago) Tomoito SUMITOMO, Duke Kinmochi SAIONJI and Duke Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, who was the former grand chamberlain, was adopted from the Takatsukasa Family by the Tokudaiji Family.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Kinto TOKUDAIJI, the father of the family head (two generations ago) Tomoito SUMITOMO, Duke Kinmochi SAIONJI and Duke Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, who was the former grand chamberlain, was adopted from the Takatsukasa Family by the Tokudaiji Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>さらに、徳大寺実則の長女順子は、鷹司信輔の父である鷹司煕通（陸軍少将、侍従長）へ嫁ぐ、というように、鷹司家と徳大寺家は網の目のような連綿とした濃い血のつながりがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, as Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI&apos;s eldest daughter Junko married Hiromichi TAKATSUKASA (Army Major General, Grand Chamberlain), father of Nobusuke TAKATSUKASA, Takatsukasa Family and Tokudaiji Family have strong blood connection like a finely meshed pattern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, as Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI&apos;s eldest daughter Junko married Hiromichi TAKATSUKASA (an army major-general and the grand chamberlain), the father of Nobusuke TAKATSUKASA, the Takatsukasa and Tokudaiji families have a finely meshed pattern of strong blood connections.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, as Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI&apos;s eldest daughter Junko married Hiromichi TAKATSUKASA (an army major-general and the grand chamberlain), the father of Nobusuke TAKATSUKASA, the Takatsukasa and Tokudaiji families have a finely meshed pattern of strong blood connections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>このように、旧華族、しかも家格が最上位の摂家、清華家の家系と密接な閨閥関係にある住友家の家系であるが、住友家が旧財閥の西の横綱であるとしたらば、東の正横綱、三井家との幾重にも重なり会ったつながりがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, Sumitomo Family has a family line with close Keibatsu, Keibatsu Blood Connection with former nobles, in particular the highest ranking Sekke, Seiga Family, and if Sumitomo Family is the west Yokozuna among old Zaibatsu, Sumitomo Family has also a close connection with Mitsui Family, the east Yokozuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, the Sumitomo Family has a family line with a close Keibatsu, Keibatsu blood connection with former nobles, particularly the highest-ranking sekke--the Seiga Family--and if the Sumitomo Family is the western yokozuna among the old Zaibatsu, the Sumitomo Family also has a close connection with the Mitsui Family, the eastern yokozuna.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, the Sumitomo Family has a family line with a close Keibatsu, Keibatsu blood connection with former nobles, particularly the highest-ranking sekke--the Seiga Family--and if the Sumitomo Family is the western yokozuna among the old Zaibatsu, the Sumitomo Family also has a close connection with the Mitsui Family, the eastern yokozuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="104">
<j>住友友純の妻満寿の妹楢光の嫁いだ先が、三井十一家の一つ「三井永坂町家」の八代目当主、元三井物産社長三井高泰（守之助）に嫁いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family Naramitsu, younger sister of Masu who was a wife of Motoito Sumitomo, married Takayasu Mitsui (Morinosuke) who was president of former Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd. and the eighth generation family head of &quot;Mitsui-Nagasakacho Family&quot;which was one of Mitsui Eleven Families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Naramitsu Family, the younger sister of Masu was the wife of Motoito SUMITOMO, married Takayasu MITSUI (Morinosuke), who was the president of the former Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd., and the eighth-generation family head of the &quot;Mitsui-Nagasakacho Family,&quot; which was one of the Eleven Families of Mitsui.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Naramitsu Family, the younger sister of Masu was the wife of Motoito SUMITOMO, married Takayasu MITSUI (Morinosuke), who was the president of the former Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd., and the eighth-generation family head of the &quot;Mitsui-Nagasakacho Family,&quot; which was one of the Eleven Families of Mitsui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>楢光の嫁入りの時は、大阪から東京まで、７台の貨車を借り切って婚礼衣裳を送ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Naramitsu married into Mitsui Family, seven freight cars were chartered to send wedding dresses from Osaka to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Naramitsu married into the Mitsui Family, seven freight cars were chartered to send wedding dresses from Osaka to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that when Naramitsu married into the Mitsui Family, seven freight cars were hired to send wedding dresses from Osaka to Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;charter&quot; is usually used for planes or boats.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>しかも三井高泰の長男高篤（元三井物産取締役）は、三井総領家である北家十代の三井八郎右衛門（高棟）の妹礼子を妻にしているので、住友家と三井家の閨閥のつながりは、単に一族と一族との結合ではなく、本家と総領家が直接に結びついた本格的なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, since Takayasu MITSUI&apos;s eldest sonTakaatsu (Torishimariyaku of Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd.) married Reiko who was youger sister of Hachiroemon MITSUI, the tenth generation Hokke which is Mitsui Soryo-ke family and heir, Keibatsu, Keibatsu Blood Connection between Sumitomo Family and Mitsui Family is not only the simple bond between one family and another family but also the genuine connection directly connecting the Honke and the Soryo-ke family and heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, since Takayasu MITSUI&apos;s eldest son Takaatsu (the torishimariyaku of Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd.) married Reiko, who was younger sister of Hachiroemon MITSUI, the tenth-generation Hokke, being the Mitsui Soryo-ke family and heir, the Keibatsu, Keibatsu blood connection between the Sumitomo and Mitsui families is not only a simple bond between one family and another family but is also a genuine connection directly connecting the Honke and Soryo-ke families and heirs.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, since Takayasu MITSUI&apos;s eldest son Takaatsu (the torishimariyaku of Mitsui &amp; Co., Ltd.) married Reiko, who was younger sister of Hachiroemon MITSUI, the tenth-generation Hokke, being the Mitsui Soryo-ke family and heir, the Keibatsu, Keibatsu blood connection between the Sumitomo and Mitsui families is not only a simple bond between one family and another family but is also a genuine connection directly connecting the Honke and Soryo-ke families and heirs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>三井家との結びつきこればかりではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the connection with Mitsui Family is not only the one as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the connection with the Mitsui Family is not only as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the connection with the Mitsui Family is not only as mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>先代吉左衛門友純の実兄徳大寺実則公爵の三女奉子は、三井・室町家の三井高従に嫁いでおり、さらに実則の三男で分家した旧男爵徳大寺則麿の長女鶴子、つまり実則の孫娘が、やはり三井・新町家の三井高直に嫁いでいるので、住友と三井両本家は、四重、五重の閨閥関係にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoko, who was the third daughter of duke Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI who is elder brother of former generation of Kichizaemon, married Koju MITSUI of Mitsui-Muromachi Family, and moreover, Tsuruko, who was the eldest daughter of former baron Norimaro TOKUDAIJI who was the third son of Sanetsune and started the branch family, that is, grand-daughter of Sanetsune married Takanao MITSUI of Mitsui-Shinmachi Family, which means Honke of Smitomo Family and Honkie of Mitsui Family have quadruple or quintuple Keibatsu, Keibatsu Blood Connections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoko, who was the third daughter of Duke Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, who is the elder brother of the former generation of Kichizaemon, married Koju MITSUI of the Mitsui-Muromachi Family; and because Tsuruko, who was the eldest daughter of the former baron Norimaro Tokudaiji, who was the third son of Sanetsune and started the branch family, that is, the granddaughter of Sanetsune married Takanao MITSUI of the Mitsui-Shinmachi Family, which means Honke of the Sumitomo Family and Honke of the Mitsui Family have quadruple or quintuple Keibatsu, Keibatsu blood connections.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoko, who was the third daughter of Duke Sanetsune TOKUDAIJI, who is the elder brother of the former generation of Kichizaemon, married Koju MITSUI of the Mitsui-Muromachi Family; and because Tsuruko, who was the eldest daughter of the former baron Norimaro Tokudaiji, who was the third son of Sanetsune and started the branch family, that is, the granddaughter of Sanetsune married Takanao MITSUI of the Mitsui-Shinmachi Family, which means Honke of the Sumitomo Family and Honke of the Mitsui Family have quadruple or quintuple Keibatsu, Keibatsu blood connections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>また当主吉左衛門の姉婿忠輝の兄の旧子爵鳥居忠一も三井・南家八代八郎次郎の長女寛子を娶っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, former viscount Tadakazu TORI, who was the elder brother of Tadateru who was a husband of the elder sister of the head family Kichizaemon, married Hiroko, who was the eldest daughter of Hachiro-jiro of Misui-Minami Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the former viscount Tadakazu Tori, who was the elder brother of Tadateru--a husband of the elder sister of the head of family Kichizaemon--married Hiroko, who was the eldest daughter of Hachiro-jiro of the Mitsui-Minami Family.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the former viscount Tadakazu TORI, who was the elder brother of Tadateru--a husband of the elder sister of the head of family Kichizaemon--married Hiroko, who was the eldest daughter of Hachiro-jiro, the eighth-generation Mitsui-Minami Family.</e>
<cmt>名字大文字「八代」ｗｐ補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>この公卿を中心とした旧華族と、三井総領家である、北家、永坂町家、室町家、南家、新町家と実に三井十一家のうち、総領家を含む三井の五家との閨閥の拡がりがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitomo Family has the expanded Keibatsu, Keibatsu Blood Connection with former nobles including especially the above-mentioned dukes, and five Mitsui Families among Mitsui Eleven Families including Mitsui Soryo-ke family and heir, Hokke, and Nagasakacho Family, Muromachi Family, Minami Family and Shinmachi Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sumitomo Family has the expanded the Keibatsu, Keibatsu blood connection with former nobles, particularly including the above-mentioned dukes, and the five Mitsui families among the Eleven Families of Mitsui include the Mitsui Soryo-ke Family and heir, Hokke, and the Nagasakacho, Muromachi, Minami and Shinmachi families.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sumitomo Family has extensive connections by marriage with former nobles, particularly with the above-mentioned court noble families, as well as with five of the eleven Mitsui families (including the Mitsui Soryo-ke family and the heir); namely, the Hokke, Nagasakacho, Muromachi, Minami, and Shinmachi families.</e>
<cmt>Again, please ask the translator not to use unexplained Japanese terms like &quot;keibatsu&quot; in their translation. Also, this is not a case of a blood relation, this is simply a relationship by marriage.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="111">
<j>祠堂祭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shido-sai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shido-sai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shido-sai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>例年4月25日に「五山の送り火」が行われる京都東山の麓鹿ヶ谷の住友家別邸だった「有芳園」で開かれる、「祠堂祭」に住友直系グループの社長や会長、相談役といった面々が集合する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every year on April 25, presidents, chiarpersons, Sodanyaku of direct affiliate of Sumitomo group gather to attend &quot;Shido-sai&quot; held in &quot;Ariyoshi-en&quot; that was a Sumitomo-ke Bettei in Shishigadani in Kyoto Higashiyama where &quot;Gozan-no-okuribi&quot;is peformed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every year on April 25, presidents, chairpersons and sodanyaku of direct affiliates of the Sumitomo Group gather to attend the &quot;Shido-sai&quot; held in &quot;Ariyoshi-en,&quot; which was historically a Sumitomo-ke Bettei in Shishigadani in Kyoto Higashiyama, where &quot;Gozan-no-okuribi&quot; is performed.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every year on April 25, presidents, chairpersons and sodanyaku of direct affiliates of the Sumitomo Group gather to attend the &quot;Shido-sai&quot; held in &quot;Ariyoshi-en,&quot; which was historically a Sumitomo-ke Bettei in Shishigadani in Kyoto Higashiyama, where &quot;Gozan-no-okuribi&quot; is performed.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>約3000坪をこえる園内の一隅にある「芳泉堂」と名付けられた小さな祠がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a small shrine called &quot;Hosendo&quot; in a corner of Ariyoshi-en that has an area over about 9,900 sq.,m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a small shrine called &quot;Hosendo&quot; in a corner of Ariyoshi-en, which covers an area of approximately 9,900 square meters.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a small shrine called &quot;Hosendo&quot; in a corner of Ariyoshi-en, which covers an area of approximately 9,900 square meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>これは、昭和15年、日本紀元2600年の祝典が行われた年であったが、また住友では、別子銅山の開抗250年にあたる年で、歴代の住友家当主や旧住友本社幹部物故者の霊を祭るため、長谷部鋭吉の設計によって典雅な持仏堂として建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year 1940 was the year when the celebration for the 2,600th anniversary of Japan&apos;s national foundation was held, but this year was also the year for the 250th anniversary of Besshidozan copper mine opening, and to enshrine the souls of the deceased successive Sumitomo family heads and the deceased executive officers of old Smitomo Honsha this shrine was designed by Eikichi HASEBE and built as an refind hall where tablets of the above-mentioned deceased people are enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 1940 was the one in which the celebration of the 2,600th anniversary of the founding of the Japanese nation was held, but this year was also the 250th anniversary of the opening of the Besshidozan copper mine; and to enshrine the souls of the deceased successive Sumitomo family heads and the deceased executive officers of the old Sumitomo Honsha this shrine was designed by Eikichi HASEBE and built as a refined space where the tablets of the above-mentioned deceased people are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 1940 was the one in which the celebration of the 2,600th anniversary of the founding of the Japanese nation was held, but this year was also the 250th anniversary of the opening of the Besshidozan copper mine; and to enshrine the souls of the deceased successive Sumitomo family heads and the deceased executive officers of the old Sumitomo Honsha this shrine was designed by Eikichi HASEBE and built as a refined space where the tablets of the above-mentioned deceased people are enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>「祠堂祭」に参列を許されるのは、住友家ゆかりの者と、住友直系グループの社長会「白水会」のメンバーと、白水会卒業生（元社長）だけに限定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are allowed to attend &quot;Shido-sai&quot;are limited to the people who are related to Sumitomo Family and members of &quot;Hakusui-kai&quot; that is a group for presidents of direct affiliate of Sumitomo group and graduates of Hakusui-kai (former presidents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people who are allowed to attend &quot;Shido-sai&quot; are limited to those who are related to the Sumitomo Family and members of &quot;Hakusui-kai,&quot; which is a group for the presidents of direct affiliates of the Sumitomo Group and graduates of Hakusui-kai (former presidents).</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people who are allowed to attend &quot;Shido-sai&quot; are limited to those who are related to the Sumitomo Family and members of &quot;Hakusui-kai,&quot; which is a group for the presidents of direct affiliates of the Sumitomo Group and graduates of Hakusui-kai (former presidents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>つまり「祠堂祭」は、住友家当主と住友直系企業グループの社長や会長、相談役らの最高経営責任者が、年に1度「物故者慰霊祭」のために、一堂に会する日である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, &quot;Shido-sai&quot; is a day on which family head of Sumitomo Family and the highest-ranking executive officers such as presidents, chiarpersons, Sodanyaku of direct affiliate of Sumitomo group gather once a year for the &quot;memorial service for the deceased.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, &quot;Shido-sai&quot; is a day on which the family head of the Sumitomo Family and the highest-ranking executive officers such as presidents, chairpersons and sodanyaku of direct affiliates of the Sumitomo Group gather once a year for the &quot;memorial service for the deceased.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, &quot;Shido-sai&quot; is a day on which the family head of the Sumitomo Family and the highest-ranking executive officers such as presidents, chairpersons and sodanyaku of direct affiliates of the Sumitomo Group gather once a year for the &quot;memorial service for the deceased.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>なお、4月25日は「業祖」蘇我理右衛門の命日である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, April 25 is a deathday of Riemon SOGA, the &quot;Founder of business.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, April 25 is the death day of Riemon SOGA, the &quot;founder of business.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, April 25 is the death day of Riemon SOGA, the &quot;founder of business.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>また祠堂祭の幹事は、「白水会」メンバー企業の持ち回りとなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every year Shido-sai is organized by the company that is a member of &quot;Hakusui-kai&quot; by rotation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each year Shido-sai is organized by a company that is a member of &quot;Hakusui-kai,&quot; the order being established by rotation.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each year Shido-sai is organized by a company that is a member of &quot;Hakusui-kai,&quot; the order being established by rotation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="119">
<j>住友家邸宅の移り変わり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transition of the houses of Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transition of the houses of the Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transition of the houses of the Sumitomo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>旧住友家鰻谷本邸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Unagidani-Bettei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Unagidani-Bettei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Unagidani-Bettei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>旧住友家茶臼山本邸（慶沢園）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Ususan-Bettei (Keitaku-en)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Ususan-Bettei (Keitaku-en)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Ususan-Hontei (Keitaku-en)</e>
<cmt>名称のスペルミスを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>旧住友家住吉本邸（住吉村 (兵庫県)）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Sumiyoshi-Hontei (Sumiyoshi-mura (Hyogo Prefecture))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Sumiyoshi-Hontei (Sumiyoshi-mura, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Sumiyoshi-Hontei (Sumiyoshi-mura, Hyogo Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>旧住友家衣笠別邸（聖ヨゼフ修道院・門の家、登録有形文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Kinugasa-Bettei (St. Josef Shudoin Monno-Ie, Hermitage, registered tangible cultural properties)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Kinugasa-Bettei (St. Josef Shudoin Monno-Ie, Hermitage, a registered tangible cultural property)</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Kinugasa-Bettei (St. Josef Shudoin Monno-Ie, Hermitage, a registered tangible cultural property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>旧住友家鹿ケ谷別邸（有芳園）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Shikagaya-Bettei Ariyoshi-en</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Shikagaya-Bettei Ariyoshi-en</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Shikagaya-Bettei (Ariyoshi-en)</e>
<cmt>括弧の抜けを補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>旧住友家俣野別邸（国重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Matano-Bettei (national important cultural properties)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Matano-Bettei (national important cultural properties)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Matano-Bettei (national important cultural properties)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>旧住友家那須別邸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Nasu-Bettei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Nasu-Bettei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Nasu-Bettei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>旧住友家麻布別邸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Azabu-Bettei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Azabu-Bettei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Azabu-Bettei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>旧住友家駿河台別邸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Surugadai-Bettei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Surugadai-Bettei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Surugadai-Bettei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>旧住友会館（泉ガーデンタワー・泉屋博古館分館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-Kaikan, Izumi Garden Tower, Senoku-hakuko-bunkan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-Kaikan, Izumi Garden Tower, Senoku-hakuko-bunkan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-Kaikan, Izumi Garden Tower, Senoku-hakuko-bunkan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>旧住友家須磨別邸（須磨区海浜公園）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Suma Bettei (Suma Kaihin Koen Park)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old Sumitomo-ke Suma Bettei (Suma Kaihin Koen Park)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old Sumitomo-ke Suma-Bettei (Suma Kaihin Koen Park)</e>
<cmt>ハイフンの抜けを補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), Kdo84221(id:6188), Takashi Ikehara(id:134709), Los688(id:12316), 昭衛徒(id:174262), Urania(id:7213), 水野白楓(id:22811), おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), Kansai explorer(id:48975), !!!(id:66838), 輝く水(id:65241), Jazzy(id:3202), 杉山真大(id:2297), Boca samba(id:137526), 総裁(id:39230), Junger(id:10282), Tinecici(id:192914), Bokt(id:7334), 諸星団(id:72202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>