<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>村上源氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>村上源氏（むらかみげんじ）は、62代村上天皇の皇子を祖とする賜姓皇族のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan) is a shisei kozoku (member of the Imperial Family conferred with a family name) whose patriarch was the son of the 62nd emperor, Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murakami-Genji (the Minamoto clan) is a shisei kozoku (member of the Imperial Family conferred with a family name) whose patriarch was the son of the sixty-second emperor, Murakami.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murakami-Genji was a shisei kozoku (member of the Imperial Family conferred with a family name) who was descended from a son of the sixty second Emperor, Murakami.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ハイフン削除しました。Emperor大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第七親王の具平親王の子で藤原頼通の猶子となった右大臣源師房の子孫が栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of Udaijin (Minister of the Right) MINAMOTO no Morofusa, who was a son of Imperial Prince Tomohira, the seventh Imperial Prince, and who was adopted by FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, flourished.</e>
<cmt>訳文の意味が分りにくければ文章を分けた方がいいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants of Udaijin (Minister of the Right) MINAMOTO no Morofusa, who was a son of the seventh imperial prince, Tomohira, and who was adopted by FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, flourished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Morofusa was a son of the seventh Imperial Prince Tomohira that was adopted by FUJIWARA no Yorimichi; he later became Udaijin (Minister of the Right), and his descendants flourished.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Imperial Prince大文字にしました。（）削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>源師房は2歳で父親と死に別れて姉である隆姫女王に育てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Morofusa was 2 years old his father died, and he was raised by his older sister, Princess Takahime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Morofusa was two years old his father died, and consequently he was raised by his older sister, Princess Takahime.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When MINAMOTO no Morofusa was two years old, his father died, so he was raised by his older sister, Princess Takahime.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>隆姫が後に摂政藤原頼通の正室となると、子供のなかった藤原頼通は資定王と養子縁組をするために臣籍降下させ、源師房と名を変えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahime later became the lawful wife of Regent FUJIWARA no Yorimichi. Because FUJIWARA no Yorimichi had no children, he adopted Prince Sukesada and renamed him MINAMOTO no Morofusa. In the process, Prince Sukesada&apos;s status was demoted from a member of the Imperial family to that of its subject.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahime later became the lawful wife of Regent FUJIWARA no Yorimichi; however, because FUJIWARA no Yorimichi had no children, he adopted Prince Sukesada and renamed him MINAMOTO no Morofusa, whereupon Prince Sukesada&apos;s status was demoted from a member of the Imperial Family to that of its subject.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahime later became the lawful wife of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi who held the title of Sessho (Regent); however, because FUJIWARA no Yorimichi had no children, he adopted Prince Sukesada and renamed him MINAMOTO no Morofusa, whereupon Prince Sukesada&apos;s status was demoted from a member of the Imperial Family to that of a commoner.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>藤原頼通の父・藤原道長も師房を寵愛して娘を嫁がせた上に藤原頼通に男子が生まれなければ、師房を藤原氏に改姓させて摂家を相続させても構わないと言ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yorimichi&apos;s father, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, also favored Morofusa, and he made one of his daughters Morofusa&apos;s wife. Furthermore, Michinaga is considered to have said that if no sons were born to FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, he would let Morofusa change his surname to FUJIWARA and let him succeed to the sekke (line of regents and advisers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yorimichi&apos;s father, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, also favored Morofusa and made one of his daughters Morufusa&apos;s wife; furthermore, Michinaga is considered to have said that if no sons were born to FUJIWARA no Yorimichi he would let Morofusa change his surname to FUJIWARA and let him succeed to the sekke (line of regents and advisers).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yorimichi&apos;s father, FUJIWARA no Michinaga, also favored Morofusa and made one of his daughters Morufusa&apos;s wife; furthermore, Michinaga is believed to have said that if no sons were born to FUJIWARA no Yorimichi he would let Morofusa change his surname to FUJIWARA and become a member of the sekke (line of regents and advisers).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>摂家との強い結びつきは「源氏と雖も、土御門右丞相の子孫は御堂の末葉に入る」（『台記』）といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that strong ties with the sekke meant, &apos;even though of the Minamoto clan, the descendants of TSUCHIMIKADO, the Ushojo (Udaijin), count as Michinaga&apos;s descendants&apos; (&quot;Taiki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that strong ties with the sekke meant, &apos;Even though of the Minamoto clan, the descendants of TSUCHIMIKADO, the Ushojo (Udaijin) count as Michinaga&apos;s descendants&apos; (&quot;Taiki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Yorinaga)).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a dairy written by FUJIWARA no Yorinaga called &quot;Taiki,&quot; strong ties with the sekke meant, &apos;Even though the descendants of TSUCHIMIKADO, the Ushojo (Udaijin), are of the Minamoto clan, they count as Michinaga&apos;s descendants.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>すなわち師房は、村上源氏にして藤原道長を継ぐ者とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, though Morofusa belonged to Murakami-Genji, he was FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, though Morofusa belonged to Murakami-Genji, he was the heir of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, although Morofusa belonged to Murakami-Genji, he was the heir of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>though →although</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>師房は摂家を継ぐことはなかったものの、子孫からは多くの大臣を輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though Morofusa did not succeed to the sekke, many of his descendants became ministers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though Morofusa did not succeed to the sekke, many of his descendants became ministers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though Morofusa did not succeed to the sekke, many of his descendants became ministers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>源顕房の娘・藤原賢子が産んだ堀河天皇の治世では、「左右大臣、左右大将、源氏同時に相並ぶ例、未だ此の事あらず」（『中右記』寛治7年(1093年)12月27日条）、「近代公卿廿四人、源氏の人半ばを過ぎるか、未だ此の如き事あらんか」（『中右記』康和4年(1102年)6月23日条）とあるように外戚として隆盛を極めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As maternal relatives, Morofusa&apos;s descendants were at the height of their prosperity during the reign of Emperor Horikawa, who was a biological son of MINAMOTO no Akifusa&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Kenshi. This can be seen from &apos;members of the Minamoto clan positioned side by side as the Minister of the Left and the Minister of the Right, as well as the Major Captain of the Left and the Right Divisions of Inner Palace Guards, such has never happened before&apos; (&quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), written on December 27, 1093) and from &apos;there are 24 modern day kugyo (court nobility), of which more than half are from the Minamoto clan, has such ever happened before&apos; (&quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), written on June 23, 1102).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As maternal relatives, Morofusa&apos;s descendants were at the height of their prosperity during the reign of Emperor Horikawa, who was a biological son of MINAMOTO no Akifusa&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Kenshi, as can be seen from &apos;members of the Minamoto clan positioned side by side as the Minister of the Left and the Minister of the Right, as well as the Major Captain of the Left and the Right Divisions of Inner Palace Guards, which has never happened before&apos; (&quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), written on December 27, 1093) and from &apos;there are 24 modern-day kugyo (court nobility), of which more than half are from the Minamoto clan, which has never happened before&apos; (&quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), written on June 23, 1102).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As maternal relatives, Morofusa&apos;s descendants were at the height of their prosperity during the reign of Emperor Horikawa, who was a biological son of MINAMOTO no Akifusa&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Kenshi, as can be seen from &apos;members of the Minamoto clan positioned side by side as the Minister of the Left and the Minister of the Right, as well as the Major Captain of the Left and the Right Divisions of Inner Palace Guards, which has never happened before&apos; (&quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), the article of January 22, 1094) and from &apos;there are 24 modern-day kugyo (court nobility), of which more than half are from the Minamoto clan, which has never happened before&apos; (&quot;Chuyuki&quot; (diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada), the article of written on August 15, 1102).</e>
<cmt>旧暦を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>源雅実は源氏初の太政大臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Masazane was the first of the Genji to become a daijo daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Masazane was the first of the Genji to become a daijo daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Masazane was the first of the Minamoto clan to become a daijo daijin (grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、外戚の地位を閑院流に奪われて勢力は後退するが、鎌倉時代の源通親は九条家に対抗し後白河天皇・後鳥羽天皇の院政下で活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their power later deteriorated because their status as maternal relatives (of the emperor) was taken over by the Kanin line (a branch of the Fujiwara clan). MINAMOTO no Michichika vied against the Kujo family during the Kamakura period and he served successful under Emperor Goshirakwa and Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their power later deteriorated because their status as maternal relatives (of the emperor) was taken over by the Kanin line (a branch of the Fujiwara clan); MINAMOTO no Michichika vied against the Kujo family during the Kamakura period and he served successfully under the emperors Goshirakwa and Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their power later deteriorated because their status as maternal relatives of the emperor was taken over by the Kanin line of the Fujiwara clan; MINAMOTO no Michichika vied against the Kujo family during the Kamakura period, and served successfully under the cloister governments of the Emperor Goshirakwa and the Emperor Gotoba.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>土御門天皇の外祖父として権勢を振るう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He wielded power as the maternal grandfather of Emperor Tsuchimikado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He wielded power as the maternal grandfather of Emperor Tsuchimikado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He wielded power as the maternal grandfather of Emperor Tsuchimikado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>源通親の子供久我通光以降久我家を家名とし、足利義満が太政大臣となるまでは清華家である久我家・堀川家・土御門家・中院家の4家が交互に源氏長者を世襲したが、室町時代に堀河・土御門両家が断絶（戦国時代_(日本)以後の堀川・土御門家はそれぞれ藤原氏・阿倍氏の子孫）し、久我家・中院家両家の世襲となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the generation of MINAMOTO no Michichika&apos;s son, Michiteru KOGA, the family name was changed to KOGA. Until Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA became a daijo daijin the 4 Seiga families (highest court noble families in Japan at that time) of Koga, Horikawa, Tsuchimikado and Nakanoin families took turns inheriting the position as the head of the Minamoto clan. However, the Horikawa and Tsuchimikado families both came to an end during the Muromachi period (the Horikawa and the Tsuchimikado families since the Period of Warring States (Japan) are the descendants of the Fujiwara and the Abe clans, respectively), and the hereditary succession was shared between the Koga and the Nakanoin families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the generation of MINAMOTO no Michichika&apos;s son, Michiteru KOGA, the family name was changed to KOGA, and until Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA became a daijo daijin the four Seiga families (the highest court noble families in Japan at that time) of Koga, Horikawa, Tsuchimikado and Nakanoin took turns inheriting the position as the head of the Minamoto clan; however, the Horikawa and Tsuchimikado families both came to an end during the Muromachi period (the Horikawa and the Tsuchimikado families since the Warring States period (Japan) are the descendants of the Fujiwara and Abe clans, respectively), and the hereditary succession was shared between the Koga and Nakanoin families.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the time of MINAMOTO no Michichika&apos;s son Michiteru onward, the Minamoto family name was changed to KOGA, and until Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA became a daijo daijin, the position of head of the Minamoto clan was rotated among the four Seiga families (court noble families whose members were eligible for the position of daijin, or minister) of Koga, Horikawa, Tsuchimikado and Nakanoin; however, the Horikawa and Tsuchimikado families both came to an end during the Muromachi period (the Horikawa and the Tsuchimikado families that have emerged since Japan&apos;s Sengoku period are descendants of the Fujiwara and Abe clans, respectively), and the hereditary succession was shared between the Koga and Nakanoin families.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>源氏といえば武家として活躍した清和源氏を想起する人が多いが、公家社会では村上源氏が最高とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genji reminds many people of Seiwa-Genji who was successful as a samurai family. However, among the society of court nobles Murakami-Genji was considered to be at the highest rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genji reminds many people of Seiwa-Genji, who was successful as a samurai family; however, among the society of court nobles Murakami-Genji was considered to be of the highest rank.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mention of the Minamoto clan makes many people think of Seiwa-Genji, who were very active as a samurai family; among the society of court nobles, however, Murakami-Genji was considered to hold the highest rank.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>久我家からは大臣家となる中院家やその分家筋である北畠家、岩倉家他、合計10家の堂上家を輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Koga family produced the Nakanoin family, that later became the family of ministers. It also produced branch families such as the Kitabatake family, the Iwakura family and so on, with a total of 10 Tosho-ke (the hereditary lineage of court nobles occupying relatively high ranks) families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Koga family produced the Nakanoin family, which later became a family of ministers; additionally, it produced branch families such as the Kitabatake family, the Iwakura family and so on, with a total of ten Tosho-ke (the hereditary lineage of court nobles occupying relatively high rank) families.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Koga family gave rise to the Nakanoin family, which later became a family of ministers; additionally, it produced a total of ten branch families that were recognized as being Tosho-ke (hereditary court nobles occupying relatively high rank) families, including the Kitabatake and Iwakura families.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)の北畠親房、幕末の岩倉具視も村上源氏の支流である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikafusa KITABATAKE during the Period of the Northern and Southern Dynasties (Japan) and Tomomi IWAKURA from the end of the Edo period also belonged to the branch families of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikafusa KITABATAKE, during the Northern and Southern Dynasties period (Japan), and Tomomi IWAKURA, from the end of the Edo period, also belonged to branch families of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikafusa KITABATAKE, during the period of Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), and Tomomi IWAKURA, from the end of the Edo period, also belonged to branch families of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。例にならって、the period of Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) と訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>一方、播磨国赤松を名字の地とする赤松氏もまた村上源氏季房流と自称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Akamatsu clan that has Akamatsu of Harima Province for its surname also called themselves the Suefusa line of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>季房は「すえふさ」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the Akamatsu clan (after Akamatsu of Harima Province) also called themselves the Suefusa line of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Akamatsu clan (after Akamatsu of Harima Province) also called themselves the Suefusa line of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、名和長年も村上源氏雅兼流と自称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Nagatoshi NAWA also called himself as the Masakane line of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>雅兼は「まさかね」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Nagatoshi NAWA referred to himself as being of the Masakane line of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Nagatoshi NAWA claimed to be of the Masakane line of the Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>さらに奥三河の作手村城主（奥平氏）の奥平貞能・奥平信昌父子も村上源氏と自称する赤松満則流と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the father and son pair, Sadayoshi OKUHIRA and Nobumasa OKUHIRA, the lord of Tsukudemura-jo castle (the Okuhira clan) in Okumikawa, also called themselves as the Mitsunori AKAMATSU line of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>作手村は「つくでむら」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the father-and-son pair of Sadayoshi OKUHIRA and Nobumasa OKUHIRA, the lord of Tsukudemura-jo Castle (the Okuhira clan) in Okumikawa, referred to themselves as the Mitsunori AKAMATSU line of Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Sadayoshi OKUHIRA and his son Nobumasa, the lord of Tsukudemura-jo Castle (the Okuhira clan) in Okumikawa, claimed to be of the Mitsunori AKAMATSU line of the Murakami-Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Gimbrow(id:65660), Masyu(id:31065), 浩(id:70121), Jinnsg(id:43599), 玄史生(id:43670), Equaly(id:89792), 代言人(id:33675), 水野白楓(id:22811), YOSHI438(id:174755), 唐棣色(id:64681), Junger(id:10282), BAKU(id:55205), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>