<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>筒井氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tsutsui Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tsutsui Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tsutsui Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>筒井氏（つついし）は、大和国の戦国大名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tsutsui clan is the family of a war lord in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tsutsui clan was Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) of Yamato Province in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。訳漏れ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tsutsui clan was Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) of Yamato Province in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>筒井氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tsutsui Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tsutsui Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tsutsui Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>筒井氏は大神神社の神官・大神氏の一族と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tsutsui clan is said to have been originated as a Shinto priest family, the Oga clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Tsutsui clan originated from the Omiwa clan, the Shinto priest family of Omiwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「大神神社」は「おおみわ」のようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Tsutsui clan originated from the Omiwa clan, the Shinto priest family of Omiwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>筒井氏は大和国添下郡筒井の土豪として大和に勢力を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tsutsui clan maintained power in Yamato Province as a local ruler in Tsutsui district, Sonoshimonokori County in Yamato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tsutsui clan had been dominating Yamato region as a local ruler of Tsutsui, Sonoshimo-no-kori County, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tsutsui clan had been dominating Yamato region as a local ruler of Tsutsui, Sonoshimo-no-kori County, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉時代以降、大和国守護は興福寺が務めており、筒井氏もその衆徒として組み込まれるが、戦国時代 (日本)に入ると興福寺の勢力が衰退し、筒井氏や越智氏の勢力が台頭してくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the end of the Kamakura period, Kofuku-ji Temple served as Shugo (provincial constable) of Yamato Province, and the Tsutsui clan was included in the group of monk-soldiers of the temple, but since the Sengoku period began, Kofuku-ji Temple went into a decline, and local clans such as the Tsutsui and the Ochi began to rise in exchange.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Kamakura period, Kofuku-ji Temple served as Shugo (provincial constable) of Yamato Province, and the Tsutsui clan served it as Shuto (group of monk-soldiers of temple); in the Sengoku period, Kofuku-ji Temple went into a decline, and local clans such as the Tsutsui clan and the Ochi clan began to rise in exchange.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kamakura period, Kofuku-ji Temple served as Shugo (provincial constable) of Yamato Province, and the Tsutsui clan served it as Shuto (group of monk-soldiers of temple); in the Sengoku period, Kofuku-ji Temple went into a decline, and local clans such as the Tsutsui clan and the Ochi clan began to rise in exchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1467年の応仁の乱では、河内国の守護大名である畠山氏の抗争に巻き込まれて、大和国内は混乱する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Onin War in 1467, the province of Yamato was involved in the conflicts of the Hatakeyama clan, a shugo daimyo of Kawachi Province, and became turbulent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Onin War of 1467, the conflicts of Shugo Daimyo (provincial constable) of Kawachi Province the Hatakeyama clan acted as a trigger, in Yamato Province, some turbulence was caused.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Onin War of 1467, the conflicts of Shugo Daimyo (provincial constable) of Kawachi Province the Hatakeyama clan acted as a trigger, in Yamato Province, some turbulence was caused.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>そのような中で筒井氏の当主となった筒井順興は英明で、大和国人衆の一人として興福寺に属しながら宿敵・越智氏を討ち滅ぼして勢力を拡大し、筒井氏を大和の戦国大名としてのし上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, Junko TSUTSUI, who became the head of the Tsutsui clan, beat and destroyed their foe Ochi clan while remaining as a member of Yamato&apos;s local clans on the side of Kofuku-ji Temple, extended their influence, and established the clan as the Sengoku daimyo of Yamato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junko TSUTSUI, who became the head of the Tsutsui clan in the chaotic situation, demonstrated his ability very well and destroyed the longtime foe the Ochi clan while serving Kofuku-ji Temple as one of Kokujinshu (local governors) of Yamato, and he extended influence to establish the clan as one of powerful Sengoku daimyo of Yamato.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junko TSUTSUI, who became the head of the Tsutsui clan in the chaotic situation, demonstrated his ability very well and destroyed the longtime foe the Ochi clan while serving Kofuku-ji Temple as one of Kokujinshu (local governors) of Yamato, and he extended influence to establish the clan as one of powerful Sengoku daimyo of Yamato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1535年に順興は死去し、嫡男の筒井順昭が後を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junko died in 1535, and his eldest son Junsho TSUTSUI inherited the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junko died in 1535, and his eldest son Junsho TSUTSUI inherited the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junko died in 1535, and his eldest son Junsho TSUTSUI inherited the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>順昭も英明で、信貴山城を本拠にして木沢長政と戦い、遂には大和を統一。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As bright as his father, Junsho fought Nagamasa KIZAWA while residing at the Shigisan Castle as his headquarters and finally united Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As bright as his father, Junsho set his base at Shigisan-jo Castle to fight against Nagamasa KIZAWA, and finally united Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As bright as his father, Junsho set his base at Shigisan-jo Castle to fight against Nagamasa KIZAWA, and finally united Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>さらに、河内にもその勢力を伸ばし筒井氏の全盛期を築き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also extended the clan&apos;s influence in Kawachi and rose the power of his clan to the highest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also extended his influence to Kawachi Province and produced the golden age of the Tsutsui clan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also extended his influence to Kawachi Province and established the golden age of the Tsutsui clan.</e>
<cmt>produced →established</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、順昭は1550年に28歳の若さで死去し、嫡男でわずか2歳の筒井順慶が後を継ぐこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Junsho died young, at the age of 28, in 1550, and his eldest son, Junkei TSUTSUI, who was only 2 years old, inherited the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1550 Junsho died young at the age of 28, and his eldest son, Junkei TSUTSUI, who was only 2 years old, inherited the clan.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1550 Junsho died young at the age of 28, and his eldest son, Junkei TSUTSUI, who was only 2 years old, inherited the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>木阿弥の話はこの世代交代を舞台にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An episode of Mokuami was based on this transition of power from Junsho to Junkei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The famous legend which produced a proverb &quot;Mokuami&quot; (&quot;Moto no Mokuami&quot;) originated from this succession.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The famous legend which produced a proverb &quot;Mokuami&quot; (&quot;Moto no Mokuami&quot;) originated from this succession.</e>
<cmt>succession→generational change</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>筒井順慶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junkei TSUTSUI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junkei TSUTSUI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junkei TSUTSUI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>順慶はわずか2歳で当主となるが、その年齢で政務を執れるはずが無く、叔父の筒井順政が後見人を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he became the head of the family at the age of 2, he could not manage the administrative affairs at that young age, and his uncle Junsei TSUTSUI served as his guardian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junkei became the head of the family at the age of 2, however, since he could not manage the administrative affairs of course, his uncle Junsei TSUTSUI did those things as his guardian.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junkei became the head of the family at the age of 2, however, since he could not manage the administrative affairs of course, his uncle Junsei TSUTSUI did those things as his guardian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし順慶が幼少であるのを見て、三好長慶の家臣・松永久秀が大和に侵攻して来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But knowing Junkei was still juvenile, Hisahide MATSUNAGA, a vassal of Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, invaded Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, knowing Junkei was still juvenile, Hisahide MATSUNAGA, a vassal of Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, invaded Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, knowing Junkei was still juvenile, Hisahide MATSUNAGA, a vassal of Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, invaded Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>順慶は幼少で、しかも順政も1564年に死去という悪条件が重なった筒井氏には軍の統率が取れず、筒井城を久秀に奪われた（筒井城の戦い）順慶は大和から追放された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of a series of bad conditions, or Junkei&apos;s being still a child and Junsei&apos;s death in 1564, no military control was maintained in the Tsutsui clan, which resulted in the seizure of Tsutsui Castle by Hisahide (Battle of Tsutsui Castle) and expulsion of Junkei from Yamato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the series of bad conditions including Junkei&apos;s youth and Junsei&apos;s death in 1564, the Tsutsui clan didn&apos;t have any power to even control their own troops, and in the Battle of Tsutsui-jo Castle, their base Tsutsui-jo Castle finally fell to Hisahide, and Junkei was exiled from Yamato.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the series of bad conditions such as Junkei was too young and Junsei died in 1564, the Tsutsui clan didn&apos;t have any power to even control their own troops, and in the Battle of Tsutsui-jo Castle, their base Tsutsui-jo Castle finally fell to Hisahide, and Junkei was exiled from Yamato.</e>
<cmt>including Junkei&apos;s youth and Junsei&apos;s death in 1564→such as Junkei was too young and Junsei died in 1564</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>後に久秀が三好三人衆と対立したときには、三人衆に属して大和国奪回を目指したが、久秀の前にたびたび敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When later years Hisahide confronted the Miyoshi Sanninshu (or the Miyoshi Triumvirs, which are the three major members of the Miyoshi clan), Junkei joined the forces of the Sanninshu to aim at recovering Yamato but was again defeated by Hisahide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When later years Hisahide confronted the Miyoshi Sanninshu (or the Miyoshi Triumvirs, which are the three major members of the Miyoshi clan), Junkei joined in the forces of the Sanninshu aiming at recovering Yamato, however, he was defeated by Hisahide again and again.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。前置詞。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When later years Hisahide confronted the Miyoshi Sanninshu (or the Miyoshi Triumvirs, which are the three major members of the Miyoshi clan), Junkei joined in the forces of the Sanninshu aiming at recovering Yamato, however, he was defeated by Hisahide again and again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このため、順慶は当時の天下人である織田信長の家臣となり、その後ろ盾をもって信長の客将となっていた久秀から大和守護に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junkei became a vassal of Nobunaga ODA, the then ruler of the entire country, and used the influence of Nobunaga to successfully win an appointment as Shugo of Yamato Province by Hisahide, who was then a guest samurai of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Junkei became a vassal of Nobunaga ODA, the then ruler of the entire country, and used the influence of Nobunaga to successfully win an appointment as Shugo of Yamato Province by Hisahide, who was then a guest samurai of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>接続詞。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Junkei became a vassal of Nobunaga ODA, the then ruler of the entire country, and used the influence of Nobunaga to successfully win an appointment as Shugo of Yamato Province by Hisahide, who was then a guest samurai of Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後は明智光秀の与力大名として久秀討伐（信貴山城の戦い）、一向一揆討伐などで活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junkei then helped Mitsuhide AKECHI as a supporting daimyo to make military achievements including destruction of Hisahide (Battle of Shigisan Castle) and Ikko sect&apos;s revolts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Junkei helped Mitsuhide AKECHI as Yoriki Daimyo (territorial lord who supports other lords) to make military achievements including the expedition of Hisahide (the Battle of Shigisan-jo Castle) and the expedition of Ikko sect&apos;s revolts.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Junkei helped Mitsuhide AKECHI as Yoriki Daimyo (territorial lord who supports other lords) to make military achievements including the expedition of Hisahide (the Battle of Shigisan-jo Castle) and the expedition of Ikko sect&apos;s revolts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>1582年、本能寺の変が起きて光秀が信長を殺すと、その与力という関係から協調行動を勧誘されるが、順慶は拒否。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Mitsuhide murdered Nobunaga in the Honnoji Incident in 1582, Junkei was induced by Mitsuhide to join his forces because of Junkei&apos;s relationship (yoriki) with Mitsuhide, but he rejected it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Mitsuhide murdered Nobunaga in the Honnoji Incident in 1582, Junkei was induced by Mitsuhide to cooperate because Junkei had been Mitsuhide&apos;s Yoriki, however, he rejected it.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Mitsuhide murdered Nobunaga in the Honnoji Incident in 1582, Junkei was induced by Mitsuhide to cooperate because Junkei had been Mitsuhide&apos;s Yoriki, however, he rejected it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>所領は安堵された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was allowed to maintain his domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was allowed to maintain his domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was allowed to maintain his domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>このときの筒井軍の行動が後世に脚色され、日和見的態度を指す「洞ヶ峠」の由来となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The act of Tsutsui&apos;s forces at this time was dramatized years later to become the origin of &quot;Horaga-toge Pass,&quot; the term to indicate opportunism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The act of Tsutsui&apos;s forces at this time was dramatized years later to become the origin of &quot;Horaga-toge Pass,&quot; the term to indicate opportunism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The act of Tsutsui&apos;s forces at this time was dramatized years later to become the origin of &quot;Horaga-toge Pass,&quot; the term to indicate opportunism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>順慶は1584年に36歳の若さで死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Junkei died young at the age of 36 in 1584.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Junkei died young at the age of 36 in 1584.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Junkei died young at the age of 36 in 1584.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>嗣子が無いため、後を養嗣子の筒井定次が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he had no son as an heir, the Tsutsui clan was inherited by an adopted heir, Sadatsugu TSUTSUI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he had no son as an heir, the Tsutsui clan was inherited by an adopted heir, Sadatsugu TSUTSUI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he had no son as an heir, the Tsutsui clan was inherited by an adopted heir, Sadatsugu TSUTSUI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>筒井氏の滅亡とその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Destruction of the Tsutsui Clan and the Aftermath</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Destruction of the Tsutsui Clan and the Aftermath</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Destruction of the Tsutsui Clan and the Aftermath</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>定次は豊臣秀吉の家臣として仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadatsugu served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as his vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadatsugu served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as his vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadatsugu served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as his vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかしこれまでの英明な筒井氏当主に比せば見目は良いものの平凡な人物で、中坊秀祐の讒言を受け入れて名臣の島左近と対立し、これを追放してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with the past wise heads of the Tsutsui clan, he was mediocre in wisdom although he looked better in appearance, and he ousted Sakon SHIMA, an excellent vassal, after believing the false charge made by Hidesuke NAKANOBO against SHIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with the past wise heads of the Tsutsui clan, he was mediocre in wisdom although he looked better in appearance, and he ousted Sakon SHIMA, an excellent vassal, after believing the false charge made by Hidesuke NAKANOBO against SHIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with the past wise heads of the Tsutsui clan, he was mediocre in wisdom although he looked better in appearance, and he ousted Sakon SHIMA, an excellent vassal, after believing the false charge made by Hidesuke NAKANOBO against SHIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>さらに秀吉も大和には信用できる身内を置いておきたいという考えから、定次は1585年、伊賀国上野城に移封された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Hideyoshi wanted to put someone trustworthy among his family members or relatives in charge of Yamato, Sadatsugu was transferred to Ueno Castle in Iga Province in 1585.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Hideyoshi wanted to put someone trustworthy among his family members or relatives in charge of Yamato, Sadatsugu was transferred to Ueno-jo Castle in Iga Province in 1585.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Hideyoshi wanted to put someone trustworthy among his family members or relatives in charge of Yamato, Sadatsugu was transferred to Ueno-jo Castle in Iga Province in 1585.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これは四国征伐の武功による加増と言われているが、実質は40万石から20万石もの減封である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this transfer was believed to be the reward for his military achievement in the Shikoku Conquest and the resultant increase in the feud to manage, it was in reality a decrease in the area of feud from 400,000 goku to 200,000 goku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This transfer was believed to be the reward for his military achievement in the Shikoku Conquest and his hereditary rice stipend had to increase; however, in fact, the stipend was decreased from 400,000 goku (72156 cubic meters) to 200,000 goku (36078 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This transfer was believed to be the reward for his military achievement in the Shikoku Conquest and his hereditary rice stipend had to increase; however, in fact, the stipend was decreased from 400,000 koku (72156 cubic meters) to 200,000 koku (36078 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>goku→koku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>このため、筒井氏は家臣の多くを改易し、伊賀の土豪をも潰していかざるを得なかったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this transfer, it is said that the Tsutsui clan had to dismiss many of his subjects and dissolve local clans of Iga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that because of this transfer, the Tsutsui clan had to dismiss many of their subjects and dissolve local clans of Iga.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that because of this transfer, the Tsutsui clan had to dismiss many of their subjects and dissolve local clans of Iga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>定次はこの秀吉の仕打ちを恨んだのか、1600年の関ヶ原の戦いでは東軍に与して武功を挙げたことから所領を安堵され、伊賀上野藩を立藩した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Probably out of his grudge against Hideyoshi&apos;s decision, Sadatsugu sided with the Eastern Army in the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, obtained military achievements, was allowed to maintain his domain and set up Ueno Domain in Iga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Probably because of this cavalier treatment, Sadatsugu had been bearing a grudge against Hideyoshi; at the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he sided with the Eastern Army (the enemy of the Toyotomi family) and obtained military achievements; after the war, he was allowed to maintain his domain and set up Ueno Domain in Iga Province.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Probably because of this cavalier treatment, Sadatsugu had been bearing a grudge against Hideyoshi; at the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he sided with the Eastern Army (the enemy of the Toyotomi family) and obtained military achievements; after the war, he was allowed to maintain his domain and set up Ueno Domain in Iga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし1608年、幕命により改易され伊賀上野藩20万石は廃藩となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in 1608, he was deprived of his status as the lord of Ueno Domain by the Shogunate&apos;s order, and the Ueno Domain with a feud of 200,000 goku was demolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in 1608, he was deprived of his status as the lord of Ueno Domain by the Shogunate&apos;s order, and the Ueno Domain with 200,000 goku was demolished.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in 1608, he was deprived of his status as the lord of Ueno Domain by the Shogunate&apos;s order, and the Ueno Domain with 200,000 koku was demolished.</e>
<cmt>goku→koku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>定次自身の身柄は鳥居忠政預かりとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadatsugu himself was put under the custody of Tadamasa TORII.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadatsugu himself was put under the custody of Tadamasa TORII.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadatsugu himself was put under the custody of Tadamasa TORII.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>改易の理由は、定次が酒色に溺れて政務を顧みなかったこと、キリシタンであったことなどのほかに、筒井氏のような外様大名を畿内に置いておくのは危険と考えた幕府の有力外様大名取り潰し政策の一環とも伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reasons of his dismissal include his dissolute life, his indifference to governing and his being a Christian, and it is also said that the decision of his dismissal was part of the policy of the Tokugawa Shogunate to abolish powerful non-Tokugawa feudal lords because of the possible danger of allocating such a powerful daimyo as the Tsutsui clan in Kinki region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the reasons of his dismissal, it is said that he neglected the administrative affairs addicting himself to alcohol and women; he was a Christian; and it might have been a result of the Shogunate&apos;s policy to abolish powerful non-Tokugawa feudal lords, because the Tsutsui clan was one of such lords even ruling an important area of Kinai region (including five powerful provinces near to Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the reasons of his dismissal, it is said that he neglected the administrative affairs addicting himself to alcohol and women; he was a Christian; and it might have been a result of the Shogunate&apos;s policy to abolish powerful non-Tokugawa feudal lords, because the Tsutsui clan was one of such lords even ruling an important area of Kinai region (including five powerful provinces near to Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>そして1615年、定次は大坂冬の陣で城方に内通したという責めによって、幕命により息子の筒井順定とともに自害を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1615, Sadatsugu was ordered by the Shogunate to commit suicide together with his son Juntei TSUTSUI for the charge of his secret communication with the Osaka Castle side during Osaka Fuyu no Jin (Winter Siege of Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1615, Sadatsugu was ordered by the Shogunate to commit suicide together with his son Juntei TSUTSUI for the charge of his secret communication with the people of Osaka-jo Castle (the enemy) during Winter Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1615, Sadatsugu was ordered by the Shogunate to commit suicide together with his son Juntei TSUTSUI on charge of his secret communication with the people of Osaka-jo Castle (the enemy) during Winter Siege of Osaka.</e>
<cmt>for the charge of→on charge of</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その後筒井定慶が大和郡山1万石を与えられたが、大坂夏の陣で定慶が戦死したため、大名としての筒井氏は滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Years later Juntei TSUTSUI was granted a domain of 10,000 goku in Yamato Koriyama, but he was killed in action during Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), and the Tsutsui clan as a daimyo family disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Years later Juntei TSUTSUI was granted a domain of 10,000 goku in Yamato Koriyama, however he was killed in action during Summer Siege of Osaka, at the result, the Tsutsui clan as Daimyo family disappeared.</e>
<cmt>用語の統一。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Years later Juntei TSUTSUI was granted a domain of 10,000 koku in Yamato Koriyama, however he was killed in action during Summer Siege of Osaka, at the result, the Tsutsui clan as Daimyo family disappeared.</e>
<cmt>goku→koku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>その後、順慶の養子順斎（福須美順弘の次男）が徳川家康に仕え旗本となり、1千石を与えられ家名は幕末まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later an adopted son of Junkei, Junsai (who was the second son of Junko FUKUZUMI), served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became a hatamoto (direct retainer of the Shogunate) with 1,000 goku, and his clan survived until the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later an adopted son of Junkei, Junsai (who was the second son of Junko FUKUZUMI), served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became a hatamoto (direct retainer of the Shogunate) with 1,000 goku, and his clan survived until the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later an adopted son of Junkei, Junsai (who was the second son of Junko FUKUZUMI), served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became a hatamoto (direct retainer of the Shogunate) with 1,000 goku, and his clan survived until the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>幕末に日露和親条約の交渉を行った筒井政憲はその末裔である（久世氏の出身で養子として筒井氏を継いでいる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born to the Kuze clan and having inherited the Tsutsui clan as an adopted heir, Masanori TSUTSUI, who was engaged in negotiation for the Treaty between the Russian Empire and the Empire of Japan at the end of the Edo period, was Junsai&apos;s descendant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanori TSUTSUI who was active at the end of the Edo period was a Junsai&apos;s descendant; he was born to the Kuze clan, inherited the Tsutsui clan as an adopted heir, and engaged in negotiation for the Treaty between the Russian Empire and the Empire of Japan at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanori TSUTSUI who was active at the end of the Edo period was a Junsai&apos;s descendant; he was born to the Kuze clan, inherited the Tsutsui clan as an adopted heir, and engaged in negotiation for the Treaty between the Russian Empire and the Empire of Japan at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tosiho(id:73924), Gimbrow(id:65660), Yanahan(id:2437), Kogane(id:28186), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), ブレイズマン(id:183852), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), シェーラ(id:17988), 水野白楓(id:22811), 百人(id:16483), KurmUmy(id:202680), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>