<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大江氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oe clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oe clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oe clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大江（おおえ）氏は古代から近世の貴族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oe clan was a noble from ancient times until early modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oe clan were nobles from ancient times until early modern times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oe clan were nobles from ancient times until early modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源、平、藤原、橘と同じく姓(本姓)であり、苗字ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a sei (honsei) and not a myoji.</e>
<cmt>「姓」と「苗字」を区別するこの議論が正確には理解できず、英語への翻訳ができません。（「広辞苑」、「新和英大辞典」でも区別されていないと思われます。）そのため、[sei (honsei)」「myoji」として、原文の意味を伝えることを試みました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a sei (honsei) and not a myoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &quot;Oe&quot; is a Sei (or Honsei) which is a family name representing a large group of blood relatives, such as Minamoto, Taira, Fujiwara, and Tachibana; it is not a Myoji, which is a family name originating from the name of the region from which the person came or the job the person does.</e>
<cmt>姓は古くは苗字とは別だったので訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>奈良時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>古代の氏族である土師氏が源流とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Haji clan in the ancient times was the origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Haji clan in ancient times was their origin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Haji clan in ancient times was their origin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>桓武天皇が即位10年となった延暦9年（791年）に、縁戚関係にある大枝諸上らに大枝の姓を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 791, the Emperor Kanmu, in his tenth year of reign, gave OE no Morogami and so on with whom the Emperor was relative, gave the sei of Oe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 791, Emperor Kanmu, in the tenth year of his reign, gave OE no Morogami, with whom the Emperor was a relative, gave the sei of Oe.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 791, Emperor Kanmu, in the tenth year of his reign, gave OE no Morogami, with whom the Emperor was a relative, gave the Sei of Oe.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>866年には大枝音人が姓を改め、大江音人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 866, OE no Otondo (大枝音人) changed the sei and became OE no Otondo (大江音人)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 866, OE no Otondo (大枝音人) changed sei and became OE no Otondo (大江音人)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 866, OE no Otondo (大枝音人) changed Sei and became OE no Otondo (大江音人)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大江氏には優れた歌人や学者が多く、朝廷に重く用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oe clan had many excellent kajin (waka poets) and academians and they were given important posts by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oe clan had many excellent kajin (waka poets) and academia&apos;s and they were given important posts by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oe clan had many excellent kajin (waka poets) and academia&apos;s and they were given important posts by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>academia&apos;s→academias</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>中古三十六歌仙と呼ばれる和歌の名人三十六撰に、大江氏から大江千里 (歌人),大江匡衡,大江嘉言,女性からは和泉式部,赤染衛門らが選出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For thirty-six excellent waka poets called &quot;chuko-sanjurokkasen,&quot;OE no Chisato (wakanpoet), OE no Masahira, OE no Yoshitoki, and from ladies, Izumi Shikibu, Akazome Emon and so on were chosen from the Oe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirty-six excellent waka poets called &quot;chuko-sanjurokkasen,&quot;OE no Chisato (wakanpoet), OE no Masahira, OE no Yoshitoki, and from ladies, Izumi Shikibu, Akazome Emon, were chosen from the Oe clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirty-six excellent waka poets called &quot;chuko-sanjurokkasen,&quot;OE no Chisato (wakanpoet), OE no Masahira, OE no Yoshitoki, and from ladies, Izumi Shikibu, Akazome Emon, were chosen from the Oe clan.</e>
<cmt>文頭のため数字表記変更しません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>大江匡衡の孫に平安時代屈指の学者であると共に河内源氏の源義家(八幡太郎義家)に兵法を教えたとされる大江匡房がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a grandson of OE no Masahira, there was OE no Masafusa, who was one of the best acedemians in the Heian Period and reportedly taught art of warfare to MINAMOTO no Yoshiie (Hachimantaro Yoshiie) of Kawachi-Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a grandson of OE no Masahira, there was OE no Masafusa, who was one of the best acedemia in the Heian Period and reportedly taught the art of warfare to MINAMOTO no Yoshiie (Hachimantaro Yoshiie) of Kawachi-Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a grandson of OE no Masahira, there was OE no Masafusa, who was one of the best acedemia in the Heian Period and reportedly taught the art of warfare to MINAMOTO no Yoshiie (Hachimantaro Yoshiie) of Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>(Minamoto clan) 追記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>鎌倉時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1184年に河内源氏の棟梁の源頼朝に仕えた大江広元は大江匡房の孫であり、頼朝の覇業を内政面で支える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OE no Hiromoto, who served MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, who was the head of the Kawachi-Genji, was a grandson of OE no Masafusa and supported Yoritomo&apos;s achievement from the aspect of domestic administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OE no Hiromoto, who served MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, the head of the Kawachi-Genji, was a grandson of OE no Masafusa and supported Yoritomo&apos;s achievements from the aspect of domestic administration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OE no Hiromoto, who served MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, the head of the Kawachi-Genji, was a grandson of OE no Masafusa and supported Yoritomo&apos;s achievements from the aspect of domestic administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>頼朝が鎌倉幕府を開くと、広元は幕府の中枢にまで昇りつめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoritomo opened he Kamakura bakufu, Hiromoto rose to the nerve center of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoritomo opened the Kamakura bakufu, Hiromoto rose to the nerve center of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoritomo opened the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Hiromoto rose to the nerve center of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>幕府の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このことから大江広元の系統は、武家の大江氏として毛利氏をはじめとする武家の祖となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, the line of OE no Hiromoto became, as the OE clan as samurai family, the origin of samurai families including the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, the line of OE no Hiromoto became the OE clan, the origin of samurai families including the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, the line of OE no Hiromoto became the OE clan, the origin of samurai families including the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>1247年に大江広元の四男の大江季光(毛利季光)が、鎌倉幕府に対し謀反を起こした三浦泰村に味方したため、武家大江氏の嫡流は衰退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because OE no Suemitsu (MORI Suemitsu), who was the fourth son of OE no Hiromoto supported Yasumura MIURA, who raised a rebellion against the Kamakura bakufu, the direct line of the Oe clan as samurai family declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because OE no Suemitsu (MORI Suemitsu), the fourth son of OE no Hiromoto, supported Yasumura MIURA who raised a rebellion against the Kamakura bakufu, the direct line of the Oe clan as samurai family declined.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because OE no Suemitsu (Suemitsu MORI), the fourth son of OE no Hiromoto, supported Yasumura MIURA who raised a rebellion against the Kamakura bakufu, the direct line of the Oe clan as samurai family declined.</e>
<cmt>MORI Suemitsu→Suemitsu MORI</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>大江広元の後裔は各地方で武家として活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants from OE no Hiromoto actively worked as samurai family in various regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants from OE no Hiromoto actively worked as members of the samurai family in various regions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants from OE no Hiromoto actively worked as members of the samurai family in various regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その末裔に以下がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their descendants include the following clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their descendants include the following clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their descendants include the following clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>安芸国出雲国の毛利氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mori clan in Aki Province and Izumo Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mori clan in Aki Province and Izumo Province</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mori clan in Aki Province and Izumo Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>三河国の海東氏,酒井氏,芦澤氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaito clan, Sakai clan and Yasuda clan in Mikawa Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kaito clan, Sakai clan, and Yasuda clan in Mikawa Province</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kaito clan, Sakai clan, and Yasuda clan in Mikawa Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>越後国の越後北条氏,安田氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Echigo-Hojo clan and Yasuda clan in Echigo Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Echigo-Hojo clan, and Yasuda clan in Echigo Province</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Echigo-Hojo clan, and Yasuda clan in Echigo Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>出羽国の寒河江氏,長井氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagae clan and Nagai clan in Dewa Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sagae clan, and Nagai clan in Dewa Province</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sagae clan, and Nagai clan in Dewa Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>上野国の那波氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nawa clan in Kozuke Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nawa clan in Kozuke Province</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nawa clan in Kozuke Province</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>また、広元の兄匡範の子孫は宮廷官人として残り、室町時代後半からは北小路家を称し、江戸時代は地下家として3家（蔵人2家、近衛家諸大夫1家）を輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendants of Masanori, Hiromoto&apos;s elder brother, remained as officials of Imperial court and called themselves the Kitakoji family and, in the Edo Period, three families (two as kurodo (chamberlain) and one as shodaibu of the Konoe family) appeared as Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Descendants of Masanori, Hiromoto&apos;s elder brother, remained as officials of the Imperial court and called themselves the Kitakoji family and, during the Edo Period, three families (two as kurodo - chamberlain) and one as shodaibu of the Konoe family) appeared as Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Descendants of Masanori, Hiromoto&apos;s elder brother, remained as officials of the Imperial court and called themselves the Kitakoji family from the end of the Muromachi period and, during the Edo Period, three families (two as kurodo - chamberlain and one as Shodaibu [aristocracy lower than Kugyo] of the Konoe family) appeared as Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace).</e>
<cmt>「室町時代後半からは」訳漏れ対応しました。諸大夫の説明補足chamberlain)→chaberlain</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この内、代々蔵人を勤めた2家は江戸時代後期の弘化4年12月17日 (旧暦)（1848年1月22日）堂上家（半家 (公家)）に列せられた（最後の堂上家昇格）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, two families which served as kurodo for generations were promoted to toshoke (hanke (court noble)) on January 22, 1848 at the last stage of the Edo Period (last promotion to toshoke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, two families which served as kurodo for generations were promoted to toshoke (hanke - court nobles) on January 22, 1848 duging the last stage of the Edo Period (last promotion to toshoke).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, two families which served as kurodo for generations were promoted to toshoke (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks) (hanke [lowest rank for toshoke] [kuge - court nobles]) on January 22, 1848 duging the last stage of the Edo Period (last promotion to toshoke).</e>
<cmt>堂上家（半家 (公家)）の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略系図</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief genealogical table</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief genealogical table</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief genealogical table</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Gimbrow(id:65660), Y.Sanada(id:36926), セプテンバー(id:198896), 玄史生(id:43670), Geogie(id:143809), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), 陽一(id:92099), UMBRO(id:100484), 春秋君(id:174988), 越中掾(id:149423), Snap55(id:89773), 沢田(id:40580), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>