<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳大寺家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The House of Tokudaiji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The House of Tokudaiji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokudaiji Family</e>
<cmt>&quot;House of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～Family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳大寺（とくだいじ）家は、清華家の家格を有する公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The House of Tokudaiji is kuge, court noble having the house status of Seigake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The House of Tokudaiji is a kuge (court noble) having the house status of Seigake.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokudaiji Family is a kuge (court noble) having the house status of Seigake (one of the statuses of court nobility which is inferiror to the sekke but superior to minister).</e>
<cmt>清華家の説明として (one of the statuses of court nobility which is inferiror to Sekke but superior to minister)　を追加&quot;House of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～Family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸時代は同志社大学の構内にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the house was on the premises of Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period the house was on the premises of what is now Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period the house was on the premises of what is now Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原氏藤原北家の閑院流で西園寺家や三条家とは兄弟筋にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The House of Tokudaiji is of Kan&apos;in Line of the House of Fujiwara North of the House of Fujiwara, and has sibling relationship with the House of Saionji and the House of Sanjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The House of Tokudaiji is of the Kan&apos;in line, of the House of Fujiwara North of the House of Fujiwara, and has sibling relationships with the House of Saionji and the House of Sanjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokudaiji Family is of the Kanin line, of the House of Fujiwara North of the Fujiwara clan, and has sibling relationships with the Saionji Family and the Sanjo Family.</e>
<cmt>Fujiwara clan&quot;House of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～Family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家紋は木瓜花菱浮線綾を使用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family insignia; armorial insignia; is Mokko Hanabishi Fusenryo.</e>
<cmt>木瓜花菱浮１線綾→定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family insignia (armorial insignia) is Mokko Hanabishi Fusenryo.</e>
<cmt>style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The crest is Mokko Hanabishi Fusenryo.</e>
<cmt>crestとして統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>笛を家業とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flute is their family business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family business was the flute.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family business was the flute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原公実の四男藤原実能を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original forefather is FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi, the fourth child of FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt>藤原実能→http://jiten.search.biglobe.ne.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original forefather was FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi, the fourth child of FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original forefather was FUJIWARA no Saneyoshi, the fourth child of FUJIWARA no Kinzane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>平安時代末期、左大臣時代の実能が衣笠山の西南麓を所有した別邸を営み、その中に持仏堂を建て徳大寺（得大寺）と命名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Heian period, Saneyoshi, who were then Minister of the Left, owned a villa at the southwest foot of Mount Kinugasayama, and built therein jibutsudo (the hall for the family&apos;s protective deity) to name it Tokudai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the late Heian period the Saneyoshi, who were then minister of the left, owned a villa at the southwest foot of Mount Kinugasayama, and built therein a jibutsudo (the hall for the family&apos;s protective deity) called Tokudai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the late Heian period, Saneyoshi, who were then minister of the left, owned a villa at the southwest foot of Mount Kinugasayama, and built therein a jibutsudo (the hall for the family&apos;s protective deity) called Tokudai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>the削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これが後に家名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This later became the family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This later became the family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This later became the family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>後にこの別邸は細川勝元に譲られて龍安寺の元となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, this villa was given Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, which became the basis of Ryoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, this villa was given Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, which became the basis of Ryoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, this villa was given to Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, which became the basis of Ryoan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>to　追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>徳大寺公英は美術評論家として有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kimihide TOKUDAIJI is famous as an art critic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimihide TOKUDAIJI is famous as an art critic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimihide TOKUDAIJI is famous as an art critic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお自動車評論家の「徳大寺有恒」はペンネームであり、本項の徳大寺家とは全く関係が無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, &quot;Aritsune TOKUDAIJI&quot; who is a car critic is the pen name and has nothing to do with the House of Tokudaiji of this page.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, &quot;Aritsune TOKUDAIJI,&quot; the pen name of an automotive critic, has nothing to do with the House of Tokudaiji described on this page.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, &apos;Aritsune TOKUDAIJI,&apos; the pen name of an automotive critic, has nothing to do with the House of Tokudaiji described on this page.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Arpeggio(id:9385), Amigomr(id:6515), Y.Sanada(id:36926), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Kanoe(id:17203), Himazin(id:22034), Point136(id:211299), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>