<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>倉橋家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kurahashi Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kurahashi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kurahashi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>倉橋家（くらはしけ）は、阿倍氏土御門庶流の堂上家、家格は、半家 (公家)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kurahashi family was a &quot;Tosho-ke&quot; (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks) of a branch family of Tsuchimikado of the Abe clan and its social standing was hange, kuge of lower rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kurahashi family was a &quot;Tosho-ke&quot; (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks) of a branch family of Tsuchimikado of the Abe clan and its social standing was hange, kuge of lower rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kurahashi family was a &quot;Tosho-ke&quot; (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks) of a branch family of Tsuchimikado of the Abe clan and its social standing was hange, kuge of lower rank.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを消去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>慶長17年（1612）、安倍晴明の末裔である陰陽頭（従三位・非参議）・土御門久脩の次男・泰吉が分家して「倉橋」を称したのにはじまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family started when a decendant of ABE no Seimei, Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Buereau of Divination) (Junior Third Court Rank, non-Councilor) Hisanaga TSUCHIMIKADO&apos;s second son Yasuyoshi created a branch family named &quot;Kurahashi&quot; in 1612.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family started when a decendant of ABE no Seimei, Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Buereau of Divination) (Junior Third Court Rank, non-Councilor) Hisanaga TSUCHIMIKADO&apos;s second son Yasuyoshi created a branch family named &quot;Kurahashi&quot; in 1612.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family started when a decendant of ABE no Seimei, Onmyo no kami (Director of Onmyoryo, or Buereau of Divination) (Junior Third Rank, non-Councilor) Hisanaga TSUCHIMIKADO&apos;s second son Yasuyoshi created a branch family named &apos;Kurahashi&apos; in 1612.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。&quot;Junior Third Court Rank&quot; -&gt; &quot;Junior Third Rank&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>「倉橋」とは遠祖・安倍倉橋麻呂の名に因んだと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said &quot;Kurahashi&quot; that was named after their forefather ABE no Kurahashimaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said &quot;Kurahashi&quot; was named after their forefather ABE no Kurahashimaro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said &apos;Kurahashi&apos; was named after their forefather ABE no Kurahashimaro.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>初代・民部卿・倉橋泰吉以降、代々陰陽道を業とし、江戸時代の石高は、150石であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the first family head, Minbukyo Yasuyoshi KURAHASHI, Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements) was their family business for generations, and they had 150 Goku crop yields in Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the first family head, Minbukyo Yasuyoshi KURAHASHI, Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements) was their family business for generations, and they also had 150 Goku crop yields during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the first family head, Minbukyo (Minister of Popular Affairs) Yasuyoshi KURAHASHI, Onmyodo (way of Yin and Yang; occult divination system based on the Taoist theory of the five elements) was their family business for generations, and they also had 150 koku crop yields during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>民部卿の補足を入れました。統一リストに基づき、150石→150 kokuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>10代当主の治部卿・倉橋泰聡で明治に至り華族に列し子爵に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji Era, the tenth family head was Jibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) Yasutoshi KURAHASHI, and the family was raised to the peerage and viscount.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji Era, the tenth family head was Jibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) Yasutoshi KURAHASHI, and the family was raised to the peer level and viscount.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji Era, the tenth family head was Jibukyo (Minister of the Ministry of Civil Administration) Yasutoshi KURAHASHI, and the family was raised to the peer level and viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>家紋は、土御門家に倣い「蝶」、菩提寺は「真如堂」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest was the &quot;butterfly&quot; followed after the Tsuchimikado family, and the family temple was Shinnyo-do temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest was the &quot;butterfly&quot; following after the Tsuchimikado family, and the family temple was Shinnyo-do temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest was the &apos;butterfly&apos; following after the Tsuchimikado family, and the family temple was Shinnyo-do temple.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>居所は「堺町御門外」とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their residence was in Inzan-cho Nishiyori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their residence was in Inzan-cho Nishiyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their residence was in Sakai-machi Gomongai.</e>
<cmt>堺町御門外の読みを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Seibuabina(id:37532), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>