<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>正親町家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogimachi family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogimachi family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogimachi family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>正親町家（おおぎまちけ）は羽林家の家格を有する公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakayama family was a kuge (court noble) with kakaku (family status) of urinke (the fourth highest family status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nakayama family were kuge (court nobles) with kakaku (family status) of urinke (the fourth highest family status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogimachi family were kuge (court nobles) with kakaku (family status) of urinke (the fourth highest family status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt>Nakayama→Ogimachi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家閑院流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They came under the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They came under the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>文末にピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>洞院家支流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Branch line of the Toin family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were a branch of the Toin family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were a branch of the Toin family.</e>
<cmt>文末にピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本家である洞院家は室町期に断絶したが、清華クラスの家柄であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head family, Toin family, which was discontinued in the Muromachi Period, was a seiga class family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head family, the Toin family, discontinued during the Muromachi Period, was a seiga class family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head family, the Toin family, discontinued during the Muromachi Period, was a seiga class family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は355石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was 355 koku (approx. 64 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was 355 koku (approx. sixty-four cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was 355 koku (approx. sixty-four cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>明治維新後、伯爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, count</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Meiji Restoration, they held the title of count</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, they held the title of count.</e>
<cmt>文末にピリオドMeiji Restoration→the Meiji Restoration</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>太政大臣西園寺公経の孫で、太政大臣洞院公守の二男正親町実明から始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This family began from Saneakira OGIMACHI, who was a grandson of Kintsune SAIONJI, Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), and the second son of Kimimori TOIN, Daijo-daijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This family began from Saneakira OGIMACHI, who was the grandson of Kintsune SAIONJI, Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), and the second son of Kimimori TOIN, Daijo-daijin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This family began from Saneakira OGIMACHI, who was the grandson of Kintsune SAIONJI, Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), and the second son of Kimimori TOIN, Daijo-daijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代元禄時代の正親町町子は、正親町実豊の女で柳沢吉保の側室である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machiko OGIMACHI in the Genroku Era in the Edo Period was a daughter of Sanetoyo OGIMACHI and a concubine of Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Machiko OGIMACHI in the Genroku Era during the Edo Period was the daughter of Sanetoyo OGIMACHI and a concubine of Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Machiko OGIMACHI in the Genroku Era during the Edo Period was the daughter of Sanetoyo OGIMACHI and a concubine of Yoshiyasu YANAGISAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「松蔭日記（東源氏）」を著わした才媛として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was known as a talented woman who wrote &quot;Shoin Nikki (Azuma Genji).&quot;</e>
<cmt>「東源氏」の正しい読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was known as a talented woman who wrote &quot;Shoin Nikki (Azuma Genji).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was known as a talented woman who wrote &quot;Shoin Nikki (Azuma Genji).&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>寛政年間の正親町公明は、尊号一件で中山愛親とともに処分された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinaki OGIMACHI in the Kansei Era was punished together with Naruchika NAKAYAMA for the songo ikken (literally, incident concerning honorific title).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinaki OGIMACHI in the Kansei Era was punished together with Naruchika NAKAYAMA for the songo ikken (literally, incident concerning honorific title).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinaki OGIMACHI in the Kansei Era was punished together with Naruchika NAKAYAMA for the Songo ikken (Songo Incident).</e>
<cmt>尊号一件の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治維新後の明治17年7月8日正親町実正に伯爵の位を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration on July 8, 1884, the peerage of count was conferred on Sanemasa OGIMACHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration on July 8, 1884, the peerage of count was conferred on Sanemasa OGIMACHI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration on July 8, 1884, the peerage of count was conferred on Sanemasa OGIMACHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>実正は、埼玉県知事、侍従長、賞勲局総裁を歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanemasa filled various posts including the Governor of the Saitame Prefecture, Grand Chamberlain and President of Decoration Bureau.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanemasa filled various posts including the Governor of the Saitame Prefecture, Grand Chamberlain, and President of the Decoration Bureau.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanemasa filled various posts including the Governor of Saitama Prefecture, Grand Chamberlain, and President of the Decoration Bureau.</e>
<cmt>the Saitame→Saitama</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Gimbrow(id:65660), こぶまき(id:38278), Point136(id:211299), Kawai(id:5634), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>