<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大宮家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omiya Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omiya Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omiya Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大宮家（おおみやけ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omiya family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omiya family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omiya family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家閑院流の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a kuge (court noble) that belongs to the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omiya family was a kuge (court noble) that belonged to the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omiya family were kuge (court nobles) that belonged to the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>小槻氏姓の地下家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a jigeke (family with the status of non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the Imperial Palace) with the family name of Otsuki (also Ozuki).</e>
<cmt>Ozuki と Otsuki の両方のあります。Otsuki に統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a jigeke (family with the status of non-noble retainers who were not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the Imperial Palace) having the family name of Otsuki (also Ozuki).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were jigeke (lower rank court officials) who used the family name of Otsuki (also Ozuki).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官務家と称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known as a kanmu family (a family whose members were allowed to hold top government posts).</e>
<cmt>官務家，定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was known as a kanmu family (a family whose members were allowed to hold top government posts).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were known as a kanmu family (a family whose members were allowed to hold top government posts).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>大宮家（藤原北家閑院流）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omiya family (the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omiya family (the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omiya family (the Kanin line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>大宮家（おおみやけ）は、日本の氏族（公家）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omiya family is a clan in Japan (kuge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omiya family was a clan in Japan (kuge).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omiya family was a Japanese clan who were kuge.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原北家藤原公季流（閑院流）西園寺家の庶流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a branch family of the Saionji family, which belongs to the Fujiwara no Kimisue line (the Kanin line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a branch family of the Saionji family, which belonged to the Fujiwara no Kimisue line (the Kanin line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a branch family of the Saionji family, which belonged to the FUJIWARA no Kimisue line (the Kanin line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>苗字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>家格は羽林家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its family status is urinke (a family whose members serve as the emperor&apos;s guards, and they are allowed to hold certain high government positions).</e>
<cmt>羽林家，定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its family status was urinke (a family whose members serve as the emperor&apos;s guards, and who were allowed to hold certain high government positions).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They held the rank of Urinke (which entitled them to hold military ranks).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>家紋は左三つ巴（西園寺家と同じ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kamon (family crest) is hidari mitsudomoe (a type of pattern used for family crests) (same as that of the Saionji family).</e>
<cmt>左三つ巴，定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kamon (family crest) was hidari mitsudomoe (a type of pattern used for family crests) (same as that of the Saionji family).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family&apos;s kamon (crest) was hidari mitsudomoe (a counter-clockwise pattern comprising three comma-shaped figures in a circle) (the same as that of the Saionji family).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>季衡（右大臣大宮季衡）は鎌倉時代中期の左大臣西園寺公衡の次男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suehira (Udaijin Suehira OMIYA) was the second son of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) Kinhira SAIONJI during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suehira (Udaijin Suehira OMIYA) was the second son of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) Kinhira SAIONJI during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suehira OMIYA (who served as Udaijin, or Minister of the Right) was the second son of Kinhira SAIONJI, who served as Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) during the mid-Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>季衡は西園寺家から分家して大宮家と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suehira branched out from the Saionji family and name the family the Omiya family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suehira branched out from the Saionji family and name the family the Omiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suehira branched out from the Saionji family, adopting Omiya as his family name.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>季衡の家系は一時期中断した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suehira&apos;s family line once became interrupted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suehira&apos;s family line was interrupted.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suehira&apos;s family line was interrupted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、江戸時代前期に内大臣西園寺公益の次男季光（近衛府大宮季光）が大宮家を再興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, during the early Edo period, the second son of Naidaijin (Minister of the Palace) Kinmasu SAIONJI, Suemitsu (Suemitsu OMIYA of Konoefu (Division of Inner Palace Guards)), revived the Omiya family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during the early Edo period, the second son of Naidaijin (Minister of the Palace) Kinmasu SAIONJI, Suemitsu (Suemitsu OMIYA of Konoefu (Division of Inner Palace Guards)), revived the Omiya family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the early Edo period, however, the Omiya family was revived by Suemitsu OMIYA (who was a member of the konoefu, or Inner Palace Guards), the second son of Kinmasu SAIONJI (who served as Naidaijin, or Minister of the Palace).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>家禄は130石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 130 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 130 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His karoku (hereditary stipend) was 130 koku.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし季光自身は狂疾のため蟄居し、貞享元年（1684年）に没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Suemitsu was confined to his house because he became mentally ill, and he passed away in 1684.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Suemitsu was confined to his house because he became mentally ill, and he passed away in 1684.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suemitsu was confined to his house when he became mentally ill, however, and passed away in 1684.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この家系から公卿が出たのは正三位近衛府大宮昌季（1743年 ‐1804年）以降。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kugyo (court nobles) from this family line came after Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Konoefu Masasue OMIYA (1743-1804).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処大宮昌季は「おおみや　まさすえ」としましたが、読み方不明。大宮盛季は「おおみや　もりすえ」としましたが、読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kugyo (court nobles) from this family line came after Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) Konoefu Masasue OMIYA (1743-1804).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konoefu Masasue OMIYA (1743 - 1804) was the first of this family line to become a kugyo (high-ranking court noble) when he was awarded the rank of Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>江戸時代では大宮盛季（1768年‐1835年）が正二位中納言になったのが最高位だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, Morisue OMIYA (1768 - 1835) became Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Chunagon (Middle Counselor), which was the highest rank ever achieved by the family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, Morisue OMIYA (1768 - 1835) became Shonii (Senior Second Rank) Chunagon (Middle Counselor), which was the highest rank ever achieved by the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Morisue OMIYA (1768 - 1835) held the position of Chunagon (Middle Counselor) and was awarded the rank of Shonii (Senior Second Rank), which was the highest rank ever achieved by any member of the family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>明治時代に華族に列し、明治17年（1884年）大宮以季が子爵になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Meiji period, the family was raised to the peerage, and Mochisue OMIYA became a viscount. in 1884.</e>
<cmt>大宮以季は「おおみや　もちすえ」としましたが、読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, the family was raised to the peerage, and Mochisue OMIYA became a viscount. in 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, the family was raised to the peerage, and Mochisue OMIYA became a viscount in 1884.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>大宮家（小槻氏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omiya family (the Otsuki clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omiya family (the Otsuki clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omiya family (the Otsuki clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>大宮家（おおみやけ）は、朝廷に仕えた官人の家系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omiya family is a family line whose members became government officials and served at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omiya family is a family line whose members became government officials and served at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omiya family is a family line whose members became government officials and served at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>小槻氏の嫡流の地位を壬生家壬生家（小槻姓）と争った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It fought against the Mibu family of the Mibu family (with the family name of Otsuki) over which family should become the main branch of the Otsuki clan.</e>
<cmt>直訳した訳文は少し理解しにくい文章になってます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It fought against the Mibu family of the Mibu family (with the family name of Otsuki) over which family should become the main branch of the Otsuki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It entered into a dispute with the Mibu family about which family should become the main branch of the Otsuki clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>小槻広房を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The patriarch was Hirofusa OTSUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The patriarch was Hirofusa OTSUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The patriarch was Hirofusa OTSUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>長く土御門大宮に邸宅があったことから「大宮」を家号にしたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omiya&apos; became the family name because the family had its mansion in Tsuchimikado Omiya for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family name became known as &quot;Omiya&quot; because the family possessed a mansion in Tsuchimikado Omiya for a long time.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family acquired the name &apos;Omiya&apos; because they possessed a mansion in Tsuchimikado Omiya for a long time.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>小槻氏は中世より太政官の諸記録を司っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Otsuki clan was responsible for record keeping for the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) since the medieval times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Otsuki clan was responsible for record keeping for the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) since the medieval times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Otsuki clan had been responsible for record keeping for the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) since medieval times.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>五位の官務（左大史上首）を世襲したため官務家と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the hereditary succession of the government position at the rank of Goi (Fifth Rank) (Sadaishi Joshu (Head of First Secretary of the Left, or Senior Recorder of the Left)), the family was called the kanmu family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the hereditary succession of the government position at the rank of Goi (Fifth Rank) (Sadaishi Joshu (Head of First Secretary of the Left, or Senior Recorder of the Left)), the family was called the kanmu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the government position of Sadaishi Joshu (Chief First Secretary of the Left, or Senior Recorder of the Left), which held the rank of Goi (Fifth Rank), was hereditary, the family was known as a kanmu family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、平安時代末に小槻隆職が源頼朝の不興を買った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, during the late Heian period, OTSUKI no Takamoto fell from grace with MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during the late Heian period, OTSUKI no Takamoto fell from grace with MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during the late Heian period, OTSUKI no Takamoto fell from favor with MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>兄小槻永業の子である広房が官務に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the government position was given to Hirofusa, the son of his older brother, 小槻永業.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処小槻永業、読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the government position was given to Hirofusa, the son of his older brother, 小槻永業.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, OTSUKI no Takamoto was replaced as Sadaishi Joshu by Hirofusa, the son of Takamoto&apos;s older brother, OTSUKI no Naganari.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その後、隆職が復帰すると官務の地位は広房の子孫（大宮家）と隆職（壬生家壬生家（小槻姓））の子孫のうち、小槻氏の氏長者にある方が官務の地位に就くことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, after Takamoto returned to his job, the government post was given to the descendant of either Hirofusa (the Omiya family) or Takamoto (the Mibu family of the Mibu family (with the family name of Otsuki)) who became the head of the Otsuki clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, after Takamoto returned to his job, the government post was given to the descendant of either Hirofusa (the Omiya family) or Takamoto (the Mibu family of the Mibu family (with the family name of Otsuki)) who became the head of the Otsuki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, after Takamoto was returned to his job, the government post of Sadaishi Joshu was held by whichever descendant of Hirofusa (i.e. the Omiya family) or Takamoto (i.e. the Mibu family) became head of the Otsuki clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>両家の争いは絶えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the two families fought continuously.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the two families fought continuously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dispute between the two families continued, however.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>特に室町時代後期の大宮長興・大宮時元親子と壬生晨照・壬生晴富親子の時期には朝廷や室町幕府を巻き込んだ激しい対立となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the feud between the father-and-son pair, Nagaoki OMIYA and Tokimoto OMIYA, and the father-and-son pair, Asateru MIBU and Harutomi MIBU, was intense enough to involve the Imperial Court and the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処壬生晴富は「みぶ　はるとみ」としましたが、読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the feud between the father-and-son pair, Nagaoki OMIYA and Tokimoto OMIYA, and the father-and-son pair, Asateru MIBU and Harutomi MIBU, was intense enough to involve the Imperial Court and the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the feud between Nagaoki OMIYA and his son Tokimoto OMIYA on the one side, and Asateru MIBU and his son Harutomi MIBU on the other was intense enough to necessitate the involvement of the Imperial Court and the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>大宮長興は同氏で初めて八省卿（治部卿）に任じられるなど、家名再興に尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaoki OMIYA was the first person from the clan to be appointed to hassho-kei (jibukyo (Minister of Civil Administration)), and he made an effort to revive the family name.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagaoki OMIYA was the first person from the clan to be appointed to hassho-kei (jibukyo (Minister of Civil Administration)), and he made an effort to revive the family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagaoki OMIYA&apos;s promotion to the position of jibukyo (Minister of Civil Administration) meant that he was the first person from the clan to be appointed a minister of one of the eight central ministries, and he made a great effort to revive the family name.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし、応仁の乱によって官務の権威の源泉とも言える官文庫とその古文書を喪失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because of the Onin War, he lost his kanbunko (library of the Omiya family) and its ancient documents, which were effectively the source of authority as a government official.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because of the Onin War, he lost his kanbunko (library of the Omiya family) and its ancient documents, which were effectively the source of authority as a government official.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the Onin War, however, he lost the Omiya family library, which contained a number of ancient documents and was effectively the source of his authority as a government official.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>一応は文書を守り通して後に自己の官文庫を再建した壬生晴富と明暗を分ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The result became clear because Harutomi MIBU managed to protect his documents and later rebuilt his own kanbunko (library of the Mibu family).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The result became clear because Harutomi MIBU managed to protect his documents and later rebuilt his own kanbunko (library of the Mibu family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, Harutomi MIBU managed to protect his documents and later rebuilt the Mibu family library.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>長興の没後、先例の蓄積である官文庫の古文書を失った大宮家は官務としての仕事が困難となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the Omiya family lost the ancient documents in their kanbunko, which was an accumulation of works from the past generations, it became difficult for the Omiya family members to work as government officials after Nagaoki&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Omiya family lost the ancient documents in their kanbunko, which was an accumulation of works from the past generations, it became difficult for the Omiya family members to work as government officials after Nagaoki&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Omiya family lost the ancient documents in their kanbunko, which was an accumulation of works from the past generations, it became difficult for the Omiya family members to work as government officials after Nagaoki&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>時元の子・大宮伊治は周防国大内氏を頼って下向する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokimoto&apos;s son, Koreharu OMIYA, left the capital to go to Suo Province in order to seek help from the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokimoto&apos;s son, Koreharu OMIYA, left the capital to go to Suo Province in order to seek help from the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokimoto&apos;s son, Koreharu OMIYA, left the capital to go to Suo Province in order to seek help from the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>伊治の娘は大内義隆の寵愛を受けて後継者である大内義尊を儲けるた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koreharu&apos;s daughter was favored by Yoshitaka OUCHI, and she bore Yoshitaka&apos;s heir, also named Yoshitaka OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処大内義隆と大内義尊はどちらも「おおうち　よしたか」で、漢字が違いますが、訳文ではどちらも Yoshitaka Ouchi す。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koreharu&apos;s daughter was favored by Yoshitaka OUCHI, and she bore Yoshitaka&apos;s heir, also named Yoshitaka OUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koreharu&apos;s daughter was favored by Yoshitaka OUCHI, and she bore him an heir who was also called Yoshitaka (the Japanese kanji used to write his name was different, however).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし、天文 (元号)20年（1551年）に大宮家は大内義隆に対する謀反の兵を挙げた陶隆房によって攻められて滅亡した（大寧寺の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1551, the Ouchi family was attacked and destroyed by Takafusa SUE, who raised an army to rebel against Yoshitaka OUCHI (the Revolt of Taineiji).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1551, the Ouchi family was attacked and destroyed by Takafusa SUE, who raised an army to rebel against Yoshitaka OUCHI (the Revolt of Taineiji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1551, however, the Omiya family was attacked and destroyed by Takafusa SUE, who raised an army in rebellion against Yoshitaka OUCHI (an event known as the Taineiji Incident).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), Point136(id:211299), Tribot(id:186681), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>