<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>坊門家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bomon Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bomon Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bomon Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>坊門家（ぼうもんけ）は、鎌倉時代から室町時代にかけて存在した公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bomon family was an aristocratic family that lived from the Kamakura period into the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bomon family was an aristocratic family that lived from the Kamakura period into the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bomon family was an aristocratic family that lived from the Kamakura period into the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>坊門を名乗る家系はいくつか存在するが、藤原北家の関白藤原道隆の子孫が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While there are several different family lineages that adopted the name &quot;Bomon,&quot; perhaps the most well-known is that of the descendants of the Kanpaku (Chief Advisor) FUJIWARA no Michitaka of the Northern House Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While there are several different family lineages that adopted the name &quot;Bomon,&quot; perhaps the most well-known is that of the descendants of the Kanpaku (Chief Advisor) FUJIWARA no Michitaka of the Northern House Fujiwara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While there are several different family lineages that adopted the name &quot;Bomon,&quot; perhaps the most well-known is that of the descendants of the Kanpaku (Chief Advisor) FUJIWARA no Michitaka of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>the Noethern House Fujiwara →the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>道隆の子の藤原伊周と藤原隆家は叔父藤原道長と対立し、花山天皇に矢を射かけた罪で左遷された（長徳の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two of Michitaka&apos;s sons, FUJIWARA no Korechika and FUJIWARA no Takaie, fell into conflict with their uncle FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and were demoted in disgrace (in what is known as the Chotoku Incident) for the crime of shooting an arrow at Emperor Kazan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two of Michitaka&apos;s sons, FUJIWARA no Korechika and FUJIWARA no Takaie, fell into conflict with their uncle FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and were demoted in disgrace (in what is known as the Chotoku Incident) for the crime of shooting an arrow at Emperor Kazan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two of Michitaka&apos;s sons, FUJIWARA no Korechika and FUJIWARA no Takaie, fell into conflict with their uncle FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and were demoted in disgrace (in what is known as the Chotoku Incident) for the crime of shooting an arrow at Emperor Kazan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後に罪を許され、隆家の子の藤原経輔は正二位大納言まで昇進したが、道隆の弟の道長の子孫が藤原北家の嫡流となり摂政・関白を世襲していったため、道隆の子孫はしばらく不遇の時代を送ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their crime was later pardoned, and Takaie&apos;s son FUJIWARA no Tsunesuke rose as far as the senior second rank at court, holding the position of Dainagon (Chief Counselor), but the lineage of Michitaka&apos;s younger brother Michinaga became the principal heir&apos;s lineage in the Northern House Fujiwara, securing hereditary control over the positions of Sessho (Regent) and Kanpaku (Chief Advisor) and thus sending Michitaka&apos;s descendants into a long age of eclipse and misfortune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their crime was later pardoned, and Takaie&apos;s son FUJIWARA no Tsunesuke rose as far as the senior second rank at court, holding the position of Dainagon (Chief Counselor), but the lineage of Michitaka&apos;s younger brother Michinaga became the principal heir&apos;s lineage in the Northern House Fujiwara, securing hereditary control over the positions of Sessho (Regent) and Kanpaku (Chief Advisor) and thus sending Michitaka&apos;s descendants into a long age of eclipse and misfortune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their crime was later pardoned, and Takaie&apos;s son FUJIWARA no Tsunesuke rose as far as Shonii (Senior Second Rank) at court, holding the position of Dainagon (Chief Counselor), but the lineage of Michitaka&apos;s younger brother Michinaga became the principal heir&apos;s lineage in the Northern House of Fujiwara clan, securing hereditary control over the positions of Sessho (Regent) and Kanpaku (Chief Advisor) and thus sending Michitaka&apos;s descendants into a long age of eclipse and misfortune.</e>
<cmt>”正二位”を修正しました。Northern House Fujiwara→Northern House of Fujiwara clan と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>平安時代の後期になると、経輔の孫の藤原経忠は妻の藤原実子が鳥羽天皇の乳母であったことから院近臣として白河天皇および鳥羽法皇に仕え従二位中納言まで昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in the latter days of the Heian period, FUJIWARA no Jisshi, the wife of Tsunesuke&apos;s grandson FUJIWARA no Tsunetada, was wetnurse to Emperor Toba, which led to Tsunetada serving both Emperor Shirakawa and Cloistered Emperor Toba as an In no kinshin (vassal to the retired emperor), reaching the junior second rank and holding the position of Chunagon (Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in the latter days of the Heian period, FUJIWARA no Jisshi, the wife of Tsunesuke&apos;s grandson FUJIWARA no Tsunetada, was wetnurse to Emperor Toba, which led to Tsunetada serving both Emperor Shirakawa and Cloistered Emperor Toba as an In no kinshin (vassal to the retired emperor), reaching the junior second rank and holding the position of Chunagon (Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in the latter days of the Heian period, FUJIWARA no Jisshi, the wife of Tsunesuke&apos;s grandson FUJIWARA no Tsunetada, was wetnurse to Emperor Toba, which led to Tsunetada serving both Emperor Shirakawa and Cloistered Emperor Toba as an In no kinshin (vassal to the retired emperor), reaching Junii (Junior Second Rank) and holding the position of Chunagon (Middle Counselor).</e>
<cmt>”従二位”を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>経忠の孫の藤原信隆は生前は正三位非参議止まりであったが、安徳天皇が伊勢平氏一門とともに都落ちすると、信隆の娘で高倉天皇の典侍となっていた藤原殖子（七条院）所生の後鳥羽天皇（後鳥羽天皇）が皇位を継承し、後鳥羽天皇の外祖父にあたる信隆は従一位左大臣を追贈された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunetada&apos;s grandson FUJIWARA no Nobutaka was only able to rise during his lifetime as far as senior third rank and was not assigned a court position, but after Emperor Antoku fled the capital along with the Ise branch of the Taira clan, the throne passed to Emperor Gotoba--who had been born of FUJIWARA no Shokushi (whose religious name was Shichijoin), Nobutaka&apos;s daughter and a onetime lady-in-waiting to Emperor Takakura--whereupon Nobutaka, Emperor Gotoba&apos;s maternal grandfather, was posthumously promoted to junior first rank and given the position of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunetada&apos;s grandson FUJIWARA no Nobutaka was only able to rise during his lifetime as far as senior third rank and was not assigned a court position, but after Emperor Antoku fled the capital along with the Ise branch of the Taira clan, the throne passed to Emperor Gotoba--who had been born of FUJIWARA no Shokushi (whose religious name was Shichijoin), Nobutaka&apos;s daughter and a onetime lady-in-waiting to Emperor Takakura--whereupon Nobutaka, Emperor Gotoba&apos;s maternal grandfather, was posthumously promoted to junior first rank and given the position of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunetada&apos;s grandson FUJIWARA no Nobutaka was only able to rise during his lifetime as far as Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and was not assigned a court position, but after Emperor Antoku fled the capital along with the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan), the throne passed to Emperor Gotoba--who had been born of FUJIWARA no Shokushi (whose religious name was Shichijoin), Nobutaka&apos;s daughter and a onetime lady-in-waiting to Emperor Takakura--whereupon Nobutaka, Emperor Gotoba&apos;s maternal grandfather, was posthumously promoted to Juichii (Junior First Rank) and given the position of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left).</e>
<cmt>”正三位”、”従一位”を修正しました。”伊勢平氏”を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>坊門を家号としたのは信隆の子の坊門信清と坊門隆清の代からとされるが、実質的には信隆が坊門家の祖であると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought to be in the time of Nobukiyo BOMON and Takakiyo BOMON, Nobutaka&apos;s sons, that &quot;Bomon&quot; was first used as a family name, but in any case, the substance of the matter is that Nobutaka can be called the founder of the Bomon family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought to be in the time of Nobukiyo BOMON and Takakiyo BOMON, Nobutaka&apos;s sons, that &quot;Bomon&quot; was first used as a family name, but in any case, the substance of the matter is that Nobutaka can be called the founder of the Bomon family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought to be in the time of Nobukiyo BOMON and Takakiyo BOMON, Nobutaka&apos;s sons, that &quot;Bomon&quot; was first used as a family name, but in any case, the substance of the matter is that Nobutaka can be called the founder of the Bomon family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>信隆の子の信清は後鳥羽天皇の叔父にあたり、また信清の娘は鎌倉幕府将軍源実朝の正室となったことから、坊門家は皇室・幕府いずれに対しても大きな影響力を持つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobukiyo, Nobutaka&apos;s son, was Emperor Gotoba&apos;s uncle, and Nobukiyo&apos;s daughter became the legal wife of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, Shogun of the Kamakura bakufu; as a result, the Bomon family came to hold enormous influence over both the imperial house and the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobukiyo, Nobutaka&apos;s son, was Emperor Gotoba&apos;s uncle, and Nobukiyo&apos;s daughter became the legal wife of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, Shogun of the Kamakura bakufu; as a result, the Bomon family came to hold enormous influence over both the imperial house and the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobukiyo, Nobutaka&apos;s son, was the Emperor Gotoba&apos;s uncle, and Nobukiyo&apos;s daughter became the legal wife of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, Shogun of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun); as a result, the Bomon family came to hold enormous influence over both the imperial house and the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>the Emperor と修正しました。カッコ部分を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、建保4年（1216年）に信清が薨去して以降、建保7年（1219年）には将軍源実朝が暗殺され、承久3年（1221年）の承久の変においては信清の子の坊門忠信は後鳥羽上皇ら討幕勢力に与したため流罪に処せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, following Nobukiyo&apos;s death in 1216, the Shogun MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated in 1219, and in the Jokyu War of 1221 (the third year of the Jokyu era) Nobukiyo&apos;s son Tadanobu BOMON sided with Retired Emperor Gotoba and lent his military strength to the effort to strike down the shogunate, leading to his exile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, following Nobukiyo&apos;s death in 1216, the Shogun MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated in 1219, and in the Jokyu War of 1221 (the third year of the Jokyu era) Nobukiyo&apos;s son Tadanobu BOMON sided with Retired Emperor Gotoba and lent his military strength to the effort to strike down the shogunate, leading to his exile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, following Nobukiyo&apos;s death in 1216, the Shogun MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated in 1219, and in the Jokyu War of 1221, Nobukiyo&apos;s son Tadanobu BOMON sided with the Retired Emperor Gotoba and lent his military strength to the effort to strike down the shogunate, leading to his exile.</e>
<cmt>(the third year of the Jokyu era) は必要ないと判断し、削除しました。 the Retired Emperor と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>当時、忠信は大納言の地位にあり、討幕計画に関与した公家の中では最も官位が高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that point in time Tadanobu held the position of Dainagon (Major Counselor), making him the man of the highest official rank of all the noblemen who participated in the plan to strike down the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that point in time Tadanobu held the position of Dainagon (Major Counselor), making him the man of the highest official rank of all the noblemen who participated in the plan to strike down the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that point in time Tadanobu held the position of Dainagon (Major Counselor), making him the man of the highest official rank of all the noblemen who participated in the plan to strike down the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>討幕計画に関与した公家の多くが処刑されており、本来であれば忠信も死罪は免れない状況ではあったが、亡き将軍実朝の義兄にあたることから罪一等を減じて流罪とされたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the noblemen who were involved in the plot to strike down the shogunate were executed, and by all rights Tadanobu could hardly have hoped to escape execution either, but because he was the brother-in-law of the slain Shogun Sanetomo, his crime was reduced from the highest and worst degree and his punishment downgraded to banishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the noblemen who were involved in the plot to strike down the shogunate were executed, and by all rights Tadanobu could hardly have hoped to escape execution either, but because he was the brother-in-law of the slain Shogun Sanetomo, his crime was reduced from the highest and worst degree and his punishment downgraded to banishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the noblemen who were involved in the plot to strike down the shogunate were executed, and by all rights Tadanobu could hardly have hoped to escape execution either, but because he was the brother-in-law of the slain Shogun Sanetomo, his crime was reduced from the highest and worst degree and his punishment downgraded to banishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>以後、鎌倉時代を通して坊門家から公卿が輩出されることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But from that point onwards, for the entire remainder of the Kamakura period the Bomon family never again produced anyone who reached the court nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But from that point onwards, for the entire remainder of the Kamakura period the Bomon family never again produced anyone who reached the court nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But from that point onwards, for the entire remainder of the Kamakura period the Bomon family never again produced anyone who reached the court nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>南北朝時代(日本)になると、信清の子孫の坊門信行が北朝において公卿に列し、隆清の子孫の坊門清忠は後醍醐天皇の側近となり公卿に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once Japan&apos;s Period of Northern and Southern Courts began, however, Nobuyuki BOMON, Nobukiyo&apos;s descendant, was ranked among the nobility at the Northern Court, while Takakiyo&apos;s descendant, Kiyotada BOMON, became a trusted retainer to Emperor Godaigo and was ranked among the nobility of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once Japan&apos;s Period of Northern and Southern Courts began, however, Nobuyuki BOMON, Nobukiyo&apos;s descendant, was ranked among the nobility at the Northern Court, while Takakiyo&apos;s descendant, Kiyotada BOMON, became a trusted retainer to Emperor Godaigo and was ranked among the nobility of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) began, however, Nobuyuki BOMON, Nobukiyo&apos;s descendant, was ranked among the nobility at the Northern Court, while Takakiyo&apos;s descendant, Kiyotada BOMON, became a trusted retainer to the Emperor Godaigo and was ranked among the nobility of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>the Emperor と修正しました。Japan&apos;s Period of Northern and Southern Courts→the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかしいずれの系統も断絶したために後世に家名を伝えることはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet both of these family lines died out, leaving no chance for the Bomon family name to be passed down to later generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet both of these family lines died out, leaving no chance for the Bomon family name to be passed down to later generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet both of these family lines died out, leaving no chance for the Bomon family name to be passed down to later generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、坊門忠信は坊門家庶家の水無瀬信成を養子としたが、信成の子孫からは水無瀬家・七条家・町尻家・桜井家・山井家の5家が堂上家に列し、明治にはいずれも華族となって子爵を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet Tadanobu BOMON did adopt Nobunari MINASE of the Minase branch of the Bomon family; Nobunari&apos;s descendants split into five different Tosho (high nobility) families, the Minase, the Shichijo, the Machijiri, the Sakurai, and the Yamai families, all of which became Kazoku (peers) in the Meiji period, while the head of each family was then given the rank of Viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet Tadanobu BOMON did adopt Nobunari MINASE of the Minase branch of the Bomon family; Nobunari&apos;s descendants split into five different Tosho (high nobility) families, the Minase, the Shichijo, the Machijiri, the Sakurai, and the Yamai families, all of which became Kazoku (peers) in the Meiji period, while the head of each family was then given the rank of Viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet Tadanobu BOMON did adopt Nobunari MINASE of the Minase branch of the Bomon family; Nobunari&apos;s descendants split into five different Tosho (high nobility) families, the Minase, the Shichijo, the Machijiri, the Sakurai, and the Yamai, all of which became Kazoku (peers) in the Meiji period, while the head of each family was then given the rank of Viscount.</e>
<cmt>重複するfamilies を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 まさふゆ(id:232040), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>