<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>一条家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The House of Ichijo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The House of Ichijo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The House of Ichijo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>一条（いちじょう）家は、摂家のひとつで公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house of Ichijo is one of the Sekke (Regent) House and a kuge, court noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house of Ichijo is one of the sekke (regent) houses and a kuge (court nobility).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ichijo Family is one of the sekke (regent) houses and a kuge (court nobility).</e>
<cmt>&quot;house of Ichijo&quot; -&gt; &quot;Ichijo Family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;Overview&quot; -&gt; &quot;Summary&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原氏藤原北家摂関家九条流で、鎌倉時代の公卿である、九条道家三男一条実経を祖とし、道家が創建した一条殿を実経が受け継いで住んだ事が家名の由来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kujo Line of Sekkan (regent and senior regent) House, the House of Fujiwara North; a kugyo, court noble, in the Kamakura period; the original forefather is Sanetsune ICHIJO, the third son of Michiie KUJO; the name of the House comes from the fact that Sanetsune inherited Ichijo Hall that was built by Michiie to live in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kujo line of sekkan (regent and senior regent) houses, the House of Fujiwara North; a kugyo (court noble) during the Kamakura period; the original forefather was Sanetsune ICHIJO, the third son of Michiie KUJO; the name of the house comes from the fact that Sanetsune inherited Ichijo Hall, which had been built by Michiie to live in.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kujo line of sekkan (regent and senior regent) houses, the House of Fujiwara North of the Fujiwara clan, was a kugyo (court noble) during the Kamakura period; the original forefather was Sanetsune ICHIJO, the third son of Michiie KUJO; the name of the house was due to the fact that Sanetsune had inherited Ichijo Hall, which had been built by Michiie as a residence.</e>
<cmt>the Fujiwara clanを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>序列は近衛家に次ぎ、九条家、二条家、鷹司家と同格扱いであった（なお、九条家とは南北朝時代_(日本)に嫡流を巡って相論となったが、後光厳天皇によりいずれも嫡流であるとの綸旨が下された。詳細は九条家の項目を参照のこと）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the ranking, the House of Ichijo was inferior to Konoe Family and equal to Kujo Family, Nijo Family, and Takatsukasa Family (The House of Ichijo was opposed to Kujo Family over the legitimate blood of the family in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), and Emperor Go-Kogen gave the imperial order that both of the family lines should be the legitimate blood of the family. For the details, see the item of Kujo Family.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the ranking, the House of Ichijo was inferior to the Konoe Family and equal to the Kujo, Nijo and Takatsukasa families (the House of Ichijo was opposed to the Kujo Family over the legitimate blood of the family during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), so Emperor Go-Kogen gave the imperial order that both of the family lines should be the legitimate blood of the family. For details, see the item on the Kujo Family.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the ranking, the Ichijo Family was inferior to the Konoe Family but was equal to the Kujo, Nijo and Takatsukasa families (the Ichijo Family was opposed to the Kujo Family over the legitimate blood of the family during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), so the Emperor Go-Kogen gave the imperial order that both family lines should be the legitimate blood of the family. For details, see the item on the Kujo Family).</e>
<cmt>南北朝を the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan)　としました。&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。&quot;House of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～Family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>別称、桃華坊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another name is Tokabo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another name is Tokabo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another name is Tokabo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家紋は一条藤。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crest is Ichijo wisteria.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The crest is the Ichijo wisteria.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The crest is the Ichijo wisteria.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は初め1000石、後に1500石へ加増、幕末は2044石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stipend in the Edo period was 1000 koku at the beginning, raised to 1500 koku later, and 2044 koku at the end of the Edo Shogunate period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stipend during the Edo period was 1000 koku at the beginning, which was later raised to 1500 koku and up to 2044 koku by the end of the Edo shogunate period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stipend during the Edo period was 1000 koku at the beginning, which was later raised to 1500 koku and up to 2044 koku by the end of the Edo shogunate period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>明治維新後、公爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a prince after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was ranked as a prince after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>室町時代の一条兼良は、政治以外に、学問や連歌の文化的活躍も残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanera ICHIJO in the Muromachi period was active not only in the politics but also in the cultural world such as academics and renga, linked verse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanera ICHIJO, during the Muromachi period, was active not only in politics but also in the cultural world such as academics and renga (linked verse).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanera ICHIJO, during the Muromachi period, was active not only in politics but also in the cultural world such as academics and renga (linked verse).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、戦国時代 (日本)には一条教房が所領であった土佐に下向し、分家が戦国大名化し土佐一条氏となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku period; the Warring States period (Japan), Norifusa ICHIJO moved down to Tosa that was his fief, and the branch family became a Sengoku-daimyo, Tosa-Ichijo family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku period (the Warring States period (Japan)), Norifusa ICHIJO moved down to Tosa, which was his fief, and the branch family became a Sengoku-daimyo, Tosa-Ichijo family.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku period (the Warring States period (Japan)), Norifusa ICHIJO moved down to Tosa, which was his fief, and the branch family became a Sengoku-daimyo (warring lord), the Tosa-Ichijo family.</e>
<cmt>戦国大名に(warring lord)を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代初期、関白一条昭良の次男醍醐冬基が醍醐家（清華家の家格）を創立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, Fuyumoto DAIGO, the second son of senior regent Akiyoshi ICHIJO established the House of DAIGO (the House of Seigake status).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early in the Edo period, Fuyumoto DAIGO, the second son of the senior regent Akiyoshi ICHIJO, established the House of DAIGO (with House of Seigake status).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early in the Edo period, Fuyumoto DAIGO, the second son of the senior regent Akiyoshi ICHIJO, established the House of Daigo (of the status of Seigake (a status of court nobility)).</e>
<cmt>Daigoとしました。清華家の説明を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>幕末期の当主・一条忠香の三女・美子が明治天皇の皇后となった（昭憲皇太后）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haruko, the third daughter of Tadaka ICHIJO who was the family head at the end period of Edo Shogunate became the empress of Emperor Meiji (Empress Shoken).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haruko, the third daughter of Tadaka ICHIJO, who was the family head at the end of the Edo shogunate period, became the empress of Emperor Meiji (Empress Shoken).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haruko, the third daughter of Tadaka ICHIJO, who was the family head at the end of the Edo shogunate period, became the empress of Emperor Meiji (Empress Shoken).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>主な人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main figures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main figures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main figures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>一条実経(1223年－1284年)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanetsune ICHIJO (1223 to 1284)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanetsune ICHIJO (1223 to 1284)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanetsune ICHIJO (1223 to 1284)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>一条経嗣(1358年－1418年)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunetsugu ICHIJO (1358 to 1418)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunetsugu ICHIJO (1358 to 1418)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunetsugu ICHIJO (1358 to 1418)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>一条兼良(1402年－1481年)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanera ICHIJO (1402 to 1481)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanera ICHIJO (1402 to 1481)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanera ICHIJO (1402 to 1481)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>一条教房(1423年－1480年)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norifusa ICHIJO (1423 to 1480)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norifusa ICHIJO (1423 to 1480)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norifusa ICHIJO (1423 to 1480)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一条冬良(1465年－1514年)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuyuyoshi ICHIJO (1465 to 1514)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuyuyoshi ICHIJO (1465 to 1514)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuyuyoshi ICHIJO (1465 to 1514)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>一条房家(1475年－1539年)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fusaie ICHIJO (1475 to 1539)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fusaie ICHIJO (1475 to 1539)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusaie ICHIJO (1475 to 1539)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>一条昭良(1605年－1672年)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akiyoshi ICHIJO (1605 to 1672)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akiyoshi ICHIJO (1605 to 1672)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akiyoshi ICHIJO (1605 to 1672)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Nnh(id:474), Cprobot(id:97843), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), Iwaro(id:60082), Himazin(id:22034), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Snap55(id:89773), Poohpooh817(id:157250), Kaba(id:17904), 博物学博士(id:33603), 伏儀(id:142093), けんち(id:5147), Safkan(id:423), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>