<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小早川氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kobayakawa Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kobayakawa Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kobayakawa Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小早川氏（こばやかわうじ／こばやかわし）は、日本の氏族の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kobayakawa clan is a shizoku (clan) in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kobayakawa clan is a shizoku (clan) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kobayakawa clan is a shizoku (clan) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>著名な一族は、相模国土肥郷を発祥とする、中世から近世にかけての武家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of this famous family was in Dohigo, Sagami Province and they were a samurai family of the Kamakura to Meiji periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of this famous family was in Dohigo, Sagami Province and they were a samurai family from the medieval to the early modern period.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of this famous family was in Dohigo, Sagami Province and they were a samurai family from the medieval to the early modern period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本宗家は江戸時代初期に断絶したが、明治時代に至り、毛利元徳の子・四郎が小早川家を再興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head family ended in the early Edo period but in the Meiji period, Shiro, the fourth son of Motonori MORI restored the Kobayakawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head family ended in the early Edo period but in the Meiji period, Shiro, the fourth son of Motonori MORI restored the Kobayakawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head family ended in the early Edo period but in the Meiji period, Shiro, the fourth son of Motonori MORI restored the Kobayakawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>発祥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>相模国を本拠地とする平氏土肥氏の分枝で、鎌倉時代初期、源頼朝に仕えた土肥実平の子・小早川遠平が土肥郷の北部・小早川（神奈川県小田原市付近）に拠って小早川の名字を称したのが始まりと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan branched off from the Heishi-Dohi clan and it is said to have started when Tohira KOBAYAKAWA, the son of Sanehira DOI who was serving Yoritomo MINAMOTO, named himself as Kobayakawa from Kobayakawa of the north of the Dohi-go village (around Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>http://kankodori.net/japaneseculture/buildings/053/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan branched off from the Heishi-Dohi clan and it is said to have started when Tohira KOBAYAKAWA, the son of Sanehira DOI, who was serving Yoritomo MINAMOTO, named himself as Kobayakawa from Kobayakawa of the north of the Dohi-go village (around Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>固有名詞が先行詞のため、非制限用法に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan branched off from the Heishi-Dohi clan and it is said to have started when Tohira KOBAYAKAWA, the son of Sanehira DOI, who was serving Yoritomo MINAMOTO, named himself as Kobayakawa from Kobayakawa of the north of the Dohi-go village (around Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>遠平は平氏討伐の恩賞として平氏家人沼田氏の旧領であった安芸国沼田荘（ぬたのしょう、現在の広島県三原市本郷町付近）の地頭職を拝領し、これを譲られた養子・小早川景平（実父は平賀義信であったとされる。）が、安芸国に移住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tohira was given the position of Jitoshiki (manager and lord of a private estate) when he received the Nutanosho estate in Aki Province (current Mihara City, Hiroshima Prefecture), the former territory of the Nuta clan who were the housemen of the Taira clan, as a reward; and the adopted child Kagehira KOBAYAKAWA (whose real father was believed to be Yoshinobu HIRAGA) moved to the Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>「沼田氏」の読みですが、「沼田氏、安芸」で検索するとその地域ではほとんどが「ぬまた」ではなく「ぬた」と呼ばれているようですので、ここでも「ぬた」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tohira was given the position of Jitoshiki (manager and lord of a private estate) when he received the Nutanosho estate in Aki Province (current Mihara City, Hiroshima Prefecture), the former territory of the Nuta clan who were the housemen of the Taira clan, as a reward; and the adopted child Kagehira KOBAYAKAWA (whose biological father was believed to be Yoshinobu HIRAGA) moved to the Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。real father→biological father</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tohira was given the position of Jitoshiki (manager and lord of a private estate) when he received the Nutanosho estate in Aki Province (current Mihara City, Hiroshima Prefecture), the former territory of the Nuta clan who were the housemen of the Taira clan, as a reward; and the adopted child Kagehira KOBAYAKAWA (whose biological father was believed to be Yoshinobu HIRAGA) moved to the Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1206年（建永元年）、景平は、長男小早川茂平に沼田本荘を与え、次男小早川季平には沼田新庄を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1206, Kagehira gave the Nuta Honjo to his eldest son Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA and Nuta Shinjo to his second son Suehira KOBAYAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>「小早川季平」は読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1206, Kagehira gave the Nuta Honjo to his eldest son Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA and Nuta Shinjo to his second son Suehira KOBAYAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1206, Kagehira gave the Nuta Honjo to his eldest son Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA and Nuta Shinjo to his second son Suehira KOBAYAKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、小早川茂平は承久の乱で戦功をあげ、同国の都宇荘・竹原荘（つうのしょう・たけはらのしょう　現在の広島県竹原市周辺）の地頭職を加えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA played a great role in the Jokyu War and was given another position of Jitoshiki at estates of Tsuunosho and Takeharanosho in the same province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA played a great role in the Jokyu War and was given another position of Jitoshiki at estates of Tsuunosho and Takeharanosho in the same province (around Takehara City, Hiroshima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを追加しました。「(･･･現在の広島県竹原市周辺)」＝(around Takehara City, Hiroshima Prefecture)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA played a great role in the Jokyu War and was given another position of Jitoshiki at estates of Tsuunosho and Takeharanosho in the same province (around Takehara City, Hiroshima Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沼田小早川氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nuta-Kobayakawa Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nuta-Kobayakawa Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nuta-Kobayakawa Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>小早川茂平の三男・ 小早川雅平が沼田本荘などを与えられ、高山城 (安芸国)を本拠としたのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan started when Masahira KOBAYAKAWA, the third son of Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA, settled in the Takayama-jo Castle (Aki Province) after receiving the estate of Nuta Honjo, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan started when Masahira KOBAYAKAWA, the third son of Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA, settled in the Takayama-jo Castle (Aki Province) after receiving the estate of Nuta Honjo, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan started when Masahira KOBAYAKAWA, the third son of Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA, settled in the Takayama-jo Castle (Aki Province) after receiving the estate of Nuta Honjo, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>小早川氏嫡流の一族で、本家筋にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This clan is the family of the main branch of the Kobayakawa clan and the lineage of the head family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This clan is the family of the main branch of the Kobayakawa clan and the lineage of the head family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This clan is the family of the main branch of the Kobayakawa clan and the lineage of the head family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>元弘の乱では小早川朝平は鎌倉方として六波羅探題に味方し付き従ったため、建武政権によって沼田本荘を没収されるが、竹原小早川家のとりなしなどにより、旧領を安堵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Genko War, Tomohira KOBAYAKAWA was on the side of the Rokuhara Tandai (the office of shogunal deputy in Kyoto placed by the Kamakura shogunate) and fought for them, so the Kenmu Government took the Nuta Honjo but with the mediation of the Takehara-Kobayakawa clan, the estate was guaranteed by the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Genko War, Tomohira KOBAYAKAWA was on the side of the Rokuhara Tandai (the office of shogunal deputy in Kyoto placed by the Kamakura shogunate) and fought for them, so the Kenmu Government took the Nuta Honjo but with the mediation of the Takehara-Kobayakawa clan, the estate was guaranteed by the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Genko War, Tomohira KOBAYAKAWA was on the side of the Rokuhara Tandai (the office of shogunal deputy in Kyoto placed by the Kamakura shogunate) and fought for them, so the Kenmu Government took the Nuta Honjo but with the mediation of the Takehara-Kobayakawa clan, the estate was guaranteed by the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、小早川宣平、小早川貞平、小早川春平　の三代の間に芸予諸島に進出し、小早川水軍の基礎を築く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through three generations of Nobuhira KOBAYAKAWA, Sadahira KOBAYAKAWA and Haruhira KOBAYAKAWA, the clan advanced to the Geiyo Islands and formed the basis for the Kobayakawa Navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through three generations of Nobuhira KOBAYAKAWA, Sadahira KOBAYAKAWA and Haruhira KOBAYAKAWA, the clan advanced to the Geiyo Islands and formed the basis for the Kobayakawa Navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through three generations of Nobuhira KOBAYAKAWA, Sadahira KOBAYAKAWA and Haruhira KOBAYAKAWA, the clan advanced to the Geiyo Islands and formed the basis for the Kobayakawa Navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>竹原小早川氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takehara-Kobayakawa Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takehara-Kobayakawa Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takehara-Kobayakawa Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>小早川茂平が、四男・小早川政景に、承久の乱に得た都宇・竹原荘、沼田荘梨子羽郷の一部を分与し、木村城を本拠としたのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan started when Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA gave his fourth son Masakage KOBAYAKAWA a part of the estates of the Tsuunosho and Takeharanosho which he received after the Jokyu War and Nutanosho Nashi-go village and settled in the Kimura-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>「木村城を本拠とした」のが茂平なのか政景なのか不明です。また、「分与」したのが「都宇・竹原荘全部と沼田荘梨子羽郷の一部」なのか「都宇・竹原荘の一部と沼田荘梨子羽郷の一部」なのかも不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan started when Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA gave his fourth son Masakage KOBAYAKAWA a part of the estates of the Tsuunosho and Takeharanosho which he received after the Jokyu War and Nutanosho Nashi-go village, and Masakage settled in the Kimura-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>「木村城を本拠とした」のは茂平ではなく政景のようですので、表現を修正しました。http://www.k3.dion.ne.jp/~tnk/01siro/kimura/kimura.html「分与」に関しては確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan started when Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA gave his fourth son Masakage KOBAYAKAWA a part of the estates of the Tsuunosho and Takeharanosho which he received after the Jokyu War and Nutanosho Nashi-go village, and Masakage settled in the Kimura-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この竹原小早川家は小早川氏の分家筋にあたるが、元弘の乱以降、足利高氏の下で戦い、室町幕府成立に貢献したこともあり、徐々に勢力を拡大し、室町時代中期には本家・沼田小早川家と拮抗するまでに至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Takehara-Kobayakawa clan is a branch of the Kobayakawa clan but since the Genko War, they fought under Takauji ASHIKAGA and contributed to the establishment of the Muromachi Bakufu (Shogunate); they gradually increased their power and by the mid-Muromachi period, they were competing against the Nuta-Kobayakawa clan, the head family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Takehara-Kobayakawa clan was a branch of the Kobayakawa clan but since the Genko War, they fought under Takauji ASHIKAGA and contributed to the establishment of the Muromachi Bakufu (Shogunate); they gradually increased their power and by the mid-Muromachi period, they were competing against the Nuta-Kobayakawa clan, the head family.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。is→was</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Takehara-Kobayakawa clan was a branch of the Kobayakawa clan but since the Genko War, they fought under Takauji ASHIKAGA and contributed to the establishment of the Muromachi Bakufu (Shogunate); they gradually increased their power and by the mid-Muromachi period, they were competing against the Nuta-Kobayakawa clan, the head family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>中世以降の小早川氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kobayakawa Clan in the Kamakura and Muromachi Periods and after</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kobayakawa Clan after the medieval period</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kobayakawa Clan after the medieval period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>勢力の衰退と沼田・竹原両小早川の統合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decline of power and Integration of the Nuta and Takehara Kobayakawa Clans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decline of power and Integration of the Nuta and Takehara Kobayakawa Clans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decline of power and Integration of the Nuta and Takehara Kobayakawa Clans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)に入ると大内氏傘下の国人領主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period (period of warring states), the clan became Kokujin Ryoshu (local samurai lord) under the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku Period (period of warring states), the clan became Kokujin Ryoshu (local samurai lord) under the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period (period of warring states), the clan became Kokujin Ryoshu (local samurai lord) under the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この頃、竹原・沼田両家で当主の早世が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In both Takehara and Nuta families, the heads died young one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In both Takehara and Nuta families, the heads died young one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In both Takehara and Nuta families, the heads died young one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1543年には竹原家の小早川興景が子を残さずに没したため、1544年に毛利氏出身の興景夫人の従弟にあたる小早川隆景（毛利元就の三男）が養子に迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1543, Okikage KOBAYAKAWA of the Takehara family died without producing children, Takakage KOBAYAKAWA (the third son of Motonari MORI), a cousin of Okigage&apos;s wife who was originally from the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1543, Okikage KOBAYAKAWA of the Takehara family died without producing children, Takakage KOBAYAKAWA (the third son of Motonari MORI), a cousin of Okigage&apos;s wife who was originally from the Mori clan, was adopted into the family.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを追加しました。「養子に迎えられた。」＝was adopted into the family.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1543, Okikage KOBAYAKAWA of the Takehara family died without producing children, Takakage KOBAYAKAWA (the third son of Motonari MORI), a cousin of Okigage&apos;s wife who was originally from the Mori clan, was adopted into the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>一方の沼田家でも、大内氏と尼子氏の影響下で活動しているが、1539年（天文8年）には、尼子方に内通しようと画策し、逆に大内氏によって居城の高山城 (安芸国)を占拠され、城番を置かれるという事態に陥る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Nuta family were living under the influence of the Ouchi and Amago clans but when they were planning to hold secret communication with the Amago clan, their residence of the Takagi-jo Castle (Aki Province) ended up with being occupied by the Ouchi clan and a guard was placed over them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Nuta family were living under the influence of the Ouchi and Amago clans but when they were planning to hold secret communication with the Amago clan, their residence of the Takayama-jo Castle (Aki Province) ended up with being occupied by the Ouchi clan and a guard was placed over them.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。Takagi-jo Castle→Takayama-jo Castle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Nuta family were living under the influence of the Ouchi and Amago clans but when they were planning to hold secret communication with the Amago clan, their residence of the Takayama-jo Castle (Aki Province) ended up with being occupied by the Ouchi clan and a guard was placed over them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>当主の小早川正平も軟禁状態に置かれるが、後に赦された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family head Masahira KOBAYAKAWA was put under loose house arrest but was released later on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family head Masahira KOBAYAKAWA was put under loose house arrest but was released later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family head Masahira KOBAYAKAWA was put under loose house arrest but was released later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>1543年（天文12年）には、小早川正平が大敗に終わった大内義隆による出雲遠征に従軍して21歳の若さで戦死し、幼い嫡子小早川繁平が後を継いだものの、繁平は幼くして失明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1543, Masahira KOBAYAKAWA served in the expedition to Izumo by Yoshitaka OUCHI but was killed at the young age of 21 and his legitimate son Shigehita KOBAYAKAWA took over but Shigehira became blind at a young age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1543, Masahira KOBAYAKAWA served in the expedition to Izumo by Yoshitaka OUCHI but was killed at the young age of 21 and his legitimate son Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA took over but Shigehira became blind at a young age.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。Shigehita→Shigehira</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1543, Masahira KOBAYAKAWA served in the expedition to Izumo by Yoshitaka OUCHI but was killed at the young age of 21 and his legitimate son Shigehira KOBAYAKAWA took over but Shigehira became blind at a young age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>大内家と毛利家の圧力、また強力な後ろ盾を望む重臣の要望により、後見役の重臣・田坂全慶らは殺害されて、繁平は出家させられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the wishes of the senior vassals who were after power and backed up by the Ouchi and Mori families, Zenkei TASAKA and other guardian vassals were killed and Shigehira was sent away to be a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the wishes of the senior vassals who were after power and backed up by the Ouchi and Mori families, Zenkei TASAKA and other guardian vassals were killed and Shigehira was sent away to be a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the wishes of the senior vassals who were after power and backed up by the Ouchi and Mori families, Zenkei TASAKA and other guardian vassals were killed and Shigehira was sent away to be a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>その後、竹原家の隆景が繁平の妹と結婚して沼田家を継ぎ、両小早川家は再統一されたが、それと同時に桓武平氏流小早川本家の血筋は途絶えることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage of the Takehara family married Shigehira&apos;s sister and inherited the Nuta family and both Kobayakawa families were joined together again but at the same time, the genealogy of the head family of the Kanmu-Heishi-Kobayakawa came to an end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage of the Takehara family married Shigehira&apos;s sister and inherited the Nuta family and both Kobayakawa families were joined together again but at the same time, the genealogy of the head family of the Kanmu-Heishi-Kobayakawa came to an end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage of the Takehara family married Shigehira&apos;s sister and inherited the Nuta family and both Kobayakawa families were joined together again but at the same time, the genealogy of the head family of the Kanmu-Heishi-Kobayakawa came to an end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これ以降は毛利一門に組み込まれ、毛利家から多くの家臣が小早川家に送り込まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the clan was integrated with the Mori family and many vassals of the Mori family were sent to the Kobayakawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the clan was integrated with the Mori family and many vassals of the Mori family were sent to the Kobayakawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the clan was integrated with the Mori family and many vassals of the Mori family were sent to the Kobayakawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>名将・小早川隆景の登場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Rise of the Great Commander Takakage KOBAYAKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rise of the Great Commander Takakage KOBAYAKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rise of the Great Commander Takakage KOBAYAKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>隆景は兄の吉川元春とともに毛利家を支えて「両川」と呼ばれ（毛利両川体制）、主に山陽地方の経略を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage supported the Mori family with his brother Motoharu KIKKAWA and he was called &apos;Ryosen&apos; (Mori-Ryosen system) and was in charge of the conquest of mainly the Sanyo region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage supported the Mori family with his brother Motoharu KIKKAWA and he was called &apos;Ryosen&apos; (Mori-Ryosen system) and was in charge of the conquest of mainly the Sanyo region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage supported the Mori family with his brother Motoharu KIKKAWA and he was called &apos;Ryosen&apos; (Mori-Ryosen system) and was in charge of the conquest of mainly the Sanyo region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>本能寺の変後、賤ヶ岳の戦いで豊臣秀吉が織田信長の後継者としての地位を確立すると、隆景は進んで毛利家を羽柴秀吉の天下統一事業に参加させ、には四国征伐の功賞として伊予国一国を与えられて独立した大名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Honnoji Incident, when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI established his status as the successor of Nobunaga ODA at the Battle of Shizugatake, Takakage willingly got the Mori family in on Hideyoshi HASHIBA&apos;s task of unification of the whole country; he was given a whole Iyo Province after the Conquest of Shikoku and became an independent daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Honnoji Incident, when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI established his status as the successor of Nobunaga ODA at the Battle of Shizugatake, Takakage willingly got the Mori family in on Hideyoshi HASHIBA&apos;s task of unification of the whole country; in 1585, he was given a whole Iyo Province after the Conquest of Shikoku and became an independent daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>原文の「･･･に参加させ、には四国征伐の功賞として･･･」の箇所ですが、wikipediaの記事を確認すると、「･･･に参加させ、1585年（天正13年）には四国征伐の功賞として･･･」となっており、本来、こちらが正しいと思われます。訳文に西暦を付け加えておきます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Honnoji Incident, when Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI established his status as the successor of Nobunaga ODA at the Battle of Shizugatake, Takakage willingly got the Mori family in on Hideyoshi HASHIBA&apos;s task of unification of the whole country; in 1585, he was given a whole Iyo Province after the Conquest of Shikoku and became an independent daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1587年（天正15年）には九州征伐により筑前国名島に35万石に転じ、豊臣政権下では五大老にまでなるが、1595年（文禄4年）に隠居し、1597年（慶長2年）に没する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1587, he received Najima, Chikuzen Province after the Conquest of Kyushu and his land become 350,000 koku; he became a Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) under the Toyotomi government but retired in 1595 and died in 1597.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">n 1587, he received Najima, Chikuzen Province after the Conquest of Kyushu and his land became 350,000 koku; he became a Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) under the Toyotomi government but retired in 1595 and died in 1597.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。become→became</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">n 1587, he received Najima, Chikuzen Province after the Conquest of Kyushu and his land became 350,000 koku; he became a Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) under the Toyotomi government but retired in 1595 and died in 1597.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>豊臣・徳川政権下の小早川氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kobayakawa Clan under the Toyotomi &amp; Tokugawa Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kobayakawa Clan under the Toyotomi &amp; Tokugawa Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kobayakawa Clan under the Toyotomi &amp; Tokugawa Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>隆景には子供がいなかったため、家督は豊臣秀吉の甥・小早川秀秋が養子として継ぎ、隆景の弟で養子であった毛利秀包は廃嫡され別家を立てた（のち毛利に改姓）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Takakage had no children, the family estate was inherited by an adopted son Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA who was a nephew of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Hidekane MORI, Takakage&apos;s brother, who also was adopted, was cut off and started a branch family (later on changed his family name to Mori).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Takakage had no children, the family estate was inherited by an adopted son Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA, who was a nephew of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and Hidekane MORI, Takakage&apos;s brother, who was also adopted, was cut off and started a branch family (later on changed his family name to Mori).</e>
<cmt>固有名詞が先行詞のため、非制限用法に修正しました。副詞の位置を修正しました。who also was adopted→who was also adopted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Takakage had no children, the family estate was inherited by an adopted son Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA, who was a nephew of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and Hidekane MORI, Takakage&apos;s brother, who was also adopted, was cut off and started a branch family (later on changed his family name to Mori).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この時点をもって、小早川氏は大江氏流毛利氏から豊臣氏に移ったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, the Kobayakawa clan was moved from the Oe-Mori clan to the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, the Kobayakawa clan was moved from the Oe-Mori clan to the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, the Kobayakawa clan was moved from the Oe-Mori clan to the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>さらに隆景の死後、毛利家から小早川家に送り込まれた家臣、及び小早川家一門衆・譜代家臣の大半は毛利家に引き揚げており、これ以降の小早川本家は毛利一門ではなく、豊臣一門といえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Takakage&apos;s death, most of the vassals who were sent from the Mori family, clansmen of the Kobayakawa family and heredity vassals moved to the Mori family, so the head family of Kobayakawa after that was not a Mori family but a Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Takakage&apos;s death, most of the vassals who were sent from the Mori family, clansmen of the Kobayakawa family and heredity vassals moved to the Mori family, so the head family of Kobayakawa after that was not a Mori family but a Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Takakage&apos;s death, most of the vassals who were sent from the Mori family, clansmen of the Kobayakawa family and heredity vassals moved to the Mori family, so the head family of Kobayakawa after that was not a Mori family but a Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>小早川秀秋は関ヶ原の戦いでの功績により、備前国51万石に加増移封されたが、1602年（慶長7年）に嗣子なくして病没し、小早川家は名実ともに断絶したというのが定説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA changed the territory to the Bizen Province of 510,000 koku with additional properties but died from an illness in 1602 without an heir, so it is believed that the Kobayakawa clan ended both in name and reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA changed the territory to the Bizen Province of 510,000 koku with additional properties but died from an illness in 1602 without an heir, so it is believed that the Kobayakawa clan ended both in name and reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA changed the territory to the Bizen Province of 510,000 koku with additional properties but died from an illness in 1602 without an heir, so it is believed that the Kobayakawa clan ended both in name and reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ただし、2007年10月、秀秋には側室所生の子土肥秀行がおり、足守木下家に仕えて存続したとする家伝が、隆景像とともに子孫である足守藩士の家から発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in October 2007, ancestral records was found together with a statue of Takakage from a house of his descendant samurai of the domain of Ashimori; and according to the records, Hideaki had a son called Hideyuki DOI with a concubine and Hideyuki&apos;s descendants were serving for Ashimori-Kinoshita clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in October 2007, ancestral records was found together with a statue of Takakage from a house of his descendant samurai of the domain of Ashimori; and according to the records, Hideaki had a son called Hideyuki DOI with a concubine and Hideyuki&apos;s descendants were serving for Ashimori-Kinoshita clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in October 2007, ancestral records was found together with a statue of Takakage from a house of his descendant samurai of the domain of Ashimori; and according to the records, Hideaki had a son called Hideyuki DOI with a concubine and Hideyuki&apos;s descendants were serving for Ashimori-Kinoshita clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この家系が他の秀秋の兄弟による跡目の継承によって復活したものでない秀秋の血統であるとすると、豊臣姓小早川（土肥）氏は現在も存続していることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this family line was not recreated by the heirs of Hideaki&apos;s brothers but Hideaki&apos;s own blood line, the Toyotomi-Kobayakawa clan should still be remaining.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this family line was not recreated by the heirs of Hideaki&apos;s brothers but Hideaki&apos;s own blood line, the Toyotomi-Kobayakawa clan should still be remaining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this family line was not recreated by the heirs of Hideaki&apos;s brothers but Hideaki&apos;s own blood line, the Toyotomi-Kobayakawa clan should still be remaining.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>明治期以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Period and after</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Period</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>明治時代に至り、公爵毛利元徳の子・四郎が小早川家を再興し、華族に列して男爵の爵位を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the son of Prince Motonori MORI, Shiro restored the Kobayakawa family and was in the peerage to become a Baron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, the son of Prince Motonori MORI, Shiro restored the Kobayakawa family and was in the peerage to become a Baron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the son of Prince Motonori MORI, Shiro restored the Kobayakawa family and was in the peerage to become a Baron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>（近世以降）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(After the early-modern times)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(After the early-modern times)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(After the early-modern times)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>小早川隆景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>小早川秀秋（豊臣秀吉の正室高台院の甥）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiseaki KOBAYAKAWA (a nephew of Kodaiin, the lawful wife of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA (a nephew of Kodaiin, the lawful wife of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。Hiseaki→Hideaki</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA (a nephew of Kodaiin, the lawful wife of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>断絶（江戸時代初頭より明治時代まで）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extinction (from the early Edo period to the Meiji period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extinction (from the early Edo period to the Meiji period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extinction (from the early Edo period to the Meiji period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>小早川三郎（毛利元徳の子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saburo KOBAYAKAWA (son of Motonori MORI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saburo KOBAYAKAWA (son of Motonori MORI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saburo KOBAYAKAWA (son of Motonori MORI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>小早川四郎（毛利元徳の子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiro KOBAYAKAWA (son of Motonori MORI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiro KOBAYAKAWA (son of Motonori MORI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiro KOBAYAKAWA (son of Motonori MORI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>小早川元治（毛利元徳の孫で毛利元昭の子）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoharu KOBAYAKAWA (a grandson of Motonori MORI and son of Motoakira MORI)</e>
<cmt>「小早川元治」は読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoharu KOBAYAKAWA (a grandson of Motonori MORI and son of Motoakira MORI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoharu KOBAYAKAWA (a grandson of Motonori MORI and son of Motoakira MORI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こまくさ(id:42220), Straysheep(id:42448), やりたこ(id:113528), Ayakarennjyaku(id:250660), Aotake(id:34929), Iwaro(id:60082), 1600915mk(id:242476), Rusk(id:9895), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), トホホ川(id:50502), Safkan(id:423), Yosemite(id:5808), ヤトゥヒン(id:26570), Louperibot(id:128971), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>