<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五辻家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Itsutsuji Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Itsutsuji Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Itsutsuji Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>五辻家（いつつじけ）は宇多源氏の流れを引く源氏堂上源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Itsutsuji family is a member of Genji Tosho Genji (the Minamoto clan members who are court nobles above a certain rank), who is a descendant of Uda-Genji (the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Itsutsuji family is a member of Genji Tosho Genji (the Minamoto clan members who are court nobles above a certain rank), descendants of Uda-Genji (the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Itsutsuji family is a member of Genji Tosho Genji (Minamoto clan members who are court nobles above a certain rank), descendants of Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>用語共有に沿って、(the Minamoto clan → (Minamoto clan　に修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>左大臣・源雅信の子源時方（ときまさ）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its patriarch was MINAMOTO no Tokimasa, a son of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) MINAMOTO no Masanobu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its patriarch was MINAMOTO no Tokimasa, the son of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) MINAMOTO no Masanobu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its patriarch was MINAMOTO no Tokimasa, the son of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) MINAMOTO no Masanobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>五辻仲兼（生没年不詳）以降に五辻家を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nakakane ITSUTSUJI (year of birth and death unknown) the family name was changed to the Itsutsuji family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nakakane ITSUTSUJI (year of birth and death unknown) the family name was changed to the Itsutsuji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nakakane ITSUTSUJI (year of birth and death unknown) the family name was changed to the Itsutsuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>五辻仲兼以降は蔵人所や北面の武士を務める地下人だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakakane ITSUTSUJI was a jigenin (low ranking court noble) who served at Kurododokoro (Chamberlain&apos;s Office) and as a member of the Imperial Palace Guards of the north side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakakane ITSUTSUJI was a jigenin (low ranking court noble) who served at Kurododokoro (Chamberlain&apos;s Office) and as a member of the Imperial Palace Guards of the north side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakakane ITSUTSUJI was a jigenin (a lower rank of ancient Japanese nobility) who served at Kurododokoro (Chamberlain&apos;s Office) and Hokumen no bushi (the Imperial Palace Guards for the north side).</e>
<cmt>用語共有に沿って、地下人、北面の武士の表現を修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、1538年に五辻諸仲（従三位・治部省）（1487年～1540年）が従三位に叙せられてからは、堂上家に加わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after Moronaka ITSUTSUJI (Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank) and Jibusho (the Ministry of Civil Administration)) (1487 - 1540) was given the rank of Jusammi in 1538, the family was added as a toshoke family (hereditary lineage of court nobles above a certain rank).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Moronaka ITSUTSUJI (Jusanmi - Junior Third Rank) and Jibusho (the Ministry of Civil Administration) (1487 - 1540) was given the rank of Jusammi in 1538, the family was added as a toshoke family (hereditary lineage of court nobles above a certain rank).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Moronaka ITSUTSUJI (Jusanmi - Junior Third Rank) and Jibusho (the Ministry of Civil Administration) (1487 - 1540) was given the rank of Jusanmi in 1538, the family was added as a toshoke family (hereditary lineage of court nobles above a certain rank).</e>
<cmt>Jusammi →Jusanmi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>家格は半家 (公家)、極官は従二位・非参議。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family status is hanke (family of lower ranking court nobles) (kuge (court noble)), and the highest court positions appointed were Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Hisangi (advisor at large).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family status is hanke (family of lower ranking court nobles) (kuge -court noble), and the highest court positions appointed were Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Hisangi (advisor at large).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family status is hanke (family of lower ranking court nobles) (kuge -court noble), and the highest court positions appointed were Junii (Junior Second Rank) and Hisangi (advisor at large).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>家業は雅楽。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family specialized in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) as their profession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family specialized in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) as their profession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family specialized in gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music) as their profession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>五辻家からは慈光寺家が分かれ出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jikoji family branched out from the Itsutsuji family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jikoji family branched out from the Itsutsuji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jikoji family branched out from the Itsutsuji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kaba(id:17904), Gamy-Gamy-Gamy(id:287400), 水野白楓(id:22811), NDR(id:5500), 輝く水(id:65241), BAKU(id:55205), ウラヌス(id:25954), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>