<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>壬生家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mibu family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mibu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mibu Family</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>壬生家（みぶけ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mibu family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mibu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mibu family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家中御門流の公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A court noble of Nakamikado-ryu (the Nakamikado line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Court nobility of Nakamikado-ryu (the Nakamikado line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;court noble&quot; to &quot;court nobility&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Court nobility of Nakamikado-ryu (the Nakamikado line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>小槻氏姓の地下家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jige family of the Ozuki/Otsuki clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jige family of the Ozuki/Otsuki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jige family of the Ozuki (the family name is also read Otsuki) clan.</e>
<cmt>(the family name is also read Otsuki)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>官務家と称す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Identified itself as the Kanmu family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family identified itself as the Kanmu family.</e>
<cmt>Original is not a sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family identified itself as the Kanmu family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>壬生家（藤原北家中御門流）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mibu family (Nakamikado-ryu of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mibu family (Nakamikado-ryu of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mibu family (Nakamikado-ryu of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>壬生家（みぶけ）は、羽林家の家格を有する公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mibu family was a court noble with a family status of the Urin family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mibu family was court nobility with a family status of the Urin.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;court noble&quot; to &quot;court nobility&quot;, Also removed &quot;family&quot; to avoid repetition.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mibu family was court nobility with a family status of the Urin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原北家中御門流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakamikado-ryu of the northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakamikado-ryu of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakamikado-ryu of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>持明院家支流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A branch of the Jimyoin family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A branch of the Jimyoin family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A branch of the Jimyoin family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代初期に園基音の末子、壬生基起によって創立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was created by Motooki MIBU, the youngest son of Motonari SONO, in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family originated with Motooki MIBU, the youngest son of Motonari SONO, in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;was created by&quot; to &quot;originated with&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family originated with Motooki MIBU, the youngest son of Motonari SONO, in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は130石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 130 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 130 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 130 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>明治維新後に子爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family became a viscount after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was awarded the title of viscount after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was awarded the title of viscount after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後に伯爵に陞爵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later it ranked up to a count.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later the title was upgrated to count.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later the title was upgraded to count.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>主な人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main characters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important members of the family</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important members of the family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>幕末、明治維新期の壬生基修（もとおさ）は、七卿落ちの一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoosa MIBU at the end of Edo period to the Meiji Restoration was one of shichikyo-ochi members (defeated seven nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of Edo period and the beginning of the Meiji Restoration, Motoosa MIBU was one of shichikyo-ochi members (defeated seven nobles).</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of Edo period and the beginning of the Meiji Restoration, Motoosa MIBU was one of shichikyo-ochi members (defeated seven nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>維新後は、参与。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a Senior Counselor after the Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a Senior Counselor after the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became a Senior Counselor after the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>戊辰戦争では参謀となり従軍し、会津藩を攻略した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He joined the army as ageneral staff in the Boshin War and captured the domain of Aizu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He joined the army as a staff officer in the Boshin War and captured the domain of Aizu.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He joined the army as a staff officer in the Boshin War and captured the domain of Aizu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>越後府知事、東京府知事を経て、元老院議官、貴族院_(日本)となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a councilor of the senate and joined the House of Lord after he served as the Governors of Echigo Prefecture and Tokyo Prefecture in turn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served as the Governors of Echigo Prefecture and Tokyo Prefecture and proceeded to become a councilor of the senate and join the House of Lord after he</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served as the Governors of Echigo Prefecture and Tokyo Prefecture and proceeded to become a councilor of the senate and join the House of Lord.</e>
<cmt>after he削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>明治17年7月8日子爵の位を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He received the viscountship on July 8, 1884.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He received the viscountship on July 8, 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He received the viscountship on July 8, 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>明治24年伯爵に陞爵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ranked up to a count in 1891.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was promoted to count in 1891.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was promoted to count in 1891.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>壬生基義（もとよし）は、陸軍士官学校_(日本)を卒業後、陸軍軍人の道を歩み陸軍少将まで累進し、侍従武官も務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoyoshi MIBU followed the path of soldier in the army after he graduated from a military academy and was promoted to an Army Major General, and also served as a military attache to the palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoyoshi MIBU became a soldier after graduating from military academy and was promoted to Major General in the army, and also served as a military attache to the palace.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoyoshi MIBU became a soldier after graduating from military academy and was promoted to Major General in the army, and also served as a military attache to the palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>夫人は久邇宮朝彦親王の第8王女篶子（すずこ）女王。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His wife was Princess Suzuko, the eighth princess of the Imperial Prince Asahiko KUNINOMIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His wife was Princess Suzuko, the eighth daughter of the Imperial Prince Asahiko KUNINOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>8th princess may be better as 8th daughter.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His wife was Princess Suzuko, the eighth daughter of the Imperial Prince Asahiko KUNINOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>壬生基泰（もとやす）も貴族院議員を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoyasu MIBU also served as the member of House of Lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoyasu MIBU also served as the member of House of Lords.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;Lord&quot; to &quot;Lords&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoyasu MIBU also served as the member of House of Lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>壬生基博（もとひろ）は、昭和天皇の第1皇女成子内親王と東久邇宮稔彦王の長男東久邇盛厚（もりひろ）の二男。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohiro MIBU was the second son of Princess Shigeko, the first daughter of Emperor Showa, and Morihiro HIGASHIKUNINOMIYA was the first son of Naruhikoo HIGASHIKUNINOMIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohiro MIBU was the second son of Princess Shigeko, the first daughter of Emperor Showa, and Morihiro HIGASHIKUNINOMIYA was the first son of Naruhikoo HIGASHIKUNINOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohiro MIBU was the second son of Princess Shigeko, the first daughter of the Emperor Showa, and Morihiro HIGASHIKUNINOMIYA was the first son of Naruhikoo HIGASHIKUNINOMIYA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>初名は秀彦（ひでひこ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first name was Hidehiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His was originally called Hidehiko.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was originally called Hidehiko.</e>
<cmt>His→He</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>壬生家の養子となり、第一ホテル専務などを務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was adopted by the Mibu family, and served as the executive managing director of Dai-ichi Hotel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was adopted by the Mibu family, and became as the executive managing director of Dai-ichi Hotel.</e>
<cmt>&quot;served&quot; doesn&apos;t really work here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was adopted by the Mibu family, and became as the executive managing director of Dai-ichi Hotel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>壬生家（小槻姓）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mibu family (the family name is Ozuki/Otsuki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mibu family (the family name is Ozuki/Otsuki)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mibu family (the family name is Ozuki/Otsuki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>壬生家（みぶけ）は、朝廷に仕えた地下家の官人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mibu family was a government official of the Jige family served the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mibu family was a government official for the Jige family which served the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mibu family was a government official for the Jige family which served the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>小槻氏の嫡流で小槻隆職を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the lineage of eldest son, and OTSUKI no Takamoto was the ancestor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was descended from the eldest son of OTSUKO no Takamoto</e>
<cmt>Clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was descended from the eldest son of OTSUKI no Takamoto</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は100石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 100 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 100 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hereditary stipend in the Edo period was 100 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>明治維新後男爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family became a baron after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was awarded the title of baron after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was awarded the title of baron after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>小槻氏は中世より太政官の諸記録を司り、五位の官務（左大史上首）を世襲したため官務家と呼ばれたが、平安時代末に小槻長業の子の小槻広房と弟の隆職がその職を争い、五位の官務は隆職の子孫（壬生家）、算博士は広房の子孫（大宮家）が世襲することとなり、二流に分裂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ozuki family administered the records of Imperial Japanese Council of State since the Middle Ages, and was called as the official position family as it succeeded to the official position of the fifth rank (sadaishi joshu (左大史上首)) from fathers to children; The family was divided into two streams: OZUKI no Hirofusa, the son of 小槻長業, and OZUKI no Takamoto, the younger brother, fought for the position, and eventually the official position of the fifth rank was to be succeeded by the descendants of Takamoto (the Mibu family), and the sanhakase (a position teaching mathematics and growing mathematicians) was by the descendants of Hirofusa (the Omiya family).</e>
<cmt>左大史上首→sadaishi joshu[正しい読み方が不明です] 小槻長業→不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ozuki family administered the records of Imperial Japanese Council of State from the Middle Ages, and was, due to its inherited position of fifth rank (sadaishi joshu (左大史上首)), known as the family of administrative service; when OZUKI no Hirofusa, the son of 小槻長業, and OZUKI no Takamoto, Hirofusa&apos;s younger brother, fought over the position, the family was divided into two streams with the position of fifth rank going Takamoto and his descendents (the Mibu family) and the post of sanhakase (a position teaching mathematics and looking after mathematicians) going to Hirofusa and his descendants (the Omiya family).</e>
<cmt>I have attempted write in clearer English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ozuki family administered the records of Imperial Japanese Council of State from the Middle Ages, and was, due to its inherited position of fifth rank (sadaishi joshu), known as the family of administrative service; when OZUKI no Hirofusa, the son of 小槻長業, and OZUKI no Takamoto, Hirofusa&apos;s younger brother, fought over the position, the family was divided into two streams with the position of fifth rank going Takamoto and his descendents (the Mibu family) and the post of sanhakase (a position teaching mathematics and looking after mathematicians) going to Hirofusa and his descendants (the Omiya family).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除 (左大史上首)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>中世以降壬生家は官務に加え修理東大寺大仏長官（または造東大寺次官）・主殿頭、のち室町時代末期に大宮家が断絶したため、壬生孝亮以降は算博士も世襲することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Middle Ages, the Mibu family had taken over the positions of the chief of the repair section of Todai-ji-Temple Great Buddha (or the vice minister of Todai-ji Temple charge) and the chief of Tonomonoryo (Palace Custodians and Supply Bureau), and also sanhakase (a position teaching mathematics and growing mathematicians) after the era of Takasuke MIBU as the Omiya family failed at the end of Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Middle Ages onwards, the Mibu family held the positions of repair section chief of Todai-ji-Temple Great Buddha, the chief of Tonomonoryo (Palace Custodians and Supply Bureau), and also, from when the Omiya family was discontinued at the end of Muromachi period, sanhakase (a position teaching mathematics and growing mathematicians) after the era of Takasuke MIBU</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Middle Ages onwards, the Mibu family held the positions of repair section chief of Todai-ji-Temple Great Buddha, the chief of Tonomonoryo (Palace Custodians and Supply Bureau), and also, from when the Omiya family was discontinued at the end of Muromachi period, sanhakase (a position teaching mathematics and growing mathematicians) after the era of Takasuke MIBU.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、官務を世襲した壬生家は、局務（大外記上首）を世襲した押小路家（中原氏）と並んで両局と称され、地下家の筆頭格とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mibu family that took over the official position from fathers to children was called ryokyoku together with the Oshikoji/Oshinokoji family (the Nakahara family) that took over kyokumu (the chief of the Senior secretary of the Council of State), and was considered as the head of the Jige family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mibu family which held the the inherited administrative position of kammu and the Oshikoji/Oshinokoji family (the Nakahara family) which held the inherited position of kyokumu (Chief Senior Secretary of the Council of State) were collectively known as ryokyoku, and had the status of Jige.</e>
<cmt>I have attempted to write in clearer English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mibu family which held the inherited administrative position of kanmu and the Oshikoji/Oshinokoji family (the Nakahara family) which held the inherited position of kyokumu (Chief Senior Secretary of the Council of State) were collectively known as ryokyoku, and had the status of Jige.</e>
<cmt>the削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>壬生家の家格は地下家であったが江戸時代後期に壬生知音・壬生以寧は従三位に叙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family status of the Mibu family was the Jige family; however, Chiin MIBU and Ine MIBU were ranked up to Jusani (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mibu family had the status of Jige, but Chiin MIBU and Ine MIBU were promoted to the rank of Jusani (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>Readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mibu family had the status of Jige, but Chiin MIBU and Ine MIBU were promoted to the rank of Jusani (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>庶流に同じ地下家で太政官の史を世襲した村田家がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Murata family, the same Jige family, took over the position of the Imperial Japanese Council of State in the illegitimate family lineage,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The illegitimate descendents of the Mibu family include the Murata family, which also had the status of Jige family and held the inherited position of Imperial Japanese Councilor of State.</e>
<cmt>I have changed the expressions use to make the meaning clearer.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The illegitimate descendents of the Mibu family include the Murata family, which also had the status of Jige family and held the inherited position of Imperial Japanese Councilor of State.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Snap55(id:89773), Riekanu(id:65656), Kawai(id:5634), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>