<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朝倉氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asakura clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asakura clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asakura clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朝倉氏（あさくらし）は、越前国を拠点とした豪族で、後に発展して戦国大名となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asakura clan was a local ruling family whose home base was Echizen Province, and the clan later ascended to be a sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku Period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asakura clan was a local ruling family whose home base was Echizen Province, and the clan later ascended to be a sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku Period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asakura clan was a local ruling family whose home base was Echizen Province, and the clan later ascended to be a sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku Period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>越前国守護である斯波氏の守護代を務めたが、のちに朝倉氏自体が守護に任命されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, he was serving the Shiba clan, Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province, as its Shugodai (provisional governor), but later the Asakura clan itself came to be appointed Shugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, the clan served the Shiba clan, Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province, as its Shugodai (provisional governor), but later the Asakura clan itself came to be appointed to Shugo.</e>
<cmt>he was serving→the clan served と修正しました。to を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, the clan served the Shiba clan, Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province, as its Shugodai (provisional governor), but later the Asakura clan itself came to be appointed to Shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通し字は「景」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family members&apos; Toshiji (or toriji, character-in-common, one of two chinese characters adopted by members of the same family) was 景 (kage)</e>
<cmt>通し字→定訳不明：Toshiji (or toriji, character-in-common, one of two chinese characters adopted by members of the same family)としました。 &apos;景&apos;→景 (kage)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Toshiji (or toriji, character-in-common, one of two Chinese characters adopted by members of the same family) was &apos;景&apos; (kage).</e>
<cmt>「通し字」は用語集にて確認しました。family members&apos; を削除しました。chinese→Chinese,クォーツ、ピリオドを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Toshiji (or toriji, character-in-common, one of two Chinese characters adopted by members of the same family) was &apos;景&apos; (kage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>出自は但馬国養父郡朝倉（兵庫県養父市）であり、はじめは日下部氏（くさかべ）を姓とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its origin was Asakura, Yafu Country, Tajima Province (Yafu City, Hyogo Province), and at first the clan used the name of Kusakabe clan as his sei (authentic surname).</e>
<cmt>姓→sei (authentic surname)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its origin was Asakura, Yabu County, Tajima Province (Yabu City, Hyogo Prefecture), and at first the clan used the name of Kusakabe clan as its sei (authentic surname).</e>
<cmt>Yafu→Yabu,Country→County,Province→Prefecture,his→its と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its origin was Asakura, Yabu County, Tajima Province (Yabu City, Hyogo Prefecture), and at first the clan used the name of Kusakabe clan as its sei (authentic surname).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『越州軍記』によると開化天皇、『朝倉始末記』によると孝徳天皇の後裔とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to an epic &quot;Esshu gunki&quot; (an epic of the Asakura clan in Echizen Province), he was Emperor Kaika&apos;s descendent, while according to &quot;Asakura Shimatsuki&quot; (History of the Asakura family), he was Emperor Kotoku&apos;s descendent.</e>
<cmt>『越州軍記』→定訳不明：&quot;Esshu gunki&quot; (an epic of the Asakura clan in Echizen Province)としました。 『朝倉始末記』→定訳不明：&quot;Asakura Shimatsuki&quot; (History of the Asakura family) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to an epic &quot;Esshu gunki&quot; (an epic of the Asakura clan in Echizen Province), the clan was the Emperor Kaika&apos;s descendent, while &quot;Asakura Shimatsuki&quot; (History of the Asakura family) states that, the clan was the Emperor Kotoku&apos;s descendent.</e>
<cmt>he→the clan,the を補いました。according to→states that と修正しました。『越州軍記』、朝倉始末記』の定訳は共に確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to an epic &quot;Esshu gunki&quot; (an epic of the Asakura clan in Echizen Province), the clan was the Emperor Kaika&apos;s descendent, while &quot;Asakura Shimatsuki&quot; (History of the Asakura family) states that, the clan was the Emperor Kotoku&apos;s descendent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>越前国守護斯波氏に仕える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province, the Shiba clan.</e>
<cmt>越前国守護斯波氏→Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province, the Shiba clanとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan served the Shiba clan, Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>He→The clan,オーダーを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan served the Shiba clan, Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>甲斐氏、織田氏と共に斯波三守護代の第二席。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan occupied the second precedence of the three Shugodais (provisional governors) to the Shiba clan, together with the Kai clan and the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>第二席→定訳不明：second precedenceとしました。 斯波三守護代→定訳不明：three shugodais (provisional governors) to the Shiba clan としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status of the clan was the second in precedence of the three Shugodai (provisional governors) of the Shiba clan, together with the Kai clan and the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>clan occupied→status of the clan was,second precedence→second in precedenceShugodais→Shugodai,to→of と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status of the clan was the second in precedence of the three Shugodai (provisional governors) of the Shiba clan, together with the Kai clan and the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>のちに守護代三家で斯波氏領国三国を分けることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later the territory of three countries dominated by the Shiba clan was divided among these three Shugodai families.</e>
<cmt>斯波氏領国三国→territory of three countries dominated by the Shiba clan としました。 守護代三家→three Shugodai familiesとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the territory of three provinces ruled by the Shiba clan was divided among these three Shugodai families.</e>
<cmt>countries→provinces,dominated→ruled と修正しました。カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the territory of three provinces ruled by the Shiba clan was divided among these three Shugodai families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>室町時代には朝倉敏景（英林孝景）が守護代甲斐常治とともに主である斯波義敏と対立し、足利将軍家の家督争いなどから発展した応仁の乱では山名持豊(宗全)率いる西軍から細川勝元率いる東軍に属し、越前から甲斐氏を追う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Muromachi Period, Toshikage ASAKURA (Eirin Takakage) was opposed to his lord Yoshitoshi SHIBA with Tsuneharu KAI, and in the Onin War, which broke out from the internal squabble of the Ashikaga Shogun family over the family reign, he switched from the West squad lead by Mochitoyo YAMANA (Sozen) to the East squad lead by Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and he expelled the Kai clan from Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, Toshikage ASAKURA (Eirin Takakage) came to oppose his lord Yoshitoshi SHIBA with Tsuneharu KAI, and in the Onin War, which broke out from the internal squabble of the Ashikaga Shogun family over the family reign, he switched from the West army lead by Mochitoyo YAMANA (Sozen) to the East army lead by Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and he expelled the Kai clan from Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>Period→period,was opposed to→came to oppose,squad→army,スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, Toshikage ASAKURA (Eirin Takakage) came to oppose his lord Yoshitoshi SHIBA with Tsuneharu KAI, and in the Onin War, which broke out from the internal squabble of the Ashikaga Shogun family over the family reign, he switched from the West army lead by Mochitoyo YAMANA (Sozen) to the East army lead by Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and he expelled the Kai clan from Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>朝倉孝景は越前国守護に取り立てられ一乗谷城に拠った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA was preferentially given the post of Shugo (military governor) in Echizen Province and took the Ichijodani Castle as his headquarters.</e>
<cmt>朝倉孝景→Takakage ASAKURAは、 上列の朝倉敏景（英林孝景）→Toshikage ASAKURA (Eirin Takakage)と同一人物か不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage ASAKURA was promoted to the Shugo (military governor) in Echizen Province and took the Ichijodani Castle as his headquarters.</e>
<cmt>preferentially given the post of→promoted to, the を補いました。なお、朝倉孝景と「朝倉敏景」は同一人物であると確認しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA was promoted to the Shugo (military governor) in Echizen Province and took the Ichijodani Castle as his headquarters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>孝景は分国法である『朝倉敏景十七ヶ条』を制定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage set up bunkokuho (an autonomous law that individual sengoku daimyo enforced in their own domain of provincial control) called &quot;The seventeen articles of Toshikage ASAKURA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>分国法→定訳不明：bunkokuho (an autonomous law that individual sengoku daimyo enforced in their own domain of provincial control)としました。　 『朝倉敏景十七ヶ条』→&quot;The seventeen articles of Toshikage ASAKURA&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage established bunkokuho (an autonomous law that individual sengoku daimyo enforced in their own domain of provincial control) called &quot;The seventeen articles of Toshikage ASAKURA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>set up→established と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage established bunkokuho (an autonomous law that individual sengoku daimyo enforced in their own domain of provincial control) called &quot;The seventeen articles of Toshikage ASAKURA.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>旧主の斯波義敏が越前守護職を回復せんと、朝倉氏の越前実効支配について幕府に異議を申し立てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former lord of the province, Yoshitoshi SHIBA brought to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) an objection about the Asakura clan&apos;s practical rule over the Echizen Province, in order to recover the post of Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former lord of the province, Yoshitoshi SHIBA brought to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) an objection about the Asakura clan&apos;s effective control over Echizen Province, in order to recover the post of Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。practical rule→effective control と修正しました。the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former lord of the province, Yoshitoshi SHIBA brought to the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) an objection about the Asakura clan&apos;s effective control over Echizen Province, in order to recover the post of Shugo (military governor) of Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>すると、かつての守護斯波義廉の子を鞍谷氏の養子として足利義俊と名乗らせた上で、幕府の反対を押し切ってこの義俊を”名目上越前国主”として擁立し越前守護の斯波氏に対抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage, therefore, forced the Kuratani clan to adopt the son of Shugo Yoshiyasu SHIBA and made the adopted son proclaim himself Yoshitoshi ASHIKAGA, and then, in order to cope with the Shiba clan, which was formal Shugo of Echizen Province, Takakage backed up Yoshitoshi as &apos;the nominal provincial lord of Echizen Province,&apos; overriding resistance from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　　 守護斯波義廉→Shugo Yoshiyasu SHIBAとしました。 ”名目上越前国主”→定訳不明：&apos;the nominal provincial lord of Echizen Province&apos; としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage, therefore, forced the Kuratani clan to adopt the son of Shugo Yoshiyasu SHIBA and made the adopted son proclaim himself Yoshitoshi ASHIKAGA, and then, to oppose the Shiba clan, which was the Shugo of Echizen Province, Takakage backed up Yoshitoshi as &apos;the nominal provincial lord of Echizen Province,&apos; overcoming resistance from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>”かつてのの子”では意味が通らず、ウェブ上から”かつての守護斯波義廉の子”を補ってオリジナル部を修正しました。in order to come with→to oppose, formal→ the,overriding resistance from→overcoming resistance from と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage, therefore, forced the Kuratani clan to adopt the son of Shugo Yoshiyasu SHIBA and made the adopted son proclaim himself Yoshitoshi ASHIKAGA, and then, to oppose the Shiba clan, which was the Shugo of Echizen Province, Takakage backed up Yoshitoshi as &apos;the nominal provincial lord of Echizen Province,&apos; overcoming resistance from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>（鞍谷氏は、足利義持の弟、足利義嗣の子・足利嗣俊を祖とする。室町将軍家の越前における分家、鞍谷御所と呼ばれて尊崇を集めていた。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The Kuratani clan&apos;s ancestor was Tsugutoshi ASHIKAGA, who was the son of Yoshitsugu ASHIKAGA and smaller brother of Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, and it was highly respected as a branch family called Kuratani gosho (Kuratani Palace) of the Muromachi Shogunate family in Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　　鞍谷御所→定訳不明：Kuratani gosho (Kuratani Palace) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The Kuratani clan&apos;s ancestor was Tsugutoshi ASHIKAGA, who was the son of Yoshitsugu ASHIKAGA and younger brother of Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, and it was highly respected and called Kuratani gosho [Kuratani Palace], as a branch family of the Muromachi Shogunate family in Echizen Province.)</e>
<cmt>smaller→younger,文半ばを文脈より修正しました。カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Kuratani clan&apos;s ancestor was Tsugutoshi ASHIKAGA, who was the son of Yoshitsugu ASHIKAGA and younger brother of Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, and it was highly respected and called Kuratani gosho [Kuratani Palace], as a branch family of the Muromachi Shogunate family in Echizen Province.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>のちに朝倉氏自体が越前守護に任じられることとなったため、鞍谷公方足利氏は朝倉氏の客将と化し、朝倉氏が名実ともに同国の大名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, as the Asakura clan itself was appointed Echizen shugo (military governor of Echizen Province), Kuratani kubo Ashikaga clan ended as a guest shogun of the Asakura clan, and the Asakura clan became the daimyo (territorial lord) of the province in name and in reality.</e>
<cmt>鞍谷公方足利氏→定訳不明：Kuratani kubo Ashikaga clan としました。 客将→定訳不明：guest shogun としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, as the Asakura clan itself was appointed to Echizen shugo (military governor of Echizen Province), the Kuratani kubo Ashikaga clan became a guest commander of the Asakura clan, and the Asakura clan became the daimyo (territorial lord) of the province in name and in reality.</e>
<cmt>to, the を補いました。ended as→became と修正しました。「客将」の定訳は確認できておりません。しかし、ここでの”将軍”は意味が通らないと思い、shogun→commander と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, as the Asakura clan itself was appointed to Echizen shugo (military governor of Echizen Province), the Kuratani kubo Ashikaga clan became a guest commander of the Asakura clan, and the Asakura clan became the daimyo (territorial lord) of the province in name and in reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>戦国時代には越前支配のみならず、隣国若狭国、近江国にも進攻し、領土を広げたが、尾張国の織田信長と対立し、1573年、滅ぼされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period (period of warring states), the clan not only establish the dominance in Echizen Province, but also extended its territory over the neighboring provinces, Wakasa and Omi, but the confrontation with Nobunaga ODA of Owari Province lead the clan to destruction in 1573.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), the clan not only established the dominance in Echizen Province, but also extended its territory over the neighboring provinces, Wakasa and Omi, but the confrontation with Nobunaga ODA of Owari Province led the clan to fall in 1573.</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を修正しました。establish→established,lead→led,destruction→fall と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), the clan not only established the dominance in Echizen Province, but also extended its territory over the neighboring provinces, Wakasa and Omi, but the confrontation with Nobunaga ODA of Owari Province led the clan to fall in 1573.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>子孫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Descendents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>土佐に早期に分かれた分家（朝倉友景系）が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Tosa Province, there remained a branch family (Tomokage ASAKURA line), which split earlier.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Tosa Province, there was a branch family (Tomokage ASAKURA line) remained, which split earlier.</e>
<cmt>スムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Tosa Province, there was a branch family (Tomokage ASAKURA line) remained, which split earlier.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>早期に分家した一族と考えられている溝江氏が、豊臣秀吉に馬廻として仕え、のち1万石で旧領復帰。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mizoe clan, which is also considered a branch family split earlier from the Asakura family, served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as umamawari (a horse guard), and later it recovered its former territory of a 10,000-koku crop yield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mizoe clan, which is also considered as a branch family split earlier from the Asakura family, served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as umamawari (a horse guard), and later recovered its former territory of a 10,000-koku crop yield.</e>
<cmt>as を補いました。it を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mizoe clan, which is also considered as a branch family split earlier from the Asakura family, served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as umamawari (a horse guard), and later recovered its former territory of a 10,000-koku crop yield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>関ヶ原にて西軍に所属して改易となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara, as he belonged to the West squad, he underwent Kaieki sanction (sudden dismissal and deprivation of position, privileges and properties).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Sekigahara, as he belonged to the West squad, he underwent Kaieki sanction (sudden dismissal and deprivation of position, privileges and properties).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara, as he belonged to the West squad, he underwent Kaieki sanction (sudden dismissal and deprivation of position, privileges and properties).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後、浪人したのち、彦根藩士として存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, for a while the clan lived a masterless period, and later it persisted as a feudal retainer of the Hikone Domain.</e>
<cmt>浪人→masterless periodとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, the clan lived a masterless period for a while, and later it continued as a feudal retainer of the Hikone clan.</e>
<cmt>persisted→continued と修正しました。「彦根藩士」を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, the clan lived a masterless period for a while, and later it continued as a feudal retainer of the Hikone clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>水戸藩には、朝倉時景系と伝わる小田原北条氏家臣の朝倉氏が藩士として存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Asakura clan that was supposed to be the family from the Tokikage ASAKURA line and was once the Tawara-Hojo clan&apos;s vassal, survived as a feudal retainer of the Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Asakura clan, that was supposed to be the line of Tokikage ASAKURA and was once the Odawara-Hojo clan&apos;s vassal, survived as a feudal retainer of the Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。 Tawara→Odawara,スムースに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Asakura clan, that was supposed to be the line of Tokikage ASAKURA and was once the Odawara-Hojo clan&apos;s vassal, survived as a feudal retainer of the Mito Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>同家から分かれた江戸幕府旗本朝倉家もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A branch family split from the Asakura family also formed the Asakura family, which became Edo bakufu hatamoto (a direct retainer of Edo bakufu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was also the Asakura family who became Edo bakufu hatamoto (a direct retainer of Edo bakufu), split from the Asakura who served the Odawara-Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was also the Asakura family who became Edo bakufu hatamoto (a direct retainer of Edo bakufu), split from the Asakura who served the Odawara-Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>英林孝景の次男・朝倉秀景の孫・朝倉政元は、後北条氏、豊臣秀次、徳川家康と仕え、政元の子・朝倉政明は徳川秀忠に仕え、500石の旗本として存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto ASAKURA, who was the second son of Takakage Eirin (Toshikage ASAKURA) and grandson of Hidekage ASAKURA, served the Gohojo clan, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in a consecutive manner, and Motomasa&apos;s son Masaaki ASAKURA served Hidetada TOKUGAWA as hatamoto (a direct retainer of the bakufu) with a stipend of 500-koku crop yield.</e>
<cmt>英林孝景→Takakage Eirin (Toshikage ASAKURA) としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamoto ASAKURA, who was the second son of Erin Takakage (Toshikage ASAKURA) and grandson of Hidekage ASAKURA, served the Gohojo clan, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in a consecutive manner, and Motomasa&apos;s son Masaaki ASAKURA served Hidetada TOKUGAWA as hatamoto (a direct retainer of the bakufu) with a stipend of 500 koku crop yield.</e>
<cmt>Takakage Erin→Erin Takakage,500-koku→500 koku と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamoto ASAKURA, who was the second son of Erin Takakage (Toshikage ASAKURA) and grandson of Hidekage ASAKURA, served the Gohojo clan, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in a consecutive manner, and Motomasa&apos;s son Masaaki ASAKURA served Hidetada TOKUGAWA as hatamoto (a direct retainer of the bakufu) with a stipend of 500 koku crop yield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>徳川家康家臣→駿河大納言徳川忠長付家老→古河土井氏家臣と続いた朝倉氏（朝倉宣正系）がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an Asakura clan (Nobumasa ASAKURA line) that persisted by changing its lord, from as a vassal of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and Karo (the chief retainer) to Dainagon (major councilor) of Suruga Province Tadanaga TOKUGAWA to a vassal of the Furukawa-Doi clan.</e>
<cmt>駿河大納言徳川忠長付家老→Karo (the chief retainer) to Dainagon (major councilor) of Suruga Province Tadanaga TOKUGAWAとしました。 古河土井氏家臣→vassal of the Furukawa-Doi clanとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an Asakura clan (Nobumasa ASAKURA line) that continued as this; a vassal of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, then Karo (the chief retainer) to Dainagon (major councilor) of Tadanaga TOKUGAWA of Suruga Province, then a vassal of the Furukawa-Doi clan.</e>
<cmt>persisted→continued と修正しました。 by changing its lord を削除し、修正しました。パンクチュエーションを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an Asakura clan (Nobumasa ASAKURA line) that continued as this; a vassal of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, then Karo (the chief retainer) to Dainagon (major councilor) of Tadanaga TOKUGAWA of Suruga Province, then a vassal of the Furukawa-Doi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>朝倉景鏡の甥とされるが、父親の動向等に不明な点が多く、越前朝倉氏との関連は確定ではない（北条家臣、もしくは伊勢、遠江の朝倉氏等の系統か？）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of his clan was said to be the nephew of Kageakira ASAKURA, but there are many unclear points about his father&apos;s life among others, and the connection with the Echizen-Asakura clan can not be confirmed (his father could have been a retainer of the Hojo clan, or a member of a certain family line of the Asakura clan of Ise province or the Asakura clan of Totomi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of this clan was said to be the nephew of Kageakira ASAKURA, but there are many unclear points about his father&apos;s life and so on, and the connection with the Echizen-Asakura clan can not be confirmed (His father could have been a retainer of the Hojo clan, or a member of a certain family line of the Asakura clan of Ise Province or the Asakura clan of Totomi Province.)</e>
<cmt>his→this, among others→and so on,カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of this clan was said to be the nephew of Kageakira ASAKURA, but there are many unclear points about his father&apos;s life and so on, and the connection with the Echizen-Asakura clan can not be confirmed (His father could have been a retainer of the Hojo clan, or a member of a certain family line of the Asakura clan of Ise Province or the Asakura clan of Totomi Province.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>越前朝倉氏滅亡後、越後国に朝倉愛王丸が落ち延びたという伝承が、また、出羽国などにも子孫伝承が残るが、真偽は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a legend of Aiomaru ASAKURA, in which he is said to have escaped safely to Echigo Province after the fall of the Echizen-Asakura clan, and in Dewa Province, etc. there were also legends related to the clan&apos;s descendents, however the authenticity of any of these legend is not confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a legend of Aiomaru ASAKURA, in which he is said to have escaped safely to Echigo Province after the fall of the Echizen-Asakura clan, and there were also legends related to the clan&apos;s descendents in Dewa Province, and so on, however the authenticity of any of these legends is not confirmed.</e>
<cmt>オーダーを修正しました。etc.→and so on,,legend→legends と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a legend of Aiomaru ASAKURA, in which he is said to have escaped safely to Echigo Province after the fall of the Echizen-Asakura clan, and there were also legends related to the clan&apos;s descendents in Dewa Province, and so on, however the authenticity of any of these legends is not confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>日本海側各所に一向宗と結びついた「朝倉末裔伝説」がパターン流布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In various places along the Sea of Japan, variations of a patterned &apos;legend of the descendent from the Asakura clan&apos; connected with the Ikko sect are widespread.</e>
<cmt>「朝倉末裔伝説」→定訳不明：&apos;legend of the descendent from the Asakura clan&apos; としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In various places along the Sea of Japan coast, the legend which the Asakura clan connected to the Ikko sect as &apos;legend of the descendent from the Asakura clan&apos; is widespread in different patterns.</e>
<cmt>coast を補いました。文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In various places along the Sea of Japan coast, the legend which the Asakura clan connected to the Ikko sect as &apos;legend of the descendent from the Asakura clan&apos; is widespread in different patterns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>上杉謙信を頼り、朝倉家再興を果たそうとした朝倉景嘉がいるが、謙信の死により頓挫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In one of these variations, Kageyoshi ASAKURA tried to resuscitate the Asakura family, counting on Kenshin UESUGI, but his dream was frustrated due to Kenshin&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was Kageyoshi ASAKURA, who tried to resuscitate the Asakura family, and relied on Kenshin UESUGI, but his dream was halted due to Kenshin&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>最初の部分を修正しました。（この部分は上記のものとは関係ないと確認しました）counting→and relied, frustrated→halted と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was Kageyoshi ASAKURA, who tried to resuscitate the Asakura family, and relied on Kenshin UESUGI, but his dream was halted due to Kenshin&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>備後国の鞆の浦にいた足利義昭（実質的には毛利氏）に頼り朝倉家を再興しようと奔走した朝倉宮増丸、及び家督後継者と擬せられていた朝倉景忠がいるが、中国戦線の悪化により不成功に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another story tells about Miyamasumaru (宮増丸) ASAKURA, who scrambled for rebuilding the Asakura family depending on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA (in reality depending on the Mori clan) who was stationed at Tomonoura in Bingo Province, as well as Kagetada ASAKURA, who was falsely presumed to be the successor to the family reign, and according to the story, their attempt was failed due to the deteriorated war situation at the Chinese front.</e>
<cmt>朝倉宮増丸→正式な読み方が不明です：Miyamasumaru (宮増丸) ASAKURA としました。 家督後継者と擬せられていた→was falsely presumed to be the successor to the family reignとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was Miyamasumaru (宮増丸) ASAKURA, who scrambled to restore the Asakura family depending on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA (in reality depending on the Mori clan) who was stationed at Tomonoura in Bingo Province, as well as Kagetada ASAKURA, who was falsely presumed to be the successor of the family reign, although their attempt was failed due to the deteriorated war situation against China.</e>
<cmt>Another story tell about→There was,for rebuilding→to restore,to→of,and according to the story→although,at the Chinese front→against China と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was Miyamasumaru (宮増丸) ASAKURA, who scrambled to restore the Asakura family depending on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA (in reality depending on the Mori clan) who was stationed at Tomonoura in Bingo Province, as well as Kagetada ASAKURA, who was falsely presumed to be the successor of the family reign, although their attempt was failed due to the deteriorated war situation against China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Flamelai(id:34490), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), ドルチェット(id:46458), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), Nnh(id:474), 陽一(id:92099), Iwaro(id:60082), Lilium auratum(id:13615), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Tsql(id:31541), GAVVA(id:47103), らりた(id:1327), 桔梗store(id:64229), 寒(id:53831), A-Taul(id:41790), 代言人(id:33675), 秀の介(id:490), Loveless(id:129239), こぶまき(id:38278), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Daranome(id:1429), Yanahan(id:2437), Seibuabina(id:37532), 大日本帝國海軍博物學大尉(id:98848), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), YurikBot(id:18605), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Labyfrag(id:9446), Kuma83(id:31177), Junger(id:10282), Louperibot(id:128971), SieBot(id:126695), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>