<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>内藤氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Naito clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naito clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naito clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>内藤氏（ないとうし、ないとううじ）は、日本人の姓。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naito-shi or Naito-uji is a Japanese surname.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naito-shi or Naito-uji is a Japanese surname.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naito-shi or Naito-uji is a Japanese surname.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中世から近代まで栄えた豪族・大名の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Naito clan is a family of the gozoku (a local ruling family) and the daimyo (a feudal lord) that flourished from the Medieval to the Modern Ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naito clan is a clan of gozoku (local rulers) and daimyo (feudal lords) which has flourished from the Middle ages to Modern times.</e>
<cmt>I think Medieval times is better as &quot;Middle ages&quot;. Also since the Naito clan is still around, it is better to use &quot;has flourished&quot; rather than &quot;flourished&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naito clan is a clan of gozoku (local rulers) and daimyo (feudal lords) which has flourished from the Middle ages to Modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>藤原北家秀郷流（道長流）内藤氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Naito clan of the House of Fujiwara North, Hidesato Line (Michinaga Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naito clan of the House of Fujiwara North, Hidesato Line (Michinaga Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naito clan of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, Hidesato Line (Michinaga Line)</e>
<cmt>「藤原北家」の訳語を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>以下の内藤氏が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The prominent Naito clans were as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following Naito clans are well known.</e>
<cmt>Changed to make the sentence more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following Naito clans are well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉時代に源頼朝に仕えた内藤盛家・内藤盛時がこれらの内藤氏の共通の先祖にあたるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moriie NAITO and Moritoki NAITO who served MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in the Kamakura period were the common ancestors of those Naito clans mentioned below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moriie NAITO and Moritoki NAITO who served MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in the Kamakura period were the common ancestors of those Naito clans mentioned below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moriie NAITO and Moritoki NAITO who served MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in the Kamakura period were the common ancestors of those Naito clans mentioned below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>丹波国の守護代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugodai, the acting Military Govenor, of the Privince of Tamba</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugodai, the acting Military Governor, of Tamba Province</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;Privince of Tamba&quot; to &quot;Tamba Province&quot; as per term list of July 31st.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) of Tanba Province</e>
<cmt>意味が不明瞭。.彼は &quot;Tanba Province&quot;の出身なのか、&quot;Military Governor of Tanba province&quot;の出身なのかが不明。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>細川氏に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It served the Hosokawa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Naito clan served the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>It is not clear what &quot;it&quot; is referring to. If it refers to one of the famous Naito clans, then it is better to write &quot;This Naito clan served the Hosokawa clan&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Naito clan served the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>藤原氏秀郷流を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It claimed to be the Fujiwara family, Hidesato line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It claimed to be the Fujiwara family, Hidesato line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It claimed to be the Fujiwara clan, Hidesato line.</e>
<cmt>family→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>長門国の守護代。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugodai, the acting Military Govenor, of the Province of Nagato</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugodai, the acting Military Governor, of Nagato Province</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;Province of Nagato&quot; to &quot;Nagato Province&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) of Nagato Province</e>
<cmt>意味が不明瞭。.彼は &quot;Nagato Province&quot;の出身なのか、&quot;Military Governor of Nagato Province&quot;の出身なのかが不明。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大内氏に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It served the Ouchi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Naito clan served the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>It is not clear what &quot;it&quot; is referring to. If &quot;it&quot; is the one of the famous Naito clans, then it is better to write &quot;This Naito clan served the Ouchi clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Naito clan served the Ouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>藤原氏秀郷流または道長流を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It claimed to be the Fujiwara family, Hidesato line or Michinaga line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It claimed to be the Fujiwara family, Hidesato line or Michinaga line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It claimed to be the Fujiwara clan, Hidesato line or Michinaga line.</e>
<cmt>family→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>松平氏に仕えた三河国の豪族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gozoku (local ruling family) of the Province of Mikawa, serving the Matsudaira family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gozoku (local ruling family) of the Province of Mikawa, serving the Matsudaira family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gozoku (local ruling family) of the Province of Mikawa, serving the Matsudaira family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1、2の内藤氏と同族と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It claimed to be descended from the same family as the first two Naito clans mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>1,2の表示が原文にない為、このように訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It claimed to be descended from the same family as the first two Naito clans mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It claimed to be descended from the same family as the first two Naito clans mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>甲斐国の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family of the Province of Kai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family of the Province of Kai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A family of Kai Province</e>
<cmt>The→A &quot;the Province of Kai&quot; -&gt; &quot;Kai Province&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1、2の内藤氏と同祖とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered to share the common ancestors with the first two Naito clans mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>1,2の表示が原文にない為、このように訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Naito clan is thought to share the common ancestors of the first two Naito clans mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It was considered&quot; is rather awkward. I changed this to &quot;is thought to&quot; and reworked the sentence accordingly.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Naito clan is thought to share the common ancestors of the first two Naito clans mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>武田氏に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It served the Takeda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It served the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;family&quot; to &quot;clan&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It served the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>内藤昌豊が有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatoyo NAITO was a prominent figure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatoyo NAITO was a prominent figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatoyo NAITO was a prominent figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>内藤氏（丹波系）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Naito clan of Tamba lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naito clan of Tamba lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naito clan of Tanba lineage</e>
<cmt>Tamba→Tanba</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>藤原氏藤原秀郷の一族とされるが前歴は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered to be descended from the family of Fujiwara no Hidesato-Fujiwara family, but its background was not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Naito clan is thought to be descended from the family of Fujiwara no Hidesato-Fujiwara family, but its background is not well known.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It was considered&quot; is rather awkward. I changed this to &quot;is thought to&quot; and reworked the sentence accordingly.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Naito clan is thought to be descended from the family of Fujiwara no Hidesato-Fujiwara clan, but its background is not well known.</e>
<cmt>family→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、細川内衆とされていることから、細川氏の直属の家臣であったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it could be an immediate retainer of the Hosokawa family because it was called Hosokawa-Uchishu (the Hosokawa houseman).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, from the fact that it was called Hosokawa-Uchishu (the Hosokawa houseman), it may have provided immediate retainers to the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence to make it more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since it was called Hosokawa-Uchishu (the Hosokawa houseman), it may have provided immediate retainers to the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>構文に問題。 “from the fact that” → “since”。（. “from the fact that”という文がくる場合には、結果に繋げるフレーズが続く必要があるため。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1431年に丹波守護代である香西元資が罷免されると、細川氏の被官である内藤信承が守護代に就任、入国した内藤氏は船井郡八木に根拠を構えたことから内藤氏の丹波支配が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Motosuke KOZAI, the shugodai of Tamba, was dismissed in 1431, Nobusuke NAITO, a direct vassal of the Hosokawa family, became the shugodai, and as soon as the Naito clan entered Tamba-no-kuni, it began to rule Tamba by setting up its base in Funai district Yagi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Motosuke KOZAI, the shugodai of Tamba, was dismissed in 1431, Nobusuke NAITO, a direct vassal of the Hosokawa clan, became the shugodai, and the Naito clan then set up a base in the Funai district Yagi and began to rule Tamba</e>
<cmt>Reworked last part of sentence to make it more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Motosuke KOZAI, the shugodai of Tanba, was dismissed in 1431, Nobusuke NAITO, a direct vassal of the Hosokawa clan, became the shugodai, and the Naito clan then set up a base in the Funai district Yagi and began to rule Tanba</e>
<cmt>Tamba→Tanba</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>但し、細川氏は領国支配政策として分郡守護代制を布いていることから、内藤氏が丹波一国を支配していたかどうかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was uncertain whether the Naito clan ruled the whole of Tamba because the Hosokawa family placed the c as its governing policy for the territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the Hosokawa clan used the Shugo system, a county-by-county ruling system, as the governing system for its territory, it is uncertain whether the Naito clan ruled the whole of Tamba.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;it was uncertain&quot; to &quot;it is uncertain&quot;. Also part of the original translation seems to be missing.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the Hosokawa clan used the Shugo system, a county-by-county ruling system, as the governing system for its territory, it is uncertain whether the Naito clan ruled the whole of Tanba.</e>
<cmt>Tamba→Tanba</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>応仁の乱の際、但馬国より出撃した山名氏方の将・太田垣氏と丹波諸豪を従え夜久野で交戦している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Onin War, the Naito clan, accompanied by other local ruling families of Tamba, fought at Yakuno with the generals of the Otagaki family which had supported the Yamana family from the Province of Tajima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Onin War, the Naito clan, accompanied by other local ruling families of Tamba, fought at Yakuno under the generals of the Otagaki clan in support of the Yamana family from the Province of Tajima.</e>
<cmt>&quot;将・太田垣氏&quot; seems to have been translated as &quot;generals of the Otagaki clan&quot;. I have made the corrections assuming that this translation is correct, but a further check is required.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Onin War, the Naito clan, accompanied by other local ruling families of Tanba, fought at Yakuno with the generals of the Otagaki clan which had supported the Yamana clan from Tajima Province.</e>
<cmt>内藤氏と太田垣氏が戦った、と判断しました。fight under　the generals of the Otagaki clan では、敵味方の別が違うと思われたので、fight with～に戻しました。&quot;the Province of Tajima&quot; -&gt; &quot;Tajima Province&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、1479年に内藤元貞が細川被官の一宮氏と何らかのトラブルを起こしたため1482年守護代を罷免される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Motosada NAITO was relieved of the shugodai&apos;s post in 1482 due to some sort of trouble with the Ichinomiya family, the Hosokawa family&apos;s direct vassal, in 1479.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Motosada NAITO was relieved of the shugodai post in 1482 due to some sort of trouble with the Ichinomiya clan, the Hosokawa clans&apos;s direct vassal, in 1479.</e>
<cmt>shugodai&apos;s post is better as shugodai post (noun as adjective).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Motosada NAITO was relieved of the shugodai post in 1482 due to some sort of trouble with the Ichinomiya clan, the Hosokawa clans&apos;s direct vassal, in 1479.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>代わって守護代に就いたのは上原元秀で、彼は丹波物部の豪族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohide UEHARA from a local ruling family of Tamba Mononobe was appointed the shugodai in the place of Motosada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motosada was replaced with Motohide UEHARA from a local ruling family from Tamba Mononobe.</e>
<cmt>Not sure what &quot;Tamba Monobe&quot;. I have interpreted this as a place within Tamba.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motosada was replaced with Motohide UEHARA from a local ruling family from Tanba Mononobe.</e>
<cmt>Tamba→Tanba</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>細川政元の信任厚かったものの驕慢の振る舞いが多かったため丹波諸豪族の怒りを買い1489年9月に位田の乱が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohide was greatly trusted by Masamoto HOSOKAWA, but he behaved so arrogantly that other local ruling families of Tamba felt a great deal of anger against him, which led to the Iden Uprising in September, 1489.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohide was greatly trusted by Masamoto HOSOKAWA, but he behaved so arrogantly that other local ruling families of Tamba became resentful, and this led to the Iden Uprising in September, 1489.</e>
<cmt>Reworked latter part of sentence to make it more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohide was greatly trusted by Masamoto HOSOKAWA, but he behaved so arrogantly that other local ruling families of Tanba became resentful, and this led to the Iden Uprising in September 1489.</e>
<cmt>句点は削除。”September, 1489”. -&gt; “September 1489”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>このため1495年上原元秀が罷免され、内藤元貞が復任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a consequence, Motohide UEHARA was dismissed in 1495 and Motosada NAITO restored to his former post of shugodai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a consequence, Motohide UEHARA was dismissed in 1495, and Motosada NAITO was reinstated as shugodai.</e>
<cmt>&quot;restored to his former post of&quot; is better as &quot;reinstated as&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a consequence, Motohide UEHARA was dismissed in 1495, and Motosada NAITO was reinstated as shugodai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>その後、細川氏が細川高国派と細川晴元派に分裂、内藤氏ら丹波諸豪は高国に属して度々晴元の攻撃を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Hosokawa family split into Takakuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s group and Harumoto HOSOKAWA&apos;s group, so the Naito clan and other local ruling families of Tamba, which belonged to Takakuni&apos;s group, were freequently attacked by Harumoto&apos;s group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the Hosokawa clan split into two groups, one led by Takakuni HOSOKAWA and the other by Harumoto HOSOKAWA, with the result that the Naito clan and other local ruling families of Tamba, which belonged to the Takakuni group, were frequently attacked by the Harumoto group.</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence to make it read better.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the Hosokawa clan split into two groups, one led by Takakuni HOSOKAWA and the other by Harumoto HOSOKAWA, with the result that the Naito clan and other local ruling families of Tanba, which belonged to the Takakuni group, were frequently attacked by the Harumoto group.</e>
<cmt>Tamba→Tanba</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>特に内藤氏は丹波の入り口に位置していたために細川氏らの攻撃を直接受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, because the Naito clan was in the front line of Tamba, it was directly attacked by the enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position of Naito clan at the entrance to Tamba meant that they, more often than the other families, suffered direct attacks from the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Especially&quot; is awkward here. I reworked the sentence to make it read better.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position of the Naito clan at the entrance to Tanba meant that they, more often than the other families, suffered direct attacks from the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>構文問題。 “Naito clan”前に定冠詞必要。”The Naito clan&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>再三の守護代罷免・復任劇は内藤氏が如何に細川氏内紛に関わっていたかを物語るとする見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a view that these dramatic and repeated replacements of the shugodai showed how deeply the Naito clan was involved in the internal conflict of the Hosokawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a view that these dramatic and repeated replacements of the shugodai show how deeply the Naito clan was involved in the internal conflict of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;There was a view&quot; is better as &quot;There is a view&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a view that these dramatic and repeated replacements of the shugodai show how deeply the Naito clan was involved in the internal conflict of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし、1515年八上城を築いて根拠とした波多野氏が次第に勢力を増大させていくにしたがって内藤氏の勢いは衰える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the Hatano family, which built the Yakami-jo Castle in 1515 as its base, gradually expanded its power, the Naito clan became weakening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power of the Naito clan waned as the Hatano family, which built Yakami-jo Castle in 1515 as its base, gradually expanded its power.</e>
<cmt>&quot;However&quot; is strange here since the previous sences isn&apos;t talking about the &quot;power&quot; of the Naito clan.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The power of the Naito clan waned as the Hatano clan, which built Yakami-jo Castle in 1515 as its base, gradually expanded its power.</e>
<cmt>family→clan（氏）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1533年に波多野氏が内藤国貞を破って丹波を手中にすると1538年には三好氏と結んだ波多野秀忠によって八木城を陥落させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Hatano family defeated Kunisada NAITO, and captured Tamba in 1533, Hidetada HATANO, allied with the Miyoshi family, made the Yakami-jo Castle fall in 1538.</e>
<cmt>八木城→八上城としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hatano clan defeated Kunisada NAITO, and captured Tamba in 1533, but Hidetada HATANO, allied with the Miyoshi clan, brought about the surrender of Yakami-jo Castle in 1538.</e>
<cmt>Is this correct? Did Hidetada Hatano really fight against his own family?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hatano clan defeated Kunisada NAITO, and captured Tanba in 1533, but Hidetada HATANO, allied with the Miyoshi clan, brought about the surrender of Yakami-jo Castle in 1538.</e>
<cmt>Tamba→Tanba</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>その後、国貞も三好長慶と組み八木城によって抵抗するものの1553年9月内藤国貞の戦死で戦国大名としての内藤氏は滅んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Kunisada joined hands with Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, and resisted by holing up in the Yakami-jo Castle, but Kunisada NAITO was killed in the battle in September, 1553, which resulted in the downfall of the Naito clan as a the Warring loads.</e>
<cmt>八木城→八上城としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therafter, Kunisada also allied himself with Nagayoshi MIYOSHI and resisted the Hatano clan with the help of the Yakami-jo Castle, but was killed in battle in September 1553, bringing about the downfall of the Naito clan as Warring loads.</e>
<cmt>In the first translation, it is not clear who the Kunisdasa was resisting. From the previous sentence, it seems that it was the Hatano clan.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therafter, Kunisada also allied himself with Nagayoshi MIYOSHI and resisted the Hatano clan with the help of the Yakami-jo Castle, but was killed in battle in September 1553, bringing about the downfall of the Naito clan as Warring loads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>1553年三好長慶が八木城を奪回し、松永長頼を内藤氏の婚姻者とし八木城主として丹波経略を開始するが、彼は三好政権の傀儡に過ぎず、長慶死後の1565年8月に赤井直正の猛攻にあって戦死している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nagayoshi MIYOSHI recaptured the Yakami-jo Castle in 1553, building a marital relationship between Nagayori MATSUNAGA and the Naito clan, Nagayori pursued a conquest of Tamba as the lord of the castle, but he was no more than a puppet of the Miyoshi administration, and was killed by the fierce attack of Naomasa AKAI in August, 1565 after the death of Nagayoshi.</e>
<cmt>八木城→八上城としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayoshi MIYOSHI took over Yakami-jo Castle in 1553 and arranged a marriage between Nagayori MATSUNAGA and the Naito clan, whereupon Nagayori became lord of the castle and pursued a conquest of Tamba, but Nagoyori was really no more than a puppet of the Miyoshi administration, and, after the death of Nagayoshi, was killed in a fierce attack by Naomasa AKAI in August 1565.</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence to make it read better.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayoshi MIYOSHI took over Yakami-jo Castle in 1553 and arranged a marriage between Nagayori MATSUNAGA and the Naito clan, whereupon Nagayori became lord of the castle and pursued the conquest of Tanba, but Nagoyori was really no more than a puppet of the Miyoshi administration, and, after the death of Nagayoshi, was killed in a fierce attack by Naomasa AKAI in August 1565.</e>
<cmt>構文問題。“a conquest” -&gt; “the conquest”.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>その後、内藤国貞の遺児・内藤貞勝が1573年に足利義昭と織田信長の決戦の際、京都に出陣し信長と戦っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, in the decisive battle between Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA and Nobunaga ODA in 1573, Sadakatsu NAITO, a son of the late Kunisada NAITO, went to Kyoto to fight with Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakatsu NAITO, a son of the late Kunisada NAITO, went to Kyoto to fight with Nobunaga ODA for the decisive battle between Nobunaga and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA in 1573,</e>
<cmt>Best to ignore &quot;later&quot; here, since the information in this sentence isn&apos;t directly connected with that of the preceding sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakatsu NAITO, a son of the late Kunisada NAITO, went to Kyoto to fight with Nobunaga ODA for the decisive battle between Nobunaga and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA in 1573,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その後も明智光秀の丹波経略に内藤氏も名を留めており、貞勝とする見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The one from the Naito clan who later joined Mitsuhide AKECHIi&apos;s conquest of Tamba was considered Sadakatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakatsu is also thought to be the member of the Naito clan who later joined the conquest of Tamba by Mitushide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was considered&quot; is not used like this. Reworked sentence using &quot;is thought to be&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakatsu is also thought to be the member of the Naito clan who later joined the conquest of Tanba by Mitushide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>Tamba→Tanba</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この貞勝がキリスト教を信仰した内藤如安となる（なお、如安は内藤宗勝の子ともいわれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was Sadakatsu who professed Christianity, and was later to become Joan NAITO. (In addition, Joan was said to be a son of Munekatsu NAITO.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Sadakatsu who professed Christianity, and was later to become Joan NAITO. (Joan is also said to be a son of Munekatsu NAITO.)</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;This was&quot; to &quot;It was&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Sadakatsu who professed Christianity, and was later to become Joan NAITO. (Joan is also said to be a son of Munekatsu NAITO.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>彼は豊臣秀吉に仕え、朝鮮出兵にも参戦、小西行長とともに講和交渉に活躍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, participated in the expeditionary forces to Korea, and made great efforts for peace negotiations with Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, was a member of the expeditionary force to Korea, and was involved in peace negotiations with Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt>Changed sentence to make it more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, was a member of the expeditionary force to Korea, and was involved in peace negotiations with Yukinaga KONISHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>のち、加賀藩に仕えるもキリスト教禁教令が発布された1614年、マニラに追放され、1626年同地で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he served the Kaga domain, but when the Ban on Christianity was imposed in 1614, he was exiled to Manila, and died there in 1626.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he served in the Kaga domain, but when the Ban on Christianity was imposed in 1614, he was exiled to Manila, and died there in 1626.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Then&quot; seems a little strange here. I think &quot;thereafter&quot; is better.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later served in the Kaga domain, but when the ban on Christianity was imposed in 1614, he was exiled to Manila where he remained until his death in 1626.</e>
<cmt>“Ban”→&quot;ban&quot; 布告された法律でない限り、大文字で始まる必要はなし。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>内藤氏(周防長門系)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Naito clan of Suo Nagato</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naito clan of Suo Nagato lineage</e>
<cmt>I added &quot;lineage&quot; to make it clear what Suo Nagato is.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naito clan of Suo Nagato lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>藤原氏藤原秀郷（又は藤原道長）の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A family of FUJIWARA no Hidesato-Fujiwara family or FUJIWARA no Michinaga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Naito clan was related to the Hidesato-Fujiwara of the FUJIWARA clan (or Michinaga of the FUJIWARA clan)</e>
<cmt>It is not clear what &quot;no&quot; means to a non-Japanese speaker. Also, I am not sure that the brackets can be left out here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Naito clan was related to the Hidesato-Fujiwara of the Fujiwara clan (or Fujiwara no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>藤原道長の表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>周防国に土着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It settled in the Province of Suo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It settled in the Province of Suo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It settled in Suo Province.</e>
<cmt>Suo Province に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>内藤盛貞の代に大内氏に仕え、室町時代中期以降は鷲頭氏に代わって長門国の守護代を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It served the Ouchi family during Morisada NAITO&apos;s time, and after the mid-Muromachi period, Morisada was appointed the shugodai of the province of Nagato in the place of the Washizu family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The generation of Morisada NAITO served the Ouchi family, but from the mid-Muromachi period onwards, members of the clan were appointed as shugodai of the province of Nagato in place of the Washizu family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;室町時代中期以降&quot; includes the mid-Muromachi period. I reworked the sentence with this in mind.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The generation of Morisada NAITO served the Ouchi family, but from the mid-Muromachi period onwards, members of the clan were appointed as shugodai of Nagato province in place of the Washizu family.</e>
<cmt>Nagato province に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>大内政弘に仕えた内藤弘矩、大内義興・大内義隆に仕えた内藤興盛が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hironori NAITO who served Masahiro OUCHI, and Okimori NAITO who served Yoshioki OUCHI and Yoshitaka OUCHI were prominent figures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hironori NAITO who served Masahiro OUCHI, and Okimori NAITO who served Yoshioki OUCHI and Yoshitaka OUCHI were prominent figures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hironori NAITO who served Masahiro OUCHI, and Okimori NAITO who served Yoshioki OUCHI and Yoshitaka OUCHI were prominent figures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>大内氏の滅亡と同時に興盛の孫の内藤隆世が自刃し、嫡流は断絶したが、興盛の五男の内藤隆春が毛利氏に仕えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the downfall of the Ouchi family, Takayo NAITO, a grandson of Okimori committed suicide by the sword, so the main line of the family was terminated, but Takaharu NAITO, Okimori&apos;s fifth son, served the Mouri family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayo NAITO, a grandson of Okimori, committed hara-kiri at the downfall of the Ouchi family, ending the main line of the family, but Takaharu NAITO, Okimori&apos;s fifth son, served the Mouri family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;suicide by the sword&quot; is unnatural. It is probably better to say hara-kiri (was there any other way to do it)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayo NAITO, a grandson of Okimori, committed seppuku at the downfall of the Ouchi clan, ending the main line of the family, but Takaharu NAITO, Okimori&apos;s fifth son, served the Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>“hara-kiri” -&gt; ”seppuku”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>毛利輝元の母が内藤氏の出身であったため重用されたが、その養子内藤元盛が大坂の陣で大坂城に入城したため子の内藤元珍らもともに切腹し没落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was entrusted with an important position because Terumoto MOURI&apos;s mother came from the Naito clan, but because his adopted son, Motomori NAITO, made a triumphal entry into the Osaka-jo Castle in the Siege of Osaka, he committed hara-kiri with his son, Motoyoshi NAITO, and ultimately, his family was declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was entrusted with an important position because Terumoto MOURI&apos;s mother came from the Naito clan, but when his adopted son, Motomori NAITO, made a triumphal entry into the Osaka-jo Castle in the Siege of Osaka, he was forced to commit hara-kiri with his son, Motoyoshi NAITO, and the fortunes of the family declined.</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence to make it more natural. Specifically, I changed &quot;because&quot; to &quot;when&quot;, judging that the the cause and effect relationship is implicit.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was entrusted with an important position because Terumoto MOURI&apos;s mother came from the Naito clan, but when his adopted son, Motomori NAITO, made a triumphal entry into the Osaka-jo Castle in the Siege of Osaka, he was forced to commit seppuku with his son, Motoyoshi NAITO, and the fortunes of the family declined.</e>
<cmt>“hara-kiri” -&gt; ”seppuku”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>以後は子孫が小禄の長州藩士として存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, his descendants had retained the family as a familysman with a small vassal of Choshu domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family line continued as vassals of the Choshu domain.</e>
<cmt>First translation is confusing. I have attempted a simplification.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family line continued as vassals of the Choshu domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>凡例　太字は当主、太線は実子、細線・二重線は養子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family tree: the head of the family indicated in bold letters; the biological child with a heavy line; the adopted child with a thin line or a double line</e>
<cmt>凡例→系図としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family tree: the head of the family is indicated in bold letters, biological children with heavy lines, and adopted children with thin or double lines</e>
<cmt>Changed singulars to plurals and omitted articles to make sentence more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family tree: the head of the family is indicated in bold letters, biological children with heavy lines, and adopted children with thin or double lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>内藤氏（三河系）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Naito clan of Mikawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naito clan of Mikawa lineage</e>
<cmt>see above comment</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naito clan of Mikawa lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>三河国の松平氏（徳川氏）の家臣で江戸時代に大名となった内藤氏は上述の丹波・周防の内藤氏と同祖とされるが、この間、戦国期までの事蹟は明らかではなく、仮冒の可能性も強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Naito clan, which was a vassal of the Matsudaira family (the Tokugawa family) in the Province of Mikawa, and became the daimyo (feudal lord) during the Edo period, was considered to share the common ancestors with the Naito clans of Tamba and Suo mentioned above, but there was a strong possibility that it was a fabricated pedigree because the history of the family to the Sengoku era (the Warring States period) was not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Naito clan, which was a vassal to the Matsudaira clan (the Tokugawa clan) in the Province of Mikawa and provided daimyo (feudal lords) during the Edo period, is documented to share ancestors with the Naito clans of Tamba and Suo mentioned above, but the history of the clan during the Sengoku period (the Warring States period) is not known, and there is strong possibility that the pedigree was fabricated.</e>
<cmt>The clan itself didn&apos;t become daimyo. I changed &quot;the clan… became the daimyo&quot; to &quot;the clan… provided daimyo&quot;. Also &quot;feudal lord&quot; is better in the plural. Also, I reworked the second half of the sentence to make it read better.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Naito clan, which was a vassal to the Matsudaira clan (the Tokugawa clan) in Mikawa Province and provided daimyo (feudal lords) during the Edo period, is documented to share ancestors with the Naito clans of Tanba and Suo mentioned above, but the history of the clan during the Sengoku period (the Warring States period) is not known, and there is strong possibility that the pedigree was fabricated.</e>
<cmt>Mikawa Province に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)から安土桃山時代にかけて、内藤清長・内藤正成・内藤家長・内藤信成らが徳川家康に仕え活躍し、その功績により江戸幕府の成立後は数家に分かれ譜代大名として隆盛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Sengoku period (Japan&apos;s Warring States period) to the Azuchi-Momoyama period, Kiyonaga NAITO, Masashige NAITO, Ienaga NAITO, and Nobunari NAITO served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and worked so hard that the family was granted to establish several branch families, which flourished as a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa House.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Sengoku period (Japan&apos;s Warring States period) to the Azuchi-Momoyama period, Kiyonaga NAITO, Masashige NAITO, Ienaga NAITO, and Nobunari NAITO served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and worked so hard that the family was granted the right to establish several branch families, which flourished and provided hereditary daimyo to the Tokugawa House.</e>
<cmt>Translation of &quot;として&quot; as &quot;as&quot; here is a bit forced. I have reworked the English to make it more natural. Also, see above comment about relationship between families and daimyo.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Sengoku period (Japan&apos;s Warring States period) to the Azuchi-Momoyama period, Kiyonaga NAITO, Masashige NAITO, Ienaga NAITO, and Nobunari NAITO served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and worked so hard that the family was granted the right to establish several branch families, which flourished and provided hereditary daimyo to the Tokugawa House.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>凡例　太字は当主、太線は実子、細線・二重線は養子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family tree: the head of the family indicated in bold letters; the biological child with a heavy line; the adopted child with a thin line or a double line</e>
<cmt>凡例→系図としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family tree: the head of the family is indicated in bold letters, biological children with heavy lines, and adopted children with thin or double lines</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family tree: the head of the family is indicated in bold letters, biological children with heavy lines, and adopted children with thin or double lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>内藤氏（甲斐系）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Naito clan of Kai lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naito clan of Kai lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naito clan of Kai lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>内藤氏には甲斐に土着した一派も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was the Naito clan&apos;s family which settled in Kai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Naito clan settled in Kai.</e>
<cmt>This is a simplification, but it fits with what went before (each separate Naito lineage is a &quot;clan&quot;)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the Naito Clan settled in Kai.</e>
<cmt>「一派も存在する」を訳出するため主語を「Some of the Naito Clan」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>代々武田氏に仕えたとされるが内藤虎資が武田信虎に殺害され一時断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It served the Takeda family for generations, but the family was discontinued for a while because Toramoto NAITO was killed by Nobutora TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It served the Takeda family for generations, but was discontinued temporarily when Toramoto NAITO was killed by Nobutora TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;for a while&quot; is better as &quot;temporarily&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It served the Takeda clan for generations, but was discontinued temporarily when Toramoto NAITO was killed by Nobutora TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>family→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>なお、武田二十四将の内藤昌豊（工藤祐長）の出自は工藤氏であり、実父の工藤虎豊は甲斐武田氏に仕えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Masatoyo NAITO (Sukenaga KUDO), who was one of the Twenty-Four Generals of the Takeda clan, came from the Kudo clan, and his father, Toratoyo KUDO served the Takeda family in Kai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatoyo NAITO (Sukenaga KUDO), who was one of the Twenty-Four Generals of the Takeda clan, was born into the Kudo clan, his father, Toratoyo KUDO serving the Takeda family in Kai.</e>
<cmt>&quot;In addition&quot; is unnatural here. &quot;なお&quot; can just be ignored.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatoyo NAITO (Sukenaga KUDO), who was one of the Twenty-Four Generals of the Takeda clan, was born into the Kudo clan, his father, Toratoyo KUDO serving the Takeda clan in Kai.</e>
<cmt>family→clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>一時小山田氏とともに油川信恵に味方したがのちに信恵を討った武田信虎に許され帰参する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temporarily, Toratoyo took Nobushige ABURAKAWA&apos;s side with the Oyamada family, but later, he was permitted to serve again Nobutora Takeda who defeated Nobushige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Toratoyo temporarily allied himself with the Oyamada clan and Nobushige ABURAKAWA, who fought against and lost to Nobutoru TAKEDA, he was allowed to return to service.</e>
<cmt>The first translation is very confusing. I have reworked it.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Toratoyo temporarily allied himself with the Oyamada clan and Nobushige ABURAKAWA, who fought against and lost to Nobutora TAKEDA, he was allowed to return to the Takeda family&apos;s service.</e>
<cmt>信虎のスペル訂正。「信虎に許され」という意味が出るように訳出し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>だがのちに信虎に疎まれ虎資とともに手討ちにされたため、祐長ら工藤氏一族は甲斐国を出奔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he was then treated coldly by Nobutora, and was put to death with TAKEDA, so the Kudo family&apos;s family including Sukenaga ran away from Kai-no-kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutora subsequently froze out Toratotyo and put him to death together with Toramoto, causing the Kudo clan family, including Sukenaga, Toratoyo&apos;s son, to flee Kai.</e>
<cmt>This sentence is easier to understand with Nobutora as the subject.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutora subsequently froze out Toratoyo and put him to death together with Toramoto, causing the Kudo clan family, including Sukenaga, Toratoyo&apos;s son, to flee Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>Toratoｔyo→Toratoyo、Kai→Kai Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>その後、信虎を追放した武田信玄によって、虎豊の遺児の祐長が呼び戻され所領を回復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Sukenaga, a son of the late Toratoyo, was called back by Shingen TAKEDA who exiled Nobutora, and regained his domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingen TAKEDA later exiled Nobutora and called back Sukenaga who regained the domain for the Kudo clan.</e>
<cmt>Moved explanation of Sukenaga to previous sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingen TAKEDA later exiled Nobutora and called back Sukenaga, a son of the late Toratoyo, who regained the domain for the Kudo clan.</e>
<cmt>a son of the late Toratoyoを追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>祐長は信玄の為に大いに活躍し、虎資の死後途絶えていた甲斐の名跡内藤氏の名乗りを与えられて「内藤昌豊」と名を改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukenaga worked so earnestly for Shingen that he was allowed to use the name of the Naito clan, the distinguished family in Kai, which had been discontinued since Toramoto&apos;s death, and subsequently, changed his name to &quot;Masatoyo NAITO.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukenaga worked so earnestly for Shingen that he was allowed to use the name of the Naito clan, the distinguished family in Kai, which had been discontinued since Toramoto&apos;s death, and subsequently changed his name to &quot;Masatoyo NAITO.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Removed comma after &quot;subsequently&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukenaga worked so earnestly for Shingen that he was allowed to use the name of the Naito clan, the distinguished family in Kai, which had been discontinued since Toramoto&apos;s death, and subsequently changed his name to &quot;Masatoyo NAITO.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>信玄の没後、昌豊は長篠の戦いで討死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Shingen&apos;s death, Masatoyo was killed in the Battle of Nagashino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Shingen&apos;s death, Masatoyo was killed in the Battle of Nagashino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Shingen&apos;s death, Masatoyo was killed in the Battle of Nagashino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>その跡は保科氏からの養子内藤昌月が継ぎ、以後は会津保科氏（のちの会津松平氏）に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Masaaki NAITO, an adopted child from the Hoshina family, carried on the family name, and served the Hoshina family in Aizu (later known as the Matsudaira family in Aizu) from that time on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Masaaki NAITO, an adopted child from the Hoshina clan, carried on the family name while serving Hoshina family in Aizu (later known as the Matsudaira family in Aizu).</e>
<cmt>It is too much to use both &quot;thereafter&quot; and &quot;from that time on&quot;. I have used &quot;Thereafter&quot; instead.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Masaaki NAITO, an adopted child from the Hoshina clan, carried on the family name while serving Hoshina family in Aizu (later known as the Matsudaira clan in Aizu).</e>
<cmt>family→clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>その他の内藤氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other Naito clans</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other Naito clans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other Naito clans</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>相模国にも内藤姓を名乗った一族が存在し（相模内藤氏）、この内藤氏も秀郷流を称するが定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family which claimed to be the Naito clan (the Sagami-Naito clan) and also identified itself as the Hidesato group existed in the Province of Sagami, but it was not certain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A family (the Sagami-Naito clan) which claimed to be of Naito clan and also identified itself as the Hidesato group existed in the Province of Sagami, but the origin of this family is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>Reworked first translation to make it more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A family (the Sagami-Naito clan) which claimed to be of Naito clan and also identified itself as the Hidesato group existed in Sagami Province, but the origin of this family is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>Sagami Province に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また、織田信長に仕えた内藤勝介なる人物もおり、こちらの出自は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was also a person called Katsusuke NAITO who served Nobunaga ODA, but his origin was not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was also a person called Katsusuke NAITO who served Nobunaga ODA, but his origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;was not known&quot; to &quot;is unknown&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was also a person called Katsusuke NAITO who served Nobunaga ODA, but his origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>若狭国の武田氏の被官にも内藤氏の一族が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the direct vassals of the Takeda family in the Province of Wakasa, there was also the Naito clan&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The direct vassals of the Takeda family in the Wakasa Province also included a Naito clan family.</e>
<cmt>Reworked first translation to make it more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The direct vassals of the Takeda clan in Wakasa Province also included a Naito clan family.</e>
<cmt>faimily→clan（氏）the Wakasa Provinceの the 不要</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Y.Sanada(id:36926), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Nevylax(id:38464), Raff(id:14006), Law soma(id:45202), Iwaro(id:60082), Takuan-Osyou(id:67158), Yanahan(id:2437), ヤトゥヒン(id:26570), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>