<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三善氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Miyoshi clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三善氏（みよしし）は、日本の姓氏の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan is one of the surname in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyoshishi is a Japanese surname.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miyoshi is one of clans in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元は渡来人系の一族であるが、実際には百済系の一族と漢族系の一族の2系統が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally a clan of toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese), and actually there exist the two lineages of the clan from Kudara (Baekje) and the clan of the Han race from China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This clan is descended from toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese), and actually has two distinct lineages, one Kudara (Baekje) lineage and one Han race lineate from China.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This clan is descended from toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese) with two distinct lineages, one from Kudara (Baekje) and the other of Han race from China.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ただし、後世において2つの系統が結び付けられているものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some people in later ages related the two lineages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later these lineages became intertwined.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later these lineages became intertwined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>百済系三善氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan of Kudara lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Miyoshi clan of Kudara lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan of Kudara lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>『新撰姓氏録』によれば、元は百済の速古大王の末裔で錦部首、後に錦部連を名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility),&quot; it was originally a descendant of King Sokgo in Kudara and identified itself as Nishikori no Obito, Nishigori no Muraji later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility),&quot; the Miyoshi clan was descended from King Sokgo in Kudara and had been named Nishikori no Obito, and later Nishigori no Muraji.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility), the Miyoshi clan was originally descended from King Sokgo in Kudara and had been named Nishikori no Obito, and later Nishigori no Muraji.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションの位置を買え、「元は」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>延暦年間の桓武天皇後宮に、錦部姉継・同弟姉という女官がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the kokyu (empress&apos;s residence) of the Emperor Kanmu in the Enryaku era, there were court ladies named NISHIGORI no Shikei and NISHIGORI no Teishi (弟姉).</e>
<cmt>「弟姉」の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the kokyu (empress&apos;s residence) of the Emperor Kanmu in the Enryaku era, there were court ladies named NISHIGORI no Shikei and NISHIGORI no Teishi (弟姉).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two of the consorts that Emperor Kanmu had between 782 and 806 were court ladies named NISHIGORI no Shikei and NISHIGORI no Teishi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。この場合の「後宮」は「a consort of the Emperor.」だと思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同24年（805年）頃にその一族が三善宿禰を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 805 the clan was bestowed the name of Miyoshi no Sukune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 805 the clan was bestowed the name of Miyoshi no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the year of 806, the name of Miyoshi no Sukune (third highest of the eight hereditary titles) was bestowed on the family of these court ladies.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>醍醐天皇の時代に三善清行が大学頭・文章博士を務めて参議まで至り、延喜3年（903年）頃にはカバネを宿禰から朝臣に改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the era of the Emperor Daigo, Kiyoyuki (or Kiyotsura) MIYOSHI was put in charge of Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education) and Monjo hakase (professor of literature) and assigned to Sangi (councilor), and its kabane (official status title) was changed from Sukune to Ason around 903.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the era of the Emperor Daigo, Kiyoyuki (or Kiyotsura) MIYOSHI was appointed Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education) and Monjo hakase (professor of literature), rising to the postion of Sangi (councilor), and the kabane (official status title) of the clan was changed from Sukune to Ason around 903.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the era of the Emperor Daigo, Kiyoyuki (or Kiyotsura) MIYOSHI was appointed Daigaku no kami (Director of the Bureau of Education) and Monjo hakase (professor of literature), rising to the position of Sangi (councilor), and the kabane (official status title) of the clan was changed from Sukune to Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) around 903.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>子として文章博士三善文江や式部省三善文明、僧侶の浄蔵・日蔵が知られるが、文明の子・三善道統が文章博士になったのを最後に歴史から姿を消す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fumie MIYOSHI who was Monjo hakase, Fumiaki MIYOSHI who worked for Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonial), Jozo and Nichizo who were priests, are known as his children, but this lineage disappeared from the history after Michimune MIYOSHI, a child of Fumiaki, became Monjo hakase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that Kikyoki&apos;s sons were Fumie MIYOSHI who became Monjo hakase, Fumiaki MIYOSHI who worked for Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonies), and Jozo and Nichizo who were priests, and that Fumiaki&apos;s son, Michimune MIYOSHI also became Fumiaki, but thereafter the lineage disappears from history.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyoyuki&apos;s sons include a Monjo hakase Fumie MIYOSHI, a Shikibu-sho (the Ministry of Ceremonies) official Fumiaki MIYOSHI, and the priests Jozo and Nichizo; and Fumiaki&apos;s son Michimune MIYOSHI who was also a Monjo hakase, was the last Miyoshi who left his mark in the history.</e>
<cmt>FBに基いて訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>漢族系三善氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan of the Han lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Miyoshi clan of the Han lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Miyoshi clan of the Han lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>『類聚符宣抄』によれば、元は漢の東海王の末裔であった波能志（はのし）の子孫で錦部村首、後に錦宿禰を名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Ruiju fusensho (A collection of official documents dating from the years 737 to 1093),&quot; it was originally a descendant of Hanoshi, who was the descendant of Prince of Donghai in Han, and identified itself as Nishikori no muraobito (錦部村首) and Nishiki no Sukune later.</e>
<cmt>「錦部村首」の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Ruiju fusensho (A collection of official documents dating from the years 737 to 1093),&quot; the founder was a descendant of Hanoshi, who was himself the descendant of Prince of Donghai in Han, and was known as Nishikori no Muraobito (錦部村首) later as Nishiki no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Ruiju Fusensho&quot; (a collection of official documents dating from the years 737 to 1093), the founder of this lineage of the Miyoshi was a descendant of Hanoshi, who was himself a descendant of Prince of Donghai in Han, named Nishikori no Muraobito (錦部村首) later as Nishiki no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>貞元 (日本)2年（977年）頃に三善朝臣の姓が授けられ、その1人であった三善茂明が主税寮兼算博士に就任し、その子孫は代々算博士を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 977, it was given the surname of Miyoshi Ason, and Shigeaki MIYOSHI, one of the clan, was assigned to Shuzeiryo (Bureau of Taxation) and sanhakase (a position teaching mathematics and growing mathematicians) and his descendant succeeded sanhakase through the ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 977, the clan was given the surname of Miyoshi Ason, and Shigeaki MIYOSHI, was appointed as Shuzeiryo (position in Bureau of Taxation) and sanhakase (a position with responsibilty for teaching mathematics and looking after mathematicians). Shigeaki descendants inherited the post of sanhakase for generations.</e>
<cmt>Split into two sentences.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the year of 977, the clan was given the surname of Miyoshi Ason, and among the members of the clan, Shigeaki MIYOSHI was appointed as Shuzeiryo (a position in Bureau of Taxation) in addition to Sanhakase (a position with responsibility for teaching mathematics and looking after mathematicians), the position that his descendants inherited for generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>茂明の孫の三善為長は、越中国出身の門人射水為康を養子に迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamenaga MIYOSHI, a grandchild of Shigeaki, adopted Tameyasu IMIZU, a student from the Etchu Province, as a son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamenaga MIYOSHI, a grandchild of Shigeaki, adopted Tameyasu IMIZU, a student from Etchu Province, as a son.</e>
<cmt>Removed &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeki&apos;s grandson Tamenaga MIYOSHI adopted Tameyasu IMIZU, a student from Etchu Province (present-day Toyama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>三善為康は算道・紀伝道に通じた学者として多くの著作を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tameyasu MIYOSHI left many works as a scholar of Sando (study of mathematics) and Kidendo (the study of the histories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tameyasu MIYOSHI left produced a number of important works as a scholar of Sando (mathematics) and Kidendo (history).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tameyasu MIYOSHI left a number of important works as a scholar of Sando (mathematics) and Kidendo (history).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その子孫である三善長衡以後、代々西園寺家家司を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nagahira MIYOSHI of his descendant, it had put in charge of Keishi (household superintendent) of the Saionji family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tameyasu&apos;s descendant Nagahira MIYOSHI and subsequent generations served as Keishi (household superintendent) for the Sainoji family.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tameyasu&apos;s descendant Nagahira MIYOSHI served as Keishi (household superintendent) for the Saionji family and it became a hereditary position.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>地下家官人の今小路家はその子孫とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imanokoji family, a government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) of Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace), was regarded as its descendant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendents of Nagahira are thought it be the Imanokoji family, government officials ranked as Jige-ke (non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace).</e>
<cmt>Cut down explanation for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imanokoji family of government officials ranked as Jige-ke (non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace) is believed to be the descendents of Nagahira.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>また、鎌倉幕府の初代問注所執事となった三善康信もこの一族とされ、子孫として町野氏・太田氏・飯尾氏・布施氏らが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Yasunobu MIYOSHI, the first head of Monchujo (Board of Inquiry) of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was also regarded as a member of this clan, and the Machino clan, the Ota clan, the Iio clan and the Fuse clan were included in its descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mihoshi clan also included Yasunobu MIYOSHI, the first head of Monchujo (Board of Inquiry) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and numbers the Machino clan, the Ota clan, the Iio clan and the Fuse clan among its descendants.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This lineage of the Miyoshi clan also included Yasunobu MIYOSHI, the first head of Monchujo (Board of Inquiry) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and his descendants include the Machino, Ota, Iio and Fuse clans.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>彼らは鎌倉幕府引付衆あるいは室町幕府奉行衆として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They played an active role as Hikitsukeshu (Coadjustor of the High Court) of the Kamakura bakufu or bugyoshu (group of magistrates) of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These clans an active role as Hikitsukeshu (Coadjustors of the High Court) in the Kamakura bakufu and Bugyoshu (groups of magistrates) in the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>It is not clear who &quot;彼ら&quot; refers to, but I have assumed it is the clans mentioned in 26.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These clans actively played roles of Hikitsukeshu (Coadjutors of the High Court) in the Kamakura bakufu and Bugyoshu (groups of magistrates) in the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>三善氏には2つの系統があり、紀伝道を世襲した三善氏と算道を世襲した三善氏は別系統であったのは史料等で明らかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two lineages of the Miyoshi clan, and it is clear that the Miyoshi clan who succeeded Kidendo and the Miyoshi clan who succeeded Sando originated from different lineages according to historical sources.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two Miyoshi clan lineages, and it is clear from historical sources that the generations of Miyoshi who devoted themselves to Kidendo (history) and the generations of Miyoshi clan who devoted themselves to Sando (mathematics) were from different lineages.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two Miyoshi clan lineages, and historical sources clearly indicate that the lineage that inherited Kidendo (history) and the other that inherited Sando (mathematics) were distinct from each other.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>が、後年後者の子孫は自己の学識の由来を高く見せるために高名な学者・公卿である三善清行と結び付けようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in later years, the descendants of the latter tried to relate Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI, a famous scholar and Kugyo (the top court officials), with them in order to make the origin of their knowledge seen more highly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, descendants of the latter tried claim Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI, a famous scholar and Kugyo (the top court officials), as one of their own to add prestige to their academic past.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, descendants of the latter tried to claim that they inherited their academic legacies from Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI, a famous scholar and Kugyo (the top court officials), to add prestige to their origin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>清行の次の世代に史 (律令制)を務めた錦良助（錦宿禰）を三善氏の旧姓である錦部首を名乗った後に錦宿禰を授けられた清行の子とし、その子錦連行を三善茂明の父として位置づける系図を作成した（『諸家系図纂』所収「南家系図」など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They made such a family tree as considering Ryosuke NISHIKI (Nishiki no Sukune) who was in charge of shi (a recorder in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code)) in the next generation of Kiyoyuki as a child of Kiyoyuki, who identified himself as Nishikori no Obito (an original family name of the Miyoshi clan) and was given Nishiki no Sukune later, and regarding his son Tsurayuki NISHIKI as the father of Shigeaki MIYOSHI (&apos;the family tree of the South family&apos; in the &quot;Shoka keizusan (the genealogies of the various families)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To this end a family tree was drawn with Ryosuke NISHIKI (Nishiki no Sukune), who became Shi (recorder in the Ritsuryo system) in the generation after Kiyoyuki, depicted as Kiyoyuki&apos;s son under the name of Nishikori no Obito (an original family name of the Miyoshi clan) and later Nishiki no Sukune, and Ryosuke&apos;s son Tsurayuki NISHIKI as the father of Shigeaki MIYOSHI (&apos;the family tree of the South family&apos; in the &quot;Shoka keizusan (the genealogies of the various families)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>錦部首を名乗った後に錦宿禰を授けられた清行の子としWho took on these names, Kiyoyuki or the guy who was positioned as Kiyoyuki&apos;s son?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They fabricated family trees (such as &apos;the family tree of the South family&apos; in the &quot;Shoka keizusan&quot; (the genealogies of the various families)) depicting that Ryosuke NISHIKI (Nishiki no Sukune), who became Sadaishi (senior recorder of junior fifth rank) in the next generation of Kiyoyuki, as Kiyoyuki&apos;s son under the name of Nishikori no Obito (an original family name of the Miyoshi clan) who later received the title of Nishiki no Sukune; and Ryosuke&apos;s son Tsurayuki NISHIKI as the father of Shigeaki MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>だが、錦連行の実在性は確かではなく、実在人物である錦良助と三善清行・三善茂明との血縁関係の有無も不明である（勿論、「三善清行－錦良助－錦連行－三善茂明」という茂明を清行の曾孫とする系譜は事実ではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the existence of Tsurayuki NISHIKI is not sure and the blood relationship between Ryosuke NISHIKI, who was a real person, and Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI and Shigeaki MIYOSHI is also unknown (of course, the family tree which shows Shigeaki as the great-grandson of Kiyoyuki such as &apos;Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI - Ryosuke NISHIKI - Tsurayuki NISHIKI - Shigeaki MIYOSHI.&apos; is not true).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the existence of Tsurayuki NISHIKI uncertain and the blood relationship between Ryosuke NISHIKI, who did exist, and Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI and Shigeaki MIYOSHI is unknown (and the family tree which depicts Shigeaki as the great-grandson of Kiyoyuki with the relationship &apos;Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI - Ryosuke NISHIKI - Tsurayuki NISHIKI - Shigeaki MIYOSHI&apos; is certainly false).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is uncertain, however, whether Tsurayuki NISHIKI really existed, and whether Ryosuke NISHIKI, who did exist, was related to Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI and Shigeaki MIYOSHI (and it is certainly not true to state that Shigeaki was a great-grandson of Kiyoyuki as depicted in the family line of &apos;Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI - Ryosuke NISHIKI - Tsurayuki NISHIKI - Shigeaki MIYOSHI&apos;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、三善康信が為康の血縁であることは間違いないと考えられているが、系譜上為康の子・康信の父とされる三善康光（康久）についての詳細は不明で実際に為康と康信がどのような血縁関係にあるのか定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is considered to be a true that Yasunobu MIYOSHI was a relative of Tameyasu, but the detail of Yasumitsu (Yasuhisa) MIYOSHI who was considered as the son of Tameyasu and the father of Yasunobu on the family tree, is not clear, and the actual blood relationship between Tameyasu and Yasunobu is not sure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought to be true that Yasunobu MIYOSHI was a relative of Tameyasu, but there is little detail about Yasumitsu (Yasuhisa) MIYOSHI who is depicted as the son of Tameyasu and the father of Yasunobu on the family tree, and the nature of the relationship between Tameyasu and Yasunobu is therefore uncertain.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is highly plausible that Yasunobu MIYOSHI was a relative of Tameyasu, little details are known about Yasumitsu (Yasuhisa) MIYOSHI who was depicted on the family tree as a son of Tameyasu and the father of Yasunobu; therefore, the nature of the relationship between Tameyasu and Yasunobu is uncertain.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 超プロ住民(id:279825), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>