<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>澤家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sawa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>澤家（さわけ）は、清原氏の流れを汲む堂上家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sawa family was a toshoke (the hereditary lineage of court nobles allowed to enter the tenjonoma in the palace) in the line of the Kiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sawa family was a toshoke (within the hereditary lineage of court nobles allowed to enter the tenjonoma in the palace) down line of the Kiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sawa family was a toshoke (within the hereditary lineage of court nobles allowed to enter the tenjonoma in the palace) down line of the Kiyohara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>伏原宣幸（のぶゆき）（正二位・大蔵省）（1637年-1705年）の次男沢忠量（ただかず）（従二位・衛門府）（1637年-1754年）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of the family was Tadakazu SAWA (Junii (Junior Second Rank, Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards))(1673-1754) who was the second son of Nobuyuki FUSEHARA (Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Okurasho (Ministry of Finance)(1637-1705)</e>
<cmt>沢忠量の生年は1637年ではなく(父親と同じということはあり得ません)、1673年のようなのでそのように訂正して表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the family was Tadakazu SAWA (Junii - Junior Second Rank, Emonfu - Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards) (1673-1754) the second son of Nobuyuki FUSEHARA (Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Okurasho (Ministry of Finance) (1637-1705)</e>
<cmt>punctuation, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the family was Tadakazu SAWA (Junii - Junior Second Rank, Emonfu - Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards) (1673-1754) the second son of Nobuyuki FUSEHARA (Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Okurasho [Ministry of Finance]) (1637-1705).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を[]に変更文末にピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>幕末には澤為量・澤宣嘉父子が勤皇攘夷派の急先鋒として活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last days of Tokugawa Shogunate, Tamekazu SAWA and his son, Nobuyoshi SAWA actively worked as vanguards of sonnojoi ha (supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate, Tamekazu SAWA and his son, Nobuyoshi SAWA actively worked as vanguards of the sonnojoi ha (supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate, Tamekazu SAWA and his son, Nobuyoshi SAWA actively worked as vanguards of the sonnojoi ha (supporters of the doctrine of restoring the emperor and expelling the barbarians).</e>
<cmt>文末にピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は30石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was 30 koku (approx. 5.4 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was thirty koku (approx. 5.4 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was 30 koku (approx. 5.4 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>明治時代以降は為量・宣嘉父子の功績が認められ伯爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Meiji Period, count as a result of appreciation for achievements of Tamekazu and his son, Nobuyoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Meiji Period, they were given the title count in appreciation for the achievements of Tamekazu and his son, Nobuyoshi</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Meiji Period, they were given the title count in appreciation for the achievements of Tamekazu and his son, Nobuyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kaba(id:17904), 輝く水(id:65241), Charenji(id:7908), 水野白楓(id:22811), ウラヌス(id:25954), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>