<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高倉家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house of Takakura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house of Takakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takakura family</e>
<cmt>house of→family</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高倉家（たかくらけ）は藤原北家である藤原長良の子孫である藤原範賢の子高倉永季（ながすえ）（位階・参議）（1338年 - 1392年）を祖とする堂上家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house of Takakura, one of the houses of Dojo, was established by Nagasue TAKAKURA (Court Rank, Councillor, 1338-1392) whose father was FUJIWARA no Norikata, a descendant of FUJIWARA no Nagayoshi of the Fujiwara Hoku family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house of Takakura, one of the houses of Dojo, was established by Nagasue TAKAKURA (Court Rank, Councillor, 1338-1392) whose father was FUJIWARA no Norikata, a descendant of FUJIWARA no Nagayoshi of the the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;Fujiwara Hoku family&quot; to &quot;the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan&quot; as per term list of July 31st.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takakura family, one of the families of Dojo, was established by Nagasue TAKAKURA (Court Rank, Councillor, 1338 - 1392) whose father was FUJIWARA no Norikata, a descendant of FUJIWARA no Nagayoshi of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>house of→familyハイフンの前後にスペースthe重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>長良の系統は藤原北家の主流から大きく外れ、永季の父藤原範賢までは六位蔵人を務める地下官人だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayoshi&apos;s family line was extremely out of the mainstream of the Fujiwara Hoku family, and the house of Takakura was ranked as a common courtier, serving as the Chamberlain of Sixth Court Rank till the time of FUJIWARA no Norikata, Nagasue&apos;s father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayoshi&apos;s family line was a long way from the main line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and the house of Takakura was ranked as a common courtier, serving as the Chamberlain of Sixth Court Rank till the time of FUJIWARA no Norikata, Nagasue&apos;s father.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;Fujiwara Hoku family&quot; to &quot;the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan&quot; as per term list of July 31st.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayoshi&apos;s family line was a long way from the main line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and the Takakura family was ranked as a common courtier, serving as the Chamberlain of Sixth Court Rank till the time of FUJIWARA no Norikata, Nagasue&apos;s father.</e>
<cmt>house of→family</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし高倉永季（ながすえ）は衣文道を以って後光厳天皇・後円融天皇・後小松天皇の3代にわたって仕え、その功により公卿の仲間入りを果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Nagasue TAKAKURA served three Emperors, such as Emperor Gokogon, Emperor Goenyu, and Emperor Gokomatsu to teach &quot;Emondo,&quot; the style of the costumes, and consequently, the family was ranked as the Court nobles for its services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nagasue TAKAKURA served three generations of Emperor, Emperor Gokogon, Emperor Goenyu, and Emperor Gokomatsu, teaching &quot;Emondo,&quot; the style of costumes, and the family was promoted to the Court nobility for its services.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nagasue TAKAKURA served three generations of Emperor, the Emperor Gokogon, the Emperor Goenyu, and the Emperor Gokomatsu, teaching &quot;Emondo,&quot; the style of costumes, and the family was promoted to the Court nobility for its services.</e>
<cmt>句点不必要。 &quot;Emondo,&quot; -&gt; &quot;Emondo&quot;, -&gt; OK&quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>高倉永季の子の高倉永行（位階・参議）（生年不詳 - 1416年）以降は足利将軍家の衣文道の指導にも当たり、朝廷での有職故実を山科家にも伝授した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the time of Nagasue TAKAKURA&apos;s son, Nagayuki TAKAKURA (Court Rank, Councillor, date of birth unknown -1416), the family taught &quot;Emondo&quot; to the Ashikaga shogunate, and gave instruction in the court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette to the house of Yamashina.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the time of Nagasue TAKAKURA&apos;s son, Nagayuki TAKAKURA (Court Rank, Councillor, date of birth unknown -1416) onwards, the family taught &quot;Emondo&quot; to the Ashikaga shogunate, and gave instruction in the court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette to the house of Yamashina.</e>
<cmt>&quot;以降&quot; includes the time of Nagayuki Takakura. I have changed the sentence accordingly.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the time of Nagasue TAKAKURA&apos;s son, Nagayuki TAKAKURA (Court Rank, Councillor, date of birth unknown - 1416) onwards, the family taught Emondo to the Ashikaga shogunate, and gave instruction in the court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette to the Yamashina family.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入原文に『』のない&quot;　&quot;を削除house of→family</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これが衣文道の高倉流・山科流の始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the opening of the Takakura and the Yamashina schools of Emondo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the beginning of the Takakura and the Yamashina schools of Emondo.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;is the opening&quot; to &quot;was the beginning&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the beginning of the Takakura and the Yamashina schools of Emondo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の高倉永相（ながすけ）（1530年 - 1585年）は最後の室町幕府将軍・足利義昭とともに二条城で織田信長と対決したが敗北し、信長に投降した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Warring States period (Japan), Nagasuke TAKAKURA (1530-1585) fought against Nobunaga ODA in the Nijo Castle under Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the last Shogun of the Muromachi shogunate, but he was defeated and surrendered to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Warring States period (Japan), Nagasuke TAKAKURA (1530-1585) fought against Nobunaga ODA in Nijo-jo Castle under Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the last Shogun of the Muromachi shogunate, but he was defeated and surrendered to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;Nijo Castle&quot; to &quot;Nijo-jo&quot; castle as is conventional.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Warring States period (Japan), Nagasuke TAKAKURA (1530 - 1585) fought against Nobunaga ODA in Nijo-jo Castle under Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the last Shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), but he was defeated and surrendered to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンの前後にスペーススペース削除shogunate→bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして後に許されて位階・権大納言となり、これ以降の高倉家の当主の極官となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he was allowed to become the Court Rank, Junior Chief Councillor of State, which was the top rank the house of Takakura&apos;s head could attain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he ascended to the Court Rank of Junior Chief Councillor of State, which was the top rank the head of the house of Takakura would attain.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he ascended to the Court Rank of Junior Chief Councillor of State, which was the top rank the head of the Takakura family would attain.</e>
<cmt>house of→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代は代々徳川将軍家の衣装調達や衣文道の指導にも当たり、江戸滞在の折には各大名家で有職故実や衣文道の知識を広めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, the family supplied costumes and taught &quot;Emondo&quot; for the Tokugawa shogunate for generations, and when the family stayed in Edo, it gave each feudal lord the knowledge of court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette as well as &quot;Emodo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, the family supplied costumes and instructed the Tokugawa shogunate in &quot;Emondo&quot; for generations, and, when staying in Edo, worked to spread the knowledge &quot;Emondo&quot; and other court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette among the feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>Changed for readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, the family supplied costumes and instructed the Tokugawa shogunate in Emondo for generations, and, when staying in Edo, worked to spread the knowledge of Emondo and other court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette among the feudal lords.</e>
<cmt>of が抜けている。 “knowledge Emondo” -&gt; “knowledge of Emondo”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>家格は半家で極官は位階・権大納言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was ranked as &quot;Hanke,&quot; a type of family status of the Court nobles, and the top rank the family could attain was the Court Rank, Junior Chief Councillor of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was ranked as &quot;Hanke,&quot; a type of family status in the Court nobility, with the top rank attained being the Court Rank, Junior Chief Councillor of State.</e>
<cmt>Changed to eliminate repetition of &quot;the family&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was ranked as &quot;Hanke,&quot; a type of family status in the Court nobility, with the top rank attained being the Court Rank, Junior Chief Councillor of State.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は812石、明治時代以降は子爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hereditary stipend was 812 koku in the Edo period, and after the Meiji period, the family was given the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hereditary stipend was 812 koku in the Edo period, and from the Meiji period onwards, the family held the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>明治時代以降includes the meiji period.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hereditary stipend was 812 koku in the Edo period, and from the Meiji period onwards, the family held the title of viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="11">
<j>高倉家伝来の古文書・典籍・装束などは、現在（旧名「高倉文化研究所」）に所蔵されており、同研究所は伝統保持のための運動を地道に進めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancient documents, books and costumes that had been handed down in the house of Takakura are now in the possession of the Takakura Culture Institute (former name), and this insutitute are making steady efforts to preserve the tradition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ancient documents, books and costumes that have been handed down through the generations in the house of Takakura are now in the possession of the Takakura Cultural Institute (former name), which is making steady efforts to preserve the traditions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Takura Culture Institute&quot; better as &quot;Takura Cultural Institute&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ancient documents, books and costumes that have been handed down through the generations in the Takakura family are now in the possession of the Takakura Cultural Institute (former name), which is making steady efforts to preserve the traditions.</e>
<cmt>house of→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Iwaro(id:60082), 黒砂糖(id:38164), Kaba(id:17904), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), BAKU(id:55205), ウラヌス(id:25954), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>