<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>春日家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kasuga Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kasuga Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kasuga Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>春日家（かすがけ）は、公家の家名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kasuga family was one of Japan&apos;s noble families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kasuga family was one of Japan&apos;s noble families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kasuga family was one of Japan&apos;s noble families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>春日家（宇多源氏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kasuga family (of the Uda Genji (Minamoto clan))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kasuga family (of the Uda Genji (Minamoto clan))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kasuga family (of the Uda Genji [Minamoto clan])</e>
<cmt>カッコを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>宇多源氏五辻家流で源時方の後裔である地下家の家名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were a family of jige (lower-ranking courtiers) descended from MINAMOTO no Tokikata of the Itsutsuji line of the Uda Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were a family of jige (lower-ranking courtiers) descended from MINAMOTO no Tokikata of the Itsutsuji line of the Uda Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were a family of jige (lower-ranking courtiers) descended from MINAMOTO no Tokikata of the Itsutsuji line of the Uda Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>久我家の家人であった源仲基を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also claim MINAMOTO no Nakamoto, who was a house retainer of the Koga family, as an ancestor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also claim MINAMOTO no Nakamoto, who was a house retainer of the Koga family, as an ancestor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also claim MINAMOTO no Nakamoto, who was a house retainer of the Koga family, as an ancestor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>室町時代には春日仲興・春日仲重と二代続けて従三位に昇り公卿を輩出するが、二度に亘り断絶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the family turned out great numbers of noblemen, and notably Nakaoki KASUGA and Nakashige KASUGA, representing two generations in a row, ascended as far as the junior third rank at court, but these two generations having passed, the family line died out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, the family turned out great numbers of noblemen, and notably Nakaoki KASUGA and Nakashige KASUGA, representing two generations in a row, ascended as far as the junior third rank at court, but these two generations having passed, the family line died out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the family turned out great numbers of noblemen, and notably Nakaoki KASUGA and Nakashige KASUGA, representing two generations in a row, ascended as far as the junior third rank at court, but these two generations having passed, the family line died out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代に入り春日仲見が地下家として再興し、代々久我家諸大夫を勤めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But then in the Edo period Nakami KASUGA revived the family line as a jige (lower-ranking courtier) family, and for generations thereafter family members served the Koga family as high stewards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But then in the Edo period Nakami KASUGA revived the family line as a jige (lower-ranking courtier) family, and for generations thereafter family members served the Koga family as high stewards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But then in the Edo period Nakami KASUGA revived the family line as a jige (lower-ranking courtier) family, and for generations thereafter family members served the Koga family as high stewards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>春日家（村上源氏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kasuga family (of the Murakami Genji (Minamoto clan))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kasuga family (of the Murakami Genji (Minamoto clan))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kasuga family (of the Murakami Genji [Minamoto clan])</e>
<cmt>カッコを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>村上源氏北畠家流で北畠親房の子北畠顕信（春日左少将）、及び春日顕時（春日中将）（親房の子または親房の弟冷泉持房の孫）が春日を号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akinori KITABATAKE (the Kasuga Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of the Palace Guards)), the son of Chikafusa KITABATAKE of the Kitabatake line of the Murakami Genji (Minamoto clan), as well as Akitoki KASUGA (the Kasuga Chujo (Middle Captain), who was either Chikafusa&apos;s son or younger brother, and was of the lineage of Mochifusa REIZEI), both took the name &quot;Kasuga.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akinori KITABATAKE (the Kasuga Sashosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of the Palace Guards)), the son of Chikafusa KITABATAKE of the Kitabatake line of the Murakami Genji (Minamoto clan), as well as Akitoki KASUGA (the Kasuga Chujo (Middle Captain), who was either Chikafusa&apos;s son or younger brother, and was of the lineage of Mochifusa REIZEI), both took the name &quot;Kasuga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akinobu KITABATAKE (the Kasuga Sashosho [Minor Captain of the Left Division of the Palace Guards]), the son of Chikafusa KITABATAKE of the Kitabatake line of the Murakami Genji (Minamoto clan), as well as Akitoki KASUGA (the Kasuga Chujo [Middle Captain], who was either Chikafusa&apos;s son or younger brother, and was of the lineage of Mochifusa REIZEI), both took the name &quot;Kasuga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Akinori→Akinobu,カッコを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、春日顕国（春日侍従）（源国信の後裔源顕行の子か）も同様に春日を号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Akikuni KASUGA (the Kasuga Jiju (chamberlain), who may have been the son of MINAMOTO no Akiyuki, who himself was the descendant of MINAMOTO no Kuninobu) also took the name &quot;Kasuga.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Akikuni KASUGA (the Kasuga Jiju (chamberlain), who may have been the son of MINAMOTO no Akiyuki, who himself was the descendant of MINAMOTO no Kuninobu) also took the name &quot;Kasuga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Akikuni KASUGA (the Kasuga Jiju [chamberlain], who may have been the son of MINAMOTO no Akiyuki, who himself was the descendant of MINAMOTO no Kuninobu) also took the name &quot;Kasuga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>カッコを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>それぞれ南北朝時代 (日本)に南朝 (日本)方の武将として転戦したが、南朝の衰微により中央貴族としての子孫は残らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All three of these men were heavily involved in fighting as military commanders on the side of the Southern Court during Japan&apos;s Period of Northern and Southern Courts; when the Southern Court fell into decline, they all, as noblemen central to the Southern Court&apos;s existence, were unable to leave behind any descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All three of these men were heavily involved in fighting as military commanders on the side of the Southern Court during Japan&apos;s Period of Northern and Southern Courts; when the Southern Court fell into decline, they all, as noblemen central to the Southern Court&apos;s existence, were unable to leave behind any descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All three of these men were heavily involved in battles as military commanders on the side of the Southern Court during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan); when the Southern Court fell into decline, they all, as noblemen central to the Southern Court&apos;s existence, were unable to leave behind any descendants.</e>
<cmt>fighting→battles と修正しました。Japan&apos;s Period of Northern and Southern Courts→the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>春日家（藤原北家魚名流）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kasuga family (of the Uona line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kasuga family (of the Uona line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kasuga family (of the Uona line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan)</e>
<cmt>Fujiwara family→Fujiwara clan と修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>藤原北家魚名流六条家庶流で、藤原顕輔の曾孫藤原家季を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coming from a branch line of the Rokujo family, itself of the Uona line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family, the family claims descent from FUJIWARA no Iesue, the great-grandson of FUJIWARA no Akisuke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coming from a branch line of the Rokujo family, itself of the Uona line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family, the family claims descent from FUJIWARA no Iesue, the great-grandson of FUJIWARA no Akisuke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coming from a branch line of the Rokujo family, itself of the Uona line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, the family claims descent from FUJIWARA no Iesue, the great-grandson of FUJIWARA no Akisuke.</e>
<cmt>Fujiwara family→Fujiwara clan と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉時代に家季・季範・顕範と三代に亘り公卿に列したが、南北朝時代に断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kamakura period three generations, namely Iesue, Suenori, and Akinori, all were ranked among the court nobility, but in the Period of Northern and Southern Courts their family line died out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kamakura period three generations, namely Iesue, Suenori, and Akinori, all were ranked among the court nobility, but in the Period of Northern and Southern Courts their family line died out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kamakura period three generations, namely Iesue, Suenori, and Akinori, all were ranked among the court nobility, but in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts their family line died out.</e>
<cmt>the Period of Northern and Southern Courts→the period of the Northern and Southern Courts</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Snap55(id:89773), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>