<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>竹内家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeuchi family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeuchi family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeuchi family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>竹内家（たけのうちけ）は公家のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeuchi family was a court noble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takeuchi family were a court nobles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takeuchi family were a court noble.</e>
<cmt>nobles→noble</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Original family name was Minamoto (the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original family name was Minamoto (the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original family name was Genji (the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>Minamoto→Genji （〇〇源氏が次に出てくるため、ここで原文どおり Genji としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>いわゆる堂上源氏で家系は清和源氏の一家系 河内源氏の傍流 甲斐源氏の平賀氏の一族の流れである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was so-called dojo genji and a line of the Hiraga clan, which belonged to Kai-Genji, which was a branch of Kawachi-Genji, which belonged to Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were the so-called dojo genji and were down line line of the Hiraga clan, that belonged to Kai-Genji, a branch of Kawachi-Genji, that belonged to Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were the so-called dojo genji and were down line of the Hiraga clan, that belonged to Kai-Genji, a branch of Kawachi-Genji, that belonged to Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>line 一つ削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>久我家の諸大夫であった竹内季治（1518年 - 1571年：正三位・大膳職）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of the family was Sueharu TAKENOUCHI (1518-1571; Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank), Daizenshiki (Office of the Palace Table)) who was a shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo) of the Kuga family..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the family was Sueharu TAKENOUCHI (1518-1571; Shosanmi - Senior Third Rank), Daizenshiki (Office of the Palace Table) who was a shodaibu (aristocrat lower than Kugyo) of the Kuga family..</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the family was Sueharu TAKENOUCHI (1518-1571; Shosanmi - Senior Third Rank), Daizenshiki (Office of the Palace Table) who was a shodaibu (aristocrat lower than Kugyo) of the Kuga family..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>室町幕府将軍家（足利氏）の執奏によって堂上家に加えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was added to toshoke through recommendation by shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Ashikaga clan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was added to toshoke upon recommendations by the shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Ashikaga clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was added to toshoke (the hereditary lineage of court nobles allowed to enter the tenjonoma in the palace) upon recommendations by the shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (Ashikaga clan).</e>
<cmt>幕府、堂上家の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>竹内惟庸は冷泉流の歌道の名人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koretsune TAKENOUCHI was a master of waka poetry of Reizei school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koretsune TAKENOUCHI was a master of waka poetry from the Reizei school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koretsune TAKENOUCHI was a master of waka poetry from the Reizei school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>次代、惟永以降、冷泉家一門からの養子が続き、和歌の家となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the next generation, Korenaga, adopted children form the Reizei family continued and this family became the house of waka poetry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the next generation, Korenaga, adopted children from the Reizei family and this family became the house of waka poetry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the next generation, Korenaga, adopted children from the Reizei family and this family became the house of waka poetry.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>家格は半家 (公家)、家業は弓術と笙と和歌。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family status was hanke (lowest rank for toshoke)(noble) and the family businesses were the art of Japanese archery, sho (Japanese flute) and waka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family status was hanke (lowest rank for toshoke) (noble) and the family businesses were the art of Japanese archery, sho (Japanese flute), and waka.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family status was hanke (a kind of family status of the Court nobles) (kuge [court noble]) and the family businesses were the art of Japanese archery, sho (Japanese flute), and waka.</e>
<cmt>半家、公家の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>極官は正三位非参議であったが、孝治(惟庸の祖父)、惟庸、惟永は従二位に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyokkan (the highest rank to which one can be appointed) was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Hisangi (advisor at large), but Takaharu (grandfather of Koretsune), Koretsune and Korenaga were promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyokkan (the highest rank to which one can be appointed) was Shosanmi (Senior Third Rank) and Hisangi (advisor at large), but Takaharu (grandfather of Koretsune), Koretsune and Korenaga were promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyokkan (the highest rank to which one can be appointed) was Shosanmi and Hisangi (advisor at large), but Takaharu (grandfather of Koretsune), Koretsune and Korenaga were promoted to Junii (Junior Second Rank).</e>
<cmt>既出単語の説明削除Koretsune の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は187石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) in the Edo Period was 187 koku (approx. 33.7 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karoku (hereditary stipend) during the Edo Period was 187 koku (approx. 33.7 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) during the Edo Period was 187 koku (approx. 33.7 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>明治時代以降は子爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Meiji Period, viscount</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Meiji Period, they held the title viscount</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Meiji Period, they held the title viscount.</e>
<cmt>文末にピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kaba(id:17904), 海衛士(id:19229), Himazin(id:22034), Iwaro(id:60082), BAKU(id:55205), Snap55(id:89773), ウラヌス(id:25954), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>