<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大炊御門家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oinomikado family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oinomikado family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oinomikado family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大炊御門家（おおいのみかどけ）は、清華家の家格を有する公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oinomikado family was a kuge (court noble) with kakaku (family status) of seigake (the second highest family status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oinomikado family were kuge (court nobles) with kakaku (family status) of seigake (the second highest family status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oinomikado family were kuge (court nobles) with kakaku (family status) of seigake (the second highest family status for court nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>家業は書道・和歌・笛・装束。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family businesses were shodo (calligraphy), waka (tanka), fue (Japanese flute) and shozoku (costume).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their family businesses were shodo (calligraphy), waka (tanka), fue (Japanese flute) and shozoku (costume).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their family businesses were shodo (calligraphy), waka (a 31-syllable Japanese poem), fue (Japanese flute) and shozoku (costume).</e>
<cmt>tanka→a 31‐syllable Japanese poem</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は400石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karoku in the Edo Period was 400 koku (approx. 72.2 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karoku during the Edo Period was 400 koku (approx. 72.2 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karoku (hereditary stipend) during the Edo Period was 400 koku (approx. 72.2 cubic meters).</e>
<cmt>家禄の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家紋は菱に片喰草。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its kamon (family crest) is Hishi ni Katabamiso crest (diamond and cuckooflower).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its kamon (family crest) is Hishi ni Katabamiso crest (diamond and cuckooflower).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its kamon (family crest) is Hishi ni Katabamiso crest (diamond and cuckooflower).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>侯爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Marquis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marquis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marquis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原北家藤原師実流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Fujiwara no Morozane line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were within the Fujiwara no Morozane line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were within the Fujiwara no Morozane line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>平安時代末期摂政関白藤原師実の子藤原経実（1068年-1131年）を祖として創立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was founded in the last days of the Heian Period by FUJIWARA no Tsunezane (1068-1131), who was a son of FUJIWARA no Morosane, Sessho Kanpaku (regent and chief adviser to the Emperor), as the founder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was founded during the last days of the Heian Period by FUJIWARA no Tsunezane (1068-1131), who was a son of FUJIWARA no Morosane, Sessho Kanpaku (regent and chief adviser to the Emperor), as the founder.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was founded during the last days of the Heian Period by FUJIWARA no Tsunezane (1068-1131), who was a son of FUJIWARA no Morozane, Sessho Kanpaku (regent and chief adviser to the Emperor), as the founder.</e>
<cmt>Morosane→Morozane</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大炊御門北、万里小路東に邸宅があったため大炊御門を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As his mansion was located in Oinomikado-kita (north of Oinomikado) and Madenokoji-higashi (east of Madenokoji), he named himself Oinomikado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his mansion was located in Oinomikado-kita (north of Oinomikado) and Madenokoji-higashi (east of Madenokoji), he named himself Oinomikado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his mansion was located in Oinomikado-kita (north of Oinomikado) and Madenokoji-higashi (east of Madenokoji), he named himself Oinomikado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>経実は大納言どまりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Tsunezane&apos;s highest rank was dainagon (a chief councillor of state).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunezane&apos;s highest rank was dainagon (chief councillor of state).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunezane&apos;s highest rank was dainagon (chief councillor of state).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、その子藤原経宗（1119年-1189年）は平治の乱で当初藤原信頼・源義朝方に付きながら寝返って平清盛方の勝利に貢献。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his son, FUJIWARA no Tsunemune (1119-1189), on the occasion of Heiji Disturbance, contributed to the victory of TAIRA no Kiyomori side by first joining FUJIWARA no Nobuyori/MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo side at first and changing side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外措置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his son, FUJIWARA no Tsunemune (1119-1189), on the occasion of the Heiji Disturbance, contributed to the victory of the TAIRA no Kiyomori side by first joining the FUJIWARA no Nobuyori/MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo side at first and then changing sides.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his son, FUJIWARA no Tsunemune (1119-1189), on the occasion of the Heiji War, contributed to the victory of the TAIRA no Kiyomori side by first joining the FUJIWARA no Nobuyori/MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo side at first and then changing sides.</e>
<cmt>Disturbance→War</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、二条天皇の外舅として勢威をふるい、左大臣に昇って清華家の家格を確保した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he wielded great power as maternal father of the Emperor Nijo and he was promoted to sadaijin (Minister of the left) and secured kakaku of segake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he wielded great power as the maternal father of Emperor Nijo and he was promoted to sadaijin (Minister of the left) and secured kakaku of segake.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he wielded great power as the maternal father of Emperor Nijo and he was promoted to sadaijin (Minister of the left) and secured kakaku of seigake.</e>
<cmt>segake→seigake</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>経宗の子藤原頼実（1155年-1225年）は二度に渡って太政大臣を務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunemune&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Yorizane (1155-1225) took the position of Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister) twice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunemune&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Yorizane (1155-1225) took the position of Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister) twice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemune&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Yorizane (1155-1225) took the position of Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister) twice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>明治維新後、大炊御門幾麿（いくまろ）の代に侯爵を授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, the position of marquis was conferred on this family in the generation of Ikumaro OINOMIKADO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the position of marquis was conferred on this family during the generation of Ikumaro OINOMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the position of marquis was conferred on this family during the generation of Ikumaro OINOMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Gimbrow(id:65660), 左衛門三郎(id:132836), Andee(id:20421), 伏儀(id:142093), 伊(id:146699), 主水(id:200976), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>