<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徳川氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokugawa Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokugawa Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokugawa Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徳川氏（德川氏、とくがわし）は、徳川家康が創始した日本の名字。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokugawa clan name was created by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa clan name was created by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa clan name was created by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>信憑性に乏しいが、系図上では新田氏系得川氏の末裔ということにされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whilst the veracity is doubtful, it is said that descendants come from the Egawa Clan of the Nitta Clan branch that sits at the top of the family tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whilst the veracity is doubtful, it is said that descendants come from the Egawa Clan of the Nitta Clan branch that sits at the top of the family tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whilst the veracity is doubtful, it is said that descendants come from the Egawa clan of the Nitta clan branch that sits at the top of the family tree.</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>発祥の地は、上野国新田郡得川郷（現・群馬県太田市徳川）とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan had its origins in Tokugawa hamlet, Nitta county in Kozuke Province (present day Tokugawa, Oda City, Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan had its origins in Tokugawa hamlet, Nitta county in Kozuke Province (present day Tokugawa, Oda City, Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan had its origins in Tokugawa hamlet, Nitta County in Kozuke Province (present day Tokugawa, Ota City, Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>徳川家康に始まる徳川氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokugawa Clan Commenced by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa Clan Commenced by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa clan commenced by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>徳川氏は、徳川家康が創始した名字。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">`Tokugawa` is the family name used by the clan commenced by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">`Tokugawa` is the family name used by the clan commenced by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokugawa&apos; is the family name used by the clan commenced by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>系図によると、ルーツは三河国（愛知県）の在地領主の松平氏に婿養子に入った時宗の遊行僧と伝えられる徳阿弥である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the family tree, the clan roots supposedly come from Tokuami who was a wandering Buddhist priest who became an adopted son of the of the Matsudaira Clan, the feudal lords of Mikawa Province (present day Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the family tree, the clan roots supposedly come from Tokuami who was a wandering Buddhist priest who became an adopted son of the of the Matsudaira Clan, the feudal lords of Mikawa Province (present day Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the family tree, the Tokugawa clan is supposedly descended from Tokuami, a wandering Buddhist priest who married into the Matsudaira clan, which ruled Mikawa Province (present day Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>重複削除全角削除用語統一「婿養子に入る」は単に養子になるのとは違うので、marry into the Mtsudaira clanとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>浪人となり、大浜称名寺 (碧南市)で開かれた連歌会での出会いが信重の養子に入るきっかけと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon becoming a Ronin (a wandering masterless samurai), legend has it that a chance meeting at a poetry reading held at Ohamashomyo-ji temple (Hekinan City) lead to him becoming an adopted son of Nobushige</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon becoming a Ronin (a wandering masterless samurai), legend has it that a chance meeting at a poetry reading held at Ohamashomyo-ji temple (Hekinan City) lead to him becoming an adopted son of Nobushige</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon becoming a Ronin (a wandering masterless samurai), legend has it that a chance meeting at a poetry reading held at Ohamashomyo-ji Temple (Hekinan City) lead to him becoming an adopted son of Nobushige.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除用語統一ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（父祖の地上野国新田郡徳川郷の時宗寺院、徳川満徳寺は後に縁切寺とされた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(His ancestor&apos;s temples (Jishu-jiin [Jodo (Pure Land) sect] and Tokugawa Mantoku-ji temple) located in Tokugawa hamlet, Nitta county in Kozuke Province later on became Engiri-ji temple (a refuge for women seeking divorce).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(His ancestor&apos;s temples (Jishu-jiin [Jodo (Pure Land) sect] and Tokugawa Mantoku-ji temple) located in Tokugawa hamlet, Nitta county in Kozuke Province later on became Engiri-ji temple (a refuge for women seeking divorce).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(His ancestor&apos;s temples (Jishu-jiin [Jodo (Pure Land) sect] and Tokugawa Mantoku-ji Temple) located in Tokugawa hamlet, Nitta County in Kozuke Province later on became Engiri-ji temple (a refuge for women seeking divorce).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>還俗して松平親氏と名のったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On his return to secular life he went by the name of Chikauji MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his return to secular life he went by the name of Chikauji MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On his return to secular life he went by the name of Chikauji MATSUDAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、諸国を流浪する遊行僧だの、入り婿に入っただのという設定は、所詮本来無関係な新田氏と松平氏を系譜上つなげるために、おそらく家康の代に唱えられた創作に過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said he adopted the name of a wife during his sojourns between various provinces as an itinerant monk and, to link himself with the pedigree of the Nitta and Matsudaira clans (which at the end of the day, he bore no relation to) ultimately, it is conceivable he created the so-called Ieyasu generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said he adopted the name of a wife during his sojourns between various provinces as an itinerant monk and, to link himself with the pedigree of the Nitta and Matsudaira clans (which at the end of the day, he bore no relation to) ultimately, it is conceivable he created the so-called Ieyasu generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story of this Buddhist priest wandering from one province to the next and his marriage into the Matsudaira clan is probably just a fictional story that was created during Ieyasu&apos;s generation in order to establish a genealogically link with the Nitta clan and the Matsudaira clan, which were originally unrelated.</e>
<cmt>「つなげる」のは新田氏と松平氏であること。「入り婿に入る」は単に he adopted the name of a wifeにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>要するに親氏以前の確かな系譜はわからないのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In short, any pedigree prior to Chikauji is not known for sure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In short, any pedigree prior to Chikauji is not known for sure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In short, any pedigree prior to Chikauji is not known for sure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>松平親氏を初代とする松平家九代（安祥松平家六代）の家康が起こした親氏流松平氏嫡流である徳川将軍家（徳川宗家）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking Chikauji MATSUDAIRA as the first generation, Ieyasu emerges as the 9th Matsudaira generation (6th generation of the Yasuyoshi MATSUDAIRA family) who founded the Tokugawa shogun family dynasty (eldest son lineage of the Chikauji branch of the Matsudaira Clan) who in turn formed the head family of the clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking Chikauji MATSUDAIRA as the first generation, Ieyasu emerges as the 9th Matsudaira generation (6th generation of the Yasuyoshi MATSUDAIRA family) who founded the Tokugawa shogun family dynasty (eldest son lineage of the Chikauji branch of the Matsudaira Clan) who in turn formed the head family of the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking Chikauji MATSUDAIRA as the first generation, Ieyasu emerges as the 9th Matsudaira generation (6th generation of the Yasuyoshi MATSUDAIRA family) who founded the Tokugawa shogun family dynasty (eldest son lineage of the Chikauji branch of the Matsudaira clan) who in turn formed the head family of the clan.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのほかに徳川姓を許されるのは、家康直系の子孫（親藩）のうちでも特に徳川御三家（尾張徳川家・紀州徳川家・水戸徳川家）、御三卿（田安徳川家・一橋徳川家・清水徳川家）およびこれらの後嗣のみであり、これらの家に養子として入る者も家康の男系の子孫たちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides this, also included as recognized heirs to the Tokugawa name are Ieyasu`s offspring who are direct descendents (ie part of the family domain) and in particular, the 3 major households of the Tokugawa family (Owari Tokugawa household, Kishu Tokugawa household and Mito Tokugawa household) as well as their heirs and, individuals adopted into the family were also considered as part of Ieyasu`s male lineage.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides this, also included as recognized heirs to the Tokugawa name are Ieyasu`s offspring who are direct descendents (ie part of the family domain) and in particular, the 3 major households of the Tokugawa family (Owari Tokugawa household, Kishu Tokugawa household and Mito Tokugawa household) as well as their heirs and, individuals adopted into the family were also considered as part of Ieyasu`s male lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides this, also included as recognized heirs to the Tokugawa name are Ieyasu&apos;s offspring who are direct descendents (ie part of the family domain) and in particular, the three privileged branches of Tokugawa family (Owari Tokugawa family, Kishu Tokugawa family and Mito Tokugawa family), the three branches of Tokugawa family (Tayasu Tokugawa family, Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family and Shimizu Tokugawa family) as well as their heirs and, individuals adopted into the family were also considered as part of Ieyasu&apos;s male lineage.</e>
<cmt>赤字部分訳漏れ対応しました。Household→familythe 3 major families of the Tokugawa family→three branches of Tokugawa family`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>「徳川」創称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origins of the name `Tokugawa`</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origins of the name `Tokugawa`</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origins of the name &apos;Tokugawa&apos;</e>
<cmt>`→&apos;</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>永禄9年（1566年）、朝廷の許可を得て、家康個人が「徳川」に「復姓」（事実上の改姓）し、従五位下三河国に叙任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1566, Ieyasu obtained the consent of the imperial court to use `Tokugawa` as his hereditary surname (in actual fact a change of name) and was invested with the imperial court rank of Jugoige (Lower Junior Fifth Rank) of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1566, Ieyasu obtained the consent of the imperial court to use `Tokugawa` as his hereditary surname (in actual fact a change of name) and was invested with the imperial court rank of Jugoige (Lower Junior Fifth Rank) of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1566, Ieyasu obtained the consent of the imperial court to use &apos;Tokugawa&apos; as his hereditary surname (in actual fact a change of name) and was invested with the imperial court rank of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除用語統一`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このとき正親町天皇は前例のない申請に対して躊躇したが、新田氏系得川氏が「藤原氏」を称した前例が公家の奔走により見つかり、許可された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time, Emperor Ogimachi hesitated over this unprecedented petition however, permission was granted based on the efforts of nobles working behind-the-scenes who found that the Nitta branch of the Egawa Clan was purported to be part of the dynastic Fujiwara Clan (which had close ties to the court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, Emperor Ogimachi hesitated over this unprecedented petition however, permission was granted based on the efforts of nobles working behind-the-scenes who found that the Nitta branch of the Egawa Clan was purported to be part of the dynastic Fujiwara Clan (which had close ties to the court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, Emperor Ogimachi hesitated over this unprecedented petition however, permission was granted based on the efforts of nobles working behind-the-scenes who found that the Nitta branch of the Egawa clan was purported to be part of the dynastic Fujiwara clan (which had close ties to the court).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このため当時の記録に「藤原家康」の署名が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, there are documents remaining from that time signed by `Ieyasu FUJIWARA`.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, there are documents remaining from that time signed by `Ieyasu FUJIWARA`.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, there are documents remaining from that time signed by &apos;Ieyasu FUJIWARA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>慶長8年（1603年）に家康が源氏長者・征夷大将軍に任ぜられるときには、「清和源氏」となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1603, when Ieyasu took charge of the extended Minamoto family/became unifying expeditionary shogun (commander-in-chief) he became part of the `Seiwa Minamoto&apos; Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1603, when Ieyasu took charge of the extended Minamoto family/became unifying expeditionary shogun (commander-in-chief) he became part of the `Seiwa Minamoto&apos; Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1603, when Ieyasu took charge of the extended Minamoto family/became seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) he became part of the &apos;Seiwa-Genji&apos; (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>ここで重要なのは、松平一族が徳川に改姓したのではなく、「徳川」は家康個人のみに許される称号であったことである（嫡男の松平信康については、名乗った説とそうでない説がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is important about this event is, not that the Matsudaira family (in entirety) changed its name to Tokugawa but rather, Ieyasu was the sole individual permitted to use the surname `Tokugawa` and as such, opinion is divided whether his eldest son (Nobuyasu MATSUDAIRA) appropriated the Tokugawa name, or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is important about this event is, not that the Matsudaira family (in entirety) changed its name to Tokugawa but rather, Ieyasu was the sole individual permitted to use the surname `Tokugawa` and as such, opinion is divided whether his eldest son (Nobuyasu MATSUDAIRA) appropriated the Tokugawa name, or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is important about this event is, not that the Matsudaira family (in entirety) changed its name to Tokugawa but rather, Ieyasu was the sole individual permitted to use the surname &apos;Tokugawa&apos; and as such, opinion is divided whether his eldest son (Nobuyasu MATSUDAIRA) appropriated the Tokugawa name, or not.</e>
<cmt>`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>「徳川」姓は、家康個人が松平氏内部で専制権力を確立して松平一族と家臣団を統制するために使われたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The `Tokugawa` surname established Ieyasu&apos;s autocratic powers within the Matsudaira Clan and as such, it is thought Ieyasu exploited the entire Matsudaira Clan and framework of retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The `Tokugawa` surname established Ieyasu&apos;s autocratic powers within the Matsudaira Clan and as such, it is thought Ieyasu exploited the entire Matsudaira Clan and framework of retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Tokugawa&apos; surname established Ieyasu&apos;s autocratic powers within the Matsudaira clan and as such, it is thought Ieyasu exploited the entire Matsudaira clan and framework of retainers.</e>
<cmt>用語統一`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>初代家康が慶長10年（1605年）に将軍職と当主の座を辞して隠居するまでに徳川姓を称したのは、世子の徳川秀忠ただ一人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1605, the founder Ieyasu stood down from his roles as shogun and family head and until his retirement use of the `Tokugawa` surname was limited to one individual: his heir Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1605, the founder Ieyasu stood down from his roles as shogun and family head and until his retirement use of the `Tokugawa` surname was limited to one individual: his heir Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1605, the founder Ieyasu stood down from his roles as shogun and family head and until his retirement use of the &apos;Tokugawa&apos; surname was limited to one individual: his heir Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>公認される限り十一人いた家康の男子で徳川姓を許されたのは、三男で世子の秀忠、及び御三家の祖となる九男徳川義直・十男徳川頼宣・十一男徳川頼房の4名にすぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of the Tokugawa name was limited to 11 individuals who were Ieyasu`s male heirs of which only 4 took the name: Hidetada (3rd son and successor), Yoshinao TOKUGAWA (forefather of one of the 3 main families and 9th son), Yorinobu TOKUGAWA (10th son) and, Yorifusa TOKUGAWA (11th son).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Use of the Tokugawa name was limited to 11 individuals who were Ieyasu`s male heirs of which only 4 took the name: Hidetada (3rd son and successor), Yoshinao TOKUGAWA (forefather of one of the 3 main families and 9th son), Yorinobu TOKUGAWA (10th son) and, Yorifusa TOKUGAWA (11th son).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only 4 of Ieyasu&apos;s 11 officially recognized male heirs were allowed to take the surname &apos;Tokugawa&apos;: Hidetada (his 3rd son and successor), Yoshinao TOKUGAWA (his 9th son, and the forefather of one of the three main families), Yorinobu TOKUGAWA (his 10th son), and Yorifusa TOKUGAWA (his 11th son).</e>
<cmt>赤字部分の意味がずれていると思われるため、変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>後の3名は、秀忠が二代当主（将軍）になって以後に元服したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of the 3 subsequent individuals, after Hidetada became the 2nd generation clan head (Shogun) his coming-of-age ceremony was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the 3 subsequent individuals, after Hidetada became the 2nd generation clan head (Shogun) his coming-of-age ceremony was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the 3 subsequent individuals, after Hidetada became the 2nd generation clan head (Shogun) his coming-of-age ceremony was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>清和源氏を称した事情</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Circumstances Surrounding the Naming of the Seiwa Minamoto Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Circumstances Surrounding the Naming of the Seiwa Minamoto Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Circumstances surrounding the naming of the Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>用語統一文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>徳川氏の系譜は、系図上は清和源氏の新田氏の支流得川氏の末裔と位置付けられており、従って本姓は源姓であり、源朝臣という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tokugawa Clan pedigree sitting at the top of the family tree is the Egawa Clan branch (decedents of Nitta Clan of the Seiwa Minamoto Clan) and accordingly the original family name is said to have been either; the Minamoto surname or Minamoto no Ason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tokugawa Clan pedigree sitting at the top of the family tree is the Egawa Clan branch (decedents of Nitta Clan of the Seiwa Minamoto Clan) and accordingly the original family name is said to have been either; the Minamoto surname or Minamoto no Ason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tokugawa clan pedigree sitting at the top of the family tree is the Egawa clan branch (decedents of Nitta clan of the Seiwa-Genji) and accordingly the original family name is said to have been either; the Minamoto surname or Minamoto no Ason.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一説には、当初朝廷の許可では徳川氏は源氏ではなく藤原氏の氏族として認められていたが、家康が江戸幕府を開くに当たって、幕府の長たる征夷大将軍は源氏という慣例があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory is that the initial imperial court consent was approved on the basis that the Tokugawa Clan was of Fujiwara Clan (rather than Minamoto Clan) stock however, when Ieyasu set up the Edo Bakufu (Shogunate) the convention was that a Minamoto Clan member be the Shogunate&apos;s leading unifying Shogun (commander-in-chief).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory is that the initial imperial court consent was approved on the basis that the Tokugawa Clan was of Fujiwara Clan (rather than Minamoto Clan) stock however, when Ieyasu set up the Edo Bakufu (Shogunate) the convention was that a Minamoto Clan member be the Shogunate&apos;s leading unifying Shogun (commander-in-chief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory is that the initial imperial court consent was approved on the basis that the Tokugawa clan was of Fujiwara clan (rather than Minamoto clan) stock however, when Ieyasu set up the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) the convention was that a Minamoto clan member be the Shogunate&apos;s leading unifying Shogun (commander-in-chief).</e>
<cmt>用語統一’→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そのために、系図の粉飾が行われたのだとも言うが、実はそれより先の1567年に三河守を受領するために、すでに系図の粉飾が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As such, it can be said there was some window dressing of the family tree for this reason or, subsequently in 1567 there was embellishment to the pedigree to secure an appointment as Governor of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As such, it can be said there was some window dressing of the family tree for this reason or, subsequently in 1567 there was embellishment to the pedigree to secure an appointment as Governor of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As such, it can be said there was some window dressing of the family tree for this reason or, subsequently in 1567 there was embellishment to the pedigree to secure an appointment as Governor of Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>三河守を受領する前の家康の官位は蔵人佐という低いものであったが、三河統一を成し遂げ名実とともに三河の支配者となった時点で、三河守受領のために必要な位階を家康は持っていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to the posting as Governor of Mikawa Province, Ieyasu`s official rank was a lowly kurandonosuke (assistant official of kurodo) however, although he accomplished the unification of Mikawa, at the time he became the virtual ruler of Mikawa, Ieyasu lacked the necessary rank to be posted as Governor of Mikawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to the posting as Governor of Mikawa Province, Ieyasu`s official rank was a lowly kurandonosuke (assistant official of kurodo) however, although he accomplished the unification of Mikawa, at the time he became the virtual ruler of Mikawa, Ieyasu lacked the necessary rank to be posted as Governor of Mikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the posting as Governor of Mikawa Province, Ieyasu&apos;s official rank was a lowly kurandonosuke (assistant official of kurodo) however, although he accomplished the unification of Mikawa, at the time he became the virtual ruler of Mikawa, Ieyasu lacked the necessary rank to be posted as Governor of Mikawa.</e>
<cmt>全角削除`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>三河守受領の為の位階は従五位下に相当するが、当時の慣例では、従五位下の位階を与えられる姓の系統は限られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To obtain the Mikawa Governor post, it was customary at that time to hold a rank of equivalent to a Jugoige (Lower Junior Fifth Rank) however, there were rigid hereditary family line limitations to who was awarded Jugoige rank.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To obtain the Mikawa Governor post, it was customary at that time to hold a rank of equivalent to a Jugoige (Lower Junior Fifth Rank) however, there were rigid hereditary family line limitations to who was awarded Jugoige rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To obtain the Mikawa Governor post, it was customary at that time to hold a rank of equivalent to a Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) however, there were rigid hereditary family line limitations to who was awarded Jugoinoge rank.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>祖父松平清康がかつて世良田氏（得川氏の同族）の末裔であると主張している故事に倣って、「松平氏は得川氏の末裔」説を唱えはじめ、系図を新田氏につなげたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To address this, the stance was to firstly emphasize the historical fact that &apos;the Egawa Clan are descended from the Matsudaira Clan&apos; and they were decedents following in the lineage of Kiyomasa MATSUDAIRA (as grandfather) who was once part of the Serata Clan (same family lineage as the Egawa Clan) and, that the Nitta Clan were linked in the family tree.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To address this, the stance was to firstly emphasize the historical fact that &apos;the Egawa Clan are descended from the Matsudaira Clan&apos; and they were decedents following in the lineage of Kiyomasa MATSUDAIRA (as grandfather) who was once part of the Serata Clan (same family lineage as the Egawa Clan) and, that the Nitta Clan were linked in the family tree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To address this, the stance was to firstly emphasize the historical fact that &apos;the Egawa clan are descended from the Matsudaira clan&apos; and they were decendents following in the lineage of Kiyomasa MATSUDAIRA (as grandfather) who was once part of the Serata clan (same family lineage as the Egawa clan) and, that the Nitta clan were linked in the family tree.</e>
<cmt>用語統一decedents →decendents ’→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>足利氏でなく新田氏を選んだのは、隣接する今川氏が足利一門の名門で、足利系統の系譜に精通していた事が原因といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for selecting the Nitta Clan instead of the Ashikaga Clan is because the celebrated Imagawa Clan formed part of the Ashikaga Clan and, knowledge of the Ashikaga pedigree was the main cause.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for selecting the Nitta Clan instead of the Ashikaga Clan is because the celebrated Imagawa Clan formed part of the Ashikaga Clan and, knowledge of the Ashikaga pedigree was the main cause.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the reason the Nitta clan was selected instead of the Ashikaga clan was because the neighboring Imagawa clan was familiar with the family tree of the Ashikaga lineage as they were part of the distinguished Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>「隣接する」訳漏れに対応しました。「といわれている」の訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし、同時代史料による限り、3代信光は賀茂氏姓を名乗っており、おそらくこれが松平氏の最も古い本姓であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, whilst limited to historical records of the day, 3rd generation Nobumitsu assumed the Kamo Clan family name and perhaps, this is the oldest original surname of the Matsudaira Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, whilst limited to historical records of the day, 3rd generation Nobumitsu assumed the Kamo Clan family name and perhaps, this is the oldest original surname of the Matsudaira Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, whilst limited to historical records of the day, 3rd generation Nobumitsu assumed the Kamo clan family name and perhaps, this is the oldest original surname of the Matsudaira clan.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかしこの姓では、官位受領などで不利に扱われると考えたのか、すでに信光のころから源姓を称しており、家康は若い頃はむしろ藤原姓を称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However whether it is because it was thought that this surname would be disadvantageous in dealing with the issue of confirming official rank or, at some stage from Nobumitsu&apos;s time onwards he took this original family name, either way Ieyasu was known by the Fujiwara surname from a young age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However whether it is because it was thought that this surname would be disadvantageous in dealing with the issue of confirming official rank or, at some stage from Nobumitsu&apos;s time onwards he took this original family name, either way Ieyasu was known by the Fujiwara surname from a young age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However whether it is because it was thought that this surname would be disadvantageous in dealing with the issue of confirming official rank or, at some stage from Nobumitsu&apos;s time onwards he took this original family name, either way Ieyasu was known by the Fujiwara surname from a young age.</e>
<cmt>`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>徳川と松平</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokugawa &amp; Matsudaira</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokugawa &amp; Matsudaira</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokugawa and Matsudaira</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>徳川家康個人の男系子孫たる徳川氏諸家は、松平の名乗りのみを認められた家康子孫の諸松平家（越前松平家・会津松平家等）とともに親藩を構成していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The core domain was formed using only Ieyasu TOKUGAWA`s personal male descendents or various families of the Tokugawa Clan and, together with Ieyasu`s descendents allowed to use the Matsudaira surname.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The core domain was formed using only Ieyasu TOKUGAWA`s personal male descendents or various families of the Tokugawa Clan and, together with Ieyasu`s descendents allowed to use the Matsudaira surname.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The core domain was formed using only Ieyasu TOKUGAWA&apos;s personal male descendents or various families of the Tokugawa clan and, together with Ieyasu&apos;s descendents allowed to use the Matsudaira surname such as Echizen Matsudaira family and Aizu Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>用語統一赤字部分訳漏れ対応しました。`→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>江戸時代の約270年に渡って日本の支配層として君臨した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They formed the ruling class which controlled Japan for the duration of the Edo period: approximately 210 years,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They formed the ruling class which controlled Japan for the duration of the Edo period: approximately 210 years,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They formed the ruling class which controlled Japan for the duration of the Edo period: approximately 270 years,</e>
<cmt>数字修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>明治維新の後も、徳川氏は武家の最上流として華族に遇せられ,宗家は公爵、御三家は侯爵、御三卿は伯爵に列せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being an elite samurai family the Tokugawa Clan was treated as nobles even after the Meiji Restoration with a line of priority: the family head as a Duke, the 3 main families as Marquis, and heads of the 3 families as Counts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being an elite samurai family the Tokugawa Clan was treated as nobles even after the Meiji Restoration with a line of priority: the family head as a Duke, the 3 main families as Marquis, and heads of the 3 families as Counts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being an elite samurai family the Tokugawa clan was treated as nobles even after the Meiji Restoration with a line of priority: the family head as a Duke, the 3 main families as Marquis, and heads of the 3 families as Counts.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また第15代将軍だった徳川慶喜は宗家から別家して徳川慶喜家を創設し、同じく公爵を授けられて伝統的な地位を保った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the 15th generation Shogun, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was removed from the main family home to another residence and Yoshinobuke TOKUGAWA installed, appointed as a Duke and held onto the traditional position.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the 15th generation Shogun, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was removed from the main family home to another residence and Yoshinobuke TOKUGAWA installed, appointed as a Duke and held onto the traditional position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the 15th generation Shogun, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA was removed from the main family home to another residence and Yoshinobuke TOKUGAWA installed, appointed as a Duke and held onto the traditional position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>現在、徳川家康の子孫で徳川を姓とする家は次の9家とその別家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently the descendents of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and families using the Tokugawa name can be divided into the following 9 separate families:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently the descendents of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and families using the Tokugawa name can be divided into the following 9 separate families:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently the descendents of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and families using the Tokugawa name can be divided into the following 9 separate families:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>徳川将軍家（将軍家。徳川宗家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokugawa Samurai Families (Shogun family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokugawa Samurai Families (Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokugawa Shogun Families (Shogun family. Original Tokugawa Family)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が別々になっていたのでひとつにまとめました。Samurai →Shogun</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="38">
<j>尾張徳川家（御三家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owari Tokugawa Household (three major households)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owari Tokugawa Household (three major households)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owari Tokugawa family (three major familys)</e>
<cmt>Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="39">
<j>紀州徳川家（　〃　）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kishu Tokugawa Household (ditto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishu Tokugawa Household (ditto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishu Tokugawa family (ditto)</e>
<cmt>Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="40">
<j>水戸徳川家（　〃　）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mito Tokugawa Household (ditto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mito Tokugawa Household (ditto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mito Tokugawa family (ditto)</e>
<cmt>Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="41">
<j>一橋徳川家（御三卿）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitotsubashi Tokugawa Household (3 Counts)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitotsubashi Tokugawa Household (3 Counts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitotsubashi Tokugawa family (3 Counts)</e>
<cmt>Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="42">
<j>田安徳川家（　〃　）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tayasu Tokugawa Household (ditto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tayasu Tokugawa Household (ditto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tayasu Tokugawa family (ditto)</e>
<cmt>Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="43">
<j>清水徳川家（　〃　）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimizu Tokugawa Household (ditto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimizu Tokugawa Household (ditto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimizu Tokugawa family (ditto)</e>
<cmt>Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>徳川慶喜家（宗家別家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA Household (removed from the original family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA Household (removed from the original family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA family (removed from the original family)</e>
<cmt>Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="45">
<j>松戸徳川家（水戸徳川家分家）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsudo Tokugawa household (branch family of the Mito Tokugawa Household)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsudo Tokugawa household (branch family of the Mito Tokugawa Household)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsudo Tokugawa family (branch family of the Mito Tokugawa family)</e>
<cmt>Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="46">
<j>現在の子孫は、徳川・松平一門の会に所属し、その会員数は約600名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently descendants of the entire Tokugawa/Matsudaira clan belong to an association with approximately 600 members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently descendants of the entire Tokugawa/Matsudaira clan belong to an association with approximately 600 members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently descendants of the entire Tokugawa/Matsudaira clan belong to an association with approximately 600 members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="47">
<j>他方、次の家は絶家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the following households have become extinct:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the following households have become extinct:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the following families have become extinct:</e>
<cmt>households→families</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>近年の研究では徳川姓ではなく、松平氏を名乗っていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In research in recent years it is not the Tokugawa surname that appears but, the Matsudaira name that appears.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In research in recent years it is not the Tokugawa surname that appears but, the Matsudaira name that appears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In research in recent years it is not the Tokugawa surname that appears but, the Matsudaira name that appears.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="49">
<j>駿河徳川家（当主徳川忠長が切腹して断絶。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suruga Tokugawa Household (ending with the ritual suicide of the household head Tadanaga TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suruga Tokugawa Household (ending with the ritual suicide of the household head Tadanaga TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suruga Tokugawa family (ending with the ritual suicide of the family head Tadanaga TOKUGAWA.)</e>
<cmt>)補足Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="50">
<j>甲府徳川家（御両典）（二代当主徳川家宣が六代将軍を継いだため消滅。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kofu Tokugawa Household (referred as &quot;Goryoden&quot;) (lapsed when 2nd generation clan chief Takanobu TOKUGAWA inherited the role of 6th generation Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofu Tokugawa Household (referred as &quot;Goryoden&quot;) (lapsed when 2nd generation clan chief Takanobu TOKUGAWA inherited the role of 6th generation Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofu Tokugawa family (referred as &quot;Goryoden&quot;) (lapsed when 2nd generation clan chief Ienobu TOKUGAWA inherited the role of 6th generation Shogun.)</e>
<cmt>人名修正)補足Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="51">
<j>館林徳川家（御両典）（当主徳川綱吉が五代将軍を継いだため消滅。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatebayashi Tokugawa Household (referred as &quot;Goryoden&quot;) (lapsed when 5th generation clan chief Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA inherited the role of 5th generation Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatebayashi Tokugawa Household (referred as &quot;Goryoden&quot;) (lapsed when 5th generation clan chief Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA inherited the role of 5th generation Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatebayashi Tokugawa family (referred as &quot;Goryoden&quot;) (lapsed when 5th generation clan chief Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA inherited the role of 5th generation Shogun.</e>
<cmt>Household→family</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="52">
<j>2003年、徳川宗家第18代当主徳川恒孝は、宗家の貴重な遺産を管理するために、財団法人徳川記念財団を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2003, Tsunenari TOKUGAWA (18th generation clan chief of the Original Tokugawa family line) established the Tokugawa Memorial Foundation (徳川記念財団) to manage the precious Tokugawa legacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2003, Tsunenari TOKUGAWA (18th generation clan chief of the Original Tokugawa family line) established the Tokugawa Memorial Foundation (徳川記念財団) to manage the precious Tokugawa legacy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2003, Tsunenari TOKUGAWA (18th generation clan chief of the Original Tokugawa family line) established the Tokugawa Memorial Foundation to manage the precious Tokugawa legacy.</e>
<cmt>(徳川記念財団)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>恒孝の長男・徳川家広は、両親に猛反対されたがベトナム人女性と結婚したと報道された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">News reports have appeared of Iehiro (Tsunenari`s eldest son) marrying a Vietnamese woman which was vehemently opposed by his parents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">News reports have appeared of Iehiro (Tsunenari`s eldest son) marrying a Vietnamese woman which was vehemently opposed by his parents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">News reports have appeared of Iehiro (Tsunenari`s eldest son) marrying a Vietnamese woman which was vehemently opposed by his parents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dfabdsosdgs(id:228055), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Nnh(id:474), ノトス(id:42992), Aotake(id:34929), Charenji(id:7908), Annogoo(id:127074), KurmUmy(id:202680), 陽一(id:92099), 藤太(id:82705), 佐渡のこあら販売機(id:225421), 野菜汁酢(id:70556), Snap55(id:89773), タビックスJapan(id:52714), Toto-tarou(id:16648), DNCAL(id:120593), るがこむ(id:181), 新芽(id:50924), カイの迷宮(id:72682), GURAX(id:107578), Loveless(id:129239), こぶまき(id:38278), ＫＪ達磨(id:101625), Shimoxx(id:9332), 越中掾(id:149423), Yosemite(id:5808), Kouko0515(id:100370), YukkeBot2(id:251491), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Lemon(id:11234), Poe(id:16973), Gimbrow(id:65660), Tosiho(id:73924), 目白梅(id:141468), Izayohi(id:13095), やりたこ(id:113528), Osu-mike(id:61051), 水野白楓(id:22811), 古聞(id:110289), 松茸(id:27535), PixelBot(id:166734), Daranome(id:1429), 総州之毛豆(id:26880), Kagetudo(id:163875), Shota(id:10854), 松平定治(id:146386), MDR-SK(id:192066), Richie Hiraga(id:34348), ゐ(id:795), Mochi(id:9489), 藤田真央(id:119719), 参謀中佐(id:11557), トホホ川(id:50502), Safkan(id:423), 板の魔術師(id:103435), General s 46(id:85273), 松貝舟(id:214792), Junger(id:10282), Enter456(id:247777), Hamasaki gion higashi(id:144985), SieBot(id:126695), 電田蒸(id:249216), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>