<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>松木家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Matsunoki Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsunoki Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsunoki Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>松木家（まつのきけ・中御門家（なかみかどけ））は、藤原北家中御門流本宗の堂上家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Matsunoki family (the Nakamikado family) is a dojoke (a family whose members were allowed to visit the Imperial Palace) that belongs to the main branch of the Nakamikado line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>本宗、定訳不明。堂上家、定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsunoki family (the Nakamikado family) is a dojoke (a family whose members were allowed to visit the Imperial Palace) that belonged to the main branch of the Nakamikado line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsunoki family (also known as the Nakamikado family) was a dojoke (a family whose members were allowed to visit the Imperial Palace) that belonged to the main branch of the Nakamikado line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>家格は羽林家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its family status is urinke (a family whose members serve as the emperor&apos;s guards, and they are allowed to hold certain high government positions).</e>
<cmt>羽林家、定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its family status was urinke (a family whose members serve as the emperor&apos;s guards, who were allowed to hold certain high government positions).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They held the rank of Urinke (which entitled them to hold military ranks).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家業は楽道・笙。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family specialized in Japanese Court music and sho (Japanese flute).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family specialized in Japanese Court music and sho (Japanese flute).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family specialized in Japanese Court music and playing the sho (traditional Japanese wind instrument similar to the pan flute).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>明治維新後に伯爵に叙せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration the family was given the status of a count.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Meiji Restoration the family was given the status of a count.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the family was awarded the title of count.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>当初は、中御門を称していたが、室町時代以後家名を松木と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, the family used the name Nakamikado, but they changed their family name to Matsunoki after the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning, the family used the name Nakamikado, but they changed their family name to Matsunoki after the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, the family used the name Nakamikado, but they changed their family name to Matsunoki after the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原道長の子である藤原頼宗・藤原俊家父子はともに右大臣を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Yorimune, and Yorimune&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Toshiie, both served as Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Michinaga&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Yorimune, and Yorimune&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Toshiie, both served as Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yorimune, who was the son of FUJIWARA no Michinaga, and his son, FUJIWARA no Toshiie, both served as Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その子孫を中御門流と称し、松木家（中御門家）はその嫡流にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their descendants are called the Nakamikado line, and its main family branch is the Matsunoki family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their descendants are called the Nakamikado line, and its main family branch is the Matsunoki family.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their descendants are called the Nakamikado line, whose main family branch is the Matsunoki family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>俊家の嫡男大納言藤原宗俊が中御門に邸宅を持っていたことから「中御門」と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was named &apos;Nakamikado&apos; because Toshiie&apos;s heir, Dainagon (Major counselor) FUJIWARA no Munetoshi, had a mansion in Nakamikado.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was named &apos;Nakamikado&apos; because Toshiie&apos;s heir, Dainagon (Major counselor) FUJIWARA no Munetoshi, had a mansion in Nakamikado.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was named &apos;Nakamikado&apos; because Toshiie&apos;s heir, FUJIWARA no Munetoshi (who held the position of Dainagon, a chief councilor of state), had a mansion in Nakamikado.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これがのが家号の始まりとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is considered to be the start of this family name.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is considered to be the start of this family name.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is considered to be the start of this family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>宗俊は笙・笛の達人として知られていたが大臣には昇らずに没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetoshi was known as an expert in the sho and the Japanese flute, but he died without becoming a minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetoshi was known as an expert in the sho and the Japanese flute, but he died without becoming a minister.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetoshi was known as an expert in the sho and the Japanese flute, but he died without ever having been a minister.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その子藤原宗忠は右大臣に昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son, FUJIWARA no Munetada, became Udaijin (Minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son, FUJIWARA no Munetada, became Udaijin (Minister of the right).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son, FUJIWARA no Munetada, became Udaijin.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>弟の藤原宗輔は太政大臣、宗忠の嫡男藤原宗能は内大臣に昇った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetada&apos;s younger brother, FUJIWARA no Munesuke, became Daijo Daijin (Grand Minister), and Munetada&apos;s heir, FUJIWARA no Muneyoshi became a Naidaijin (Minister of the Palace).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「弟の藤原宗輔」は「宗忠の弟」として訳してありますが、未確認です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetada&apos;s younger brother, FUJIWARA no Munesuke, became Daijo Daijin (Grand Minister), and Munetada&apos;s heir, FUJIWARA no Muneyoshi became a Naidaijin (Minister of the Palace).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetada&apos;s younger brother, FUJIWARA no Munesuke, became Daijo Daijin (Grand Minister), and Munetada&apos;s heir, FUJIWARA no Muneyoshi, became Naidaijin (Minister of the Palace).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>宗能の子大納言藤原宗家は議奏公卿の1人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneyoshi&apos;s son, Dainagon FUJIWARA no Muneie, was one of the giso kugyo (Noble Council) members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muneyoshi&apos;s son, Dainagon FUJIWARA no Muneie, was one of the giso kugyo (Noble Council) members.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muneyoshi&apos;s son, Dainagon FUJIWARA no Muneie, was a member of the Giso kugyo (Noble Council).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>宗忠は日記『中右記』（「中御門右大臣日記」の意味）を著し、宗輔は「蜂飼大臣」の故事で知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetada authored a diary, &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (implies &apos;a diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada&apos;), and Munesuke is known for the historical event of &quot;Hachikai no Otodo&quot; (Beekeeper Minister of State).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetada authored a diary, &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (implies &apos;a diary of FUJIWARA no Munetada&apos;), and Munesuke is known for the historical event of &quot;Hachikai no Otodo&quot; (Beekeeper Minister of State).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetada wrote a diary called &quot;Chuyuki&quot; (an abbreviation for &quot;Nakamikado Udaijin Nikki,&quot; literally meaning the diary of Nakamikado, Minister of the Right), and Munesuke became known as &apos;Hachikai no Otodo&apos; (the Beekeeper Minister of State) due to his obsession with bees.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、正式に中御門を家名としたのは、宗家の曾孫にあたる中御門宗雅・中御門宗実兄弟が宗俊の笙・笛の才能と名声を慕って付けたものと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that the name Nakamikado officially became their family name because Muneie&apos;s grandsons, Munemasa NAKAMIKADO and Munezane NAKAMIKADO brothers, decided on the family name out of respect for Munetoshi&apos;s talent and fame in playing the sho and the Japanese flute.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that the name Nakamikado officially became their family name because Muneie&apos;s grandsons, Munemasa NAKAMIKADO and Munezane NAKAMIKADO brothers, decided on the family name out of respect for Munetoshi&apos;s talent and fame in playing the sho and the Japanese flute.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed, however, that the family adopted Nakamikado as their official family name because Muneie&apos;s great-grandsons, Munemasa NAKAMIKADO and Munezane NAKAMIKADO (who were brothers), changed their family name to Nakamikado out of respect for Munetoshi&apos;s talent and fame in playing the sho and the Japanese flute.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>中御門家（松木家）は、家格的には羽林家とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nakamikado family (the Matsunoki family) is considered to be an urinke in terms of its status.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nakamikado family (the Matsunoki family) is considered to be an urinke in terms of its status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nakamikado family (also known as the Matsunoki family) held the rank of Urinke (which entitled them to hold military ranks).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、一般的な羽林家とは違っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it differed from an ordinary urinke.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it differed from an ordinary urinke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the status afforded them was different from that of an ordinary Urinke.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>近衛次将から弁官に昇進して参議を兼ねるという羽林家と名家 (公家)の昇進過程を併せ持つ特殊な家であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had a special status because the family was entitled to the promotion process of both the urinke and the meika (kuge (court noble)), so that the family members could be promoted from a 近衛次将 (a captain of the palace guards) to a benkan (top government official), and still hold an additional post as a sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処近衛次将、定訳不明。弁官、定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The title held a special status because the family was entitled to the promotion process of both the urinke and the meika (kuge (court noble)), so that the family members could be promoted from a 近衛次将 (a captain of the palace guards) to a benkan (top government official), and still hold an additional post as a sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title afforded them a special status in that the family was entitled to promotion both as Urinke and meika (an upper rank of kuge, or court noble), enabling family members to be promoted from the position of Konoe no Jisho (vice-minister of the Palace Guards) to that of benkan (official of the dajokan, or Grand Council of State), and still hold an additional post such as that of sangi (councilor).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>極端な例としては、南北朝時代 (日本)の中御門宗重（宗雅の曾孫）の例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an extreme example, there is an example of Muneshige NAKAMIKADO (a grandson of Munemasa) during the Period of Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an extreme example, there is an example of Muneshige NAKAMIKADO (a grandson of Munemasa) during the Period of Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An extreme example of this was Muneshige NAKAMIKADO (a grandson of Munemasa), who lived during the period of Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>少納言から近衛府、近衛府を経て弁官となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a shonagon (lesser counselor) who became a member of Konoefu (Division of Inner Palace Guards), and then from Konoefu to a benkan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a shonagon (lesser counselor) who became a member of Konoefu (Division of Inner Palace Guards), and then promoted from Konoefu to a benkan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally a Shonagon (lesser councilor of state), he became a member of the Konoefu (Division of Inner Palace Guards), and was later promoted from Konoefu to become a benkan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。少納言 = Shonagon (lesser councilor of state)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>再度頭中将となって公卿に昇って中納言を極位極官としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became a tono chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) again, then became a kugyo (court noble), and ultimately became a chunagon (middle counsellor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became a tono chujo (the first secretary&apos;s captain) again, then a kugyo (court noble), until ultimately becoming a chunagon (middle counsellor).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After becoming a tono chujo (first secretary&apos;s captain) again, he was made a kugyo (court noble) and ended up becoming a Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。中納言 = Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ただし、松木家は若くして出家もしくは病没する当主が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many of the Matsunoki family heads became priests or became ill and passed away at a young age.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many of the Matsunoki family heads became priests or became ill and passed away at a young age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the Matsunoki family heads, however, became priests or died from illness at a young age.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>中納言もしくは参議を極位極官とし、公卿に至らずに没する当主も少なからずいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were more than a few family heads who passed away with chunagon or sangi as their ultimate status and their ultimate government position, without ever becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were more than a few family heads who passed away with chunagon or sangi as their ultimate status and their ultimate government position, without ever becoming a kugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, more than a few family heads passed away having reached the position of chunagon or sangi but without having become a kugyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、戦国時代 (日本)には生活困窮から伊勢国に下向していた時期もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, during the Period of Warring States (Japan), there was a time during which the family moved away from the capital to Ise Province because of poverty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, during the Period of Warring States (Japan), there was a time during which the family moved away from the capital to Ise Province due to poverty.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, during the Sengoku period (Period of Warring States) (Japan), lack of funds forced the family to move away from the capital to Ise Province for a while.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>室町時代の松木宗量（松木宗宣・宗重の孫）の代に家名を「松木」と改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the generation of 松木宗量 (grandson of Munenobu and Muneshige MATSUNOKI) in the Muromachi period, the family name was changed to &apos;Matsunoki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>松木宗量、読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the generation of 松木宗量 (grandson of Munenobu and Muneshige MATSUNOKI) in the Muromachi period, the family name was changed to &apos;Matsunoki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the time of Munekazu (宗量) MATSUNOKI (or Munenobu MATSUNOKI, grandson of Muneshige) in the Muromachi period, the family name was changed to &apos;Matsunoki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その子松木宗継が宗家以来260年ぶりに大納言に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son, Munetsugu MATSUNOKI, assumed his position as a dainagon 260 years after Muneie.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処松木宗継は「まつのき　むねつぐ」としましたが、確認取れず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son, Munetsugu MATSUNOKI, assumed his position as a dainagon 260 years after Muneie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son, Munetsugu MATSUNOKI, assumed the position of Dainagon (chief councilor of state) 260 years after Muneie held it.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。大納言 = Dainagon (chief councilor of state)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>またその子松木宗綱は室町幕府征夷大将軍足利義稙の信任を受けて従一位准大臣となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munetsugu&apos;s son, Munetsuna MATSUNOKI, became Juichii (Junior First Rank) Jun-daijin (Vice Minister) because he had the trust of Seii Taishogun (great general who subdues the barbarians) Yoshitane ASHIKAGA of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munetsugu&apos;s son, Munetsuna MATSUNOKI, became Juichii (Junior First Rank) Jun-daijin (Vice Minister) because he had the trust of Seii Taishogun (great general who subdues the barbarians) Yoshitane ASHIKAGA of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munetsugu&apos;s son, Munetsuna MATSUNOKI, was promoted to the rank of Juichii (Junior First Rank) and the position of Jun-daijin (Vice Minister) because he had the trust of the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of that time, Yoshitane ASHIKAGA of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、江戸時代に霊元天皇の典侍となった松木宗子（敬法門院）が東山天皇を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, during the Edo period, Muneko MATSUNOKI (Keihomonin), who became Emperor Reigen&apos;s naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank), gave birth to Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, during the Edo period, Muneko MATSUNOKI (Keihomonin), who became Emperor Reigen&apos;s naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank), gave birth to Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Muneko MATSUNOKI (Keihomonin), Emperor Reigen&apos;s naishi no suke (a court lady of the first rank), gave birth to a child who would later become Emperor Higashiyama.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>東山天皇の外戚となった松木宗条とその子松木宗顕は内大臣に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, Munenaga MATSUNOKI and his son, Muneaki MATSUNOKI, who became Emepror Higashiyama&apos;s maternal relatives, were appointed to Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, Munenaga MATSUNOKI and his son, Muneaki MATSUNOKI, who became Emepror Higashiyama&apos;s maternal relatives, were appointed to Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to Munenaga MATSUNOKI and his son, Muneaki MATSUNOKI, who were now maternal relatives of Emperor Higashiyama, being appointed to the position of Naidaijin.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>宗顕の次男松木宗長（兄松木宗弥養子）も准大臣となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneaki&apos;s second son, Munenaga MATSUNOKI (Munenaga&apos;s older brother, Muneya MATSUNOKI, was adopted) also became a Jun-daijin (Vice Minister).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「兄松木宗弥養子」は「宗長の兄、松木宗弥は養子であった」という意味に訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muneaki&apos;s second son, Munenaga MATSUNOKI (Munenaga&apos;s older brother, Muneya MATSUNOKI, was adopted) also became a Jun-daijin (Vice Minister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muneaki&apos;s second son, Munenaga MATSUNOKI (adopted by Munenaga&apos;s older brother, Muneya MATSUNOKI) also became a Jun-daijin (Vice Minister).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>その後は再び当主の交代が相次ぎ、低迷傾向が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, however, the head of the family continued to change often, and the family cotinued on the path to its decline.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, however, the head of the family continued to change often, and the family cotinued on this path to its decline.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, however, the position of head of the family changed hands often, until eventually the family fell into decline.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>それでも、外戚となったことで家領は江戸時代初期の191石余から幕末には341石余に増加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even then, because the family became the maternal relatives of the emperor, the hereditary stipend increased from 191 koku from the early Edo period to 341 koku at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite this the hereditary stipend increased from 191 koku from the early Edo period to 341 koku at the end of the Edo period due to the family becoming the maternal relatives of the emperor,</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite this, however, the family&apos;s hereditary stipend increased from 191 koku to 341 koku throughout the course of the Edo period due to the family having become maternal relatives of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>松木宗有の代に明治維新を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji Restoration took place during Muneari MATSUNOKI&apos;s generation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiji Restoration took place during Muneari MATSUNOKI&apos;s generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Restoration took place while Muneari MATSUNOKI was head of the family.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その子松木宗隆の代に華族令によって伯爵に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the generation of his son, Munetaka MATSUNOKI, he was given the status of a count because of the Peerage Law.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his son&apos;s generation, Munetaka MATSUNOKI, he was given the status of a count because of the Peerage Law.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When his son, Munetaka MATSUNOKI, was head of the family, the Matsunoki family was given the status of count because of the Peerage Law.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。the Matsunoki familyに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>