<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>甘露寺家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanroji Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanroji Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanroji Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>甘露寺家（かんろじけ）は、藤原北家高藤流勧修寺一門嫡流の堂上家、家格は、名家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanroji family was &quot;Tosho-ke&quot; (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks) of the main branch of Kajuji line of the Takafuji group of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and its social standing was prestigious family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanroji family was &quot;Tosho-ke&quot; (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks) of the main branch of the Kajuji line of the Takafuji group of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and its social standing was prestigious family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanroji family was &quot;Tosho-ke&quot; (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks) of the main branch of the Kajuji line of the Takafuji group of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and its social standing was prestigious family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>内大臣・藤原高藤（勧修寺流の祖）の曾孫である権大納言・藤原為輔が甘露寺を号したことから、為輔を甘露寺家の祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Naidaijin (minister of the center) FUJIWARA no Takafuji&apos;s great-grandchild, Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) FUJIWARA no Tamesuke was called Kanroji, Tamesuke was considered to be the founder of the Kanroji family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Naidaijin (minister of the center) FUJIWARA no Takafuji&apos;s great-grandchild, Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) FUJIWARA no Tamesuke was called Kanroji, Tamesuke was considered to be the founder of the Kanroji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Naidaijin (minister of the center) FUJIWARA no Takafuji&apos;s great-grandchild, Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor) FUJIWARA no Tamesuke was called Kanroji, Tamesuke was considered to be the founder of the Kanroji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>鎌倉時代の終わりまで、「吉田家」を称していたが、権中納言・吉田藤長の頃から「甘露寺」を家名とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they were called the &quot;Yoshida family&quot; to the end of the Kamakura period, &quot;Kanroji&quot; became their family name from the time of a Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) Fujinaga YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they were called the &quot;Yoshida family&quot; until the end of the Kamakura period, &quot;Kanroji&quot; became their family name from the time of a Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) Fujinaga YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they were called the &apos;Yoshida family&apos; until the end of the Kamakura period, &apos;Kanroji&apos; became their family name from the time of a Gon Chunagon (Provisional Middle Counselor) Fujinaga YOSHIDA.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>甘露寺藤長以降、代々笛・儒道を家業とし、江戸時代の石高は200石であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Fujinaga KANROJI, flute and Confucianism were their family business for generations, and they had 200 Goku crop yields in Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Fujinaga KANROJI, the flute and Confucianism were their family business for generations, and they also had 200 Goku crop yields during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Fujinaga KANROJI, the flute and Confucianism were their family business for generations, and they also had 200 koku crop yields during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>200石→200 kokuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>42代当主の参議・甘露寺勝長で明治に至り、子孫は華族に列し伯爵に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Meiji Era the forty-twoth family head was Sangi (councillor) Katsunaga KANROJI, and the family was raised to the peerage and count.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji Era the forty-second family head was Sangi (councillor) Katsunaga KANROJI, and the family was raised to the peer level and count.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji Era the forty-second family head was Sangi (councillor) Katsunaga KANROJI, and the family was raised to the peer level and count.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>