<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>上野氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The UENO clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ueno clan</e>
<cmt>個人名ではないので通常表記にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ueno clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>上野氏（うえのし）は、日本の氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The UENO clan was a clan in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ueno clan was a shizoku (family) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ueno clan was a shizoku (family) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>幾つかの流れがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several lines in the UENO clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ueno clan had some family lines</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ueno clan had some family lines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>清和源氏足利流上野氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The SEIWA-GENJI (the MINAMOTO clan) ASHIKAGA-lined UENO clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seiwa-Genji (the Minamoto clan) ASHIKAGA-lined UENO clan</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seiwa-Genji (the Minamoto clan) ASHIKAGA-lined UENO clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本項で詳述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Explained in this section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Explained in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Explained in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>有道氏上野氏は、武蔵七党の一派児玉党の一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ARIMICHI-lined UENO clan belonged to a family from the KODAMA party, which was one of the MUSASHI-Shichito Parties.</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディアには、有道氏ではなく、有道姓となっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Arimichi-lined Ueno clan belonged to a family of the Kodama party, which was one of the Musashi-Shichito Parties.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Arimichi-lined Ueno clan belonged to a family of the Kodama party, which was one of the Musashi-Shichito Parties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>木曾氏流上野氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The KISO-lined UENO clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The KISO-lined UENO clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The KISO-lined UENO clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>信濃国木曾谷の国人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Kokujin (a local lord) of the Kiso-dani Valley in Shinano no kuni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan worked as Kokujin (local lord) of the Kiso Valley in Shinano Province</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan worked as Kokujin (local lord) of the Kiso Valley in Shinano Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>源姓と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Referred to the family name of MINAMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adopted Minamoto as the family name.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adopted Minamoto as the family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>藤原氏上野家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The FUJIWARA-lined UENO family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The FUJIWARA-lined UENO family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The FUJIWARA-lined UENO family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>公家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Kuge (a Court noble)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Kuge (a Court noble)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Kuge (a Court noble)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>上野秋親後胤上野長富が、戦国 (日本)末期京都より紀伊国に下向し定住。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagatomi UENO, a descendent of Akichika UENO, left the capital city of Kyoto and settled in Kii no kuni at the end of the Sengoku era (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagatomi UENO, a descendent of Akichika UENO, left the capital city of Kyoto and settled in Kii Province at the end of the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagatomi UENO, a descendent of Akichika UENO, left the capital city of Kyoto and settled in Kii Province at the end of the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>後裔は現存。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their descendents still exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their descendents still live.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their descendents still live.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>清和源氏足利流　上野氏嫡流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A direct descendent of the SEIWA-GENJI ASHIKAGA-lined UENO clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A direct descendent of the Seiwa-Genji ASHIKAGA-lined UENO clan</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A direct descendent of the Seiwa-Genji ASHIKAGA-lined UENO clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their real family name is GENJI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their real family name is Genji.</e>
<cmt>GENJI を通常表記に戻しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their real family name is Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>家系は河内源氏の流れを汲む足利氏の庶家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family line was a branch family of the ASHIKAGA clan which was related to the KAWACHI-GENJI clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan was a branch family of the Ashikaga clan who was related to Kawachi-Genji (the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan was a branch family of the Ashikaga clan who was related to Kawachi-Genji (the Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>足利泰氏の六男、上野義弁に始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family lineage started at Yoshihira UENO, the sixth son of Yasuuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>義弁の呼び名不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family lineage started with 上野義弁, the sixth son of Yasuuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>上野義弁は読みがわかりませんでしたので、日本語表記に戻しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family lineage started with 上野義弁, the sixth son of Yasuuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>義弁の祖父足利義氏 (足利家3代目当主)が三河国守護補任を契機として、同国には足利一門の扶植がはじまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With his appointment to the assistant governor of Mikawa no kuni, Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (the third head of the ASHIKAGA family), the grandfather of Yoshibira, the Fushoku (implantation) of the ASHIKAGA clan in Mikawa no kuni begun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (the third head of the Ashikaga family), 義弁&apos;s grandfather, was appointed as assistant governor of Mikawa Province, which event triggered the family&apos;s settlement in the province.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (the third head of the Ashikaga family), 義弁&apos;s grandfather, was appointed as assistant governor of Mikawa Province, which event triggered the family&apos;s settlement in the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そして、三河における足利氏の所領のうち、八条院領上野荘の地頭職を得て足利一門として重きをなした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, they gained the Jitoshiki (stewardship rights) of the Uenosho of the Hachijyo-ryo in the Shoryo (territory) in the Mikawa region which belonged to the ASHIKAGA clan and became one of the more important families within the ASHIKAGA clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the family established a presence by gaining stewardship for the Hachijoin&apos;s manor (Ueno no sho) which was one of the family&apos;s territories in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the family established a presence by gaining stewardship for the Hachijoin&apos;s manor (Ueno no sho) which was one of the family&apos;s territories in Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>義弁の孫上野頼兼は、足利尊氏が鎌倉幕府に反旗を翻し挙兵した際には従軍している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Takauji ASHIKAGA raised a rebellion against the Kamkura Bakufu and ordered troops, Yorikane UENO, the grandson of Yoshibira, went to fight on the front lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Takauji ASHIKAGA raised an army against the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Yorikane UENO, a grandson of 上野義弁, sided with him.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Takauji ASHIKAGA raised an army against the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Yorikane UENO, a grandson of 上野義弁, sided with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>南北朝の動乱の中、尊氏は九州に落ち延び、頼兼もこれに従軍する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji saved his life by escaping to Kyushu during the coup of the Northern and Southern Dynasties, and Yorikane follwed him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji and Yorikane fled to Kyushu during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji and Yorikane fled to Kyushu during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>1336年（建武 (日本)3年）3月には南朝方の肥後国の菊池氏を討って武功を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorikane defeated the KIKUCHI clan of the Higo Province, which belonged to the Southern Dynasty, and accomplished the military exploits in March, 1336.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, 1336, Yorikane was credited with defeating the Kikuchi clan of Higo Province who sided with the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, 1336, Yorikane was credited with defeating the Kikuchi clan of Higo Province who sided with the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>やがて、尊氏が勢力を盛り返して京都奪還のために東上すると、石見国守護に補任され、西国における北朝・幕府勢力の拡大と南朝勢力の追討に尽力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he climbed in power, Takauji moved towards the east to recapture Kyoto; thus, Yorikane was appointed to the Shugo of Ishimi no kuni and made an effort to expand the power of the Northern Dynasty and the Bakufu while defeating the Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji, regaining his power, moved eastward to recapture Kyoto, while Yorikane, as Shugo (provincial constable) of Iwami Province, put his emphasis on the extension of the Northern Court&apos;s and the Muromachi bakufu&apos;s influence and the elimination of the Southern Court&apos;s influence in western part of Japan.</e>
<cmt>・表現の修正・「幕府勢力」は室町幕府と明記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji, regaining his power, moved eastward to recapture Kyoto, while Yorikane, as Shugo (provincial constable) of Iwami Province, put his emphasis on the extension of the Northern Court&apos;s and the Muromachi bakufu&apos;s influence and the elimination of the Southern Court&apos;s influence in western part of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>上野氏は佐渡国守護等、数ヶ国の守護を歴任したものの、子孫代々世襲されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The UENO clan succeeded in holding the position of the Shugo (provincial military governor) throughout several provices including Sado no kuni; however, the position was not passed on to their descendants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family took over as Shugo of Sado and several other provinces, but the posts were not passed down to the descendants.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family took over as Shugo of Sado and several other provinces, but the posts were not passed down to the descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>京都にあって奉公衆三番頭となる一方、御部屋衆、御供衆、申次衆を代々務めるなど、足利将軍家の近臣として幕府の中枢の業務を担った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By holding positions as the Oheyashu (person in charge of keeping night watch outside the shogun&apos;s bed chamber), the Otomoshu (group that accompanied the Takauji Shikaga to Kyoto), and the Moshitsugishu (civil servant post in Muromachi Shogunate) for generations, and by being appointed to the third leader of the Hokoshu (shogun military guard), the UENO clan carried out the central tasks of the Bakufu as the trusted vessal of the ASHIKAGA Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, the family, as a trusted vassal of Ashikaga Shogun family, served not merely as the leader of the third squad of Hokoshu (shogunal military guard) but also as Oheyashu (the person in charge of keeping night watch of the shogun&apos;s bed chamber), Otomoshu (attendant group who attended the Shogun Takauji Ashikaga to go up to the ancient capital kyoto), and Moshitsugishu (a civil servant post in Muromachi Shorgunate) for generations.</e>
<cmt>・表現の修正・「奉公衆三番頭」は「奉公衆三番隊の長」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, the family, as a trusted vassal of Ashikaga Shogun family, served not merely as the leader of the third squad of Hokoshu (shogunal military guard) but also as Oheyashu (the person in charge of keeping night watch of the shogun&apos;s bed chamber), Otomoshu (attendant group who attended the Shogun Takauji Ashikaga to go up to the ancient capital kyoto), and Moshitsugishu (a civil servant post in Muromachi Shorgunate) for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>足利義稙が管領細川政元より追放されると、1509年（永正6年）、上野氏は上野信孝が義稙の命により二階堂政行、伊勢貞信とともに備中国に入部する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was expelled by the Shogunal Deputy, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, Nobutaka UENO of the UENO clan joined the government of Bicchu no kuni together with Masayuki NIKAIDO and Sadanobu ISE under the order of Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was expelled by the Shogunal Deputy, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, Nobutaka UENO entered Bicchu Province with Masayuki NIKAIDO and Sadanobu ISE under the order of Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was expelled by the Shogunal Deputy, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, Nobutaka UENO entered Bicchu Province with Masayuki NIKAIDO and Sadanobu ISE under the order of Yoshitane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>信孝は備中国下道郡下原郷鬼邑山城に入り、義稙方の拡大に奔走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutaka made every effort to expand the Yoshitane&apos;s power by joining him in the Kimurayama-jo Castle in Shimohara-Go, Shimotsumichi County Bicchu no kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based in Kimurayama-jo Castle in Shimohara-Go, Shimotsumichi County, Bicchu Province, Nobutaka tried to extend Yoshitane&apos;s influence.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based in Kimurayama-jo Castle in Shimohara-Go, Shimotsumichi County, Bicchu Province, Nobutaka tried to extend Yoshitane&apos;s influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その後、永正年間中に信孝は京に帰還し、足利義輝の重臣を務め、永禄6年(1563年)に逝去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he returned to the capital during the Eisho era, where he held the position of chief retainer for Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA. He died in 1563.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, during the Eisho era, he returned to Kyoto, where he served as a chief retainer for Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA and died in 1563.</e>
<cmt>翻訳ではcapital としていますが、「京都」と明言しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, during the Eisho era, he returned to Kyoto, where he served as a chief retainer for Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA and died in 1563.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>また、信孝の嫡子上野清信は、足利義昭の重臣として、歴史に名を記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Kiyonobu UENO, a legitimate child of Nobutaka, is historically remembered as Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA&apos;s chief retainer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyonobu UENO, a legitimate child of Nobutaka, is historically remembered as Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA&apos;s chief retainer.</e>
<cmt>Furthermore は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyonobu UENO, a legitimate child of Nobutaka, is historically remembered as Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA&apos;s chief retainer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>なお、上野氏嫡流の当主は代々の将軍から偏諱があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heads of the direct descendents of the UENO clan were granted Henki (the use of the name of a person of higher rank) from the Shogun for generations; some of those names were as followed: Akirakane UENO was given one letter from Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, Mitsukane UENO from Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, Mochiyori UENO from Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, and Naonaga ASHIKAGA was from Yoshinao ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>詮兼の呼び名不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heads of the main branch of the Ueno clan had one portion of the name of successive Ashikaga Shoguns granted.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heads of the main branch of the Ueno clan had one portion of the name of successive Ashikaga Shoguns granted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>例えば、上野詮兼は足利義詮から、上野満兼は足利義満、上野持頼は足利義持から、上野尚長は足利義尚からそれぞれ諱の一字を授けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Akirakane was given one portion of the name of Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, Mitsukane one portion of the name of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, Mochiyori one portion of the name of Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, and Naonaga one portion of the name of Yoshinao ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処・上野詮兼は「あきかね」の可能性もあります。・全ての人物に「上野」を付けると、くどくどしいので名前のみ表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Akirakane was given one portion of the name of Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, Mitsukane one portion of the name of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, Mochiyori one portion of the name of Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, and Naonaga one portion of the name of Yoshinao ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>備中上野氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bicchu (the Western part of Okayama prefecture) UENO clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bicchu Ueno clan</e>
<cmt>括弧内の説明は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bicchu Ueno clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>備中上野氏は、上野信孝の一門の上野高直が信孝の後を受け継ぎ喜村山城(鬼邑山城)に入ったことにはじまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bicchu UENO clan originated when Takanao UENO, a family of Nobutaka UENO, succeeded Nobutaka and joined a clan in the Kimurayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bicchu Ueno clan started when Takanao UENO who belonged to Nobutaka UENO&apos;s family succeeded Nobutaka and entered Kimurayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bicchu Ueno clan started when Takanao UENO who belonged to Nobutaka UENO&apos;s family succeeded Nobutaka and entered Kimurayama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>上野頼久は松山城に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorihisa UENO joined the Matsuyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorihisa UENO moved to Matsuyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorihisa UENO moved to Matsuyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>(後、喜村山城他一連の城は滅亡し、一方、松山城は存続し繁栄したことから、後世において、史実が主従逆転し、錯誤して伝えられることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Later, an array of castles including the Kimurayama-jo perished; however, the Matsuyama-jo Castle remained and prospered; therefore, it is considered that the incorrect historical fact was told so that the relationship of the master and servant were reversed.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Later, because Kimurayama-jo Castle and other related castles were destroyed and Matsuyama-jo Castle continued to exist and enjoyed prosperity, the historical fact was reversed and, as a consequence, incorrect history was passed down to future generations.</e>
<cmt>「史実が主従逆転し」の意味が分かりません。主従が文字通りの意とすると誰が主で誰が従なのか不明です。「史実が逆転し、間違った歴史が後世に伝わった」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Later, because Kimurayama-jo Castle and other related castles were destroyed and Matsuyama-jo Castle continued to exist and enjoyed prosperity, the historical fact was reversed and, as a consequence, incorrect history was passed down to future generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>)この頃の上野氏は備中守護細川氏の下、石川氏・庄氏とともに備中守護代を務めて家格を誇っていたが、この両氏と異なり、早くに守護代の地位を失っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The UENO clan at the time worked as the Bicchu Shugodai (the assistant military gonernor) under the supervision of the Bicchu Shugo HOSOKAWA clan together with the ISHIKAWA and SHO clans; however, they quickly lost their position as the Shugodai although the ISHIKAWA and SHO clans kept their position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, the Ueno clan enjoyed prosperity by working as Shugodai (deputy military governor) together with the Ishikawa clan and the Sho clan under the supervision of the Hosokawa clan, the military governor of Bicchu, but unlike the other clans, the Ueno clan lost the post in early stage.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, the Ueno clan enjoyed prosperity by working as Shugodai (deputy military governor) together with the Ishikawa clan and the Sho clan under the supervision of the Hosokawa clan, the military governor of Bicchu, but unlike the other clans, the Ueno clan lost the post in early stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>備中上野氏二代　頼久は、備中松山の臨済宗天柱山安国寺(頼久寺)を再興し菩提寺とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorihisa, the second head of the UENO clan, restored the Tenchuzan Ankoku-ji Temple (the Yorihisa-ji Temple) of the Rinzai sect in Bicchu Matsuyama, and turned it into the family temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorihisa, the second head of the Bicchu Ueno clan, restored Tenchuzan Ankoku-ji Temple (Raikyu-ji Temple) of the Rinzai sect in Bicchu Matsuyama and turned it into the family temple.</e>
<cmt>「頼久寺」は「らいきゅうじ」と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorihisa, the second head of the Bicchu Ueno clan, restored Tenchuzan Ankoku-ji Temple (Raikyu-ji Temple) of the Rinzai sect in Bicchu Matsuyama and turned it into the family temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>頼久の後は、嫡子上野頼氏が家督を継ぎ備中松山城主となったが、頼氏は天文二年(1533)に庄為資によって攻め滅ぼされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriuji UENO, the legitimate child, succeeded the family estate after Yorihisa and became the lord of the Bicchu Matsuyama-jo Castle; however, he was overthrown by Tamemoto SHO in 1533.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yorihisa, Yoriuji UENO, his legitimate child, took over as head of the family and became the lord of the Bicchu Matsuyama-jo Castle, but was overthrown by Tamemoto SHO in 1533.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yorihisa, Yoriuji UENO, his legitimate child, took over as head of the family and became the lord of the Bicchu Matsuyama-jo Castle, but was overthrown by Tamemoto SHO in 1533.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>この頃、守護代の地位を失ったものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the UENO clan lost its status as the Shogodai (deputy military governor) around this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible that the Bicchu Ueno clan was dismissed as Shugodai around this time.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible that the Bicchu Ueno clan was dismissed as Shugodai around this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="38">
<j>中国太平記によれば、「大松山には上野伊豆守居住して小松山の城には同右衛門尉を置かれける処に、天文二年猿掛の城主庄為資押し寄せて相戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Chugoku Taiheiki,&quot; &apos;Tamemoto SHO, the lord of the Sarukakeno-jo Castle attacked and fought against both the resident of Izu no kami (the Governor of Izu Province) UENO, resided in Mt. Taisho and the resident of Uemon no jo (the third ranked official of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) UENO, resided in Mt. Kosho in 1533.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Chugoku Taiheiki, &apos;Tamemoto SHO, the lord of Sarukakeno-jo Castle attacked and fought against Ueno Izu no kami (Yoriuji UENO) residing in Mt. Taisho and Ueno Uemon no jo (Yoriuji&apos;s brother) residing in Mt. Kosho in 1533.</e>
<cmt>・「伊豆守」の説明がここではそぐわないので、削除しました。・若干補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Chugoku Taiheiki, &apos;Tamemoto SHO, the lord of Sarukakeno-jo Castle attacked and fought against Ueno Izu no kami (Yoriuji UENO) residing in Mt. Taisho and Ueno Uemon no jo (Yoriuji&apos;s brother) residing in Mt. Kosho in 1533.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>庄は当国の旗頭たるにより、植木下野守秀長、庄に力を合わせ横谷より攻め掛け、上野の勢を追い崩した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHO who was the Hatagashira (the leader of troops); therefore, UEKI Shimotsuke no kami Hidenaga helped SHO to attack and shrink the UENO force from the valley on the side.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Sho clan is ruling this province, Ueki Shimotsuke no kami Hidenaga and the clan attacked the Ueno force from the valley side and beat it.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Sho clan is ruling this province, Ueki Shimotsuke no kami Hidenaga and the clan attacked the Ueno force from the valley side and beat it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>そして、伊豆守を討ち取り、大松山を乗取った」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamemot SHO then killed IZU no kami and took over Mt. Taisho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamemoto SHO killed Izu no kami and took over Mt. Taisho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamemoto SHO killed Izu no kami and took over Mt. Taisho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>小松山の上野右衛門尉も植木が一族若林二郎右衛門に討たれし」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chugoku Taiheiki&quot; also mentioned &apos; UENO Uenomon no jo was defeated by Jirouemon WAKABAYASHI, a member of the UEKI family.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chugoku Taiheiki also mentioned &apos;Ueno Uemon no jo was defeated by Jirouemon WAKABAYASHI, a member of the Ueki family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chugoku Taiheiki also mentioned &apos;Ueno Uemon no jo was defeated by Jirouemon WAKABAYASHI, a member of the Ueki family.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="42">
<j>上野高直は、下道郡市場村の臨済宗万寿山報恩寺を再興し菩提寺とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takanao UENO restored the Manju-zan Hoon-ji Temple of the Rinzai sect in the Ichiba village in Shimotsumichi County, turned it into the family temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takanao UENO restored Manju-zan Hoon-ji Temple of the Rinzai sect in Ichiba Village, Shimotsumichi County and turned it into the family temple.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takanao UENO restored Manju-zan Hoon-ji Temple of the Rinzai sect in Ichiba Village, Shimotsumichi County and turned it into the family temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>高直の後は、嫡子上野肥前守高徳が家督を継ぎ喜村山城主となったが、高徳は、弘冶年中(1555～1558)に備前常山城に移り、この城を居城とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">UENO Hizen no kami Takatoku, the legitimate child, succeeded the family estate after Takanao and became the lord of the Kimurayyama-jo Castle; however, Tkatoku moved to the Bizen Tsuneyama-jo Castle in sometime between 1555 and 1558 and resided in this castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Takanoa, Ueno Hizen no kami Takatoku, his legitimate child, took over as head of the family and became the lord of Kimurayyama-jo Castle, but he moved to Bizen Tsuneyama-jo Castle at a certain point between 1555 and 1558 and resided in this castle.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Takanoa, Ueno Hizen no kami Takatoku, his legitimate child, took over as head of the family and became the lord of Kimurayyama-jo Castle, but he moved to Bizen Tsuneyama-jo Castle at a certain point between 1555 and 1558 and resided in this castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="44">
<j>また、上野隆徳は、備中松山で無残な最期を遂げた一族上野伊豆守頼氏らの仇敵である庄為資の嫡子高資を討った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Takatoku UENO defeated Takatsugu, the legitimate child of Tametsugu SHO, and enemy of several UENO clans like UENO Izu no kami Yoriuji who had a cruel end in Bicchu Matsuyama.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Takatoku UENO defeated Takasuke SHO, the legitimate child of Tamemoto SHO, the enemy of one of his family members Ueno Izu no kami Yoriuji who met a tragic end in Bicchu Matsuyama.</e>
<cmt>・表現の修正・「高資」は「たかすけ」と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Takatoku UENO defeated Takasuke SHO, the legitimate child of Tamemoto SHO, the enemy of one of his family members Ueno Izu no kami Yoriuji who met a tragic end in Bicchu Matsuyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>そして、備中松山城主となった三村家親の娘を室とし、石川氏･庄氏両備中守護代家同様、備中一円に勢力を広げる三村氏との縁故を深めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Takatoku married one of the daughters of Iechika MIMURA who became the lord of the Bicchu Matsuyama-jo Castle and became close relatives of the MIMURA clan who spread its power to the entire Bicchu region, as well as both the ISHIKAWA and the SHO clans who were the Bicchu Shugodai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, by marrying one of the daughters of Iechika MIMURA who became the lord of the Bicchu Matsuyama-jo Castle, Takatoku deepened his relationship with the Mimura clan who was extending power over the entire Bicchu as well as the Ishikawa clan and the Sho clan, both of whom were serving as Shugodai of Bicchu.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, by marrying one of the daughters of Iechika MIMURA who became the lord of the Bicchu Matsuyama-jo Castle, Takatoku deepened his relationship with the Mimura clan who was extending power over the entire Bicchu as well as the Ishikawa clan and the Sho clan, both of whom were serving as Shugodai of Bicchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>三村家中ではかなりの発言力を有し、三村隆徳とも称していたという（備中兵乱記）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatoku had an influential voice and it is said that he called himself Takatoku MIMURA according to &quot;Bicchu Heiranki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatoku had an influential voice, calling himself Takatoku MIMURA according to Bicchu Heiranki (Record on disturbance in the Bicchu area).</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatoku had an influential voice, calling himself Takatoku MIMURA according to Bicchu Heiranki (Record on disturbance in the Bicchu area).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="47">
<j>元来、上野氏は、信孝を通じて毛利氏とも格別の信頼関係を有していたが、信孝も、また、元就も他界して後、隆徳は、三村家親の嫡子元親に加担して毛利氏に対抗することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the UENO clan had a trustworthy relationship with the MORI clan through Nobutaka; however, Takatoku supported Motochika, the legitimate child of Iechika MIMURA, and opposed the MORI clan after both Nobutaka and Motonari died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the UENO clan had a trusting relationship with the Mori clan through Nobutaka, but after Nobutaka and Motonari MORI died, Takatoku opposed the Mori clan by supporting Motochika, the legitimate child of Iechika MIMURA.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the UENO clan had a trusting relationship with the Mori clan through Nobutaka, but after Nobutaka and Motonari MORI died, Takatoku opposed the Mori clan by supporting Motochika, the legitimate child of Iechika MIMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>その挙句、天正3年(1575年)に小早川隆景が率いる毛利軍によって攻め滅ぼされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, Takatoku was defeated by the MORI force led by Takakage KOBAYAKAWA in 1575.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Takatoku was defeated by the Mori force led by Takakage KOBAYAKAWA in 1575.</e>
<cmt>「毛利軍」は通常表記にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Takatoku was defeated by the Mori force led by Takakage KOBAYAKAWA in 1575.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>これが、世に云う常山合戦である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was known as the Battle of Tsuneyama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is known as the Battle of Tsuneyama.</e>
<cmt>現在形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is known as the Battle of Tsuneyama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="50">
<j>上野隆徳は、備前常山城主として臨済宗豊岳山久昌寺を再興しているが、上野氏の菩提寺であった報恩寺(倉敷市真備町)には、隆徳とその室で三村家親の息女・鶴姫の当時からの位牌が、今も祭られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatoku UENO restored the Hogakusan Kyusho-ji Temple of the Rinzai sect as the lord of the Bizen Tsuneyama-jo Castle; however, the original ancestral tablets of Takatoku and his wife, Tsuruhime, who was the daughter of the MIMURA family, were dedicated within the Hoon-ji Temple, the family temple (Mabi-cho Kurashiki City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Takatoku UENO restored the Hogakusan Kyusho-ji Temple of the Rinzai sect as the lord of the Bizen Tsuneyama-jo Castle, the original ancestral tablets of Takatoku and his wife, Tsuruhime, a daughter of the MIMURA family, are still placed in Hoon-ji Temple, the Ueno clan&apos;s family temple (Mabi-cho Kurashiki City).</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Takatoku UENO restored the Hogakusan Kyusho-ji Temple of the Rinzai sect as the lord of the Bizen Tsuneyama-jo Castle, the original ancestral tablets of Takatoku and his wife, Tsuruhime, a daughter of the MIMURA family, are still placed in Hoon-ji Temple, the Ueno clan&apos;s family temple (Mabi-cho Kurashiki City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>豊後上野氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bungo Ueno clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bungo Ueno clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bungo Ueno clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>尚、また、足利一門上野氏の三代 上野頼兼の次男　上野直兼を祖とする豊後上野氏は、尊氏の腹心として九州下向に随従、上野氏一門の中で唯一九州に留まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the Bungo UENO clan which originated from Naokane UENO, the second son of Yorikane UENO who was the third head of the UENO clan beloned to the ASHIKAGA family, followed Ujitaka as his trustworthy assistant to the trip to the downward of Kyushu and stayed as the sole member of the UENO clan in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originating from Naokane UENO, the second son of Yorikane UENO who was the third head of the Ueno clan belonging to a branch family of the Ashikaga clan starting with Yasuuji ASIKAGA, the Bungo Ueno clan accompanied Takauji on his trip to Kyushu as his trustworthy assistant and stayed there as the sole family of the Ueno clan.</e>
<cmt>・表現の修正・ここでは明言されていませんが、本箇所の「足利一門」は上述の足利泰氏に始まる足利氏の庶流のことなので、そのことを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originating from Naokane UENO, the second son of Yorikane UENO who was the third head of the Ueno clan belonging to a branch family of the Ashikaga clan starting with Yasuuji ASIKAGA, the Bungo Ueno clan accompanied Takauji on his trip to Kyushu as his trustworthy assistant and stayed there as the sole family of the Ueno clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>そして、孫の上野氏繁の代に豊後守護大友氏の傘下に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, at the generation of Naokane&apos;s grandson, Ujishige UENO, became under the umbrella of the Bungo no Shugo OTOMO clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan had been under the umbrella of the Otomo clan, governor of Bungo Province, since the era of Ujishige Ueno, Naokane&apos;s grandson.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan had been under the umbrella of the Otomo clan, governor of Bungo Province, since the era of Ujishige Ueno, Naokane&apos;s grandson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>代々、大友氏の当主より偏諱がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bungo UENO clan was granted with Henki (the use of a character from the superior&apos;s real name) from the lord of the OTOMO clan; thus, Shigekane UENO, Shigenobu UENO were granted with Henki from Chikashige OTOMO, Harunobu OENO was from Chikaharu OTOMO, Shigenobu UENO and Shigemoto UENO, a father and a son, and Shigemasa UENO, Shigenobu&apos;s brothe, was from the lord Yoshishige OTOMO (Sorin OTOMO, later).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heads of the clan had one portion of the name of successive heads of the Otomo clan granted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heads of the clan had one portion of the name of successive heads of the Otomo clan granted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>例えば、上野繁兼、上野繁信は大友親繁の偏諱を、上野治信は大友親治より偏諱を、上野鎮信、上野鎮基親子及び鎮信の弟　上野鎮政は、主君大友義鎮（後の大友宗麟）より偏諱を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Shigekane and Shigenobu were given one portion of the name of Chikashige OTOMO, Harunobu one portion of the name of Chikaharu OTOMO, Shigenobu and his sons Shigemoto and Shigemasa one portion of the name of Yoshishige OTOMO (later Sorin OTOMO).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処・全ての人物に「上野」を付けると、くどくどしくなるので、名前のみ表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Shigekane and Shigenobu were given one portion of the name of Chikashige OTOMO, Harunobu one portion of the name of Chikaharu OTOMO, Shigenobu and his sons Shigemoto and Shigemasa one portion of the name of Yoshishige OTOMO (later Sorin OTOMO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>鎮信は大友宗麟に家政に関して諫言したものの聞き入れられず、一族は大友氏を離れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigenobu adviced Sorin OTOMO concerning the family policy without success and the Bungo UENO clan left the OTOMO clan to become either the family line which became a vassal of the RYUZOJI clan or a village headman by returning to be a farmer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigenobu gave some advice on household management to Sorin OTOMO but without success, which incident led the clan to leave the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigenobu gave some advice on household management to Sorin OTOMO but without success, which incident led the clan to leave the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>その後、竜造寺氏の家臣になった家系、帰農し庄屋として存続した家系とにわかれて存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the clan was divided into the family that worked as a vassal of the Ryuzoji clan and the one that survived as shoya (village headman) in an agricultural community.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the clan was divided into the family that worked as a vassal of the Ryuzoji clan and the one that survived as shoya (village headman) in an agricultural community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>家紋は丸に二引両。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest is the circle with two lines inside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest was the circle with two horizontal lines inside.</e>
<cmt>「引両」は水平に描かれた横筋なので、「水平」を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest was the circle with two horizontal lines inside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>信濃上野氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinano UENO clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinano Ueno clan</e>
<cmt>Ueno としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinano Ueno clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>『高遠記集成』（『木曽福島町史』）によると、信濃国木曾谷の木曾家領主・木曾家村（木曾義仲七世孫と称する）の甥・木曾家佐（木曾家定の子）が木曽郡上野に土着したことから始まるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Koenkishusei&quot;([Kisofukushimachoshi]), it is said that the Shinano UENO clan started when Iesa KISO (a child of Iesada KISO), a nephew of Iemura KISO (said to be the 7th grandchild of Yoshinaka KISO) who was the lord of the KISO family of Kisodani in Shinano no kuni, settled in UENO, Kiso County.</e>
<cmt>木曾家佐の読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Koenkishusei&quot; (A History of Kisofukushima Town), the clan started when 木曾家佐 (Iesada KISO&apos;s son), a nephew of Iemura KISO (claimed to be the seventh descendent of Yoshinaka KISO), the lord of the Kiso family in Kiso-dani Valley, Shinano Province, settled in Ueno, Kiso County.</e>
<cmt>「木曾福島町史」は英語表記にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Koenkishusei&quot; (A History of Kisofukushima Town), the clan started when 木曾家佐 (Iesada KISO&apos;s son), a nephew of Iemura KISO (claimed to be the seventh descendent of Yoshinaka KISO), the lord of the Kiso family in Kiso-dani Valley, Shinano Province, settled in Ueno, Kiso County.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>または、牧野氏と混同されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shinano UENO clan sometime is mistaken for the MAKINO clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan is sometime mistaken for the Makino clan.</e>
<cmt>表現の修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan is sometime mistaken for the Makino clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mie Kishu(id:193240), Bargauge(id:93367), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), Shrimp(id:193253), GAVVA(id:47103), 小者(id:172526), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>