<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>北条氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>北条氏（ほうじょうし）は、伊豆国出身の豪族で、鎌倉幕府の執権職を世襲した一族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo clan was a Gozoku (local ruling family) from the Izu Province who succeeded the regent of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) by heredity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan was a Gozoku (local ruling family) from Izu Province which provided hereditary regents of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo clan was a gozoku (local ruling family) originating in Izu Province which provided hereditary regents of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。余分なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、代々鎌倉幕府執権職を継承したことから執権北条氏ともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it was also said to be the regent Hojo clan since it succeeded the regent of the Kamakura bakufu through the ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as the Regent Hojo clan thanks to its provision of generations of regents to the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as the Regent Hojo clan owing to its control of the hereditary title of regent of the Kamakura Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>桓武平氏・平貞盛の流れを汲む平直方の子孫を称し、時方のとき伊豆国となって伊豆国北条郷（現静岡県伊豆の国市）に土着し、北条氏を名乗ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It identified itself as the descendant of TAIRA no Naokata, which was the lineage of TAIRA no Sadamori, the Kanmu-Heishi, and when Tokikata was assigned to the kokushi (provincial governors) of the Izu Province, it began to live at Hojogo, Izu Province (present Izunokuni City, Shizuoka Prefecture) with using the name Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>「伊豆国となって」は「伊豆国司となって」と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan identified itself as the descendants of TAIRA no Naokata of the lineage of TAIRA no Sadamori from the Kanmu-Heishi, took is said to have taken on the name Hojo when Tokikata was appointed as kokushi (provincial governor) of the Izu Province and settled in Hojogo, Izu Province (present Izunokuni City, Shizuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being of the lineage of TAIRA no Sadamori from the Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan), the Hojo clan identified itself as the descendants of TAIRA no Naokata; they are said to have taken the name &quot;Hojo&quot; when Tokikata was appointed to the position of suke (vice governor) for Izu Province and settled in Hojogo, Izu Province (present-day Izunokuni City, Shizuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし今日伝わる北条氏系図はいずれも時政以前の世系がまちまちで一致せず、疑点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, any existing family tree of the Hojo clan is full of question marks because there are many differences on the generations before Tokimasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are doubts over the Hojo clan lineage because all the Hojo clan family trees in existence today differ significantly with regard to the generations before Tokimasa.</e>
<cmt>More natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are doubts over the Hojo clan lineage because the Hojo clan family trees in existence today provide conflicting records of the generations before Tokimasa.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>時政の本拠地である北条の地は、伊豆国田方郡に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place of Hojo, the base of Tokimasa, locates at Tagata-gun, Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The home territory of the Hojo, which was the base of Tokimasa, is Tagata-gun in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area called Hojo, the base of Tokimasa, was located in Tagata-gun in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「条」とは、郡・郷よりさらに小さい規模の領域を示す単位であり、郡規模あるいはそれ以上の範囲に領域支配を展開する他の東国有力武士団である三浦氏・千葉氏・小山氏・秩父氏などは、どれも何代か前から多くの有力な一族を各地に分派させているが、北条氏にはそうした一族が少しもみられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &apos;jo&apos; refers to a unit which shows the smaller area than gun and go, and although any other major armed groups in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) such as the Miura clan, the Chiba clan, the Koyama clan and the Chichibu clan, who ruled the scale of gun or larger area, had separated many major branch families in various places since former generations, the Hojo clan had no branch family like those.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A &apos;jo&apos; is a unit of area smaller than a &apos;gun&apos; or &apos;go&apos;, and unlike other major armed groups in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) who ruled territories on the scale of &apos;gun&apos; or larger (e.g. the Miura clan, the Chiba clan, the Koyama clan and the Chichibu clan) and had, at some point in the past, produced powerful branch families which ruled elsewhere, the Hojo clan did not have any branch families.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A &apos;jo&apos; is a unit of area smaller than a &apos;gun&apos; (county) or &apos;go&apos; (village), and unlike other major armed groups in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) who ruled territories of &apos;gun&apos; or larger area (e.g. the Miura, Chiba, Koyama and Chichibu clans) and had been scattering their powerful branch families across Togoku since generations before, the Hojo clan did not have any such branch families.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして40歳を越えた北条時政が、ただ北条四郎と名乗っているのみで、介はもとより、何の官位も持っていなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And only Tokimasa HOJO who was over 40 years old identified himself as Shiro HOJO, and he had neither suke (vice governor of provincial offices) nor official rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Tokimasa HOJO who was over 40 years old had simply identified himself as Shiro HOJO without having the post of suke (vice governor) or any official rank.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Tokimasa HOJO who was already in his forties had simply identified himself as Shiro HOJO without having the post of suke (vice governor) or any official rank.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>それらの点から考えて、北条氏を桓武平氏直方の流れをひく伊豆の大豪族で、他の東国武士団より強い勢力を持っていたとは考えられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from those points, it cannot be thought that the Hojo clan was the Gozoku in the Izu Province with the lineage of Naotaka, the Kanmu-Heishi, and that it had stronger power than other armed groups in Togoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this basis, it cannot be supposed that the Hojo clan were drawn from the lineage of Naotaka of the Kanmu-Heishi, nor that they were the Gozoku in the Izu Province and more powerful than other armed groups in Togoku.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on these facts, it is impossible to assume that the Hojo clan were the great Gozoku in the Izu Province in the lineage of TAIRA no Naotaka of the Kanmu-Heishi and had greater influence than other armed groups in Togoku.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>伊豆の在庁官人として北条の地に館をかまえる武士であったが、その規模はけっして大きくなく、伊豆においても中流クラスの存在であったとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a samurai who resided at Hojo as Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) in the Izu Province, but it did not have a big power and was a samurai in the middle class in the Izu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather, they were samurai who resided at Hojo in the capacity of Zaichokanjin (local officials) without a great deal of power, belonging to the middle class in Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is assumed that they were the middle-class samurai in Izu Province resided at Hojo in the capacity of Zaichokanjin (local officials) without a great deal of power.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>時方の子北条時政は、娘北条政子が源頼朝の妻となったことから頼朝の挙兵に協力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokimasa HOJO, a son of Tokikata, helped MINAMOTO no Yoritomo to raise an army, because his daughter Masako HOJO had become Yoritomo&apos;s wife, and he made an effort to establish the Kamakura bakufu and gained the position as a major gokenin (an immediate vassal of the Shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) after Yoritomo was assigned to seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his daughter Masako HOJO married MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, Tokimasa HOJO, a son of Tokikata helped MINAMOTO no Yoritomo to raise an army, devoted himself to establishing the Kamakura bakufu, and became gokenin (an immediate vassal of the Shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) after Yoritomo was appointed seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A son of Tokikata, Tokimasa HOJO married his daughter Masako HOJO to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and helped his son-in-law to raise an army.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>時政は鎌倉幕府の創立に尽力し、頼朝が征夷大将軍に任じられると、有力御家人としての地位を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokimasa devoted himself to establishing the Kamakura bakufu, and after his son-in-law Yoritomo was appointed to seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), he gained the status of powerful gokenin (an immediate vassal of the Shogunate).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>頼朝亡き後もその子源頼家・源実朝の外戚として幕府内で強い影響力を持ち、初代執権となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after Yoritomo died, he had a strong influence inside bakufu as a maternal relative of MINAMOTO no Yoriie and MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, who were Yoritomo&apos;s sons, and became the first regent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after Yoritomo died, as the grandfather of Yorimoto&apos;s sons MINAMOTO no Yoriie and MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, Tokimasa remained influential inside bakufu and became the first regent.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after Yoritomo died, Tokimasa remained influential in the bakufu as the grandfather of Yorimoto&apos;s sons MINAMOTO no Yoriie and MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, and became the first regent.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>2代将軍頼家を追放し、修善寺に幽閉した上で謀殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He exiled the second Shogun Yoriie and killed him with malice aforethought during the confinement at the Shuzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He banished the second Shogun Yoriie and then had him confined and murdered at Shuzen-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He banished the second Shogun Yoriie and confined him to the Shuzen-ji Temple and murdered.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>さらに、3代将軍実朝をも暗殺して娘婿の平賀朝雅を将軍に立てようとしたが、娘の政子や息子の北条義時に反対され出家させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he tried to assassinate the third Shogun Sanetomo and make his daughter&apos;s husband Tomomasa HIRAGA become Shogun, but he was forced to become a priest because of the oppositions of his daughter Masako and his son Yoshitoki HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he assassinated the third Shogun Sanetomo and attempted to make his daughter&apos;s husband Tomomasa HIRAGA the Shogun, but was forced to become a priest after his daughter Masako and his son Yoshitoki HOJO opposed him.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he assassinated the third Shogun Sanetomo in an attempt to make his son-in-law Tomomasa HIRAGA the Shogun, but faced oppositions from his daughter Masako and his son Yoshitoki HOJO and was forced to become a priest.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>2代執権義時から数代にわたって他の有力御家人を次々と排除し、執権政治を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It removed other major gokenin one after another during some generations from the second regent Yoshitoki, and established the government of regent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over several generations, from the time of the second regent Yoshitoki, the Hojo clan disposed of other powerful gokenin (immediate vassals of the Shogunate) and established government by regent.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over generations from the second regent Yoshitoki, the Hojo clan had disposed of other powerful gokenin and established the solid base of regency.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>実朝が暗殺されると、義時は京都から九条頼経を4代将軍に迎え（摂家将軍）、将軍の地位を名目的なものとし、後鳥羽天皇の討幕運動である承久の乱に勝利し、幕府を安定させることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sanetomo was assaulted, Yoshitoki set up Yoritsune KUJO from Kyoto as the fourth Shogun (Sekke Shogun (Shogun from a regent family)), which made the position of Shogun nominal, and he won in Jokyu War, an anti-Shogunate movement, and made a success to stable the governance by bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the assassination of Sanetomo, Yoshitoki set up Yoritsune KUJO from Kyoto as the fourth Shogun (Sekke Shogun (Shogun from a regent family)), reducing the position of Shogun to a nominal one, won the Jokyu War against the anti-Shogunate movement of Emperor Gotoba, and successfully stabilized the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the assassination of Sanetomo, Yoshitoki helped Yoritsune KUJO from Kyoto to the fourth Shogun (Sekke Shogun (Shogun from a regent family)) to make the Shogun a nominal status, won the Jokyu War against the anti-Shogunate movement of Emperor Gotoba, and successfully stabilized the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>3代執権北条泰時は御成敗式目を制定し、幕府の御家人支配をゆるぎないものにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third regent Yasutoki HOJO established Goseibai-shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai), which firmed the rule of gokenin by bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third regent Yasutoki HOJO established Goseibai-shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai), which strengthened control over the gokenin of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third regent Yasutoki HOJO adopted the Goseibai-shikimoku (the code of conduct for samurai) to strengthen the bakufu&apos;s control over the gokenin.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>北条氏は、得宗と呼ばれる嫡流を中心に名越、赤橋、常葉、塩田、金沢、大仏などの諸家に分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo clan separated to branch families such as Nagoshi, Akahashi, Tokiwa, Shiota, Kanazawa and Osaragi other than the main branch of a family called Tokuso (the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan separated into branch families composed of a main branch which was called Tokuso, and sub-branches including the Nagoshi, Akahashi, Tokiwa, Shiota, Kanazawa and Osaragi.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo clan was composed of the head family called Tokuso and branch families including the Nagoshi, Akahashi, Tokiwa, Shiota, Kanazawa and Osaragi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>一門で執権、連署、六波羅探題などの要職を独占し、評定衆や諸国の守護の多くも北条一族から送り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It dominated the major positions such as regent, rensho (assistant to regents) and Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), and many of the hyojoshu (a member of Council of State) and Shugo (provincial constable) in various provinces were also assigned from the Hojo clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These families dominated the major positions including that of regent, rensho (assistant to regent) and Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), and also provided many of the Hyojoshu (members of Council of State) and the Shugo (provincial constables) for a great number of provinces.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These families dominated the major positions including that of regent, rensho (assistant to regent) and Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), and also provided many of the Hyojoshu (members of Council of State) and the Shugo (provincial constables).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>得宗家の家臣は御内人と呼ばれ、しばしば得宗の代官として得宗家の所領や守護所などに派遣されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vassals of the Tokuso family were called Miuchibito (private vassals of the Tokuso) and often dispatched to the territories of the Tokuso family and shugosho (provincial administration) as the local governor of Tokuso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vassals of the Tokuso family were called Miuchibito (private vassals of the Tokuso) and were often dispatched to the territories and shugosho (provincial administrations) of the Tokuso family as their agents.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vassals of the Tokuso family were called Miuchibito and were often dispatched as the agents to the Tokuso family&apos;s territories and shugosho (provincial administrations).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、得宗家の家政を取り仕切る最高責任者は内管領と呼ばれ、長崎円喜のように権力を振るうものも現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a person who held most of the responsibility for the private affairs of the Tokuso family was called Uchi-Kanrei (head of Tokuso Family), and some of them such as Enki NAGASAKI wielded power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officials who held most responsibility for the private affairs of the Tokuso family were called Uchi-Kanrei, and some of them, such as Enki NAGASAKI, wielded power.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chief officials of the private affairs of the Tokuso family were called Uchi-Kanrei, and some of them, such as Enki NAGASAKI, wielded power.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>摂家将軍頼経、九条頼嗣は成長すると独自の政権運営を指向し、執権に反抗的な態度を取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritsune and Yoritsugu KUJO, who were Sekke Shogun, aimed to manage the government by themselves after they grew up, and stroke an attitude of defiance against regent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sekke Shogun, Yoritsune and Yoritsugu KUJO, aimed to govern themselves after growing up and struck an attitude of defiance against the regent.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sekke Shoguns, Yoritsune and Yoritsugu KUJO, struck an attitude of defiance against the regent after they had grown up aiming at establishing their own administration.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>5代執権北条時頼は5代将軍頼嗣を追放し、宗尊親王を6代将軍に迎える事でこの危機を乗り切った（宮将軍）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fifth regent Tokiyori HOJO got through this crisis by exiling the fifth Shogun Yoritsugu and having the Imperial Prince Munetaka as the sixth Shogun (miyashogun (shogun from the Imperial Court)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fifth regent Tokiyori HOJO got through this crisis by exiling the fifth Shogun Yoritsugu and setting up the Imperial Prince Munetaka as the sixth Shogun (Miyashogun (shogun from the Imperial Court)).</e>
<cmt>What did he do about Yoritsune?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifth regent Tokiyori HOJO got through this crisis by exiling the fifth Shogun Yoritsugu and setting up the Imperial Prince Munetaka as the sixth Shogun (Miyashogun (shogun from the Imperial Court)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>8代執権北条時宗は元 (王朝)からの国書を黙殺して、御家人を統率して元寇と戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ignoring the diplomatic message from the Yuan (Dynasty), the eighth regent Tokimune HOJO led the goikenin agains the Yuan (Mongol invasion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ignoring the diplomatic message from the Yuan (Dynasty), the eighth regent Tokimune HOJO led the goikenin agains the Yuan (Mongol invasion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ignoring the diplomatic document from the Yuan (Dynasty), the eighth regent Tokimune HOJO led the gokenin against the Yuan (Mongol invasion).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これを機に鎌倉幕府は非御家人への軍事指揮権も獲得したほか、西国での支配権が強化され、北条一門が鎮西探題、長門探題として派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this event, the Kamakura bakufu got the power of military command against higokenin (non-vassal), and strengthened the ruling power in Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)) by dispatching the persons of Hojo clan to Chinzei tandai (office of the military governor of Kyushu) and Nagato tandai (Shogunal deputies in Nagato).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamakura bakufu used this opportunity to take command of higokenin (non-vassal), strengthen their control over Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)), and appoint members of the Hojo clan as Chinzei tandai (military governor of Kyushu) and Nagato tandai (Shogunal deputies in Nagato).</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamakura bakufu used this opportunity to take command of higokenin (non-vassals) and strengthen their control over Saigoku (western part of Japan (esp. Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)) where members of the Hojo clan were dispatched as Chinzei tandai (military governor of Kyushu) and Nagato tandai (Shogunal deputies in Nagato (in present-day Yamaguchi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、北条一門の諸国守護職の独占も進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Hojo clan became to dominate the position of Shugo in various provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Hojo clan occupied further Shugo postions in various provinces.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Hojo clan occupied more and more positions of Shugo throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>時宗の息子・9代執権北条貞時は平禅門の乱で内管領の平頼綱を滅ぼして得宗専制を確立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ninth regent Sadatoki HOJO, a son of Tokimine, established the tokuso autocracy after killing TAIRA no Yoritsune, Uchi-Kanrei, at Heizenmon War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ninth regent Sadatoki HOJO, a son of Tokimine, established a Tokuso autocracy after killing the Uchi-Kanrei, TAIRA no Yoshitsune in the Heizenmon War.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ninth regent Sadatoki HOJO, a son of Tokimune, killed TAIRA no Yoritsuna the Uchi-Kanrei in the Heizenmon War to secure a Tokuso autocracy.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これらにより、御家人層の没落が進行し、没落した御家人の中には御内人になる者もあらわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By those events, the class of gokenin were brought to ruin, among whom some gokenin became Miuchibito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These events destroyed the gokenin class, although some were able to take up positions as Miuchibito.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the gokein class was ruined to the extent that some were reduced to being Miuchibito.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>貞時の子・14代執権北条高時は後醍醐天皇の挙兵計画である正中の変を未然に防いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourteenth regent Takatoki HOJO, a son of Sadatoki, prevented the Shochu Disturbance before happens, which was the plan to raise an army by the Emperor Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourteenth regent Takatoki HOJO, a son of Sadatoki, put a stop to the Shochu disturbance, a plan by Emperor Godaigo to raise an army, before it could be implemented.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourteenth regent Takatoki HOJO, a son of Sadatoki, forestalled the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s plans to raise an army against the bakufu, which is called the Shochu Incident.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。d小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし、後醍醐が2度目の計画である元弘の変に続いて1333年（元弘3年/正慶2年）に再度挙兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the Emperor Godaigo raised an army again in 1333 soon after the Genko Disturbance, his second plan, Takauji ASHIKAGA, the top gokenin, destroyed Rokuhara Tandai in Kyoto in concert with it and Yoshisada NITTA in the Ueno Province also raised an army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1333, after implementing a second plan known as the Genko Disturbance, the Emperor Godaigo raised an army again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following to his second attempt known as the Genko Disturbance, the Emperor Godaigo raised an army one more time in 1333.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>御家人筆頭の足利尊氏がこれに呼応して京都の六波羅探題を滅ぼし、上野国の新田義貞も挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji ASHIKAGA, the top gokenin, responded by destroying Rokuhara Tandai in Kyoto and Yoshisada NITTA in the Ueno Province also raised an army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA, the top gokenin, acted in concert with the Emperor and destroyed Rokuhara Tandai in Kyoto, and Yoshisada NITTA in the Kozuke Province also followed them in raising an army.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>高氏の嫡子千寿王（足利義詮）が合流すると関東の御家人が雪崩を打って倒幕軍に寝返り、鎌倉を陥落させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Senjuo (Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), the legitimate child of Takauji, joined the army, the gokenin in the Kanto region to the army of overthrowing the Shogunate one after another and made Kamakura fall.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Senjuo (Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), the legitimate child of Takauji, joined the army, the gokenin in the Kanto region all switched sides together, and allowed Kamakura to fall.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Prince Senju (Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), the legitimate child of Takauji, joined his father, a large number of gokenin vassals from the Kanto region suddenly joined the anti-Shogunate army, and this led to the fall of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。I can&apos;t see why the kanji for Senju would be necessary here so I have deleted it.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この結果、北条一族のほとんどが討死または自害し、北条氏は滅亡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, almost all Hojo clan were killed or committed suicide, and the Hojo clan went to ruin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, almost all Hojo clan were killed or committed suicide, and the Hojo clan went to ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Almost the entire Hojo clan died in the battle or killed themselves, resulting in the collapse of the clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="34">
<j>鎌倉幕府滅亡後に建武の新政が開始された後も、北条氏の残党は津軽地方や日向国、伊予国など各地で散発的に反乱を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kenmu Restoration was begun after the fall of the Kamakura bakufu, the remnants of the Hojo clan sometimes raised a revolt in various places such as Tsugaru region, the Hyuga Province and the Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the fall of the Kamakura bakufu and the Kenmu restoration, the remnants of the Hojo clan occasionly revolted in places such as the Tsugaru region, Hyuga Province and Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the fall of the Kamakura bakufu was followed by the Kenmu restoration, the remnants of the Hojo clan occasionally revolted in places such as the Tsugaru region, Hyuga Province and Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1335年（建武 (日本)2年）に京都に潜伏していた高時の弟北条泰家（時興）が公家の西園寺公宗と政権転覆を計画するが未然に発覚する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1335 Yasuie (Tokioki) HOJO, a brother of Takatoki who stayed at Kyoto secretly, plotted against the regime with Kinmune SAIONJI, a kuge (court noble), but it was known before happened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1335 Yasuie (Tokioki) HOJO, a brother of Takatoki who was lying low in Kyoto secretly plotted against the regime with Kinmune SAIONJI, a kuge (court noble), but the plot was discovered.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1335 Yasuie (Tokioki) HOJO, a younger brother of Takatoki, who was lying low in Kyoto, and Kinmune SAIONJI, a kuge (court noble), secretly plotted against the regime but the plot was detected.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>公宗は後醍醐暗殺に失敗し誅殺されたが、泰家は逃亡して各地の北条残党に挙兵を呼びかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinmune failed to assault the Emperor Godaigo and was killed, but Yasuie escaped and asked the remnants of the Hojo clan in various placed to raise an army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinmune failed to assasinate Emperor Godaigo and was killed, but Yasuie escaped and called on the remnants of the Hojo clan in various locations to raise an army.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Kinmune failed to assassinate the Emperor Godaigo and was killed, Yasuie escaped and called on the remnants of the Hojo clan in various locations to take up arms.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>北条氏の拠点のひとつであった信濃国で高時の子北条時行らが挙兵し、中先代の乱を起こす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Shinano Province, which was one of the strongpoint of the Hojo clan, Tokiyuki HOJO, a son of Takatoki, and others raised an army, which was called Nakasendai War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shinano Province, one of the strongholds of the Hojo clan, Tokiyuki HOJO, a son of Takatoki, and others raised an army, and started the Nakasendai War.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shinano Province, one of the strongholds of the Hojo clan, Takatoki&apos;s son Tokiyuki HOJO and others raised an army and started the Nakasendai War.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>時行軍は信濃守護小笠原貞宗を破り、鎌倉を占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army of Tokiyuki defeated Sadamune OGASAWARA, the Shugo in the Shinano Province, and occupied Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army of Tokiyuki defeated Sadamune OGASAWARA, the Shugo in Shinano Province, and occupied Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>Removed &quot;the&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokiyuki&apos;s army defeated Sadamune OGASAWARA, the Shugo in Shinano Province, and occupied Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>鎌倉にいた尊氏の弟足利直義は、幽閉されていた護良親王を時行に担がれる事を恐れて殺害する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA, a brother of Takauji who stayed in Kamakura, killed the Imperial Prince Moriyoshi who was confined, because he was afraid that he would be set up by Tokiyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji&apos;s brother Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA who was in Kamakura killed the imprisoned Imperial Prince Moriyoshi because he was afraid that he would be set up by Tokiyuki.</e>
<cmt>I assume that trans1 means &quot;set up as emperor&quot;?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being in Kamakura at this time, Takauji&apos;s younger brother Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA killed the imprisoned Imperial Prince Moriyoshi, because he was afraid that Tokiyuki would support the Prince.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>足利尊氏は後醍醐天皇の勅状を得ないまま乱の討伐に向かい、時行を駆逐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA went to putting down the war without getting the imperial order of the Emperor Godaigo, expelled Tokiyuki and remained at Kamakura, leaving from the government of Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Without receiving the official order from Emperor Godaigo,Takauji ASHIKAGA went to end the war, expelled Tokiyuki and remained at Kamakura, thus leaving the government of the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Without receiving the official order from the Emperor Godaigo, Takauji headed for putting down the rebellion and expelled Tokiyuki.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>尊氏はそのまま鎌倉へ留まり建武政権から離反する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji remained at Kamakura and broke away from the Kenmu administration.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="42">
<j>その後、時行は南朝 (日本)から朝敵免除を受け、観応の擾乱の際に武蔵国で再度挙兵するが、尊氏に敗れて捕らえられ斬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Tokiyuki was released from the name of Emperor&apos;s enemy by the Southern Court and raised an army again in the Musashi Province at the time of Kanno Disturbance, but he was defeated by Takauji, captured and killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Tokiyuki was pardoned by the Southern Court and, at the time of Kanno Disturbance, raised an army again in Musashi Province, but was defeated, captured and killed by Takauji.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Tokiyuki was pardoned by the Southern Court and raised an army again in Musashi Province in the Kanno Disturbance, but he was defeated, captured and killed by Takauji.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="43">
<j>その子孫は横井氏を称し、南朝方について戦ったと言われているが、詳細ははっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that its descendant identified itself as the Yokoi clan and fought on the side of the Southern Court, but the detail is not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that his descendants identified themselves as the Yokoi clan and fought on the side of the Southern Court, but the details of this remain unclear.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that his descendants identified themselves as the Yokoi clan and joined the Southern Court army, but the details of this remain unclear.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>横井氏の子孫からは、幕末の熊本藩士で越前藩越前松平家に派遣され活躍した横井小楠が出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the descendant of the Yokoi clan, Shonan YOKOI is well-known, who was a statesman of the Kumamoto clan in the end of the Edo period, dispatched and played an active role in the Echizen Matsudaira family in the Echizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants of the Yokoi clan include Shonan YOKOI, a statesman of Kumamoto at the end of the Edo period, who was transferred to the Echizen Matsudaira family in the Echizen Province where he played an active role.</e>
<cmt>Natural English</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendants of the Yokoi clan include Shonan YOKOI, a statesman of Kumamoto in the late Edo period who was invited by the Matsudaira family of the Echizen (present-day Fukui Prefecture) domain where he became influential in politics.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), MD242(id:11277), Makuin-goo(id:94937), 経済準学士(id:22656), Eskimbot(id:29676), Slady(id:81121), Doskoi 8(id:1070), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Ash Crow(id:26765), Tanoshimo(id:151030), Alex K(id:86829), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), 百人(id:16483), 新芽(id:50924), 玄史生(id:43670), Whiz(id:15769), GURAX(id:107578), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 怪蘇(id:45514), Frei(id:12101), Loveless(id:129239), Yas(id:739), 越中掾(id:149423), Yosemite(id:5808), Fuji 3(id:52650), Lemon(id:11234), Mnd(id:15140), CHELSEA ROSE(id:118129), 松茸(id:27535), 古聞(id:110289), ちちぶ(id:184715), STBot(id:137943), Sat.K(id:3751), Riekanu(id:65656), Clarin(id:60278), 小者(id:172526), Rusk(id:9895), SilvonenBot(id:190970), ゐ(id:795), 海衛士(id:19229), 藤原朝臣太政大臣忠宣公(id:48007), Thijssie!bot(id:111619), わたあめひみつ(id:81640), Safkan(id:423), Junger(id:10282), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>