<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>地下家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jigeke (Jige families)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jigeke (Jige families)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jigeke (Jige Families)</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>地下家（じげけ）は、昇殿が許されない廷臣の家格。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jigeke was a family status of court officials which were not permitted to enter the Courtiers&apos; Hall in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jigeke was a family status of court officials who were not permitted to enter the Courtiers&apos; Hall in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jigeke was a family status of court officials who were not permitted to enter the Courtiers&apos; Hall in the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸時代に約460余家あった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, more than 460 Jigeke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, there were more than 460 Jigeke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, there were more than 460 Jigeke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>昇殿とは天皇の日常生活の場である清涼殿南廂にある殿上へ昇ることで、平安時代は家格・官位に関係なく、廷臣ごとに勅許を得ることでこれを許されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the Courtiers&apos; Hall in the Imperial Palace&apos; means entering the Courtiers&apos; Hall called Tenjo No Ma in the emperor&apos;s private living quarters, i.e., in the south side of the emperor&apos;s residence Seiryoden; and during the Heian period, court officials were authorized by imperial sanction to enter the Hall without regard for their family rank and court rank.</e>
<cmt>ウェブのページがリンクになっており、「殿上人」は「昇殿」、二つめの「殿上人」は「殿上」に訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering the Courtiers&apos; Hall in the Imperial Palace&apos; means entering the Courtiers&apos; Hall called Tenjo No Ma in the emperor&apos;s private living quarters, i.e., in the south side of the emperor&apos;s residence Seiryoden; and during the Heian period, court officials were authorized by imperial sanction to enter the Hall without regard for their family rank and court rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering the Courtiers&apos; Hall in the Imperial Palace&apos; means entering the Courtiers&apos; Hall called Tenjo No Ma in the emperor&apos;s private living quarters, i.e., in the south side of the emperor&apos;s residence Seiryoden; and during the Heian period, court officials were authorized by imperial sanction to enter the Hall without regard for their family rank and court rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかしながら、中世以降は昇殿を許される家（堂上家）と昇殿を許されない家（地下家）として、家格で明確に区分されるようになり成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Medieval Ages, the status Jigeke was established when the court officials were clearly divided according to their family rank, and the families permitted to enter the Hall were called Toshoke, and the families not permitted to enter the Hall were called Jigeke.</e>
<cmt>「中世日本」は「中世」の誤り、「家格公家の」はリンクになっているため誤って挿入されたものと思われますので、訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Medieval Ages, the status of Jigeke was established when court officials were clearly divided according to their family rank, and families permitted to enter the Hall were called Toshoke, and families not permitted to enter the Hall were called Jigeke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Medieval Ages, the status of Jigeke was established when court officials were clearly divided according to their family rank, and families permitted to enter the Hall were called Toshoke, and families not permitted to enter the Hall were called Jigeke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従って、地下家の廷臣は三位に昇っても昇殿は許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the court officials from Jigeke were not permitted to enter the Hall, even if their official rank was raised to Third Rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, court officials from Jigeke were not permitted to enter the Hall, even if their official rank was raised to the Third Rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, court officials from Jigeke were not permitted to enter the Hall, even if their official rank was raised to Sanmi (Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、六位蔵人は地下人であっても昇殿が許され、その中でもっとも上位である極臈を1代で3度務めるか、3代連続で務めた家は堂上家となる例があったが実例は少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet, although chamberlains of Sixth Rank were low-ranking court officials called Jigenin, they were permitted to enter the Hall; besides, there were cases--though a few cases--that when the chamberlain of six rank served as the highest ranked chamberlain called &apos;gokuro&apos; three times in his lifetime, or a family of the chamberlain of six rank produced the highest ranked chamberlain for three successive generations, they were raised to Toshoke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet, although chamberlains of Sixth Rank were low-ranking court officials called Jigenin, they were permitted to enter the Hall; besides, there were cases--though few cases--when a chamberlain of the six rank served as the highest ranked chamberlain called &apos;gokuro&apos; three times in his lifetime, or the family of the chamberlain of the six rank produced the highest ranked chamberlain for three successive generations, they were raised to Toshoke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, although chamberlains of Rokui (Sixth Rank) were low-ranking court officials called Jigenin, they were permitted to enter the Hall; besides, there were cases--though few cases--when a chamberlain of Rokui served as the highest ranked chamberlain called &apos;gokuro&apos; three times in his lifetime, or the family of the chamberlain of Rokui produced the highest ranked chamberlain for three successive generations, they were raised to Toshoke.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、堂上家と同様旧家・新家の区分があったが、桜町天皇（在位1735年 - 1747年）の時代にみだりに新家を立てることが停止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the division into Toshoke and Jigeke, there were another division of families into Kyuka (the families with long family genealogy) and Shinke (the families established around the Edo period); however, during the reign of Emperor Sakuramachi (reigned 1735-1747), it was banned to establish a new family without permission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the division into Toshoke and Jigeke, there were other divisions of families into Kyuka (families with a long family genealogy) and Shinke (families established during the Edo period); however, during the reign of Emperor Sakuramachi (1735-1747), it was forbidden to establish a new family without permission.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the division into Toshoke and Jigeke, there were other divisions of families into Kyuka (families with a long family genealogy) and Shinke (families established during the Edo period); however, during the reign of Emperor Sakuramachi (1735-1747), it was forbidden to establish a new family without permission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>明治維新後、地下家の筆頭格であった押小路家・壬生家は堂上家に準じて、また、伊丹家（伊丹重賢：青蓮院諸大夫）・尾崎家（尾崎三良：三条家諸大夫）・富井家（富井政章：聖護院坊官）は勲功により華族（男爵）に列せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the title of Danshaku (Baron - one of the titles of Kazoku (nobility)), was given to the Oshikoji family (or the Oshinokoji family) and the Mibu family, which were the leading Jigeke, correspondingly to raise them to Toshoke; and the Itami family (Shigekata ITAMI: court official served at Shorenin Temple), the Ozaki family (Saburo OZAKI: court official served at the Sanjo family), and the Tomii family (Masaakira Tomii: a senior servant at Shogoin Temple) in recognition of merit.</e>
<cmt>「地下の押小路家（中原氏流）」「壬生家（小槻姓）」はリンクになっているため誤って挿入されたものと思われますので、訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the title of Danshaku (Baron - one of the titles of Kazoku - nobility), was given to the Oshikoji family (or the Oshinokoji family) and the Mibu family, the leading Jigeke, correspondingly to raise them to Toshoke; and the Itami family (Shigekata ITAMI: court official served at Shorenin Temple), the Ozaki family (Saburo OZAKI: court official served at the Sanjo family), and the Tomii family (Masaakira Tomii: a senior servant at Shogoin Temple) in recognition of merit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the title of Danshaku (Baron - one of the titles of Kazoku - nobility), was given to the Oshikoji family (or the Oshinokoji family) and the Mibu family, the leading Jigeke, correspondingly to raise them to Toshoke; and the Itami family (Shigekata ITAMI: court official served at Shorenin Temple), the Ozaki family (Saburo OZAKI: court official served at the Sanjo family), and the Tomii family (Masaakira Tomii: a senior servant at Shogoin Temple) in recognition of merit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>だが、押小路家・壬生家の両家に次ぐ蔵人所出納の平田家以下、ほとんどの地下家は原則として士族として扱われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Primarily, however, the treatment of Shizoku (the family of samurai descendants) was applied to most families of Jigeke, including the Hirata family which served as a secretary at the Bureau of Archivists and ranked next to the Oshikoji family and the Mibu family in Jigeke.</e>
<cmt>「地下の押小路家（中原氏流）」「壬生家（小槻姓）」は誤って挿入されたものと思われますので訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Primarily, however, the treatment of Shizoku (the family of samurai descendants) was applied to most families of Jigeke, including the Hirata family who served as a secretary at the Bureau of Archivists and ranked next to the Oshikoji family and the Mibu family in Jigeke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Primarily, however, the treatment of Shizoku (the family of samurai descendants) was applied to most families of Jigeke, including the Hirata family who served as a secretary at the Bureau of Archivists and ranked next to the Oshikoji family and the Mibu family in Jigeke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>地下家の世職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jigeke - Hereditary officials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jigeke - Hereditary officials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jigeke - Hereditary officials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>地下家も堂上家と同様、世職世業であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like those of Toshoke, offices and businesses of Jigeke were hereditary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like those of Toshoke, offices and businesses of Jigeke were hereditary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like those of Toshoke, offices and businesses of Jigeke were hereditary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸時代には地下の世職は局務（外記上首：押小路家が世襲）・官務（左大史上首：壬生家が世襲）・蔵人所出納（平田家が世襲）が、それぞれ外記方・官方・蔵人方の世襲の諸役人を管掌し、朝廷の各種行事の運営を司った（催官人）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, the hereditary officials from Jigeke--the Head of Secretaries &apos;Kyokumu&apos; (the leader of secretaries in the Council of State Secretaries, inherited by the Oshinokoji family), the Head of Secretaries &apos;Kanmu&apos; (the leader of Senior Recorders of the Left, inherited by the Mibu family), and the court official at the Bureau of Archivists &apos;Kurodo dokoro Suino&apos; (inherited by the Hirata family)--were collectively called &apos;Saikanjin&apos; and respectively managed events and ceremonies of the Imperial Court by supervising the hereditary officials of secretaries, recorders, and staff of the Bureau of Archivists.</e>
<cmt>「地下の押小路家（中原氏流）」「史（律令制）」「壬生家（小槻姓）」「年中行事」はリンクになっているため誤って挿入されたものと思われますので、訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, hereditary officials from Jigeke--the Head of Secretaries &apos;Kyokumu&apos; (leader of secretaries in the Council of State Secretaries, inherited by the Oshinokoji family), the Head of Secretaries &apos;Kanmu&apos; (leader of Senior Recorders of the Left, inherited by the Mibu family), and the court official at the Bureau of Archivists &apos;Kurodo dokoro Suino&apos; (inherited by the Hirata family)--were collectively called &apos;Saikanjin&apos; and respectively managed events and ceremonies of the Imperial Court by supervising the hereditary officials of secretaries, recorders, and staff of the Bureau of Archivists.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, hereditary officials from Jigeke--the Head of Secretaries &apos;Kyokumu&apos; (leader of secretaries in the Council of State Secretaries, inherited by the Oshinokoji family), the Head of Secretaries &apos;Kanmu&apos; (leader of Senior Recorders of the Left, inherited by the Mibu family), and the court official at the Bureau of Archivists &apos;Kurodo dokoro Suino&apos; (inherited by the Hirata family)--were collectively called &apos;Saikanjin&apos; and respectively managed events and ceremonies of the Imperial Court by supervising the hereditary officials of secretaries, recorders, and staff of the Bureau of Archivists.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>特に、局務と官務を並べて両局と称され、幕末には出納を加えた三催という言葉も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, &apos;Kyokumu&apos; and &apos;Kanmu&apos; were collectively called &apos;both offices&apos;; later, at the end of the Tokugawa shogunate, &apos;Suino&apos; was added and the three offices were collectively called &apos;Sansai&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, &apos;Kyokumu&apos; and &apos;Kanmu&apos; were collectively called &apos;both offices;&apos; later, at the end of the Tokugawa shogunate, &apos;Suino&apos; was added and the three offices were collectively called &apos;Sansai&apos;.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, &apos;Kyokumu&apos; and &apos;Kanmu&apos; were collectively called &apos;both offices;&apos; later, at the end of the Tokugawa shogunate, &apos;Suino&apos; was added and the three offices were collectively called &apos;Sansai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>催官人の3家以外の地下家の官人は、並官人と呼ばれ、更にその下には儀式などの際に雑用を担当する下官人と呼ばれる人々がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the three families called Saikanjin, the court officials from Jigeke were called Namikanjin (general court officials) and had subordinates called Shimokanjin, who did heavy labor for the events and ceremonies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the three families called Saikanjin, the court officials from Jigeke were called Namikanjin (general court officials) and had subordinates called Shimokanjin, who did heavy labor for the events and ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the three families called Saikanjin, the court officials from Jigeke were called Namikanjin (general court officials) and had subordinates called Shimokanjin, who did heavy labor for the events and ceremonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>並官人は六位から立身するのに対して、下官人は七位もしくは史生から立身するのが通例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, Namikanjin rose from Sixth Rank, whereas Shimokanjin rose from Seventh Rank or Shisho (lower-ranked officials).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, Namikanjin rose from Sixth Rank, whereas Shimokanjin rose from Seventh Rank or Shisho (lower-ranked officials).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, Namikanjin rose from Rokui (Sixth Rank), whereas Shimokanjin rose from Nanai (Seventh Rank) or Shisho (lower-ranked officials).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>下官人は一種の「株」の形で身分を売買することが行われ（表面上は買主が売主の養子縁組に入る場合が多い）、また必要な人員確保を理由とした官司による取立も行われたため、京都や周辺の商人や農民が社会的身分の上昇や生活の糧（仕事）の獲得などを目的に地下官人の身分を得る例もあった（催官人は官司からの地下人補任の申請があれば、ほとんどの場合そのまま受理していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rank of Shimokanjin was traded in the form of &apos;stock&apos; ostensibly through adoption of &apos;the buyer&apos; by &apos;the seller&apos; in most cases, and sometimes &apos;collected&apos; by the government office on the pretext of staff acquisition, which led some cases of merchants and farmers in Kyoto and its surroundings acquiring the rank of Jige official for the purpose of raising their social status or earning their living, i.e., securing their jobs (In most cases, Saikanjin accepted the application for appointment of Jigenin by the government office without question.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rank of Shimokanjin was traded in the form of &apos;stock&apos; ostensibly through adoption of &apos;the buyer&apos; by &apos;the seller&apos; in most cases, and sometimes &apos;collected&apos; by the government office on the pretext of staff acquisition, which led some cases of merchants and farmers in Kyoto and its surroundings acquiring the rank of Jige official for the purpose of raising their social status or earning their living, i.e., securing their jobs (In most cases, Saikanjin accepted the application for appointment of Jigenin by the government office without question.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rank of Shimokanjin was traded in the form of &apos;stock&apos; ostensibly through adoption of &apos;the buyer&apos; by &apos;the seller&apos; in most cases, and sometimes &apos;collected&apos; by the government office on the pretext of staff acquisition, which led some cases of merchants and farmers in Kyoto and its surroundings acquiring the rank of Jige official for the purpose of raising their social status or earning their living, i.e., securing their jobs (In most cases, Saikanjin accepted the application for appointment of Jigenin by the government office without question).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>下官人は江戸後期の朝儀再興に伴う人手不足を補うために増員され、『地下次第』によれば延享5年（1746年）には73名であったものが、寛政8年（1796年）には110名、嘉永2年（1849年）には170名に増加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimokanjin was increased to meet the manpower shortage caused by imperial ceremony restoration in the latter half of the Edo period: According to &quot;Jige Shidai&quot; (Records of Jige), they were 73 in 1746, increased to 110 in 1796 and to 170 in 1849.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimokanjin was increased to meet the manpower shortage caused by imperial ceremony restoration during the latter half of the Edo period: According to &quot;Jige Shidai&quot; (Records of Jige), they were 73 in 1746, increased to 110 in 1796 and to 170 in 1849.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimokanjin was increased to meet the manpower shortage caused by imperial ceremony restoration during the latter half of the Edo period: According to &quot;Jige Shidai&quot; (Records of Jige), they were 73 in 1746, increased to 110 in 1796 and to 170 in 1849.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 のりまき(id:53470), Snap55(id:89773), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>