<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>六角家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Rokkaku Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rokkaku Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rokkaku Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>六角家（ろっかくけ）は、江戸時代に成立した公家の家系である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Rokkaku family is a family of court nobles established in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rokkaku family is a family of court nobles that were established during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rokkaku family is a family of court nobles that were established during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家の系統であるが、違う系統のものが並存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family belongs to the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, but other Rokkaku families also existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family belongs to the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, but other Rokkaku families also existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family belongs to the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, but other Rokkaku families also existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>中御門流園家の六角益通を初代とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of the family is Masumitu ROKKAKU of the Sono family of Nakamikado line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the family was Masumitu ROKKAKU of the Sono family of the Nakamikado line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the family was Masumitu ROKKAKU of the Sono family of the Nakamikado line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>羽林家の格式を持ち、書道・神楽を家業とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family has the same social standing as the Urin family, and its family business is Japanese Calligraphy and “Kagura” (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family had the same social standing as the Urin family, and its family business is Japanese Calligraphy and “Kagura” (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family rank was the House of Urin, and its family business is Japanese Calligraphy and “Kagura” (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines.)</e>
<cmt>用語集に沿って、修正。また格式の表現を他のファイルに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>明治維新後は子爵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was given the title of viscount after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was given the title of viscount after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was given the title of viscount after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>後水尾天皇の3男・守澄法親王が日光山輪王寺門跡となった際に、烏丸光広の次男烏丸広賢は随従したまま京都に戻らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Cloisered Imperial Prince Shucho, the third son of Emperor Gomizunoo, became the chief priest of Nikko-zan Rin-noji Temple, Hirokata KARASUMARU, the second son of Mitsuhiro KARASUMARU, accompanied him and did not return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Cloisered Imperial Prince Shucho, the third son of Emperor Gomizunoo, became the chief priest of Nikko-zan Rin-noji Temple, Hirokata KARASUMARU, the second son of Mitsuhiro KARASUMARU, accompanied him and did not return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Cloistered Imperial Prince Shucho, the third son of Emperor Gomizunoo, became the chief priest of Nikko-zan Rin-noji Temple, Hirokata KARASUMARU, the second son of Mitsuhiro KARASUMARU, accompanied him and did not return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Cloisered →Cloistered</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>彼が後に江戸幕府に仕えて高家に列した際に「六角院（ろっかくいん）」と名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when Hirokata served the Edo shogunate and became a “koke” (master of ceremony,) he called himself “ROKKAKUIN.”</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, when Hirokata served the Edo shogunate and became a “koke” (master of ceremony,) he called himself “ROKKAKUIN.”</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, when Hirokata served the Edo shogunate and became a “koke” (privileged family under Tokugawa Shogunate), he called himself “ROKKAKUIN.”</e>
<cmt>用語集に沿って、修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そして、その子孫がこれを略して「六角」家と名乗るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then his descendants shortened the name and began to call themselves the “Rokkaku” family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then his descendants shortened the name and began to call themselves the “Rokkaku” family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then his descendants shortened the name and began to call themselves the “Rokkaku” family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幕末期に所領のあった下野国で圧制を強いて田中正造ら地元住民に激しく抵抗された事でも知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also noted that the family was fiercely resisted by local residents including Shozo TANAKA, because the family oppressed them in Shimotsuke Province where the family had their &quot;syoryo&quot; (territory) at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also noted that the family was fiercely resisted by local residents including Shozo TANAKA, because the family oppressed them in Shimotsuke Province where they had their &quot;syoryo&quot; (territory) during the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also noted that the family was fiercely resisted by local residents including Shozo TANAKA, because the family oppressed them in Shimotsuke Province where they had their &quot;syoryo&quot; (territory) during the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Snap55(id:89773), 海衛士(id:19229), 水野白楓(id:22811), Aoooooooo(id:101274), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>