<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>松殿家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house of Matsudono</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house of Matsudono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsudono Family</e>
<cmt>&quot;house of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>松殿家（まつどのけ）は、摂関家として創設され、『本来であれば』摂家の近衛家・九条家に並ぶ序列の公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house of Matsudono established as the house of Regent and Senior Regent was, &quot;properly speaking,&quot; ranked with the house of Regent such as the house of Konoe and the Kujyo as the Court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house of Matsudono, established as a house of Regents and Senior Regents was, in theory, ranked at the same level as the houses of Regents such as the Konoe family and the Kujo family in the Court nobility.</e>
<cmt>No &quot;y&quot; is required in the romanization of &quot;じょ&quot;. Also, I think &quot;in theory&quot; is better than &quot;properly speaking&quot; here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsudono Family, established as a house of Regents and Senior Regents was, in theory, ranked at the same level as the houses of Regents such as the Konoe family and the Kujo family in the Court nobility.</e>
<cmt>&quot;house of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原氏藤原北家の嫡流の藤原忠通の次男、松殿基房が祖で、京都に松殿と呼ばれる屋敷を構えた事が家名の由来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name comes from the fact that Motofusa MATSUDONO, the originator, the second son of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, and a direct descendant of the Fujiwara clan of the Fujiwara-Hokke, built the residence called Matsudono, a pine palace, in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name comes from a residence called Matsudono, a pine palace built in Kyoto by the founder of the house, Motofusa MATSUDONO, who was the second son of FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, and a direct descendant of the the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>I think &quot;founder&quot; is better than &quot;originator&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name comes from a residence called Matsudono, a pine palace built in Kyoto by the founder of the house, Motofusa MATSUDONO, who was the second son of Fujiwara no Tadamichi, and a direct descendant of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA→Fujiwara、, theを削除（重複分）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『本来であれば』と断りを入れたのには理由がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several reasons that the phrase &quot;properly speaking&quot; was mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The phrase &quot;in theory&quot; was inserted above for a reason.</e>
<cmt>I couldn&apos;t find several reasons in subsequent sentence and changed the &quot;several reasons&quot; to &quot;a reason&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The phrase &quot;in theory&quot; was inserted above for a reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>それは藤原北家嫡流でありながら、摂関は2人でその後は大体が参議、出世しても大納言がやっとで、戦国時代 (日本)に早くも断絶してしまったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because only two members of the family could become the Regent, and most of the others were barely promoted to the Councilor or the Chief Councilor of State even though the family was the direct descendant of the Fujiwara-Hokke, and the family was ultimately discontinued even in the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite being direct descendants of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, the family only provided two Regents - subsequent generation getting no further than Councilor or, at best, Chief Councilor of State - and was quickly discontinued in the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>Took out &quot;it is because&quot; - it is implicit that this the reason mentioned above.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite being direct descendants of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, the family only provided two Regents - subsequent generation getting no further than Councilor or, at best, Dainagon (chief councilor of state) - and was quickly discontinued in the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Chief Councilor of State&quot; -&gt; &quot;Dainagon (chief councilor of state)&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>松殿基房・松殿師家・（松殿）隆忠の時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time of Motofusa MATSUDONO, Moroie MATSUDONO, and Takatada (MATSUDONO)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The era of Motofusa MATSUDONO, Moroie MATSUDONO, and Takatada (MATSUDONO)</e>
<cmt>I think &quot;time&quot; is unnatural in this context.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The era of Motofusa MATSUDONO, Moroie MATSUDONO, and Takatada (MATSUDONO)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>初代である松殿基房が高倉天皇の関白だった1179年、後白河天皇と平清盛の対立が頂点に達し、ついに清盛が法皇の幽閉と高官達の追放を断行、それに巻き込まれた基房も大宰権帥へと左遷となり、失意の内に36歳の若さで出家してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the originator, Motofusa MATSUDONO, was the Senior Regent of Emperor Takakura in 1179, the conflict between Emperor Go-Shirakawa and TAIRA no Kiyomori was so extremely intensified that TAIRA no Kiyomori resolutely carried out Emperor&apos;s imprisonment and senior officials&apos; exile, and subsequently, Motofusa, who had got involved in the incident, was demoted to the Dazai-no-Gonnosotsu, Deputy Governor of Dazaifu, and dejectedly became a priest at the age of 36.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Motofusa MATSUDONO, the founder of the house, was the Senior Regent of Emperor Takakura in 1179, the conflict between the retired Emperor Shirakawa and TAIRA no Kiyomori reached its peak with TAIRA no Kiyomori imprisoning the retired Emperor and exiling his senior officials, whereafter Motofusa, who had become involved, was demoted to Dazai-no-Gonnosotsu, Deputy Governor of Dazaifu, and left, mired in disappointment, to become a priest at the age of 36.</e>
<cmt>Reworked the sentence to make it read more naturally. Also changed &quot;the Emperor Go-Shirakwa to &quot;the retired Emperor, as per the term list of July 31st.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Motofusa MATSUDONO, the founder of the house, was the Senior Regent of the Emperor Takakura in 1179, the conflict between the retired Emperor Shirakawa and Taira no Kiyomori reached its peak with Taira no Kiyomori imprisoning the retired Emperor and exiling his senior officials, whereafter Motofusa, who had become involved, was demoted to Dazai-no-Gonnosotsu, Deputy Governor of Dazaifu, and left, mired in disappointment, to become a priest at the age of 36.</e>
<cmt>TAIRA→Taira &quot;the&quot; を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかも、基房は生母の父が太政大臣であるからという理由で長男の藤原隆忠（後の左大臣）ではなく、わずか8歳の松殿師家を後継者にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Motofusa appointed not his eldest son, FUJIWARA no Takatada (later to become the Minister of the Left), but Moroie MATSUDONO of only eight years old as his successor simply because the father of Moroie&apos;s real mother was the Grand Minister of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As his successor, Motofusa appointed not his eldest son, FUJIWARA no Takatada (later to become the Minister of the Left), but Moroie MATSUDONO who was only eight years old. on the basis that Moroie&apos;s maternal grandfather was the Grand Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>I think it is best to leave out &quot;moreover&quot; here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As his successor, Motofusa appointed not his eldest son, Fujiwara no Takatada (later to become the Minister of the Left), but Moroie MATSUDONO who was only eight years old on the basis that Moroie&apos;s maternal grandfather was the Grand Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA→Fujiwara</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、木曾義仲が都に入ると基房は娘を義仲の側室に差し出す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afther that, when Yoshinaka KISO entered Kyoto, Motofusa offered his daughter as Yoshinaka&apos;s concubine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, when Yoshinaka KISO entered Kyoto, Motofusa offered him his daughter as a concubine.</e>
<cmt>I think &quot;thereafter&quot; is better than &quot;after that&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, when Yoshinaka KISO entered Kyoto, Motofusa offered him his daughter as a concubine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その甲斐があって1183年師家は義仲の支持を背景にわずか12歳で摂政・内大臣・藤氏長者で就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such efforts paied off, and Moroie became the Regent, Inner Minister, Chief of the To Family at the age of only 12 with the support of Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These efforts paid off and, in 1183, with the support of Yoshinaka, Moroie became a Regent taking up the post of Inner Minister, Chief of the To clan at the age of only 12.</e>
<cmt>Promoted &quot;with the support of Yoshinaka&quot; to earlier in sentence for better linking with Yoshinaka.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These efforts paid off and, in 1183, with the support of Yoshinaka, Moroie became a Regent taking up the post of Inner Minister, Chief of the To clan at the age of only 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>だが、その数ヵ月後には源義経に義仲は討たれて、師家は解任されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, several months later, Yoshinaka was defeated by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, and Moroie was dismissed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a few months later, Yoshinaka was defeated by MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, and Moroie was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>I feel that the nuance of the source text is that not much time elapsed, hence &quot;a few months later&quot; rather than &quot;several months later&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a few months later, Yoshinaka was defeated by Minamoto no Yoshitsune, and Moroie was dismissed.</e>
<cmt>MINAMOTO→Minamoto</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、半世紀近くも師家は官職に就く事が出来ずに失意の日々を過ごした（ちなみに師家は甥にあたる道元を養子に迎えようとして失敗している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Moroie could not take an official post for about a half century, and spent his days in despair. (In addition, Moroie failed his attempt to adopt his nephew, Dogen.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moroie was subsquently unable to take an official post for close to half century, and spent his life in disappointment (he also failed in attempt to adopt his nephew, Dogen).</e>
<cmt>&quot;dispair&quot; seems to me to be too strong a word here. I prefer disappointment.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moroie was subsequently unable to take an official post for close to half century, and spent his life in disappointment (he also failed in attempt to adopt his nephew, Dogen).</e>
<cmt>subsquently→subsequently</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>隆忠は、この間、弟の前内大臣師家を官職の上で追い抜き、1211年まで左大臣をつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatada got promoted in a government position ahead of his brother, Moroie of the former Inner Minister, and served as Minister of the Left until 1211.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Takatada got promoted to Minister of the Left, a post which ranked above the post of Inner Minister fomerly occupied by his younger brother, and served until 1211.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity and readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Takatada got promoted to Minister of the Left, a post which ranked above the post of Inner Minister formerly occupied by his younger brother, and served until 1211.</e>
<cmt>fomerly→formerly</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>師家の子孫と南北朝争乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of Moroie and the conflict of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants of Moroie and the conflict of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendants of Moroie and the conflict of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、師家の弟や息子の代には大納言や権大納言を輩出したものの、次の世代には位こそは正二位に進む事は出来ても、役職は中納言・参議がやっとというクラスまでに低下する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in the days of Moroie&apos;s brother and son, the Chief Councilor of State or the Junior Chief Councilor of State were produced, but in the next generation, the family was downgraded in such a way that they managed to advance to the Senior Second Court Rank, but they barely got the position of the Deputy Chief Councilor of State or the Councilor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the generation Moroie&apos;s brother and son occupied the posts of Chief Councilor of State and the Junior Chief Councilor of State, the stock of the house declined, and subsequent generations advanced no further than Deputy Chief Councilor of State and Councilor with a Senior Second Rank.</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although during the generations of Moroie&apos;s brother and son, other members of the Matsudono family held the posts of Chief Councilor of State and Acting Chief Councilor of State, the stock of the house declined, and subsequent generations advanced no further than Deputy Chief Councilor of State and Councilor with a Senior Second Rank.</e>
<cmt>世代は二世代あり、所有格によりひとつの文にすべき。“the generation Moroie&apos;s” -&gt; “the generations of Moroie&apos;s “To be honest the translation we submitted is not terribly clear but if we use &quot;the generations of Moroie&apos;s brother and son occupied the posts of Chief Councilor of State and the Junior Chief Councilor of State&quot; this effectively means that &quot;generations&quot; held posts, which doesn&apos;t really make sense. I have tried to rewrite this more clearly.&quot;house of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そして南北朝時代 (日本)の松殿忠嗣（基房からみて玄孫）の代に権大納言に昇って家名復活の兆しが出てきたその矢先に、忠嗣は吉野朝廷側へ離反してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Tadatsugu MATSUDONO (Motofusa&apos;s great-great grandson) advanced to the Junior Chief Councilor of State, and at the time when the family name was about to be restored, Tadatsugu drifted away to the Yoshino Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Tadatsugu MATSUDONO (Motofusa&apos;s great-great grandson) advanced to the post of Junior Chief Councilor of State, but drifted away to the Yoshino Court just as the family name was about to be restored.</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Tadatsugu MATSUDONO (Motofusa&apos;s great-great grandson) advanced to the post of Junior Chief Councilor of State, but drifted away to the Yoshino Court just as the family name was about to be restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このため、南北朝合一後は再び衰退への道を歩む事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For these reasons, the family follwed a course of decline again after the unification of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the family fortunes continued to decline, even after the unification of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence for readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the family fortunes continued to decline, even after the unification of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>衰退と断絶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The decline and the fall of the family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decline and the fall of the family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The decline and the fall of the family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>その後、1508年に忠嗣の玄孫にあたる松殿忠顕が従三位に叙せられて後に正三位参議となり、その子松殿家豊が従五位上に叙された後の系譜が途絶えており、戦国時代中期には断絶したものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, in 1508, Tadatsugu&apos;s great-great grandson, Tadaaki MATSUDONO was raised to the Junior Third Court Rank, later becoming the Senior Third Court Rank, Councilor, and Tadaaki&apos;s son, Ietoyo MATSUDONO was raised to the Junior Fifth-High Court Rank, but from that time on, the genealogical record broke off; thus, the family might be discontinued in the middle of the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsugu&apos;s great-great grandson, Tadaaki MATSUDONO was promoted to the Junior Third Rank in 1508, and later to the Senior Third Court Rank as a Councilor, and Tadaaki&apos;s son, Ietoyo MATSUDONO reached the Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, but the genealogical record ceases thereafter, suggesting that the family was discontinued during the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence for readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsugu&apos;s great-great grandson, Tadaaki MATSUDONO was promoted to the Junior Third Rank in 1508, and later to the Senior Third Rank as a Councilor, and Tadaaki&apos;s son, Ietoyo MATSUDONO reached the Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, but the genealogical record ceases thereafter, suggesting that the family was discontinued during the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Senior Third Court Rank&quot; -&gt; &quot;Senior Third Rank&quot;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>再興と再度の断絶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The restoration and another fall of the family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The repeated restoration and fall of the family</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence for readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The repeated restoration and fall of the family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、江戸時代に入って松殿家を再興する動きがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a movement to restore the house of Matsudono at the beginning of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of the Edo period, there was a movement to restore the house of Matsudono.</e>
<cmt>I think the timing of the movement should be promoted to the beginning of the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of the Edo period, there was a movement to restore the Matsudono family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;house of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>所領1000石が新たに朝廷より下賜され九条幸家の3男松殿道基が松殿家を復興して1642年に従三位に叙されたが、1代で途絶え、続いて九条尚実の次男松殿忠孝が1765年に再度松殿家を再興して2年後に従三位に叙されたが、これも1代で断絶している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michimoto MATSUDONO, the third son of Yukiie KUJYO, who was newly granted the fief of 1,000 koku from the Court, restored the house of Matsudono, and was raised to the Junior Third Court Rank in 1642, but the family was discontinued in one generation, and subsequently, Tadataka MATSUDONO, the second son of Naozane KUJYO restored the house of Matsudono again in 1765, raised to the Junior Third Court Rank two years later, but this family was also discontinued in one generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Granted a fief with a yield 1,000 koku of rice by the Court, Michimoto MATSUDONO, the third son of Yukiie KUJO, restored the house of Matsudono and was promoted to Junior Third Rank in 1642, but his family was discontinued in a single generation; Tadataka MATSUDONO, the second son of Naozane KUJO, restored the house of Matsudono again in 1765 and reached Junior Third Rank two years later, but this family was also discontinued in a single generation.</e>
<cmt>Reworked the sentence to try and make it more readable.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Granted a fief with a yield 1,000 koku of rice by the Court, Michimoto MATSUDONO, the third son of Yukiie KUJO, restored the Matsudono family and was promoted to Junior Third Rank in 1642, but his family was discontinued in a single generation; Tadataka MATSUDONO, the second son of Naozane KUJO, restored the Matsudono family again in 1765 and reached Junior Third Rank two years later, but this family was also discontinued in a single generation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;house of～&quot; -&gt; &quot;～family&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>明治期には松園家と鶴殿家が興った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji era, the house of Matsuzono and the house of Tsurudono were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji era, the house of Matsuzono and the house of Tsurudono were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji era, the house of Matsuzono and the house of Tsurudono were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Ponsaku(id:31417), Andee(id:20421), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Riekanu(id:65656), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>