<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>摂家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekke (Setsu Family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sekke (Setsu Family)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sekke (Setsu Family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>摂家（せっけ）とは、鎌倉時代に成立した藤原氏嫡流で公家の家格の頂点に立った5家のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekke is five families that are the main branch of the Fujiwara clan family established in the Kamakura era and achieved the top of court noble&apos;s Kakau (family status).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sekke consisted of five families, which were the main branch of the Fujiwara Family clan established during the Kamakura era and achieved the top rank of court nobility kakau (family status).</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sekke consisted of five families that the main branch of the Fujiwara Family clan had established during the Kamakura era, whereby it achieved the top rank of court nobility kakaku (family status).</e>
<cmt>kakau→kakakuに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大納言・右大臣・左大臣を経て摂政・関白に昇任できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were able to be promoted to regent or chief adviser to the Emperor through chief councillor of state, minister of the right, and minister of the left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were able to be promoted to regent or chief adviser to the Emperor through the chief councilor of state, minister of the right and minister of the left.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were able to be promoted to regent or chief adviser to the Emperor through dainagon (chief councilor of state), udaijin (minister of the right) and sadaijin (minister of the left).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the chief councilor of state&quot; -&gt; &quot;dainagon (chief councilor of state)&quot;、&quot;minister of the right&quot; -&gt; &quot;udaijin (minister of the right)&quot;、&quot;sadaijin (minister of the left)&quot;　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>近衛家・九条家・一条家・二条家・鷹司家の5家がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sekke consists of five families, Konoe Family, Kujo Family, Ichijo Family, Nijo Family, and Takatsukasa Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sekke consisted of five families: Konoe, Kujo, Ichijo, Nijo and Takatsukasa.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sekke consisted of five families: Konoe, Kujo, Ichijo, Nijo and Takatsukasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>摂関家（せっかんけ）、五摂家（ごせっけ）、執柄家（しっぺいけ）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekke is also called Sekkan Family (Sekkannke), Gosekke (Gosetsu Family), or Shippei Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sekke is also referred to as the Sekkan Family (Sekkannke), Gosekke (Gosetsu Family) or Shippei Family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sekke is also referred to as the Sekkan Family (Sekkannke), Gosekke (Gosetsu Family) or Shippei Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この5家の中から藤氏長者も選出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leader of Toshi/Toji had also been elected from the five families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The leader of Toshi (Toji) had also been elected from among the five families.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The leader of Toshi (Toji) had also been elected from among the five families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>五摂家の成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of Gosekke (Gosetsu Family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the Gosekke (Gosetsu Family)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the Gosekke (Gosetsu Family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原北家の藤原良房の嫡流を経て、鎌倉初期に至り藤原忠通の子の近衛基実と九条兼実がそれぞれ近衛流摂関家と九条流摂関家を成立させ、嫡流が2家に分裂した（この他に同じ忠通の子である松殿基房を祖とする松殿流摂関家の松殿家があったが、松殿師家が摂政になった後は摂政・関白を輩出することなく何度も断絶を繰り返しているため摂家には数えない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through the main branch of the family of FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa of Fujiwara Hokke (Fujiwara Hoku Family), in the Early Kamakura era FUJIWARA no Tadamichi&apos;s sons, Motozane KONOE and Kanezane KUJO established Sekkan Family (Sekkan-ke) of Konoe group and Kujoryu Sekkan-ke, Regent family, respectively, which resulted in the divison of the main branch of the family into two families (although there was Matsudono Family of Sekkan Family (Sekkannke) of Matsudono group, the originator of which was Motofusa MATSUDONO who was also a son of Tadamichi, other than the two families, Matsudono Family is not counted as Sekke because after Moroie MATSUDONO became regent, no one became regent or chief advisor of the Emperor from Matsudono Family and the family line failed many times).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the main branch of the family of FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa of Fujiwara Hokke (Fujiwara Hoku Family), in the early Kamakura period, FUJIWARA no Tadamichi&apos;s sons, Motozane KONOE and Kanezane KUJO established the Sekkan Family (Sekkan-ke) of the Konoe group and Kujoryu Sekkan-ke, a regent family, respectively; this resulted in the division of the main branch of the family into two families (although there was the Matsudono Family of the Sekkan Family (Sekkannke) of the Matsudono group, the originator of which was Motofusa MATSUDONO, who was also a son of Tadamichi; but other than the two families, Matsudono Family is not counted as sekke because after Moroie MATSUDONO became regent no one from the Matsudono Family became a regent or chief advisor of the Emperor and the family line failed many times.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the main branch of the family of FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa of Fujiwara Hokke (Fujiwara Hoku Family), in the early Kamakura period, FUJIWARA no Tadamichi&apos;s sons, Motozane KONOE and Kanezane KUJO established the Sekkan Family (Sekkan-ke) of the Konoe group and Kujoryu Sekkan-ke, a regent family, respectively; this resulted in the division of the main branch of the family into two families (although there was, in addition the Matsudono Family of the Sekkan Family (Sekkannke) of the Matsudono group, the originator of which was Motofusa MATSUDONO, who was also a son of Tadamichi; but, the Matsudono Family is not counted as sekke, with the two families because, after Moroie MATSUDONO became regent, no one from the Matsudono Family became a regent or chief advisor of the Emperor and the family line failed many times).</e>
<cmt>長文でわかりにくいですが、「although there was, in addition the Matsudono Family of the Sekkan Family (Sekkannke)」　in additionなどを入れて少しわかりやすくしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>のち、近衛流摂関家からは嫡流の近衛家ならびに、鷹司兼平により鷹司家が成立。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Konoe Family that was the main branch of the family was established from Sekkan Family (Sekkan-ke) of Konoe group, and Takatsukasa Family was established by Kanehira TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the Konoe Family, which was the main branch, was established from the Sekkan Family (Sekkan-ke) of the Konoe group, and the Takatsukasa Family was established by Kanehira TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Konoe Family, which was the main branch, was established from the Sekkan Family (Sekkan-ke) of the Konoe group, and the Takatsukasa Family was established by Kanehira TAKATSUKASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>さらに九条流摂関家からは、九条道家の子の二条良実、一条実経、教実により、それぞれ二条家、一条家、九条家が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Nijo Family, Ichijo Family, and Kujo Family were established by Michiie KUJO&apos;s sons, Yoshizane NIJO, Sanetsune ICHIJO, and Norizane KUJO, respectively, from Kujoryu Sekkan-ke, Regent family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the Nijo, Ichijo and Kujo families were established by Michiie KUJO&apos;s sons Yoshizane NIJO, Sanetsune ICHIJO and Norizane KUJO, respectively, from Kujoryu Sekkan-ke, the regent family.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the Nijo, Ichijo and Kujo families were established by Michiie KUJO&apos;s sons Yoshizane NIJO, Sanetsune ICHIJO and Norizane KUJO, respectively, from Kujoryu Sekkan-ke, the regent family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>上図の補注 兄弟は、年長の順に左から並んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additional notes for the above figure: brothers are shown in the seniority order from the left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additional notes for the above figure: the brothers are shown from the left in their order of seniority.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additional notes for the above figure: the brothers are shown from the left in their order of seniority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>摂家以外からの摂政・関白就任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking a position of regent or chief advisor to the Emperor from the family other than Sekke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking a position of regent or chief advisor to the Emperor from the family other than Sekke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking a position of regent or chief advisor to the Emperor from the family other than Sekke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>五摂家成立以後は、摂政・関白にはこの5家の者のみが任じられ、摂家たる5家は摂政、関白職を独占した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the establishment of Gosekke, only the member of the Gosekke was appointed as regent or chief advisor to the Emperor, which means that five families that were Sekke dominated the positions of regent and chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the establishment of Gosekke, only a member of the Gosekke could be appointed as regent or chief advisor to the Emperor, meaning that the five families comprising the Sekke dominated the positions of regent and chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the establishment of Gosekke, only a member of the Gosekke could be appointed as regent or chief advisor to the Emperor, meaning that the five families comprising the Sekke dominated the positions of regent and chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、関白就任を目論んだ豊臣秀吉（豊臣秀吉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who tried to take a position of chief advisor to the Emperor (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI tried to take a position as chief advisor to the Emperor (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI tried to take a position as chief advisor to the Emperor (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>当時は平朝臣を称していた）は、1585年（天正13年）に近衛前久の猶子となり藤原秀吉となることで関白就任を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, he called himself TAIRA no Ason) became Yoshi, adapted child of Sakihisa KONOE in 1585 to become FUJIWARA no Hideyoshi thereby achieving the position of chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time he called himself TAIRA no Ason but became Yoshi, the adapted child of Sakihisa KONOE in 1585; ultimately, he became FUJIWARA no Hideyoshi and thereby achieved the position of chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time he called himself TAIRA no Ason but became Yoshi, the adapted child of Sakihisa KONOE in 1585; ultimately, he became FUJIWARA no Hideyoshi and thereby achieved the position of chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、豊臣秀吉の養子である豊臣秀次は「豊臣朝臣」として関白に任じられており、これが五摂家以外で関白に任じられた唯一の例外である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s adopted child, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, was appointed to be chief advisor to the Emperor, which was the only exception that a member of the family other than Gosekke was appointed as chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s adopted child, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, was appointed as the Emperor&apos;s chief adviser; thus marking the only exception to the tradition that no member of the family other than Gosekke would be appointed as the chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s adopted child, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, was appointed as the Emperor&apos;s chief adviser under the name of TOYOTOMI no Ason, thus marking the only exception to the tradition that no member of the family other than Gosekke would be appointed as the chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>under the name of TOYOTOMI no Asonを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>江戸幕府と摂家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo Shogunate and Sekke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Shogunate and the Sekke</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Bakufu and the Sekke</e>
<cmt>&quot;Shogunate&quot; -&gt; &quot;Bakufu&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸幕府が成立すると、幕府は禁中並公家諸法度を制定して、摂政・関白は幕府の推薦なくして任命できない仕組みとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Edo Shogunate was established, the Shogunate enacted Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto (Court Noble&apos;s Act), whereby the structure in which the appointment of regent or chief advisor to the Emperor cannot be made without recommendation by Shogunate was created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Edo shogunate was established, it enacted the Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto (Court Noble&apos;s Act), whereby the structure in which the appointment of a regent or chief advisor to the Emperor could be made without a recommendation by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was established, it enacted the Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto (Court Noble&apos;s Act), whereby the structure in which the appointment of a regent or chief advisor to the Emperor could not be made without a recommendation by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>notを補足しました。&quot;shogunate&quot; -&gt; &quot;bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その一方で、幕府は摂政・関白並びに摂家に対する公然・非公然の支援を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Shogunate offered official and unofficial support for regent, chief advisor to the Emperor, and Sekke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the shogunate offered official and unofficial support for the regent, chief advisor to the Emperor and the sekke.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the bakufu offered official and unofficial support for the regent, chief advisor to the Emperor and the sekke.</e>
<cmt>&quot;shogunate&quot; -&gt; &quot;bakufu&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この結果、寛永年間以後は摂関政治の時代ですら建前上決定に参与出来なかった朝議を摂政・関白が主宰し、清華家以下の公家は大臣であっても参加権・発言権が剥奪されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, after the Kan-ei period, regent and chief advisor to the Emperor presided over Imperial court&apos;s deliberation that regent and chief advisor to the Emperor were not able to participate in, in principle, even in the period of Sekkan (regent to the emperor) government, and court noble who is from Seiga Family or other families of the lower position was deprived of the rights of participation and speaking even if the court noble is minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, after the Kan-ei period the regent and chief advisor to the Emperor presided over the Imperial Court&apos;s decision that the regent and chief advisor to the Emperor were, as a general rule, not able to participate, even in the period of the Sekkan (regent to the Emperor) government; thus any court noble who was from the Seiga Family or another family of lower position would be deprived of the rights of participation and speaking, even if the court noble was a minister.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, after the Kan-ei period the regent and chief advisor to the Emperor presided over the Imperial Court&apos;s decision that the regent and chief advisor to the Emperor were, as a general rule, not able to participate, even in the period of the Sekkan (regent to the Emperor) government; thus any court noble who was from the Seiga Family or another family of lower position would be deprived of the rights of participation and speaking, even if the court noble was a minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、摂家が断絶した場合の後継の養子には必ず皇族か同じ摂家からの養子しか認められなくなり、太政大臣の任官要件に摂政・関白・征夷大将軍の経験者という暗黙の規定が追加されて、清華家以下の公家は朝廷中枢から排除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in the case where a Sekke&apos;s family line fails, only the adopted child from imperial family or the adopted child from the same Sekke was allowed to inherit the Sekke, and the tacit provision that only the person who once took the position of regent, chief advisor to the Emperor, or Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) shall be appointed as grand minister of state was added, whereby court noble from Seiga Family and other families of the lower position was expelled from the mainstay of the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in the case where a family line of the Sekke failed, there was an additional provision that only the adopted child from the Imperial Family or the adopted child from the same sekke was allowed to inherit the sekke, and the tacit provision that only the person who once took the position of regent, chief advisor to the Emperor or seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians; great, unifying leader) could be appointed as the grand minister of state, whereby court nobles from the Seiga Family and other families of the lower position were expelled from their positions as mainstays of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in the case where a family line of the Sekke failed, there was an additional provision that only the adopted child from the Imperial Family or the adopted child from the same sekke was allowed to inherit the sekke, and the tacit provision that only the person who once took the position of regent, chief advisor to the Emperor or seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) could be appointed as the grand minister of state, whereby court nobles from the Seiga Family and other families of the lower position were expelled from their positions as mainstays of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>&quot;seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians; great, unifying leader)&quot; -&gt; &quot;seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>その結果、江戸時代の朝廷は五摂家の当主の合意のみでの運営が可能となり、天皇と言えどもそれに抗う事は困難となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, it became possible to administer the Imperial court in the Edo era by the agreements of Gosekke alone, and therefore it became difficult even for the Emperor to opposed to the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, it became possible to administer the Imperial Court of the Edo period by the agreements of the Gosekke alone, so that it became difficult even for the Emperor to oppose the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, it became possible to administer the Imperial Court of the Edo period by the agreements of the Gosekke alone, so that it became difficult even for the Emperor to oppose the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>更にその五摂家の当主ですら幕府が摂政・関白の任命権を事実上掌握している以上、幕府の意向に反する事は出来なかったために、その結果、幕府→摂家・武家伝奏（最大でも5＋4名）→天皇及び諸公家という幕府にとっては非常に効率の良い朝廷統制の仕組みが完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, as long as Shogunate virtually controlled the right of appointment of regent or chief advisor to the Emperor, even the family head of Gosekke could not oppose to the intention of Shogunate, and the system for controlling the Imperial court, which was the orderly sequence of from Shogunate through Sekke/samurai families (five plus four peaple at most) to Emperor and each court noble, was therefore established, which was the extremely efficient system for Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, as long as the shogunate virtually controlled the right of appointment of regent or chief advisor to the Emperor, even the family head of the Gosekke could not oppose the intention of the shogunate, and the system for controlling the Imperial Court, which was the orderly sequence from the shogunate through the sekke/samurai families (five plus four people at most) to the Emperor and each court noble, was thereby established as an extremely efficient system for the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, as long as the bakufu virtually controlled the right of appointment of regent or chief advisor to the Emperor, even the family head of the Gosekke could not oppose the intention of the bakufu, and the system for controlling the Imperial Court, which was the orderly sequence from the bakufu through the sekke/samurai families (five plus four people at most) to the Emperor and each court noble, was thereby established as an extremely efficient system for the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;shogunate&quot; -&gt; &quot;bakufu&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>もっとも、天皇や摂家以外の公家もこれに素直に従う事はなく、機会を捉えて抵抗を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nontheless, Emperor and cout nobles from families other than Sekke were not amenable and continued resistance when the opportunity arose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nonetheless, the Emperor and court nobles from families other than the Sekke were not amenable and continued their resistance when the opportunity arose.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nonetheless, the Emperor and court nobles from families other than the Sekke were not amenable and continued their resistance when the opportunity arose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その不満が後水尾天皇・霊元天皇両太上天皇による院政や宝暦事件・尊号一件・廷臣八十八卿列参事件などの形で噴出することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their discontent erupted as the form of cloister governments by both Ex-Emperors who were Gomizuno Emperor/Reigen Emperor, or Horeki Conspiracy, Songo Ikken (incident), and Demo of eighty-eight retainers of Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their discontent erupted in the form of cloister governments by both former emperors Gomizuno (Emperor/Reigen Emperor), in the Horeki Conspiracy or Songo Ikken (incident) and Demo, of the 88 retainers of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their discontent erupted in the form of cloister governments by both former emperors Gomizuno (Emperor/Reigen Emperor), in the Horeki Conspiracy or Songo Ikken (incident) and Demo, of the 88 retainers of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>明治維新後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>明治維新後は、各々の家の当主は公爵に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, the family head of each family was entitled to duke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, the family head of each family was entitled to be a duke.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, the family head of each family was entitled to be a duke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また明治新政権が太政官制を敷いた為、摂家から摂政及び関白に任じられることはなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, since the Meiji new administration adopted System of Departments of State, Sekke was no longer appointed as regent or chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, since the Meiji&apos;s new administration adopted the system of departments of state, the sekke was no longer appointed as regent or chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, since the Meiji&apos;s new administration adopted the system of departments of state, the sekke was no longer appointed as regent or chief advisor to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>従って明治以降の5家については、「旧摂家」或いは｢旧摂関家」など「旧」を冠して呼称することが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the five families after the Meiji era are, most of the time, referred to as &quot;Old Sekke&quot; or &quot;Old Sekkan Family&quot; with a prefix &quot;Old&quot; being added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the five families after the Meiji era are now generally referred to as &quot;Old Sekke&quot; or &quot;Old Sekkan Family&quot; with the prefix &quot;Old&quot; being added.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the five families after the Meiji era are now generally referred to as &apos;Old Sekke&apos; or &apos;Old Sekkan Family,&apos; with the prefix &apos;Old&apos; as an addition.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」にあわせて&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>戦前の旧皇室典範に於いては皇族男子との結婚資格は皇族と華族に与えられていたが、将来の皇后たるべき皇室嫡流の正室（即ち皇太子妃）となるべき者は、皇族若しくは旧摂家の女子に限るという不文律が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to old Imperial House Act before the World War II, royalty and new nobility were qualified to get married to man of royalty, and there existed a consuetude that a legitimate wife of the main branch of Imperial Family who is to be the future empress (i.e., crown princess) shall be limited to a female from royalty or Old Sekke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to old Imperial House Act implemented before World War II, a person of royalty or new nobility was qualified to marry a man of royalty, and there existed a consuetude that a legitimate wife of the main branch of the Imperial Family who was a future Empress (i.e., the crown princess) should be limited to a female from royalty or the Old Sekke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to old Imperial House Act implemented before World War II, a person of royalty or new nobility was qualified to marry a man of royalty, and there existed a consuetude that a legitimate wife of the main branch of the Imperial Family who was a future Empress (i.e., the crown princess) should be limited to a female from royalty or the Old Sekke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), Lonicera(id:20638), Nnh(id:474), Kawai(id:5634), 水野白楓(id:22811), Eskimbot(id:29676), Extrahitz(id:26245), Himazin(id:22034), Aphaia(id:3132), Anton21(id:158479), BAKU(id:55205), Fryed-peach(id:63402), 寶馬山(id:130474), 玄史生(id:43670), Geogie(id:143809), 伏儀(id:142093), TANUKI(id:28527), Kzhr(id:131), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>