<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>白川伯王家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shirakawa-hakuo family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shirakawa-hakuo family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shirakawa-hakuo Family</e>
<cmt>大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>白川伯王家（しらかわはくおうけ）、又は白川家（しらかわけ）とは花山天皇の皇孫の延信王（清仁親王の王子）から始まり、古代からの神祇官に伝えられた伝統を受け継いだ公家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shirakawa-hakuo family, or the Shirakawa family, was the Court nobles whose ancestor was &quot;Nobuzane-o&quot; (the prince of Imperial Prince Kiyohito &amp; the imperial grandson of Emperor Kazan), and the family inherited the ancient tradition which was entrusted to &quot;Jingikan&quot; (department of worship).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shirakawa-hakuo family, or the Shirakawa family, was the Court nobles whose ancestor was &quot;Nobuzane-o&quot; (the prince of Imperial Prince Kiyohito &amp; the imperial grandson of Emperor Kazan), and the family inherited the ancient tradition entrusted to &quot;Jingikan&quot; (department of worship).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shirakawa-hakuo family, or the Shirakawa family was the court noble that had been originated from &apos;Prince Nobuzane&apos; (the prince of Imperial Prince Kiyohito), who was the imperial grandson of Emperor Kazan, and the family inherited the ancient tradition handed over through Jingikan (officer of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>皇室の宮中祭祀を司どっていた伯家神道(白川流神道)の家元。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was &quot;iemoto&quot; (the head family of a school) of &quot;Hakke Shinto&quot; (Shirakawa school of Shinto), which took charge of the court ritual of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was &quot;iemoto&quot; (the head family of a school) of &quot;Hakke Shinto&quot; (Shirakawa school of Shinto), which took charge of the court ritual of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family conducted the court rituals of the Imperial Family as &apos;iemoto&apos; (the head family of a school) of &apos;Hakke Shinto&apos; (Shirakawa school of Shinto).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>なお、花山天皇の子孫の源氏である花山源氏（かざんげんじ）に該当するのは、この白川伯王家のみであるため、両者は事実上同一のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, it was only this Shirakawa-hakuo family that fell under &quot;Kazan Genji&quot; (the Minamoto clan of Emperor Kazan&apos;s descendants), so the Shirakawa-hakuo family and Kazan Genji is practically the same thing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, it was only this Shirakawa-hakuo family that fell under &quot;Kazan Genji&quot; (the Minamoto clan of Emperor Kazan&apos;s descendants), so the Shirakawa-hakuo family and Kazan Genji were practically the same.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, it was only this Shirakawa-hakuo family that fell under Kazan Genji (the Minamoto clan of Emperor Kazan&apos;s descendants), so the Shirakawa-hakuo family and Kazan Genji were practically the same.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>花山源氏と白川家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan Genji and Shirakawa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan Genji and Shirakawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan Genji and Shirakawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>白川家（しらかわけ）は花山源氏を出自とする堂上家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shirakawa family was &quot;Tosho-ke&quot; (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks), and had the origin of Kazan Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shirakawa family was &quot;Tosho-ke&quot; (the hereditary lineage of Court nobles occupying relatively high ranks), and had origins in Kazan Genji.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shirakawa family was &quot;Tosho-ke&quot; (the hereditary lineage of court nobles occupying relatively high ranks), and had origins in Kazan Genji.</e>
<cmt>court を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>花山天皇の皇孫の延信王（のぶざねおう）は源氏を賜り臣籍降下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuzane-o, the imperial grandson of Emperor Kazan, was granted the family name of &quot;Minamoto&quot; when he became a subject of the state, and in later years he was appointed to &quot;Jingi haku,&quot; head of Jingikan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuzane-o, the imperial grandson of Emperor Kazan, was granted the family name of &quot;Minamoto&quot; when he became a subject of the state, and in later years he was appointed to &quot;Jingi haku,&quot; head of Jingikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuzane-o, the imperial grandson of Emperor Kazan, was granted the family name of Minamoto when he became a subject of the state.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後に神祇官の長官である神祇伯に任官された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years he was appointed to Jingi haku, head of Jingikan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これ以降、その子孫が神祇伯を世襲するようになったために「伯家」と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Jingi haku was hereditarily handed down to the descendants of Nobuzane-o, so the Shirakawa family began to be called &quot;Hakke.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Jingi haku was hereditarily handed down to the descendants of Nobuzane-o, so the Shirakawa family began to be called &quot;Hakke.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Jingi haku was hereditarily handed down to the descendants of Nobuzane-o, so the Shirakawa family began to be called &apos;Hakke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、神祇伯に就任してからは王氏に復するのが慣例であったことから「白川王家」とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the family was also called &quot;Shirakawa oke&quot; (the Shirakawa prince family) because the person who assumed Jingi haku conventionally got back the family name of &quot;O&quot; (the title of &quot;prince&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。*「王」には「氏（姓）」以外に「称号」としての意味もあるので、その旨補ってあります（最後の括弧内）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the family was also called &quot;Shirakawa oke&quot; (the Shirakawa prince family) because the person who assumed Jingi haku conventionally got back the family name of &quot;O&quot; (the title of &quot;prince&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was also called &quot;Shirakawa oke&quot; (the Shirakawa prince family) because the person who assumed Jingi haku conventionally got back the family name of &quot;O&quot; (the title of &quot;prince&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、室町時代になって代々神祇大副（神祇官の次官）を世襲していた卜部氏の吉田兼倶が吉田神道を確立し、神祇管領長上を称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in the Muromachi period, &quot;Kanetomo YOSHIDA&quot; of the Urabe clan, which hereditarily assumed &quot;Jingi taifu&quot; (Senior Assistant Head of the Department of Shinto), established Yoshida Shinto and began to call himself &quot;Jingikan ryochojo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, &quot;Kanetomo YOSHIDA&quot; of the Urabe clan, who inherited &quot;Jingi taifu&quot; (Senior Assistant Head of the Department of Shinto), established Yoshida Shinto and began to call himself &quot;Jingikan ryochojo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, Kanetomo YOSHIDA of the Urabe clan, who inherited the title of Jingi taifu (Senior Assistant Head of the Department of Shinto), established Yoshida Shinto and began to call himself &quot;Jingi kanrei chojo&quot; (Shinto-in-Chief).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>吉田家が全国の神社の大部分を支配するようになると白川家の権威は衰退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Yoshida family put most shrines all over Japan under its influence, the authority of the Shirakawa family declined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Yoshida family exerted includence over most shrines in Japan, the authority of the Shirakawa family declined.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Yoshida family exerted influence over most shrines in Japan, the authority of the Shirakawa family declined.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>江戸時代になって白川家は伯家神道を称して吉田家に対抗するも、寺社法度が制定されて以降は吉田家の優位は動かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the Shirakawa family called itself Hakke Shinto and competed with the Yoshida family, but after &quot;Jisha Hatto&quot; (Act governing temples and shrines) was enacted, the superiority of the Yoshida family did not change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the Shirakawa family called itself Hakke Shinto and competed with the Yoshida family, but after &quot;Jisha Hatto&quot; (Act governing temples and shrines) was enacted, the superiority of the Yoshida family could not be offset.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the Shirakawa family called itself &quot;Hakke Shinto&quot; and competed with the Yoshida family, but after Jisha Hatto (Act governing temples and shrines) was enacted, the superiority of the Yoshida family could not be offset.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>家格は半家 (公家)、代々の当主は近衛府を経て神祇伯になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kakaku&quot; (the family status) of the Shirakawa family was &quot;hanke&quot; (a kind of family status of the Court nobles), and every head of the family worked in the Division of Inner Palace Guards before becoming Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kakaku&quot; (the family status) of the Shirakawa family was &quot;hanke&quot; (a kind of family status of the Court nobles), and every head of the family worked in the Division of Inner Palace Guards before becoming Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kakaku (family status) of the Shirakawa family was hanke (the lowest rank for Tosho-ke court nobles), and every head of the family worked in the Division of Inner Palace Guards before becoming Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は200石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Karoku&quot; (the hereditary stipend) of the family in the Edo period was 200 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Karoku&quot; (the hereditary stipend) of the family in the Edo period was 200 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Karoku&quot; (the hereditary stipend) of the family in the Edo period was 200 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>他に神祇領・神事料100石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, the family was given 100 koku as &quot;jingiryo&quot; (the land owned by Jingikan) &amp; &quot;shinjiryo&quot; (the fee for Shinto rituals).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides this, the family was given 100 koku as &quot;jingiryo&quot; (the land owned by Jingikan) &amp; &quot;shinjiryo&quot; (the fee for Shinto rituals).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides this, the family was given 100 koku as &quot;jingiryo&quot; (the land owned by Jingikan) &amp; &quot;shinjiryo&quot; (the fee for Shinto rituals).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>明治時代になると王号を称することを止められ、白川家の当主の資訓王は子爵に叙せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the family was stopped using the title of prince, and the then head of the family Sukekuni-o got the investiture of Count instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, the family stopped using the title of prince, and the then head of the family Sukekuni-o received the investiture of Count instead.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was forced to stop using the title of prince in the Meiji period, and the then head of the family (Sukekuni-o) received the investiture of Count instead.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>資訓の後を継いだ白川資長には実子がなく、伯爵上野正雄（北白川宮能久親王の庶子）の男子の上野久雄を養子縁組に迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukenaga SHIRAKAWA, who succeeded Sukekuni, had no child, so Sukenaga adopted Hisao UENO, the son of Count Masao UENO (the illegitimate child of Imperial Prince Kitashirakawa no Miya Yoshihisa).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukenaga SHIRAKAWA, who succeeded Sukekuni, was childless, so Sukenaga adopted Hisao UENO, the son of Count Masao UENO (the illegitimate child of Imperial Prince Kitashirakawa no Miya Yoshihisa).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukenaga SHIRAKAWA, who succeeded Sukekuni, was childless, so Sukenaga adopted Hisao UENO, the son of Count Masao UENO (the illegitimate child of Imperial Prince Kitashirakawa no Miya Yoshihisa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、後にこの養子縁組は解消となり、白川家は断絶となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the adoption was broken off afterward, when the Shirakawa family was ended.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the adoption was broken off afterward, when the Shirakawa family was ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the adoption was broken off afterward, and the Shirakawa family was ended.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>白川家の成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How the Shirakawa family was formed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the Shirakawa family</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the Shirakawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>白川家の特徴は、神祇伯の世襲と、神祇伯就任とともに「王 (皇族)」を名乗れたことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics of the Shirakawa family were that Jingi haku was hereditary and that the family descendants could use the title of &quot;prince&quot; (a member of the Imperial Family) on becoming Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics of the Shirakawa family were that Jingi haku was hereditary and that the family descendants could use the title of &quot;prince&quot; (a member of the Imperial Family) on becoming Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristics of the Shirakawa family were that Jingi haku was hereditary and that the family descendants could use the title of &apos;prince&apos; (a member of the Imperial Family) on becoming Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「王」の身位は天皇との血縁関係で決まり、本来は官職に付随する性質のものではない（詳しくは皇族を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether the title of prince could be given or not was decided by the blood relationship with the emperor, and so a certain post was not essentially accompanied by the title; if you want to know about this in detail, please refer to the article of &quot;Imperial Family.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether the title of prince could be given or not was decided by the blood relationship with the emperor, and so a certain post was not essentially accompanied by the title; if you want to know about this in detail, please refer to the article of &quot;Imperial Family.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether the title of &apos;prince&apos; could be given or not was decided by the blood relationship with the emperor, and so a certain post was not essentially accompanied by the title (for details refer to the article of &quot;Imperial Family.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>一部表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>非皇族でありながら、王号の世襲を行えたのは白川家にのみ見られる特異な現象である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a phenomenon peculiar to the Shirakawa family that the title of prince could be hereditarily handed down to the descendants despite not being the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a phenomenon peculiar to the Shirakawa family that the title of prince could be hereditarily handed down to the descendants despite not being the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a phenomenon peculiar to the Shirakawa family that the title of prince could be hereditarily handed down to the descendants despite not being the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>以下、このことに留意しつつ白川家の成立について説明する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this point taken into account, how the Shirakawa family was formed is explained below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this point taken into account, how the establishment of the Shirakawa family is explained below.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this point taken into account, how the establishment of the Shirakawa family is explained below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>万寿2年（1025年）に花山天皇の皇孫である延信王が源姓を賜り臣籍降下して、寛徳3年（1046年）に神祇伯に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1025, Nobuzane-o, the imperial grandson of Emperor Kazan, was granted the family name of Minamoto when he became a subject of the state, and in 1046 he was appointed to &quot;Jingi haku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1025, Nobuzane-o, the imperial grandson of Emperor Kazan, was granted the family name of Minamoto when he became a subject of the state, and in 1046 he was appointed to &quot;Jingi haku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1025, Nobuzane-o, the imperial grandson of Emperor Kazan, was granted the family name of Minamoto when he became a subject of the state, and in 1046 he was appointed to Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>白川家はこの延信王に端を発していると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shirakawa family is said to have originated from this Nobuzane-o.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shirakawa family is said to have originated from this Nobuzane-o.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shirakawa family is said to have originated from this Nobuzane-o.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>当時の呼称は「源」または「王」であり、「白川家」や「伯家」「白川王家」と呼ばれるのはもっと時代が下ってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But at that time they were called by the family name &quot;Minamoto&quot; or &quot;O,&quot; so it was in a later era that they began to be called &quot;Shirakawa family,&quot; &quot;Hakke&quot; or &quot;Shirakawa oke.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But at that time they were called by the family name &quot;Minamoto&quot; or &quot;O,&quot; so it was in a later era that they began to be called &quot;Shirakawa family,&quot; &quot;Hakke&quot; or &quot;Shirakawa oke.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, however, they were called by the family name &quot;Minamoto&quot; or &quot;O&quot;, and it was in a later era that they began to be called &quot;Shirakawa-ke&quot;, &quot;Hakke&quot; or &quot;Shirakawa oke.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>延信王以後、康資王、顕康王、顕広王と白川家の人物が神祇伯に補任されている（ただし顕康王に関しては確証がないとの見方がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobuzane-o, the members of the Shirakawa family, Yasusuke-o, Akiyasu-o, Akihiro-o, were in turn appointed to Jingi haku; a theory says there is no hard evidence that Akiyasu-o became Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobuzane-o, the members of the Shirakawa family, Yasusuke-o, Akiyasu-o, Akihiro-o, were in turn appointed to Jingi haku; a theory says there is no hard evidence that Akiyasu-o became Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobuzane-o, the following members of the Shirakawa family were appointed to the position of Jingi haku: Yasusuke-o, Akiyasu-o, and then Akihiro-o. Some believe, however, that there is no hard evidence that Akiyasu-o became Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかし、この時期はまだ神祇伯は世襲されるものではなく、王氏、源氏及び大中臣氏が補任されるものと認識されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it was recognized at the time that Jingi haku was not hereditary and that the members of the O clan, the Minamoto clan and the Onakatomi clan were equally qualified to be appointed to it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it was recognized at the time that Jingi haku was not hereditary and that the members of the O clan, the Minamoto clan and the Onakatomi clan were equally qualified to be appointed to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, however, the post of Jingi haku was not yet regarded as hereditary but as open to the O clan, the Minamoto clan and the Onakatomi clan to be appointed to it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>事実先の四名の間に大中臣氏が補任されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, a member of the Onakatomi clan was appointed to Jingi haku in between the four above.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, a member of the Onakatomi clan was appointed to Jingi haku in between the four above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, a member of the Onakatomi clan was appointed to the post of Jingi haku in between the assignments of the aforementioned four members.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しましたActually→In factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>顕広王は本来は源氏であり、神祇伯就任とともに王氏に復し、退任後に源氏に戻る最初の例となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akihiro-o originally had the family name of Minamoto, and he was the first person who got back the family name of O on becoming Jingi haku, and who got back once again the family name of Minamoto after retirement; incidentally, a theory points out Akihiro-o could have belonged to the O clan before his assumption of Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akihiro-o originally had the family name of Minamoto, and he was the first person who got back the family name of O on becoming Jingi haku, and who once again took back the family name of Minamoto after retirement; incidentally, a theory points out Akihiro-o could have belonged to the O clan before his assumption of Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akihiro-o&apos;s family name was originally Minamoto, and he was the first person to get back the family name of O on becoming Jingi haku and then take back the family name of Minamoto after retirement.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました一原文一訳文の例外処理ただし日本語の文ですが、「顕広王は本来源氏であり、神祇伯就任とともに王氏に復し」とあります。復すということは、本来は王氏である、ということをすでに示唆していると思いますが、その後の括弧内の説明で、「ただし顕広王は神祇伯就任以前から王氏であった可能性も指摘されている」とあります。英語では原文どおりに訳しておりますが、日本語自体が少し矛盾していると思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>（ただし顕広王は神祇伯就任以前から王氏であった可能性も指摘されている）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, one theory suggests that Akihiro-o may have belonged to the O clan before his accession to the position of Jingi haku.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>顕広王の王氏復帰は源氏及び神祇伯の特殊性と婚姻関係によるものであると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akihiro-o&apos;s return to the O clan is attributed to both the uniqueness of the Minamoto clan &amp; Jingi haku and his relationship with other families by marriage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akihiro-o&apos;s return to the O clan is attributed to both the uniqueness of the Minamoto clan &amp; Jingi haku and his relationship with other families by marriage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akihiro-o&apos;s return to the O clan is considered to be both the uniqueness of the Minamoto clan and Jingi haku, and his relationship with other families by marriage.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>神祇とは神を祀ることであり、その責任者は天皇であって、朝廷にとって最も重要な行為であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jingi&quot; means the worship of God, and the emperor was responsible for it, so it was the most important ritual for the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jingi&quot; means the worship of God, for which the emperor was responsible, and was the most important ritual for the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jingi, meaning to worship deities, was the most important ritual for the Imperial Court because the Emperor assumed the responsibility for it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。emperorのeを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>神祇伯は神祇官の長官であり、最上位の官職であるとともに、奉幣使としても重要な職務である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jingi haku,&quot; the head of Jingikan, occupied the best position of all titles in the Imperial Court, and it also did an important work as &quot;Hoheishi&quot; (an imperial messenger to a Shinto shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jingi haku,&quot; the head of Jingikan, occupied the best position of all titles in the Imperial Court, and held an important function as &quot;Hoheishi&quot; (an imperial messenger to a Shinto shrine).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jingi haku, the head of Jingikan, not only held the highest rank of the official posts but also played an important function as Hoheishi (an imperial messenger to a Shinto shrine).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その神祇伯の重要性と、源氏という最も高貴な血筋、及び顕広王の室で仲資王の母が大中臣氏である上に、顕康王が有力な村上源氏の源顕房の猶子となっているという、多くの要素により、王氏復帰が成立したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akihiro-o&apos;s return to the O clan is attributed to many factors, such as this importance of Jingi haku, the most noble stock of the Minamoto clan, the fact that the wife of Akihiro-o (also the mother of Nakasuke-o) came from the Onakatomi clan, and in addition, and the fact that his father Akiyasu-o became an adopted child of &quot;MINAMOTO no Akifusa&quot; who belonged to the influential Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akihiro-o&apos;s return to the O clan is attributed to many factors, such as the importance of Jingi haku, the most noble stock of the Minamoto clan, the fact that the wife of Akihiro-o (also the mother of Nakasuke-o) came from the Onakatomi clan, and in addition, and the fact that his father Akiyasu-o became an adopted child of &quot;MINAMOTO no Akifusa&quot; who belonged to the influential Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Akihiro-o&apos;s return to the O clan was attributed to various factors: in addition to the above mentioned importance of Jingi haku and the paramount nobility of the lineage of the Minamoto clan, the Akihiro-o&apos;s wife, who was also the mother of Nakasuke-o, had come from the Onakatomi clan, and his father Akiyasu-o was an adopted child of MINAMOTO no Akifusa, who belonged to the influential Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>顕広王の子である仲資王（源仲資）が顕広王の後を継いで神祇伯となり、仲資王の退任後はその子の業資王（源業資）が神祇伯に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakasuke-o (MINAMOTO no Nakasuke) succeeded his father Akihiro-o as Jingi haku, and after the retirement of Nakasuke-o, his son Narisuke-o (MINAMOTO no Narisuke) was appointed to Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakasuke-o (MINAMOTO no Nakasuke) succeeded his father Akihiro-o as Jingi haku, and after the retirement of Nakasuke-o, his son Narisuke-o (MINAMOTO no Narisuke) was appointed to Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakasuke-o (MINAMOTO no Nakasuke) succeeded his father Akihiro-o as Jingi haku, and after the retirement of Nakasuke-o, his son Narisuke-o (MINAMOTO no Narisuke) was appointed to Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>その後業資王が急死し、弟の資宗王（源資宗）は神祇伯に任ぜられるための必要的措置として源氏から王氏に復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Narisuke-o died suddenly, and his younger brother Sukemune-o (MINAMOTO no Sukemune) returned his family name from &quot;Minamoto&quot; to &quot;O&quot; as necessary measures to be appointed to Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, Narisuke-o died suddenly, and his younger brother Sukemune-o (MINAMOTO no Sukemune) changed his family name from &quot;Minamoto&quot; to &quot;O&quot; as required in order to be appointed to Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of Narisuke-o&apos;s unexpected death at a later time, his younger brother Sukemune-o (MINAMOTO no Sukemune) changed his family name from Minamoto to O as a necessary process to be appointed to Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>これらが先例となり、以後、白川家による神祇伯の世襲化と神祇伯就任による王の呼称が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These cases set a precedent for both the hereditary succession of Jingi haku by the Shirakawa family &amp; naming them &quot;O&quot; on the appointment to Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These cases set a precedent for both the hereditary succession of Jingi haku by the Shirakawa family &amp; naming them &quot;O&quot; on the appointment to Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These cases set a precedent for both the hereditary succession of Jingi haku by the Shirakawa family and their being given the name &quot;O&quot; on their appointment as Jingi haku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>以上の経過により、顕広王の王氏復帰をもって白川家の成立とみなすことが多い（十三世紀初頭の資宗王によって成立したという見解もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the process above, the generally accepted theory says the Shirakawa family was formed when Akihiro-o returned his family name to &quot;O&quot;; another theory says it was formed by Sukemune-o in the early thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the process above, the generally accepted theory says the Shirakawa family was formed when Akihiro-o returned his family name to &quot;O&quot;; another theory says it was formed by Sukemune-o in the early thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the process above, the generally accepted theory says the Shirakawa family was formed when Akihiro-o returned his family name to &quot;O&quot;; another theory says it was formed by Sukemune-o in the early thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="39">
<j>なお「白川」の呼称は13世紀中ほどからしか確認できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the name of &quot;Shirakawa&quot; can be identified to have been used only from the middle of the thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the name of &quot;Shirakawa&quot; can be identified to have been used only from the middle of the thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the name of &apos;Shirakawa&apos; can be identified to have been used only from the middle of the thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="40">
<j>「神祇伯家学則」にある神道の大要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary of Shinto written in &quot;Jingi hakke gakusoku&quot; (Regulations of Jingi hakke)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of Shinto written in &quot;Jingi hakke gakusoku&quot; (Regulations of Jingi hakke)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of Shinto written in &apos;Jingi hakke gakusoku&apos; (Regulations of Jingi hakke)</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>同学則にはこうある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It says as follows :</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It says as follows :</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It says as follows :</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>「神道というものは、古今を通じて変わらない根本原則であり、いずれの国においても通用する大道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shinto is not only the basic principles of the universe that are everlasting throughout ancient &amp; modern times, but also the moral principles that can apply to every country;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shinto is not only the basic principles of the universe that are everlasting throughout ancient &amp; modern times, but they are also moral principles that apply to every country;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto provides not only the basic principles of the universe that are everlasting throughout ancient and modern times, but also the moral principles that apply to every country.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>神道と武道（相撲を含む）は一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto and the Japanese martial arts, including sumo, cannot be separated;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto and the Japanese martial arts, including sumo, cannot be separated;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto and the Japanese martial arts, including sumo, cannot be separated.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>身を修め、家を整え、国を治めるといったことの要領も、古事記・日本書紀・古語拾遺等の皇典を研鑚するうちにわかる。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">by studying diligently the literature related to Shinto, such as &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; (History of the Inbe clan), you can gradually learn the point of the maxim, &apos;To put the world in order, we must first put the nation in order; to put the nation in order, we must put the family in order; to put the family in order, we must cultivate our personal life.&apos; &quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　1)「身を修め～といったこと」については、「修身斉家治国平天下」で検索をかけると&quot;Kudoz translation help&quot;のサイトに左の訳が出ています。）　2)「皇典」については、「神道に関わる文献」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">by studying diligently the literature related to Shinto, such as &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; (History of the Inbe clan), you can gradually learn the point of the maxim, &apos;To put the world in order, we must first put the nation in order; to put the nation in order, we must put the family in order; to put the family in order, we must cultivate our personal life.&apos; &quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The essentials in controlling oneself, managing a household and governing the country can be acquired through diligent study of the Shinto literatures, such as Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters), Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) and Kogo-shui (History of the Inbe clan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Masyu(id:31065), Nnh(id:474), Kaba(id:17904), 代言人(id:33675), Juyukichi(id:16958), まさふゆ(id:232040), 黄金もち(id:102311), Ponsaku(id:31417), Njt(id:11249), 黒砂糖(id:38164), 輝く水(id:65241), BAKU(id:55205), ウラヌス(id:25954), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>