<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三条家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjo Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjo Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三条家（さんじょうけ、正字体：三條）は、藤原氏藤原北家閑院流の嫡流にあたる日本の氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjo family (as written三條 in orthographic style) was a clan that directly descended from the Fujiwara North House of Kan-in Line in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjo family (as written三條 in orthographic style) was a clan that directly descended from the Fujiwara North House of Kan-in Line in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjo family (as written三條 in orthographic style) was a clan that directly descended from the Kan-in Line ofthe Northern House of the Fujiwara clan in Japan.</e>
<cmt>the Fujiwara North House of Kan-in Line→the Kan-in Line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>公家・華族の家柄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Social standing of the Sanjo family was court noble/new nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Social standing of the Sanjo family was court noble/new nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Social standing of the Sanjo family was court noble/new nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>公家としての家格は清華家、華族としての家格は公爵家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house status of the Sanjo family ranked one of the Seiga families among the court nobles and duke as among the new nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The house status of the Sanjo family ranked sdone of the Seiga families among the court nobles and duke among the new nobility.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The house status of the Sanjo family ranked as one of the Seiga families among the court nobles and duke among the new nobility.</e>
<cmt>sdone　→ as one</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家業は笛と香道。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family specialized in playing the flute and flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family specialized in playing the flute and flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family specialized in playing the flute and flower arrangement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家紋は唐菱花（三条花角、三条家花角とも言う）を使用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kamon (family crest) was Karabishibana crest (Chinese rhombic flower) (also known as Sanjo Hanakaku or Sanjo-ke Hanakaku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kamon (family crest) was the Karabishibana crest (Chinese rhombic flower) (also known as Sanjo Hanakaku or Sanjo-ke Hanakaku).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kamon (family crest) was the Karabishibana crest (Chinese rhombic flower) (also known as Sanjo Hanakaku or Sanjo-ke Hanakaku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>明治維新までに三条家が輩出した公卿の数は39名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjo family produced 39Kugyo (the top court officials) prior to the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjo family produced thirty-nine Kugyo (top court officials) prior to the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjo family produced thirty-nine Kugyo (top court officials) prior to the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>うち太政大臣まで昇った者が5名、左大臣まで昇った者が5名、右大臣まで昇った者が8名、内大臣まで昇った者が7名となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The foregoing thirty-nine court nobles included 5 Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), 8 Udaijin (minister of the right) and 7 Ministers of the center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The foregoing thirty-nine court nobles included five Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), eight Udaijin (minister of the right) and seven Ministers of the center.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foregoing thirty-nine court nobles included five Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state), eight Udaijin (minister of the right) and seven Ministers of the center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大臣家の正親町三条家と三条西家を筆頭に分流も多くある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were numerous branch families including the Ogimachisanjo family which was the house of minister and the Sanjonishi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were numerous branch families including the Ogimachisanjo family that was the house of the minister and the Sanjonishi family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were numerous branch families including the Ogimachisanjo family that was the house of minister and the Sanjonishi family.</e>
<cmt>the house of the minister→the house of minister</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>閑院流は、白河天皇・鳥羽天皇期に上皇・天皇の外戚たる地位をほぼ独占し、院近親として絶大な権勢をふるった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the days of Emperor Shirakawa and Emperor Toba, the Kan-in Line wielded their enormous power, effectively monopolizing the all positions as maternal relatives of the retired emperor and emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the days of Emperor Shirakawa and Emperor Toba, the Kan-in Line wielded their enormous power, effectively monopolizing the all positions as maternal relatives of the retired emperor and the emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the days of Emperor Shirakawa and Emperor Toba, the Kan-in Line wielded their enormous power, effectively monopolizing the all positions as maternal relatives of the retired emperor and the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>閑院流の嫡流である藤原公実の二男藤原実行を祖とするのが三条家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjo family was founded by FUJIWARA no Saneyuki who was the second son of FUJIWARA no Kinzane of the main line of the Kan-in Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjo family was founded by FUJIWARA no Saneyuki who was the second son of FUJIWARA no Kinzane of the main line of the Kan-in Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjo family was founded by FUJIWARA no Saneyuki who was the second son of FUJIWARA no Kinzane of the main line of the Kan-in Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>実行は、三条の他、八条とも称したが、子の三条公教、孫の三条実房の嫡流が京都三条の北、高倉に邸を構えたことから、家名が定まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saneyuki also referred himself to as HACHIJO in addition to SANJO but due to the fact that his son Kiminori SANJO and the direct descendants of his grandson Sanefusa SANJO had their residence in Takakura, north of Kyoto Sanjo, the family name SANJO became established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saneyuki also referred to himself as HACHIJO in addition to SANJO, but due to the fact that his son Kiminori SANJO and the direct descendants of his grandson Sanefusa SANJO had their residence in Takakura, north of Kyoto Sanjo, the family name SANJO became established.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saneyuki also referred to himself as HACHIJO in addition to SANJO, but due to the fact that his son Kiminori SANJO and the direct descendants of his grandson Sanefusa SANJO had their residence in Takakura, north of Kyoto Sanjo, the family name SANJO became established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>二代公教は鳥羽上皇の後見役として権勢をふるった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second generation family head Kiminori exercised his power as the conservator of the retired Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second generation family head Kiminori exercised his power as the conservator of the retired Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second generation family head Kiminori exercised his power as the conservator of the retired Emperor Toba.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>三代実房は「愚昧記」の著者として知られ、公事の師と仰がれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third generation family head Sanefusa was well-known as the author of Gumaiki, being respected as the master of political operations and ceremonies of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third generation family head Sanefusa was well-known as the author of Gumaiki, being respected as the master of political operations and ceremonies of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third generation family head Sanefusa was well-known as the author of Gumaiki, being respected as the master of political operations and ceremonies of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>実房の後、嫡流は長男の三条公房が継ぎ三条を称したが、三男の正親町三条公氏も三条を称したため、嫡流を転法輪三条（てんぽうりん-）、公氏の流を正親町三条と呼び区別するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sanefusa, his oldest son Kinfusa SANJO succeeded the main branch of the family carrying the name of SANJO but as Kinuji OGIMACHISANJO, the third son of Sanefusa, also referred himself as SANJO, they decided to refer to the main family branch as the Temborin Sanjo family and the Kinuji line as the Ogimachisanjo family to distinguish one from the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Sanefusa, his oldest son Kinfusa SANJO succeeded the main branch of the family carrying the name of SANJO but as Kinuji OGIMACHISANJO, the third son of Sanefusa, also referred to himself as SANJO, they decided to refer to the main family branch as the Temborin Sanjo family and the Kinuji line as the Ogimachisanjo family to distinguish one from the other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Sanefusa, his oldest son Kinfusa SANJO succeeded the main branch of the family carrying the name of SANJO but as Kinuji OGIMACHISANJO, the third son of Sanefusa, also referred to himself as SANJO, they decided to refer to the main family branch as the Temborin Sanjo family and the Kinuji line as the Ogimachisanjo family to distinguish one from the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>戦国時代の当主三条公頼は山口の戦国大名大内義隆の元に滞在中、義隆家臣の陶晴賢の反乱に巻き込まれ、殺害されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While staying with Yoshitaka OUCHI, a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in Yamaguchi in the Sengoku Period, the then family head Kinyori SANJO, getting involved in the rebellion of Harukata SUE, was killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While staying with Yoshitaka OUCHI, a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in Yamaguchi during the Sengoku Period, the family head Kinyori SANJO, involved in the rebellion of Harukata SUE, was killed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While staying with Yoshitaka OUCHI, Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in Yamaguchi, the family head Kinyori SANJO, involved in the rebellion of Harukata SUE, was killed.</e>
<cmt>a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in Yamaguchi during the Sengoku Period→Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) in Yamaguchi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>分家の三条西家から三条家に養子が入れられて継ぐことになった（以後、香道が三条家にも伝わる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the sons of the Sanjonishi family, a branch of the Sanjo family, was subsequently adopted to succeed as the head of the latter family (and, thereafter, Kodo (incense appreciation) was introduced to the Sanjo family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the sons of the Sanjonishi family, a branch of the Sanjo family, was subsequently adopted to succeed as the head of the latter family (and, thereafter, Kodo (incense appreciation) was introduced to the Sanjo family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the sons of the Sanjonishi family, a branch of the Sanjo family, was subsequently adopted to succeed as the head of the latter family (and, thereafter, Kodo (incense appreciation) was introduced to the Sanjo family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>江戸時代の家禄ははじめ269石余、のちに469石余。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo Period, Karoku (hereditary stipend) of the family initially was approximately 269 koku which subsequently increased to 469 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo Period, Karoku (hereditary stipend) of the family initially was approximately 269 koku which subsequently increased to 469 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo Period, Karoku (hereditary stipend) of the family initially was approximately 269 koku which subsequently increased to 469 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>清華家として公家の中でも高い家格を誇り、大臣を多数輩出する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sanjo family enjoyed their prominent status among the court nobles as one of the Seiga families, producing a number of ministers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sanjo family enjoyed their prominent status among the court nobles as one of the Seiga families, producing a number of ministers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sanjo family enjoyed their prominent status among the court nobles as one of the Seiga families, producing a number of ministers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また代々、笛と装束の調達を家業とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family, in addition, specialized in playing the flute and procurement of costume and clothing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family, in addition, specialized in playing the flute and the procurement of costumes and clothing</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family, in addition, specialized in playing the flute and the procurement of costumes and clothing.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>幕末・明治時代には、明治維新の功臣三条実万・三条実美父子を輩出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between the end of the Edo Period and Meiji Era, the family produced Sanetsumu SANJO and his son Sanetomi SANJO who made significant contribution to the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between the end of the Edo Period and Meiji Era, the family produced Sanetsumu SANJO and his son Sanetomi SANJO who made a significant contribution to the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between the end of the Edo Period and Meiji Era, the family produced Sanetsumu SANJO and his son Sanetomi SANJO who made a significant contribution to the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>特に三条実美は、内閣総理大臣が置かれるまでの日本の首相にあたる右大臣や太政大臣の職をつとめて活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanetomi SANJO, in particular, played an active role in the government serving as Minister of the Right and Dajo Daijin that were equivalent of the Prime Minister of Japan in the days before that position became established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanetomi SANJO, in particular, played an active role in the government serving as Minister of the Right and Dajo Daijin that were equivalent of the Prime Minister of Japan in the days before that position became established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanetomi SANJO, in particular, played an active role in the government serving as Minister of the Right and Dajo Daijin that were equivalent of the Prime Minister of Japan in the days before that position became established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>清華家は原則として華族の侯爵家に列したが、三条家は三条実美の功績を持って一段高い公爵家に列している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a general rule, a Seiga family was appointed as a marquis among the new nobility but, in recognition of the achievements made by Sanetomi SANJO, the Sanjo family was granted the title of duke which was a rank higher than marquis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a general rule, the Seiga family was appointed as a marquis among the new nobility but, in recognition of the achievements made by Sanetomi SANJO, the Sanjo family was granted the title of duke, a rank higher than marquis.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a general rule, the Seiga family was appointed as a marquis among the new nobility but, in recognition of the achievements made by Sanetomi SANJO, the Sanjo family was granted the title of duke, a rank higher than marquis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TTTNIS(id:169490), Y.Sanada(id:36926), PANYNJ(id:38638), Nnh(id:474), Hadge(id:9555), Law soma(id:45202), 松茸(id:27535), Himazin(id:22034), Point136(id:211299), TDK(id:86111), Andee(id:20421), PuzzIeBacheIor(id:18744), 伊集院聖(id:53199), Zippin(id:9885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>