<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>持明院家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jimyoin family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jimyoin family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jimyoin Family</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字に</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>持明院家（じみょういんけ）は、日本の氏族（公家）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jimyoin family is a Japanese clan (court noble).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jimyoin family was a Japanese clan (court nobles).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jimyoin family was a Japanese clan (court nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原北家藤原頼宗流（中御門流）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The FUJIWARA no Yorimune line (Nakamikado Line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were from the FUJIWARA no Yorimune line (Nakamikado Line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were from the FUJIWARA no Yorimune line (Nakamikado Line) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家格は羽林家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kakaku (family status) is the House of Urin (holding military ranks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kakaku (family status) was the House of Urin (holding military rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kakaku (family status) was the House of Urin (holding military rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家業は書道・神楽・鷹匠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Calligraphy, Kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines) and Takajo (a hawker) were their family businesses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Calligraphy, Kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines) and Takajo (a hawker) were their family businesses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Calligraphy, Kagura (sacred music and dancing performed at shrines) and Takajo (a hawker) were their family businesses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家紋は杏葉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest is Gyoyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest is Gyoyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest is Gyoyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原基頼（頼宗の孫）を始祖として平安時代末期に成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This family was founded in the end of the Heian period with FUJIWARA no Motoyori (Yorimune&apos;s grandson) as the originator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This family was founded in the end of the Heian period with FUJIWARA no Motoyori (Yorimune&apos;s grandson) as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This family was founded in the end of the Heian period with FUJIWARA no Motoyori (Yorimune&apos;s grandson) as the originator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>基頼は邸内の持仏堂を持明院と名付け、後世これが家名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoyori named the Jibutsu-do hall (the nobility&apos;s private Buddha statue hall) in his site Jimyoin, which has later become the family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoyori named the Jibutsu-do hall (the nobility&apos;s private Buddha statue hall) in his site Jimyoin, which later became the family name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motoyori named the Jibutsu-do hall (the nobility&apos;s private Buddha statue hall) in his site Jimyoin, which later became the family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>持明院基家の娘持明院陳子（北白河院）は後高倉院の妃となり後堀河天皇を出産し、持明院は後高倉院・後堀河の仙洞御所となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinshi JIMYOIN (Kitashirakawa-in), a daughter of Motoie JIMYOIN, married with Gotakakura-in and bore the Emperor Gohorikawa, and thereafter Jimyoin was used as the Sento Imperial Palace of Gotakakura-in and Gohorikawa.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinshi JIMYOIN (Kitashirakawa-in), the daughter of Motoie JIMYOIN, married Gotakakura-in and bore Emperor Gohorikawa, and thereafter Jimyoin was used as the Sento Imperial Palace of Gotakakura-in and Gohorikawa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinshi JIMYOIN (Kitashirakawa-in), the daughter of Motoie JIMYOIN, married Gotakakura-in and bore Emperor Gohorikawa, and thereafter Jimyoin was used as the Sento Imperial Palace of Gotakakura-in and Gohorikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、後深草天皇とその子孫の仙洞御所になったため、この系統の天皇家を持明院統と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it later became the Sento Imperial Palace of the Emperor Gofukakusa and his posterity, this emperor&apos;s family line was called Jimyoin Line.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処分割時に、文頭「、その後に」を「その後、」に修正。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it later became the Sento Imperial Palace of Emperor Gofukakusa and his posterity, this emperor&apos;s family line was called the Jimyoin Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it later became the Sento Imperial Palace of Emperor Gofukakusa and his posterity, this emperor&apos;s family line was called the Jimyoin Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)に世尊寺家（能書で名高い）が断絶し、世尊寺行高の門人だった持明院基春が朝廷の書役を務め、以後書道の家として入木道伝授の宗家（持明院流）となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku period (period of warring states), the Sesonji family (which was famous for Nosho (excellent calligraphy)) ended, so Motoharu JIMYOIN, a disciple of Yukitaka SESONJI, worked as a clerical in the Imperial Court, and since then the family served as the head family for the initiation of calligraphy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku period (period of warring states), the Sesonji family (famous for Nosho - excellent calligraphy) ended, so Motoharu JIMYOIN, a disciple of Yukitaka SESONJI, worked as a cleric in the Imperial Court, and since then the family served as the head family for the initiation of calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku period (period of warring states), the Sesonji family (famous for Nosho - excellent calligraphy) ended, so Motoharu JIMYOIN, a disciple of Yukitaka SESONJI, worked as a cleric in the Imperial Court, and since then the family served as the head family for the initiation of calligraphy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また神楽・鷹匠をも家業とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also conducted Kagura and Takajo also as their family business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also conducted Kagura and Takajo as their family business.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also conducted Kagura and Takajo as their family business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>慶長20年（1615年）に持明院基久が豊臣秀頼方に従い大坂の役で没したため、家系は断絶の危機にさらされたが、遠縁の持明院基定（徳川氏の家臣大沢基宿の子）が相続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Motohisa JIMYOIN fought on the Hideyori TOYOTOMI side and died in 1615 during the Sieges of Ozaka, the family faced with danger of extinction, but a distant relative, Motosada JIMYOIN (a son of Motoie OSAWA, a vassal of the Tokugawa clan) succeeded the family line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Motohisa JIMYOIN fought on the Hideyori TOYOTOMI side and died in 1615 during the Sieges of Ozaka, the family faced the danger of extinction, but a distant relative, Motosada JIMYOIN (son of Motoie OSAWA, a vassal of the Tokugawa clan) succeeded the family line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Motohisa JIMYOIN fought on the Hideyori TOYOTOMI side and died in 1615 during the Sieges of Ozaka, the family faced the danger of extinction, but a distant relative, Motosada JIMYOIN (son of Motoie OSAWA, a vassal of the Tokugawa clan) succeeded the family line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>江戸時代の家禄は200石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 200 koku in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 200 koku during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their Karoku (hereditary stipend) was 200 koku during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>明治17年に持明院基哲が子爵となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1884 基哲 JIMYOIN was bestowed the title of Viscount.</e>
<cmt>基哲：読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1884 基哲 JIMYOIN was bestowed the title of Viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1884 基哲 JIMYOIN was bestowed the title of Viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>基頼の子園基氏は園家の祖となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motouji SONO, a son of Motoyori, became the originator of the Sono family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motouji SONO, the son of Motoyori, became the originator of the Sono family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motouji SONO, the son of Motoyori, became the originator of the Sono family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>基定の子高野保春は高野家の祖となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motosada&apos;s son, Yasuharu TAKANO became the originator of the Takano family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motosada&apos;s son, Yasuharu TAKANO became the originator of the Takano family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motosada&apos;s son, Yasuharu TAKANO became the originator of the Takano family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また堂上庶流は他に石野家・東園家・壬生家・石山家・六角家がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are other Tosho (high court nobility) branches, the Ishino, Higashisono, Mibu, Isiyama and Rokkaku families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are other Tosho (high court nobility) branches, the Ishino, Higashisono, Mibu, Isiyama, and Rokkaku families.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are other Tosho (high court nobility) branches, the Ishino, Higashisono, Mibu, Ishiyama, and Rokkaku families.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、源頼朝の縁戚として朝廷にも影響力を有した一条家 (中御門流)（のち断絶）及び江戸幕府高家の大沢氏も持明院家の系統である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ichijo family (Nakamikado-ryu (the Nakamikado line)) who had strong influence on the Imperial Court as a relative of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (and was later extinguished) and the Osawa clan, a Koke (a privileged family under Tokugawa Shogunate), are also from the Jimyoin family line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ichijo family (Nakamikado-ryu - the Nakamikado line) who had strong influence on the Imperial Court as a relative of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (later extinguished) and the Osawa clan, a Koke (privileged family under the Tokugawa Shogunate), were also from the Jimyoin family line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ichijo family (Nakamikado-ryu - the Nakamikado line) who had strong influence on the Imperial Court as a relative of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (later extinguished) and the Osawa clan, a Koke (privileged family under the Tokugawa Shogunate), were also from the Jimyoin family line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 伏儀(id:142093), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Blowback(id:173308), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>