<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中臣氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakatomi Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakatomi Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakatomi Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中臣氏（なかとみうじ）は、古代の日本において、忌部氏とともに神事・祭祀をつかさどった中央豪族で、古くから現在の京都市山科区中臣町付近の山階を拠点としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nakatomi clan, together with the Inbe clan, was a powerful family serving the Yamato court in ancient Japan, who took charge of Shinto rituals and religious services, and had occupied the region Yamashina--approximately corresponding to today&apos;s Nakatomi-cho, Yamashina-ku Ward, Kyoto City--as their base through the ages.</e>
<cmt>｢中央豪族」は対訳が見つからなかったので、&quot;a powerful family serving the Yamato court&quot;と翻訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nakatomi clan, together with the Inbe clan, was a powerful family serving the Yamato court in ancient Japan, who took charge of Shinto rituals and religious services, and had occupied the region Yamashina--approximately corresponding to today&apos;s Nakatomi-cho, Yamashina-ku Ward, Kyoto City--as their base through the ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nakatomi clan, together with the Inbe clan, was a powerful family serving the Yamato court in ancient Japan, who took charge of Shinto rituals and religious services, and had occupied the region Yamashina -approximately corresponding to today&apos;s Nakatomi-cho, Yamashina Ward, Kyoto City - as their base through the ages.</e>
<cmt>Yamashina-ku Ward→Yamashina Wardとし、スペース修正、ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>天児屋命（アメノコヤネ）を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was descended from Amenokoyane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was descended from Amenokoyane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was descended from Amenokoyane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>姓（かばね）は連（むらじ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their &quot;kabane&quot; (hereditary title) was &quot; Muraji&quot; (one of the highest family names).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their &quot;kabane&quot; (hereditary title) was &quot; Muraji&quot; (one of the highest family names).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their kabane (hereditary title) was Muraji (one of the highest family names).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション、余分なスペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>物部氏とともに仏教受容問題で蘇我氏と対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well as the Mononobe clan, the Nakatomi clan came into conflict with the Soga clan over the matter of accepting Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As well as the Mononobe clan, the Nakatomi clan came into conflict with the Soga clan over the acceptance of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As well as the Mononobe clan, the Nakatomi clan came into conflict with the Soga clan over the acceptance of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>中臣鎌足は645年の大化の改新で活躍し、669年の死に臨んで、藤原姓を賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">NAKATOMI no Kamatari played an important role in the Taika Reforms in 645 and was given Fujiwara cognomen upon his death in 669.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">NAKATOMI no Kamatari played an important role in the Taika Reforms in 645 and was given Fujiwara cognomen upon his death in 669.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">NAKATOMI no Kamatari played an important role in the Taika Reforms in 645 and was given Fujiwara cognomen upon his death in 669.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以後鎌足の子孫は藤原氏を名乗ったが、本系は依然として中臣を称し、代々神祇官・伊勢神官など神事・祭祀職を世襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of Kamatari declared themselves as the Fujiwara clan while the original line continued to use the name of Nakatomi and maintained their hereditary position of Shinto rituals and religious services providers such as &quot;Jingikan&quot;(department of worship) and a Shinto priest of Ise-jingu Shrine for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants of Kamatari declared themselves the Fujiwara clan while the original line continued to use the name of Nakatomi and maintained their hereditary position of Shinto rituals and religious services providers such as &quot;Jingikan&quot;(department of worship) and a Shinto priest of Ise-jingu Shrine for generations.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendants of Kamatari declared themselves the Fujiwara clan while the original line continued to use the name of Nakatomi and maintained their hereditary position of Shinto rituals and religious services providers such as Jingikan (department of worship) and a Shinto priest of Ise-jingu Shrine for generations.</e>
<cmt>スペース追加、クォーテーション削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Benjamin58(id:73071), Nnh(id:474), 代言人(id:33675), 陽一(id:92099), Point136(id:211299), 越中掾(id:149423), Robert De Smith(id:28533), Rimota(id:65657), BAKU(id:55205), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>