<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大村藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain of Omura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura Domain</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大村藩（おおむらはん）は、肥前国彼杵（そのぎ）地方を領した藩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain of Omura is the one which ruled Sonogi region in the Province of Hizen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura Domain was a feudal domain that ruled the Sonogi region of Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>Changed to make the sentence read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura Domain was a feudal domain that ruled the Sonogi region of Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藩庁は玖島城（長崎県大村市）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seat of the domain was Kujima Castle (Omura City, Nagasaki Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kujima Castle (located in present-day Omura City, Nagasaki Prefecture) was the domain&apos;s seat of power.</e>
<cmt>Changed to make the sentence read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kujima Castle (located in present-day Omura City, Nagasaki Prefecture) was the domain&apos;s seat of power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>略史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary of history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>当藩の藩主である大村氏は古来よりこの地の領主であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omura clan, the lord of the domain, had been the main proprietor of this land since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Omura clan, who were the feudal lords of this domain, had been the proprietary lords of this land since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>Changed to make the sentence read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Omura clan, who were the feudal lords of this domain, had been the proprietary lords of this land since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天正15年（1587年）の豊臣秀吉の九州平定後もこの地を領することを許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was permitted to rule this land even after the subjugation of Kyushu by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in 1587.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was permitted to continue to rule this land even after the subjugation of Kyushu by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in 1587.</e>
<cmt>Changed to make the sentence read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was permitted to continue to rule this land even after the subjugation of Kyushu by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in 1587.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>キリシタン大名の大村純忠（有馬晴純の次男で大村氏の養子となった）の子で、初代藩主・大村喜前は江戸幕府開府後も引き続きこの地において2万7900石を有する領主として存続し、明治維新を迎えた極めて稀な藩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki OMURA, the son of Sumitada OMURA of Christian daimyo (the second son of Haruzumi ARIMA adopted by the Omura clan) and the first lord of the domain, remained as the lord who had had 27,900 koku there continuously after the beginning of the Edo Shogunate, and the domain had entered the Meiji Restoration, which was unusual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Son of Sumitada OMURA (a Christian daimyo who was the second son of Haruzumi ARIMA and was adopted by the Omura clan), Yoshiaki OMURA was the first lord of this domain and he continued to rule over this land, which yielded 27,900 koku in rice, even after the establishment of the Edo Shogunate. This domain was extremely unusual given the fact that it was still intact at the time of the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>The exact meaning of &quot;明治維新を迎えた極めて稀な藩である&quot; here is extremely unclear, I think, as the subject seems to switch from being Yoshiaki OMURA to suddenly being the domain. Please check that I have understood this correctly. Also, given the switch in subjects, I have had to split this sentence in two.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Son of Sumitada OMURA (a Christian daimyo who was the second son of Haruzumi ARIMA and was adopted by the Omura clan), Yoshiaki OMURA was the first lord of this domain and he continued to rule over this land, which yielded 27,900 koku in rice, even after the establishment of the Edo Shogunate. This domain was extremely unusual given the fact that it was still intact at the time of the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)より長崎市を有し、南蛮貿易を通じた豊かな経済力を誇っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain had held Nagasaki City since the Sengoku period: the Warring States period (Japan), and enjoyed its powerful economy through trade with European.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domain included Nagasaki City from the Sengoku, or Warring States, period and enjoyed a strong economy thanks to trade with Europe.</e>
<cmt>Changed to make the sentence read more naturally. Also, &quot;domain included..&quot; is better than &quot;domain held..&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The domain included Nagasaki City from the Sengoku, or Warring States, period (Japan) and enjoyed a strong economy thanks to trade with Europe.</e>
<cmt>(Japan)追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし豊臣政権・江戸幕府と長崎は中央政権直轄領となり、貿易利潤を喪失することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the domain lost the profits of trade because Nagasaki became a demesne of the central government under the Toyotomi regime and the Edo Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, under the Toyotomi regime and the Edo Shogunate, the domain no longer benefited from the profits of this trade because Nagasaki became a demesne of the central government.</e>
<cmt>I think the part about the &quot;Toyotomi regime&quot; is better at the front of the sentence&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, under the Toyotomi regime and the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the domain no longer benefited from the profits of this trade because Nagasaki became a demesne of the central government.</e>
<cmt>Edo Shogunate→Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>立藩当初、藩主直轄領がわずか4000余石しかなく、逆に大村庶家一門15家の領地合計は8000余石にのぼっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it became an independent domain, the demesne of the lord of the domain was only 4000 koku; however, the territories of 15 families of the side line of the family in total increased to 8000 koku on the other hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When intially established as an independent domain, the demesme of the lord of the domain was only 4000 koku in rice, while the territories of the 15 families in the side line of the family were worth a total of 8000 koku rice.</e>
<cmt>Changed to make the sentence read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When initially established as an independent domain, the demesme of the lord of the domain was only 4000 koku in rice, while the territories of the 15 families in the side line of the family were worth a total of 8000 koku rice.</e>
<cmt>intially→Initially</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>第2代藩主・大村純頼は慶長12年（1607年）、財源確保と藩主権力強化のため、「御一門払い」と呼ばれる一門の領地没収を強制的に実行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiyori OMURA, the 2nd lord of the domain, forfeited the lands of the clan forcibly, which was called &quot;Goichimon Barai&quot;, to secure the financial source and enforce the power of the lord of the domain in 1607.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1607, Sumiyori OMURA, the 2nd lord of the domain annexed the lands of these families in a move known as &quot;Goichimon Barai&quot; to secure a source of income and sure up his position as lord of the domain.</e>
<cmt>Here &quot;forfeited&quot; is mistaken: Sumiyori took the lands of the other families!</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1607, Sumiyori OMURA, the 2nd lord of the domain annexed the lands of these families in a move known as &quot;Goichimon Barai&quot; to secure a source of income and shore up his position as lord of the domain.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス “sure” -&gt; “shore”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>第4代藩主・大村純長時代の明暦3年（1657年）、城下北部の郡村3村より多数の隠れキリシタンが発覚し逮捕されるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1657, the era of Suminaga OMURA, the 4th lord of the domain, a large number of crypto-Christians were exposed and arrested in three villages in a rural district in northern part of the castle town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1657, the era of Suminaga OMURA, the 4th lord of the domain, a large number of crypto-Christians were exposed and arrested in three villages in a rural district in a northern part of the castle town.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1657, the era of Suminaga OMURA, the 4th lord of the domain, a large number of crypto-Christians were exposed and arrested in three villages in a rural district in a northern part of the castle town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「郡崩れ」と呼ばれるこの事件は、キリスト教禁教令より45年を経過した後のことであり藩の存亡を揺るがす重大事件となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident called &quot;Gun kuzure&quot;, a breakdown of the region, was a serious event which destabilized the existence of the domain as it happened after 45 years of the order to ban Christianity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Happening as it did 45 years after the order to ban Christianity, this &quot;Gun kuzure&quot;, or breakdown of the region, was a serious event which destabilized the domain.</e>
<cmt>Changed the structure of the sentence to make it read more naturally. Emphasized &quot;45 years after order to ban Christiantity&quot; by moving it to the front of the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Happening as it did 45 years after the order to ban Christianity, this &quot;Gun kuzure&quot;, or breakdown of the region, was a serious event which destabilized the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、純長の実父であり勘定奉行を務めるなど幕府の要職にあった旗本・伊丹勝長を通じ、幕府に対し即座に事件の実情報告を行い恭順したため咎を受けなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the domain reported the actual condition of the incident to Shogunate immediately through Katsunaga ITAMI, a hatamoto, or shogun&apos;s vassal, who was the father of Suminaga and served the key post of Shogunate such as a commissioner of shogunate demesne, and obeyed so that it avoided accusation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the domain escaped censure by following procedure and reporting the particulars of the incident immediately through Katsunaga ITAMI, a hatamoto, or shogun&apos;s vassal, who was also Suminaga&apos;s father and served as commissioner of shogunate demesne and in other key posts.</e>
<cmt>The original translation is confusing and so I reworked the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the domain escaped censure by following procedure and reporting the particulars of the incident immediately through Katsunaga ITAMI, a hatamoto, or shogun&apos;s vassal, who was also Suminaga&apos;s father and served as commissioner of shogunate demesne and in other key posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これ以後、キリシタンへの徹底した予防と探索を行い、領民に対し仏教・神道への信仰を強化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, the domain implemented thorough prevention and search of Christianity and enforced the faith of Buddhism and Shintoism to people of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, the domain worked to seek out and suppress Christianity, and looked to strengthen the faith of the people of the domain in Buddhism and Shintoism</e>
<cmt>Changed to more natural English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, the domain worked to seek out and suppress Christianity, and looked to strengthen the faith of the people of the domain in Buddhism and Shintoism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>最後の藩主である第12代藩主・大村純熈が藩主に就任した時代は幕末であり、藩論は佐幕と勤王に大きく分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the last days of Tokugawa Shogunate when Sumihiro OMURA, the 12th and the last lord of the domain, assumed the post of lord, and the opinion of the domain was mainly divided to supporters of Bakufu and pro-imperialists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumihiro OMURA became the 12th and last lord in the final days of the Tokugawa shogunate when opinion in the domain was largely divided between support for the Bakufu and support for the pro-imperialists.</e>
<cmt>Better with Sumihiro as the subject of the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumihiro OMURA became the 12th and last lord in the final days of the Tokugawa shogunate when opinion in the domain was largely divided between support for the Bakufu and support for the pro-imperialists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>文久2年（1862年）、純熈が長崎奉行となると佐幕派が台頭し、尊皇派はこれに対し改革派同盟を結成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1862, the supporters of Bakufu gained power when Sumihiro became the Nagasaki magistrate, and the pro-imperialists organized the alliance of reform group in contrast.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The supporters of Bakufu gained power in 1862 when Sumihiro became the Nagasaki magistrate, and in repsonse, the pro-imperialists organized the alliance for reform group.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Alliance of reform&quot; is better as &quot;alliance for reform&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The supporters of Bakufu gained power in 1862 when Sumihiro became the Nagasaki magistrate, and in response, the pro-imperialists organized the alliance for reform group.</e>
<cmt>in repsonse→in resｐonse</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>元治元年（1864年）、純熈の長崎奉行辞任により逆に尊皇派が台頭した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1864, the pro-Imperialists became conspicuous when Sumihiro&apos;s resignation of the Nagasaki magistrate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1864, the pro-imperialists took back power on Sumihiro&apos;s resignation of the Nagasaki magistrate.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Became conspicuous&quot; is unnatural. I think the sentence mean that the pro-imperialists &quot;took back power&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1864, the pro-imperialists took back power on Sumihiro&apos;s resignation of the Nagasaki magistrate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）、改革派同盟の盟主である針尾九左衛門・松林飯山らが暗殺された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1867, Kyuzaemon HARIO and Banzan MATSUBAYASHI, the leaders of the alliance of reform group, were assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1867, Kyuzaemon HARIO and Banzan MATSUBAYASHI, the leaders of the alliance for reform group, were assassinated.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Alliance of reform&quot; is better as &quot;alliance for reform&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1867, Kyuzaemon HARIO and Banzan MATSUBAYASHI, the leaders of the alliance for reform group, were assassinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>逆にこの「小路騒動（こうじそうどう）」と呼ばれた闘争を契機に藩論が一気に尊皇倒幕へと統一され、在郷家臣団を含む倒幕軍が結成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This battle called &quot;Koji disorder&quot; unified the opinion of the domain into pro-imperialism and overthrow of the Tokugawa Shogunate at once, and the army for overthrow of bakufu including the group of subordinates in the region was organized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This battle known as the &quot;Koji disorder&quot; had the unintended effect of unifying opinion in the domain behind pro-imperialism, and an army was orgainzed for the overthrow of the bakufu and their subordinates in the region.</e>
<cmt>The English of the original translation is poor. I reworked the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This battle known as the &quot;Koji disorder&quot; had the unintended effect of unifying opinion in the domain behind pro-imperialism, and an army was organized for the overthrow of the bakufu and their subordinates in the region.</e>
<cmt>orgainzed→organized</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>以後、薩摩藩・長州藩などと共に倒幕の中枢藩の一つとして活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the domain had performed actively as one of the core domains to overthrow bakufu together with the domains of Satsuma and Choshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, together with domains of Satsuma and Choshu, the domain played a central role in the overthrow of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>The English of the original translation is poor. I reworked the sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, together with domains of Satsuma and Choshu, the domain played a central role in the overthrow of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>明治4年（1871年）、廃藩置県により大村県となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, it became Omura Prefecture under the abolition of domains and establishment of prefectures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, with the abolition of domains and establishment of prefectures, the domain became Omura Prefecture</e>
<cmt>Better to use &quot;with the&quot; rather than &quot;under the&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, with the abolition of domains and establishment of prefectures, the domain became Omura Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>のち、長崎県に編入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, it was transferred into Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It later became part of Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think &quot;transferred&quot; is correct here.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It later became part of Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>大村家は明治17年（1884年）には子爵となり、華族に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Omura family became a viscount and was raised on the peerage in 1884.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The House of Omura was raised to the peerage in 1884, receiving the rank of viscount.</e>
<cmt>The becoming a viscount&quot; and being raised to the peerage are part of the same thing.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The House of Omura was raised to the peerage in 1884, receiving the rank of viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後、倒幕の功が認められ、明治24年（1891年）には伯爵へと陞爵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its merit of overthrowing bakufu was recognized after that, and it was promoted in peerage to a count.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its role in overthrowing the bakufu was recognized with a promotion to the rank of count in 1891.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;merit&quot; to &quot;role&quot; for more natural English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its role in overthrowing the bakufu was recognized with a promotion to the rank of count in 1891.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>勤皇派藩士の一人であった中村喜八郎は維新の功績により山桜を拝領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kihachiro NAKAMURA, one of the pro-imperial domain warriors, received a mountain cherry tree as the merit of the Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kihachiro NAKAMURA, one of the pro-imperial warriors, received a mountain cherry tree in recognition of his contribution to the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Reworked sentence for more natural English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kihachiro NAKAMURA, one of the pro-imperial warriors, received a mountain cherry tree in recognition of his contribution to the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その先祖は江戸時代初期に漁村(大村藩の密貿易の港兼用)代官所の手代(算盤方)として郷士格村役人の家より出仕、後に勘定方藩士として取り立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His ancestor went into service as a clerk (of accounting) at a local government of a fishing village (also a smuggling port of the domain of Omura) from a family of village officer of goshi status at the beginning of the Edo period, and was promoted as a accounting officer later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His ancestors from a family of goshi, or village officer, status had served as (accounting) clerks in the local government of a fishing village (also a smuggling port of the domain of Omura) at the beginning of the Edo period, and were later promoted to accounting officer status.</e>
<cmt>I think this is talking about his &quot;ancestors&quot; plural rather than a single ancestor. I reworked the sentence with this in mind.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His ancestors from a family of goshi, or village officer, status had served as (accounting) clerks in the local government of a fishing village (also a smuggling port of the domain of Omura) at the beginning of the Edo period, and were later promoted to accounting officer status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>喜八郎の祖父は長崎番十人組頭をし彼の孫の松雄が第二次世界大戦前夜の上海で特務機関員をしていた時にドイツ軍の親衛隊から迫害されていたユダヤ人の一団を三菱から徴用した船で米国へ逃がしたが、そのことは如何にもキリシタン大名を輩出した大村藩と開明的長崎港の歴史的縁を偲ぶ物語と言えよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grandfather of Kihachiro was Nagasaki-ban Junin-gumi kashira, a head of the autonomous group with 10 families, and he released a group of Jewish which was persecuted by Schutzstaffel (SS) to the U.S. by a ship conscripted from Mitsubishi when Matsuo, his grandson, served as the Special Service Agency at Shanghai on the eve of the Second World War; this was a story which obviously reminds us of the historical bond between the domain of Omura, that produced Christian daimyos, and the open and liberal Nagasaki port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kihachiro&apos;s grandfather was Nagasaki-ban Junin-gumi kashira, head of an autonomous group of 10 families, and is known for helping a group of Jews who were being persecuted by the Schutzstaffel (SS) to escape to the U.S. on a ship conscripted from Mitsubishi when Matsuo, his grandson was serving as in Special Service Agency in Shanghai on the eve of the Second World War; a story which reminds us of the historical bond between the domain of Omura that produced Christian daimyos and the open and liberal port of Nagasaki.</e>
<cmt>This doesn&apos;t make any sense chronologically. Kihachiro is stated to be one of the pro-imperial warriors in 34, but here his grandfather is rescuing Jews from the SS on the eve of WWII!</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kihachiro&apos;s grandfather was Nagasaki-ban Junin-gumi kashira, head of an autonomous group of 10 families, and is known for helping a group of Jews who were being persecuted by the Schutzstaffel (SS) to escape to the U.S. on a ship conscripted from Mitsubishi when Matsuo, his grandson was serving as in Special Service Agency in Shanghai on the eve of the Second World War; a story which reminds us of the historical bond between the domain of Omura that produced Christian daimyos and the open and liberal port of Nagasaki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>歴代藩主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successive lords of the domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lords chronological order</e>
<cmt>This is more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chronological order of the Lords.</e>
<cmt>訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>大村（おおむら）家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>外様大名　27,900石</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tozama daimyo (outside lords) with 27,900 koku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tozama daimyo (outside lords) with 27,900 koku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tozama daimyo (outside lords) with 27,900 koku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>大村喜前（よしあき）〔従五位下、丹後守〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki OTOMO (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki OTOMO (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>大村純頼（すみより）〔従五位下、民部大輔〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiyori OTOMO (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Mimbuno-Daifu, Deputy Minister of Popular Affairs Office)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiyori OTOMO (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Mimbuno-Daifu, Deputy Minister of Popular Affairs Office)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiyori OTOMO (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Mimbuno-Daifu, Deputy Minister of the Popular Affairs Office)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>大村純信（すみのぶ）〔従五位下、丹後守〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suminobu OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suminobu OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suminobu OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>大村純長（すみなが）〔従五位下、因幡守〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suminaga OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Imba)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suminaga OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Imba)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suminaga OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Imba)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>大村純尹（すみまさ）〔従五位下、筑後守〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumimasa OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Chikugo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimasa OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Chikugo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimasa OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Chikugo)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>大村純庸（すみつね）〔従五位下、伊勢守〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumitsune OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Ise)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumitsune OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Ise)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumitsune OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Ise)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>大村純富（すみひさ）〔従五位下、河内守〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumihisa OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Kawachi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumihisa OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Kawachi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumihisa OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Kawachi)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>大村純保（すみもり）〔従五位下、弾正少弼〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumimori OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Danjyo-shohitsu, Minor Second Officer of impeachment office)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumimori OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Danjyo-shohitsu, Minor Second Officer of impeachment office)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumimori OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Danjyo-shohitsu, Minor Second Officer of the impeachment office)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>大村純鎮（すみやす）〔従五位下、信濃守〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiyasu OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Shinano)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiyasu OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Shinano)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiyasu OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Shinano)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>大村純昌（すみよし）〔従五位下、丹後守〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiyoshi OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiyoshi OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiyoshi OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>大村純顕（すみあき）〔従五位下、丹後守〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiaki OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiaki OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiaki OMURA (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Tango)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>大村純熈（すみひろ）〔従五位下、丹後守　長崎奉行〕</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumihiro OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango, Nagasaki magistrate)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumihiro OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango, Nagasaki magistrate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumihiro OMURA (Junior Fifth-low Court Rank, Governor of Tango, Nagasaki Magistrate)</e>
<cmt>〔従五位下、・・・〕の表記を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), ドルチェット(id:46458), VolkovBot(id:105371), Reggaeman(id:6214), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>