<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>水無瀬家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minase family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Minase family</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Minase Family</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>水無瀬家（みなせけ）は、藤原北家藤原隆家流の堂上家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Minase family was the FUJIWARA no Takaie line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and was Toshoke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Minase family fell under the FUJIWARA no Takaie line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and was Toshoke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Minase family fell under the FUJIWARA no Takaie line of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, and was Toshoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>家格は羽林家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family rank was Urinke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family rank was Urinke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family rank was Urinke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代中期、藤原隆家は兄藤原伊周とともに叔父藤原道長と摂関の地位を争って敗れ、出雲国国司に左遷された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the mid Heian period, FUJIWARA no Takaie, together with his elder brother FUJIWARA no Korechika, vied with FUJIWARA no Michinaga for the regent-chancellor post &apos;Sekkan&apos;, but defeated and demoted to governor of Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the mid Heian period, FUJIWARA no Takaie, together with his elder brother FUJIWARA no Korechika, vied with FUJIWARA no Michinaga for the regent-chancellor post &apos;Sekkan,&apos; but was defeated and demoted to the governor of Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the mid Heian period, FUJIWARA no Takaie, together with his elder brother FUJIWARA no Korechika, vied with FUJIWARA no Michinaga for the regent-chancellor post &apos;Sekkan,&apos; but was defeated and demoted to the governor of Izumo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その後、隆家は京に戻り、次男藤原経輔は正二位大納言となり、水無瀬大納言と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Takaie returned to Kyoto, whereas his second son FUJIWARA no Tsunesuke became Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Dainagon (Major Counselor) and called &apos;Minase Dainagon&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Takaie returned to Kyoto, whereas his second son FUJIWARA no Tsunesuke became Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Dainagon (Major Counselor) and was called &apos;Minase Dainagon&apos;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Takaie returned to Kyoto, whereas his second son FUJIWARA no Tsunesuke became Shonii (Senior Second Rank), Dainagon (Major Counselor) and was called &apos;Minase Dainagon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>経輔の子孫は五堂上家に分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tunesuke&apos;s descendants were divided into five Toshoke families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tunesuke&apos;s descendants were divided into five Toshoke families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tunesuke&apos;s descendants were divided into five Toshoke families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このうちの一家が水無瀬家で明治維新まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the families was the Minase family and continued until the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the families was the Minase family and they continued until the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the families was the Minase family and they continued until the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)に血統が途絶え、歌道で有名な三条西家から養子をむかえたため、以後水無瀬家も和歌の家となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Minase family line ended during the Sengoku period (warring states period, 1493-1573), the family adopted a son from the Sanjonishi family, which was famous for their waka poetry; therefore, the Minase family also inherited the waka poetry skill since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Minase family line ended during the Sengoku period (warring states period, 1493-1573), the family adopted a son from the Sanjonishi family, who were famous for their waka poetry; therefore, the Minase family also inherited waka poetry skills.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Minase family line ended during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States, 1493-1573), the family adopted a son from the Sanjonishi family, who were famous for their waka poetry; therefore, the Minase family also inherited waka poetry skills.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明治時代、唯一の大阪府出身の華族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Meiji period, the Minase family became the only Kazoku (nobility) came from Osaka prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, the Minase family became the only Kazoku (nobility) from Osaka prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, the Minase family became the only Kazoku (nobility) from Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>16世紀末に「駒の銘は水無瀬公の筆をもって宝とす」と賞賛され、書家として知られた水無瀬家4代の間、駒銘を書いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the 16th century, people praised the Minase family for its calligraphy as &quot;shogi pieces inscribed with Master Minase&apos;s calligraphy is a treasure&quot;, and the four generations of the Minase family which were famous for calligraphy wrote letters for shogi pieces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the sixteenth century, people praised the Minase family for its calligraphy and &quot;shogi pieces inscribed with Master Minase&apos;s calligraphy are considered a treasure,&quot; and the four generations of the Minase family which were famous for calligraphy wrote the letters for shogi pieces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the sixteenth century, people praised the Minase family for its calligraphy and &apos;shogi pieces inscribed with Master Minase&apos;s calligraphy are considered a treasure,&apos; and the four generations of the Minase family which were famous for calligraphy wrote the letters for shogi pieces.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>特に水無瀬兼成（かねなり）とその孫の兼俊（かねとし）がよく知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, Kanenari MINASE and his grandson Kanetoshi MINASE were well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, Kanenari MINASE and his grandson Kanetoshi MINASE were well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, Kanenari MINASE and his grandson Kanetoshi MINASE were well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>大阪府三島郡 (大阪府)島本町の水無瀬神宮にその作品が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their works are in the Minasejingu shrine in Shimamoto-cho, Mishima-gun, Osaka prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their works are stored in the Minasejingu shrine in Shimamoto-cho, Mishima-gun, Osaka prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their works are stored in the Minase-jingu Shrine in Shimamoto-cho, Mishima-gun, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>兼成の駒製作記録「将棊（しょうぎ）馬日記」から、その作と特定された、注文主が道休（足利義昭の出家した後の名）の象牙の駒などが有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the famous pieces are ivory pieces ordered by Dokyu (Buddhist name of Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA), which were identified as made by Kanenari based on Kanenari&apos;s Records on making shogi pieces, &quot;Shogi Uma Nikki&quot; (Shogi pieces diary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the most famous are ivory pieces ordered by Dokyu (Buddhist name of Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA), identified as made by Kanenari based on Kanenari&apos;s Records on making shogi pieces, &quot;Shogi Uma Nikki&quot; (Shogi pieces diary).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the most famous are ivory pieces ordered by Dokyu (Buddhist name of Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA), identified as made by Kanenari based on Kanenari&apos;s Records on making shogi pieces, &quot;Shogi Uma Nikki&quot; (Shogi pieces diary).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>主な人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main Descendants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main Descendants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main descendants</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字スペース削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>水無瀬兼成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanenari MINASE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanenari MINASE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanenari MINASE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>水無瀬氏信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujinobu MINASE</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujinobu MINASE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujinobu MINASE</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>右衛門佐局</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emonnosuke no Tsubone</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emonnosuke no Tsubone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emonnosuke no Tsubone</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>- 氏信の娘で江戸城大奥女中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">: a daughter of Ujinobu, waiting woman in women&apos;s quarters for the Tokugawa shoguns in Edo castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">: the daughter of Ujinobu, waiting woman in women&apos;s quarters for the Tokugawa shoguns in the Edo castle</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The daughter of Ujinobu, waiting woman in women&apos;s quarters for the Tokugawa shoguns in the Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>:削除用語統一ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 HASIDATE(id:181052), Happy B.(id:111020), やりたこ(id:113528), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>